<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.1.stemmler</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">“Undisturbed above once in a Lustre”: Francis Douce, George Cumberland and
William Blake at the Bodleian Library and Ashmolean Museum</title>
        <author n="Stemmler">Joan K. Stemmler</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>E.B. Bentley</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Srigley</name>
              <name>Joan K. Stemmler</name>
              <name>Julia M. Wright</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-9" n="9"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">“Undisturbed above once in a Lustre”: Francis Douce, George
                        Cumberland and William Blake at the Bodleian Library and Ashmolean
                        Museum</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Joan K. <name>Stemmler</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>When Francis Douce died on 5 April 1834, he bequeathed to the Bodleian Library
                    almost all the printed books, coins, prints, and manuscripts he had
                        collected.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">1</ref>
Sir Frederic Madden believed
                    that in “leaving them to the Bodleian he consigns them to neglect and
                    oblivion!” where they would “sleep on . . . undisturbed above once
                    in a lustre by some prying individual of antiquarian celebrity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">2</ref> On the 150th anniversary of the bequest, an
                    exhibition and catalogue celebrated the rich deposit, now divided between the
                    Bodleian Library and the Ashmolean Museum. Through Douce’s antiquarian
                    activities, he met and corresponded with a number of similarly-minded
                    individuals; the letters were bequeathed to the British Museum and in 1930 given
                    to the Bodleian Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">3</ref> Of interest to
                    this art historian was a pattern revealed in these sources of direct and
                    indirect contacts between Douce and the life-long friends, George Cumberland and
                    William Blake. Although I was well acquainted with Cumberland<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">4</ref> and Blake, Douce’s connections with these men
                    were only marginally known to me<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">5</ref> until I
                    explored selected sections of the Bodleian catalogues, Douce’s collected
                    letters, his notebooks, especially his “Collecta,” his portfolios
                    and his lists and notes relating to proposed publications in the archives at the
                    Ashmolean Museum.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For his history, Last Will and Testament, and
                        the start and history of the development of his manuscript collection, see
                            <hi rend="i">The Douce Legacy, An exhibition to commemorate the 150th
                            anniversary of the bequest of Francis Douce (1757-1834)</hi> (Bodleian
                        Library, Oxford, 1984) vii-xiii, 13, 15, 130-139, hereafter cited as 
<hi rend="i">DL</hi> with the page number.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 15, 17, 18 for Madden’s <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>
and a letter to Sir Thomas Phillipps.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 130.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">4</hi> In initial research, I relied on Clementina
                        Black, ed., <hi rend="i">The Cumberland Letters, Being the Correspondence of
                            Richard Dennison Cumberland and George Cumberland between the Years 1771
                            and 1784</hi> (London: M. Secker, 1912); C. F. Bell, ed., <hi rend="i">Annals of
Thomas Banks, Sculptor, Royal Academician</hi> (Cambridge:
                        Cambridge UP, 1938), hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">Annals</hi>; Geoffrey
                        Keynes, “Some Uncollected Authors XLIV. George Cumberland,
                        1754-1848,” <hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi> 19 (1970): 32-65,
                        hereafter cited as “Uncollected Authors”; Gerald E. Bentley,
                        Jr., <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of George Cumberland</hi> (New York:
                        Garland Publishing Co., 1975), hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>;
Gerald E. Bentley Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969), hereafter cited as 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> with the page number. Also consulted was the Cumberland
                        correspondence, formerly in the British Museum where it was cited in the
                        literature as British Museum Additional Manuscripts, B.M. Add. MSS. 36,495 -
                        36,497, June 1785-94, and now in the British Library, hereafter cited as
                        B.L. Add. MSS with number. I wish to thank the British Library for their
                        kind permission to quote from these manuscripts.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">5</hi> In “Uncollected Authors” 35-36,
                        Douce is mentioned briefly in connection with the Cumberland correspondence
                        now in the British Library. In Bentley’s valuable bibliographies and
                        records published in regard to Blake and Cumberland the name Douce is also
                        mentioned.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Preliminary lists of the bequest were made by
                        A. C. Madan, “Rough Catalog of Douce Prints and Summary
                        Guide,” Vol. I, 1915-16; G. R. Scott, “A Catalogue of the
                        Collections in Portfolio of Engravings . . .,” Vol. II, Feb-July 1916
                        [R.6.260]. A printed catalogue was made by [H. O. Coxe, with Henry Symonds,
                        Arthur Brown], <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Printed Books and Manuscripts
                            bequeathed by Francis Douce Esq. to the Bodleian Library</hi> (Oxford:
                        Oxford UP, 1840 [R.6.92]), hereafter cited as 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue.</hi> The
correspondence, MSS. Douce d. 20-29, d. 32, d. 39,
                        extending from 1788 to 1834 was consulted. Three small notebooks of
                        purchases, the “Collecta,” MS. Douce e. 66, 1803-1810; e. 67,
                        1811-1823; e. 68, 1824-1834, the socalled “Diary of Antiquarian
                        Purchases” were consulted, along with the typed transcript [R6.91],
                        hereafter cited as TS. “Collecta.” I wish to thank the
                        Bodleian Library for their permission to publish material from these
                        sources. I owe thanks to the librarians in Duke Humphrey’s Library at
                        the Bodleian Library for their attentive help, and especially to Clive
                        Hurst, Head of Special Collections at the Bodleian Library, who confirmed
                        and corrected where necessary some of my readings of the passages in the
                        “Collecta” and in the typescript by comparing my citations
                        with the original notebooks. The Ashmolean holdings are of prints and
                        manuscripts formerly at the Bodleian Library which, judged to be primarily
                        of artistic rather than literary interest, were transferred to the
                        University Galleries in 1863; in 1915, another exchange occurred, so that
                        more fine prints and drawings came to the Department of Prints and Drawings
                        at the Ashmolean. In the Ashmolean Archives are notebooks, manuscripts and
                        miscellaneous material on art, the Douce Bequest, The Bell Bookcase, 3
                        Boxes. I would like to thank the Ashmolean Museum for their permission to
                        publish material from this source. My thanks also go to the Assistant
                        Keepers in the Department of Prints and Drawings in the Ashmolean Museum,
                        Dr. John Whiteley and Dr. Catherine Whistler and to the Print Room
	    <corr type="emend">Supervisor,</corr> Dr. Bernadette Nelson, for their patient and generous
                        help.</note></p>
        <p>This paper will show when and how these three individuals, first only loosely
                    connected through location and developing common interests, finally came into
                    closer contact by the 1800s. Though we know that in Douce’s collection at
                    his death there were two books of illuminated printing by Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage
of Heaven and Hell</hi> Copy B with the separate plate,
                    “Our End is come,” and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> Copy I,
                    plus the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> Copy H and a third state of the
                        <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">7</ref>
                    a 1794 purchase which will be discussed below has not been previously noted,
                    Blake’s <hi rend="i">For Children: the Gates of Paradise.</hi> Douce
                    likewise collected some of Cumberland’s books, but more important is the
                    revelation of the way Douce used Cumberland as one of his resources for
                    information about the visual arts. Campbell Dodgson called Douce a bibliophile
                    and collector of woodcuts of advanced taste.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n35" type="note">8</ref> I suggest that Cumberland, in his appreciation of early woodcuts
                    and the work of Giulio di Antonio Bonasone<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n36" type="note">9</ref>
                    and in his advocacy of Blake, both personally and through his books, played a
                    role in forming that taste. This essay also offers corroborating information to
                    that recently published by Joseph Viscomi.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">10</ref>
                    With his suggestion that Isaac D’Israeli, a close friend and
                    correspondent of Douce, bought in 1834 part of George Romney’s collection
                    of books in illuminated printing by Blake, Viscomi focuses interest on new ways
                    of understanding how Blake’s books were produced and collected,
                    illuminating the “tenuousness of our assumptions regarding patronage and
                    the earliest modes by which illuminated books were produced and
                        disseminated.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">11</ref> In the Douce
                    bequest, a hitherto unpublished network of relationships reveals more
                    information about practices of selling and collecting books and prints during
                    the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">7</hi>
Douce B. 790, Arch. A. d. 22, <hi rend="i">The Book of
                        Thel</hi>, ?1786-1803; Douce MM. 834, Arch. G. d. 53, <hi rend="i">The
                            Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, 1790-93, as in <hi rend="i">DL</hi>
                        89-90. For information on these holdings, see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
Books: Annotated Catalogues of William Blake’s
                            Writings</hi> . . . (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977) 57, 118-128,
                        133-138, 285-298, hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">BB</hi> with page number.
                        See <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 658, #553, for the Douce 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> 32,
where only <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> and Hayley’s 
<hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> are listed, and to which the other books should be added.
                        For the impression, 1A, “Our End is come,” bound in with 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate
                            Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP,
                        1983) 30, hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">SP.</hi> For <hi rend="i">Canterbury
Pilgrims</hi>, see Essick <hi rend="i">SP</hi> 63,
                        impression 3D.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Woodcuts of the Fifteenth Century in the Ashmolean Museum,
with
                            notes of similar prints at the Bodleian</hi>, ed. Campbell Dodgson
                        (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1929) 6.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The first catalogue of Bonasone (fl. 1531-74)
                        was written by Cumberland (see note 30 below). Cumberland and his
                        contemporaries spelled Bonasone with a terminal <hi rend="i">i</hi> which I
                        retain for their writings.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">10</hi> “The Myth of Commissioned Illuminated
                        Books: George Romney, Isaac D’Israeli, and “ONE HUNDRED AND
                        SIXTY designs . . . of Blake’s,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23
                        (1989): 48-74.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Viscomi 65.</note></p>
        <p>Douce and Blake were both born in 1757, Cumberland three years earlier.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">12</ref> Socially, Douce’s family was more
                    highly placed than that of the middleclass Cumberland or the artisan Blake. All
                    three were younger sons, a position affecting their education and income: in the
                    1770s, Douce was admitted as an attorney of the King’s Bench, Cumberland
                    worked at the Royal Exchange Assurance Office in London, finally earning
                    £60 per annum,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">13</ref>
and Blake served his
                    apprenticeship with James Basire, the engraver for the Society of Antiquaries.
                    Cumberland was admitted as a student at the Royal Academy in 1772, an expression
                    of his true interests.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">14</ref> In their third
                    decade, the three men approached the world of books and prints from different
                    directions. Douce was said to have made his first purchase of an antique coin at
                    age 10.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">15</ref> Elected
as a Fellow of the Society
                    of Antiquaries by 1779, he tried to devote himself to literary and antiquarian
                    pursuits as much as possible. Blake was said to have frequented print-shops and
                    auction sales as a boy. He aspired to be a painter and poet: his first
                    exhibition at the Royal Academy was reviewed by Cumberland. Upon the death of
                    his father in 1784, he went into a brief partnership with James Parker as an
                    engraver and printseller, after which he began to make his own books and
                    reproductive engravings for others. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Unless
                        otherwise noted, I draw the following material on Douce and Blake from the
                        “Introduction” in <hi rend="i">DL</hi> and from <hi rend="i">BR.</hi></note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Black (see note 4 above) 24, 85.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> Bibliography</hi> 49, according to the MS. list of Students
                        Admitted to the Royal Academy.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 22, #34.</note></p>
        <p>Cumberland had an omnivorous interest in learning and in writing; by 1780 he
                    reported to his brother that he had met some “Geniuses and Men of
                        Science.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">16</ref>
By 1784, he knew and
                    wrote on behalf of the sculptor, Thomas Banks, and through him met Richard
                    Cosway, and, later, Thomas Johnes and Horne Tooke.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n44" type="note">17</ref> In 1784, Cumberland came into a £300 inheritance, releasing
                    him from his fourteen years of “servitude” <pb id="p26-10" n="10"/>
at the Royal
Exchange.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">18</ref> Devoting himself
                    to experiments in printing and practical ways of self-publishing, he probably
                    shared this knowledge with Blake. Traveling several times to the continent,
                    Cumberland met Baron de Murr in Nuremberg and the librarian of the Grand Duke of
                    Tuscany in Florence, experiences he later recorded in his book <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
Outline</hi> of 1796.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">19</ref>
                    Settling in Italy by 1788, away from the “cold weather and cold
                    receptions” given to his unorthodox family in England,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">20</ref> he cultivated friends like John Irvine in that
                    “school of real students in sculpture and painting” in Rome.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">21</ref> He established lifelong relationships with
                    dealers and gem-cutters of Rome, collecting gems, books, prints and information.
                        <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Black 267.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">17</hi><hi rend="i"> Annals</hi> 25, 56, 57; Black 307. For a full account of
Johnes
                        and his connections with Cumberland and Blake, see Morton D. Paley,
                        “Thomas Johnes, ‘Ancient Guardian of Wales,’”
                            <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 2 (1969): 65-67, hereafter cited as
                        “Johnes.”</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">18</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36, 494, fol. 225, as cited
                        in “Uncollected Authors” 32.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> Thoughts on Outline, Sculpture, and the System that guided
the
                            ancient artists in composing their figures and groupes: Accompanied with
                            free remarks on the practice of the moderns, and liberal hints cordially
                            intended for their advantage. To which are annexed twenty-four designs
                            of classical subjects invented on the principles recommended in the
                            essay by George Cumberland</hi> (London, 1796) 27, hereafter cited as
                            <hi rend="i">Thoughts.</hi></note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">20</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,496, fols. 16, 17, 31 July
                        1788, to his Mother. Cumberland went to Italy with the abused wife and
                        children of his former landlord, making a monetary settlement arranged by
                        John Flaxman with her former husband. B.L. Add. MSS. 36,495, fol. 372, 10
                        May 1788, from Mrs. E. Cumberland, “I am now your own for you have
                        paid dearly for me.”</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">21</hi><hi rend="i"> Thoughts</hi> 10; George Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Outlines
from
                            the Antients, exhibiting their principles of composition in figures and
                            basso-rilievos taken chiefly from inedited monuments of Greek and Roman
                            sculpture.</hi> With an introductory essay (London, 1829) iv.</note></p>
        <p>Douce began in 1779 a correspondence with Richard Twiss, a wealthy older fellow
                    antiquary, traveler and miscellaneous writer, from which we gain an insight into
                    Douce’s early concern with collecting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n49" type="note">22</ref> Twiss mentions in 1788 Mr. Edwards, Mr. Raspe, Mr. Marchand,
                    bookseller, cataloguer and gem-cutter respectively,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">23</ref> as men in whom Douce would take an interest. The Edwards
brothers,
                    James and John, opened their Pall Mall book-shop in 1784. Jean Hagstrum suggests
                    that Blake probably knew the shop and that he may have seen there medieval
                    prayer books, like the Bedford Book of Hours.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n51" type="note">24</ref> In 1788, Blake is said to have discovered how to print illuminated
                    books using relief-etched plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">25</ref> In the
                    same year Douce makes one of his major purchases, an illuminated book of hours
                    printed in Paris in 1505.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">26</ref> No connection is
                    claimed between Douce and the two others at this time, but all express from
                    different perspectives their interest in similar fields. 
<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">22</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, Bushhill, Edmonton and other
                        addresses, 1779-1806; <hi rend="i">DL</hi> 122, #179; <hi rend="i">Dictionary of
National Bibliography.</hi></note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">23</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 3, 18 October 1788;
                        fol. 7, 26 November 1788; fol. 8, 7 December 1788. Douce also corresponds
                        with Ritson, Steevens, and Edwards in this period, and later was in frequent
                        contact with the Cosways.</note>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">24</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake: Poet and Painter</hi> (Chicago: University of
                        Chicago P, 1964) 31-33; David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against
                            Empire: A poet’s interpretation of the history of his own
                            times.</hi> 3rd rev. ed. (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1977) 130,
                        507.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">25</hi> For a full explanation of Blake’s
                        process of relief-etching, see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake,
                            Printmaker</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1980) chapter 3.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">26</hi> The purchase was made at the sale of Thomas
                        Pearson in April of 1788. Douce CC 290(3), <hi rend="i">DL</hi>
                    135.</note></p>
        <p>The French Revolution causes Cumberland to return to England in 1790, settling
                    first in Lyndhurst, near Southhampton, and then moving to Bishopsgate near
                    Windsor Great Park by 1794.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">27</ref> Cumberland has
                    the Edwards’ shop bind his books; Douce also patronizes the Edwards in
                    1790, buying printed books and two manuscripts from the catalogue.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">28</ref> Blake, working in London all this time,
                    publishes in 1789 <hi rend="i">The Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
                        Book of Thel</hi>; by 1790, his imagination fired by the Revolution, he
                    finishes some plates of his <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> By
                    1795 he makes eight more books, prints color-prints, and does much reproductive
                    engraving. In the same year, Richard Edwards, the younger brother of the
                    booksellers, asks Blake to make drawings and engravings for an edition of
                    Young’s <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">27</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,496, fols.
                        184, 199; B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fols. 298, 299, 12 May 1794,
                        Bishopsgate.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">28</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fols. 59, 60, 19
                        October 1791; <hi rend="i">DL</hi> 136.</note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Cumberland also publishes three books:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">29</ref>
                        he mentions on 17 January 1792 that he has laid his work before “one
                        of our first rate London Collectors, a Dignitary of high literary character
                        who unites to a great fortune great knowledge in all that is worth knowing
                        or having” and has had it approved.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">30</ref> The work, <hi rend="i">Some Anecdotes of the life of Julio
                            Bonasoni</hi>, published by 17 February 1793,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">31</ref> is dedicated to Sir William Hamilton who may have
                        been the “London Collector.” By 6 March over half these books
                        were sold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">32</ref>
Douce purchases
                        Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Bonasoni</hi> by November 1793, as we know
                        from a letter of thanks from Andrew Lumisden, who borrowed the book of
                        Douce: “I return you, with many thanks, Cumberland’s anecdotes
                        of the life of Bonasoni.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">33</ref>
                        Cumberland visits Johnes, a patron of Banks and Stothard, between May and
                        July 1794, and dedicates in 1796 a “really beautiful book,”
                            <hi rend="i">An Attempt to Describe Hafod</hi>, describing the residence
                        in Wales.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">34</ref>
Johnes uses the
                        Edwards’ Pall Mall bookshop for more than antiquarian purchases: he
                        sends Cumberland a halibut in care of Edwards.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n62" type="note">35</ref> At the same time, Cumberland and Blake are in very close touch
                        as Blake engraves for Cumberland eight plates dated 1794 and 1795 for 
<hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">36</ref>
                        Two preserved letters from Blake to Cumberland in 1795 and 1796 show the
                        strength and familiarity of this relationship.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n64" type="note">37</ref> Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> was
                        inventoried in Douce’s bequest but he did not purchase it until
                            1818.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">38</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">29</hi> See “Uncollected Authors”
                            57-65, for the complete bibliography, to which information from 
<hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> 3-36, and G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
                            “Cumberland Bibliography Addenda,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                            11 (1977): 128 should be added.</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">30</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fols. 109, 110,
                            27 January 1792.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">31</hi><hi rend="i"> Some Anecdotes of the life of Julio Bonasoni, a Bolognese
                                artist, who followed the styles of the best schools in the sixteenth
                                century. Accompanied by a catalogue of the engravings, with their
                                measures, of the works of that tasteful composer. And remarks on the
                                general character of his rare and exquisite performances. To which
                                is prefixed, a plan for the improvement of the Arts in England</hi>
                            (London, 1793), hereafter cited as Bonasoni; B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497,
                            fols. 234, 235, 17 Feb. 1793, Richard Cumberland to George Cumberland;
                            fol. 236, 27 Feb. 1793, Charles Long to Cumberland.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">32</hi> In a letter from Cumberland’s
                            bookseller, W. Lucas, B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fol. 241, 11 March
                            1793.</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">33</hi> MS. Douce d. 20, fol. 52, 30 November
                            1793.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">34</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fols. 300, 301,
                            ?29 May 1794, and 318, 28 July 1794, from Johnes to Cumberland. A. C.
                            Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London: 1906) 12,
                            notes that Stothard decorated the library of Hafod. See also 
<hi rend="i">Annals</hi> 120; “Johnes” 66-67;
                            “Uncollected Authors” 58.</note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">35</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fol. 318, 28 July
                            1794.</note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">36</hi><hi rend="i"> Bibliography</hi> 15-17.</note>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">37</hi><hi rend="i"> The Letters of William Blake with related Documents</hi>,
                            3rd ed., ed. Geoffrey Keynes (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1980) 5, 6; 6
                            December 1795 and 23 December 1796.</note>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">38</hi> 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>(note 6
                            above), where it is listed as C. subt. 180; see <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> 17
for Cumberland’s withdrawal of the book
                            from the market and his subsequent public sales of it between 1804 and
                            1815. See note 115 below for details.</note></p>
          <p>By 6 August 1792, Twiss is in Paris buying for Douce.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n66" type="note">39</ref> However, in a hastily scrawled letter of 25 August
                        1792, Twiss recounts his relief at his escape from Paris, with his head
                        still affixed to his body and not on a pike: “The Lord have mercy on
                        the two thousand English now in Paris!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n67" type="note">40</ref> Blake’s close associates, the Swiss artist, Henry
                        Fuseli, and Joseph Johnson, the publisher and bookseller, plan to go to
                        France as well in the same year, but are deterred by the events of the
                        Terror. The name Fuseli is mentioned in connection with another facet of
                        Douce’s interest in natural science: Twiss had begun sending to Douce
                        unhatched pupae, describing in detail the butterflies which would emerge,
                        including information on mounting the specimens. Among the books about which
                        he tells Douce is one by Fuseli’s brother, “‘Fuesleis
                        [sic] les insectes de la Suisse’, 4<hi rend="s">to</hi>, with 55
                            Col.<hi rend="s">d</hi> plates.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n68" type="note">41</ref> On 2 September 1794, Twiss mentions “the book of
                        directions for insects from johnson” at St. Paul’s Churchyard,
                        indicating that Douce already has it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n69" type="note">42</ref>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">39</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 44.</note>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">40</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 45.</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">41</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fol. 55, 9 April
                            [?August] 1794. See Eudo Mason, <hi rend="i">The Mind of Henry Fuseli:
                                Selections from his Writings with an Introductory Study</hi>(London:
                            Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1951) 358, for a listing of Johan H.
                            Fuseli’s review of his translation of a book by his brother, J.
                            C. Fuseli, in the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> 21 (May 1795):
                            523. Mason mistakenly gives the title as <hi rend="i">Archives of
                                Etymology</hi>, but it should be Fuessly’s <hi rend="i">Archives of
Entomology, containing the History, or ascertaining the
                                Characters and Classes of Insects not hitherto described,
                                imperfectly known, or erroneously classified</hi> (London: Joseph
                            Johnson, 1795) 523-24. The original designs were by Schellenberg.</note>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">42</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fols. 68, 69, 2
                            September 1794.</note></p>
          <p>Despite these indications that Douce had a marginal knowledge of Fuseli and
                        Johnson, figures well known to Blake, the first mention of the name of Blake
                        in connection with that of Douce occurs in a letter from Twiss to Douce on
                        13 September 1794.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">43</ref> Blake had printed
                            <hi rend="i">For Children: Gates of Paradise</hi>, “Published by
                        William Blake #13 Hercules Building Lambeth and J. Johnson St. Paul’s
                        Churchyard” by 1793.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">44</ref> In a
                        letter to Douce whose first two paragraphs deal with exchanges of books and
                        with entomology, Twiss mentions the book in the third paragraph. 
						<q> . . . a
                            lady here has just shown me . . . two curious works of Blake No. 13
                            Hercules Build[ing] Lambeth. One “the gates of Paradise”,
                            16 etchings. 2 A <hi rend="s">mo</hi> the other “Songs of
                            innocence” printed [crossed out] colours. I suppose the man to be
                            mad, but he draws very well. have [you] anything by him?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">45</ref></q>
Douce underlines this last question in red ink, a habit
he had
                        initiated in the 1780s to emphasize passages which 
<pb id="p26-11" n="11"/>
                        interested him in letters he received. Douce must have commissioned Twiss to
                        obtain the mentioned books, because in Twiss’s next letter, we find
                        underlined in red ink <hi rend="i">Saturday, next, 27th.</hi><q> On Saturday, next,
27th, any time after 12 o’clock, if you will
                            be so good as to send to the Black Bull Holborn, you will find there
                            ready, your Barbuth, Monffot, 3 [?impastein] Donovans insects<hi rend="s">t</hi>
[?Jere] Taylors, Mandeville on Stews, &amp; my
                            Curtis insects &amp; Blakes Paradise, and also a very curious 
<hi rend="i">Caterpillars</hi>, which will produce next May Linnaeus <hi rend="i">Phalena Pudebunda.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">46</ref></q>
This hitherto unnoted and unmentioned
copy of <hi rend="i">For
                            Children: Gates of Paradise</hi> must not have been kept by Douce as it
                        does not appear to be in the Bodleian Library now.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">47</ref>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">43</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 70<hi rend="s">r</hi>. In April of 1991, when I did
my research at the Bodleian
                            Library, Mr. J.A. Brister kindly offered help to me by showing me his
                            corrected transcript of the “Collecta” and by mentioning
                            to me his rememberance of a reference to Blake in the Douce
                            correspondence. His sharing of this recollection led me to look for and
                            find the Blake material mentioned in this paper. Mr. Brister’s
                            death in June marks not only a personal deprivation for his colleagues
                            but a loss for scholars in this area.</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">44</hi> See <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 185-193, for
                            details about <hi rend="i">Gates.</hi></note>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">45</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, 13 September 1794,
                            fol. 70<hi rend="s">v</hi>.</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">46</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, 25 September 1794,
                            fol. 72<hi rend="s">r</hi>.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">47</hi> This book is not listed in the
                            unreferenced 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue.</hi> See Gerald E. Bentley
                            Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement: Being New Materials Relating
                                to the Life of William Blake Discovered Since the Publication of
                                Blake Records</hi> (1969) (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1988) 85, hereafter
                            cited as <hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi>, where five copies, none in the
                            Bodleian, are listed. Copy A, now in the Library of Congress, Lessing G.
                            Rosenwald Collection, is the only known proof copy. While in the hands
                            of W. E. Moss, six copies of Copy A were printed in perhaps 1942 of
                            photographic reproductions; I infer one of these is the one mentioned as
                            at the Bodleian Library (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 185, 192, 193).</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland makes contacts with other collectors, noting in the <hi rend="i">Anecdotes of
Bonasoni</hi> that he knows the exquisite collection of
                        the Rev. Mr. Cracherode. 
						<q> I lately, saw in the portfolios of Mr.
                            Cracherode, a print of a battle of naked men, ten or twelve figures, in
                            folio, well preserved, with a label, on which was written, Antionio
                            Pollojolo [sic] opus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75"
type="note">48</ref>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">48</hi><hi rend="i"> Bonasoni</hi> 34, 66, referring to what is probably a
                                copy of Anthonio Pollaiuolo, <hi rend="i">Battle of the Nudes</hi>,
                                B.001.</note></q>
Clayton Mordaunt Cracherode, the reclusive London collector
who
                        bequeathes his collection to the British Museum in 1799,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">49</ref> has interests similar to those of Douce. On 12 May
                        1795, Douce receives this invitation, “Mr. Cracherode presents his
                        complements to Mr. Douce, and will be very happy to see him on Thursday
                        next, at any time that may be convenient to him from eleven to two
                            o’clock.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">50</ref> In a Douce
                        manuscript of unknown date, the “Curiosities of Engraving or
                        Anecdotes of Prints,” he mentions Cracherode’s copy of
                        “Cupid and Psyche by A Venetian &amp; Cumberland’s opinion of
                            it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">51</ref>
Thus, while there is
                        no hard evidence that Douce knows Cumberland and Blake personally, their
                        paths are certainly parallel and perhaps touch. <note id="n76"><hi rend="s">49</hi><hi
rend="i"> Dictionary of National Biography.</hi></note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">50</hi> MS. Douce d. 20, fol. 61, 12 May 1795,
                            Queen’s Square.</note>
	<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">51</hi> “The Curiosities of Engraving or
                            Anecdotes of Prints,” 103, Box 2, Bell Bookcase, Douce Bequest
                            1834, Department of Prints and Drawings, Ashmolean Museum, hereafter
                            cited as “Curiosities.”</note></p>
          <p>By 1793 D’Israeli and Douce were on friendly terms, D’Israeli
                        writing to Douce from Exeter. D’Israeli, preparing a new addition of
                        the second volume of <hi rend="i">Curiosities of Literature</hi>, asks Douce
                        on 24 July for corrections and improvements.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n79" type="note">52</ref> On 2 September 1794, D’Israeli mentions Dyer’s
                        catalogue which is “pretty bulky;” it has 300 pages and
                        consists of 1186 works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">53</ref> As of 14
                        September 1793, Douce apparently does not yet own the catalogue.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">54</ref> Again on 25 June 1796,
                        D’Israeli reminds Douce that “Dyer is preparing a rich and
                        voluminous Catalogue.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82"
type="note">55</ref>
	<note id="n79"><hi rend="s">52</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fols. 1, 2.</note>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">53</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fols. 3, 4.</note>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">54</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fols. 5, 6.</note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">55</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fols. 22,
                        23.</note></p>
          <p>In Exeter by 1783, Gilbert Dyer advertised a catalogue of his library, an
                        example of the beginning of circulating libraries; by 1811, Dyer was selling
                        libraries as large as 2600 items for several thousand pounds.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">56</ref> This method of sales from
                        “Retailers of libraries by Marked Catalogues,” as well as from
                        “Sellers of books by the Hammer” was prevalent at the
                            time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">57</ref>
Dyer’s importance
                        here is in connection with a sale of a Blake book to Douce, as we shall see
                        below. <note id="n83"><hi rend="s">56</hi> For Dyer, 1743-1820, see Ian
                            Maxted, “‘4 rotten cornbags and some old books’:
                            The Impact of the Printed Word in Devon,” in Robin Myers and
                            Michael Harris, eds. <hi rend="i">Sale and Distribution of Books, from
                                1700</hi> (Oxford: Oxford Polytechnic Press, 1982) 66, 69n74.</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">57</hi> See Gwyn Walters, “Early Sale
                            Catalogues: Problems and Perspectives,” in Myers and Harris 118
                            (note 56 above), quoting Richard Gough (1735-1809), “Father of
                            British Antiquity.”</note></p>
          <p>Twiss gossips with Douce in a letter of 17 April 1797 that “Caleb Wms
                        is married to the Rights of Woman for sure,” referring of course to
                        William Godwin and Mary Wollstonecraft.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n85" type="note">58</ref> He mentions that he expects at his home Thomas Holcroft and
                        his daughter who plays the piano well.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n86" type="note">59</ref>
                        With these references, Twiss displays his knowledge of the radical circle
                        with which Blake was connected and, at the same time, indicates that Douce
                        would be interested in learning about them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n87" type="note">60</ref> Douce’s politics and religion are summarized in the
                        Bodleian catalogue: a Deist, he was “A Radical in politics, his
                        watchwords were Liberty and Justice, and his hero was Napoleon.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">61</ref>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">58</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 96.</note>
	<note id="n86"><hi rend="s">59</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 97<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 8 January 1796.</note>
	<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">60</hi> Erdman <hi rend="i">Prophet</hi> 38-39,
                            154, 156, 159, describes this circle, mentioning in particular the
                            friendship among James Barry, Thomas Holcroft and William Godwin. He
                            notes the dinners in Johnson’s rooms where Fuseli, Godwin,
                            Holcroft, and Blake were present, and he is certain Blake must have been
                            acquainted with the Society for Constitutional Information, revived by
                            Hollis and Tooke, who in turn is Cumberland’s friend. According
                            to William St. Clair, <hi rend="i">The Godwins and the Shelleys: The
                                Biography of a Family</hi> (London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1989) 163,
                            Godwin was introduced to Blake 26 May 1796.</note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">61</hi> As cited in <hi rend="i">DL</hi> 8,
                            9.</note></p>
          <p>In 1799, at the death of both his father and mother, Douce has £3000
                        settled on him, expanding his ability to purchase books, prints,
                        manuscripts, and coins.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89"
type="note">62</ref> The artist
                        James Barry, a familiar of Godwin and Holcroft, is known to Douce by 1800:
                        D’Israeli invites Douce to dine, proposing also to ask Barry and
                        “Dr. Grant, a friend of Fuseli.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n90" type="note">63</ref> Douce records that in 1800 and 1801 he bought from Barry his
                        letters to the “dilettanti society” and to the “society
                        of arts”; he also lent books to Barry during the same period.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">64</ref> In April 1807, Douce bought drawings
                        by Barry at his sale.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92"
type="note">65</ref> Blake, by 1800
                        in Felpham for three years, also indicated a renewed interest in Barry at
                        this time, recording in outrage that “While Sr Joshua was rolling in
                        Riches Barry was Poor &amp; unemployd except by his own Energy.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93" type="note">66</ref>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">62</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> ix.</note>
	<note id="n90"><hi rend="s">63</hi> For Barry, see <hi rend="i">DL</hi> 3-5,
                            which cites MS. Douce d. 33, fol. 152.</note>
	<note id="n91"><hi rend="s">64</hi> MS. Douce e. 69, fols. 4, 5; Douce e.
                            74, 1800.</note>
	<note id="n92"><hi rend="s">65</hi> TS. “Collecta” 21, #5 (MS.
                            Douce e. 66, fol. 20<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">66</hi> In Blake’s Annotations to <hi rend="i">The Works of Sir Joshua
Reynolds</hi>, ed. Edward Malone
                            (London, 1798), as in David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete
                                Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (New York:
                            Doubleday, 1988) 636.</note></p>
          <p>A closer connection between Cumberland and Douce emerges in 1798, when
                        Cumberland prints <hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar: An
                            African Tale</hi>, a disguised satire critical of the Pitt
                        administration, a book of which Mr. Erskine “deemed it dangerous,
                        under Mr. Pitt’s maladministration, to publish.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94" type="note">67</ref> Keynes names Mr. Horne Tooke and Mr.
                        Douce as Cumberland’s supporters, Tooke having made Cumberland read
                        the Manuscript through the whole way in one sitting,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95" type="note">68</ref> and Douce buying the book.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96" type="note">69</ref> Johnes, friend of Cumberland and patron of Stothard
                        and Banks, sends Douce digitalis seeds before 1805.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97" type="note">70</ref> The names of Stothard, Westall and Flaxman, mutual
                        acquaintances of Cumberland and Blake, appear frequently in Douce’s
                        writings. <note id="n94"><hi rend="s">67</hi> “Uncollected
                            Authors” 60-61. See also <hi rend="i">Annals</hi> 126-27, for
                            Banks’s introduction to Erskine in 1798. Thomas Erskine
                            (1750-1823), Lord Chancellor of England, defended Thomas Paine in 1792
                            and John Horne Tooke in 1794.</note>
	<note id="n95"><hi rend="s">68</hi> “Uncollected Authors”
                            60-61.</note>
	<note id="n96"><hi rend="s">69</hi> 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> where
                            it is listed as C.476.</note>
	<note id="n97"><hi rend="s">70</hi> MS. Douce d. 21, fol. 12.</note></p>
          <p>By the middle of 1801 Cumberland has to leave the London area in search of a
                        less expensive place to live; moving to Sussex, he leaves his possessions in
                        the care of his old friend, the sculptor Banks, with instructions to sell
                        over 1120 prints and 195 books through Mr. Thomas Philipe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98" type="note">71</ref> Thomas Dodd, whose name will appear in
                        Douce’s book of purchases, is one of the purchasers of some of
                        Cumberland’s collection at the sale which took place before 14 August
                            1802.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99" type="note">72</ref> In
the matter of collecting
                        prints, Dodd, who began issuing sale catalogues in 1806,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100" type="note">73</ref> would seem to be important in a new kind of
                        acquisition on the part of Douce. Douce begins in 1803 to keep the
                        “Collecta” and Dodd’s name begins to show up with
                        increasing frequency as a source for prints in Douce’s list of
                            acquisitions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n101"
type="note">74</ref> For instance, Douce
                        purchases from Dodd in March 1805 anonymous woodprints of a “man
                        drawing a woman sleeping,” <pb id="p26-12" n="12"/>
and “Women
                        bathing”: the first seems related to an Albrecht Dürer woodcut
                        and the second to a rare reproduction of a Dürer drawing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n102" type="note">75</ref> Dürer’s name appears in
                        June 1805, with the purchase of “Alb. Durer’s triumph of
                        Maximilian compleat.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103"
type="note">76</ref>
	<note id="n98"><hi rend="s">71</hi><hi rend="i"> Annals</hi> 140-42. Bell identified the print and
                            book-seller Thomas Philipe in Frits Lugt, <hi rend="i">Les Marques de
                                Collections de Dessins &amp; D’estampes</hi> (Amsterdam,
                            1921) 457, #2451. For Philipe, see also Walters 121 (note 57
                            above).</note>
	<note id="n99"><hi rend="s">72</hi> For the sale and the vicissitudes
                            surrounding it, see <hi rend="i">Annals</hi> 151, 153, 171. Another sale
                            by Cumberland is recorded by Frits Lugt, <hi rend="i">Repertoire des
                                Catalogues des Ventes Publiques, 1660-1825</hi> (The Hague: Martinus
                            Nijhoff, 1938) in 1803, #6616, 28 May 1803, London “A Gentleman
                            Leaving Town to reside in the Country,” conducted by
                            Phillips.</note>
	<note id="n100"><hi rend="s">73</hi> Walters 121.</note>
	<note id="n101"><hi rend="s">74</hi> TS. “Collecta” 5,
                            December 1803; 8 May 1804, 10 October 1804 (MS. Douce e. 66, fol. 3<hi
rend="s">r</hi>, 5<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 7<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n102"><hi rend="s">75</hi> TS. “Collecta” 12 (MS.
                            Douce e. 66, 9<hi rend="s">v</hi>). This probably refers to the woodcut
                            B. 149 (160), <hi rend="i">Draftsman Drawing a Nude in the Manual of
                                Measurement</hi>, as in Walter E. Strauss, ed. <hi rend="i">Wood-Cuts and Wood
Blocks of Albrecht Dürer</hi> (New York:
                            Abaris, 1980) [SW 204]. The drawing, <hi rend="i">Women’s
                                Bath</hi>, reproduced in <hi rend="i">The Complete Drawings of
                                Albrecht Dürer</hi>, vol. I, ed. Walter E. Strauss (New York:
                            Abaris, 1974) 142 [SD 1493/4], was copied. See Campbell Dodgson,
                            “Rare Woodcuts in the Ashmolean Museum—I,” <hi rend="i">The Burlington
Magazine</hi> 63 (1930): 21-24, who notes
                            among Douce’s collection of Dürer and copies of
                            Dürer in the Ashmolean the “rare <hi rend="i">Women’s Bath</hi>, reproducing
in reverse
                            Dürer’s drawing of 1496,” but does not mention the
                                <hi rend="i">Draughtsman.</hi></note>
	<note id="n103"><hi rend="s">76</hi> TS. “Collecta” 13, June
                            1805 (MS. Douce e. 66, fol. 10<hi rend="s">v</hi>), perhaps referring to
                            what is listed by Bartsch as <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">The Triumph of Emperor
                                Maximilian</hi>,</corr> B. 139 (154), <hi rend="i">The Great Triumphal
                                Car</hi>, 1522, [SW 188]. See Dodgson 21, for the “not very
                            early (seventeenth century?) copy of the portraits of Maximilian
                            I” in the Douce collection.</note></p>
          <p>From 1807 to 1811, Douce serves as Keeper of the Department of Manuscripts in
                        the British Museum. Unlike Cumberland, who wrote and published several
                        books, Douce published, in addition to many submissions to the Society of
                        Antiquaries, only one important book, his 1807 <hi rend="i">Illustrations of
                            Shakspeare</hi>, with one section on the Morris Dance, and, in 1833, the
                        study on The Dance of Death.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104"
type="note">77</ref>
	<note id="n104"><hi rend="s">77</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 65; <hi rend="i">Illustrations of Shakspeare, and
                                of ancient manners: with dissertations on the clowns and fools of
                                Shakspeare; on the collection of popular tales entitled Gesta
                                Romanorum; and on the English morris dance</hi>, 2 vols. (London:
                            Longman, 1807).</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland’s sons, George Jr. and Sydney, move to London in 1808;
                        their father recommends that they look up well-placed men, including in his
                        list of names that of Mr. Douce.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105"
type="note">78</ref> The
                        young men, also liaisons to Blake, stay briefly at the home of Robert
                        Cromek, who in 1807 employs Blake to draw the illustrations for
                        Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n106" type="note">79</ref> Douce’s present and future friends are interested in
                        the book: Dawson Turner, whose correspondence with Douce begins in 1821,
                        mentions the “1st edition of Blake’s Blair’s
                        Grave” which he wants.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107"
type="note">80</ref> Among
                        Dodd’s papers is Cromek’s Prospectus for <hi rend="i">The
                            Grave</hi>, along with a brief biography of Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108" type="note">81</ref> Douce, however, appears not to have purchased 
<hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi>
	<note id="n105"><hi rend="s">78</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 209.</note>
	<note id="n106"><hi rend="s">79</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 209. For Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> and
                            Blake’s <corr type="emend">involvement</corr>, see Robert N. Essick and Morton Paley, <hi rend="i">Robert
Blair’s</hi> “<hi rend="i">The
                                Grave”: A study with facsimile</hi> (London: Scolar Press,
                            1982).</note>
	<note id="n107"><hi rend="s">80</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 5; <hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi> 72.</note>
	<note id="n108"><hi rend="s">81</hi> A favorable comment on the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> is quoted by Bentley
from the microfilm of B.L. Add. MS.
                            33,402, fol. 153, the papers of Thomas Dodd (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 171n4).
                            The Prospectus from B.L. Add. MS. 33,397, fol. 144, is reproduced in 
<hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi> 35, 36.</note></p>
          <p>Douce’s bequest to the Bodleian Library also includes the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi> of 1809 accompanying Blake’s
                            exhibition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n109"
type="note">82</ref> Bentley says that the
                        catalogues were “issued in unlabelled greyish-Blue wrappers . . . to
                        the ‘Fit audience . . . tho few’ who paid <hi rend="i">2s.6d.</hi> to see
Blake’s exhibition in 1809-10.”
                        Different from the undistributed ones, two mistakes in those issued
                        catalogues are corrected by Blake’s hand, leading Bentley to
                        conjecture that its possessors must have seen the exhibit in person. There
                        is, however, no mention in Douce’s “Collecta” of Blake
                        in 1809-10: even though Douce owned a corrected catalogue, whether he was
                        one of the few who saw the exhibition is unknown. 
<note id="n109"><hi rend="s">82</hi><hi rend="i"> BB</hi> 134-136, Copy H.</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland’s name begins to appear as one of Douce’s sources of
                        information in his small, but undated, note-book of queries.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n110" type="note">83</ref> The first letter from Cumberland in
                        the Douce correspondence is from Culver Street, Bristol, where Cumberland
                        finally settles in 1807. Between 1809 and 1834, Douce receives from
                        Cumberland at least 52 letters, touching not only on artistic matters, but
                        on radical political ones as well.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n111" type="note">84</ref> On
                        17 April 1809, Cumberland sends to Douce a mold of an Egyptian Torso, the
                        first of several gifts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n112"
type="note">85</ref>
	<note id="n110"><hi rend="s">83</hi> MS. Douce e. 62, 22<hi rend="s">v</hi>;
                            e. 63, 9<hi rend="s">v</hi>.</note>
	<note id="n111"><hi rend="s">84</hi> MS. Douce d. 21, 1; d. 22, 14; d. 23,
                            1; d. 24, 7; d. 25, 8; d. 26, 8; d. 27 11; d. 32, 3. See below for one
                            collected letter in <hi rend="i">MS.</hi> Douce d. 25 actually from
                            George Cumberland, Jr., not George Cumberland, Sr.</note>
	<note id="n112"><hi rend="s">85</hi> MS. Douce d. 21, fol. 221.</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland writes often to Blake about publishing his new method of engraving
                        without ever persuading him, and in 1810 Cumberland jots in his notebook:
                        “communicated to Douce my Plans of engraving [omitted] publish them
                        in Nicholson.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113"
type="note">86</ref> Continuing to
                        keep in touch with Douce, he gives Douce some prints of old little
                            Masters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n114"
type="note">87</ref> After selling his
                        Bonasone prints to the British Museum,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n115" type="note">88</ref> he replies to a Douce letter with information relative to
                        Cennino Cennini and Baron de Murr, topics mentioned in the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
Outline</hi>: in the same letter he thanks Douce for his
                            <hi rend="i">Morris Dance.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n116" type="note">89</ref>
                        The following year, Douce buys a Bonasone print of <hi rend="i">Elysium</hi>, perhaps
spurred by Cumberland’s own interest in this
                            artist.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n117" type="note">90</ref>
Systematically, although
                        with inaccurate orthography, Douce recorded in 1811 and 1812 purchases and
                        exchanges of books dealing with the history of art and prints, including
                        “Winckelman sur les arts. In exchange Priestley,” “De
                        Murr hist des graveurs. Deboffe,” and “Bartch’s [sic]
                        ‘Peintre graveur’ of Deboffe.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n118" type="note">91</ref> There is a rhythmic sequence between the letters
                        and the note-books: Douce asks questions of Cumberland, Cumberland responds,
                        Douce underlines significant passages in red ink and subsequently purchases
                        the referenced object, recording it in the “Collecta.” The
                        implication is that Douce gains information from Cumberland and follows up
                        on his advice. In July 1812, Cumberland writes mentioning the loss of Horne
                        Tooke, their mutual friend.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n119"
type="note">92</ref> Although
                        Cumberland uses phrases suggesting person to person contact with
                        Douce—“when we meet” or “we will talk
                        over,” other letters indicate that he fails to see Douce on visits
                        made to London.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n120"
type="note">93</ref> In the next year,
                        Cumberland calls on Blake, Cosway and Stothard.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n121" type="note">94</ref>
	<note id="n113"><hi rend="s">86</hi> For this correspondence see Gerald E.
                            Bentley Jr. and Martin Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi>
                            (Minneapolis: U of Minnesota Press, 1964) 63, citing Cumberland’s
                                <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> for 1810, B.L. Add. MSS. 36,520A, fols.
                            14-16. William Nicholson’s <hi rend="i">Journal of Natural
                                Philosophy, Chemistry and the Arts</hi> was the intended
                            publication.</note>
	<note id="n114"><hi rend="s">87</hi> TS. “Collecta” 45,
                            February 1811, #3 (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 1<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n115"><hi rend="s">88</hi> Lugt, <hi rend="i">D’estampes</hi> 55 (note 71 above), says the sale
was
                            1811.</note>
	<note id="n116"><hi rend="s">89</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 45, 8 April
                            1811.</note>
	<note id="n117"><hi rend="s">90</hi> TS. “Collecta” 49, June
                            1812, #7 (MS. Douce e. 67, 5<hi rend="s">v</hi>). This print is probably
                            the one now in the Ashmolean: D.IT 10.Roy., B.xv.139.101, <hi rend="i">Love caught
in the Elystan Fields and bound to a tree</hi>, 1563,
                            Giulio Bonasone, inventore.</note>
	<note id="n118"><hi rend="s">91</hi> TS. “Collecta” 47,
                            December 1811, #5; 49, June 1812, #10; 50, July 1812, #12, (MS. Douce e.
                            67, fols. 3<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 6<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 6<hi
rend="s">v</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n119"><hi rend="s">92</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 100, 15 July
                            1812.</note>
	<note id="n120"><hi rend="s">93</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 46<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 8 April 1811; MS. Douce d.
22, fol. 82<hi rend="s">r</hi>,
                            10 February 1812; fol. 142, 26 December 1813.</note>
	<note id="n121"><hi rend="s">94</hi> “Uncollected Authors”
                            46.</note></p>
          <p>In January 1813, Cumberland answers a question regarding an edition of
                        Boccaccio in English of 1634,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n122"
type="note">95</ref> by
                        spring, Cumberland sends Douce his “Tales.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n123" type="note">96</ref> In the “Collecta,” Douce enters:
                        “Mr. Cumberland gave me two curious Engl. editions of Bocaccio and of
                        the Q. of Navarre’s tales.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n124"
type="note">97</ref> By April, Douce appears to have bought the Tales.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n125" type="note">98</ref> Cumberland mentions to Douce his
                        plans for a publication and his trust in the print-seller Colnaghi.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n126" type="note">99</ref> Douce seems to have offered his help,
                        as Cumberland says he will be guided entirely by Douce’s advice in
                        regard to a publisher.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n127"
type="note">100</ref> This letter
                        ends: “God bless you &amp; keep you from Despotism,” one of
                        several allusions to their mutual aversion to the present political state.
                        In Douce’s “Curiosities of Engraving,” Cumberland is
                        mentioned twice in connection with prints by Bonasone: there are references
                        “to Cumberland’s letter to me of the 10th April 1813”
                        and to a page number in Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Bonasoni.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n128" type="note">101</ref>
	<note id="n122"><hi rend="s">95</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 110<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 19 January 1813.</note>
	<note id="n123"><hi rend="s">96</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fols. 117, 118, 28
                            March 1813.</note>
	<note id="n124"><hi rend="s">97</hi> TS. “Collecta” 53, March
                            1813, #8 (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 9<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n125"><hi rend="s">98</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 119<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 20 April 1813.</note>
	<note id="n126"><hi rend="s">99</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fols. 117, 118, 28
                            March 1813.</note>
	<note id="n127"><hi rend="s">100</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 120<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 12 April 1813.</note>
	<note id="n128"><hi rend="s">101</hi> “Curiosities” 23, 71
                            (note 51 above).</note></p>
          <p>This relationship becomes more intense in 1814. Cumberland must have sent his
                        manuscript to Douce, because he writes a letter apologizing for careless
                        errors in it due to hasty writing; the errors have been corrected by
                        Douce’s exacting scholarship.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n129"
type="note">102</ref>
                        In the same letter, Cumberland begins to renew his descriptions of his
                        collection of instructional prints, incorrectly called “the Tarocchi
                        Cards of Mantegna.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n130"
type="note">103</ref> These
                        were owned by other Englishmen of the period, including Douce;
                        Cumberland’s is one of the earliest extant sets. Cumberland mentions
                        specific ones, describing his “ancient plates” of the
                        “Prima Causa” and “an old half naked man and a
                            dog.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n131"
type="note">104</ref> Douce, interested
                        in playing cards, soon sees 
<pb id="p26-13" n="13"/>
Cumberland’s
                        collection, copying into his “Curiosities of Engraving” 
						<q>
                            Some Account of the 8° volume containing 50 prints by Boticello
                            [sic] or Maldivi mentioned in p. 43, and now, June 1814, in the
                            collection of Geo. Cumberland Esq. who lent me the book.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n132" type="note">105</ref></q>
Douce goes on to describe the book in great detail.
<note id="n129"><hi rend="s">102</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 162, 8 May 1814.</note>
	<note id="n130"><hi rend="s">103</hi> See Arthur M. Hind, <hi rend="i">Early
                                Italian Engraving</hi>, Vol. I (London: Quaritch Ltd., 1938) 221-40
                            for “Tarocchi cards”; Cumberland’s set at the Royal
                            Academy is the E Series. For illustrations of Cumberland’s
                            prints, including the <hi rend="i">Prima Causa</hi>, see Jay Levenson,
                            Konrad Oberhuber, and Jacquelyn L. Sheehan, <hi rend="i">Early Italian
                                Engravings from the National Gallery of Art</hi>, Exh. Cat.,
                            Washington, 1973, 81-157, esp. #66.</note>
	<note id="n131"><hi rend="s">104</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 163<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 8 May 1814.</note>
	<note id="n132"><hi rend="s">105</hi> “Curiosities”
                            47-57.</note></p>
          <p>The “Curiosities of Engraving” contains extensive notes and
                        plans for a book treating the subject of prints, but Douce’s
                        painstaking efforts never came to fruition, as his work was already
                        superseded by the now standard reference book on prints, Bartsch’s
                            <hi rend="i">Le Peintre-Graveur.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n133" type="note">106</ref> Revelatory of Douce’s careful method of research and
                        annotation are notes on the back of a duplicate of a Bonasone print still in
                        the Bodleian Portfolio, <hi rend="i">The Triumph of Love.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n134" type="note">107</ref> The Bodleian print bears the
                        following notations on its verso: “Bartsch XV.141, No. 106, See
                        Cumberland p. 75 No 200 The Elysium of Lovers, Felsina Pittrice di Malvasia,
                        1st vol, p. 75.” <note id="n133"><hi rend="s">106</hi> I thank Dr.
                            John Whiteley for this observation. Adam von Bartsch, [1757-1821], <hi rend="i">Le
Peintre-Graveur</hi>, 21 vols., Vienna: 1803-1821; see
                            now <hi rend="i">The Illustrated Bartsch</hi>, ed. Walter L. Strauss
                            (New York: Abaris Books, 1980).</note>
	<note id="n134"><hi rend="s">107</hi> Douce Portfolio, W.2.3c.70, <hi rend="i">The Triumph of Love.</hi> A
better version of the same
                            print, also from Douce’s collection, now is in the Ashmolean
                            Museum, D.IT 10.Roy., B.xv.141.106, <hi rend="i">The Triumph of
                                Love</hi>, 1545, “Bonahso.”</note></p>
          <p>A poignant and uncharacteristic self-pity breaks from Cumberland in a letter
                        in December 1814. The previous May, Cumberland had written: “If you
                        get the Bartsch book I would like to see it when I get to town.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n135" type="note">108</ref> Finally, in December, evidently
                        having tried to obtain the book of Colnaghi, he asks for the loan of
                        Douce’s Bartsch since he has no answer from the bookdealer. 
						<q> [Y]ou
                            have a thousand choice things to amuse you with, and live in the midst
                            of everything you want, while I am chained to a Rock among Savages.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n136" type="note">109</ref>
	<note id="n135"><hi rend="s">108</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 161, 1 May
                                1814.</note>
	<note id="n136"><hi rend="s">109</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 180<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 18 December
1814.</note></q>
By Christmas, the Bristol exile thanks Douce for finding the 4 volumes
                        of the Italian Schools by Bartsch, saying that George Junior will pay
                            him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n137" type="note">110</ref>
Cumberland received his
                        Bartsch in January and in a point by point refutation justifies in a letter
                        to Douce his own 1793 <hi rend="i">Bonasoni</hi>, denying this egotistical
                        German’s account of the beginning of printing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n138" type="note">111</ref>
	<note id="n137"><hi rend="s">110</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 183<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 25 December 1814.</note>
	<note id="n138"><hi rend="s">111</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fols. 186, 187, 5
                            January 1815.</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland also advises Douce, this time about Giambattista della Porta. 
		<q>
                            [I] think if you ever do find him he will be a fragment—for no
                            other reason will people part with such singular things—&amp;
                            these sort of books of Physiognomy I have generally found
                                mutilated.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n139"
type="note">112</ref>
	<note id="n139"><hi rend="s">112</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 183<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 25 December 1814,
referring to the Italian
                                physiognomist who wrote <hi rend="i">De humana physiognomonia</hi>
                                in 1586.</note></q>
In September 1815, Douce finds and buys “Porta’s
                            physognomia”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n140"
type="note">113</ref> and, in
                        April 1816, buys from Smith “Bonasoni’s Gods.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n141" type="note">114</ref> The last entry in December 1818
                        includes “Cumberl. outlines” indicating that Douce finally
                        purchased Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n142" type="note">115</ref>
	<note id="n140"><hi rend="s">113</hi> TS. “Collecta” 63, #4
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 20<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n141"><hi rend="s">114</hi> TS. “Collecta” 66, #17
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 24<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n142"><hi rend="s">115</hi> TS. “Collecta” 76, #14
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 32<hi rend="s">v</hi>). My thanks to Mr. Hurst
                            for confirming this reading in the original MS. fol. 32<hi rend="s">v</hi>.
Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Outlines of the
                                Ancients</hi> (see note 21 above) was not published until 1829 so
                            the entry must refer to his earlier book, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
                                Outline.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Although one surviving letter indicates continuing contact, correspondence
                        between Cumberland and Douce falls off somewhat between 1815 and 1821, as
                        Cumberland readies his book for publication.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n143" type="note">116</ref> He says “I dread the [illeg.] of printing” and
                        notes that “[t]ruth speaking is a dangerous habit here.” Not
                        until 1827 will the book, <hi rend="i">An Essay on the utility of collecting
                            the best works of the ancient engravers of the Italian School</hi>, be
                            published.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n144"
type="note">117</ref>
	<note id="n143"><hi rend="s">116</hi> MS. Douce d. 23, fol. 82, 6 May
                            1818.</note>
	<note id="n144"><hi rend="s">117</hi> See “Uncollected
                            Authors” 49-50, for details of the negotiations with Robert
                            Triphook as publisher and that it was finally sold in 1827 by three
                            other booksellers, including Colnaghi. <hi rend="i">An Essay on the
                                utility of collecting the best works of the ancient engravers of the
                                Italian School, accompanied by A Critical Catalogue, with
                                interesting anecdotes of the engravers, of a chronological series of
                                rare and valuable prints, from the earliest practice of the art in
                                Italy to the year 1549, now deposited in the British Museum and
                                Royal Academy</hi> (London, 1827).</note></p>
          <p>Financial necessity leads Cumberland to dispose of his other Italian
                        engravings, including the Tarocchi Cards, to the Royal Academy.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n145" type="note">118</ref> In July 1820, Douce notes that
                        “Smith gave me cast of Cumberland’s (now his)
                            hermaphrodite.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n146"
type="note">119</ref> Yet, in
                        the midst of his own need, one of Cumberland’s more endearing but
                        aggravating traits, his ceaseless intercession on behalf of his friends and
                        relatives, is revealed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n147"
type="note">120</ref> In an
                        undated letter,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n148"
type="note">121</ref> he asks Douce to
                        recommend his son’s <hi rend="i">Spanish Lives</hi>, Douce scratches
                        in the margin, “Nothing but self, self &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> from
                        all my worthy friends.” George Jr. had returned to London from Lisbon
                        in 1815; <hi rend="i">Views in Spain and Portugal</hi> was published by
                            1820.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n149" type="note">122</ref>
	<note id="n145"><hi rend="s">118</hi><hi rend="i"> Annals</hi> 58.</note>
	<note id="n146"><hi rend="s">119</hi> TS. “Collecta” 82, #16
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, 38<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n147"><hi rend="s">120</hi> Instances showing this abound in his
                            correspondence. Francis Greenacre, <hi rend="i">The Bristol School of
                                Artists: Francis Danby and Painting in Bristol, 1810-1840</hi>, Exh.
                            Cat., City Art Gallery, Bristol, 4 September-10 November 1973, no.
                            98-99, 250, alludes to this trait, noting that Sir Thomas Lawrence and
                            Stothard were the main contacts through whom Cumberland, after moving to
                            Bristol, helped almost every English artist.</note>
	<note id="n148"><hi rend="s">121</hi> MS. Douce d. 29, n.d., fol. 190<hi rend="s">r</hi>, addressed to
Kensington Square, where Douce lived
                            from 1821 to 1825, proposed here as written probably shortly after
                            1821.</note>
	<note id="n149"><hi rend="s">122</hi> See “Uncollected
                            Authors” 48.</note></p>
          <p>Dawson Turner writes to Docue in the spring of 1821.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n150" type="note">123</ref> Turner had earlier directly contacted Blake; on 9
                        June 1818, Blake sent him a price list for some illuminated books.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n151" type="note">124</ref> D’Israeli too is interested
                        in Blake: on 7 January 1819, he writes to Dyer that “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>.
D’Israeli wants as soon as possible a copy of
                        Blake’s Young.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n152"
type="note">125</ref> T. F.
                        Dibdin, a Douce correspondent,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n153"
type="note">126</ref> whose
                            <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi> provide recollections of Douce, recalled
                        that Blake visited him in the summer of 1816 to talk about the minor poems
                        of Milton; he subsequently purchases from Blake a copy of the <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n154" type="note">127</ref> Dibdin
                        too was aware of Dyer’s library, commenting in 1810 on a catalogue,
                        saying that it contains twenty thousand volumes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n155" type="note">128</ref> Blake had become famous enough to be included in
                            <hi rend="i">A Biographical Dictionary of the Living Authors of Great
                            Britain and Ireland.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n156"
type="note">129</ref>
                        Despite this fame and evidence of direct and indirect contacts between Blake
                        and Douce’s friends, Douce and Blake do not seem to have met after
                        the possible contact at Blake’s exhibit. <note id="n150"><hi rend="s">123</hi> MS.
Douce d. 23, fol. 240, 3 April 1821.</note>
	<note id="n151"><hi rend="s">124</hi><hi rend="i"> BB</hi> 118-120.</note>
	<note id="n152"><hi rend="s">125</hi><hi rend="i"> BR Supp.</hi> 73, quoted from a photocopy of the MS in
                            Pierpont Morgan Library.</note>
	<note id="n153"><hi rend="s">126</hi> See MS. Douce d. 32, from 1808 to
                            after 1832 for these letters.</note>
	<note id="n154"><hi rend="s">127</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 242-243; Viscomi, citing 
<hi rend="i">Reminiscences
                                of a Literary Life</hi> (London, 1836) 2: 787.</note>
	<note id="n155"><hi rend="s">128</hi> Maxted 66n74 (see note 56
                            above).</note>
	<note id="n156"><hi rend="s">129</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 244.</note></p>
          <p>Blake too had to sell his collection of prints about the same time, Colnaghi
                        handling the sale.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n157"
type="note">130</ref> In April 1821
                        Douce records the purchase of “Blake’s marr of heaven &amp;
                        hell Dyer,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n158"
type="note">131</ref> referring to Copy
                        B of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> now at the Bodleian
                            Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n159"
type="note">132</ref> That by
                        “Dyer” is meant Gilbert Dyer, the bookseller to Dibdin and
                        D’Israeli, seems certain.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n160"
type="note">133</ref>
	<note id="n157"><hi rend="s">130</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 276, 395. Records about the sale have been
                            lost.</note>
	<note id="n158"><hi rend="s">131</hi> TS. “Collecta” 86, #4
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 40<hi rend="s">v</hi>); <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                            289.</note>
	<note id="n159"><hi rend="s">132</hi> See note 7 above.</note>
	<note id="n160"><hi rend="s">133</hi> See Viscomi 56n29 for “Bentley
                            has not identified Dyer, other than to suggest “(George?)
                            Dyer,” by which he probably means the poet (1755-1841) (<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
289). Perhaps “Dyer” was the
                            “honest, worthy, painstaking bookseller, the brother of the late
                            Rev. Mr. Dwyer,” whom Dibdin mentions in <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi> (1:
194). Essick suggests Charles George Dyer, a
                            London printseller, noting that Bentley withdraws his tentative earlier
                            suggestion that the seller may have been the author George Dyer 
(<hi rend="i">SP</hi> 30). Bentley notes there is no London bookseller by
                            the name of Dyer and speculates correctly that D’Israeli’s
                            Dyer is Douce’s Dyer (<hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi>
                        73n3).</note></p>
          <p>Correspondence from “G. Dyer” to Douce begins in 1805, with a
                        note in which Dyer thanks Douce for a favorable account of his book’s
                            principles.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n161"
type="note">134</ref> From Dyer’s
                        description of how he had to trace the names of our Rivers, Hills, Vallies
                        and Towns in an etymological search, the book must be <hi rend="i">A
                            restoration of the ancient modes of bestowing names on the rivers,
                            hills, vallies, plains, and settlements of Britain; recorded by no
                            ancient, nor explored by any modern author</hi> . . ., Exeter, printed
                        for G. Dyer, 1805.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n162"
type="note">135</ref> Dyer also
                        encloses “the set of Adam,” indicating that Douce was now
                        making purchases of him. In September 1808, Douce had dealings with Dyer;
                        his name continues to appear yearly in Douce’s note-book of
                            purchases.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n163"
type="note">136</ref> Dyer, like other
                        Exeter booksellers, probably had agents in London so that he could
                        conveniently make purchases these;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n164" type="note">137</ref>
                        dealing with him would have been easy. It is not far-fetched to suppose that
                        Dyer may have purchased Blake books at the Colnaghi sale, <pb id="p26-14" n="14"/>
given that he knew that collectors like Douce, D’Israeli
                        and Dibdin were interested in the artist. This adds to our information
                        regarding the wide-ranging practices of bookselling and collecting proposed
                        by Viscomi. <note id="n161"><hi rend="s">134</hi> MS. Douce d. 21, 15
                            December 1805, fol. 60.</note>
	<note id="n162"><hi rend="s">135</hi> As determined from the <hi rend="i">National Union Catalog.</hi></note>
	<note id="n163"><hi rend="s">136</hi> TS. “Collecta” 28, Sept.
                            1808, between #9 and #10 (MS. Douce e. 66, fol. 28<hi rend="s">v</hi>).
                            Thereafter, between 1808 and 1821, Dyer’s name appears 22 times
                            at least one a year.</note>
	<note id="n164"><hi rend="s">137</hi> Maxted 66.</note></p>
          <p>Seven letters and a gift come from Cumberland in 1824, as Douce enters in the
                        “Collecta,” “Mr. Cumberland gave me 3 antique
                            pastes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n165"
type="note">138</ref> The name of the
                        gem-maker Tassie, whom Cumberland first championed in <hi rend="i">Thoughts
                            on Outline</hi>, occurs in Douce’s list of acquisitions in 1805.
                        Cumberland considered Tassie a preeminent gem-maker of ancient and modern
                        copies: Tassie had made molds and paste reproductions of some of
                        Cumberland’s and Cracherode’s collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n166" type="note">139</ref> In 1824, Cumberland, responding to a question from
                        Douce about Tassie’s processes, tells Douce to make inquiries of
                        Tassie as to how he makes his gems: “He will show you as he showed
                        me.” Cumberland ends with “God send you a speedy
                            Settlement.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n167"
type="note">140</ref> This last
                        wish may indicate the reason for Cumberland’s renewed interest in
                        Douce. Douce was involved at the time in negotiations related to settling
                        the estate of Nollekens from which Douce eventually inherited enough money
                        to enable him to collect on a greater scale than before. 
<note id="n165"><hi rend="s">138</hi> TS. “Collecta” 95, January 1824 (MS.
                            Douce e. 68, fol. 1<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n166"><hi rend="s">139</hi><hi rend="i"> Thoughts</hi> 25, 29. At the Scottish National Portrait
                            Gallery there is a unique copy of a “Manuscript Catalogue”
                            by Tassie called “Tassie Gems MS. Supplement to Raspe.”
                            Filled with 2889 entries of gems, it lists multiple examples of
                            reproductions by Tassie of gems taken from Cumberland’s
                            collection and at least one from Cracherode’s, #550. My thanks to
                            Miss Helen Watson who kindly assisted me.</note>
	<note id="n167"><hi rend="s">140</hi> MS. Douce d. 24, fols. 210, 211, 20
                            January 1824.</note></p>
          <p>The next month, Cumberland, visiting his sick brother, Richard, at Driffield,
                        writes a long letter to Douce, referring to the disposition of his print
                        collection, which he says are “out to good pasture in the Academy and
                        the Museum.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n168"
type="note">141</ref> Noting that he
                        received from Irvine in Rome a copy of the book of Cennino Cennini’s
                            <hi rend="i">Treatise on Painting</hi> published at Rome 1821 by G.
                        Tambroni, he tells Douce that the first notice about it appeared in his 
<hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n169" type="note">142</ref>
Douce also owns Cennino’s <hi rend="i">Treatise</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n170"
type="note">143</ref> and the subject
                        of priority of knowledge becomes a disputed topic, as Cumberland shows by a
                        querulous comment. 
						<q> You say you had Cennino di Cennini before I wrote
                            about him— that is news, as I believe and know he was never
                            printed till very lately—perhaps you have a copy of the
                            Manuscript which De Murr of Augusburg [sic], the Jesuit, told me 40 yrs
                            ago he never saw and gave me the clue to find it? . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n171" type="note">144</ref></q>
The next year, Cumberland tries unsuccessfully to see
Douce three
                        times. <note id="n168"><hi rend="s">141</hi> MS. Douce d. 24, fol. 315, 3
                            December 1824.</note>
	<note id="n169"><hi rend="s">142</hi> For Cennino, see Joan K. Stemmler,
                            “Cennino, Cumberland, Blake and Early Painting
                            Techniques,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 17 (1984): 145-48.</note>
	<note id="n170"><hi rend="s">143</hi> See 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>,
                            C. 548, Cennini, Trattato, Giuseppi Tambroni, 8°, Roma,
                            1821.</note>
	<note id="n171"><hi rend="s">144</hi> MS. Douce d. 25, fol. 41<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 9 March 1825.</note></p>
          <p>In 1824 or 1825, Douce purchases Blake’s print of Canterbury Pilgrims
                        from Hurst and Robinson for £3/3/2.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n172" type="note">145</ref> It is a third state, made between 1810 and 1820, now
                        deposited in the Ashmolean Museum.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n173" type="note">146</ref> A
                        steady correspondence about Cumberland’s Runic ring which he sent to
                        Douce results in the publication in <hi rend="i">Archaeologia</hi> in 1827
                        by Douce of a “Dissertation on the Runic Jasper Ring belonging to
                        George Cumberland, Esq. of Bristol.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n174" type="note">147</ref>
	<note id="n172"><hi rend="s">145</hi> It is listed twice in TS.
                            “Collecta” 97, November 1824, (Douce MS. e. 68, fol. 2<hi rend="s">v</hi>),
“Blake’s print of Canterbury
                            pilgrimage. Hurst,” and TS. “Collecta” 98, March
                            1825, #6 (Douce MS. e. 68, fol. 3<hi rend="s">v</hi>),
                            “Blake’s Canterbury Pilgr. Hurst &amp; Robins.”
                            This is probably a double entry, as there is but one state in the
                            Ashmolean Museum. Douce had noted in TS. “Collecta” 91,
                            April 1822 (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 45<hi rend="s">r</hi>) that he now
                            bought of Hurst &amp; Robinson, formerly Woodburne. The price is in
                            pencil on the verso.</note>
	<note id="n173"><hi rend="s">146</hi> See <hi rend="i">SP</hi> 60-89,
                            especially 63 for Canterbury Pilgrims, Ashmolean impression numbered
                            3D.</note>
	<note id="n174"><hi rend="s">147</hi> MS. Douce d. 29, n.d., fol. 191. This
                            letter should be given a t.a.q. of 20 January 1824 because it logically
                            precedes MS. Douce d. 24, fol. 210, 20 January 1824 in its subject. See
                            also <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> 5 (<hi rend="i">Archeologia</hi> 21
                            [1827]: 119-27); “Uncollected Authors” 36, for the
                            information that Stothard broke the ring.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s name appears in a letter to Douce not sent by George
                        Cumberland, but by his son, George Cumberland Jr. Taking on his
                        father’s role as advocate, the younger Cumberland writes on 14 June
                        1826: 
						<q> If you call upon M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Blake The Artist you will
                            see a very fine work of his just published but not in the Shops. I
                            mention it for that reason if you can recommend it to notice you will
                            oblige.<lb/>
 Yours very truly<lb/>
 G. Cumberland J<hi rend="s">r</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n175"
type="note">148</ref>
	<note id="n175"><hi rend="s">148</hi> MS. Douce d. 25, fol. 194,
                                Glo’ster Cottage, Old Brompton.</note></q>
Of interest is the fact that
George Junior assumes a knowledge by Douce
                        of the address of Blake which may suggest that the two had met face to face.
                        The elder Cumberland follows up on this subject in January 1827. Referring
                        to “a great original,” he continues: 
						<q> . . . and so is Blake
                            who has lately published a strange and clever book of Job in 22 plates
                            all line engravings as ever I saw—but I think it a bad education
                            not to say I [illeg.] to represent as he has done, the Creator as an old
                            man with a long beard whether by Rafael or him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n176" type="note">149</ref>
	<note id="n176"><hi rend="s">149</hi> MS. Douce d. 26, fols. 8<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 21 January
1827.</note></q></p>
          <p>Blake writes a grateful letter to Cumberland on 12 April 1827, in which he
                        mentions the tiny copper card plate Cumberland had given him to
                            ornament.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n177"
type="note">150</ref> After Blake’s
                        death on 12 August 1827, Cumberland writes to his widow Catherine that
                        “latterly I have not only been unable to continue Collecting but have
                        even sold all I had Collected—yet still preserving all I possessed of
                        his graver.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n178"
type="note">151</ref> Douce, in
                        contrast, seems not to have valued the later work of Cumberland or Blake,
                        since he purchases neither Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Essay</hi> nor
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job.</hi> In 1827, Douce notes that “R.
                        Stothard gave me a cast of a compartment of a sculptured chest in G.
                        Cumberland’s possn (or fragments of one),” an indication of
                        the value to Douce of Cumberland’s scattered former possessions.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n179" type="note">152</ref> Continuing to purchase books and
                        prints brought to his attention by Cumberland, he acquires by 1829
                        DeMurr’s own copy of “Nuremb. library” and at the sale
                        of the collection of Sir Thomas Lawrence buys more prints by Bonasone.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n180" type="note">153</ref>
	<note id="n177"><hi rend="s">150</hi> “Uncollected Authors”
                            51.</note>
	<note id="n178"><hi rend="s">151</hi> “Uncollected Authors”
                            53; Keynes 172, 25 November 1827 (see note 37 above).</note>
	<note id="n179"><hi rend="s">152</hi> TS. “Collecta” 103,
                            January 1827, #6 (MS. Douce e. 68, fol. 7<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n180"><hi rend="s">153</hi> TS. “Collecta” 110, June
                            1829, #4; 113, May 1830, #3 (MS. Douce e. 68, fol. 13<hi
rend="s">v</hi>).</note></p>
          <p>At Douce’s death in 1834, Cumberland, along with D’Israeli,
                        Turner and others, is remembered in Douce’s will with a ring, valued
                        at five guineas.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n181"
type="note">154</ref> The printed
                        portraits of Cowper, Cumberland, Holcroft, Tooke, Barry, Bewick, Cosway,
                        Fuseli and Richard Brothers, are among the 634 which Douce assembled during
                        his lifetime.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n182"
type="note">155</ref> However, there is no
                        representation among either the portraits of painters and engravers or those
                        of remarkable characters, of the one whose work is now the most famous,
                        William Blake. <note id="n181"><hi rend="s">154</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 13,
14.</note>
	<note id="n182"><hi rend="s">155</hi> As listed in Scott, Vol. II, fols.
                            76-96 ff. (note 6 above) and found in Portfolios, PO. 135, New Bodleian,
                            Room 132, numbered 43, 44, 87, 176, 204, 211, 230, 246, 479.</note></p>
          <p>Thomas Dodd, the now retired printseller and auctioneer, was given the task
                        of writing the catalogue of Douce’s prints.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n183" type="note">156</ref> In 1835, commenting on the pages in <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>
where Cumberland praised Blake for his
                        “facsimiles of my originals,” Dodd said “Mr
                        Cumberland’s inventions in outline as far as his hand hath been
                        concerned in them is not in unison with his ideas—. . . However, some
                        few of the accompanying pieces are etch’d by <hi rend="i">W.
                            Blake</hi>, which are decidedly more correct than those produced by the
                            author.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n184"
type="note">157</ref> Of
                        Cumberland’s Bonasone catalogue, it was the opinion of Dodd that the
                        author possessed only the “slightest knowledge of engravings by early
                        italian artists” and that his catalogue of old prints was
                        “vague, erroneous and ridiculous.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n185" type="note">158</ref>
	<note id="n183"><hi rend="s">156</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 17. Found inadequate and never printed,
                            Dodd’s handwritten Catalogue of the Prints &amp; Drawings, c.
                            1836-40, the “Fair Copy” of the catalogue with notes and
                            indexes by Douce, is now in the Douce Room at the Ashmolean Museum as
                            Mr. John Whiteley kindly showed me.</note>
	<note id="n184"><hi rend="s">157</hi> Cited in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 56 and
                                <hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi> 12, from British Library, Add. MS.
                            33,398, fol. 257.</note>
	<note id="n185"><hi rend="s">158</hi><hi rend="i"> Bibliography</hi> 12.</note></p>
          <p>In the same year, the remainder of Cumberland’s collection was sold by
                        auction in London at Christie &amp; Manson: <pb id="p26-15" n="15"/>
among
                        the books listed were DeMurr’s <hi rend="i">Bibliotheque de
                            Peinture</hi>, Malvasia’s <hi rend="i">Felsina Pittrice</hi>,
                        Tambroni’s <hi rend="i">Trattato</hi>, Bartsch’s <hi rend="i">Italian School</hi>,
and Vasari’s <hi rend="i">Vite di
                            Pittori</hi>, books from which he liberally dispensed information to his
                        fellow antiquarians and friends.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n186"
type="note">159</ref>
                        Sadly, he was forced to sell too the productions of his old friend, William
                        Blake. Living frugally in Bristol, Cumberland died at age 94, still writing
                        letters exploring his new interests and supporting friends to the end.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n187" type="note">160</ref>
	<note id="n186"><hi rend="s">159</hi><hi rend="i"> A Catalogue of the Collection of Books on Art, Antique
                                Bronzes, Terra Cottas, and Coins, the property of George Cumberland,
                                Esq.</hi>, Christie &amp; Manson, St. James’s Square,
                            London, 1835.</note>
	<note id="n187"><hi rend="s">160</hi> For the Bristol years, see Greenacre
                            (note 120 above).</note></p>
          <p>The Bodleian Library’s body of archival material bequeathed by Douce
                        deserves more than the quinquennial wakening predicted for it by Sir
                        Frederic Madden when he said it would be disturbed but once in a lustre.
                        Lustre reverberates with lustrous, a term we might apply to Douce’s
                        bequest, for its reflected light shines into darker corners of other
                        histories, illuminating them. My sympathies for Cumberland, a good-hearted
                        and expansive gentleman, and my particular interest in Blake, led me to
                        concentrate on them. Thus additional information about Blake’s <hi rend="i">Gates of
Paradise</hi> was uncovered, the way in which Douce
                        drew upon Cumberland’s knowledge was brought to light, and three new
                        letters in which Blake is mentioned were found. Other of Douce’s
                        letters from his wide circle of friends which I “disturbed”
                        are equally fascinating and informative. Douce’s careful annotations,
                        scrupulous scholarship, meticulous cataloguing, and most of all, concern for
                        what we today call cultural history,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n188" type="note">161</ref>
                        make his legacy to us particularly useful in discovering more about
                        interactions among persons of learning in the eighteenth century. 
<note id="n188"><hi rend="s">161</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 64.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p26-16-18" n="16-18" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
