<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Elusive Ladies</title>
        <author n="Bentley">Elizabeth B. Bentley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>E.B. Bentley</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Srigley</name>
              <name>Joan K. Stemmler</name>
              <name>Julia M. Wright</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <pb id="p26-30" n="30"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Elusive Ladies</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>E. B. <name>Bentley</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
		<q> The angels keep their ancient places<lb/>
 Turn but a stone, and start a
                        wing!<lb/>
 ’Tis ye, ’tis your estrangèd faces<lb/>
 That
                        miss the many-splendored thing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n216"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n216"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Francis Thomson, “The Kingdom of
                            God,” stanza 4.</note></q>
          <p>Two engravings executed on one plate by William Blake in 1782 have long been
                        known and mentioned and speculated about, but the book for which they were
                        intended has never been clearly identified. It has even been suggested that
                        the book was never published. The engravings I am dealing with are inscribed
                            “<hi rend="i">A Lady in the full Dress, &amp; another in the
                            most fashionable Undress now worn</hi>” and “<hi rend="i">The Morning
Amusements of her Royal Highness the Princess Royal &amp;
                            her 4 Sisters</hi>” (illus 1). These two designs after Thomas
                        Stothard are to be found in the British Museum Print Room. A copy of the
                        book in which the engravings appeared has not been discovered, but I believe
                        that a small volume in the Huntington Library provides very clear
                        indications of what we should seek and therefore increases the likelihood of
                        turning up a copy of the ephemeral book in which the prints were
                        published.</p>
          <corr type="emend" rend="plain">
			  <figure n="Blake.Stothard.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="305">
				<figTranscr>A Lady in the full Dress, &amp; another in the<lb/>
				most fashionable Undress now worn.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				The Morning Amusements of her Royal Highness the Princess Royal &amp; her 4 Sisters.<lb/>
				Published by J. Johnson St. Paul’s Church Yard Novr I, 1782.</figTranscr>
				<head>1. Blake’s engravings of Stothard’s designs for <hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket
Memorandum-Book</hi>
								(1782), in the British Museum (reproduced from the photograph supplied
								by Robert N. Essick and used in his <hi rend="i">Separate Plates of
									William Blake</hi> [1983]).</head>
				<figDesc><corr type="emend">Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</corr></figDesc>
			  </figure>
          </corr>
          <p>Those who search for Blake engravings have long known from Gilchrist’s
                        biography of the existence of engravings after Thomas Stothard of
                        “two frontispieces to Dodsley’s <hi rend="i">Lady’s
                            Pocket Book</hi>—‘The morning amusements of H.R.H. the
                        Princess Royal and her four sisters’ (1782), and ‘A Lady in
                        fulldress’ with another ‘in the most fashionable undress now
                        worn’ (1783).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n217"
type="note">2</ref> Gilchrist
                        does not specify where he had noticed these illustrations, and the reference
                        to “1783” would appear to be an error. In <hi rend="i">Thomas
                            Stothard, R.A.</hi>, A. C. Coxhead said the prints were designed by
                        Stothard for <hi rend="i">The Lady’s Magazine</hi>, but he does not
                        name any engraver. He based his list on the designs by Stothard which were
                        to be found in the Print Room of the British Museum but confessed that he
                        had not been able to find any copy of the magazine with all the plates
                        intact and implied that he had not found Stothard’s designs of either
                        “Morning Amusements” or “A Lady in full dress”
                        in <hi rend="i">The Lady’s Magazine.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n218" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n217"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life
                                of William Blake</hi>, “<hi rend="i">Pictor
                            Ignotus</hi>,” 2 vols. (London and Cambridge: Macmillan and Co.,
                            1863) 1: 51 and 2: 259.</note>
	<note id="n218"><hi rend="s">3</hi> A. C. Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas
                                Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London: Bullen, 1906) 42-47.</note></p>
          <p>In 1912, Archibald G. B. Russell listed the two Stothard designs with Blake
                        named as the engraver and joined Gilchrist in attributing them to <hi rend="i">The
Lady’s Pocket Book</hi> (edited by Dodsley),
                        repeated Gilchrist’s 1782 and 1783 dates, and declared that
                        “The numbers for 1782 and 1783 contain frontispieces engraved in line
                        by Blake <corr type="emend">after</corr> Stothard.” This last assertion was simply
taken from
                        Gilchrist and was not based on the discovery of these
                        “numbers.” He added that the two plates printed side by side
                        on a single sheet were in the Robert Balmanno collection of
                        Stothard’s works in the Print Room of the British Museum and noted
                        that the periodical “is not to be found in the British Museum and the
                        writer has been unable to meet with it elsewhere.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n219" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n219"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Archibald G. B. Russell, <hi rend="i">The Engravings of William
Blake</hi> (London: Grant Richards, Ltd.,
                            1912) 142.</note></p>
          <p>Geoffrey Keynes in his 1921 bibliography of Blake also located the elusive
                        ladies in the publication named by Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">The Lady’s
                            Pocket Book</hi>, and added the imprint information inscribed 
<pb id="p26-31" n="31"/>
<figure n="Titlepage.LadiesPocketBook.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="459">
	<head>2. Title page of <hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket
                                    Memorandum-Book</hi> for 1780 (1779), courtesy of the Henry
                                E.</head>
	<figDesc>Huntington Library.</figDesc>
</figure> on the engraving: “<hi rend="i">The Morning Amusements of
                            her Royal Highness the Princess Royal &amp; her 4 Sisters. Published by
                            J. Johnson . . . Nov</hi><hi rend="s">r</hi> I, 1782 <hi rend="i">Stothard del
Blake Sc.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n220" type="note">5</ref> Keynes tried to
solve the problem introduced by the Johnson
                        imprint for the design intended for a Dodsley publication by supposing that
                        the publication was “Edited by Dodsley for J. Johnson 1782,”
                        but he confessed that he had never been able to find the elusive
                        “volume.” He did not say why he thought it was edited by
                        [James] Dodsley for Johnson. <note id="n220"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Geoffrey
                            Keynes, <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William Blake</hi> (New York: The
                            Grolier Club, 1921) 226.</note></p>
          <p>Upon becoming a reader at the Bodleian Library (1953) and the British Museum
                        [Library] (1958), my first tasks were prolonged by fruitless searches for
                            <hi rend="i">The Ladies/Lady’s Pocket Book</hi> and variations
                        upon the title. When Bentley and Nurmi published their bibliography, they
                        reviewed previous findings about the Pocket Book, added that the Rosenwald
                        collection contained a proof impression of “The Morning
                        Amusements” design, speculated that the publication may have been a
                        descendant of Robert Dodsley’s <hi rend="i">The Ladies New Memorandum
                            Book</hi>
<figure n="Prints.LadiesPocketBook.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="434">
	<head>3. The two facing prints in <hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite
                                    Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi> for 1780 (1779), courtesy of the
                                Huntington Library.</head>
</figure> for 1758, and suggested that Gilchrist’s Dodsley must have
                        been Robert’s (1703-64) brother James (1724-97).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n221" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n221"><hi rend="s">6</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., &amp; Martin K.
                            Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: University
                            of Minnesota Press, 1964) 136.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, the descendent of <hi rend="i">A Blake
                            Bibliography</hi>, lists the work as “UNTRACED.” The entry
                        offers as “prime evidence [that the <hi rend="i">Pocket Book</hi>
                        existed] the two plates on one leaf in the BMPR”: 
						<q> 1. <hi rend="i">‘The Morning
amusements of her Royal Highness the Princess
                                Royal &amp; her 4 Sisters.’ ‘Stothard del.’,
                                ‘Blake sc.’, ‘Published by J. Johnson S<hi rend="s">t</hi> Paul’s
Church Yard, Nov<hi rend="s">r</hi> I.1782’.</hi> (Design size: 12.6 × 9.6cm).
                            (Proofs are also in the Royal Academy [before title] and the Rosenwald
                            Collection.)<lb/>
<lb/>
 2. <hi rend="i">‘A Lady in the full Dress,
                                &amp; another in the most fashionable Undress now worn.’
                                ‘T.S. del’, ‘W.B. sc’</hi> (design size:
                            6.5 × 9.6 cm). (A proof with only Blake’s name is in the
                            Royal Academy.)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n222"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n222"><hi rend="s">7</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
Press, 1977) 591.</note></q></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> lists nine works with variations of the
                        Gilchrist title which had proved not to be the book with the plates engraved
                        by Blake after Stothard or to contain illustrations which might fit the
                        titles given on those in the Print Room, and also comments: “The
                        title was casually used, and Stothard signed a receipt of 11 April 1795 for
                        ‘sixteen guineas [<hi rend="i">for</hi>] two drawings for
                        Lady’s [Pocket Book <hi rend="i">del</hi>]
                            Maggazien.’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n223"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n223"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The receipt is in Princeton University
                            Library (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 592).</note></p>
          <p>Robert N. Essick has not only diligently joined in the search but also has
                        assisted searchers to identify what they were seeking by his meticulous
                        descriptions of the impressions in the Royal Academy, the British Museum and
                        the Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C. and by
                        reproductions of the two designs which have proved so elusive.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n224" type="note">9</ref> Like Coxhead, he looked vainly in <hi rend="i">The Lady’s
Magazine</hi>, and he notes the paradox of
                        placing an engraving bearing a Johnson imprint in a magazine published by G.
                        G. J. and J. Robinson. <note id="n224"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Robert N. Essick,
                                <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake</hi> (Princeton:
                            Princeton University Press, 1983) 239-41 and figures 108-09. They are
                            omitted from his <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
                                Illustrations</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991), because he
                            excludes “plates probably executed for publication in books but
                            known only through separate impressions” (vi).</note></p>
          <p>I cannot claim that the hunt was strongly publicized. When Shelley M. Bennett
                        published <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard: The Mechanisms of Art Patronage in
                            England Circa 1800</hi>, she cited Coxhead’s descriptions of our
                        elusive ladies in relation to the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine.</hi> She
                        also cited Bentley and Essick and said Essick doubts the book was ever
                        published and Bentley lists the book as “untraced.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n225" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n225"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Thomas
                                Stothard</hi> (Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1988) 65-66.
                            The “1778 volume” of “<hi rend="i">The Ladies
                                Comlete Pocket Book</hi>” which she locates in the
                            “British Library (P.P. 2469 cl [I])” is, according to the
                            British Library Catalogue, for 1769, not
                        “1778.”</note></p>
          <pb id="p26-32" n="32"/>
          <p>Many librarians are amused by my searches and others try to remind me that
                        this is a search for very “ephemeral stuff.” I have long
                        realized that it would probably be by serendipity if the book with
                        Blake’s and Stothard’s illustrations were ever found, but I
                        have clung to my conviction that it would turn up some time, some where.
                        Over the years I have looked for a <hi rend="i">Lady’s Pocket
                            Book</hi> in collections in India, China, Australia, New Zealand, Hong
                        Kong, Japan, Taiwan, Guatemala, Algeria, Austria, France, Germany, England,
                        Canada, the United States, and elsewhere. At the Bodleian in July 1991, I
                        checked the microfiche copy of the <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century Short
                            Title Catalogue</hi> without success. In the late autumn I looked for
                        the title at the Lilly Library in Bloomington, Indiana, and the Spencer
                        Library in Lawrence, Kansas. The librarians were eager to help find a 
<hi rend="i">Ladies Pocket Book</hi>, and there was even a lead or two to
                        follow. Alas, the ladies continued to be elusive.</p>
          <p>Recently, at the Huntington, I was looking for a book entitled <hi rend="i">My Ladies
Casket</hi>, and that put me in mind of the old quest. In the
                        card catalogue there was an entry which aroused a flicker of hope, so I
                        called up the book.</p>
          <p>This is the title of the book which came to my trembling hand: 
		<q> THE |
                            LADIES | NEW AND POLITE | Pocket Memorandum-Book, | For the Year of our
                            Lord 1780. | Being the Twentieth of King George III, the | Twenty-ninth
                            of the New Style in Great | Britain, and Bissextile or Leap-Year. |
                            Embellished with a beautiful Copper-Plate, representing | His Royal
                            Highness Prince WILLIAMHENRY as a | NAVAL OFFICER on board the FLEET;
                            also the most | elegant and genteel FULL DRESS and UNDRESS worn. |
                            CONTAINING, | [2 columns: column 1:] I. A Useful Memorandum | Book,
                            &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. | II. Table of Interest from one | Pound to
                            one Thousand. | III. Holidays, Birth-Days, | and other remarkable Days
                            in 1780. | IV. Good natured Credulity. | A Fable. | V. Experiment on the
                            Pro- | perties of Colours in im- | bibing the Rays of the Sun. | VI.
                            Anecdotes and enter- | taining Moral Essays. [Column 2:] VII. Curious
                            Descriptions in | Natural History. | VIII. Select Pieces of Poe- | try,
                            by the most admired | Wits. | IX. The most esteemed New | Songs, sung at
                            Vauxhall, |Ranelagh, the Theatres, | and Catch Club. | X. New Country
                            Dances | for 1780. | XI. Marketing Tables, Rates | of Hackney Coachmen,
                            | Chairmen, &amp;c. &amp;c. [End of columns.] | LONDON: | Printed for
                            J. JOHNSON, No. 72, St. Paul’s Church-yard. | [<hi rend="i">To be
                                continued annually. Price One Shilling.</hi>] &lt;Huntington:
                            429524&gt; (illus. 2) </q></p>
          <p>This publication is an excellent candidate for what has been so long sought.
                        The title of the second print in it, ‘a Lady in the newest full
                        Dress, and another in the most fashionable Undress,’ is remarkably
                        similar to Blake’s ‘A Lady in the full Dress, and another in
                        the most fashionable Undress now worn.’ The style of the lettering is
                        also remarkably similar. J. Johnson is the publisher for both the Blake
                        engraving and this “1780” edition. The format of the fashion
                        images is the same in both plates, with the ‘full Dress’
                        figure on the right and the ‘Undress’ figure on the left. The
                        size of Blake’s plate for the “1783” edition and that
                        for “1780” is the same, while the royal scenes are the same
                        height and clearly intended to be folded when bound into the book.</p>
          <p>It is a very small book (12.2 high x 7.6 cm wide) with tattered boards only
                        barely hanging on, and the engravings are very close in size to the Blake
                        prints in the British Museum.</p>
          <p>There are two anonymous plates engraved by Page, the platemarks are invisible
                        (frame for the images 9.5 × 6.5 and 9.5 × 6.5), the first of
                            “<hi rend="i">A Lady in the newest full Dress, and | another in
                            the most fashionable Undress</hi>” and the other of “<hi rend="i">His Royal
Highness</hi> Prince William Henry, | <hi rend="i">Their MAJESTY’s Third</hi> Son, <hi rend="i">in his naval
Uni- |
                            form, on board the</hi> Prince George, <hi rend="i">attended | by</hi>
                        Admiral Digby” (illus. 3).</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">CONTENTS</hi>; Titlepage (p. 1); Simple Interest at 5 1. per
                        Cent. from 1 Pound to 1000 (p. 2); Laws at Quadrille (pp. 3-4); Good Natured
                        Credulity. A Fable (pp. 4-6); Entertainment [experiments, anecdotes,
                        &amp;c] (pp. 6-11); Rules to be observed respecting Hackney Coachmen (p.
                        12); Memorandums for the beginning of the Year 1780 [largely blank, to be
                        filled in] (pp. [13-15]); Memorandum pages for January 1780-December 1780
                        (pp. [15-120]); The Pride of Rank and Opulence abased, a story (pp.
                        121-126); Select Pieces of Poetry [from Sheridan, Isaac Watts, &amp;c] (pp.
                        127-140); New Songs (pp. 140-144). <hi rend="i">N.B.</hi> There is a
                        catchword on the last page, strongly implying that there is a gathering or
                        more missing from the Huntington copy. The missing pages should contain the
                        New Country Dances and the Marketing Tables, &amp;c.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">COLLATION:</hi> 12° in sixes: A-M<hi rend="s">6</hi>; 12
                        gatherings.</p>
          <p>This volume has been used very sporadically by a contemporary for notes,
                        appointments, &amp;c., e.g., Friday January 28th: “M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Sawbridge
and F. Sawbridge set out for Hackney”; there
                        are repeated other references to Mr. Sawbridge, to Weston and Hackney and
                        Portland Place.</p>
          <p>The Huntington pocket book arrived in 1973 with 50 similar items. There must
                        be many others still in existence. The nature of the publication strongly
                        suggests that there were issues for other years, and other copies for this
                        and other years must be extant.</p>
          <p>Having found a book which fits with the Johnson name, the illustration of
                        “FULL DRESS and UNDRESS now worn,” I’m convinced we
                        have found the correct series. <hi rend="i">The National Union Catalog</hi>
                        and the British Library catalogue supplements were rapidly consulted with no
                        new discoveries. Searches in the various computer listings were followed
                        eagerly. Through RLIN, the on-line Research Libraries Information Network, I
                        located and saw at the Folger Shakespeare Library 
						<q> THE | LADIES | NEW AND
                            POLITE | Pocket Memorandum-Book, | For the Year of our Lord 1778. | . .
                            . | Embellished with a beautiful Copper-Plate, representing the NINE
                            LIVING MUSES of GREAT BRITAIN, | in the Temple of Apollo, viz. Miss
                            Carter, Mrs. | Barbauld, Mrs. Montagu, Mrs. Angelica Kauffman, | Mrs.
                            Macauley, Miss More, Mrs. Lenox, Mrs. Grif- | fifths, and Mrs. Sheridan.
                            | Also the MOST ELEGANT | and GENTEEL FULL DRESS and UNDRESS worn. | . .
                            . | LONDON: | Printed for J. JOHNSON, No. 72, St. Paul’s
                            Church-year [1777]. | [<hi rend="i">To be continued annually. Price One
                                Shilling</hi>] </q></p>
          <p>And the on-line <hi rend="i">ESTC</hi> (1992) directed me to an edition for
                        1789 in the 
<pb id="p26-33" n="33"/>
John Johnson Cellection in Bodley:
<q>
                            THE | LADIES | NEW AND POLITE | Pocket Memorandum-Book, | For the Year
                            of our Lord 1789. | . . . | Embellished with a beautiful Copper-Plate,
                            representing | two Ladies in the most fashionable Dresses now worn; |
                            also an elegant Engraving of Somerset-Place from the | Water [<hi rend="i">missing
in the Bodley copy</hi>]. | . . . | LONDON: |
                            Printed for J. JOHNSON, . . . [1788]. </q></p>
          <p>We now know that an annual publication entitled <hi rend="i">The Ladies New
                            and Complete Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi> was published by Joseph Johnson
                        beginning as early as 1777 and continuing at least through 1788. Of the
                        three copies now located, for 1778, 1780, and 1789, those for 1778 and 1780
                        certainly have two images engraved on one plate designed so that the printed
                        sheet could be folded, leaving the prints to face one another, like
                        Blake’s, and that for 1789 apparently did so (the second engraving
                        announced on the title page is missing from the Bodley copy). Each of the
                        three editions offers fashion illustration, two of them using the same
                        wording as in Blake’s engravings: “Full Dress and Undress
                        worn.” The two illustrations of royalty (1780, 1783) and the one of
                        the muses of Apollo (1778) show a related interest in elegant subjects.</p>
          <p>Now we know we should be looking for a copy of the memorandum book for the
                        year 1783, since presumably such annuals were published before the new year
                        so that they could be sold in time for use on 1 January. The November 1782
                        date in the imprint of Blake’s plate fits such a pattern. I am
                        convinced that copies will turn up and will continue my pursuit.</p>
          <p>What we should expect to find is this: 
		<q> THE | LADIES | NEW AND POLITE |
                            Pocket Memorandum-Book, | For the Year of our Lord 1783. | Being the
                            Twenty-third of King George III, and the | Thirty-second of the New
                            Style in Great Britain. | Embellished with a beautiful Copper-Plate,
                            representing The Morning Amusements of Her Royal Highness | the Princess
                            Royal &amp; Her 4 Sisters; also a Lady | in the FULL DRESS &amp;
                            another in the Most Fashionable UNDRESS now worn. | CONTAINING, | [<hi rend="i">2
columns</hi>: column 1:] I. A Useful Memorandum | Book,
                            &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. II. Table of Interest . . . [<hi rend="i">End
                                of columns.</hi>] LONDON: | Printed for J. JOHNSON, No. 72, St.
                            Paul’s Church-yard [1782]. | [<hi rend="i">To be continued
                                annually. Price One Shilling.</hi>]<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="i">COLLATION</hi>: 12° in sixes: A-N<hi rend="s">6</hi>; 12.2 × 7.6 cm. </q></p>
          <p>There has to be a <hi rend="i">Ladies New and Polite Pocket
                            Memorandum-Book</hi> . . . for 1783 . . . Printed for J. JOHNSON waiting
                        for us somewhere.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
