<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.1.srigley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Sickness of Blake’s Rose</title>
        <author n="Srigley">Michael Srigley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>E.B. Bentley</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Srigley</name>
              <name>Joan K. Stemmler</name>
              <name>Julia M. Wright</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">The Sickness of Blake’s Rose</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Michael <name>Srigley</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>Blake’s poem, <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> is probably one of the
                    best-known, best-loved and yet, as I hope to show, least understood poems in the
                    English language. Its popularity is due to its apparent simplicity and to its
                    generous ambiguity. When students are asked to give their own impressions of the
                    poem, their responses are usually vague and various. It is about love or beauty
                    undergoing corruption; it is about the frailty of goodness or the destructive
                    power of time. All the interpretations have in common a general sense of
                    something beautiful being defiled or desecrated. A similar variety of
                    interpretation within the same limits is found in literary criticism. One of the
                    most elaborate interpretations is offered by Kathleen Raine. She suggests that
                    the key to the poem is to be found in the tale of Psyche and Eros in
                    Apuleius’ <hi rend="i">The Golden Ass</hi>, which Blake is known to have
                        admired.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> The
mysterious
                    “invisible worm” of the poem is traced to Eros as the invisible
                    winged serpent whom Psyche will marry according to the Oracle of Apollo. David
                    Erdman approaches the meaning of the poem through Blake’s illustrations
                    to it, and finds both markedly erotic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> In
                    one illustration, a worm “extends a curved phallic body out from the
                    flower centre and about the human form of the Rose.” The girl’s
                    face “registers desperation and we see the sharp proboscis of the worm
                    turning out from below her dress as about to attack her.” Despite the
                    phallic imagery and the suggestions of incipient rape, Erdman interprets both
                    the etchings and the poem as basically optimistic; their message, he concludes,
                    is that “life is mortal.” He also finds a sign of hope in the
                    upraised arms of one of the girls: it indicates that “a worm hidden in
                    secret may be reborn as a boy or girl.” <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
                        Kathleen Raine, Blake and Tradition, 2 vols. (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP,
                        1968) 2: 199-201.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The Illuminated Blake, annotated by David V.
                        Erdman (Garden City, NJ: Anchor P/Doubleday, 1975) 81-82.</note></p>
        <p>It is not my purpose to criticize or dismiss such interpretations of <hi rend="i">The Sick
Rose</hi>; each of them in its own way throws some light on the
                    poem’s ‘intention,’ to use the Renaissance term. Rather, I
                    wish to suggest that there is an alternative approach to a lyric such as this,
                    one that concentrates on the details of the poem and seeks to elucidate
                        them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> As
various, more recent studies of
                    Blake’s deceptively simple poems have shown, they are often richly
                    complex and repay close analysis. <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> belongs to
                    this category. Kathleen Raine has written that 
					<q> Blake’s obscurities
                        are never vague; they are hard, precise, and insoluble until we have the key
                        to their meaning; then they vanish altogether.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Paul Robinson, “What Psychology Won’t
                            Explain” in Michigan Quarterly Review (1980): 45-46.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Kathleen Raine, Blake and Antiquity
                            (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1977) 12.</note></q>
I believe this is true in
particular of certain obscurities in <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi>, not least the nature of the nocturnal
“invisible
                    worm” which causes the sickness of the Rose. 
                </p>
        <p>First the poem itself: 
		<q> O Rose, thou art sick!<lb/>
 The invisible worm<lb/>
                        That flies in the night,<lb/>
 In the howling storm,<lb/>
 Has found out thy
                        bed<lb/>
 Of crimson joy:<lb/>
 And his dark secret love<lb/>
 Does thy life
                        destroy. </q>
In a draft of this poem, the ‘his’ of the
                    penultimate line is replaced by ‘her.’ This indicates that in
                    Blake’s mind the invisible worm could be of either sex. Further
                    information about the worm can be gleaned from the poem. It is invisible, it
                    flies by night in a howling storm, and it seeks out the Rose as the object of
                    its “dark secret love.” Its love is in some way surreptitious; as
                    the imagery of the poem suggests it is sexual; and as we learn from the final
                    line it is destructive. It causes the Rose to become sick. Let us look more
                    closely at the various meanings of the word <hi rend="i">worm.</hi></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">The Worm</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Among the more normal meanings of this word listed in the Oxford English
                        Dictionary, there are two figurative ones that might throw some light on
                        Blake’s “invisible worm.” According to one (II. 1) it
                        is “a grief or passion that preys stealthily on a man’s heart
                        or torments his conscience (like a worm in a dead body or a maggot in
                        food),” with examples from 900 A.D. onwards. Alternatively (II.b), it
                        is defined as “a whim or ‘maggot’ in the brain; a
                        perverse fancy or desire; a streak of madness or insanity, often <hi rend="i">wild
worm.</hi>” This figurative worm is the embodiment
                        of some powerful human feeling that preys stealthily on the mind and causes
                        a form of abnormality. Behind these figurative meanings lies a long
                        tradition of various nocturnal wormlike spirits that can travel to a human
                        being and induce some form of abnormal state. It is to this tradition that
                        Blake’s “invisible worm” belongs. These invisible
                        spirits, known as <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">larves</hi></corr> or <hi rend="i">larvae</hi>, are
                        mentioned by St. Augustine in his <hi rend="i">Civitas Dei</hi> (Ix. ix.
                        Loeb ed.) and became part of the demonic lore inherited by the Middle Ages
                        and the Renaissance. Boccaccio in his influential iconographical work, <hi rend="i">De
deis gentium</hi> (1472, p. 295a) states that these spirits
                        were created by Morpheus, the deity of dreams, as phantasms which according
                        to popular belief “invade the sleeping and weigh down on them,
                        pressing and oppressing the senses.” In the form of incubi and
                        succubi they visited sleeping persons, causing them to have vivid erotic
                        dreams. In the 12th Book of <hi rend="i">Orlando Furioso</hi>, Orlando is
                        described as being pursued by a phantom copy of his Angelica. This phantom
                        is called “notturne larve,” a nocturnal ghost or spirit that
                        haunts lovers. A similar incident occurs in Spenser’s <hi rend="i">Faerie
Queene</hi> (I.i.34 ff) when Archimago employs two magical flies
                        to 
<pb id="p26-5" n="5"/>
deceive the Red Cross Knight. One fly is sent to
                        procure a lascivious dream from Morpheus, while the other becomes a phantom
                        copy of Una which attempts to seduce the Knight and arouse him sexually.
                        These nocturnal spirits travel to men or women and cause them to have erotic
                        dreams that can result in orgasm. In a learned commentary on Genesis
                        published in 1601, Benedictus Pererius gave the standard view of what are
                        today called ‘wet dreams’: 
						<q> when men are polluted by
                            nocturnal seed, a succubus-demon is there, acting through a body of air
                            in the form of a woman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Pererius, <hi rend="i">Commentarium et
                                    Dusoputationem in Genesim</hi> (1601), v. I, p. 387, col. b,
                                para. 64.</note></q>
We can now understand why Blake could vacillate about the
gender of the
                        “invisible worm.” If it was visiting a man it would be the
                        female succubus, and a male incubus if visiting a woman. We can therefore
                        deduce that the Rose in the final version of the poem stands for a young
                        woman being visited by a male incubus in the form of an “invisible
                        worm.”</p>
          <p>The idea of the “wild worm” infecting the mind of a person and
                        a nocturnal <hi rend="i">larva</hi> fused in the seventeenth century, when
                        the meaning of <hi rend="i">larva</hi> as ghost, skeleton, or mask, was
                        extended by biologists to include grub or maggot, a meaning which the word
                        “worm” also once had (O.E.D. under “worm,” 5).
                        To obtain some idea of how Blake may have visualized the “worm/That
                        flies by night,” let us now consider a seventeenth-century engraving
                        found in a work that Blake almost certainly knew. This is the <hi rend="i">Lumen de
lumine</hi> (1652), the alchemical allegory written by Thomas
                        Vaughan, brother of the metaphysical poet, Henry Vaughan. As Raine has
                        suggested, this allegorical vision of Thalia revealing the secrets of
                        alchemy to an adept in the depths of the earth is a major inspiration of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi> Blake would certainly
                        have been interested in the emblematic engraving which opens <hi rend="i">Lumen de
lumine</hi>, as well as in the commentary on it in the main
                        text. The central panel of the engraving shows an oval of illuminated ground
                        surrounded by darkness. In the center is an altar with a candle on it
                        signifying <hi rend="i">Lumen Naturae</hi>, the Light of Nature. An Angel
                        with raised sword and a ball of thread is seen to the left, while to the
                        right a blindfolded man is groping his way towards the surrounding darkness
                        designated <hi rend="i">Regio Phantastica</hi>, the Region of Fantasy.
                        Awaiting to seize him there are various winged creatures including basilisks
                        and winged serpents or worms with coiled tails. As we learn from
                        Vaughan’s commentary on this scene, the blindfolded figure being
                        initiated into the mysteries of alchemy will stray into the monstrous region
                        of fantasy unless he accepts the protection of the Angel and uses the thread
                        of Ariadne to guide him through the labyrinth of the alchemical 
<hi rend="i">opus.</hi> His goal is both above and below him. Above is the <hi rend="i">Mons Magorum
Invisibilis</hi>, the Invisible Mountain of the
                        Magicians. Below is a large winged dragon with its tail in its mouth, the
                        alchemical <hi rend="i">ourobouros</hi> enclosing a heap of gold on which a
                        child is sitting and the inscription <hi rend="i">Non nisi parvilis</hi>,
                        intimating that only as children can we enter the Kingdom of Heaven.
                        Concerning the basilisks and winged worms that infest the Region of Fantasy,
                        Vaughan has this to say: in gaining access to the caverns of the Invisible
                        Mountain where the secrets of alchemy are to be discovered, great care must
                        be taken because 
						<q> they are very dangerous places after Night, for they
                            are haunted with Fires, and other strange Apparitions, occasion’d
                            (as I am told by the Magi) by certaine spirits, which dabble
                            lasciviously with the sperm of the world, and imprint their Imaginations
                            on it, producing many times fantastic, and monstrous Generations.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Thomas Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Lumen de
                                    Lumine</hi> in <hi rend="i">The Works of Thomas Vaughan</hi>,
                                ed. Alan Rudrum (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1984) 317, 643-48.</note></q>
It is
these monstrous productions of sexual imagination that are shown
                        flying in the dark as basilisks and worms or snakes, seeking to waylay the
                        candidate during his maze-like initiation into <hi rend="i">the Mysteries of
                            this my</hi> &lt;<hi rend="i">Thalia’s</hi>&gt; 
<hi rend="i">Schoole.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> As the
                        alchemists repeatedly claimed, sexual abstinence was a prime requirement for
                        accomplishing the Work; the basilisks and winged worms therefore represent
                        erotic temptation to the practitioner of alchemy. As we shall see, these
                        nocturnal spirits were believed to be created from a special sperm created
                        during erotic dreams or imaginings. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Vaughn
                            310, 435-36.</note></p>
          <p>It has been necessary to investigate this highly taboo area of human belief
                        in order to discover the lost context of a poem like <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose.</hi> It was precisely such an investigation into the taboos
                        surrounding sex in his own age that Blake undertook. It is well-known that
                        he regarded the Pauline Christian attitude towards sex as unhealthy and as
                        the cause of much abnormality. It warped the natural sexuality of young men
                        and women; it corrupted family life; and it led to prostitution and venereal
                        disease. Through enforced celibacy it was also the cause of much sexual
                        prurience in the Church itself. In his poetry, Blake frequently attempted to
                        expose this diseased attitude to sex, and some of the key passages will be
                        cited later. The point I wish to make here is that <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose</hi>, far from being a vaguely romantic evocation of the
                        susceptibility of beauty to corruption, is in fact a detailed analysis of
                        the causes of the sexual malady of Blake’s times. Its general
                        diagnosis can now be summarized. The “invisible worm” is the
                        embodiment of the sexually heated fantasies of a male, traveling by night
                        through the “howling storm” of erotic passion to the woman
                        being imagined and desired by the solitary lover. To understand this strange
                        idea of what can be called telepathic sexual intercourse between a man and a
                        woman who are physically apart, we must now consider the writings of someone
                        who inspired both Vaughan and Blake. This is the sixteenth-century physician
                        and alchemist, Paracelsus.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Paracelsus and Invisible Illnesses</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Blake left it on record that the two figures to whom he was most indebted
                        were the mystic, Jakob Boehme, and the physician, Paracelsus. In <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, he claims that
                        “any man of mechanical talents may from the writings of Paracelsus or
                        Jacob Behmen produce ten thousand 
<pb id="p26-6" n="6"/>
volumes of equal
                        value with Swedenborg’s.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref>
                        In a verse letter to John Flaxman of 1800 he again mentions Paracelsus and
                        Boehme as sources of inspiration, claiming that they have actually appeared
                        to him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
Discussing the influence of
                        Paracelsus on Blake, S. Foster Damon has suggested that the paramount
                        importance given by Blake to the human imagination derives ultimately from
                            Paracelsus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> This is true also of
                        the negative power of the human imagination when uncontrolled or distorted
                        by wrong desire. What a man imagines, he becomes, declared Paracelsus in his
                            <hi rend="i">Archidoxis</hi>, which would have been available to Blake
                        in the English translation of 1656.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
                        This applies both to the use of the creative imagination and of a diseased
                        imagination. Paracelsus’ fullest treatment of uncontrolled
                        imagination as the cause of various psychological or physical diseases is
                        his <hi rend="i">De Causis et Origine Morborum Invisibilium</hi>, originally
                        published in German in 1565 in <hi rend="i">Opera Omnia</hi>, and reissued
                        in Geneva in 1658 in Latin translation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Leaving aside for the moment the question of whether Blake was
                        acquainted with this work, I shall first give an account of its relevant
                        portions. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Complete Writings of William
Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey
                            Keynes (London; New York, Toronto: Oxford UP, 1966) 158.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Keynes 799</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi>
                            (1979), ed. by S. Foster Damon, under “Paracelsus.” See
                            also Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study
                                of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford, 1970)
                            passim, for parallels between the thought of Paracelsus and
                            Blake.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> The Archidoxes of Magic by Paracelsus</hi>, transl. by R.
                            Turner (London, 1656); 2nd ed. 1975 (London: <corr type="emend">Askin Publishers,</corr> 1975)
                            introd. by Stephen Skinner.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> All quotations are from the ed. of
                            1656.</note></p>
          <p>As the title of the book indicates, it deals with the causes and origin of
                        invisible diseases. Among these Paracelsus includes diseases born of the
                        imagination, and these he covers in Book III of <hi rend="i">De
                            Origine.</hi> When uncontrolled the human imagination was shameless and
                        obstinate and gave rise to many human ills.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n13" type="note">13</ref> This was particularly so in illnesses deriving from an
                        overactive sexual fantasy. It is this fantasy that creates a false sperm
                        from which incubi and succubi are produced. More particularly, this false
                        sperm or “corrupted salt” is 
						<q> born of the imagination in
                            Amor Heroes &lt;solitary sex&gt;. What is this love? It is none
                            other than when someone creates a woman in his mind through the power of
                            fantasy, and making love with her satisfies his love. From this act
                            results the ejaculation of a useless, feeble sperm incapable of
                            generating children. From this sperm, however, incubi and succubi are
                            created. (<hi rend="i">Iam vero sperma hoc, ita productum,
                                eximaginatione in amore Hereos natum est. Quid vero iste amor est?
                                Nihil aliud, quam quod sibi aliquis per phantasiam in animo foeminam
                                fingit, &amp; cum hac re habendo, amorem suum exsatiat. Unde surdi
                                quo-que fatui spermatis exitus est, quod ad liberorum generationem
                                ineptum est. Exillo tamen spermate</hi> Incubus <hi rend="i">&amp;</hi>
Succubus <hi rend="i">gignuntur</hi>).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> De Causis</hi> 128, in <hi rend="i">Opera
                                    Omnia.</hi></note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> De Causis</hi> 120.</note></q>
The adulterated sperm
produced by the erotic imagination is carried off
                        by nocturnal spirits (<hi rend="i">per nocturnos spiritus</hi>), and
                        “hatched into serpents, worms (<hi rend="i">vermes</hi>), toads and
                        similar impure creatures,” including as Paracelsus also says
                        basilisks. They pass from the heated imagination of one person to the person
                        being imagined. This can explain acts of black magic. For example, 
						<q> if a
                            man has a strong and evil imagination, and wishes to injure another,
                            such beings are always ready to hand to lend a helping hand for the
                            accomplishment of his purpose.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Franz Hartmann, <hi rend="i">Paracelsus: Life and Prophecies</hi> (New
York: Rudolph Steiner
                                Publications, 1973) 92.</note></q>
The <hi rend="i">larvae</hi> used for such
a transmission 
<q> can only
                            act upon men if the latter make room for them in their minds. A healthy
                            mind is a castle that cannot be invaded without the will of its master;
                            but if they are allowed to enter, they excite the passions of men and
                            women, they create cravings in them, they produce bad thoughts which act
                            injuriously upon the brain; they sharpen the animal instinct and
                            suffocate the moral sense.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Hartmann 93.</note></q>
In a passage from <hi rend="i">Philosophia
Saqax</hi>, Paracelsus
                        describes how this transmission takes place: 
						<q> Spirits desire to act upon
                            &lt;a person’s imagination&gt;, and they therefore often
                            make use of his dreams for the purpose of acting upon him. During sleep
                            the sidereal man may by the power of the imagination be sent out of the
                            physical form, at a distance to act for some purpose. No place is too
                            far for the imagination to go, and the imagination of one man may
                            impress that of another, wherever it reaches.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Hartmann 112.</note></q>
The same idea is found in another passage:
<q>
One man may communicate
                            his thoughts to another with whom he is in sympathy, at any distance
                            however great it may be, or he may act upon the spirit of another person
                            in such a manner as to influence his actions after the latter awakens
                            from his sleep, and in this way he may even injure the health of the
                            latter, and upon this law of Nature is based the possibility of
                            witchcraft and sorcery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Hartmann 213-14.</note></q>
In these various excerpts from the writings
of Paracelsus are to be
                        found, I believe, either the main source of or a striking analogue to ideas
                        used by Blake in <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose.</hi> The poem is essentially a
                        distillation of the Paracelsan teaching concerning the transmission at a
                        distance of passionate imaginings from one person to another, as found
                        primarily in <hi rend="i">De Origine morborum <corr type="emend">invisibilium</corr></hi> but also
                        referred to in other works by Paracelsus. The sickness of the Rose has been
                        caused by the fantasizing of a lonely young man as he conjures up an image
                        of a woman and imagines making love to her. From the ethereal sperm produced
                        by this act of erotic imagination, an “invisible worm” is
                        created which flies through the tempestuous night from the lover to the
                        beloved. As an expression of his “dark secret love” it carries
                        out an act of violation on the young woman. It is for this reason that Blake
                        speaks of this form of love as destructive. 
                    </p>
          <p>The role of the young lover in the drama evoked in <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose</hi> is concealed, but it comes out clearly in a passage in 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, describing the erotic
                        experiences of a young girl and youth as each lies alone in bed: 
						<q> The
                            moment of desire! The moment of desire! The virgin<lb/>
 That pines for
                            man shall awaken to enormous joys<lb/>
 In the secret shadows of her
                            chamber: the youth shut up from<lb/>
 The lustful joy shall forget to
                            generate and create an amorous image<lb/>
 In the shadows of his curtains
                            and in the folds of his silent pillow.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Keynes 194.</note></q>
The girl is awakening from a powerful erotic
dream, while the young
                        man, deprived of natural “lustful joy,” conjures up in his
                        solitude “an amorous image” of the desired woman. The two
                        halves of the passage are joined by a colon, perhaps suggesting that the
                        sexual climax of the girl and the erotic imaginings of the young man are
                        interrelated and simultaneous. Her pining for a man travels to him as
                        “an amorous 
<pb id="p26-7" n="7"/>
image”; his longing for her
                        travels to the girl to become her partner in the sexual dream. As in <hi rend="i">The
Sick Rose</hi> with its “dark secret love,”
                        their loves are conceived in “secret shadows” and in
                        “the shadows of his curtains.” Here for Blake lies the
                        unnatural character and essential sickness of their love. It is also
                        unnatural in that the youth “shall forget to generate.” This
                        may echo the observation of Paracelsus that erotic imaginings lead to a form
                        of sterile sperm that is incapable of producing children. The young man,
                        condemned by the Christian norms of society to living in unnatural celibacy,
                        is compelled to create “a woman in his mind through the power of
                        fantasy,” as Paracelsus wrote.</p>
          <p>The sickness in the love of the boy and girl is traced by Blake to religion.
                        In lines that immediately follow those we have just discussed, Blake writes
                        in fierce irony about monastic celibacy and its effects: 
						<q> Are not these
                            the palaces of religion, the rewards of continence;<lb/>
 The
                            self-enjoyings of self-denial? why dost thou seek religion?<lb/>
 Is it
                            because acts are not lovely that thou seekest solitude<lb/>
 Where the
                            horrible darkness is impressed with reflections of desire?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Keynes 194.</note></q>
Enforced continence leads to sexual sickness in
the form of
                        narcissistic “self-enjoyings of self-denial” in darkness and
                        solitude. This abuse of sexuality is seen by Blake as epidemic in quality
                        and as spreading almost as a viral infection to all young love. Here again
                        his conception of the “self-enjoyings of self-denials” found
                        at the heart of the celibate Church is remarkably close to
                        Paracelsus’ view. In his treatise on plagues, <hi rend="i">De
                            pestilate</hi>, Paracelsus draws attention to the dangers of convents,
                        monasteries, and houses of prostitution, because in such places a lascivious
                        and evil imagination is especially active, and great quantities of sperma
                        are there collected by evil spirits, and that sperma contains a powerful
                        Mumia which may be extracted, and transformed into evil things.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Hartmann 124.</note></p>
          <p>From the revulsion towards sexuality inculcated by the Church arises a
                        psychic pestilence that is destroying the Garden of Love. Its victims are
                        named in <hi rend="i">The Sunflower</hi>:
<q> Youth pined away with
                            desire,<lb/>
 And the pale Virgin shrouded in snow.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Keynes 215.</note></q>
As William J. Keith has rightly suggested, the
individuals in this poem
                        and in <hi rend="i">Vision of the Daughters of Albion</hi> are varieties of
                        Ovid’s Narcissus, but it is important to stress that for Blake their
                        self-consuming, sickly narcissism was imposed on them by the puritanical
                        norms of a superficially Christian society.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> William J. Keith, “The
                            Complexities of Blake’s Sunflower: An Archetypal
                            Speculation,” in <hi rend="i">Blake: A Collection of Critical
                                Essays</hi>, ed. by Northrop Frye (Englewood Cliffs, NJ:
                            Prentice-Hall, 1966) 58.</note></p>
          <p>This interpretation of <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> and of related poems
                        by Blake rests on the assumption that Blake was conversant with
                        Paracelsus’s strange ideas concerning invisible diseases and
                        telepathic infection. As we have seen, Blake himself claimed to have been in
                        direct contact with the spirits of Paracelsus, Boehme, Milton and other
                        discarnate entities, but such a claim is treated today with skepticism.
                        Eliminating then direct communication with the spirit of Paracelsus as the
                        source of Blake’s information about invisible diseases, there is the
                        possibility that Blake read <hi rend="i">De Origine</hi> in the Latin of the
                        1658 edition. It is know that by 1803 Blake could read both Latin and Greek,
                        and that his Greek was as fluent as that of “an Oxford
                            scholar.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">24</ref> Unfortunately, it
                        is not known when Blake began learning these languages. There remains the
                        possibility that Blake could have learnt Paracelsus’s teachings about
                        invisible diseases from people in his circle of friends who were interested
                        in such matters. In her forthcoming work entitled <hi rend="i">Men of
                            Desire: Swedenborg, Blake and Illuminist Freemasonry</hi>, Marsha Keith
                        Schuchard investigates, among other things, the keen interest in Paracelsus,
                        Swedenborg and in Cabalism in the circles that Blake frequented. She has
                        generously allowed me to make use of some of her findings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Keynes 821.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> The information and quotations contained
                            in the following paragraph documenting the interest in Paracelsus in the
                            eighteenth century were kindly supplied to me by Dr.
                        Schuchard.</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Paracelsus in the Late Eighteenth Century</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>In the <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Ancient and Modern Books</hi> (1787) listed
                        as available in the London bookshop of John Denis, Dr. Schuchard notes the
                        following items: <list type="simple">
	<item><p># 4945 Auriolus Phillipus Theophrastus, his five Books of the
                                    Causes of Invisible Diseases, <hi rend="i">manuscript, fairly
                                        wrote</hi></p></item>
	<item><p># 4927 <hi rend="i">Paracelsi Opera Omnia</hi> (1662)</p></item>
	<item><p># 5241 <hi rend="i">Paracelsus his Archidoxes</hi> (1660)</p></item>
</list> John Denis was the English agent for the distribution of
                        Swedenborg’s works in England. Schuchard has also examined a handlist
                        “Catalogue of the Library of Richard Cosway,” now in the
                        Huntington Library. Cosway, painter and mystic, was a lifelong friend of
                        Blake’s. The Catalogue contains the following works by Paracelsus in
                        English translation: <hi rend="i">On the Nature of Things</hi> (1650 and
                        1674); <hi rend="i">New Light of Alchymy</hi> (1674); <hi rend="i">The
                            Supreme Mysteries of Nature</hi> (1656); <hi rend="i">Philosophy
                            Reformed</hi> (1657). The catalogue does not list Cosway’s
                        collection of occult manuscripts. A catalogue of the library of the artist,
                        Philippe Jacques de Loutherbourg, now in the Victoria and Albert Museum,
                        includes under item 136 a number of books by Paracelsus. Like Cosway, de
                        Loutherbourg was a Freemason and a follower of Swedenborg, and probably
                        known to Blake. Schuchard points out that interest in Paracelsus was also
                        widespread in a wider circle of Swedenborgian Freemasons. Such figures as
                        Manoah and Ebenezer Sibly, General Charles Rainsford and Dr. Sigismund
                        Bacstrom all possessed private libraries of occult literature, and refer to
                        Paracelsus in their published writings and manuscripts.</p>
          <p>It is clear then that in the final decades of the eighteenth century
                        Paracelsus continued to be read and studied and that his teachings
                        interested the members of the occult circles that Blake frequented. The
                        printed works of Paracelsus were still available in private libraries and
                        for sale in John Denis’s bookshop in and about the year 1787. It is
                        of particular interest that 
<pb id="p26-8" n="8"/>
in that year Denis had
                        for sale a manuscript English translation of Paracelsus’s <hi rend="i">De Origine
morborum <corr type="emend">invisibilium</corr></hi>, the very work which, as
                        I claim, Blake was influenced by when he came to write <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose</hi> only a few years later. Blake and his wife joined the
                        Swedenborgian Society in 1789, and it is reasonable to assume that Blake
                        frequented John Denis’s bookshop. The copies of Swedenborg’s
                            <hi rend="i">Heaven and Hell</hi> and <hi rend="i">Divine
                            Providence</hi> in English translation which Blake procured in 1789 and
                        1790 were published by John Denis.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
                        Even if Blake had not read the English translation of Paracelsus’s
                            <hi rend="i">De Origine</hi> available in Denis’s bookshop, there
                        were a number of Swedenborgians and other esotericists close to Blake who
                        were interested in Paracelsus, as Schuchard has documented, and who could
                        have supplied him with the requisite information about its ideas. 
<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Information about Denis’s role in
                            the publication of these two works of Swedenborg was kindly supplied by
                            Dr. Schuchard.</note></p>
          <p>In whatever exact way Blake may have acquired knowledge of
                        Paracelsus’s <hi rend="i">De Origine</hi>, it seems to me clear this
                        work played a significant part in the genesis of <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose</hi> and that an awareness of its ideas illuminates the central
                        drama of the poem. It enables us to understand more exactly the nature of
                        the invisible worm that flies by night, the urge that drives it through the
                        storm, and why its love is destructive. It also throws light on one of
                        Blake’s major preoccupations: the blighting effect on young people of
                        the Church’s condemnation of sexuality as sinful by nature. Because
                        of this condemnation, sexual attraction does not lead to sexual union, nor
                        does it result in generation. It leads only to solitary, imagined sex which
                        Blake sees as enfeebling and as sick and sterile. The poem is therefore an
                        expression in a powerfully compressed and suggestive form of Blake’s
                        conviction that the Church’s condemnation of sexuality as
                        intrinsically shameful has caused a widespread social and psychological
                        sickness. It leads to the breaking of the marriage bond, to prostitution, to
                        venereal disease, and to a fevered eroticism that is essentially unhealthy.
                        It manifests as a destructive “dark secret love” instead of
                        Oothoon’s “lovely copulation” in bright daylight. It is
                        furtive instead of open. <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> not only forms an
                        integral part of Blake’s attack on negative Christian attitudes
                        towards human sexuality, but it is remarkable for its specific diagnosis of
                        the illness that this attitude has brought about. Using traditional demonic
                        lore but above all the ideas of Paracelsus, Blake suggests that the human
                        imagination when unregulated is able to create a strange psychic cloud of
                        pollution hovering over society and infested by the weird creatures of
                        erotic longing. It is these in the form of the “invisible
                        worm,” the spectral <hi rend="i">vermis</hi> of Paracelsus’s
                            <hi rend="i">De Origine</hi>, that travel telepathically from person to
                        person bearing erotic infection. As Blake wrote “He who desires but
                        acts not, breeds pestilence.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Keynes 151.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
