<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.1.wright</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Empire is no More”: Odin and Orc in America</title>
        <author n="Wright">Julia M. Wright</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>E.B. Bentley</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Srigley</name>
              <name>Joan K. Stemmler</name>
              <name>Julia M. Wright</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
	<pb id="p26-26" n="26"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Empire is no More”: Odin and Orc in <hi rend="i">America</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Julia M. <name>Wright</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Orc appears in a number of Blake’s poems, but his character in <hi rend="i">America</hi> (1793)
is uniquely drawn. A howling, flaming
                        figure in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794) and a chained infant in <hi rend="i">The
[First] Book of Urizen</hi> (1794), the Orc of <hi rend="i">America</hi> is described in a wealth of detail
that is matched only by
                            <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1797).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n209" type="note">1</ref> The details that are provided, however, differ. In both <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">America</hi>, for instance,
                        Orc claims that his spirit can leave his chained body, but the Orc of <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi> represents his spirit as “A Worm
                        compelld” (80.31), while that of <hi rend="i">America</hi> chooses
                        figures of power: 
						<q> on high my spirit soars;<lb/>
 Sometimes an eagle
                            screaming in the sky, sometimes a lion,<lb/>
 Stalking upon the
                            mountains, &amp; sometimes a whale I lash<lb/>
 The raging fathomless
                            abyss, anon a serpent . . .<lb/>
 On the Canadian wilds I fold. (1.12-17)
						</q>
						These figures have been associated with various sets of symbols of
                        power, as Rodney M. Baine suggests that the shapes are all images of regal
                        power over nature (130), while David V. Erdman identifies some of the
                        animals as revolutionary emblems (259). Although the female later claims
                        that Orc courts her in these shapes, they are quite violent in Orc’s
                        speech: the shapes are “screaming,” “stalking,”
                        “lashing,” and, by “folding,” encircle and bind,
                        like the serpent of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi> The Orc
                        of <hi rend="i">America</hi> thus chooses a diversity of shapes that are not
                        only unbound but associated with aggressive power. This characterization of
                        Orc is reinforced and elaborated through allusions to Norse mythology that
                        can be used to explore the complexity of this revolutionary figure as he is
                        constructed in <hi rend="i">America.</hi>
	<note id="n209"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I cite the dates on Blake’s title
                            pages rather than rehearse bibliographical debates regarding the dating
                            of these texts.</note></p>
          <p>In his discussion of the first quarter of the Preludium, Harold Bloom writes
                        that “The mythic world suggested is the Northern one of Odin and
                        Thor, the Eddic literature known to Blake through Mallet’s <hi rend="i">Northern
Antiquities</hi> . . . and the poems and translations
                        of Thomas Gray” (118). Bloom emphasizes the references to iron, and
                        his identification of the female as the daughter of a Thor-like smith
                        (118-19), while Erdman finds in the action of the poem an allusion to Paul
                        Henri Mallet’s explanation of human sacrifice “as a harvest
                        rite” (251). Both <hi rend="i">America</hi> and Blake’s notes
                        for his designs for the 1790 edition of Gray’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> indicate a
knowledge of Gray’s free translation of an
                        Icelandic lay, <hi rend="i">The Descent of Odin</hi>, and a familiarity with
                        Norse mythology that extends beyond 
<pb id="p26-27" n="27"/>
that poem.
                        Blake’s notes, for instance, refer to “The Serpent who girds
                        the Earth” (680), which is not mentioned in Gray’s poem, as
                        well as “The Serpent &amp; the Wolvish Dog. two terrors in the
                        Northern mythology” (680), which recall Orc’s form as a
                        serpent and the “eternal Wolf” (9.2). Orc, moreover, like Lok
                        in Gray’s <hi rend="i">Descent</hi>, is riveted by a “tenfold
                        chain” (1.12; Gray 65), as has been noted by Mark Schorer (406n) and
                        Erdman (262n).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n210"
type="note">2</ref> While critics have
                        indicated the Norse background for this poem and others by Blake, however,
                        there are close correspondences between <hi rend="i">America</hi>’s
                        Orc and Odin that have not been addressed. <note id="n210"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See
Erdman (262n) and Schorer (405-06n) for other
                            correspondences between Gray’s translation and Blake’s
                            poetry.</note></p>
          <p>In asserting that he can transform his spirit into the shapes of a whale, a
                        serpent, an eagle, and a lion, Orc evokes a distinguishing feature of Odin.
                        In the <hi rend="i">Ynglinga Saga</hi>, Snorre Sturlason writes that Odin
                        “could transform his shape: his body would lie as if dead, or asleep;
                        but then he would be in shape of a fish, a worm, a bird, or beast”
                        (11), the four categories of Orc’s avatars.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n211" type="note">3</ref> The <hi rend="i">Heimskringla</hi>, of which the <hi rend="i">Ynglinga
Saga</hi> is the first part, was not published in an
                        English translation until 1844, although the closeness of Sturlason’s
                        description of Odin’s transformative abilities to Orc’s
                        description of his metamorphic powers invites speculation that Blake had
                        access to unpublished or as yet unidentified information. Through
                        Mallet’s <hi rend="i">Northern Antiquities</hi>, however, which
                        “is almost certainly Blake’s source for Norse
                        mythology” (Bloom 441), Blake would have had access to a more general
                        knowledge of the saga, since it is both discussed and paraphrased in that
                        work. Bishop Percy’s translation of Mallet’s text was
                        published in 1770, and it notes Odin’s ability to transform his shape
                        and to travel widely: “[Odin] persuaded his followers that he could
                        run over the world in the twinkling of an eye, that he had the direction of
                        the air and tempests, that he could transform himself into all sorts of
                        shapes” (83). Like Mallet’s Odin, Orc merely claims such
                        abilities; there is no narratorial authority for Orc’s
                        transformations in <hi rend="i">America</hi>, as there is in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi> In eighteenth-century antiquarian discourse, Odin
                        is persistently constructed as a confidence-man rather than a god, a human
                        being whose rhetorical and poetic abilities allowed him to convince his
                        followers, through speech alone, that he was a god.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n212" type="note">4</ref>
                        <hi rend="i">America</hi> is the only poem of the early 1790s in which Orc
                        is articulate, and he not only speaks, but speaks eloquently in a voice that
                        “shook the temple” (5.7) and “In thunders ends”
                        (7.1). In Odin and <hi rend="i">America</hi>’s Orc, then, we have two
                        compelling orators who claim to have the ability to change their shape and
                        travel widely. There are, however, even closer correspondences between the
                        language with which Mallet describes Odin and that with which Blake
                        describes Orc in <hi rend="i">America.</hi>
	<note id="n211"><hi rend="s">3</hi> In eighteenth-century terms, these
                            classifications are legitimate: the whale was referred to as a fish well
                            into the nineteenth century.</note>
	<note id="n212"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See, e.g., Lemprière and Mallet.
                            Odin is identified as a poet by Lemprière (417) and Mallet (83),
                            the inventor of poetry by Mallet (83), and the inventor of writing by
                            both Warton (xx) and Mallet (83).</note></p>
          <p>Odin is the “God of War” (Mallet 91), and it is as such that he
                        excites “terror” (Mallet 84) and bears the epithet,
                        “The terrible and severe God” (Mallet 91), recalling the
                        persistence with which Orc is associated with forms of the word
                        “terror,” and his appearance “like the planet
                        red” (5.2), which is named for the Roman god of war, Mars.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n213" type="note">5</ref> Odin, as a martial deity, is called
                        upon by his devotees to embolden them in battle, and Percy’s
                        translation of Mallet makes this point in language that appears in 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, noting that “[Odin] often descended to
                        intermix in the conflict himself, to inflame the fury of the
                        combatants” (92). Orc’s inspiration of the American rebels is
                        repeatedly described in terms of flame: “And the flame folded roaring
                        fierce within the pitchy night / Before the Demon red, who burnt towards
                        America . . . gath’ring thick / In flames as of a furnace on the land
                        from North to South” (12.8-9, 12.11-12). This depiction of Orc as
                        flaming appears elsewhere in Blake’s works, but other details
                        regarding Orc’s non-inflammatory participation in the revolution do
                        not. In paraphrasing the <hi rend="i">Ynglinga Saga</hi>, Mallet writes that
                        Odin was a great warrior who “inspired his enemies with such terror,
                        that they could not describe it better, than by saying he rendered them
                        blind and deaf; that he would appear like a wolf all desperate” (84).
                        Mallet’s combination of “terror,” battle, a wolf,
                        blindness, and difficulty with hearing, occurs in the reaction of
                        Albion’s Angel to Orc’s speech: “Loud howls the Eternal
                        Wolf! . . . / America is darkned; and my punishing Demons terrified . . .
                        clouds obscure my aged sight” (9.2-3, 9.12). <note id="n213"><hi rend="s">5</hi> It
is the martial Odin that appears in
                            Blake’s other works by name (<hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> 3.30;
                                <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 25.52-53; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                            83.19). Sotha, linked to Odin in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
                            (1795), also appears in a canceled plate for <hi rend="i">America</hi>(b.21). This
additional connection between Odin and <hi rend="i">America</hi> is suspect, however, because of the question
                            of dating, since <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> was printed two years
                            after <hi rend="i">America</hi>, and the date of the canceled plate is
                            unknown.</note></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">America</hi>, Blake constructs an Orc that specifically
                        recalls the Norse god: both are associated with the shape of a wolf during
                        war, “inflame” warriors, blind opponents, have remarkable
                        oratorical abilities, and claim to possess extraordinary powers that allow
                        them to change shape and journey extensively. Why, then, does 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> have an Orc who echoes Mallet’s Odin in so many
                        specifics while, for instance, the contemporaneous <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                        does not? The answer, I would argue, lies in the difference between the
                        political situations that are represented. Unlike <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                        and the other poems in which Orc appears, <hi rend="i">America</hi> is
                        concerned specifically with oppression as imperial rule—and so is
                        Mallet’s discussion of Odin. Mallet indicates that Odin was
                        considered a nationalist hero in material available to him: 
						<q> Several
                            learned men have supposed that a desire of being revenged on the Romans
                            was the ruling principle of his whole conduct. . . . He had no other
                            view, according to them, in running through so many distant kingdoms,
                            and in establishing with so much zeal his sanguinary doctrines, but to
                            spirit up all nations against so formidable and odious a power. This
                            leaven, which he left in the bosoms of the northern people, fermented a
                            long time in secret; but the signal, they add, once given, they all fell
                            as it were by common consent upon this unhappy empire; and after many
                            repeated shocks, entirely overturned it. (82-83) </q>
“Stiff
                        shudderings shook the heav’nly thrones” (16.16): Odin inspires
                        rebels to overthrow the Roman Empire, the “enemies of universal
                        liberty” (Mallet 82), while Orc inspires rebels to overthrow the
                        British Empire, crying, “Empire is no more” (6.15).</p>
          <p>A poet who inflamed the rebels that freed Northern Europe from Roman 
<pb id="p26-28" n="28"/>
rule, Odin appears to be an ideal figure with which
                        to affiliate the articulate Orc who inflames the rebels that free the
                        American colonies from British rule. Mallet’s Odin, however, is more
                        complex than this. According to eighteenth-century antiquarians, Odin was
                        not a Norse god, nor even a Northern European, but an exile from Asia
                        (Warton xx; Bell 233) who escaped into Northern Europe after participating
                        in a failed Scythian revolt against the Romans (Mallet 79). Mallet maintains
                        that Odin’s real name was Sigge, and vilifies him for imposing a
                        violent religious and political system on Northern Europeans through deceit
                        and violence: Sigge assumed the name of the deity Odin, “a title so
                        proper to procure him respect among the people he meant to subject,”
                        and “marched towards the north and west of Europe, subduing, we are
                        told, all the people he found in his passage” (80).
                        “[A]mbitious” (80), Mallet’s Odin is not only a
                        catalyst for the expulsion of the Roman Empire from Northern Europe, but a
                        conqueror of Northern Europe himself, and Mallet only offers the
                        characterization of Odin as an anti-imperialist hero in order to refute
                        it.</p>
          <p>Blake’s allusions to Mallet’s Odin, an anti-imperial conqueror,
                        can thus provide a schema through which to address two questions raised by
                            <hi rend="i">America:</hi> why is the champion of the oppressed in the
                        Prophecy depicted raping the female in the Preludium? And why are indigenous
                        Americans so thoroughly removed from the Prophecy’s conflict? (By
                        “Prophecy,” I mean the text within <hi rend="i">America</hi>
                        that is labelled as such, rather than the whole work.) While critics have
                        legitimated the rape, and so sustained Orc’s status as the
                        poem’s hero, Blake’s language suggests both violence and
                        illicit conquest: “[Orc] siez’d the panting struggling
                        womb” (2.3).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n214"
type="note">6</ref> While the female
                        is not explicitly identified with Amerindians, she declares herself to be
                        the proprietor of American land (2.10),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n215" type="note">7</ref> and Erdman suggests that, in the illustration for plate 1, she
                        “appears in her American Indian form” (259). Viewing this
                        “daughter” (1.1) as a representative of the aboriginal peoples
                        would, moreover, be consistent with the iconography of loyalist engravings,
                        in which, as Stephen C. Behrendt points out, Britannia is represented as a
                        matriarch and her “‘daughter’ [is] the emblematic
                        American Indian” (32). The evidence linking the female with the
                        Amerindians is tenuous, but it is congruous with a parallel between the
                        female and this elided group to which I wish to draw attention. There
                        exists, I would suggest, a homomorphism between the situations of the
                        American revolutionaries, Orc, and Mallet’s Odin, in terms of their
                        relationships to martial power, a homomorphism in which the female occupies
                        the same position as the Amerindians, and the Northern Europeans, in being
                        the object of violence and conquest for a revolutionary figure who fights on
                        behalf of the oppressed. Wars between the colonists and the first nations
                        began before the American Revolution, and continued in the context of the
                        Revolution, since most of the aboriginal peoples of the northeast, including
                        the Iroquois Confederacy and the Delaware, sided with the British. The
                        revolutionaries were thus in the ideologically contradictory position of
                        trying to conquer one group while crying for liberty from another. Orc is
                        placed in a similarly contradictory position, identifying himself with
                        animals engaged in violent activities and seizing another against her will,
                        and then speaking on behalf of the oppressed Americans of European descent.
                            <note id="n214"><hi rend="s">6</hi> The rape has been described as
                            “desire fulfilling itself” (Doskow 176), “patriots
                            . . . making love to good earth” (Erdman 261), and Orc’s
                            attempt to “give his voice, and his passion, to silent
                            nature” (Bloom 120). More recently, Michael Ferber has
                            acknowledged the problem of “identifying the actions of the
                            American colonists . . . with a violent act” (95), but resolves
                            it by characterizing the rape as “a reclamation of the usurped
                            land by those who deserve her” (96). This reclaimed
                            “land,” however, complains at the end of the Preludium of
                            “eternal death” (2.17), “limb rending pains”
                            (2.15), “howling pains” (2.16), and
                            “torment” (2.17), and the bard of the canceled lines
                            echoes her “cry” (2.6) with “sick &amp; drear
                            lamentings” (2.21). The only reference to joy is limited to the
                            womb—“It joy’d” (2.4), not
                            “she,” or “he” for that matter. Even if the
                            rape has positive consequences, as fertilization or as the release of
                            the female’s voice, the act itself is one of violence and
                            conquest, and the final lines of the Preludium draw attention to the
                            negative implications of that violence, not a justification of
                            it.</note>
	<note id="n215"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The phrase, “my American
                            plains” (2.10), could be used to identify the female as a
                            personification of those plains (see, e.g., Doskow and Erdman), but the
                            detail that concerns me is the word “my”: whether the
                            plains are external to her body or are tropologically equated with it,
                            she asserts that they are hers.</note></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">America</hi>, through the figure of Odin, Blake narrows the
                        scope of his rebel to anti-imperial rebellion, a focus that is not
                        especially relevant to the other works in which Orc appears. Like Odin,
                        Orc’s colonists liberate a nation from imperial rule, but it is a
                        nation that they have themselves “siez’d.” Thus, in his
                        celebration of the American Revolution, Blake, like Mallet, does not elide
                        the investment of the revolutionaries in violence and conquest, the violence
                        and conquest through which they, like Mallet’s Odin, gained the
                        ground from which they fought against their own subjugation to imperial
                        rule. Orc’s violence does not erode the legitimacy of the rebellion,
                        against Urthona or Albion’s Angel, and need not be legitimized as a
                        means to that end, but stands as a reminder that to engage the struggle for
                        power is to be contaminated by the means of that struggle.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Works Cited</title>
            </head>
            <p>Baine, Rodney M. <hi rend="i">The Scattered Portions: William
                                Blake’s Biological Symbolism.</hi> Athens, GA: privately
                            printed, 1986.</p>
            <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “‘This Accursed Family’:
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and the American
                            Revolution.” <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century</hi> 27 (1986):
                            26-51.</p>
            <p>Bell, John. <hi rend="i">Bell’s New Pantheon.</hi> 1790. 2 vols.
                            New York: Garland, 1979. Vol. 2.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman. Rev. ed. Toronto: Doubleday,
                            1988.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic
                                Argument.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1963.</p>
            <p>Doskow, Minna. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">America:</hi>
                            The Story of a Revolution Betrayed.” <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Studies</hi> 8 (1979): 167-86.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire.</hi> Rev.
                            ed. Garden City: Doubleday, 1969.</p>
            <p>Ferber, Michael. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and the
                            Birth of Revolution.” <hi rend="i">History and Myth: Essays on
                                English Romantic Literature.</hi> Ed. Stephen C. Behrendt. Detroit:
                            Wayne State UP, 1990. 73-99.</p>
            <p>Gray, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Descent of Odin.</hi> 1768. <hi rend="i">The Works of Thomas
Gray in Prose and Verse.</hi> Ed. Edmund Gosse.
                            4 vols. New York: AMS P, 1968. 1: 59-65.</p>
            <p>Lemprière, John. <hi rend="i">Classical Dictionary of Proper Names
                                Mentioned in Ancient Authors Writ Large.</hi> 1788. 3rd ed. New
                            York: Routledge, 1984.</p>
            <p>Mallet [Paul Henri]. <hi rend="i">Northern Antiquities.</hi> Trans.
                            Bishop Percy. 1770. Additional notes and text by I. A. Blackwell.
                            London: Bohn, 1859.</p>
            <pb id="p26-29" n="29"/>
            <p>Schorer, Mark. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Politics of Vision.</hi>
                            New York: Holt, 1946.</p>
            <p>Snorre Sturlason. <hi rend="i">Ynglinga Saga. Heimskringla: The Norse
                                King Sagas.</hi> Trans. S. Laing. 1844. Rev. ed. New York: Dutton,
                            1951. 7-43.</p>
            <p>Warton, Thomas. “Of the Origin of Romantic Fiction in
                            Europe.” 1774. <hi rend="i">The History of English Poetry.</hi> 3
                            vols. Additional Notes by Ritson, Ashby et al. London: Tegg, 1840. 1:
                            i-lvi.</p>
            <p>All quotations of Blake’s writings are taken from Erdman’s
                            edition, and will be from <hi rend="i">America</hi> unless otherwise
                            noted; quotations of the poetry will be cited by plate and line number,
                            and references to the prose will be cited by page number.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <figure n="Tarot.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="452"/>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
