<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.1.sketches</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Two Newly Identified Sketches for Thomas Commins’s An Elegy and Further
Rediscovered Drawings of the 1780s</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>E.B. Bentley</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Srigley</name>
              <name>Joan K. Stemmler</name>
              <name>Julia M. Wright</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <pb id="p26-21" n="21"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Two Newly Identified Sketches for Thomas Commins’s <hi rend="i">An Elegy</hi>
and Further Rediscovered Drawings of the
                            1780s</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Three typical pen and wash drawings of the 1780’s, two on one sheet of
                        paper, have turned up in the United States. Two seem to be related to Thomas
                        Commin’s <hi rend="i">An Elegy</hi>, while the other appears to be an
                        independent composition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n201"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n201"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I am indebted to Henry Wemyss of
                            Sotheby’s, London, for letting me know of the existence of the
                            drawings in the United States and for letting me have
                            photographs.</note></p>
          <p>In my catalogue I listed, as number 98, a “Sketch for Thomas
                        Commins’s ‘An Elegy,’” the only evidence for
                        which was the fact that it was in possession of Messrs. Robson in 1913.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n202" type="note">2</ref> The newly identified sheet of drawings
                        may be this work, but the two drawings are different enough from
                        Blake’s finished engraving for the identification to have been easily
                        missed in 1913; if so, there is a further drawing waiting to be discovered.
                            <note id="n202"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Martin Butlin. <hi rend="i">The
                                Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven, CT: Yale
                            UP, 1981) 38 no. 98, the engraving repr. pl. 103. In the rest of this
                            article references to my catalogue are given in the form
                            “B98.”</note></p>
          <p>Blake designed and engraved the frontispiece for Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, published
in 1786. The engraving itself is
                        inscribed “W.Blake del<hi rend="s">t</hi>. &amp; sculp<hi rend="s">t</hi>.” (the
identification of the final raised letter 
<figure n="Commin.Elegy.Frontispiece.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="414">
	<head>1. Frontispiece to Thomas Commin’s <hi rend="i">An
                                    Elegy</hi>, 1786.</head>
	<figDesc>Hand-tinted etching and engraving, 17.3 × 13.8 cm.,
                                British Museum, London.</figDesc>
</figure> is not altogether clear). Below the design are four lines of
                        verse, arranged in two columns: 
						<q> The shatter’d bark from adverse
                            winds<lb/>
 Rest in this peaceful haven finds<lb/>
 And when the storms of
                            life are past<lb/>
 Hope drops her anchor here at last. </q>
Below is the
                        publisher’s imprint: “Published July 1. 1786 by J. Fentum N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 78
Corner of Salisbury Street, Strand” (on the
                        British Museum copy the final word is almost lost through the wearing of the
                        paper; it is reconstructed here on the basis of the imprint at the head of
                        the music itself).</p>
          <p>The engraved design shows a young man leaping out of an anchored boat towards
                        a young woman and child, presumably his family, awaiting him on the shore;
                        behind are trees and what appears to be a cliff (illus. 1). The design is
                        framed by a border of palm fronds, forming an upright oval. (The British
                        Museum copy is colored by 
<pb id="p26-22" n="22"/>
<figure n="Commins.Elegy.AltDesign.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="414">
	<head>2. Alternative design for Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>
                                c. 1786.</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil on paper, cut irregularly, approx 34.0
                                × 26.5cm. Private collection, U.S.A.</figDesc>
</figure> hand, but a relative lack of subtlety, and in particular the way
                        in which the color runs over the edges of the forms in the framing oval,
                        suggests the work of an amateur, not Blake himself.)</p>
          <p>The full title of Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, at the head of
                        the first of five pages of music (printed on three sheets of paper), is
                        “AN ELEGY / set to Music by / THO<hi rend="s">s</hi>: Commins,/
                        Organist of Penzance, Cornwall./LONDON./Printed &amp; sold by J. Fentum,
                            N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 78, corner Salisbury S<hi rend="s">t</hi>..,
                        Strand.” The verses accompanying the music run (with a long
                        “s” used whenever appropriate): 
						<q> Sigh not ye winds as
                            passing o’er the Chambers of the dead ye fly,<lb/>
 Weep not ye
                            dews for these no more shall ever weep, shall ever sigh.<lb/>
 Why mourn
                            the throbbing heart at rest<lb/>
 How still it lies within the
                            breast<lb/>
 Why mourn since death presents us peace,<lb/>
 And in the
                            grave our sorrows cease.<lb/>
<lb/>
 [The last two lines are repeated,
                            followed by the first two lines]<lb/>
<lb/>
 The shatter’d Bark
                            from adverse winds<lb/>
 Rest in this peaceful Heaven finds<lb/>
 And when
                            the storms of Life are past<lb/>
 Hope drops her Anchor here at
                            last.<lb/>
<lb/>
 [The last two lines are repeated]. </q>
<figure n="Commins.Elegy.Sketch.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="292">
	<head>3. Sketch for Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, c. 1786
                                (verso of illus. 2).</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil on paper, cut irregularly, approx 26.5
                                × 34.0 cm. Private collection, U.S.A.</figDesc>
</figure> It is noticeable that in the song text the
                        “shatter’d Bark” finds rest in a peaceful
                        “Heaven” whereas in the lines below the frontispiece rest is
                        found in a peaceful “Haven”; this last is closer to what Blake
                        illustrates in his engraving.</p>
          <p>The recto of the rediscovered sheet of drawings shows a much varied version
                        of the engraved design, in reverse (illus. 2). An older, bearded man gets
                        out of the boat in a considerably less agile fashion, looking apprehensively
                        over his shoulder the while; two angels await him on the shore, and there
                        are trees behind. The composition is again an upright oval, within a roughly
                        drawn outline. The presence of the angels gives a greater feeling of Heaven
                        than in the engraving.</p>
          <p>This however is absent from the drawing on the reverse, in which a young man
                        has just finished rowing his boat into a small creek or haven (illus. 3).
                        There are no figures on the shore. Again there are trees behind but of a
                        totally different kind. The composition is an oblong. In the lower
                        right-hand quarter of the drawing there is what may be the beginnings of an
                        oval composition which would have continued to the right over the cut edge
                        of the existing paper. This drawing presumably preceded the one on the
                        recto, before even the format of the final engraving had been
                        determined.</p>
          <p>Another rediscovered drawing in the same American collection, and apparently
                        sharing the same provenance, is similar in style and, like the two drawings
                        here related to Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, datable to the
                        early or mid seventeen eighties (illus. 4). It shows three groups of figures
                        in what seems to be Heaven. Three bearded men float in the air just to the
                        left of center, facing the spectator, and another group of three figures,
                        one old, two young, float on the right facing two middle-aged dark-bearded
                        men who soar up from the left. In general character, and in the long flowing
                        robes ending in scroll-like folds, the drawing resembles the group of pen
                        and ink drawings illustrating scenes from the Old Testament, B112-4 in my
                        catalogue.</p>
          <p>Various inscriptions together with an attached piece of paper bearing a
                        printed title on the back of the first drawing indicate that it comes from
                        the collection of Henry Cunliffe “of the South Kensington
                        Museum.” Two inscriptions in ink are similar in handwriting 
<pb id="p26-23" n="23"/>
and in the mistakes they embody to inscriptions on
                        other drawings that belonged to Henry Cunliffe, B69, 113, 119<hi rend="s">A</hi>, 144,
190 and 650. The inscription to the right reads “A
                        Sketch by William Blake. Obit 12 Aug. 1828/For a Biog<hi rend="s">Y</hi> of
                        B. see Cunninghams British Painters.” The reference is to Allan
                        Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters,
                            Sculptors, and Architects</hi>, first published in 1830 and again, with
                        a more balanced account of Blake, the same year; this is the source for the
                        mistaken date of Blake’s death (actually 1827). The inscription to
                        the left reads “Purchased at Sothebys in a Lot/28 Ap. 1862.”
                        Again there is a mistake: the anonymous sale, but one long identified as
                        being of works from the collection of Frederick Tatham, took place on the
                        29th of April.</p>
          <p>A further inscription, in pencil and running along the left-hand side of the
                        drawing, reads “From the Collection of Henry Cunliffe/of the South
                        Kensington Museum.” To the left of this is a printed title, “A
                        Man getting out of a Boat, two angels standing by him,/trees in the
                        background, <hi rend="i">in water-colours</hi>, with a Sketch/in pencil of a
                        man rowing a boat on the back.” This can be identified as coming from
                        the catalogue of the sale at Sotheby’s on 11 May 1895 of, inter alia,
                        “. . . A Series of Drawings by W. Blake, The Property of the Late
                        Henry Cunliffe, Esq.. ..”; the title is that of lot 105, bought by
                        Keppel for sixteen shillings.</p>
          <p>The works from the Cunliffe collection in the 1895 sale comprise, as well as
                        four lots by other artists, 10 lots containing works attributed to Blake,
                        numbers 96 to 105 (plus an india proof impression of the portrait by Linnell
                        of Blake), but none of the more important illuminated books that passed to
                        Henry Cunliffe’s nephew Walter, grandfather of the present Lord
                        Cunliffe. With the reappearance of these two sheets of drawings it seems
                        that one can now identify all the drawings in the 1895 sale and, in turn,
                        those purchased by Henry Cunliffe in 1862.</p>
          <figure n="AnEncounterinHeaven.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="326">
            <head>4. “An Encounter in Heaven,” c. 1780-85.</head>
            <figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil on paper, approx 30.5 × 40.5 cm.
                            Private collection, U.S.A.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>The 10 lots containing Blakes consist of 13 works in all, 12 drawings and one
                        print, although not every individual work is described and even those that
                        are described are often described in fairly vague terms. Certain lots can be
                        identified straightaway: 96, “A Group of Five Figures (one on
                        Horseback), a town in the background with mountains in the distance, the man
                        and woman in the centre are supposed to represent Blake and his Wife, <hi rend="i">a
highly finished drawing in indian ink, apparently intended to
                            illustrate some story</hi>” is the finished drawing finally
                        identified in 1978 as an illustration to Robert Bage’s 
<hi rend="i">Hermsprong</hi>(B682); 97, “PESTILENCE. An allegorical design in
                        water colours of five figures and corpses” is B190, the version of
                        the much repeated composition later, like the <hi rend="i">Hermsprong</hi>
                        illustration, in the collections of William and George Bateson; 100,
                        “The Canterbury Pilgrims, the original drawing by Blake from the
                        picture to reduce the subject to the size of his plate, <hi rend="i">in
                            pencil</hi>” is B654, which was bought in at the 1895 sale,
                        eventually passed to the Hon. Merlin Cunliffe and now belongs to the British
                        Museum; 101, “Jane Shore doing Penance, <hi rend="i">highly finished
                            in watercolours, varnished</hi>” is B69, now in the Tate Gallery;
                        102, “Queen Emma walking over the red hot plough-shares,”
                        similarly described, is B59, in a private collection; 103, “The Witch
                        of Endor raising Samuel, <hi rend="i">spirited drawing in
                        water-colours</hi>” is B144, now in the New York Public Library; 104,
                        “Good and Evil Spirits contending for the possession of a Child, <hi rend="i">an
allegorical subject in water-colours</hi>” is,
                        despite the medium given in the catalogue, the version of the large color
                        print of “1795” formerly in the collection of Mr. &amp; Mrs.
                        John Hay Whitney, B324.</p>
          <p>This leaves lots 98 and 99, which together with lots 103 and the rediscovered
                        lot 105 were bought by Keppel, apparently the New York dealer Frederick
                        Keppel, whose son David gave B119A, a drawing of <hi rend="i">Goliath
                            cursing David</hi>, to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, in 1914;
                        Frederick himself had bequeathed an impression of <hi rend="i">The
                            Accusers</hi> to the same museum in October 1913.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n203" type="note">3</ref> The only other recorded purchase of a Blake by
                        Keppel apart from those at this sale was at Sotheby’s on 8 July 1895
                        when he bought lot 125, <hi rend="i">Death on a Pale Horse</hi>, 
<pb id="p26-24" n="24"/>
now in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge (B517). In
                        addition, in about 1919-20 his firm owned the separate color-printed design
                        from plate 12 of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> now in the Pierpont Morgan
                        Library, New York (B261 <hi rend="i">10</hi>), and also a copy of the
                        title-page to <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n204" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n203"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The
                                Separate Plates of William Blake</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP,
                            1983) 33 no. 3D.</note>
	<note id="n204"><hi rend="s">4</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977) 162.</note></p>
          <p>Lot 98 is described as “A Sketch in sepia of Angels with spirits of
                        women approaching them; and two other Sketches.” Lot 99 was “A
                        Group of Six Greek Warriors, <hi rend="i">in pen and ink</hi>; and a fine
                        impression of the Child of Nature, after C. Borckhardt, by W. Blake, 
<hi rend="i">fastened together at the corners.</hi>” It is tempting
                        to identify the drawing of eight airborne figures, which seems to have the
                        same provenance as lot 105, definitely bought by Keppel, as the main work in
                        lot 98, the “Sketch in sepia of Angels with the spirits of women
                        approaching them.” This allows for the habitual inaccuracy of
                        descriptions in sale catalogues, particularly from as long ago as 1895: at a
                        very quick look two of the figures on the right just could be women!</p>
          <p>Two further drawings with typical Cunliffe inscriptions on the back are
                        otherwise unaccounted for in the 1895 sale: B113, <hi rend="i">The Elders of
                            Israel receiving the Ten Commandments (?)</hi>, and B119A, <hi rend="i">Goliath
cursing David</hi>, already mentioned as having belonged to
                        David Keppel. This last, again allowing for a fair laxity in description,
                        could, given the round shields carried by three of its six figures, be the
                        “Group of Six Greek Warriors” of lot 99. Assuming one of the
                        undescribed drawings in lot 98 to be B113, <hi rend="i">The Elders of
                            Israel</hi> . . ., one further work remains to be discovered and,
                        conveniently, one of the drawings reported in my last article on
                        rediscovered Blakes seems to fit the gap.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n205" type="note">5</ref> This is the sketch for <hi rend="i">Joseph’s Brethren
                            bowing before him</hi> discovered by David Bindman in Berlin which also,
                        David Bindman tells me, bears the typical Cunliffe inscription
                        “Purchased in a Lot at Sothebys 28 April 1862 HC<corr type="emend">”</corr>
                        together with “A Sketch by William Blake Obit 12 August 1828./In
                        Cunninghams Lives of British Painters Ch.1 Blake”; there is also an
                        inscription matching the pencil inscription on the drawing for
                        Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, “From the collection of
                        Henry Cunliffe of the South Kensington Museum.” <note id="n205"><hi rend="s">5</hi>
Martin Butlin, “Six New Early Drawings by
                            William Blake and a Reattribution,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23
                            (1989) 110-11, repr. fig. 6.</note></p>
          <p>It is of course tempting to equate any known drawing one can find with those
                        that one knows to be missing, but at least the total number of works now
                        matches up and, although I have been caught out making similar
                        identifications in the past that have subsequently proved to be inaccurate,
                        it is at least for the present a working hypothesis that we now have all the
                        drawings sold by Henry Cunliffe in 1895. One can also venture further and
                        see how these 12 drawings fit with the only 12 works to have been bought by
                        Toovey in the Frederick Tatham sale held at Sotheby’s on 29 April
                        1862, some of which can quite definitely be shown to have been in Henry
                        Cunliffe’s collection. The lots bought by Toovey were as follows:
                        161, “The Original reduced Drawing of the Canterbury Pilgrimage, from
                        which he [Blake] engraved his plate,” lot 100 in 1895, B654; 170,
                        “A Pestilence, and other designs, <hi rend="i">in indian
                        ink</hi>,” six works in all, of which the named work was lot 97 in
                        1895, B190; 171, “Queen Emma walking over the red hot Ploughshares,
                        and Jane Shore doing Penance, <hi rend="i">both highly finished in
                            colours</hi>,” lots 102 and 101 respectively in 1895, B59 and 69;
                        175, “The Witch of Endor raising the Spirit of Samuel, <hi rend="i">in
colours</hi>,” lot 103 in 1895, B144; 182, “An
                        Allegorical Subject - A Man holding a Child, with a chained demon issuing
                        from a fiery abyss, <hi rend="i">highly finished in colours</hi>,”
                        lot 104 in 1895, B324; and 184, “A Design, apparently intended in
                        illustration of a tale, <hi rend="i">highly finished in indian
                        ink</hi>,” lot 96 in 1895, B682. Lot 195 was also bought by Toovey,
                        “Another set” of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                            Experience</hi> “wanting three plates,” the posthumous
                        Copy i still in the Cunliffe collection. The five unidentified works in lot
                        170, all described as being “<hi rend="i">in indian ink</hi>,”
                        can therefore be equated with the following five works sold in 1895: 98,
                        “A Sketch in sepia of Angels . . . and two other Sketches,”
                        three works in all; 99, “A Group of Six Greek Warriors, <hi rend="i">in pen and
ink</hi>,” sold with the print of the “Child
                        of Nature”; and 105, “A Man getting out of a Boat . . . <hi rend="i">in
watercolours</hi>, with a Sketch in pencil of a man rowing a
                        boat on the back.” Q.E.D.!</p>
          <p>After all this supposition it should be easy enough to say something about
                        “Henry Cunliffe of the South Kensington Museum.” But, despite
                        the helpfulness of the present Lord Cunliffe and of Ronald Parkinson and his
                        colleagues at the Victoria and Albert Museum, as the South Kensington Museum
                        is now known, there seems to be very little information. The present Lord
                        Cunliffe’s great-great-uncle Henry Cunliffe was born in 1827 and died
                        in 1883, apparently in Germany; he is buried in the family plot at Headly in
                        Surrey. He was, typically for a number of mid nineteenth-century Blake
                        collectors, primarily a bibliophile and left his collection of books to his
                        favorite nephew Walter Cunliffe. Unfortunately, there is no record of a
                        Henry Cunliffe at the V &amp; A either in the diaries of Sir Henry Cole,
                        the famous director from its beginnings until 1873 (but there is mention of
                        an Edward Cunliffe), nor is he mentioned in the Precis and Board Minutes
                        between 1863 and 1877. (Just to confuse matters, Sir Francis Philip
                        Cunliffe-Owen, who lived from 1828 until 1894, did work at the Victoria
                        &amp; Albert Museum, having owed his first post in the Science &amp; Art
                        Department to the recommendation of his elder brother Lieutenant Colonel
                        Henry Charles Cunliffe-Owen [1821-67] who, in the course of a mainly
                        military career had been connected with the Great Exhibition of 1851 and was
                        also inspector of Art Schools under the Board of Trade; in 1857 Francis
                        CunliffeOwen became deputy general-superintendent at the South Kensington
                        Museum under Sir Henry Cole, in 1860 assistant director, and in 1873, in
                        succession to Cole, full director. In the 1850s and 1860s the Cunliffe-Owens
                            <pb id="p26-25" n="25"/>
called themselves Owen, which further
                        distinguishes them from our Henry Cunliffe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n206" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n206"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For the Cunliffe-Owens see the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National
Biography.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Two further pen and wash drawings of the 1780s, listed in my catalogue as
                        untraced and not reproduced there, have turned up recently. B139, called 
<hi rend="i">The Bed of Death</hi> and cataloged as untraced since the sale
                        at Christie’s on 15 July 1957, has re-emerged and been reproduced in
                        the catalogue for the Christie’s sale of 9 July 1991, Lot 86. This
                        has been reproduced and discussed by Robert N. Essick in the last issue of
                            <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 25 (1992) 148, fig. 4. Whether the drawing
                        really shows a death bed seems unlikely, and it is certainly not related,
                            <hi rend="i">pace</hi> my catalogue entry, to my numbers B137 verso and
                        138. (The 1991 Christie’s catalogue also reproduces, at lot 85, the
                        Visionary Head of <hi rend="i">Jonathan</hi> in its present state; it was
                        previously reproduced, unrestored, in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> following its
                        sale at Christie’s on 9 July 1985.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n207" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n207"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the
                            Marketplace 1985,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 20 (1986) repr. p. 16,
                            fig. 3.</note></p>
          <p>The other rediscovered drawing, <hi rend="i">Lady Macbeth approaching the
                            Sleeping Duncan</hi> (illus. 5) is much more exciting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n208" type="note">8</ref> Its position in my catalogue, as B249, is too late;
                        rather, as hinted at in my entry, it should be placed earlier as one of the
                        pen and wash drawings of about 1785. The full medium is pen and wash over
                        pencil on laid paper watermarked “JWHATMAN.” As well as the
                        usual grey wash there is some brown along the draperies down the back of
                        Lady Macbeth and below her left hand. The paper seems to have been trimmed
                        all round, cutting the inscription “Blake,” perhaps a
                        signature, in the lower right-hand corner. The drawing illustrates the
                        passage from act II, scene ii of <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>, where Lady
                        Macbeth describes how 
						<q> I laid their daggers ready,<lb/>
 He could not miss
                            ’em. Had he not resembled<lb/>
 My father as he slept, I had
                            done’t </q>
This is in fulfillment of Macbeth’s
                        suggestion, in act I, scene vii, that he should use the daggers belonging to
                        Duncan’s two chamberlains, made drunk by Lady Macbeth, so that it
                        would look as if they had committed 
<figure n="LadyMacbeth.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="334">
	<head>5. “Lady Macbeth and the Sleeping Duncan,”
                                c.1785.</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and grey and brown washes over pencil, on paper, trimmed,
                                32.7 × 42.6 cm. Thos. Agnew &amp; Sons, Ltd,
                                London.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="LadyMacbeth.verso.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="359">
	<head>6. Verso of “Lady Macbeth and the Sleeping Duncan,”
                                c. 1785.</head>
	<figDesc>Pencil with some brown wash on paper, trimmed, 32.7 ×
                                42.6 cm. Thos. Agnew &amp; Sons, Ltd, London.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p26-26" n="26"/>
the deed. Blake shows Lady Macbeth with the daggers
                        standing over the sleeping Duncan, who has gone to bed with his crown on.
                            <note id="n208"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Andrew Wyld of Thos. Agnew &amp;
                            Sons, Ltd, told me about the drawing in London, let me examine it and,
                            again, supplied photographs. I am most grateful to my friends among art
                            dealers and auctioneers in keeping me informed about works by Blake as
                            they turn up.</note></p>
          <p>On the reverse there is a variant in pencil alone of the same composition,
                        inscribed, again in the lower right-hand corner, “Lady Macbeth/King
                        Duncan” (illus. 6). Also on the reverse, with the paper to be seen as
                        an upright with the left-hand edge at the bottom, is a slightly inclined
                        profile facing right, just possibly a study for the profile of Lady Macbeth.
                        On the reverse she stands on the right, leaning over Duncan in a much more
                        threatening manner than on the recto; he lies as before except that his left
                        arm seems to lie across his chest. Pentimenti on the recto show that Lady
                        Macbeth was originally in the same stooping position as on the verso; Blake
                        also drew her in an intermediary position before finally adopting the
                        present upright stance. The drawings therefore are a particularly
                        interesting example of how Blake improvised his compositions. Some of the
                        forms of the recto have come out on the verso, perhaps because it was drawn
                        with the paper laid on a dirty surface, and some of the brownish wash also
                        appears on the reverse, presumably as the result of an accident.</p>
          <p>The drawing, which is listed by William Rossetti as indicated in my entry,
                        seems to be one of the items in lot 165 in the Tatham sale at
                        Sotheby’s on 29 April 1862, “Lady Macbeth and Duncan, Angels
                        conducting the Souls of the Just to Paradise, &amp;c. <hi rend="i">in
                            indian ink</hi>,” four items in all, bought by Palser for
                        thirteen shillings; the lot comes among other drawings that can be
                        identified as pen and wash drawings of the 1780s. The recent history of the
                        drawing is no clearer than was indicated in my entry; all that can be said
                        is that it has recently turned up in the trade. Rossetti’s dismissive
                        description, “Not carried far beyond the outline. Ordinary”
                        seems far from the mark. In fact the drawing is one of the most dramatic and
                        boldly drawn of this whole group.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
