<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.2.wittreich</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">“An Unperishing Sun . . . This Golden Age”: Joachimism and Heaven in the Age of Blake;
Marjorie Reeves and Warwick Gould, Joachim of Fiore and the Myth of the Eternal Evangel in the Nineteenth Century; 
Colleen McDannell and Bernhard Lang, Heaven: A History</title>
        <author n="Wittreich">Joseph Wittreich</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Jeffery D. Parker</name>
              <name>Marsha Keith Schuchard</name>
              <name>Irene Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-58" n="58"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main" rend="main">“An Unperishing Sun . . . This Golden Age”: Joachimism and Heaven in the Age
of Blake</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Marjorie Reeves and Warwick Gould. <hi rend="i">Joachim of Fiore and the Myth
of the Eternal Evangel in the Nineteenth Century.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1987. x + 365 pp. 3 illus.
$65.00. Colleen McDannell and Bernhard Lang. <hi rend="i">Heaven: A History.</hi> New Haven and London: Yale
University Press, 1988. xiv + 410 pp. 69 illus. $35.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Joseph <name>Wittreich</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Diminishing in number over the last decade, contextualizations of Blake (if we may judge from the
two books here under review) are undiminished in their historical savvy, methodological sophistication, and
critical acuity.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n0">The terms in the title of this essay derive from a poem, “Eternal Evangel,” in the second
volume (entitled <hi rend="i">Medieval Legends</hi>) of the Czech poet Jaroslav Vrchlicky’s 
<hi rend="i">Frescoes and Tapestries</hi> (Prague, n. d.) 166-68, reprinted in Reeves and Gould, 
<hi rend="i">Joachim of Fiore</hi> (323-25).</note> Rigorous interrogations, both books effect reconsideration,
refinement, and sometimes a complete recasting of critical cliches and cultural commonplaces. Moreover, each
of these books confirms what has become a working premise of Blake criticism: namely, that what matters for
Blake is less the tradition than his transgressions of it.</p>
          <p>Taking Joachim of Fiore as “a classic example of the problems which arise in assessing the
nature and extent of influence in the realm of ideas” (7), Marjorie Reeves and Warwick Gould challenge a
line of historical investigation that, commencing with G. K. Chesterton, also comprehends J. G. Davies, A. L.
Morton, Désirée Hirst, and J. F. C. Harrison, according to whom Joachimism is a shaping influence on Blake.
But it is an influence not so much direct as oblique and trackable chiefly through the writings of
mid-seventeenth-century millennial tracts. The authors of this book are insistent questioners: “what
substance is there in the claim that he [Blake] knew of, and consciously drew upon, the Joachimist myth of the
Eternal Evangel?” To which question they respond emphatically, thus giving their imprimatur to a conclusion
also advanced by David Erdman: “a Joachimist perspective in Blake’s poem does not provide a satisfactory
reading of the poem, nor does it really cast any new light on Blake’s antinomianism, nor does it help us to
understand his other ‘prophetic books,’ nor does it really contribute to our understanding of his concept
of the alternating of ‘good’ and ‘evil’. . .” (33-34). Nor has the case for an allusion to Joachim
in Blake’s title, “The Everlasting Gospel,” been proved (38). Rather, Reeves and Gould argue, there is
“no clear evidence of a consciously held Joachimist tradition that can be found among the
mid-seventeenth-century English sectarians,” and while they have “no quarrel with the view that Blake was
heir to a complex antinomian tradition,” they nevertheless spurn the notion that “this tradition was in
itself a Joachimist one, and that Blake saw it as such”:
<q>
The conclusion must be . . . that the medieval heresy of the <hi rend="i">Evangelium Æternum</hi> adds
nothing to our appreciation of Blake and that it could not have formed a significant part of his sources in
the literature of the preceding two centuries. [In no way did Blake] initiate the nineteenth-century awareness
of Joachimism. In so far as there can be discerned any interest in the subject prior to George Eliot’s, it
is to be found, not in the writings of the millenarians and millenialists, but in the learned pages of the 
<hi rend="i">British Magazine</hi> in 1839-40, where the Hon. Algernon Herbert wrote as an unsympathetic antiquary
on <hi rend="i">Antichrist in the Thirteenth Century.</hi> (39)
</q>
The conclusion, very simply, is that “Of Joachim of Fiore’s complete system of thought . . . there would
appear
<figure n="ReevesGould.bkcover.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="388"/>
to have been little knowledge in the later seventeenth and eighteenth or early nineteenth centuries”
(40-41). The obvious caveat is that
<q>
influence is often oblique, not direct, and is to be charted according to hidden roads, not well-trodden
paths.
</q></p>
          <p>As Morton Paley remarks, Richard Hurd (1772) reveals “an awareness of millenarian
interpretation, . . . even referring to Joachim of Fiore.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n80" type="note">1</ref> Or in Mary Shelley’s <hi rend="i">Valperga</hi> (1823), Beatrice is
represented as one who “delighted to read and pretended to explain the prophecies of the sacred writings,
and the modern ones of Merlin, the abbot Joachim and Methodius.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n81" type="note">2</ref> Not just these but other such exclusions, once documented, tear at the fabric
of Reeves’s and Gould’s argument wherein complicating—even contradictory—evidence occasionally goes
unnoticed. For example: B. S. Capp’s citation of John Securis whose almanac of 1569 draws on the prophecies
of Joachim, as do the writings of Francis Moore or even those of Restoration figures like William Lilly who
turn to popular traditions that for Capp (if not for Reeves and Gould) derive ultimately from Joachim of
Fiore.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">3</ref> Or witness T. Wilson Hayes’s
reference to Collier Putney, one of whose sermons
<pb id="p26-59" n="59"/>
is said to contain a “clear statement of the Joachite concept [of history]”; or Katharine Firth’s
contention that John Knox’s quotations of, John Bale’s use of, and John Foxe’s comments upon Joachim
evince that his writings are part of the “intellectual inheritance of the Reformation,” even if their
influence is not easily summarized or ascertained.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83"
type="note">4</ref> And witness further Richard Bauckham’s acknowledgment of “the paucity of 
<hi rend="i">direct</hi> Joachist influence . . . [in Tudor England], despite the high reputation which Joachim
and his followers enjoyed,” together with the “many echoes of Joachist exegesis” that appear in some
writers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">5</ref> Consider, moreover, the
contrary argument of Frank and Fritzie Manuel that Joachimism, “a hidden force in heterodox medieval
thought,” is also “an active, unbroken tradition well into the seventeenth century” when much of the
discourse (and very notably Winstanley’s) has “a Joachimite resonance.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">6</ref> If such resonances go unheard, the silence may be owing to
the seemingly faulty premise (enunciated by Reeves) that the bond of prophecy, the conception of history
shared by the Middle Ages and Renaissance, thereafter ceases to be of importance, “except on the fringes of
modern civilization.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">7</ref> Quite to the
contrary, M. H. Abrams has shown the extent to which prophetic and apocalyptic traditions, including their
respective visions of history, are at the center of romanticism, the first phase of modernism. Like Reeves and
Gould, Abrams refers to the passage concerning “the time of a <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">new</hi> everlasting</corr> Gospel”
from  G. E. Lessing’s <hi rend="i">The Education of the Human Race</hi> (1780); but Abrams also argues,
contrary to Reeves and Gould, that the citation of “certain visionaries of the thirteenth and fourteenth
centuries” comprehends “Joachim . . . and his followers.” Later, Abrams speaks of “Schiller’s 
<hi rend="i">drittes Reich</hi>” (not mentioned by Reeves and Gould) as “an unmistakable allusion to the
apocalyptic ‘third kingdom’ which had been prophesied by Joachim of Fiore.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Morton Paley, <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime</hi> (New Haven and
London: Yale UP, 1986) 32.</note>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">2</hi> 3 vols. (G. and W. B. Whittaker, 1823) 2: 42.</note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">3</hi> B. S. Capp, <hi rend="i">English Almanacs 1500-1800: Astrology and the
Popular Press</hi> (Ithaca, N. Y.: Cornell UP, 1979) 166, 174, 252.</note>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See T. Wilson Hayes, <hi rend="i">Winstanley the Digger</hi> (Cambridge,
Mass. and London: Harvard UP, 1979) 225; and Katharine R. Firth, <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Tradition in
Reformation Britain 1530-1645</hi> (Oxford: Oxford UP, 1979) 2, 4-5.</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Richard Bauckham, <hi rend="i">Tudor Apocalypse</hi> (Oxford: Sutton
Courtenay Press, 1978) 25, 211 (my italics).</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Frank E, Manuel and Fritzie P. Manuel, <hi rend="i">Utopian Thought in the
Western World</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard UP, 1979) 50, 210.</note>
	<note id="n86"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Marjorie Reeves, <hi rend="i">The Influence of Prophecy in the Later
Middle Ages: A Study of Joachimism</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969) 508.</note>
	<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">8</hi> M. H. Abrams, <hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism: Tradition and
Revolution in Romantic Literature</hi> (New York and London: W. W. Norton, 1971) 202, 351.</note></p>
          <p>The point is not that Reeves and Gould are wrong. They simply do not engage—and thus they are
unable to extinguish—these contrary opinions. There is insufficient review, not to mention probing, of
alternative perspectives: that Joachim is a point of reference in Blake studies not because 
<hi rend="i">he</hi> influenced Blake but, instead, because he was a crucial figure in traditions—let’s say of
exegesis on The Book of Revelation—that most assuredly <hi rend="i">did influence Blake</hi>; that the
influence may be second-hand, deriving from esoteric traditions and sometimes figures like J. C. Mosheim who
are its conduits—or even on occasion from such marginalized writers as Mrs. Attaway and Jane Lead; that even
if Blake is not <hi rend="i">the</hi> romantic Joachimist, romanticism may very well have had a Joachimist in
Perch Bysshe Shelley whose visions of hope, whose envisioning of a quickened and enlarging consciousness, may
have moorings in Joachim’s notion of <hi rend="i">renovatio mundi.</hi></p>
          <p>If the pages dealing with Blake should be read with a suspicious eye, those devoted to later
authors—Pierre Leroux, George Sand, George Eliot, Ernest Renan, and Matthew Arnold, as well as (indeed 
<hi rend="i">especially</hi>) those devoted to John Addington Symonds, Walter Pater, Oscar Wilde, and W. B. Yeats
are rich, rewarding, riveting. In a powerful argument, full of deft observation, Yeats is shown to have used
“Joachim and Nietzsche to ‘complete’ Blake in what amounts to a revision of his earlier thinking about
the English poet and artist whose works he had edited in 1893” (202). Giving “a Joachimist slant” to
Blake, imposing “a Joachimist gloss” upon his writings, Yeats quickly turns a “Joachimist
reinterpretation of Blake . . . into a recognizably Nietzschean rereading of Blake” (232, 234).</p>
          <p>Joachimism thus becomes a point of contact between Blake and one of his most eminent
critics—and between Blake and the Romantic poet Shelley with whom he displays the greatest affinities, these
two poets humanizing apocalypse, historicizing prophecy, and simultaneously interiorizing both.</p>
          <figure n="McDannellLang.bkcover.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="364"/>
          <p>A less rigorously particularized scrutiny of Blake’s traditions is afforded by Colleen
McDannell and Bernhard Lang in <hi rend="i">Heaven: A History—</hi>a book that declares itself to be “a
‘social and cultural history’ of heaven” (xii) and that captures within its large embrace apocalyptic
and Hellenistic Judaism, early Christianity, the Church Fathers, Renaissance artists and writers (both
Catholic and Protestant), plus Milton, Swedenborg, and Blake quite notably. Early in the Renaissance, this
book argues, “heaven was split into two levels, one human and one divine” with both heavens thus receiving
their due but also with “the human side of heaven gain[ing] more prominence” as concepts like the earthly
garden, the new Jerusalem, and heavenly love are “redefined and brought into a new configuration” (111,
112). The Renaissance initiates the processes of historicizing, humanizing, secularizing, and interiorizing
that romanticism completes.</p>
          <p>This book goes a long way toward confirming the suspicion that Copernican theory, in a poem like
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, is an aspect of the poet’s “‘science of salvation’” (157), implying
an analogy between the physical and spiritual suns. Thus, as astronomy was heliocentric, so religious life was
theo- or Christocentric, “with the soul moving
<pb id="p26-60" n="60"/>
around the deity as its center” and with woman herself coming increasingly to fill “one part of that
divine center” (157, 167). This book provides an underpinning logic for Milton’s centering of both Christ
and Eve in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and for the prominence later accorded the emanation in Blake’s
mythological system. Between Milton and Blake, Swedenborg derives certain perspectives from Milton, even
occasionally echoing Milton’s writings. In the process, Swedenborg subverts the “theocentric model” of
heaven where worldly activities have no place and where the whole matter of “doing” is irrelevant: “the
modern heaven comes clearly into focus: a heaven near at hand, material, full of activity and progress, and
based on social relationships” (178, 228). If Milton is “a transitional figure in the development of an
anthropocentric heaven,” Swedenborg is the principal precursor of Blake and other romantic innovators for
whom man and woman are “fragments of a once primordial whole” and for whom heaven is a place of intense
mental activity, as well as highly developed social relationships—a place that, for Blake no less than for
Wordsworth, is to be found <hi rend="i">in this world</hi>, or not all (233, 234, 245). Among the unexpected
rewards of this book are the paths of influence it charts between Milton and Swedenborg and then the heady
observations it makes on Blake’s Swedenborgianism.</p>
          <p>Both of these books remind us that The Age of Blake was rife with prophetic expectations, which,
if they invoked the idea of returning to an Age of Gold, also made clear that what really mattered was the
forward thrust of history. The process envisioned was less a return to, or renewal of, past history than
escaping from it into a future that was, nevertheless, always located within history, though history in the
future tense. The prophet was not a proponent but rather an opponent of the reigning orthodoxies; his
obligation was not to predict but to create a future; and his—or her—means to that end was (Joachim-like)
to roll stones away from the mind, letting the light shine forth; or (Blakelike) to open the doors of
perception, thereby enlarging human consciousness and, simultaneously, bringing history to its consummation.
Whether or not the romantics read him, Joachim of Fiore prophesies their agenda and in the case of the
Shelleys, Mary no less than than Percy, particularizes their program, giving definition to their heaven on
earth—their paradise in history. 
                    </p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
