<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.2.parker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Hazard Adams, ed., Critical Essays on William Blake</title>
        <author n="Parker">Jeffrey D. Parker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Jeffery D. Parker</name>
              <name>Marsha Keith Schuchard</name>
              <name>Irene Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
	<pb id="p26-60" n="60"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-2-0008">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Critical Essays on William Blake.</hi> Ed. Hazard Adams. Boston:
G.K. Hall &amp; Co., 1991. 207 pp. $40.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Jeffrey D. <name>Parker</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The most recent edition to the Critical Essays on British Literature Series, under the general
editorship of Zack Bowen at the University of Miami, is <hi rend="i">Critical Essays on William Blake</hi>,
edited by Hazard Adams. For this volume Adams includes an introductory essay, sixteen previously published
essays, an afterward, and a selected bibliography. His introduction, like the volume itself, is divided into
two parts.</p>
          <p>Part one of the introduction provides a thumbnail sketch of Blake’s reputation and notes the
enormous amount of Blake scholarship accumulated during the past few decades. Adams then cites landmarks in
modern Blake scholarship beginning in 1924 with the publication of S. Foster Damon’s <hi rend="i">William
Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, followed in 1947 by Northrop Frye’s <hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry</hi>, and in 1954 by David V. Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Prophet Against Empire.</hi> Although other
scholars continued to follow the leads of Damon, Frye, and Erdman, the next major event does not occur until
1964 with the recognition of the important relationship between text and design. Inspired by Northrop Frye’s
pioneering essay “Poetry and Design in William Blake” published in 1951, the first detailed examination of
this new avenue of scholarship begins with the publication of Jean Hagstrum’s <hi rend="i">William Blake:
Poet and Painter</hi>, and is followed by the scholarship of David V. Erdman, David Bindman, Raymond Lister,
W. J. T. Mitchell, John Grant, Robert N. Essick,
<pb id="p26-61" n="61"/>
<figure n="Adams.review.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="361"/>
Morris Eaves, and Morton D. Paley. It is from the critical contributions by Frye, Erdman, Hagstrum, Mitchell,
Paley, and Essick that Adams selects six of the sixteen essays as representative examples of modern Blake
scholarship.</p>
          <p>In part two of his introduction Adams provides a rationale for having selected the sixteen essays
reprinted for this volume, and for dividing the collection into two parts. The first part of the collection
deals with Blake’s reputation in the nineteenth century and begins with Deborah Dorfman’s “Knowledge and
Estimation of Blake during His Lifetime,” followed by the well- known criticism of Blake by Robert Hunt in
“Mr. Blake’s Exhibition,” Allan Cunningham’s discussion of Blake from <hi rend="i">Lives of The Most
Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi>, and a selection from <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi>
by Henry Crabb Robinson. Also included in part one is a letter to Alexander Gilchrist from Samuel Palmer
providing information on Blake for Gilchrist’s biography. Although the majority of these essays are quite
familiar, they are included together here as examples of attitudes toward Blake during his lifetime.</p>
          <p>The second part of this volume draws from recent Blake criticism and is, according to Adams,
meant to be read sequentially. This is a bit curious since Adams does not arrange these essays in
chronological order, suggesting instead that the reader’s attention be focused on the varieties of critical
discourse rather than a concern for chronological developments in Blake scholarship as the first part of his
introduction implies. Part two also includes “Spectre and Emanation,” a selection from Morton D. Paley’s
<hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi>(1983), Steven Shaviro’s article “Striving with Systems: Blake and
the Politics of Difference” (1982), and “The Return to Logos” from <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
Language of Adam</hi> (1989) by Robert N. Essick, as examples of what Adams refers to as “the so-called
postmodern emphasis on difference, deconstruction, Hegelian negation, and language” (6). The inclusion of
these three essays by Paley, Shaviro, and Essick, produces a radically different Blake than the one presented
in the earlier essays in part two by Frye, Erdman, Hagstrum, and Mitchell. In order to remedy this disparity,
it would be more useful to the student unfamiliar with contemporary critical discourse, or for the generalist
audience for whom the book is intended, to have divided the book into three sections, with the third section
devoted to postmodern approaches to Blake.</p>
          <p>Given the editorial objectives of the Critical Essays on British Literature Series, one of which
is to develop a unique perspective on its subjects, Adams’ strategy is successful. By providing essays on
Blake from nineteenth century accounts of him, and, selections representative of major critical directions
taken by Blake scholars, Adams’ <hi rend="i">Critical Essays on William Blake</hi> underscores the wide
disparity between attitudes toward Blake’s art and poetry by his contemporaries, and the wide range of
critical directions taken by Blake scholars in the twentieth century.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
