<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.2.schuchard</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Secret Masonic History of Blake’s Swedenborg Society</title>
        <author n="Schuchard">Marsha Keith Schuchard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Jeffery D. Parker</name>
              <name>Marsha Keith Schuchard</name>
              <name>Irene Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-40" n="40"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">The Secret Masonic History of Blake’s Swedenborg Society</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Marsha Keith <name>Schuchard</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>Blake’s attitude toward Swedenborg and his devotees has long been the subject of controversy
among critics. That Blake and his family were Swedenborgians was once accepted as given fact, then rejected as
mythology, and subsequently resurrected as a real possibility.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref> However, most commentators have relied too heavily on Robert Hindmarsh’s 
<hi rend="i">Rise and Progress of the New Jerusalem Church</hi>, published posthumously in London in 1861. Few
have realized that Hindmarsh deliberately slanted the history to maximize his own role and to serve a
counter-revolutionary political agenda.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> Like Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Southey, Hindmarsh labored to cover up his own early
revolutionary leanings and to distance himself and the New Church from charges of subversive “illuminism.”
By omitting or distorting the dominant role of foreign Freemasons in organizing the New Jerusalem Temple in
London, Hindmarsh created a conservative, prudish, and inaccurate version of eighteenth-century
Swedenborgianism that fit comfortably into a Victorian milieu. Though Blake fit most uncomfortably into
Hindmarsh’s context, the visionary artist and radical prophet found a congenial—even
inspirational—milieu among the Masonic <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> who were the driving force behind the
Swedenborgian movement. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Morton Paley, “‘A New Heaven is Begun’:
William Blake and Swedenborgianism,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 12 (1979): 64-90, for a summary of opinion
until 1979 and for important source material on the Swedish context of events in England; also, Christopher
Heppner, “Blake’s ‘New Jerusalem Descending’: a Drawing (Butlin #92) Identified,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 20 (1986): 4-11.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Paley (87n8) warned that “Hindmarsh was not a disinterested party as
concerns the schisms within the New Jerusalem Church.” James Hyde, the able New Church historian, also
warned that the standard biography of Hindmarsh by Carl Odhner could not be trusted: “it shows no sense of
proportion, no historic perspective; it magnifies the insignificant, and belittles the worthy; it paints the
subject’s errors as his great achievements”; see “Some Notes Respecting Robert Hindmarsh,” 
<hi rend="i">New Church Magazine</hi> 24 (1905): 114-23.</note></p>
        <p>To bring to the surface these underground <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> of the 1780s, it is
necessary to dig back to their roots in an older clandestine world of international Jacobite-Masonic intrigue.
However, it is difficult to penetrate the network of “irregular” Freemasonry in England, because of the
oath-bound vows of secrecy and political risks incurred by members of foreign-affiliated lodges. These dangers
reached their peak during the recurrent Jacobite agitations after the 1745 rebellion,
<figure n="FreeMasonryCrownd.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="389">
	<head><hi rend="i">All illustrations are courtesy of the Library Museum of the United Grand Lodge of
England.</hi></head>
</figure>
the revolt of the American colonies in 1776, and the French invasion scare of 1798.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> At each of these periods, Freemasonry was deeply polarized
into revolutionary and loyalist factions (called generically the “Ancients” versus the “Moderns”), and
governmental crackdowns on the former led to destruction of rècords, surveillance of members, and closure of
lodges. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The standard but deficient histories of eighteenth-century
Freemasonry in England are Robert F. Gould, <hi rend="i">The History of Freemasonry</hi> (New York: John C.
Yorston, 1885), and Bernard Fay, <hi rend="i">Revolution and Freemasonry, 1680-1800</hi> (Boston: Little
Brown, 1935); for a recent corrective view, see Paul Monod, <hi rend="i">Jacobitism and the English
People</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1989) 300-05.</note></p>
        <p>From the time when Emanuel Swedenborg first visited London in 1710-13, his activities were shrouded
in deliberate obscurity and encoded documents, for he participated in the FrancoSwedish-Jacobite conspiracies
that gave the Hanoverian kings of England nightmares throughout his lifetime.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Returning many times to London between 1744 and 1772,
Swedenborg acted as a secret agent for the French king and the pro-French party in Sweden, known as the
“Hats.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> In fact, Louis XV
personally subsidized the anonymous publication of Swedenborg’s theosophical writings in London as a cover
for his espionage activities. To serve both his political agenda and his theosophical ambitions, Swedenborg
utilized a network of Masonic lodges in England and Sweden that were linked with sister lodges in France,
Holland, Germany, Poland, and Russia. By the time of his death in March 1772, these “illuminated” Masons
were laying the foundations of the Swedenborgian Theosophical Society that Blake joined in the 1780s. 
<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See my “Swedenborg, Jacobitism, and Freemasonry,” in <hi rend="i">Swedenborg
and His Influence</hi>, ed. Erland Brock (Bryn Athyn: Academy of New Church, 1988) 359-79; on Sweden’s
prolonged support of the Jacobites, see Claude Nordmann, <hi rend="i">Grandeur et Liberté de la Suède</hi>
(Paris: Beatrice-Nauwelaerts, 1971).</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See F. G. Lindh, “Swedenborgs Ekonomi,” <hi rend="i">Nya Kyrkans
Tidning</hi> (1929): 85-91, 112-18; and my “Yeats and the Unknown Superiors: Swedenborg, Falk, and
Cagliostro,” in <hi rend="i">Secret Texts</hi>, eds. Marie Roberts and Hugh Ormsby-Lennon (New York: AMS, in
press).</note></p>
        <p>The Swedish lodges of Blake’s day claimed to possess precious documents that contained the
Masonic secrets embedded in “the hieroglyphic language of the old Jewish wisdom books.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Some of these documents were obtained by
Swedenborg from Jewish and French Masons in London.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> During his visits to the city, Swedenborg often resided in the Queen’s Arms Tavern in
Wellclose Square, which hosted a French-affiliated lodge that welcomed Jewish Masons. His immediate neighbor
in the square was Dr. Samuel Jacob Falk, a Jewish alchemist and Cabalist, who became revered and feared as one
of the “Unknown Superiors” of illuminist Masonry.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref> Secretly associated with the radical Sabbatians of Poland and with French agents of the
Stuart cause, Falk instructed Swedenborg in Cabalistic trance techniques and sexual magic, which they believed
would usher in a spiritual and political millennium. <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> In-Ho Lee Ryu,
“Freemasonry Under Catherine the Great: a Reinterpretation” (Harvard University, Ph.D. Dissertation, 1967)
136, 145-59.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Detailed documentation on Swedenborg’s Masonic activities and Cabalistic
contacts will be given in my <hi rend="i">Emanuel, the Desire of Nations: Swedenborg, Jacobitism, and
Freemasonry</hi> (forthcoming).</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Hermann Adler, “The <hi rend="i">Baal Shem</hi> of London,” 
<hi rend="i">Transactions of the Jewish Historical Society of England</hi> (1908) 148-73.</note></p>
        <p>Both Falk and Swedenborg were associated with the “Rite of Seven Degrees,” a shadowy Masonic
order directed by Pierre Lambert de Lintot (a former French military officer, Jacobite agent, and talented
engraver), who initiated many visitors to London.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> Anglicizing his name as Peter Lambert, the artist infused Swedenborgian themes into the
mystical high degrees. He also produced a series of complex,
<pb id="p26-41" n="41"/>
hieroglyphical engravings that were widely sought by European Masons who believed they contained the key to
the Cabalistic arcana possessed by Falk and Swedenborg.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> That the ritual term “Los” was an important symbol in these degrees provides a new
perspective on Blake’s own symbolic figure of “Los” in his illuminist prophecies of the 1790s. 
<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> W. Wonnacott, “The Rite of Seven Degrees in London,” <hi rend="i">Ars Quatuor
Coronatorum</hi> [AQC] 39 (1926): 63-98; George Draffen, “Some Further Notes on the Rite of Seven Degrees in
London,” <hi rend="i">AQC</hi> 68 (1956): 94-110; Livre des délibérations de la loge de l’Union, #70 (c.
1772-90), Ms. BE 166 Uni, in Grand Lodge Library, London.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Erich Lindner, <hi rend="i">The Royal Art Illustrated</hi>, trans. Arthur
Lindsay (Graz: Akademische Druck, 1976) 136-46.</note></p>
        <p>Swedenborg successfully maintained his <hi rend="i">incognito</hi> in London until the 1760s, when
he began to receive many Masonic admirers. In 1769 he was visited by a group of alchemists—the chemist Peter
Woulfe, the musician Michael Arne, and the bankrupt Robert Peacock—who discussed Hermetic philosophy with
him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Receiving an unflattering
report about this discussion from Peacock, the French physician Benedict Chastanier decided not to call on
Swedenborg and, instead, pursued his own independent Masonic initiatives. Chastanier had become a high-ranking
Mason in France, and he was fascinated by Swedenborg’s anonymous writings. In 1767 he established a lodge of
<hi rend="i">Illuminés Théosophes</hi> in London; though the rituals drew on Swedenborgian symbolism,
Chastanier did not know the identity of the author of his source texts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Soon after this, the Marquis de Thomé (who had met
Swedenborg in Paris in 1769) began to assist his <hi rend="i">frère</hi> J. P. Moët (a royal librarian) in
translating Swedenborg’s works into French, and he established a special Swedenborgian rite in Paris by
1773.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Benedict Chastanier, <hi rend="i">A Word of Advice to a Benighted
World</hi> (London, 1795); rare copy in Royal Library, Stockholm.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Alain Le Bihan, <hi rend="i">Francs-Maçons et Atéliers Parisiens de la
Grand Loge de France au XVIIIe siècle</hi> (Paris: Bibliothèque Nationale, 1973) 53-239; Carl Lenning, 
<hi rend="i">Encyclopädie der Freimaurerei</hi> (Leipzig, 1822) 2: 448-49.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Le Bihan 239, 285-86; Alice Joly, “La ‘Sainte Parole’ des
Illuminés d’Avignon,” <hi rend="i">Les Cahiers de la Tour Saint-Jacques</hi> 2-4 (1960): 103; Antoine
Faivre, “Un familier des sociétés esoteriques: Bourée de Corberon,” <hi rend="i">Revue des sciences
humaines</hi>, n.s (January-March 1967): 260.</note></p>
        <p>Three years later, Chastanier learned that Swedenborg was the author of the books he so cherished,
and he determined to establish a Masonic society that would publish and disseminate the master’s writings.
Joining with those Masons who shared his devotion, Chastanier formed in 1776 the “London Universal Society
for the Promotion of the New Jerusalem Church.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> Maintaining a low profile because of the current government crackdown on “irregular”
and Ancient lodges, the Universal Society apparently included Peter Woulfe, Michael Arne, General Charles
Rainsford, Lord Percy, Reverend Thomas Hartley, Dr. Husband Messiter, Dr. William Spence, Edward Maubach,
Francis Barthelemon, and Henry Servanté. The artists Richard Cosway and Phillipe Jacques de Loutherbourg, who
were early admirers of Swedenborg and interested in Masonry, may also have supported the
Universalists.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> James Hyde, “Benedict Chastanier and the Illuminati of Avignon,” 
<hi rend="i">New-Church Review</hi> 14 (1907): 181-205.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> See my “Yeats”; also, “Blake’s ‘Mr. Femality’: Freemasonry,
Espionage, and the Double-Sex’d,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi> 122
(1992).</note></p>
        <p>Chastanier and Thomé joined forces with an ambitious lodge of occult research, the 
<hi rend="i">Philaléthes</hi>, which was launched in Paris in 1775 and which investigated the theosophical claims
of Falk, Swedenborg, and other <hi rend="i">gurus</hi> of illuminism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Thomé evidently met Falk in Paris or London, for in December 1777 he
described to a visiting rabbi his earlier studies in Cabala under the <hi rend="i">Baal-Shem.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> In winter 1776-77 the Duke of Chartres (Grand
Master of the Grand Orient system of French Masonry) traveled to London where he sought out Falk, who
consecrated a talismanic ring that would ensure the Duke’s accession to the French throne.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> In the early days of the Rite of Seven
Degrees, Chartres was cited by Lambert as his Deputy Grand Master.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref> Chartres later became the Duke of Orleans and then <hi rend="i">Phillipe
Égalité</hi>, an intimate friend of Richard Cosway and a hero to William Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> J. E. S. Tuckett, “Savalette de Langes, Les Philaléthes, and the
Convent of Wilhelmsbad, 1782,” <hi rend="i">AQC</hi> (1917): 131-71; series of articles in <hi rend="i">Le
Monde Maçonnique</hi>, 14-15 (1873-74).</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Elkan Adler, <hi rend="i">Jewish Travellers</hi> (London, 1930)
357-59.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Charles Henri, Baron von Gleichen, <hi rend="i">Souvenirs</hi> (London:
Leon Techener, 1868) 176. Gleichen was a <hi rend="i">Philaléthe.</hi></note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Wonnacott 71-76. In 1764-72, Lintot claimed affiliation with French Grand
Masters (Prince of Clermont and Duke of Chartres) under the international Grand Mastership of Prince Charles
Edward Stuart. In 1774 he transferred the Rite’s allegiance to Henry Frederick, Duke of Cumberland,
disaffected brother of George III.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Hubert La Marle, <hi rend="i">Phillipe Égalité: Grand Maître de la
Revolution</hi> (Paris: Nouvelles Editions Latines, 1989); Stephen Lloyd, “Richard Cosway, RA: the Artist as
Collector, Connoisseur, and <hi rend="i">Virtuoso</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> (June 1991): 399-400;
William Blake, <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> (1791) 10.</note></p>
        <figure n="GrandLodge.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="402"/>
        <p>It was probably at this time (1777-79) that Chastanier began to collaborate with Lambert, who had
moved next door to him on Tottenham Court Road and who corresponded with members of the Swedish Rite
abroad.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Lambert exhibited pictures
at the Society of Artists and Free Society of Artists, and his highly finished, complex engravings may have
become known to those artists who were interested in Swedenborg and mystical Masonry (such as Loutherbourg,
Cosway, Sharp, and—possibly—Blake). General Rainsford, who was friendly with Loutherbourg and Cosway,
participated in the Universal Society and Rite of Seven Degrees, and he later inherited the Masonic
engravings, manuscripts, and regalia of Lambert.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref> The similarity of many themes and symbols in Lambert’s and Blake’s engravings is
provocative. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> They lived at #62 and #64, respectively; see Algernon Graves,
<hi rend="i">The Society of Artists of Great Britain</hi> (London, 1907; facs. rpt. Bath: Kingsmead, 1969)
142-43.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Gordon Hills, “Notes on the Rainsford Papers in the British Museum,”
<hi rend="i">AQC</hi> 26 (1913): 93-129. Lindner reproduced some of the engravings held by a lodge in Bamberg,
Germany, and Freemasons’ Hall, London; the latter possesses additional engravings and manuscripts by
Lambert.</note></p>
        <p>In 1777 the Universalists were visited by Charles Bernhard Wadström, a Swedish Mason who was
undertaking a secret mission of industrial espionage for King Gustav III, and who returned with news of the
Swedenborgian publishing enterprise in London.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">23</ref> He also told his friend Augustus Nordensjköld about Dr. Mordecai Gumpel Levison, a
remarkable Jewish physician in London, who practiced alchemy and was a Swedenborgian Mason.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> Determined to collaborate with Dr. Levison,
Nordensjköld traveled to London in 1779, where he moved into the Jew’s residence in Soho Square (nearby
Rainsford’s home in the square). In December Nordensjköld and Levison began printing <hi rend="i">A Plain
System of Alchymy</hi>, which combined Swedenborgian metaphysics with practical chemistry. They interrupted
the printing when they decided to travel to Stockholm in order to solicit the sponsorship of Gustav III for
their alchemical endeavors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> At this
time, a “Mrs. Levison” was a subscriber to the <hi rend="i">Discourses on Various Subjects</hi> (1779),
written by the Reverend Jacob Duché, a Swedenborgian whose work also attracted William Blake and other
artists.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> It was in Duché’s home
at the Lambeth Asylum
<pb id="p26-42" n="42"/>
that the Universalists often met in the 1780s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> See the sources on Wadström and the Nordensjkölds in Paley, 84-85n98;
also, Hills 111.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Gösta Bodman, “August Nordenskiöld, en Gustav IIIs alkemist,” and
Hans J. Schoeps, “Lakaren och Alkemisten Gumpertz Levison,” in <hi rend="i">Lychnos</hi> (1943): 189-229,
230-48; A. E. Arppe, <hi rend="i">Anteckningar om Finsk Alkemister</hi> (Helsingfors: Finska Vetenskaps
Societen, 1870) 1-110.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Copy of the printed fragment in Royal Library, Stockholm.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> In the second London edition (1780), Duché included Mrs. Levison among
subscribers omitted from the first edition. That she was the wife of Dr. Levison, the Jewish Swedenborgian, is
suggested by the additional Jewish subscribers, Dr. de la Cour and Naphtali Hart Mier (sic), who were
Freemasons and friends of Dr. Falk.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Clarke Garrett, “The Spiritual <corr type="emend">Odyssey</corr> of Jacob Duché,” 
<hi rend="i">Proceedings of American Philosophical Society</hi> 119 (1975): 143-55; and, “Swedenborg and the
Mystical <corr type="emend">Enlightenment</corr> in Late Eighteenth-Century England,” <hi rend="i">Journal
of History of Ideas</hi> 45 (1984): 67-81.</note></p>
        <p>By 1778 the Swedenborgians in London and Stockholm were corresponding with kindred souls in Berlin,
where the Abbé Antoine Joseph Pernety and Count Thaddeus Grabianka led a Masonic lodge of 
<hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> who studied the master’s works, while carrying out alchemical and Cabalistic
experiments.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> In April 1782 the
unexpected death of Dr. Falk upset an international Masonic project undertaken by Falk, Rainsford, and the 
<hi rend="i">Philaléthes.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref> It was
perhaps this development that influenced Rainsford and Chastanier to publish a brochure that sought new
members for the Universal Society—the <hi rend="i">Plan général d’une Société Universelle</hi>
(London: R. Hawes, 1782). The work was sold at the London book-shop of John Denis, who attended Lambert’s
lodge and who acted as agent for Swedenborgian publications.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n30" type="note">30</ref> Chastanier appealed to high-degree Masons to join their Swedenborgian rite:
<q>
Afin de favoriser l’Élite des Alchymistes, des Cabalistes, des Francs-Maçons, et, en un mot, de tous les
Savans occultes, qui, quoi qu’en pensent ceux qui ignorent la nature de leurs travaux, doivent
nécessairement avoir leur utilité particulière dans un systême Universel, ces Savans tiendront quand et
comme ils le jugeront à propos des Assemblées secrètes, où les Membres d’une autre espèce ne pourront
être introduite sous aucun prétexte. La Société aura pour objet de concilier toutes les Doctrines, et
même tous les interêts, en employant san cesse tous ses talens et tous ses pouvoirs, au bonheur de toute la
Terre en général, et du Pays oú elle s’établira en particulier.<lb/>
<lb/>
On institutera différens Grades suivant les différens degrés de la Science; lesquels degrés seront formés
d’après ceux qui existent dans la forme humaine, mesure et raison de toutes choses.<lb/>
<lb/>
Chaque grade sera marqué par des ordres distinctifs, significatifs, ou symboliques, pris dans la Science des
analogies ou correspondances.<lb/>
<lb/>
Il sera libre à chaque Membre, de porter son grade dans le monde comme un marque d’honneur; mais dans la
Société chacun sera constamment obligé de s’en decorer, comme d’un signe qui le rappelle à sa place et
a sa fonction particulières . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">31</ref></q>
<figure n="Night.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="433"/>
Chastanier appealed especially to artists to join the society of Universalists, for they would study the
symbolic arts in their highest expression. By January 1783, according to a Swedish journal, various artists
had joined this Swedenborgian society in London.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Micheline Meillassoux, <hi rend="i">Dom Pernety (1716-1796) et les
Illuminés d’Avignon</hi> (Milan and Paris: Editions Arché, 1992).</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Hills 105; see Schuchard, “Yeats.”</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> John Denis, <hi rend="i">Denis’ Catalogue of Ancient and Modern Books
for 1787</hi> (London, 1787); James Lackington, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, 7th rev. ed. (London: Lackington,
1794) 207-10.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> I found the brochure enclosed in a previously uncut volume of
Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">De la Nouvelle Jérusalem et de sa Doctrine Céleste</hi> (Londres, 1782), which
was edited by Chastanier; in archives of Swedenborg Society, London.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi><hi rend="i"> Uppfostrings Salskapets Almanna Tidningar</hi> 27
(Stockholm, 1787): 212.</note></p>
        <p>Within three months, Chastanier was encouraged enough by the expansion of Illuminism in lodges
abroad that he once again went public in his quest for new members. On 1 April 1783 he placed an ad in the 
<hi rend="i">Courier de l’Europe: Gazette Anglo-Française</hi>, which was published on Great Queen Street and
which had a large English and Continental readership.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">33</ref> He clearly linked the Swedenborg society in London with its affiliated societies abroad,
which were actually the illuminist lodges at Stockholm, Paris, Avignon, Berlin, and St. Petersburg. Despite
Hindmarsh’s later claim that he placed the first ad and convened the first public meeting of Swedenborgians
in London in December 1784, Chastanier actually earned the honor.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">34</ref> But Hindmarsh, who was a Freemason in his younger days, was later determined
(in the post-Napoleonic era) to cover up the Masonic nature of these first meetings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> The famous Freemasons’ Hall and Tavern were located on Great Queen
Street, where Blake spent his apprentice years.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> For Hindmarsh’s inaccurate claim, see Charles Higham, “A London
New-Church Advertisement in December 1783,” <hi rend="i">Morning Light</hi> 36 (1913): 516-17.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi> Count Grabianka recruited Robert Hindmarsh as a fellow Mason in 1786, and
his brother John Hindmarsh (an artist) was listed as a Mason in 1783. See Hindmarsh 19, 41-49; and “Index to
Antients Register: London Lodges,” vol. 41; Grand Lodge Library, London.</note></p>
        <p>In late fall 1783 Charles Frederick Nordensjköld (brother of Augustus the alchemist) arrived in
London, where he joined the Universalists and gave them some of Swedenborg’s manuscripts. In
Nordensjköld’s voluminous journals and letters covering his experiences over the next three years, a
valuable new perspective emerges on the subsequent development of the Swedenborg society in London.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref> Nordensjköld listed many names that
Hindmarsh suppressed (including “Mr. Cosway, Painter in History”), and he amusingly recounted the occult
enthusiasm and political radicalism of most of the members.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">37</ref> To help Chastanier’s publishing efforts, Nordensjköld donated the
proceeds from his Masonic publication, <hi rend="i">Oneiromäntien</hi> (Stockholm, 1783), which was based on
Swedenborg’s unpublished Italian journal of alchemical symbolism and dream interpretation. 
<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> Photocopies of correspondence by the Nordensjkölds, Wadström, Thomé, and
fellow <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> are preserved in the Academy Collection of Swedenborg Documents (ACSD) at
the Academy of the New Church, Bryn Athyn, Pennsylvania. I am grateful to David Glenn for giving me access to
the archives. See also C. F. Nordensjköld, <hi rend="i">Considérations générales sur le Christianisme
actuel, et la Lumière que Mr. Emanuel Swedenborg répand sur les Religions</hi> (posthume, 1819); this
autobiography was banned and confiscated in Sweden, but a copy was smuggled to London, where Dr. Garth
Wilkinson preserved it. There is a microfilm copy (#78) in the archives of the Swedenborg Society,
London.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi> ACSD #1664.3101—“List of Those Devoted to Swedenborg’s
Doctrines,” compiled by C. F. Nordensjköld in 1784. Hindmarsh omitted the names of Cosway, Lord Percy
(later Duke of Northumberland), William Bousie (friend of Cagliostro and co-founder of Berlin 
<hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi>), and many others. Nordensjköld lists 25 names, plus “etc., etc.”</note></p>
        <p>After the printer Hindmarsh joined the society, a decision was made to form a
<pb id="p26-43" n="43"/>
<figure n="Science.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="392"/>
more public organization—the “Theosophical Society”—which would function as the publishing arm of the
secret Universal Society. The two societies still collaborated, with Hindmarsh and Chastanier serving as
co-secretaries (the latter handling the foreign correspondence). That the early members of the Theosophical
Society shared the ecumenical spirit of the <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> is suggested by a statement in their
published manifesto:
<q>
We wage war with none, but are determined to maintain peace and friendship with all; and being sensible that
without variety, in religion as well as other concerns, there cannot exist harmony or true order, we allow all
men the free exercise of their respective modes of worship, according to their different persuasions and
habits of education; and wish nothing more than to renounce every appearance of a sectarian spirit.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">38</ref>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">38</hi> Hindmarsh 24.</note></q></p>
        <p>Earlier in 1783 Chastanier had traveled to Paris, where he visited the Marquis de Thomé and
informed him about the Universal Society. Thomé became so enthusiastic that he visited the group in London in
early 1784 and held forth on his plans to launch a Swedenborgian balloon expedition to Africa. According to
Nordensjköld, Thomé “thinks it will be the second Noah’s Ark, which shall save the faithful from the
frightful desolation which is to overcome the whole of Europe.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n39" type="note">39</ref> While Thomé expounded his fantasy of liberating the enslaved Africans via
balloon, another ardent abolitionist visited the Universal Society. James Glen was a Scottish-born planter
from Demerara, who became a strong supporter of the Universalist agenda. Glen arranged for Hindmarsh to ship a
collection of the society’s publications to the United States and then undertook a Swedenborgian-Masonic
mission to the new world. In June-July 1784, Glen lectured in Philadelphia and Boston on “the extraordinary
SCIENCE of Celestial and Terrestrial Connections and Correspondencies, recently revived, by the late and
Honourable Emanuel Swedenborg”:
<q>
The sublime Science teaches us from every Object in the World of Nature to learn things Spiritual and
Heavenly; it is the most ancient and excellent of all Sciences, being that whereby the Holy Scriptures were
written; according to which the highest Angels form their Ideas, and through the medium of which the earliest
of the Human Race held Converse and Communion with these blessed Beings. The Knowledge of this useful Science
has for many Ages been lost to the World. The Egyptian Hieroglyphics, the Greek and Roman Mythology, and the
Modern Free-Masonry being the last remnants of it. The honourable Emanuel Swedenborg, the wonderful Restorer
of this long lost Secret . . . was thus taught this Science of Heaven.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n40" type="note">40</ref></q>
In his lectures, Glen included discourses on Jewish manners and customs, hieroglyphics, and Freemasonry. Glen
took advantage of the famous Masonic history of the Green Dragon Tavern in Boston (where many Scottish-Rite
Masons gathered to plan the Boston Tea Party) to recruit members to the Swedenborgian cause.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">39</hi> C. F. Nordensjköld to C. B. Wadström, 31 January-13 February 1784;
translation in ACSD #1664.31.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">40</hi> Charles Higham, “James Glen: the New Church Pioneer and Hermit,” 
<hi rend="i">The New-Church Review</hi> 19 (1912): 532-72. Glen’s Swedenborgian belief in the importance of
nudity throws an amusing perspective on the alleged nudity of William and Catherine Blake.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Albert Mason, “Planting the New Church in Massachusetts,” 
<hi rend="i">New Jerusalem Magazine</hi> 47 (1884): 129-32.</note></p>
        <p>On 2 June Nordensjköld expressed his hope that the wealthier members of the Universal Society,
such as Rainsford and Lord Percy, would draw in more high-ranking members, and he vowed to translate
Chastanier’s <hi rend="i">Plan</hi> into Swedish.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">42</ref> From Nordensjköld’s notes and list of devotees of Swedenborg, it is clear that the
Universal Society had more eclectic occult interests than the Theosophical Society, which maintained a more
limited publishing agenda. On 14 June Edward Maubach, a radical writer who had recently returned from Paris,
notified Rainsford that Savalette de Langes, chief of the <hi rend="i">Philaléthes</hi>, was pleased with the
information he had received from the Universal Society and asked for more copies of the 
<hi rend="i">Plan</hi>, for many French Masons were “très jalouse” to become corresponding members.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref> Maubach wanted to re-publish the 
<hi rend="i">Plan</hi> in French and English, to advertise it in Maty’s <hi rend="i">New Review</hi>, and to
publicize the fact that many “personnes de sang et merite” were interested in the Masonic project. 
<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">42</hi> ACSD #1664.37.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">43</hi> British Library: Add. Mss. 23, 669.f.92.</note></p>
        <p>Rainsford and his friend William Bousie, an Anglo-French merchant, had been corresponding with the
<hi rend="i">Philaléthes</hi> since summer 1783.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">44</ref> The Parisian lodge was laying the groundwork for an international Masonic convention to
investigate all the different high-degree systems. During the sessions from August 1784 through June 1787, the
Swedenborgian <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> in London participated in person and by correspondence.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">45</ref> Rainsford provided valuable information on
Swedenborg, Falk, and the Cabalistic symbolism of the high degrees, while Chastanier was praised for his
Swedenborgian publication efforts. Rainsford and Woulfe were also members of <hi rend="i">Der Pilger</hi>
lodge in London, which worked in German and practiced the Swedish Rite, and they worked with several foreign
members to present information on the Swedish high degrees. However, the material was partially censored
because of Sweden’s stringent requirements of secrecy. Based on Chastanier’s letters and their own
investigations, the <hi rend="i">Philaléthes</hi> concluded on 29 March 1787:
<q>
Du tout il résulte qu’il existe depuis longtemps, en Suède et à Londres, et en d’autres villes de
l’Europe, des sociétés fraternelles, réunies pour la propagation de la doctrine de Swedenborg; que,
concurrement à l’établissement de ces sociétés, il s’en était formé dans le nord de Europe, qui,
dirigées par divers moyens, avaient pour put et objet des sciences réligieuses, mais analogues au 
<hi rend="i">Christ</hi> . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">46</ref></q>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">44</hi> Though little is presently known about the Bousie brothers, they played
central roles in the development of illuminist Masonry. William was friendly with Cagliostro in London in
1776, helped found the Berlin <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> in 1778, worked with the Universal and Theosophic
societies in 1783-87, and served as liaison between the Swedenborgians in London, Paris, and Avignon in
1787-90. A full biography is a scholarly <hi rend="i">desideratum.</hi></note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">45</hi> The proceedings are reproduced in <hi rend="i">Le Monde Maçonnique</hi>,
14-15 (1873-74) <hi rend="i">passim.</hi></note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">46</hi><hi rend="i"> Monde Maçonnique</hi> 15 (1874): 165-66.</note></p>
        <p>In the meantime in London, however, the relationship between the Universal and Theosophical
Societies was
<pb id="p26-44" n="44"/>
becoming strained, as certain of the more provincial, lower-class British members became resentful at the more
international, upper-class participants. In August 1785 the Marquis de Thomé returned to London, where he
urged the implementation of Chastanier’s ambitious publishing plans. The Frenchman’s elegance and 
<hi rend="i">esprit</hi> delighted Duché, Nordensjköld, Rainsford, and many members, but his “foreign”
interference offended others. Thomé insisted that the publishing society change its name from
“Theosophic” to “Philanthropic” because the first word connoted paganism. Though a majority accepted
his reasoning, some of the British members insisted on the more localized name of the “British Society for
the Propagation of the Doctrines of the New Church.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">47</ref>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">47</hi> Charles Higham, “Pierre Frederic Gosse,” <hi rend="i">New-Church
Magazine</hi> (October 1916) 442-44.</note></p>
        <p>A discouraged Chastanier wrote Rainsford about the personality clashes and feuding that plagued the
attempted cooperation of the two societies, but he soldiered on in his ecumenical efforts. Though “la
Société de ceux qui se disent Swedenborgites ou Swedenborgiens” rejected his proposal to publish
Swedenborg’s Latin manuscript of <hi rend="i">Apocalypsis Explicata</hi>, they agreed to bring out two
English translations of smaller works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">48</ref> Despite the “British” name change, however, Nordensjköld continued to use the term
Philanthropic; when he founded the “Exegetic and Philanthropic Society” in Stockholm in 1786, he claimed
that it was a copy of the London society. Though the public Exegetic society did not call itself a Masonic
lodge, all the members were Masons and they planned to share a printing press and publishing agenda with the
Masons.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">49</ref> This apparently mirrored the
arrangement in London between the public Theosophical and secret Universal societies. 
<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">48</hi> British Library, Add. Mss. 23, 669.f.99.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">49</hi> Robert Sundelin, <hi rend="i">Svedenborgianismens Historia i Sverige</hi>
(Upsala: W. Schultz, 1886) 216.</note></p>
        <p>By 1786 the revolutionary developments in France added to the unease of the more conservative
British Swedenborgians. During that year, when the Diamond Necklace Trial rocked the throne of France, two
leaders of
<figure n="GrandElectd.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="383"/>
radical Masonry—Cagliostro and Grabianka—arrived in London and sought recruits among the
Swedenborgians.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">50</ref> Cagliostro, who knew
Dr. Levison, merged the teachings of Swedenborg and Falk into his Egyptian Rite.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">51</ref> Similarly, Grabianka merged those of Swedenborg and “a
rich Cabbalon Philosopher” into his Illuminist Rite.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">52</ref> When Hindmarsh wrote his history of this period, he never mentioned Cagliostro, who won
over many disciples, and he downplayed Grabianka, who won over Hindmarsh. Moreover, Hindmarsh later covered up
the Masonic goal of Grabianka’s recruitment in London, and he falsely claimed that the London society soon
broke its ties with the <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> of Avignon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n53" type="note">53</ref>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">50</hi> See my “Mr. Femality”; Clarke Garrett, <hi rend="i">Respectable
Folly</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP, 1975) 100-20.</note>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">51</hi> See my “Yeats”; Arppe 99.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">52</hi> Chastanier 25.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">53</hi> Grabianka’s correspondence in 1788-89 makes clear his continuing
Masonic ties with the London Swedenborgians; in “Grabianka Staroste et Les Illuminés d’Avignon, Lettres
de Grabianka 1788, 1789,” transcripts in Kloss Collection, Grand Lodge Library, The Hague. Though Hindmarsh
does not mention it (see 46-47), he was the printer of Grabianka’s <hi rend="i">Letter from a Society in
France, to the Society for Promoting the Heavenly Doctrines of the New Jerusalem, in London</hi> (London,
1787).</note></p>
        <p>Chastanier was initially enthusiastic about the link-up between London and Avignon, and he
determined to recruit Masons from rival lodges to the Swedenborgian agenda. When he learned that the
Swedenborgians in Stockholm had founded a special Masonic lodge in 1787, to circumvent clerical opposition to
the Exegetic society, he utilized his newly launched <hi rend="i">Journal Novi-Jerusalemite</hi> to praise the
new Swedish lodge.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">54</ref> It would serve
the good of humanity if the whole earth became covered with such lodges. He also urged those Masons who did
not belong to the <hi rend="i">Philaléthes</hi> to study Swedenborg as they searched for the true secrets of
the fraternity:
<q>
Maçons francs et libres, dont j’ai l’honneur d’être frère, votre société respectable est faite pour
être leur émule. Vous cherchez maintenant plus que jamais la vérité, témoins les lettres circulaires que
le GrandOrient de Paris fait partout distribuer. Voici qu’elle se présente à vous. Ce sont les oeuvres de
Swédenborg qui vous la dévoilant dans tous ses emblèmes, symboles et figures que vous ne connaissiez encore
que superficiellement. Ne ferezvous rien en pénétrer l’intérieur? Il est de votre intéret de concourir
à la réussité de mon plan . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">55</ref></q>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">54</hi> “Minutes and Papers of the <hi rend="i">Pro Fide et Charitate</hi>
Society in Stockholm,” p. 439. Trans. and ed. Alfred Stroh. Typescript (1912) in ACSD.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">55</hi> Quoted by Achatius Kahl in Johan Tybeck, <hi rend="i">Le Nouveau
Salem</hi> (Bale: J. Schweighauser, 1871) 147. At this time, the <hi rend="i">Philaléthes</hi> were competing
with the Grand Orient.</note></p>
        <p>Chastanier’s journal, which targeted Masons of differing rites, continued throughout 1787-88, as
he appealed to British lodges to admit women and to all lodges to support the revolutionary changes in France.
He also made clear that the <hi rend="i">Bureau Typographique de la Nouvelle Église</hi>, which published the
journal in London, was a Masonic society composed of “Amateurs de la Vérité” who were “Très secrets
Associés du dit Bureau.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">56</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">56</hi> [Benedict Chastanier], <hi rend="i">Journal Novi-Jerusalemite</hi> (1787):
149, 165-66, 171; (1788): 105-06.</note></p>
        <p>However, the visits of Cagliostro and Grabianka—foreign prophets of revolution—brought an
unwelcome public spotlight on the Swedenborgians. Reinforced by personal antagonisms and class resentments,
the political polarization erupted into battles between the Universalists and the Separatists.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">57</ref> The latter group—a small minority of the
Swedenborgians—hired a chapel at Great Eastcheap where they planned to establish a separate public church
dedicated to a sectarian religion of Swedenborgianism. The Universalists argued instead that members should
remain affiliated with their original churches while studying Swedenborg and other theosophers in private
homes and secret lodge meetings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">58</ref>
Initially, many of the Universalists tried to participate in the Eastcheap meetings and, though Hindmarsh did
not mention them, the names of Grabianka and Thomé were successfully proposed for membership on 7 May
1787.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">59</ref> On 3 September William Bousie
was nominated, but he was rejected by a vote of
<pb id="p26-45" n="45"/>
12 to 1, perhaps because of his linkage with Cagliostro. <note id="n57"><hi rend="s">57</hi> Peter Lineham,
<hi rend="i">The English Swedenborgians, 1770-1840: a Study in the Social Dimensions of Religious
Sectarians</hi> (Ph.D. Thesis, University of Sussex, 1978) 216-20.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">58</hi> The Duché family remained loyal to Grabianka and the Universal Society;
they did not participate at Eastcheap but continued to be involved with the Lambeth Asylum. Thomas Spence
Duché corresponded with Rainsford about alchemy and Illuminism until his death in 1790. See Garrett
“Spiritual” 153-54, and Rainsford Papers: British Library Add. Mss. 26, 669.f.129-30.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">59</hi><hi rend="i"> Minutes of the Great Eastcheap Conference.</hi> “Minute
Book . . . 7 May 1787 to 7 November 1791. Copy in Conference Library, Swedenborg Society, London.</note></p>
        <p>In May 1788 Chastanier also rejected the influence of Cagliostro and warned about “ces grand
Instititeurs de ces prétendues Loges Égyptiennes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">60</ref> He worried that Cagliostro’s disciples in London tried to cure diseases by the
Cabalistic pronouncement of the name of Jehovah. Though he targeted his publications at the Masons, the
ecumenical Chastanier still hoped to cooperate with the sectarians. Thus, in May he also published a
charitable view of the congregation at the Eastcheap Chapel:
<q>
Nous avons assisté à leur Culte, et nous y avons observé . . . le plus grand recueillement et la plus grand
décence; il nous a même paru que le nombreux auditore de gens simples qui composoient l’assemblée étoit
intimement pénétré des grandes verités qu’on lui developpoit. Au reste ceux qui reprochent à cette
branche des amateurs de la Nouvelle dispensation d’avoir été contre l’intention de Swedenborg, en
formant une secte . . . doivent encore réfléchir que tout est progressif au spirituel comme au naturel . .
.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">61</ref></q>
The Eastcheap minutes reveal the continuing arguments about priestcraft and expulsions for “irregularity,”
but by December 1788 Chastanier was allowed to join. With Augustus Nordensjköld, Charles Wadström, and their
English supporter J. A. Tulk also attending meetings, it seemed that a cooperative relationship might be
revived. <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">60</hi><hi rend="i"> Journal Novi-Jerusalemite</hi> (1788): 159.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">61</hi><hi rend="i"> Journal Novi-Jerusalemite</hi> (1788): 189-90.</note></p>
        <p>The in-fighting was still confined to a small number, so most admirers of Swedenborg (who were on
the list of 500 readers invited in December 1788 to the Great Eastcheap Conference) were not aware of the
controversies. Nordensjköld, Chastanier, and Wadström managed to influence the final manifesto of the
Conference, so that it represented a patched-together compromise. Thus, when William and Catherine Blake
signed the minute book in April 1789, they did not necessarily take sides in the controversies. James Glen,
who had returned from his Masonic mission to America, also signed the official statement, and he
<figure n="FreeMasonsAtWork.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="382"/>
did not foresee then that Hindmarsh would eventually become “a pronounced ecclesiastic” and a “Bishop of
Babylon.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">62</ref> Soon after the
Conference, however, two new issues erupted that would polarize the members over the next few months (and
which Hindmarsh would later try to conceal). Both were triggered by Nordensjköld’s radical views of
sexuality and alchemy, which were based on his accurate and intimate knowledge of Swedenborg’s real
theories. <note id="n62"><hi rend="s">62</hi> “Epistolary Correspondence of the Earlier Members of the
Church,” <hi rend="i">Monthly Observer</hi> 1 (1857): 311, 418; 2 (1858): 279-81.</note></p>
        <p>In Swedenborg’s unpublished diaries and in the Latin edition of <hi rend="i">Conjugial Love</hi>,
he revealed with unusual explicitness the breathing and meditation techniques of Yogic-Cabalism that could
produce a prolonged erection and state of orgasmic trance.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n63" type="note">63</ref> Because this visionary sexual technique was crucial to the achievement of
“spiritual influx,” Swedenborg worked out a radical theory of marriage and concubinage to ensure that all
<hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> had access to this key to spiritual vision. Nordensjköld based his plans for
African colonization and community organization on the central premise of prolonged “Virile
Potency.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">64</ref> In May he presented his
thesis with such enthusiasm that even the young Hindmarsh agreed with him, but the “concubine” promoters
were subsequently expelled by more conservative members. The minutes were subsequently ripped out, and an
older Hindmarsh never mentioned the affair in his history.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n65" type="note">65</ref>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">63</hi> For examples, see Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">Journal of Dreams</hi>,
#87-88, 113, 157, 170-73; <hi rend="i">Spiritual Diary</hi>, #3208, 3353, 4145, 6055, 6067, 6096, 6110; 
<hi rend="i">Conjugial Love</hi>, #51-55, 110, 310, 258.</note>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">64</hi> [Augustus Nordensjköld], <hi rend="i">Plan for a Free Community upon the
Coast of Africa, under the Protection of Great Britain; but Intirely Independent of all European Laws and
Government</hi> (London: Robert Hindmarsh, 1789) 35.</note>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">65</hi> Paley 71-72.</note></p>
        <p>Though the sexual visionaries may have been temporarily expelled from Eastcheap, Nordensjköld had
another plan which must have appealed to the many Hermetic students among the Conference participants. On 26
May he issued a broadside manifesto to “the True Members of the New Jerusalem Church,” who “sincerely
wish to separate themselves both internally and externally from the Old Church”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">66</ref> (see appendix). This remarkable document, which has never
been mentioned in New Church histories or Blake studies, presents the Swedenborgian alchemical views that he
and Dr. Levison first promulgated in 1779, and which Nordensjköld had now perfected. As a genuinely talented
chemist and metallurgist, Nordensjköld was experienced in the practical techniques of alchemy, and he invited
any interested Swedenborgians to help him set up a lab and furnace (Athanor) in order to pursue the great
work. At the same time, the alchemist would undergo spiritual regeneration, which would render “the Day of
his Tabernacling in the Body a continual State of Bliss.” Any profits from the production of gold and the
universal medicine would be consecrated to the use of the New Jerusalem Church. The broadside was sent as a
circular letter “to the fiends of the New Church only,” but it was “particularly requested, that the
Contents of this Letter be not made public; and that all Answers be directed to me at Mr. Robert Hindmarsh’s
. . . 32, Clerkenwell-Close.” <note id="n66"><hi rend="s">66</hi> The only known copy is preserved among the
Nordensjköld papers in the University Library, Helsinki, Finland. That this copy survived the destruction
carried out by the sectarians raises the hope that the lost list of 500 readers invited to the Eastcheap
Conference might also survive.</note></p>
        <p>That Blake probably received Nordensjköld’s proposal is provocative, given the artist’s
subsequent use of alchemical symbolism and preoccupation with the furnace of Los. Moreover, Lambert de Lintot
was perhaps inspired by Nordensjköld and the Universalists in 1789 to issue new Masonic engravings with
Swedenborgian and alchemical themes. In one striking plate, there is a circular emblem in which three human
legs emerge from a shared genital area. The circle
<pb id="p26-46" n="46"/>
is ringed by the motto “UNA TRINUS AB UNO” at the top and “DE LOS” at the bottom, with a crown and sun
relating to the respective phrases.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">67</ref>
In his circular letter, Nordensjköld pointed out that “the fundamental error in theology has been “the
setting up a Trinity of Persons, instead of a Trinity in One Person”; similarly, the fundamental error in
Alchymy consisted in adopting the “Trinity or Three-fold Principle of Matters instead of a Trinity or
Three-fold Principle in the Matter.” For Swedenborg and Nordensjköld, the sexual dynamics between the male
and female potencies created the “triune” equilibrium or androgynous unity. As Lambert appealed to
illuminated Masons to help place the “First &amp; Last Stone of the Jerusalem Church” and engraved on a
pedestal “How have I found it/ By work and Experience/ SOL’S,” the possibility that Blake had access to
this secretive illuminist undertaking takes on plausibility. <note id="n67"><hi rend="s">67</hi> Lindner
136.</note></p>
        <p>The subsequent history of the Universal Society and Swedenborgian Masonry in London remains
difficult to piece together. Evidence of the polarizations over political and theosophical issues survives in
the rival Swedenborgian journals published in the 1790s, in the manuscripts of Duché and Rainsford, and in a
plethora of pamphlets and memoirs published by the participants.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n68" type="note">68</ref> In the wake of the 1794 treason trials, which threw a frightening light on
those Swedenborgians who worked for the London Corresponding Society, the <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> found
themselves in a dangerous position. The intensifying crackdown on radical Masonry culminated in the Secret
Societies Act of 1799, which rendered all “irregular” lodges illegal and treasonous. Subsequently, the
widespread destruction of documents by the increasingly secretive <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> and the
counter-revolutionary coverup by the conservatives means that the Swedenborgian underworld remains largely
buried. <note id="n68"><hi rend="s">68</hi> The Universalists published <hi rend="i">The New Jerusalem
Magazine</hi> in 1790-91, which carried on the illuminist agenda; the Separatists, led by the increasingly
conservative Hindmarsh, published the rival New Jerusalem Journal in 1792. Rainsford’s letters make clear
that he continued to promote a secret Masonic lodge that drew together Swedenborgians and students of the
occult, until at least 1798. The subsequent history, from 1790 to 1826, will be given in my <hi rend="i">The
Men of Desire: William Blake and Illuminist Freemasonry</hi> (forthcoming).</note></p>
        <p>However, it is crucial when reading Blake’s allusions, both favorable and unfavorable to
Swedenborg and the
<figure n="Strength.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="461"/>
Swedenborgians, to recognize that he was responding to controversies and arguments that inspired or distressed
many of his associates. The issue was not so much his response to Swedenborg—whom he accepted as a great
though flawed prophet, a <hi rend="i">confrère</hi> of Paracelsus and Boehme—but his responses to the
warring factions and eclectic opinions among the motley crew of Swedenborgians. Though Blake scorned the
prudish “angels” of the Eastcheap Society, he would have found ready sympathizers for his illuminated
prophecies among the illuminist “devils” of the Universal Society.</p>
        <figure n="UnaTribus.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="200" height="233"/>
        <pb id="p26-47" n="47"/>
        <figure n="TheScience.26.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="388"/>
        <pb id="p26-48" n="48"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Appendix</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">An</hi> ADDRESS <hi rend="i">to the True</hi> MEMBERS <hi rend="i">of the</hi> NEW
JERUSALEM CHURCH, <hi rend="i">revealed by the</hi> LORD <hi rend="i">in the Writings of</hi> EMANUEL
SWEDENBORG, <hi rend="i">who sincerely wish to separate themselves both internally and externally from the Old
Church</hi>:</p>
          <p>THE LORD having, by Means of the new Revelation and Opening of his Word, communicated to us the
<hi rend="i">Spiritual Philosopher’s Stone</hi>, which will infallibly operate in the moral World, and by
Degrees change and restore it to it’s primitive Order and Perfection, it is my Intention therefore to shew,
by the Observations annexed to this Address, that the Discovery of the <hi rend="i">material</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">natural Philosopher’s Stone</hi> must of Course take Place, which in like Manner will operate in
the natural or material World, by progressively changing and restoring all material Substances to their
primitive State of Purity and Splendor.</p>
          <p>It is by Means of the Writings of Emanuel Swedenborg that the Foundation is laid for the
Destruction of moral Evil; for had not Providence now sent to us these Writings, Adultery and Anti-conjugal
Life, the very Fundamental of Hell, among Christians even apparently the most moral, would have soon been
regarded as no Sin at all, or as a Matter perfectly unconnected with Religion; and hence Marriages would
ultimately become intirely adulterous, and a general Corruption of Manners would have prevailed throughout all
Societies.</p>
          <p>But for the Destruction of natural Evil, which is the Tyranny of Money, the Foundation cannot be
laid, before Alchymy becomes a general Art, and the <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi> is universally
known.</p>
          <p>The Difference between the <hi rend="i">Spiritual</hi> and <hi rend="i">natural Philosopher’s
Stone</hi>, is nothing else than this; namely that the former is the Opening of the literal Sense of the Word
of God, to disclose it’s Spiritual Contents, and the latter is the Opening of Gold and Diamond to the
Manifestation of <hi rend="i">Urim</hi> and <hi rend="i">Thummim.</hi> The Reason of this Correspondence is,
that the Holy Word is as Gold, Silver, and Diamond, the interior Quality of which has been hitherto unknown,
nay, it has been intirely denied.</p>
          <p>It is evident that the Abuse of the literal Sense of the Word has been producing and confirming
all moral Evil. This detestable and abominable Abuse of these two Things, the one in the <hi rend="i">moral
World</hi>, and the other in the <hi rend="i">natural</hi>, cannot be removed, without their being unfolded,
so that their interior Purity and Perfection may be generally known. It then necessarily follows, that the
Word cannot be made Use of, as a Monopoly among the Clergy, and moreover Gold, Silver, and their
Representations, as a Monopoly among the Wealthy and commercial World.</p>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Spiritual Stone</hi>, it is already acknowledged, is to be found in the Word of
God, by Means of the Writings of Emanuel Swedenborg, as Man may thereby be regenerated and purified: But the
<hi rend="i">natural Stone</hi> has not yet been discovered and known. However I hope, with the Assistance of
the Lord, that this in a short Time
<pb id="p26-49" n="49"/>
will also be done, when the Regeneration of all Mankind will commence as well in the Spiritual as in the
Natural.</p>
          <p>It is easy to see the Importance and Necessity of this Discovery in the New Church, when we
consider that by Means of the Unfolding of the literal Sense of the Word, or the <hi rend="i">Spiritual
Stone</hi>, the Lord has now restored Spiritual Liberty, and destroyed the Monopoly of the literal Sense of
the Word among the Clergy, together with their Sulisidian System; but the Correspondence hereof, namely the
Restoration of natural Liberty in the Destruction of the Monopoly of Gold, Silver, &amp;c. in the commercial
World, and by Consequence their <hi rend="i">Money alone</hi>, (which constitutes an abominable Tyranny over
Mankind) cannot possibly be effected but by Means of the <hi rend="i">natural Stone</hi>, nor can the new
Power and Strength, which is now descending from the New Heaven, become operative, before the Correspondence
of the interior and exterior of the Substantial and the Natural is completed even in the Ultimates. Therefore,
that a plain Idea may be given to every Lover of the New Revelation of the Lord, the following Articles are
offered for serious Consideration.</p>
          <p>I. That there are two Worlds, the Spiritual or Substantial, and the Natural or Material.</p>
          <p>II. That in each World there is a distinct Sun, in the Spiritual World a Spiritual Sun, and in
the Natural World a Material Sun.</p>
          <p>III. That the Emanation proceeding from the Spiritual Sun is Spiritual Heat and Light, or what is
the same, Love and Wisdom.</p>
          <p>IV. That the Receptacles of the Heat and Light of the Spiritual Sun are all the Subjects of the
Vegetable and the Animal Kingdom, the most perfect of which is Man, who is the true organick Form in all
it’s Power and Effect.</p>
          <p>V. That the Emanation proceeding from the Material Sun is the Material Heat and Light.</p>
          <p>VI. That the Receptacles of the Heat and Light of the Material Sun, are all the Subjects of the
Mineral Kingdom, such as Airs; Waters; and Earths, the most perfect of which is Gold, which is the principal
[un]organick Form in all it’s Power and Effect.</p>
          <p>VII. Hence it follows, that here on Earth, these two Worlds may be manifestly seen in their
Ultimates, viz., the <hi rend="i">Spiritual World</hi>, in what is called Organick Nature, including
Vegetables, Animals, and man, all which Subjects receive Influx from the Spiritual Sun; the 
<hi rend="i">Material World</hi> in what is called Unorganick Nature, including Airs, Waters, and Earths, which
Subjects receive Influx from the Material Sun.</p>
          <p>VIII. That all the material Substances which envelope Vegetables, Animals, and Man, are only
borrowed from the material Kingdom, and must be restored again. This is clearly seen, when we consider the
first Rudiments of Seeds, and afterwards the successive Food and Increases they receive to their Forms, and
lastly their Decay and Death, when their material Forms and Clothes return to the Air, Water, and Earth, which
composed them, and from which they were derived, as from a common Store-House of Matter.</p>
          <p>IX. Consequently that the material Substances in Organick Nature are not new Matters, in any
Respect different from the material Substances which compose Unorganick Nature; which every Natural
Philosopher can prove, by decomposing them and reducing them to their first Elements, namely, Air, Water, and
Earth, from whence they were derived.</p>
          <p>X. And therefore, that the Subject of the physical <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi> is no
wise to be taken from Organick Nature.</p>
          <p>XI. That as the Progression of Matters in Unorganick Nature, or in the Material Kingdom, is 
<hi rend="i">first</hi>, all Kinds of Air; <hi rend="i">second</hi>, all Kinds of Water; <hi rend="i">third</hi>,
all Kinds of Salt; <hi rend="i">fourth</hi>, all Kinds of Phlogiston; <hi rend="i">fifth</hi>, all Kinds of
Stones; <hi rend="i">sixth</hi> and last, all Kinds of Metals, of which Gold is the highest and most perfect:
And inasmuch as all these Kinds of Matters are but Receptacles of the Heat and Light of the Sun in different
Forms; and as Gold is the most powerful and complete Receptacle of that Heat and Light; hence it follows, that
the physical <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi> must be a Receptacle of the Sun’s Heat and Light,
infinitely more powerful and perfect than Gold itself; consequently that the <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s
Stone</hi> can only be made of Gold alone.</p>
          <p>XII. That every Angel, by his Wisdom and his Love, is a spiritual and a moral 
<hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi>; but to attempt to form an Angel out of any other Being but Man, or out of
any of the inferior Animals, would be as ridiculous as to attempt to make the physical 
<hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi> out of any other Matter but Gold itself.</p>
          <p>XIII. That the Lord Himself, and consequently His Word, is the true Spiritual and Moral 
<hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi>, but inasmuch as the fundamental Error in Theology has been the setting up
a Trinity of Persons, instead of a Trinity in One Person, so in like Manner the fundamental Error in Alchymy
consisted in adopting a Trinity of Matters, instead of a Trinity or Three-fold principle in the Matter;
consequently that it is necessary to take Gold alone to make the physical <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s
Stone.</hi></p>
          <p>XIV. That in all Things, even in the smallest and most simple Substance, there is a Two-fold and
a Three-fold Principle; consequently also in Gold itself, the same Two-fold and Three-fold Principles exist;
and that those Principles cannot be formed by Composition and Mixture of different Substances.</p>
          <p>XV. In short, the whole Universe is composed of two grand Series, or Chains of Links, which is
manifested in the general Kingdoms of Organick and Unorganick Nature.</p>
          <p>XVI. That the Beginning in the first Series is God in the Spiritual Sun, and in the second
Series, the visible material Sun.</p>
          <p>XVII. That the last Link in the first Series is Man, and the last Link in the second Series is
Gold.</p>
          <p>XVIII. Consequently, that there are four cardinal Points, if we may be allowed the Expression, in
the whole Universe, namely, God, Man, the Sun, and Gold.</p>
          <p>XIX. That to perfect Man, is to render him more and more receptive of God, or of his Heat and
Light, that is, or his Love and Wisdom.</p>
          <p>XX. That to perfect Gold is to render it more and more receptive of the Sun, or of it’s Light
and Heat.</p>
          <p>XXI. That there are no Bounds in this Perfection; for Men as well as Gold can be rendered more
and more receptive of the Heat and Light of their respective Suns, and thus be perfected <hi rend="i">ad
infinitum.</hi></p>
          <p>XXII. That as God, by means of the Natural Sun as an Instrument, has created all Nature or the
Material Kingdom, and also continues to support it thereby; so in like Manner must Man, by Means of Gold as an
Instrument, regenerate all Nature, or the whole material Kingdom, and afterwards constantly support it in a
regenerate State: For as Creation is the Work of the Lord only, so is the restoring it back to Order or it’s
Regeneration the Work of Man alone, and that so essentially, that if he doth not study this Doctrine of
Regeneration, both he and all Nature must needs remain imperfect to all Eternity, and his Habitation the Earth
must also remain in Misery and Wretchedness, which State, however, Man has it in his Power to change into
Glory.</p>
          <p>XXIII. That in this and in no other Manner, Man can actually become Master of all Nature, for
which he was created; he can
<pb id="p26-50" n="50"/>
restore the Earth, with all it’s Materials, and bring it back to Glory, and render the Day of his
Tabernacling in the Body a continual State of Bliss, correspondent with the spiritual State of Happiness,
which was prepared in him before; consequently that this is only possible with the Man or Members of the New
Church of the Lord.</p>
          <p>XXIV. That the only genuine Science of Alchymy consists in the three following Branches; namely,
1st, the Theory concerning the Matter; 2d, the Theory of the Furnace; and 3d, that of the Regulation of the
Fire. The first Theory shews that Gold is the only Subject Matter of the Work; the second shews that this Work
requires a Furnance that can stand the Fire for the Space of a Year at least, and admits of being regulated
with Ease and Facility; and the third Theory shews by what a Regulation of Fire Gold may be so opened in the
Furnace, as to discover it’s two-fold and it’s three-fold Principles, and how to put them into Action, in
Order to accomplish it’s Perfection.</p>
          <p>XXV. That the characteristic Difference between the true and the false Alchymist may be seen at
once from the Theory of Matter, for, as the first works on no other Subject except Gold <hi rend="i">per
se</hi>, so the other works on all Sorts of Materials, and is always employed with Compositions and Mixtures;
as is the Case with Theology, for true Divinity admits of no other God save Jesus Christ alone, whereas the
false, on the other Hand, does not accept of the Lord, or when it does, it takes him always in Conjunction
with other Powers.</p>
          <p>XXVI. The Alchymist who will not see, when it is laid open for him, that Gold only is the Subject
Matter of the <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi>, shews thereby he has little Knowledge in natural
History, little in natural Philosophy, little in Chemistry, and none at all in the Science of Correspondences;
for from these four Sciences it may be confirmed that Gold <hi rend="i">per se</hi> is the only Subject Matter
of the <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone.</hi></p>
          <p>XXVII. That true Alchymy to this Day has been an intirely sealed Science, and an absolutely
impenetrable Mystery, is from no other Reason but because they have not been able to see and perceive that
Gold <hi rend="i">per se</hi> is the only Subject for the <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi>, and that by
Means of this only can Gold be made, or Transmutation rendered possible.</p>
          <p>XXVIII. That every other Way or Method that can be imagined, in any Manner whatever throughout
all Nature, to make Gold and the universal Medicine, besides that of exalting and rendering prefect common
Gold <hi rend="i">per se</hi> for the <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi> merely by Fire, and after that
by Means of the same to operate very wonderful Transmutations, is not only contrary to every Experience, but
in the highest Degree irrational and absurd, when examined into with a sound Judgment.</p>
          <p>XXIX. However, after being finally convinced that Gold is the only Subject Matter for the making
the Stone of the Ancients, our Knowledge would yet be very incomplete in Alchymy, if we had not the Knowledge
of the <hi rend="i">Construction of the Furnace</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Regulation of Fire</hi>, two Things
not to be attained without great and long Experience, although this in itself is very simple when known.</p>
          <p>XXX. That in these two chief Points, <hi rend="i">viz.</hi> the Furnance, and particularly the
Regulation of the Fire, I have laboured these 20 Years, and endeavoured to render myself Master of them; but
that I did not till very lately attain to so much Knowledge and Experience as I now have; so that I can at
present look on myself as almost Master of these two essential Points.</p>
          <p>XXXI. That Alchymical Furnance or Athanor, which I was so happy as to discover 12 Years ago, and
which has since been much improved, for Simplicity, Commodiousness, and the Ease of it’s Regulation, is not
only the best Alchymical Furnance, but also a real Regulator for Chemists, and all such as use lasting Fires
in their Works.</p>
          <p>XXXII. That the Regulation of the Fire consists in the Theory of the four Elements of Alchymists,
the Weights, the Inclusion of the Matter, or the Hermetic Seal, the two Parts of the Work; namely, the
Preparatory and the Afterwork, &amp;c. all which together are nothing else but the Gradation of Fire. The
Regulation of the Fire is the most difficult and mysterious Work in the whole Art of Alchymy, and can only be
obtained by long Experience.</p>
          <p>XXXIII. That in a continual and well-regulated Fire, Gold goes through a regular Circle of
Colours, passing from it’s own Redness to that of Blood; such a regular Circle of Colours, always consisting
of three Colours, <hi rend="i">viz.</hi> the Black, the White, and the Red, between which all the other
intermediate Colours arise during the Process. Three such regular Circulations at least must Gold undergo,
before it can become the true <hi rend="i">Philosopher’s Stone</hi>, or transmuting Fire. The Gold undergoes
only <hi rend="i">per se</hi> the first of these Circulations, but all the succeeding Circulations must always
be done with the Addition either of Gold already exalted, or of fresh and raw Gold. The first Revolution takes
9 or 12 Months, the second 2 or 3 Months, and the third is performed in 1 Month or even less. These
Revolutions can be so reiterated <hi rend="i">ad infinitum</hi>, that the Gold at last will pass through all
it’s Colours in one hour, or even in a shorter Space of Time, and on the most gentle Fire.</p>
          <p>XXXIV. That this Process has in all Respects the most perfect Analogy with the Process of the
Regeneration of Man; the fore Part of the Work answering to his Reformation and the Progress of the same, and
the after or second Part to the State of Regeneration. The Black Period answers to Repentance, or the
Rejection of Evils and Falses, the White to the Implantation of Truth, and the Red to the Implantation of
Good; the four Elements answer to the celestial and spiritual, or to the internal and external Good and Truth.
The Inclusion of the Matter answers to the Conjunction of Good and Truth, by means whereof Regeneration is
veiled over, in the State of Temptations, and so forth.</p>
          <p>XXXV. That this complete Science, which in the afore-mentioned Period of 20 Years has been
confirmed in me by a most solid Theory, and a very extensive Experience, I now offer to all the Members of the
<hi rend="i">New Jerusalem Church</hi>, who being fully convinced of it’s Reality, find themselves disposed
to put this Science into Execution.</p>
          <p>XXXVI. This I will do without any Regard to pecuniary interest or Reward, as I would not make a
private Advantage of the Things and Gifts of God; consequently whosoever is desirous to receive my Information
and Assistance, shall have it gratuitously whenever he gives me Notice, either by calling personally, or by a
Letter directed as below. The whole Apparatus can be set up, and put into complete Order, within the Space of
three Weeks or a Month.</p>
          <p>XXXVII. If one single person (which I should prefer) cannot undertake this highly important Work,
I should then advise that several would associate and chuse one in whom they can place Confidence, when I
would undertake to instruct him in all that is necessary to this Work.</p>
          <p>XXXVIII. The most material Expence for this Course is in the Charcoal or Fuel, after that, in the
Board of two or three Servants; and lastly, in the Erection of a proper Laboratory and Furnace. As to the
Expence of the Matter itself which is to be used, though it be Gold, it will be very trifling, not exceeding
15 or 20 Grains.</p>
          <pb id="p26-51" n="51"/>
          <p>XXXIX. The only Condition I have to impose on teaching the Mystery is, that the Produce shall be
consecrated to the Use of the <hi rend="i">New Jerusalem Church</hi>, and not to any civil or political
Purpose in any Society, where the New Revelation of the Lord is not received.</p>
          <p>XL. I had three Ways opened to me to make Use of this Knowledge, acquired in Alchymy, as 1st, to
set to work myself in the Process, and thus bring it out; 2d, by Means of an open Publication, to communicate
the same to the whole World; or 3d, by Means of a circular Letter to impart the same to the Friends of the New
Church only. As to the first, I have already tried it myself for these 20 Years, but not being independent, I
was always interrupted in the Pursuit. As to the second Way, I have often intended to do it, but found that,
for many Reasons, this Way should not be pursued. The third Way, therefore, appears to me the most useful, and
more suited for this present Time.</p>
          <p>XLI. At length I must declare, that I have not this Knowledge of myself, but from another, who
died in 1756 in Finland, and who had obtained this Science by a supernatural Way. The same had even
Revelations concerning the Last Judgment, that was to take Place in 1757, and concerning the New Church of the
Lord that was to be established afterwards.</p>
          <p>XLII. The latest Author in true Alchymy, Eireneus Philaletha, an Englishman, lived 100 Years ago
in America, and was an anonymous Writer. Since which Time, in the whole learned World there has not been one
proper Work published in this Science; and before his Time no other Writings deserve to be read, but what he
himself has recommended in his Preface to his <hi rend="i">Ripley Revived</hi>, and his 
<hi rend="i">Metamorphosis Metallorum.</hi></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">London, May</hi> 26, 1789.</p>
          <p>AUGUST NORDENSKJÖLD<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Member of the New Jerusalem Church in London, and one of his Majesty’s Superintendents of the
Mines in Sweden</hi></p>
          <p>P.S. It is particularly requested, that the Contents of this Letter be not made public; and that
all Answers be directed for me at Mr. Robert Hindmarsh’s, Printer to his Royal Highness the Prince of Wales,
No, 32, Clerkenwell-Close, London.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
