<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.4.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Bintley, Job (San Francisco Ballet, 17 March 1992)</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1993</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Margaret Storch</name>
              <name>John Vice</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-4-0008">
        <pb id="p26-166" n="166"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Bintley’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> at the San Francisco Ballet, 17 March
1992</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>A new ballet of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, choreographed by David Bintley, was given its world
premiere by the San Francisco Ballet on 17 March 1992. Like the earlier <hi rend="i">Job</hi> ballet<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">1</ref> that was choreographed by Ninette de Valois
after a scenario by Geoffrey Keynes, Bintley’s work is set to the music of Ralph Vaughan Williams and is
divided into nine scenes. Unlike the Keynes-de Valois work, it is not a translation of Blake’s designs into
balletic terms but is rather a re-interpretation of the biblical story. Nevertheless the presence of Blake’s
visual conceptions lingers in a number of places, and there are some interesting thematic parallels and
contrasts as well. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Sir Geoffrey Keynes, “Blake’s Job on the
Stage,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 2nd ed., 1971): 187-95; Mary Clarke,
“The <hi rend="i">Job</hi> Ballet,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 12 (1978): 18-25. In the San Francisco Ballet
program there appears an article “Vaughan Williams, William Blake, and Job” by Allison Sanders McFarland
(<hi rend="i">Performing Arts</hi> 5 (1992): 10-11.)</note></p>
          <p>Hayden Griffin’s imaginative set is meant to recall the world of Andrew Wyeth, as is
immediately established by the visual quotation of <hi rend="i">Christina’s World</hi> as the curtain rises.
The front of the stage is flat, but the rear part is steeply raked and covered with an astroturf field.
Further back, we later learn, is an abyss. The nine scenes proceed as follows.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1. “Hast Thou considered my servant Job?”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Job and his family seem to be posing for a family portrait— a brilliant reworking of the
family scene in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 1—with the unseen photographer in the position of the
audience. One daughter spontaneously dances out of the group, then sees that she has forgotten herself, and
rejoins the family’s placid regidity. The Sons of the Morning, led by the Messenger, advance in wedge-shaped
formation. They are androgynous, danced by both males and females wearing body suits, and in their postures
very suggestive of the morning Stars of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 14.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2. “So Satan went forth from the presence of the Lord”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Satan moves out from among the family, who never see him. He dances a dramatic, intricate solo
(illus. 1), brilliantly performed by Ashley Wheater. As in the Keynes-de Valois <hi rend="i">Job</hi>,
Satan’s role is conceived as intensely athletic.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">3. “Then came a great wind and smote the four corners of the house and it fell
among the young men and they were dead”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The house is a two-dimensional Midwestern-style farmhouse. “Job’s sons and their wives
dance a formal, slightly voluptuous minuet” (<hi rend="i">Performing Arts</hi>, 13). Satan moves among them
and strikes each dead with a touch. The bodies are discovered by Job and his wife. Job hunches eloquently in
dazed despair. Jim Sohn portrayed Job here as throughout with immense pathos and dignity.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">4. “In thoughts from the visions of the night . . . fear came upon me and
trembling”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Job sits on a bench at stage right (much as in Blake’s engraving 11) and then is attacked by
visions of Death, Famine, and Plague dispatched by Satan (illus. 2).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">5. “There came a messenger”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The messenger is not Blake’s running athlete but the tall, graceful Muriel Maffre, who also
leads the Sons of the Morning in scences 1 and 7. After the destruction of his former prosperity, Job surveys
his fields looking something like Gary Cooper in a Dust Bowl movie.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">6. “Behold, happy is the man whom God correcteth”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The three comforters appear, wearing round black hats and black frock coats suggestive of some
religious sect. Their hands are at one point raised high as in <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engraving 7; at another
they point accusingly as in engraving 10. Above, Satan is revealed in the heavenly throne—a disk in which he
stands like Vitruvian man.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">7. “Ye are old and I am very young”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Elihu’s lyrical dance commences. His role, which continues into the following scenes, is much
larger than in Blake’s illustrations, the Keynes-de Valois ballet, or, for that matter, the biblical text.
In Bintley’s words “Elihu’s beauty, purity, and innocence becomes the vessel for God’s reply to Job”
(San Francisco Ballet cast list for March 17, 1992). All this was eloquently conveyed by Bruce Sansom. At one
point, Elihu seems to become the crucified Christ supported by the Messenger (illus. 3).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">8. “All the Sons of God shouted for Joy”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Satan falls from the celestial disk and then disappears into the abyss at the back of the
stage. The 14 Sons of the Morning, led by the Messenger, reappear, their arm and hand gestures especially
reminiscent of Blake’s famous image.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">9. “So the Lord blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>After the joyful music stops, Job goes to the rear of the stage and seems to muse while gazing
into the abyss.</p>
            <p>Neither Blake nor David Bintley accepts the meaning of the Book of Job as it is usually
understood. The message of God from the whirlwind is satirized in Blake’s interpretation and entirely absent
from Bintley’s. For Blake the meaning lies in the casting off of a past self and in regeneration through
suffering; for Bintley it is the divinely human Elihu who transforms Job. God, shown by Blake (and by
Keynes-de Valois) to be Job’s ego projection, does not appear in Bintley at all. Although Bintley’s
brilliant new <hi rend="i">Job</hi> is not a recasting of Blake’s designs, it clearly bears some suggestion
derived from Blake’s images and conceptions. It would be fascinating to see it on the same program with the
Keynes-de Valois work.</p>
            <pb id="p26-167" n="167"/>
            <figure n="Wheater.26.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="150" height="408">
              <head>1. Ashley Wheater as Satan</head>
              <figDesc>Photo by Marty Sohl c. 1992. Reproduced by permission of the San Francisco
Ballet.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="WheaterBerman.26.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="332">
              <head>2. Ashley Wheater as Satan, Joanna Berman as Death.</head>
              <figDesc>Photo by Marty Sohl c. 1992. Reproduced by permission of the San Francisco
Ballet.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="SansomMaffre.26.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="324">
              <head>3. Bruce Sansom as Elihu, Muriel Maffre as The Messenger.</head>
              <figDesc>Photo by Marty Sohl c. 1992. Reproduced by permission of the San Francisco
Ballet.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
