<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.4.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Blake as Craftsman and Artist: Two Exhibitions in Tokyo</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1993</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Margaret Storch</name>
              <name>John Vice</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-4-0008">
        <pb id="p26-168" n="168"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main" rend="main">Blake as Craftsman and Artist: Two Exhibitions in Tokyo</title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title type="main"><hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (Yanagi: Blake no deai): <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>
(Great Encounter: Yanagi and Blake) [To accompany an exhibition] September 1-October 28 [1990 at Mingeikan:]
The Japan Folk Crafts Museum, Komaba, Tokyo, Japan. [Tr. Kenkichi Kamijima &amp; Teiko Utsumi.] (Tokyo: The
Japan Folk Crafts Museum, 1990) 110 pp. 100 illus. 4to.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">1</ref></title>
              <title type="main"><hi rend="i">William Blake: William Blake</hi> [Catalogue of an exhibition] 25
September-25 November 1990 [at] The National Museum of Western Art, Tokyo. [Tr. Koji Yukiyama, Chikashi
Kitazaki &amp; Akiya Takahashi.] (Tokyo Nihon Keizai Shimbun: The National Museum of Western Art, 1990) xiv +
314 pp. 441 plates; 4to . . . 2nd edition . . . (1990). xii + 314 pp. 441 plates; 4to. 
<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">1</hi> In this review translations of Japanese words in brackets are supplied by GEB; those without
brackets are given in the originals in English. The transliterations were supplied by my friend Keiko
Aoyama.</note></title>
            </head>
            <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
            <p>For 75 years William Blake has been the subject of great and growing excitement in Japan, until
today there are more works on Blake published in Japanese than in all other non-English languages
combined.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">2</ref> The first great book on
Blake in Japanese was <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> by Soetsu (Muneyoshi) Yanagi<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">3</ref> in 1914, and the first exhibition on Blake in Japan was
organized by Yanagi for The White Birch Society in 1919. There were subsequent Blake exhibitions in Tokyo in
1927 (for the centenary of Blake’s death) and 1957 (for the bicentenary of his birth), but none of these
exhibitions showed originals of Blake’s art or writings. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i">
Blake Studies in Japan</hi>: A Bibliography of Works on William Blake Published in Japan 1911-1990 by G.E.
Bentley, Jr. with the assistance of Keiko Aoyama, which will be published by the Japan Society of English
Romanticism, summarizes the growth of Japanese Blake studies numerically as:
<table rows="5" cols="4"><row>
	<cell>1911-19:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">17</hi></cell>
	<cell>1960-69:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">67</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1920-29:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">45</hi></cell>
	<cell>1970-79:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">202</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1930-39:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">71</hi></cell>
	<cell>1980-89:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">168</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1940-49:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">16</hi></cell>
	<cell>1990:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">23</hi>[incomplete]</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1950-59:</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">74</hi></cell>
	<cell><hi rend="b">Total</hi></cell>
	<cell><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">683</hi></hi></cell>
</row></table></note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Mr Yanagi’s given name is represented by a character which is pronounced
“Muneyoshi” in Japanese but “Soetsu” in Chinese; in Japanese he was referred to as “Muneyoshi,”
but when he wrote in English he identified himself as “Soetsu.”</note></p>
            <p>The first exhibition of Blake’s art in Japan which dealt with original materials officially
opened on 21 September 1990—and so did the second! The two exhibitions, and the volumes which accompany and
commemorate them, are extraordinarily different; the first exhibition, at the Japan Folk Crafts Museum, is
quiet, discrete, and very Japanese; the second, at the National Museum of Western Art, is grand, impressive,
and thoroughly international, an admirable machine for pictureviewing. All Blake scholars will recognize the
exhibition at the National Museum of Western Art as being of major importance, one of the really great Blake
exhibitions, comparable to those in 1939 (Philadelphia), 1978 (London), and 1982-83 (New Haven &amp; Toronto),
and the catalogue is in many ways, such as illustrations and scholarly essays, greatly superior to all other
Blake exhibition catalogues. But William Blake would have been bewildered by the impersonality of the
building, the high-tech lighting, the hype, the fashionable crowds, and the èclat of an International Event.
At the elegant opening in the capacious, anonymous foyer, diplomats rubbed shoulders with royalty, security
guards were discretely omnipresent, guests nibbled appetizers and chatted of London and fashion, and a few
drifted through the corridors of glory of the dazzling exhibition itself.</p>
            <p>The exhibition at the Japan Folk Crafts Museum was altogether more humane and individually
memorable. On entering the traditional Japanese wooden building, guests removed their shoes and donned soft
slippers so as not to profane the glowing wooden floors. Round the walls, in gentle, natural light, were
anonymous works of everyday craftsmanship, water jugs and work clothes, knives and tables and cups, exhibiting
a dignified simplicity and modest integrity which justified the hopes of the founder, Soetsu Yanagi, that they
would convey to others an unpretentious, traditional, and medieval beauty. Neither craftsman nor creation
called out for attention, and indeed the former were largely unknown and the latter had been largely
unnoticed. Nothing was decorative, and all were beautiful.</p>
            <p>Amongst these permanent exhibits were scattered pictures by Blake, almost all of them
reproductions of reproductions, often multiplied in size, and of course all of them were both decorative (that
is, having no practical, mundane function) and in kind unlike anything else in the museum. Their first
justification was that such works had been the first love of the founder, Soetsu Yanagi. But the inspiration
of Yanagi’s son, the present director, that Blake’s works would harmonize with such folk crafts was
satisfactorily justified. Little attempt was made to link Blake’s pictures to a context in Blake’s work or
in western civilization, and, indeed, it was not always clear from captions at the exhibition and in the
accompanying volume which works were originals and which were reproductions. This was carried so far that the
only original works in the exhibition of significant importance, the plates for Dante and posthumous pulls
from <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> pl. 22, 28, 30, 39 (copy o), 40, 44-46, 48 (a and b), were not even mentioned in
the volume. The exhibition at the Japan Folk Crafts Museum was valuable for the demonstration of harmony
between Blake’s works and traditional Japanese ways of life.</p>
            <p>Many of the myriads of Japanese Blake enthusiasts are persuaded that there are strong
similarities between Blake’s ideas and those of traditional Japan, particularly Japanese Buddhism. The
Mingeikan exhibition showed the immanence of a similar simple and divine harmony in Japanese folk crafts and
the art of William Blake.</p>
            <p>The exhibition at the Museum of Western Art might have been held in any sophisticated
metropolis in the world, and it would have done any of 
<pb id="p26-169" n="169"/>
them proud. The Museum is set in the Ueno Park, a cultural haven with galleries, trees, a festival hall, a
baseball-field—and pink folk in head-bands sitting on the ground offering handmade flutes and jewelry for
sale to the gadget-happy Japanese. The Museum itself is modern, air-conditioned, and impressive, with dim
rooms beautifully lit in the latest style. Panels protruding from the walls held individual plates of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> for intimate viewing, and the great color-prints were shown in a spaciousness of setting
which did them justice. One of the most exciting things about the exhibition was that it showed two versions
of some prints, such as “Glad Day” from the British Museum (colored), and National Gallery, Washington
(uncolored), or <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> from the British Library (uncolored) and Glasgow University
(colored), so that it was possible to compare the originals as would never be possible in their home
institutions. Eight of the great color prints were reproduced from seven collections in Altadena, Edinburgh,
London, Malibu, New Haven, and New York. Even more exciting, a number of major works were shown which have
never been exhibited before, such as the newly discovered Large Blake-Varley sketchbook, or have never been
seen outside of their home institution, such as <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (Z). Works were borrowed
from round the world, from institutions in Australia (1), Germany (1), Great Britain (12), Japan (3), and the
United States (17), not counting anonymous lenders, and viewers could range over Blake’s art from his
apprenticeship to his noblest maturity, from sketches to watercolors to colorprints, from single pictures to
books in Illuminated Printing.</p>
            <p>Some Blake-lovers hoped that the exhibition would include important originals which are known
or suspected to have emigrated to Japan, but such hopes were disappointed. The only works from Japanese
collections were Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1808), Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797), 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1826), and Dante (?1838), which are sufficiently
<figure n="Tokyo.26.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="333">
	<figTranscr>ウィリアム・ブレイク<lb/>
	William Blake</figTranscr>
	<head>The giant “William Blake” poster at the entrance to the exhibition in the National Gallery of
Western Art (Tokyo), with Keiko Aoyama, Dr. and Mrs. Bentley, Professor and Mrs. James Hiao Kodama, and
Professor Kodama’s class (<corr type="emend">September</corr> 1990).</head>
</figure>
common to be owned by mere mortals. The exhibition did not reveal any Blake collection in Japan comparable to
the major Shakespeare collection in Tokyo, or even any very significant minor collections of original
materials. But it is likely that the exhibition will foster the formation of such collections.</p>
            <p>The exhibition was “commissioned” by Gert Schiff, who, alas, was too ill to see it and who
died shortly after it closed. When Dr. Schiff’s illness prevented him from completing the catalogue, the
work was taken up on very short notice by Martin Butlin, who is responsible for an unidentified third of the
entries in the catalogue. The volume has important essays by Gert Schiff, Martin Butlin, Robert Essick, and
David Bindman and tantalizingly brief contributions by others such as Detlef Dörrbecker and Joseph Viscomi.
Those by Butlin and Essick are largely distillations of their scholarship elsewhere, but those by Schiff (in
the 2nd edition), Bindman, Dörrbecker, and Viscomi are significant new contributions to Blake scholarship,
especially the last two. The most original entry in the catalogue (No. 31) is for the design usually called
“Hecate” but here called “The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy”:
<q>
The likeliest explanation of the print is . . . that it allegorizes Enitharmon’s scheme to enslave mankind
by way of sexual repression.
</q></p>
            <p>Readers who do not read Japanese must hope that an edition will be published in English for
access to the texts, but they do not have to wait to profit greatly from the catalogue, for the reproductions
include virtually everything in the exhibition. Further, the color plates include reproductions (usually
reduced in size and therefore not facsimiles) for the first time of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (A), 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (“A,” i.e., “a”), <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (C), <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> (H), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>(Z), and Hayley’s “Little Tom the Sailor”
(Schiller copy, the only known colored copy). The catalogue is therefore of considerable value for its unique
reproduction of whole Illuminated books. But in the exhibition, there were few entries of
<pb id="p26-170" n="170"/>
books <hi rend="i">qua</hi> books. Most of the works in Illuminated Printing were shown broken up, as
collections of pictures.</p>
            <p>We are very fortunate to have the reproduction of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (Z),
which has not been seen outside the royal library in Munich since about 1840 and which was only recently
identified as an original.</p>
            <p>The Larger Blake-Varley sketchbook was not broken up, as the Smaller Blake-Varley sketchbook
had been. Patient viewers had to come back every day to see a new page—but alas! we could see it only
twice.</p>
            <p>The two Blake exhibitions were extraordinarily interesting in their different ways. That at the
National Museum of Western Art is a major contribution to Blake understanding, a fitting last accomplishment
for Gert Schiff, and the catalogue is wonderfully valuable even for those who do not read Japanese. That at
the Japan Crafts Museum is a far more idiosyncratic accomplishment—and perhaps more fitting for the
idiosyncratic William Blake.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Appendix</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The bilingual contents of the Japan Folk Crafts Museum volume consist chiefly of (1) Sori
Yanagi [the son of the founder], “Goaisatsu: Foreword” (3); (2) messages from the Prime Ministers of
Britain and Japan, the British Ambassador to Japan, and the Director of the British Council<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">4</ref> (4-7);(3) Bunsho Jugaku, “‘William Blake
to Yanagi Muneyoshi tono oinaru deai’ ten wo yorokobu: A Delightful Exhibition on ‘A Great Encounter of
William Blake and Soetsu Yanagi’” (9); (4) G. E. Bentley, Jr., “William Blake to sozoryoku no teikoku:
William Blake and the Empire of the Imagination” (10-21); Kimiyoshi Yura, “Yanagi shiso no shihatsu eki:
‘William Blake’: The Great Encounter: Soetsu Yanagi and William Blake” (22-31), adapted from 
<hi rend="i">Yanagi Muneyoshi Zenshu</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Complete Works of Muneyoshi Yanagi</hi>], Vol. IV
(1981); Anon., “Zuhan mokuroku: List of Plates” (98-102). <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Both
exhibitions were part of what was called “UK90: A Celebration of British Arts.”</note></p>
              <p><hi rend="i">N.B.</hi> There is no catalogue of the exhibition as such; some of the works
exhibited, such as posthumous pulls for <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> and the Dante
plates, are not mentioned in the book. The 100 plates, 25 large ones in handsome color, include 16 for 
<hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise.</hi></p>
              <p>The contents of the National Museum of Western Art catalogue, in Japanese unless otherwise
identified,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">5</ref> are chiefly (1) The
National Museum of Western Art: Nihon Keizai Shinbun Inc., “Foreword” in Japanese and English (vi-vii);
(2) Gert Schiff, untitled introduction, in English (viii-ix); (3) Koji Yukiyama, untitled explanation of the
catalogue (x-xi in the first edition; omitted in the 2nd edition); (4) Gert Schiff, “[Young Blake and his
Moral Rebellion]” (5-14 in the 2nd edition; not present in the first edition); Martin Butlin, “William
Blake (1757-1827),” tr. Hiroyuki Tanida (15-22); (5) Robert N. Essick, “Blake to shokugyo to shite no
hanga seisaku [Blake and the Profession of Printmaking],” tr. Koji Yukiyama (23-32); (6) Martin Butlin,
“William Blake no shikaku teki hyogen shudan no hatten [William Blake: The Evolution of his Visual Means of
Expression],” tr. Chikashi Kitazaki (33-39); (7) David Bindman, “Wataxhi jishin no kokoro ga watashi no
kyokai de aru, Blake to Paine to French kakumei [‘My own mind is my own church’: Blake, Paine and the
French Revolution],” tr. Kozo Shioe (40-51); (8) Gert Schiff &amp; Martin Butlin, “Katarogu: Catalogue”
and “Sakuhin kaisetsu [Works Commentary],” tr. Keiko Kokatsu, Akiko Shimohama, Naoko Seki, Kumiko Tanaka,
<corr type="emend">Hideko Numata,</corr> Nobuko Hitomi, Noriko Mintao, &amp; Miyuki Yasumatsu (53-264), with an English summary and
“Works Cited” (265-79); (9) Beth A. Mandelbaum, “Nenpu [Chronicle],” tr. Hoko Fukumitsu (281-306);
(10) Martin Butlin, “Literature” (i.e., bibliography), in English (307-10); and (11) Martin Butlin, list
of “Exhibitions,” in English (310-11). <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The translations of Japanese
titles and summaries of contents derive from reproductions of the original typescripts generously sent me by
the National Museum of Western Art and the contributors.</note></p>
              <p>There are 104 entries in the catalogue, some of them (e.g., <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>)
representing many pages exhibited. The 441 plates include color reproductions (mostly reduced in size) of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> (A), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (a and B), <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (D), 
<hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (C), <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (H), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
(Z), and Hayley’s “Little Tom” (Schiller copy), plus black-and-white reproductions of copies of the
Blake plates for Blair, Dante, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Virgil (17), and Young.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
