<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.4.vice</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Blake—A Man Without Marx</title>
        <author n="Vice">John Vice</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1993</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Margaret Storch</name>
              <name>John Vice</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-162" n="162"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-4-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main" rend="main">William Blake—A Man Without Marx</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>John <name>Vice</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>I</title>
            </head>
            <p>In 1953, 10 years after Jacob Bronowski had written his acclaimed biography of William Blake,
<hi rend="i">A Man Without A Mask</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">1</ref> he arrived in New York’s port authority with book in hand. The United States was then in
the ugly grip of McCarthyism, so Bronowski was met by a customs officer whose job was to read all imported
literature and to weed out anything that was deemed to be un-American, particularly what was socialist or
communist. Bronowski recalled the awkward moment when the official began flicking through the Blake biography:
“I thought, ‘we may be in trouble, there are all kinds of references to Karl Marx, socialism, the
Industrial Revolution and other taboo subjects.’” But the customs officer, astonished after reading just
two sentences, said, “You write this, bud? Psshh, this ain’t never gonna be no best seller!”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The book has gone through a variety of titles: <hi rend="i">A Man Without A
Mask</hi> when it was first published (London: Secker and Warburg, 1944, and New York: Transatlantic Arts,
1947), <hi rend="i">William Blake: 1757-1827</hi> (Harmondsworth: Pelican Books, 1954) and 
<hi rend="i">William Blake and the Age of Revolution</hi> in its first major American edition (New York: Harper
and Row, 1965; also London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1972), when Bronowski added a new introduction. It is
due to be reprinted by Harcourt Brace Jovanovich in winter 1993. I refer to it throughout as 
<hi rend="i">WB</hi> with page references from, respectively, the 1944, 1954, and 1965 editions.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">2</hi> From J. Bronowski, <hi rend="i">The Origins of Knowledge and
Imagination</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1978) 138.</note></p>
            <p>Many literary critics, who have pointed to a methodological affinity between Marxism and the
approach in Bronowski’s book, would argue that the customs officer should have been more alert to the red
menace in <hi rend="i">A Man Without A Mask.</hi> One month after it was published, <hi rend="i">The
Listener</hi> first made charges about its Marxist connection: “Bronowski’s method of interpreting Blake
derives from Marx.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">3</ref> Two months
later, in July 1944, Herbert Read announced that Bronowski presented “A Marxian Blake” and criticized the
result.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">4</ref> Kathleen Raine agreed with
both diagnosis and criticism:
<q>
Mr Bronowski, while not in the narrowest sense a Marxist, assumes dialectical materialism as a standard of
reference . . . The result is <hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi> without the Prince of Denmark—or should one say the
<hi rend="i">Divina Comedia</hi> without God? Mr Bronowski may consider the Marxists right and Blake wrong,
but he cannot persuade us that Blake was ever a materialist.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">5</ref></q>
Twenty-five years later she dismissed the book with greater brevity as “A Marxist view of Blake,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">6</ref> and later still asserted, “His book on Blake
is excellent as sociology of the turn of the eighteenth century, but when he tries to write about the poems he
shows no understanding of them at all. He had not that kind of mind.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">7</ref> Likewise, Maynard Solomon traced the book’s influence to
its connection with the Marxist critic Christopher Caudwell: “Jacob Bronowski . . . would acknowledge
himself neither a Marxist nor a Caudwellian, but he came closer to utilizing Caudwell’s poetics than any
other critic of British literature.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Unsigned review, <hi rend="i">The Listener</hi>, 18 May 1944.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Herbert Read, “A Marxian Blake,” <hi rend="i">The New Leader</hi>, 15
July 1944.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">The Dublin Review</hi>, July 1944.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: Thames and
Hudson, 1970) 209.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Correspondence with the author, 3 July 1988.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">8</hi> In Maynard Solomon, ed., <hi rend="i">Marxism and Art: Essays Classic and
Contemporary</hi> (Sussex: Harvester Press, 1979) 343.</note></p>
            <p>Now, nearly 50 years after the book’s publication, and on the eve of its re-publication, it
stands in need of reassessment. I believe that the customs officer was right to overlook its connection with
Marxism, because Bronowski’s stated aims in the biography contradict those of a Marxist approach. However,
the official was wrong to belittle the book’s standing—even if it failed to become a bestseller—because
it created a new approach to Blake’s poetry. Bronowski suggested, for the first time, that Blake was best
studied not as an inspired visionary of a private universe but as a realist poet and social critic whose work
could only be understood in relation to the major historical events of the late eighteenth century: the
American and French revolutions and the Industrial Revolution.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>II</title>
            </head>
            <p>Did Bronowski present a Marxist view of Blake in <hi rend="i">A Man Without A Mask?</hi> An
immediate difficulty with answering that question is that neither Marx nor Engels made a systematic study of
aesthetics. As a result, their fragmentary remarks have been cited in support of several mutually exclusive
literary theories. However, one thesis that a Marxist approach to literature should involve is that of a
particular, determining relationship between the economic base of a society and its superstructure, or
culture, including its arts, politics and legal system. As Marx classically put it: “The mode of production
of material life conditions the social, political and intellectual life-process in general.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">9</ref> However, the relation between a work of art
and its underlying economic or material cause is not necessarily direct, as Engels explained: “It is not
that the economic situation is <hi rend="i">cause, solely active</hi>, while everything else is only passive
effect. There is, rather, interaction on the basis of economic necessity, which <hi rend="i">ultimately</hi>
always asserts itself.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Karl Marx, <hi rend="i">A Contribution to the Critique of Political
Economy</hi>, quoted in Solomon, 29.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Friedrich Engels, in a letter to W. Borgius, quoted in Solomon,
33.</note></p>
            <p>Bronowski certainly had considerable sympathy with Marx—he argued that Marx, “the greatest
of social critics,” had carried out “the most searching study of the war of society with
itself.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">11</ref> He also compared Blake
with Marx, decided that they were “driven by the same loves and indignations,” and, in what he later
called “a climax to the argument of the book,” said that Marx’s labor theory of value was identical in
spirit with the verse in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> that begins, “Shall not the King call for Famine
from the heath.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> WB</hi> 142, 93/ 204, 137/ 190, 130.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> WB</hi> 142/204/190 and J. Bronowski, “Recollections of
Humphrey Jennings,” <hi rend="i">The Twentieth Century</hi> 165 (1959): 48.</note></p>
            <p>However, there is nothing Marxist about finding connections between the thought of Blake and of
Marx. Rather, the charge that Bronowski’s book was Marxist derives from the amount of economic detail that
he included in his book—nearly 40 pages are devoted to describing details about water pumps, iron furnaces
and other features of economic life in eighteenth-century England. The implication behind that charge is that
Bronowski discussed economics because it determined Blake’s work. Bronowski included such detail, however,
not because he was reading Blake by the light of Marxism but because Blake wrote about economic conditions and
the social revolution that they brought. One could not, Bronowski
<pb id="p26-163" n="163"/>
felt, understand Blake’s language and poetry without such detail:
<q>
The life of Blake, and his thought . . . are there, for all to read, in the history of his time; in the names
of Pitt, of Paine, and of Napoleon; in the hopes of rationalists, and in the despair of craftsmen. Until we
know these, we shall not understand Blake’s poems, we shall not understand his thought, because we shall not
speak his language.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> WB</hi> 15/28/36.</note></q>
Bronowski argued that Blake’s language was that not of an Old Testamentary mystic but of a political
revolutionary who retreated behind the obscure symbolism of the Prophetic Books only because he feared
prosecution for sedition and grew skeptical about the ability of politics to improve people’s welfare.
Throughout his life, Bronowski felt, Blake’s work remained rooted in the social, political and economic
conditions in which he lived. The overtly political tones of “The French Revolution” are echoed in
“Visions of the Daughters of Albion,” “America” and “Europe,” although they are disguised, often
symbolically, in the conflict between Orc or Los and Rintrah or Palamabron. Likewise, Bronowski prefaced his
discussion of Blake’s Seditious Writings with a description of the economic and political nature of
Britain’s response to the American and French revolutions because that was what Blake wrote about. Again,
Bronowski argued that Blake’s theme in the Prophetic Books, especially <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, was the social war that the Industrial Revolution waged against Britain’s working
classes, and he felt that one could not pierce the sulphurous rhetoric of those poems without understanding
that social revolution. Bronowski included political and economic detail, then, not because it conditioned, or
was the ultimate cause of, Blake’s poetry, but because Blake wrote about politics and economics, and he felt
that one could not understand Blake’s language or poetry without that detail.</p>
            <p>Since Bronowski made no attempt to connect causally the economics of eighteenth-century England
with Blake’s work, he was able to deal with a criticism that Herbert Read leveled against him, and which is
generally raised against Marxist approaches to literature:
<q>
A lot of material which Mr. Bronowski digs up . . . is fascinating, but what has it to do with Blake? Just as
much, one would say, as it has to do with William Wordsworth, or Coleridge, or any other poet of the period.
The limitations of his method would be experienced by Mr. Bronowski himself if he were to turn now to
Wordsworth or Coleridge.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Read, <hi rend="i">The New Leader.</hi></note></q>
But Bronowski was fully aware of the limitations of his method, as he made clear in a passage to which Read
should have paid more attention: “the world in which Blake lived stands stark in the <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi>; but it did not of itself make the <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>; and it certainly
does not make them good or bad.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">15</ref>
Moreover, Bronowski felt that the only reason for studying Blake’s language was so that a critical or
aesthetic judgment about Blake’s creative work could be made. Detail about water pumps was merely a
preliminary to that aesthetic judgment: “When we have learnt Blake’s language, we have still to judge what
he said with it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> WB</hi> 17/32/39.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> WB</hi> 17/31/39.</note></p>
            <p>A second element that is common to many Marxist approaches to literature is a view about the
permanence and universality of art. In a controversial passage, Marx wrote: “It is well known that certain
periods of highest development of art stand in no direct connection with the general development of society,
nor with the material basis and the skeleton of its organisation.” He went on to say that Ancient Greek art
remained “the standard and unattainable ideal” for our, and for every, society, and that it exercised
“an eternal charm” over all of us.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Karl Marx, <hi rend="i">Grunrisse, quoted in Solomon
61-62.</hi></note></p>
            <p>Bronowski picked up the same theme about the universal, cross-cultural nature of art, and
developed it by saying that because man had a vertical plane of near-symmetry, walked upright and used his
hands for tools, he was “fixed to ways of seeing, of thinking, and of behaving which time cannot change
unless it changes him.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">18</ref> Bronowski
felt that Blake explored such universal truths in his poetry: “The kinds of thought and feeling, the kind of
truth to which Blake held and for which we read him . . . are not . . . impermanent.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">19</ref> Bronowski felt that Blake saw more clearly
than virtually any of his contemporaries into the dilemmas of urban life and the hierarchies of power in
industrialized society. Blake was a radical dissenter who sided with the individual in all confrontations with
authority, and his awareness and exploration of such problems, Bronowski maintained, involved a universal
insight into the human condition. Blake’s poems, Bronowski said, “speak from one age to another because
[they are] founded in experiences which are simple, common, profound, which are human and
universal.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">18</hi><hi rend="i"> WB</hi> 138/199/185-86.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> WB</hi> 138/198/185.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">20</hi> J. Bronowski, “A Prophet for our Age,” <hi rend="i">The Nation</hi>
185 (1957): 411.</note></p>
            <p>Thus far Bronowski’s view seems to chime with that of Marx, and of Christopher Caudwell, who,
in a passage quoted by Bronowski, argued: “great art . . . has something universal, something timeless and
enduring from age to age.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">21</ref>
However, such a resonance is not sufficient justification for treating Bronowski as a Marxist, for two
reasons. First, Marx’s view that Greek art exercises “an eternal charm” over all cultures and economic
systems has been held by many to be inconsistent with Marxism proper. Max Raphael, for instance, argued with
great force that Marx’s view was “essentially incompatible with historical materialism”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">22</ref>—if the material conditions of a society
determine its art, and if all art is class art, then its art cannot hold the same value for a society with a
different mode of production. So, although Marx believed in the universality of art, he should not have done,
and would not have done if he had made a systematic study of the relation between aesthetics and historical
materialism. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Christopher Caudwell, <hi rend="i">Illusion and Reality</hi>
(London: Lawrence &amp; Wishart, 1957) 339, quoted in <hi rend="i">WB</hi> 138/199/185.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Max Raphael, <hi rend="i">Proudhon, Marx and Picasso</hi> (London:
Lawrence &amp; Wishart, 1933) 76.</note></p>
            <p>Secondly, although Bronowski and Marx had a similar view of the universality of art, that view
is not specifically Marxist. It was a central part of Plato’s theory of ideal types, and has remained a
basic part of western aesthetics since the Renaissance, with 
<pb id="p26-164" n="164"/>
proponents ranging from Kant and Schiller to Schopenhauer and Collingwood. Moreover, Bronowski did not embrace
the view on Marxist grounds; his reasons for adopting it derive from Laura Riding’s poetics and the
threatened Nazi invasion of Britain in 1940—two parts of western culture that are not usually connected.</p>
            <p>In 1933, Bronowski went to live with Laura Riding and Robert Graves in Mallorca, where they
edited a small poetry journal. Bronowski quickly fell under the powerful influence of Riding, and, although
they eventually fell out after an argument, adopted her view of poetry without hesitation. She felt that “A
poem is an uncovering of truth of so fundamental and general a kind that no other name besides poetry is
adequate except truth.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">23</ref> Bronowski’s
first book, <hi rend="i">The Poet’s Defence</hi>, written three years after leaving Mallorca, was a study of
the history of that idea. It could be found, he argued, in the work of all the great poets from Philip Sidney
onwards. With phrasing that could have come straight from Riding, Bronowski wrote: “I believe in one worth
only: Truth. I defend poetry because I think that it tells that truth.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">24</ref> That view implied a particular relation between an
artist’s work and his or her society, namely that a description of their society could not fully reveal the
absolute truths that appear in their best poetry: “The mind of man has a knowledge of Truth beyond the
near-truths of science and society. I believe that poetry tells this Truth.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Laura Riding, <hi rend="i">The Poems of Laura Riding</hi> (Manchester:
Carcanet Press, 1980) 407.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">24</hi> J. Bronowski, <hi rend="i">The Poet’s Defence</hi> (Cambridge:
Cambridge Univ Press, 1939) 10.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Bronowski, <hi rend="i">The Poet’s Defence</hi> 11.</note></p>
            <p>The book, in Bronowski’s view, was only a partial success because it failed to persuade
critics—Marxists among them—who believed that poetry was merely another social utterance which was given
shape by the society in which the poet lived or the class to which he or she belonged. He therefore planned in
his next book, which he called <hi rend="i">Two Poets: Pope and Blake</hi>, to compare Blake with Alexander
Pope, hoping to establish how much the work of either poet owed to his society, and how much was an assertion
of poetic Truth, which was independent of that society. Bronowski argued that he could find the eternal truths
of poetry
<q>
not by pointing to them, but by pointing to everything else. Everything in the poem which is measurable and
common can be listed: the learning, the history, the psychology; the private foibles and the public
commonplaces; the wish and the indignation. This book must be full of such lists; and at the end of each it
must ask, Is this the whole poem? For if it is not, but only if it is not, there is some truth in the poem
which has no social names.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Bronowski’s manuscript for <hi rend="i">Two Poets: Pope and Blake</hi>,
private collection, 2.</note></q>
Information about water pumps was relevant to Blake’s work, then, both because it was one of Blake’s
themes and because it was part of one such list of “measurable and common” subjects. One would prove the
existence of poetic Truth only if those lists failed to capture all that poetry said. The lists would help to
generate a flash of light of empirical data that could be used to create a silhouette of the universal truths
of poetry, which could not be illuminated directly.</p>
            <p>The book, however, was never published. Bronowski completed it in mid 1941 only to have it
rejected by several publishing houses. War did not encourage publishers to take risks with books that might
not sell, and Bronowski’s book was, as Cambridge University Press told him, “open to the objection that
you have pulled history (not to say poetry) over to your side. Your side is an accusation [that could] . . .
make the right people uncomfortable, even angry.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">27</ref> A controversial book involved publishers in too great a risk during wartime. However,
after numerous rejections, Chatto and Windus suggested that Bronowski should use some of the material in the
book to write a short study of Blake, which they would be prepared to publish. Bronowski, then working as a
mathematics lecturer at University College, Hull,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">28</ref> started writing it in mid August 1942 and, remarkably, completed it six weeks later.
Several publication dates came and went, because Chatto and Windus were suffering acute paper shortages, but
the book eventually appeared in April 1944. The first edition bore the date “1943” on its title page as a
scar of its long gestation period. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Letter from J. Kendon to J. Bronowski,
5 May 1944, Bronowski papers, University of Toronto, box 133.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">28</hi> In the introduction to <hi rend="i">WB</hi> 1965 Bronowski said: “the
body of this book was written in 1942. At that time, I was working every day of the week at the tasks of
destruction which war sets for a scientist” (16). However, in 1942 Bronowski was still a mathematics
lecturer at University College, Hull. He became involved with the mathematics of bombing strategies when he
was recruited by the Ministry of Home Security in May 1943.</note></p>
            <p>So <hi rend="i">A Man Without A Mask</hi> was originally conceived as part of a larger work
that would have proved that great poetry told a truth that was independent of social life. It was also written
during wartime, and the truths that it purported to prove, and which Bronowski found in Blake, were those
under attack from Nazism: the right of individuals not to be controlled by society, the evils of repression
and the value of freedom.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">29</ref> The
intellectual roots of the book lay with Laura Riding’s conception of poetry and the threat to liberalism
that Nazism posed; they did not include Marxism or an attempt to show that Blake was a Marxist—even though
Blake and Engels share the same birth date. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">29</hi> See <hi rend="i">WB</hi>
136-44/197-206/183-91.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>III</title>
            </head>
            <p>What, today, is the value of Bronowski’s book? Its outstanding contribution was, as Bronowski
himself put it, that it “gave a new direction to Blake criticism.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n35" type="note">30</ref> It rejected for the first time the view that Blake was a mystical visionary
whose time and place of birth were mere accidents of fate, by showing that he was a realist poet whose
Prophetic Books were best read as social criticism. In 1944 Bronowski feared that such a view would seem
“outrageous to everybody.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">31</ref> The
fact that that view is now a commonplace is a measure of the success of his argument, which has been extended
and developed in, for instance, Mark Schorer’s <hi rend="i">The Politics of Vision</hi> (1946), David
Erdman’s <hi rend="i">William Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi> (1954) and Sabri-Tabrizi’s 
<hi rend="i">The “Heaven” and “Hell” of William Blake</hi>(1973). Bronowski’s approach has crucially
redirected Blake criticism, as Geoffrey Keynes argued in a review in 1944:
<q>
Mr. Bronowski’s book is a real contribution to the study of Blake, for never before have the social and
political bearings of his thought been so carefully extracted from the body of his writings, or set so
satisfactorily against the background of his time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">32</ref></q>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">30</hi> J. Bronowski, <hi rend="i">The Visionary Eye</hi> (Cambridge, MA and
London: MIT Press, 1978) 3.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Bronowski, “Recollections” 48.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, “William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Time and Tide</hi>, 3
June 1944.</note></p>
            <pb id="p26-165" n="165"/>
            <p>Of course Bronowski’s work has its faults: for example, he too swiftly dismissed Blake’s
paintings and engravings, and missed, therefore, the important connections between Blake’s art and his
poetry; and—a surprising criticism to make of a writer who made his reputation as a popularizer of science,
most notably in the television series <hi rend="i">The Ascent of Man</hi>— the book is in places badly
written and misleading. However, it remains an important and influential reading of Blake. Bronowski made it
impossible to regard Blake as an isolated, apolitical muse by showing that in his poetry he lived the hopes
and horrors of eighteenth-century England. And Blake was the first to admit that England’s grinding poverty,
far from improving his work, had helped to shackle it, as he wrote:
<q>
Some people &amp; not a few Artists have asserted that the Painter of this Picture would not have done so well
if he had been properly Encourag’d. Let those who think so, reflect on the State of Nations under Poverty
&amp; their incapability of Art; tho’ Art is Above Either, the Argument is better for Affluence than
Poverty; &amp; tho’ he would not have been a greater Artist, yet he would have produc’d Greater works of
Art in proportion to his means.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">33</ref>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">33</hi> I am indebted to Harriet Coles and Sue Vice for their perceptive comments
on this article.</note></q></p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
