<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.1.otto</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Reply to De Luca’s review of Constructive Vision and Visionary
Deconstruction</title>
        <author n="Otto">Peter Otto</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1993</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Helen Bruder</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Vincent A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
	<pb id="p27-29" n="29"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <head>
          <title type="section-subtitle">
            <hi rend="i">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of thought</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Reply to De Luca’s review of <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision and Visionary
Deconstruction</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Peter <name>Otto</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>After allowing that <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision</hi> “has at its core an interesting and
valuable idea about Blake,” De Luca’s critique gets underway with the assertion that the book’s
“argument tends to proceed more by ungrounded assertions, associative leaps, and rhetorical sleights of hand
than by rigorous philosophical analysis.” I suppose that as the author of the book I should just accept De
Luca’s vigorous and rhetorical strictures and leave it at that. However, in this instance the right of reply
has proved too tempting, though I will try to confine myself to a few brief remarks.</p>
          <p>De Luca’s first example of “ungrounded assertions, associative leaps, and rhetorical sleights
of hand” is a parallel between Newtonian time and the “ORDERD RACE” (26, E 171) of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that is drawn in the first paragraph of the third chapter of <hi rend="i">Constructive
Vision.</hi> I am happy to believe that almost all of the issues that would arise from this conjunction are
left unexplained or undeveloped <hi rend="i">in this paragraph</hi>—it is after all an introductory
paragraph—but De Luca wants to argue that the reading of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> contained by the last
four chapters of <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision</hi> somehow depends upon connections established here.
According to De Luca, in this small paragraph a parallel between <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and fallen time
is established on which an entire “superstructure of commentary proceeds to be built.” In fact, this
opening and introductory paragraph is in no sense the <hi rend="i">ground</hi> of the reading that follows.
<pb id="p27-30" n="30"/>
The claims and certainties of the first paragraph represent a naive or first approximation that is
complicated, and qualified, by the very next paragraph, and then by the rest of the chapter. The following
chapters treat Newtonian time as at best one aspect (a superficial one at that) of fallen time. Newtonian time
is not the subject of detailed analysis because this particular correlation is not of great importance for the
argument that follows. <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision</hi> does argue that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
mirrors “some of our most fundamental experiences of time,” but this claim is first made seven pages after
the paragraph referred to by De Luca. Moreover, the claim is substantiated by an analysis of critical accounts
of the experience of reading <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, a discussion of Locke’s account of time in 
<hi rend="i">An Essay</hi>, and then by the extended reading of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> which follows.</p>
          <p>De Luca’s second example of “ungrounded assertions” is meant to be more substantial and
more devastating. De Luca introduces it as an instance of a “slippery and elliptical kind of reasoning”
that is “especially disturbing when it is employed to establish the major premises of the book’s argument
or to challenge the consensus critical position on Blake.” I must admit that my language in the passage
quoted by De Luca is a bit woolly and probably too earnest and enthusiastic. However, in his attempt to
discredit my argument before it gets started, De Luca seems unnecessarily obtuse. Why should the phrase
“somewhat like a guinea” refer only to size? What is so extraordinary about the assumption that “an
Innumerable company of the Heavenly host crying Holy Holy Holy is the Lord God Almighty” is able to “talk,
move and sing?” Why is the “therefore” in the penultimate sentence of the passage quoted by De Luca
surreptitious and unearned? Isn’t it reasonably self-evident that in this context talking, moving and
singing had been understood to imply an alterity which cannot be reduced to our perception of it? Surely the
phrase “interpenetrated with others” is, in this context, not as equivocal as De Luca suggests. Why
doesn’t he consider the possibility that “others” refers to the angelic hosts? There is after all a
footnote to page 11 that, in an attempt to reduce the possibility of the kind of confusion alluded to by De
Luca, explains the sense in which the word “other” is used in my argument. Or finally, why should De Luca
be so resistant to the thought that “The world formed by Frye’s imagination might discover within its
bounds a force and presence which far exceeds its domain”? If domain can mean: (a) “estate, lands,
dominions;” (b) “district under rule, realm, sphere of influence;” and “scope, field, province of
thought or action,” then surely for most people it is not an unusual experience to come across (within the
bounds of their world) a force and presence which exceeds their domain. There is an inside/outside paradox
here, but I really don’t see why De Luca should find it so difficult to fathom.</p>
          <p>One of the self-revealing moments in De Luca’s review occurs when he claims that I
“deliberately and persistently” conflate “the world-forming imagination of the idealist tradition with
the Urizenic making of enclosed, exclusionary worlds.” De Luca believes that in so doing I align myself
“with those currently flourishing Schools of Resentment that are engaged in undermining further the fading
prestige of romanticism in general and Frye in particular.” There is no doubt that De Luca is here raising a
number of important issues but, rather than debating them, he frames them as charges to be answered in court.
If I am to be charged with these views and these alliances (and I don’t think that the issues are as cut and
dried as he suggests), why not at least gesture towards the readings which after all make up more than 90% of
the text? As my introduction carefully explains, when I wrote this book it was my opinion that “The nature
of Los and the relationship between time and Eternity in Blake’s oeuvre” (which together constitute, after
all, the main subject matter of the book, not the reputation of Northrop Frye or the nature of the imagination
in romanticism) could be elaborated most profitably “only within a discussion of the body of Blake’s
poetry.” It is these readings that provide the ground and evidence for the wider generalizations that are
made from time to time in <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision.</hi> It seems a shame that rather than arguing his
case from the views put forward in <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision</hi> and clearly identifying his own
“interest” in the issues at stake, De Luca chose a much easier course.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
