<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.1.davies</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">William Muir and the Blake Press at Edmonton with Muir’s letters to Kerrison
Preston</title>
        <author n="Davies">Keri Davies</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1993</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Helen Bruder</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Vincent A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
      <pb id="p27-14" n="14"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">William Muir and the Blake Press at Edmonton with Muir’s letters to Kerrison
Preston</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Keri <name>Davies</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>William Muir (1845-1938) is remembered, if at all today, for the hand-colored facsimiles of the
Prophetic Books of William Blake published by “The Blake Press at Edmonton.”</p>
		<q>
Twelve<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">1</ref> works in Illuminated Printing
were issued between 1884 and 1890, printed and coloured by hand at great trouble and with considerable
success. These works have, on occasion, been accidentally sold as originals. The size of the editions was
small, but their influence was appreciable, and their scope has only been equalled in recent times by the
facsimiles of the Blake Trust.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The Blake Press at Edmonton issued 15 titles, of which 12 were
hand-colored: <hi rend="i">Act of Creation</hi> (1885?), <hi rend="i">America</hi> (1887), <hi rend="i">The
Book of Thel</hi> (1884), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1887), <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> (1888),
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (1885), <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (1886), <hi rend="i">The
Song of Los</hi> (1890), <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (1885), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
(1884), <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> (1886), <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi> (1884), and three were issued as monochrome facsimiles, <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>
	  (1888), <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi><corr type="emend"> (1886),</corr> <hi rend="i">On Homer’s Poetry On Virgil</hi>
(1886).</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">2</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P,
1977) 28.</note></q>
        <p>Robert Essick suggests that Muir may have been responsible for the facsimiles of the frontispiece
to “Europe” (<hi rend="i">The Ancient of Days</hi>) mistakenly included in the 1978 William Blake
exhibition at the Tate Gallery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">3</ref> Muir
worked with no intent to deceive but the confusion at the Tate Gallery points up the best features of Muir’s
copies. They maintain a truth to Blake’s processes, if not always to his images, by continuing the basic
combination of a printed monochrome image with hand coloring. “Muir’s productions capture something of the
spirit of the originals, their various textures and hand-made craftsmanship, better than any photographic
reproductions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
Catalogue</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983). The disputed prints were items 66 and 67 in the catalogue of
the 1978 Tate Gallery exhibition.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Robert N. Essick, “<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> Manchester, England: Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19 (1985): 39.</note></p>
        <p>Muir’s obituary in the <hi rend="i">Oban Times</hi> was subtitled “a man of ability and
resource.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">5</ref> In the course of his
long life, Muir had been a quarry manager on the Ross of Mull, a journalist in Aberdeen, a businessman in
London; an author, printer, publisher, and inventor. He was a Blake scholar and collector; and the friend of
crofters and Princes. <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Alex Gartshore, “The late Mr William Muir: a man of
ability and resource” <hi rend="i">Oban Times</hi>, 19 October 1940, 3 col 4. Biographical statements not
otherwise supported are derived from this account.</note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Childhood<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Principal sources for this section are <hi rend="i">Post-Office Annual
Glasgow Directory</hi> 1844-45 to 1846-47; <hi rend="i">Old Parish Registers: Gorbals Parish</hi> [Microfilm
and typescript indexes in Mitchell Library, Glasgow]; <hi rend="i">Glasgow Register of Electors</hi>
1846-55.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <p>William Muir was born on 7 May 1845 at 20 Clyde Terrace, Gorbals, Glasgow. He was the eldest
child of George Walker Muir and his wife Christina Penman. His father’s family came from Kilmarnock,
Ayrshire, and G. W. Muir is listed in directories of the time as a “commission merchant.” His mother was a
native Glaswegian; William was born in the tenement where his mother’s family lived for many years.</p>
          <p>By the time of the 1851 Census, William had been joined by a brother (Andrew) and two sisters
(Christina and Hannah).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">7</ref> The fifth
child, George Walker Muir junior, was born in November. By 1851, William’s father had given up his job as
“commission merchant” and enrolled as a student of Law at Glasgow University.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">8</ref> He never took his degree. In fact, he changed his occupation
again in 1855 when he was granted the first of four patents.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n48" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Census 1851, <hi rend="i">Enumerators’ returns for Glasgow,
Gorbals.</hi> (Microfilm ref. 613-9).</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">8</hi> W. Innes Addison, <hi rend="i">The Matriculation albums of the University
of Glasgow from 1728 to 1858</hi> (Glasgow: Maclehose, 1913).</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">9</hi> UK Patents nos. 25 “Warming &amp; ventilating,” 1173 “Furnaces,”
2912 “Steamboilers” (1855); and no. 52 “Warming &amp; ventilating” (1858).</note></p>
          <p>Invention will be a recurring topic in this brief history of Muir and his family. George Walker
Muir’s patents were granted over the years 1855 to 1858 and are all concerned with heating and ventilating.
They have in fact a rather modern concern with energy efficiency. In 1855, G. W. Muir moved with his family to
Manchester, where he set up as a freelance heating engineer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n49" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Slater’s <hi rend="i">General and classified directory and street
register of Manchester and Salford</hi> 1855-58.</note></p>
          <p>Around 1860, William Muir was apprenticed in a stockbroker’s office in Glasgow, where he was to
remain for some years. But 1860 also saw the death of his brother Andrew Penman Muir, aged just 14. This death
seems to have affected Muir deeply. It was not until 1917 that he was in a position to arrange for an
inscription on his brother’s tomb. “Grief endures,” it says.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Niven lair, Glasgow Cathedral. Graveslab reads:
<q>
THE PROPERTY OF DAVID NIVEN, BOOKSELLER OF GLASGOW ANDREW PENMAN MUIR (SECOND SON OF G. W. MUIR) BORN 4TH
SEPT. 1846: DIED 16TH JULY 1860 AT ASCOG, BUTE CHRISTINA PENMAN (GRAND DAUGHTER OF D. NIVEN AND WIFE OF G. W.
MUIR BORN 4TH SEPT 1818: DIED 14TH NOVR 1869 Grief endures. W M MUIR 1917
</q></note></p>
          <p>Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, ‘Pictor Ignotus’</hi> was published in
1863. One can only speculate about the impact it would have made on the 18-year-old Muir, but I am tempted to
suggest that he would have reacted particularly strongly. Blake too had lost a younger brother and as with
Muir the loss of his brother was an enduring grief.</p>
          <p>There is another possible reason for Muir’s interest in Blake. Muir was great great-nephew of
the journalist, inventor, and biblical controversialist Alexander Tilloch<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">12</ref> Blake was one of the signatories in 1797 to a testimonial in
favor of Tilloch’s process for preventing the forgery of banknotes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n52" type="note">13</ref> Could some family tradition have led Muir towards Blake? Certainly
Tilloch’s sisters Rabina and Margaret were residents of Clyde Terrace in 1841 along with Muir’s mother and
grandmother.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">14</ref> Rabina Niven was
Muir’s great grandmother. Margaret Tilloch (she never married) had kept house in London for Tilloch after
his wife’s death in 1783 and could conceivably have met Blake. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">12</hi> See the
<hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Biography</hi> 56: 391-92.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">13</hi> G. E. Bentley Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P,
1967) 58.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Census 1841, <hi rend="i">Enumerators’ returns for Glasgow,
Gorbals</hi> (Microfilm ref. 644<hi rend="s">2</hi>-47)</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Quarry Manager</title>
          </head>
          <p>In August 1867, when just 22, Muir moved from Glasgow to the Inner Hebrides to become the quarry
manager at the Tormor Quarry<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">15</ref> on the
Ross of Mull just across the Sound from Iona. The quarry at that time was operated by G. &amp; J. Fenning.
Following the Fenning’s bankruptcy, the quarry was taken over by the Shap Granite &amp; Concrete
Co.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">15</hi> “Memories of Oban in the Sixties” <hi rend="i">Oban Times</hi>, 5 May
1934.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">16</hi> For a history of the quarry at Tormor, see Joan Faithfull’s article in
<hi rend="i">Am Muileach: community newspaper for Mull and Iona</hi>, February 1990.</note></p>
          <pb id="p27-15" n="15"/>
          <p>He lived at Fionnphort where the ferry now sails for Iona (his sister Hannah kept house for him);
and there he made the acquaintance of the MacCormick family. Their father Neil MacCormick was quarry foreman
and of his 8 sons, two also worked in the quarry. The family preserve to this day memories of Muir’s
friendship.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Personal communication from Neil MacCormick’s granddaughter, Miss
Margaret Harper-Nelson, October 1990.</note></p>
          <p>Muir left his post as quarry manager in 1875.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">18</ref> (The <hi rend="i">Oban Times</hi> obituary refers to a period spent in
Aberdeen as editor of an agricultural newspaper but I have so far been unable to verify this.) He seems to
have spent a year or so in Manchester before moving to London. He left his foreman, Neil MacCormick, as quarry
manager. The 1881 Census shows Muir at 9 Angel Row, Edmonton (now 191 Fore Street, London N9).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">19</ref> His sister Hannah joined him in Edmonton a
couple of years later. <note id="n57"><hi rend="s">18</hi><hi rend="i"> Oban Times</hi>, 13 February
1875.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Census 1881, <hi rend="i">Enumerator’s returns for Middlesex</hi>,
Edmonton. (Microfilm ref. ED4 Edmonton Schedule 242).</note></p>
          <p>The 1881 census gives Muir’s occupation as “granite agent.” Ross of Mull granite had been
used in a number of engineering projects of the 1860s and 1870s, such as the piers of Blackfriars Bridge,
docks in New York, parts of the Thames Embankment, and bridges in Glasgow. In later years the decorative
qualities of the granite (it has a distinctive pink color) were exploited by architects and sculptors. It was
presumably as supplier of granite that Muir made the acquaintanceship of Count Gleichen.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Count Gleichen<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">20</hi> See <hi rend="i">DNB Supplement</hi> 3: 388-89.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <p>Count Gleichen, or Prince Victor of Hohenlohe-Langenburg to give him his proper title, was a
nephew of Queen Victoria. Prince Victor had a successful naval career, seeing service in the Baltic, the
Crimea, and in China, but retired from the Navy in 1866 because of ill-health and devoted himself to an
artistic career, taking up sculpture as a serious profession. Queen Victoria granted him a suite of apartments
at St James’ Palace where he set up his studio. His best known work is a colossal statue of 
<hi rend="i">Alfred the Great</hi> in the market square at Wantage in Oxfordshire.</p>
          <p>At Woolwich, just off the Repository Road and not far from the Rotunda, stands the Afghan and
Zulu Wars Memorial by Count Gleichen. It consists of six blocks of pink granite assembled to form a simulacrum
of a giant boulder.
<figure n="parish.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="438">
	<head>1. Clyde Terrace and Gorbals Parish Church, Glasgow, in 1845.</head>
	<figDesc>Number 20, where Muir was born, is the five-story tenement just visible on the left-hand side. (From
a watercolor in The Mitchell Library Glasgow Room. Reproduced by permission of Glasgow City
Libraries.)</figDesc>
</figure>
The granite was supplied by the Shap Granite Company.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">21</ref> Also at Woolwich, Gleichen’s statue of Louis Bonaparte, the Prince Imperial, was
unveiled in January 1883. It too had a pink granite plinth.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n61" type="note">22</ref> I suggest that Muir may have been the agent for the granite used in these
works. <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Contemporary accounts of the two monuments at Woolwich can be found
in <hi rend="i">The Times</hi>, 5 October 1882: 7 and 15 January 1883: 10. Confusingly, the 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> reporter manages to ascribe the distinctive pink granite of cairn and plinth both to
Cumberland and to Aberdeenshire.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">22</hi> I have been unable to locate the present whereabouts of the monument to
the Prince Imperial.</note></p>
          <pb id="p27-16" n="16"/>
          <figure n="quarry.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="278">
            <head>2. In 1867, Muir became quarry manager at the Tormor Quarry on the Ross of Mull in the Inner
Hebrides.</head>
            <figDesc>This is the view from Iona looking over the fifteenth-century Abbey towards the island of
Mull—it would be hard to imagine a location of greater contrast to his childhood in Glasgow and Manchester.
(Photo: Ted Ryan.)</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Blake Press</title>
          </head>
          <p>Muir remained associated with the granite trade to the end of the century, but friendship with
Count Gleichen must have encouraged his own artistic ambitions, and in 1884 he began the work for which he is
now remembered: the production of hand-colored facsimiles of the Prophetic Books of William Blake.</p>
          <p>Muir’s facsimiles were dedicated to Count Gleichen, whom he terms his “Patron.” For
example, the Preface to Muir’s facsimile of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> is dedicated</p>
		<q>
To his serene highness, Prince Victor Hohenlohe-Langenburg, Count Gleichen &amp;c. Your Serene Highness and my
kind Patron . . . I have to thank your highness for the interest that you have been pleased to take in this
enterprise. Blake is preeminently an Artist’s artist. He has created for himself a realm of pure Imagination
in which he works alone, and his results are most stimulating to the imaginations of those who study them. I
am your Highness Humble servant, Wm Muir, Edmonton 1885.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">23</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">The book of Thel; the author &amp; printer
William Blake, 1789</hi> (The edition of the works of Blake prepared by the Blake Press at Edmonton; vol. 1)
(Edmonton, 1884).</note></q>
          <p>In a “Programme” attached to that same facsimile, he spells out the intentions behind his
edition:
<q>
My desire and intention is to reproduce ALL the important works by Wm Blake that exist in book form and also
some of his finest designs and this by methods of working as nearly the same as Blake himself used as the need
of maintaining fidelity to his results will allow. I will not use either photography or chromolithography. All
outlines are drawn and all the colouring is by hand. I produce fifty copies only of each book and each of them
is numbered.
</q></p>
          <p>The bookseller John Pearson, who sold the first of Muir’s facsimiles, retired from business in
1885.</p>
		<q>
Mr Pearson sold the first twelve copies [of the Songs of Innocence facsimile] between Jany and May 1885. Then
he retired from business “Because he had made £20,000 and was content” - He introduced me to Mr Bernard
Quaritch who continued the work. He received and sold the remaining 38 copies between May 1885 and August
1886. So completing the Edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Muir’s note in his master copy for the <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> facsimile, now in John Rylands Library, University of Manchester.</note></q>
          <p>The firm of Bernard Quaritch remained Muir’s agent for the Blake Press facsimiles for the next
50 years. Prices for Blake Press titles ranged from one guinea for the single sheets to 8 guineas for a
lengthy work such as <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">25</ref> Quaritch’s commission was the usual one-third of published price. 
<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Price list included in Muir’s facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> (Edmonton,
1890).</note></p>
          <figure n="quarryremains.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="354">
            <head>3. The remains of the quarry tramway at Tormor.</head>
            <figDesc>Iona is visible in the distance. (Photo: K. Davies.)</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Blake had printed his prophetic books from etched copper plates and the printed image was then
decorated in color. Muir had first to reverse this process. Working from an original lent him by Pearson or
Quaritch, he had to reconstruct the printed image that lay under the painted decoration. His careful outline
drawing was then transferred to a zinc plate.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">26</ref> The zinc plate in turn was used directly as a lithographic printing plate (as with the
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> facsimile) or etched in relief (for the facsimile of <hi rend="i">There
is No Natural Religion</hi>) or even etched in intaglio (for the <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi>).
Multiple copies of each page of these outlines would then be printed in ink matching as closely as possible
the ink of the original. One of these printed copies would serve as the basis for a fully hand-colored copy
made after the original; this was Muir’s master copy from which his assistants would work. (“Fidelity . .
. is obtained by each of my friends working on every copy, thereby obliterating each other’s
mannerisms.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">26</hi> A discussion of the various processes available for the lithographic
printing of facsimiles can be found in Michael Twyman, <hi rend="i">Early Lithographed Books</hi> (London:
Farrand P, 1990). The period covered precedes Muir, of course, but indicates the technical possibilities
available to the capable amateur.</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Prospectus bound with Muir’s master copy for the <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> facsimile. See n24 above.</note></p>
          <p>Muir was in full-time employment as “granite agent” until at least 1902. I
<pb id="p27-17" n="17"/>
assume that he and his friends gathered together on just one or two evenings each week to work on the
facsimiles. I interpret the evidence of the letters as implying that just a sufficient number of copies of
each title were hand-colored to keep ahead of demand, and that Muir had printed monochrome outlines in excess
of the stated limitation to allow for any wastage in the coloring process.</p>
          <p>Some modification of his methods was required in later years when he had fewer collaborators or
did not have an original at hand. Each copy then took some six or eight weeks to complete.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">28</ref> It is clear that production of the facsimiles
extended over a much longer period than their printed dates would indicate. A facsimile of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> was completed as late as 1929 despite bearing a publication date of 1887.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">29</ref> Muir’s increasing age and infirmity would
supply ample reason for the noticeable variation between copies. <note id="n67"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Muir’s
letter to Kerrison Preston, 28 July 1916.</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Muir’s letter to Quaritch, 17 Feb. 1936.</note></p>
          <p>Muir’s principal collaborators were his sister Hannah and Emily Druitt. Emily was the daughter
of Jabez Druitt, a monumental mason in East London, and presumably a granite trade connection. Emily was a
watercolorist of considerable accomplishment and shared Muir’s enthusiasm for Blake. In 1866 Muir married
her sister Sophia. After her marriage, Sophia too joined the Blake Press team.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>A. H. Mackmurdo<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">30</ref>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Accounts of Mackmurdo’s role in the development of English Art Nouveau
	  and the influence of Blake on the movement can be found in Stephan <corr type="emend">Tschudi-Madsen,</corr> <hi rend="i">Sources of Art
Nouveau</hi> (Oslo: H. Aschehoug, 1956); Nikolaus Pevsner, <hi rend="i">Studies in Art, Architecture and
Design.</hi> Vol. 2: <hi rend="i">Victorian and after</hi> (London: Thames &amp; Hudson, 1968) 134-35; Robert
Schmutzler, <hi rend="i">Art Nouveau</hi> (London: Thames &amp; Hudson, 1964) and in many subsequent
studies.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <p>During the 1880s a number of artists were exploring the possibilities of new expressive means in
the graphic arts—what would eventually be termed <hi rend="i">Art Nouveau.</hi> Designers such as A. H.
Mackmurdo tried to incorporate in their own work some of the vitality and expressiveness they found in
Blake.</p>
          <p>Mackmurdo and Herbert Horne (Mackmurdo’s pupil and later partner in his design firm, the
Century Guild) sought to spread their ideas by publishing a magazine which they called the 
<hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">31</ref> It reprinted texts by Blake and its illustrations included facsimiles of
<figure n="angelrow.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="322">
	<head>4. 9 Angel Row (home of the Blake Press) is the second house from the right.</head>
	<figDesc>(From a photograph in the Local History collection of Enfield Libraries and used by
permission.)</figDesc>
</figure>
Blake’s works prepared by Emery Walker &amp; Boutall. The volume for 1886 lists “the names of those
workers in art whose aim seems to us most nearly to accord with the chief aim of this magazine”; the names
include “Mr Muir, The Blake Press, Edmonton.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">31</hi> For studies of the <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> see
Lorraine Lively Hunt, <hi rend="i">The Century Guild Hobby Horse: A Study of a Magazine</hi> (University of
North Carolina doctoral thesis, 1965) and Peter Frost, “The Century Guild Hobby Horse and Its Founders”
<hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi> 27 (1978): 348-60.</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">32</hi> See for example <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> Jan. 1889
(unnumbered pages following page 40).</note></p>
          <p>That 1886 volume reproduced Blake’s broadsheet <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi> with an
article on Blake by Herbert H. Gilchrist.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">33</ref> Muir had assured purchasers that neither photography nor chromolithography would be
employed in his facsimiles.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">34</ref> He may
have breached this promise with his facsimile of Little Tom. Presumably this required a larger printing plate
than he could handle; he seems to have bought in a stock of prints from Walker &amp; Boutall and incorporated
the <hi rend="i">Hobby Horse</hi> reproduction into his Blake Press edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">35</ref> However, he eschewed making use of another 
<hi rend="i">Hobby</hi> Horse facsimile, the socalled “Sybilline leaf,” <hi rend="i">On Homers’ Poetry; On
Virgil</hi> and prepared his own outline for printing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75"
type="note">36</ref>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">33</hi> Herbert H. Gilchrist, “Nescio quae nugarum no. III: The Ballad of
Little Tom the Sailor,” <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> 1 (Oct. 1886): 159-60. The facsimile is
bound as frontispiece to this issue, facing page 121.</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">34</hi><hi rend="i"> Proposal for the publication of the Prophetic Books and the
Songs of Innocence and of Experience by W. Blake</hi> (London: J. Pearson, 1884).</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">35</hi> I have modified the interpretation given by Geoffrey Keynes, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 2nd. ed. (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1971) 105-10.</note>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">36</hi> Here I disagree with Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 335, 488,
836. Muir’s facsimile and that printed with Herbert R. Horne, “Blake’s Sibylline leaf on Homer and
Virgil” <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> 2 (1887): 115-16 differ in a number of respects and are
unlikely to derive from the same lithographic plate.</note></p>
          <p>Incidentally, Muir and Herbert Horne seem to have planned a working collaboration.
<figure n="victor.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="414">
	<head>5. Prince Victor of Hohenlohe-Langenburg, Count Gleichen. Muir’s “Patron.”</head>
	<figDesc>(Caricature published in <hi rend="i">Vanity Fair</hi> 5 July 1884. From a print in the possession
of Ted Ryan.)</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p27-18" n="18"/>
<figure n="sea.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="422">
	<head>6. To mark the start of his publishing career, on 1 April 1884, Muir issued this little jeu d’esprit:
“<hi rend="i">Ode to Sea-Sickness.</hi>”</head>
	<figDesc>It bears the address 42 Old Broad Street where D. D. Fenning, granite merchant and W. Muir, agent
occupied offices on the second floor. Reproduced by courtesy of the Trustees of the National Library of
Scotland.)</figDesc>
</figure>
A note in the <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> for 1886 stated: “During the new year, Mr Muir
hopes to publish engraved work from the designs of Mr Herbert P. Horne.” Nothing seems to have come of that
particular project.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">37</ref>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">37</hi> But among a collection of drawings by Christopher Whall in the William
Morris Gallery are single sheets from Muir’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1885) and 
<hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi> (1888) facsimiles, the former marked up to suggest Muir may also have planned
a collaboration with Whall.</note></p>
          <p>Mackmurdo’s circle included Mrs. Anne Gilchrist, widow of Blake’s biographer, herself a
writer and the English friend of Whitman. He was also acquainted with her son Herbert, the painter, and her
daughter Hannah. (When, in 1844, Mackmurdo organized the Enfield Art Exhibition, Hannah Gilchrist lent Blake
prints and drawings from the family collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">38</ref>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">38</hi> “Enfield Local Art Exhibition,” <hi rend="i">Meyer’s Observer and
Local and General Advertiser</hi> [Enfield], 14 June 1884: 6 and 7:
                            <p>“Miss H. Gilchrist’s loan collection included a singular work in oil colour
“The Descent to the Grave”, by Blake; engravings, “Southwark Fair”, and “The Distressed Poet”, (by
Hogarth) also an oil colour, “The Translation of Enoch”, by Blake; and a charcoal “Study”, by D.G.
Rossetti.”</p></note></p>
          <p>Mackmurdo’s collaborators included Selwyn Image, designer, lecturer on Blake, and later Slade
Professor of Art at Oxford; Christopher Whall, the stained glass designer (Whall was a great admirer of
Blake’s art); and of course, Herbert Horne, who wrote on Blake and his followers, and collected drawings by
Blake.</p>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Hobby Horse</hi> ran, in one form or another, for 10 years. “During this
period Mackmurdo himself was operating as a patron of the arts. He maintained a large house in Fitzroy Street
in which he accommodated most of the inner circle of the Century Guild as well other artistic strays . .
.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">39</ref> Herbert Horne had a room there,
as did the poet Lionel Johnson. Laurence Binyon and W. B. Yeats, both of whom would make important
contributions to Blake studies, were frequent visitors. <note id="n78"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Frost
348-60.</note></p>
          <p>It was into this milieu with its passionate interest in the art of Blake that Muir introduced the
facsimiles of the Blake Press. Muir’s facsimiles not only made Blake’s works in “Illuminated Printing”
accessible for the first time in reliable copies and helped establish Blake’s reputation as visual artist
alongside his reputation as poet, but I feel must also have contributed to the most advanced ideas in English
art of the 1880s. Mackmurdo and Horne helped create the artistic climate in which the Blake Press could
flourish. Muir through his Blake facsimiles provided a design resource on which the artists of the 1880s and
1890s could draw.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p27-19" n="19"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Iona Press<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">40</ref>
	<note id="n79"><hi rend="s">40</hi> This brief account of the Iona Press draws largely on Mairi MacArthur.
“Pages from Iona’s Past,” <hi rend="i">Scotsman Magazine</hi> (December 1987): 29.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <p>With the Blake Press underway, Muir began a second publishing venture: the Iona Press—producing
small lithographic editions of Gaelic poetry in the design of which the style of Blake’s prophetic books was
followed closely. Muir in Edmonton was proprietor, manager, editor; John Mac-Cormick (son of the quarry
foreman at Tormor) at Fionnphort initially worked the press and bound the booklets issued.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">41</ref> The designs in the “Iona Press”
publications were painted by girls on the island, under the instruction of Muir and Miss Flora Ritchie, whose
father was proprietor of the St. Columba Temperance Hotel on Iona. <note id="n80"><hi rend="s">41</hi> John
MacCormick (born 1860) is known as a Gaelic writer chiefly of plays and humorous sketches. The 
<hi rend="i">Scottish Gaelic Union Catalogue</hi> (Edinburgh: National Library of Scotland, 1984) lists 13 titles
by MacCormick published between 1908 and 1931.</note></p>
          <p>Between 1887 and 1893, around a dozen small booklets<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n81" type="note">42</ref> were produced on a lithographic press shipped from Edmonton and housed in a
bothy (now the Iona Bookshop) opposite the St. Columba Hotel. Muir and Mac Cormick stated that their aim was
to give tourists to Iona “an opportunity of carrying back with them literary as well as geological mementoes
of the sacred isle.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">43</ref>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">42</hi> Iona Press titles known to me are as follows:
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p>(i) The Blessing of the ship, 1887 - reprinted 1893</p></item>
	<item><p>(ii) Bas Fhraoich or The Death of Fraoch, 1887 (letterpress)</p></item>
	<item><p>(iii) Ossian’s Address to the sun, 1887</p></item>
	<item><p>(iv) The Burial march of King Duncan, 1888</p></item>
	<item><p>(v) A Highland New Year’s carol, 1888</p></item>
	<item><p>(vi) Prayer formerly used by all the children of Iona at school, 1888 - 2nd ed. 1893</p></item>
	<item><p>(vii) The Death of Fraoch, 1888</p></item>
	<item><p>(viii) The Great hymn “Altus” of St Columba, 1889</p></item>
	<item><p>(ix) Iona, by the Marquis of Lorne, 1889</p></item>
	<item><p>(x) Views from an artist’s sketchbook [by Elizabeth McHardy], 1889</p></item>
	<item><p>(xi) The Life of St Columba, by William Muir, 1889 (letterpress)</p></item>
	<item><p>(xii) Iona autograph album, 1891</p></item>
	<item><p>(xiii) The Great hymn “Altus” of St Columba, 1897 (new edition)</p></item>
	<item><p>(xiv) Map of Iona, n.d.</p></item>
	<item><p>(xv) Sailm cvii, 30, n.d. (single sheet)</p></item>
</list></note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">43</hi> Prospectus of the Iona Press. Quoted in E. Mairi MacArthur 
<hi rend="i">Iona: The Living Memory of a Crofting Community</hi> (Edinburgh: Edinburgh UP, 1990).</note></p>
          <p>A travel book of the time carries the following account of the press:
<q>
A special feature of Iona is its printing press, which was commenced in 1887 by Mr William Muir, Mr John
M’Cormick, Miss Muir, and Miss Ritchie, and stands within a few hundred yards of Reilig Odhrain and the
Cathedral. The Iona Press is quite a unique and interesting little establishment, superintended personally by
Miss Muir, a clever, active, intelligent maiden lady, assisted by a tall, handsome, dark-eyed, native damsel
hardly out of her teens, whom I have seen with her well-formed arms working hard at the press.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">44</ref>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">44</hi> Malcolm Ferguson, <hi rend="i">A Visit to Staffa and Iona.</hi> (Dundee
and Edinburgh, 1894).</note></q></p>
          <p>By the end of the century, production of the books had ceased, although postcards were printed
under the name of the Press and sold in a souvenir shop run until the 1920s by Hannah Muir.</p>
          <figure n="march.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="408">
            <head>7. <hi rend="i">The Burial March of King Duncan</hi> (Iona Press, 1888).</head>
            <figDesc>Outline before hand-coloring. (Reproduced by courtesy of the Trustees of the National
Library of Scotland.)</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Inventor</title>
          </head>
          <p>If the 1880s had been the decade of Muir’s activity as publisher, the following decade found
him devoting a lot of his energies to chemical experiment. In 1892 he was granted a patent for a process for
extracting tin from slag.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">45</ref> And then
in 1902 a patent described as “Improvements in or relating to Igniting Material for Matches, Cartridge Fuses
and the like.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">46</ref> The patent
describes how matches may be made using the red allotropic from in place of the highly dangerous white
phosphorus. He sold his rights in the patent for £900 to R. Bell &amp; Co., who had a match factory at
Bromley by Bow.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">47</ref>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">45</hi> UK Patent No. 1907 (1892) “Extracting tin &amp;c from slag.”</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">46</hi> UK Patent No. 11,503 (1902) “Matches &amp;c.”</note>
	<note id="n86"><hi rend="s">47</hi> “Death of notable Kilmarnock man” <hi rend="i">Kilmarnock
Standard</hi>, 15 January 1938.</note></p>
          <p>In 1901, Muir and his wife had left Angel Place and had moved to 97 Church Street,
Edmonton.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">48</ref> In October of that year he
issued a short religious tract: <hi rend="i">The Greatest of All Visions</hi>—a brief commentary on some
verses from the Apocalypse of St. John.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88"
type="note">49</ref> Like
<pb id="p27-20" n="20"/>
the Iona Press titles it consists of the lithographic reproduction of a handwritten text. Though with the
printingpress now with his sister on Iona, he had to make use of a commercial lithographer. One hundred copies
were printed. <note id="n87"><hi rend="s">48</hi> Kelly’s <hi rend="i">Enfield, Edmonton &amp; Winchmore
Hill directory</hi> and <hi rend="i">Kelly’s Tottenham &amp; Edmonton directory</hi> 1893-1909.</note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">49</hi> William Muir, <hi rend="i">The greatest of all visions, being the text of
part of The Book of Revelation C4 V1 to C6 V2, with a commentary interpreting it</hi> (Edmonton, 1901) Copy:
Mitchell Library Glasgow pressmark A217141.</note></p>
          <p>In 1907 the Muirs moved again—to 153 Church Street, Edmonton. And again in 1908 to Claremont,
Bury Street; always to surprisingly large houses considering there was just himself, Sophia, and a servant. He
and his wife would move four times in 10 years. I imagine his neighbors complained about the chemical
experiments.</p>
          <p>Finally, in 1912, and after 30 years in Edmonton, the Muirs moved for the last time, to Romford
Road, Forest Gate, from where all the letters that follow were written.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Blake Society<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">50</ref>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">50</hi> Some documents of the Blake Society survive in the Thomas Wright
collection in Buckinghamshire County Record Office.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <p>The inaugural meeting of the Blake Society took place in 1912. Muir, along with Mrs. Muir, and
his sister-in-law, Emily Druitt, were active members. In 1917 he gave a paper to the society on an
appropriately Scottish theme: “Blake’s view of Wallace.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n90" type="note">51</ref>
	<note id="n90"><hi rend="s">51</hi> The reference is presubably to Blake’s Visionary Heads of “Edward I,
and William Wallace” (two on one sheet) formerly in John Linnell’s collection, and now in the collection
of Robert N. Essick.</note></p>
          <p>In April 1920 the annual meeting of the Blake Society was held at the Hampstead home of Thomas J.
Wise. Muir was chairman at that meeting. In 1920, his host, Wise, was at the height of his reputation as
bibliographer, collector and scholar. Many years later, Wise was to be exposed as a forger and a
thief.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">52</ref> It is tempting to speculate
if Wise or his accomplice Harry Buxton Forman had a hand in any Blake forgeries. 
<note id="n91"><hi rend="s">52</hi> The most recent account of their criminal careers is John Collins, <hi rend="i">The Two
Forgers: A Biography of Harry Buxton Forman &amp; Thomas James Wise</hi> (Aldershot: Scolar P,
1992).</note></p>
          <p>In 1920, Muir produced a new facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> (32 copies
completed), and in 1927 (the centenary of Blake’s death), new facsimiles of the <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi> (100 copies planned; 55 completed). In 1928 he began work on a new 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (50 copies planned; 11 completed).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92" type="note">53</ref> His collaborators in these last facsimiles included
Frederick Hollyer, the portrait photographer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93"
type="note">54</ref> Forty years
<figure n="iona.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="670" height="905">
	<head>8. The Iona Press printing house.</head>
	<figDesc>Today the building has been refurbished by the proprietors of the St. Columba Hotel as a second-hand
bookshop. (Photo: K. Davies.)</figDesc>
</figure>
earlier, Hollyer like Muir had been listed in the <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> among “the
names of those workers in art whose aim seems to us most nearly to accord with the chief aim of this
magazine.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94" type="note">55</ref>
	<note id="n92"><hi rend="s">53</hi> Numbers planned derive from a letter “To the Reviewer” [1928?] once
inserted in Muir’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (2nd ed.) and now in the collection
of Raymond Lister. Numbers completed derive from Muir’s letter to Quaritch, 17 Feb. 1936.</note>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">54</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 489.</note>
	<note id="n94"><hi rend="s">55</hi> See n32 above.</note></p>
          <p>Thomas Wright summed up Muir’s career in his <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>:
<q>
Numerous and important have been the services to Blake students rendered by Mr William Muir. It was in 1884
that he began his admirable series of reproductions of Blake’s books. Copies of the British Museum 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, the Flaxman <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, and the Beckford <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> done by him then, now command prices comparable with those paid sixty years ago for the
original Blakes. The <hi rend="i">Milton, Europe, America, Marriage of Heaven and Hell, Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi>, and all the others have maintained the high standard of the enterprise, and the
Beaconsfield <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> now being executed
show no falling off in love and fidelity. For any one to find himself in Mr Muir’s company, and to hear him
talk about Blake, is a liberal education.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95"
type="note">56</ref>
	<note id="n95"><hi rend="s">56</hi> Thomas Wright, <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi> (Olney, Bucks:
T. Wright, 1929).</note></q></p>
          <p>Not until 1935, when he was 90 years old, did failing eyesight cause him to give up work on Blake
facsimiles. It may have been at this time that he disposed of the master copies of four of his facsimiles to
the John Rylands Library, Manchester.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96"
type="note">57</ref> The lithographed outlines have been colored with great care and occasional marginal
drawings of details have been added as a help to Muir’s assistants. <note id="n96"><hi rend="s">57</hi><hi
rend="i"> America</hi> (1887), <hi rend="i">The Marriage of heaven and hell</hi> (1885), <hi rend="i">The
Songs of Innocence</hi> (1885), and <hi rend="i">The Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1885) were
accessioned in September 1939 but are likely to have been in the possession of the Library for some time
before then. (Personal communication from David W. Riley, Keeper of Printed books, John Rylands University
Library of Manchester, 17 October 1990.)</note></p>
          <p>William Muir died on 2 January 1938, aged 92. He is buried alongside his in-laws in the City and
East London Cemetery. Sophia survived her husband another five years. She died on 30 January 1943 at Helston
in Cornwall, at the home of her niece Winifred Catling.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97"
type="note">58</ref>
	<note id="n97"><hi rend="s">58</hi> Probate register (England and Wales) 1943.</note></p>
          <p>Muir long outlived the Victorian world in which he grew up; he seems to us today very typical of
that world—typical in his enthusiasm, his energy, his confidence and his piety. But let Kerrison Preston
have the last word
<q>
. . . there was a remarkable refinement about him, such as I imagine one might have noticed about Blake
himself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98" type="note">59</ref>
	<note id="n98"><hi rend="s">59</hi> Kerrison Preston, letter to Raymond Lister 25 Aug. 1961.</note></q></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Letters to Kerrison Preston</title>
          </head>
          <p>The collector Kerrison Preston was born in 1884 and practiced as a solicitor in Bournemouth from
1909 to 1949. Until October 1953 he lived at St. Julian’s, 22 Knyveton Road, Bournemouth, and then moved to
The Georgian House, Rockshaw Road, Merstham, Surrey. He issued a catalogue of his collection in 1960.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99" type="note">60</ref> In 1967, Preston donated his collection of
books by and concerning Blake to Westminster City Libraries. He died in 1974 and his papers, including five
letters from Muir, were deposited in Westminster City Archives.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n100" type="note">61</ref>
	<note id="n99"><hi rend="s">60</hi> Kerrison Preston, <hi rend="i">Notes for a catalogue of the Blake Library
at The Georgian House Merstham</hi> (Cambridge: Golden Head P, 1960).</note>
	<note id="n100"><hi rend="s">61</hi> Westm. Accession 924: Papers of I. Kerrison Preston, donated by his
daughter Mrs. Angela Alabaster, and his son David C. Preston, 1 April 1977.</note></p>
          <p>These letters, with the letters to Quaritch edited by Bentley, both groups dating form the last
20 years of Muir’s life, yield considerable insight into the productions of the Blake Press and clarify a
number of features of the facsimiles commented on by previous writers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n101" type="note">62</ref> But Muir’s letters are not just a business correspondence; they record
the growth of a friendship that Preston was to value highly. <note id="n101"><hi rend="s">62</hi> Recent
papers that make reference to Muir are:
                            <p>Morton D. Paley, “A Victorian Blake Facsimile” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 15
(1981): 27. (Paley illustrates the first page of Muir’s prospectus for the <hi rend="i">Song of
Los.</hi>)</p>
	<p>Robert N. Essick, “<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience:</hi>
Manchester, England: Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19 (1985): 39.</p>
	<p>Raymond Lister, “William Muir” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 20 (1986): 49. (Reprints a letter about Muir
from Kerrison Preston.)</p></note></p>
		<q>
. . . I mention certain vitalising experiences of friendship which have brought me into closer contact with
Blake.
</q>
          <pb id="p27-21" n="21"/>
          <p>Thirty years ago Graham Robertson introduced me to his Bogey Room containing the most stupendous
Blake pictures, and I have never been the same since. He let me slowly browse upon these and the rest of his
wonderful Blake collection in London and the country, and I gained a whole new world of thought and feeling .
. .</p>
          <p>Many years after and many miles away, I spent a memorable afternoon at the charming home in
America of Mr Robertson’s friend Mrs William Emerson, who showed me the famous <hi rend="i">Rossetti
Manuscript</hi>, that well-filled note-book of writings and designs used by Blake himself for thirty years,
revealing him intimately at work. The Nonesuch Press has done well in issuing a photographic copy of the
complete book, but it does not quite convey the thrill of the original pages with the very writing of Blake
and Rossetti together.</p>
          <p>In the meantime the late William Muir, who was in many ways a Blake-like character himself, had
lent me some of his facsimiles to copy, and I had followed the excellent example of both Blake and Rossetti
and got my wife to colour them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n102" type="note">63</ref>
These brought home to me the necessity for studying Blake’s words in their original form of decorated pages,
in which the meaning is often suggested by the little pictures no less than by language.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103" type="note">64</ref>
	<note id="n102"><hi rend="s">63</hi> The Preston Blake Library in Westminster City Libraries contains a
number of Muir’s facsimiles, including a copy of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> handcolored by Mrs. A. E.
Preston.</note>
	<note id="n103"><hi rend="s">64</hi> Kerrison Preston, <hi rend="i">Blake and Rossetti</hi> (London: A.
Moring, (1944) 5.</note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>-Letter 1<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104" type="note">65</ref> -
<note id="n104"><hi rend="s">65</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., points out that although Muir states in this letter
that he has “two copies of the ‘Heaven &amp; Hell’ and two or three of the ‘Ancient of Days,’” he
in fact sold <hi rend="i">three</hi> copies of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (nos. 48-50 on 9 Nov. 1916 and
23 Feb., 16 July 1917, and sold <hi rend="i">four</hi> copies of the <hi rend="i">Ancient of Days</hi> (which
he calls the “Act of Creation”) on 4 June 1917, 1 Apr., 27 June, 14 Aug. 1918 (nos. 47-50). The copy of
<hi rend="i">America</hi> “specially coloured from an original now in U.S.A.” imitates copy B, which has
been in the Pierpont Morgan Library in New York since 1909. The copy of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> “coloured
from the BM copy” imitates copy D. The British Museum copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> which he
copied is probably copy T. (Personal communication from G. E. Bentley, Jr., 18 May 1992.)</note>
	</title>
            </head>
            <p>538 Romford Road</p>
            <p>Forest Gate, London E</p>
            <p>18 July 1916</p>
            <p>K. Preston Esq.</p>
            <p>Dear Sir</p>
            <p>In reply to your favour of yesterday’s date, on Fly leaf please find a list of my Blake
facsimiles —Those marked x are all sold. I still have two copies of the “Heaven &amp; Hell”, two or
three of the “Ancient of Days” and a few of the others not marked x. —A copy of those all sold can
occasionally be got from Mr Quaritch for he buys up any that come into the market as libraries containing them
are sold.</p>
            <p>Soliciting your commands I am</p>
            <p>Yours faithfully</p>
            <p>W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Muir</p>
            <table rows="16" cols="2">
              <row>
                <cell>x Songs of Innocence &amp; of Experience</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>x Book of Thel</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>x Visions of the Daughters of Albion</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>x Urizen</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>x The Song of Los</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>x Little Tom the Sailor</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Marriage of Heaven &amp; Hell</cell>
                <cell>£3. 3. 0.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Milton</cell>
                <cell>10. 0. 0.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>There is no Natural Religion</cell>
                <cell>1. 1. 0.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>The Ancient of Days—a single plate.</cell>
                <cell>1. 1. 0.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Blake’s favourite work.</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>America a Prophecy</cell>
                <cell>4. 4. 0.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Do specially coloured from an original now in U.S.A.—very effective</cell>
                <cell>5. 5. 0</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Europe coloured from the BM copy</cell>
                <cell>5. 5. 0.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>x The Gates of Paradise copper plate not coloured</cell>
                <cell>3. 3. 0.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>In addition to these I have <hi rend="i">one copy</hi> of the Songs of Experience
coloured from the Brit Mus copy.</cell>
                <cell>£5. 5. 0.</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <figure n="columba.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="383">
              <head>9. <hi rend="i">The Life of St Columba</hi> written by Muir, is his only extended work and
his only book conventionally set in type.</head>
              <figDesc>His collaborator the Rev. J. C. Rendell had been curate at St James’ Edmonton in 1884
when Muir was sidesman there. (Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British Library.)</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p27-22" n="22"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>- Letter 2 -</title>
            </head>
            <p>538 Romford Road Forest Gate</p>
            <p>London E</p>
            <p>28 July 1916</p>
            <p>Dear Sir</p>
            <p>I duly received your card of 23<hi rend="s">rd</hi> I fear that Mr Quaritch cannot sell you any
of my out of print facsimiles of Blake’s works cheap, for they usually fetch higher prices now than I got
for them — I saw one set on sale (and sold) at £110. —But—If <hi rend="i">uncoloured</hi> copies answer
your purpose I could let you have “Milton”, “America” &amp; “Europe” for 10/- each. —I have
never before known uncoloured copies be asked for but no doubt the text is the feature that interests you.</p>
            <p>Each copy takes six or eight weeks to colour.—Milton takes longer.—Hence the high
price.</p>
            <p>Yours faithfully</p>
            <p>W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Muir</p>
            <figure n="dream.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="328">
              <head>10. <hi rend="i">A Dream</hi> from the master copy of Muir’s facsimile of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Outlines printed by lithography with hand-coloring. A slip bearing a hand-drawn detail
has been pasted to the page. (Reproduced by courtesy of the Director and University Librarian, the John
Rylands Library of Manchester.)</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>- Letter 3 -</title>
            </head>
            <p>538 Romford Road Forest Gate</p>
            <p>London</p>
            <p>14 Augt 1916</p>
            <p>K. Preston Esq.</p>
            <p>Dear Sir</p>
            <p>With this I have posted per registered parcel post your uncoloured copy of Milton and your copy
N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 37 of “No Nat Relig”.</p>
            <p>The parcel should arrive two or three posts after this letter.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Re the Milton.</hi> Please do not blame me for the <hi rend="i">very</hi> rude
engraving of one or two of the illustrations. They are so in the original. —One, in especial, is positively
ugly—I suspect that it was engraved by <hi rend="i">M<hi rend="s">rs</hi></hi> Blake—as rich colouring
makes them look quite different.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Re No Nat Relig.</hi> No <hi rend="i">complete</hi> copy of this book (or books)
exists This is made up from three copies, all imperfect, and still one plate is lacking as you will see.
Assuring you that the colouring (slight as it is) is faithful to Blake and hoping that you will be pleased I
am</p>
            <p>Yours faithfully</p>
            <p>W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Muir</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>- Letter 4 -</title>
            </head>
            <p>538 Romford Road Forest Gate</p>
            <p>London E</p>
            <p>23 August 1916</p>
            <p>My dear Sir</p>
            <p>I thank you for your kind letter of 16<hi rend="s">th</hi> and am glad that the No Nat. Relig.
&amp; the Milton please you — but I am sorry that your Milton is not coloured.</p>
            <p>It occurs to me that you may possibly be an Artist, or at least have some skill in water colour
work.</p>
            <p>If so I would be very willing to <hi rend="i">lend</hi> you a coloured Milton free (no payment)
for a month or two and in that time you could colour your own copy yourself —The meticulous accuracy that I
habitually use is not necessary (would not be necessary) in your case.</p>
            <p>You can easily get the general effect, if you, or any one of your household, can use colours at
all.</p>
            <p>Yours very truly</p>
            <p>W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Muir</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>- Letter 5 -</title>
            </head>
            <p>538 Romford Rd London E7</p>
            <p>23 Jany 1922</p>
            <p>Dear Mr Kerrison Preston</p>
            <p>How stupid of me! It is entirely my fault! I had kept no record, and somehow had got it into my
mind that Jany <hi rend="i">15</hi><hi rend="s">th</hi> had been arranged—Of course complete your copy —Do
not on any account return the book till that is done. —It will suit me quite well if I have the book back by
February 28<hi rend="s">th</hi> <hi rend="i">if you have finished by that time.</hi> — Do not distress your
self or your good wife. make your copy a good one, take time, and don’t let her neglect the children for the
book.</p>
            <p>If not finished by Feby 28<hi rend="s">th</hi> let me have a postcard saying so and that will
be all right.</p>
            <p>Thanks for your kind and interesting letter. So your wife has had the prevalent influenza? I
have had it also but am quite better.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Traberne</hi> Thanks for your remark — I will alter the 1647 to 1674 — as it
should be as he was born about 1636</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Garth Wilkinson</hi>’s “poems”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n105" type="note">66</ref> are more curious than beautiful but he hits on a good thing by accident
occasionally. I think the little poem “A Landscape” is a <hi rend="i">gem.</hi> Rossetti was interested in
the “poems” because they were written in much the same way as Blake wrote his “Prophetic books” —
putting the words down just as they came to mind — Garth Wilkinson’s book is <hi rend="i">very</hi>
scarce. I don’t suppose six copies are known — I <hi rend="i">know</hi> only two, the B. M. copy
<pb id="p27-23" n="23"/>
and my own, which I got on a costermonger’s barrow for 4<hi rend="s">d</hi>—[(in margin) its real worth as
<hi rend="i">literature</hi>] that was why I copied some onto blank pages in my Blake. 
<note id="n105"><hi rend="s">66</hi> J. J. Garth Wilkinson, <hi rend="i">Improvisations from the Spirit</hi> (London and
Manchester, 1857). The <hi rend="i">National Union Catalogue</hi> lists six copies.</note></p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Quaritch’s</hi> announcements of 1888 interest you. I do not remember them, but
I note your remarks. Most, perhaps all, have (no doubt) gone to the U.S.A.</p>
            <p>The only facsimiles we have now for sale would not interest you—when you are in London some
time you can see them if you can find time to call, letting us know the day before.</p>
            <p>I am so glad you like the Bournemouth Guide<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n106" type="note">67</ref> — I got it on a costermonger’s barrow for 2<hi rend="s">d</hi>, which
was <hi rend="i">less</hi> than its value as literature — Notice the account in the medical appendix of the
“Brocken Spectre” seen near <hi rend="i">Edinburgh.</hi>
	<note id="n106"><hi rend="s">67</hi> John Sydenham (publisher), <hi rend="i">The visitor’s guide to
Bournemouth and its neighbourhood . . . 2nd ed. containing additions and corrections with an appendix by
Thomas Johnstone Aitkin</hi> (Poole and Bournemouth, 1842). Aitkin’s appendix (“A dissertation on the
climate of the district of Bournemouth and its adaptation to health”) takes up pages 53 to 152 of this work.
His account of the optical phenomenon here called the “Demon of the Brocken” is on pages 121-23 of the
Appendix.</note></p>
            <p>I thought the proper place for the book was in the hands of a Bournemouth man and I am glad you
value it.</p>
            <p>You wonder what you could give to me! I will tell you what I would like very much. If it would
not be too much trouble a copy <hi rend="i">tinted</hi> perhaps (ain’t I greedy!) tinted perhaps— a
copy— not a facsimile but just a freehand copy of the View of Bournemouth that is at the beginning of the
Guide would be very welcome<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p23u1" type="note">*</ref> It may
not be elaborately faithful, but just something giving the general effect. I would frame it and hang it in
this room where I am writing.— Now please don’t worry over this if it is not convenient, but if as I
suppose you or your wife <hi rend="i">do</hi> sketch occasionally it will not come very difficult. If you 
<hi rend="i">don’t</hi> sketch then please don’t attempt it.
	<note id="p23u1">It might be a little bigger than the engraving— say the size of this paper 7″ × 9″ or
so.</note></p>
            <p>With our united kind regards to you both I am</p>
            <p>Yours very Truly</p>
            <p>W<hi rend="s">m</hi>Muir</p>
            <p>My account of Muir’s life had its origin in an invitation from the Edmonton Hundred
Historical Society to speak on “William Muir and the Blake Press at Edmonton” in February 1991. I am
grateful to the Society and to Mr. D. O. Pam, its chairman, for encouraging me to put my haphazard notes on
Muir into a semblance of order. Mrs. Angela Alabaster kindly granted permission to publish her father’s
letters from Muir. I should also acknowledge here Raymond Lister’s role (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, fall 1986)
in suggesting that Muir’s letters may have survived amongst the Kerrison Preston papers. My particular
thanks are due to Dr. E. Mairi MacArthur for her help in locating references to Muir in Scottish newspapers,
and for sharing her unrivalled knowledge
<figure n="shepherd.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="455">
	<head>11. <hi rend="i">The Shepherd</hi> from the master copy of Muir’s facsimile of <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>A drawing of an enlarged detail has been tipped in, presumably as a guide for Muir’s assistants.
(Reproduced by courtesy of the Director and University Librarian, the John Rylands Library of
Manchester.)</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p27-24" n="24"/>
of Iona history. Ted Ryan was generous with assistance and advice. My brother Geoff gave successive drafts a
close and critical reading. I gratefully acknowledge the help received from G. E. Bentley, Jr., who allowed me
to see his essay on Muir, coincidentally written at the same time as my own, and to improve mine on the basis
of his.</p>
            <figure n="grave.27.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="368">
              <figTranscr>IN LOVING REMEMBRANCE OF<lb/>
				SOPHIA.<lb/>
				BELOVED AND DEVOTED WIFE OF<lb/>
				JABEZ DRUITT.<lb/>
				WHO DIED 10TH JULY 1888,<lb/>
				AGED 64 YEARS.<lb/>
				ALSO THE ABOVE-NAMED<lb/>
				JABEZ DRUITT,<lb/>
				WHO DIED 18TH MAY 1900,<lb/>
				AGED 75 YEARS.<lb/>
				ALSO WILLIAM MUIR,<lb/>
				SON-IN-LAW OF THE ABOVE<lb/>
				AND BELOVED HUSBAND OF<lb/>
				SOPHIA ELIZABETH DRUITT,<lb/>
				WHO DIED 2 JANUARY 1938,<lb/>
				AGED 92 YEARS.</figTranscr>
              <head>12. William Muir is buried alongside his in-laws in the City and East London Cemetery.</head>
              <figDesc>(Photo: K. Davies.)</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p27-25" n="25" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
