<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.2.mandell</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Rehistoricizing Romantic Ideology: New Perspectives on Class and Gender Conflict, 1730-1800;
Henry Abelove, The Evangelist of Desire: John Wesley and the Methodists;
Donna Landry, The Muses of Resistance: Laboring-Class Women’s Poetry in Britain, 1739-1796</title>
        <author n="Mandell">Laura Mandell</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1993</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
      <pb id="p27-46" n="46"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main" rend="main">Rehistoricizing Romantic Ideology: New Perspectives on Class and Gender
Conflict, 1730-1800</title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title type="main">Henry Abelove, <hi rend="i">The Evangelist of Desire: John Wesley and the
Methodists.</hi> Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1990. 136 pp. $25.00; Donna Landry, <hi rend="i">The
Muses of Resistance: Laboring-Class Women’s Poetry in Britain, 1739-1796.</hi> New York: Cambridge
University Press, 1990. 325 pp. $39.50.</title>
            </head>
            <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Laura <name>Mandell</name></docAuthor></byline>
            <p>Henry Abelove’s <hi rend="i">Evangelist of Desire</hi> and Donna Landry’s 
<hi rend="i">Muses of Resistance</hi> both contribute substantially to the fields of history with which they are
concerned.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n46">Without implying that they agree with the thoughts presented here, I would like to thank
Michael Fischer, <corr type="emend">Shalini Puri,</corr> Walter Cohen, and the editors of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> for much material and
intellectual support.</note> Abelove enters into debates over why John Wesley had such an enormous influence
among English plebeians during the eighteenth century; how Wesley contributed to the rise and spread of
Methodism; and, specifically, how the construction of Wesley as a leader of the movement, a construction in
which his brother Charles, George Whitefield, and other Methodists participated, ensured the movement’s
staying power even after “the revivalist wave ebbed” in Britain and America during the 1750s (5). Landry
adds to the history of feminism by bringing to
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
light poems protesting the oppression of women which were written by laboring-class female poets living before
“the advent of the organized women’s movements of the nineteenth century” (15), before feminism as we
know it. Landry analyzes works written from the 1740s to the late 1790s, and thereby contributes substantially
to the history of “protofeminism,” the title often given to protests against sexism appearing before Mary
Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> (1792).</p>
            <p>But, more important than these specific contributions to history, Abelove and Landry also have
a great deal to say about how to do a specifically <hi rend="i">literary</hi> history. The women of the
laboring classes whose works Landry analyzes wrote pastoral poetry; they therefore tried to enter a tradition
that excludes male and female labor from view (see Williams, <hi rend="i">Country</hi> 32). Landry explicitly
addresses the difficulty these women had in entering such a tradition. Similarly, Abelove analyzes the diaries
and journals of plebeian Methodists, marginal writers to be sure, recounting their own spiritual biographies.
Unlike Landry, he does not explicitly address the problem of these accounts’ relation to literature.
However, I will show below that writing on the history of early Methodism means confronting the problem that a
literary historian must confront, namely whether and how desires subversive of the existing social order can
be represented in conventional forms. Insofar as both Landry and Abelove try to determine the extent to which
merely entering conventional literary and religious discourses requires adopting classist and sexist
interests, they enter into debates carried on both here in the pages of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> and in
romantic studies generally.</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology</hi> of 1983, Jerome McGann argued for using the
methodology of what has come to be called American new historicism. McGann states the problem of literary
criticism, and how to resolve that problem by turning toward history, in a passage worth quoting at length:
<q>
The example of Abrams helps us to see another characteristic of scholarly treatments of Romanticism: that the
scholarship is everywhere informed by ideological commitments of various kinds. . . . The presence of ideology
in criticism is particularly difficult to see because the chief disciplines of cultural analysis are
themselves vehicles for the production of ideology. . . . The reader [of criticism] must therefore be on his
guard to demystify such works of their ideological self-representations if he is to be in a position to assess
the adequacy of their assertions. . . . [I have demonstrated] the interested,
<pb id="p27-47" n="47"/>
partisan focus which critical argumentation will take. . . . [C]riticism . . . will vitiate its own activity
to the extent that it has not shown a clear understanding of the symmetries and differences which hold between
the critics’ values on the one hand, and the (historically removed) subject on the other. . . . We may take
it as a rule, then, that any criticism which abolishes the distance between its own (present) setting and its
(removed) subject matter—any criticism which argues an unhistorical symmetry between the practicing critic
and the descending work—will be, to that extent, undermined as criticism. (28-30)
</q>
The question is, how do we read literature written in the past in its own terms rather than forcing it to
comply with our own? How do we read literature, not merely as an image of ourselves, reflecting our own
ideological blindnesses back to us, but rather as distinctively Other or symbolically self-constituting,
revealing its own ideological resistances and complicities rather than ours?</p>
            <p>One answer which differs from McGann’s is that we cannot. For some post-structuralists, the
“Other” names the set of exclusions necessary for symbolization to take place, and therefore the Other by
definition cannot speak to us (see Fuss 12). That kind of post-structuralist assumption suspiciously shifts
responsibility for exclusions based on class, race, and gender from individuals to institutional structures,
or worse, to language itself. S. P. Mohanty argues against the theoretical validity and practical efficacy of
such a shift in responsibility: if we are to avoid “replicat[ing] the patterns of repression and subjugation
we notice in [our] traditional conceptual frameworks,” we must, he argues, assume that the Other 
<hi rend="i">can be</hi> symbolically self-constituting (4). As McGann says in this passage, the answer to the
problem of how to avoid projecting our own beliefs onto past Others begins at least with the acknowledgment
that we bear responsibility for erasing the interests of people writing in the past by confusing what they say
with our own particular concerns. Returning to history is one way, McGann argues here, to stop projecting
ourselves onto the past. A large part of recent romantic criticism has been stimulated by the demand made by
McGann and others like him that literary criticism become literary history and, by distinguishing past
writers’ interests from ours, try to make explicit “the ideological polemic of criticism” (McGann
30).</p>
            <p>However, for some prominent romanticists who claim to follow McGann’s lead, focusing on this
polemic has not worked. It has not worked to give critics “a clear understanding of the symmetries and
differences which hold between the critics’ values on the one hand, and the (historically removed) subject
on the other.” Even Marjorie Levinson, a prominent member of McGann’s critical school, charges the new
historicism with containing “the positivism, subjectivism, and relativism of the rejected [old] historicist
methodology” (<hi rend="i">Rethinking Historicism</hi> 20). Nor has focusing on “the ideological polemic
of criticism” worked to turn critics toward history. “[L]et us above all refuse the consolation of a
‘return’ to history,” David Simpson said in 1988, “and ponder instead all the reasons why we have not
yet been there” (“Literary Criticism” 747).</p>
            <p>Why hasn’t McGann’s program worked? One error frequently made by new historicist critics
consists in assuming that it is inherently historical to ask questions about an author’s attitude toward
class, race, sexuality, or gender. It is not; one must question an author’s attitude in historically
responsible ways. For example, Wordsworth is often attacked for universalizing. To universalize 
<hi rend="i">now</hi>, to claim that a street person’s spirit is just like mine, would be to deny that economic
conditions constitute possibilities of subjectivity. However, universalizing in the 1790s had an entirely
different political valence than does universalizing now. In 1792, the London Corresponding Society debated
for five nights over whether “we who are Tradesmen, Shopkeepers and mechanics [have] any right to seek to
obtain a parliamentary reform” giving them the right to vote (qtd. in Goodwin 193). Universalizing 
<hi rend="i">then</hi>, saying that a beggar is no different from a member of the ruling class 
<hi rend="i">then</hi>, would be to take up the radical position advocating electoral reform. There is no
“timeless conservatism,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">1</ref> and the
terms in which people debate issues of race, class, and gender change throughout time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I am indebted to Michael Fischer for this phrase.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">2</hi> On McGann’s misuse of the term “radical,” and his subsequent
misconception of the kind of radical Keats could have been, silenced or not, see Fry 211-14.</note></p>
            <p>One way to elicit a past writer’s interests is to use historically responsive terms. As to
the terms “laboring-class” and “plebeian,” Landry specifies her usage:
<q>
[F]or ‘laboring class,’ read workers in an agrarian economy; for ‘the poor,’ a need on the part of
contemporaries to signify a certain pathos within socio-economic hierarchies; for ‘plebeian,’ the mainly
cultural opposition to ‘patrician’ or ‘polite.’ (9)
</q>
There is a difference between Abelove and Landry here. Abelove uses the term “plebeians” in order to avoid
anachronistically projecting class consciousness onto the eighteenth-century working poor (see Thompson,
“Class Struggle” 145, 146-150, 151). Landry, relying on the work of R. S. Neale and David Levine, would
like to argue for the existence of some kind of class consciousness before industrialization (Landry 23-24,
56). But, more important than monitoring their own terms in order to avoid uncritically projecting our time
onto the past, Landry and Abelove try to recreate the conflicts surrounding class and gender at that time.</p>
            <p>The two books under review here change—drastically, as I hope to show—the meaning of
certain terms and rhetorical structures used by Blake and Wordsworth because they give us knowledge of
contemporaneous debates on class and gender issues. Landry and Abelove analyze two specific kinds of
laboring-class or plebeian discourse, the highly conventionalized poetry written by women, and the forms of
expression developed by Wesley and his followers. Insofar as Wordsworth and Blake entered into these
discourses, assumed them as a context for their own work,
<pb id="p27-48" n="48"/>
and appropriated them for their own purposes, we do not know what Blake and Wordsworth were trying to do in
their poetry without knowing something about the religious exercises performed by the Methodists and the
debates within and surrounding a “new form of literary production” emerging in 1739 and continuing
throughout the eighteenth century, “the publication by subscription of volumes of verse by laboring-class
women” (Landry 11).</p>
            <p>Reconstructing conflicts that have been suppressed from the historical record, either because
the subjects of history were unable to register them or because subsequent histories have elided them, thus
provides greater objectivity, allowing Blake’s and Wordsworth’s texts to reveal their own ideological
complicities and dissonances instead of ours. This reconstruction gives us a more objective view, but not
because it keeps Abelove and Landry from projecting their own interests onto the past. It doesn’t. As Landry
says explicitly, the laboring-class, female poets whom she studies “attend to the ‘muses of resistance,’
but it is never entirely clear where the resistance is coming from. The political desires, both theirs and
mine, out of which such an investigation and reconstruction emerge can never be fully articulated” (3).
Abelove and Landry give us a better sense of what their subjects were trying to say not in spite of but
precisely because of their partisanship; their partisanship enables them to be more, not less, objective.</p>
            <p>The definition of objective knowledge bequeathed to us by logical positivism as knowledge which
is absolutely true, regardless of who views the object, surreptitiously informs much literary theory despite
having long been discredited (Mohanty 18). As Hilary Putnam puts it, even scientific descriptions of reality
come from various and different perspectives: “As Dewey and Pierce taught us, real questions require a
context and a point. But this is as true of scientific questions as it is of ethical ones” (177). There is
no “<hi rend="i">single</hi> theory” upon which “science converges,” and therefore no “absolute
conception of the world” which is independent of any description of it (171). Since all knowledge depends
upon description, and all descriptions come from a perspective (Putnam 169-170, 173), the only way to get a
view of the world of the eighteenth century is through retrieving perspectives that have been lost. Recovering
plebeian and female perspectives of the eighteenth century will give us an objective view of it. But here
getting such a view depends upon recovering histories that have not yet quite been written. To provide an
objective account, the literary historian must adopt the partisanship necessary for extracting those histories
from the conventions which threaten to conceal them.</p>
            <p>Thus, in describing political criticism of Shakespeare, Walter Cohen claims that partisanship
is not antithetical to objectivity, but, on the contrary, essential to achieving it: “The vast majority of
political writing on Shakespeare has sided with the victims of state power, class hierarchy, patriarchy,
racism, and imperialism, a partisanship, it is worth asserting, not only compatible with but also necessary to
a commitment to objectivity in scholarship” (20). I will allow some of the insights gleaned from Abelove’s
and Landry’s books to enter into some contemporary romanticists’ debates over the politics, sexual and
otherwise, of canonical romantic poetry, for the sake of providing an “objectivity in scholarship”
otherwise lacking. Neither Landry nor Abelove distinguishes their work from American new historicism; in fact,
Landry allies herself with it (3). But, I would like to argue that Abelove’s and Landry’s partisanship
differs crucially from the partisanship to be found in attacks on Wordsworth’s politics that come out of
McGann’s work. Before looking at how the implications of their work might change assumptions we make about
Wordsworth and Blake, I will first try to show the difference between these two kinds of partisanship as a way
of demonstrating Landry’s and Abelove’s achievement.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>I. A Case in Which Opposition is not true friendship</title>
              </head>
              <p>In a sympathetic account of new historical romanticists, Paul Cantor praises them for
critiquing romantic ideology by showing that gender, race, and class issues inform the poets’ ostensibly
“universal” truths. But Cantor gently admonishes and at the same time glosses over some new
historicists’ failure to acknowledge that the romantics “were Revolutionaries, indeed the first literary
radicals,” however ineffectual. It is surprising, he says, that the romantics would be subjected to this
kind of critique since they protested against “social injustice, political oppression, and the dehumanizing
effects of industrialization”: “It is a sign of the increasing ideological purity in today’s academy
that these critics, who have demonstrated their genuine admiration for the Romantics by devoting their careers
to them, are now convinced that as progressive as the Romantics may have been, they did not go far enough”
(706-07). I would like to suggest that one very rarely gets the sense from reading new historicist accounts
that the romantics went far but just did not go far enough; romantic radicalism in new historicist accounts
seems much more constricted than that.</p>
              <p>In McGann’s account of Keats (1979), Levinson’s account of “Tintern Abbey” (1986),
and Marlon Ross’s account of romantic, masculine desire (1989), one gets the distinct message that
literature is always allied with ideology. Catherine Gallagher would disagree; she says that new historicists
precisely do not ally literature and ideology:
<q>
New historicists were often bent on proving that the relationship between form and ideology was neither one of
simple affirmation, in which form papers over ideological gaps, nor one of subversive negation, in which form
exposes ideology and thereby helps render it powerless. The contribution of the new historicism has been to
identify a third alternative in which the very antagonism between literature and ideology becomes, in specific
historical environments, a powerful and socially
<pb id="p27-49" n="49"/>
functional mode of constructing subjectivity. (44)
</q>
This statement might apply more to Renaissance than to romanticist new historicists. Romanticist new
historicists do in fact see aesthetic form as that which “paper[s] over ideological gaps.”</p>
              <p>Thus, in a recent detailed analysis of McGann, Levinson, and Ross, Susan Wolfson complains
that “[i]n the interests of locating and critiquing the text in a certain ideological constellation, these
readers tend to neglect textual nuance, ambiguity of import, and ambivalence of tone, or treat such matters as
a suspect aesthetic complexity that artificially resolves the ideological pressure of sociopolitical
reality” (430-31). Wolfson explicitly reproaches McGann for allying literature with ideology: “My quarrel
is not with the effort to discern an ideology behind ideas or interpretive emphasis; but I do want to suggest
that literary texts often signal their own capacity for mounting the kind of critique that readers such as
McGann assume can be made only from a point outside the poem’s own procedures” (439).</p>
              <p>To say as McGann and Levinson do that poems try to “transform lived contradiction” by
“redemptive figural definition” (Levinson 4, qtd. in Wolfson 431) allies poems with ideology. That
aesthetic form is capable of such resolutions and redemptions is also a suspect, and perhaps fundamentally New
Critical assumption (see Fischer 36): although McGann values differently than the New Critics did the power of
literature to resolve conflict, he believes it has that power. Thus, when in <hi rend="i">Social Values and
Poetic Acts</hi> McGann does come up with the poets who are not merely ideological tools (Blake and the
language poets), it turns out that art can only be nonconsoling through representing the incommensurable.
Refusing the consolations of form, heterodox texts “hold a mirror up to the [heterodox] world” revealing
its real “incoherence” (<hi rend="i">Social Values</hi> 9). This is to say that representations can only
work against ideology through failing to represent. Because for McGann representation is ideological, only its
failure could contest ideology, a questionable principle, to say the least.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">3</ref> We are back to the conception of an unrepresentable Other,
back to the idea that interests in conflict with hegemonic ones cannot be represented. 
<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">3</hi> McGann thus opens <hi rend="i">Social Values and Poetic Acts</hi> by declaring the genius of
Paul de Man. De Man comes perilously close to connecting the aim of rhetorical theory (revealing that
linguistic structures are undecidable) with ideology critique in his essay “The Resistance to Theory”
(11). However, it is a mistake to associate “undecidability” with the successful suspension of
meaningfulness and thus to overcoming ideological closure. Dan Miller fully analyzes this mistake in his
review of <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms</hi> (120). Miller points out that the post-structuralist notion of the
incommensurate is often unwittingly used to stand, not for the problem of meaning, but rather for the most
meaningful of meanings: incommensurability is often asserted to be a meaninglessness which is absolutely
significant, as it is here in McGann’s case, where it signifies the refusal of ideology for the sake of
history. It is impossible to communicate meaninglessness or formlessness, as deconstructionists readily
recognize; meaning reconstitutes itself faster than any deconstructor can trace out its dispersal.</note></p>
              <p>Romantic new historicists typically argue that, because writing literature is fundamentally a
matter of cooperating with the reigning, conservative ideology, poets of the high romantic tradition therefore
sacrificed their political radicalism to aesthetic requirements or to an overarching narrative of spiritual
development. A bald summary of Levinson’s work on “Tintern Abbey,” however unfairly it flattens her
critique of the poem, has the virtue of showing us the form that so much romanticist new historicism takes: as
Cantor describes it, “Levinson brilliantly argues that “Tintern Abbey” constitutes a kind of ideological
smokescreen, a swerve away from genuine political engagement and into the Romantic myth of nature” (707).
Ross could be said to have done the same thing: a poetry indistinguishable from gender ideology swerves into
the myth of masculine and feminine desire. Wolfson objects to this “monolithic critique that finds all
poetic self-contestation displaced from the contradictions of socio-historical reality into an aesthetics of
reconciliation and spiritual transformation” (432). In the new historicist’s tale, radicalism always
capitulates to aesthetic or religious form. The same is true, according to Cohen, for new historicist critics
of Shakespeare: “their readings of individual Shakespearean plays almost always demonstrate the triumph of
containment”:
<q>
This <hi rend="i">non sequitur</hi> involves a certain fidelity to Foucault, . . . whose historical analyses
revealed the unconstrained victory of power. . . . Despite the presence of internal conflict, society and
especially the theater are organized down to their smallest details for the benefit of those in power. . . .
New historicism ends up if not with something like a totalitarian model, then at least with a sense of the
almost inevitable defeat of the poor, the innocent, and the oppressed. (Cohen 35)
</q></p>
              <p>Because new historicist accounts of “Tintern Abbey” focus on how Wordsworth tries to
transcend politics and history, and how he thereby participates in power’s inevitable victory over the
oppressed, there is in these accounts nothing like Kenneth Johnston’s recognition that it is the poem itself
which insists upon our analyzing its politics. The poem, Johnston says,
<q>
is not required to supply an exact demonstration of the relation of aesthetic experience—whether landscape
viewing or poetry writing (or reading)—to social responsibility and ultimate values. Nonetheless, the poem
itself provokes such questions, and if in what follows I seem often to go outside the poem and to imply that
Wordsworth is neglecting or sublimating unpleasant associations, it’s not to suggest that he like any poet
can’t write the poem he wants to write, but that he himself has imbedded it with language which
simultaneously invites and resists probing, opening up just those areas of concern that it determinedly seeks
to elide or contain in more manageable terms. (7)
</q>
We are aware that the political is silenced in “Tintern Abbey” or <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi> in part
because Wordsworth is struggling with the relation between landscape viewing and social responsibility. In
fact, it is only against a view of the romantics’ radicalism that the insights of new historicism are
startling, and most valuable: that even the young, radical Wordsworth holds views in common with Burke, or
that Paine and Burke or Wollstonecraft and More are in ideological collusion<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">4</ref> is amazing <hi rend="i">only</hi> against a backdrop of their
overt antagonism. That Wordsworth was really an escapist, and Blake truly a pious quietist is interesting only
to people who care about them personally. Such information becomes theoretically significant only if it can
tell us something about how ideology works. New historicist, romantic criticism shows us how radicalism (or
less often, conservatism) can be coopted by the opposition. But that very insight depends upon recognizing
that the romantics were radicals. <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">4</hi> On the young, overtly radical
Wordsworth’s relation to Burke, see Chandler, “Burke Blamed and Praised” (<hi rend="i">Wordsworth’s
Second Nature</hi> 15-30). On how Burke and Paine collude in economic ideology, see Aers 156-59. On how their
“shared socio-economic ideology” leads to “collusions of discourse,” see UEA English Studies Group
(Punter, Aers, Clark, Cook, Elsasser) 87-91. On how Burke and Paine collude in revolutionary concepts of
language, see Smith 38-39. On More and Wollstonecraft, see Meyers 211, 201, qtd. in Landry 257-58.</note></p>
              <pb id="p27-50" n="50"/>
              <p>Thus Gallagher sees one of the greatest achievements of new historicism as the posing of this
question: “Was it possible, we asked, that certain forms of subjectivity that felt oppositional were really
a means by which power relations were maintained?” (42). The question, Gallagher says, relies on an insight
gleaned from the women’s liberation movement:
<q>
by focusing attention on our gendered individuation as the deepest moment of social oppression, some of us
called into question the political reliability of our own subjectivity. We effectively collapsed the
self/society division and began regarding our “normal” consciousness and “natural” inclinations as
profoundly untrustworthy. We, along with our erstwhile political optimism, became for ourselves the objects of
a hermeneutics of suspicion. (42-43)
</q>
Instead of naively believing that exposure of social oppression through “the discourse of liberation”
would inevitably lead to the destruction of a fragile social system, or naively believing that poetry has a
radical potential because it presents ideological contradictions to us, the new historicist shows how power
structures contain radical opposition, shows that it may not “theoretically [be] possible even to
differentiate the individual subject [radical or conservative] from a system of power relationships”
(Gallagher 42).</p>
              <p>There is a lot to be said about this hermeneutics of suspicion, about whether Foucault’s
historical analyses actually do participate in it, as Cohen says that they do; but suffice it to say here that
suspicion as to the actual existence of the subject as defined by liberal humanism, the subject who 
<hi rend="i">can</hi> effectively choose to support the political program he or she wishes, does not rid new
historicist analyses of an inherently fallacious subjectivity. On the contrary, it erects subjects even more
fallacious than the one posited by liberal humanism, insofar as that latter subject is at least capable of
unconscious motivation.</p>
              <p>Thus, in her article “Sex and History in <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi> (1805),” Gayatri
Spivak rightly insists that she is talking about “Wordsworth” (only in quotation marks) or Wordsworth’s
own “ideological victimization”; but she often slips into talking about Wordsworth as if he were
deliberately, consciously, and malevolently calculating all of the counterrevolutionary effects of his poetry
(211, 218-19). It is this fallacious subjectivity that Simpson tries to correct in formulating the idea of
Wordsworth’s “poetry of displacement.” McGann used the term “displacement,” Simpson says, “to
describe an apparently conscious strategy whereby the unpleasant or challenging details of a real landscape
are excluded or decentered from the poem, a process attended by a further displacement of the natural scene to
the spiritual plane of attention” (<hi rend="i">Wordsworth’s Historical Imagination</hi> 14). Simpson
protests: “We can admit that there is in many poems an attempt to establish an alternative (displaced)
consolation beyond the empirical-historical; but the language of such attempts very often contains the terms
of its own undermining. If we are looking to judge Wordsworth as a moral agent, we must then entertain the
possibility that displacement is something he experienced and perhaps even suffered as much as he achieved”
(14). Although many new historicists agree with Simpson in theory, in their practice, Wordsworth appears to be
consciously manipulating this displacement of political concerns by aesthetic ones.</p>
              <p>Romantic new historicism turns all past subjects into a timeless, faceless, colossal image of
conservatism: Wordsworth, Coleridge, Paine, perhaps even Blake—they are all just colossal Burkes in
disguise. The new historicist partisanship is of an us-them kind (see Mohanty, esp. 20): “we” are cultural
critics, sensitive to the exclusions of high literature; “they” are the writers of high literature who
exclude history, politics, the Real, for the sake of producing “great” poetry. This undialectical
antagonism of us against them erects the monolithic egos of an imaginary relation: the only “subjects”
here have no unconscious mind, are not self-contradictory, but rather wholly against each other. “Where we
fall back into the received Romantic field,” Levinson says, in incisive self-criticism, “is in our failure
. . . to articulate the subject-object, present-past, criticism-poetry polarities as a mode of relation”
(20), thus leaving them polarities, or poles, and the relation a mere binary opposition or imaginary
antagonism.</p>
              <p>The partisanship the new historicist takes, then, is his or her own part against those
writing in the past, or representation <hi rend="i">per se.</hi> But these past writers under attack are
disturbingly not someone else from another time. The new historical romanticists’ assumption that
representation is always on the side of ideology, that “all poetic self-contestation” is ultimately
coopted, that ideological fissures and gaps are always healed by poetry, denies them access to the past. As I
hope to show below in examining Abelove’s and Landry’s accounts, the literary historian’s partisanship
with those who rather actively suffer class and gender oppression will give us a more objective view of that
world: it will give us an understanding of a past which is past and not a mirror reflection of our present.
This objectivity is achieved only through the assumption that aesthetics does not reconcile, that spirituality
does not transform completely; that we can hear oppressed subjects (not victims, but full subjects) of the
past contest, rework, and accommodate themselves to systems of oppression, and thereby speak to us on their
own terms.</p>
              <p>The subjects of Abelove’s and Landry’s histories existed outside the dominant discourses
of the period; the stories they tell are, in many ways, the story of their struggle to represent themselves
even though dispossessed of a means for doing so. Both Abelove and Landry are thus keenly aware of the
temptation to “colonize” the histories of Methodists and early feminists in their own recounting of them,
and each one adopts a particular strategy for dealing with that temptation, as will be seen below. Abelove and
Landry therefore contribute to our understanding
<pb id="p27-51" n="51"/>
of how to present the histories of classes traditionally underrepresented in the academic disciplines<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">5</ref> without rewriting those histories, without
repeating in a more insidious because less visible way the very act of class warfare by which they were
excluded from the tradition in the first place. Because Abelove and Landry ask how the lower classes and women
registered their protests against oppression, they are able to historicize the terms of gender, class, and
sexuality. Paradoxically, it is not through questioning the possibility of willful action by considering the
subject to be an effect of power, but rather through assuming the existence of the subject of liberal
humanism, a subject who has choices and can exercise will, that one can construct a history which allows for
both unconscious and conscious effects. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">5</hi> This is significantly not true in
Blake studies, though some Blake scholars may have experienced marginalization by the discipline as a
result.</note></p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>II. What is a Church? &amp; What Is a Theatre? are they Two &amp; not One?<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Blake, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 57: 8-9 (E 207).</note>
	</title>
              </head>
              <p>While most of the historical work interesting to theorists of literature and of cultural
studies is heavily theorized, Henry Abelove’s elegantly written monograph on Methodism is very quietly so:
you can read the short book blissfully unaware that anything even vaguely “theoretical” is taking place.
The questions that occupy him are straightforward and simple: historians have long acknowledged the tremendous
influence Wesley had on Britain; Abelove asks, “how did John Wesley succeed in attracting to himself so many
long-staying followers? Of what he taught these followers once he had attracted them, how much did they really
accept?” Yet these two “simple” questions have important implications for the theory of history.</p>
              <p>Let me first discuss the number of Wesley’s followers. Wesley was ordained in the Church of
England and was thus himself “still . . . precariously within the church” (77) rather than a Dissenter.
Relatively few of his “helpers” or lay-preachers were ordained in the Church, although Wesley believed in
1769 that fully one-fourth of them could be ordained and could even seek preferment in the church if they
wanted to (112). After John and his brother Charles had returned from a two-year mission to America in 1737,
they were forbidden to preach in Anglican churches, prompting George Whitefield to inaugurate the practice of
“field-preaching” (John Wesley’s Obituary 282). Thus, the leaders of Methodism were deprived of the
official capacity to administer sacraments of various kinds for the Church of England, at least insofar as the
members of the church agreed in practice.</p>
              <p>Although excluded from the Anglican Church, Methodism did not become a sect until the
beginning of the nineteenth century; during the eighteenth century, it was an evangelical movement. While the
writer of Wesley’s obituary in the <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> does call Wesley “the leader
of a sect,” he or she does so only to add that it was “a sect no way differing in essentials from the
Church of England” (283). “[T]he Methodism of Wesley’s day” that Abelove analyzes “was not a sect.
It was a revival, a field of force.” Because it was a movement, its numbers are difficult to determine:
“It kept many adherents and affected many others without involving them in formal membership” (Abelove
44n11).</p>
              <p>The movement began, Abelove tells us, “in the late 1730’s, [when] virtually the whole
Protestant world was undergoing an evangelical awakening” (4). Especially in the North American colonies,
which “Wesley’s collaborator Whitefield” visited seven times, there was a terrific “revivalist
fervor” (5). But the awakening did not last: the American evangelical movement had died altogether by 1760,
and other movements ebbed. Things turned out differently for Wesley: “When he died in 1791, the Methodists
owned 588 preaching-houses in the British Isles, and their members numbered 72,476” (5). 72,476 may seem
relatively few, in a population of between 6 and 8.5 million.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n20" type="note">7</ref> However, “[i]n addition” to these 72,476 actual members of Methodist
societies, Abelove says, “there were thousands of people who never formally joined a society but were still
Methodists, still followers of Wesley” (44). But even if that were not true, just to know the views shared
in broad outline by 72,000 people is to know a great deal about attitudes of the time. 
<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">7</hi> In 1777, John Cartwright asserted that there were “6 million souls” in England (33). The
figure for the year 1801 was 8.5 million.</note></p>
              <p>The number of Methodists at Wesley’s death is one-fourth the number of those who could vote
in England and Wales: the electorate was 282,000 for the years 1754-90 (O’Gormon 179, table 4.2). We quite
often take enactments of law as material testimony to attitudes of the time, despite not only the corruption
of the voting system, but also the questionable assumption that voters in the Commons adequately reflected the
interests of their constituents. John Cartwright, founder of the Society for Constitutional Information in
1780 (Goodwin 63), describes how absolutely unrepresentative the Commons actually was in 1777: “Those who
now claim the <hi rend="i">exclusive</hi> right of sending to parliament the 513 representatives for about 6
million souls (amongst whom are one million five hundred thousand males, <hi rend="i">competent as
electors</hi>) consist of about two hundred and fourteen thousand persons; and 254 of these representatives
are elected by 5,723 . . .” (Cartwright 33, emphases in the original). Another way to describe the number of
Wesley’s followers, then, is to say that there were 12 times as many Methodists (72,476) as there were
people who could vote for half of Parliament (5,723).</p>
              <p>Because the Methodists were for the most part poor, studying their attitudes will give us
insights into “the age” which the official history, history made by and from canonical texts, might leave
out or repress. Any history of ideas, as critics like McGann have pointed out, will be classbound: it will be
the history of the ideas of the class that had the power to represent its ideas; or worse, and as McGann
explicitly contends against M. H. Abrams, such a study will not only be the history of an
<pb id="p27-52" n="52"/>
ideology used to oppress subaltern classes, it will continue that work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">8</ref> Notice how adroitly Abelove’s second “simple” question
moves us out of a history of ideas: he will not tell us Wesley’s doctrines in order to describe the
attitudes of Wesley’s followers; rather, he will look for evidence of which among those doctrines the
Methodists adopted, which they rejected, and how they revised them. “It cannot be assumed, or rather it can
be assumed only naively, that what Wesley taught was what the Methodists learned. To discover how they reacted
to him, what they actually absorbed of what he taught, must be a matter for actual inquiry” (3). This move
packs quite a theoretical punch, one which is directed not only backward to the historian of ideas, but also
forward to new historicists who still remain caught, as Cohen argues, within “formalist assumptions,”
those who “commit a methodological error by deducing [the sociological] effect [of cultural productions, in
this case Shakespeare’s plays] from form and context” (Cohen 36). <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">8</hi>
McGann, <hi rend="i">Romantic Ideology</hi> 32, 38. “McGann is much harder on twentieth-century critics of
romanticism than he is on the romantics themselves,” Fischer 34.</note></p>
              <p>Abelove’s interest in Methodism was inspired by E. P. Thompson’s <hi rend="i">The Making
of the English Working Class</hi>, he tells us in an afterword, but he objects to one of Thompson’s
methodological assumptions: “[Thompson] writes of [the] Methodism [of Wesley’s lifetime] as though it were
something entirely foreign to England’s plebeians, something just imposed on them. It seemed to me unlikely
that they would have valued it as they did if they had not found in it the means to fulfill needs and purposes
of their own” (119). Rather than deducing Wesleyan Methodism from Wesley’s doctrines (from “form and
context,” as Cohen puts it), Abelove examines the letters, diaries, journals, confessional diaries,
autobiographies, memoirs and pamphlets written by Wesley’s followers, and the minutes of conferences and
portions of Wesley’s journals reflecting what his followers said to him, as well as the concerted actions
they took, to determine what they accepted, used, and modified of the doctrines Wesley offered them. They did
not modify Methodism just for themselves, but also for Wesley. In each chapter of his analysis, Abelove
explains first what Wesley taught, and then takes an historical turn, examining what the Methodists actually
learned from him (45, 48, 58, 63).</p>
              <p>Historians often attribute part of the success of Methodism to Wesley’s talent for
organization. However, as Abelove points out, Wesley did not so much organize his flock as learn how to
organize from them. One of “the great organizational features of Methodism, the class meeting, was suggested
by a member of the Bristol flock in 1742” (48n21). Rather than attributing the size and persistence of
Wesleyan Methodism to Wesley’s theology or to his organizational skills, Abelove insists that the movement
rose and endured precisely because it provided for its plebeian members a space of articulation and
resistance.</p>
              <p>Some of Wesley’s doctrines were directly empowering. His doctrine of “free grace,” his
insistence that anyone could have eternal life who wanted it, reassured his plebeian followers whose
“self-esteem was in many ways low. They could believe salvation was possible for them only if they were
continually assured that it was available on easy terms to everybody” (32). Through his discouragement of
marriage, and through “the ongoing pastoral arrangements” which encouraged same-sex intimacy (67), Wesley
unwittingly provided a space for resisting power relations constructed by “family life as conventionally
ordered” (72) and those new power relations being constructed by a new valuation of sex for
reproduction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">9</ref> The weekly meetings
called “bands,” made up of small groups of members of the same sex, and “select-bands,” made up of
Methodists “already Perfected,” and more intimate still, encouraged same-sex feeling:
<q>
These arrangements—separate seating [male on one side, female on the other] at worship, bands and select
bands, the continuous exhorting to stay single—they resisted but they also lived with. They found themselves
often thrown together intimately, men with men, women with women, and they responded to each other. . . .
Sometimes they not only responded but actually fell in love. (67)
</q>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">9</hi> On the increasing insistence, throughout the eighteenth century, that
“sexual intercourse” be defined as cross-gender intercourse for reproduction, and on the possible reasons
for such a change, see Abelove, “Some Speculations.”</note></p>
              <p>In addition, Wesley’s doctrine of Perfection allowed for a distinctively feminist
resistance by sanctioning “long-term conjugal abstinence at the wife’s insistence,” one of the only
ways, besides abortion and infanticide, that a woman had to assert her reproductive rights during this period
(70): women who had attained Perfection or “freedom from all inward sin” (70) were perfectly justified in
refusing to have sex with their husbands (70, 81). While Wesley did not intend to deliver a protofeminist
message, his doctrines may have had a feminist effect, not only in giving women a choice in their own
reproductive practices (81), but also in allowing women to feel justified in rejecting other demands made upon
them by their families. Contemporaries worried about the diversion of women from their domestic tasks, so much
so that the absence of a wife from her home actually stimulated an anti-Methodist riot at Wednesbury in
Staffordshire (64-65).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Keith Thomas has similarly analyzed the extent to which Puritan sects of
the civil war period unwittingly provided justification and means for “female emancipation.”</note></p>
              <p>While some of Wesley’s ideas were directly empowering to the laboring classes, most of his
doctrines were empowering only because his followers were able to modify them. Wesley’s “doctrine” as a
whole, a hodgepodge of his particular inflection of Anglicanism, was motivated less for theological reasons
than for the sake of securing his followers’ emotional attachment to him. Both consciously and
unconsciously, Wesley wanted to keep himself at the center of the movement and “keep the attention of his
flock fixed firmly on himself” (74). Wesley’s doctrine changed over time so that he might constantly
distinguish himself from competitors and thereby demand the full love and attention of his adherents.
Paradoxically, the strength of his leadership gave his followers the capacity to dissent from his doctrines,
<pb id="p27-53" n="53"/>
and to use them for their own purposes.</p>
              <p>Abelove relies on Freud’s <hi rend="i">Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego</hi> to
explain how this is so. Wesley’s popularity and his followers’ ability to revise his doctrine came from
the same source: Wesley’s seduction of his followers. Through many means exhaustively documented by Abelove,
Wesley “seduced” his followers into loving him. Such seduction does not exact blind obedience, but, on the
contrary, enriches “intellectual life” (119). With Wesley in the position of ego-ideal, the Methodists
were able to identify with each other:
<q>
It might be supposed that because Wesley had magnetized all these many thousands, because they deferred to him
and loved him, they would do anything he asked, learn what he taught, believe what he said. But that
supposition would be mistaken. For the result of their attachment to him was not just docility. It was
something else as well, something almost contrary to docility. It was union with one another. (45)
</q>
Putting Wesley in the place of the group’s ego ideal allowed them to hear what he said “in ways that
suited them mutually,” and thereby to convert Wesleyanism into a Methodism which “was a compromise between
his word and their need” (48).</p>
              <p>From Wesley’s instructions, the Methodists “selected out what they jointly knew and
valued already, Puritanism” (86). They selected three main elements: “the ideal of a new birth; the ideal
of a personal relation of spiritual experience, as an important facet of membership in the group; and the
ideal of an imminent apocalypse” (88). They interpreted Wesley’s doctrine of Perfection as “just the old
Puritan apocalypse, internalized” (92). That is, as Hester Roe Rogers’s journal puts it, the change
wrought in those who were Perfected turned their world into “‘a Heaven below’” (qtd. on 92). Many
confessional diaries, journals, and spiritual letters also relate stories of “new birth,” of the moment
when a follower of Wesley’s would realize that he or she was in fact saved (88-89). The striking thing for
Abelove is that these conversion narratives repeatedly show the Methodists discovering grace “[i]n everyday
scenes and everyday circumstances”—on a walk, or when gathering eggs from the barn (90).</p>
              <p>Methodist spirituality, organized around weekly class meetings, can be characterized, Abelove
says, as “the Puritan relation made continuous.” While the Methodists did not have to publicly relate
their conversion experience in order to gain admission to the church, as did the Puritans, they did have
<q>
to make some kind of public relation of their spiritual experiences at least once every week at a class
meeting; again at a band meeting . . . ; again at a select band meeting . . . ; possibly at the monthly or
quarterly lovefeast [“a special meeting of the flock held at night” often for relating spiritual
experiences (82)]; and possibly also at the full society meetings, whenever they happened to be scheduled.
(94)
</q>
The Methodists heard Wesley speak “only a couple of times a year”; but on a weekly and an almost daily
basis, they “share[d] with one another the developing record of their hopes and fears, faults and successes,
doubts and certainties, anxieties and loves” (94). This description of Methodist spirituality could easily
be used to describe “Tintern Abbey.”</p>
              <p>As Abelove points out, the “Puritan relation made continuous” is a kind of
“‘egotistical sublime’”:
<q>
This phrase is of course Keats’s description of Wordsworth’s poetry. I use it here to lead up to a point I
want to make in passing. It seems to me that to review this account of the spirituality of the Methodist
people is to gain a potentially useful perspective on the origins of Romanticism. The discovery of grace at
everyday places; the internalization of apocalypse; the privileged and continuous self-exploration and
self-expression: these are the basic features of the Methodist appropriation of the Puritan tradition, and
they may also have been among the basic features of the poetry that Wordsworth and Coleridge introduced in
1798. (95n73)
</q>
What would be the effect of situating “Tintern Abbey” in the context of Methodist religious exercises,
rather than, as we so often automatically do, within John Stuart Mill’s distinction of poetry from mere
rhetoric or, as he calls it, “eloquence”: “eloquence is <hi rend="i">heard</hi>, poetry is 
<hi rend="i">overheard</hi>”; at the moment when the poet, “turns round and addresses himself to another
person; when the act of utterance is not itself the end, but a means to an end . . . , by that desire of
making an impression upon another mind, then it ceases to be poetry and becomes eloquence” (Mill 539-40).
Locating romantic lyrics within Mill’s insistence that poetry is purely disinterested soliloquy, the effect
of isolation from the world rather than intercourse with it (540), has a history. In his article, “English
Romanticism: The Spirit of the Age” (1963), Abrams asserted that good poetry came from a withdrawal from
active political engagement.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">11</ref> The
distinction between quietist poetry and activist rhetoric is often uncritically repeated by historical critics
who ignore Thompson’s 1969 rebuttal of Abrams’s argument.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n25" type="note">12</ref> Thus, Marilyn Butler simply repeats the notion that high romantic poetry is
a- or even anti-political. Poetry as Wordsworth and Coleridge developed it after renouncing their radicalism
merely “ponders the experiences of recluses and private men,” in contradistinction to pamphleteering,
journalism, real “political prose” which we have only been taught to denigrate by Wordsworth and
Coleridge, “by literary men after their political defeat” (16). Butler uncritically opposes poetry to
prose, and “personal experience” to “public problems,” just as Mill and Abrams do, while claiming that
such distinctions were fabricated by the romantic poets through renunciation. 
<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Abrams calls it a “militant quietism” (73-74), but it is quietism nonetheless.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">12</hi> David Garcia pointed out to me the connection between Thompson’s
“Disenchantment or Default?” and Abrams’s “The Spirit of the Age.”</note></p>
              <p>James Chandler’s <hi rend="i">Second Nature</hi> also unwittingly and uncritically grants
Abrams’s proposition that the hope for the reformation of society “produced mainly declamation” (66)
while “disillusionment” produced “‘the higher poetry’” (69, 72). Chandler’s argument goes along
with the idea that the radical Wordsworth who wrote <hi rend="i">A Letter to the Bishop of Llandaff</hi> could
not have
<pb id="p27-54" n="54"/>
written great poetry, and intensifies the last part of Abrams’s proposition: the Wordsworth of the great
period was not only disillusioned; he had renounced his radicalism, although he could not consciously admit to
himself that he was in fact a “conservative” (45).</p>
              <p>Chandler claims that his argument is convincing if we accept the idea that Wordsworth’s
“sense of opprobrium [was] sufficiently powerful . . . to account for an effort on Wordsworth’s part to
conceal his changed opinions (as much from himself as from the world)” (275n24). I would like to suggest
that Chandler’s argument is sustained by much more than biography. That Wordsworth felt an inordinate need
to repress from his own consciousness “the thought of turning his coat” (275) is made convincing by the
tacit collapse of poetry into ideology: before launching into his “golden decade” and writing his greatest
poetry, Chandler feels, Wordsworth <hi rend="i">must</hi> have renounced radical politics (31-32; 62-63). 
<hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>, Chandler says, “the magnum opus of the great decade . . . is written from an
ideological perspective that is thoroughly Burkean. In later chapters I will try to show,” he continues,
“that if we understand ‘conservative’ to mean ideological proximity to Burke, then the visionary and
experimental writing for which Wordsworth is revered, his program for poetry, is from its very inception
impelled by powerfully conservative motives” (31-32).</p>
              <p>The Burke of the <hi rend="i">Reflections on the Revolution in France</hi> is spearheading
the counter-revolutionary reaction in England, to be sure, but in whose interests? Is Burke “conservative”
because he is promoting the interests of the aristocracy, or bourgeois interests? If trying to conserve the
aristocratic order, Burke was indeed a conservative <hi rend="i">then</hi>, but would be allied with
progressives who wish to demystify bourgeois ideology <hi rend="i">now.</hi> There may be some deep affinities
between Burke’s idealizations in the <hi rend="i">Reflections</hi> and Marxist idealizations of
precapitalist culture. If by “conservative” Chandler means that Burke was instrumental in the institution
of bourgeois hegemony, as Macpherson and the UEA English Studies Group maintain, he was progressive 
<hi rend="i">then</hi>, though he would be considered conservative <hi rend="i">now.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">13</ref> In this a-historical use of the term “conservative,”
Chandler has slipped into the present and is in this passage fighting present battles rather than analyzing
one of the past.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">14</ref> It often seems to
me that new historicists who attack Wordsworth for aestheticizing and thereby “resolving” historical
problems are really angry at Abrams for his assertion that good poetry is made out of bad politics, but,
because they accept that assertion as true, their anger gets displaced onto “good” poetry: great poetry is
always already coopted. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">13</hi> See Williams, <hi rend="i">Marxism</hi>, for a
definition of “hegemony” (108-14) and for an account of ideological change which takes account of shifts
in power (“Dominant, Residual, and Emergent,” 121-27).</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Kramnick contests the picture of Burke as the “father of
conservatism” (4) and argues that historians writing before the late 1970s have used Burke’s alleged
“conservatism” in order to express cold-war era, anti-communist sentiment (3). Just as Chandler uses Burke
as an image of contemporary conservatism, literary critics begin to wage present battles when discussing in an
a-historical manner Burke’s anti-“theory” sentiment, so vividly expressed in the 
<hi rend="i">Reflections.</hi> They forget that Burke attacks the systematizing impulse of Enlightenment
philosophy, the very rationalism assaulted by Derrida and Lacan.</note></p>
              <p>But Wordsworth did not separate poetry from radical politics; as Johnston points out (quoted
above), Wordsworth’s poetry questions the separation of poetry from politics. This poetry gives us the
relation between poetry and politics as a problem. It is an imposition to read back into romantic poetry the
context of Mill, Kant, and Abrams who give us a solution to the problem rather than the problem itself. The
opposition between “disinterested” aesthetics and politics, attributable to Mill and to Kant, like
Abrams’s opposition between political declamation and a-political lyric, may be imposed on the romantics
only by anachronism. “Tintern Abbey,” <hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads</hi>, the Intimations Ode, Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, all of these might differ slightly in meaning if the lyric is seen not as a
soliloquy, but rather as self-expression directed to an audience who, like the Methodists, is seen as judging
one’s spiritual development, and where spiritual development potentially has more consequences for the
community than for the individual.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">15</hi> That is, where “spiritual development” does not automatically imply
an individual quest, as it did to earlier critics, Abrams among them.</note></p>
              <p>Of course, romantic lyrics have long been interpreted as fundamentally dramatic in structure,
but the context of Methodism provides an historical basis for doing so. It further provides an historical
basis for claiming, as Johnston, Wolfson, and Simpson have done, that romantic lyrics portray not the triumph
of form or spirituality as a way out of politics, but anxieties aroused by the fact of self-expression taking
place in an inevitably formal mode—anxieties about theatricality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">16</ref> For the Methodists, telling how one felt “inside” oneself, whether one
truly loved God or not, was no simple matter, despite Wesley’s repeated assurance that it was (Abelove 38).
Methodists rejected theater even “more enthusiastically” than Wesley had wanted them to (104), in part
because of their predilection for Puritanical aspects of Wesley’s teaching (86). As Jonas Barish has shown,
Puritans attacked the theater for the same reasons they attacked the theatricalism of Rome, and, in their
prejudice against theater, puritanical Methodists reiterated sentiments that had led to the
Reformation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">17</ref> In addition, Abelove
contends that it was precisely because of their anxiety over establishing the sincerity of the spiritual
autobiographies they recited before an audience of their peers that the Methodists were so hostile to theater:
<q>
[T]he Methodists disapproved of adult play, and especially theater, because they had an ongoing theater of
their own, which they liked better than the one dramatists provided. In their theater they were the stars as
well as the audience. Their lines were the lines that were remembered and commented upon afterward. Their
concerns were the subject of the play, and . . . . the words were familiar, even if heightened . . . . If the
Methodists, then, were making a theater of their own among themselves, they might easily have felt impelled to
a hostile view of ordinary theater and ordinary play. . . . [T]he all-too-obvious similarity might be
threatening enough to evoke fear and anger. (105-06)
</q>
The Methodists angrily rejected theater as a way of “abjecting” the possibility of theatricality from
self-expression itself. But, as Lacan would say, what is disavowed in psychic life has a way of returning in
the Real: Abelove points out that the Methodists sometimes rented empty theater buildings in which to hold
their meetings, and admitted
<pb id="p27-55" n="55"/>
members to society meetings only if they had what the Methodists called “‘tickets’” (106); the
admission ticket was an article of faith so important to them that some members asked to be buried with them
(108). <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">16</hi> See Simpson on Wordsworth’s “dramatic method” 
(<hi rend="i">Wordsworth’s Historical Imagination</hi> 7) and Wolfson on how Wordsworth “stages . . . his
struggles with historical self-awareness” (435); her concept of Wordsworth’s “interrogative mode”
(439-40) may fit into an account of theatrical lyric soliloquy. Abelove mentions “Jean-Christophe Agnew’s
observations [in Agnew’s <hi rend="i">Worlds Apart</hi>] on the revival of what he calls a ‘theatrical
perspective’ among the literate classes in eighteenth-century England” (Abelove 106n42). On
eighteenth-century and romantic theatricality, see also Marshall, <hi rend="i">Figure of Theater</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Surprising Effects of Sympathy.</hi> On theatricality and Wordsworth, see Marshall, “The
Eye-Witnesses of <hi rend="i">The Borderers</hi>,” Parker, and Jacobus.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Barish 159. Morton Paley suggested to me that Methodist
anti-theatricality lies firmly within this tradition, which has its foundations in Plato; on the “Platonic
foundations” of anti-theatrical sentiment, see Barish 5-37.</note></p>
              <p>Situating romantic lyrics in the context of Methodist religious exercises makes it more
likely that the “egotistical sublime” was conceived of as a public rather than a private affair, with the
poets expecting to have scrutinized the spirituality of the speaker portrayed, and with residual, unconscious
anxieties over the contradiction between private meaning and public form. Was such self-expression a radical
political act? That is a real question. For the Methodists, the weekly public relation of their spiritual
trials was something they “liked to do [and something] they found ‘comfortable’” (Abelove 94). Such
“recollection in [the] tranquility” of each other’s eyes was for plebeian Methodists a rhetorical mode
enabling the assertion of their interests, and whether such self-assertion defused or encouraged radicalism is
perhaps still up for grabs. But, to take a cue from Abelove, we can only begin to listen to their interests by
assuming that the “Puritan relation made continuous” in their diaries, memoirs, and spiritual letters is
capable of communicating their needs and wants.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>III. What is a Poet? . . .<lb/>
He is a man speaking to men<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">18</hi> William Wordsworth, Preface to <hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads</hi> 138.
These two lines do not appear in the 1800 version, but rather in the much expanded Preface of 1802.</note>
	</title>
              </head>
              <p>The cultural debate carried on before and during the romantic period over poetry’s relation
to class and gender has been described in all its material detail by Donna Landry in <hi rend="i">The Muses of
Resistance.</hi> But this debate rarely enters into arguments about Blake and Wordsworth’s alleged sexism,
classism, anti-classism or feminism. To begin with, no studies have been done on how the early romantics
responded to female writers’ poetry: it’s as if the only women writers they knew were Dorothy Wordsworth
and Mary Wollstonecraft. Wordsworth’s praise for the poetry of Anne Finch, Countess of Winchilsea, situates
her very much in the landscape of his predecessors, right up there with Pope: “Now, it is remarkable,”
Wordsworth says, in his Essay Supplementary to the Preface of 1815, “that, excepting the nocturnal Reverie
of Lady Winchilsea, and a passage or two in the Windsor Forest of Pope, the poetry of the period intervening
between the publication of the Paradise Lost and the Seasons does not contain a single new image of external
nature . . .” (73). Wordsworth’s relation to Pope as a literary predecessor has been well documented
(Chandler, “Pope”; Griffin). But Wordsworth’s relation to Finch remains unexplored, despite his praise
for her in the Essay Supplementary and elsewhere.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">19</hi> The connection has been noted by scholars interested in Finch. Thus,
Roger Lonsdale points out that in the only anthology of poetry which Wordsworth compiled, an anthology
compiled for Lady Mary Lowther in 1819 and not published until 1905, “seventeen of the fifty poems he
included were by Lady Winchilsea. In October 1829, [Wordsworth] told Alexander Dyce that he was ‘especially
partial’ to [Finch] and had ‘perused her Poems frequently’. A few months later he sent Dyce detailed
comments on her verse and in May 1830 wrote that ‘her style in rhyme is often admirable, chaste, tender, and
vigorous; and entirely free from sparkle, antithesis and . . . over-culture” (qtd. in Lonsdale 6).
                                    <p>When Wordsworth wrote to Dr. Robert Anderson in 1814 asking him, on
behalf of himself, Coleridge and Southey, to expand his edition of English poetry, he asked him to include
poems by “Lady Winchelsea” (154). In 1829, Wordsworth tentatively approached Dionysius Lardner, compiler
of <hi rend="i">The Cabinet Cyclopaedia of Eminent Literary and Scientific Men</hi>, with the idea of
contributing “an Account of the Deceased Poetesses of Great Britain—with an Estimate of their Works,”
but decided not to undertake the project (4). Later that year, he asked Alexander Dyce for the “honor of
being consulted by [him]” on a second edition of <hi rend="i">Selections from the Poetry of English
Ladies.</hi> “By accident, I learned lately that you had made a Book of Extracts, which I had long wished
for an opportunity and industry to execute myself” (157).</p></note></p>
              <p>Marlon Ross’s <hi rend="i">The Contours of Masculine Desire: Romanticism and the Rise of
Women’s Poetry</hi> tries to correct such myopia in criticism of the romantics, primarily by adding women to
the list of poets writing at the time: Hannah More, Anna Barbauld, Felicia Hemans, Joanna Baillie, Letitia
Elizabeth Landon. But Ross’s study is marred by his ignorance of eighteenth-century female poets. He claims
that a tradition of what he calls “feminine poetry” was born during the romantic period: he mentions some
of the “Augustan foremothers” (193) influencing Barbauld and More (Lady Mary Wortley Montagu is the only
one he actually discusses), but argues that women did not begin publishing poetry for the most part until the
1780s (187-91). This would be quite a surprise to Roger Lonsdale: “From the 1730s, for various reasons,
women began to find it easier and more acceptable to publish their verse” (xxvi). Lonsdale ruthlessly
excerpts long poems, and claims to have been faced with terrible editorial choices about whom to exclude from
his 550-page volume of eighteenth-century women poets. Women did not begin to publish poetry in the 1780s, as
Ross claims; they began 40 years earlier. If anything, the number of published volumes of occasional verse
written by women of the working classes declined after 1796 (Landry 276-80).</p>
              <p>Although readers can be grateful to Ross for his discussion of female poets important during
the romantic period and yet ignored by us now, his account of eighteenth-century women’s poetry is
inaccurate. He says that, besides Aphra Behn, Eliza Haywood, and a group of women known as the blue-stockings
(Elizabeth Vesey, Elizabeth Carter, Frances Boscawen, and Elizabeth Montagu), the women “who presumed to
write poetry . . . were only a handful from the most privileged class, and their urge to write was usually
limited to their diaries and journals.” This would be a surprise to Landry: “In eighteenth-century Britain
a specific form of literary production emerges, the publication by subscription of volumes of verse by
laboring-class women” (11); it began with the publication in 1739 of “The Women’s Labour,” a poem
written to Stephen Duck by Mary Collier, “the Petersfield washerwoman,” as she was called. Although
seventeenth-century women writers may have been few and confined to the upper classes, Ross erroneously
assumes the same to be true of women writers of the eighteenth century: “There were in fact dozens of women
at all social levels who, with variable ambition and competence, [wrote] verse and, by one means or another,
found their way into print” (Lonsdale xxi). Can Ross have adequately “chart[ed] the rise of a uniquely
feminine poetics out of the specific historical circumstances of eighteenth-century British culture” (13)
based on Lady Mary Wortley Montagu?</p>
              <p>Ross’s argument would also have been a surprise to eighteenth-century Britons. Late in the
seventeenth century, when there were as Ross claims only a few, upper-class publishing female poets, John
Dunton’s <hi rend="i">Athenian Mercury</hi> encouraged women’s intellectual endeavors by inviting them to
ask questions of the members of the Athenian Society who ostensibly edited the journal (actually Dunton
himself was editor).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">20</ref> The 
<hi rend="i">Mercury</hi>
	<pb id="p27-56" n="56"/>
explicitly defended the idea that women can think as well as men even though less educated (3.13, Sept. 8
1691; 5.3, Dec. 8, 1691), insisting “that we have receiv’d <hi rend="i">Questions of as great weight and
concern from their Sex, as from any of ours</hi>. . . . ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">21</ref> The Athenian Society maintained that women could become as learned and
accomplished as men (Dunton, <hi rend="i">Supplement</hi> 24; Gildon, <hi rend="i">Oracle</hi> 382-83), and
entertained questions like “Whether Sappho or Mrs. Behn were the b[est] Poetess?” (5.13, Jan. 12, 1691
[1692]). Further, it indirectly encouraged women to write poetry: the Athenian Society encouraged “the
Ingenious of Either Sex” to write to them in verse by proposing to answer any poetical queries with verse of
the same form.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">22</ref> Lonsdale notes that
“Elizabeth Singer Rowe . . . [was able to] anticipate the opportunities offered by the developing periodical
press at a later period by sending . . . large quantities of her verse for anonymous publication . . . in John
Dunton’s <hi rend="i">Athenian Mercury</hi>” (xxii).</p>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Early in the <hi rend="i">Athenian Mercury</hi>’s history, women were
invited to send questions by a change in the journal’s title. To the original title, “The 
<corr type="emend">Athenian</corr> Gazette or Casuistical Mercury, Resolving all the most Nice and Curious questions
Propos’d by the Ingenious,” Dunton added “of Either Sex” (2.17, April 19, 1691, advertisement; see
also the title page to vol. 2). In the eighteenth volume, the <hi rend="i">Mercury</hi> announced that it
would devote papers published on “the first Tuesday in every month” to answering only questions received
“from the Fair Sex” (2.18, May 23, 1691); other papers answered questions from both sexes.
                                    <p>Jonathan Swift thought that there was indeed a society of
“far-exalted men” in charge of the journal (“Ode to the Athenian Society,” line 60, 48); Swift “was
put out,” Rogers says in his note to the poem, upon discovering that he had really written his Ode to
Dunton, “sole editor” of the <hi rend="i">Mercury</hi> (Rogers 604).</p></note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">21</hi> 5.3, Dec. 8, 1691. The <hi rend="i">Mercury</hi>’s protestations on
behalf of the “other” sex seem to be serious—the Society argues very well that “the soul of woman”
cannot be “inferiour to the Soul of Man”—but Dunton includes in the paper a letter from a woman asking
how to cure her corns, which provides the <hi rend="i">Mercury</hi> with the opportunity to indulge in a
little misogyny: one of the “many <hi rend="i">weighty</hi> Reasons assigned for this sore Calamity,” the
Society says sardonically, is that woman is “a Flinty-hearted Creature.”</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Dunton decided upon this procedure 5.1, 1 Dec., 1691; 5.11, 5 Jan., 1691
[1692]. In examining only the first year and a half of <hi rend="i">Mercuries</hi>, I was able to find
examples of poetical questions which were explicitly written by women in 8.6, 17 Sept., 1692; 8.21, 8 Nov.,
1692.</note>
              <p>Although the publication of female poets did not begin in earnest until the 1730s, women were
beginning to publish verse right at the beginning of the eighteenth century. At least one of Charles
Gildon’s collections (1701) contained poems written by women other than Aphra Behn (Anne Finch, Mrs.
Wharton); <hi rend="i">The Nine Muses</hi>, a collection of “Poems written by nine several ladies upon the
death of the late famous John Dryden,” appeared in 1700 and contained “Poems by Mrs. Manley, Lady Pierce,
Mrs. Field [Sarah Fyge Egerton], Mrs. Pix, Mrs. C. Trotter [Catherine Trotter Cockburn], and Mrs. D. E.” In
the 1750s, there was a spate of books printed about women who write poetry.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">23</ref> Among them, George Ballard’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs of
Several Ladies</hi> (1752) was printed 27 years before the appearance of the first volumes of Johnson’s 
<hi rend="i">Lives of the Poets.</hi> Volumes called <hi rend="i">Poems on Several Occasions</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">24</ref> which were published before 1780 were written
by: Katherine Philips (1664; 1667 [rpt. 1669, 1678, 1710]; 1743); Aphra Behn (1684), Mary Barber (1734, rpt.
1735), Mary Chudleigh (1703, rpt. 1709, 1722), Elizabeth Carter (1738; 1762, rpt. 1766, 4th ed. 1789),
Catharine Trotter Cockburn (1751), Sarah Fyge Egerton (1703, rpt. 1706), Mary Jones (1750), Mary Leapor (1748,
1751), Anne Killigrew (1686), Mary Monck (1716), Margaret Lucas Cavendish, Duchess of Newcastle (1653, rpt.
1664, 1668), Laetitia Pilkington (1748-1754), Elizabeth Singer Rowe (1696, rpt. 1736, 1738, 1759; 1736, rpt.
six times in England by 1759, three times in the United States by 1784; 1734, rpt. 4 times by 1749, enlarged
and rpt. 1750, 1756, 1772), Eliza Fowler Haywood (1724), and Joan Philips (1679, rpt. 1682), just to name a
few. There were so many women writers, and enough people interested in them, that a collection of poetry
devoted exclusively to women poets was published in 1755.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">25</ref> This poetry was not just published but discussed: the poetry of Mary Leapor, a cookmaid
who died in 1746, for example, was noted, reprinted and discussed throughout the second half of the century,
by Samuel Richardson, Christopher Smart in <hi rend="i">The Midwife</hi> (1750), John Duncombe in 
<hi rend="i">The Feminead</hi> (1754), Alexander Dyce in <hi rend="i">Specimens of British Poetesses</hi> (1827),
Frederic Rowton in <hi rend="i">The Female Poets of Great Britain</hi> (1848); by the <hi rend="i">Monthly
Review</hi> (1749, 1751), <hi rend="i">The Lady’s Poetical Magazine</hi> (1782), <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s
Magazine</hi> (1784), and <hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Magazine</hi> (1837).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">23</hi> See Ballard, Colman and Thornton, Duncombe, Shiels. Shiels’s 
<hi rend="i">Lives</hi> was attributed to Theophilus Cibber; according to Lonsdale, it contained the biographies
of 15 women, Anne Finch among them (Lonsdale xxix, 5). Ferguson has noticed this “mid-century burgeoning of
sympathetic male interest in women authors,” and adds two more: Thomas Armory’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs of
Several Ladies of Great Britain</hi> (1755) and an anonymous <hi rend="i">Biographium Femineum</hi> (1766)
(Ferguson 359).</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">24</hi> For variations on this title in specific cases, please see the list of
Works Cited.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Also, Dodsley’s <hi rend="i">Collection of Poems</hi> (1748) contained
poems by women, and a poetic manifesto, written by Anna Seward’s father Thomas, called “The Female Right
to Literature” (2.296-302; see Lonsdale xxix).</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Landry 78. On Samuel Richardson’s introduction of Leapor’s poetry to
Christopher Smart, and on Richardson’s letters about Leapor whose poetry he printed, see Rizzo
(24-25).</note></p>
              <p>It is within this context that high romantic writers wrote: they were responding to debates
over “natural genius” in these women writers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">27</ref> Ruminations over the problem of natural poetry first took place in discussing women
writers who were considered “natural” because uneducated. “Stephen Duck,” Landry writes,
<q>
was presented to the world with a long covering narrative by the Rev. Joseph Spence, making much of his class
privations and his thus nearly incredible poetic genius. . . . Duck’s female counterparts [i.e., female
laboring-class poets] . . . . come down to us [as] . . . . the curious productions of a ‘natural genius,’
a working-class prodigy . . . As Morag Shiach has observed, polite interest in this poetry in the eighteenth
century lay in the extent to which it could “support particular theories about the relations between nature
and poetic writing, rather than in any desire to re-evaluate the cultural and social role of the
peasantry.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Lonsdale xxvii-xxix; Landry 18-22, 255-56, 262-67.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Shiach 6, qtd. in Landry 4.</note></q>
“And my thoughts naturly fall into Rime,” a seventeenth-century poet, Hester Wyat wrote, “Rude and
unpolish’t from my pen they flow / So artless I my native tongue scarce know”—I’m so natural, she says
sarcastically, I barely know how to talk.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">29</hi> See Greer, ed., 6. This particular poem of Hester Wyat’s may have been
published for the first time in Greer’s anthology <hi rend="i">Kissing the Rod</hi>, but by the time Colman
and Thornton published their anthology in 1755, the idea that women poets were natural, unaffected, and
uncultivated was common coin (Colman and Thornton, iii-iv; Lonsdale, xxix).</note></p>
              <p>The romantics inherit the debate about natural diction on this ground, and perhaps a lot of
what they say about “effeminacy” is an attempt to change the ground. It is sexist for Wordsworth to speak
of poets as if they were only men, and only spoke to men. Yet in the Preface and Appendix to 
<hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads</hi>, Wordsworth uses “men” most often to mean ordinary people. What is the
political valence of calling common people “men” in a culture which is in the process of feminizing the
lower classes? In a culture which insists that unlettered female (and lower-class) male poets are “natural
geniuses,” effeminate, and interesting not because of their poetry but only because of the oddity that they,
as lower-class men and women, have the capacity to produce poetry at all—is it sexist <hi rend="i">then</hi>
to assert that natural diction is manly? is it patronizing <hi rend="i">then</hi> to idealize rustic speech as
poetic? Potentially not. Attributing manliness to ordinary language and defending it as poetic is potentially
in fact feminist and anti-classist: when feminine” is a pejorative term, it may be feminist to call a female
“masculine”; it may be anti-classist to resist the feminization of the lower classes by calling them real
men, and their language the language of real thought. Studying the debates surrounding laboring-class, male
and female poets changes—dramatically, I would say—the meaning of Wordsworth’s prefaces.</p>
              <p>But studying laboring-class, female poets provides an objective basis for arguments about
romantic ideology in
<pb id="p27-57" n="57"/>
another way as well. Ann Yearsley, also known as the “milkwoman from Bristol” (Landry 120) was first
patronized and later dropped by Hannah More (16-22). Blake’s “Nurse’s Song” in 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and his “Nurses Song” in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> would be profitably
discussed in the context of Yearsley’s <hi rend="i">To Mira, On the Care of Her Infant</hi> (1796).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">30</ref> Landry discusses Yearsley’s poem in
connection with the Blessed Babe passage of <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>, showing how these idealizations of
mothers (Yearsley’s from the mother’s point of view, Wordsworth’s from the child’s) depend upon the
exclusion of the laboring-class, hired “mother,” the wetnurse (264), who then returns as an evil threat to
the child in Yearsley’s poem and perhaps, I would say, in the nurses’ songs written by Blake. 
<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Lonsdale was only able to provide an excerpt from the poem; Landry discusses it
in great detail, 260-67, especially the figure of the nurse, 266.</note></p>
              <p>Yearsley, Wordsworth, and Blake all participate in and resist this consolidation of the
bourgeois family by “abjecting the lower-class nursemaid,” visible to us in Yearsley’s poem because of
the blatant contradiction between her attack on laboring-class hirelings and her own self-construction, in
other poems, as “Lactilla, the savage milkwoman and resentful antagonist of the propertied classes”
(Landry 266). Here one can see how listening to the voices of laboring-class female poets, however
contradictory, can bring about greater objectivity in the study of canonical poets: classist and antifeminist
exclusions become especially visible when they deprive the author of a place in her own poem; Yearsley’s 
<hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi> thereby provides a model for such exclusions, and resistances to them, that they might be
visible elsewhere.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>IV. How can I be defiled when I reflect thy image pure?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">31</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> 3: 16
(E 47).</note>
	</title>
              </head>
              <p>One might expect that neoclassical rhetoric, with its obvious privileging of the upper
classes—its “overcultured” allusiveness and diction; its tendency, for example, to represent the lower
classes satirically, as clowns or buffoons, or to exclude them from view altogether—would be inhospitable to
laboring-class poets. However, Roger Lonsdale and Margaret Doody describe an entirely different state of
affairs. “In view of the rising flood of publications by both women and undereducated men” in the 1730s,
Lonsdale says, “(the situation deplored by Pope in the <hi rend="i">Dunciad</hi>), it is clear that the high
ideals of Augustanism, ‘polite’ taste and ‘correctness,’ did little to inhibit many writers and their
readers” (xxvii). In fact, Doody argues persuasively that Augustan satire and neoclassical style enabled
lower-class and middling women writers of both the early and late eighteenth century to find a voice
(“Swift”; review). While one would think that learning to imitate educated, upper-class modes would
silence the interests of “these laboring women, these upstarts, these cookmaids, laundresses, field hands,
and women of obscure parentage” (5) discussed by Landry, it does not. They are able to use neoclassical
conventions for subversive purpose:
<q>
Writing verse that ventriloquizes and thus challenges the verse forms and values of mainstream culture is a
way of speaking out, and of altering social discourse. This is ventriloquism in the sense employed by Margaret
Doody and others, that is, ventriloquism with a subversive twist. It is as if the dummy did not merely serve
to demonstrate the master’s skill at speaking through another’s body, but took on a life of its own, began
to challenge the master by altering the master’s text. (6)
</q></p>
              <p>Thus, pastoral poetry became a vehicle for class protest as can be seen in Stephen Duck’s
<hi rend="i">The Thresher’s Labour</hi> discussed by Raymond Williams and in works by the female poets
Landry discusses, despite (or perhaps because of) the tendency of pastoral poetry to obscure labor from view.
As Williams has shown in <hi rend="i">The Country and the City</hi> (32), the pastoral form represses agrarian
labor by deploying images of an edenic nature freely fumishing forth by its own agency a bountiful store. The
pastoral thus idealizes class oppression out of existence (Williams 32). However, in <hi rend="i">The
Thresher’s Labour</hi> (1736), Duck put the laborers’ “toil” back into the pastoral landscape
(Williams 32, 88). Mary Collier’s <hi rend="i">The Woman’s Labour: An Epistle to Mr. Stephen Duck</hi>
(1739) shows that female labor is doubly invisible in the pastoral: even Duck himself, in his protesting
modification of that tradition, excludes women’s labor from view. Collier “reformulat[ed] the plebeian
georgic mode in the service of laboring women” (Landry 76) by putting female labor back into the landscape
of pastoral poetry.</p>
              <p>In detailed analyses of Collier’s use of Duck and Mary Leapor’s use of Pope, Landry
demonstrates that writing was for these women and others like them “a site of resistance.” Leapor was
probably dismissed from service at Weston Hall for her writing. One of her poems describes a servant’s
defiance of her master’s injunction to stop writing. The poem imitates Pope’s <hi rend="i">First Satire of
the Second Book of Horace</hi>, which represents his refusal to stop writing: Pope’s poem “enables
Leapor’s defiance, and perhaps her dismissal from service” (Landry 102). The examples of Collier and
Leapor justify Landry’s assumption of the following premise:
<q>
[W]riting that has been dismissed as derivative, conventional, or imitative needs now to be reread for its
dialogic, innovative, and critical possibilities, for its muted protests and attempts at subversion, its
curtailed yet incorrigible desires. . . . If Collier turns the georgic to plebeian feminist protest against
male workers’ scorn and refusal even to “see” women’s labor as productive, Leapor turns the pastoral
dialogue, the neoclassical epistle and the country-house poem to surprisingly unconventional ends. (7, 13)
</q></p>
              <p>Yet the radical potential of these poems is not always simply available, as in the case of
Collier’s insistence that women laborers work hard, and Leapor’s demand that she be allowed to write.
Despite a female poet’s conscious desire to adopt bourgeois values, as in the case of Yearsley’s poem on
mothering, her text “tell[s] a different story, of the politicization of the laboring-class writer
encountering bourgeois subjectivity and making a contradictory,
<pb id="p27-58" n="58"/>
sometimes radical accommodation to it” (21): the poem remains a site of conflict despite the poet’s
conscious desire to adopt the values she portrays. In the case of the female poet’s direct appropriation of
conventions and male poet’s voices for her own ends, for the sake of protesting her condition, or in the
case of her attempt to fit herself into those conventions and voices, with contradictory results—in either
case, “[b]eing ravished by the master’s text means empowerment for the unknown female poet” (50):
<q>
For the female laboring poet, transference on to a poetic text often involves a class-conscious dynamic
compounded of ambition and humility, eroticism and homage. Ravished by the beauty of a poetic discourse which
is alien to her, and from which she is often specifically excluded, yet ironically aware of the space occupied
within that discourse by subservient female figures in the form of muses, she raids and ravishes by both
praising and appropriating what she admires. (46)
</q>
The ravished laboring female poet does not “reflect [the master’s] image pure,” but, on the contrary,
ravishes it right back; her desire to ravish “the great male bard” (Landry 46) precisely enables her to
use traditional literary forms to articulate her own demands.</p>
              <p>Both Landry and Abelove describe a relation of desire between plebeians and the
fathers—Wesley on the one hand, Pope and Duck on the other—which enables British plebeians to manipulate a
form—be it Methodist spirituality, or neoclassical conventions—in order to express their needs. The
stunning results, Abelove’s and Landry’s access to histories previously unavailable to us and the
potential for greater objectivity in analyses of canonical poets provided by these histories, offer a twofold
lesson to romanticist new historical critics, articulated by Levinson in her retrospective on the limitations
and achievements of new historicism.</p>
              <p>New historicists certainly declare their partisanship in battles against other contemporary
critics, but they do not articulate it in their analyses of the past. Landry and Abelove are firmly on the
side of the lower classes whose protests against and refusals of sexual, gender, and class oppression they are
determined to recover. New historicists are not: in trying not to impose a predetermined point of view on the
past, they evince what Cohen has called a “commitment to arbitrary connectedness” of texts and events; as
it turns out, Levinson says, this refusal to use “some . . . model of epochal relatedness,” be it “a
dynamic concept of ideology on the one hand, [or] of structural determination on the other” (Levinson 20),
constitutes a refusal to take sides, a refusal to decide whether the lower-classes effectively subvert or are
always already contained by the dominant culture (Cohen 34). By their partisanship, Abelove and Landry give us
objective history, whereas many romantic new historicists do not. About the failure of new historicists to
take sides, Levinson concludes:
<q>
It is precisely our failure to articulate a critical field that sights <hi rend="i">us</hi> even as we compose
<hi rend="i">it</hi>, that brings back the positivism, subjectivism and relativism of the [old] historicist
methodology. (20)
</q>
The new historicists’ refusal of partisanship with their objects of study leaves them out of the objective
field of view—they are making another stab at the old positivist view of objectivity, unwittingly trying to
deny that objects can only be viewed from a perspective. Instead they use their objects of study in an
imaginary battle. This imaginary partisanship of us against them vitiates the history they would present.</p>
              <p>Second, Abelove and Landry do not equate representation or form with ideology. Both of them
reject, for example, Thompson’s assessment “of working-class religion, particularly Methodism and
evangelicalism, in the latter part of the eighteenth century as ‘the chiliasm of despair.’”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">32</ref> Mary Collier writes poetry both to articulate
“resignation to continued servitude” and to protest the occlusion of female labor; this “may strike us
as paradoxical,” Landry says, “but that sense of paradox marks the difference of our historical moment
from hers” (76). Gallagher has shown that it is part of our historical moment to be suspicious over whether
“certain forms of subjectivity that [feel] oppositional” actually are oppositional. Landry and Abelove
would say that there is something to be gained first in assuming that oppressed people of the past had the
power, if not to oppose outright, at least to resist and modify the terms of their oppression, and second in
figuring out what transferences, what “loves,” enabled them to do so. Partisanship is necessary to an
objective recovery of the past, but it must be partisanship with the subjects of histories so far neglected,
not the partisanship of us against them, now against then, critics of ideology against an always already
ideological literary form. <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Landry 74; see also Abelove 119, qtd. 21-22
above. Landry quotes Thompson’s discussion of Joanna Southcott who prophesied during the late 1790s and
early 1800s. Thompson sees the evangelism of the earlier eighteenth-century as containing “dormant seeds of
political Radicalism”; but for Thompson those seeds remain dormant in Methodism because of John Wesley,
without whom “19th-century Non-conformity might have assumed a more intellectual and democratic form”(<hi
rend="i">The Making of the English Working Class</hi> 36-37).</note></p>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Abelove, Henry. “Some Speculations on the History of Sexual Intercourse During the Long
Eighteenth Century in England.” <hi rend="i">Genders</hi> 6 (1989): 125-30.</p>
                <p>Abrams, M. H. “The Spirit of the Age.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Reconsidered: Selected
Papers from the English Institute.</hi> Ed. Northrop Frye. New York: Columbia UP, 1963. 26-72. Rpt. in 
<hi rend="i">The Correspondent Breeze: Essays on English Romanticism.</hi> New York: W. W. Norton, 1984.
44-75.</p>
                <p>Aers, David. “Coleridge and the Egg that Burke Laid: Ideological Collusion and Opposition
in the 1790s.” <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 9.2 (1983): 152-63.</p>
                <p>Ballard, George. <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Several Ladies of Great Britain who have been
Celebrated for their Writings or Skill in the Learned Languages, Arts, and Sciences.</hi> Oxford: W. Jackson,
1752. Rpt. 1775, with the title <hi rend="i">Memoirs of British Ladies who have been [etc.].</hi> London: T.
Evans, 1775.</p>
                <p>Barber, Mary. <hi rend="i">Poems on Several Occasions.</hi> London: Printed for C.
Rivington, 1734. Rpt. 1735.</p>
                <p>Barish, Jonas. <hi rend="i">The Anti-theatrical Prejudice.</hi> Berkeley: U of California
P, 1981.</p>
                <pb id="p27-59" n="59"/>
                <p>Behn, Aphra. <hi rend="i">Poems upon Several Occasions: With a Voyage to the Island of
Love. By Mrs. A. Behn.</hi> London: Printed for R. Tonson and J. Tonson, 1684.</p>
                <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Eds.
David Erdman and Harold Bloom. Newly rev. ed. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday/Anchor, 1982. Referred to in the
text as “E.”</p>
                <p>Burke, Edmund. <hi rend="i">Reflections on the Revolution in France.</hi> Ed. Conor Cruise
O’Brien. New York: Viking/Penguin, 1968.</p>
                <p>Butler, Marilyn. Introductory Essay. <hi rend="i">Burke, Paine, Godwin, and the Revolution
Controversy.</hi> Ed. Marilyn Butler. New York: Cambridge UP, 1984. 1-17.</p>
                <p>Carter, Elizabeth. <hi rend="i">Poems upon Particular Occasions.</hi> London: E. Cave,
1738.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Poems on Several Occasions.</hi> London: J.
Rivington, 1762. 2nd ed. To which are appended <corr type="emend">nos.</corr> 44 and 100 of <hi rend="i">The Rambler</hi> written by
her. London: J. Rivington, 1766. 4th ed. 1789.</p>
                <p>Cantor, Paul. “Stoning the Romance: The Ideological Critique of Nineteenth-Century
Literature.” <hi rend="i">Contemporary Perspectives on Romanticism.</hi> Spec. issue of <hi rend="i">South
Atlantic Quarterly</hi> 88 (1989): 705-20.</p>
                <p>Cartwright, John. <hi rend="i">The Legislative Rights of the Commonalty Vindicated. The
English Radical Tradition 1763-1914.</hi> Ed. S. MacCoby. London: Nicholas Kaye, 1952.</p>
                <p>Cavendish, Margaret (Lucas), Duchess of Newcastle. <hi rend="i">Poems and Fancies.</hi>
London: Printed by T.R. for F. Martin and F. Alleystrye, 1653. Rpt. as <hi rend="i">Poems, and phancies.</hi>
2nd. rev. ed. London: William Wilson, 1664. Rpt. as <hi rend="i">Poems; or Several Fancies in Verse.</hi> 3rd
ed. London: A. Maxwell, 1668.</p>
                <p>Chandler, James. <hi rend="i">Wordsworth’s Second Nature: A Study of the Poetry and
Politics.</hi> Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1984.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> “The Pope Controversy: Romantic Poetics and the English
Canon.” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 10 (1984): 481-509.</p>
                <p>Chudleigh, Mary. <hi rend="i">Poems on Several Occasions. By the Lady Chudleigh.</hi>
London: Printed by W.B. for Bernard Lintott, 1703. London: Printed by D.L. for Bernard Lintott, 1709. 3rd
corrected ed. London: Printed for Bernard Lintott, 1722.</p>
                <p>Cockburn, Mrs. Catharine (Trotter). <hi rend="i">The Works of Mrs. Catharine Cockburn,
theological, moral, dramatic and poetical, revised and published</hi> . . . Ed. Thomas Birch. London: Printed
for J. and P. Knapton, 1751.</p>
                <p>Cohen, Walter. “Political Criticism of Shakespeare.” <hi rend="i">Shakespeare
Reproduced: The Text in History &amp; Ideology.</hi> Eds. Jean E. Howard, Marion F. O’Connor. New York:
Routledge, 1987. 18-46.</p>
                <p>Colman, George, and Bonnell Thornton, eds. <hi rend="i">Poems by Eminent Ladies,
Particularly: Mrs. Barber, Mrs. Behn, Miss Carter, etc.</hi> London: R. Baldwin, 1755. Courtesy of Cornell
University, Department of Rare Books.</p>
                <p>De Man, Paul. “The Resistance to Theory.” <hi rend="i">The Pedagogical Imperative:
Teaching as a Literary Genre.</hi> Spec. issue of <hi rend="i">Yale French Studies</hi> 63 (1982): 3-20. Rpt.
in <hi rend="i">The Resistance to Theory.</hi> Minneapolis: U of Minnesota P, 1986. 3-20.</p>
                <p>Dodsley, Robert. <hi rend="i">A Collection of Poems in Three Volumes by Several Hands.</hi>
2nd ed. London: J. Hughes, 1748. Courtesy of Cornell University, Department of Rare Books.</p>
                <p>Doody, Margaret Anne. Rev. of <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century Women Poets</hi>, ed. Roger
Lonsdale. <hi rend="i">The London Review of Books</hi> 2.24 (21 December 1989): 3-5.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> “Swift Among the Women.” <hi rend="i">Yearbook of
English Studies</hi> 18 (1988): 68-92.</p>
                <p>Duncombe, John. <hi rend="i">The Feminiad. A Poem.</hi> London: M. Cooper, 1754. Rpt. with
the title <hi rend="i">The Feminead: or, Female Genius. A Poem.</hi> London: Printed for R. and J. Dodsley,
1757.</p>
                <p>Dunton, John. <hi rend="i">The Athenian Gazette: Or Casuistical Mercury.</hi> Vols. 1-2.16
London: Printed for P. Smart, 1691. Vols. 2.17-5. London: Printed for John Dunton, 1691-1692. Courtesy of the
University of New Mexico Special Collections. Vol. 8. London: John Dunton, 1692. Courtesy of Cornell
University, Department of Rare Books.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Supplement to the First Volume of the Athenian
Gazette.</hi> London: John Dunton, 1691. Courtesy of Cornell University, Department of Rare Books.</p>
                <p>Egerton, Sarah Fyge. <hi rend="i">Poems on Several <corr type="emend">Occasions</corr> together with a pastoral, by
Mrs. S. F.</hi> London: J. Nutt, 1703 or 1706[?]. Rpt. as <hi rend="i">A Collection of Poems on Several
Occasions . . . by Mrs. Sarah Fyge Egerton.</hi> London: The Booksellers of London and Westminster, 1706.</p>
                <p>Ferguson, Moira. “‘The Cause of My Sex’: Mary Scott and the Female Literary
Tradition.” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 50 (1987): 359-77.</p>
                <p>Fischer, Michael. Rev. of <hi rend="i">Social Values and Poetic Acts</hi>, by Jerome J.
McGann, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989): 32-39.</p>
                <p>Fry, Paul. “History, Existence, and ‘To Autumn.’” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 25 (1986): 211-19.</p>
                <p>Fuss, Diana. <hi rend="i">Essentially Speaking: Feminism, Nature &amp; Difference.</hi> New
York: Routledge, 1989.</p>
                <p>Gallagher, Catherine. “Marxism and the New Historicism.” Veeser 37-48.</p>
                <p>Gildon, Charles. <hi rend="i">The Athenian Oracle: Being an Entire Collection of all the
Valuable Questions and Answers in the Old</hi> Athenian Mercuries. The Second Edition, more correct. Vol. 1.
London: Printed for Andrew Bell, 1704. Courtesy of Cornell University, Department of Rare Books.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">A New Miscellany of Original Poems, On Several
Occasions.</hi> London: Peter Buck, George Strahan, 1701. Courtesy of Cornell University, Department of Rare
Books.</p>
                <pb id="p27-60" n="60"/>
                <p>Greer, Germaine, Susan Hastings, Jeslyn Medoff, Melinda Sansone, eds. <hi rend="i">Kissing
the Rod: An Anthology of Seventeenth-Century Women’s Verse.</hi> London: Virago P, 1988.</p>
                <p>Griffin, Robert J. “Wordsworth’s Pope: The Language of his Former Heart.” 
<hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 54 (1987): 695-715.</p>
                <p>Goodwin, Albert. <hi rend="i">The Friends of Liberty: The English Democratic Movement in
the Age of the French Revolution.</hi> Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard UP, 1979.</p>
                <p>Haywood, Eliza (Fowler). <hi rend="i">The Works . . . Consisting of Novels, Letters, Poems,
and Plays.</hi> London: Printed for Dan. Browne Junr., Sam. Chapman, 1724.</p>
                <p>Jacobus, Mary. “‘That Great Stage Where Senators Perform’: <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>
and the Politics of Romantic Theater.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 22 (1983): 353-87. Rpt. in
<hi rend="i">Romanticism Writing and Sexual Difference: Essays on The Prelude.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, P,
1989. 33-68.</p>
                <p>Johnston, Kenneth R. “The Politics of ‘Tintern Abbey.’” <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth
Circle</hi> 14 (1983): 6-14.</p>
                <p>Jones, Mary. <hi rend="i">Miscellanies in Prose and Verse. By Mary Jones.</hi> Oxford:
Dodsley, 1750.</p>
                <p>Killigrew, Anne. <hi rend="i">Poems, by Mrs. Anne Killigrew.</hi> London: S. Lowndes,
1686.</p>
                <p>Kramnick, Isaac. <hi rend="i">The Rage of Edmund Burke: Portrait of An Ambivalent
Conservative.</hi> New York: Basic Books, 1977.</p>
                <p>Leapor, Mary. <hi rend="i">Poems Upon Several Occasions. By Mrs. Leapor of Brackley in
Northamptonshire.</hi> Vol. 1. London: J. Roberts, 1748. Vol. 2. Ed. Isaac Hawkins Browne. London: J. Roberts,
1751.</p>
                <p>Levinson, Marjorie. “Insight and Oversight: Reading ‘Tintern Abbey.’” 
<hi rend="i">Wordsworth’s Great Period Poems.</hi> Cambridge, Eng.: Cambridge UP, 1986. 14-57.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> “The New Historicism: Back to the Future.” 
<hi rend="i">Rethinking Historicism: Critical Readings in Romantic History.</hi> By Marjorie Levinson, Marilyn
Butler, Jerome McGann, and Paul Hamilton. New York: Basil Blackwell, 1989. 19-63.</p>
                <p>Lonsdale, Roger, ed. <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Women Poets: An Oxford Anthology.</hi>
New York: Oxford UP, 1989.</p>
                <p>McGann, Jerome. “Keats and the Historical Method in Literary Criticism.” 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 94 (1979): 988-1032. Rpt. in <hi rend="i">The Beauty of Inflections:
Literary Investigations in Historical Method and Theory.</hi> New York: Oxford UP, 1985. 17-65.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical
Investigation.</hi> Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1983.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Social Values and Poetic Acts: The Historical
Judgment of Literary Work.</hi> Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard UP, 1988.</p>
                <p>Macpherson, C. B. <hi rend="i">Burke.</hi> Past Masters Series. New York: Hill and Wang,
1980.</p>
                <p>Marshall, David. “The Eye-Witnesses of <hi rend="i">The Borderers.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 27 (1988): 391-98.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">The Figure of Theater.</hi> New York: Columbia
UP, 1986.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">The Surprising Effects of Sympathy.</hi>
Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1988.</p>
                <p>Meyers, Mitzi. “Reform or Ruin: ‘A Revolution in Female Manners.’” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture II.</hi> Ed. Harry C. Payne. Madison: U of Wisconsin P,
1982.</p>
                <p>Mill, John Stuart. “What is Poetry?” <hi rend="i">Critical Theory Since Plato.</hi> Ed.
Hazard Adams. New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1971. 537-43.</p>
                <p>Miller, Dan. Rev. of <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality.</hi> Ed. by Nelson
Hilton and Thomas Volger. <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 21 (1987-88): 116-24.</p>
                <p>Mohanty, S. P. “Us and Them: On the Philosophical Bases of Political Criticism.” 
<hi rend="i">The Yale Journal of Criticism</hi> 2.2 (1989): 1-31.</p>
                <p>Monck, Mary. <hi rend="i">Marinda. Poems and Translations upon Several Occasions.</hi>
London: J. Tonson, 1716.</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">The Nine Muses. Or Poems Written by Nine Several Ladies upon the Death of John
Dryden, Esq.</hi>, . . . Ed. Ric. Basset[?] London: Printed for Richard Basset, 1700.</p>
                <p>O’Gormon, Frank. <hi rend="i">Voters, Patrons, and Parties: The Unreformed Electoral
System of Hanoverian England 1734-1832.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1989.</p>
                <p>Parker, Reeve. “‘In some sort seeing with my proper eyes’: Wordsworth and the
Spectacle of Paris.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 27 (1988): 369-89.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> “Reading Wordsworth’s Power: Narrative and Usurpation in
<hi rend="i">The Borderers.</hi>” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 54 (1987): 299-331.</p>
                <p>Philips, Joan. <hi rend="i">Female Poems on Several Occasions. Written by Ephelia.</hi>
London: William Downing, 1679. 2nd ed. <hi rend="i">Female Poems.</hi> London: James Courtney, 1682.</p>
                <p>Philips, Katherine. <hi rend="i">The Crooked Sixpence.</hi> Ed. James Bramston. London: R.
Dodsley, 1743.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Poems. By the Incomparable Mrs. K. P.</hi>
London: Printed by J. G. for Rich. Marriott, 1664.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Poems by the Most Deservedly Admired Mrs
Katherine Philips the Matchless Orinda.</hi> London: Printed by J.M. for H. Herringman, 1667. Rpt. 1669.
London: H. Herringman, 1678. London: Printed for Jacob Tonson, 1710.</p>
                <p>Pilkington, Laetitia (Van Lewen). <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Mrs. Laetitia Pilkington, . . .
Written by Herself. Wherein are Occasionally Interspersed All Her Poems.</hi> Dublin, 1748. Rpt. London: R.
Griffits and G. Woodfall, 1748-54.</p>
                <p>Putnam, Hilary. “Objectivity and the Science/Ethics Distinction.” <hi rend="i">Realism
with a Human Face</hi>, by Hilary Putnam. Ed. James Conant. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard UP, 1990. 163-78.</p>
                <p>Rizzo, Betty W. “Christopher Smart, The ‘C.S.’ Poems, and Molly Leapor’s
Epitaph.” <hi rend="i">The Library</hi> 6th ser. 5 (1983): 22-31.</p>
                <pb id="p27-61" n="61"/>
                <p>Ross, Marlon. <hi rend="i">The Contours of Masculine Desire: Romanticism and the Rise of
Women’s Poetry.</hi> New York: Oxford UP, 1989.</p>
                <p>Rowe, Elizabeth (Singer). <hi rend="i">The History of Joseph.</hi> A poem. London: T.
Worrall, 1736. 2nd ed. London: Printed for T. Worrall. “2nd ed.” London: Printed for B.D., 1738. 3rd ed.
London: B. Dodsley, 1741. Rpt. with name of author added to title page. Dublin, 1742. London: B. Dodsley,
1744. London: D. Winter, 1759. Philadelphia: B. Franklin, 1739. Philadelphia: David Hall and William Sellers,
1767. Harford, 1784. [etc.]</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">The Miscellaneous Works in Prose and Verse of
Mrs. Elizabeth Rowe.</hi> Ed. Mr. Theophilus Rowe. London: R. Hett, et. al., 1734. London: Printed for R. Hett
and R. Dodsley, 1737. Rpt. 1739. 2nd ed. 1749. Enlarged, combined with <hi rend="i">The History of
Joseph.</hi> London: S. Birt, et. al., 1750. Rpt. 1756. New ed. London: Printed for J. Buckland, et. al.,
1772. [etc.]</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Poems on Several Occasions. Written by
Philomela.</hi> London: Printed for John Dunton, 1696. Rpt. as <hi rend="i">Philomela: Or, Poems by Mrs.
Elizabeth Singer (now Rowe).</hi> 2nd ed. London: E. Curll, 1736. Rpt. as <hi rend="i">Philomela; or
Poems.</hi> Dublin: S. Powell, 1738. Rpt. as <hi rend="i">Poems on Several Occasions.</hi> London: Printed for
D. Midwinter, 1759.</p>
                <p>Shiach, Morag. <hi rend="i">Discourse on Popular Culture: Class, Gender and History in the
Analysis of Popular Culture.</hi> Oxford: Polity P, 1989.</p>
                <p>Shiels, Robert. <hi rend="i">The Lives of the Poets of Great Britain and Ireland, to the
Time of Dean Swift, by Mr. Cibber.</hi> London: R. Griffiths, 1753.</p>
                <p>Simpson, David. “Literary Criticism and the Return to ‘History.’” 
<hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 14 (1988): 721-47.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Wordsworth’s Historical Imagination: The
Poetry of Displacement.</hi> New York: Methuen, 1987.</p>
                <p>Smith, Olivia. <hi rend="i">The Politics of Language 1791-1819.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P,
1984.</p>
                <p>Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty. “Sex and History in <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi> (1805):
Books IX to XIII.” <hi rend="i">Texas Studies in Language and Literature</hi> 23 (1981) 324-60. Rpt. in 
<hi rend="i">Post-Structuralist Readings of English Poetry.</hi> Eds. Richard Machin and Christopher Norris. New
York: Cambridge UP, 1987. 193-226.</p>
                <p>Swift, Jonathan. <hi rend="i">Jonathan Swift: The Complete Poems.</hi> Ed. Pat Rogers. New
Haven: Yale UP, 1983.</p>
                <p>Thomas, Keith. “Women and the Civil War Sects.” <hi rend="i">Past and Present</hi> 13
(1958): 42-62.</p>
                <p>Thompson, E. P. “Disenchantment or Default? A Lay Sermon.” <hi rend="i">Power and
Consciousness.</hi> Eds. Conor Cruise O’Brien and William Dean Vanech. New York: New York UP, 1969.
149-82.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> “Eighteenth Century English Society: Class Struggle
Without Class?” <hi rend="i">Social History</hi> 3 (1978): 133-65.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">The Making of the English Working Class.</hi>
New York: Random House/Pantheron, 1963.</p>
                <p>UEA English Studies Group (David Punter, David Aers, Robert Clark, Jonathan Cook, Thomas
Elsasser). “Strategies for Representing Revolution.” <hi rend="i">1789: Reading Writing Revolution.</hi>
Proceedings of the Essex Conference on the Sociology of Literature, July 1981. Colchester, Eng.: U of Essex,
1982. 81-100.</p>
                <p>Veeser, H. Aram, ed. <hi rend="i">The New Historicism.</hi> New York: Routledge, 1989.</p>
                <p>John Wesley’s Obituary. <hi rend="i">The Gentleman’s Magazine: And Historical
Chronicle</hi>, 61 Part I (March 1791): 282-85.</p>
                <p>Williams, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Country and the City.</hi> New York: Oxford UP,
1973.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Marxism and Literature.</hi> New York: Oxford
UP, 1977.</p>
                <p>Wolfson, Susan. “Questioning ‘the Romantic Ideology’: Wordsworth.” 
<hi rend="i">Revue Internationale de Philosophie</hi> 44 (3/1990, No. 174): 429-47.</p>
                <p>Wordsworth, William. “To Alexander Dyce.” 16 October 1829. Letter 474 in 
<hi rend="i">Letters, The Later Years, Part II.</hi> 156-58.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> “To Dionysius Lardner.” 12 January 1829. Letter 398 in
<hi rend="i">Letters, The Later Years, Part II.</hi> 4-5.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> “To Dr. Robert Anderson.” 17 September 1814. Letter 326
in <hi rend="i">The Letters of Willam and Dorothy Wordsworth.</hi> Ed. Ernest de Selincourt. 2nd rev. ed. Vol.
3. <hi rend="i">The Middle Years, Part II 1812-1820.</hi> Rev. by Mary Moorman, Alan G. Hill. Oxford:
Clarendon P, 1970. 151-55. 6 vols.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> Essay Supplementary to the Preface of 1815. 
<hi rend="i">Prose Works.</hi> Vol. 3. 62-107.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">The Letters of William and Dorothy
Wordsworth.</hi> Ed. Ernest de Selincourt. 2nd rev. ed. Vol. 5. <hi rend="i">The Later Years, Part II,
1829-1834.</hi> Rev. by Alan G. Hill. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1978. 6 vols.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> Preface to <hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads. The Prose Works of
William Wordsworth.</hi> Eds. W. J. B. Owen, J. W. Smyser. Vol. 1. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1974. 111-89. 3
Vols.</p>
                <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">The Prose Works of William Wordsworth.</hi>
Eds. W. J. B. Owen, J. W. Smyser. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1974. 3 vols.</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p27-62-63" n="62-63" rend="hidden"/>
        </div2>
      </div1> 
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
