<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.3.huntington</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Blake at the Huntington, Fall 1994</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1993-1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993/94</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <name>Stacy Nabors</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Paula R. Feldman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Robert Kiely</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>George Anthony Rosso</name>
              <name>Chris Rubinstein</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Welch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993-1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
      <pb id="p27-98" n="98"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">BLAKE AT THE HUNTINGTON, FALL 1994</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Over the last few years, the Huntington Library in San Marino, California, has disbound its
superb collection of Blake’s illuminated books. This procedure, required for purposes of long-term
conservation, has the happy consequence of permitting the display of individual plates from the Huntington’s
copies of <hi rend="i">All Religions are One, Songs of Innocence, The Book of Thel, Visions of the Daughters
of Albion, America, Songs of Experience, The Song of Los</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> An exhibition of
these works will be held in the Huntington Art Gallery from 27 September 1994 to 15 January 1995. “William
Blake’s Illuminated Prints,” curated by Robert N. Essick, will also include three of Blake’s 1795 color
prints: <hi rend="i">Lamech and His Two Wives</hi>, the magnificent impression of <hi rend="i">Satan Exulting
over Eve</hi>
<figure n="s-los.e.p4-8" id="s-los.e.illbk.04" work-copy="s-los.e" rend="db" width="754" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>Blake, <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, plate 8, copy E.</head>
	<figDesc>Color printed in 1795 from a copperplate, probably unincised, 23.5 × 17.5 cm. Huntington Library.
To be included in the Huntington’s exhibition, “Blake’s Illuminated Prints,” fall and winter
1994.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="houseofwilliamblake.27.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="306">
	<head>The House of William Blake, 17 South Molton Street, London W1Y 1DE</head>
</figure>
on loan from the J. Paul Getty Museum, and the recently cleaned Huntington impression of 
<hi rend="i">Hecate.</hi></p>
          <p>In conjunction with this major exhibition, the Huntington will host a symposium, “William
Blake’s Illuminated Books: Images and Texts,” on Saturday, 29 October 1994. W. J. T. Mitchell will deliver
the keynote address; the other speakers will be David Bindman, Anne K. Mellor, Tilottama Rajan, and Joseph
Viscomi. The presentations will be published in the <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>; a special
printing of the issue will be available for purchase from the Huntington.</p>
          <p>Harry N. Abrams, Inc., will publish <hi rend="i">Blake at the Huntington</hi> in fall 1994. This
paperback volume features 64 full-color reproductions of works by Blake in the Library and Art Gallery
collections, including a generous selection of plates from the illuminated books and the complete series of
water-color illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus, Nativity Ode</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost.</hi> Robert Essick has written an introduction and plate-by-plate commentary for this volume.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
