<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.3.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Another Rediscovered Small Color Print by William Blake</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1993-1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993/94</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <name>Stacy Nabors</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Paula R. Feldman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Robert Kiely</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>George Anthony Rosso</name>
              <name>Chris Rubinstein</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Welch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993-1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
    <pb id="p27-68" n="68"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title type="section"> 
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Another Rediscovered Small Color Print by William Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>A small color-printed version of the design at the head of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> plate
3—usually known as “Oh! Flames of Furious Desires” on the basis of an inscription, not by Blake himself,
on the back of the version from the collection of Sir Geoffrey Keynes now in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge
(B 261 <hi rend="i">4</hi>)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>—has
reappeared in a private collection. This print was acquired at Sotheby’s on 17 December 1970, lot 14, when
it was catalogued as being merely by “Blake,” at that time a polite way of saying that the work was not
thought to be by the artist indicated. However, a recent direct comparison between this work and the version
from the first copy of the Small Book of Designs in the British Museum (B 260 9) suggests that it is a genuine
second pull, similar in the color printing and largely following the British Museum print in the subsequent
application of water color and ink, probably from the point of a fine brush, to define the outlines. This
would relegate the version in the
<figure n="flames.27.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="241">
	<head>1. “‘Oh! Flames of Furious Desires,’ Plate 3 of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>,” c. 1796.</head>
	<figDesc>Color-printed relief etching finished in ink and water color, 6.1 × 9.9 cm. Private collection,
Great Britain.</figDesc>
</figure>
Fitzwilliam Museum, which I previously suggested<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> was a second pull from the original coloring, to third position in the sequence of pulls;
the coloring is thinner and the outlining in ink is more extensive, extending to the modeling of the back and
limbs, while the hair, unlike the dense, dark hair of the British Museum and newly discovered versions, is
looser and fairer. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> All references in this form are to Martin Butlin, 
<hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 1981, where the works are illustrated in the second
volume.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See Martin Butlin, “A New Color Print from the Small Book of Designs,”
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 26 (1992): 19.</note></p>
          <p>Unfortunately both the new version and the Fitzwilliam Museum version have been trimmed to the
border of the design so that there is no possibility of seeing whether the distinctive framing lines and page
numbers found in the second copy of the Small Book of Designs can identify whether either of these two designs
belonged to that copy. I had presumed that the Fitzwilliam Museum version came from the second copy of the
book but the closeness of the new version to that in the first copy in the British Museum suggests that it may
have been not only the second to be executed but also the print incorporated in the second book.</p>
          <p>One puzzle remains. The figure in the new version is distinguished by a small but quite distinct
female breast. No such feature appears in the Fitzwilliam Museum version although close inspection reveals
that there is a putative breast in the British Museum version. The possibility that the figure is female can
also be read into at least some of the copies of the original book of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> as well. Up to
now the figure has always been identified as a youth, for instance in the detailed analysis by David
Erdman,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> but the rediscovered design
introduces a new element of ambiguity. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The
Illuminated Blake</hi> (London: Oxford UP, 1975) 185.</note></p>
          <p>Suspicions that the new print might be a copy, like that in the Tate Gallery which is a direct
copy of the version in the Fitzwilliam Museum,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> are dispelled by the presence of a typically undefined pencil sketch on the back of the
paper, which is itself discolored, apparently from having been mounted on a wood-based card or board for a
considerable period. In style and apparent purpose the drawing is particularly close to that for the title
page of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> (B 232 <hi rend="i">verso</hi>) though it is difficult to identify
it with any more finished composition. It does, however, bear some resemblance to the skeletal form on plate 8
of <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827</hi> (Tate Gallery
Collections: Volume 5, London, 1990) 80-81, no. 24.</note></p>
          <figure n="revflames.27.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="388">
            <head>2. Reverse of “Oh! Flames of Furious Desires,” pencil on paper, 9.9 × 6.1 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Private collection, Great Britain.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
