<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.3.kiely</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed., George Cumberland, The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar: 
An African Tale in Two Parts</title>
        <author n="Kiely">Robert Kiely</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1993-1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993/94</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <name>Stacy Nabors</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Paula R. Feldman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Robert Kiely</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>George Anthony Rosso</name>
              <name>Chris Rubinstein</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Welch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993-1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
	<pb id="p27-82" n="82"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">
              <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">George Cumberland, <hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar: An
African Tale in Two Parts.</hi> Ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr., Montreal &amp; Kingston: McGill-Queen’s University
Press, 1991. 361 pp.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Robert <name>Kiely</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Had George Cumberland (1754-84?) lived in the sixteenth century he might have qualified as a
“Renaissance man.” Since, instead, he was an eighteenth-century man of parts and of leisure, heir to a
modest but sufficient income, neither a courtier nor a soldier, he is thought of as a gifted amateur, a
dabbler in many arts and sciences, a dilettante. His interest and talents ranged from poetry to physics,
travel writing to geology, political and social reform to painting and engraving. He was an inventor, a
collector of natural and artificial objects, a gentleman farmer, and, most of all, a prodigious writer of
essays, poems, journals, and narratives. He and Blake were evidently friends as early as 1780, and Blake’s
last engraving, 
<pb id="p27-83" n="83"/>
<corr type="emend">left unfinished</corr> at his death, was a message card to Cumberland.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar</hi>, as G. E. Bentley, Jr. shows in his
admirable edition of the text, has had a peculiar printing and publishing history. Part I was printed in 1798,
but withheld from publication by the author until 1810. Cumberland feared stirring up controversy and risking
prosecution for his radical ideas, yet when the text was finally published it aroused no controversy and
little interest. Part II, like much of Cumberland’s writing, remained in manuscript form until the
appearance of the present edition.</p>
          <p>The first problem facing a reader of Cumberland’s narrative, once past the fascinating
distractions of the author’s life and the odd history of the manuscripts, is to figure out what it is.
Bentley appropriately calls attention to its affinities with the utopian novel, the romance, and the romantic
novel. It is true that the subject matter and the narrator’s tone of voice can shift abruptly from Sir
Thomas More to Shelley and back again. Like Beckford’s <hi rend="i">Vathek</hi> and Godwin’s 
<hi rend="i">Caleb Williams</hi>, Cumberland’s narrative also contains touches of gothic and surreal
fantasy.</p>
          <p>Without the devastating clarity of Swift or the rich abundance of observed detail of Dickens, 
<hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar</hi> seems not simply heterogeneous but undecided. The reader is
less likely to feel like the observer of a Bakhtinian dialogic than like a traveler following a guide who
cannot make up his mind about where to go or how to get there. For this reason, the postmodern
reader—especially a reader of Borges or Eco—may be just the audience that Cumberland’s mysterious
manuscripts were waiting for.</p>
          <p>In Part I, “The Sophians,” a rich young Venetian named Memmo (a pun Pynchon or Barth might
envy) finds himself imprisoned in a stone castle somewhere in a kingdom resembling Egypt. His sole fellow
prisoner is Lycus (Like us?), an elderly
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
Greek, who has filled his years of captivity by decorating the walls, ceilings, and floors of the castle’s
interior with ingenious and elaborate architectural designs, “three dimensional sculptures,” and vistas.
Lycus is a master of trompe l’oeil. Indeed, everything about the castle, like everything about the
narrative, strains eerily for verisimilitude while showing itself to be hopelessly sealed off from
reality.</p>
          <p>In a further stage of removal, Lycus narrates for the benefit of Memmo (who later remembers and
records it) the story of his journey into the heart of Africa where he discovered the land of the Sophians.
Though the travel through jungles and encounters with African tribes anticipates H. Rider Haggard, the
descriptions of life among the Sophians mixes familiar eighteenth-century utopian dreams of peaceful communal
living and “natural religion” with fantasies of untroubled and unrepressed sexuality, union without
marriage, an exchange of partners without divorce, and a liberal, unembarrassed attitude toward the body.</p>
          <p>If the reader is led or misled into looking for a “center” in this many-layered invention, he
or she will not encounter the empty horror of Conrad’s <hi rend="i">Heart of Darkness</hi>, nor a simple
rationalistic moral. While “calmness,” “order,” and “tranquillity” have been attained by the
apparently ideal Sophian society, the agitations and unfulfilled desires of the Greek narrator and his
Venetian cellmate are never far from the surface of the text. In admiring the wholesome and unselfconscious
nudity of the Sophians, for example, Lycus cannot help leering. His preoccupation with “every fleshy
protuberance,” “the red, porous, and . . . warm points of the body,” and the perfect shapes worthy of
Phidias verges on soft porn because, for the storyteller, the objectified and dehumanized figures are
occasions of curiosity, longing, and forbidden pleasure. Insofar as the “perfect” society is described and
interpreted by an imperfect narrator, it floats in a Borgesian realm in which philosophical idealism, delight,
and frustration are permanently entangled.</p>
          <p>In Part II, “The Reformed,” Cumberland literally attempts to clean up his act. Lycus dies and
Memmo, the Venetian, escapes imprisonment and embarks on his own journey into the heart of Africa. The even
more “perfect” society that he encounters is composed of descendants of Italian followers of the
fourth-century monk Jovinius who attempted to reform the early Church, was declared a heretic, and escaped to
Africa with a band of disciples. The Jovinians do not drink wine, they have no fine arts, they spend long
hours at prayer in church, and they definitely do not practice nudity. Everyone lives simply, contributes to
the common well-being, and has a voice within a benevolent patriarchal “democracy.” In short, they sound
like eighteenth-century reformed Protestants, tranquilized Methodists, or talkative Quakers.</p>
          <p>The word most frequently repeated in “The Reformed” is “clean.” Houses, streets,
clothing, nature itself seem “cleaner” in the land of the Jovinians than elsewhere. It is understandable,
then, on one level, even if inconsistent with the apparent moral of the social allegory, that the Venetian
narrator grows homesick for his beautiful but tainted city. Memmo returns to Venice,
<pb id="p27-84" n="84"/>
immerses himself in its enchanting, melancholy, dank atmosphere and discovers to no one’s surprise that his
beloved has taken the veil. He retires to a family castle, committing himself to a life of celibacy and good
works—far enough from the Jovinians to idealize them, but close enough to the sullied Rialto for an
occasional visit. Though Cumberland has tried alternately to reproduce the scoured virtues of a Scandinavian
health spa and a sedate revival meeting in the heart of Africa, Memmo, his hero, recalls us to Venice and a
less ideal harmony, reflected, distorted, and rendered irresistable by murky, odiferous waters.</p>
          <p>On the surface, the Christianized Part II appears to be a repudiation of the pagan utopia of Part
I, and both a rejection of life in late eighteenth-century Europe and Britain. Yet the two parts of
Cumberland’s odd and entertaining narrative do, in the end, make a kind of sense together. They are not so
much the fantasies of a mad genius nor the visions of a political radical as the dreams of a man who
frequently wishes his times were different (freer, healthier, more rational, more peaceful, more fun), but
who, at the end of the day, is comfortable enough to settle at the edge of things as they are.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
