<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.3.feldman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Felicia Hemans and the Mythologizing of Blake’s Death</title>
        <author n="Feldman">Paula R. Feldman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1993-1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993/94</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <name>Stacy Nabors</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Paula R. Feldman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Robert Kiely</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>George Anthony Rosso</name>
              <name>Chris Rubinstein</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Welch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993-1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-3-0004">
        <pb id="p27-69" n="69"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Felicia Hemans and the Mythologizing of Blake’s Death</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Paula R. <name>Feldman</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In February 1832, Felicia Hemans, at that time Britain’s most popular and widely read poet,
published in <hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</hi> a short poetic drama entitled “The
Painter’s Last Work.—A Scene,” confiding in a conspicuous footnote that the piece was “suggested by
the closing scene in the life of the painter Blake; as beautifully related by Allan Cunningham.” Though
Cunningham’s early sketch of Blake in <hi rend="i">The Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors
and Architects</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">1</ref> has received
attention from almost all of Blake’s biographers, Heman’s poem has been entirely overlooked; though it was
frequently reprinted throughout the nineteenth century in dozens of British and American editions of
Hemans’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> and was, therefore, a far more widely disseminated account of
Blake’s death that Cunningham’s, modern scholars have been unaware of it, in part because Hemans’s
complete <hi rend="i">Works</hi> have not been reprinted since they last appeared in an Oxford University
Press edition in 1914. <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">1</hi> 6 vols. (London: John Murray, 1830) 2:
140-79.</note></p>
          <p>Hemans spent most of her life in Wales and is unlikely ever to have met Blake. She visited London
only briefly as a child (in the winters of 1804 and 1805), never to return. What she knew of Blake before
reading Cunningham is unclear; but her friend William Wordsworth might have mentioned Blake to her on one of
their walks together in the Lake District where she vacationed during the summer of 1830, shortly before
drafting her poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">2</ref> Still, she was
probably unaware of the errors, embellishments, and outright fabrications in Cunningham’s account.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">3</ref> Cunningham had written of Blake: 
<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Henry Crabb Robinson records reading Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
of Experience</hi> to Wordsworth on 24 May 1812 and notes, “He was pleased with some of them, and considered
Blake as having the elements of poetry a thousand times more than either Byron or Scott.”</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Some early reviews did take notice of the unreliability of certain aspects
of Cunningham’s account. See, for instance, <hi rend="i">The Athenaeum</hi> for Saturday, 6 February 1830
and the <hi rend="i">London University Magazine</hi> for March 1830. John Linnell also made no secret of his
dismay at the liberties Cunningham took with the truth. [G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969) 395.] Mona Wilson believes that the speech beginning “I glory in dying” and
the other beginning “I am a changing man” are Cunningham’s own inventions. See <hi rend="i">The Life of
William Blake</hi> (New York: Cooper Square Publishers, 1969) 191, 301, 370n372.</note></p>
          <figure n="hemans.27.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="455">
            <head>1. Felicia Hemans (1828).</head>
            <figDesc>Engraved by Edward Scriven after a portrait by William E. West. Harriet Hughes, the
poet’s sister, used this engraving for the frontispiece to her 7-volume, 1839 edition of Hemans’s 
<hi rend="i">Works.</hi></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>He had now reached his seventy-first year, and the strength of nature was fast yielding. Yet he
was to the last cheerful and contented. “I glory,” he said, “in dying, and have no grief but in leaving
you, Katharine; we have lived happy, and we have lived long; we have been ever together, but we shall be
divided soon. Why should I fear death? Nor do I fear it. I have endeavoured to live as Christ commands, and
have sought to worship God truly—in my own house, when I was not seen of men.” He grew weaker and
weaker—he could no longer sit upright; and was laid in his bed, with no one to watch over him, save his
wife, who, feeble and old herself, required help in such a touching duty.</p>
          <p>The Ancient of Days was such a favourite with Blake, that three days before his death, he sat
bolstered up in bed, and tinted it with his choicest colours and in his happiest style. He touched and
retouched it—held it at arm’s length, and then threw it from him, exclaiming, “There! that will do! I
cannot mend it.” He saw his wife in tears—she felt this was to be the last of his works—“Stay, Kate!
(cried Blake) keep just as you are—I will draw your portrait—for you have ever been an angel to
me”—she obeyed, and the dying artist made a fine likeness.</p>
          <p>The very joyfulness with which this singular man welcomed the coming of death, made his dying
moments intensely mournful. He lay chaunting songs, and the verses and the music were both the offspring of
the moment. He lamented that he could no longer commit those inspirations, as he called them, to paper[.]
“Kate,” he said, “I am a changing man—I always rose and wrote down my thoughts, whether it rained,
snowed, or shone, and you arose too and sat beside me—this can be no longer.” He died on the 12th of
August, 1828,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">4</ref> without any visible
pain—his wife, who sat watching him, did not perceive when he ceased breathing. 
<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Blake died in 1827, and was 69, not 71.</note></p>
          <p>While Cunningham emphasizes Blake’s cheerfulness in approaching death and the technical
achievement of his last drawing (“a fine likeness”), Hemans responded to another aspect of this account,
one to which she was particularly attuned. Famous for celebrating the “domestic affections,” Hemans had
only recently published <hi rend="i">Records of Woman</hi> (1828), highlighting the nobility and courage of
heroines in various difficult and often melancholy circumstances; she was herself still emotionally devastated
from having nursed her mother in her last illness. So her attention was drawn to the suggestions in
Cunningham’s account of Catherine Blake’s extraordinary character and the painfulness of her situation; in
Hemans’s retelling, the focus shifts from the painter and his remarkable skills even at “death’s door”
to a valorization of his artistic subject—the woman he loves and admires. William’s declaration to
Catherine in Cunningham’s account, “you have ever been an angel to me,” forms the subtext to Hemans’s
retelling.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">5</ref> To foreground this aspect
of the drama, she takes her epigraph from Thomas Campbell’s “Gertude of Wyoming:”
<q>
Clasp me a little longer on the brink<lb/>
Of life, while I can feel thy dear caress;<lb/>
And when this heart hath ceased to beat, oh! think,<lb/>
And let it mitigate thy woe’s excess,<lb/>
That thou hast been to me all tenderness,<lb/>
And friend to more than human friendship just.
</q>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">5</hi> She also draws on Cunningham’s later observation: “The affection and
fortitude of this woman [Catherine Blake] entitle her to much respect. She shared her husband’s lot without
a murmur, set her heart solely upon his fame, and soothed him in those hours of misgiving and despondency
which are not unknown to the strongest intellects.”</note></p>
          <pb id="p27-70" n="70"/>
          <p>Proficient in Italian, Hemans probably set her poetic drama in Italy because of her great
admiration for Italian art and literature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">6</ref> It seems likely that she gives the Italian name “Francesco” to the William Blake
character to underline his frankness, sincerity, and openness (“franchezza”), to suggest the spiritual
freedom he embodies, and perhaps to point towards the reassurance he gives his wife (“francheggiare”).
Similarly, it appears she names the Catherine Blake character “Teresa” to suggest at one and the same time
the earthly region (“terra”) she must continue to inhabit and her fear (“terrore”) of approaching
widowhood. Following is the text of Hemans’s dramatization of the death of Blake as it was first published
in 1832. It is worth quoting in its entirety because all subsequent appearances reprint a substantially
revised, inferior text. <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">6</hi> One of her earliest books was <hi rend="i">The
Restoration of the Works of Art to Italy: a Poem</hi>, 1816.</note></p>
		<q>
Scene—A Room in an Italian Cottage. The Lattice opening upon a Landscape at sunset.<lb/>
<lb/>
Francesco—Teresa.<lb/>
<lb/>
Teresa.<lb/>
The fever’s hue hath left thy cheek, beloved!<lb/>
Thine eyes, that make the day-spring in my heart,<lb/>
Are clear and still once more. Wilt thou look forth?<lb/>
Now, while the sunset with low-streaming light—<lb/>
The light thou lov’st—hath made the chestnut-stems<lb/>
All burning bronze, the lake one sea of gold!<lb/>
Wilt thou be raised upon thy couch, to meet<lb/>
The rich air fill’d with wandering scents and sounds?<lb/>
Or shall I lay thy dear, dear head once more<lb/>
On this true bosom, lulling thee to rest With vesper hymns?<lb/>
<lb/>
Francesco.<lb/>
No, gentlest love! not now:<lb/>
My soul is wakeful—lingering to look forth,<lb/>
Not on the sun, but thee! Doth the light sleep<lb/>
So gently on the lake? and are the stems<lb/>
Of our own chestnuts by that alchemy<lb/>
So richly changed?—and is the orange-scent<lb/>
Floating around?—But I have said farewell,<lb/>
<figure n="titlepg.27.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="443">
	<head>2. Title page to the first of Hemans’s books to include “The Painter’s Last Work,” a poem about
the death of Blake.</head>
	<figDesc>This 1834 version differed significantly from the text that appeared two years earlier in 
<hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
Farewell to earth, Teresa! not to thee,<lb/>
Nor yet to our deep love, nor yet awhile<lb/>
Unto the spirit of mine art, which flows<lb/>
Back on my soul in mastery!—one last work!<lb/>
And I will shrine my wealth of glowing thoughts,<lb/>
Clinging affection and undying hope,<lb/>
All that is in me for eternity,<lb/>
All, all, in that memorial.<lb/>
<lb/>
Teresa.<lb/>
Oh! what dream<lb/>
Is this, mine own Francesco? Waste thou not<lb/>
Thy scarce-returning strength; keep thy rich thoughts<lb/>
For happier days! they will not melt away<lb/>
Like passing music from the lute;—dear friend!<lb/>
Dearest of friends! thou canst win back at will<lb/>
The glorious visions.<lb/>
<lb/>
Francesco.<lb/>
Yes! the unseen land<lb/>
Of glorious visions hath sent forth a voice<lb/>
To call me hence. Oh! be thou not deceived!<lb/>
Bind to thy heart no <hi rend="i">earthly</hi> hope, Teresa!<lb/>
I must, <hi rend="i">must</hi> leave thee! Yet be strong, my love,<lb/>
As thou hast still been gentle!<lb/>
<lb/>
Teresa.<lb/>
Oh, Francesco!<lb/>
What will this dim world be to me, Francesco,<lb/>
When wanting thy bright soul, the life of all—<lb/>
My only sunshine!—How can I bear on?<lb/>
How can we part? We that have loved so well,<lb/>
With clasping spirits link’d so long by grief—<lb/>
By tears—by prayer?<lb/>
<lb/>
Francesco.<lb/>
Ev’n <hi rend="i">therefore</hi> we can part,<lb/>
With an immortal trust, that such high love<lb/>
Is not of things to perish.<lb/>
Let me leave<lb/>
One record still, to prove it strong as death,<lb/>
Ev’n in Death’s hour of triumph. Once again,<lb/>
Stand with thy meek hands folded on thy breast,<lb/>
And eyes half veil’d, in thine own soul absorb’d,<lb/>
As in thy watchings, ere I sink to sleep;<lb/>
And I will give the bending flower-like grace<lb/>
Of that soft form, and the still sweetness throned<lb/>
On that pale brow, and in that quivering smile<lb/>
Of voiceless love, a life that shall outlast<lb/>
Their delicate earthly being. There—thy head<lb/>
Bow’d down with beauty, and with tenderness,<lb/>
And lowly thought—even thus—my own Teresa!<lb/>
Oh! the quick glancing radiance, and bright bloom<lb/>
That once around thee hung, have melted now<lb/>
Into more solemn light—but holier far,<lb/>
And dearer, and yet lovelier in mine eyes,<lb/>
Than all that summer flush! For by my couch,<lb/>
In patient and serene devotedness,<lb/>
Thou hast made those rich hues and sunny smiles,<lb/>
Thine offering unto me. Oh! I may give<lb/>
Those pensive lips, that clear Madonna brow,<lb/>
And the sweet earnestness of that dark eye,<lb/>
Unto the canvass—I may catch the flow<lb/>
Of all those drooping locks, and glorify<lb/>
With a soft halo what is imaged thus—<lb/>
But how much rests unbreathed! My faithful one!<lb/>
What thou hast been to me! This bitter world,<lb/>
This cold unanswering world, that hath no voice<lb/>
<pb id="p27-71" n="71"/>
To greet the heavenly spirit—that drives back<lb/>
All Birds of Eden, which would sojourn here<lb/>
A little while—how have I turn’d away<lb/>
From its keen soulless air, and in <hi rend="i">thy</hi> heart,<lb/>
Found ever the sweet fountain of response,<lb/>
To quench my thirst for home! The dear work grows<lb/>
Beneath my hand—the last! Each faintest line<lb/>
With treasured memories fraught. Oh! weep thou not<lb/>
Too long, too bitterly, when I depart!<lb/>
Surely a bright home waits us both—for I,<lb/>
In all my dreams, have turn’d me not from God;<lb/>
And Thou—oh! best and purest! stand thou there—<lb/>
There, in thy hallow’d beauty, shadowing forth<lb/>
The loveliness of love!
</q>
          <p>Francesco’s answer to Teresa’s fear of impending loss, her apprehension of life’s painful
mutability, is to create, as his last tangible gift, a portrait of her own face. He offers this declaration of
his love and this testament of his admiration and gratitude as a consolation, an immortal remnant of their
mutual, enduring love. Hemans’s work ends, not like Cunningham’s with the focus firmly on William Blake,
but instead in a celebration of Catherine Blake, her virtue, strength, and beauty. Transformed into an icon of
“the loveliness of love,” Teresa/Catherine is deified as the Madonna of the home, halo and all, the sunny
solace of Francesco/William in a “cold unanswering world.” Together husband and wife become a single
emblem of love’s perfection and of its eternal character. But the iconography is every bit as much verbal as
visual; as Francesco draws, he eloquently describes the qualities he sees in Teresa’s face. The poem itself
becomes a verbal painting, as Hemans, like Francesco, describes the process of artistic creation in the very
act of creating. Though Cunningham tends to dismiss much of Blake’s poetry as “utterly wild” and
emphasizes Blake’s achievement as a visual artist, Hemans clearly reached a different conclusion after
reading the poems he quotes; her
<figure n="lastwork.27.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="442">
	<head>3. “The Painter’s Last Work” appeared in this 1836 American edition of Hemans’s 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> and in dozens of other collections published throughout the nineteenth century on
both sides of the Atlantic.</head>
</figure>
Blake character, with his verbal tribute to Teresa, is as much poet as painter. It is hard to escape the
implicit parallel between the portrait drawn by the dying Blake and Hemans’s own creative act, here and
elsewhere, of foregrounding and celebrating the quiet dignity and heroism of women. In fact, Francesco’s
chief virtue would seem to be his capacity for appreciating Teresa’s enormous worth and his skill in
immortalizing her in art, even on his deathbed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Disconcertingly, life has a way of imitating art. Only three years after
the first publication of “The Painter’s Last Work,” Hemans was herself dying, writing until nearly the
end. Biographers and contemporary readers would make much of her last poem, “Sabbath Sonnet,” dictated
from her deathbed, amid fever and delirium.</note></p>
          <p>Two years after its first publication, Hemans included “The Painter’s Last Work,”
substantially revised, in <hi rend="i">Scenes and Hymns of Life, with Other Religious Poems.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">8</ref> Her own health was by this time seriously
deteriorating, and the nature of her poetry was becoming increasingly devotional. Her shifting poetic focus
leads her to include three more lines from Campbell in the epigraph:
<q>
Oh! by that retrospect of happiness,<lb/>
And by the hope of an immortal trust,<lb/>
God shall assuage thy pangs when I am laid in dust!
</q>
Retaining the name “Teresa” for the Catherine Blake character, she alters the name of the William Blake
character to “Eugene,” an even more forceful statement about his value, for it recalls the Greek terms for
“generous” or “noble” (literally “well-born”). While twentieth-century critics have found fault
with Blake’s view of women, it is worth noting that his contemporary, a poet who championed the female
perspective, often in subtly subversive ways, drew an unqualified positive portrayal of him, much more
approving in many respects than Cunningham’s. Though there are minor revisions throughout this second
version, the major alteration is to the conclusion. Hemans deletes the last stanza—the final nine lines of
her earlier version—and adds the following:
<q>
Teresa.<lb/>
(falling on his neck in tears.)<lb/>
Eugene, Eugene!<lb/>
Break not my heart with thine excess of love!—<lb/>
Oh! must I lose thee—thou that hast been still<lb/>
The tenderest—best—<lb/>
<lb/>
Eugene.<lb/>
Weep, weep not thus, belov’d!<lb/>
Let my true heart o’er thine retain its power<lb/>
Of soothing to the last!—Mine own Teresa!<lb/>
Take strength from strong affection!—Let our souls,<lb/>
Ere this brief parting, mingle in one strain<lb/>
Of deep, full thanksgiving, for God’s rich boon—<lb/>
Our perfect love!—Oh! blessed have we been<lb/>
In that high gift! Thousands o’er earth may pass<lb/>
With hearts unfreshen’d by the heavenly dew,<lb/>
Which hath kept <hi rend="i">ours</hi> from withering.—Kneel, true wife!<lb/>
And lay thy hands in mine.—[She kneels beside the couch; he prays.] O, thus receive<lb/>
Thy children’s thanks, Creator! for the love<lb/>
Which thou hast granted, through all earthly woes,<lb/>
To spread heaven’s peace around them; which hath bound<lb/>
Their spirits to each other and to there,<lb/>
With links whereon unkindness ne’er hath breathed,<lb/>
<pb id="p27-72" n="72"/>
Nor wandering thought. We thank thee, gracious God!<lb/>
For all its treasured memories! tender cares,<lb/>
Fond words, bright, bright sustaining looks unchanged<lb/>
Through tears and joy. O Father! most of all<lb/>
We thank, we bless Thee, for the priceless trust,<lb/>
Through Thy redeeming Son vouchsafed, to those<lb/>
That love in Thee, of union, in Thy sight,<lb/>
And in Thy heavens, immortal!—Hear our prayer!<lb/>
Take home our fond affections, purified<lb/>
To spirit-radiance from all earthly stain;<lb/>
Exalted, solemnized, made fit to dwell,<lb/>
Father! where all things that are lovely meet,<lb/>
And all things that are pure—for evermore,<lb/>
With Thee and Thine!
</q>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Published in 1834, in Edinburgh, by William Blackwood and in London by T.
Cadell.</note></p>
          <p>This melodramatic prayer of thanksgiving changes the final emphasis of the poem from a
celebration of Catherine/Teresa to a more conventional celebration of God the Father—from a matriarchal to a
patriarchal vision, from the human to the divine. The painter/poet now becomes priest as well. Hemans revises
Cunningham’s construct this second time to reflect the way in which her own agenda and notion of her poetic
role had changed toward the end of her life. But in both of her retellings, Blake is neither the wild
eccentric nor the mad painter, but a sensitive, generous, and talented artist/poet with a nobility of spirit
and an enormous capacity for love. That Felicia Hemans, a poet who probably sold more books than Byron,
identified with Blake and mythologized his death in such a positive way to a large general reading public only
four and a half years after the event, suggests that the story of Blake’s early posthumous reputation may be
far more complex and interesting than biographers have so far acknowledged.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
