<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.3.rubinstein</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">William Blake: A Man without Marx . . . ?</title>
        <author n="Rubinstein">Chris Rubinstein</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1993-1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993/94</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <name>Stacy Nabors</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Paula R. Feldman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Robert Kiely</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>George Anthony Rosso</name>
              <name>Chris Rubinstein</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Welch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993-1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
      <pb id="p27-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <head>
          <title type="section-subtitle">
            <hi rend="i">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of thought</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake: A Man without Marx . . .?</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Chris <name>Rubinstein</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>“William Blake: A Man without Marx” . . . surely an untoward headline for the absorbing and
informative review by John Vice (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 26 [1993]: 162) of Bronowski’s famous book. A close
reading of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, along with a bit more of his work, makes
it clear enough that Blake’s and Marx’s living faiths significantly over-lapped, though Blake died when
Marx was a child, and Marx apparently never knew of Blake.</p>
          <p>There is a problem of elaboration because of the sheer intensity of the two thought systems, but
nonetheless some basic principles are shared—against the mores of their times as each was aware. It would be
totally uncharacteristic of admiration of Blake’s verbal and visual art form to let any political bias
impede a just comparison. Ideally, two memo books, each of excerpts from their writings, would assist. In the
case of Marx’s works, the famous 11 theses on Feuerbach dating from 1845 make a good start.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The full text of the 11 theses on Feuerbach may be found in the English
translation (London: Lawrence and Wishart, 1950) of volume 1 of the <hi rend="i">Selected Works of Marx and
Engels</hi> (365-67). The Manifesto of the Communist Party (sic) is in the same volume.
                            <p>In addition to the references to <hi rend="i">Milton and Jerusalem</hi> above,
the following may provide examples of Blake’s ideology compared with Marxism: <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 38:
28-32, 40: 9-11; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 9: 17-27, 29: 33-40, 31: 13-18, 33: 17-34, 42: 25-28, 49: 65-76,
55: 55-66, 63: 26-31, 89 (the covering cherub), and 91: 21-29.</p></note></p>
          <p>The sweep of Marxism in a monist context is consistent with Blake’s emphasis on monism and on
translucence having no limit—the closing plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and plates 20 to 28 of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> provide a good example. Mastery of dialectics is mutual property, and Blake’s
linguistic ability may have the edge—e.g., compare Blake’s “minute particulars” with the Marxist
“concrete,” or the daring concept of “the covering cherub” with the ponderous “a revolutionary
situation.” Each of them postulated an eventual near millennial transformation of human society, and dealt
in his own way with a national transitional period, partly in the future—accepting as the duty of a
philosopher not only to interpret the world but also to change it.</p>
          <p>While the contrast between Marx’s materialism and Blake’s idealism cannot be absent from any
evaluation, Blake’s own comment (<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> iii: 13-18) carries conviction:
<q>
Then tell me, what is the material world, and is it dead?<lb/>
He laughingly answer’d: I will write a book on leaves of flowers<lb/>
If you will feed me on love-thoughts, &amp; give me now and then<lb/>
A cup of sparkling poetic fancies; so when I am tipsie,<lb/>
I’ll sing to you this soft lute; and shew you all alive<lb/>
The world, when every particle of dust breathes forth its joy.
</q>
So what is the significance of the ideological gap or gulf between the materialism and idealism? There may be
no simple decisive answer to this question. It is clear that both Blake and Marx were aware of the
consideration and refused to be deterred by it. Blake’s utilization of phenomena, social inter alia, was in
keeping with his realization, that whatever the ultimate assessment should be, the World is a material one. We
can refer to Bronowski’s major theme: Blake as an insightful commentator on the presteam locomotive era of
the industrial revolution based in England.</p>
          <p>An outstanding example is to be found in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 59: 26-55, with a powerful
description of the stream of consciousness of women at work in the new industrial system—their energy. The
fact that the image of their agonies may be interpreted as deriving from a neo-Platonist view of human souls
about to be born does not obviate the reference to infestation by vermin of a textile workshop and parts of
creatures, living or dead, identifiable as commodities for production for the market. The women work to the
point of exhaustion.</p>
          <p>Nor should Blake’s castigation of the Sons of Albion be overlooked (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
10: 7-16). The liberal-minded and Whig-orientated section of the intelligentsia, led by Leigh Hunt and his
brother with <hi rend="i">The Examiner</hi> (the Hand of Jerusalem) fell, as Blake saw it, for an erroneous
ideology—one not dialectical. Los drives the point home (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 17: 33-35 and 38:
67-68) and Albion, with a sign of Blake’s sense of humor, peevishly complains of “Two bleeding Contraries
equally true” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 24: 3)! It would be tedious here to cite excerpts at length but
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> certainly undergoes a remarkably intense learning process with a commitment typical
of the real Milton and later Marxists (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32: 8-38).</p>
          <p>Why should we be surprised that similar cultural movements influenced Blake and Hegel
(1770-1832)?</p>
          <p>If Blake had survived to a ripe old age unimpaired, what would have been his opinion of 
<hi rend="i">The Communist Manifesto</hi> of 1848? Would he have seen it as a sequel to <hi rend="i">The Marriage
of Heaven and Hell</hi> or as a significant contribution to the Bible of Hell or as a new vision of Albion’s
or perhaps Los’s?</p>
          <p>My own conclusion is that whereas Marxism encapsulates for the human mind phenomena as
essentially social phenomena, objectively and scientifically ascertainable, Blake at the other polarity
emphasizes the vehicle of human consciousness as primary. That each added significantly to our understanding
of the human condition, and that their systems complement rather than contradict each other, seems to me to be
beyond doubt.</p>
          <p>Bronowski, when he wrote his book in or about 1942, almost certainly firmly believed that the
post-war world would see a form of socialism or communism, likeable or otherwise, in the ascendant, and that
the culture of Blake could act as humanizing influence on the apparently scientific claims of Marxism.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
