<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.3.cox</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Stephen Cox, Love and Logic: The Evolution of Blake’s Thought</title>
        <author n="Esterhammer">Angela Esterhammer</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1993-1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993/94</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <name>Stacy Nabors</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Paula R. Feldman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Robert Kiely</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>George Anthony Rosso</name>
              <name>Chris Rubinstein</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Welch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993-1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
	<pb id="p27-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">
              <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Stephen Cox, <hi rend="i">Love and Logic: The Evolution of Blake’s
Thought.</hi> Ann Arbor: U of Michigan P, 1992. 314 pp. $32.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Angela <name>Esterhammer</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Stephen Cox’s new book is well worth reading for what it says about Blake, about Blake’s
critics, and about the evolution of ethical, aesthetic, and logical thought over the past two centuries. 
<hi rend="i">Love and Logic</hi> will no doubt become best known for its determined opposition to postmodernist
readings of Blake. Postmodernism is widely defined here to include deconstruction as well as other forms of
poststructuralism, historicism, and psychoanalysis; the most consistent targets of the argument appear to be
critics like McGann, Hilton, Essick, Glen, Larrissy, and Mitchell. In defiance of all critics who stress the
undecidability and indeterminacy of Blake’s texts, Cox’s aim is to remind us that, Blake’s time not
being our own, Blake lived in a logical universe dominated by a concept of objective truth, and his unfailing
purpose was to persuade readers to reject error and embrace that truth, even though he was all too aware of
the difficulties of representing it.
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
<q>
Blake wants to make the clearest possible distinction between truth and falsehood. . . . Nothing could be
farther from his ambitions than the projects of those postmodern theorists who have abandoned, with no visible
sign of regret, any attempt to locate a reliable truth. (235)
</q>
What makes this a powerful and relevant rebuttal is that (as Cox notes) most postmodern critics have at least
implicitly coopted Blake’s intentions into their argument, claiming not just that his texts are responsive
to postmodern readings, but that Blake himself more or less consciously anticipated postmodernism.</p>
          <p>Cox embarks on his reading of Blake with a strongly worded defense of authorial intention and its
importance for interpretation. He deflects some, if not all, of the customary arguments against
intention-oriented criticism by clearly defining intention in logical rather than psychological terms: it is
not Blake’s purported marital problems that are significant to his vision of love (though Cox is
occasionally tempted to allude to them anyway), but the effective choices he makes as an author, choices which
organize his worldview and limit the referential scope of his texts. Cox acknowledges the influence of
economist and philosopher of human action Ludwig von Mises on this critical perspective, but one is also
tempted to draw comparisons with E. D. Hirsch, Jr., and Cox’s previous publications show that his approach
derives from a sustained investigation into hermeneutics and the limits of interpretative method.</p>
          <p>Thus Cox’s book resolutely reads the direction of Blake’s logic from signs that others have
found indeterminate or infinitely referential. If it is true that “some readers may be surprised . . . by
[an] emphasis on logic, and hence on reason” (1), as Cox initially suggests, the excellent introductory
chapter should convince many of those readers that logic may be regarded as the organizing principle of
Blake’s vision. “Logic,” here, is primarily the establishment of relationships between ideas, and Cox
maintains that Blake’s favorite methods for handling ideas are substantialization (giving ideas a physical
and spatial form), universalization (expanding the scope of individual ideas), and identification (equating
ideas with one another). Blake’s poetic works then become experiments with different ways of grasping and
arranging concepts, particularly
<pb id="p27-85" n="85"/>
concepts of love—though love is defined broadly enough here to include freedom and individuality as well as
familial, sexual, and religious relationships.</p>
          <p>The logic of Cox’s own book, as reflected in his subtitle, is severely chronological. This is
explicitly a study in the <hi rend="i">evolution</hi> of Blake’s thought, which means not only that the
poetry is studied in chronological sequence (problems of dating, while not dwelt on, are competently handled),
but also that the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, for instance, are counterpointed with marginalia from
the 1780s and the <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> are paired with contemporaneous notebook poems, even
studied in their notebook versions. One consequence of this perspective is that Cox’s narrative of Blake’s
career is unrelentingly teleological. The motivations of characters within each poem are likely to be
explained by appeal to the development of the poem’s logical pattern. More significantly, each work leads
logically on to the next as if they were a series of computer programs to be tested and debugged in turn, or,
to use Cox’s more historical metaphor, as if they were the projects of a tinkerer or workshop inventor. The
result is a curious view of Blake’s oeuvre as “a series of experiments in using logic to construct a
universe congenial to love” (35). The teleological bias may be an accurate reflection of Blake’s pursuit
of a goal, and thus justifiable within the limits of Cox’s intentionalist perspective, but its corollary is
a more dubious determinism: it sometimes seems as if Blake’s works could not possibly have been other than
they were, or been produced in a different order, given the logical problems they consecutively posed for
him.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, this approach leads to some excellent, thought-provoking, original readings. It
accounts—logically—for characteristics of some works that other critics have seen as indefensible, and
therefore either as weaknesses or as indications that Blake must have been aiming at indeterminacy or
deconstruction of his own texts. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, in particular, emerges here as a
deliberate limitation of the world to certain kinds of logical love-relationships, so that emotional responses
follow “as seemingly inevitable inferences from a logical relationship, the identification of God and
humanity” (42). Cox’s interpretation accounts for the limitation of innocence without identifying it as a
limitation of Blake’s awareness or his abilities. This makes possible a refreshing study of lyrics which
have been pressed into deconstructive service so often that it hardly seemed possible any more to identify
their embodiment of an ideal as a component of their meaning. Cox, however, realizes that love in 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> “is purely and simply good—not because Blake cannot imagine any arguments against
this ideal, but because he chooses to construct a world that corresponds to it” (39). In this context, the
things about which the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> are silent can be interpreted positively (what
would a world look like which had these boundaries?) instead of negatively (since Blake must be saying
something about the “real” world, what have these boundaries excluded or repressed?).</p>
          <p>The insightful reading of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> may point up a few weaknesses in readings
of other poems. Granted that <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> is, as Cox suggests, an inverse and parody of the vision
of innocence, why can the interpretation of <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> be substantiated by historical
circumstances when these would distort the interpretation of <hi rend="i">Innocence?</hi> The superficial
answer is that <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> adopts a different logical framework from the <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi>, which deliberately excluded historical cause and effect; a more considered answer might be
that a book which examines Blake’s authorial choices is justified in considering the context in which those
choices were made. Yet introducing the context of eighteenth-century attitudes to love and familial
relationships, as Cox occasionally does, seems somehow to detract from one of his most significant arguments,
which is that Blake’s characters and states are more readily comprehensible as <hi rend="i">logical</hi>
constructs than as the “realistic,” historical, or psychological constructs we might expect to find in
novels. <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> benefits particularly from this approach; Cox traces
the consequences of its substantializing and dialectical logic and argues convincingly that it is neither
naturalistic nor antinomian. A chapter on <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> provides a marvelous pendant to
the analysis of dialectical logic in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, since Cox reads <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>
as a parody of Blake’s own “essentializing, dualizing, universalizing, and substantializing vision”
(146).</p>
          <p>Despite Cox’s repeated dissociation of his viewpoint from that of “traditional” critics as
well as from postmodernists, it seems to me that one of the critics he is closest to in terms of his patterns
and priorities is Northrop Frye. If Frye regarded Blake’s corpus as a quasi-architectural system, Cox sets
that system in motion so that it becomes a series of components re-arranging themselves into different
positions and progressively generating new members. His perspective is similar to Frye’s in that it
emphasizes the overall shape of Blake’s thought rather than the often contradictory details—focusing, one
might say, on <hi rend="i">langue</hi> rather than <hi rend="i">parole.</hi> His consistently deductive
approach even suggests the extent to which the choice of focus determines the resulting vision. An emphasis on
significant detail is likely to result in a postmodernist reading full of paradox and conflicting or
indeterminate reference, while a focus on deep structure is more likely to result, like Cox’s study and
Frye’s, in the discovery of logical patterns.</p>
          <p>The originality and power of the book seem to me to lie in its focus on logic, but the primary
subject of Cox’s analysis is, after all, love. Love and logic are not related dialectically here, but rather
as material and method: it is the vagaries of love that Blake, and Cox, try to work through in logical terms.
The second half of <hi rend="i">Love and Logic</hi> addresses Blake’s major prophecies,
<pb id="p27-86" n="86"/>
all of which are read as “the torments of Love &amp; Jealousy in The Death and Judgement of Albion the
Ancient Man,” or as a “history of the human heart” (167-68). In Cox’s terms, the complexity of these
poems results from Blake’s attempt to set competing forms of logical thought side by side within the same
text, rather than working through one possible logical organization of love as each of the shorter poems does.
By working inward from Blake’s logical method to the vision that method produces, Cox arrives at significant
insights into the origins of sexual love and jealousy (consequences of dualistic thought itself), and the
meaning of substantializations such as Beulah (“an effort to work out the logical conditions of an
environment in which spiritual love can inhabit temporality,” 231) or the Spectre of Los (a necessary parody
of logic). Blake’s solution to the torments of love and jealousy is a substantial and uncompromising vision
of Christian love, a logical principle of redemption which can harmonize previously competing conceptual
drives such as universality and individual identification.</p>
          <p>Ironically, when viewed from this perspective Blake’s method can come across as rather
postmodern: instead of grand narratives, his major prophecies offer heterogeneity and continuous
experimentation with logic. Cox indeed argues that Blake and postmodernism share some forms of logical thought
(“The great problem of Blake and the postmodernists is the habit of imputing to propositions and logical
operations the characteristics of substantial things” [235]), but they differ on the crucial issue of
representation. In Blake’s major prophecies the logical principles that he initially shares with
postmodernism are taken a step further, toward a paradoxical “parody of a parody, a reproduction of
reproductions” for which Cox coins the noun “paralectic” (239-40). Paralectic is the method of salvation
in Blake’s later works, a logical method by which Blakean realities are represented as parodic likenesses of
a material world that Blake knows and demonstrates to be itself a parody of the eternal world. This is the
culmination of Blake’s substantializing logic, and of Cox’s predominantly spatializing explication of that
logic (demonstrated, for instance, by his persistent interest in terms which etymologically convey some sort
of positioning, such as “parody” and “dialectic”). Spatializing logic of this kind (which is again
reminiscent of Frye) allows for a distinction between the postmodernists’ “paradox,” which is
undecidability, and paradox in Blake, which literally means two beliefs existing side by side. Ultimately, the
difference between Blake and the postmodernists resides in Blake’s conviction and demonstration that paradox
and indeterminancy, far from undermining the concept of objective truth, instead verify the existence of a
truth beyond the power of human representation. Discussing Los’s laborious efforts in building Golgonooza,
Cox concludes that
<q>
The final effect is not, however, a denial of the power of vision; and it is not an affirmation of the value
of mystery or indeterminacy. . . . It is, rather, a sign that Blakean visions are not emptily self-reflexive
but are imperfect and unapologetically inelegant aids to the contemplation of a truth beyond themselves.
(270-71)
</q></p>
          <p>Not least among the strengths of Cox’s argument is its ability to contain its own opposition,
by a process analogous to the way Blake himself (according to Cox) contains negations by substantializing them
and assigning them a place in his logical system. Cox agrees that there is profound indeterminacy in Blake’s
vision, only he redefines indeterminacy so that it is not limitlessness of meaning, but rather a kind of
pluralism which results from Blake’s “constantly varying involvement with logic,” his “multiplication
of logical strategies that organize meanings in a variety of momentarily determinate ways” (10). If, as Cox
seems to suggest in his opening chapter, the mid-twentieth-century critics who set out to elucidate Blake’s
system represented a certain innocence that has given way to the experienced state of postmodernist criticism,
then Cox’s own book represents a kind of organized innocence that is able to contain the postmodernist
vision as a systematic part of a larger whole.</p>
          <p>Still, it is worthwhile to have someone remind us, from a strongly intentionalist, mildly
historicist perspective, that Blake did care more for mastery, persuasion, clarity, and a stable truth than
many contemporary critics would comfortably admit. Blake’s language and imagery, his psychology and his
ideology continue to be fair game for critics fascinated by the capacity for play in his kaleidoscopic work.
But these readings will also continue to contend with a tradition of interpretation which emphasizes the
coherence and teleology of Blake’s thought, a tradition now infused with new energy by <hi rend="i">Love and
Logic.</hi></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
