<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.3.welch</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Stephen C. Behrendt, Reading William Blake</title>
        <author n="Welch">Dennis M. Welch</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1993-1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1993/94</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <name>Stacy Nabors</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Paula R. Feldman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Robert Kiely</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>George Anthony Rosso</name>
              <name>Chris Rubinstein</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Welch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1993-1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
	<pb id="p27-91" n="91"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">
              <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Stephen C. Behrendt, <hi rend="i">Reading William Blake.</hi> New York: St.
Martin’s Press, 1992. xv + 196 pp. $45.00</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Dennis M. <name>Welch</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>This book explores the dynamics of the reading process involved in reading William Blake’s
illuminated poems,” focusing specifically on “some of the demands” that his texts place on us by
embodying “a fertile intersection among frequently differing. . .[artistic] systems of reference. . .”
(viii). Following “A Note on Copies,” in which Behrendt acknowledges multiple differences among various
copies of the illuminated texts and proposes therefore to “deal only sparingly with these matters of
variation” (xv), he includes six chapters: “Introduction: Reading Blake’s Texts,” 
“<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>,” “Three Early Illuminated Works,” “Lambeth
Prophecies I: History of the World,” “Lambeth Prophecies II: History of the Universe,” and “Epic Art:
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”</p>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <p>The Introduction lays out primarily Behrendt’s theory of Blake’s perspective on readers and
reading: his “works challenge. . . our assumptions and expectations about the authority of both narrator
(and/or author) and text,” requiring that we possess “both equilibrium and a good deal of
self-assurance” and “serve as co-creators of the work under consideration” (1). Behrendt initially
offers us the comforting assurance that “Blake does not <hi rend="i">require</hi> [although he
‘encourages’] of his readers elaborate preparation” in order to read with feeling and intelligence what
Behrendt calls (via Wolfgang Iser) Blake’s intertextual “metatexts.” But if the poet-and-artist’s aim
is in fact “to liberate” us “from conventional ways of reading” (4), then 
<hi rend="i">dis</hi>equilibrium seems to be a primary strategy for fostering such liberation. As Behrendt himself
observes, Blake’s texts are in a sense “non-authoritative” (5), tempting us to impose on them
reductivist understanding. It is this temptation that helps to unsettle us and to transform our vision.</p>
          <p>Citing Robert Adams’s <hi rend="i">Strains of Discord: Studies in Literary Openness</hi> (1958)
and Umberto Eco’s <hi rend="i">The Role of the Reader</hi> (1979) and <hi rend="i">The Open Work</hi>
(1989), Behrendt considers Blake’s illuminated work “open” like the novels of Fielding and Sterne and
the history painting of Benjamin West—open to countless interpretations, making “readers” take
responsibility for them. While certainly democratic, this view is true only to a point. There is little doubt
that Blake had strong convictions although he was open to change (“Expect poison from the standing
water”). Indeed, the refusal in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> even “to converse
with” the Angel “whose works are only Analytics” (pls. 9, 20; E 37, 42) implies that he was not always
open-minded. Nor do I believe (despite my desires otherwise) that his texts and his expectations from readers
are always open-minded. His
<pb id="p27-92" n="92"/>
metaphor of conventional Bible readers reading “black” where he reads “white” (E524) implies to me
that the line of his understanding and of being understood is firm and wiry. Behrendt seems almost to
recognize this line when he refers (uncharacteristically and rather too extremely) to the readers’ need to
“affirm the existence . . . of absolute right and wrong, truth and falsehood” and to “read” and
rebuild Jerusalem “properly” (148, 149). But perhaps he puts the matter more accurately by saying that
Blake’s iconographic (and, of course, poetic) signification does not drift “aimlessly in a sea of
indeterminacy.” Instead, it engages “in a form of intellectual sabotage that tests both the limits of his
own art and the alertness and intellectual independence of his reader . . .”(37).</p>
          <p>Like the emphasis on openness, the emphasis on independence may be put too heavily, however:
“We must . . . learn to depend upon ourselves, and upon our own imaginative and experiential resources. For
it is there, perhaps even more than in that remarkable artist’s illuminated pages, that the real meaning . .
. of Blake’s poetry lies” (35). Yes and no. I become a little skeptical about a theory of reading that
emphasizes self-sufficiency sometimes at the expense of interaction and interchange, especially since Blake
was radically reformulating the eighteenth-century ideal of self-sufficient consciousness as conceptualized by
one of his chief intellectual enemies—John Locke.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">1</ref> As implied in Behrendt’s own language—“Blake expects [readers] to be paying
attention” (37)—self-sufficiency without adequately hearing, seeing, and learning from what the texts say
and show is utterly insufficient. Stanley Cavell argues that writers—in particular, the romantic poets—who
want us to “imagine that which we know” make extraordinary demands on us as readers. They seek “to
prevent understanding which is unaccompanied by inner change,” or, as Michael Fischer puts it, “to prevent
our substituting belief in what they say for being touched or moved by it.” The implication in this for our
reading involves the idea of personal growth through interaction with the text, indeed a form of discipleship
that is strenuous friendship with it. “Blake’s model for the relationship between artist and audience is
Jesus and his followers . . . (John 15:15-16).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For two of the most important sources on Locke’s understanding of
autonomous self-consciousness and its relationships to reason, memory, self-concernment, and moral as well as
political “independence,” see <hi rend="i">An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi>, ed. Peter H.
Nidditch (Oxford: Clarendon, 1975), 2.27; and <hi rend="i">Some Thoughts Concerning Education, The Educational
Writings of John Locke</hi>, ed. James L. Axtell (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1968) 109-325.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See Stanley Cavell, “The Avoidance of Love,” <hi rend="i">Must We Mean
What We Say?</hi> (1969; rpt. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1976) 324-25; Michael Fischer, “Accepting the
Romantics as Philosophers,” <hi rend="i">Philosophy and Literature</hi> 12 (1988): 186; and Morris Eaves,
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1982) 193.</note></p>
          <p>Chapter 2 of Behrendt’s book “explore[s] the contributions made by Blake and his individual
reader to the process of reading” the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (41). Attempting to be “neither prescriptive
nor proscriptive” in order to avoid “imputing . . . operations and observations that are in fact my own”
(51), Behrendt proceeds nonetheless to a fairly prescriptive assertion that “in fact” the action of the
male figure on the general title page of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> depicts “the moment of the
consciousness of guilt” (52). While I tend to agree with this assertion, it is worth noting that this
“real Fall of humanity” into the sense of guilt became apocalyptically evident to Blake in his era, for
the consciousness that Locke and others associated with personal identity had deep and disturbing ties with
moral accountability, self-accusation, and legalistic justice.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">3</ref> Of course, seventeenth- and eighteenth-century puritan and evangelical views
helped foster such consciousness. And as Jean Hagstrum observes, in dictionaries from 1662 on, “conscious”
was defined as “inwardly guilty,” “culpable,” “self-convicted.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See Locke, <hi rend="i">Essay</hi> 2.27.22, 26 and 3.11.16; Ernest Lee
Tuveson, <hi rend="i">Imagination as a Means of Grace: Locke and the Aesthetics of Romanticism</hi> (Berkeley:
U of California P, 1960) 44, 48; and Antony Flew, “Locke and the Problem of Personal Identity,” 
<hi rend="i">Locke and Berkeley: A Collection of Critical Essays</hi>, ed. C. B. Martin and D. M. Armstrong (New
York: Anchor, 1968) 155.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Jean H. Hagstrum, “Towards a Profile of the Word 
<hi rend="i">Conscious</hi> in Eighteenth-Century Literature,” <hi rend="i">Psychology and Literature in the
Eighteenth Century</hi>, ed. Christopher Fox (New York: AMS, 1987) 27.</note></p>
          <p>Part of Behrendt’s exploration of the process of reading the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> involves
his comparison of their multiple resonating voices to a kind of polyphony in which words and sounds interact
to form another “metatext,” not unlike that of the interaction of words and pictures. This comparison is
evocative, but as happens often in verbal discussions of music it tends to remain somewhat abstract. Perhaps
this is why Behrendt advises us to try to “imagine” the music of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> But perhaps
an even more helpful strategy might have been for him to select three or four Songs that in most copies are
adjacent to one another and discuss the various voices and tones that speak, or rather sing, those Songs.</p>
          <p>Examining briefly but contextually <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel, Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, chapter 3 shows that “Blake plants the
seeds of his subversion of reader expectations already in his early works” (73). After pointing out several
ambiguities in the motto and first five lines of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, Behrendt says that such “calculated
indeterminacy pervades not just . . . <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> but many of Blake’s finest poems . . .” (80).
Another example of such calculated indeterminacy that “forces . . . readers to construct yet a third text [a
‘metatext’] that partakes of both the verbal and visual texts . . . but which is precisely coincident with
neither” (89) is the frontispiece of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (in all copies but one). But while Behrendt
offers an appropriately sympathetic view of Oothoon, who faces “enormous odds . . . in the male
establishment” around her (90), he tends to follow the pattern of judging her performance as a success or
failure when, I think, the whole thrust of the prophecy and her distinctly <hi rend="i">un</hi>woeful rhetoric
is to present a strenuous voice of resistance. Hence, he is disturbed by her “acceding to . . . male
dominance and male-emulation” (90) when she asks, “How can I be defild when I reflect thy image pure?”
(pl. 3.16, E 47)—a question which in context is ironic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">5</ref> Insisting that the faithless Theotormon look at her (pl. 3.15, E 47), Oothoon’s wish to
reflect him becomes a subtle but nonetheless critical form of resistance that uses his limited epistemological
perspective against him. Because from his merely surface or sensory perspective she reflects his filthy
(“mudded”) image, then looking at her as defiled he should see who and what <hi rend="i">he</hi> really
is. On the other hand, because she is in fact a “clear spring” (pl. 2.19, E 46) that cannot reflect the
real Theotormon, he should by contrast to her still see who and
<pb id="p27-93" n="93"/>
what he is—but only if he acknowledges his hypocrisy. <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See James A. W.
Heffernan, “Blake’s Oothoon: The Dilemmas of Marginality,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 30
(1991): 12 and 14n20.</note></p>
          <p>Placing three of Blake’s most openly political prophecies (<hi rend="i">America, Europe</hi>,
and <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>) in the context of late eighteenth-century millenarianism, chapter 4
shows how he “marshals his verbal and visual forces to present for infernal reading a documentary history”
of the era’s millennial signs (105). Such signs are traced in the prophecies through two phenomena that
challenge and influence the reading process—metamorphosis and encyclopedic allusion. For example, the notion
of absolute space, whereby eighteenth-century science served to “bind the infinite” 
(<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 2.13, E 61), is both imaged and undermined by the dynamic and allusive aspects of the
Urizenic creator and the huge coiling serpent on the frontispiece and the title page respectively in 
<hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> With these designs the reader’s imagination is called upon to “discover and create
something greater than what is represented . . .” (115). Similarly, absolute time is both represented and
subverted in verses such as “The times are ended; shadows pass the morning gins to break . . .” 
(<hi rend="i">America</hi> pl. 8.2, E 54), where “Blake superimposes upon one another two very different
conceptions of time, presenting us with the paradoxical situation in which metamorphosis is both continually
progressing and already completed” (116). But for Behrendt to say that “Blake’s texts supply verbal and
visual commentaries on events and ideas whose ultimate specific location is in fact in the reader’s
consciousness” (120) seems something of an exaggeration, if not a contradictory misstatement, given the
highly allusive nature of those texts.</p>
          <p>Whereas chapter 4 discusses the more historical and topical “minor” prophecies (as
mythological histories of the then-known world—Europe, America, Asia, and Africa), chapter 5 discusses the
prophecies concerned with a “history of the universe that involves the events” of Genesis and Exodus
(126). These prophecies are <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The
Book of Los</hi>, in which Behrendt traces examples of inversion (such as the de-creation in 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>), aimed at attacking authority and getting us to “read” our Bibles and our worlds in
contrary and liberating ways. Inversion and reversal appear also in the “seemingly erratic organization”
of plates in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, implying as Behrendt says (citing Eco) “an assault on artistic
structure” and on “received notions of reality” (135, 136). Although he appears to imply (as he did
earlier) what these notions are when he says that the organization seeks “to <hi rend="i">liberate</hi>”
the verbal text from “time and place,” the received notions were probably those of absolute space and
time—not to mention the Lockean, Newtonian, and Humean concepts of identity (“a solid without
fluctuation”?), which turns out to be radically transient (like the horizon to which Urizen’s name in
Greek refers). The deletion of plate 4 in copies D, E, and G—eliminating the “solid” (pl. 4.11, E 71)
that Urizen seeks for his self—may imply some of the discontinuity in identity that is based on memory and
reason (or “consciousness,” as Locke defined it).</p>
          <p>Chapter 6 deals with Blake’s epic art, specifically in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and largely in the context of history painting. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is . . .
an interdisciplinary analogue to grand style eighteenth-century history painting . . . that directly engages
artist, subject and audience in a community activity of consciousness-raising” (155). Returning from
Eternity into space and time in order “to correct the errors in his own vision,” Blake’s Milton
“offers the reader . . . the personal paradise of visionary insight that is the Miltonic-Blakean legacy”
(156, 157). And the offer is made in the form of metatexts that readers must construct imaginatively from the
visual, verbal, and allusive details of individual plates. Such readers, who are taxed even further by the
linearity and simultaneity, the extensive allusiveness, and the multiple perspectivity in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, are finally said to be “ideal readers” (167)—self-sacrificing and forgiving,
knowledgeable and enthusiastic.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Reading William Blake</hi> is a well-documented book. The practice of referring to
specific page and/or plate numbers of designs not included in it but in David Erdman’s 
<hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi>, Martin Butlin’s <hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>,
and elsewhere is also very useful. There are, however, a few documentary citations that deserve to have been
made. Given the interpretive problem of many differences among various copies of the illuminated texts,
reference to the studies by Myra Glazer-Schotz and by her and Gerda Norvig would have been
appropriate.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">6</ref> Also deserving of
reference is Graham Pechey’s essay on <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, one of the best on that work.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">7</ref> Since Joseph Viscomi’s excellent study of
Blake’s relief-etching technique supercedes Ruthven Todd’s, John Wright’s, and even Robert Essick’s,
it should have been mentioned in note 1 of Chapter 4 (184).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n39" type="note">8</ref> Finally, Morris Eaves’s discussion of Blake’s audience is among the very
best and in several ways complements Behrendt’s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Myra Glazer-Schotz, “Blake’s Little Black Boys: On the Dynamics of
Blake’s Composite Art,” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 16 (1980): 220-36; Myra Glazer-Schotz
and Gerda Norvig, “Blake’s Book of Changes: On Viewing Three Copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
and of Experience</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 9 (1980): 100-21.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Graham Pechey, “<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>: A
Text and its Conjuncture,” <hi rend="i">Oxford Literary Review</hi> 3 (1979): 54-76.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated
Prints</hi> (Manchester, Eng.: Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983).</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Cited above in n. 2.</note></p>
          <p>As with most good books, <hi rend="i">Reading William Blake</hi> includes some brief comments
which one would like to see elaborated. These include but are not limited to: (1) the statement that the
“complex polyphony” among the Songs “enables us . . . better to resolve the problems created . . . by
Blake’s decisions to alter” their “order” (21); (2) the tantalizing remark about “the enthusiasm
with which Blake and . . . the radical Johnson circle must have responded to the substantial contemporary 
<hi rend="i">support</hi>” for Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> (85); and
(3) the briefly mentioned intertextualities between Ecclesiastes 12.5 and the motto of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>,
between the madonna-like figure of Thel in plate 5 and the figure of Constance in Fuseli’s <hi rend="i">Here
I and Sorrows Sit</hi> (180n8), and between the scenes in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> plates 4 and 5 and the
dynamics
<pb id="p27-94" n="94"/>
of the hiding and finding of Moses—subjects that Blake later painted (81).</p>
          <p>Far outnumbering such tantalizing tidbits are Behrendt’s many informative and commendable
discussions of such topics as: (1) “open” texts parallel to Blake’s in eighteenth-century fiction,
history painting, caricature, and cartoons; (2) his interest in various forms of music, especially hymns and
religious songs for children; (3) the primping nurse in “Nurses Song” (<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>); (4)
the senses and their representation in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>; (5) multiple parallels among designs within
and between Blake’s works; (6) similar parallels between his designs and eighteenth-century illustrations of
Miltonic subjects; and (7) late eighteenth-century millenarianism and its dependence (like that of Blake’s
work) on a highly attentive audience. Despite my quibbles raised earlier (mostly as matters of emphasis, not
substance) and despite the inattentiveness of its copy editor, <hi rend="i">Reading William Blake</hi> is a
fine book. With its overall focus, breadth, and lucidity and with its 16 well chosen, nicely reproduced, and
appropriately discussed plates, the book constitutes a splendid advanced introduction to Blake—well suited
to upper-division English majors, graduate students, and anyone else seeking a concise but well-informed 
<hi rend="i">entrée</hi> into Blake’s illuminated work.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
