<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>27.4.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Wendy Wassyng Roworth, ed., Angelica Kauffman: A Continental Artist in Georgian
England</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">27.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Interns</resp>
              <name>Lauren Raimondi</name>
              <name>Stacy Nabers</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_27">
    <body>
      <pb id="p27-130" n="130"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-27-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEW</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Angelica Kauffman: A Continental Artist in Georgian England.</hi>
Ed. Wendy Wassyng Roworth. London: Reaktion Books, 1992, in association with the Royal Brighton Pavilion Art
Gallery &amp; Museums, Brighton. Distributed in the U.S. and Canada by the University of Washington Press. 216
pp., 149 illus. £9.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Though William Blake is not referred to in <hi rend="i">Angelica Kauffman</hi>,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> the book is surprisingly illuminating of
Blake’s context and ambitions. For one thing, Angelica Kauffman lived in Golden Square, round the corner
from where Blake was born and brought up in Broad Street; he probably knew of her as a neighbor, not to
mention as the finest female painter in England and a founder-member of the Royal Academy in 1768; indeed, he
may have bought some of her etchings after her own designs, sold at her house in Golden Square (151). 
<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The book was published “To coincide with the exhibition at Brighton Museum and
Art Gallery” 14 November 1992-3 January 1993, according to a flyer for the exhibition; the pictures were
also exhibited in York 23 January-7 March 1993.</note></p>
          <p>For another, at the time that Blake’s father introduced him to the wonderfully fashionable
engraver William Wynne Ryland as a possible apprentice, “Ryland was the engraver most responsible for
spreading Kauffman’s fame” (143) and one of the most prolific engravers and publishers of history
paintings. He was extraordinarily successful, and in 1783 he said that he had
<q>
shares worth £7,000, a royal pension of £200 annually, and that “My stock in trade is worth £10,000 and
the net produce of my business falls little short of £2,000 a year.” (173)
</q>
In the light of Ryland’s conspicuous success, Blake’s adolescent dislike of him must have seemed merely
willful: “I do not like the man’s face; he looks as if he will live to be hanged” (<hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> [1969], 511). But in 1782, when Ryland found that he had overextended his credit, he forged two
India bills and was indeed hanged the following year. Blake is likely to have been particularly aware of
Angelica Kauffman because of the proposal that he should be apprenticed to her chief engraver.</p>
          <p>For yet another, Angelica Kauffman was one of the very small number of painters in Blake’s
England who was able to live handsomely from the sale of her history paintings, the branch of the art which
Blake and most of his contemporaries believed to be the highest accomplishment of the painter, corresponding
in literature to epic poetry. “What distinguishes Kauffman from most artists active in England during the
eighteenth century, and from virtually all women artists before the twentieth, was her ambition to achieve
standing as a history painter” (21). Oddly, the only painters successful then in this line of high art in
Britain were from outside England: the Americans Benjamin West (who became President of the Royal Academy) and
Copley, the Swiss Angelica Kauffman and Blake’s friend Henry Fuseli, and the Irishman James Barry—though
Barry was reduced to living on apples when painting his great frescoes for the Society of Arts, as Blake
remarked bitterly. It was chiefly as a result of the work of Benjamin West and Angelica Kauffman, and their
engravers, that history painting was made, at least for a short time, fashionable. The <hi rend="i">Public
Advertiser</hi> for 2 May 1775 remarked:
<q>
It has long been a matter of <hi rend="i">complaint</hi> in this Country, that there is very little
Encouragement for Historical Painting; and that most Men extend their Ideas of Painting no farther than to get
their own Portrait executed, and perhaps that of their Wife or favourite Child. . . . However well founded the
above-mentioned Complaint might [<hi rend="i">have</hi>] be[<hi rend="i">en</hi>] some Years ago, yet it is
certainly not so at the present. . . .(24)
</q></p>
          <p>As an aspiring history painter, Blake would certainly have been aware of Angelica Kauffman’s
paintings, and even more important the engravings after her paintings. For she not only painted pictures from
history and literature, such as <hi rend="i">Zeuxis Selecting Models for his Painting of Helen of Troy</hi>
(1778, pl. 37 here) and <hi rend="i">Ariadne Abandoned by Theseus</hi> (1794, pl. 61 here), but she and
Benjamin West were the first members of the Royal Academy to exhibit paintings from British history (1771),
though “the society of Artists had offered premiums since 1760 for paintings of British History” (62).
British history was a subject very close to Blake’s heart in his early years; not only did he make many
drawings and paintings of British historical subjects in Westminster Abbey when he was working for Basire as
an apprentice (1772-79), but he embarked upon a small book of designs illustrating British history. Angelica
Kauffman painted <hi rend="i">The Tender Eleanora Sucking the Venom out of the Wound which Edward I, her Royal
Consort, Received from a Poisoned Dagger from an Assassin in Palestine</hi> (1776, pl. 43 here),<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> which was engraved by W. W. Ryland (1780, pl.
140 here), and one of Blake’s most ambitious early engravings called “Edward &amp; Elinor” (18 August
1793) is of exactly the
<pb id="p27-131" n="131"/>
same subject; the only known copy was cut in two and used as pages 87-90 of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> The coincidence of subject matter is at least curious. 
<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The subject derives from Paul de Rapin-Thoyras, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi> (1726-31)
(<hi rend="i">Angelica Kauffman</hi> 62).</note></p>
		<q><hi rend="i">Angelica Kauffman</hi> consists chiefly of:
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1 Wendy Wassyng Roworth, “Kauffman and the Art of Painting in England” (11-95,
193-97);</p></item>
	<item><p>2 Angela Rosenthal, “Kauffman and Portraiture” (96-111, 198-99);</p></item>
	<item><p>3 Malise Forbes Adam and Mary Mauchline, “Kauffman’s Decorative Work” (111-40,
199-201);</p></item>
	<item><p>4 David Alexander, “Kauffman and the Print Market in Eighteenth-Century England” (141-78,
201-03);</p></item>
	<item><p>5 David Alexander, “Chronological Checklist of [<hi rend="i">311</hi>] Singly-Issued English
Prints after Angelica Kauffman” (179-89);<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> N.b.: “an expanded and indexed copy of this list has been deposited in
the British Museum Print Room” (179).</note></p></item>
	<item><p>6 149 illustrations, 40 of them in color, of Angelica Kauffman’s remarkably fine paintings and the
engravings after them.</p></item>
</list></q>
          <p>The most novel and important aspects of the book are probably the demonstrations that, first,
“almost all the decorative compositions [<hi rend="i">on furniture, china, etc., commonly</hi>] attributed
to her are reproductions, and were executed after her designs by copyists” (Adam and Mauchline 113), and
second,
<q>
There were more singly issued stipples engraved in England after the work of Angelica Kauffman than after any
other painter. Between 1774 and 1781—the second half of her stay in England—some 75 stipple engravings
were published after her paintings and drawings, and nearly double that number appeared between her departure
in 1781, and 1800. . . . it is likely that a higher proportion of her pictures were not only painted to be
engraved but were also bought by printsellers than any other painter of standing in eighteenth-century
England. (Alexander 141, 178)
</q></p>
          <p>Angela Kauffman demonstrated that an artist could make a living by creating history paintings.
Any young artist with the same ambition is likely to have been vividly aware of her accomplishment.</p>
          <p>The most enduringly valuable sections of <hi rend="i">Angelica Kauffman</hi> are likely to prove
to be the checklist of separate prints after her designs and the masterful essay on “The Print Market in
Eighteenth-Century England” by David Alexander.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
