<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.1.orr</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Life of W. Blake</title>
        <author n="Orr">Chris Orr</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Chris Orr</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <pb id="p28-35" n="35"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-1-0006">
        <figure n="OrrImage.28.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="523"/>
        <figure n="OrrImage2.28.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="529">
        	<figTranscr>W BLAKE</figTranscr>
        </figure>
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Life of W. Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Chris <name>Orr</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>T<hi rend="i">he Life of W. Blake</hi> is a set of 8 colored prints that I published in
            1992. They are a complex mix of etching and monoprint techniques. Although in a limited
            edition of 20 examples, each image is uniquely printed much in the way that Blake’s
            engravings are individual productions, varying slightly between copies. The main plate
            is drawn on copper, etched, revised and proofed through many variations. Drypoint
            techniques are added. The text and additional elements are similarly etched onto copper
            but are printed by the counter-proof method. Although this is a recognized technique, I
            believe that I have developed counter proofing more than any other artist in Britain
            recently. It is essentially an offset method. An impression is taken onto tissue paper
            and then reprinted. This allows the artist to work the correct way round. Printing a
            hand-written text suddenly becomes straightforward! It also permits the artist to print
            anywhere on the paper. For example the grasshopper in the “Visions” print can be placed
            on the extreme bottom left-hand corner, echoing the real grasshopper that came into my
            studio whilst I was making that print. (I fondly imagined that it was a visit from
            Blake’s ghost.) Monoprinting, the final element in the work, is a direct print from a
            brushstroke or smear of printing ink. Only one impression can be made before the mark
            must be re-made.</p>
          <p>One of the first art books I ever bought reproduced a selection of Blake engravings and
            he has been in a corner of my mind ever since, although for most of my career I have
            been associated with the tradition stemming from William Hogarth. A combination of
            things brought Blake bubbling to the surface for me in 1992, but it was a Scots poet who
            assailed me at a private view in London, accusing the English of producing no great
            artists or poets who lit the blue touch paper. I breathed the name of William Blake, he
            writhed in agony and left me. Every little English boy and girl is bathed in Blake at
            least once. He is selectively quoted, sung and admired for a few of his works but he is
            buried in Bunhill Fields not Westminster Abbey, we have acres of Turners on view at the
            Tate Gallery and a measly display of Blake. A National Hero? He was never knighted,
            never admitted to the Royal Academy and a printmaker to boot.</p>
          <p>My W. Blake is somewhere in between an autobiography and a historical fantasy. A homage
            but not a <corr type="emend">sycophantic</corr> illustration of the good engraver Blake. He 
          <pb id="p28-36" n="36"/>
          <figure n="OrrImage3.28.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="581">
          	<figTranscr>Socrates<lb/>
          	Socrates<lb/>
          	Socrates<lb/>
          	Socrates<lb/>
          	am Socrates<lb/>
          	I am Socrates<lb/>
          	I am Socrates<lb/>
          	I am Socrates<lb/>
          	I am Socrates<lb/>
          	I am Socrates<lb/>
          	I am Socrates<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Socrates<lb/>
          	Socrates<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	E3<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	BLAKE</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p28-37" n="37"/>
          <figure n="OrrImage4.28.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="580">
          	<figTranscr>DIEU ET MON<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	W BL[AKE]</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p28-38" n="38"/>
          <figure n="OrrImage5.28.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="557">
          	<figTranscr>BLAKE</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <figure n="OrrImage6.28.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="556"/> 
        	has never suffered the fate of poor
            Vincent and been lampooned into a Lust for Life production, but my work does take all
            necessary liberties with the facts. I can claim some kinship with Blake. I, too, am a
            printmaker and painter struggling away in my workshop with word and image convinced of
            my own peculiar set of dreams. My W. Blake, never parted from his straw hat (straw hat
            varnish, an acid resistant liquid still used by etchers today) stumbles through his
            world, ecstatic in his alchemical etching studio, bemused at art school by the fatuous
            behavior of fellow students and dreaming of fabulous tigers (inflated domestic moggy due
            to indigestion). In the country he wears a home-made tarpaulin and whistle holding cloak
            whilst nearby a sheep stares sadly at a knitted woollen jumper by its feet. Don’t look
            for a perfect televisual period recreation of eighteenth-century England, the odd
            transistor radio and fire extinguisher has crept in.</p>
          <p>The text that weaves through the images comes from <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, by
            G. E. Bentley, Jr. This is a biography constructed out of contemporaneous letters,
            newspapers reviews and reminiscences from which we learn that Blake once passed the
            remark that he thought the earth was flat. The recorder, Henry Crabb Robinson, tried to
            raise the question of circumnavigations, but at that moment dinner was called and the
            reply was lost. Saved by the gong. The general verdict on Blake seems to have
            been that he was mad but harmless. Blake neatly counters; “. . . there are probably men
            shut up as mad in Bedlam who are not so: that possibly the madmen outside have shut up
            the sane people.” It has recently been suggested that prescribed the “right” drugs Blake
            could have been “cured” of his visions. He was an obstinate man and believed he walked
            and talked with Socrates, Jesus Christ, and Michael Angelo. Unlike Doris Stokes of
            Balham (the south London medium who produced pastiches of the music of Beethoven seated
            at her piano and with her eyes closed) Blake proceeded after years of humdrum engraving
            commissions to produce his own most exquisite works of the imagination. During his
            lifetime he suffered much rejection. Not until we caught up with him and developed a
            proper respect for the inner eye did his star rise. It is difficult now to imagine our
            civilization without him.</p>
          <p>The 8 prints <hi rend="i">The Life of W. Blake</hi> are available as a boxed set from
            the artist. Write to 7 Bristle Hill, Buckingham MK18 1EZ England. Telephone 0280 815255.
            Price on application.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>