<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.2.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Marshall Brown, Preromanticism; G. J. Barker-Benfield, The Culture of
Sensibility: Sex and Society in Eighteenth-Century Britain</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <pb id="p28-62" n="62"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Marshall Brown, <hi rend="i">Preromanticism.</hi> Stanford University Press,
1991. xiv + 500 pp. $45. G. J. Barker-Benfield, <hi rend="i">The Culture of Sensibility: Sex and Society in
Eighteenth-Century Britain.</hi> University of Chicago Press, 1992. xxxiv + 520 pp.,11 illus. $49.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>These two books, each brilliant and deeply rewarding in its own way, make for an enlightening
comparison-and-contrast study of that era which Northrop Frye once proposed we label “the Age of Blake”
(<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> [Princeton 1947] 167). However that may be, Blake in these books remains
<hi rend="i">hors de concours</hi>, as the historian Barker-Benfield never mentions him, and the literary
critic’s most sustained comment on the poet trails away in clouds of his preferred writer:
<q>
It is worth remembering that one great outsider, William Blake, resolutely continued the vein of sensibility.
He rejected exchange and use and struggled to correct and convert the psychic economy of sensibility directly
into a blinding vision of universal truth. . . . plainly Blake’s “aching joys” and “dizzy raptures”
(to borrow some phrases from “Tintern Abbey”) were not of their time; they belong to that more adolescent
state of universal feeling when “nature. . ./ To me was all in all.” (103)
</q></p>
          <p>As “a history of the origins of literary Romanticism in Britain” (362), Brown’s exercise in
new formalism focuses on “the factors that promoted literary change and the processes that guided the course
of development specifically toward romanticism as we know it” (178)—even as it aims to correct “the
pseudoteleology of the old preromanticism” (360). A reading of the materialist Barker-Benfield, though,
recalls Blake’s argument that “the ratio of all we have already known. is not the same that it shall be
when we know more” (E 2). His book never forgets either the ubiquitous interpellative insistence of
strengthening British commercial capitalism or the figure of his chosen cultural hero, Mary Wollstonecraft:
“It was her <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> that first suggested to me that sensibility
was a culture, and a culture of women. . . . Because Wollstonecraft made sex the conscious and central subject
of her study, I have woven her analysis through my text” (xxviii). Wollstonecraft, however, is absent
entirely from Brown’s account. For Brown, Burns is “the original genius of romanticism” (363), but
Barker-Benfield mentions him not at all; for Brown, “[i]f sensibility is regarded as the cult of
            <figure n="MercierBibleLessons.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="310">
	<head>1. Phillippe Mercier, <hi rend="i">Bible Lesson</hi>, 1743.</head>
</figure>
feelings, then Boswell is its hero” (113), but no reference to his journals appears in the other book. Brown
devotes more pages to Goldsmith than to any other, a chapter to Cowper (<hi rend="i">The Task</hi>), another
to Sheridan (<hi rend="i">The School for Scandal</hi>), a long chapter to Wordsworth, and he discourses
elegantly on the “urbane sublime” and “transcendental aesthetics” of Gray and
Collins—Barker-Benfield mentions Goldsmith twice, Gray once, Collins, Sheridan, Cowper, and Wordsworth
never. But other names which recur regularly through <hi rend="i">The Culture of Sensibility</hi> are not to
be found in <hi rend="i">Preromanticism</hi>: Anna Laetitia Barbauld, Maria Edgeworth, Mary Hays, Hannah More,
Ann Radcliffe, John Wesley (each with more than 10 citations).</p>
          <p>Brown, then, concerns himself with a selection of literary masterpieces or “touchstones”
which collectively articulate problems and terms “that shaped discourses in the period: self-consciousness,
pure space and time, feeling, closure, the aesthetic, story, synthesis, sign, action, experienced time, and
finally, in Wordsworth, the fusion of all such concerns under the rubric of simplicity” (376).
Barker-Benfield’s more social text is the “continuous struggle” over the meanings and values of a
word—“sensibility”—which “signified revolution, promised freedom, threatened subversion, and became
convention,” which “denoted the receptivity of the senses and referred to the psychoperceptual scheme
explained and systematized by Newton and Locke,” and which “connoted the operation of the nervous system,
the material basis of consciousness” (xvii). The drama of this text is in how, “[s]elected by people in
accordance with the changing social circumstances of both sexes, elements of the nerve paradigm, of political
thought, the campaign for the reformation of manners, the evangelical challenge to orthodoxy, of literacy and
the commercialization of publishing—each integrally connected with the other and all to the establishment of
a consumer society—sensibility became a culture” (215).</p>
          <pb id="p28-63" n="63"/>
          <p>The different concerns of each book can be seen in their respective discussions of
“delicacy.” For Brown, the word—as in the title of Hugh Kelly’s 1768 play <hi rend="i">False
Delicacy</hi>—“refers to the negative functioning of language” since “the delicate person refrains
from uttering desires” (231). It is “an overrefined moral sense” which “internalizes inherited, partly
unspoken social codes” (231). Barker-Benfield begins by noting how “delicacy” was “virtually
synonymous with sensibility” and connoted “the nerve structure assumed by the latter term,” but he
emphasizes its role in sexual politics: “Traditional, patriarchal male control of female sexuality seems to
have been basic to shaping the code of delicacy” (299-300). He quotes John Bennett, who wrote in 1789 that
“Delicacy was [sic; ‘has’?] a very general and comprehensive quality. It extends to everything where
woman is concerned. Conversation, books, attitude, gesture, pronunciation should all come under its salutary
restraints” (207). “Delicacy” is thus revealed as a cornerstone of sensibility’s support of gender
distinctions under the commonplace, “man was made to reason, woman to feel” (302). For Wollstonecraft, the
code of delicacy “was symptomatic of the danger posed by women’s acculturation to the civilizing
process” (303).</p>
          <p>For Brown, preromanticism concerns the lurching movement toward the separation of consciousness
from experience: “when the separation is completed by the joining of the pure forms of space and of time,
consciousness becomes generalized”—as “romantic sensibility”—“into an abstracted reverie,
disembodied and out of touch with the world of sensation” (58). Cowper’s <hi rend="i">The Task</hi> is an
important staging-ground for this march from Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> and Gray’s 
<hi rend="i">Elegy</hi> to <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>, and Brown offers some fascinating pages relating the
changed views of consciousness represented by Cowper and Kant. Those who struggle with the meaning of
“polypus,” “vortex,” and “emanation” might sense a curious sympathy when Brown writes of Kant:
<q>
One need only observe the terminological welter—with its “idea” and “ideal,” its “transcendent”
and “transcendental,” its “axioms,” “anticipations,” “analogies,” and “postulates,” its
“syntheses” of “apperception,” “reproduction,” and “recognition” (none of these is an ordinary
German word), its “amphibole,” “paralogisms,” and “antinomies,” not to speak of its “dialele”
or “dialexis” (the text is uncertain), its “subreption of hypostasized consciousness,” and its
“euthanasia of pure reason”—one need only pass these terms in review to recognize an eighteenth-century
trait gone mad. Such extravagances differ from the personified abstractions of the urbane sublime in that they
reify states of consciousness rather than emotions and moral sentiments, but their function is comparable. . .
.(72)
</q></p>
          <p>To support the argument that “self-definition, self-regulation, and closure” (113) were
sensibility’s central problems, Brown makes Goldsmith a prominent indicator of the period’s literary
anxieties. His discussion of <hi rend="i">The Traveller, or a Prospect of Society</hi>, has Goldsmith seeming
to anticipate Blake’s mental traveler: “Governed by a visionary consciousness, the poem tends toward
making all consciousness visionary (and thus a covert projection of the traveler)”—though “the poem
contains signs intimating a covert recognition that its truth is at odds with its manifest content” (120,
123). The chapter on <hi rend="i">The Vicar of Wakefield</hi> is quite simply the best discussion I’ve ever
read of that apparently “simplest and most naive” of “influential masterworks,” that “paradigm of
literary beauty,” “carnival text” and “prototype for romantic organic form,” that nearly
“encyclopedic novel” and “revolutionary book” (166, 174, 175, 176, 177, 178). Brown is clearly taken
with “Goldsmith’s intense formalism” (179), and gives some insight into the psychodynamics of formalist
concerns when he admits to being “fonder of the page that discusses Goldsmith’s vowel harmony than of
anything else in the present study, for no better reason than that I was unable to enjoy reading his poetry
until I chanced to imagine that I could now hear his voice” (21).</p>
          <p>From Goldsmith, Brown turns to “the semiotic crisis” in Sheridan’s <hi rend="i">The School
for Scandal</hi>, the scandal being “the nonconformity of sign and significance” (222), and to the further
rethinking of the relationship between body and spirit in <hi rend="i">Le Mariage de Figaro</hi> of
Beaumarchais. That relationship is precisely the focus of <hi rend="i">Tristram Shandy</hi>, the “most
sensational and influential literary text of the period” (260—Barker-Benfield mentions the novel once),
and the subject of <hi rend="i">Preromanticism</hi>’s chapter on Sterne’s trajectory “[b]eyond reason
and fact, and toward story” (262). Frye identifies Sterne as the “chief prose writer” of “the Age of
Blake,” and surely the student of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> will see some possible connections
through Brown’s remarks that “Consciousness in Sterne is . . . the antithesis of reason. Reason is order,
logic, logos. Nothing is so irritating as an interruption, for that calls attention to the horizon limiting
the power of reason. . . . Sterne regularly turns his ridicule on immortal essences, bodiless minds, idealized
emotions. (‘<hi rend="i">If you will turn <hi rend="u">your eyes in</hi>wards upon your mind</hi>,’ Walter
Shandy pontificates in a pseudophilosophical discourse upon time . . .)” (270 [<hi rend="i">Tristram
Shandy</hi> 3.18], emphasis added). And Blake’s comment on the wide and unpassable gulf between simplicity
and insipidity (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 30) takes new resonance after Brown’s subchapter on “Simplicity After
Sterne” and the claim that “simplicity was the central literary problem in the last decades of the
century” (296)—a problem highlighted as much by the “fragmentation of perspectives” in the epistolary
novel with multiple correspondents (296) as by Sterne’s “chaotic overlay of incidents and chronologies”
(299).</p>
          <pb id="p28-64" n="64"/>
          <p>Brown’s book ends, then, with the complex simplicity of Wordsworth, whose mastery of “the
multiple modalities of time” correlates with “the unity of his consciousness with respect to the scene”
(349). In the author’s words, <hi rend="i">Preromanticism</hi><q>
narrates the rites of passage that chasten and subdue sensibility into romantic humanism. The conception of a
transcendental time and space and of a transcendental ego, the birth of an aesthetic imagination, the mastery
of plot and character development, the assemblage of an order of the organic, the emergence of will and of
action as the primary categories of selfhood, the disposition of the multiple temporality of the event. ..
(359-60)
</q>
All this is finely done, though one can’t help agreeing with the author in his conclusion, as he hopes that
his book “will affect the way readers think, but knows it will not so affect many, nor much, nor long . .
.” (382).</p>
          <p>Barker-Benfield’s book, on the other hand, should find a wide, receptive, and appreciative
audience, not least among Blakeans, who will find themselves already quite at home with <hi rend="i">The
Culture of Sensibility.</hi> Here we learn how “Newton emphasized that the vibrations of the ether could be
‘excited in the brain by the power of the will and propagated from thence’ [cf. ‘he his Emanations
propagated’ <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 4.2] through ‘the Nerves into the Muscles’” (5; cf. “Come into my
hand / . . . descending down the Nerves” <hi rend="i">M</hi> 2.5-6]; how other writers, like Richardson and
Burke, “used ‘fibres’ and ‘nerves’ interchangeably” (17); how “‘Spirits’ was a more specific
psychological and physiological referent” (18—cf. “every thing is conducted by Spirits” 
<hi rend="i">J</hi> 3); how “‘Vibration’ was yet another sign of the nerve paradigm” (20); and, in sum,
why and how Albion created “the female will,” and how Wollstonecraft resisted. The seemingly self-evident
juxtaposition of “the Church” and “the Ale-house” in “The Little Vagabond” assumes new depth as we
see how taverns, having assumed recreational activities driven out of the churchyard (57), became the object
of a fierce campaign of regulation in the 1770s and 1780s: “Along with the triumph of evangelism, strict
‘alehouse regulation became a cornerstone of local administrative policy’” (93).</p>
          <p>Bernard Mandeville emerges as a figure worth considering with regard to Blake: he “stated
unequivocally and repeatedly that women ‘lust’ as men do. Sexual appetite is ‘innate both in Men and
Women’” (128). With the examples Barker-Benfield supplies, we see how Mandeville “rejoiced in
physiological directness, puns, and other form [sic] of free and playful sexual speech” (126); for
Mandeville, “[w]omen were ‘educated’ into their ‘Weakness of frame and Softness,’” “pity was as
much ‘a frailty of our nature as Anger, Pride, or Fear,’” and denial a pervasive aspect of human
psychology: “‘we hide even from our selves the vast Extent of Self-Love, and all its different
Branches’” (127, 125, 121). The discussion of “Sensibility’s Method: Conversion” (250-58) enriches
the context of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>’s concern with what (if anything) changes when Saul becomes Paul, or
Milton, Blake—the poem’s occasion, in any event, certainly reflects an age in which “[w]riters made the
effects of reading a subject for their readers” (259).</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Culture of Sensibility</hi> includes 11 well-chosen illustrations, including
Francesco Bartolozzi’s <hi rend="i">London Merchants in the Royal Exchange</hi>, which supplies one physical
referent for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 24.42 (“In the Exchanges of London every Nation walkd”). Perhaps
the most interesting, however—for its version of the popular “scene of instruction” motif which appears
on the title page of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>—is the reproduction of Phillippe Mercier’s 1743
painting, <hi rend="i">Bible Lesson</hi> (fig. 1 [“Collection, Myles Hildyard, Photograph, Courtesy of the
Paul Mellon Center for Studies in British Art, London”]). The image aptly illustrates Barker-Benfield’s
discussion of how the early ideology of sensibility’s “culture of reform” centered on “the progenitrix
of social affections, a woman and usually a mother, in Richardson’s 1740 words, serving the ‘cause of
Virtue and Religion’” (217). On the other hand, anticipating the “female will” that resisted such
positioning and which was to culminate in the anti-Jacobin bogey of the Wollstonecraftian amazon at the end of
the century, Barker-Benfield quotes from “Mrs. C’s Complaint for the Loss of the Ace of Hearts” in a
1741 number of the <hi rend="i">Bath Miscellany</hi>:
<q>
Men oft-times sued in vain, with various arts,<lb/>
To seduce me from my charming ace of hearts,<lb/>
To no effect, I baffled all their skill,<lb/>
I scorned their offers, and pursued my will. (199)
</q>
“Conflict over the possibilities for women’s selfhood in the culture of sensibility and over the
directions their wishes should take” (xxvii) is thus a major theme, and the concluding chapter,
“Wollstonecraft and the Crisis over Sensibility in the 1790s” takes us straight into Blake’s valley of
vision with a new and vital appreciation of how, because “the definition of gender was seen to be
fundamental both to the Jacobin prospects for reform and to the Anti-Jacobin attempt to maintain the natural
order, the debate over sensibility became a key issue in British politics” (360).</p>
          <p>While neither book is without human failing, each makes a rewarding contribution to our sense of
the literary and cultural context of Blake’s work, a context whose daunting complexity they together
reiterate.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
