<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.2.viscomi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle: Lost or Found?</title>
        <author n="Viscomi">Joseph Viscomi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <pb id="p28-44" n="44"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main"><hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi>: Lost
            or Found?</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Joseph <name>Viscomi</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>In 1784, William Blake exhibited works at the Royal Academy entitled <hi rend="i">A
            Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi> and <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an
            Angel. Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi> (Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings
            and Drawings of William Blake</hi> 187, hereafter referred to as Butlin; numbers are
          catalogue entries).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n0">I am grateful to
            Martin Butlin and Robert N. Essick for reading early drafts of this article and for
            their many helpful suggestions.</note> The latter work, which may have been paired
          causally with <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>, is lost, and the identity of the former is a
          matter of debate. Some critics assume that the version exhibited is either the one now in
          the Ackland Museum of Art (Robertson 175; Blunt 11n27) or the one in the Carnegie Museum
          of Art (Cummings 160, Rosenblum 154n27), while others believe that it too is lost and that
          the Carnegie and Ackland versions are c. 1790-95 and c. 1795-1800 respectively (Pressly
          138-39; Butlin 188). In this study, I argue that there are strong technical and aesthetic
          reasons to believe that the drawing in the Ackland Museum is both the second version and
          the one exhibited in 1784, and that the first two versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>
          are also incorrectly dated. My intention, though, is not only to argue that Robertson and
          Blunt were correct about the Ackland version of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>, but also to
          examine why and how the same artifact can appear to one art historian to have been
          produced c. 1784 and to another as late as 1800. While disagreement about dates is not
          unprecedented in Blake studies, this one is unusually pronounced and raises serious
          questions about the assumptions and kinds of evidence (e.g., historical documents,
          techniques, materials, styles, and themes) used to date these and other Blake designs.
          Indeed, by redating versions of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>, I am not only redating
          versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> but am also challenging currently accepted ideas
          of Blake’s pictorial style and development in the 1780s and 1790s. Furthermore, the
          inconsistencies in the hypotheses used to date and sequence the versions of <hi rend="i">A
            Breach</hi> and <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> require our rethinking the date and place
          of a particular sketch (illus. 12) in the evolution of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>—which,
          in turn, questions Blake’s use and understanding of sketching in general.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">The Production and Evolution of <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the
                  Morning after the Battle</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The extant versions of Blake’s <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the
              Battle</hi> are in the Carnegie Museum (illus. 1), the Ackland Museum (illus. 2), and
            the Fogg Art Museum (illus. 3), though we know this last version as 
              <hi rend="i">War.</hi> These three watercolors are dated c. 1790-95, c. 1795-1800, and 1805,
            respectively (Butlin 189, 191, 195). They appear to have been executed or at least
            paired with versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, which are in the collections of
            the late Gregory Bateson (on loan to the Ackland Museum) (illus. 13), the Bristol Museum
            and Art Gallery (illus. 14), and the Boston Museum of Fine Arts (illus. 15; Butlin 190,
            192, 193).</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> and <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> were first described in
            Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> (1863), but the descriptions are
            the source of much subsequent confusion. Gilchrist was unaware that there was more than
            one version of <hi rend="i">A Breach.</hi> From the 1784 Royal Academy exhibition
            catalogue, he knew of the exhibited version and of <hi rend="i">War Unchained</hi>, but
            he had seen neither work (1: 54). He identifies the theme of both as “the supreme
            despicableness of War” and claims that they “gave birth about twenty years later to four
            very fine water-colour drawings, . . . <hi rend="i">Fire, Plague, Pestilence</hi>, and
              <hi rend="i">Famine</hi>” (1: 54). By “Pestilence” Gilchrist apparently means 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>: <hi rend="i">The Death of the First Born</hi> (Butlin 442),
            because he had titled the c. 1805 version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (illus. 15) as
            “Plague” and had it reproduced as a wood-engraving by W. J. Linton and inserted to face
            page 54.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Gilchrist’s
mistitling suggests that he was
            also unaware that there was more than this one version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>,
            since both early versions were so titled by Blake (illus. 13, 14). 
                <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The c. 1805 version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> was
acquired by
              J. C. Strange from Thomas Butts, Jr. at Foster’s on 29 June 1853 (lot #131). Gilchrist
              apparently borrowed the work from Strange for W. J. Linton to reproduce.</note></p>
          <p>In 1862, a year after Gilchrist died and a year before the <hi rend="i">Life of
              Blake</hi> was published, William Michael Rossetti, using Gilchrist’s lists and those
            of William Haines, began to compile for the <hi rend="i">Life</hi> the first catalogue
            raisonné of Blake’s drawings and paintings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> Like
            Gilchrist, Rossetti had seen neither <hi rend="i">War Unchained</hi> nor the two early
            versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, though he had examined the sketch (241,
              #18).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Unlike Gilchrist,
he had also examined the
            Carnegie version of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>, which had sold in “Mr. [Elhanan]
            Bicknell’s Sale, [May] 1863” as “The Plague,” a title that Rossetti recognized was
            “decidedly a mistake,” since that was what Gilchrist and he called the c. 1805 version
            of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (207, #55). Rossetti apparently identified the
            Bicknell/Carnegie drawing as <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>, the work exhibited in the Royal
            Academy in 1784 (201, #5), on the basis of its subject—a breached city wall filled with
            dead soldiers and mourners—since the work itself was not inscribed or titled or in any
            other way identified by Blake. <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The catalogue is
              included in the second volume of the <hi rend="i">Life</hi> (199-268) and is here
              referred to as Rossetti, followed by page and catalogue numbers.</note>	
                <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Rossetti was thought to have examined the Bristol version of
                <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, but Butlin’s provenance (192) is actually that of the
              sketch (see Essick, <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 118; Bennett 136, 138), while the Bristol
              version itself “remains without a provenance until the sale of works from the
              collection of Henry Willet at Christie’s on 10 April 1904” (Butlin “Footnotes” 17).
              Rossetti’s unawareness of the Bateson version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> is
              troubling, since it was sold at Sotheby’s on 29 April 1862, supposedly by Frederick
              Tatham. He is identified as the vendor to this anonymous sale because of the number of
              Blake works sold (over 200 items) and the preponderance of sketches, the kind of work
              Tatham inherited through Mrs. Blake. That Rossetti was corresponding with Tatham at
              this time but unaware of the sale (the works from the sale that he records were known
              to him through their new owners, like Harvey, Palser, and Palgrave, and not from the
              sale or its catalogue) raises the possibility that the vendor was someone other than
              Tatham, and/or that someone was purchasing works from Mrs. Blake between 1827 and
              1831.</note></p>
          <pb id="p28-45" n="45"/>
          <p>Like Gilchrist, Rossetti was unaware that there was more than one version of 
              <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>, Bicknell’s version being the only one that he actually
            examined. He knew of the Fogg version, but he knew it as <hi rend="i">War</hi> and
            appears not to have realized that it was a version of <hi rend="i">A Breach.</hi> He
            knew of <hi rend="i">War</hi> because it was “mentioned” by that title “in the account”
            (209, #68), by which he means Thomas Butts’s account of 12 May 1805 
              (<hi rend="i">Life</hi> 2: 256; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 572). But Rossetti
            lists <hi rend="i">War</hi> twice, implying that there were two works so titled. The
            second he records as belonging to a “Mr. Fuller” (238, #227), whose Blake collection of
            nine watercolors he knew only through an 1852 Sotheby’s sale catalogue.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
              type="note">4</ref> By 1876, <hi rend="i">War</hi> belonged to J. F. Hall, who lent it
            to the Burlington Fine Arts Club exhibition. One assumes that Rossetti saw it at that
            time, since he reviewed the exhibition for <hi rend="i">Academy</hi> (9 [1876]: 364-65).
            In his revised 1880 lists, he continues to record it as <hi rend="i">War</hi>, the work
            “mentioned in the account” (216, #75), but deletes the second reference because he comes
            to believe that Fuller’s <hi rend="i">War</hi> is <hi rend="i">War Unchained</hi> of
              1784.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> More confusing
still, Rossetti fails to
            mention the connection of Hall’s <hi rend="i">War</hi> to <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>,
            despite that connection having been explicitly made in the 1876 exhibition catalogue.
              <hi rend="i">War</hi> is listed there as “Breach in the City Wall: Morning After the
            Battle. Water colour. No. 5 in Catalogue, ‘Gilchrist’s Life.’ Exhibited at the Royal
            Exhibition, 1784” (entry 185). <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Fuller was probably
              Joseph or Samuel Fuller, print dealers in London from 1808 to 1862. He bought his
              Blake watercolors on 26 June 1852 at Sotheby’s. For an examination of this auction,
              its vendors, and the Blake works sold, see my “Blake and the Marketplace
              1852.”</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> In his annotated copy, Rossetti writes
              next to Fuller’s <hi rend="i">War.</hi> “So far as one can surmise, may be the same as
              No 4,” by which he means <hi rend="i">War Unchained.</hi> Next to #4 he writes “Mr.
              Fuller from Mr. Butts,” which in the 1880 lists is shortened to “Butts,” because Butts
              and Linnell are the only owners recorded in the second edition. <p>Rossetti’s
                annotated copy of the <hi rend="i">Life</hi> is in the Houghton Library, Harvard
                University, annotated supposedly between 1868 and 1876 (see Wittreich and Butlin,
                “Annotations”). But Rossetti appears to have begun making notes very soon after
                publication of the <hi rend="i">Life.</hi> In a letter of 6 November 1863, Anne
                Gilchrist refers to Rossetti’s “annotations to the Blake,” which were, Rossetti
                explained, “certain pencillings I had made in my copy of Gilchrist’s 
                  <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, which was by this time already published” 
                  (<hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers</hi> 41, 40).</p></note></p>
          <p>In 1863, Rossetti was unaware of the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> altogether. This
            version, the only one titled by Blake, was then owned by Alfred Aspland, whose extensive
            collection of Blake watercolors and drawings was then unknown to Rossetti. Aspland lent
            his version to the 1876 Burlington Fine Arts Club exhibition, where it was described as
            “A Breach in the City: The Morning After the Battle. Water colour. This title is written
            on it by Blake, with the date apparently of 1780. This drawing, or another with the same
            title, was exhibited in 1784. See No. 5 in Catalogue, ‘Gilchrist’s Life’” (entry 157).
            The Burlington title differs slightly from the inscription on the watercolor itself,
            which reads, “A Breach in A City the Morning / after the Battle / W Blake inv &amp; d.”
            The supposed date of “1780” is a misreading of “inv &amp; d,” one recorded by Rossetti
            in 1880 (208, #5). The ampersand—if that is what it is—is completely indistinct (illus.
            8). Nor are there periods after it, “inv,” and “W” (pace Robertson 175), or after
“inv”
            and “&amp;” (pace Butlin 191, Pressley 138). In his revised 1880 lists, Rossetti records
            the Aspland/Ackland version at the end of the entry for the Carnegie version (208, #5),
            but he fails to indicate which version was exhibited in 1784.</p>
          <p>Aspland’s version was acquired in 1904 by W. Graham Robertson, who reproduced it in his
            1907 edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> as the one exhibited (1: 54). It is
            so identified in his <hi rend="i">Blake Catalogue</hi> of 1952 (175-77, pl. 56), and his
            view was apparently shared by Kerrison Preston—who edited the catalogue and acquired the
            work in 1961, a year before it went to the Ackland Museum—and shared by Anthony Blunt as
            well (11n27, pl. 8b). These owners and critics do not sequence the early versions of 
              <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> or pair them with versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, nor
            do they explain their reasons for choosing the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> as the
            one exhibited.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Apparently,
they believe their choice
            is self-evident, probably because the inscription suggests as much, since it is the
            title by which the work is identified in the Royal Academy catalogue. At any rate, they
            clearly do not find the style of the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> to be inconsistent
            with Blake’s pen and wash style of the mid-1780s. <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> In
              Robertson’s catalogue, the Fogg and Carnegie versions are conflated; the latter is
              described with the former’s measurements and provenance (176-77).</note></p>
          <p>Frederick Cummings and Robert Rosenblum believe that Blake exhibited the Carnegie
            version and that the Ackland version followed, though how long afterwards they do not
            say. This position, articulated in Cummings’s 1968 exhibition catalogue, maintains that
            the “care, detail, and emotional conviction” of the Carnegie version suggest that it was
            the version exhibited, whereas the Ackland version, because it “is less detailed, [and]
            has less conviction,” is but “a simpler reworking” of the Carnegie (160).<ref
              target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Placing the 
<pb id="p28-46" n="46"/>
<figure n="breachInACity.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="313">
              <head>1. <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi>, c.
                1784.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor (29.7 × 46.3 cm.). Museum of Art, Carnegie Institute,
                Pittsburgh.</figDesc>
            </figure> Carnegie version <hi rend="i">before</hi> the Ackland is certainly correct,
            but not because the Carnegie is more detailed and carefully executed than the subsequent
            version. The same stylistic features characterize revisions or second versions of other
            works, while relaxed handling may reflect an artist’s first thoughts on a subject.
            Indeed, the Carnegie’s companion piece, the Bateson version of 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (illus. 13), is sketchier and was shown less care than the
subsequent
            Bristol version (illus. 14). <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Rosenblum states that
              David Bindman agrees with Cummings about the Carnegie version of <hi rend="i">A
                Breach</hi> (154n27). Bindman, though, in his <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi>,
              agrees with Cummings’s sequence but not his dates. Apparently the care noted by
              Cummings leads Bindman to the conclusion that the Carnegie “seems too accomplished”
              for 1784, “unless Blake re-worked it later.” Adding to the confusion, Bindman
              reproduces the Ackland version but identifies it as the version in the Fogg (plate
              59), and believes that both the Ackland and Fogg versions “may be post-1800” (231n19).
              The Fogg, of course, is dated by Blake 1805, but a post-1800 date for the Ackland is
              even later than the one suggested by Butlin, which, as we shall see, is inferred from
              a misreading of the signature’s form.</note></p>
          <p>While an increase or decrease in detail does not reliably mark sequence, changes
            between versions that are also corrections do. For example, in the bottom left corner of
            the Carnegie version (illus. 1), the right foot of the soldier crosses the line forming
            the arm of another soldier, rendering the foot transparent. In the Ackland version
            (illus. 2), Blake corrected this mistake by repositioning the arm. The hand retains its
            original gesture, but instead of grasping a strap that appears connected to a shield,
            contrary to the manner in which the bottom shield is held, it now grasps either the hilt
            of a sword or the top (and wrong end) of a banner. The figure to the right, outstretched
            in the breached wall, is solidly on top of bodies in the Ackland version, whereas in the
            Carnegie version this figure is tentatively drawn over and through a curved line that
            apparently was meant to suggest a shield rather than the figure’s chest or robe. The
            high-arching back of the mourning woman was repeated in the Ackland version but then
            erased and lowered, while her long neck was shortened, making her proportions more
            realistic. Perhaps the most significant alteration was the addition of the old man’s
            crutches in the Ackland version, though traces of them are visible in the Carnegie,
            where the right one goes only as high as the sash and the left one seems to have been
            made of glass, passing through a hand (illus. 1). Blake apparently added the crutches
            after he had drawn the hand—that is, he decided to add them only after the composition
            had been designed and drawn in ink. Initially, the hand may have grasped the hilt of a
            sword, pole, or spear, which in turn may have suggested the idea of crutches, an idea
            developed in the second version.</p>
          <p>The fingers and toes of the figures in the Carnegie version are generally more detailed
            and carefully drawn than those in the Ackland, but the assumption that the Carnegie
            version in its entirety was shown more “care” ignores the many drawing mistakes Blake
            had made, as well as the fact 
<pb id="p28-47" n="47"/>
<figure n="BUT191.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="667">
              <head>2. <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi>, c.
                1784.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor (32.9 × 47.9 cm.). Ackland Art Museum, University of North
                Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figDesc>
            </figure> that the Carnegie version is unfinished. Not only are the crutches incomplete,
            but the old man’s robe, painted blue above the sash, was left uncolored below and to the
            left of the sash. Such an assumption also ignores the very weak blocking of the Carnegie
            design. For example, the breach is so crowded with bodies and armor that it lacks visual
            and thematic focus, expressing the effect of war on a city’s defenses, instead of the
            horrors of war per se. By removing the shield at the far left and the soldier left of
            the casket, Blake shows more of the wall and, more significantly, more of the soldier
            outside the wall. This soldier, lost among bodies in the Carnegie version, is now
            distinct with highlighted chest and face, representing the numerous but face-less dead
            behind him and the wall. By simplifying the configuration of bodies at the breach and
            giving the distant dead a face, Blake expresses more clearly the theme that “War” is the
            fountain of “bitter Death &amp; of corroding Hell / Till Brotherhood is changd into a
            Curse” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 35: 3-4).</p>
          <p>This theme is far more overt in the 1805 version (illus. 3), where the “enemy” dead,
            rather than being dehumanized, are delineated as carefully as those lying inside the
            walls. The top figure appears collapsed in despair over his comrades rather than one of
            the dead; embracing two of them, he is analogous to the woman mourning her lover. In the
            Ackland version, the two camps are not yet so neatly parallel, but they are moving in
            that direction, as is suggested by the woman in the killing fields. Like the figures
            standing beside the wall, she witnesses the carnage, but the sympathy she elicits is due
            more to her moving cautiously and looking apprehensively, gestures of fear suggested by
            her dramatically outstretched hands and, most significantly, her wide open eye. Both
            gestures are missing in the Carnegie version, where she is drawn less expressively and
            has no eye at all. The removal of the soldier left of the casket also reveals that the
            Ackland version is moving toward paralleling the warring camps. This middle soldier,
            with the awkwardly formed armor, is replaced by even clearer symbols of war: a
            spear—enlarged dramatically, relative to the Carnegie version—and a banner. Implements
            that are thrust upward in military gallantry lie fallen and futile. The addition of the
            infant and crutches in the Ackland version also infuse the overall situation, rather
            than the breached wall, with horror, implying that everyone, from newborns to mothers,
            soldiers, and aged, is equally affected by war. The Ackland version is simpler, but it
            is not simplistic. Blake’s changes, generated by aesthetic and technical needs, resulted
            in a more focused, powerful, and expressive work.</p>
          <p>The inference, then, that the Carnegie was the version 
<pb id="p28-48" n="48"/>
			<figure n="BUT195.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="737">
              <figTranscr>inv<lb/>
              WB<lb/>
              1805</figTranscr>
              <head>3. <hi rend="i">War</hi>, 1805.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen, pencil, and watercolor (29.8 × 38.7 cm.). Fogg Art Museum, Harvard
                University, Cambridge, Massachusetts.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            exhibited, based entirely on the premises that it is more carefully executed
            than the Ackland version and that care reflects Blake’s intention to exhibit, is
            unconvincing. I suspect that Blake executed the Carnegie version first, recognized his
            various mistakes while washing the design, and proceeded immediately to produce a
            second, revised version, which he inscribed most likely with an eye to exhibition. Blake
            chose to repeat the composition on wove paper instead of laid—the support he used for
            the Carnegie version—which also suggests that he intended to exhibit the new and
            corrected version of his design, since the wove, the heavier and more expensive paper,
            took dark washes better, and since the three extant watercolors Blake exhibited at the
            Royal Academy in 1785 were also executed on wove paper.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Three of Blake’s exhibited works in the
              1780s are untraced: <hi rend="i">Death of Earl Godwin, War Unchained</hi>, and 
                <hi rend="i">The Bard</hi> (Butlin 60, 187, 160). But the three watercolors of 
                <hi rend="i">Joseph and his Brethren</hi>, exhibited in 1785, are on wove paper and,
              like the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi>, trimmed to the image, which was routinely
              required of drawings exhibited (see Essick, “Blake’s 1812 Exhibition,” 36).</note></p>
          <p>This scenario, however, differs completely from the one Martin Butlin proposes. Butlin
            believes Cummings’s sequence but believes also that both versions of <hi rend="i">A
              Breach</hi> are too “accomplished” for 1784, that both were produced in the 1790s,
            possibly five to 10 years apart, and that the exhibited version is lost. The Carnegie
            version, he argues, “seems rather too advanced for the work exhibited in 1784, being
            somewhat freer and more accomplished than that of the illustrations to 
              <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789, to which it is otherwise fairly close. It is probably the
            companion to the Bateson collection <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> of the early 1790s”
            (189). Butlin dates the Carnegie and Bateson works c. 1790-95. He concedes that the
            Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> “has sometimes been confused with that exhibited at the
            Royal Academy in 1784,” but he notes that its “style is somewhat more relaxed: for
            instance the head of the standing woman on the right is no longer in strict, classical
            profile” (193). He dates the Ackland version c. 1795-1800.</p>
          <p>If the Carnegie and Ackland versions appear more accomplished than the 
              <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> illustrations—which neither does to me—it may be because they are
nearly
            twice their size (which accounts for their handling “being somewhat freer”) and were
            executed as autonomous works, whereas the illustrations have some of the stiffness
            characteristic of designs executed to be engraved, in which washes are laid in precisely
            to facilitate the engraver’s effort to translate them into linear codes. The “early
            1790s” date for the Bateson <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, with which the Carnegie 
              <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> is linked, is itself suspect. It is based on two premises: first,
              <pb id="p28-49" n="49"/>
that the Bateson version stylistically resembles the pen and
            wash drawing, <hi rend="i">The House of Death</hi>, and second, that this drawing is c.
            1790 (Butlin 190, 259). But the second premise is based on its style appearing to be “a
            later development of the style and technique of the pen and wash drawings of the 1780s,”
            a set of drawings that excludes all versions of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> and 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (Butlin 259). The logic, in other words, is circular.
            Moreover, the c. 1790 date of <hi rend="i">The House of Death</hi> is relative to that
            of <hi rend="i">The Good and Evil Angels</hi>, a watercolor dated c. 1793-94 because it
            follows plate 4 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, which is
            supposedly 1790-93 (Butlin 257; Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 285). 
              <hi rend="i">House</hi> is clearly before <hi rend="i">Angels</hi>, and 
              <hi rend="i">Angels</hi> seems easy enough to date; the problem is that <hi rend="i">Angels</hi>
            could be as early as 1790, because that is most likely the end date for 
              <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Idea</hi> chap. 26). If the sequence and
spacing
            hold—and I believe they do—then <hi rend="i">House</hi> dates from the mid-1780s.</p>
          <p>The dates for the Carnegie and Ackland versions of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> are in
            part derived from those of their pendants, the Bateson and Bristol versions of 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (illus. 13, 14). It is probably true that the paired works
            share the same date. However, if one version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> was
            executed before 1790 then both were, for they were executed very close to one another,
            and not five to 10 years apart. The Bateson version, which is certainly not as
            accomplished as the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> illustrations, is sketchier than the
            Bristol version, with the gravedigger’s face redrawn so that the chin rests on the
            chest, an alteration retained in the Bristol. Other than this difference, they are
            exceedingly close compositionally and stylistically. In both versions, the hair color of
            the two women is yellow, the hair on three of the men is orangish-brown, the skirts of
            the front pallbearer and gravedigger are orange and yellow respectively, and the
            background wash is a yellowish grey.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> Given that both
            versions are essentially monochromatic wash drawings with touches of color, the same
            palette and placing of colors strongly suggest that the first and second versions were
            executed and finished very near to one other. Had there been years between versions, one
            would expect differences as pronounced as those between the second and third versions.
            Indeed, such differences in coloring and/or design mark all versions of works reproduced
            a year or more after the first, even when the new versions were modeled closely on the
            original composition. Compare, for example, the second versions of <hi rend="i">Paradise
              Lost, Comus, House of Death, God Judging Adam</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Good and Evil
              Angels</hi> (Butlin 536, 528, 320, 294, 323) with their models (Butlin 529, 527, 259,
            257, 258). Copies of illuminated books from different editions also show pronounced
            differences, whereas copies from the same edition—say, <hi rend="i">Songs of
              Innocence</hi> copies B and E—are exceedingly similar, sharing the same palette and
            coloring style and differing only in the placement of some colors (see Viscomi, 
              <hi rend="i">Idea</hi> chap. 14).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi
                rend="s">9</hi> In Butlin’s color reproduction of the Bateson 
                <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (189), the background wash is pinkish, which makes the washes of
              the two works seem less similar than they are.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> The works commisioned by Linnell, like the <hi rend="i">Wise and Foolish
                Virgins</hi>, c. 1822, the three <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs, and 
                <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi> (Butlin 479, 537, 551), may seem like exceptions
              because they repeat the original (or previously executed) compositions so exactly
              (Butlin 478, 536, 550). The repetition results from Blake’s working from tracings of
              the originals and reflects the purpose of the commissions, which presumably was to
              keep as close as possible to the works that generated the commissions in the first
              place. Even when the composition remained the same, however, the coloring and
              highlights differed, sometimes radically, as they did in the Linnell versions. The
              subtle and not-so-subtle changes made among versions of the same work, even from
              tracings and from impressions from the same illuminated plate, reflect what Essick
              calls Blake’s “creative revisionism” (<hi rend="i">Language of Adam</hi>
            116).</note></p>
          <p>Nothing in the production of the second versions of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> and 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> suggests that they were not done the same week or month as
            the first. Both were developed from tracings of the first versions. The tracings can be
            inferred from the fact that the sizes of the figures and the relations among them are
            the same in the two versions, despite slight differences in paper size.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
              type="note">11</ref> The Bristol version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> even repeats
            exactly the anatomically incorrect positioning of the back pallbearer’s foot beneath the
            woman. Such similitude is neither accidental nor the result of redrawing freehand. It
            results from either graticulating or “calking” the original. The first method requires
            drawing a grid over the original and redrawing the design on a support similarly
            squared, keeping the same coordinates between design and grid as in the original. But
            this method was used to enlarge or reduce copy. The method usually used to transfer
            outlines onto clean sheets of paper (or copper plates covered with etching ground) was
            “calking.” A tracing of the original outline is made on transparent paper (or thin post
            paper) and placed over a clean sheet of paper. <corr type="emend">Transference</corr> required either that the
            verso of the tracing be covered with black or red chalk, or that a thin sheet so treated
            be inserted between the tracing and new sheet of paper. The outline is then retraced
            with a stylus and thereby transferred to the new support. An alternative method was to
            work from the original itself and not from a tracing, by inserting a calking sheet
            between the original and the new 
<pb id="p28-50" n="50"/>
<figure n="BUT144.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="644">
              <head>4. <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</hi>,
                1783.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor (28.3 × 42.3 cm.). New York Public Library.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<figure n="witchOfEndorInscription.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="73">
              <head>4a. <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</hi>, detail of
                inscription.</head>
            </figure>
<figure n="witchOfEndorSignature.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="99">
              <head>4b. <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</hi>, detail of
                signature.</head>
            </figure> sheet of paper and tracing the original’s outline with a stylus. In this
            latter method, though, the artist needs to press harder over the outline to transfer
            lines and thus subjects the original to possible defacement. When it is used, as it was
            to transfer a few of Blake’s designs for Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original
              Stories</hi> (e.g., “Oeconomy &amp; Self-denial”) to copper plates, the verso of the
            paper shows the indention of the stylus (see also Butlin 340). Such markings are absent
            from the second versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> and <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>,
            though the latter has a few indentions of a stylus on its face (along the eagle, wall,
            and reclining figures).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
These indentions are
            presumably from the pencil or stylus used to calk the outline from the tracing. The
            pinholes in the top right and left corners of the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi>
            support this hypothesis, for tracings were often fastened to the new sheet by pins.
              <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Ordinary writing or printing paper is made
              transparent when washed with a 50-50 solution of linseed oil and turpentine. Such
              paper becomes yellow and brittle over time and has a very short life span. Thin post
              paper or regular sheets of writing paper are made more transparent and effective when
              the model is placed over a light source, like a window. Transferring outlines to
              copper from tracings was standard procedure in graphic art; Blake’s use of the method
              is evinced by the pinholes and wax marks on designs he reproduced (see, for example,
              the glue marks on the emblem drawings for <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi> in
              Blake’s Notebook). It is also evinced by his borrowing Butt’s <hi rend="i">Book of
                Job</hi> watercolors for Linnell to trace for the new series (Bentley, 
                <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 273-74). The only Blake tracings extant are of 
                <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> and of <hi rend="i">The Virgin Hushing the Young
                Baptist</hi> (Butlin 646 and 645, 408 and 406; see also 831).</note>	
                <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> I discovered the stylus marks with the aid of a strong
              magnifying glass, but I found independent confirmation in <hi rend="i">The Ackland Art
                Museum Newsletter</hi> 16 (1984), which described <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> as “pen
              and black ink, gray wash and watercolor, with traces of stylus(?), underdrawing on
              off-white wove paper” (2).</note></p>
          <p>The only marked difference between the two versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> is
            that the faces of two figures were changed from profile to three-quarter view; the same
            repositioning of heads also differentiates the two versions of <hi rend="i">A
              Breach</hi> and partly accounts for why this design’s first and second versions are
            paired with those of <hi rend="i">Pestilence.</hi> But three-quarter views are not why
            the second versions are second. In both designs, Blake appears to have repositioned
            heads and gazes for dramatic effect and to diversify the pictorial plane. Technically
            and aesthetically, he did nothing he hadn’t done earlier and as well. Indeed, in 
              <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</hi> (illus. 4; Butlin 144),
            which Blake signed and dated 1783, the faces alternate between profile and
            three-quarter, much as they do in the Bristol <hi rend="i">Pestilence. Joseph</hi><pb
              id="p28-51" n="51"/><hi rend="i">Ordering Simeon to Be Bound</hi> (Butlin 156), which
            Blake exhibited in 1785, also shows a deliberately diverse range of facial positions.
            This latter work is especially telling, for it is based on a sketch (Butlin 158) in
            which two of the three-quarter faces are profiles and one of the profiles is
            three-quarter. The sketch and finished drawing were executed near one another in time,
            and the changes between them are analogous to those found in the first and second
            versions of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> and <hi rend="i">Pestilence.</hi> Three-quarter
            views signify neither special accomplishment nor an advanced drawing style, nor do
            repositioned heads signify years between versions.</p>
          <p>The Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> is, indeed, more “relaxed” and even sketchier than
            it appears in Butlin’s atrocious color reproduction, probably the worst in his
            magnificent catalogue. The original in Chapel Hill is not muddy, as it is in the
            reproduction, nor is it as dark and pinkish.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> The
            bodies in the killing fields beyond the breached wall, for example, are mere circles and
            arched lines (illus. 5), but so are those in the Carnegie version. Technically, the
            Ackland version lies somewhere between a pen and wash and a watercolor drawing; it is
            monochromatic except for traces of pink in the old man’s robe, the dead woman’s wrap,
            the arm of the soldier at the far left, and yellowish-brown hair in the three right
            figures. It is more relaxed and less advanced than the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> drawings
            and even the illustrations of <hi rend="i">Joseph</hi> (Butlin 155-57), and certainly
            less sophisticatedly painted or “accomplished” than color-print drawings and the
            illustrations to <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> and Gray’s “Poems,” with which its c.
            1795-1800 date associates it. Indeed, its coloring is less sophisticated than that of
            the large-paper copies of illuminated books or <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copies I, J, L,
            N, and O, all of which were produced and colored c. 1794-95—before the illustrations to
            the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> and Gray’s “Poems.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Because many of the large-paper copies of illuminated books
and copies of
              <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> had been misdated post-1800, Blake’s development as a colorist
            seemed erratic and his work as a painter and printmaker appeared disconnected. Hence,
            his period styles seemed either indeterminate or inconsistent. When these copies of
            illuminated books are perceived as the work of the mid-1790s, however, they reveal that
            Blake’s coloring style for drawings and relief prints was consistent. They also reveal
            that the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> was executed in an earlier period, more in the
            style of works like <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor</hi> (illus. 4) and <hi rend="i">The
              Spirit of a Just Man Newly Departed Appearing to His Mourning Family</hi> (Butlin
            135), works executed by the mid-1780s. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> According to
              Martin Butlin, the fault for the reproduction lies entirely with the poor transparency
              that the Ackland sent to Yale University Press, the catalogue’s publisher.</note>	
              <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> For the dates and coloring styles of these last sets of
              illuminated books, see Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Idea</hi> chap. 30.</note></p>
          <p>The second versions of both <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> and <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>
            are tied technically to the first versions and resemble them stylistically. 
<figure n="aBreachInACityDetail.28.2" rend="file" width="662" height="1000">
              <head>5. <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi>, c.
                1784.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor; detail of breached wall. Ackland Art Museum, University
                of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figDesc>
            </figure> There are no good reasons to believe that they were executed five to 10 years
            after the first. What would have motivated Blake to return to these works at that time?
            Why work from a tracing instead of freehand, which provides far greater freedom to
            rethink the design, as evinced in the third versions of both 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> and <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>? More importantly, why would he
            duplicate the minimalist coloring in or after 1795, when he employed an enriched palette
            and coloring style in his other works? Returning years later to an earlier style of
            execution seems <corr type="emend">implausible;</corr> conversely, the similarity in style
suggests that Blake
            returned to the works while they were still fresh in mind. The aesthetic quality of the
            first version of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> may have provided the motivation to revise
            the composition. The incompletely colored robe in the Carnegie <hi rend="i">Breach</hi>
            suggests that Blake stopped before finishing, presumably having already decided to
            redraw it instead of erasing lines and figures. This decision probably influenced the
            one to redraw <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> as well, creating the second pair. As noted,
            Blunt and Robertson believe that the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> is 1784, while
            Cummings and Rosenblum believe that the Carnegie version is 1784. All four were probably
            correct.</p>
          <pb id="p28-52" n="52"/>
          <figure n="War1805.detail.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="268">
            <head>6. <hi rend="i">War</hi>, 1805.</head>
            <figDesc>Pen, pencil, and watercolor; detail. Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University,
              Cambridge, Massachusetts.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="bb74.1.14.ms.detail" id="bb74.1.ms.14" work-copy="bb74.1" rend="file" width="958" height="270">
            <figTranscr>{Let cherubim &amp; seraphim now raise their voices high}<lb/>
            Then like a mighty wind they raise to heavn the voice of song<lb/>
            Or like harmonious thunderings the seats of heavn among<lb/>
            Beneath them sit the revrend men the guardians of the poor<lb/>
            Then cherish pity lest you drive an angel from your door<lb/>
            After this they all sat silent for a quarter of an hour {&amp; Mrs Sigtagatist} &amp; Mrs Nannicantipot<lb/>
            said it puts me in Mind of my {grand} mothers song</figTranscr>
            <head>7. <hi rend="i">The Island in the Moon</hi>, page 7, c. 1784.</head>
            <figDesc>Pen and ink (30.8 × 18.5 cm.); detail. Fitzwilliam Museum of Art.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Why then does Butlin date these works so late? The idea that they are too advanced or
            accomplished for mid-1780s seems predicated on their size and their having figures with
            three-quarter views, as though such gazes are technically and psychologically more
            complex and advanced. These reasons, however, are secondary in Butlin’s overall
            argument, which is actually anchored by a solid hypothesis misapplied: that the forms of
            Blake’s signature are dateable. Of the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi>, he states: “its
            style, size and form of signature show it to be a companion to the version of 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> at Bristol and to date probably from the later 1790s” (193).
            The Ackland and Bristol drawings are signed “W Blake inv &amp; d” and “WBlake inv d”
              respectively.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
Moreover, they are the only
            drawings in which “inv” and “d” were combined, which suggests a deliberate pairing.<ref
              target="n16" type="note">16</ref> They are dated c. 1795-1800 because their signatures
            supposedly resemble the monogram that Blake began using almost exclusively in watercolor
            drawings and prints between 
<pb id="p28-53" n="53"/>
<figure n="aBreachinaCity.signature.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="91">
              <head>8. <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi>, c.
                1784.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor; detail of signature. Ackland Art Museum, University of
                North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<figure n="pestilence1784.signature.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="97">
              <head>9. <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, c. 1784.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor; detail of signature. City of Bristol Museum and Art
                Gallery.</figDesc>
            </figure> 1795 and 1805. The questions to ask of both works, then, are these: are the
            signatures really like the monogram? Were the works signed when produced, or were they
            signed afterward? <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> The “d” is for “delineavit,”
              usually shortened to “del” and meaning “has drawn it.” When used on drawings, as it
              was by Francis Towne in the 1780s, it implies both invention and execution. On
              reproductive prints, it refers to either the painter—signified also by “pinxit” (“has
              painted it”) or “invenit” (“has invented it”)—or to an intermediary draughtsman who
              prepared the drawing for the engraver. The engraver was identified either by
              “sculpsit” (“has engraved it”), “fecit” (“has made it”), or “incisit”
(“has engraved
              it”). In his original graphic art, Blake used “del” and “inv” interchangeably, the
              former to mean the latter, as in “del &amp; sc”, the combination favored by his
              teacher, James Basire, but he used the two terms together only four times (see n16),
              perhaps because the combination is redundant.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> A Breach</hi> and <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> are the only
              two drawings with “inv” and “d,” though two other works, both post-1805, have similar
              signatures: the <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> is signed “W Blake inv
              &amp; del: 1808” (Butlin 643), and the <hi rend="i">Whore of Babylon</hi> is signed
              “WBlake inv &amp; del 1809” (Butlin 523). <hi rend="i">Epitome of James Hervey’s
                “Meditations among the Tombs”</hi> (c. 1820) is signed “W Blake inv &amp;,” with
              “del” possibly trimmed away (Butlin 770); Blake also combined “inv” with “del” in
the
              plates in Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi> (1803), inscribing six designs
              “Maria Flaxman inv &amp; del” and “W Blake sculp.”</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s monogram was formed by a stylized italic <hi rend="i">W</hi> and 
              <hi rend="i">B.</hi> The top and bottom loops of the <hi rend="i">B</hi> were formed by round
            strokes. The swash tail circles over both initials to connect to the left serif of the
            W, and “inv” was placed inside the loop (illus. 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">17</ref> Starting with the serif on the <hi rend="i">W</hi>, the two initials were
            written in one continuous gesture of up and down strokes, with the tips of the 
              <hi rend="i">W</hi>’s right leg and the <hi rend="i">B</hi>’s stem connected. In the
            signature of the Ackland version, the <hi rend="i">B</hi> of “Battle” and “Blake” were
            formed alike but different from the monogram’s <hi rend="i">B</hi>; the top loop is much
            smaller than the bottom and is formed by a downward rather than curved stroke. The same
            style of <hi rend="i">B</hi> is present in the signature of <hi rend="i">The Witch of
              Endor</hi> (illus. 4b), dated by Blake 1783, and throughout <hi rend="i">The Island in
              the Moon</hi> c. 1784 manuscript (illus. 7; see “Beneath” in line 3).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
              type="note">18</ref> Furthermore, the Ackland’s <hi rend="i">W</hi> differs from the
            monogram’s in that it has no left upward serif and is separate from the 
              <hi rend="i">B.</hi> The form of just one part of the Ackland signature resembles the monogram,
            and then only superficially and inadvertently. The stem of the “d” loops over the “inv
            &amp;” (illus. 8), creating a monogram-like feature, which in fact supports a 1780s
            date—or at least does not rule it out—because it is simply the style that Blake used to
            write his “d”s at this time, as is evinced by nearly all the “d”s in <hi rend="i">An
              Island in the Moon.</hi> Note that “wind” and “mind” create similar monogram-like
            forms (illus. 7, lines 1 and 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi
                rend="s">17</hi> Sometimes the <hi rend="i">B</hi>’s swash tail circled to the “i”
              of “inv” (Butlin 440) or to the “v” of “inv” (Butlin 450). On three color-print
              drawings possibly pulled in 1795, Blake incised “Blake” (Butlin 316, 310, 291), though
              not necessarily at the time of the pulls.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi>
              Butlin records the signature on <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor</hi> as “1783 W Blake
              inv” (144), which is how it was initially written, with a long trailing serif on the
              “v.” But the signature has been slightly damaged and is now difficult to make out
              completely. In the photograph (illus. 4b), it unfortunately appears to read “1723 W
              Blake.” The flag emanating from the top of the <hi rend="i">B</hi> and connecting it
              to the <hi rend="i">W</hi> is still visible. This kind of connection between capital
                <hi rend="i">W</hi>s and the following letter was typical of Blake’s hand (see
              Blake’s <hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi> manuscript or Notebook). A similar but
              more pronounced kind of connection is made between the <hi rend="i">W</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">B</hi> in the five “Fresco W Blake inv” signatures (Butlin 295, 299, 307,
              317, 326).</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> See also the final “d” of
              “departed” in the inscription of <hi rend="i">The Spirit of a Just Man Newly Departed
                Appearing to His Mourning Family</hi>, c. 1780-85 (Butlin 135).</note></p>
          <pb id="p28-54" n="54"/>
          <p>The resemblance to the monogram was formed inadvertently, by an ornamental flourish
            characteristic of Blake’s calligraphic hand. But the situation may be more complicated
            than that, because the loop may have been extended after the fact, as is suggested by
            the break in the line just above the “v” of “inv” and to the left of the dot for the
“i”
            (illus. 8). Moreover, the ink of the indistinct ampersand and “d” is a lighter hue, and
            the flag-like serif of the “v” crosses instead of extends the right leg of the “v” and
            crosses the stem of the “d,” raising the possibility that all three forms, and not just
            the extension of the “d”’s loop, were added later. While the similarity of the strokes
            of the letters and their extensions argues against this, the possibility cannot be ruled
            out entirely, because Blake did alter the inscription, changing four lower-case letters
            to capitals. Initially, “A,” “Breach,” “A,” and “City” were not capitalized
(illus. 8).
            If they were capitalized after 1784, then the original inscription was closer to the
            1784 Royal Academy catalogue entry (#400): “A breach in a city, the morning after a
            battle W. Blake” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 28). Whether these changes
            were made the following day or years later may be impossible to tell, but the
            inscription and signature are clearly in the same ink and made by the same pen or brush,
            and their letter forms are perfectly consistent with those used in the 1780s and differ
            considerably from the signature Blake designed c. 1795.</p>
          <p>The Ackland version appears to have been signed when produced, though parts of the
            inscription and possibly a part of the signature may have been altered afterwards. The
            Bristol version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, however, appears to have been signed
            after it was produced. The ink of the signature is darker and the letter strokes wider
            than those of the inscription (“Pestilence”) and the design itself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
              type="note">20</ref> The letter forms of this signature (illus. 9) are closer to those
            in the monogram than are those in the Ackland version, but they still vary. The 
              <hi rend="i">W</hi> lacks its upward left serif but connects with the B. The “d”’s stem is
            not as extended, and the “inv” is formed very differently from that of the Ackland
            version and monogram (illus. 6). The “v” has a long winding serif like the one in the
            Ackland signature and, though illus. 4 does not show it, like the one in 
              <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor</hi>, but the “n” is <corr type="emend">misshapen</corr> or redrawn. The feature of
the
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> signature that most resembles the monogram is the 
              <hi rend="i">B</hi>’s swash tail, but this feature also makes the signature unique.<ref
              target="n21" type="note">21</ref> It is the only signature in which the surname begins
            with a monogram-styled <hi rend="i">B</hi>; elsewhere, this style of <hi rend="i">B</hi>
            was used only for the initial. The assumption seems reasonable, then, that the form
            Blake either develops into the monogram or was influenced by it. In either case, it
            seems that Blake signed the work after it was produced, deliberately to match the form
            and text of the signature of its companion. <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> I am
              grateful to Francis Greenacre, the curator at the Bristol Museum, for this
              information.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> The signature appears
              consistent with itself, yet the <hi rend="i">B</hi> and “l” of “Blake” also appear
              initially to have been joined, and the circling tail appears possibly to have been
              inserted just outside the <hi rend="i">B</hi>’s bottom loop. A line was drawn from the
              top of the “l” through the “k” to near the “i” of “inv.” Traces of a letter or
number
              seem to be under the <hi rend="i">B</hi>’s top loop, possibly from a differently
              formed <hi rend="i">B</hi>, one like the <hi rend="i">B</hi> of “Battle” and “Blake”
              in the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi>, with a higher but smaller top loop and a stem
              to the right of the present stem. Again, whether these marks and lines signify changes
              or false starts, made when the signature was written or later, may be impossible to
              discern.</note></p>
          <p>Because Blake sometimes signed and dated works years after they were produced, the
            possibility that the Ackland alterations and the Bristol signature itself occurred long
            after production cannot be ruled out.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref> Dating these
            works by the form of their signatures must remain suspect—especially when the
            signatures’ texts are excluded from the dating rationale. As Butlin has demonstrated,
            the signatures with Blake’s surname, “WBlake 1795” and “Fresco W Blake inv” (Butlin 292,
            303, 321; 295, 299, 307, 317, 326), are on color prints possibly pulled in 1795 but
            probably added after 1805 (Butlin, “Physicality” 8-9). These two forms of signatures are
            dated after 1805 precisely because they are inconsistent with the monogram in form and
            text, and because they appear to be variants of “WBlake inv,” which Blake began to use
            after 1805 (Butlin, “Physicality” 8). By the same logic, the texts of the Ackland and
            Bristol signatures, “W Blake inv &amp; d” and “WBlake inv d,” place the works either
            before 1795 or after 1805, as does the placement of “inv” beside the surname instead of
            above Blake’s initials. The third version of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> is dated by
            Blake 1805 and is clearly in a later drawing and coloring style (illus. 3). A pre-1795
            date is left, but this terminal date can be pushed further back. 
                <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> The Tate impression of the color-print drawing 
                <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> is on 1804 paper but is signed “1795 WB inv” in monogram. For an
              overview of Blake’s habit of signing works after production, and a bibliography, see
              Butlin’s “Physicality.”</note></p>
          <p>The watercolors <hi rend="i">Los and Orc</hi> and <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>,
            dated c. 1792-93 and 1790-93 respectively (Butlin 255, 258), are both signed “W Blake,”
            without “inv &amp; d.” These, the only signed watercolors between c. 1790 and 1795, are
            also among the very few watercolors Blake appears to have produced during this period,
            which was dominated by illuminated printing and commercial engravings—and even these may
            be earlier than supposed. Like <hi rend="i">House of Death</hi>, they are dated relative
            to <hi rend="i">The Good and Bad Angels</hi>, which, as noted, is possibly as early as
            1790 and not as late as 1794. In any event, their “W Blake” resembles Blake’s signature
            on the illuminated books from 1788 to 1795: “The Author &amp; Printer W [or Will]
            Blake,” as well as his signature in the 1780s. The terminal date, then, for the
            signature on the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> appears no later than 1790, but this
            earlier date need not be accepted by process of elimination. It is actually suggested by
            the inclusion and placement of “inv” in <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor</hi>, signed
            “1783 W Blake inv” (illus. 4b). As noted, this work’s lower right corner is slightly
            damaged, and its right margin appears to have been trimmed 
<pb id="p28-55" n="55"/>
            after “inv,” through the “v”’s long serif (see n18). A brush or pen mark from the edge
            of the sheet curves over the “v” of “inv,” possibly a fragment of a looping “d”
trimmed
            off, in which case the signature may have originally read “1783 W Blake inv [&amp;] d,”
            like the Ackland and Bristol works (see n16 for a work similarly trimmed).</p>
          <p>For the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> to have been signed when executed and the
            Bristol <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> signed afterwards would not be so strange, for it
            is not the signatures that make them companions. Indeed, the last version of 
              <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> is signed and dated, but its companion, the Boston version of 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, is neither signed nor dated. Moreover, Blake consistently
            signed finished drawings after 1795 and in forms consistent enough to discern dateable
            patterns, but not before. Of the 140 known drawings and sketches produced in the 1770s
            and 1780s (Butlin 49-190), only eight—including the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> and
            Bristol <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>—are signed. Of these, <hi rend="i">Moses with the
              Tables of Stone</hi> is untraced but is reported to have been signed “W Blake 1774
            [?]” and “WB [in monogram] 1774” (Butlin 49).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">23</ref> The
            presence of a signature on another is dubious (Butlin 184), and the signatures on three
            appear to me as possibly in a hand other than Blake’s (Butlin 119, 126, 179A).<ref
              target="n24" type="note">24</ref> But two of the latter, <hi rend="i">Saul and
              David</hi>, c. 1780-85, and <hi rend="i">A Medieval Battle Scene</hi>, c. 1780, are
            signed “W Blake inven”; if these are Blake’s signatures, then the likelihood that 
              <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> and <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> were signed mid-1780s is
            further strengthened. While admittedly there are too few signed works from the 1770s and
            1780s to indicate conclusively the evolution of Blake’s signature during this 20-year
            period, it is clear that the texts resemble one another, that all eight are variations
            on “W Blake inv,” and that the “d” is more likely to have been included in the signature
            during this period than the period in which the surname is dropped altogether and “inv”
            is newly positioned. In fact, no drawings signed during the period in which the monogram
            was regularly used (1795-1805) include both “inv” and “d” or have “inv” 
              <hi rend="i">beside</hi> the <hi rend="i">B.</hi> It seems very unlikely, then, that Blake
signed
            these works while using the true monogram (see n16). <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi>
              Butlin infers the possible signatures on <hi rend="i">Moses</hi> from information
              supplied by the 6 April 1925 Sotheby sale catalogue (lot 153), which states that the
              work is “signed and dated W.B. 1774.” There is no mention of a monogram, but a near
              monogram in the mid-1770s is not impossible. Blake’s teacher signed his works “Basire
              del &amp; sc” and “JBasire del &amp; sc,” often combining his initials into a
              monogram.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> The signatures are “W. Blake”
              (179A) and “W Blake inven” (119, 126). The bowed legs of the former’s 
                <hi rend="i">W</hi> are especially un-Blakean, and none of the <hi rend="i">B</hi>s matches
the
              style used throughout <hi rend="i">The Island in the Moon</hi> manuscript.</note></p>
          <p>We can only speculate why Blake signed some works and not others, or some long after
            production. Probably, as Butlin suggests, sales prompted signatures (“Physicality” 8).
            The earliest provenances of the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> and the Bristol 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> are unknown, and so the idea that the latter’s signature and
            its presumably deliberate echoing of the Ackland’s were instigated by sale of the two as
            a pair cannot be proven or disproven.</p>
          <p>While the form of the signature has been misread to indicate a c. 1795-1800 date, the
            very presence of an inscription on <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi>, a clearer indicator of
            date, has been given little attention. The few works whose titles are inscribed on the
            picture surface itself are all from the 1780s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n25" type="note">25</ref>
            These include <hi rend="i">Samuel Presenting Saul to the People</hi> c. 1780-85,
            inscribed “Behold your King,” <hi rend="i">The Spirit of a Just Man Newly Departed
              Appearing to His Mourning Family</hi> c. 1780-85, so inscribed, <hi rend="i">The Witch
              of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</hi>, 1783, so inscribed, <hi rend="i">The King
              of Babylon in Hell</hi> c. 1780-85, inscribed “Hell beneath is moved for thee to meet
            thee at thy coming.—Isaiah,” <hi rend="i">Pestilence, Probably the Great Plague of
              London</hi> c. 1780 (illus. 10), inscribed “Lord have m<hi rend="s">er</hi> on us,”
            and both versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (illus. 13, 14), so inscribed (Butlin
            117, 135, 144, 145, 184, 190, 192). Works finished after 1790, including the
            Wollstonecraft designs, the color-print drawings, and the designs in the 
              <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi> copy B, have inscriptions written below rather than on
the
              design.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi>
              Bentley’s list of “titles Blake wrote on his pictures” (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
              210-12) is inadvertently misleading in that the titles recorded were not on the
              pictures themselves but in the Royal Academy catalogues, below the designs, or by
              other hands.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Inscriptions below the image
              became Blake’s standard mode of presenting the biblical watercolors executed for
              Butts. These works were signed usually in the bottom right corner, with a biblical
              reference in ink just under the signature and image (Butlin 499, 500), and possibly a
              title centered below the image. However, there are very few works in this original
              condition, because most were trimmed to the image when inserted into mounts. These
              were pasted down in windows cut in thick matboard. The information trimmed away was
              replaced in pencil on the mount in copperplate hand. The titles on these mounts may be
              repeating what was cut away or, more likely, were created by Butts, who derived them
              from the biblical reference. For further description of this style of re-presenting
              Blake’s works, see my “Blake and the Marketplace 1852.”</note></p>
          <p>Severing the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi> from its c. 1795-1800 date forces us to
            reconsider the opinions of those who believe that the exhibited version is not lost.
            Their position is supported rather than refuted by the Ackland’s signature, which is
            textually closer to the signatures of the 1780s than to those in the 1790s. The visual
            similarity between it and the c. 1795 monogram is based on the looping stem of the “d,”
            an ornamental flourish characteristic of Blake’s hand in the 1780s. The differences
            between the signature and monogram are more substantial and troubling. If the Ackland
            version of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> was executed in 1795 or later, then it is not only
            a return to an earlier style of drawing and coloring, but it is also the only known pen
            and wash or watercolor c. 1795-1800 inscribed on the design’s surface, and, with the
            partial exception of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, probably the only one signed with
            “inv” beside the surname and <hi rend="i">W</hi> and <hi rend="i">B</hi> unconnected.
            Rather than suppose that Blake returned haphazardly to a signing style abandoned years
            earlier, it seems more reasonable 
            <pb id="p28-56" n="56"/>
            <figure n="BUT184.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="706">
              <figTranscr>Lord have<lb/>
              mer[cy] on us</figTranscr>
              <head>10. <hi rend="i">Pestilence, Probably the Great Plague of London</hi>, c.
                1779-80.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor (13.8 × 18.6 cm.). Robert Tear Collection.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            to assume that he signed the Ackland version at the time of production, c.
            1784. It is also reasonable to assume that the work exhibited was inscribed, for the
            title in the exhibition catalogue quotes nearly verbatim that inscription rather than
            referring to the work by subject—say <hi rend="i">War</hi>, or simply <hi rend="i">A
              Breach in a City Wall.</hi> Why “the morning after the battle”? Nothing in the Ackland
            version suggests morning or, for that matter, twilight; there is no rose or yellow in
            the sky. In other words, the drawing is not titled generically or by subject, as were
            the Joseph watercolors exhibited in 1785 (e.g., “Joseph making himself known to his
            brethren,” cat. no. 449; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 30). If the
            exhibited version was inscribed but is now lost, then why would the Carnegie, the
            subsequent version, have compositional errors but no inscription, while the Ackland, the
            next version, corrects these errors but has the inscription? It makes little sense to
            assume that the Carnegie version was modeled on an earlier version but included drawing
            errors and excluded its title, or that the Ackland version was executed 10 or more years
            later only to return to the original model’s title, despite the title’s absence in the
            supposed intermediate (Carnegie) version.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">The <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> Sketch</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The corrections made in the composition of the Ackland <hi rend="i">Breach</hi>
            indicates that it follows the Carnegie version. Inferred from the fact that heads were
            changed from “strict, classical profile” (Butlin 191) to three-quarter view is the
            hypothesis that there is a “progression” from one to the other (Essick, 
              <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 118). Using this hypothesis, Essick places the recently discovered
sketch
            of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (illus. 12) after instead of before the Bateson version,
            interpreting it as an intermediate study between the Bateson and Bristol versions
            (illus. 13, 14) instead of as a preliminary study for the composition itself. According
            to Essick, “the unfinished character of the Huntington sketch, and the hesitant and
            studied nature of its lines, suggest that it is Blake’s first experiment at changing
            some figures to three-quarter view to develop the expressive potential of their faces”
              (<hi rend="i">Works</hi> 118).</p>
          <p>This hypothesis lies at the heart of Shelley Bennett’s analysis of the sketch. At
            first, Bennett suspected that the sketch might have been a preliminary study for 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, between it and the earliest versions of the subject (illus.
            10, 11), which appear to have evolved from Blake’s English history series (Butlin 184,
              185).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> In attempting to
place the sketch, she
            notes the shape of the doorway behind the pallbearer—curved in the sketch, square in the
            three finished designs—and suggests that the sketch may have preceded the designs, as
            its medium suggests. She reasons that “the pencil drawing may represent an earlier idea
            that was modified in the three later variations. The fact that this work is executed in
            pencil, a medium which Blake, [like] his contemporaries, used for preliminary studies,
            also reinforces this arrangement in sequence. It seems likely that Blake would begin his
            complete reworking of the earlier composition with a pencil study before proceeding to
            watercolor” (134). This is exactly right, but instead of trusting the purpose of
            sketching and the material facts of production, Bennett proceeds 
            <pb id="p28-57" n="57"/>
            <figure n="BUT185.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="639">
              <figTranscr/>
              <head>11. <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, c. 1780-84.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor (18.5 × 27.5 cm.). Robert N. Essick Collection, Altadena,
                California.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            to argue that “the three-quarter turn of the female’s head in the Huntington
            drawing and Bristol and Boston watercolors links these works and suggests that they, in
            turn, follow the Bateson watercolor” (135). And, of course, the supposed c. 1790-95 date
            for the Bateson <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (Butlin 190) implies that the sketch is
            mid-1790s. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> These works are now referred to as 
                <hi rend="i">Pestilence, Probably the Great Plague of London</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (Butlin 184, 185). Both were referred to as <hi rend="i">The
                Plague</hi> in various nineteenth-century auction catalogues.</note></p>
          <p>Precedent exists for placing a sketch between two finished versions of the same
            subject. The six designs of the second series of <hi rend="i">On The Morning of Christ’s
              Nativity</hi>, c. 1815, were radically reworked after the first series of 1809.
            Preliminary sketches for <hi rend="i">Descent of Peace</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Flight
              of Moloch</hi> are extant (Butlin 539, 541). But the material and aesthetic
            circumstances are completely different from those surrounding the first and second
            (Bateson and Bristol) versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence.</hi> The second series of 
              <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> is considerably smaller, which means that the original series
            was not traced or calked. Technically, Blake could have squared up tracings to reduce
            the original images, but apparently he used the new series as an opportunity to
            reconceive the designs, a process which in turn required visual rethinking or sketching.
            These new <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> sketches are to their first versions of the subject
            what the <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> sketch is to the <hi rend="i">earliest</hi>
            versions of <hi rend="i">Plague/Pestilence</hi> (illus. 10, 11)—i.e., “a complete
            reworking of the earlier composition” (Bennett 134). However, if the 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> sketch follows the Bateson version, then the situation is not
            analogous, for the sketch differs as slightly from the Bateson as from the Bristol
            version, from the design it supposedly reworks as from the design it supposedly
            prepares.</p>
          <p>Placing such a sketch between two finished designs that vary so insignificantly ignores
            the primary purpose of sketching: to develop ideas and block out compositions. It
            supposes that Blake needed to sketch in order to solve such minor technical problems as
            repositioning a figure or a head. That supposition ignores Blake’s virtuosity as well as
            his watercolor technique, which encouraged continuous invention. Indeed, Blake’s
            watercolor technique—drawing lightly in pencil and finding (“invenire”) the subject in
            the resulting marks, erasing excess pencil lines and firmly determining the subject
            decided upon through washes, colors, and pen outlining—discouraged producing preliminary
            sketches in any great detail or to size. In other words, his technique encouraged
            sketches to be “unfinished” (Essick, <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 118).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
              type="note">28</ref> Assuming that Blake needed to sketch in this instance, after
            completing the Bateson version and in preparation for the Bristol version, also ignores
            what profiles and three-quarter views are to artists: mere technical tricks performed as
            easily as any other from well-rehearsed visual repertories. The position of a head does
            not signify evolved technical mastery, but rather an aesthetic choice made during the
            composing or recomposing process, a choice predicated upon the schemata that enables
            artists to draw in the first place, to delineate faces, hands, bodies, and the like in
            diverse forms with facility, almost automatically. Examples of the non-progressive
            implication of turning heads are the 
<pb id="p28-58" n="58"/>
<figure n="thePlaguePestilencePencil.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="394">
              <head>12. <hi rend="i">The Plague/Pestilence</hi>, c. 1784.</head>
              <figDesc>Pencil (24.2 × 29.8 cm.). Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San
                Marino, California.</figDesc>
            </figure> faces of Michael, Satan, and the other angels in the three sketches for 
              <hi rend="i">Warring Angels: Michael Contending with Satan</hi>, c. 1780; they are
            variously formed in each subsequent version (Butlin 114, 115, 116). And, as noted, the
            sketch and watercolor of <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simon to Be Bound</hi> (Butlin
            158, 156) exemplify the same facility. <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> As Bennett
              correctly points out, the sketch “bears all the earmarks of Blake’s distinctive
              calligraphic style. In particular, it displays the rather crude, often hesitant line
              which is associated with his preparatory pencil studies, . . . from such gauche
              beginnings Blake would develop the flowing, expressive contour lines characteristic of
              his finished designs” (132). This refinement and development, it must be understood,
              usually occurred in the watercolors themselves, due to Blake’s two-stage process of
              sketching out designs, erasing unneeded lines, and adding washes and pen and ink
              outlining.</note></p>
          <p>The sketch appears to be derived from rather than leading to the Bateson version
            because it shares features with both the Bateson and Bristol versions. But placing the
            sketch between two finished designs is troubling, not only because the latter design was
            developed from a tracing of the former, but also because it asks us to believe the
            following: the mourning man’s profile is copied exactly in the sketch (illus. 12) as it
            is delineated in the Bateson version (illus. 13), only to be independently changed to
            three-quarter view in the Bristol version (illus. 14); the rear pallbearer and the
            mourning woman were moved to the left, relative to the Bateson version, a new position
            only to be ignored in the Bristol version, which repeats that of the Bateson; and the
            gravedigger was also repositioned, moved closer to the front pallbearer, a position
            ignored in the Bristol, which repeats that of the Bateson. These changes and repetitions
            are troubling because they indicate that Blake ignored most of his own recommendations
            and was able to make changes in the new version as it was being worked up and without
            recourse to a sketch. Why, then, would he execute a sketch?</p>
          <p>The question is not whether Blake used sketches to rethink whole designs, but whether
            he used them to try out minute changes in pre-existing designs. If he intended to change
            a few faces—or to see if a turned face would work—he did not need to redraw the entire
            design. Indeed, Blake’s mode of production, in both the first and second versions,
            encouraged revision and eliminated the need to sketch revisions on a separate sheet of
            paper. The first version differs from the sketch because it was redrawn freehand, a
            process in which the original invention continues to evolve through execution. The
            second version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> differs from the first, despite its
            development from a tracing, because the changes, like turned heads, raised arms, added
            or deleted figures, were made on the tracing itself, or on the new sheet of paper as the
            calked outline was being worked up in pencil. By transferring just the outline and not
            the details, artists (or engravers) leave room for revision; thus, they prevent
            execution from being merely an act of reproduction.</p>
          <p>Redrawing the composition freehand on a larger sheet of paper accounts for the
            differences between the Bateson version and the sketch. The differences between the
            Bristol and Bateson versions were created either on the tracing paper or on the new
            support when the outline was calked. The Boston version (illus. 15), executed in 1805,
            differs from the Bristol (illus. 14) but repeats features from both the sketch and the
            Bateson (illus. 10, 11). Rossetti knew the sketch and the last version, but not the
            first two versions, so he logically assumed that the sketch was “an expressive and
            reasonably careful sketch for the grand water-colour” (241, #18). Hence, Rossetti
            misdated the sketch 1805, but he may have been correct about the relation. The
            provenance of the Bristol version is now believed to be that of the sketch, which means
            that the sketch was probably acquired by Harvey from the 29 April 1862 auction at
            Sotheby’s. The 
<pb id="p28-59" n="59"/>
<figure n="Pestilence1784.Ackland.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="334">
              <head>13. <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, c. 1784.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor (31.6 × 48.1 cm.). Ackland Art Museum, University of North
                Carolina at Chapel Hill; loan of Lois Bateson.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<figure n="Pestilence1784Bristol.28.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="332">
              <head>14. <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, c. 1784.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor (32.2 × 48.4 cm.). City of Bristol Museum and Art
                Gallery.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<pb id="p28-60" n="60"/>
<figure n="BUT193.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="676">
              <head>15. <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>, c. 1805.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor over pencil (31.2 × 43 cm.). Museum of Fine Arts,
                Boston.</figDesc>
            </figure> Bateson version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> sold in the same auction to
            Toovey (Butlin 190), a dealer with whom Rossetti apparently had no contact. As I
            mentioned, the sale may or may not have been Tatham’s, but the works sold were the kind
            that would have remained in Blake’s studio and possibly have been sold by his widow
            between 1827 and 1831 (see n3). The sketch and the Bateson version, then, were most
            likely in the studio when Blake executed the 1805 version and probably remained till his
            death.</p>
          <p>The third version repeats features from the sketch and the Bateson version but hardly
            any from the Bristol. The face of the rear pallbearer (illus. 15) is that of the Bateson
            (illus. 13), but his position is that of the sketch (illus. 12); he, and the doorway
            behind him, have been moved from behind the man’s shoulders to behind his head, which
            eliminated the awkward foot beneath the woman; the mourning woman’s face is that of the
            sketch, but her position is that of the Bateson version; the digger returns to the
            position occupied in the sketch, close beside the pallbearer; the bodies being buried
            are again closer to the digger’s feet than to his hands and the shovel’s handle; the
            mourning man’s hand is again spiky, and the mourning woman is again in three-quarter
            view, as in the sketch. The last version contains differences as well: the digger holds
            the shovel with his left hand instead of his right, and the spade is in front of instead
            of behind his feet; the infant’s right leg is lifted, and its right arm is extended
            along its mother’s right leg.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref> Only the
            three-quarter view of the mourning man is possibly drawn from the Bristol version, but
            this change, like the others, could have been drawn without reference to the Bristol, if
            the three-quarter view of the rear pallbearer in the sketch was once again transferred
            to the mourning man. <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Bennett finds that “in the
              Bristol and the Boston watercolors the baby’s left arm has been extended across the
              mother’s legs in a crucifix-like position more clearly and expressively indicating the
              child’s sad condition” (133). I see an extended right arm in the Boston version but no
              left arm at all, while in the Bristol version I see a baby formed much as he was in
              the sketch and first two versions, with perhaps the right arm or leg partially visible
              over the mother’s left knee.</note></p>
          <p>To believe that the Bristol version of <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> (illus. 14) was
            executed after the Bateson (illus. 13) version is not difficult, but the reason is not
            that its figures are drawn in three-quarter views. To assume so requires focusing
            completely on parts instead of the composition as a whole. More significantly, such an
            assumption ignores Blake’s mode of production and the techniques that enabled him both
            to repeat himself and to vary his own designs while doing so.</p>
          <p>Authenticating and dating art works, long at the heart of art historical analysis,
            cannot be dismissed as merely the concerns of connoisseurs, beneath the notice of
            scholars and critics, for they are essential in establishing the visual texts studied
            and the chronologies that define periods. When a work is redated, our ideas of period
            style, technique, and media—the features that assist in dating and identifying works—are
            called into question. When one work is redated, nearly always others require redating as
            well, and even the parameters or defining features of a period or style can be altered.
            The earliest extant versions of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> and of 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi> are a case in point. They were probably produced by 1784 and not in
            the 1790s. The Carnegie and Bateson versions of these works were the first executed
            within their groups, followed closely by the Ackland and Bristol versions. 
              <pb id="p28-61" n="61"/>
Both second versions are signed, and they have been dated
            post-1795 because the form of one part of their signatures resembles the monogram Blake
            began using that year. Butlin’s hypothesis that the <hi rend="i">form</hi> of Blake’s
            signature is dateable is probably sound, but it is helpful only in dating works produced
            in and after 1795, when Blake began to sign works consistently and uniformly, and not
            before. Moreover, in the Ackland version, the monogram-like features were inadvertently
            produced, while in the Bristol version they were probably made after production, though
            how long afterwards is probably impossible to determine. Furthermore, the 
              <hi rend="i">texts</hi> of these signatures differ significantly from those of the mid- and
            latter-1790s but are similar to those of the 1780s. The new dates for the Carnegie and
            Ackland versions of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> raise the possibility that the latter
            version was the work exhibited in 1784. Its inscription and monochromatic wash style
            support this supposition and date. If the Ackland version is the supposedly untraced 
              <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi> (Butlin 188), then the
            three extant versions of the composition were probably the only ones executed, in which
            case no version of <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> is lost, and our ideas about Blake’s
            drawing style in the 1780s require rethinking.</p>
          <p>The second versions of both <hi rend="i">A Breach</hi> and <hi rend="i">Pestilence</hi>
            differ from the first by the presence of three-quarter views in place of profiles.
            Mistakenly inferred from this stylistic feature is a hypothesis about development in
            Blake’s style. This hypothesis, combined with a tendency to overlook the material facts
            of production, Blake’s technique of watercolor drawing, and the purpose of sketching,
            has led to misdating and misplacing a sketch in the evolution of 
              <hi rend="i">Pestilence.</hi> The sketch is exactly what it looks like: a preliminary study for
            the composition in general and for the Bateson version in particular, executed by c.
            1784 and not the mid-1790s.</p>
          <p>I am not questioning the assumption that Blake’s pictorial compositions move towards
            greater technical and emotional complexity as they were reworked. Three-quarter views
            may indeed be more prevalent in later works than in earlier, more neoclassical works,
            but, in and of themselves, such views do not signify later production. I am questioning
            the tendency to assign higher evidentiary status to particular facial gestures than to a
            composition’s overall style, to selected visual details than to technique and
            production.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">WORKS CITED</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bennett, Shelly M. “A Newly Discovered Blake at the Huntington.” 
                <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-85): 132-39.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969.</p>
            <p>Blunt, Anthony. <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake.</hi> New York: Columbia
              University Press, 1959.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. “Footnotes on the Huntington Blakes.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 22 (1988): 17-18.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New Haven:
              Yale University Press, 1982.</p>
            <p>—. “William Rossetti’s Annotations to Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William
                Blake.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 2 (1968-69): 39-40.</p>
            <p>Cummings, Frederick, and Allen Staley. <hi rend="i">Romantic Art in Britain:
                Paintings and Drawings, 1760-1860.</hi> Philadelphia: Philadelphia Museum of Art,
              1968.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake’s 1812 Exhibition.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                Quarterly</hi> 27 (1993): 36-42.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of Adam.</hi> Oxford: Oxford
              University Press, 1989.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake in the Huntington Collections.</hi> San
              Marino: The Huntington Library, 1985.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. London:
              Macmillan, 1863.</p>
            <p>—. Life of William Blake. New and Enlarged Edition. 2 vols. London: Macmillan,
              1880.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> Ed. W. Graham Robertson. London:
              Macmillan, 1907.</p>
            <p>Pressly, Nancy L. <hi rend="i">The Fuseli Circle in Rome.</hi> New Haven: Yale Center
              for British Art, 1979.</p>
            <p>Robertson, Graham W. <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of W. Graham Robertson.</hi>
              Ed. Kerrison Preston. London: William Blake Trust, 1952.</p>
            <p>Rosenblum, Robert. <hi rend="i">Transformations in Late Eighteenth-Century Art.</hi>
              Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1967. 3rd printing, 1974.</p>
            <p>Rossetti, William Michael. “Annotated Catalogue of Blake’s Pictures and Drawings.” In
              Gilchrist 1863, 2: 199-268.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers 1862 to 1870.</hi> London: Sands, 1903.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> Princeton:
              Princeton University Press, 1993.</p>
            <p>—. “Blake and the Marketplace 1852: Thomas Butts, Jr. and Other Unknown
              Nineteenth-Century Blake Collectors.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
              (forthcoming).</p>
            <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony. “Further Observations on William Rossetti’s Annotations to
              Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 3
              (1969): 48-51.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
