<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.2.simpson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Which Newton for the British Library?</title>
        <author n="Simpson">David Simpson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
	<pb id="p28-77" n="77"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">DISCUSSION</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Which Newton for the British Library?</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>David <name>Simpson</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>I was very interested to read, in a recent issue of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Martin Butlin’s
account of the recent controversy over Sir Eduardo Paolozzi’s sculptural adaptation of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Newton</hi> projected for the British Library. Butlin ends by advising us against imposing “too
strictly a Blakean interpretation on Paolozzi’s sculpture.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">1</ref> I have often wondered whether there is any “strict” Blakean
interpretation of Newton, especially of the famous print on which the controversial sculpture is
based.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">2</ref> Colin St. John Wilson, as
reported by Butlin, notes the ambivalence of the portrait of Sir Isaac, at once narrowly obsessed with a
geometrical problem and beautifully delineated in its naked energy, like a coiled spring, or a revolution
waiting to happen. Other commentators, among them Robert Essick, have noted similar ambiguities in the
print.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">3</ref> And we should not forget that
Edmund Burke himself made much of the connection between the geometrical spirit and the French Revolution,
with its “geometrical and arithmetical constitution” threatening to “uncover our nakedness” and banish
the “Christian religion” in favor of some “degrading superstition.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">4</ref> By 1795, the year of Blake’s print, many in Britain had
come to share Burke’s contempt for France. And if Blake himself might also have come to endorse some of the
regnant emotionalist distrust of scientific and mathematical method as applied to political and social
reorganization, we may yet see in the taut body and tight curls of the Newton figure the signature of an
alternative reading. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Martin Butlin, “Paolozzi’s Newton,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 27 (1993): 45.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The standard listing of the sources for and discussions of the print is
ed. Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New Haven and
London: Yale UP, 1981) 1: 166-67. Butlin notes both negative and positive components of Blake’s attitude to
Newton, along with graphic precursors in Michelangelo and elsewhere.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert N. Essick, “Blake’s Newton,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>
3 (1971): 149-62. The major account of Blake’s relation to Newton is, of course, Donald D. Ault’s 
<hi rend="i">Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton</hi> (Chicago and London: U of Chicago P, 1974),
which has a very full sense of the complexities of the relationship.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Edmund Burke, <hi rend="i">Reflections on the Revolution in France</hi>,
ed. Conor Cruise O’Brien (Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1976) 144, 187-88.</note></p>
          <p>So far, I have said nothing new. But my question is this: is the figure in the print Sir Isaac,
or only Sir Isaac? It certainly bears a facial resemblance to the famous images of the aquiline, slightly
petulant and even neurotic genius known as Isaac Newton, so that it seems hard to imagine that that this is
not the distinguished Fellow of Trinity and
<pb id="p28-78" n="78"/>
Lucasian Professor depicted here in naked glory.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">5</ref> But the Newton more familiar to Blake’s generation was another, the Rev. John Newton,
adventurer, author and divine. John Newton had an extraordinary life, and he wrote about it at some length and
on various occasions. An enthusiastic disciple of Whitefield and friend of Wesley, John Newton became rector
of Olney, where he knew and worked with William Cowper, with whom he coauthored the <hi rend="i">Olney
Hymns</hi> (1779). In 1780 he moved to the <corr type="emend">benefice</corr> of St. Mary Woolnoth with St.
Mary Woolchurch, Lombard St., London. Here, in Blake’s London, he preached to large congregations and
published against the slave trade in support of Wilberforce. In his last years he went blind, and he died in
London in 1807. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See Martin K. Nurmi, “Blake’s ‘Ancient of Days’ and
Motte’s Frontispiece to Newton’s <hi rend="i">Principia</hi>”, in ed. Vivian da Sola Pinto, 
<hi rend="i">The Divine Vision: Studies in the Poetry and Art of William Blake</hi> (London: 1957)
205-16.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s figure bears no resemblance to the fleshy, rather commonplace portrait of the Rev. John
prefaced to <hi rend="i">The Works of the Rev. John Newton</hi> in 12 volumes (London, 1821). But it is
Newton’s early life that may be relevant to that figure. In the 1740s he had served on a slave ship and
found himself stranded on an island off the coast of Africa. His <hi rend="i">Authentic Narrative</hi>, first
published in 1764 and something of a classic in evangelical circles, offers the following:
<q>
Though destitute of food and clothing, depressed to a degree beyond common wretchedness, I could sometimes
collect my mind to mathematical studies. I had bought <hi rend="i">Barrow’s Euclid</hi> at 
<hi rend="i">Portsmouth</hi>; it was the only volume I brought on shore; it was always with me, and I used to take
it to remote corners of the island by the sea side, and draw my <hi rend="i">diagrams</hi> with a long stick
upon the sand. Thus I often beguiled my sorrows, and almost forgot my feeling:—and thus, without any other
assistance, I made myself, in a good measure, master of the first six books of 
<hi rend="i">Euclid.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> The Works of the Rev. John Newton</hi>, 1:
xlvi.</note></q></p>
          <p>This was a famous anecdote: Wordsworth transcribes it faithfully in <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>
(1805, 6: 160ff; 1850, 6: 142ff.). And it describes something very close, of course, to the posture of
Blake’s Newton, bending over the sand or sea floor with his scroll and compasses. For John Newton, this was
a stage upon life’s way, a habit to be discontinued after his conversion, when he “laid aside the 
<hi rend="i">mathematics.</hi> I found they not only cost me much time, but engrossed my thoughts too far: my head
was literally full of <hi rend="i">schemes.</hi> I was weary of cold contemplative truth, which can neither
warm nor amend the heart, but rather tends to aggrandize <hi rend="i">self</hi>” (1: lxxxviii). Essick has
noted an iconographic connection in Dürer between geometry and melancholy,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">7</ref> John Newton found it out for himself on a tropical beach and
wrote it into the narrative of his Christian awakening. <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Essick
156-57.</note></p>
          <p>And is it part of Blake’s print? More would have to be done to convert this possibility from
hunch or hypothesis to firm persuasion. But it does explain the posture and one of the possible locations for
Blake’s figure. Blake liked complex allusions, and this one adds another temporal dimension to the moment of
<hi rend="i">Newton.</hi> John Newton gave up geometry in order to find God; Isaac Newton perhaps represents a
God found by way of mathematics.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">8</ref> If
Sir Isaac himself was a manifold figure, conjuring up energy and repression, orthodoxy and revolution—and we
might recall that Sir Isaac was a theological oddball as well—then the copresence of another Newton, John
Newton, imaged in the most famous event of his life, pictures another and companionate history in the pulse of
this particular graphic artery, a history of error preliminary to truth, or mathematical truth preliminary to
spiritual truth. If Blake is joining faith with rational science in an image of <hi rend="i">two</hi> Newtons,
and playfully implying the precursive presence of Sir Isaac in the Reverend John, then the synthetic energy of
Paolozzi’s sculpture is greater than we have yet realized, and its potential to represent the bringing
together of the sciences and humanities, as intended by Michael Saunders Watson (as reported by Martin
Butlin), is all the greater. As for revolution . . . of that we had best be silent. 
<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">8</hi> In <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> there is a miniature prototype of the
‘Newton’ print (noted by Butlin, <hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings</hi>, p. 167), accompanied by the
legend “He who sees the infinite in all things, sees God. He who sees the Ratio only sees himself only”.
What is not unambiguously clear here is whether the geometer sees one or the other, or both.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
