<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.2.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">E. P. Thompson, Witness Against The Beast: William Blake and the Moral
Law</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1994</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-2-0006">
        <pb id="p28-65" n="65"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">E. P. Thompson, <hi rend="i">Witness Against The Beast: William Blake and the
Moral Law.</hi> New York: The New Press. 1993. xxi + 234 pp. with 20 illus. $30.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Many of us can remember when the antinomian tradition was treated with undisguised scorn by
literary historians. Even students of Blake were slow to come to terms with the extent to which he shared his
vision of the abolition of moral law with predecessors and contemporaries. A. L. Morton’s <hi rend="i">The
Everlasting Gospel</hi> tried to remedy this by placing passages from Blake into relationship with Ranter
texts, but these juxtapositions were largely unconvincing—“the everlasting gospel” is itself, after all,
a term from the Book of Revelation. More indicative of what might be done on the subjects were historical
studies whose focus was not Blake: particularly those of Christopher Hill and E. P. Thompson himself. 
<hi rend="i">The World Turned Upside Down</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Making of the English Working Class</hi>
treated antinomianism and the frequently allied phenomenon of millenarianism seriously as part of a social
fabric. This pointed the way for some later essays, but it was left for Thompson himself to produce a full
scale study on the subject as related to William Blake.</p>
          <p>Thompson divides his subject matter into antinomian, Swedenborgian, and “Jacobinical,” and
his discussion of each is richly configured. The opening chapters are of great interest not only for their
clear expositions of the varieties of antinomian doctrine but also in their delineations of how these could
have been transmitted to Blake through printed texts. Some of Thompson’s research reveals new connections
among figures other than Blake. It is worth knowing, for example, that the Swedenborgian doctor Benedict
Chastanier and the artist Phillippe Jacques de Loutherbourg were well versed in the writings of the
Philadelphian mystic Jane Lead (documentation is provided for this but not for the interesting statement [43]
that Loutherbourg was a disciple of Richard Brothers in the 1790s). There is also some valuable information
about private libraries, though not about Richard Cosway’s, to which Blake is thought to have had access.
The whole of this material is greater than the sum of its parts—we get a picture of the confluence of many
streams in the later eighteenth century.</p>
          <p>The same may be said of Thompson’s exploration of radical dissent. To the older movements of
sects are added Moravians, Sandemanians, Hutchinsonians, and “irregular” Methodists. One would especially
like to know more about the Sandemanians: William Godwin was educated in a Sandemanian academy and for a short
time was a Sandemanian minister, as was William Hazlitt’s father. Later comers, the Unitarians, also offer
interesting analogies to Blake. However, the single group that most interests Thompson is the group known as
Muggletonians. Founded by John Reeve (d. 1658) and Ludowick Muggleton (d. 1698), the Muggletonian sect had an
astonishing longevity, especially considering the very low profile it kept: there were still 100 male
believers in 1803; in 1975 there was one left. Thompson’s extraordinary account of his meeting with the last
Muggletonian and the consequent transfer of the 89 volumes of the Muggletonian archive to the British Library
is a fascinating one, but the main thrust of his argument here is Blake’s possible knowledge of and sympathy
with Muggletonian beliefs. The three Muggletonian doctrines that Thompson finds especially pertinent are
“the specifically antinomian tradition, with its repudiation of the Moral Law” (91), “the explicit and
repetitive identification of ‘Reason’ as the Satanic principle” (94), and “the unusual symbolism of
the Fall, and of the Serpent-Angel’s actual copulation with Eve and transmutation into flesh and blood in
her womb” (96). While stating his own conviction that there is a connection with Blake, Thompson avoids
special pleading and even notes that Blake would have abhorred some of the Muggletonian teachings, such as the
predestinarian doctrine of the two Seeds. In the absence of any documentary evidence linking Blake with the
Muggletonians, each reader must judge whether an examination of these doctrinal matters and a comparison of
passages establishes any link between Blake and the Muggletonians. I am myself unpersuaded that there is a
particular link, for the very reason that makes <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast</hi> a work of such
interest: and that is the impact on Blake of the antinomian/millenarian/radical subculture in its many forms,
with some of which Blake did have demonstrable contact.</p>
          <p>Although I have said that documentary evidence does not link Blake and the Muggletonian
teachings, there is one documentary matter here of considerable interest to Blake scholarship. Blake’s
mother has been known as Catherine Harmitage, but Thompson reads the entry in the register of St. George’s
Chapel, Hanover Square, as “Hermitage.” He argues that she was the widow of Thomas Hermitage, hosier, of
28 Broad Street and that she afterwards married James Blake, hosier, of Glasshouse Street, and brought the two
businesses together at the Broad Street address. This in itself, with some ancillary facts (120-21),
constitutes an important discovery. Thompson draws on it to suggest that a George Hermitage who wrote
Muggletonian songs in the mid-century could have been related to Blake’s mother through her first marriage.
This of course does not prove that Blake even saw these songs—Thompson handles this material with his
customary tact and engages in no special pleading.</p>
          <p>Moving from the sects already mentioned to one with which Blake is known to have had contacts
brings another dimension to the discussion. Thompson has deeply investigated the rise and progress of the New
Jerusalem Church and rightly warns us that Richard Hindmarsh’s book of that name merits “as much and as
little respect as Stalin’s <hi rend="i">Short History of the CPSU(B)</hi>” (135). As a participant in the
events he documents, Hindmarsh is both a valuable and a suspect
<pb id="p28-66" n="66"/>
source. Thompson’s three chapters on Blake and Swedenborgianism are at the same time comprehensive and
incisive, as this fine summary passage indicates:
<q>
The first year or two of the [New Jerusalem] Church were clouded with dissension. For the Blakes the entire
Swedenborgian movement was fraught with conflict, but was nevertheless of profound significance. We cannot
clearly identify Blake with any of the conflicting groups, but again and again we seem to see his face,
obliquely situated to a particular argument. There is his recognition of a body of visionary writing
undoubtedly carrying some of the old Behmenist imagery. There is identification not only with certain beliefs
(Christ is man) but also with the very notion of a New Church of regenerated humankind. There is also some
shared jargon of correspondences (chariot for doctrine, Edom for what is natural, dragon for the ‘falses’
of religion). The influence was deep, and with <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, productive
of polemic. It would also seem that Blake’s antinomian tenets were resisted from the start by the orthodox
within the Church. (168-69)
</q></p>
          <p>Thompson discusses “The Divine Image,” “To Tirzah,” and “I saw a chapel all of gold”
in the light of Blake’s changing relations with Swedenborgian thought. He interestingly associates the
chapel in “I saw a chapel all of gold” with the Swedenborgians’ Great Eastcheap meeting house and
ingeniously suggests that the “sty” of the last line “was that of advanced radicalism,” the
“swine” being associated with the satirical variations on Burke’s “swinish multitude” made by
radicals such as Daniel Isaac Eaton and Thomas Spence. One of the important elements of this part of 
<hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast</hi> is Thompson’s sense that the books Blake read were not merely
“sources” or even negative sources but the productions of a culture comprising various overlapping
constituencies.</p>
          <p>With Thompson’s brilliant exposition of “London” we leave the discourse of Swedenborgianism
and approach that of Paineite radicalism. The well-known revision of “dirty” to “charter’d” acquires
a new context in Paine’s rejection of the freeborn Briton’s pride in his chartered rights. “Every
chartered town,” Paine wrote, “is an aristocratical monopoly in itself, and the qualifications of electors
proceeds out of those chartered monopolies.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">1</ref> In citing such examples Thompson is not engaging in mere source-hunting but is, as he
later puts it in comparing Blake’s use of the verb “appall” with that of William Frend, “‘finding a
vocabulary and stock of images common to a particular group or a particular intellectual tradition, in this
case that of radical Dissent” (185n21). Yet, as Thompson argues, the poem is not only a political vehicle,
for Blake’s vision is wider, combining in the last stanza of “London” the image of the exploited girl
sold for a bit of bread with the archetypal whore of Babylon. The relationship of discourses is, as the author
puts it “fraternal but transformed.” <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">1</hi> No footnote is given for this
quotation, which is from Part I of <hi rend="i">Rights of Man</hi> (page 75 in the Penguin edition), and it
should be noted that while Thompson’s posthumous manuscript has generally been well edited there are
occasional omissions such as this one and the absence of the name Hermitage from the index. One would also
like to know the identity of the Siegvolk (first name not given) who wrote a work called <hi rend="i">The
Everlasting Gospel</hi> (226-27). There are also a few typographical errors, the most important of which is
the misprinting (twice) of the title of an important source for the history of Swedenborgianism: P. F.
Gosse’s <hi rend="i"><corr type="emend">Portefeuille</corr> d’un ancien Typographe.</hi></note></p>
          <p>In “Human Images,” the penultimate chapter of <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast</hi>,
the authors juxtaposed with Blake are Gibbon (especially chapters 20 and 49 of <hi rend="i">Decline and Fall
of the Roman Empire</hi>) and Constantin de Volney. Although Blake, unlike Byron, did not sympathize with
Gibbon’s sapping a solemn creed with solemn sneer, he did read the <hi rend="i">Decline and Fall</hi>, or at
least parts of it. David Erdman has demonstrated the relevance of chapter 1 to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
and Thompson shows convincingly how Constantine and Charlemagne are linked through the intermediacy of Gibbon.
Volney’s <hi rend="i">Ruins</hi> is never mentioned by Blake but it is hard to believe that this radical’s
Bible was unknown to him, and Volney’s vision of human history culminating in a revolutionary society may
have seemed to Blake for a time compatible with his own. As Thompson remarks, “He was happy, at least until
1795, to co-exist with atheists and deists,” though I am not sure why Godwin is specifically excluded from
the list (215). Godwin, on the contrary, may be responsible for much of Blake’s anti-institutionalism as
well as for what appears to be a consistent indifference to the extension of the vote. The crucial difference
between the Blake of the 1790s and the radicals with whom he fellow-travelled was that, as Thompson puts it,
“Blake, while appropriating some of their arguments, placed a full emphasis upon affective and imaginative
‘culture’” (215). <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast</hi> is consistently true to Blake’s
commitment to such culture (to dispense with inverted commas), broadening our understanding of Blake’s
political and religious interests by viewing them as components of his creative work.</p>
          <p>Some time in the 1980s I <corr type="emend">visited</corr> a William Morris exhibition at the ICA Gallery in London. The
installation concentrated less upon the display of objects, though there were plenty of those, than upon the
re-creation of both Morris’s historical ambiance and his imaginative world. The last item in the show was
not by Morris, though it featured someone who had written a book about him. It was a black-and-white
photograph of a large crowd standing in the rain. Rising above a sea of umbrellas was the white-maned head of
Edward Thompson, addressing a nuclear disarmament rally. It was a fitting emblem of the subject of the
exhibition and, one might now add, of the subject of <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast.</hi></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
