<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.3.lussier</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Charles D. Minahen, Vortex/t: The Poetics of Turbulence</title>
        <author n="Lussier">Mark S. Lussier</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1994/95</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994/95</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Alma Bennett</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mark Lussier</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>June Sturrock</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994/95"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-3-0007">
        <pb id="p28-111" n="111"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Charles D. Minahen, <hi rend="i">Vortex/t: The Poetics of
                                Turbulence.</hi> University Park, PA: The Pennsylvania State UP,
                            1992. 205 pp. $28.50</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Mark S. <name>Lussier</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The power of Charles Minahen’s <hi rend="i">Vortex/t: The Poetics of
                            Turbulence</hi> resides in its willingness to speculate creatively with
                        somewhat limited evidence. However, the work also has holes, and while
                        perhaps appropriate given its attempted “hermeneutical disclosure of
                        symbolic turbulence” in diverse philosophical and poetic writings,
                        these holes qualify somewhat the insights achieved. Those wishing to derive
                        maximum benefit from the book should invert normal reading procedure and
                        proceed immediately to the work’s closing appendix to come to grips
                        with the confusing terms “Vortices, Helices, Spirals, and
                        Gyres” often wrongly applied to related but different phenomena.
                        Normally, such a definition of terms occurs at the opening of a work, but
                        the inverse reading has the function of tapping the processes diachronically
                        and synchronically explored in the three major divisions of the book. The
                        appendix traces vortical phenomena “at all levels of the known
                        universe,” which are “widely dispersed through the whole range
                        of phenomena from the micro- to the macrocosmic, and inhering in both
                        organic and inorganic systems and states” (149). Yet the terms
                        (vortex, helix, spiral, gyre) differ in their spatial properties, and these
                        differences are crucial in Minahen’s mapping of “symbolic
                        turbulence” (3) in the authors considered in his study.</p>
          <p>In exploring the differences in the specific definitions of the varied yet
                        related terms of turbulence, readers gain insights grounded in physical
                        phenomena, and this grounding makes legible the barrage of technical
                        language at the beginning of Minahen’s complicated assessment of the
                        literal presence and symbolic function of vortical figuration in widely
                        disparate works. The opening “Archaeology of Symbolic
                        Turbulence” (3) charts the “mystical cosmic and religious
                        significance” (3) of two types of symbols to establish a
                        characteristic structural dialectic of embodied “polar opposition and
                        synthesis” (3). The text then observes vortical symbols from the
                        Hebraic and Hellenic traditions and successfully argues that vortextual
                        processes, although different in their origins, undergird Western
                        epistemologies from “the whirlwind [as] Yahweh’s distinct
                        emblem” (10) to “vortical symbolism [that]. . . typifies the
                        Homeric conception of the cosmos” (14).</p>
          <p>Having identified literary and philosophic aspects of symbolic turbulence
                        embedded in Hellenic and Hebraic thought and practice, Minahen undertakes an
                        exploration of “vortical cosmogonic theory” (20) in relation
                        to the pre-Socratic philosophers Heraclitus, Anaxagoras, Empedocles, and
                        Democritus, and the chasm between poetry and science in Western tradition:
                        “[Aristotle’s] response is indicative of the tension, in the
                        episteme, between the more rigorous ‘scientific’ method
                        espoused by Aristotle, concerned with the validity of the mechanics of the
                        theory, and the ‘poetic’ tradition which Empedocles is still a
                        part of and which Aristotle ignores altogether” (20). While the
                        chapter is set up as a diachronic exploration of thinkers concerned with
                        “a matrix from which the entire Western tradition of discursive
                        thinking issues” (15), it offers one noticeable critical anachronism
                        when Yeats’s <hi rend="i">A Vision</hi> is used to illustrate the
                        conceptual possibility of “the Empedoclean double process”
                        (22). While Yeats’s gyres give the “perfect example of
                        dialectic (i.e., polarity, antithesis, and synthesis, simultaneously and/or
                        in sequence)” (21), his presence in a chapter on pre-Socratic
                        thinkers breaks an otherwise implied historical progression. Furthermore,
                        given both Yeats’s exploitation of the vortex at the foundation of
                        his ‘system’ and his appropriation of the concept from Blake
                        (who is discussed in chapter 7), this brief inclusion only points to the
                        more striking exclusion of Yeats from his logical position, towards the end
                        of the book. What binds the pre-Socratics is the element of chance or
                        necessity at work in “sequences of mechanical interaction”
                        (25), rendering the diverse expression of vorticality in their thought
                        “as much a metaphor as a scientific cosmogonic principle”
                            (25).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">1</hi> However, as Roger Jones discusses in his
                                <hi rend="i">Physics as Metaphor</hi> (Minneapolis: U of Minnesota
                            P, 1982), there is some validity to the representational interweaving of
                            physics and metaphor: “we were all poets and the world was our
                            metaphor,” since “the observer and observed form an
                            integrated unit that cannot be broken down into independent
                            components” (3, 6).</note></p>
          <p>Minahen’s discussion of Plato’s “Great Whorl,” in
                        chapter 3, rightly focuses on the myth of Ur that concludes the 
<hi rend="i">Republic</hi>, and the mythic narrative of a soldier’s death and
                        return to life that brings him to view “a vision of the structure of
                        the cosmos” (28). The cosmos, gyrating hemispheres that correspond to
                        astrological and planetary movements, is a “revolving vault”
                        (28), with eight “whorls in all, lying within one another”
                        (29), and its operations are linked to that of a “free circular
                        vortex,” where “velocities vary in a manner inversely 
<pb id="p28-112" n="112"/>
proportional to the distance from the central
                        axis” (33). One’s reservations about this chapter stem not
                        from the technically dense language, a type of hermetic scientism, but
                        rather from the rhetorically manufactured debate with an isolated critic (in
                        this case, Francis M. Cornford), which detracts from the significant insight
                        that “the Great Whorl represents a culmination, an apex, in the
                        development of an epistemic vortex symbol” (36).</p>
          <p>The same critical practice that structures chapter 3 continues in chapter 4,
                        “Epicurean Whirlings and Lucretius’s Turbulent Flux,”
                        where Minahen confronts Donald A. Mackenzie’s denial of the vorticity
                        in the thought of Epicurus. The crux of the matter hinges upon
                        Epicurus’s discomfort with the role that “necessity” or
                        “chance” plays in pre-Socratic and Platonic thought, due to
                        “the teleological implications” (38) of the <hi rend="i">clinamen</hi> or random
swerve at the foundation of atomist theory.
                        Although Epicurus cites certain meteorological phenomena as demonstrative of
                        the presence of the vortex, his thought does “lack the symbolic
                        multivocity of other examples we have seen” (38). In contrast to the
                        use of previous interpretations as critical cannon-fodder, Minahen’s
                        confrontation with conflicting interpretations of Lucretius’s <hi rend="i">De Rerum
Natura</hi> (Mackenzie versus Michel Serres)
                        successfully provides a frame for Lucretius’s cosmology of
                        “many vortices coming into and out of existence in ever-changing
                        complexes of colliding atoms and swarming fluid flows” (40). As a
                        result, his use of Lucretius as the terminus to the opening section elevates
                        the concluding discussion of “the vortex” (48), clarifying
                        “its evolution into so rich and complex a symbol by the end of the
                        classical age” (48) and its “reemerge[nce] as a quintessential
                        symbol of the late Medieval Christian vision in the work of Dante”
                        (48).</p>
          <p>Once into the second section, “Visionary Break-through,”
                        Minahen’s text supplies just that, breaking through its negative
                        dialogical engagement with isolated critics to confront the complexities of
                        Dante’s use of “circular, spiral, and vortical properties [as]
                        a reservoir of symbolic possibilities with which to fashion his mystical
                        vision of the after-life” (51). In “Dante’s Vortical
                        Triptych” (chapter 5), Minahen does justice to the prevalent layering
                        of spiral, vortical, and helical symbols in the large structures of hell,
                        purgatory, and heaven and in the smallest descriptive details, with the
                        minute particulars of local symbolism reinforcing the grand gyrations of
                        bodies and spheres. The most obvious example is hell; the pit spirals
                        downward to a singularity, powered by the “association of vortical
                        turbulence with sin” (54) appropriated from St. Augustine, and
                        displays characteristics defined by “the concentric streamlines of a
                        ‘free circular vortex’ . . . . in which the velocities are
                        backward [fast on the periphery and stagnant at the center]”
                        (52).</p>
          <p>Dante’s sensitivity to structural possibilities in vortical phenomena
                        can be seen when “purgatory reveals itself to be an enantiomorph of
                        hell, turned inside-out” (59). The prototypical spiro-helical
                        qualities of pyramids and mountains are pressed into Dante’s service,
                        and, true to its inverse relationship with hell, activity intensifies with
                        the ascent just as, in hell, activity decreases with descent.
                        “Whereas hell and purgatory are visible entities in Dante’s
                        scheme . . . the system of concentric crystalline spheres of the Ptolemaic
                        universe . . . is transparent and invisible” (62). This obvious
                        difference and its moral implications lead Minahen into a discussion of the
                        “four great symbols” (63) that structure paradise: “the
                        ‘wheel’ of planetary orbits”; “the ‘nest
                        of hemispheres’ . . . that turn on the axis of the North
                        Star”; “the primum mobile,” and “the celestial
                        rose” (63). The interweaving of these symbols brings
                        “concentrically circular, spiro-helical, or vortical
                        structures” (63) into conjunction in such a way that deity can be
                        both center and circumference, and the terms and instances of vorticality
                        increase as the poet moves through the heavens. The penultimate and ultimate
                        images of vortical phenomena in heaven are the juxtaposed primum mobile and
                        celestial white rose, and Minahen’s analysis of the “paradox
                        of this inverse double image” (69) justifies his conclusion that
                        Dante’s “elaboration of spiro-vortical symbolism” has
                        been of “seminal importance in the history of ideas” (69).</p>
          <p>The brief analysis of Descartes, in “The Turbulent Dream-Vision of
                        Descartes’s ‘Olympian’ Experience” (chapter 6),
                        provides a transition into the modern period of “scientific
                        cosmology” (71) yet resists the exploration of the vortices upon
                        which Descartes built his mechanics of planetary movement, preferring,
                        instead, to examine a tripartite dream vision experienced by Descartes which
                        proved pivotal to the development of his thought. This is a clever and wise
                        procedure, and Minahen’s “reading” of
                        Descartes’s dream provides a tangible example of the
                        philosopher’s symbolic intertwining of “physics and
                        metaphysics” at the foundation of his material analysis. Minahen
                        concludes that “Descartes’s turbulent cosmology was thus
                        figuratively correct, even if literally misapplied, since the vortical
                        configuration is ubiquitous in the universe” (72). Minahen’s
                        selection also skillfully bridges the gap between the Ptolemaic Christian
                        vision of Dante and the post-Newtonian visionary physics 
<pb id="p28-113" n="113"/>
pursued by Blake. Descartes’s dream reveals him as a
                        man grappling with “a profound conflict between science and religion,
                        knowledge and faith, vanity and deference to divinity” (83), and
                        these dualities, characteristic of vortical phenomena in nature,
                        symbolically “anticipate such important antitheses as body and soul,
                        doubt and certainty, dream and reality” that shaped philosophical
                        discourse in the eighteenth century. Additionally, the focus on
                        “dream” helps shorten the distance between the material
                        dualism of Descartes and Blake’s radical eradication of dualities,
                        since Blake too turns to dream discourse for solutions.</p>
          <p>The next chapter, “‘. . . That Every Thing Has Its/Own Vortex 
                        . . . ‘: Dialectics of Vortical Symbolism in Blake,” ends the
                        center section of the text with Blake’s “pithy, if somewhat
                        cryptic, synthesis of many of the vortical images examined
                        heretofore” (85). Minahen discusses the symbol’s verbal and
                        visual manifestations to explore Blake’s negative and positive uses
                        of spiral and vortical imagery: the former associated with Urizen’s
                        vortical passage in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (Night 6) and with plate
                        11 of the Job illustrations; the latter associated with the famous
                        “vortex” passage from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and plate 13 of
                        the Job illustrations. The ambiguities of Blake’s use of the vortex
                        are considered at the conclusion of the chapter through one of
                        Blake’s better-known watercolors to Dante, “Beatrice
                        Addressing Dante from the Car”; Beatrice represents the
                        “Female Will,” and the painting “epitomizes the
                        equivocal, dialectical function of the vortex in Blake’s art”
                        (95). As these last formulations indicate, this chapter adds little to our
                        understanding of Blake, his use of the vortex, or his place in a line of
                        thinkers operating in a counter-linear fashion in relation to culture. There
                        are some troubling generalizations scattered throughout this and other
                        chapters: for example, Minahen’s claim that Blake reinforces
                        “lefthandedness” (90) as the direction of error ignores
                        Blake’s propensity for inverting exactly these stereotypical
                        categories, as in the title page to <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                            Hell.</hi></p>
          <p>The last section of the book, “Threshold of the Unknown,” opens
                        with “Descents into Poe’s Maelstrom” (chapter 8), in
                        which Minahen “consider[s] Edgar Allan Poe a symbolist along with
                        Rimbaud and Mallarmé” (101). Certainly, all three writers
                        liberate the vortical symbolism from its nebulous dependence upon
                        “necessity” in the first section and the markedly Christian
                        orientation found in the second section, and the growth of the symbol from
                        Poe to Mallarmé might very well “identify a specific
                        nineteenth-century symbolist episteme” (102). It is not new to find
                        “‘the recurrence of the <hi rend="i">spiral</hi> or <hi rend="i">vortex</hi>’ as
one of [Poe’s] most pervasive
                        symbols” (quoting Richard Wilbur 102), and Minahen examines such
                        symbols in Poe’s early “MS. Found in a Bottle” and the
                        later “A Descent into the Maelstrom.” Both stories, which
                        conclude with a narratorial descent into a watery vortex, present
                        “the vortex [a]s literally a natural destructive force” (103).
                        In the first, the natural experience collapses into a teleological event
                        with “Dantesque” overtones of “evil, hopelessness, and
                        death” (106). In the second, the narrator’s visual observation
                        of a vortex, punctuated by an old sailor’s verbal narration of
                        surviving his passage through one, takes on the aesthetic and dramatic
                        dimensions of the sublime and the cathartic. Both stories achieve, in lesser
                        and greater degree (respectively), a double <hi rend="i">mise en abyme</hi>,
                        an interpenetration of content and style as well as the intertwining of
                        narrative layers. According to Minahen, “the paradox of Poe’s
                        vortex” resides in its ambiguous functions as
                        “threshold” and “state of suspension” (112), but
                        this could be said about several of the previous writers; Minahen’s
                        singular focus on the natural and symbolic correspondences between text and
                        world creates blindspots that could be pursued to widen the effects of
                        vortical symbolism as a viable epistemology.</p>
          <p>My point here is simply illustrated. When we apply, as I believe we must,
                        terms and concepts drawn from quantum mechanics and relativistic physics to
                        our discussions of the structure and effects of literary phenomena, as
                        Minahen does in evoking terms drawn from black hole theory in this chapter
                        (104), then we are equally obligated to perform an analysis of
                        psyche’s role in the construction of that reality, since the two are
                        inseparably entwined, as both the poet Blake and the physicist Heisenberg
                        know too well. Given the attention paid to Poe by postmodern critics (Lacan,
                        Derrida, Holland, et al.), it seems inconceivably neglectful to cite Marie
                        Bonaparte’s rather infantile and shallow reading of Poe, when the
                        full psychoanalytic dimensions of Poe’s use of the symbol in fact
                        support a reading that his and all texts incorporating <hi rend="i">mise en
                            abyme</hi> techniques often function as ‘vortexts.’<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">2</hi> I discuss such
                            “vortextuality” in “‘Vortext’ as
                            Philosopher’s Stone: Blake’s Textual Mirrors and the
                            Transmutation of Audience” <hi rend="i">New Orleans Review</hi>
                            13 (1986): 40-50. In regard to the postmodern ‘uses’ made
                            of Poe that could further this argument, I only point to Lacan’s
                            use of the Yin/Yang symbol, the very symbol that opens Minahen’s
                            attempted archaeological recovery of the vortical episteme, in his
                            discussion of inversions, double structures, and reversals in
                            Poe’s “The Purloined Letter” (<hi rend="i">The
                                Purloined Poe: Lacan, Derrida, and Psychoanalytic Reading</hi>, John
                            P. Muller and William J. Richardson [Baltimore and London: The Johns
                            Hopkins UP, 1988] 28-54).</note></p>
          <p>Minahen’s analysis of vortex as modern episteme achieves significant
                        insights when confronting the poetic phenomena unleashed in chapter 9,
                        “‘Tourbillons de Lumiere’: Rimbaud’s
                        Illuminating Vortices.” <pb id="p28-114" n="114"/>
Minahen approaches
                        Rimbaud’s “bizarre symbolic universe” (115) at both the
                        level of image and the literal level of appearance of words floating on
                        blank pages with interesting results, although a similar approach in the
                        Blake and Poe chapters would bolster and complicate the symbol’s
                        efficacy there in forcing the “breakdown in the linguistic sign
                        itself” (116) observed in several of Rimbaud’s poems. Clearly,
                        Rimbaud’s most intense engagement with symbolic turbulence occurs in
                        three “illuminations” (“Marine,”
                        “Mouvement,” and “Mystique”), and the analyses
                        of these poems are illuminating. In “Marine,” the “free
                        association of subject-predicate” evokes a stylistic vortical
                        dynamic, tapping the “opposition, tension, and possible
                        fusion” (118) that the symbol has gathered to itself in its passage
                        through time. The turbulence discussed in “Mouvement” grows
                        out of “vortical synecdoches that abound throughout the text”
                        (120) and unveils “the vertiginous ‘dis-covery’ of
                        poetic insight” (123). The last poem, “Mystique,”
                        differs from the previously discussed illuminations in its movement away
                        from aquatic contexts and toward the poem as “a window into a kind of
                        noumenal world beyond that of phenomenal appearances” (124). These
                        readings support Minahen’s contention that “the Rimbaldean
                        vortex is a metamorphosing entity . . . that develops across the young
                        poet’s career, becoming increasingly hermetic and complex”
                        (127).</p>
          <p>“Whirling Toward the Void in Dead Center: Symbolic Turbulence in
                        Mallarmé’s <hi rend="i">Un Coup de des</hi>” (chapter
                        10) clarifies the metaphorical differences in “the symbolist concept
                        of reality” (129) that become apparent in the nexus of their
                        turbulent representations. Mallarmé’s use of the shipwreck
                        reaccesses the associations of aquatic phenomena with vortical symbolism
                        found in all three sections of Minahen’s text, and the graphic
                        dispersal of terms on the page embodies the oppositions explored in the
                        poem’s content in a manner analogous to Rimbaud’s. Confronting
                        Mallarmé’s poetic “epistemological statement that
                        depicts the complex, fragmented nature of thought” (130), Minahen
                        enters the poem’s “absences and omissions” (130) to
                        elucidate “the vortex paradigm . . . established throughout”
                        (131). The effect of this effort, while admirable, accounts for the sense of
                        the chapter’s “constructed” feel; in this way, the poem
                        seems to function more like a mirror that comes to reflect the
                        author’s desire for closure, even though vortical symbolic clusters
                        are present. Mallarmé’s use of the vortex, where transcendent
                        ideas are subsumed in a vortex that leads to death, intersects practices
                        traced in all previous chapters but in inverse fashion, since
                        Mallarmé’s metaphors of turbulence function as “a
                        negating absence at the center of all experience” (141).</p>
          <p>In summary, although the work articulates, at the outset, <hi rend="i">a
                            desire to pursue</hi> these matters through “a synchrony of the
                        symbol” (ix), <hi rend="i">the actual pursuit</hi> is clearly
                        established as a diachronic sequence from earlier to later writers, creating
                        inexplicable holes where evidence seems to support the progression. Drawing
                        an example from the material most familiar to me, the chapter on Blake
                        places the poet in an epistemological line issuing forth from Descartes (in
                        spite of Blake’s repeated attacks on Cartesian dualism) and situates
                        Blake’s vortical practices within the framework of critical consensus
                        by powerful readers of Blake’s poetic and visual designs (Mitchell,
                        Raine, and Ault, among others). However, Minahen neglects to connect
                        Blake’s use of the vortex in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> to the intense
                        inquiries into cones of vision as vortical phenomena in the diverse writings
                        of Newton, Berkeley, Priestley (to name only a few) and, of course, Blake
                        himself. Worse still, the chapter neglects specific attempts to address
                        Blake’s use of the vortex; the most glaring omission, to this reader,
                        is failure to reference the information provided in Nelson Hilton’s
                        chapter of <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination</hi> entitled “Word and
                        Text: Vortex and Wheel,” although other examples could be cited.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">3</hi> E.g., Kay Parkhurst Easson and Roger
                            Easson’s “Commentary” to their edition of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (Boulder:
Shambhala Press; New York: Random
                            House, 1978) which speaks directly to the function of the eye as
                            vortical in nature (145-50) and the vortex itself as
                            “Blake’s image of spiritual travel” (151
                            ff.).</note></p>
          <p>There is much to recommend a reading of <hi rend="i">Vortex/t: The Poetic of
                            Turbulence</hi>, for the continuity and development of vortical
                        symbolism as a counter epistemology capable of embodying the inner and outer
                        turbulence of thought and experience is thoroughly established. However,
                        there is considerable room for disagreement with individual readings in the
                        text, and readers should be prepared to engage the text dialogically,
                        probing the limits of Minahen’s application of vortical processes and
                        entering, in the process, the vortex of mental strife that Blake terms
                        “mental war.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>