<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.3.sherman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Philip D. Sherman’s Blakes at Brown University</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander S. Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1994/95</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994/95</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Alma Bennett</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mark Lussier</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>June Sturrock</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994/95"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <pb id="p28-94" n="94"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-3-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Philip D. Sherman’s Blakes at Brown University</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Alexander S. <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>A visit to an exhibition of Brown’s choice holdings has led to the recognition of five
            printed plates from Blake’s illuminated books that had been untraced: a single leaf
            bearing on its front and back uncolored impressions of plates 11 (“Arise O Rintrah . .
            .”) and 17 (“Ethinthus Queen of Waters . . .”) from the assemblage called copy c of 
              <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and three leaves from the posthumous copy o of 
              <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> bearing uncolored pulls of plates 13 (“The Little Boy lost”), 20 and
21
            (the first and second plates of “Night”). These items, along with a posthumous pull of
            Blake’s wood engraving XIII for Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi>, 1874 restrikes of
            plates 15 and 20 of the <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, and a
            Colnaghi restrike of the fifth state of Blake’s engraving of <hi rend="i">Chaucers
              Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are now in the Koopman collection in the John Hay Library at
            Brown University. All were given to Brown by Philip D. Sherman, an Oberlin professor and
            Brown alumnus who died in 1957, as part of a huge collection that he named in honor of
            Koopman, a Brown librarian. G. E. Bentley, Jr., Robert N. Essick, Mary Lynn Johnson,
            Charles Ryskamp, Joseph Viscomi, and the staff of the John Hay Library (especially
            Jennifer Lee) helped me to make sense of these discoveries.</p>
          <p>Sherman purchased the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> leaf, <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 20 and 21,
            the proof from Thornton’s Virgil, and the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings from the
            Weyhe Gallery (New York) in 1938 or 1939; in his copy of Weyhe’s Catalogue #81 (December
            1938), preserved at Brown, he wrote “Mine” in the margin next to several entries on pp.
            11 and 12, and dated the annotations 4 August 1939. (Sherman may have been mistaken in
            claiming the entry for <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>—see below.) <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 13
            could have come through Weyhe as well, but it is not listed in this catalogue; because
            it has been trimmed differently and bound separately, it may have been acquired at
            another time. According to <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, the Weyhe Gallery probably
            broke up copy o of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, which once contained at least 17 plates from
            both <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> (Bentley 429).
            Bentley’s forthcoming <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> will describe the fates
            of eight additional pages from <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> o.</p>
          <pb id="p28-95" n="95"/>
          <figure n="europe.c-proof.P11" rend="file" width="708" height="1000">
            <head>1. <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, plate 11.</head>
            <figDesc>Relief etching with white-line engraving. Koopman Collection, John Hay Library,
              Brown University.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">
                  <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                </hi>
                <hi rend="b">c</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The leaf containing two plates from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (accession number KPR
              142) is much more important from a scholarly perspective than the posthumous pages
              from <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and the other restrikes. The <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
              leaf was matted for the exhibition at Brown, but it is now loose in the portfolio that
              also contains the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings. Its left edge (recto) is irregular
              where it has been cut from an earlier binding: the leaf now measures 22.3 centimeters
              across the top, 22.7 across the bottom, and is 31.2 centimeters high. It bears various
              unidentified dealers’ or collectors’ annotations in pencil (recto, top left: “18,”
              lower left: “Rx,” and “Europe page 6,” bottom margin: “This is the one in the [?]”;
              verso, top left: “19,” lower left: “Europe page 16”), as well as the number 38,
              written in ink at upper right in the recto. The leaf came from what is called copy c
              of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, which was never an actual copy of the book but the
              uncoordinated plates from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> that were once included in a volume
              of miscellaneous Blakeana assembled by George A. Smith in the mid-nineteenth century.
              This collection is described in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> under “The Order in
              which the Songs of Innocence and Experience ought to be paged” (337-41).</p>
            <p>The leaf from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> c at Brown is well printed on heavy wove
              paper, without watermarks, in two different colors of ink: a slightly brownish gray
              for plate 11 (illus. 1) and a grayish blue for plate 17 (illus. 2), with slight
              vestiges of black ink appearing along the edges of a few relief areas on both sides.
              Plate 11 probably would be darker but still gray if printed more heavily, and 17 would
              be decidedly blue, but not so bright a blue as the ink on plate 17 in copy B (on inks,
              see Viscomi 95). Both plates are printed squarely, and appear to have been carefully
              registered to each other in the recto/verso format. The plate border (the relief line
              around the edges of the plate created by the strips of wax used to hold acid on the
              plate during etching) has been wiped before printing on plate 17 and on the upper left
              corner of 11, as Blake often did in printing relief plates before 1795. This must be a
              1794 impression because plate 17 is in the first of three states: line 32 reads “She
              ceas’d, and all went forth to sport,” rather than “She ceas’d, for All were forth at
              sport,” and line 35 still ends “and the angel trumpet blew”; this phrase was gouged
              out of the plate in later states. The leaf at Brown must therefore have been printed
              by Blake, even if he never finished it or assembled into a book the pages known as 
                <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> c.</p>
            <p>The discovery of this leaf solves some old puzzles and raises some new questions. A
              leaf of a slightly different size but bearing plates 11 and 17 on recto and verso that
              was formerly in the collection of Charles Ryskamp (sold in July 1994 by a Connecticut
              dealer to Robert N. Essick) has been confused with the one just discovered at Brown.
              In <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> Bentley traced the Ryskamp/Essick leaf from George A.
              Smith to Quaritch to Muir to Macgeorge to George C. Smith to Weyhe, after which it
              disappears until sold by “Allen of New York” in about 1964 to Ryskamp (Bentley
              339-41). Sherman’s annotation in the Weyhe catalogue, noted above, and the closer fit
              of the Brown leaf to the fuller description in the 1938 Parke-Bernet catalogue of the
              George C. Smith sale (quoted below), led me at first to believe that this entire
              provenance should be assigned to the leaf at Brown, leaving the Ryskamp/Essick leaf an
              orphan. But the entry in the Weyhe catalogue that was claimed by Sherman is more
              likely a description of the Ryskamp/Essick leaf, which is printed in green on both
              sides, than of the leaf at Brown, which is unmistakably gray and blue: 
                <pb id="p28-96" n="96"/>
<figure n="EuropePl17.28.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="537">
                <head>2. <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, plate 17.</head>
                <figDesc>Relief etching. Koopman Collection, John Hay Library, Brown
                  University.</figDesc>
              </figure>
			<q> 125. “ARISE O RINTRAH . . .” Plate 6 of “Europe a Prophecy”, almost full
                page composition of a kneeling woman clasping a patriarch with outstretched arms,
                superb in design, etched on copper and printed in relief as a woodcut in green ink;
                and on the reverse page 16 of the same book, “Ethinthus Queen [sic] of Waters”, also
                printed in green ink, MacGeorge Coll., exceedingly scarce 125.00 (Weyhe 11).
			</q></p>
            <p>Thus the Ryskamp/Essick leaf is probably first recorded in this Weyhe entry; the leaf
              is now closely trimmed, and does not bear an ink page number like those George A.
              Smith wrote on the items bound with “The Order of the ‘Songs,’” though it might have
              been part of that collection or the later Macgeorge collection, as claimed in the
              Weyhe catalogue. The leaf at Brown does have an ink page number, 38, that corresponds
              to an appropriate place in the collected volume (which place had been tentatively
              assigned to an untraced impression of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 15; see Bentley 338).
              Both the Ryskamp/Essick and the Brown leaves must have come through Weyhe at some
              point; the Brown leaf was probably purchased from Weyhe in 1939 (Sherman must have
              recalled from whom he bought it and when, even if he didn’t closely check the ink
              color in the catalogue entry). The Brown leaf is certainly 
<pb id="p28-97" n="97"/>
              the one sold to Weyhe in 1938, as described in the Parke-Bernet catalogue: 
			<q> 32.
                [Blake]. Five Plates for “Europe, a Prophecy”. 5 <hi rend="i">plates on</hi> 3 
                  <hi rend="i">leaves printed in gray, grayish-blue, sepia, and in black.</hi><lb/>
                These are apparently proofs.<lb/>
 (1) Begins “Arise O Rintrah”. Printed in gray.
                Measures 12 5/16 by 8 7/8 inches [31.3 by 22.5 cm].<lb/>
 (2) Begins “Ethinthus queen
                of waters”. Printed in grayish-blue on the reverse of the preceding plate
                (Parke-Bernet 17). </q></p>
            <p>These colors are correct for the Brown leaf, as are the dimensions; the
              Ryskamp/Essick leaf is much smaller: 25.6 cm high and 19.3 cm wide.</p>
            <p>The pairing of plates 11 and 17 on these leaves could have been an artifact of
              experimental proof-printing in which, to save paper, Blake grabbed at random an unused
              impression of plate 11 and proofed plate 17 on the other side to see how the latter
              looked. Perhaps something like that sequence happened a decade or two later with those
              plates of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> that have plates from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
              printed on the other side (Bentley 144).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">1</ref> But the
              conjunction of plates 11 and 17 on recto and verso may be something more than an
              ordinary consequence of proof-printing on salvaged paper. The pairing may instead be a
              vestige of an early version of the book that was superseded rather than a mere
              accident. There are at least three additional 11/17 pairs, none of them in copies of
                <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> that are generally regarded as complete: in copy a, at the
              British Museum; in copy b, at the Morgan Library; and another leaf from 
                <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> c at the Newberry Library (Bentley 144). The mere existence of five
              such pairs suggests that they were created deliberately rather than randomly.<ref
                target="n53" type="note">2</ref> Further, Blake wiped the plate borders before
              printing the Ryskamp/Essick, Newberry and Brown 11/17 leaves (and perhaps the others
              as well), a procedure that would not have been necessary for most workshop proofs,
              such as those created to check the progress of a design or to monitor the adjustment
              of the press. <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Unused impressions of plate 11 might
                be expected to exist, for the extensive white-line engraving (executed with a burin
                after etching) that delineates the clouds on that plate might have called for
                regular proofing to check progress. But in fact plate 11 on the Brown leaf is in
                exactly the same state as all other surviving impressions—so it probably didn’t
                become scrap paper because Blake was dissatisfied with the design or the text on the
                copperplate. Further, plate 11 printed at least as well as in pages that were used
                in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, so it wouldn’t have been rejected for that
                reason.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">2</hi> It is also possible that Blake
                and/or his wife became confused in trying to print pages in recto/verso format, the
                arrangement used in several early copies. Losing one’s place would be easy in the
                case of a book with no printed page numbers and few catchwords. Viscomi shows in 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> that Blake usually produced
                illuminated books in small editions, so he and Catherine could have printed plate 17
                several times on the back of good impressions of plate 11 when they meant to print
                plate 12, and then put these leaves aside when they discovered the error. But plate
                17 is in at least three different colors in these 11/17 pairs, which makes a single
                printing disaster a little less likely.</note></p>
            <p>Evidence in the text confirms that the leaf at Brown and its 11/17 cousins, some of
              which have been modified extensively in various ways, mark phases in the transition
              from one version of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, probably a shorter one, to the version
              that he produced as finished copies in several configurations. Andrew Lincoln noticed
              in 1978 that copy a, the “incomplete” uncolored copy in the British Museum (with an
              11/17 pair), could actually constitute an “early version” of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
              that lacked the episode on plates 12-16. It is not hard to envision the material on
              plate 17 following that on 11, for both consist of roughly parallel invocations of her
              offspring by Enitharmon. (For those using Erdman’s revised edition or <hi rend="i">The
                Illuminated Blake</hi>, plates 11 and 17 in Bentley’s pagination correspond with
              Erdman’s plates 8 and 14.) As Lincoln suggested, the narrative on plates 12-16 must be
              an interpolation, though it could have been assembled in part from plates that were
              originally elsewhere in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (see also Larrissy, who describes
              connections with <hi rend="i">America</hi>). Plates 12-16 encompass an independently
              coherent description of Enitharmon’s 1800-year sleep, beginning abruptly at the top of
              plate 12 and ending on plate 16, when she wakes up and returns to her invocations. It
              is true that Ethinthus, addressed at the beginning of 17, is first mentioned in the
              last four lines of 16, but as Viscomi notes in correspondence, the 11 lines at the end
              of this plate can be seen as a transitional device to reintroduce the interrupted song
              of Enitharmon.</p>
            <p>Blake apparently made the textual revisions on plates 17 and 18, the mechanics of
              which are described by Viscomi (278-79), in order to accommodate the new narrative
              created by the interpolation. He modified line 17:32 from “She ceas’d, and all went
              forth to sport,” the original printed text in the 11/17 pairs, to “She ceas’d, for All
              were forth at sport” in the finished copies because, once plates 12-16 had been added,
              the party to which Enitharmon was calling her sons and daughters had already been
              going on without her for 1800 
<pb id="p28-98" n="98"/>
<figure n="thornton.virgil.28.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="550" height="252">
                <head>3. Plate XIII, Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil.</hi></head>
                <figDesc>Wood engraving. Koopman Collection, John Hay Library, Brown
                  University.</figDesc>
              </figure> years. Similarly, the angel and his trumpet were excised from lines 17:35
              and 18:1 in the completed books because this comparatively simple apocalyptic gesture
              had been replaced by the more complicated episode involving the “red limb’d Angel” and
              the “mighty Spirit” of Newton on plate 16 (see Lincoln 213 and Bentley 155).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> as a whole generated an unusual number of surviving “proof”
              pages and variant states (Viscomi 276-79); each of these may have its own story to
              tell. Some of these pages appear to have been rejected preliminaries, some
              transitional states, and others private afterthoughts, as David Erdman regards the
              variant title pages (397). We certainly have an extraordinary wealth of complex
              evidence to work with: the other 11/17 pairs, especially those with modifications in
              ink and by erasure; other variant pages; additional recto/verso pairs of other plates;
              inferences that can be drawn from the order in which Blake used the backs of the 
                <hi rend="i">America</hi> copperplates to make the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copperplates
              (see Bentley 145 and Viscomi 413n3); offsets on “proofs” and other pages; and more. It
              is possible that the version of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> in which 17 followed 11 was
              merely one of several orders with which Blake experimented. Yet because there are five
              11/17 pairs, Blake probably had settled on a complete ur-<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
              (perhaps corresponding to copy a, as Lincoln suggests) that he regarded as ready to
              publish, and he began to do so. Then he decided to make radical changes, one
              consequence of which is the extraordinary number of unused plates from this
              illuminated book. Scholars attempting to sort out the composition process of 
                <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> must carefully consider the potential significance of all the
              “proof” leaves, especially the recto/verso pairs, but even a study of the further
              implications of the 11/17 pairs alone will depend on a much more thorough survey of
              them than I have done.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">
                  <hi rend="i">Songs o</hi>
                </hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>All three plates from the posthumous <hi rend="i">Songs o</hi> at Brown are printed
              in the orange-brown ink that Bentley describes as having been used for 
                <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 39, copy o, in his collection (Bentley 371). <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
13
              and 20 are underinked, and all three plates were printed with their borders. The poor
              inking and the unwiped borders are characteristic of posthumous pulls by Frederick
              Tatham, as is the fact that the platemark dimensions run about two millimeters larger
              than those of copies printed by Blake, who dampened the paper before printing to
              improve ink absorption; it shrank as it dried (Bentley 67). <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 13
              and 20 both show portions of a J WHATMAN watermark that do not include a date, though
              the paper is probably the same as that of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 39, copy o, which
              has an 1831 Whatman watermark (Bentley 371).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 13 is by itself in blue boards, together with a loose
              fragment trimmed from the page; the leaf now measures 16.0 by 23.0 centimeters (using
              width by height as in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>). The fragment measures 18.1 by
              2.5 centimeters; the whole leaf 
<pb id="p28-99" n="99"/>
was therefore almost as wide
              as Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 39 from this copy of the book, which measures
              18.6 centimeters. The fragment, inscribed in pencil “Page from Blake’s Songs of
              Innocence Chas Eliot Norton/ SP 40,” identifies one nineteenth-century owner of the
              whole book. <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 20 and 21 are bound together in the same kind of
              blue boards as those containing <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 13, but the two leaves have
              been even more severely trimmed, to 11.8 by 20.0 centimeters. They are both inscribed
              (at the bottom of the leaves, in the same hand as on the scrap from 
                <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 13), “Blake Songs of Innocence Charles Eliot Norton Collection.”
The
              accession numbers in the Koopman Collection for the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> pages are
              KPR 178-80.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Other Blakes</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The impression of Blake’s wood engraving XIII from Thornton’s 
                <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi> (illus. 3; accession number KPR 177) is probably what its mount
claims
              it to be, a posthumous impression once owned by Samuel Palmer that was taken by Edward
              Calvert from the blocks when they were owned by John Linnell. The heavily inked print
              is on thin paper without a visible watermark, trimmed to the very edge of the image at
              7.8 by 3.6 centimeters, mounted on a thick card that is only about a millimeter wider
              all around, then pasted on heavy wove paper and bound in brown boards. An inscription
              on the original mount by A. H. Palmer, Samuel’s son, has been copied onto the stiff
              paper on which the print and card are now mounted: “These identical proofs [there is
              only one now] of Blake’s Philips’s Pastoral (and this mount) were S. Palmer’s constant
              companions for many years. The proofs were printed by Edward Calvert, at Brixton, for
              John Linnell. See No. 28, V and A Museum Exhibition Catalogue p. 27. A. H. P.” One
              might suspect the younger Palmer of mild puffery here. Samuel Palmer also owned (and
              gave away) at least one impression from the unmutilated blocks made in his presence by
              Blake himself (Palmer 2: 707-08), and the particular image on Plate XIII contributed
              less decisively to the Shoreham style than did the pastoral scenes among Blake’s
              illustrations in this series. But the gracefully distorted dancers here resemble
              figures that appear in Palmer’s work and that of the other “Ancients” (see Paley), and
              this print may well have been important to him.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings (accession numbers KPR 140 and 141) are good
              “post-proof” impressions on thin India paper laid into unmarked heavy wove paper; they
              are probably from the final 1874 issue of 100 copies ordered by John Linnell (Bentley
              524). The wove paper of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 15 measures 33.0 by 45.9 centimeters
              (India 16.3 by 20.8); <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 20 is 34.3 by 42.5 (India 16.2 by
              21.1).</p>
            <p>The copy of <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> (KPR 258) at Brown is
              sealed in a mat and frame and was not available for close inspection, but it is
              certainly a fifth state impression on India laid on wove paper, probably a late
              nineteenth-century Colnaghi restrike (see Essick 85-86). This print is much less
              heavily inked than the Sessler restrikes of the 1940’s and seems almost gray by
              comparison; Essick attributes the flatness of Colnaghi restrikes to inadequate
              cleaning of the plate before printing (85).</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">WORKS CONSULTED</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, 1977.</p>
              <p>Brown University. <hi rend="i">The Collections of Brown University.</hi>
                Providence: n.p., 1992.</p>
              <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi>
                Newly rev. ed. Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1982.</p>
              <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> Garden City, NY:
                Doubleday, 1974.</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake.</hi>
                Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983.</p>
              <p>Larrissy, Edward. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi>: An Early Version?” 
                  <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 30 (1983): 217-19.</p>
              <p>Lincoln, Andrew. “Blake’s ‘Europe’”: An Early Version?” <hi rend="i">Notes and
                  Queries</hi> 25 (1978): 213.</p>
              <p>Paley, Morton D. “The Art of ‘The Ancients.’” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library
                  Quarterly</hi> 52 (1989): 97-124.</p>
              <p>Palmer, Samuel. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Ed. Raymond Lister.
                2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon, 1974.</p>
              <p>Parke-Bernet Galleries. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Renowned Collection of
                  First Editions, Original Drawings, Autograph Letters, and an Important Painting in
                  Oils . . . Collected by the Late George C. Smith, Jr.</hi> (Catalogue #59). New
                York, Parke-Bernet, 1938.</p>
              <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> Princeton:
                Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
              <p>Victoria and Albert Museum. <hi rend="i">Catalogue of an Exhibition of Drawings,
                  Etchings and Woodcuts by Samuel Palmer and other Disciples of William Blake.</hi>
                London: Victoria and Albert Museum, 1926.</p>
              <p>Weyhe Gallery. <hi rend="i">Fine Prints Old and New, Drawings and Sculpture.</hi>
                New York: Weyhe Gallery, 1938.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
