<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.3.dorrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert N. Essick, William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations: A Catalogue
and Study of the Plates Engraved by Blake after Designs by Other Artists</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1994/95</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994/95</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Alma Bennett</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mark Lussier</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>June Sturrock</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994/95"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-3-0007">
        <pb id="p28-103" n="103"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
                                Illustrations: A Catalogue and Study of the Plates Engraved by Blake
                                after Designs by Other Artists.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991.
                            [xv] + 138 pp. 295 illus. on unnumbered pp. at end. £60.00/$115.00
                            cloth.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>D.W.
                        <name>Dörrbecker</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Does anybody actually <hi rend="i">need</hi> a full-blown catalogue of this
                        particular sort of material, illustrated with no less than 295 high-quality
                        reproductions? Or is its publication just another ritual move in the process
                        of Blake’s canonization as a hero of late eighteenth-century British
                        culture? In order to understand Blake’s “original”
                        works, his poetry and his creative art, does one have to care, really, about
                        “copy” engravings such as his frontispieces after Saverio
                        Dalla Rosa’s drawings of the statues of Catullus and his friend,
                        Cornelius Nepos (#XXX, 66)? With the author of the book under review, I
                        should like to argue that the answer to these and similar questions
                        concerning the scholarly legitimation of the production of this catalogue
                        very definitely has to be in the affirmative. Due to some classicist notions
                        that still define what is to be considered an “original” work
                        of art, and what is “merely” a
                        “reproduction”—ideological norms and concepts that as
                        yet await deconstruction—Blake’s work as a commercial engraver
                        remains the least known aspect of his output. This alone would justify the
                        publication of Robert N. Essick’s latest book. In addition there are
                        some other very good reasons for supplanting the earlier bibliographical
                        checklists of Blake’s commercial engravings with a complete
                        chalcographical catalogue raisonné of the book illustrations, reasons
                        I hope to suggest in what follows.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n54" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For a list of earlier catalogues of
                            Blake’s reproductive engravings, see Essick’s
                            “Abbreviations and Works Frequently Cited”
                        (xv).</note></p>
          <p>At the very beginning of his introduction Robert Essick reminds his readers
                        that the 
						<q> modern aesthetic, one that Blake helped to initiate, emphasizes
                            original print-making and devalues reproductive prints. Consequently,
                            Blake’s translations on to copperplates of images first executed
                            in other media by other artists are given short shrift and their
                            multifaceted importance to his life is overlooked. It would be foolish
                            to claim for these copy plates artistic equivalence with <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> or the illustrations to The Book of Job,
                            but an understanding of the economic and graphic matrix in which Blake
                            created these visual and verbal masterpieces requires some attention to
                            the lesser productions of his etching needle and graver. (1) </q></p>
          <p>This much one may learn simply by looking at the dates inscribed on the
                        prints catalogued in the present publication, and by comparing them with the
                        chronology of Blake’s dated paintings and the printings of his own
                        illuminated books. Evidently a considerable amount of the work which went
                        into the production of Blake’s poetry and of what is today considered
                        his “original” drawings, paintings, and engravings was
                        financed—and thus made possible—only by Blake’s
                        commissions for commercial “reproductive” engravings after
                        designs by other artists.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">2</hi> In his introductory study, Essick
                            comments on the “crucial financial support for Blake’s
                            first efforts in relief etching” (7) that may have been provided
                            by the fee the engraver had received for the large plate after Hogarth
                            (#XX), first published in 1788.</note></p>
          <p>Both the “original” works and the “reproductive”
                        engravings were often executed with the same tools and at the same working
                        table. This much granted, it is more than reasonable to assume that there
                        are also technical, formal, and iconographical characteristics shared by the
                        products of both of these realms of the poet-artist’s activities. For
                        the very first time, Essick’s catalogue allows for a systematic
                        investigation of such cross-currents. Also, it seems more than likely that,
                        much as Blake’s imagery would have absorbed a considerable number of
                        motifs from his commercial engravings after the designs of others (and the
                        entries in the catalogue under review are full of suggestive comparisons
                        between the book illustrations and Blake’s other works), so his ideas
                        about the generic functioning of printed images would have been shaped in
                        part by his work as a reproductive engraver. For example, the peculiarities
                        in the production and “marketing” of Blake’s
                        illuminated books are, I think, best understood if seen in connection with
                        that of the engraved galleries of pictures rather than that of late
                        eighteenth-century books of poetry.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n56" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Similar observations and closely related
                            matters are also discussed in detail in Joseph Viscomi’s <hi rend="i">Blake and
the Idea of the Book</hi> (Princeton, NJ:
                            Princeton UP, 1993).</note></p>
          <pb id="p28-104" n="104"/>
          <p>In 1987-88, the Huntington Library and Art Gallery presented an exhibition
                        devoted to <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries and
                            Followers.</hi> The works on show had been selected “from the
                        Collection of Robert N. Essick,” arguably the finest and, in any
                        case, for the scholar the most interesting collection of Blake’s
                        works currently in private hands. In the introduction to the exhibition
                        catalogue, the collector and author of <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                            Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (hereafter abbreviated as 
<hi rend="i">CBI</hi>) gave a brief account of “the shape of [his]
                        Blake collection and the principles by which it was assembled.” While
                        still “a graduate student of English literature in the late
                        sixties,” Essick set for himself “the modest goal of acquiring
                        the standard texts and works of criticism on William Blake’s poetry
                        and art as a reference library to assist [his] own early attempts at
                        becoming a scholar.” He unquestionably succeeded, and any subscriber
                        to <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> is certainly well aware of his prolific output of
                        books and articles devoted to the study of Blake and his contemporaries.</p>
          <p>As a collector Essick was soon to find that “no one bitten by the
                        bibliomania bug can limit himself to merely practical needs.” Because
                        availability and cost “are important in any collecting,” he
                        decided “in the early seventies, to acquire books containing
                        Blake’s commercial illustrations—the one area of his
                        activities as an artist and craftsman not already well mined by dealers and
                        collectors. Thus, almost by default,” the author of <hi rend="i">CBI</hi> has been
able to bring together (and only <hi rend="i">inter
                            alia</hi>, to be sure) what now probably is “the largest
                        collection of editions containing Blake’s engravings (the British
                        Library is second).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">4</ref> At the same
                        time, and starting with his groundbreaking study of the iconography of
                        graphic styles in “Blake and the Traditions of Reproductive
                            Engraving,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">5</ref> the
                        scholar-collector began to demonstrate the “research interest”
                        of the materials he collected. Following the example of the late Sir
                        Geoffrey Keynes, Essick developed “the habit of combining scholarship
                        and collecting,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">6</ref> a habit from
                        which all readers of his book on Blake’s printmaking processes, of
                        his catalogue raisonné of Blake’s separate plates, and now of
                            <hi rend="i">CBI</hi> may profit enormously.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Robert N. Essick,
                            “Introduction,” <hi rend="i">William Blake and His
                                Contemporaries and Followers: Selected Works from the Collection of
                                Robert N. Essick</hi>, exh. cat. (San Marino, CA: Henry E.
                            Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1987) 3.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 5.1
                            (1972): 59-103. Similarly important essays that are of relevance in the
                            present context are Essick’s “William Blake, William
                            Hamilton, and the Materials of Graphic Meaning,” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 52
(1985): 833-72, and his “[Blake and the
                            Profession of Printmaking],” in Gert Schiff, et al., <hi rend="i">William
Blake</hi>, exh. cat. (Tokyo, Jap.: Nihon Keizai Shimbun,
                            for the National Museum of Western Art, 1990) 23-32 [in
                            Japanese].</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See Essick 1987 (n. 4) 6.</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker</hi>
(Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1980)
                            and <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi>
                            (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1983).</note></p>
          <p>This study of Blake’s commercial engravings begins with
                        Essick’s account of the relationship between the new catalogue and
                        some earlier surveys of some of the same material, especially the extant two
                        of the three volumes planned as a bibliographical and chalcographical
                        account of <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator.</hi> These he
                        himself coauthored with Roger R. Easson, and the two volumes were published
                        in 1972 and 1979. “The present catalogue is not a revision of Easson
                        and Essick, but it is intended to replace the print catalogue and
                        reproductions in the second volume and treat most of the materials intended
                        for the absent third” (v). The preface then outlines the purpose of
                            <hi rend="i">CBI</hi>:
<q> I have taken as my first responsibility the
                            recording of facts about Blake’s reproductive book
                            illustrations—their sizes, inscriptions, progressive states,
                            locations of preliminary drawings, and the quotation or summary of all
                            documents relating to their production. I have supplemented this basic
                            information with discussions of graphic techniques and styles,
                            Blake’s revisions of preliminary designs, his borrowings of
                            motifs for his own compositions, the relationships of illustrations with
                            their texts, and the role major commissions played in Blake’s
                            life and the shaping of his ideas. (v) </q></p>
          <p>The second part of the book’s preface details “a few
                        guidelines” (vi) to the use of the catalogue entries. It establishes
                        the meaning of certain technical terms in Essick’s text, introduces
                        the conventions employed in the measurements of prints, the recording of
                        signatures, titles, and imprints, and explains the author’s use of
                        cross-references and the coverage of the index.</p>
          <p>Like the catalogue entries themselves, Essick’s introductory study of
                        “Blake’s Reproductive Book Illustrations” is organized
                        chronologically, following Blake’s career as a professional
                        reproductive engraver from the years of his apprenticeship to Basire up to
                        his late book illustrations after Flaxman. This arrangement not only offers
                        a chance to view the plates Blake executed for the book publishers in
                        historical perspective, it also leaves enough room for the author’s
                        interpolation of a systematic discussion of some key issues connected 
<pb id="p28-105" n="105"/>
with the artist’s commercial engravings.
                        Thus, it allows Essick to define clearly what he thinks is the
                        “multifaceted importance” of Blake’s work as a
                        reproductive engraver and to describe “the multiple interactions
                        between art and commerce, graphic execution and literary conception, that
                        shaped Blake’s life and works” (1, 15).</p>
          <p>As a synopsis, or as the <hi rend="i">summa</hi>, of many of his earlier
                        studies of Blake’s printmaking processes, Essick’s
                        introduction by necessity returns to some of the subjects he has previously
                        treated in his publications. However, the new vantage-point supplied by the
                        book illustrations results in a considerable shift of focus. Essick provides
                        an account of the “characteristics of Basire’s shop practices
                        [which] influenced Blake’s later career and aesthetic
                        concepts” (2; see also 6), and he explains “the basic systems
                        for the production of intaglio copperplate book illustrations in the late
                        eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries” (2), stressing the
                        decisive role played by the publisher in these systems (see 2-3). He then
                        briefly glances at the more important of the techniques that were employed
                        in the engraver’s workshop, and next turns to the economics of the
                        trade in general and, in particular, to the fees paid to the copy engravers
                        (see 3-4). One learns of the division of labor between the engraver of the
                        pictorial image, the professional writing engraver and the copperplate
                        printer (see 4-5). The function of working proofs and of published proofs in
                        prepublication states is explained, as is the reason for the succession of
                        the various published states of a copperplate engraving (see 3 and 5).</p>
          <p>At this point, a less restricted discussion of some of the problems of
                        attribution that are involved might have been in place. In discriminating
                        between a first and a second state of any of Blake’s separate plates
                        one takes it for granted—usually without a moment’s
                        hesitation—that it was no one other than the <hi rend="i">peintre-graveur</hi>
himself who was responsible for the
                        “purposeful changes . . . on the copperplate” (5n7) which
                        transformed the earlier into the later state. In this respect, there is no
                        difference whatsoever between the chalcographical examination of the three
                        states of “The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder” (1793-c.
                        1810 or later), of the five states of “Chaucers Canterbury
                        Pilgrims” (1810-c. 1823 or later),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n61" type="note">8</ref> or of the dramatic changes between the first and the eighth
                        state of Rembrandt’s “Christ Presented to the People”
                        (dated 1655 in its seventh state).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n62" type="note">9</ref> But
                        with an engraving that serves as a book illustration, and with the plate
                        usually owned by the publisher, not the engraver (see 4), the situation is
                        slightly different. Can the original engraver be identified with the
                        engraver who reworks a plate for use in a later edition? Or does one have to
                        speculate that at least occasionally a publisher would employ someone else
                        to restore a set of worn copperplates? <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">8</hi>
                            See Essick 1983 (n. 7) 30-37 (#VIII) and 61-89 (#XVI).</note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">9</hi> For a descriptive analysis of this
                            etching (B. 76) and its states see, e.g., Christopher White, 
<hi rend="i">Rembrandt as an Etcher: A Study of the Artist at Work</hi>
                            (London: A. Zwemmer, 1969) i: 87-92.</note></p>
          <p>Essick tells his readers this much: “It seems to have been common
                        practice to hire the original engraver to rework plates whenever possible,
                        but this of course would become increasingly less likely as the time since
                        first execution lengthened” (5). He thus hints at the possibility
                        that some of the later states of Blake’s commercial book
                        illustrations which are recorded in his catalogue may in fact have to be
                        attributed to anonymous journeyman engravers, yet he does not enlarge on the
                        subject. If, however, one thinks of the 1811 and 1818 editions of
                        Richardson’s <hi rend="i">Sir Charles Grandison</hi>, published by C.
                        Cooke and T. Kelly respectively and illustrated with impressions from the
                        plates Blake had engraved for <hi rend="i">The Novelist’s
                            Magazine</hi> (#XI[6-8], 32-33), one might feel tempted to suspect that
                        the engravings Blake did for Harrison &amp; Co. in 1783 have been
                        “substantially reworked” (32) for their third and fourth
                        states by some other engraver(s). The reworked states recorded for
                        Blake’s plates in later issues of Wedgwood’s catalogue of
                        earthenware and porcelain (#L) present another, even more obvious case in
                        point. At the same time, Blake may himself have been employed occasionally
                        to rework plates that had originally been engraved by one of his colleagues,
                        and he may thus have added to his income. Here then is a field that might
                        offer some interesting research opportunities, though since it has not been
                        singled out as particularly promising by Essick, the evidence available from
                        publishers’ account books and other period documents may well be all
                        too scanty to allow for convincing results.</p>
          <p>While the variety of stylistic modes of representation available to the
                        artist-artisan are of course well-characterized in the introduction, Essick
                        also underscores the fact that “reproductive engraving was dependent
                        upon a rigorous division of labour and the subordination of individual
                        expression to uniformity and repeatability” (5). This phenomenon and
                        its effects are described by reference to Blake’s early commissions
                        and his “graphic involvement 
<pb id="p28-106" n="106"/>
with
                        Stothard” (6) and with the William Walker circle of engravers working
                        after Stothard’s designs in the 1780s and 1790s. The problems
                        encountered when attempting to distinguish the graphic vocabulary and syntax
                        used by James Heath in one of his plates after Stothard from that employed
                        by Blake in a reproduction of another of the same artist’s designs
                        signify “the inevitable interweaving of economic exigencies and
                        aesthetic norms that shaped eighteenth-century reproductive graphics”
                        (6). At the same time, such pertinent observations help the reader to
                        understand why the attribution of an unsigned book illustration to Blake (or
                        any other of his colleagues) can seldom be based entirely on stylistic
                            considerations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See Essick’s discussion of this
                            matter in the book’s two appendices (especially 115-17 [#C] and
                            121).</note></p>
          <p>The introductory study to the catalogue also pays considerable attention to
                        the examination of some representative working relations between Blake and
                        one of his publishers, with an author of some of the texts he engraved for,
                        and with two of his fellow artists whose designs he translated onto
                        copperplates. In fairly detailed discussions, one learns of Blake’s
                        business relationships with Joseph Johnson and with Henry Fuseli as one of
                        Johnson’s favorite illustrators (see 7-9),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n64" type="note">11</ref> with William Hayley (see 9-11), and with John
                        Flaxman (see 11-12). Essick’s keen and experienced eyes enable him to
                        observe how, in Blake’s plates for Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original
Stories</hi>, the “graphic syntax . . . begins
                        to emerge above the threshold of the visual apprehension and become
                        self-referential. As we view such images, we are given both the illusion of
                        three-dimensional objects in space and an awareness of the medium in which
                        that illusion is created.” This in turn allows for a demonstration of
                        “how experiments in original graphics influenced reproductive
                        styles” (8)—and <hi rend="i">vice versa.</hi> The introduction
                        offers many similarly stimulating comments, for example on “the
                        conceptual implications of stippled lines” (12) as used in
                        Blake’s engravings after Flaxman’s Hesiod compositions, before
                        Essick summarizes the influence of Blake’s career as a copy engraver
                        on the formation of those of the artist’s ideas that were given
                        expression in his “more private and more important endeavours”
                        (13). <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Following a suggestion first made
                            by the late Ruthven Todd, Essick had previously discussed the case of
                            Blake’s engravings after Fuseli—and what there appears to
                            be “an unusual amount of responsibility for the completion of the
                            design, not merely its translation to copper” (7)—in
                            Essick 1980 (n. 7) 51-52. While I am still not entirely convinced of
                            this hypothesis (especially because Fuseli is known to have been hard
                            for any other reproductive engraver to satisfy), I wish to stress that
                                <hi rend="i">CBI</hi> is characterized by an exemplary scholarly
                            open-mindedness that invites, rather than suffocates, such differences
                            of opinion. Essick himself points out alternatives to his preferred
                            reading of the evidence, and in a proviso he alerts his readers to the
                            possibility that here as elsewhere Blake may have “worked from a
                            far more detailed preliminary drawing, of the type conventionally
                            supplied by an artist to a copy engraver” (#XVIII,
                        41).</note></p>
          <p>At the end of his introductory study Essick turns to the research
                        opportunities offered by the material described in his catalogue. Discussing
                        “the conventions of text-design relationships” of
                        Blake’s times, and drawing on examples from Blake’s engravings
                        after Stothard, Fuseli, and his own inventions, Essick finds that ultimately
                        what Blake learned “from his contemporaries about illustrative
                        strategies by engraving their work, and the way in which he both
                        incorporates and diverges from their practices, are more important than his
                        occasional borrowings of specific motifs from their designs”
                            (15).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">12</ref>
While he describes many of
                        these “occasional borrowings” in the catalogue entries, Essick
                        ends this study with a brief discussion of the possibility that “the
                        texts for which Blake engraved plates [might] have been read by him and
                        [thus might have] influenced his ideas” (15). <note id="n65"><hi rend="s">12</hi>
For a more detailed discussion of these questions
                            see Essick’s recent study of “Visual/Verbal Relationships
                            in Book Illustration,” <hi rend="i">British Art 1740-1820: Essays
                                in Honor of Robert R. Wark</hi>, ed. Guilland Sutherland (San
                            Marino, CA: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1992)
                            169-204.</note></p>
          <p>Seen as a whole, the introduction successfully documents the
                        “multifaceted” interdependence of “original” art
                        and “reproductive” engraving in Blake’s career; and, at
                        the very same time, it effectively clears away the ignorance of those who
                        still do not want to see to what an extent the profession of the commercial
                        reproductive engraver actually “established Blake’s social
                        position for the majority of his contemporaries, placing him in the class of
                        urban artisans” (1), a social affiliation that is of major importance
                        for a proper understanding of Blake’s peculiar stance in a variety of
                        discourse-systems of his times. With the author, one hopes that in the
                        interpretation of Blake’s works, such insights regarding the manifold
                        impact Blake’s “low” art had on the “grand
                        style” of his “high” art productions will now be more
                        generally put into action. <hi rend="i">CBI</hi> supplies all the
                        information necessary in order to do so.</p>
          <p>In the catalogue itself (19-114), each entry begins with a short-title
                        reference to the book in which Blake’s commercial engravings can be
                        found and, wherever that is called for, to its various printings and
                        editions. A typical entry reports in an introductory 
<pb id="p28-107" n="107"/>
note
the total number of illustrations included in the
                        respective book, Blake’s own contributions and, if necessary, the
                        history of their attribution to the poet-artist (see, e.g., #XXIII), and the
                        designer(s) of the plates engraved by Blake; in addition, it supplies
                        information regarding preliminary sketches and preparatory drawings for the
                        engravings whenever the current whereabouts of these are known, working
                        proofs and proofs before (some or all) letters, documents relating to the
                        commission, the author of the text, its publisher(s), and reviews that make
                        mention of the plates discussed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">13</ref> This
                        is followed by the catalogue proper of the book’s prints with
                        documentation of the measurements, all the inscriptions, the sequence of the
                        published states, and then a generally short annotation commenting on
                        iconography, related drawings, and the possible significance of motifs that
                        Blake may have borrowed for his “original” inventions. A list
                        of the earlier secondary literature on Blake’s engravings in the book
                        catalogued marks the end of each main entry. <note id="n66"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Where
appropriate, and arguing from the perspective offered
                            by only one of the books illustrated, Essick has inserted in the entries
                            a few remarks that also apply to more general issues. E.g., his effort
                            to prevent readers from over-interpreting the “differences
                            between Blake’s plates and their prototypes” is strongly
                            in evidence if the next sentence emphasizes that some of “the
                            plates by other engravers show an equal range of variation from their
                            sources” (62).</note></p>
          <p>In order to check the accuracy of Essick’s measurements, of his
                        transcriptions of signatures, titles, and imprints, and of the descriptive
                        commentaries on the images themselves, I reexamined impressions from 165 of
                        the 271 engraved plates that are detailed under the 53 main entries in the
                        catalogue. Though I was trying hard to find some substantial errors in
                        Essick’s descriptions of the prints, the results of the endeavor
                        cannot be summarized in any other way than by stating that this catalogue
                        raisonné deserves the highest possible praise for its reliability.
                        Essick’s descriptive prose is precise—for example, he
                        discriminates between a “proof before letters” and a
                        “proof before signatures” (#XVI, 38)—unimpassioned, and
                        admirably economical. Though there is always some general reference to the
                        graphic mode employed by the artist-artisan in a given engraving (such as
                        “outline” or “stipple”), Essick describes the
                        particulars of the hatching patterns, of burnishing and the like only where
                        there is the need to distinguish a second or third state from the first
                        published version that is illustrated. This need, however, exists in many
                        more cases than may have been expected, largely because the author has
                        discovered numerous previously unrecorded states of Blake’s plates.
                        For example, even where in 1979 Easson and Essick had already recorded no
                        less than three states for Blake’s large plate after Hogarth’s
                        “Beggar’s Opera” painting, the 1991 publication more
                        than doubles this with a list of no fewer than seven states (see #XX, 43);
                        and where one may have expected two states at most for the two 1803
                        printings of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Life, and Posthumous Writings,
                            of William Cowper</hi>, Essick confronts his readers with no less than
                        four published states of Blake’s “Weather-House”
                        engraving (#XLIV[4], 88-89).</p>
          <p>In 1979 Easson and Essick still included some of the plates in
                        Bryant’s <hi rend="i">New System</hi>, in Ayloffe’s <hi rend="i">Ancient
Monuments</hi>, and in Gough’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments</hi> in the main sequence of their
catalogue of
                        the commercial book illustrations attributed to Blake as the engraver. In
                        the present publication Essick has decided in favor of a more cautious
                        approach to “Blake’s Apprentice Engravings.” Lacking a
                        “solid basis for attribution” (117), these plates have now
                        been relegated in their entirety to the first of Essick’s appendices
                        (see 115-20). This may not be pleasing, and yet it will be hard to
                        contradict the author’s statement that “for published
                        engravings, we can hardly expect the work of an apprentice to diverge in any
                        clear way from the house style taught by his master” (115).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">14</ref> In a second appendix (see 121-27)
                        Essick presents a list of 37 “False and Conjectural
                        Attributions.” Whereas some of the plates that during the 1770s came
                        from the workshop of James Basire may or may not have been engraved by Blake
                        under the supervision of his master, most of the engravings referred to in
                        Appendix ii were clearly executed by someone other than the poet-artist. A
                        few of these more than “doubtful” ascriptions date back to the
                        nineteenth century, but Essick’s list ought to prevent dealers and
                        curators from perpetuating them “innocently” (121) in the
                        future. <note id="n67"><hi rend="s">14</hi> The case of Blake’s
                            apprentice engravings is, in this respect, similar to the problems of
                            attribution presented by many eighteenth- and nineteenth-century
                            “academies,” drawings from the antique or from life that
                            were executed at the Royal Academy Schools. The attribution of such
                            academical studies to William Blake, his brother, or any other pupil at
                            the Academy Schools should, I think, be treated with the same exemplary
                            reservation that Essick suggests for the attribution of engravings from
                            the Basire workshop to Blake or any of his fellow
                        apprentices.</note></p>
          <p>Though mostly consisting of proper names, the index (see 129-38) seems to be
                        perfectly sufficient for all reference purposes. It is particularly welcome
                        (and entirely in keeping with the author’s 
<pb id="p28-108" n="108"/>
                        approach to his material) that besides the names of the artists and authors
                        among Blake’s contemporaries, and those of the “owners, past
                        and present, of drawings and pre-publication proofs” (vi), the index
                        includes the names of the publishers of the books illustrated. It thus
                        allows readers to search the catalogue for references to Blake’s
                        business connections with, say, the firm of Harrison &amp; Co. There are
                        few misprints in this book, and scarcely any of them merit ceremonious
                        correction; those I have spotted (such as the typos in the transcription of
                        a German title on page 50) in no way impair the intelligibility of the text
                        (see the appendix, below).</p>
          <p>The author and his publisher are also to be congratulated on the near-300
                        reproductions which illustrate all the engravings discussed as well as some
                        of the preliminary drawings from which Blake worked. Not only do these
                        “Figures” make it easy to use the book as a visual
                        encyclopaedia of Blake’s commercial book illustrations—and to
                        follow some of the lines for future investigations that are suggested by
                        Essick’s catalogue and study—; they are also of the highest
                        possible quality and as such successfully “replace” (v) the
                        sadly inadequate reproductions in volume 2 of <hi rend="i">William Blake:
                            Book Illustrator.</hi> To give an idea just how good the reproductions
                        are, it seems sufficient to refer to the author’s own caveat
                        concerning a “very small signature” which he thought would
                        “probably not [be] visible in the reproduction” (#XIX[1], 42).
                        Turning to figure 61, one finds that it actually is visible, regardless of
                        Essick’s concern.</p>
          <p>No doubt, as a work of reference this catalogue raisonné will
                        unquestionably (and for a long time to come) function as the definite and
                        standard source of information on Blake’s reproductive book
                        engravings. If this is high praise, it still is not enough for the book
                        under review. Though definitive in the material descriptions of
                        Blake’s copy engravings, Essick has succeeded not in closing down his
                        subject, but in efficiently opening up a new field of investigation. While
                        answering almost any question of interest to the collector, <hi rend="i">CBI</hi> also
intriguingly challenges Blake scholarship with a new set
                        of questions that deserve to be examined in greater detail. For all these
                        reasons, the acquisition of this volume can only be highly recommended.
                        Serious students as well as all collectors of Blake’s works will want
                        to have a copy ready at hand, if not on their own shelves then at least on
                        those of their preferred research library.</p>
          <p>In trying to think of any negative aspect of the publication of <hi rend="i">CBI</hi>, only one
thing comes to mind. Besides the collectors and
                        scholars that are interested in a fuller understanding of Blake’s
                        work, there are also the dealers and auctioneers whose interest in Blake is
                        likely to be informed primarily by economic considerations. With its easily
                        accessible information on all the various states of Blake’s
                        reproductive engravings and with its references to particularly scarce
                        printings of some of these plates, Essick’s catalogue will probably
                        cause a further increase in the prices asked for the books illustrated with
                        the artist-poet’s commercial engravings. Yet this is in the nature of
                        the production of any catalogue raisonné and none of the
                        author’s fault. Therefore, even its possibly disastrous effect on the
                        market for Blake’s lesser productions as a graphic artist can in no
                        way detract from the gratitude we owe the author for sharing his intimate
                        knowledge of the subject. In any case, there can be little doubt about the
                        justice of Essick’s own claim that the material presented in <hi rend="i">CBI</hi>,
“along with the introductory survey of
                        Blake’s career as a commercial book engraver and research
                        opportunities in the field, gives this volume a larger interpretive and
                        critical dimension than that offered by most print catalogues”
                        (v-vi).</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Appendix</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Robert Essick has himself gathered some “substantive additions or
                            corrections” to <hi rend="i">Blake’s Commercial Book
                                Illustrations</hi> in the appendices published with his 1990 and
                            1991 “Marketplace” reports.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n68" type="note">15</ref> The following list—in addition to a couple of
                            mostly negligible corrections of the few typographical
                            errors—offers a number of supplementary observations pertaining
                            to individual entries in the catalogue; however, none of these 
<hi rend="i">addenda et corrigenda</hi> claim to be of a
                            “substantive” nature. <note id="n68"><hi rend="s">15</hi>
                                See the “Appendix: New Information on Blake’s
                                Engravings” in Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the
                                Marketplace,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 24 (1990-91): 141; and
                                25 (1991-92): 164-67.</note></p>
            <p>pp. 4 and 137: for “William Sharpe” read “William
                            Sharp”; the spelling of the engraver’s name is not the
                            same as that of the publisher, John Sharpe.</p>
            <p>p. 13n28: for “Joachim Moller” read “Joachim
                            Möller” (which, in most library catalogues, will be
                            translated as “Moeller”).</p>
            <p>p. 14n29: I entirely agree with Essick’s rebuke to
                            Hodnett’s criticisms concerning Fuseli’s illustrations for
                            Chalmers’s 1805 edition of <hi rend="i">The Plays of
                                Shakspeare</hi>; however, readers who are interested in
                            Hodnett’s arguments will want to examine “The Fuseli
                            Shakespeare (1805),” a chapter in Edward Hodnett, <hi rend="i">Image and Text:
Studies in the Illustration</hi>
	<pb id="p28-109" n="109"/>
	<hi rend="i">of English Literature</hi> (London: Scolar P, 1982) 69-76,
                            rather than the potted version contained in the same author’s <hi rend="i">Five
Centuries of English Book Illustration</hi> that is
                            cited by Essick.</p>
            <p>p. 25: Essick’s catalogue entries discuss many of Blake’s
                            possible borrowings of specific motifs from the book illustrations he
                            was commissioned to engrave. Looking at #V(3) one feels tempted to
                            suggest an additional, non-iconographic connection between
                            Blake’s work as a professional “copy” engraver and
                            the compositional treatment of his own, “original”
                            designs. Here, in Conrad Martin [?] Metz’s design for “The
                            Fugitive Shechemites” (Fig. 14) the relation between the actual
                            two-dimensional picture plane and the illusion of pictorial space is, I
                            think, reminiscent of the same relation in a considerable number of
                            Blake’s compositions that use the vertical axis for sequencing
                            both narrative time and pictorial space (see, e.g., “The Descent
                            of Man into the Vale of Death,” the related plate among the 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations, or the “Epitome for James
                            Hervey’s <hi rend="i">Meditations among the
                            Tombs</hi>”).</p>
            <p>p. 31: #XI(4), the plate after Stothard for <hi rend="i">David
                                Simple</hi>, may have been the eidetic image at the back of
                            Blake’s mind when he was drawing the figure of the nurse for
                            plate 2 of “A Cradle Song” in <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi></p>
            <p>p. 42: commenting on #XIX(2), the plate after Rubens’s
                            “Democritus,” Essick suggests that “Blake may have
                            based his plate on the engraving of the portrait by Lucas
                            Vorsterman”; there is nothing to be said against such a
                            possibility, and yet it seems more likely to me that (in Blake’s
                            case just as elsewhere) the full-page illustrations in the earlier
                            German and French editions of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>
                            served as models for the British engravers.</p>
            <p>p. 48: Essick’s measurements for #XXI(11) read “8.7
                            × 10.6 cm.”; this appears to be a typo for “8.7
                            × 16.6 cm.”</p>
            <p>p. 50: capitalize “Zeichnungen,” and read
                            “gestochen” for “gestocken” in the German
                            title of Chodowiecki’s illustrations to Salzmann’s 
<hi rend="i">Elementarbuch.</hi></p>
            <p>p. 54: capitalize “<hi rend="i">Years</hi>” in the citation
                            of the title inscription for #XXIII(17); this minor change is certainly
                            open to debate, but compare “<hi rend="i">Want</hi>” in
                            the title quoted for #XXIII(20).</p>
            <p>p. 60: in the reference to Windle’s 1988 Wollstonecraft
                            bibliography, read “no. 17” for “no. 3” (the
                            latter is Windle’s entry for <hi rend="i">Original
                            Stories</hi>).</p>
            <p>p. 66: in the signatures of the two plates that were engraved by Blake
                            and that are here catalogued as #XXX(1-2), a “Xaverius Della
                            Rosa” is credited as the artist who “evidently made [the]
                            drawings of [the] statues” in Verona. Though Essick could
                            “find no information” about this draughtsman, the latter
                            is probably to be identified with the Veronese painter and etcher
                            Saverio Dalla Rosa (1745-1821). Dalla Rosa is not a complete unknown in
                            the history of Italian eighteenth-century art and art theory, and a
                            brief biographical account is easily accessible in volume 28 of the 
<hi rend="i">Allgemeines Lexikon der bildenden Künstler von der
                                Antike bis zur Gegenwart</hi> (ed. Ulrich Thieme and Felix
                            Becker).</p>
            <p>p. 69: for the reference to “(Bentley 1969, p. 12)” read
                            “(. . . , p. 56 n. 1).”</p>
            <p>p. 75: in his entry for Blake’s engraved portrait of “The
                            Late Mr. Wright of Derby,” Essick states that he has “not
                            been able to trace the drawing, painting, or print on which
                            Blake’s plate is based.” It seems very likely, though,
                            that Blake’s model was—a copy of or the original drawing
                            for?—a drypoint etching, presumably executed by the painter
                            himself. This scarce print, a copy of which was in the collection of
                            George Cumberland, is included in Tim Clayton’s “Catalogue
                            of the Engraved Works of Joseph Wright of Derby.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">16</hi> See Judy Egerton, et al., <hi rend="i">Wright of Derby</hi>, exh. cat.
(London: Tate Gallery
                                Publications, 1990) 254 (#P38). The print is reproduced and
                                Blake’s copy engraving is mentioned by Clayton.</note></p>
            <p>p. 83: in the title quoted for #XLII (as well as in the index [137]) read
                            “George Steevens” for “George Stevens.” The
                            measurements for #XLII(1) in <hi rend="i">CBI</hi> read “16.5
                            × 25.5 cm.” On my ruler, however, I read “16.5 (or
                            16.6) × 23.5 cm.,” a discrepancy that is too large to be
                            accounted for by paper shrinkage and similar effects.</p>
            <p>p. 84: similarly, the measurements cited by Essick for #XLII(2) read
                            “10 × 7.9 cm.,” whereas I found the actual height
                            of the image in this plate to be 10.5 cm.</p>
            <p>p. 85: the publishers’ names in the imprint for #XLIII(4) have
                            been transcribed as “Cadell &amp; Davies’ Strand,”
                            and, in fact, this is what the letters look like at first sight.
                            However, if one compares the “s” in “Davies”
                            in this engraving with the same letter in the same position in
                            #XLIII(1-3 and 6) or with Blake’s scratched inscriptions in other
                            plates of the Felpham period such as the “Weather-House”
                            tailpiece for Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>
                            (#XLIV[4]), it becomes clear, I think, that the small vertical stroke at
                            the end of “Davies” in the fourth plate Blake executed for
                            the 1803 edition of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>
                            was, at the very least, not intended to be read as an apostrophe, but
                            simply to be part of the lower case letter “s.” If one
                            insists on reading “Davies’” in the imprint for
                            #XLIII(4), then 
<pb id="p28-110" n="110"/>
one may as well read
                            “Caclell” for “Cadell” in #XXXIX(3).</p>
            <p>p. 87: for “D. Heins, . . . active . . . <hi rend="i">c.</hi>
                            1725-56” read “Dirck [John Theodore] Heins, Sr.
                                (1697-1756).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">17</hi> See Ellis Waterhouse, <hi rend="i">The Dictionary of British 18th Century
Painters in Oils and
                                    Crayons</hi> (Woodbridge, Suff.: Antique Collectors’
                                Club, 1981) 167.</note></p>
            <p>p. 88: following “. . . <hi rend="i">Church Yard</hi>,”
                            insert a period at the end of the imprint line that is quoted for
                            #XLIV(4).</p>
            <p>p. 89: Essick refers to “an untraced drawing by Francis Stone
                            (dates unknown)” as the model for #XLIV(5). The designer was
                            probably Francis Stone (1775-1834), an architect, draughtsman and
                            lithographer active in Norwich.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n71" type="note">18</ref>
                            The width of the engraving after Flaxman recorded as #XLIV(6) is,
                            including the vertical shading lines, nearer to 15.0 cm. than to
                            Essick’s “14.5 cm.” <note id="n71"><hi rend="s">18</hi> See Howard Colvin,
<hi rend="i">A Biographical
                                    Dictionary of British Architects 1600-1840</hi> (London: John
                                Murray, 1978) 785.</note></p>
            <p>p. 104: for “vials,” read “Justice’s vial,
                            pl. 13” in the entry for #LI(16).</p>
            <p>p. 105: from Essick’s preface readers learn that measurements are
                            supplied according to art historical conventions, i.e., “height
                            followed by width,” and “are of the pictorial image
                            exclusive of frames, borders, and inscriptions unless noted
                            otherwise” (vi). In theory this method of reference may seem both
                            simple and unequivocal enough; in practice, at least occasionally, even
                            measurements involve an act of interpretation and may therefore cause
                            some vexation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">19</ref> Here is an
                            appropriate example. The measurements Essick supplies for #LI(20),
                            “15.3 × 23.9 cm.,” are exactly the same as my own,
                            if, that is, one measures the framing lines of the pictorial image on
                            the right and at the top. If, however, one measures the same engraving
                            on the left and at the bottom framing line, one ends up with only
                            “15.1 × 23.4 cm.” Similar discrepancies between
                            left and right as well as top and bottom measurements can be observed in
                            many other plates (see, e.g., #LI[27 or 30]), and ideally the author
                            would have told his readers precisely <hi rend="i">where</hi> the height
                            and width of the printed images were measured. And yet this may well be
                            asking too much. Essick, no doubt, is well aware of such possible
                            discrepancies. However, with engravings that have been bound in a book
                            it is often difficult to measure at the inner margin (which, in
                            approximately 50% of all cases) may happen to be the margin that the
                            rule would call for. Therefore, users of <hi rend="i">CBI</hi> (as in
                            the case of any other print catalogue I have used extensively) will have
                            to live with a few of these occasionally irritating measurements. I
                            cannot possibly end this note, however, without emphasizing that I was
                            as much impressed by the accuracy of the measurements cited in 
<hi rend="i">CBI</hi> as by all the other data supplied for each print.
                            As a reviewer I assumed an obligation to search <hi rend="i">CBI</hi>
                            for factual mistakes of this kind; after having measured for myself more
                            than 60% of the 271 prints described in the new catalogue, I can only
                            say that I was thoroughly frustrated in this attempt. 
<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">19</hi> This is particularly true, and very obviously
                                so, where an oval engraving or an irregularly shaped pictorial image
                                has to be measured.</note></p>
            <p>p. 123: at the end of the entry for #11 in the book’s second
                            appendix read “James Neagle” instead of “John
                            Neagle.” I return to this correction, previously noted in
                            Essick’s own “New Information on Blake’s
                                Engravings,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73"
type="note">20</ref> merely in
                            order to point out that the decisive evidence for the correct version of
                            Neagle’s Christian name comes neither from the <hi rend="i">DNB</hi> nor any
other standard reference work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">21</ref>
Rather, such evidence is provided by the
                            signatures on quite a few of the plates executed by this engraver. Many
                            of Neagle’s engravings have been signed with only the
                            artist’s second name, or as engraved by “J.
                            Neagle.” However, there are also quite a few of his plates with a
                                “Ja<hi rend="s">s</hi>. Neagle” inscription, and I
                            know of at least one plate that is signed by “James
                            Neagle,” whereas I have never seen a single plate the execution
                            of which has been attributed by the artist himself or by some writing
                            engraver to a “John Neagle.” <note id="n73"><hi rend="s">20</hi> See 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 25 (1991-92): 167.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">21</hi> However, and thinking of printed
                                references, one may note that the engraver’s name is also
                                cited as “James Neagle” in the <hi rend="i">Memoirs
                                    and Recollections of the Late Abraham Raimbach, Esq.,
                                    Engraver</hi>, ed. M. T. S. Raimbach (London: Frederick Shoberl,
                                1843) 36n57.</note></p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>