<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.3.paulson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Morris Eaves, The Counter-Arts Conspiracy: Art and Industry in the Age of
Blake</title>
        <author n="Paulson">Ronald Paulson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1994/95</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994/95</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Alma Bennett</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mark Lussier</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>June Sturrock</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994/95"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <pb id="p28-101" n="101"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">The Counter-Arts Conspiracy: Art and
                                Industry in the Age of Blake.</hi> Ithaca and London: Cornell
                            University Press, 1992. xxix + 286 pp., illus., bibliography.
                            $37.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Ronald <name>Paulson</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In one sense Morris Eaves’s book fills in the context of earlier art
                        histories for Blake’s narrative of art history in his <hi rend="i">Public
Address</hi> and <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue.</hi> This
                        is to focus on chapters 3 and 4. But in a larger sense the context 
<hi rend="i">is</hi> the book. This is a fascinating study in
                        historiography—a narrative of “narratives,”
                        “histories,” and “stories” of the English School
                        of painting and engraving, with heroes and villains in its artists and
                        patrons. Eaves shows the interdependence of the narratives of art and of
                        British commerce and religion. He studies the alternative narratives their
                        variants and common structures, categorizing them as progressive based on
                        improvement of technical and aesthetic education (the Vasari canon, the
                        Carracci eclecticism, the de Piles <hi rend="i">balance de la
                        peinture</hi>), cyclic and regressive based on recovery and return, and
                        static based on native ability (due possibly to the English climate).
                        Narrative is a more flexible term than discourse, more various than
                        deterministic, suggesting more of Propp than Foucault. It permits Eaves to
                        separate truth from myth, showing how a myth reflected in the interested
                        party who invented and promulgated it, and often how narrative—also
                        another word for theory—fitted with practice.</p>
          <p>It is a relief to read that “the fit between the simplicities of
                        official theory and the complexities of practice had become ill indeed; the
                        margins were threatening to outgrow the text.” Eaves’s book
                        covers most of the same ground as Barrell’s <hi rend="i">Political
                            Theory of Painting</hi> but offers a much broader, less claustrophobic
                        perspective. Barrell’s book explored one master discourse (or theory)
                        which projected one narrative, the one sanctified by Reynolds in which
                        English art grows from the imitation of continental art (but in practice
                        essentially the collecting of it), reaches its peak in the patronage of
                        Charles I, declines in the iconoclasm of his Puritan opponents, and except
                        for the momentary flowering of Wren and Thornhill’s St. Paul’s
                        (in Prince Hoare’s narrative), only recovers when Reynolds reunites
                        the English School once again with the continental and founds an academy on
                        the French model.</p>
          <p>The great printseller John Boydell is the central figure of Eaves’s
                        own narrative. He is the symbolic middleman, initiator of the Shakespeare
                        Gallery project which fulfilled the earlier narratives of blocking and
                        opportunity, bringing together painter and engraver with the great English
                        literary subject, Shakespeare. Boydell’s personal myth of the
                        shopkeeper Maecenas (in its most elaborate form laid out by John Pye II) is
                        shown being created, developed, discredited, and utilized by artists from
                        James Barry to Prince Hoare and John Landseer. Eaves focuses on the
                        historiographical moment when Boydell, the art of reproductive engraving,
                        and the international dissemination of English prints triumphantly merged,
                        just before the French Revolution changed all the rules. Eaves—who
                        ends with an exceptionally lucid chapter on the technical problems of
                        engraving in the period—<corr type="emend">demonstrates</corr> the centrality of the
history of
                        engraving in the Boydell era, when engraving was “coupled with the
                        commercial success of English painting”; it served the Reynolds ethos
                        of academic copying and expanded the audience of art (in theory at least)
                        beyond imagining, while at the same time—as Landseer and Blake were
                        to show—its distinctions between original and copy undermined the
                        role of the artist.</p>
          <p>The counter-narrative, suppressed but implicit in Boydell’s project,
                        surfaces in Hazlitt (the villain of Barrell’s academic narrative)
                        and, above all, in Allan Cunningham, whose <hi rend="i">Lives of the most
                            Eminent British Painters</hi> (1829-33) has been unfairly shunted aside
                        by art historians as a mere popularization. Indeed, their writings are a
                        culmination of that large body of relatively journalistic (as opposed to
                        “philosophical”) material that from the 1730s onward had
                        projected an opposing tradition. In Cunningham’s story of the
                        Reformation, far from a disaster, begins the process of liberating English
                        artists from foreign influence and domination (Roman Catholicism, and
                        Holbein, Rubens, and Van Dyck), making way for a Protestant and therefore
                        English artist, Hogarth. This was, of course, Hogarth’s own
                        narrative, pointing the way to the primitivistic Signpainters’
                        Exhibition, which consisted of examples of that form of aboriginal English
                        painting; but more than Cunningham seems aware he developed and
                        demonstrated, in his engraved works, the principles of Protestant iconoclasm
                        itself. Cunningham picked up through the Hogarth narrative, at its most
                        agitated in the academy dispute of the 1750s, when Hogarth opposed the
                        primary principle of Reynolds and his followers who argued for “the
                        continuity of English with continental art.”</p>
          <pb id="p28-102" n="102"/>
          <p>Cunningham’s words on Hogarth show how antithetical this narrative is
                        to the academic: (1) Hogarth was antiacademic and original: “That his
                        works are <hi rend="i">unlike those of other men</hi>, is his merit, not his
                        fault. He belonged to <hi rend="i">no school of art</hi>; he was the produce
                        of <hi rend="i">no academy</hi>; no man living or dead had any share in
                        forming his mind, or in rendering his hand skilful.” (2) And he was
                        native English: “He was the spontaneous offspring of <hi rend="i">the
                            graphic spirit of his country</hi>, as native to the heart of England as
                            <hi rend="i">independence</hi> is, and he may be fairly called, in 
<hi rend="i">his own way</hi>, the <hi rend="i">first-born</hi> of her
                        spirit” (emphasis added). Although the perennial “in his own
                        way” is retained, to delimit his genius, Hogarth is given the
                        temporal priority reserved in the academic discourse for Reynolds. It is, of
                        course, another myth, as prejudiced as the Reynolds-Royal Academy one, but
                        it is good to see Cunningham, if not Hogarth himself, replaced in the
                        history from which theorists from Reynolds to Barrell have elided him.</p>
          <p>Boydell was near enough in time to recognize this, and his Shakespeare
                        Gallery was signalized—as was his term as lord mayor—by the
                        purchase of the copperplates and publication of the folios of
                        Hogarth’s engraved works. For Hogarth was <hi rend="i">his</hi>
                        model, as the first English painter to show how painting can be
                        commercialized, how the international market can be broached, how more and
                        less expensive versions of a print can be produced, and how to exploit all
                        the intricacies of subscription and every other kind of publication Boydell
                        later developed. Hogarth even anticipated aspects of the business of
                        popularizing “high art” missed by Boydell but exploited by
                        Wedgewood, such as the talent for “commercializing history” by
                        utilizing events, heroes, and villains. Though he did not fit into
                        Barry’s academic discourse, he also prefigured Barry’s Society
                        of Arts paintings with his St. Bartholomew’s Hospital paintings.</p>
          <p>After the marshalling of these conflicting narratives, in chapter 3 Eaves
                        turns to the other “original,” William Blake. The main point
                        is clear enough—that Blake traced the history of engraving all the
                        way back to Egypt and Moses and wrote a history in which the Bible and the
                        technology of engraving intersect in interesting ways that are now, in the
                        light of the various more conventional narratives we have seen, much more
                        easily understood. It is less easy to turn from exposition of the discursive
                        prose of Hazlitt and Cunningham to the density of Blakean myth and poetry to
                        its exegesis. We lose (at least in chapter 3, if not 4) the broad
                        perspective we enjoyed with the other narratives. We are reading 
<hi rend="i">inside</hi> this narrative and our author 
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/> 
                        is a
                        Blakean who takes us from rational analysis to special pleading; from public
                        argument, in a shared discourse, to personal imagery based on these
                        arguments <hi rend="i">and</hi> a private system, which carries over into
                        the “discursive” <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi> and <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue.</hi> Characteristically, Blake
                        introduces a Christian narrative: his vocabulary (Florentine vs. Venetian,
                        original-imitation, art-counter-arts, Christian-Neoclassical, artist-priest,
                        white-black, Jesus-Moses) is all based on the old New Testament-Old
                        Testament contrast of spirit and law. As Eaves puts it plainly,
                        Blake’s argument “soars high above the average level of the
                        most acute critiques of English-school discourse” (183).</p>
          <p>With a few exceptions in the Blake chapters, Eaves’s book treats his
                        subject with brilliant commonsense, and it will be a pity if his book does
                        not enjoy the same level of critical attention accorded recent
                        art-historical studies of the period which have offered formulas, easily
                        expanded by eager graduate students, into which such complex pictures as
                        Eaves’s will not easily fit. Eaves’s study, in all its gaudy
                        variety, is of greater utility and imagination, as well as enjoyment in the
                        reading.</p>
          <p>Typographically the book offers further pleasures. The illustrations are
                        generous and well-placed. The text which accompanies them sometimes runs on
                        for pages at a time parallel with the regular text. The effect is somewhere
                        between Derrida’s <hi rend="i">Glas</hi> and a <hi rend="i">Time-Life</hi> art book.
The lessons, both theoretical and practical,
                        in the history of print technology and engraving techniques are alone worth
                        the price of admission.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>