<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.3.behrendt</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Possible Corollary Source for The Gates of Paradise 10</title>
        <author n="Behrendt">Stephen C. Behrendt</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1994/95</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994/95</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Alma Bennett</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mark Lussier</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>June Sturrock</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994/95"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-3-0006">
        <pb id="p28-92" n="92"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Possible Corollary Source for <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                                Paradise</hi> 10</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Stephen C. <name>Behrendt</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In the course of examining Gerda S. Norvig’s new study, <hi rend="i">Dark Figures in the
Desired Country: Blake’s Illustrations to
                            The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, I was struck by the author’s
                        discussion of plate 10 of Blake’s 1793 <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                            Paradise</hi> (“Help! Help!”), which discussion echoes
                        David V. Erdman’s earlier argument that a strong connection exists
                        between this plate and the preceding one (“I Want! I Want!”),
                        and a well-known caricature print by James Gillray from the same year, 
<hi rend="i">The Slough of Despond.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">1</ref>
Norvig argues that Gillray deliberately invoked the context of
                            <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, both in his explicit
                        citation of Bunyan’s title (in the title he inscribed at the bottom
                        of the print) and in the verbal and iconographic details he included, and
                        that Blake’s subsequent engravings are therefore indebted both to
                        Gillray and to Bunyan. While both the visual correspondences in
                        Blake’s two engravings (like the similar shapes of the land masses in
                        the distance in the Gillray and “Help! Help!”) and the verbal
                        connections between their captions and Gillray’s print (especially
                        the recurrence of the phrase, “Help! Help!”) certainly support
                        the suggestion that Blake had Gillray’s print in mind, another visual
                        precedent may well be involved here as well. <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Gerda
S. Norvig, <hi rend="i">Dark Figures in the Desired
                                Country: Blake’s Illustrations to The Pilgrim’s
                                Progress</hi> (Berkeley: U of California P, 1993) 61-69. See also
                            David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 3rd
                            ed. (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1977) 203-04 and Erdman, ‘William
                            Blake’s Debt to James Gillray,” <hi rend="i">Art
                                Quarterly</hi> 12 (1949): 165-70.</note></p>
          <p>In 1778 the American painter John Singleton Copley’s remarkable
                        painting, <hi rend="i">Watson and the Shark</hi>, became the sensation of
                        that year’s exhibition at the Royal Academy of Art. A contemporary
                        critic fairly brimmed over with praise: “We heartily congratulate our
                        Countrymen on a Genius, who bids fair to rival the great Masters of the
                        Ancient Italian Schools.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">2</ref> While
                        Blake was not formally admitted to the Royal Academy Schools until 8 October
                            1779,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">3</ref> it
seems scarcely credible
                        that he could have been unaware of the painting that had achieved such
                        popular success in the previous year’s exhibition. Moreover, Copley
                        profited from the large 
<figure n="gates-child.d.p12" id="gates-child.d.illbk.12" work-copy="gates-child.d" rend="db" width="634" height="844">
	<figTranscr>10 Help! Help!<lb/>
	Publishd by WBlake 17 May 1793</figTranscr>
	<head>1. William Blake, <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of
                                    Paradise</hi>, plate 10.</head>
	<figDesc>Ca. 1 ¾ × 2 ⅛ inches. Library of
                                Congress.</figDesc>
</figure> number of engravings made after his picture,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">4</ref> and it is therefore reasonable to assume that Blake
                        likely knew the picture in both versions. The original painting (Copley
                        painted a near-duplicate, which he never sold, and several years later a
                        smaller, vertical version) was commissioned by Brook Watson, the Watson of
                        the title who, appearances notwithstanding, survived the shark’s
                        attack although it cost him a leg, and who left the painting to
                        Christ’s Hospital when he died. The engraved version of
                        Copley’s picture was published in 1779, “seemingly with very
                        good success,” by Valentine Green, the successful engraver who also
                        prepared engraved versions of other Copley paintings like the 1782 engraving
                        after the full-length portrait of Henry Laurens that was intended as a
                        companion-piece to a portrait of George Washington also engraved by
                            Green.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">5</ref>
The less well-known engraved
            <pb id="p28-93" n="93"/>
<figure n="copley.watsonandtheshark.28.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="327">
	<head>2. John Singleton Copley, <hi rend="i">Watson and the Shark</hi>
                                (1778); engraving by Valentine Green (1779).</head>
	<figDesc>Ca. 26 × 21 inches. Reproduced by permission of the
                                Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure> version is reproduced with this present note, rather than the more
                        familiar and frequently reproduced painted version housed in the National
                        Gallery of Art, in Washington, D.C. That Blake was familiar with
                        Copley’s work generally became apparent again later as well, when on
                        the first page of the Prophecy section of <hi rend="i">America</hi> he
                        borrowed, for the group fleeing the flames in the left margin, from a group
                        at the lower right corner of Copley’s <hi rend="i">Death of Major
                            Peirson</hi> (1784), which likewise existed in a widely-known engraved
                            version.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Quoted in William James Williams, <hi rend="i">A Heritage of American
Paintings from the National Gallery
                                of Art</hi> (New York: Rutledge Press, 1981) 30.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">3</hi> David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an
                                Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977) 19.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Williams 30.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Jules David Prown, <hi rend="i">John
                                Singleton Copley</hi> (2 vols.; Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP, 1966) 2:
                            272, 293.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">6</hi> I have discussed this connection in
                            another context in my essay, “‘This Accursed
                            Family’: Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and the
                            American Revolution,” <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: Theory
                                and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 26-51.</note></p>
          <p>The struggling figure in Blake’s “Help! Help!” bears
                        striking visual resemblances to Copley’s figure of the endangered and
                        seemingly helpless Brook Watson, which figure is itself borrowed from the
                        figure of a helpless child in Raphael’s last altarpiece.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">7</ref> The relationship of Blake’s
                        little figure to Copley’s monumental one becomes even more striking
                        when we recall that in reproductive engraving the engraver generally
                        reverses the right-left orientation of his or her original, which in this
                        case would produce a figure very much like that which Blake has drawn,
                        complete with dramatically extended hand and with hair streaming out and
                        away in the water from the figure’s head. The waves in Blake’s
                        engraving are likewise much like those in Copley’s painting. Norvig
                        makes much of the curious 
<pb id="p28-94" n="94"/>
unidentified object that
                        bobs on the crest of the wave to the right of the man’s arm in
                        Blake’s engraving. I have no idea, either, of what this is supposed
                        to be, nor does either the painted or the engraved version of
                        Copley’s picture offer any useful guidance. There is something there,
                        certainly, perhaps a bobber or flotation device of some sort (the specks on
                        the object might be taken to suggest the texture of cork, for instance).
                        Even under magnification, however, the object refuses to divulge its
                        identity with any certainty. <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Williams
                            30.</note></p>
          <p>Finally, a clear thematic connection exists between the two images. In the
                        Copley the figure of Watson (whose vulnerability is underscored by his being
                        rendered naked) is seemingly faced with imminent destruction: the various
                        efforts of would-be rescuers appear to be both ineffective and too late.
                        Even the life-line that has been offered Watson proves valueless, draped as
                        it is across the extended forearm of the unresponsive Watson. Blake’s
                        engraving only makes physically explicit (by actually isolating the
                        struggling figure) what is implicit in Copley’s painting: the
                        apparently total inability of the struggling figure to help, or to save,
                        himself. Whether we take Geoffrey Keynes’ word that Blake’s
                        emblem is “self-explanatory”—that it depicts
                        “Man drowning helplessly in the materialistic Sea of Time and
                        Space”—or whether we go further and agree with Gerda Norvig
                        that the engraving asserts that drowning in the disappointed recognition
                        that what one desires is out of reach constitutes “the next critical
                        stage in the integration of the whole man,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n51" type="note">8</ref> the fact remains that both Blake’s image and
                        Copley’s portray individuals in desperate straits indeed. That
                        Copley’s Watson cannot be helped by his friends would have been less
                        important to Blake—though he would have appreciated the
                        pathos—than the fact that he cannot help himself, as the neglected
                        life-line indicates. It is this thematic connection that seems to me to
                        underscore the validity of recognizing in Blake’s apparent borrowing
                        from <hi rend="i">Watson and the Shark</hi> a connotation that is
                        intellectual as well as merely iconographical. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">8</hi>
William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>, ed.
                            Geoffrey Keynes, 3 vols. (London: Trianon Press/Blake Trust, 1968)1: 17;
                            Norvig 65-66.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	</body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>