<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.3.ward</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Who Was Robert Blake?</title>
        <author n="Ward">Aileen Ward</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1994/95</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994/95</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Alma Bennett</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mark Lussier</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>June Sturrock</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994/95"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
      <pb id="p28-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Who Was Robert Blake?</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Aileen <name>Ward</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>What G. E. Bentley once called “the decent ignorance which still
                        obscures Blake’s family”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref>
                        is still far from dispelled. The ages and even the identities of the Blake
                        children have been especially problematic. Among his nineteenth-century
                        biographers, Alexander Gilchrist mentioned only three of Blake’s
                        siblings and knew the names of only two; J. T. Smith and Allan
                        Cunningham’s information was still scantier, and B. H. Malkin spoke
                        only of Blake’s father among his family members.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Frederick Tatham in his manuscript <hi rend="i">Life
                            of Blake</hi> gave the names though not the birthdates of Blake’s
                        four surviving siblings but got their birth order wrong.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> However, his <hi rend="i">Life</hi> was not known to
                        Gilchrist and the other early biographers: it did not come to light till
                        1864, after Gilchrist’s death, and was referred to only casually by
                        Swinburne and E. J. Ellis; it was in fact not published till A. G. B.
                        Russell’s 1906 edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Letters.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> No doubt it was this
                        publication that spurred Arthur Symons to search the St. James Parish
                        register, where in 1907 he discovered the names and birthdates of six
                        children of James and Catherine Blake: James, born 10 July 1753; John, born
                        12 May 1755; William, born 28 November 1757; a second John, born 20 March
                        1760; Richard, born 19 June 1762; and Catherine, born 7 January 1764.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> All six were duly baptized a few weeks
                        after birth. But Symons’s discovery raised almost as many questions
                        as it answered. The duplication of the name John could be 
<figure n="robertblake.nakedyouth.28.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="413">
	<head>1. <hi rend="i">A Naked Youth Seen from the Side, Perhaps Robert
                                    Blake</hi>, c. 1779-80 (Butlin 71).</head>
	<figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British
                                Museum.</figDesc>
</figure> explained by the assumption that the first John died in infancy,
                        though there is no record of his death. Blake himself, in describing the
                        second John as “the evil one” (E 721), left no doubt of his
                        existence, but almost nothing is know of his life.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> The name of Richard is another puzzle, since he is
                        never mentioned again in the Blake records. If, like the first John, he died
                        in infancy, this fact is not recorded, although the death or burial dates of
                        young children are found fairly often in parish registers of the
                        time—witness those of four young siblings of Catherine Boucher
                            Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> And
most puzzling of all,
                        nowhere in the St. James Parish register is the birth or baptism of
                        Blake’s beloved younger brother Robert to be found. 
<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
                            (Oxford: Clarendon, 1977; hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">BB</hi>)
                            30.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Though Gilchrist knew from Blake’s
                            letter to Flaxman of September 1800 that he had a sister, he referred to
                            her only as “Miss Blake” (<hi rend="i">Life of William
                                Blake</hi> ed. Ruthven Todd [London: Everyman, 1945; hereafter cited
                            as <hi rend="i">LWB</hi>] 357-58).</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1969; hereafter cited as 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>) 508. Tatham presumably had his information from
                            Catherine Blake, who was understandably vague about the details of her
                            husband’s childhood. Bentley provides a full account of the birth
                            and baptism dates of the Blake children, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                            1-7.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Deborah Dorfman, <hi rend="i">Blake in the
                                Nineteenth Century</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1969) 33n11. Ellis
                            mentioned the “four other children” but actually listed
                            only the three brothers (“Memoir,” <hi rend="i">The Works
                                of William Blake</hi>, ed. E. E. Ellis and W. B. Yeats [London:
                            Quaritch, 1893] I: 4-5); <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 23n1 and 31.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Arthur Symons, <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake</hi> (London: Cape, 1907) 22.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See Tatham in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 508-09
                            and Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 509n1 and n2.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 5.</note></p>
          <p>Robert’s absence from the record remains the most controverted
                        question about the makeup of Blake’s family. Symons answered it by
                        suggesting that the parish clerk made a careless mistake in entering
                        Robert’s name as Richard at the time of 
<pb id="p28-85" n="85"/>
<figure n="ESIII.1.1.SP.300c" rend="file" width="724" height="1000">
	<head>2. <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Relief and white-line etching. Reproduced by permission of the
                                Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure> his birth in June 1762—as he had previously done in
                        recording the name of Blake’s father as John, not James, at the birth
                        of the first John in 1755. This plausible supposition satisfied Blake
                        scholars—including Mona Wilson and Geoffrey Keynes<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>—for over 50 years. Then in 1969 Bentley
                        offered a new explanation of the omission of Robert from the parish records.
                        In the roster of the Royal Academy Schools he discovered a Robert Blake
                        enrolled as a student of engraving in April 1782 and described as having
                        been “14 last 4th August”—i.e., born in 1767. This he
                        conjectured was in all probability Blake’s youngest brother, five
                        years younger than hitherto supposed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">9</ref> To
              explain why Robert’s name was missing from the St. James 
<figure n="milton.d.p37-33" id="milton.d.illbk.37" work-copy="milton.d" rend="db" width="683" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>37<lb/>
	ROBERT</figTranscr>
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 37.</head>
	<figDesc>Copy D. Courtesy of the Library of Congress.</figDesc>
</figure> Parish register, Bentley proposed that some time after his
                        daughter’s birth in 1764 James Blake Sr. joined the Baptist Church
                        and so never had the infant Robert baptized. In support of this theory he
                        noted that one “—Blake” (no Christian name given) was
                        listed among the members of the Grafton Street Baptist Church from 1769 to
                            1772<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref>—two years after the
                        conjectured date of Robert’s birth, it should be noted. While Bentley
                        thought it possible that the Royal Academy student was not related to Blake,
                        he dismissed the idea as “unlikely,” seeing “no good
                        reason to challenge [the] accuracy” of the entry as “the only
                        record of the birthdate of Blake’s favorite brother.” And from
                        the time of the publication of his <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> this
                        hypothesis has been almost unanimously accepted as the solution to the
                        puzzle of Robert’s birthdate and non-baptism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Mona Wilson, <hi rend="i">The Life of
                                William Blake</hi> (London: None-such, 1927) 2 and 339n; Geoffrey
                            Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 1st ed. (London: Hart-Davis,
                            1949) 3.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 7, 20; see also Sidney C. Hutchison, “The
                            Royal Academy Schools, 1768-1830,” <hi rend="i">Walpole
                                Society</hi> 38 (1962): 146. Hereafter, to avoid confusion, this
                            Royal Academy student will be referred to as “Robert
                            Blake,” and Blake’s youngest brother simply as
                            “Robert.”</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 7-8.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 20 and n3. Only David V. Erdman (<hi rend="i">Blake:
Prophet Against Empire</hi> [3rd ed. rev., Princeton:
                            Princeton UP, 1971] 98) keeps to the earlier conjecture of a 1762
                            birthdate for Robert, without, however, alluding to Bentley’s
                            hypothesis.</note></p>
          <pb id="p28-86" n="86"/>
            <figure n="BUTR2.1.1r.WD.300c" rend="file" width="958" height="682">
            <head>4. <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Pen and sepia wash (Butlin R2). Reproduced by permission of the
                            Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>And yet some doubts remain. A number of small facts or inferences—none
                        of them decisive evidence taken singly, but certainly suggestive in their
                        totality—point in another direction. First of all, the assumption
                        that the Robert Blake who entered the Royal Academy Schools in 1782 was in
                        fact Blake’s youngest brother is questionable, given the
                        “hosts of Blakes” living in London at the time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Bentley himself collected some 23
                        London contemporaries who bore the name of William Blake, one of whom was
                        also an engraver, and today “Robert Blakes” are at least as
                        common as “Williams.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref>
                        This profusion of Blakes also undermines the probability of the nameless
                        “Blake” of the Grafton Street Baptist Church being
                        Blake’s father, the premise of Bentley’s explanation for the
                        absence of a baptismal record for Robert. Furthermore, it is striking that
                        not one of Blake’s early biographers—neither Malkin, to whom
                        Blake described his own experience at the Academy, nor Smith, who knew
                        Robert personally, nor Tatham, who got his information mainly from Catherine
                            Blake<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref>—spoke of
                        Robert’s studying at the Royal Academy Schools, certainly a
                        noteworthy event if it actually occurred. And if, as seems likely, Blake
                        continued attending the Schools for a full six year term after his admission
                        in 1779,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> the
brothers’
                        overlapping terms would be a still more notable circumstance—though
                        if, as is generally assumed, Blake left the Academy in disgust after a few
                        months, it is hard to see why Robert would have decided to apply there two
                        years later. Nor can Robert’s surviving drawings be taken as evidence
                        of Academy tutelage. While his work reveals some genuine talent, not unlike
                        Blake’s own in theme and mood, it is an undeveloped one, showing
                        neither the precocious ability that would have gained him admission to the
                        Academy at the unusually early age of 14 nor the influence of Academy
                        training thereafter<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref>—though of
                        course there is no record of how long he remained there if he actually
                        enrolled. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> See <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 22
                            and n1, 553-54.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">N&amp;Q</hi> 210
                            (1965): 172-78; see also Symons 26-28. Today there are eight Robert
                            Blakes (plus three Williams) listed in the Manhattan telephone book. The
                            current London telephone directory unhelpfully identifies most of its
                            subscribers merely by their initials, but it does list two
                            “Roberts” among 35 “R. Blakes,” with only
                            nine “W. Blakes” and no “Williams.”</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> It might be noted that Robert’s
                            supposed admission to the Academy occurred only four months before
                            Blake’s marriage in August 1782, which would seem to ensure that
                            Catherine knew of his studying there.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> See Aileen Ward, “Sir Joshua and
                            His Gang,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 52
                            (1989): 78-79.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Only eight boys (including John Flaxman)
                            aged 14 or younger were among the 414 students admitted to the Schools
                            prior to Robert Blake in 1782 (see Hutchison 313-46). On Robert’s
                            “barely passable” drawing, as for example in “The
                            Approach of Doom,” one of his latest works (1785 according to R.
                            N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake</hi>
                            [Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983] 12), see David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an
Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon Press Ltd., 1977)
                            40.</note></p>
          <pb id="p28-87" n="87"/>
          <p>Yet since it appears that Blake at some point tutored Robert in
                        drawing—“a task which he must have found above all others
                        delightful”—this has been taken to imply that the older
                        brother was preparing the younger to qualify for admission to the
                            Academy.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref>
This would seem to
                        strengthen the likelihood that Robert was actually the student of engraving
                        admitted to the Schools in 1782, and indeed it appears a remarkable
                        coincidence that two Robert Blakes both born in the 1760s should both be
                        training as engravers at the same time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">18</ref> Yet a number of similar duplications occur in the roster of
                        the Royal Academy Schools which—like that of Blake’s namesake
                        engraver—considerably diminish the coincidentality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> As for Blake’s teaching Robert, the story
                        stems from Smith’s mention that William “considered him
                        [Robert] his pupil” around the time Blake opened his printshop with
                            Parker,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
and since the discovery of
                        the name of Robert Blake in the Academy roster it has been fortified by
                        reference to the <hi rend="i">Robert Blake Sketch Book</hi>, first described
                        by Geoffrey Keynes in 1949.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref> This
                        rather decrepit notebook containing about 50 pages of drawings is inscribed
                        “Robert Blake’s / 1777 Book” on the front cover, with
                        similar signatures elsewhere and seven occurrences of the date 1778.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> Many of the pages contain competent
                        sketches of various parts of the human body on the left hand side,
                        apparently by some instructor, with rather hesitant copies filling up the
                        rest of the page, progressing from lips, noses, eyes, hands, arms and legs
                        to faces, busts and full figures.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">23</ref>
                        Despite some awkwardness, especially in the early pages,, the work shows
                        real ability for a 10 or 11 year old boy. He was evidently aiming at a kind
                        of academic realism: later pages include heads of women with
                        eighteenth-century hats and hairstyles as well as carefully detailed
                        drawings of birds, animals and a rural scene. But his pedestrian manner
                        contrasts strongly with the abstract and archaic but imaginatively
                        expressive figures of the authentic drawings by Blake’s brother found
                        in the Notebook of William Blake and elsewhere, and indeed the drawings that
                        served as the boy’s models have a more assured and detailed grasp of
                        human anatomy than Blake’s own work at the time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> It is hard to see these sketches as the work of
                        either William or Robert. A final argument against linking the Sketch Book
                        to Blake’s teaching Robert in 1777-78 is the date implied in
                        Smith’s account—that the lessons occurred during
                        Blake’s partnership in the printshop, i.e., around 1784, two years
                        after Robert’s supposed entrance at the Schools and not, as Bentley
                        suggests, prior to his enrollment.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n25" type="note">25</ref>
                        Whatever the instruction amounted to, its purpose was probably to train
                        Robert as an assistant with his engraving, as Blake later did with
                        Catherine—a supposition which gives point to the vision of Robert
                        later providing Blake with his most valuable trade secret. 
<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 29 and 20.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> As G. E. Bentley has argued in
                            correspondence, noting also that there is no record of either one being
                            formally apprenticed or later continuing in the profession.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Counting only students born within a
                            dozen years of one another and enrolled in the same field, we find the
                            following pairs: among architects, two Richard Hollands (born 1750 and
                            1752), two George Moores (born 1806 and 1810), two James Pennethornes
                            (born 1801 and 1810), two Charles Smiths (born 1790 and 1792), and two
                            George Smiths (born 1782 and 1790); among painters, two pairs of John
                            Grahams (born 1755 and 1766 and 1792 and 1795 respectively), two William
                            Rosses (born 1795 and 1798), two William Turners (born 1763 and 1774),
                            and two George Wards (born 1789 and 1801). Simple duplications of names
                            among the 1551 students enrolled between 1768 and 1830 are too numerous
                            to include (cf. Hutchison 183-91 passim).</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 457—a point echoed by Cunningham 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 482).</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Keynes 4-5.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The
                                Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon,
                            1981) 1: 617; Essick, <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake in the
                                Huntington Collections</hi> (San Marino, CA: Huntington Library,
                            1985) 235-36.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Butlin 1: cat. R1; 2: pls. 1126-1177.
                            This procedure echoes the teaching method Blake encountered a decade
                            earlier at the Pars’s School (where, as Bindman notes [12], he
                            did not distinguish himself). See the record of Thomas Jones, quoted
                            Bindman 227n12, and Janet Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of
                                Art</hi> (Montreal: McGill-Queens UP, 1984) chap. 2.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> For Robert’s work, see <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi>,
ed. David V. Erdman
                            (Oxford: Clarendon, 1973) NN. 1, 3, 5, 7, 9; Butlin 1: cat. R2-R11, 2:
                            pls. 176 and 1178-90. For Blake’s early drawings, see Butlin 2:
                            pls. 71, 73, 106, 107, et seq., and Bindman’s comment (“an
                            almost complete lack of natural dexterity”), <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
16-17.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 20. Both Erdman (<hi rend="i">Prophet</hi> 98) and
                            Jack Lindsay (<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> [New York: Braziller,
                            1978] 33) also accept a date as early as 1777 for the lessons on the
                            evidence of the Sketch Book.</note></p>
          <p>Although Keynes and Butlin accept the attribution of the Sketch Book to
                        Blake’s brother, both Bindman and Essick are quite doubtful.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> Apart from its dissimilarity to the
                        brothers’ work, the provenance of the book, as given in a long note
                        inside the front cover by an unidentified hand sometime after 1878, is
                        suspicious. The note claimed 
<pb id="p28-88" n="88"/>
onetime friend Thomas
                        Stothard after his death in 1834 and again in the sale of Sir Alexander
                        Spearman’s books in 1878; thereafter it disappeared, to surface again
                        in 1919 when it was purchased for the Huntington Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> However, it was not listed among the 1500 items in
                        the catalogue of the Stothard sale or (apparently) in that of the Spearman
                            sale.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref>
Wherever it came from, the
                        book was not linked to Blake’s brother Robert till a century after
                        his death by its nameless late nineteenth-century owner, whose note may not
                        have been a deliberate fabrication so much as a bit of wishful thinking.
                        Moreover, there is no reason to think that Blake would have given Stothard
                        such a treasured memento as this Sketch Book if indeed it was his
                        brother’s: there is no evidence of a close friendship between Robert
                        and Stothard, but rather a seven if not a 12-year difference in age, and
                        Blake had ceased collaborating with Stothard a year before Robert’s
                        death, perhaps as a result of a cooling of their friendship.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref> All in all, it is a more likely guess
                        that the book belonged to the other Robert Blake—the precocious lad
                        who entered the Royal Academy Schools at 14. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi>
Keynes 4-5; Butlin I: 617; Bindman 232n3; Essick, <hi rend="i">Huntington</hi> 235-36.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Butlin 1: 617; Keynes 5-6.</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi><hi rend="i"> BB</hi> 656 and cf. 661, where the Spearman sale is not
                            included in Bentley’s chronological listing of catalogues
                            mentioning Blake’s work from 1780 to 1974—though it may
                            have been omitted as of minor importance (cf. 649).</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> See <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 611, also
                            Blake’s 1803 letter to his brother James (E725) on the break in
                            their friendship some years earlier.</note></p>
          <p>If then Blake’s youngest brother was not the Robert Blake enrolled in
                        the Schools in 1782, who was he, or rather when was he born? The
                        preponderant evidence seems to point back to Symons’s
                        conjecture—that he was in fact the mysterious Richard Blake conjured
                        into being in June 1762 by a slip of the parish clerk’s pen. Several
                        other considerations support this hypothesis. First of all, the absence of a
                        death record for Richard Blake (or any other record subsequent to that of
                        his birth) suggests that a child of that name never existed. That a death
                        record is also lacking for the first John is not material: he may have died
                        elsewhere than in London, as Bentley suggests, or even have been the son not
                        of James but of John Blake, the father’s name given in the entry of
                        his birth, and lived to maturity for all we know.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref> Second, Blake’s mother, who was born around
                        1722, would have been 45 in 1767, the supposed date of Robert’s
                        birth: a not impossible age for child-bearing, but an improbable one,
                        especially considering that this would have been her seventh child. Again,
                        the close intimacy between William and Robert, which probably dates from
                        Blake’s return home at the end of his apprenticeship in 1779, is far
                        more likely to have been based on a five than a 10 year’s difference
                        in age. The “Academy study” of a naked youth seen from the
                        side, dated c. 1779-80, which Keynes took to be a portrait of Robert
                        represents a youth of about 17 or 18, not a boy of 12:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> and though both date and identification are
                        tentative, this too would support a birth date for Robert of 1762 rather
                        than 1767.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Bentley raises this second possibility
                            only to argue against it (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 3n3). It should be noted
                            that eighteenth-century parish records are far from complete, and the
                            definitive central register at Somerset House of all births and deaths
                            occurring in Great Britain was not established till the passage of the
                            Births and Deaths Registration Act in 1836 (<hi rend="i">Encyclopaedia
                                Britannica</hi>, 11th ed. [Cambridge UP, 1910] 3: 990).</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Butlin 1: cat. 71; Keynes 4 and pl.
                            1.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> The fact that Robert’s birthdate
                            is given as 1767 in the London section of the Mormon Genealogical
                            Register does not prove Bentley’s theory, since the source given
                            is Bentley’s own <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> Unfortunately
                            the other Robert Blake (born in August 1767) is not listed anywhere in
                            England, in London or outside: but this proves nothing, since the
                            Genealogical Register relies on fragmentary parish records for its
                            information.</note></p>
          <p>The most telling argument against the Bentley hypothesis, however, is the
                        fact that the only two early biographers to mention Robert’s age at
                        the time of his death in February 1787 both gave it as 24: Tatham, whose
                        information came from Blake’s widow, and Gilchrist, who never saw
                        Tatham’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> and relied on other informants such
                        as Linnell and Palmer, both of whom knew Blake well.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> By this 
<pb id="p28-89" n="89"/>
account, Robert
                        must have been born sometime between February 1762 and February 1763.
                        Apparently it was their independent testimony that persuaded Symons that the
                        name of Richard in the parish register for June 1762 must have been a
                        clerical error for Robert; and indeed their record of Robert’s age at
                        death is in the end the only explicit evidence we have for his
                            birthdate.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">34</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> Tatham in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 510;
                            Gilchrist 51. Gilchrist placed Robert’s death “in his
                            twenty-fifth year,” i.e., a few months before his twenty-fifth
                            birthday in June. Bentley noted this testimony but was not convinced by
                            it (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 31, 510n1); yet the congruence of two
                            independent records is impressive. That Gilchrist had not seen
                            Tatham’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> seems clear from internal
                            evidence. His few direct citations of Tatham mostly concern matters not
                            mentioned in Tatham’s own <hi rend="i">Life</hi> (cf. <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 261,
366) and often appear to be based on oral
                            reports (e.g. <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 352); but where Gilchrist discusses
                            matters which are included in Tatham’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> his
                            account either significantly departs from Tatham’s (cp. <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 10
and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 511, <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 81 and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 530, <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 355
                            and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 534) or contradicts it (<hi rend="i">LWB</hi>
                            85 and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 521) or is attributable to another source
                            (cp. <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 31-32 and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 517 and 459,
                                <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 351 and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 471). Though
                            Gilchrist’s account of Blake’s midnight composition seems
                            to derive from Tatham (cp. <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 31-32 and <hi rend="i">BR</hi>
526n1), the unnamed “cordially appreciative
                            friend” who supplied Gilchrist with this and much of his other
                            information is almost certainly Samuel Palmer in one of his frequent
                            discussions with Gilchrist of matters probably familiar to all the
                            Ancients. Gilchrist’s mentions of Tatham are infrequent and
                            perfunctory compared with his own many cordial references to Palmer (cf.
                                <hi rend="i">LWB</hi> 299). Thus, while Tatham’s information
                            about Robert’s age at death was no doubt supplied by Catherine,
                            with whom he <corr type="emend">became</corr> familiar after Blake’s death,
                            Gilchrist’s most probably derived from Blake himself through
                            Palmer.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Bentley points out in correspondence
                            that even the evidence of a death date is not definitive: Blake’s
                            brother James’s age at death is given wrongly as 71 in the
                            perfunctory six-word entry in the Bunhill Fields Burial register when he
                            as actually 73 and a half (cf. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 340 and n4).
                            However, James’s death was not the subject of any biographical
                            interest that would have corrected the record, while Robert’s
                            death was a matter of concern to Blake’s early biographers.
                            Unfortunately his age is not given in the Bunhill Fields register as
                            quoted by Bentley (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 32). I wish to thank Professor
                            Bentley for his generosity in reading the final draft of this article
                            and offering perceptive criticism on this and other matters.</note></p>
          <p>Thus when all aspects of the question are considered, the conclusion seems
                        almost inescapable: Robert was born in June 1762, not August 1767, and a
                        slip of the pen accounts for the confusion over his name. More than merely
                        revising the record, however, this investigation underscores a basic
                        principle of biography. A single document, however impressive its
                        credentials, cannot establish a fact apart from its total narrative context.
                        The entry from the Schools register remains a tantalizing but isolated item,
                        unsupported by any firm corroborative evidence, among the myriad minute
                        particulars which the biographer of Blake must sift and assemble. Written
                        evidence, while it can provide uniquely valuable information, can also be
                        mistaken or misleading, and must therefore be scrutinized as carefully as
                        all other kinds; conversely, non-verbal evidence may be admitted even where
                        it appears to contradict the written evidence. In short, documentary
                        evidence should not be privileged to the exclusion of all other kinds; we
                        should remember how little of any life finds its way into written accounts,
                        and keep our minds open to the mute testimony of things and circumstances
                        and inferences from them. Every piece of biographical evidence, documentary
                        or otherwise, must be viewed against the total experience of the
                        biographical subject. It is the living context of each event that shapes
                        isolated records into the semblance of biographical truth.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>