<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>28.3.sturrock</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“What have I to do with thee?”</title>
        <author n="Sturrock">June Sturrock</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1994/95</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1994/95</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">28.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Alma Bennett</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mark Lussier</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>June Sturrock</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1994/95"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_28">
    <body>
	<pb id="p28-89" n="89"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-28-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“What have I to do with thee?”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>June <name>Sturrock</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The rejected “thee” of the fourth line of “To
                        Tirzah” is Mary in that she was the original recipient of
                        Jesus’s snub at the marriage at Cana (John 2.4); she is also Tirzah
                        because that is how the poem is addressed. Yet perhaps the preceding three
                        lines may be read as directed (in rebuke? in consolation?) rather towards
                        the two women who on the green hill below the text of the poem support the
                        decaying corpse of a man: 
						<q> Whate’er is Born of Mortal Birth,<lb/>
                            Must be consumed with the Earth<lb/>
 To rise from Generation free.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Blake is quoted from Erdman’s
                                edition, which is abbreviated as E with page numbers following in
                                the parenthetical references. Other abbreviations include B
                                (Butlin’s catalogue) and IB (Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Illuminated
Blake</hi>).</note></q></p>
          <p>This group suggests Mary and Martha of Bethany with their brother Lazarus<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">2</ref> already decomposing, as Martha warns
                        Jesus (John 11.39). Indeed the central figure resembles Lazarus in
                        Blake’s painting of <hi rend="i">The Raising of Lazarus</hi> in
                        Aberdeen (B 487), in that Lazarus is emerging from the ground (not the
                        sepulchre mentioned in John 11.38-41) and seems to be half in and half out
                        of the grave. Certainly the inscription on the robes of the old man bending
                        over the corpse—“It is raised a spiritual body” (1
                        Corinthians 15.44)—suggests Blake’s reading of the raising of
                        Lazarus as a spiritual resurrection misinterpreted by a materialistic church
                            <pb id="p28-90" n="90"/>
which completed its creed with the assertion of
                        belief in “the resurrection of the <hi rend="i">body</hi> and the
                        life everlasting.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Both Mellor and Lincoln speak of Lazarus
                            in this connection, but neither identifies Mary and Martha, or deals
                            fully with the implications of the Lazarus story. Mellor says of this
                            design “an old man pours a reviving. baptismal water upon a
                            corpse held by two women. This iconographic fusion of the descent from
                            the cross and the raising of Lazarus is summed up in the lines engraved
                            upon the old man’s robe—‘It is raised a Spiritual
                            Body.’ Mortal existence is totally evil; only through death can
                            fallen man be freed from his corrupted human form and redeemed 
<corr type="emend">as</corr> a
                            spiritual, purified body” (p.189) Lincoln, who foregrounds the
                            negative reading of the design allows that “seen as an image of
                            redemption the design shows humanity “Raised a Spiritual Body,
                            “brought back from the grave like Lazarus (whose two sisters had
                            faith in his resurrection,” but qualifies this by saying that
                            “the Saviour who presides over this vision of Liberty is not
                            Jesus but his Father, the God who promotes the vision of human nature as
                            sinful” (201-02).</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The Apostle’s Creed in the
                            translation of the Anglican Book of Common Prayer: my
                        emphasis.</note></p>
          <p>The comforting of Martha and Mary by the promise of resurrection for their
                        brother is a repeated note in <hi rend="i">Vala, or The Four Zoas</hi>,
                        where they appear as Daughters of Beulah: 
						<q> The daughters of Beulah saw
                            the Divine Vision they were comforted<lb/>
 And as a Double female form
                            loveliness &amp; perfection of beauty<lb/>
 They bowd the head &amp;
                            worshippd &amp; with mild voice spoke these words<lb/>
<lb/>
 Lord.
                            Saviour if thou hadst been here our brother had not died<lb/>
 And now we
                            know that whatsoever thou wilt ask of God<lb/>
 He will give it thee
                            ..............................<lb/>
 The Saviour mild &amp; gentle bent
                            over the corse of Death<lb/>
 Saying If ye will Believe your Brother
                            shall rise again<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 55.13-15; 56.1-18, E 337)
						</q></p>
          <p>This dialogue follows closely the gospel version of the exchange between
                        Martha and Jesus (John 11.21-27).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">4</ref> Again
                        in Night the Seventh the daughters of Beulah find comfort in these same
                        words in the face of death when they write on “all their tombs &amp;
                        pillars &amp; on every Urn” the eternal promise “If ye will
                        believe your B[r]other shall rise again” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
                        87.4-6, E 367). The daughters of Beulah are still identified with the
                        sisters of Bethany in Night the Eighth when in praising the Lamb of God
                        “they anoint his feet with ointment they wipe them with the hair of
                        their head” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 113.37, E 377) just as Mary of
                        Bethany tends Jesus in the brief interval in John’s gospel between
                        the raising of Lazarus and the passion narrative (12.3). Flowing hair is a
                        distinguishing mark of Mary of Bethany (as of Mary Magdalene), and in the
                        “To Tirzah” design, as in <hi rend="i">The Raising of
                            Lazarus</hi>, the two women are distinguished by their hair, one loose
                        and flowing and the other bound or (in the painting) covered. 
<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Johnson and Wilkie note that Mary and Martha
                            form the “Double female” (222).</note></p>
          <p>The old man offering a pitcher is more mysterious. He looks like the Ancient
                        Bard in “The Voice of the Ancient Bard,” which follows soon
                        after “To Tirzah” in seven copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Experience</hi>, but also resembles Blake’s portrayals of Joseph
                        of Arimathea, with his long hair, long beard and robes: this is how Joseph
                        is represented in three of the four versions of <hi rend="i">Joseph of
                            Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi> (B 262, 286,
                            780).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">5</ref> He
is long-haired, bearded
                        and old in two other paintings, <hi rend="i">The Body of Christ Borne to the
                            Tomb</hi> (B 426) and <hi rend="i">The Entombment</hi> (B 427). Joseph
                        is associated with the dead body of Jesus, as the follower who takes him
                        away for burial. If the old man in the “To Tirzah” design is
                        Joseph of Arimathea, Mellor’s suggestion of “an iconographic
                        fusion of the raising of Lazarus and the descent from the cross”
                        (189) is strengthened. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">5</hi> In the other
                            version he is shown naked, but bearded and old (B 76).</note></p>
          <p>Joseph of Arimathea is associated not only with British Christianity but also
                        with the figure of the artist, for Blake sees him as “One of the
                        Gothic Artists who Built the Cathedrals in what we call the Dark
                        Ages” (E 671).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">6</ref> The dead man
                        (Lazarus) is thus possibly flanked by, on the one hand Mary and Martha, and
                        on the other hand by Joseph of Arimathea; that is on the one hand by two
                        women identified by Blake as daughters of Beulah, and thus as Muses, and on
                        the other hand by the image of the Gothic artist. If both Joseph of
                        Arimathea and the sisters of Lazarus are too concerned with physical death
                        in the biblical narratives that concern them, all three believe in the power
                        of Jesus and are associated with what can transform their vision, the work
                        of the arts. Thus indeed in this design the sexes rise “to work and
                        weep” (8). Work after all is essentially redemptive in the poems that
                        are roughly contemporary with “To Tirzah” and with the Joseph
                        of Arimathea inscription.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Presumably this is why Bindman speaks of
                            him as a figure of the artist (124).</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Erdman implies that the date of
                            “To Tirzah” is approximately 1803-06 (800). The Joseph of
                            Arimathea inscription is from 1809-10 (889). <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                            and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, texts in which work is central, date from
                            approximately 1804-15 (809) and 1804-10 (806) respectively.</note></p>
          <p>The first three lines of “To Tirzah” may thus be read as words
                        of comfort in that they speak not only of the certainty of death and
                        corruption but also of the certainty of rising again spiritually: and the
                        design addresses this element in the poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n42" type="note">8</ref> These lines are an affirmation followed by a strong rejection:
                        the words of the fourth line are as abrupt 
<pb id="p28-91" n="91"/>
and
                        disconcerting in the poem as they are in their original biblical context.
                        The various verbal elements of the poem—the harshness of these
                        repeated words, their added impact as Jesus’ own words, their
                        allusion to the mother of Jesus, the later address to “thou Mother of
                        my Mortal part” (9), the knowledge that Tirzah is elsewhere 
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 19:49-60, E 113; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        67:44-51, E 221) the cruel imprisoner of the senses, the apparent clumsiness
                        of the repetition in the first line (born, birth)—all work together
                        to foreground birth as death. Read as a visual text, however, the poem with
                        its greater complexity of biblical allusion—referring not only to the
                        Jesus who denies his mother and dies as an act of liberation, but also to
                        the Jesus who loves his friends and whose death leads to the life of a
                        “spiritual body”—addresses death as birth. This sense
                        is strengthened by the allusion to the story of Lazarus in the second
                        stanza: “Mercy changed Death into Sleep” (7). Jesus the
                        merciful, the forgiver of sins, associates the death of Lazarus with sleep
                        when speaking to his disciples: “Our friend Lazarus sleepeth, but I
                        go, that I may awake him out of sleep” (John 11.11). The rising from
                        such a sleep ends <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and is besought by the bard
                        who introduces the <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Erdman seems to prefer such a
                            “hopeful vision” suggesting that we could “see the
                            two women and the pitcher-offering old man . . . as spiritual comforters
                            . . . . As the “Mortal part” is consumed, the
                            “Spiritual Body” is welcomed into the garden, and love
                            does give support” (IB94).</note></p>
          <p>The fourth and the last eight lines of the poem are so absolute in their
                        rejection of the maternal and the natural<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n43" type="note">9</ref> that they have often obscured the other implications of both
                        song and design. Thus the female figures have been seen as necessarily
                        negative—as useless Sex-Love and Mother-Love (Keynes 52), as
                        “Tirzah-like” figures (Lincoln 201), or as Rahab and Tirzah
                        (Lindsay 83). Yet while “the extreme hostility and contempt for the
                        female and the maternal” as Mary Lynn Johnson says (61) cannot be
                        easily dismissed, the presence of the sisters of Bethany in the design
                        suggests not the overpowering anger of the third and fourth stanzas, but the
                        power of belief and the power of human art. <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Such a
connection and rejection of the maternal and the
                            natural is an aspect of various religious traditions: E. P. Thompson,
                            discussing contemporary views of the <hi rend="i">humanum maternum</hi>,
                            says of “To Tirzah” that “if we set aside the
                            enigmatic second verse, might be an expression of orthodox Swedenborgian
                            doctrine” (148). He also describes the poem as employing
                            “the imagery of the feminine principle (the womb) clothing,
                            enclosing, and binding the spirit in a way which Muggletonians as well
                            as neo-Platonists would have understood” (81).</note></p>
          <p>Rajan speaks of this song’s “deeply pessimistic
                        antinaturalism” (222); Leader sees it as “the Bard’s
                        nadir” (202); Lincoln’s long and judicious discussion of the
                        poem suggests that it can be seen in two ways, either as showing “a
                        clarification of vision” or as emphasizing the death of Jesus, which
                        emphasis “may confirm the power of Tirzah by reinforcing a
                        self-denying attitude” (201). I would add this qualification: the
                        figures of Mary and Martha of Bethany (and perhaps of Joseph of Arimathea)
                        in the design, together with the obligation “to work”
                        (“and weep”) in the text suggest that the song is not a pure
                        rejection of human life. Art remains, work remains (as the last plate of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> shows Los and Enitharmon still laboring at the
                        forge and the loom). If as Lincoln suggests “as the fruits [on the
                        tree in the design] indicate, the myth of Eden predominates here”
                        then Adam’s biblical curse—work—is seen here as his
                        blessing. The preceding reading is intended not so much to elucidate as to
                        complicate: after all, the song itself, like “The Tyger” (but
                        with no final modification), ends with a repetition of its initial
                        question.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">WORKS CITED</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman. New York: Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman.
                            New York: Anchor, 1974.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi> Ed.
                            Andrew Lincoln. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1991.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi> Ed.
                            Geoffrey Keynes.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
                                Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New Haven: Yale UP, 1981.</p>
            <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn. “Feminist Approaches to Teaching <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Approaches to Teaching
                                Blake’s “Songs of Innocence and of
                                Experience.”</hi> Ed. Robert F. Gleckner and Mark L.
                            Greenberg. New York: MLA, 1989: 57-66.</p>
            <p>Leader, Zachary. <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s Songs.</hi> London:
                            Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1981.</p>
            <p>Lindsay, David. <hi rend="i">Blake’s “Songs of Innocence
                                and of Experience.”</hi> London, 1989</p>
            <p>Mellor, Anne K. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Human Form Divine.</hi>
                            Berkeley: U of California P, 1974.</p>
            <p>Rajan, Tilottama. <hi rend="i">The Supplement of Reading: Figures of
                                Understanding in Romantic Theory and Practice.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell
                            UP, 1990.</p>
            <p>Thompson, E.P. <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast: William Blake and
                                the Moral Law.</hi> New York: The New Press, 1994.</p>
            <p>Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson. <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                                “Four Zoas”: The Design of a Dream.</hi> Cambridge,
                            Mass.: Harvard UP, 1978.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>