<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.1.stevenson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">David Simpson on Paolozzi’s Newton</title>
        <author n="Stevenson">Warren Stevenson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Lauren G. Henry</name>
              <name>J.E.M. Latham</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
	<pb id="p29-24" n="24"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">DISCUSSION</title>
        </head>
        <head>
          <title type="section-subtitle"><hi rend="i">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of
thought</hi></title>
        </head>
        <p>David Simpson’s suggestion that the bending figure in Blake’s color print 
<hi rend="i">Newton</hi> may be a conflation of Sir Isaac Newton and the Rev. John Newton, the reformed
slave-trader, is indeed interesting. It leads by an almost irresistible imaginative progression to the further
surmise that the “mighty Spirit . . . Nam’d Newton” who “leap’d from the land of Albion” and
seized from Orc the “Trump of the last doom”
<pb id="p29-25" n="25"/>
in <hi rend="i">Europe: a Prophecy</hi> (13:1-5) may likewise be a conflation of those two (in many ways)
seeming opposites. I have always been uneasy with Northrop Frye’s explanation of what he refers to as
“that curious passage in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>” as representing Blake’s doctrine that “the mental
attitude represented by [Isaac] Newton moves toward a consolidation of error which could provoke an
apocalypse” (<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> 254) and have felt that there must be still another way of
interpreting the allusion. The passage seems to have a contemporaneous quality, with the preceding plate
(which also mentions “the trump of the last doom”) referring to Albion’s Angel, “Great George
street,” Enitharmon’s triumph, and so on. And of course the impromptu trumpet lesson the “mighty Spirit
. . . Nam’d Newton” gives the feckless Orc is followed by Enitharmon’s awakening and the information
that “eighteen hundred years were fled” (12:12-13:10), which sounds fairly specific.</p>
        <p>If Blake <hi rend="i">is</hi> referring, at least in part, to the Rev. John Newton here, he would
seem to be anticipating the shift of emphasis in his evolving myth from Orc to Los, writ large in 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, of which John Newton’s famous
conversion, evangelical fervor and anti-slavery work would be suitable, if partial, symbols, all of which find
counterparts elsewhere in Blake’s poetry.</p>
        <p>As for Professor Simpson’s reference to Martin Butlin’s account of the recent controversy over
Sir Eduardo Paolozzi’s sculpture adapted from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> intended for the British
Library, no doubt Butlin is right to warn us against imposing “too strictly a Blakean interpretation” on a
different work of art; but judging from his description and the accompanying photograph (admittedly a risky
business), I would have to say that Paolozzi’s <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> looks very nearly the antithesis of
Blake’s, <corr type="emend">wherein</corr> the lightness and delicacy of the medium is artfully contrasted to the heaviness of the
design, enhancing the satirical effect. To my bad eye, Paolozzi’s <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> resembles nothing
so much as a defecating armadillo. Cast in bronze twelve feet high, and mounted on a podium of similar height,
it could only represent (if taken in the way Butlin warns us against) a perversion of Blake’s design into a
travesty of unutterable ugliness and monumental stupidity. One can only hope that it isn’t as bad as it
looks.</p>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>Warren <name>Stevenson</name></docAuthor>
        </byline>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
