<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.1.gourlay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Joseph Viscomi, Blake and the Idea of the Book</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander S. Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Lauren G. Henry</name>
              <name>J.E.M. Latham</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
	<pb id="p29-31" n="31"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-1-0008">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Joseph Viscomi. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> Princeton:
Princeton University Press, 1993. xxvii + 453 pp. $49.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Alexander S. <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>When Robert N. Essick’s <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker</hi> came out 14 years ago, it
seemed to me the last possible word on most of Blake’s workshop techniques, and it certainly was a vast
improvement on all that had been said about them before. Joseph Viscomi’s new account of the processes used
in the illuminated books, the first of two planned studies about Blake and printing, carries the discussion
beyond the methods themselves into their consequences in the entire illuminated canon and their theoretical
implications for understanding Blake’s art. It constitutes a Grand Unified Theory of illuminated printing
and publishing, revealing important new patterns in the vast sea of data about Blake’s books that Keynes,
Wolf, Erdman, Bentley and others have compiled so lovingly. A few points in this ambitious book will no doubt
be further refined, and it will not make Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> or the forthcoming
supplement to it obsolete, but for the foreseeable future <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>
will be just as indispensable for everyone who writes about Blake’s illuminated books and his other graphic
works. Even those disputing Viscomi will do so in the terms of his arguments.</p>
          <p>Viscomi writes very clearly and carefully, though his emphatic, enthusiastic style can be trying,
even when one agrees with him—sometimes it’s like being shouted at . . . or prophesied to. But most
readers will appreciate his exhilarating distrust of all received opinion and everyone will profit from his
extraordinary ability to synthesize complex information in new ways. His most unusual asset in this
undertaking is his extensive practical experience with processes virtually identical to Blake’s, some of
which he acquired in co-publishing the Manchester Etching Workshop facsimile edition of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>: impressions from reproductions of some of Blake’s relief printing plates were
hand-colored, producing pages that look even more like Blake’s than the collotype and stencil facsimiles by
the Trianon Press. His participation in this venture afforded essential knowledge about the presswork involved
in printing relief plates and the process of finishing them. Viscomi has also thoroughly researched the
history of graphic techniques and conducted careful experiments with transfer methods, resists, etching and
engraving
<pb id="p29-32" n="32"/>
techniques, and then thought deeply about the combined implications of this information. He included with the
Manchester Etching Workshop facsimile a much shorter version of a few of the present arguments, but the
searching thoroughness in <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> distinguishes them here.</p>
          <p>The first part of the book is organized according to the steps of the process of illuminated
publishing, with excursions into variant methods and collateral questions as they arise. Several themes run
through these discussions, but three seem especially important. First, Viscomi sees Blake’s methods in
general as variations upon conventional techniques in etching and engraving rather than completely
unprecedented inventions. Second, the chief distinguishing characteristic of illuminated printing is that it
minimizes divisions between idea and execution, between text and image—divisions that are enforced by
conventional technology and that continue to be reflected in critical thinking about Blake’s books. And
third, although Blake’s publishing enterprise was always inefficient and its products more varied than those
of conventional printers, much of the process was mechanical and determined by the need for efficiency in
small-scale mass production; only later in Blake’s career were illuminated books deliberately differentiated
as unique artifacts.</p>
          <p>Viscomi begins by arguing that Blake usually created the text and design directly on the plate
with only preliminary drafting of both, rather than completely settling the text and designs and laying out
the pages in advance. Thus Blake usually did not employ the techniques for transferring designs that he must
have used in much of his other graphic work. Viscomi shows how these transfer processes work, especially in
the complex process of configuring the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> drawings, and explains why such
methods weren’t used in most illuminated pages. I found the digression as useful as the main argument, for
the description of transfer methods cleared up a question that has troubled me for years. Blake occasionally
made mysterious errors in his conventional etching/engravings which suggest that he somehow forgot the
function of a given line within a drawing, as if myopia, a mechanical process, or a singularly obtuse
assistant had intervened between a preliminary drawing and the preparation of the plate. For instance, in the
stipple engraving of the Laocoön group for Ree’s <hi rend="i">Cyclopedia</hi> (reproduced in Essick, 
<hi rend="i">Commercial</hi> fig. 278), Blake mistook a pair of lines delineating one fold of the serpent and the
inside of Laocoön’s right leg for an extra teardrop-shaped loop of serpent next to the scrotum, an error
that he had not made in the related pencil drawing or in his later annotated engraving of the subject.</p>
          <p>If Blake used squaring to reduce the images and counter-proofing to transfer them to the 
<hi rend="i">Cyclopedia</hi> plate, the lines that appeared on the copper should have been expressive enough to
prevent gross errors. At one point I hypothesized that Blake might have used a pantograph or some similar
device to reduce the image in his drawing to fit the layout of the plate, thereby creating lines so
inexpressive that they could lead to such a mistake. (Even if a pantograph makes a line in exactly the right
place, which it usually doesn’t, the line often lacks the critical variations in tone and thickness that
allow us to understand what it represents.) But I found no evidence that Blake or other engravers used
pantographs regularly, perhaps because these devices weren’t sophisticated enough to do such delicate
copying. If his eyesight was worse than the eyeglasses preserved at the Fitzwilliam suggest, I thought next,
Blake might have resorted to a loupe, which would have restricted his field of vision so severely that he
couldn’t see what he was working on in context.</p>
          <p>After reading <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> I understand that Blake must have
used squaring to make reductions, but that he then used some combination of calking (which is a little like
using carbon paper), tracing, reversed tracing, and/or counterproofing to transfer designs to the plate. Both
calking and tracing tend to produce somewhat inexpressive lines—calked lines are particularly likely to
mislead, in that they are inexact in both position and strength. Blake probably lost track of the lines of
Laocoön’s leg at the calking stage, just as a calked image of a mournful angel must have suggested an owl
at an early phase in engraving page 23 of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (In Grant, et al., the drawing is
NT44, the finished plate NT13E; the owl proof is reproduced as page 13E in the Proofs section of Volume
2).</p>
          <p>One reason why Viscomi goes to so much trouble to show that Blake did not (or, in some cases
could not) use transfer methods to create most relief plates for illuminated printing is in order to debunk
once again the persistent fallacy that Blake wrote his texts forward and then mechanically reversed them onto
the plate so that they would print forward. This is not the occasion for reiterating the debate on this
point—it has been over for 14 years, despite Bo Ossian Lindberg’s attempt to revive it in his review of
Essick’s <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>—but Viscomi goes beyond beating the dead horse to argue that the
continued presence of the aromatic carcass of the transfer theory has kept us from understanding 
<hi rend="i">why</hi> as well as <hi rend="i">how</hi> Blake made illuminated books. Transfer theories, in
Viscomi’s view, reflect the widespread eighteenth-century assumption that all printmaking processes are
essentially reproductive—that is, mere mechanisms for replicating art that “really” exists in another
medium—and they misrepresent illuminated printing by separating composition from production, illumination
from text, visual art from verbal, inspiration from execution. Viscomi argues that relief etching offered an
unpremeditated, autographic and organic alternative to existing reproductive and mechanistic media. It is
essentially drawing and writing (backward) on copper—a medium in which the artist composes text, lays out
the page, and illustrates it, working directly on the copper without a final draft of texts or designs on
paper (obviously the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> were mostly or completely written in advance, but Viscomi thinks
they are exceptional rather than typical).</p>
          <pb id="p29-33" n="33"/>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>, Essick suggested that Blake used a fine brush and a combination
of oil and tallow to write his texts and draw his designs on the copper. Viscomi argues persuasively that this
mixture would be difficult to use for writing text and unsatisfactory as a resist. He instead follows Linnell,
who reported that Blake used a version of ordinary stopping solution, probably thickened asphaltum varnish,
ground with linseed oil and diluted with turpentine. Viscomi also contends that Blake used a quill pen rather
than a brush to write his texts, but I am skeptical on this point. I can’t make a quill write anything like
a Blakean script, whether it is cut with a sharp spreading point or a square or oblique one, whether writing
backward or forward; judging from the quill-written facsimile texts that Viscomi offers, he can’t quite do
it either. Blake’s characteristic fluent cursive script and even the larger examples of his fussier upright
Roman display an immensely complex pattern of thicks and thins that seems most consistent with Essick’s
pointed brush; the texts written by Viscomi often duplicate the basic letterforms of Blake’s texts but the
strokes appear to be uniform in thickness. I will not be surprised if it turns out that Blake used more than
one tool to write with, just as he used several different scripts. A quill might well have produced the tiny
letters (without noticeable thicks and thins) of some of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> But until
someone demonstrates true Blakean scripts that have been etched in copper and printed, we won’t know for
certain how Blake did them.</p>
          <p>In addition to writing and drawing in resist, Blake worked on illuminated plates in several other
ways, some of which involved transferring designs (not texts). Even in the early illuminated books Blake
employed a variety of means for modifying the designs drawn in resist upon the plate. In most cases he simply
treated the applied resist as if it were a conventional etching ground and scratched through it before the
plate was etched, which usually printed as narrow white lines in the midst of the black areas created by the
resist. Elsewhere he worked with a burin on the plate surface after etching the design; the effect is similar,
but it may produce distinctive white lines running through the border left by the etching dam.</p>
          <p>Blake also used two processes that Viscomi identifies with the confusing memoranda on the
techniques of “woodcut on pewter” and “woodcut on copper” (Erdman 694). Both are means of producing
white lines or white spaces on a full layer of conventional etching ground, and are called “woodcuts”
because they are printed in relief as woodcuts are. “Woodcut on pewter,” as Viscomi sees it, is a
technique in which the artist transfers a design by calking or counterproofing and then simply scrapes away
both ground and underlying metal to produce a design composed of white areas surrounded by black (the ground
here is not a resist but rather facilitates transferring the design and heightening the contrast between
scraped and unscraped metal). Similarly, Viscomi argues that Blake’s “woodcut on copper” is the
equivalent of modern white-line etching, and involves scraping or scratching away at a resist on copper and
then etching the exposed metal to print whites (rather than blacks as in conventional intaglio etching).</p>
          <p>These two processes are mechanically similar to Blake’s techniques for modifying designs drawn
in resist, described above, but (and I think I’m getting this right) they are distinguishable because they
employ an area of full ground, they necessarily involve a preliminary design (though it can be sketched on the
plate itself rather than transferred), they require slightly different tools, and their white lines and spaces
delineate primary forms. Although Viscomi’s case is fairly persuasive that these techniques are those called
“woodcut on pewter” and “woodcut on copper” in Blake’s elliptical memoranda, I hope this terminology
does not catch on outside of this book: here it helps to make important distinctions between the various
white-line techniques, and wrenches some sense out of the memoranda, but the terms would be needlessly
confusing in most other contexts, and even Viscomi sometimes uses them in ways that invite
misunderstanding.</p>
          <p>Once the copper printing plate was etched and otherwise satisfactory Blake could make major
changes in the appearance of the image it generated by employing color-printing. For relief-printed
illuminated books, this involved painting viscous colored inks on the raised and/or etched surfaces of the
plate with a stump brush and printing all colors at once. Viscomi thus treats Blake’s color-printing as a
relief-printing variant upon a common eighteenth-century mode of color-printing, the single-plate intaglio
process called <hi rend="i">à la poupée</hi>, in which colored inks were applied (often rather
approximately) to different areas of the intaglio plate.</p>
          <p>In his discussion of the various printing processes used to create illuminated books from etched
plates, Viscomi ingeniously reconstructs the presswork involved in printing specific books. He shows that in
many cases Blake must have printed several copies of each book at a time. Most Blake scholars (including me)
have underestimated the amount of work involved in setting up the press to print, and therefore assumed that
Blake could have done so casually, whenever he felt like it, or when he got an order for a book. Viscomi
argues persuasively, citing both practical experience and the evidence of the books themselves, that in most
cases Blake must have printed the books in small editions of 10 or so, rather than one at a time. This a major
discovery, but in his enthusiastic pursuit of the demon Error, Viscomi is a little too hard on others who have
written about the subject. Several times, he cites someone as another dastardly perpetuator of the canard that
each copy was printed separately, when the unfortunate citee merely implied this in arguing that each copy was
unique in an editorially significant sense, that copies were finished differently, or that they were finished
at different times.</p>
          <p>Viscomi is so zealously attentive to his argument that he doesn’t always seem to recall
something he clearly knows very well: in Blake’s case, printing a copy of an illuminated
<pb id="p29-34" n="34"/>
book is not the same as producing a copy of it, which for colored copies must include the entire process of
assembling and finishing with pen, brush, ink and watercolors. Collective finishing as well as printing
appears to have occurred, but unlike printing, finishing and assembling could take place at any time, and
revisions, reassembling, and refinishing were always possible. Strictly speaking, editors must be prepared to
weigh the authority of each instance in which Blake was apparently satisfied that his work on any feature,
even a “blur or mark,” was complete or complete enough, and that may include hundreds of distinguishable
instances in the production of a single page of a single copy of a single book. We will have to decide which
differences are important and which are not. But even without dwelling on the infinite regression of
“completeness,” editors of illuminated books can’t afford to put undue emphasis on “editions” when
they are as small and as various as these. Even uncolored copies printed at the same time in the same ink on
the same paper and bound in the same order will manifest differences that may be significant from an editorial
point of view: the printed punctuation (at least) always varies, and textual editors and those discussing
illuminations will have to continue to think about as many copies as possible even if many of them were
printed at the same time. Overemphasizing the uniqueness of copies encourages certain kinds of critical
foolishness, as Viscomi shows, but he also shows that critics have been wrong in other ways when they thought
about too few copies.</p>
          <p>Even if this prophet isn’t always gracious with Error, he seems to be on good terms with Truth:
the evidence for small “editions” is abundant and various, now that he has pointed it out. Viscomi’s
account of the ways in which the work of printing, finishing, and assembling books must have proceeded or
could have proceeded is detailed and plausible. Everyone who writes about the illuminated books will have to
reckon with this theory. Most of the time Blake, working with Catherine as his “printer’s devil,” must
have printed multiple copies of each page (often in pairs); then the two of them colored the pages together
<hi rend="i">en masse</hi> (often perfunctorily) and only later assembled them into books. Casually finished
books might subsequently be touched up or even elaborately refinished at another time, as some late copies of
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> were, but most pages of most books were never the object of sustained individual
attention and their collective effect in a particular book may or may not have been in the mind of the
colorist (who may or may not have been Blake himself). The account of Blake’s publishing process here has
profound consequences for all those who think about editing illuminated books; what was already one of the
most difficult of editorial problems is made even more richly problematic. Although Viscomi’s instinct for
polemic in these chapters is sometimes distracting, he has provided the groundwork and much of the framework
for the next, more sophisticated phases of editorial theory about Blake.</p>
          <p>In the second half of the book Viscomi discusses recoverable printing history for each of the
illuminated books in detail; in every instance his account makes new sense out of old puzzles, and often the
puzzles melt away entirely. Some of the information in these chapters has already been summarized in the new
Blake Trust facsimiles that Viscomi helped to edit, but much of it is entirely new. He leaves few applecarts
unturned, redating almost the entire illuminated canon in various ways, and he indicates the consequences of
his theories for editors and even biographers. All of this is important and some of it is even exciting, but
as one might expect, several of the arguments make heavy reading if you aren’t immediately engaged in the
questions they address, as in the latter part of Chapter 32, “The Production and Evolution of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: 1804-1818,” which uncovers this complicated process in exhausting (but not exhaustive)
detail. A very useful five-page Appendix charts the hypothetical publishing history of all 21 illuminated
books from 1788 to the posthumous copies, identifying the approximate date of printing (not finishing) for
each copy. Most readers will find themselves referring to this chart regularly whenever they are working on
illuminated books.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> is handsomely laid out and sturdily constructed
in an oblong format, perhaps in deliberate imitation of Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake.</hi> It is
generously illustrated with 312 good-quality monochrome halftones that convey as much information as such
illustrations can, which is to say barely enough, and includes 13 color plates that do only a little better.
It would have been impossible to publish this book for less than $50 if more or better color had been used,
and I doubt that Princeton will make much money even as things are; the problem is that many of Viscomi’s
arguments necessarily depend on attending to phenomena that aren’t easily seen even in good offset
reproductions. Perhaps when all the pages of all copies of the illuminated books are available in
color-corrected, high-resolution digital images, as envisioned by the scholars working on the electronic Blake
archive, Viscomi will assemble an elegant illustrated hypertext version of the publication chart in Appendix A
that will make everything as clear to us as it is to him.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Works Cited</title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP,
1980.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P,
1991.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Newly
rev. ed. Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1982.</p>
            <p>Grant, John E., et al., eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s</hi>
Night Thoughts. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1980.</p>
            <pb id="p29-35" n="35"/>
            <p>Lindberg, Bo Ossian. Review of <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker</hi>, by Robert N.
Essick. <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 15 (Winter 1981-82): 140-48.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated Prints.</hi> Manchester:
Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
