<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.1.punter</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David G. Riede, Oracles and Hierophants: Constructions of Romantic
Authority</title>
        <author n="Punter">David Punter</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Lauren G. Henry</name>
              <name>J.E.M. Latham</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
	<pb id="p29-29" n="29"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-1-0008">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David G. Riede, <hi rend="i">Oracles and Hierophants: Constructions of Romantic
Authority.</hi> Cornell University Press: Ithaca and London, 1991. 283 + xi pp.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>David <name>Punter</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>David Riede in this book seeks to trace the notion of romantic authority, to explore, in other
words, why and how it was that romantic poets felt that they could speak with apparent certainty on a range of
issues literary, societal, and psychological. He simultaneously, as it were, traces the thanatic fate of this
assumption of authority by arguing that in the cases of each of the three writers with whom he deals—Blake,
Wordsworth, and Coleridge—this structure of authority comes to loom so large over their texts that it in
effect transmutes them into the sources of a new cultural authoritarianism, which is in each case avidly
seized upon by other writers and critics who wish to convert their forebears into a “church,” an
unquestionable touchstone of knowledge and feeling; and that this “worship” of romantic attitudes persists
through literary criticism and pedagogy to the present day.</p>
          <p>Blake, Wordsworth and Coleridge, then, are the main figures here; in his final chapter Riede
turns more briefly to the second generation of romantics, principally in order to differentiate their work
from their predecessors’ and to bring out the readiness with which they questioned <hi rend="i">all</hi>
authority, in response first to a prevailing sense of political betrayal and second to the perceived
“treachery” of some of the earlier poets themselves; the argument here touches on and usefully
recontextualises wider issues of romantic irony.</p>
          <p>This is a book of extreme meticulousness, full of detail and of close reading, but I have to
confess that, although I was gripped from page to page, in the end I found it oddly unsatisfying. There were
two principal reasons for this. The first was the sheer amount of argument from other critics Riede uses to
buttress his points, argument which perhaps might be necessary if one were to assume a reader unversed in
criticism of the romantics, but to my mind somewhat redundant in view of the likely readership of the
book.</p>
          <p>But my other problem was more substantial, and has to do with the use Riede makes of his central
term, “authority.” In part this follows from a passage from Hannah Arendt which he quotes, to the effect
that true authority “is incompatible with persuasion, which presupposes equality and works through a process
of argumentation. Where arguments are used, authority is left in abeyance. Against the egalitarian order of
persuasion stands the authoritarian order, which is always hierarchical” (20).</p>
          <p>The problem here is that Arendt slides effortlessly between “authority” and the
“authoritarian.” This is an easy linguistic trope; but it is nonetheless incorrect. The notion of the
authoritarian has to do with unjustifiable authority arbitrarily exercised; without some alternative notion of
<hi rend="i">authority</hi> we have no means even to describe familial or educational process. There can be no
development or pedagogy without authority, correctly exercised and subjected to appropriate questioning and
testing. Such a notion of “correctness” may well be endlessly challengeable in practice, but that does not
mean that it can be removed from political or psychological agenda.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, it is not clear to me what poetry—or writing, or text—would look like in the
absence of a sense of authority, whether we regard this as in some sense integral or as reader-induced. Riede
suggests that the second generation of romantics were “antiauthoritarian” but that “Byron, Shelley, and
Keats still struggled in various ways to establish their own poetic authority, and consequently the authority
of poetry generally.” Well, of course they did: I do not see how you can write anything without founding it
upon <hi rend="i">some</hi> notion of authority, even if it is a matter of taking on the authority to
satirize, to destroy, to rip down. All of these are forms of authority, even if their relations to the
dominant formations of culture may be various. To Riede, it seems that this is not so:
<q>
The problem with our inherited models of Romantic authority, with the continuing Romantic assumptions of much
of our criticism, is that the ideals of an authoritative culture are ultimately authoritarian, and that the
practical effects of a self-validating but self-enclosed cultural minority are extremely limited. (278)
</q></p>
          <p>I have already said that I do not believe that an authoritative stance necessarily leads to
authoritarianism; I would want to add that the issue of the effects of a cultural minority will depend on far
greater political complexities than those spelled out here, complexities in the ideological positioning of
that minority and in the overall sociopolitical fabric
<pb id="p29-30" n="30"/>
of the formation under discussion. Some cultural minorities have guns; others brandish veils.</p>
          <p>This is a complex book, and to engage with the argument in more detail I shall pick out a single
thread in relation to each of the poets. Riede begins his chapter on Blake as follows:
<q>
William Blake is probably the most extreme case in the English literary tradition of a poet claiming and
representing the authority of absolute originality, of the inspired imaginative mind or, as he would put it,
of the “Poetic Genius.” (33)
</q></p>
          <p>In one sense an unexceptionable statement; yet if we look closely we can see this notion of
authority already deconstructing itself. Did Blake, who knew a great deal about the futility of a discourse of
origins, claim “absolute originality?” He may have claimed a unique connection to a realm of the
imagination, but with what <hi rend="i">contents</hi> was that realm already stocked? Can the relationship
with Milton, which Riede goes on to discuss at some length, be considered to have left 
<corr type="emend">Blake’s</corr> imagination in a pristine condition, or the inheritance from Boehme or
Michelangelo, or most important of all from the Bible? If we are to talk about authority here, we should
surely be thinking of it in terms not of originality but of <hi rend="i">access</hi>: we may consider every
writer as a mediator—just like any priest—yet even here it would not be clear to me that Blake 
<hi rend="i">consistently</hi> regarded himself as on the end of a unique hotline; or, even when he did, whether
he consistently thought that the messages coming down it were of much use to the world at large.</p>
          <p>For Riede, “the inescapable irony of Blake’s career is that his work,” being
“disseminated at a time when ‘literature’ was in various ways being constituted as an authoritative
cultural discourse . . . became a part of the institutionalised canon of literature.” This comment, claiming
as it does that the fate of Blake’s work is inextricably embedded in the “authoritarian” requirements of
the romantic canon, depends in turn for its validity on what we think of a point of Foucault’s which Riede
mentions earlier, namely, that “‘literature’ emerged in response to the profound skepticism of the
Enlightenment, to the death of God and the consequent loss of ‘that primary, that absolutely initial, word
upon which the infinite movement of discourse was founded and by which it was limited.’” Henceforth,
Foucault continues, “language was to grow with no point of departure, no end, and no promise. It is the
traversal of this futile yet fundamental space that the text of literature traces from day to day.”</p>
          <p>The “literary,” then, is a substitute discourse and the romantics are the pioneers of the
“scrawl over the abyss.” I think the problem here is one of hypostasization: this is an interesting point
<hi rend="i">only</hi> when one’s concern is to identify the cultural construct we call “literature.” If
our concern is at all broader, with the interrelations between, say, literature, religion, and authority, then
we have a larger field to traverse, one where Milton might again assume a critical importance, one where oral
as well as written traditions take their part in this vast series of displacements which indeed embraces in a
particular way the whole articulated field of writing and the religious sense.</p>
          <p>There is something more to be said. Even if we are to agree with Nietzsche and Foucault about the
collapse of <hi rend="i">logos</hi>, it does not appear to me that the resultant (re)appearance of the abyss
is unpopulated; certainly the abyss in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> is not. When
authoritarian monotheisms go into inevitable crisis, what is left in the detritus may nevertheless be a host
of little gods, the emergence of polytheism and animism, a freed god behind every tree, or in some cases
locked inside, a populous world of which Blake, Wordsworth, and later Yeats were certainly aware. When
Mohammed came to Mecca to institute an organized Arab state, he cleared the central place of worship of its
hundreds of tribal gods; only thus could the authoritarian state at that historical moment be instituted, and
only in the iteration that there is <hi rend="i">one</hi> god could it survive the pressing world of
dissolutions, the counter-“authorities” from which alone we might expect salvation from the violence and
fossilization of the state apparatus.</p>
          <p>On Wordsworth, Riede has fascinating things to say on the motif of wandering, and on suffering
and sympathy, but his general argument is perhaps best summarized when he says that Wordsworth’s
participation in the
<q>
invention of the vast shadowy terrain of an autonomous self as at once the object and subject of literature is
part of the invention of “literature” as an autonomous yet somehow authoritative discourse, of literature
as an entity transcending history. (162)
</q></p>
          <p>Here Riede is following, as he says, Clifford Siskin’s admirable identification of romanticism
with “a penetrating gaze revealing, actually making, the depths within”; but I would still want to be wary
of the notion that such a terrain can be “invented” rather than, shall we say, “reconfigured.” The
“making” of the unitary self cannot be a formation <hi rend="i">ab initio</hi>; rather, it comes to being
in an already existent field of alternative constructions, just as does monotheism, in this case a field
including many versions of the self, including ones which rely on multiplicity, plurality of selves, in the
sense developed by Deleuze and Guattari’s so-called “schizanalysis.” This, of course, is one of the
haunting fears of romanticism, where the continuing existence of “multiplicity” exerts constant pressure
on the formation of the unitary self, which itself can be seen to come to fill the space left by the
disappearance of the singleness of god. Riede’s earlier comments on the ambiguities of madness in
romanticism are very much to the point.</p>
          <p>On Coleridge perhaps I can also supply a single quotation which seems to me to show the tenor of
Riede’s approach:
<pb id="p29-31" n="31"/>
	<q>
Coleridge never succeeded in finding an adequate poetic authority for himself, but from around 1800 to his
death he sought ways to justify a poetic authority for others—for Wordsworth, Milton, Shakespeare—on the
basis of a fully integrated self that retained its free agency, yet somehow spoke, as the Ancient Mariner did,
with an inspiration that transcended personal experience. (171)
</q></p>
          <p>This brings us back again to the “fully integrated self” as a site of endeavor and danger,
yet in the course of doing so it seems to me to obliterate the notion of writing as a matter of
undecidability. There is no space here to discuss the ambiguities of the concept of “success” or
“achievement” in the context of Coleridge, nor even to open the question as to whether it is appropriate
to use the name-of-Coleridge as the overarching sign for an “engagement” with authority and the self which
was clearly writ in much larger cultural terms around the figure of the individual suffering poet/philosopher;
but what can, I think, be said is that the notion of an inspiration that transcends personal experience is an
expression of an inescapable paradox; the paradox which we have sometimes, through many historical windings
and across many cultures, called “soul.” Our engagements with such a concept, such an experience which in
itself always points beyond experience, will always be hovering, they will always catch us at thresholds, the
thresholds which Coleridge approaches with such courage and despair in “Christabel” and “Kubla Khan”;
whether the inability to pass over a threshold which would “alter everything” represents a lack of success
is perhaps an imponderable question, for under every threshold is buried a forgotten god who will exact a
price in personal and textual transformation for our projected <hi rend="i">hubris.</hi></p>
          <p>The field which Riede traverses is a crucial one; it appears to me that in the context of the
romantic writers a supplementary approach might be through the notion of inner and outer worlds and the
problematic flow of authority between them. An emblematic text might be “The Mental Traveller”: whence
springs the observer’s authority here? From walking, we might say, on the wild side; but also and with
painful simultaneity from suffering the necessity of transferring these insights across an awesome threshold
of communication. The perception, the <hi rend="i">pathos</hi>, we might say, is clothed in words, indeed in
the garments of lamentation insofar as they invariably represent loss of authenticity, of authority; and the
result is always worse than we could imagine, because as the frail vessel emerges from the reeds it often
seems as though there is nothing left inside the clothing, we see a “signature” with no document, presumed
authority with nothing left to authorize, an already self-consumed artefact. If there is any truth in this,
then it would apply in differing ways to <hi rend="i">all</hi> writing; when we look at the romantics in
particular, perhaps the <hi rend="i">differance</hi> we sense is not in this basic structure of loss, which is
the ground of all searchings for authority, but in its reassimilation into the text, in the manifestation of a
certain agonizing level of self-awareness; a certainty that authority is problematic, floating only
temporarily on a dark sea while other, unnameable sails rise over the horizon.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
