<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Physiognomy of Lavater’s Essays: False Imprints, “1789” and “1792”</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Lauren G. Henry</name>
              <name>J.E.M. Latham</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-1-0005">
        <pb id="p29-16" n="16"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Physiognomy of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>: False
              Imprints, “1789” and “1792”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr. </docAuthor><ref target="n35"
              type="note">1</ref></byline>
          <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I am particularly grateful to Stewart Naunton, whose
            query initiated the enquiries on which this essay is based; to Robert Essick; to Detlef
            Dörrbecker, who gave me, inter alia, a complete record of the watermarks in his copy of
            the 1789-98 edition; to Joseph Viscomi, who provided remarkably shrewd advice on an
            early draft of this essay; and to Mary Lynn Johnson, who is working on a long-term
            publishing history of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> up to the first English
            editions and who generously shared her information with me.</note>
          <p>As to that false appearance which appears to the reasoner . . . it is a delusion of
            Ulro.<lb/>
 William Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (1804[-08?] pl. 28, ll. 15-16</p>
          <p>John Caspar Lavater’s attempt to systematize his observations on human physiognomy into
            a kind of science in his <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> created great
            excitement among his contemporaries. As <hi rend="i">The Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, LXXI
            (Feb. 1801): 184, commented: 
			<q> In the enthusiasm with which they were studied and
              admired, they were thought as necessary in every family as even the Bible itself. A
              servant would, at one time, scarcely be hired till the descriptions and engravings of
              Lavater had been consulted, in <hi rend="i">careful</hi> comparison with the line and
              features of the young man’s or woman’s countenance. </q></p>
          <p>The Captain of the “Beagle,” it is said, almost rejected the young Darwin because of
            the shape of his nose,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">2</ref>
and “in many places, where
            the study of human character from the face became an epidemic, the people went masked
            through the streets.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">2</hi> John Graham, “Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>: A Checklist,”
                <hi rend="i">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi> 55 (1961): 297; this
              and the essay on Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> in England are reprinted,
              apparently without change, in his <hi rend="i">Lavater’s Essays on Physiognomy</hi>: A
              Study in the History of Ideas (Berne, Frankfort am Main, Las Vegas, 1979). <p>By 1810,
                there were 16 versions of the <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> in German, 15 in French,
                2 in the US, 2 in Russian, 1 in Dutch, 1 in Italian, 20 in English, and by the 1940s
                there had been 160 publications of it (298-99). Graham lists the Hunter folio
                editions as (1) 1789-98; (2) 1792[-98]; (3) 1789-1810, in which the second and third
                entries seem to me to be significantly inaccurate. On 27 March 1962, Graham wrote to
                me that the source of his information for the 1792[-98] edition was “Auction,
                1945-1950” and for the 1789-1810 edition was the catalogues of the Boston Public
                Library and the John Rylands Library.</p></note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Encyclopaedia Britannica</hi>, Eighth Edition (1853-60), sive
              Physiognomy, cited by Graham, “Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> in England,”
                <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi> 22 (1961): 562.</note></p>
          <p>One of the handsomest works printed during the great age of the illustrated book in
            England was John Caspar Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, translated by
            Henry Hunter. It was “A sumptuous Edition”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n38" type="note">4</ref> issues
            in five folio volumes<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">5</ref>
with “more than eight hundred
            engravings . . . executed by, or under the inspection of Thomas Holloway,” and published
            by John Murray, by the translator, and by the supervising engraver in 41 Fascicles over
            11 years, from January 1789 to March 1799. (As the three titlepages are dated 1789,
            1792, and 1798, this edition is identified here as that of 1789-98.) 
                <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">4</hi> William Thomas Lowndes, <hi rend="i">The Bibliographer’s
Manual of
                English Literature</hi>, rev. Henry G. Bohn, Part V (London: Henry G. Bohn, 1860)
              1321.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The five volumes consist of Vol. I,
              Vol. II Parts i and ii, and Vol. III Parts i and ii, and the second Parts of Vol.
              II-III have no titlepages.</note></p>
          <p>The First Edition (1789-98)</p>
          <p>It was recorded on its titlepages as:</p>
          <p>ESSAYS | ON | PHYSIOGNOMY, | DESIGNED TO PROMOTE | THE KNOWLEDGE AND THE LOVE OF
            MANKIND. | BY | JOHN CASPAR LAVATER, | CITIZEN OF ZURICH, AND MINISTER OF THE GOSPEL. |
            ILLUSTRATED BY MORE THAN | EIGHT HUNDRED ENGRAVINGS ACCURATELY COPIED; | AND SOME
            DUPLICATES ADDED FROM ORIGINALS. | EXECUTED BY, OR UNDER THE INSPECTION OF, | THOMAS
            HOLLOWAY. | TRANSLATED FROM THE FRENCH |BY| HENRY HUNTER, D. D. | MINISTER OF THE SCOTS
            CHURCH, LONDON-WALL.|-| <hi rend="i">GOD CREATED MAN AFTER HIS OWN IMAGE.</hi> | - | [3
            vols. but bound in five parts] VOLUME I. | [Vignette] | LONDON: PRINTED FOR JOHN MURRAY,
            NO. 32, FLEET-STREET; H. HUNTER, D.D. CHARLES’S- | SQUARE; AND T. HOLLOWAY, NO. 11,
            BACHE’S-ROW, HOXTON. M DCC LXXXIX [1789].| VOLUME II [bound in 2 parts]|. . .|. H.
            HUNTER, D.D. BETHNAL GREEN ROAD . . . MDCCXCII [1792]. &lt;See illus. 1&gt; VOLUME III
            [bound in 2 parts]. | [Vignette] | LONDON. PRINTED FOR MURRAY AND HIGHLEY, NO. 32,
            FLEETSTREET; H. HUNTER, D.D.| BETHNAL-GREEN ROAD . . . MDCCXCVIII [1798].</p>
          <p>The description on the titlepages of Vol. I (1789), Vol. II (1792), and Vol. III (1798)
            of “MORE THAN EIGHT HUNDRED ENGRAVINGS” was, however, greatly exaggerated, for, when the
            copperplates were sold in 1818 (see below), there were only 537 of them. However, the
            exaggeration was apparently not noticed until 1799, when a somewhat lame note on
            “Errata” was added to the Directions to the Binder (bound at the end of Vol. III, Part
            ii and generously pointed out to me by Mary Lynn Johnson): 
			<q> In the Title pages,
                dele[<hi rend="i">te</hi>] ‘Upwards of Eight Hundred.” This error was not discovered
              before the titles were printed off, and it was thought better to let it pass than
              deprive the purchasers of fine impressions of the Vignettes which they contain.
			</q></p>
          <pb id="p29-17" n="17"/>
          <figure n="LavaterPhysiognomyFirstEdition.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="387">
            <head>1 J. C. Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> [first edition] Vol. II
              (1792) titlepage &lt;GEB&gt;.</head>
            <figDesc>Note that in the imprint the first “H.” of “H. Hunter” is just above the “H”
of
              “HOXTON.”</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="LavaterPhyisiognomyThirdEdition.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="420">
            <head>2 Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> [third edition] Vol. II (1792
              [i.e., 1818?]), titlepage &lt;Princeton University Library&gt;.</head>
            <figDesc>Note that the first “H.” of “H. HUNTER” in the imprint is <hi rend="i">not</hi>
              just above the “H” of “HOXTON.”</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>From its first appearance, the work was admired for the beauty of the printing and the
            engravings. It was described in <hi rend="i">The Monthly Magazine</hi>, VIII (Jan.
            1800): 988, as “the finest print book that ever appeared in this or any other country,”
            and T. F. Dibdin said that “the copper plates . . . have scarcely been equalled.”<ref
              target="n40" type="note">6</ref> It generated additional interest when the leaders of
            the Blake revival noticed that it had prints by William Blake. Blake’s part in it was
            recorded by, inter alia, William Haines in 1863,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n41" type="note">7</ref> A.
            G. B. Russell in 1906,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">8</ref>
Geoffrey Keynes in 1921,<ref
              target="n43" type="note">9</ref> and G. E. Bentley, Jr. &amp; Martin K. Nurmi in
              1964.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">6</hi> T. F.
              Dibdin, <hi rend="i">The Bibliographical Decameron</hi> (London: The Author, 1817)
              398, 399.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, 
                <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, “Pictor Ignotus”</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1863) 2: 260
              (catalogue of Blake’s engravings by William Haines, recording only two of the four
              Blake engravings; for the identity of the compiler, see <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
              [1977] 815).</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Archibald G. B. Russell, 
                <hi rend="i">The Engravings of William Blake</hi> (Boston &amp; NY: Houghton Mifflin,
              1912) 152-53, recording three Blake engravings.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William Blake</hi> (NY:
The
              Grolier Club, 1921) 233-34, recording three Blake plates.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi
                rend="s">10</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr. &amp; Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake
                Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1964) 137-38,
              recording three Blake plates. The fourth plate was pointed out in “A ‘New’ Blake
              Engraving in Lavater’s Physiognomy,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 6 (1972):
              48-49.</note></p>
          <p>The work suffered in a number of ways as it passed through the press. For one thing,
            the original publisher, John Murray [I] died on 6 November 1793, not long after the
            titlepage to the second volume had been issued (1792). During the minority of his son
            John Murray II (1778-1843) and for a few years beyond, the firm was knows as Murray
            &amp; Highley (1793-1803), and the only Lavater titlepage issued during this period (for
            Volume III) bears the names of Murray &amp; Highley.</p>
          <p>For another, the cost of the engravings, the major expense of the work, far exceeded
            the receipts from the subscriptions for the fascicles, at least for a time. The cost of
            engraving the copperplates must have been from £3 for small, simple outlines to more
            than £100 for large, ambitious plates. If the 174 large plates averaged only £40 each
            (an exceedingly modest estimate), they alone would have cost almost £7,000. When John
            Murray [I] died in November 1793, perhaps 60% of the engravings had been finished,<ref
              target="n45" type="note">11</ref> but the firm still owed thousands of pounds to the
              engravers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">11</hi>
              Most of the plates have no imprint, so it is very difficult to ascertain how many had
              been finished by November 1793.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">12</hi> In “the
              publication of Lavater’s work on Physiognomy, the engraving of the plates caused the
              principal part of the loss. The executors put the case to arbitration, and were
              eventually compelled to pay out of the estate the sum of £3,900” (Samuel Smiles, 
                <hi rend="i">A Publisher and his Friends</hi>: Memoir and Correspondence of the Late
              John Murray, with an Account of the Rise and Progress of the House, 1768-1843 [London:
              John Murray, 1891] 1: 28).</note></p>
          <pb id="p29-18" n="18"/>
          <p>Despite these difficulties, the work was finally finished in 1799, and a very handsome
            work it was. This was the only visage of the work with Blake’s prints known, or at least
            recorded, for many years.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Other Editions (“1792” and “1810”)</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>However, there are two other folio editions of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on
                Physiognomy</hi> as translated by Hunter, whose features are as handsome as those of
              the original.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">13</ref> Only in
1977, more than a century
              after Blake’s part in Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> was first noticed, or at
              least recorded, was it remarked in print that there are two other editions dated 1792
              and 1810 of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> bearing Blake’s prints.
              And even then it was not noticed how odd it is to have a complete edition dated 1792
              finished before the first edition of 1789-98 was accomplished. The somewhat feeble
              conclusion offered at the time was the “The 1792 issue was presumably for late
              subscribers, with the titlepage of Volume III ante-dated” (<hi rend="i">Blake
                Books</hi> [1977] 594). <note id="n47"><hi rend="s">13</hi> According to Lowndes,
                Part V, 1321, “Some copies were subsequently issued with the name of Stockdale as
                publisher [<hi rend="i">i.e., in 1810</hi>]; these are inferior in impression to the
                first edition. . . .” However, the type, impression, and plates in the 1810 edition
                appear to me to be quite worthy of the edition of 1789-98.</note></p>
            <p>The chief printed distinctions between the first edition of the Hunter translation
              and its successors are little more than in the dates and the publishers on the
              titlepage (John Murray in 1789-92-98, John Murray in 1792, Thomas Stockdale in 1810).
              In general, the “1792” edition is more like the first edition of 1789-98 than is that
              of 1810, as one might expect. The titlepages of the first Hunter edition (see illus.
              1) and those of “1792” (see illus. 2) claim to have “UPWARDS OF EIGHT HUNDRED PLATES,”
              whereas <corr type="emend">that dated</corr> 1810 omits “UPWARDS OF EIGHT HUNDRED PLATES” &lt;see illus.
                3&gt;.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">14</hi> G.
                E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977):
                593-95.</note></p>
            <p>There seemed, then, to be three folio editions of the Hunter translation of Lavater’s
                <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, the first issued in fascicles in 1789-99
              with titlepages dated 1789 (Vol. I), 1792 (Vol. II), and 1798 (Vol. III), the second
              in 1792, and the third in 1810. And the Blake prints did not seem to change
              significantly in any of them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">15</ref> At last our
              understanding of Lavater’s book seemed to have stabilized. 
                  <note id="n49"><hi rend="s">15</hi> “The Blake plates are not changed” 
(<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 594);
                see also Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
                  Illustrations</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991) 41-42.</note></p>
            <p>“I discern thee other then thou seem’st.” Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise
              Regained</hi>, I, 248<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">16</hi> The phrase is used in James T. Wills, “‘For I discern thee Other Then
                Thou Seem’st’: An Extra Illustration for Blake’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>
                Series,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 8 (1980): 109-19.</note></p>
            <figure n="LavaterPhysiognomySecondEdition.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="371">
              <head>3 Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> [second edition] Vol. II
                (1810) titlepage &lt;GEB&gt;.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Then, when the last changes in the text of <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>
              were being sent off to the press in the autumn of 1993, I received a puzzled letter
              from Stewart Naunton (then unknown to me) who had been given a set of the 1792
              Lavater, and, in making a more meticulous examination of it than any professional
              bibliographer apparently had done, Naunton had discovered that what he had was a
              rogue. Though the titlepage plainly said 1792 (or at least MDCCXCII), the leaves had
              watermarks of “1806,” “1812,” and “1817”—and none of the watermarks exhibited a
date
              consonant with the “1792” on the titlepage.</p>
            <p>This was very worrying. Was the “1792” set described an unique rogue?—but how could
              just one copy be printed thus? Were there other “1792” sets with anomalous
              water-marks? Perhaps all “1792” sets were in disguise like the one described to me,
              bastards of c. 1818? (just a few years after the legitimate 1810 edition) masquerading
              as legitimate heirs of the 1789-98 edition.</p>
            <p>Further, the “1792” set reported to me used paper in a very curious pattern, rarely
              exhibiting more than a few sheets of the same paper together at a time. This seemed a
              remarkably irregular, not the say inefficient, way to use paper. Did other sets
              duplicate these oddities?</p>
            <pb id="p29-19" n="19"/>
            <figure n="LavaterPhysiognomyFirstType.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="394">
              <head>4 Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> [first edition] Vol. I
                (1789), p. 31 &lt;GEB&gt;.</head>
              <figDesc>The setting of type is virtually identical in the first edition of the Hunter
                translation (1789), on watermarked 1794 and 1795 paper, and on the third edition
                (1818?), watermarked 1817 (see illus. 5).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="LavaterPhysiognomyThirdType.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="358">
                <head>5 Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> [third edition] Vol. I
                  (1792 [i.e., 1818?]), p. 31 &lt;Princeton University Library&gt;.</head>
                <figDesc>The setting of type here is scarcely distinguishable from that in the first
                  edition (1789) (see illus. 4).</figDesc>
        	</figure>
        	<p>I immediately wrote off to all the institutions which are recorded in the 
                <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Short Title Catalogue</hi> and the <hi rend="i">National
                Union Catalog</hi> as having sets of the “1792” edition<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">17</ref> to enquire about their watermarks. 
<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The
                libraries of the University of Chicago, Cooper-Hewitt Museum, Duke University, Emory
                University, the University of Iowa (reported by Mary Lynn Johnson), the University
                of Kentucky, Liverpool University, McGill University, Newcastle University, Oregon
                State University, and Princeton University are recorded as having the “1792” set of
                Lavater. I am grateful for the information generously supplied by the librarians of
                the University of Chicago, the Cooper-Hewitt Museum, Duke University, Emory
                University, the University of Kentucky, Stewart Naunton, Oregon State University,
                and Princeton University.</note></p>
            <p>Of course making a record of all the watermarks in five fat volumes is immensely
              laborious—and a feat which apparently no bibliographer had previously attempted. I
              expected to receive from the libraries to which I had written no more than a sampling
              of watermarks to ascertain whether they were or were not consonant with the “1792”
              date on the titlepage, and this of course was what I received from most institutions
              which replied. But J. Samuel Hammond, Rare Book Librarian at Duke University, recorded
              every watermark in the first volume, including laid or wove paper without letters or
              numbers, and Karen Herbaugh, Student Assistant at the Kerr Library of Oregon State
              University, provided me with a list of watermarks on every leaf in all five volumes. I am deeply
              in the debt of all the librarians who responded so generously to my queries and
              especially to Hammond and Herbaugh.</p>
            <p>The results are yet more curious than my first warning had led me to expect. In the
              first place, a very surprising variety of paper was used. The text is on paper
              watermarked “1 7” (4.5 cm apart, in the middle of the margin), “1801,” “1804,”
“1806,”
              “1809,” “1817”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">18</ref>
plus “II” or “TH,” “S,” “WL,” “95
              LEPARD,” and “LEPARD” (all wove paper except “LEPARD,” which has chain lines), and the
              prints are on paper watermarked “1806,” “1812,” “1813,” “1814,” “LEPARD,”
“SMITH,” “W
              SPEAR 1815,” and “JWHATM,” and “1794 | J WHATMAN.” More than one of these post-1800
              watermarks appear in sets of the “1792” edition in the libraries of the University of
              Chicago, the Cooper-Hewitt Museum, Duke University, Emory University, the University
              of Iowa, the University of Kentucky, Liverpool University, Oregon State University,
              Princeton University, and Stewart Naunton, and there is every reason to expect that
              all sets have a similar pattern of watermarks. And none of 
<pb id="p29-20" n="20"/>
              the paper watermarked “1801,” “1804,” “1806,” “1812,” “1813,” “1814,”
and “1817 can
              have been used at the time of the 1792 date on the titlepage. 
                  <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Some watermarks of “181” are reported, but I suspect
that this
                represents “1817,” the last digit of which is often hard to see or decipher.
                Occasionally “S” or “II” is visible on the same leaf as “1817.”</note></p>
            <p>In the genuine first edition of 1789-98, the only watermarks in the text are
              “LEPARD,” “Lepard,” and “LW,” with occasionally “17” and “95,” all on laid
paper (at
              least in my own set and that of the University of Toronto). In the 1810 edition, the
              only watermark in the text of my set is “1806” plus “II” once in every gathering of
              wove paper, and these watermarks too recur in the “1792” edition.</p>
            <p>The second oddity is the way in which the paper was used. In the Princeton set of
              “1792,” which I went down to examine myself, successive gatherings are often on
              distinctly different paper. For instance, in Volume I, gatherings P-T are on wove
              paper with “1804,” “1806,” “S,” “1817,” and without watermark, and laid paper
without
              watermark. This is a very peculiar way to print, with a different kind of paper in the
              stack for each gathering.</p>
            <p>But in fact, the situation is even odder than this, for apparently there were no
              stacks of “1804” and “1806” and “1817” paper. Instead, each stack of sheets was
              apparently of mixed watermarks for each gathering. For instance, the paper for four
              successive gatherings (G-K) in Volume I of the “1792” sets in Duke, Oregon State, and
              Princeton looked like this:</p>
            <table rows="4" cols="5">
              <head>Table: Watermark Distribution by Signature in Volume I (“1792”)</head>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>G</cell>
                <cell>H</cell>
                <cell>I</cell>
                <cell>K</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Duke</cell>
                <cell>1817</cell>
                <cell>S</cell>
                <cell>1817</cell>
                <cell>1806</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Oregon State</cell>
                <cell>1801</cell>
                <cell>1806</cell>
                <cell>1806</cell>
                <cell>1801</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Princeton</cell>
                <cell>TH</cell>
                <cell>S</cell>
                <cell>wove</cell>
                <cell>laid</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <p>And other gatherings show similar absence of pattern. Clearly the stack of sheets for
              each gathering were very mixed indeed as to watermark.</p>
            <p>Such a mixed stock of paper would have been most unusual even in the shop of a
              small-scale jobbing printer. After all, one buys paper by the ream or by the pound all
              with the same watermark, and to mix the papers thus would have been troublesome.
              Fairly plainly, these are odd sheets left over from other jobs and mixed
              higgledy-piggledy to save space. But it is very surprising to find paper thus mixed up
              in the work of a fine printer like Bensley, apparently the printer of all three
              editions.</p>
            <p>The question of who printed Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>, or rather of
              what types were used, is of some significance. A prospectus for the work of June 1787
              said that the type was to be cast on purpose for it, and “The Letter-Press will be
              executed in the most superb Manner.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">19</ref> Dibdin (ut
              supra) said that the five-volume Lavater (1789) was Bensley’s “earliest attempt at
              fine printing,” and the high quality of the type and printing seems to my
              typographically unsophisticated eye to be worthy of him. Further, as the titlepages of
              1789-92-98, 1810, and 1792 indicated (see illus. 1-3), the same type seems to have
              been used for all three editions. Whoever the compositors were, they seem to have been
              using the same type in all three editions. And it seems very odd that such careful
              composition and printing should have been associated with such a casual use of paper.
                <note id="n53"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> Collectanea:</hi> or, A Collection
                of Advertisements and Paragraphs from the Newspapers relating to various Subjects
                (Printed at Strawberry-Hill By Thomas Kirgate, for the Collector, Daniel Lysons), f.
                  81<hi rend="s">v</hi> &lt;British Library: 1881 b 6&gt;.</note></p>
            <p>The pattern of watermarks for all three editions may be seen below:</p>
            <table rows="26" cols="4">
              <head>Table of Watermarks Lavater, <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>, tr. Hunter First
                edition (1789, 1792, 1798)</head>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>Text</cell>
                <cell>Plates</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>17</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell>1794</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>95</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell>1802<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">20</hi>
                    The 1802 watermark is found at Vol. II, Part i at 3Y2 and Vol. III, Part ii at
                    3R2 and 3U2 in the Huntington set, which has binder’s flyleaves watermarked
                    1801.</note>
	</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>LEPARD<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">21</hi> The “LEPARD” watermark appears in two different positions in laid
                    paper, one parallel to the chain lines and one at right angles to them, as
                    Detlef Dörrbecker pointed out to me.</note>
	</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell>Adviune[?] 1784<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi
                      rend="s">22</hi> Mary Lynn Johnson and John Grant report that the lettering
                    with “1784” in the University of Iowa copy is exceedingly difficult to decipher
                    and that other plates there have different indecipherable
                  watermarks.</note>
	</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Lepard<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">23</hi> N.b. With all copies save those I have examined myself for the
                    purpose (i.e., GEB, Huntington, Princeton, and Toronto), I cannot be sure
                    whether the watermark is “LEPARD” or “Lepard” or whether the paper is wove or
                    laid.</note>
	</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell>LEPARD</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>LEPARD 95</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell>LW</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>LW</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell>JW</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>WL 94</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell>J Whatman | 1794</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
                <cell>1810 Edition</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>Text</cell>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>1806</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>II</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“1792” Edition</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>Text</cell>
                <cell>Plates</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>17</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell>1806</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>95</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell>1812</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>1801</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell>1813</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>1804</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell>1814</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>1806</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell>LEPARD</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>1809</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell>SMITH</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
            </table>
              <pb id="p29-21" n="21"/>
              <figure n="LavaterPhysiognomyFirstTitlepage.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="378">
                <head>6 Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> [first edition] Vol. I
                  (1789) titlepage &lt;GEB&gt;.</head>
                <figDesc>Note that the “U” of the author “HUNTER” is under the “B” of
                  “BY.”</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="LavaterPhysiognomySecondTitlepage.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="399">
                <head>7 Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> [second edition] Vol. I
                  (1789 [i.e., 1810]), titlepage &lt;University of Toronto Library&gt;.</head>
                <figDesc>Note that the “U” of the author “HUNTER” is under the “Y” of
                  “BY.”</figDesc>
              </figure>
            <table>
              <row>
                <cell>1817</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell>W. SPEAR 1815</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>II or TH</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell>J WHATMAN</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>LEPARD</cell>
                <cell>laid paper</cell>
                <cell>1794| JWHATMAN</cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>95 LEPARD</cell>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>S</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>WL</cell>
                <cell>wove paper</cell>
                <cell/>
                <cell/>
              </row>
            </table>
            <p>Note that all copies of a text-sheet must be printed at the same time (i.e., in one
              more or less continuous print-run), so that the type can then be distributed and used
              to set and print other sheets. If more copies of the text are needed after the type
              has been redistributed, for instance when a decision is made to increase the size of
              the print-run, the text must be composed and printed again.</p>
            <p>However, the plates can be printed as the need arises, since the copperplates are
              scarcely affected by the act of printing. Further, it is far more expensive and
              laborious to print plates than to print type-set text, and consequently it is sensible
              to pull only as many prints as are manifestly needed at the moment, and to wait until
              sales demonstrate the need and provide the capital to print more copies. If, for
              instance, one had 500 subscribers and hoped to sell a thousand copies altogether, one
              might print a thousand copies of the text but pull only 600 copies of the prints,
              assuming that more copies of the prints might be pulled as demand warranted.</p>
            <p>As a consequence, we should expect the text of all copies of an edition to reflect the date of
printing and first issuing them; in the
              case of the 41 Fascicles of the first edition of Lavater’s 
                <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>, this would be 1789-99—and the watermarks do reflect this, or
at
              least do not contradict it. However, the last copies sold might well include prints
              pulled long after the last of the text had been printed, and in at least one copy of
              the first edition of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> this is the case. In the
              Huntington set, three of the prints are paper watermarked “1802” (Vol. II, Part i, at
              3Y2, and Vol. III, Part II, at 3R2 and 3U2), and the work was probably bound not long
              after the “1801” watermark in the binder’s flyleaves.</p>
            <p>This “1792” edition, then cannot be earlier than 1817, the latest date in the
              watermarked paper in all copies examined for watermarks, 25 years after the date on
              the titlepage. But did the compositors for the “1792” edition follow the text of the
              first edition of 1789-98, as they followed its titlepages (though dating them all
              “1792”), or did they follow that of 1810?</p>
            <p>The printing is very careful and handsome in all three printings, but clearly they
              are separate editions rather than re-issues of the same sheets or re-impositions of
              the same type. The watermarks alone indicate that the third edition of “1792,” with
              watermarks of 1817, cannot be the same sheets as in the first edition of 1789-98, with
              text-sheets watermarked 1794 and 1795.</p>
            <pb id="p29-22" n="22"/>
            <p>Page-for-page and line-for-line the three editions are virtually identical in type,
              but there are significant differences in spacing in the second edition of 1810 and the
              third edition of “1792,” indicating that they are different settings of type rather
              than reprinted from standing type.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">24</ref>	
                  <note id="n58"><hi rend="s">24</hi> In any case, it would have been commercial folly to keep
the
                type for a five-volume folio work standing for a period of almost 30 years. Of
                course it could be done, but what would be the incentive, especially when the
                engravings, the raison d’etre of the edition, had been sold to another
                publisher?</note></p>
            <p>The precision with which the text was reset is, to me, astonishing. Taking as a test
              Vol. I, p. 31 (sig. L1<hi rend="s">r</hi>) of the three editions of 1789, 1810 and
              “1792” (1818?), the ordinary tests demonstrate that the house style produced almost
              identical results for pages set some 30 years apart. For instance, if one lays a
              straight line, such as a ruler, across the page between two arbitrarily-chosen points,
              say the top left and bottom right corners of the text, the line intersects identical
              fragments of text in each edition, though they are printed on paper watermarked 1794,
              1806, and 1817. Minute details of composition, such as the large space after the
              opening double quotations marks (“), the small one before a closing set, and the space
              before a semicolon, are uniform throughout all three editions. Since the compositor
              sees only one line as he loads his stick with type, the spacing within a line may be
              controlled very precisely, but the relationship of line to line is far more difficult
              to control and is far more a matter of chance. The near-identity of spacing throughout
              the page in each edition demonstrates an extraordinary uniformity of composing
              techniques and suggests to me that all three pages were set by the same rules of
              composition and probably by the same printing-house.</p>
            <p>Similarly, ligatures (e.g., “fi,” “si,” “sh,” “st,” and “ct”) are the same
in each
              edition, and all three editions use the long “s,” though in 1810 and 1818 this was an
              anachronism.</p>
            <p>The clearest of the tiny differences between the three editions of Vol. I, p. 31 are
              between the second edition of 1810 as compared to the first and third editions of 1789
              and “1792” (1818?) (see illus. 4-5). For instance, in the last word of text (“sign?”),
              there is a substantial space before the query in 1789 and “1792” (1818?), putting the
              query under the “g” of “energy” above it, while in 1810 the space before the query is
              markedly slimmer, and the query is beneath the “r” of “energy.” Yet more strikingly,
              “energy” is followed by a colon in 1789 and “1792” (1818?) but by a semi-colon in
              1810.</p>
            <p>Similarly, in Vol. I, p. 279 (sig. E1<hi rend="s">r</hi>) in the second edition
              (1810), in the second series of asterisks the first asterisk is under the comma of
              “upon,” but in the third edition (“1792”) it is under the “n.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
                type="note">25</ref> In the first edition (1789-98), Vol. II, Part i, pp. 143-50
              (Nn2-Pp1) are numbered correctly; in both the second edition (1810) and the third
              edition (1818?) they are mis-numbered as pp. 135-42. Since the third edition marked
              “1792” cannot have been printed earlier than 1817 (as shown by its watermarks), it
              compositors must have copied the text of the second edition (1810) rather than (as the
              titlepages would lead one to expect) the first edition of 1789-98. 
                  <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Note that the text-sheets watermarked “17 LEPARD 95”
and “LEPARD”
                in the third edition (1818?) can scarcely be from the 1810 printing, for all the
                sheets so watermarked (e.g., Vol. I, sig. B) in one set (e.g., Oregon State and
                Princeton) have much later watermarks in other copies (e.g., “1809” in Duke). It is
                just possible that the prints watermarked “LEPARD,” “J WHATM,” and “1794 J
Whatman”
                were from the early printing, but the fact that most of the other plate-watermarks
                are dated 1806 and later makes this seem unlikely.</note></p>
            <p>The differences between 1789 and “1792” (1818?) are even smaller—and never, to me
              definitive (see illus. 4-5). I can persuade myself that there are minute, scarcely
              measurable differences of spacing, but a re-examination of the same spacing usually
              leaves doubts as to whether there are clear differences. The text in 1818? must have
              been re-set when it was printed on paper of 1817, some 30 years after the original
              type was distributed, but the facsimile is so close as to make it, to me, virtually
              undetectable.</p>
            <p>There can be little doubt that the 1818? edition was created with the intention to
              deceive, for though the text itself derives inconspicuously from that of 1810, the
              titlepages copy the wording of the first edition of 1789-98, with “UPWARDS OF EIGHT
              HUNDRED ENGRAVINGS”, rather than that of 1810, which omits reference to the eight
              hundred.</p>
            <p>I would be agreeable if these perplexities could be enlightened by reference to the
              records of the publisher, but unfortunately the firm of Murray, whose name appears
              prominently on the editions of 1789-98 and of “1792” and which still survives today,
              has no trace of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy.</hi><ref target="n60"
                type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">26</hi> As Sir John Murray wrote to
                me on 10 February 1961.</note></p>
            <p>The evidence seems unambiguous that the “1792” edition of Lavater’s 
                <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> is a line-for-line reprint of the 1810 edition printed
              in or after 1817. But what was the incentive to print another edition so soon after
              the edition of 1810? If it took from 1789 until about 1810 to exhaust the stocks of
              the first edition (1789-98), it is unlikely that only about seven years would have
              sufficed to exhaust the stocks of the 1810 edition.</p>
            <p>The answer may lie in the auction by Mr. Saunders of the 537 copperplates for
              Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> with Stockdale’s stock which was
              announced in a prospectus of 2 January 1818.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n61" type="note">27</ref>
              Perhaps the purchaser attempted to capitalize promptly upon his acquisition of the
              copperplates by publishing a new edition of <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy.</hi>
              And if the new owner did not also own the copyright to Hunter’s translation of
              Lavater’s text, it may have seemed discrete to publish the work with a false imprint.
              In that case, the “1792” edition is not only a bastard but a piracy. 
                  <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">27</hi> British Library: 11902 bbb 23, Vol. II. I have not seen
or
                traced the auction-catalogue itself.</note></p>
            <pb id="p29-23" n="23"/>
            <p>This of course does not identify the fraudulent publisher of the “1792” Lavater, but
              it does help to suggest an occasion and a motive for publishing the work with a false
              imprint 25 years or more after its apparent date.</p>
            <p>Sheet-by-sheet examination of watermarks is extraordinarily tedious, keeping tallies
              of them is remarkably intricate, and in most cases what is learned is of trifling
              significance—the paper, even if it is dated, is almost invariably consistent with the
              date on the titlepage.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">28</ref>
Most bibliographers and
              editors probably check only a few sample sheets for watermarks, for “In doubtful
              questions ’tis the safest way / To learn what unsuspected ancients say,”<ref
                target="n63" type="note">29</ref> and leave it at that. 
                  <note id="n62"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Instructive exceptions are John Gay’s 
<hi rend="i">Fables</hi>
                (Stockdale, 1793, also issued with watermarks of c. 1811), John Flaxman’s designs to
                Homer’s <hi rend="i">Illiad</hi> (1793), <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> (1793), Dante
                (1793), and Aeschylus (1795) which bear watermarks of a number of different
                countries and dates, and most of William Blake’s works in illuminated printing which
                bear watermarks dated as much as 43 years later than those on the
                titlepages.</note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Dryden, <hi rend="i">Religio
                  Laici.</hi></note></p>
            <p>The danger is when the ancients are wrongfully unsuspected. Only when there is reason
              to be suspicious will a full-scale examination be made—or at least that was plainly
              the case with the credulous W. T. Lowndes, William Haines, A. G. B. Russell, Geoffrey
              Keynes, G. E. Bentley, Jr., and R. N. Essick. Doubtless one lesson to be drawn from
              this problem is that we should all be somewhat more suspicious than a really nice
              nature would ordinarily permit.</p>
            <p>But the problem with Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> is even more
              intricate than we have yet seen. We have thus far established that there were three
              editions, the first honestly dated 1789-98, the second honestly dated 1810, and the
              third marked 1792 but really of 1817 or later. Two or three libraries<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
                type="note">30</ref> claim to have editions of 1789-1810, but these are clearly
              mixed sets of the first and second editions. <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">30</hi> E.g.,
                Boston Public Library, Rylands Library of the University of Manchester, and the
                University of Toronto.</note></p>
            <p>Or so I thought until I examined the University of Toronto set of the 1789-1810
              edition. To my considerable dismay, I found that Vol. I (“1789”) and Vol. II (“1792”)
              have watermarks of “1804” and “1806”! (Vol. III [1810] also has watermarks of
“1806,”
              but of course these are not anachronistic.) Further, the titlepage and text have been
              reset with very remarkable fidelity to the first edition. For instance, on the
              titlepage of Vol. I the “U” of “HUNTER” is under the “B” of “BY” in the first
edition
              (see illus. 6) but under the “Y” in the edition watermarked “1806” (see illus. 7).
              Since the watermarks of Vol. I (“1789”) and Vol. II (“1792”) with the 1810 Vol. III
              are the same as in the sets in which all three titlepages are dated 1810, it seems
              fairly plain that they are part of the 1810 edition and that in 1810 two titlepages
              each were printed for Vol. I (dated “1789” and 1810) and Vol. II (dated “1792” and
              1810).</p>
            <p>This give us for Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> translated by Henry Hunter
                <hi rend="i">three</hi> Volume I titlepages dated 1789 (one honest, one of 1810, and
              one of 1817), <hi rend="i">three</hi> Volume II titlepages dated 1792 (one honest, one
              of 1810, and one of 1817), and <hi rend="i">three</hi> Volume III titlepages dated
              1798 (honest), 1792 (i.e., 1818?), and 1810 (honest).</p>
            <p>In the copies I have examined or which have been examined for me, sets with
              titlepages of 1789-98 and 1810 are apparently honest, while those in which the three
              volumes are dated 1792 or 1789-1810 are fraudulent (though Vol. III dated 1810 is
              apparently always honest).</p>
            <p>But it does not bear thinking of how many of the apparently honest sets of 1789-98
              are mixed sets, with Vol. I-II fraudulent and Vol. III honest. And of course there may
              be a Vol. III marked 1798 which is also fraudulent.</p>
            <p>The final tally, or at any rate the tally to date (23 August 1995), for Lavater’s 
                <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> translated by Hunter with the plates supervised
              by Holloway is: <table rows="4" cols="4">
                <row>
                  <cell>Edition</cell>
                  <cell>Volume I</cell>
                  <cell>Volume II</cell>
                  <cell>Volume III</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>First (1789-98)</cell>
                  <cell>1789</cell>
                  <cell>1792</cell>
                  <cell>1798</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Second (1810)</cell>
                  <cell>1789 or 1810</cell>
                  <cell>1792 or 1810</cell>
                  <cell>1810</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Third (1818?)</cell>
                  <cell>1789</cell>
                  <cell>1792</cell>
                  <cell>1798</cell>
                </row>
              </table></p>
            <p>And that’s quite enough intricacy to be going on with, it seems to me. I at any rate
              will endeavor in the future to be as suspicious as a really nice nature will permit
              and will glance at watermarks regularly—but I bet nothing as devious and intricate as
              Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> turns up again.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
