<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.1.henry</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Sunshine and Shady Groves: What Blake’s “Little Black Boy” Learned from
African Writers</title>
        <author n="Henry">Lauren Henry</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Lauren G. Henry</name>
              <name>J.E.M. Latham</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <pb id="p29-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Sunshine and Shady Groves: What Blake’s “Little Black Boy” Learned from
                African Writers</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Lauren <name>Henry</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>At first glance, the poetic diction, heroic verse and classical allusions
            characterizing Phillis Wheatley’s 1773 <hi rend="i">Poems on Various Subjects, Religious
              and Moral</hi> would seem to suggest that her poetry has everything to do with
            neoclassicism and nothing at all to do with romanticism. Yet a closer examination of
            Wheatley’s collection reveals its significance not just to the neoclassical tradition
            from which it derives, or even to the African-American literary tradition which it
            initiates (Gates x), but also, and quite surprisingly, to a particularly problematic
            poem of the English romantic tradition. The problematic poem is William Blake’s “The
            Little Black Boy,” and I will argue that reading this song of innocence alongside
            Wheatley’s “An Hymn to the Morning,” one of the poems in her 1773 volume, leads to a
            better understanding of Blake’s child speaker and of the intense irony used to portray
            his situation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Also
arising from the juxtaposition
            of these two poems is the interesting possibility that Blake had some familiarity with
            Wheatley’s work in particular, and with eighteenth-century England’s small but notable
            African literary community in general.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref>	
                <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Harold Bloom calls “The Little Black Boy” “one of the
most
              deliberately misleading and ironic of all Blake’s lyrics” (<hi rend="i">Blake’s
                Apocalypse</hi> 48) and many of the poem’s other readers recognize irony as its
              central element. See, for example, Howard Hinkel’s “From Pivotal Idea to Poetic Ideal:
              Blake’s Theory of Contraries and ‘The Little Black Boy’”; C. N. Manlove’s “Blake’s
              ‘The Little Black Boy’ and ‘The Fly’”; or, more recently, Alan Richardson’s
              “Colonialism, Race, and Lyric Irony in Blake’s ‘The Little Black Boy’.”</note>	
              <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> For an introduction to African-English literature of the
              eighteenth century, see Keith Sandiford’s <hi rend="i">Measuring the Moment:
                Strategies of Protest in Eighteenth-Century Afro-English Writing</hi> or Paul
              Edwards’s and David Dabydeen’s anthology of extracts, <hi rend="i">Black Writers in
                Britain 1760-1890.</hi></note></p>
          <p>The slave of a wealthy Boston family, Wheatley turned to England with her volume of
            poetry only after American publishers had rejected it (Mason 5). Yet these circumstances
            may have helped to establish and sustain her reputation, for upon its publication in
            London, the volume was widely and enthusiastically reviewed in British periodicals and
            its author acclaimed in abolitionist documents for years to 
            come.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
            <figure n="PortraitPhillisWheatley.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="373">
              <head>1 Portrait of Phillis Wheatley.</head>
              <figDesc>Courtesy of the Photographs and Prints Division, Schomburg Center for
                Research in Black Culture, New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
                Foundation.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            Blake may have read one of the many reviews of Wheatley’s volume, or he may
            have learned about the African poet as he composed his Songs of Innocence at the height
            of the English abolitionist movement in the late 1780s. This is the more plausible
            possibility, for one critic has suggested the likelihood that “Blake drew on” Thomas
            Clarkson’s celebrated 1786 <hi rend="i">Essay on the Slavery and Commerce of the Human
              Species</hi> as he wrote “The Little Black Boy” (Macdonald 178); and in one component
            of his argument against slavery (an assertion of the intellectual capacities of blacks),
            Clarkson cites Wheatley as a representative example of African intellect and educability
            as he displays excerpts of four of her poems, “An Hymn to the Morning” among them (111).
              <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> For excerpts from the reviews, see Mukhtar Ali
              Isani’s “The British Reception of Wheatley’s <hi rend="i">Poems on Various
                Subjects.</hi>” References to Wheatley’s work in Thomas Clarkson’s <hi rend="i">An
                Essay on the Slavery and Commerce of the Human Species, Particularly the
                African</hi> and in numerous issues of the weekly “founded to combat American
              slavery,” William Lloyd Garrison’s <hi rend="i">The Liberator</hi>, attest to the
              poet’s considerable impact on both English and American antislavery writing (Robinson
              53).</note></p>
          <p>Any examination of “An Hymn to the Morning” must be preceded by an understanding of
            Wheatley’s complex situation as a woman who is at once an African, an American, a slave,
            a Christian and a poet. Wheatley’s poetry has for many years been criticized by readers
            who see her verse as imitative and her reluctance to clearly condemn the institution of
            slavery as reprehensible.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
More recent critics have
              <pb id="p29-5" n="5"/>
begun to point out African elements in Wheatley’s form as well
            as her use of irony and subtle manipulations of language to censure the society that has
            enslaved her.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> They suggest
that Wheatley’s poetry
            must be read with the knowledge that she has been forced to speak “with a double tongue”
            (Erkkila 205). <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> As Sondra O’Neale puts it, Wheatley has
              been “castigated” by “many modern critics of Black American literature” as “an
              unfeeling woman foolishly immersed in colonial refinements, oblivious to her own
              status as a slave and to that of her African peers” (“A Slave’s Subtle War: Phillis
              Wheatley’s Use of Biblical Myth and Symbol” 144).</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> In “Classical Tidings from the Afric Muse: Phillis Wheatley’s Use of
Greek
              and Roman Mythology,” Lucy Hayden suggests that Wheatley may have been “drawing
              subliminally on the storytelling tradition of her African past” in her poem “Goliath
              at Gath” (435); and John Shields, in a chapter in <hi rend="i">African American
                Writers: Profiles of their Lives and Works from the 1700s to the Present</hi>,
              asserts that both “An Hymn to the Morning” and “An Hymn to the Evening” suggest “the
              recollection of an African musical setting” (357). Shields, along with Mukhtar Ali
              Isani, Lynn Matson, William H. Robinson, Jr., Sondra O’Neale, Betsy Erkkila (and
              others), are amending our understanding of Wheatley by locating points of resistance
              and rebellion in her language and poetry.</note></p>
          <p>Approaching “An Hymn to the Morning” with this knowledge, we find that the speaker
            communicates complex feelings about nature, religion, and her role as a poet in imagery
            that brings “The Little Black Boy” to mind. “[W]ritten in heroic verse,” though
            “embody[ing] the spirit of the hymn,” the poem begins as the speaker proclaims her
            intention to celebrate the dawn through her song.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">6</ref> In
            this first stanza Wheatley calls upon the muses for assistance as she composes her paean
            to the rising sun, confidently situating this poem within the classical poetic tradition
            of the society which has enslaved her. Her description of the beauty and brilliance of
            the awakening morning progresses uneventfully throughout the second stanza, but by the
            third stanza a discordant note becomes apparent, as the speaker makes a curious request:
            “Ye shady groves, your verdant gloom display/ To shield your poet from the burning
              day.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> At this point
the poet seems to feel a need
            for protection from the very object of her praise. And in the final stanza it becomes
            evident that her apprehension was not unwarranted, for here the sun, or “th’illustrious
            king of day” has, with his “rising radiance,” driven “the shades away.” Thus, the now
            unprotected poet finds that she “feel[s] his fervid beams too strong” and must abruptly
            end her composition: “And scarce begun, concludes th’abortive song” (74).<ref
              target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> John Shields,
              “Phillis Wheatley and Mather Byles,” <hi rend="i">CLA Journal</hi> (1980): 380.
              Subsequent page references will appear parenthetically and will be abbreviated
              PWMB.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Phillis Wheatley, <hi rend="i">The Poems
                of Phillis Wheatley</hi>, ed. Julian D. Mason, Jr. (Chapel Hill: University of North
              Carolina Press, 1989) 74. Subsequent page references will appear parenthetically in
              the text.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The complete text of Wheatley’s “An
              Hymn to the Morning” follows: 
			<q> Attend my lays, ye ever honour’d nine,<lb/>
 Assist
                my labours, and my strains refine;<lb/>
 In smoothest numbers pour the notes
                along,<lb/>
 For bright Aurora now demands my song.<lb/>
<lb/>
 Aurora hail, and all
                the thousand dies,<lb/>
 Which deck thy progress through the vaulted skies:<lb/>
 The
                morn awakes, and wide extends her rays,<lb/>
 On ev’ry leaf the gentle zephyr
                plays;<lb/>
 Harmonious lays the feather’d race resume,<lb/>
 Dart the bright eye, and
                shake the painted plume.<lb/>
<lb/>
 Ye shady groves, your verdant gloom display<lb/>
                To shield your poet from the burning day:<lb/>
 Calliope awake the sacred lyre,<lb/>
                While thy fair sisters fan the pleasing fire:<lb/>
 The bow’rs, the gales, the
                variegated skies<lb/>
 In all their pleasures in my bosom rise.<lb/>
<lb/>
 See in the
                east th’illustrious king of day!<lb/>
 His rising radiance drives the shades
                away—<lb/>
 But Oh! I feel his fervid beams too strong,<lb/>
 And scarce begun,
                concludes th’abortive song. (74) </q></note></p>
          <p>Clearly, the poet has mixed feelings about her purpose and her potential to accomplish
            it in this poem. We can only begin to understand the nature of those feelings if we are
            aware of the traditions which collide in these verses. The poem was certainly meant to
            be read by its original white English and American audiences as a melding of classicism
            and Christianity, in which the Greek gods of the sun and the dawn are celebrated at the
            same time that Christianity’s God and His Son are praised and glorified. Subsequent
            readers have continued to emphasize these elements of Wheatley’s work, as is evident in
            Julian Mason’s remark that Wheatley’s “mixing of Christian and classical in the many
            invocations in her poems (as well as in other parts of the poems) reflects the two
            greatest influences on her work, religion and neoclassicism” (15).</p>
          <p>Yet an integrated reading of Wheatley’s work (and of “An Hymn to the Morning” and its
            sun imagery in particular) requires recognition of cultural influences with non-Western
            roots. The reader needs to consider, for example, the strong possibility that Wheatley
            came from an African community in which sun worship was a religious practice, for
            Wheatley’s first biographer claimed that the poet could remember only one thing about
            her life in Africa, and that was that every day her mother “poured out water before the
            sun at his rising” (Odell 10-11). Because Wheatley was kidnapped and brought to America
            when she was only seven or eight years old, there is no way to be certain of either her
            place of birth or her native religious traditions, although it has been suggested that
            “she was very likely of the Fulani people in the Gambia region of West Africa” and that
            the ritual she remembered may have been a “complex, syncretized version of Islam and
            solar worship,” as “Islam had long before penetrated into the Gambia 
            region.”<ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> 
            In any case, Wheatley’s intense preoccupation with the sun in this 
<pb id="p29-6" n="6"/>
			poem and others<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
            certainly can be traced to African 
            origins<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> and
            seen as quiet confirmation of a life and religion that were hers before she was
            enslaved. 
            <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> John Shields, “Phillis Wheatley,” 
                <hi rend="i">African American Writers: Profiles in their Lives and Works</hi>, 356.
              Subsequent page references will appear parenthetically and will be abbreviated
              AAW.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Shields writes that “solar imagery
              constitutes the dominant image pattern in [Wheatley’s] poetry” (AAW 356.)</note>	
              <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> In a study of African traditional religions, John S.
              Mbiti writes that some African cultures perceive God as “‘the Sun’ which beams its
              light everywhere” and points out that “[a]mong many [African] societies, the sun is
              considered to be a manifestation of God Himself, and the same word, or its cognate, is
              used for both” (<hi rend="i">African Religions and Philosophy</hi> 31, 52.) Both
              Olaudah Equiano and James Gronniosaw also mention sun worship rituals in their
              narratives (discussed below).</note></p>
          <p>Because it is so fraught with contradictions, the sun imagery of “An Hymn to the
            Morning” calls attention to itself and to the various cultural and religious roles that
            it is asked to play. Perhaps while Wheatley encourages the reader to consider the
            cultural convergence in her depiction of this Christian/ classical/African sun, she
            concurrently questions the role that the sun in its Christian manifestation has played
            in her own life. We would certainly expect a slave carried to America and converted to
            the religion of her captors to have doubts about that religion, and of course the only
            way for her to communicate those doubts would be to cloak them in conventionality. Thus,
            the tension that exists between the poet’s glorification of the sun and her discomfort
            when exposed to its “fervid beams” may be the result of Wheatley’s ironic attitude
            towards her subject: while ostensibly praising her Christian God, she also implies that
            His presence in her life has made it impossible for her to fully express her beliefs and
            emotions, and therefore, to write the kind of poem she envisions.</p>
          <p>The speaker’s attempt to seek refuge in a “shady grove” and its “verdant gloom” may
            also be seen as evidence of Wheatley’s conflicted feelings about Christianity and her
            abiding interest in the religious traditions she left behind in Africa. For just as the
            sun in this poem suggests an aspect of the poet’s African past, so too does the shade.
            As Wheatley was composing her <hi rend="i">Poems on Various Subjects</hi> in colonial
            America, both England and America were amassing voluminous accounts of the life and land
            of Africa.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> These
geographic/ethnographic reports
            were sometimes written (or compiled) by those interested in abolitionism, but most often
            by “slave traders or naval officers involved in protecting the trade”; yet in spite of
            their glaring flaws and prejudices, they were invaluable to those who wanted at least a
            glimpse of the continent they were colonizing (Marshall, Williams 228). It seems likely
            that Wheatley’s lack of information about her homeland and “easy access” to “the three
            largest libraries in the colonies” (Shields PWMB 389n) would have led her to peruse some
            of these widely published accounts, and a reference to one of them in a 1774 letter
            suggests that she was, in fact, familiar with the genre.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Examination of some of these works reinforces this suggestion, for one of
            the African traditions repeatedly remarked upon concerns the practice of meeting and
            worshipping in a “shady grove.” <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Many of these works
              are discussed in chap. 8 of P. J. Marshall’s and Glyndwr Williams’ <hi rend="i">The
                Great Map of Mankind: British Perceptions of the World in the Age of
                Enlightenment.</hi> Philip Curtin also refers to the genre throughout 
                <hi rend="i">The Image of Africa</hi>, as does William Lloyd James in his dissertation, “The
              Black Man in English Romantic Literature, 1772-1833.”</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi
                rend="s">13</hi> In a letter to the “Rev’d Mr. Saml. Hopkins of New Port, Rhode
              Island,” Wheatley writes that she “observe[s] [his] reference to the Maps of Guinea
              &amp; Salmon’s Gazetteer, and shall consult them” (Wheatley 208). Thus it appears that
              Reverend Hopkins has directed her to some information on Africa in one of Thomas
              Salmon’s popular accounts.</note></p>
          <p>One work typical of this genre is William Smith’s <hi rend="i">A New Voyage to
              Guinea</hi>, first published in 1744. In his depiction of what was then known to the
            English as the country of Whydah (also referred to as Fida by the Dutch, and Juda by the
            French), on the Slave Coast of Africa, Smith writes that “[a]ll who have ever been here,
            allow this to be one of the most delightful Countries in the World,” in part because of
            “[t]he great Number and Variety of tall, beautiful and shady Trees, which seem as if
            planted in fine Groves for ornament” (194). He later recognizes, however, that the
            groves serve a more than ornamental purpose, when he notes that “[a]lmost every Village
            has a Grove or publick Place of Worship, to which the principal Inhabitants on a set Day
            resort to make their Offerings, &amp;c” (214).</p>
          <p>Thomas Salmon devotes the 27th volume of his encyclopedic <hi rend="i">Modern History;
              or the Present State of All Nations</hi> (1735) to an examination of Africa, and in so
            doing, also notes the importance of public shady groves in various African societies. In
            a discussion of the Congo, for example, he writes that 
			<q> [as] to the Towns belonging
              to the Negroes, most of them consist of a few Huts, built with Clay and Reeds, in an
              irregular manner; and as every Tribe or Clan has its particular King or Soveraign, his
              Palace is usually distinguished by a spreading Tree before his Door, under which he
              sits and converses, or administers Justice to his Subjects. But I perceive most of
              their Towns are in or near a Grove of Trees; for our Sailors always conclude, there is
              a Negroe Town, wherever they observe a Tuft of Trees upon the Coast. (160) </q>
As
            Salmon goes on to discuss other areas of Africa, he, like Smith, pays particular
            attention to Whydah in a description he appropriates from Willem Bosman’s firsthand
            account of the region in <hi rend="i">A New and Accurate Description of the Coast of
              Guinea</hi> (translated from Dutch into English in 1705). He writes that Bosman’s
            inquiry into the religion of this society revealed that along with serpents and the sea,
            the natives of this land show reverence for trees and groves: 
			<q> The next Things the
              Fidaians pay Divine Honours to, are fine lofty Trees and Groves. To these they apply
              in their Sickness, or on any private Misfortune; and I 
<pb id="p29-7" n="7"/>
ought to
              have taken Notice, that all the Serpents Temples are in some Grove, or under some
              spreading Tree. (228) </q></p>
          <p>Salmon’s appropriation of Bosman’s text is not unusual in this genre, for many writing
            these early accounts of Africa incorporate entire paragraphs and even pages from the
            works of their predecessors. This is especially true in the case of Anthony Benezet’s
              <hi rend="i">Some Historical Account of Guinea</hi>, an abolitionist text first
            published in 1771, for Benezet’s attempt to establish the spiritual potential of
            Africans is partially based on passages taken directly from both William Smith and
            Bosman, and these happen to be the passages portraying the religious practices of the
            Whydah blacks, which, of course, include worshipping in a shady grove (23-28).</p>
          <p>Although we must read eighteenth century travel accounts of Africa with caution,
            remembering that “travellers with closed minds can tell us little except about
            themselves” (Achebe, qtd. in Brantlinger 95), the likelihood that Wheatley consulted one
            or more of the works in this genre nonetheless sheds new light on the “shady grove” of
            “An Hymn to the Morning.” The image now seems to say less about the burning sun and
            desire for relief from it and more about Christianity and possible alternatives to it.
            Unearthing African roots in Wheatley’s “shady grove”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n14" type="note">14</ref> thus relocates the reader somewhere beyond the poem’s pious, conventional,
            Christian surface. From this new vantage point, we see Wheatley giving credence to a
            religious ritual that might have been her own had she not been enslaved, and we
            recognize the note of bitterness in the poem’s abrupt conclusion where a potentially
            African shade is driven away by a Christian incarnation of the sun. 
                <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Modern studies of African religions attest to the
continuing
              significance of “shady groves” in many African societies. For example, in a chapter on
              places and objects of worship, Dominique Zahan writes that “the tree acquires an even
              greater value when it forms a part of the thickets and groves in which man holds
              religious meetings,” and claims that “[i]n fact, groves are the most preferred places
              of worship in African religion” (<hi rend="i">The Religion, Spirituality, and Thought
                of Traditional Africa</hi> 28). Similarly, in <hi rend="i">African Religions and
                Philosophy</hi>, John S. Mbiti writes of the importance of trees and groves in the
              worship practices of many African cultures (73).</note></p>
          <p>Turning to “The Little Black Boy,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> we find that
            Blake’s poem brings Wheatley’s to mind, as it too makes the reader aware of irony and
            bitterness through tensions and contradictions in its depiction of the sun and a “shady
            grove.” As the child of Blake’s poem relates his story, he brings the reader to “the
            southern wild” where he was born and tells us of his mother’s religious lessons. We find
            that she, like Wheatley and her own mother, worships a God which she associates with the
            sun. Yet it is difficult to discern the true nature of the mother’s relationship to this
            sun/God because, like Wheatley, she presents Him both as an object of devotion and as an
            entity from which she and her child need protection. She instructs her little boy to
            celebrate this God who lives in “the rising sun,” yet at the same time explains that
            they have been “put on earth a little space/ That [they] may learn to bear the beams of
            love,” suggesting that these are in fact harsh beams to bear (E 9). At this point, the
            mother sounds remarkably like the speaker of Wheatley’s poem, as she presents her child
            with an image of the sun that evokes both Christian and African religiosity while
            espousing beliefs about God and His association with the sun which clearly contradict
            each other. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Complete
                Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David Erdman, 9. Subsequent references
              to this edition will cite it as “E,” followed by page number.</note></p>
          <p>The parallel between the two poems extends as the child quotes his mother as saying
            that “these black bodies and this sunburnt face / Is but a cloud, and like a shady
            grove” (E 9). The mother also proclaims that someday, when their “souls have learn’d the
            heat to bear,” she and her son will be called “out from the grove” by the loving voice
            of God (E 9). Determining whether or not Blake is aware of the religious implications of
            trees and groves for an African writer such as Wheatley is less important than noticing
            that the relationship he establishes between the image of a “shady grove” and an African
            sense of self and blackness duplicates the one developed in “An Hymn to the Morning.” In
            both poems the “shady grove” is associated with an African speaker’s struggle to
            construct an identity (either poetic or personal), and in both poems the image of the
            protective grove is set up in opposition to the sun and to Christianity.</p>
          <p>The complexity of the images of sun and shade in these two poems continually conducts
            the reader back to critical questions about Christianity, and more specifically, about
            the role that Christianity plays in the life of an enslaved African. When we consider
            that Christian doctrine was deployed both by pro-slavery apologists who argued that
            African servitude was ordained by God,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> and by
            abolitionists who asserted that the institution of slavery was incompatible with
            Christian teachings,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> the
relevance and importance
            of these questions become incontrovertible. Thus, Blake’s reformulation of some of the
            ideas and images of Wheatley’s poem in “The Little Black Boy” may demonstrate 
              <pb id="p29-8" n="8"/>
his struggle to try to provide his own representation of some of
            the bleak but unavoidable answers to these questions. 
                <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Illustrating the pervasive notion that Christianity
sanctioned slavery,
              Daniel Burton (secretary of London’s Society for the Propagation of the Gospel)
              explains in a 1786 letter to the Quaker abolitionist Anthony Benezet that the society
              is unwilling to support Benezet’s antislavery efforts because it “cannot condemn the
              Practice of keeping Slaves as unlawful, finding the contrary very plainly implied in
              the precepts given by the Apostles, both to Masters and Servants, which last were for
              the most part Slaves. . .” (qtd. in Winthrop Jordan’s <hi rend="i">White Over
                Black</hi> 197). For commentary on some of the pseudo-Biblical theories employed by
              early defenders of the slave trade, see Charles Lyons’ reference to the Hamitic curse
              in <hi rend="i">To Wash an Aethiop White</hi> (12) and Keith Sandiford’s discussion of
              the mark of Cain in <hi rend="i">Measuring the Moment</hi> (100).</note>	
                <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> For one discussion of the argument that slaveholding was
in
              violation of the Christian condition, see “Quaker Conscience and Consciousness” in
              Winthrop Jordan’s <hi rend="i">White Over Black</hi> (271-76).</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s struggle to come to terms with these questions and answers is reflected in his
            depiction of the child speaker of his poem. The “little black boy” is clearly confused
            by the complexity of the religious and social lessons he has been taught, and by his own
            dual role as a child of Africa and a child of God. Almost all readers of this poem point
            to the contradictory nature of the boy’s reasoning: he looks to God for love and
            protection and yet needs protection from Him; he sees his blackness as a sign that he is
            “bereav’d of light” (E 9) and as a gift from God; and he believes that when he goes to
            Heaven, he and the white English boy will both shed their cloud-bodies, and thus achieve
            some kind of equality, and yet still envisions himself serving the white child,
            “shad[ing] him from the heat” and “stand[ing] and strok[ing] his silver hair” (E 9).</p>
          <p>Some readers of the poem see the child’s “fractured theology” (Macdonald 168) as
            evidence that he has mingled the religion his mother taught him with the Christianity he
            was exposed to through missionaries or English Sunday schools in order to “produc[e] a
            self-affirming discourse of his own” (Richardson 243). While it is difficult to
            extricate the separate strands of religion and culture here, I think that it is safe to
            say that there is little of a self-affirming nature in the tensions and contradictions
            that comprise the resulting religious views of “the little black boy.” Like Wheatley, he
            has clearly learned that the spiritual teachings of his homeland are considered at best
            insufficient, and at worst, mere superstition by the society he now lives in. And, like
            Wheatley, he has learned that in order to be tolerated by this society, he is expected
            to embrace Christianity, but not to expect too much out of Christianity in return. Thus,
            as the little boy of this poem grapples with the religions of his past and his present,
            Blake suggests that confusion, contradictions, and irony are the necessary results of
            Christianity’s involvement in Africa and the slave trade.</p>
          <p>Blake does, however, provide the reader of “The Little Black Boy” with more than a
            bleak example of Christianity’s impact on Africa and Africans. In the language and
            images that his poem shares with Wheatley’s, Blake attests to the significance of
            beliefs and rituals with African origins and thus offers a revised reading of religion
            to eighteenth-century England. While recognizing, as one modern writer on Africa puts
            it, that “African traditions are no more homogeneous than those of any other continent”
            (Hountondji, qtd. in Appiah 95), we can nonetheless see that Blake’s song of innocence,
            although obviously limited by its historical situation, presents a picture of
            traditional African belief systems that is both accepting and appreciative of their
            differences from English Christian creeds.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref> This
            accepting and <figure n="PortraitOlaudahEquiano.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="435">
              <head>2 Portrait of Olaudah Equiano or Gustavus Vassa.</head>
              <figDesc>Courtesy of the Photographs and Prints Division, Schomburg Center for
                Research in Black Culture, New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
                Foundation.</figDesc>
            </figure> appreciative perspective is evident not only in the sun worship and the
            retreat to a “shady grove” central to this poem and to Wheatley’s,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
              type="note">19</ref> but also in “The Little Black Boy’s” affinities with the writings
            of other eighteenth-century Africans. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> The
              possibility that Blake would see African religion from this enlightened point of view
              is not all that surprising when we consider Blake’s “studious and respectful” attitude
              to the teachings of Emmanuel Swedenborg throughout the 1780s and some of the specifics
              of the Swedenborgians’ involvement with Africa (Paley 64). Morton Paley tells us that
              the Swedenborgians were ardent abolitionists and that “Swedenborg taught that the
              inhabitants of the interior of Africa had preserved a direct intuition of God” (65).
              For more on the Swedenborgian antislavery campaign (including the Sierra Leone
              repatriation plan), see Paley’s “‘A New Heaven is Begun’: William Blake and
              Swedenborgianism.”</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Although some of Blake’s
              later writings, notably <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, describe groves in a much more
              negative manner, these are clearly not the “shady groves” of African culture, but are
              instead “oaken groves” associated with Druidism (E 170; pl. 25, l.4). Similarly, we
              should not see in the serpent temples of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> any indictment of African religious customs, as these too are
              associated with Druidism and Blake’s view of Britain’s religious history.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s portrait of childhood in Africa, for example, reminds Paul Edwards of James
            Albert Gronniosaw’s slave narrative, published in at least four editions in England and
            America from the 1770s through the 1790s. Edwards suggests 
<pb id="p29-9" n="9"/>
<figure n="BosmanMap.29.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="283">
              <head>3 Map from Willem Bosman’s <hi rend="i">A New and Accurate Description of the
                  Goast of Guinea</hi>, 1705.</head>
              <figDesc>Courtesy of the Manuscripts, Archives and Rare Books Division, Schomburg
                Center for Research in Black Culture, New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and
                Tilden Foundation.</figDesc>
            </figure> an admittedly shaky circumstantial link between Blake and Gronniosaw’s 
              <hi rend="i">Narrative of the Most Remarkable Particulars</hi> as he explains that Blake
            was good friends with the painter Richard Cosway, whose house servant was Ottobah
            Cugoano, one of the leaders of England’s black abolitionists. Because Cugoano’s
            antislavery document, first published in 1787, mentions Gronniosaw’s work, Edwards
            proposes that Blake may have been introduced to Gronniosaw’s narrative on a visit to the
            Cosways (181).</p>
          <p>In any case, the story told by “the little black boy” of Blake’s poem bears an uncanny
            resemblance to the story Gronniosaw tells of his own childhood. Gronniosaw writes of a
            conversation he once had with his mother in Africa about the author of creation and
            reports that when he “raised [his] hands toward heaven,” and asked “who lived there,” he
            was “much dissatisfied when she told [him] sun, moon, and stars, being persuaded in
            [his] own mind that there must be some superior Power” (3). Gronniosaw then remarks that
            the members of his village often congregated under a number of “large palm tree[s]” for
            their early morning worship (8). Edwards notes the resemblance of these lines to the
            second and third stanzas of “The Little Black Boy,” and sums up the relationship by
            saying that “the two passages share a conversation between mother and child, a
            sheltering tree, and an identification of the Heavenly Power with the sun, [though] in
            Gronniosaw it is the child who appears more aware of the Heavenly Power than the mother”
              (180).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi>
              Michael Echeruo recently suggested that Paul Edwards’s article on the possible link
              between “The Little Black Boy” and Gronniosaw’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi> is in need
              of “some expansion and revision” (51). Echeruo’s argument is that “Thoughts in Exile,”
              a poem published in 1864 by the Nigerian poet William Cole, “‘challenges’ Blake’s and
              Gronniosaw’s [poems] in every particular,” especially in its depiction of an African
              child learning religious lessons underneath his father’s tree (56). In his conclusion,
              Echeruo suggests that “[i]t would be well worth the effort to identify other instances
              of this habit of ‘theologizing under a tree’ in written and oral African literature
              and determine the rhetorical uses to which the topos is variously put” (“Theologizing
              ‘Underneath the Tree’: An African Topos in Ukawsaw Gronniosaw, William Blake, and
              William Cole” 56).</note></p>
          <p>Once again encountering the tradition of worshipping the sun from the protective
            covering of a “shady grove,” we find that Blake’s poem and Gronniosaw’s narrative share
            more than the specifics of plot outlined by Edwards. Gronniosaw unmistakably establishes
            the tree and the shade it provides as emblems of African religion, for his initial image
            of the tree is extended later in the narrative when he explains that even after he had
            been enslaved and converted to Christianity, he continued to pray under a tree, although
            he had to replace the palm trees of Africa with a “large, remarkably fine” American oak,
            “about a quarter of a mile from [his first] master’s house” (24). Reading Blake’s poem
            in the light of Gronniosaw’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi> thus reinforces the suggestion
            that the specific setting of the religious lesson in “The Little Black Boy,” “underneath
            a tree,” “before the heat of day,” is intended as acknowledgement of the little that
            Blake could have known of African religious practices (E 9). And because a thorough 
              <pb id="p29-10" n="10"/>
reading of Gronniosaw’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi> confirms that
            tension and irony inevitably accompany the Christian conversion of an enslaved African,
            we can recognize in this writer one more likely model for Blake’s child speaker.</p>
          <p>If Blake was indeed familiar with Gronniosaw’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, it is
            almost certain that he would also have been aware of the work of Olaudah Equiano, a
            close friend of Cosway’s servant Cugoano, and probably the most famous of England’s
            black abolitionists. Equiano’s work, entitled <hi rend="i">The Interesting Narrative of
              the Life of Olaudah Equiano or Gustavus Vassa the African</hi> was first published in
            London in 1789 and went through at least 15 editions by 1834 (Sandiford 10). Along with
            exposing some of the horrors of slavery, the work depicts the same kind of spiritual
            struggle as is seen in Wheatley’s poem and Gronniosaw’s <hi rend="i">Narrative.</hi>
            Equiano appears in one part of the narrative to have completely supplanted his African
            religious training with Christianity and in another to be revolting against such a
            distasteful idea. We find him at his most direct when he compares English society to
            cultures with non-Christian belief systems, and when he presents the reader with an
            account of his “early life in Eboe” (1). In this account, he describes many of the
            traditional practices and beliefs with which he was raised, and after considering
            subjects such as the homes, the food, and the daily occupations of the Eboes, he states
            that “as to Religion, the natives believe that there is one Creator of all things and
            that he lives in the sun. . .” (10), thus presenting us with another possible source for
            the mother’s message to her child in “The Little Black Boy.”</p>
          <p>The parallels between Blake’s poem and these African works are valuable in and of
            themselves, for they awaken us to the fact that enslaved Africans were writing,
            publishing, and being widely read during the romantic period in England, and thus that
            they were actively influencing the tide of the abolitionist movement. At the same time,
            the possibility that this literature may have influenced Blake’s rendering of African
            experience in “The Little Black Boy” allows a better understanding of why his child
            speaker voices such paradoxical notions and what Christianity has had to do with the
            development of these notions.</p>
          <p>As Blake’s poem concludes, the “little black boy” offers the reader a vision of his
            hopes for the future. He sees himself and the little English boy, free from their
            respective clouds, together in a Heaven in which Christ is depicted as the good shepherd
            and where “round the tent of God like lambs [they] joy” (E 9). This conclusion has been
            condemned for its evasion of historical realities and its imperialist implications,<ref
              target="n21" type="note">21</ref> and the black child’s contented, unquestioning
            acceptance of this Christian afterlife in which he is the playmate and yet still the
            servant of the white child seems to substantiate such criticism. And yet the ending of
            Blake’s antislavery statement is quite similar to that of one of his African
            contemporaries, Ottobah Cugoano. In <hi rend="i">Thoughts and Sentiments on the Evil of
              Slavery</hi>, Cugoano concludes his condemnation of the slave trade with three
            proposals for the people of England. He recommends that after praying for forgiveness
            for “making merchandize” of human beings (129), and completely abolishing slavery, the
            British should convert all of the forts and factories used for the slave trade in West
            Africa into Christian missions or “shepherd’s tents,” where “good shepherds” sent from
            England will “call the flocks to feed beside them” (133). Juxtaposing these two
            conclusions makes the ironic element of Blake’s poem more apparent. If Cugoano was
            unable to represent anything other than an English/Christian vision of the future, then
            why should we be surprised that Blake’s “little black boy” finds himself in the same
            situation? Essentially, he has learned the lessons of Phillis Wheatley and his other
            real-life counterparts only too well. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> For these
              assertions, see D.L. Macdonald (“Pre-Romantic and Romantic Abolitionism” 168) and
              Ngugi wa Thiong’o (<hi rend="i">Writers in Politics: Essays</hi> 20).</note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Appiah, Kwame Anthony. <hi rend="i">In My Father’s House: Africa in the Philosophy of
                Culture.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1992.</p>
            <p>Benezet, Anthony. <hi rend="i">Some Historical Account of Guinea....</hi> London:
              1771, 1788. London: Frank Cass and Co., Ltd., 1968.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Ed.
              David Erdman. Garden City, New York: Anchor Press, 1982.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell University
              Press, 1963.</p>
            <p>Bosman, Willem. <hi rend="i">A New and Accurate Description of the Coast of
                Guinea.</hi> London, 1705. London: Frank Cass and Co., Ltd, 1967.</p>
            <p>Brantlinger, Patrick. “Victorians and Africans: The Genealogy of the Myth of the Dark
              Continent.” <hi rend="i">“Race,” Writing and Difference.</hi> Ed. Henry Louis Gates,
              Jr. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1986. 185-222.</p>
            <p>Clarkson, Thomas. <hi rend="i">An Essay on the Slavery and Commerce of the Human
                Species, particularly the African.</hi> Philadelphia: Joseph Chambers [?], 1786.
              Miami, Florida: Mnemosyne Reprinting, 1969.</p>
            <p>Cugoano, Ottobah. <hi rend="i">Thoughts and Sentiments on the Evil and Wicked Traffic
                of the Slavery and Commerce of the Human Species: Humbly Submitted to the
                Inhabitants of Great Britain by Ottobah Cugoano, a Native of Africa.</hi> London,
              1787. Ed. Paul Edwards. London: Dawsons of Pall Mall, 1969.</p>
            <p>Curtin, Philip D. <hi rend="i">The Image of Africa: British Ideas and Action,
                1780-1850.</hi> Vol. I. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, Ltd., 1964.</p>
            <p>Echeruo, Michael J.C. “Theologizing ‘Underneath the Tree’: An African Topos in
              Ukawsaw Gronniosaw, William Blake, and William Cole.” <hi rend="i">Research in African
                Literatures</hi> 23 
<pb id="p29-11" n="11"/> (1992): 51-58.</p>
            <p>Edwards, Paul. “An African Literary Source for Blake’s ‘Little Black Boy’?” 
                <hi rend="i">Research in African Literatures</hi> 21 (1990): 179-81.</p>
            <p>Edwards, Paul, and David Dabydeen, eds. <hi rend="i">Black Writers in Britain
                1760-1890.</hi> Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1991.</p>
            <p>Equiano, Olaudah. <hi rend="i">The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah
                Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa, the African, Written by Himself.</hi> 2 vols. London,
              1789. Ed. Paul Edwards. London: Dawsons of Pall Mall, 1969.</p>
            <p>Erkkila, Betsy. “Revolutionary Women.” <hi rend="i">Tulsa Studies in Women’s
                Literature</hi> 6 (1987): 189-221.</p>
            <p>Gates, Henry Louis, Jr. Foreword: “In Her Own Write.” <hi rend="i">Six Women’s Slave
                Narratives.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press, 1988.</p>
            <p>Gronniosaw, James Albert Ukawsaw. <hi rend="i">A Narrative of the Most Remarkable
                Particulars in the Life of James Albert Ukawsaw Gronniosaw, an African Prince, as
                Related by Himself.</hi> Bath: [c. 1770] and many later editions. Newport, 1774.</p>
            <p>Hayden, Lucy. “Classical Tidings from the Afric Muse: Phillis Wheatley’s Use of Greek
              and Roman Mythology.” <hi rend="i">CLA Journal</hi> 35 (1992): 432-47.</p>
            <p>Hinkel, Howard. “From Pivotal Idea to Poetic Ideal: Blake’s Theory of Contraries and
              ‘The Little Black Boy.’” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 11
              (1975): 39-45.</p>
            <p>Isani, Mukhtar Ali. “Early Versions of Some Works of Phillis Wheatley.” 
                <hi rend="i">Early American Literature</hi> 14 (1979): 129-35.</p>
            <p>Isani, Mukhtar Ali. “The British Reception of Wheatley’s <hi rend="i">Poems on
                Various Subjects.” Journal of Negro History</hi> 66 (1981): 144-49.</p>
            <p>James, William Lloyd. “The Black Man in English Romantic Literature, 1772-1833.”
              Diss. University of California at Los Angeles, 1977.</p>
            <p>Jordan, Winthrop D. <hi rend="i">White Over Black: American Attitudes Toward the
                Negro, 1550-1812.</hi> New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 1977.</p>
            <p>Lyons, Charles H. <hi rend="i">To Wash an Aethiop White: British Ideas About Black
                African Educability 1530-1960.</hi> New York: Teachers College Press, 1975.</p>
            <p>Macdonald, D.L. “Pre-Romantic and Romantic Abolitionism: Cowper and Blake.” 
                <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 4 (1994): 163-82.</p>
            <p>Manlove, C.N. “Engineered Innocence: Blake’s ‘The Little Black Boy’ and ‘The
Fly.’”
                <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 27 (1977): 112-21.</p>
            <p>Marshall, P.J. and Glyndwr Williams. <hi rend="i">The Great Map of Mankind: British
                Perceptions of the World in the Age of Enlightenment.</hi> London: J.M. Dent and
              Sons, 1982.</p>
            <p>Mason, Julian D. Introduction. <hi rend="i">The Poems of Phillis Wheatley.</hi> By
              Phillis Wheatley. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1989.</p>
            <p>Matson, Lynn R. “Phillis Wheatley—Soul Sister?” <hi rend="i">Phylon</hi> 33 (1972):
              222-30.</p>
            <p>Mbiti, John S. <hi rend="i">African Religions and Philosophy.</hi> Oxford: Heinemann
              International, 1989.</p>
            <p>Ngugi wa Thiong’o. <hi rend="i">Writers in Politics: Essays.</hi> Studies in African
              Literature. London: Heinemann, 1981.</p>
            <p>Odell, Margaretta M. <hi rend="i">Memoir and Poems of Phillis Wheatley, A Native
                African and a Slave.</hi> Boston: G.W. Light, 1834. 2nd ed. Boston: Light and
              Horton, 1835.</p>
            <p>O’Neale, Sondra. “A Slave’s Subtle War: Phillis Wheatley’s Use of Biblical Myth and
              Symbol.” <hi rend="i">Early American Literature</hi> 21 (1986): 145-65.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. “‘A New Heaven is Begun’: William Blake and Swedenborgianism.” 
                <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 50 (1979): 64-90.</p>
            <p>Richardson, Alan. “Colonialism, Race, and Lyric Irony in Blake’s ‘The Little Black
              Boy.’” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 26 (1990): 233-48.</p>
            <p>Robinson, William H., ed. <hi rend="i">Critical Essays on Phillis Wheatley.</hi>
              Boston: G.K. Hall &amp; Co., 1982.</p>
            <p>Salmon, Thomas. <hi rend="i">Modern History; or the Present State of All
              Nations</hi>.... London: 1735.</p>
            <p>Sandiford, Keith A. <hi rend="i">Measuring the Moment: Strategies of Protest in
                Eighteenth-Century Afro-English Writing.</hi> Selinsgrove: Susquehanna University
              Press, 1988.</p>
            <p>Shields, John C. “Phillis Wheatley.” <hi rend="i">African American Writers: Profiles
                of their Lives and Works from the 1700s to the Present.</hi> Ed. Valerie Smith, Lea
              Baechler, and A. Walton Litz. New York: Macmillan, 357-72.</p>
            <p>Shields, John C. “Phillis Wheatley and Mather Byles: A Study in Literary
              Relationship.” <hi rend="i">CLA Journal</hi> 23 (1980): 377-90.</p>
            <p>Smith, William. <hi rend="i">A New Voyage to Guinea.</hi> London: 1744.</p>
            <p>Stedman, J.G. <hi rend="i">A Narrative, of a Five Year’s Expedition, Against the
                Revolted Negroes of Surinam, in Guiana, on the Wild Coast of South America; from the
                Years 1772 to 1777.</hi> London, 1796.</p>
            <p>Wheatley, Phillis. <hi rend="i">The Poems of Phillis Wheatley.</hi> Ed. Julian D.
              Mason. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1989.</p>
            <p>Zahan, Dominique. <hi rend="i">The Religion, Spirituality, and Thought of Traditional
                Africa.</hi> Trans. Kate Ezra and Lawrence M. Martin. Chicago: University of Chicago
              Press, 1979.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
