<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.1.behrendt</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Gerda S. Norvig, Dark Figures in the Desired Country: Blake’s Illustrations to
The Pilgrim’s Progress</title>
        <author n="Behrendt">Stephen C. Behrendt</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Lauren G. Henry</name>
              <name>J.E.M. Latham</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
	<pb id="p29-25" n="25"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Gerda S. Norvig, <hi rend="i">Dark Figures in the Desired Country: Blake’s
Illustrations to The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> Berkeley: University of California Press, 1993. 327 pp.
$68.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Stephen C. <name>Behrendt</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>We have all seen them: those late-night television commercials for knives that cut through lead
pipes, pennies, wooden beams, and cement blocks—when all we want to do is slice a tomato. There is something
of that quality about Gerda Norvig’s impressive study of Blake’s much-neglected watercolor designs for
Bunyan’s most famous allegorical tale. This is a learned and meticulous book, as evidenced in part by the
fact that the 213 pages of primary text discussion are followed by 68 pages of notes and 14 of “Works
Cited.” Moreover, the book is splendidly illustrated. We are treated to all 28 of Blake’s designs (about
which number, more later), well reproduced in reasonably faithful color in a gathering of plates bound in the
middle of the book, plus another 42 related pictures and diagrams in black and white. In addition, the several
appendices provide 58 additional reproductions of previous <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>
illustrations up through the trend-altering designs of Blake’s erstwhile friend and colleague Thomas
Stothard, whose elliptical designs of 1788 brought to the illustration of Bunyan’s tale a wholly different
visual sensibility steeped in the visual conventions and mechanical devices of the sentimental in art. This
book is, in short, a trove of valuable visual information, and it cannot but help facilitate still further
exploration of Blake’s remarkable designs. That fact alone makes its publication both timely and
important.</p>
          <p>Why then the analogy of the knife-cum-everything? It’s partly a matter of the actual experience
of reading the book. For one thing, in working through the text a reader may become uncomfortably aware of the
inherent difficulty an author faces in structuring a book in which the reader is continually reminded of how
much preliminary ground ostensibly needs to be surveyed before the discussion can get to “the main event.”
This is especially so in that the author undertakes several complex tasks, several of which seem always to be
going forward at the same moment. By her own account she offers “a thorough case study of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Progress</hi> illustrations along with an analysis of his changing relationship to Bunyan’s
persona, Bunyan’s ideology, and Bunyan’s poetics [sic] over a period of more than thirty years” (4). At
the same time, she sets out to codify a way of reading Blake’s Bunyan designs (and presumably his designs to
other authors like Milton and Dante, though Norvig does not say so) in terms of a process of “visionary
hermeneutics,” a process based less in simply undermining or reinforcing the
<pb id="p29-26" n="26"/>
originating text than in a sort of “primary revision” that is neither more nor less derivative from some
originary internal (or Eternal) artistic vision than is the initial originating work of art (4-5). In this
respect Norvig’s discussion is heavily influenced by recent poststructuralist theories about the virtuality
of texts, as both the body of the text and the bibliographical citations make clear.</p>
          <p>The first half (roughly—117 pages) of <hi rend="i">Dark Figures</hi> fills us in on a variety
of verbal and visual materials we are given to understand we will need in order to read the Bunyan designs
aright. For example, Norvig furnishes an extended psychological reading of Blake’s proto-emblem series, 
<hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>, in which she discusses what she regards as a significant pairing of
designs that reveals “the dialectical principle of alteration” that governs the series, a pairing most
obvious in the facing plates of <hi rend="i">The Traveller Hasteth in the Evening</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Death’s Door.</hi> Norvig reads in the series as a whole a tale of the contrary operations of
expansion and contraction, and she observes about these two plates most particularly that “they attract each
other by the energy of their implied movement toward each other, and they repulse by the opposition of their
attitudes—psychological and figural—regarding the ultimate goal” (72-73). Her point is that the image of
a journey that governs the sequential images in <hi rend="i">The Gates</hi> indicates to the perceptive reader
a psychological and spiritual journey whose objective is the Jungian goal of individuation, a point she makes
in more systematic and detailed fashion about the later designs to Bunyan, in which the image of the journey
is again central. Indeed, Norvig’s overall interpretation of Blake’s Bunyan designs—as of Bunyan’s
tale and of <hi rend="i">The Gates</hi> and much else—is principally Jungian, a perspective particularly
compatible with her account of the internal journey she sees Blake tracing in his designs toward the
individuation not just of the central character(s) of the narrative but indeed of the central 
<hi rend="i">agent and object</hi> of the “real” action: the reader/viewer who interacts with both Bunyan’s
verbal text and Blake’s visual one.</p>
          <p>As much as anything, Norvig sees in Blake’s designs an exercise in reorienting the
reader/viewer—particularly in light of the findings of modern depth psychology—into a new way of
“seeing,” a new way of regarding both the verbal text of <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> and the
activity of reading it. This is why the long discussion of <hi rend="i">The Gates</hi> is here: it furnishes
both an analogy and a paradigmatic precursor for what the author sees taking place in Blake’s reading of 
<hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> And yet Norvig frankly admits that the emblems in <hi rend="i">The
Gates</hi> “are not about <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> per se, and the unravelling of
conflated allusions leads just as insistently to other literary ‘sources’” (73). But the manner in which
these emblems are treated here, as happens also with other verbal and visual texts (by Blake and by others)
which are introduced especially in the first two chapters, inherently imputes to them a disproportionate
significance which no disclaimers to the contrary can entirely mitigate. One cannot have it both ways.
Questions of “sources” and “indebtedness” are always intellectual minefields, of course, and it is
never any great surprise when explosions occur. Staying with <hi rend="i">The Gates</hi> for a moment, let me
cite a further example of how such difficulties can unfold. In discussing two familiar plates, <hi rend="i">I
Want! I Want!</hi> and <hi rend="i">Help! Help!</hi>, Norvig revisits the relationship of Blake’s images to
Gillray’s well-known print, <hi rend="i">The Slough of Despond; Vide the Patriot’s Progress</hi>, for
evidence that Blake is rereading both Gillray and Bunyan. Reminding us of David Erdman’s original discussion
of the particular visual connection suggested by the presence of a ladder in Gillray’s print and in 
<hi rend="i">I Want! I Want!</hi>, Norvig adds a new element to the discussion: “Yet when Blake adopts and
adapts the ladder imagery, he is not only attacking Gillray; he is also, and perhaps more importantly,
defending Bunyan by stressing the value (and problems) of a thematic concern for human aspiration, which is at
the root of the <hi rend="i">Progress</hi>” (62). This is rather a lot to base upon the evidence of
apparently recurrent images, and the manner of the assertion implies that we are meant to accept, with very
little question, suggestions and inferences (however attractive or credible) as interpretive certainties.</p>
          <p>I am less and less convinced that we ought quite so readily to credit Blake with the sort of
conscious and deliberate multilevel, multivalent allusions and revisions that go along with statements of this
sort, even though I have occasionally fallen into the trap myself over the years. For this whole business of
source-hunting with regard to Blake (indeed, with regard to <hi rend="i">any</hi> creative artist) tends often
to place the artist at the mercy of the interpreter, who may see connections that are not in fact there—or
perhaps not there in the sense in which the interpreter believes (or wants) them to be. In this case, while
Norvig argues convincingly for the connection between the Gillray (where the first two words in the “speech
balloon” above Charles James Fox’s head are “Help! Help!”) and the drowning figure in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Help! Help!</hi>, she fails to consider the comparably raised hand (raised, too, from amid similar
waves) of the central figure in John Singleton Copley’s 1778 painting, <hi rend="i">Watson and the
Shark</hi>, which created a sensation when it was exhibited at the Royal Academy in that year. The inability
to respond to available help (which is literally “at hand”), which lies at the intellectual and emotional
center of Copley’s painting, is perhaps as relevant thematically to Blake’s emblem, at last, as the
details of the Gillray print.</p>
          <p>I mention this minute particular because it is precisely the sort of thing that causes trouble at
a number of points along the way in <hi rend="i">Dark Figures.</hi> A particularly characteristic example
involves an image which Norvig introduces in her interesting discussion (58-59) of Blake’s print of 
<hi rend="i">The Man Sweeping the Interpreter’s Parlor</hi>, a print clearly related both to Bunyan’s tale and
to Blake’s subsequent identity among his young followers as “the Interpreter.” Norvig includes a
<pb id="p29-27" n="27"/>
copy of a print by Anton Wierix called <hi rend="i">Jesu Cor Expurgans</hi>, which image she, following Roger
Sharrock, claims directly influenced Bunyan’s scenes of the Interpreter’s rooms. Norvig says that
“Bunyan’s version of the parable <hi rend="i">is</hi> already a partial caricature of” that print and
that, further, “Blake borrowed that pose [of Wierix’s Jesus] for his representation of the Interpreter’s
Mosaic Law.” “<hi rend="i">It might have seemed</hi> a specially noteworthy irony to Blake,” Norvig
continues, that Bunyan replaced Jesus with two menials. “And <hi rend="i">if he did know the earlier
print</hi>,” she goes on, then the little creatures Blake depicts swirling about in the dust in his plate
“<hi rend="i">could be intended</hi> as allusions to the lost religion of Jesus that Wierix’s model of the
devout heart tried to embody. <hi rend="i">Thus</hi> the design of Blake’s engraving 
<hi rend="i">becomes</hi> an attempt to restore, by ironic revision, a sense of the heart’s virile, imaginative
integrity” (59; my emphases). Finally, some 10 pages later, the Wierix and the Gillray prints meet up in the
same sentence: “One could say Blake has rescued Bunyan from Gillray in these emblems [in <hi rend="i">The
Gates</hi>] as he rescued the vision of Wierix from Bunyan in the ‘Interpreter’s Parlor’ print”
(68).</p>
          <p>Rather a lot is made to hinge on several <hi rend="i">if</hi>s here, and it is not at all clear
that matters have to proceed in quite so tenuous a fashion in order for the argument to be mounted, especially
since Norvig herself reminds us in the midst of all of this of “the frequent reuse and widespread
availability of such popular illustrations in Blake’s day” (58): My point is simply that by tying one’s
argument in needlessly restrictive or exclusive fashion to <hi rend="i">particular</hi> images, particular
artists, and particular prints, one sometimes strains credibility unnecessarily and makes far too much rest
upon a shaky foundation of supposition, when it might well be sufficient to acknowledge the common currency of
the apparently “borrowed” image and reject the temptation to claim (or to imply) that Blake was working
with <hi rend="i">that particular image</hi> and that he was performing <hi rend="i">this particular
significant variation</hi> upon it and it alone. At the same time, it is surely no fault in an author to
attempt to give us as much information as possible so that we may make our own decisions about (possible)
influence in the most informed fashion. While Norvig occasionally seems to want to have it both ways, she also
credits us, generally, with both the innate sense and the critical acumen to make such decisions.</p>
          <p>Still, the rigidity (or narrowness) of interpretation that emerges at times here occasionally
interferes with the reader’s critical freedom—an irony itself in that we are reminded throughout of
Blake’s intellectual and aesthetic program of liberating the reader from the tyranny of text. But this
rigidity almost certainly results in part from the author’s efforts to marshall and discipline a great deal
of material within a study that seeks at once to introduce, describe, interpret, and contextualize a large
series of loosely organized (i. e., neither bound nor attached by explicit textual citation to the verbal
text) visual responses to <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> Indeed, we might most profitably think
about Blake’s designs as part of a dialogue in which Bunyan’s text supplies the other component. Thinking
about the designs and the dynamic of the reader/viewer’s responses to them is in fact clearly part of
Norvig’s plan, for she stresses more than once a Hegelian model reflective of the Spirit’s drive “to
redeem itself by repossessing its own lost and sundered self in an ultimate recognition of its own identity”
(117, quoting M.H. Abrams from <hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism</hi>). Interestingly, Lorraine Clark has
only recently claimed (<hi rend="i">Blake, Kierkegaard, and the Spectre of Dialectic</hi>, 1991) that in the
years following his Felpham sojourn Blake rejected the paradigm of the Hegelian dialectic in favor of an
apocalyptic embrace of Truth and an annihilation of Error. That shift from the pattern defined earlier by the
Conflict of Contraries suggests a different model of spiritual development than that which Norvig proposes
here, and yet the two are not finally incompatible.</p>
          <p>As Norvig sees it, Blake seems to have believed that Bunyan’s tale “was largely about the
visionary aim of the dreamer’s unconscious to dream the dream awake, thereby exemplifying a typological
process of psychological individuation.” Bunyan, she says, saw it differently, virtually ignoring “the
narrator’s role as shaper of the dream” and unfolding the tale “as a psychobiography not of the dreamer,
but of Christian” (129). Put another way, Blake brings the reader into the action by pairing that reader
with Bunyan’s dreamer-narrator and having both of them explore the dream. In a sense one might argue, then,
that the Hegelian dialectic is preserved in the implicit separation (even opposition) Blake posits between the
dreamer-narrator-reader and the shared dream, on the one hand, and the narrative content of that dream—the
plot through which Christian moves. And yet the apocalyptic resolution toward which Blake moves the
reader/viewer gradually eliminates entirely the narrow, time-bound, merely allegorical tale, replacing it with
an expanded visionary <hi rend="i">consciousness.</hi> Interestingly, Norvig suggests that Bunyan
intentionally left latent “the intimations that his fable contained about the curative, self-regulatory
structure of the dreamer’s imaginal life” (129). Whether Bunyan actually left this salutary substance
latent by conscious decision, or whether it is simply not there in Bunyan’s tale, is, however, more
difficult to determine.</p>
          <p>I do not wish, in ventilating these various issues and questions, to slight either the attempt or
the execution in <hi rend="i">Dark Figures</hi>, for this is going to remain a significant book, not just
because of the rich pictorial archive with which it provides us but also because of the important issues it
raises about Blake’s mature view of the nature of the imaginative life. It is worth thinking, in this
respect, about other series of illustrations in which Blake examines the relations that inhere between
literary predecessors like Milton or Gray, their works, and the “dreams” that mediate between them. The
most immediately obvious parallels lie in the designs to <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il
Penseroso.</hi> The final design for the former,
<pb id="p29-28" n="28"/>
“The Young Poet’s Dream,” offers a scenario whose visual conception is not unlike that of 
<hi rend="i">The Dreamer Dreams a Dream</hi> (<hi rend="i">Progress</hi> 1), except that the young Miltonic poet
is actually writing in a book. More immediately like the Bunyan is <hi rend="i">II Penseroso</hi> 5,
“Milton’s Dream,” in which the supine Milton is surrounded by the dream borne to him both by Sleep and
by his own expansive visionary capacity. What is different about these Milton designs is that in them Milton
is a participant in both the dreams and the waking activities the designs depict, whereas Bunyan appears only
in the first design, as “the Dreamer,” and is never part of the activity represented in subsequent
designs. Nor are we told explicitly that the latter dreamer is Bunyan, although the hairstyle and mustache are
decidedly Bunyanesque.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Dreamer Dreams a Dream</hi> is at once predictive and synoptic, gathering as it
does the chief elements of the entire tale—<hi rend="i">including the narrative frame</hi>—into a single
initial design. The “progress” moves from left to right in the “natural” <hi rend="i">visual</hi>
reading order that replicates even as it anticipates the narrative order of the verbal text. At the same time,
the physical placement of this arch of tableaux over the dreamer signals to us that the whole “sequence”
is also simultaneous—or perhaps instantaneous—in the dreamer’s visionary consciousness, 
<hi rend="i">within the dream itself</hi>, although it will take the following 27 designs (in which,
significantly, the dreamer is seen no more) to “draw out” what is here already present in the 
<hi rend="i">sleeping</hi> mind.</p>
          <p>Given my remarks above about interpretive impositions, I hesitate to say anything about the
number of designs—28—that Blake’s series comprises. But in light of the way in which, beginning in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Blake repeatedly treats the number 27 as a figure of relative incompletion and the
number 28 as a “complete” or visionarily fulfilled one, I find it interesting that only by including the
initial design of the dreamer is the set raised to the full complement of 28 designs. Was Blake perhaps
suggesting here that it is the presence of the <hi rend="i">dreamer</hi> (a commanding presence, in that he
both appears in and visually dominates the very first design) that furnishes the crucial element in
“completing” the vision encapsulated in the dream? And if so, would that fact serve to indicate to a
viewer sufficiently informed by and in the Blakean way of seeing that it is likewise the involved activity of
the <hi rend="i">reader/viewer</hi> that brings both Bunyan’s tale and Blake’s designs to fruition? While
I find the possibility tempting, especially in terms of the process of individuation involved for the
reader/viewer in reading the tale and viewing the designs, I offer it as nothing more than a suggestion.
Besides, to claim that the series is complete in 28 rather than 29 designs is to exclude a drawing variously
titled <hi rend="i">Christian Takes Leave of His Companions</hi> (Norvig), <hi rend="i">Christian with the
Shield of Faith, Taking Leave of His Companions</hi> (Butlin), and <hi rend="i">A Warrior with Angels</hi>
(its “old” title). While Martin Butlin claims that this design rightfully belongs within the full set of
designs, Norvig regards the drawing as “an alternate reading and a trial resolution of the repressive
implications of Bunyan’s passage” (181). She suggests that the ultimate narrative and thematic resolution
suggested by this design is premature, since the incident occurs before Christian’s confrontation with
Apollyon, and on this basis she proposes that the drawing “was intentionally diverted by Blake from the
current set of <hi rend="i">Progress</hi> drawings to stand or fall on its own merit” (182), a reasonable
and convenient way of resolving the difficulty, but one which seems just a bit too definitive.</p>
          <p>Norvig’s meticulous discussion of the actual Bunyan designs deftly interweaves Bunyan, Blake,
Jung, and the author’s own reading of the aim and scope of the separate projects undertaken by Bunyan and
Blake. It is hard, finally, not to respect her contention that in the designs Blake subtly shifts the focus of
Bunyan’s tale away from the history of Christian’s own spiritual development and instead onto the process
of individuation undergone by the dreamer and represented in the 27 images contained in his dreams. As I
mentioned above, Norvig proposes that Blake’s designs trace for us a quasi-Hegelian sketch of the dream
psyche, presenting us with a visual record of the development and ultimate near-resolution of what she calls a
state of “expectant evolution” (207). Interestingly, Norvig reminds us of the profound difference between
the conclusion Bunyan wrote and the final design Blake supplied. Where Bunyan ends on a “discordant and
disruptive” note, with a strong authorial assertion of the absolute distinction between the book’s
narrator and the protagonist of the dream, Blake draws the two together, superimposing them finally in the
character of the dreamer who is the reader/viewer’s representative in the designs. The difference, as Norvig
puts it, lies in the fact that Bunyan concludes by stressing the narrator’s <hi rend="i">exclusion</hi> from
the “Desired Country,” while Blake formulates a conclusion that is insistently 
<hi rend="i">inclusive.</hi> Bunyan ends not with Christian’s triumphal entry into the Celestial City, but
rather with “the cautionary tale of Ignorance’s defeat”; Blake’s dreamer “imagines an apotheosis of
the imagination as the fitting signal of an awakening in and from the dream” (209-10).</p>
          <p>It is hard, in any event, not to <hi rend="i">want</hi> Blake’s designs to be a creative,
revolutionary reworking of Bunyan’s allegories, for we instinctively want Blake’s art to take us above and
beyound the apparent reductivist simplicities of moral allegory. And so we happily “discover” that Blake
rescues precursor artists (and their visions) from various failings of vision or of spirit. And perhaps he
does; certainly his designs to the works of other authors always constitute a compelling part of an
intellectual and aesthetic dialogue whose minute particulars it behooves us always to labor carefully. The
inherent danger in such labors is, of course, an over-particularity that occasionally traps us into
absolutist, exclusive claims that are themselves a tyranny of sorts. Like many studies (and not just of Blake)
that have labored to extract complicated intellectual agendas from often elusive and always complex visual
statements, <hi rend="i">Dark Figures in the Desired Country</hi>
	<pb id="p29-29" n="29"/>
occasionally takes rather a harder, more inflexible critical line than one might wish. At the same time, as
Blake was fond of reminding us, hard, wiry bounding lines do have their place, if only in serving to delineate
figures (or intellectual positions) so that we may encounter them and argue with them. Gerda Norvig’s book
seems to me an immense achievement, and one that will necessarily provide the foundation for future discussion
of the designs to <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> She has provided us with a vast treasury of
resources, verbal and visual, together with a carefully documented reading of those designs that seeks to
account in systematic fashion for the many contexts that inform them, Bunyan’s originating narrative, and
the century and a half of intellectual, spiritual, cultural, and aesthetic evolution that separated them. She
has given us much to think about, much to talk about, and much to write about. For that, we are in her
debt.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
