<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.1.viscomi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">William Blake’s “The Phoenix / to Mrs Butts” Redux</title>
        <author n="Viscomi">Joseph Viscomi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Lauren G. Henry</name>
              <name>J.E.M. Latham</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-1-0005">
        <pb id="p29-12" n="12"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">William Blake’s “The Phoenix / to Mrs Butts” Redux</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Joseph <name>Viscomi</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In “William Blake’s ‘The Phoenix’: A Problem in Attribution,” Robert N. Essick argues
that “The Phoenix / to Mrs Butts,” a manuscript poem discovered in 1981 and first attributed to Blake by
Geoffrey Keynes, was indeed written by Blake for Mrs. Butts and is not a forgery, as Morton Paley and David
Bindman had suspected (“Phoenix” 366).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">1</ref> Essick bases his argument on the bibliographical and technical features of the work, and
not on the style of the poem or the provenance of the artifact, though he uses the provenance to support his
conclusion. And therein lies a potential problem, for the provenance given to Keynes by the poem’s owner is
impossible. A mistaken provenance does not necessarily mean that the artifact is bogus, but it does raise red
flags. In this brief note, I argue that “The Phoenix” is authentic and the provenance mistaken because two
families directly connected to Thomas Butts have been unknowingly conflated. Only one of these families,
however, is known to Blake scholars, and thus, by correcting the provenance of a minor work, I hope also to
shed light on Blake’s patron, his patron’s family, and the way in which works from the Butts collection
were distributed. (These are the subjects of two forthcoming studies.) <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
Keynes’s article was written just before his death but published two years later. The poem is included in
Erdman 517. The manuscript, which is described in detail in Essick’s “Phoenix” article, is MS 63583 in
the British Library, Department of Western Manuscripts. The provenance given to Keynes is the same as given to
Dr. Daniel Waley, the Librarian of the Department of Manuscripts.</note></p>
          <p>Keynes, the first to record the provenance, identifies the
<q>
owner . . . [as] Mr Owen D. Long, resident in Wales. It came to him through his grandmother, whose maiden name
was Mary Anne North, daughter of Mrs North, formerly Miss Cooper, who by her second marriage became Mrs Butts.
I had not been aware that she, born Cooper, had made a previous marriage as Mrs North, and this is all that
the owner knows of his descent, but it is quite plain that the document signed William Blake and addressed
‘To Mrs Butts’ has been traced to its authentic origin. (1021)
</q></p>
          <p>The idea that Mrs. Butts had been previously married may have been news to Keynes, but it was
first noted in 1956 by Bentley in “Thomas Butts, White Collar Maecenas” (1053n7). Bentley infers the
second marriage from the fact that Butts, in his will (p. 8), bequeathed rings and ten pounds to “Mary Ann
the wife of my said son Thomas Butts a Ring of the value of nineteen pounds nineteen shillings and six pence .
. . to Mrs Maria North, the daughter-in-law of my said wife [Elizabeth], to Mr Charles Long, to Mrs Mary Anne
Long his wife and who is a daughter of my wife, to Mr
            <figure n="BBWBA1.1.1.MS" rend="file" width="692" height="1000">
	<head>1 William Blake, “The Phoenix / To Mrs Butts, c. 1800-03.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
Henry Baker and to Mrs Caroline Matilda Baker his wife, who is also a daughter of my wife.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">2</ref> From this passage, specifically the mention of
a daughter-in-law named North, Bentley reasonably inferred that Mrs. Butts was married to a Mr. North before
marrying Butts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">3</ref> In the will, Butts
does not mention his wife’s maiden or married name, but <hi rend="i">Burke’s</hi> and Ada Briggs identify
her as Elizabeth Cooper (93). <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Bentley records “Maria” as “Mary”
(1053n7). Butts’s will was proved on 23 June 1845; it is #2019 in the Public Records Office, Chancery Lane,
London. The 15 unnumbered pages of the document are here numbered for convenience.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Essick constructs the same lineage: “The ‘Mary Ann Long’ in that
document is the ‘Mary Anne North’ (her maiden name) who Owen Long states was his grandmother from whom he
inherited the ‘Phoenix’ manuscript. Mary Anne’s husband and the grandfather of Owen Long was evidently
Charles Long, the ‘son-in-law’ (i.e., the husband of one of his wife’s daughters by her first marriage)
to whom Butts lent money” (“Phoenix” 375-76). Butts lent Charles Long 1500 pounds “on Mortgage of a
freehold house in Landsdowne place . . . in the county of Sussex,” and he lent him 850 pounds on mortgages
of the leasehold houses at “nos. 30 and 35 North Street Battlebridge and 87 and 25 Carlisle Street Portman
Market,” London (will p. 3-4).</note></p>
          <p>The will implies that Butts married a woman who had previously been married. Bentley and Essick
reasonably assumed that the will’s Elizabeth is Elizabeth Cooper and that she had married a Mr. North 
<hi rend="i">before</hi> marrying Butts and thus was the mother of the Butts children as well as the mother of the
North children. But if her children with Mr. North came before those with Butts, then they were born before or
no later than 1783, since Joseph Edward Butts, Butts’s eldest child, was born 4 February 1784 
(<hi rend="i">Burke’s</hi>). If so, Owen Long’s math fails to add up. It is nearly impossible
<pb id="p29-13" n="13"/>
for a daughter of Mrs. Butts born before 1783 to have a grandchild living in 1981.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">4</hi> According to <hi rend="i">Burke’s</hi>, Tommy Butts was born 27
September 1788, which means that he was 18 when he began working with his father in December 1806 (Bentley
1058). Apparently, Joseph Edward was 15 in 1799 when he began working with his father (Bentley
1057).</note></p>
          <p>At first glance, only Owen Long’s math and not the lineage itself appears incorrect. Either
Mary Ann Long was Owen Long’s <hi rend="i">great</hi> grandmother—that is, at least one remove more than
he imagined—or she was born after the Butts children. But in fact it is the lineage and not only the
chronology that he has confused. According to the International Genealogy Index (IGI), Mary Ann Long was Mary
Ann Delanney, baptized 25 January 1802 and married to Charles Long on 24 November 1827 in the parish of St.
Pancras, Euston Road, London. Her mother was Elizabeth Delanney, who married Thomas Butts on 15 June 1826 in
the parish of St. Pancras, which, according to Butts’s will (p. 6), is his parish. The record in the
marriage register of St. Pancras provides the proof that the groom is Blake’s patron:
<q>
Thomas Butts of this Parish Widower and Elizabeth Delauney of this Parish Widow were married in this Church by
Licence . . . this fifteenth Day of June in the Year One thousand eight hundred and Twenty Six by me J.
Brackenbury Curate. This Marriage was solemnized between us Thos. Butts [and] Eliz<hi rend="s">th</hi>
Delauney In the presence of John G Fearn[,] Mary Ann Delauney [,] Caroline M Delauney<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The discovery of Butts’s second marriage in the International Genealogy
Index and the examination of the marriage register for the parish of St. Pancras, Euston Road were made by
Keri Davies and Ted Ryan. I am grateful for their assistance here and for their examining army lists for me in
my research on Butts’s family. The register was verified by Lilian Gibbens of Heritage Research, who
believes that the name is Delauney and not Delanney (as recorded by Davies, Ryan, and the IGI). 
<hi rend="i">Burke’s</hi> does not mention the second marriage, perhaps because there was no progeny, but
possibly because the Captain died in 1905 and whoever provided the information to <hi rend="i">Burke’s</hi>
(presumably Captain Butts’s wife Mary Jane, or less likely, his daughter Mary, who was born in 1891), was
unaware of the marriage. Nor does <hi rend="i">Burke’s</hi> record the second marriage of Thomas Butts’s
father, a marriage verified by Butts’s will and probably the one recorded in IGI in 1767 (see “Green
House”).</note></q></p>
          <p>The names of the female witnesses prove that the widower is Blake’s patron. As noted, in his
will Butts identifies Mary Ann Long and Caroline Matilda Baker as “daughters of his wife,” and Mary
Ann’s maiden name was Delauney (or Delanney). Further search through the IGI reveals that Caroline Matilda
Delauney (or Delanney) married Henry Baker in the parish of St. Pancras, Euston Road, on 24 June
1837.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">6</ref> Their mother, the widow
Elizabeth Delauney, had married Peter Delauney in the church of St. George, Hanover Square, Westminister, on
25 October 1791. Elizabeth’s maiden name was Davis. Her daughter Caroline’s birth and christening dates
are not recorded in IGI (which means that it most likely occurred in one of the many parishes that have yet to
enter the IGI). <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">6</hi> In addition to the IGI, see the more powerful CD-Rom Family
Program (which is not available in England but is available in the NYPL and the Family Research Centers of The
Church of Jesus Christ Latter Day Saints).</note></p>
          <p>The “Elizabeth Butts” mentioned in Butts’s will was his second wife and not Elizabeth
Cooper, the mother of his children and the woman, according to Briggs, known as “Betsy.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">7</ref> This second marriage solves a minor mystery in
Blake studies: Mrs. Butts’s age at the time of her death and the place of her death. Her obituary in the 
<hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> for February 1852 records her date of death as 24 December 1851 at 81
years, implying a birth year of 1770. This is much too late for Elizabeth Cooper—unless she married Butts
when she was still a child, or lied about her age when she died. The birth year, however, is consistent with
Elizabeth Delauney. The obituary also records her dying outside her own home, “In Upper Gower St,” despite
being the “relict of Thomas Butts, esq. of Grafton-st.” She apparently died at the home of her daughter
Caroline Baker, who lived with her husband Henry, an architect, at 11 Upper Gower Street. In the 1840s, the
Bakers lived at 25 Grafton Street, a few doors down from the Butts’s at 17 Grafton. Upon Butts’s death in
1845, Tommy Butts inherited the Grafton residence and, according to the will, Mrs. Butts was required to
vacate the premises three months after her husband’s death (p. 2). She apparently moved in with her daughter
Caroline. <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Briggs was the sister of Captain Butts’s much younger second
wife, whom he married in 1889. Her knowledge of the family a hundred years earlier is unreliable and seems
based on family lore and the relics in her sister’s house. She does not mention a second marriage for Butts
and may be conflating histories. Her brother-in-law the Captain was born in 1833 and knew his grandfather’s
wife and not his biological grandmother.</note></p>
          <p>Mrs. Delauney, if 81 when she died, was around 56 when she married Butts. Butts has been
mistakenly believed to have been born in 1757 (Bentley “Butts” 1052) and thus Blake’s exact
contemporary. But he was the third son named Thomas born to Thomas Butts and Hannah Witham. The first was
baptized on 13 March 1746, the second on 12 July 1756, and the third, born 15 December 1759, was baptized on 9
January 1760.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">8</ref> Apparently, the first
two children died in infancy.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">9</ref> Hence,
he was two years younger than Blake and
<pb id="p29-14" n="14"/>
was 66 years old at the time of his second marriage, with all of his children gone, but possibly with a new
stepdaughter, Caroline Matilda Delauney, still at home.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The birth and baptism are recorded in the baptism register of the parish
of St. Luke, Old Street, Finsbury, which is in the Greater London Records Office; the IGI records only the
baptism year. <hi rend="i">Burke’s</hi> records the correct day and year of birth.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Butts’s parents were married on 19 May 1746 in St. Andrew by the
Wardrobe, London (IGI). Infant mortality was high, as any cursory examination of the burial registers of
London parishes demonstrates. The repetition of the same name for children to the same parents in the IGI
suggests the same. (Sometimes, however, male children would be given the father’s name but be known by their
middle name to increase the chances that the name on a leasehold dwelling would remain unchanged.) The Buttses
also had two Elizabeths, baptized on 14 January 1750 and 26 September 1757. (For a genealogy of the Butts
family, see Viscomi, “Green House.”)</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">10</hi> I have not been able to locate the place and date for the death of Mrs.
Cooper Butts. Unfortunately, the burial register for parish of St. Pancras, Euston Road, for the years 1810-17
are not available for consultation, and the microfilm of them in the Greater London Records Office is
overexposed and much of it I could not read. The death may have been after 1816, for Tommy appears to have
lived at home at least till then. His schoolboy friend Seymour Kirkup records visiting him and the Butts
collection between 1810 and 1816 (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 220-21). Kirkup refers to the
“Buttses” and to “they,” but he is not clear if he is referring to Mr. and Mrs. Butts, or to father
and son. Would it be suprising if she had died c. 1810-11, when Butts appears to have stopped buying Blakes?
                            <p>There are no letters between Blake and Butts after 1803, only receipts, the
last extant one in December 1810. Blake mentions in an undated letter to Linnell, c. April 1826, that Butts
visited him and purchased at discount (for lending the watercolors) a copy of the <hi rend="i">Book of
Job</hi> (Erdman 777). Blake makes no mention of the forthcoming second marriage.</p></note></p>
          <p>The second marriage of Butts supports—though only barely—Owen Long’s claim that he
inherited “The Phoenix” from his grandmother, Mary Ann Long, since she was born to Butts’s second rather
than first wife, in 1802 rather than before 1783.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">11</ref> The second marriage, however, also refutes Long’s lineage, because Elizabeth
Delauney’s maiden name was Davis and not North, and there is no record of her ever marrying a North between
Peter Delauney (1791) and Thomas Butts (1826). She was remarried as Mrs. Delauney, and her daughter Mary Ann
was also married as a Delauney. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Mary Ann Long had two sons, Edwin Williams
Long in 1832 and Charles Albert Long in 1829. For either man to have been Charles Long’s father means he
sired him very late in his own life.</note></p>
          <p>Where, then, does Owen Long come up with the name Mary Ann North? Did Mr. Long know Bentley’s
article, which mentions that Mrs. Butts was born Elizabeth Cooper and was previously married to a Mr. North
(1053n7)? Did he, in other words, deliberately construct a false provenance? Like Essick (“Phoenix” 376),
I think this is unlikely, since Bentley recorded the long “L” of “Long” as an “S,” which it very
closely resembles, and thus identified the daughter-in-law as Mary Ann Song. If Owen Long read Bentley, then
he would have not found the name Long. For that he would have had to examine the original will, and correct
what the trained eye of one of Blake studies most astute scholars missed. No, we are not dealing with a very
sophisticated forgery. Admittedly, my suspicion of the provenance made me suspect forgery and forced me to
examine the will and the poem. I can verify that the surname is “Long” (as Bentley now also acknowledges)
and, after a close inspection of the poem, that I believe it was written—both invented and executed on
paper—by Blake. The only conclusion, then, is that Owen Long’s memory played tricks on him, that he
conflated various people in Butts’s first and second families into one direct descendent. According to
Keynes, the poem’s provenance was “all that the owner knows of his descent.” Apparently, Mr. Long knew
even less than that.</p>
          <p>Did his grandmother Mary Ann Long marry a Mr. North after 1845, the year Butts’s will was
proved? While possible, it seems too much of a coincidence that Mrs. Delauney Butts’s “daughter-in-law,”
was also named Maria North. One possible explanation for Long’s mixing up Long and North is suggested by the
marriage of Cornelius Delaney and Mary Ann Mickeburg in the parish of St. Pancras, Euston Road, in 1829. This
is the parish of Butts and the Delauneys, which suggests that Cornelius may have been a son of Elizabeth and
Peter Delauney (the name was not common in any of its spellings). If so, then Mary Mickeburg would be Mrs.
Delauney Butts’s daughter-in-law, Mary (or Maria). She may have remarried a Mr. North before 1844, when
Butts wrote his will, and have been referred to by her new married name. Owen Long may have confused his great
aunt Mary Delaney-North with his grandmother, Mary Ann Delauney Long. If Long knew his grandmother, born in
1802, he would have been very young and she very old. It seems more likely that they had never met. Family
lore may have conflated the two Marys, who were sister-in-laws. A similar kind of conflation has happened in
Blake studies with the two Elizabeth Butts’s, Ms. Cooper and Ms. Delauney.</p>
          <p>Knowing that the Elizabeth of Butts’s will is his second wife forces us to re-examine not only
the poem’s provenance but also its date. Was “The Phoenix / to Mrs Butts” written for the first Mrs.
Butts, c. 1800-03, when he wrote the Butts’s regularly and even composed another poem to Mrs. Butts (E 714)?
Or was it addressed to the second Mrs. Butts, c. 1826-27—a comment on the second and resurrected marriage
bed?</p>
          <p>The poem’s visual style does not rule out a late date. The text was written in blue ink and
gone over in four colors, giving it a multi-colored appearance not unlike that of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi> copy H, which was first printed in c. 1790 but finished in Blake’s late coloring style
with the text rewritten in colored inks, presumably in c. 1821 for John Linnell. No other work produced in the
1790s has this much rewriting in colored inks, but nearly all early copies of <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel</hi> and many plates in the early copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> have texts that were
rewritten in matching and sometimes nonmatching colored inks to salvage a poorly printed line (see Viscomi,
<hi rend="i">Book</hi> ch. 15). The lettering in the motto of early copies of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (e.g., B,
E, and G, among others) was touched up in colored inks for purely
<pb id="p29-15" n="15"/>
decorative purposes. So the rewriting of text per se is not out of place c. 1800-03. Indeed, the poem, placed
between a thin willowy tree and cascading tendrils, looks like a page from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (illus. 1); the writing, drawing, and rewriting seem of a piece. The difference between
this private poem and Blake’s public works is that it was executed on paper and is truly a unique
manuscript, and not on copper, where such poems exist as “printed manuscript” (Essick, 
<hi rend="i">Language</hi> 170).</p>
          <p>Essick dates the poem c. 1794 not only because of its resemblance to early illuminated pages
(“Phoenix” 377), but also because Gilchrist states that Butts probably met Blake as early as 1793 (1:
115). But Gilchrist offers no evidence for his claim, and a meeting this early seems very unlikely. The facts
that four of Butts’s 10 illuminated books were acquired from Cumberland’s auction of 1835 (Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 657), that three of them were produced after 1810 (<hi rend="i">Milton, Ghost of
Abel</hi>, and a posthumous copy of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>), that one, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
and of Experience</hi> copy E, was purchased in 1806, and that two early works, <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> copy L
and <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> copy F, were acquired at unknown dates and are without
receipts—and possibly not acquired by Butts (see Viscomi “Marketplace 1852”)—strongly suggest that
patron and artist had met after Blake’s great period of illuminated printing, 1789-95. Blake’s first
reference to Butts is in a letter to Cumberland in 1799, where he is presumably the patron paying Blake one
guinea apiece for the biblical temperas (Keynes, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> 11).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">12</ref> Blake began writing the Butts’s only when he left London
for Felpham, between 1800 and 1803. The poem was probably written during this period, when he wrote poems to
Butts, Mrs. Butts, Flaxman, and Mrs. Flaxman (see Erdman 707-23, 733). Mr. Butts also wrote Blake a poem,
included in a September 1800 letter, explicitly acknowledging his affection for Catherine Blake and Blake’s
affection for Mrs. Butts—acknowledgments not without double entendres (see Keynes, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>
25-27). Perhaps it is not a coincidence that the couplets of Blake’s other verses have three or five beats
to the line, whereas those of “The Phoenix” have four, the same number of accents as in the couplets of
Thomas Butts’s poem to Blake (Keynes, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> 26-27).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">12</hi> For a more detailed discussion of the first meeting of artist and patron,
see my “Green House.”</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Keynes’s <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> article was accompanied by an
announcement that a longer version of the article and a color reproduction of Blake’s manuscript poem, along
with a note on the dating by Michael Phillips, was available for L14 (1022). Unfortunately, the pamphlet was
not issued. On stylistic grounds, Phillips dates the work c. 1803 (private correspondence).</note></p>
          <p>“The Phoenix” was probably written c. 1800-03 to Mrs. Cooper Butts. After she died, the poem
appears to have come into the possession of Butts’s second wife. In his will, he bequeaths “all articles
of plate jewelry trinkets and furniture whether useful or ornamental whatsoever which belonged to her at the
time of our marriage or which I may have since presented her with” (p. 1). Or perhaps the poem was simply
“inherited” by or left over for the new Mrs. Butts, who gave it to her married daughter, Mary Ann Long,
whom Owen Long misidentified as Mary Anne North, possibly confusing her with a great aunt. This minor poem’s
provenance reveals that Butts’s family was more extended than previously realized and demonstrates how works
of Blake’s—especially those of little monetary value in the mid-nineteenth century, including watercolors
selling at auction for less than or only slightly more than the original purchase price of one pound—could
exit the Butts collection through members of Butts’s second family and not solely through Thomas Butts, Jr.
Knowing now that Mr. Long’s claim may be a bit confused but at least plausible strengthens the argument that
other works exited in like manner, including (as I discuss in the forthcoming articles, “Blake in the
Market-place 1852” and “A ‘Green House’ for Butts”) a collection of Blake’s illuminated books,
illustrated books, and watercolors that was sold anonymously at Sotheby’s in March 1852, and a collection of
biblical watercolors and half the 1808 series of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> that sold at Sotheby’s in
June 1852 as part of Charles Ford’s collection.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E. Jr. “Thomas Butts, White Collar Maecenas.” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> 71 (1956):
1052-66.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, 1969.</p>
            <p>Briggs, Ada E. “Mr. Butts, the Friend and Patron of Blake.” <hi rend="i">The
Connoisseur</hi> 19 (1907): 92-97.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Burke’s Landed Gentry of Great Britain.</hi> 12th edition, London, 1914.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Rev. ed. New
York: Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of Adam.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon
Press, 1989.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake’s ‘The Phoenix’: A Problem in Attribution.” 
<hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 67 (1988): 365-84.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. <corr type="emend">London: Macmillan,
1863.</corr></p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake</hi>, 3rd edition. Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1980.</p>
            <p>—. “An Unpublished Poem by William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>
(14 September 1984): 1021-22.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton
University Press, 1993.</p>
            <p>—. “Blake in the Marketplace 1852: Thomas Butts, Jr. and Other Unknown Nineteenth-Century
Blake Collectors.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> (forthcoming).</p>
            <p>—. “A ‘Green House’ for Butts? New Information on Thomas Butts, his Residence, and
Family.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> (forthcoming).</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
