<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.2.viscomi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake in the Marketplace 1852: Thomas Butts, Jr. and Other Unknown
          Nineteenth-Century Blake Collectors</title>
        <author n="Viscomi">Joseph Viscomi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Clark</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <pb id="p29-40" n="40"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake in the Marketplace 1852: Thomas Butts, Jr. and Other Unknown
              Nineteenth-Century Blake Collectors</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Joseph <name>Viscomi</name></docAuthor></byline>
		<q> The interest attaching to the great collection of Blake’s works formed by his almost
            solitary purchaser, Mr. Butts, has induced me to specify which were once his, even in
            the instances where they have passed out of the family. In some cases, the owners have
            not been traced: in others, the imputed ownership has probably ceased to be
            correct.<lb/>
 W. M. Rossetti, in Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">The Life of William
              Blake</hi> (2: 199)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n0">I am very
              grateful to Martin Butlin and Robert Essick for reading early drafts of this article
              and for their many helpful suggestions.</note>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
              William Michael Rossetti’s lists are in the second volume of Alexander Gilchrist’s 
                <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> (1863). They are here referred to as Rossetti, followed
              by page and entry numbers.</note></q>
          <p>In 1968, while compiling his magnificent catalogue raisonné of Blake’s paintings and
            drawings, Martin Butlin appealed “for help over an untraced catalogue for a sale of
            works from the Butts collection” (“William Rossetti” 39).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref> This, the largest Blake collection ever formed, was assembled
by Thomas
            Butts, one of Blake’s most important patrons, probably between c. 1799 and c. 1810, and
            between c. 1820 and c. 1827. It consisted of over 200 biblical temperas and watercolors,
            Milton illustrations, color-print drawings, illuminated books, illustrated books, and
            engravings. Butts never catalogued the collection, but because most of it was dispersed
            through auctions, beginning in 1852 with an auction attributed to Butts Jr. (Butlin, 
              <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> p. 336, hereafter referred
            to as Butlin; numbers are catalogue entries unless preceded by a “p”), its general
            make-up can be reconstructed through sale catalogues. By knowing its contents, we can
            trace the provenances of individual works, gauge Blake’s productivity at specific
            periods in his life, and estimate the extent of Butts’s patronage. Thus, the possible
            loss of a sale catalogue is disturbing. The collection may have been larger than
            previously thought, and the provenances of works not formerly connected to Butts may
            need to be altered. Furthermore, dispersal of the collection may have begun earlier than
            1852 and undertaken by someone other than Butts Jr. Indeed, if a sale with Blakes from
            the Butts collection is found whose vendor is not Butts Jr. or another member of the
            Butts family, then Blake’s first audience was a little larger than we realize, 
              <figure n="SothebyTitlePage.29.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="454">
              <head>1 Title page, Sotheby’s sale catalogue for Charles Ford’s collection, 26 June
                1852.</head>
            </figure> consisting of collectors possibly unknown to us, and the dispersal of the
            Butts collection may not only have occurred earlier than previously thought but have
            also occurred through avenues other than auctions.</p>
          <p>Butlin infers an untraced Butts sale from comments made by William Michael Rossetti in
            his, the first, catalogue raisonné of Blake’s works (Butlin 472). Rossetti states that
            six biblical watercolors and three illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
            (1808) were acquired by a “Mr. Fuller, from Mr. Butts,” and he quotes descriptions of
            these works “from the Salecatalogue.” For example, Rossetti records the provenance of
              <hi rend="i">He Cast Him into the Bottomless Pit</hi> as “Mr. Fuller, from Mr. Butts”
            and states that it is “Described in the Sale-catalogue as ‘very powerful and
            characteristic” (229, #174). No known sale contains this work, a buyer named Fuller, or
            a similar description. Butlin, forced to conclude that a sale is untraced, records the
            early provenance of this work as: “Thomas Butts; Thomas Butts jun., untraced sale;
            Fuller by 1863. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
Rossetti records each of
            Fuller’s nine purchases in the same 
<pb id="p29-41" n="41"/>
way, quoting descriptions
            and/or titles from the “Sale-catalogue” and nothing more, which implies not only an
            untraced Butts auction took place but also that Rossetti had not seen the drawings
            themselves, that he was relying on an annotated sale catalogue or a transcript for
              information.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi>
              Butlin 524. The other Fuller purchases are similarly recorded (see Butlin 195, 513,
              519, 521, 522, and 536.1, 2, 10).</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Rossetti
              does the same with works from the 26-27 March 1852 sale that he had not examined. They
              are recorded as coming “from Mr. Butts” and their descriptions as coming “from the
              Sale-catalogue.” For example, lot 148 of this sale is “<hi rend="i">The Covenant</hi>,
              very fine,” which Rossetti records as: “<hi rend="i">The Covenant.</hi> [From Mr.
              Butts.] Described in the Salecatalogue as ‘very fine’” (231, #193). Items recorded
              simply as coming “from Mr. Butts” were often not given a present owner, presumably
              because Rossetti was unaware of their locations in 1863.</note></p>
          <p>Looking through auction catalogues in search of something else, I recently found the
            “untraced sale,” but, as is often the case, the discovery raises more questions than it
            answers. The auction was of drawings, watercolors, and paintings and was held at
            Sotheby’s on 26 June 1852. The “Fuller” recorded as buyer was almost certainly either
            Joseph or Samuel, brothers who were well-known print dealers in London between 1808 and
            1862. They frequently attended auctions and may have been buying for H. A. J. Munro, who
            sold all nine works at Christie’s on 22-24 April 1868. Rossetti implies that Fuller
            still retained ownership in 1863, but the works were probably Munro’s by that time,
            since the Fullers sold their stock of prints and drawings in 1862.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
              type="note">4</ref> In addition to Fuller’s nine acquisitions, the June 1852 auction
            included 17 other biblical watercolors, three other 1808 <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
            illustrations, and two other works by Blake that may have been prints or sketches (see
            Appendix 1 for an annotated list of the Blakes in this sale). According to the title
            page of the sale catalogue (illus. 1), the primary vendor was “Charles Ford of Bath”
            (1801-70), who was probably the miniaturist who lived and worked in Bath. According to
            Graves, he exhibited at the Royal Academy between 1830 and 1856 
              (<hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> 2: 136). He is not listed in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of
National
              Biography</hi>, in any book on Blake, or in books on British watercolorists, but is
            mentioned in a few reference works in art history (like Thieme-Becker and E. Benezit)
            and a few works on British miniaturists, one of which succinctly notes that “little is
            known about him. He was in his day one of the principal miniaturists at Bath. He may
            possibly have been related to Charles Ford, an ironmonger” (Long 156). Foskett adds a
            little more: “according to O’Brien [he] was a pupil and friend of Sir Thomas Lawrence”
              (275).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Ford collected
primarily the works of
            painters from his own generation and the one immediately preceding his, including
            Richard Parkes Bonington, David Cox, Peter De Wint, J. F. Lewis, George Chambers, A. V.
            Copley Fielding, James Harding, John Martin, David Roberts, and David Wilkie.<ref
              target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Of Blake’s generation, Ford collected J. M. W. Turner,
            Joshua Cristall, Robert Hills, George Barrett, and Thomas Gainsborough.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
              type="note">7</ref> But did he collect William Blake? 
                <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> In <hi rend="i">Kelley’s Postal Directory</hi> for 1852,
they are listed as
              “printsellers, publishers, and preparers of superfine watercolors [sic]” and were
              located at 34 and 35 Rathbone Place. A steel engraving of their shop is reproduced
              among the directory’s advertisements. The “Fuller” at the Ford auction is most likely
              the printseller, as is indicated by his purchase of lot 59: “D. Roberts, R. A. The
              bull Ring at Seville, engraved, very fine,” for £8 10s., the second highest price paid
              for an item at the auction, and his only other purchase besides the Blakes. The
              “Extensive, Interesting, and Valuable Collection of Modern Engravings, and Illustrated
              Books, principally the Stock of Messrs. Fuller (sold in consequence of the retirement
              of the senior partner)” was auctioned at Southgate and Barrett on 3 - 12 November
              1862. No Blakes were listed.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> A <corr type="emend">miniaturist</corr>
              painter named J. E. Ford lived in London at 15 Camomile Street, Bishopsgate, according
              to the <hi rend="i">Wakefield [Postal] Directory</hi> of 1794. The most famous Ford of
              Bath was Ann Ford, who married Phillip Thicknesse. Whether Charles Ford was a relative
              of either family is not known; he may have been the son or descendant of John Ford of
              Bath, a “Miniature Painter etc,” who exhibited at the Free Society of Artists in 1764,
              1774, 1775, 1776 (Graves, <hi rend="i">Society</hi>). <p>Linnell records in his
                journal for 8 May 1820: to “Mr Wyatt. with Mr Blake / To Lady Ford—saw her Pictures”
                (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> 104). According to 
                  <hi rend="i">Fraser’s Magazine</hi> 58 (July to December 1858), Lady Ford (the daughter of
                Benjamin Booth, a great collector of Wilson) had two children, Richard, the critic
                and collector, who was the oldest, and James, a prebendary (423). Richard Brinsley
                Ford, a descendant, informs me that he knows of no one in his family to have
                collected Blake (private correspondence).</p>
	<p>“O’Brien” is D. O’Brien, who wrote
                  <hi rend="i">Miniatures in the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries</hi> (London,
                1951). Both Long (156) and Foskett (275) state that Charles Ford was “an associate
                of Wordsworth and Hannah More.” No work on Wordsworth—biographies, chronologies, or
                letters—mentions him and no portrait by him of the poet is known, but Wordsworth had
                visited Bath for several weeks in April 1839, in April and May 1841, and in March
                1847 (Selincourt 3: 672-690; 4: 189-198; 4: 835-841).</p>
	<p>A “Ford” was at the
                Sotheby auction of Robert Balmanno, on 3 May 1830, and bought three prints after
                Lawrence’s portraits. A “Ford” bought lot 178 at the 29 April 1862 auction at
                Sotheby’s, which consisted of eight Blake drawings and sketches (Butlin 345, 349,
                350, and five unidentified works). A “Ford” bought Constable’s <hi rend="i">Hadleigh
                  Castle, a distant view</hi>, c. 1829, at Foster’s on 17 May 1860 (Reynolds 2:
                29.6).</p></note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Ford collected over 90 sketches
              and watercolors by Robert Hills (1769-1844), and also seems to have been especially
              interested in the works of William Henry Hunt (1790-1864), Edward Duncan (1803-82),
              and F. W. Topham (1808-77).</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Ford has been
              overlooked by Turner scholars as well as by Blakeans. He owned “Kenilworth Castle, 
                <hi rend="i">a fine drawing</hi>” (lot 67), which sold to W. Evans for £4 8s., and
              “Sands at Hastings, effect of sunset, with numerous Boats and Figures—<hi rend="i">admirably
drawn</hi>” (lot 194), which sold to J. Wilkenson for L2 4s. Wilton
              records the provenance of the first Turner as Thomas Griffith (1833); John Ruskin;
              Munro sale Christie’s 2 June 1877 (398, #842). Apparently, Ford owned it before
              Ruskin, who probably bought it from the dealer Evans. Wilton records the provenance of
              the second as “presented by Turner to Sir Anthony Carlisle, his doctor; Joseph
              Gillott, sale Christie’s 4 May 1872, now untraced” (358, #510). Apparently Ford came
              between Carlisle and Gillott.</note></p>
          <p>Included in the auction was “The Property of an Amateur,” a very common appellation.
            Theoretically, the Amateur may have owned the Blakes, in which case the Amateur may have
            been Butts Jr. The problem here is that Blake’s 29 watercolors were sold in lots 155
            through 182x, which appears to place them among Ford’s collection (lots 1-194, as I hope
            to demonstrate). And yet, assuming that Ford was 
<pb id="p29-42" n="42"/>
	<table rows="7"
              cols="3">
              <head>The Auctions</head>
              <row>
                <cell>George Cumberland</cell>
                <cell>6 May 1835</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Anonymous and Thomas Moule</cell>
                <cell>26-27 March 1852</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Charles Ford and Anonymous</cell>
                <cell>26 June 1852</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>E. V. Utterson and others</cell>
                <cell>5 July 1852</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>29 June 1853</cell>
                <cell>Foster</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Thomas Butts and others</cell>
                <cell>8 March 1854</cell>
                <cell>Foster</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Captain Frederick Butts</cell>
                <cell>24 June 1903</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              </row>
            </table> the collector is equally problematic, because at least four of the titles are
            recorded in receipts between Blake and Butts, and most of the others belong to the same
            biblical series as these. Did Blake have a patron co-extant with Butts, acquiring works
            from the same series? Complicating things further is the presence of Butts Jr. at the
            auction. He is recorded in the British Library’s annotated catalogue of the sale as a
              <hi rend="i">buyer</hi>, not a seller, acquiring 19 of the Blake watercolors. Eighteen
            of these he put up for auction a year later, on 29 June 1853 at Foster and Son. Because
            the Ford auction was unknown, Butts Jr.’s acquisitions—if that is what they
            are—appeared, like all the other Blakes in the 1853 sale, to have entered the Butts
            collection directly from Blake and without intermediate owners. Was Butts Jr. at the
            Ford auction <hi rend="i">buying in</hi> Blakes that failed to sell or meet their
            reserve, the lowest price acceptable to the vendor, or was he <hi rend="i">buying?
              Vendor</hi> or <hi rend="i">collector</hi>, that is the question.</p>
          <p>My attempt to answer this question has resulted in two interrelated articles. The
            forthcoming “A ‘Green House’ for Butts? New Information on Thomas Butts, his Residences,
            and Family” demonstrates that Butt’s family was far more extended and diverse than
            previously recognized, and it identifies the most likely moments when Blakes may have
            left the collection and the family members responsible for their departure. Like “Green
            House,” the present article means to challenge the idea that Butts Jr. inherited the
            Blake collection in its entirety and was solely responsible for its mid-nineteenth
            century dispersal—and thus for the enormous increase in Blake’s visibility and
            reputation that led in 1854 to Gilchrist’s desire to learn and write about Blake. By
            challenging the premise that Butts Jr. was necessarily the vendor of the first auctions
            in which Blakes from his father’s collection sold, I am also arguing against the
            hypothesis that Butts Jr. was the vendor of the first important Blake sale, that of
            26-27 March 1852. In arguing that the March and June sales are traces of earlier
            dispersals of Blakes from the Butts collection, I am suggesting that more collectors
            were interested in Blake than we realize and that the 1852 sales reveal and helped to
            create a market for Blake, which in turn may have prompted Butts Jr. to sell most of his
            collection in June 1853. By examining and contrasting the auctions reputed and known to
            be Butts Jr.’s, I hope also to shed new light on Butts as patron and collector, on Butts
            Jr. and his attitude toward Blake, and on Blake’s original mounting style for the
            biblical watercolors. And, finally, new information about the provenance of Butts’s copy
            of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, combined with an examination of the style in which it and
            the other c. 1816 Milton illustrations were executed (i.e., <hi rend="i">On the Morning
              of Christ’s Nativity, L’Allegro</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>), suggests
            that these works may not have been commissioned by Butts.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Thomas Butts as Collector and Butts Jr.’s Auctions</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>According to Gilchrist, “for nearly thirty years [Butts] continued (with few
              interruptions) a steady buyer at moderate prices of Blake’s drawings, temperas, and
              frescoes; the only large buyer the artist ever had. Occasionally he would take of
              Blake a drawing a week . . . As years rolled by, Mr. Butts’ house in Fitzroy Square
              become a perfect Blake Gallery” (1: 115). Bentley states that “His house gradually
              filled to overflowing with Blake’s pictures, until some must have had to be taken down
              to make room for new ones as they appeared” (“Butts” 1065), and that Butts filled “his
              house to overflowing with pictures and books” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 175).
              The idea of Butts’s house overflowing with Blakes is questionable because he appears
              to have owned a house in Dalston until 1808 and owned 16 houses when he died in 1845
              (see “Green House”). Moreover, the hypothesis is inferred from the number of Blakes he
              owned, not from descriptions. Butts died in 1845, at which time his house at 17
              Grafton Street, Fitzroy Square, was inherited by Thomas Butts Jr. Gilchrist never saw
              the house, which was vacated in 1853, a year before he had heard of Blake and began
              the biography; nor is there any record of correspondence between Butts Jr. and the
              Gilchrists or the Rossettis. When the biography was being written, Butts Jr. lived at
              20 Chester Terrace, Regent Park, which was about five blocks north of Fitzroy
                Square.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> He died there
on 14 December 1862 
                (<hi rend="i">Burke’s</hi>). The Rossettis knew Butts Jr.’s son, Captain Frederick Butts,
              through whom they were able to examine what remained of the Blake collection, the
              watercolors and temperas that failed to sell in Butts Jr.’s auctions, and nine
              color-print drawings and other works never before put up for auction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
                type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The Chester Terrace address is
                given in Butts Jr.’s will, which was written on 25 August 1862 and proved on 17
                February 1863. It is four numbered pages and is in Somerset House. Why Butts Jr. was
                not consulted by the Gilchrists or Rossettis is unknown. The only mention of Thomas
                Butts Jr. in the <hi rend="i">Life</hi> concerns his selling the Job watercolors to
                Milnes (Gilchrist 1: 282).</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Dante G. Rossetti
                records that he and his brother visited Captain Butts on 15 January 1863, but he
                does not record where (<hi rend="i">Letters of DGR</hi> 469, 471-72). Presumably, it
                was the Chester Terrace residence. Butts Jr. bequeathed his art collection to his
                son and daughter “in equal shares,” but the will had not yet been proved (see
                n8).</note></p>
            <p>As startling as it seems, there are no first-hand descriptions of the Blake
              collection as owned by Butts, no catalogue 
<pb id="p29-43" n="43"/>
of what Butts Jr.
              inherited, and no descriptions of what Butts Jr. displayed in the Fitzroy Square house
              once he owned it—or what he might have had in his own house at 5 Upper Street, Fitzroy
              Square, where he lived from c. 1830 to 1845 and which belonged to his father (Butts
              Sr.’s Will p. 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
Linnell’s awareness of the
              Book of Job watercolors suggests that he and Blake visited Butts in September 1821,
              but there is no description of what Linnell saw. Tatham had seen Butts’s Blake
              collection, but describes it merely as “splendid” and notes that he “has seen
              pictures” (i.e., temperas) “that have appeared exactly like the old cabinet pictures”
              of the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries. Palmer had hoped to make such a visit but
              did not: “Dear Mr. Blake promised to take me himself to see Mr. Butts’s collection
              —but alas! it never came off.” And Seymour Kirkup, who was a childhood school friend
              to Thomas Butts Jr. and states that he spent much time with him from “1810 to 1816,”
              did visit often but records only that he “neglected sadly the opportunities the
              Buttses threw in [his] way,” adding, though, that “They (Butts) did not seem to value
              him as we do now” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 274, 517, 515, 300, 221,
              220n2). <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Butts Sr.’s will is 15 unnumbered pages,
                which, for convenience, are here numbered. It is in the Public Records Office,
                Chancery Lane. He owned 15 houses and a farm when he died; he bequeathed the leases
                to the Grafton and Fitzroy Street residences to Butts Jr.</note></p>
            <p>Butts is not known to have had an auction, but his son is thought to have had three:
              on 26-27 March 1852 at Sotheby’s, on 29 June 1853 at Foster and Son, and on 8 March
              1854 at Foster and Son. The Blakes in this last auction, however, had been put up for
              sale the year before but bought in. Only two were sold in the 1854 sale, while the
              rest were inherited by Captain Butts, along with most of the Blakes that were never
              put up for sale.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> These
mid-nineteenth-century
              auctions were crucial in establishing Blake’s audience and market. The March 1852 sale
              was not the first to include Blake watercolors (see below), but it was the most
              important: it was the first to include Blakes from the Butts collection and the first
              to include both a substantial number and a diverse selection of Blake’s works.
              Illuminated books, illustrated books, and watercolors were sold as part of a “Valuable
              Collection of Engravings &amp; Drawings from the Portfolio of An Amateur.” This
              two-day sale of over 1500 items in 351 lots (lots 1-349, plus two lots penciled in in
              the British Library’s annotated copy) included original and reproductive engravings
              (almost exclusively proofs and early states) by and after Durer, Hogarth, Rembrandt,
              Turner, Wilkie, and many others, “Drawings by the Old Masters” (89-105), “Modern
              Drawings in Water Colour” (106-44), “Engraved Illustrations to Popular Works”
              (187-221), “Portraits” (222-29), “Landscapes” (230-39), “English Engravings”
(252-90),
              and “Works of the Late J. M. W. Turner, Esq., Chiefly Engraver’s Proofs” (291-316).
              Turner’s prints appear to have been collected assiduously, with about 70 prints and
              three watercolors in the auction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">12</ref>	
                  <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Captain Butts had an auction at Sotheby’s on 24 June
1903.
                Works bought in and works not then put up for sale were sold privately by the
                Captain’s widow in 1906, mostly through Carfax to W. Graham Robertson, to pay the
                death taxes (Butts 162-5). Two other auctions, at Sotheby’s on 21-23 March 1910 and
                19 December 1932, included a few minor items from the Butts family connected to
                Blake. while an auction at Puttick and Simpson on 2 July 1937 included prints by
                Butts Jr. The 1910 auction included copper plates and prints by Butts Jr., and a
                “working cabinet” that held the plates and engraving tools (see Essick, 
                  <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 211-26). Two copies of <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi>
                engravings also sold in this auction, though these did not necessarily belong to
                Butts. The 1932 auction included Blake’s three miniatures of Butts, Mrs. Butts, and
                Butts Jr. painted on ivory, Mrs. Butts’s needlework and tea pot, and a receipt
                signed by Blake. They belonged to Anthony Bacon Drury Butts, the Captain’s son (and
                great grandson of Butts).</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> The three Turner
                watercolors are presumably the most traceable of the auction’s works, but they yield
                no information on the identity of the vendor. The watercolors were: “View of the
                Cross at Winchester” (144), “View of Sheffield” (145), and “View of the Crypt at
                Kerkstall Abbey” (146); they sold for £5 to Hogarth, £2 3s. to Palser, and £7 7s. to
                Evans respectively. All three buyers were dealers, and none recorded the person from
                whom he acquired the work, which, Butlin assures me privately, would not have been
                expected of them. Wilton records their first owners as J. E. Taylor, Ruskin, and
                Taylor respectively (see 317, #164; 312, #102; and 325, #235). Butts is not recorded
                as having owned any Turners.</note></p>
            <p>The Blakes in this “Valuable Collection” were announced on the title page of the 1852
              sale catalogue as the “Works of that Able but Eccentric Artist, William Blake, with
              Many of his Best Drawings.” They were placed under two headings. The first, “Works of
              William Blake” (lots 50-61), consisted of 10 illuminated books, two copies of 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, a copy of Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and a
              set of <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi> engravings. The second, “Original Drawings, in
              Colours, By William Blake” (lots 147-67), consisted of 18 biblical watercolors, 
                <hi rend="i">Queen Catherine’s Vision</hi> (1807), and the six designs to Milton’s 
                <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> (c. 1816). The auction’s vendor is anonymous, recorded only
              as “Amateur”; Lugt identifies the <hi rend="i">provenance</hi>, not the vendor, as
              Thomas Butts (#20723), which is clearly inferred from the fact that the Blakes (though
              not necessarily all of them) once belonged to Butts and are the most easily traced
              works in the auction. Sotheby’s own records do not identify the “Amateur.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
                target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Indeed, as will become apparent, nothing except
              his father’s Blakes connects this Sotheby auction with Butts Jr., and nothing at all
              connects it to the auction in June 1853 at Foster and Son, the only auction whose
              catalogue identifies Butts Jr. as the vendor. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> I am
                grateful to Henry Wemyss of Sotheby’s in London for checking the master records,
                which unfortunately do not go back this far.</note></p>
            <p>Before we can ascertain whether the “Amateur” was or was not Butts Jr., we need first
              to examine the conventions of auctions and the make-up of the particular collection
              sold. We can be relatively sure that if the Blakes belonged to Butts Jr. in March
              1852, then so did the non-Blake items. Auctions consisting of works from various
              collections announce 
<pb id="p29-44" n="44"/>
that fact on the title page (e.g., the
              one on 20 June 1853 at Sotheby’s, “Catalogue of a Valuable Assemblage of Water-Colour
              Drawings, from the Portfolios of Several Distinguished Collections”); or they
              introduce secondary vendors with phrases such as “together with” and “to which is
              added.” Or they mention the secondary vendors in the catalogue itself, introducing
              lots with separate headings, such as “Another Property,” or “The Property of a
              Gentleman.” The March 1852 auction that was supposedly Butts Jr.’s did include works
              from another collection, but this fact is clearly stated on the title page: “Together
              with the Collection formed by the late Thomas Moule” (lots 350-420x).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
                type="note">14</ref> For the sake of accounting, if not also provenance, these
              subheadings are necessary. It appears, then, that the 1500 plus items that sold in
              lots 1-349 belonged to a single vendor, the “Amateur.” If the “Amateur” was Butts Jr.,
              then either he and/or his father formed the collection sold. 
                  <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Moule, a bookdealer, had the lion’s share of his
library
                auctioned on 11 March 1852 at Sotheby’s (unrecorded in Lugt); apparently, the
                remaining items from that collection were included in the 26-27 March 1852 auction.
                More of his lots were bought in than were the Amateur’s.</note></p>
            <p>Rossetti lists only the Blakes in the Butts collection, and so Butt’s collection
              appears synonymous with Blake. Is this a major distortion of the eclecticism of a
              lifetime of collecting, or is it an accurate reflection? I suspect the latter, because
              the collector responsible for the March sale was interested primarily in prints and
              drawings, and, like most serious print connoisseurs, preferred early states of
              reproductive and original engravings. This preference makes the omission of Blake’s
              separate original engravings, like <hi rend="i">Job, Ezekiel, Mirth, Albion Rose</hi>,
              and <hi rend="i">Our End Is Come</hi>, and the omission of Blake’s reproductive plates
              after Stothard, Morland, Watteau, Meheux, Fuseli, Hogarth, and Cosway, very
              suspicious. Given the tenor of the collection, one would expect to see many more
              intaglio prints by Blake if the “Amateur” collector was Blake’s patron.<ref
                target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Blake’s
                intaglio prints included in the 26-27 March 1852 auction were four plates to
                Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, a copy of <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi>
                engravings, two copies of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, and one copy of 
                  <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (lots 56, 58-61). In the 29 June 1853 auction, the
                engravings were a copy of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a copy of <hi rend="i">Night
                  Thoughts</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> engraving, all sold
                in lot 143.</note></p>
            <p>Indeed, the collection does not resemble the patron depicted by Gilchrist (1: 115) or
              Ada Briggs, Captain Butts’s sister-in-law. According to the latter, Butts was a man
              singularly devoted to collecting Blake, buying “the works of Blake alone, instead of .
              . . those of men esteemed in his day, many of them still esteemed in ours: Bartolozzi,
              Flaxman, Stothard. . . “(94). But drawings by Stothard and Flaxman and engravings by
              Bartolozzi were in the March auction (see lots 124-29, 186, 209, 223, among many
              others), whereas the three “pencil sketches of the Royal Dukes, by Laurence [sic],”
              which Briggs claims were the “only works by an artist . . . other than Blake” (94)
              that Butts bought, were <hi rend="i">not</hi> in the March 1852 auction. They were,
              however, auctioned in June 1853 (lot 24), bought in and auctioned again in March 1854
              (lot 34)—and again bought in, which means that they probably remained in the Butts
              family when Briggs was writing her profile. (They may have been sold privately, since
              they were not in the 1910 and 1932 auctions, or, more likely, they belonged to the
              Captain’s sister, Mary Ann Blanch Pigott.) Apparently, Briggs’s idea of Butt’s
              collection was formed by the items still in the Butts family and those recorded by
              Rossetti, and not by the March 1852 auction.</p>
            <p>Keynes reads the one extant letter from Butts to Blake (September 1800) as suggesting
              “that Butts was a dumb admirer of genius, which he could see but did not quite
              understand” (<hi rend="i">Letters</hi> xxii, 25-27). For Keynes, Butts acquired works
              by Blake because he wished to support Blake and not because he was an art collector.
              The only other document that we have from Butts strongly reinforces this
              interpretation. Butts’s extraordinarily detailed 15-page will makes no mention of
              Blake or of any art collection. The only book it mentions is a “folio Bible,” which
              was a “gift of Mrs Rain deceased” (p. 6). This he bequeathed to his grandson Henry
              Wellington Halse Butts. The collection that we know Butts Jr. inherited is simply
              referred to as “furniture” and came with the Fitzroy Square residence (see “Green
              House”). The will appears not to reflect the mind or habits of a genuine collector;
              conversely, the March 1852 collection of prints and drawings does not resemble the
              later Butts of the will (1845), who appears more interested in real estate than
              art.</p>
            <p>Butts Jr. does mention an art collection, but its constitution supports the
              hypothesis that he was not responsible for the one sold at Sotheby’s on 26-27 March
              1852. In his will, he states: 
			<q> I bequeath to my said Son and Daughter in equal
                shares as tennants in common all my pictures prints and drawings whether framed or
                unframed and all my bronzes of any kind whatsoever together with my Antique Roman
                Equestrain Statue of Marcus Aurelius much wishing for an amiable partition of the
                same not to be sold but to be retained in affectionate remembrance of me by whom
                they are prized by reason of family recollections provided that if either of them my
                said son and daughter shall die in my lifetime then I bequeathed the whole . . . to
                the survivor.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Thomas Butts Jr. and his wife Mary Ann had three children: Frederick
                  John, Aubrey Thomas, and Mary Ann Blanch, born in 1833, 1837, and 1845
                  respectively. Aubrey had died on 9 November 1861.</note></q></p>
            <p>Captain Butts received—or chose—most of the Blakes in his father’s collection of
              pictures, prints, and drawings. He received three miniature portraits, at least nine
              color-print drawings, nine temperas, 24 watercolor drawings, proofs of 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts, The Book of Job</hi> engravings, and a Dante 
              <pb id="p29-45" n="45"/>
engraving.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> Mary Ann Blanch Butts apparently
              received—or chose—the non-Blake items in the collection. These presumably included as
              many as 20 of the 69 drawings and paintings by, “after,” and “in the manner of”
              Vandyke, Raphael, West, Zuccarelli, Titian, Rubens, among others (lots 1-62) that were
              bought in in Butts Jr.’s June 1853 and 1854 auctions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">18</ref> Mary Ann may have also inherited as many as 17 Blake works, a hypothesis
              inferred from the history of the tempera, <hi rend="i">The Body of Abel Found by Adam
                and Eve</hi>, c. 1826 (Butlin 806). The painting may have belonged to a member of
              George Richmond’s family, but a note by W. Graham Robertson states that it belonged to
              Mrs. Graham Pigott but was returned to Captain Butts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref> Mrs. Pigott (not Piggot, pace Butlin 806) was Mary Ann Blanch, who married
              George Edward Graham Foster Pigott on 17 January 1863. Mrs. Pigott is reputed to have
              owned 16 “further works” that were destroyed in a fire (Butlin 806). The rumor of a
              conflagration might be true, and the other “works” might have included Blakes. This
              would explain why 13 or 14 temperas seen by Rossetti when visiting Captain Butts in
              January 1863—before Butts Jr.’s collection was legally divided “in equal shares”—have
              not been seen since (see Butlin 380, 384, 385, 388, 391, 393, 395, 405, 412, 413, 414,
              421, 431; see also 328). If Mary Ann received these Blakes along with the non-Blakes,
              the “bronzes,” and the statue (neither shows up in the 1903, 1910, or 1932 auctions),
              then son and daughter each received about the same number of works. 
                  <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> These are the works that Captain Butts, his widow, or
son Anthony
                Bacon Drury Butts sold. For the color-print drawings, temperas, and watercolors, see
                Butlin 289, 294, 297, 301, 306, 310, 316, 320, 323; 382, 387, 390, 392, 398, 400,
                402, 417, 673; 195, 434, 436, 450, 452, 455, 456, 459, 461, 464, 483, 490, 493,
                497-99, 503, 505,509, 511, 512, 515, 525, 675.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> There were 144 numbered lots in the 1853 auction, but the lot numbers
                jump from 62 to 70 in the catalogue, presumably because there are 69 items in the
                first 62 lots. The Blakes begin with lot 70. The 24 non-Blake items bought in in
                1853, which included the Lawrence sketches of the Royal Dukes, were put up for sale
                the following year, but only four sold.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi
                  rend="i"> The Body of Abel</hi> (c. 1826) would have been the only late tempera
                acquired by Butts, which strengthens the Richmond provenance. On the other hand,
                Butts was acquiring—or being given—works by Blake between 1822 and 1827, including
                  <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi>, which he purchased in April 1826 at a discount
                for lending the original watercolors to Linnell for the tracings, and possibly the
                Dante engraving that sold in his grandson’s 1903 auction. See also n64.</note></p>
            <p>If Briggs is right about Butts being singularly devoted to Blake, then possibly the
              Lawrence sketches and almost certainly the 69 drawings and paintings by, “after,” and
              “in the manner of” Vandyke, Raphael, et al. reflect the taste of Butts Jr. and not his
              father. After selling most of his collection in June 1853, Butts Jr. still had Blakes
              and non-Blakes to give his children 10 years later. But this collection was relatively
              small and it does not at all resemble the one that sold in March 1852. There is almost
              no overlap between the two auctions. None of the six or seven lots in the March 1852
              auction that appear to have been withdrawn, or the four that appear to have been
              bought in, was included in Butts Jr.’s June 1853 auction—nor do they show up in the
              auctions of 1903, 1910, or 1932. This omission is very troubling, because 41 of the 43
              Blake and non-Blake items that were bought in at Butts Jr.’s June 1853 auction were
              included in his March 1854 auction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref> The 1854
              catalogue’s title page states that the sale was of “Ancient and Modern Pictures, Part
              by direction of the Executors,” a heading which apparently means that part of the
              auction included works from an estate or estates put up for sale by the estate’s
                executors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> The
“Collection of Italian, Dutch,
              Flemish &amp; English Pictures” that sold consisted of works belonging to numerous
              vendors; though none is mentioned on the title page, all are recorded in the annotated
              copy of the catalogue in the Victoria and Albert Museum Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
                type="note">22</ref> Butts Jr.’s 41 Blake and non-Blake items were in 14 lots. Lots
              13-18 consisted of 17 Blake watercolors and temperas, announced on the title page as
              “A Few Drawings by the Late Mr. W. Blake” and in the catalogue itself as “Drawings by
              the Late William Blake.” Only four non-Blake items sold, and only two (now untraced)
              Blake works sold (Butlin 397, 399), and those sold to “Dean” for only 5s.6d.
                apiece.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> The failure
of the Blakes to sell in
              1853 and 1854 may have been due to quality. Possibly 
<pb id="p29-46" n="46"/>
nine of
              the 17 Blakes appear to have been temperas, and they may already have been in poor
                condition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi>
                Seven drawings, two watercolors, and one engraving appear to have been withdrawn on
                26-27 March 1852, as is indicated by a pen line drawn through the lot number and by
                the absence of price and buyer in their respective columns to the right of the lot
                entry. These works were: “Guercino. Cupid, <hi rend="i">in sepia, very fine</hi>”
                (lot 92), “Vandyke. Group of figures, <hi rend="i">very spirited</hi>” (lot 98), and
                “Landscape, by Titian” (lot 103) “Snyders, etc. Sketches of Birds, etc. [4]” (lot
                118), “Somers. View on the Coast, with Cottage and Figures” (lot 134), “Cotman.
                Ruins of an Ancient Castle in Normandy” (lot 324), “Bas Relievo, by Freebairn, 
                  <hi rend="i">india proof.</hi>” Lot 249 is crossed out: “Les Bons Amis, after Ostade,
                choice <hi rend="i">engraver’s proof before the letters</hi>”; this lot sold for £2
                4s. to Tidbury (Charles? a printseller), whose name is also crossed through, a
                deletion which suggest the work was sold but returned. Works recorded with a price,
                without a buyer, and with the price repeated to the right of the buyer’s column and
                tallied up separately appear to have been bought in. These works were: “Dartmouth,
                by Reynolds, and Fonthill by Angus” (lot 79), “Aske Hall, by J. Scott [after
                Turner], <hi rend="i">india proof</hi>” (LOT 293), “unidentified lot penciled in”
                (LOT 331++), “Portrait of Charles James Fox, after Sir Joshua Reynolds, 
                  <hi rend="i">proof</hi>” (lot 337).</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Only one estate
                is clearly noted in the catalogue: “Twelve lots by direction of the Executors”
                belong to “Charsley.”</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Also part of the
                collection of “Ancient and Modern Pictures” was “the property of a Distinguished
                Artist” (R. R. Reinagle, with most of his 37 lots consisting of his own works). Lugt
                mentions Charsley, Reinagle, and Butts as the auction’s only vendors (#21763), but
                there were also Bush, Rives, Anthony, and others.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Bentley states that “19 Blake drawings (lots 13-18) sold for L4 3s.” 
                  (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 660). Two of the items, however, were theatre portraits,
                and the £4 3s. was the sum of the reserve or buy in prices combined with the sum of
                the lot that sold. According to the Victoria and Albert Museum catalogue for the
                March 1854 sale, Dean bought lot 17 for 11 shillings, which consisted of theatrical
                portraits of Cooke and Kemble and the untraced temperas(?) of <hi rend="i">Christ
                  and his Disciples, St. Mark</hi>, and <hi rend="i">St. John.</hi> (These last
                three works had been offered together in lot 141 on 29 June 1853.) In the margin,
                though, after Dean’s name, appears “(2 Mark &amp; John),” which suggests that Dean
                acquired only two and not all five works in lot 17. <p>In the June 1853 auction, the
                  “Two Theatre portraits, Cooke and Kemble” sold last (lot 144) but still as part of
                  the Blake section. In March 1854, they were joined with three Blake paintings and
                  thus seem purposefully identified as Blake’s work. The portraits may have been
                  executed by William Blake, one of the many engravers working for the publishers
                  who produced plays and portraits for the juvenile drama, otherwise known as the
                  toy theatre or “penny plain, twopence colored” prints. A William Blake etched the
                  plates to the <hi rend="i">The Broken Sword</hi>, ca. 1816, published by Jameson.
                  I have never seen a portrait of any of the Kembles or of T. P. Cooke that was done
                  by this Blake, though most work of this kind was not signed.</p></note>	
                <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> See Butlin 386, 389, 394, 397, 401, 423, 425A, 477,
                671. In 1863, Rossetti recognized that many of the temperas were in poor condition,
                and in 1880, when he re-listed the works in the second edition of the 
                  <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, he often noted which had been restored. Of the 52 suspected
                temperas executed for Butts in 1799-1800, 23 are untraced (Butlin 379-432). Two and
                possibly three of these were unknown to Rossetti (Butlin 418, 386, 430). I suspect
                that a number of the untraced temperas no longer exist; as many as 16 might have
                been lost in a fire (see above), while others have deteriorated beyond repair. Some
                may have deteriorated before any records (in the form of Butts’s sale catalogues or
                Rossetti’s lists) were made. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Christ Baptizing</hi> was already
                being repaired in 1805 (see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
              573).</note></p>
            <p>No unsold item from the March 1852 sale shows up in the June 1853 sale and, more
              important, the artists and kinds of work in the March 1852 sale differ completely from
              the 69 drawings and paintings by, “after,” and “in the manner of” Vandyke, Raphael,
              West, Zuccarelli, Titian, Rubens, et al. that sold in the June 1853 sale. With the
              exception of five wash drawings attributed to Zuccarelli, none of these artists was in
              the March 1852 sale, despite there being headings in that sale for “pictures” and
              “paintings.” Such overt difference between two collections suggests different
              collectors, which in turn suggests that the March 1852 collection was not formed by
              Butts or his son.</p>
            <p>The number of Blakes in the March 1852 auction—39 separate books and drawings—was
              relatively small, whereas the 117 Blakes in the June 1853 auction (lots 70-143)
              represents 2/3 of the sale. This latter auction was not at Sotheby’s, like those of
              March 1852 and the Ford sale of June 1852, but at Foster and Son. The 1853 catalogue’s
              title page announced a “Collection of Pictures, Drawings and Works of Art, The
              Property of Thomas Butts, Esq., Removing from his Residence, Grafton Street.” The 117
              Blakes are announced on page 6 of the catalogue with full fanfare: “Drawings &amp;
              Pictures by the late WM. BLAKE, Whose genius and talents are familiar to the Public by
              his Illustrations to the Poem of ‘The Grave,’ ‘Young’s Night Thoughts,’ etc.” These
              drawings and pictures included watercolors, temperas, and Milton illustrations. No
              illuminated books, however, were included, and the celebrated illustrated books, 
                <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> and <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, were grouped together
              with a copy of the <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> engraving and sold in the
              same lot, instead of singularly, as the intaglio works were in the March 1852
                auction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> The
catalogue’s title page also
              announces “A Collection of Pictures and Drawings, By the Late William Blake,
              Distinguished for originality of Design, and facility of Pencil, Amongst which are
              subjects from Sacred History, Illustrations from Milton, etc. and forming a Curious
              and, perhaps, Matchless Assemblage of the Works of this Highly Gifted Artist.” The
              acknowledgement of the collection’s diversity and merit is curious. A bit of
              advertising puff, no doubt, but possibly also an allusion to the Blake sales of the
              previous year (March and June), which did not include temperas. But why imply that
              your collection is bigger and better than the others if the other sales were your own
              and the ultimate provenance was the same? <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi>
                Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> records 110 watercolors and paintings (660),
                which apparently excludes the seven small Shakespeare designs that sold in lot 102
                with the <hi rend="i">Sacrifice of Isaac.</hi></note></p>
            <p>As noted, Rossetti saw what was left of the Butts collection on 15 January 1863,
              through the auspices of Captain Butts (see n8). How much information the Captain
              supplied is not known. It appears to have been minimal, for Rossetti clearly was
              unaware of two crucial facts that one assumes the Captain would have supplied if he
              could have. Rossetti failed to recognize that the buyer “Thomas” in the June 1853
              auction was the name used by Butts Jr. (or the name given to him by the auctioneer) to
              buy-in, and he was unaware of the March 1854 auction altogether, as is evinced by his
              recording the provenance of two temperas as “Mr. Thomas, from Mr. Butts” (204, #29,
              31), despite their having sold in the March 1854 auction to Dean. He appears to have
              relied heavily on the lists first compiled by Gilchrist and William Haines, which
              probably included the information (titles and buyers) provided by the March 1852 and
              June 1853 annotated auction catalogues.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">26</ref>	
                <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Frederick John Butts enlisted in the army on 18 March
                1853 (77th, East Middlesex), and made Captain on 4 April 1855 (information supplied
                by Keri Davies and Ted Ryan). His apparent failure to inform Rossetti of these facts
                suggests that he was probably not present at either of his father’s
              auctions.</note></p>
            <p>Of the three nineteenth-century auctions now associated with Butts Jr., only the two
              at Foster and Son in 1853 and 1854 can be said with certainty to have been his. The
              first and largest of the three auctions, at Sotheby’s in March 1852, included Blakes
              from the Butts collection, but it appears also to have had a few Blakes already in it,
              or at least Blakes that cannot be traced documentarily to Butts, like <hi rend="i">The
                Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> copy F, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> copy L,
              a posthumous copy of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (copy I), and the Milton 
                <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> designs (see below).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n27" type="note">27</ref> And the
              sale contained copies of <hi rend="i">The</hi>
	<pb id="p29-47" n="47"/>	
                <hi rend="i">Grave, Night Thoughts</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi> engravings, the
              Blake works most commonly found in print and book collections of the day. The
              anonymous vendor was probably not Butts Jr. If all 1500 or so items in this auction
              belonged to Butts, then his art collection was very much larger and far more diversely
              constituted than previously imagined, and our ideas of him and his relation to Blake
              are wildly inaccurate: Blake was but one of his collecting interests and probably not
              someone whom he recognized as a visionary artist and chose to support through
              open-ended commissions. But if our picture of Butts is even near accurate, then the
              collection that sold in March 1852 was not formed by Butts. Nor does it seem likely to
              have been formed by his son; that requires assuming that Butts Jr. was a very serious
              collector of prints and drawings who sold his own large collection but kept most of
              the Blakes given to him by his father as well as works not at all like those he
              supposedly had collected. The taste reflected in his June 1853 auction strongly
              suggests that he was not the vendor of the March 1852 auction. If not, then a Blake
              collector goes unrecognized, and the possibility that the Ford sale of 26 June 1852
              was not an “untraced Butts sale” is greatly strengthened. Conversely, if the vendor of
              the Blakes in the Ford sale was Ford or someone other than Butts Jr., then the
              likelihood that the vendor of the March 1852 auction was not Butts Jr. is much
              increased. Suspicion of one casts suspicion on the other, because the rationale for
              attributing the sales to Butts Jr.—most of the Blakes in the sales came from his
              father’s collection—is the same. Indeed, as I hope will become apparent, the March and
              June 1852 auctions are not the first dispersal of the Butts collection; rather, they
              are the traces of earlier dispersals made by other members of Butts family. They are
              also signs that the circle of mid-nineteenth-century Blake collectors was not the
              “small knot” that Rossetti imagined it (<hi rend="i">Selected Letters</hi> 204).<ref
                target="n28" type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Blake lists
                “Urizen, Heaven etc etc Songs of Experience” 10s.6d.” in his 1805 account with
                Butts, but given their very low price these seem to refer to separate plates later
                bound with Blakeana (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 573 and n4). Butts is not known
                to have owned a copy of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, and he paid L6 6s. for copy E of
                  <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in 1806.</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi>
                Suspecting that Butts Jr. was not the vendor of the 26-27 March 1852 sale is one
                thing; identifying the vendor is something else again. As noted, most of the works
                sold were prints, and the provenances of multiples are exceedingly difficult to
                determine. Traceable works, like the Turners and Old Master drawings, were acquired
                by dealers who apparently did not identify their source to their buyers (n7 and
                n12), and other works are untraceable because they were titled generically (e.g.,
                landscape), making it impossible to trace their complete provenances with any
                assurance. The Blakes are the most identifiable works in the collection; for the
                possible identification of the person from whom the “Amateur” might have acquired
                the Blakes, see “Green House.”</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Traceable Mounts in an Untraced Blake Sale</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Watercolors from Blake’s biblical series sold at each of the nineteenth-century
              auctions in March 1852, June 1853, and March 1854. Watercolors from the same series
              were also sold at Ford’s auction in June 1852. What suggests that at least some of
              those in the Ford auction were once owned by Butts, and were not commissioned by
              another patron collecting at the same time (like the Rev. Joseph Thomas, who
              commissioned the first series of <hi rend="i">Comus, Paradise Lost</hi>, and 
                <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi>, in 1801, 1807, and 1809 respectively), is Butt’s receipt
              from 12 May 1805 listing titles (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 572) that
              match or echo those in lots 158, 169, 170, and 171 (see Appendix 1). Unfortunately,
              these particular echoes only suggest rather than prove because each of the works
              exists in more than one version, leaving the possibility that the versions delivered
              to Butts are not the ones sold in the June 1852 auction. What provides conclusive
              proof that these watercolors were once in the Butts collection is the style in which
              they were mounted, a style used only by Butts for his biblical watercolors and 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations.</p>
            <p>Blake’s original mode of presenting watercolors seems difficult to determine, because
              collectors routinely trim and frame their acquisitions. However, a few of the biblical
              watercolors in the Butts collection remain on untrimmed sheets of paper, and from
              these we can deduce the manner in which the other biblical watercolors were probably
              presented to Butts. Blake signed his monogram in pen, usually the bottom right corner;
              in the same corner, just under the image, he penned in a biblical reference using
              roman numerals for the chapter and arabic for the verse (as in 
                <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> plate 2). He usually drew a thin borderline in dark brown or black
ink
              along the edge of the image, which he sometimes echoed with a few more lines drawn in
              the margins, thereby creating a frame, or what was then known as a “washline mount”
              (Wilton and Lyles 299).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref> These three
              features—signature, inscription, and frame—are exemplified by <hi rend="i">Sealing the
                Stone and Setting the Watch</hi> (Butlin 499). It is signed in Blake’s monogram,
              inscribed “Matthew XXVIIc 66v,” and framed by four grey pen and ink lines, which
              create three bands, with the last band lightly washed in grey (illus. 2). A title is
              inscribed below the image in pencil; it is probably not by Blake but is possibly by
                Butts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi>
                Simulated washline mounts could be purchased at stationers. Prints and drawings
                could then be trimmed and pasted into them.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> The original right and left border lines of <hi rend="i">Sealing the
                  Stone</hi> were erased, and the design (clothes, figures, and background washes)
                was extended, presumably by Blake. The framing of <hi rend="i">The Ascension</hi>
                (Butlin 505) is even more elaborate, with five bands created by the borderline and
                five framelines. The bands are white, pale blue, white, purple, and pale blue
                respectively, with “The Ascension” written in pencil under the image, in the blue
                band, possibly in the same hand responsible for the title of <hi rend="i">Sealing
                  the Stone.</hi> Both of these designs have roman numerals at the top of the frame,
                VII and IX respectively. <hi rend="i">The River of Life</hi> (Butlin 525) is
                similarly framed, with bands in light brownish orange, blue, grey, and white, but
                has no text or numeral. <hi rend="i">Christ Crucified between Two Thieves</hi> has a
                brown borderline and a frameline outside the inscription, and a pencil line outside
                that, presumably the preliminary line for another frameline. Inscribed below (and
                not on a mount, pace Butlin 494) in pencil in copperplate hand is: “And he said unto
                Jesus, ‘Lord remember me when thou comest unto thy kingdom.’” The hand resembles
                that on <hi rend="i">Sealing the Stone. Mercy and Truth Are Met Together</hi>
                (Butlin 463) also has a washline mount (now hidden from view in a modern frame) and
                is inscribed below the image: “Mercy and Truth have met together, Rightousness and
                [?] have kissed each other” (information supplied by Martin Butlin). <p>Butlin
                  indicates untrimmed sheets by noting paper size in addition to image size (see
                  Butlin 499 and 505), though <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Samuel Appearing to
                    Saul</hi> (Butlin 458) is recorded as being 32 × 34.4 cm “on paper” 54 × 44 cm.
                  This work was trimmed to the image; it is the mount that is 55.7 × 44.5 cm.
                  Framelines and washline mounts are usually not indicated (see Butlin 494, 499,
                  505, 525).</p></note></p>
            <pb id="p29-48" n="48"/>
            <figure n="but499.1.1-insc-b.rm.300" rend="file" width="958" height="136">
              <head>2 <hi rend="i">Sealing the Stone and Setting the Watch</hi>, c. 1800-03.</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and watercolor over pencil, 40.1 × 33.3 cm on paper 51 × 43.1 cm. Yale
                Center for British Art. Detail of monogram, biblical inscription, and washline
                mount.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Watercolors with washline mounts were obviously never trimmed to the image by Butts.
              They were probably never mounted, either, or at least not in the inlaid style which
              Butts used for nearly all the other biblical watercolors in his collection. In this
              style, the sheet was trimmed to the image, which removed the margins/frame and
              biblical inscription; it was then inlaid along the edges of a window cut out of a
              large sheet of thick crayon or drawing paper (about two index cards thick)
              approximately 55.5 × 44.5 cm.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">31</ref> So treated, the
              watercolor, which is on thinner paper, became flush with its mount. The biblical
              inscription trimmed away was rewritten in pencil on the mount in the same position,
              with the roman numerals changed to arabic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">32</ref> Also
              on the mount, quotations were added below the image, and sometimes they were added
              above as titles; both were written in pencil in a fine copperplate hand. For example,
              the biblical inscription on <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the
                Sea</hi> (Butlin 521) is “Rev<hi rend="s">ns</hi>: ch: 13<hi rend="s">th</hi>: v.1:
              &amp; 2:” (illus. 3); at the top of the mount is the title, “And power was given him
              over all kindreds, &amp; tongues, &amp; nations” (illus. 4).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
                type="note">33</ref> Below the image 
<pb id="p29-49" n="49"/>
<figure n="RedDragonInscription.29.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="214">
                <head>3 <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea</hi>, c.
                  1803-05.</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and watercolor, 40.1 × 35.6 cm. The National Gallery of Art,
                  Washington, D. C. Detail of biblical inscription, copperplate hand written in
                  pencil.</figDesc>
              </figure>
<figure n="BUT521.1.1-insc-t.RM.300" rend="file" width="958" height="135"/>
              <figure n="RedDragonInscriptionDetailofTitle.29.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="40">
                <head>4 <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea.</hi></head>
                <figDesc>Detail of title, copperplate hand written in pencil.</figDesc>
              </figure> are four lines: “And I stood and saw a beast rise up out of the sea, having
              seven heads and ten horns, &amp; upon / his horns ten crowns, &amp; upon his heads the
              name of blasphemy. And the beast which I saw / was like unto a leopard, &amp; his feet
              were as the feet of a bear, &amp; his mouth as the mouth of a lion, / and the dragon
              gave him his power, &amp; his seat &amp; his great authority” (illus. 5). The absence
              of quotations on the untrimmed (washline) sheets—the sheets as given to Butts—suggests
              that the long titles and quotations were derived from Blake’s biblical inscriptions
              but supplied, if not also written, by Butts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">34</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> This style of presentation, which was
                popular throughout the nineteenth-century, is also called a “drum mount,” because
                the image is stretched over the window like a skin over a drum. <p>The nine
                  color-print drawings inherited by Captain Butts were untrimmed and seven of these
                  were inscribed below the image with the work’s title (see Butlin 289, 294, 297,
                  301, 306, 310, 316, 320, 323). Butts purchased eight of these in 1805, and at
                  least five of these appear to have been from the 1795 printing and three from a
                  new printing c. 1804 or 1805 (see Butlin, “Physicality”), printed on the same
                  paper and in the same style to match the earlier impressions. The margins left by
                  Blake on the latter impressions, in other words, were probably determined by their
                  presence in the earlier impressions. Perhaps Butts never trimmed the color prints
                  because they were too large (at 54 × 77 cm) to be inlaid into mounts or because
                  they were already on thick paper.</p>
	<p>Butts probably had the complete set of 12
                  color prints, though there is no record that he owned <hi rend="i">Naomi
                    Entreating Ruth</hi> and only 10 can be clearly traced to him (those above and
                  Butlin 325). At least one, and probably two from the series (Butlin 291 and 325)
                  were acquired by Strange by 1863, apparently through private sale. If both were so
                  acquired, then none of Butts’s color prints sold through auction—which is to say,
                  they were kept as a series by Butts and his son.</p></note>
	<note id="n32"><hi
                  rend="s">32</hi> Three watercolors once belonging to Butts were trimmed to the
                biblical inscription (about one half inch from the image) instead of to the image
                itself, but these seem to have been trimmed by Blake, who exhibited them in 1808 and
                1809. In 1808, he exhibited <hi rend="i">Jacob’s Dream</hi> and <hi rend="i">Christ
                  in the Sepulchre</hi> (Butlin 438, 500) at the Royal Academy; both works were
                exhibited the following year at Blake’s exhibition, along with <hi rend="i">The
                  Soldiers Casting Lots for Christ’s Garments</hi> (Butlin 495), which was similarly
                trimmed. Trimming watercolors to or near the image was often an exhibition
                requirement (see Essick, “Blake’s 1812 Exhibition” 36). In 1784, Blake exhibited at
                the Royal Academy <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City Wall the Morning after the
                  Battle</hi>, and in 1785 he exhibited three watercolors on the subject of Joseph
                and his brethern (Butlin 191, 155-57). These designs are to the edge of the paper
                and thus in effect appear trimmed to the image. <p>Blake gave the separate plates of
                  the <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi> copy B three or four framing lines, as
                  he did to <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copies R and V, <hi rend="i">All Religions are
                    One</hi> copy A, and <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> copy L.
                  Beginning in 1818, when he resumed illuminated printing, Blake printed his plates
                  with their borders and gave the impressions a single framing line (see Viscomi,
                    <hi rend="i">Book</hi> ch. 33).</p></note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi>
                Another example: at the top of <hi rend="i">Joseph and Potiphar’s Wife</hi> (Butlin
                439) is “Joseph and Jezebel,” the biblical inscription is “Gen. ch: 39<hi
rend="s">th</hi>. v. 17<hi rend="s">th</hi>. &amp; 18,” and below the image in two lines
                is inscribed, “And she spake unto her Lord according to these words, / saying, the
                Hebrew servant which thou has brought unto.” At least one line was cut away from the
                mount, presumably the last words of verse 17 (“us, came in unto me to mock me”). The
                two or three lines of verse 18 may also have been cut away; it was not unusual for
                the text to be four or more lines (<hi rend="i">The Ghost of Samuel Appearing to
                  Saul</hi>, for example, has 11 lines of text). <p>The intended form of the
                  biblical watercolors has been recently questioned by Bindman, who has suggested
                  that they may have been part of, or designed for, an extra-illustrated volume of
                  the bible (<hi rend="i">Job</hi> 27). Butlin believes they were meant for display
                  and cites the copperplate inscriptions as proof of their having filled that
                  intention (review of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 107). Since these inscriptions were
                  written years after the works were purchased, original intention probably cannot
                  be inferred from final form, but the original washline mounts were suitable for
                  framing as well as portfolios. The size of untrimmed sheets, approximately 52 × 43
                  cm (possibly a demy or half a double demy sheet), does not rule out Bindman’s
                  hypothesis, but it would suggest a very large bible indeed.</p></note>	
                <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> The origin of Blake’s titles is a topic beyond the
                scope of this paper, but it is integrally linked to Blake scholarship and requires
                examination. Appendix 1 gives an idea of how complex the issue is by listing the
                various titles that some works have had in various sale catalogues and catalogue
                raisonnés.</note></p>
            <p>Graham Robertson, however, has suggested that the mounts and biblical texts are the
              work of Mrs. Blake, written when the watercolors were sold to Butts (see Robertson
              122, 127, 160). If Mrs. Blake wrote the texts, then almost certainly she or Blake also
              trimmed the watercolors and inlaid them into their mounts, which, in turn, means that
              works so inscribed and mounted cannot be traced to one collection or collector. If the
              Blakes were responsible for the texts and mounts, then works mounted in this
              style—like those acquired from the Ford auction in June 1852 by Fuller (Butlin 519,
              521, 522)—could be traced to Blake and/or Mrs. Blake directly or through a patron
              other than Butts. If all the inlaid mounts of the kind described above belong to Butts
              and not the Blakes, then it is crucial to recognize that Robertson is mistaken about
              Mrs. Blake. The evidence lies in three facts: watercolors executed for other patrons,
              like Rev. Thomas or Linnell, were not so mounted; the extra time and cost of mounting
              are not reflected in the receipts that mention works that were subsequently mounted
              (see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 572-74); and, most telling, despite the
              tradition of Blake having taught Catherine to read and write, 
                <pb id="p29-50" n="50"/>
<figure n="BUT521.1.1.RedDragonDetailInscription.29.2" rend="file" width="958" height="207"> </figure>
              <figure n="RedDragonDetailofInscriptionBottom.29.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="91">
                <head>5 <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea.</hi></head>
                <figDesc>Detail of inscription, copperplate hand written in pencil.</figDesc>
              </figure> the only examples of her writing are two signatures, one in which Catherine
              is <corr type="emend">misspelled</corr> (Keynes, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> xvii). Needless to say, there is no
              evidence that she knew copperplate hand.</p>
            <p>The mounts themselves supply evidence that they were acquired by Butts and not the
              Blakes. Many are embossed in the top left corner with an oval stamp in the shape of a
              palette that reads “Turnbull’s Crayon Board” (illus. 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref> Crayon or drawing boards “are heavy drawing papers or
cardboard, white or
              tinted, with a rough surface on one side and glazed on the other, specially prepared
              for crayon drawings, sepia or water-colour work” (Labarre 126). The date of
              manufacture is difficult to ascertain. The manufacturer may have been Thomas Turnbull,
              who is listed in <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory</hi> for 1802-04 as a
              “Hot-presser” at 23 Booth Street, Spitalfields. (Hot pressing is a method of finishing
              paper by glazing with hot plates.) In Johnstone’s <hi rend="i">London Commercial
                Guide, and Street Directory</hi> for 1817, he is listed under “Calenderers &amp; Hot
              Pressers,” but not under “Card &amp; Pasteboard Makers”—whereas none of the seven
              pasteboard makers listed are hotpressers. (“Calender” refers to the rolls through
              which paper was pressed to give it its finish, and calendering is the method that
              ultimately replaced hot pressing.) Or, more likely, the manufacturer was J. L. &amp;
              J. Turnbull, who were listed in <hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory</hi> for 1819 as
              “stationers and hot pressers” at 105 Bunhill Row. This firm was first listed in 1815
              as Lucas &amp; Turnbull at 20 Chiswell Street. By 1824 they advertise themselves in
              the <hi rend="i">Post Office London Directory</hi> as “Stationers &amp; Booksellers,”
              and by 1834 as “Drawing board &amp; Card Makers and Hot-pressers” and have moved a few
              blocks east to Curtain Road, Holywell Mount, Shoreditch. 
                  <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi> The Turnbull stamp is visible on <hi rend="i">The Great
Red Dragon and
                  the Woman Clothed with the Sun, The Great Red Dragon and the Woman Clothed with
                  the Sun: “The Devil is Come Down,” The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the
                  Sea</hi> (illus. 5), <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Samuel Appearing to Saul, The Angel
                  Rolling the Stone away from the Sepulchre, The Three Maries at the Sepulchre, The
                  Devil Rebuked; The Burial of Moses</hi> (Butlin 519, 520, 521, 458, 501, 503,
                449), among others. These works were all mounted by the same person or shop, and
                while copperplate hand is a generic calligraphic hand, distinctive flourishes among
                the texts strongly indicate that they were written by the same person. For example,
                three of these works (Butlin 520, 521, and 458) have inscriptions beginning with an
                “A” whose left leg extends into the same style of large and very decorative swash or
                loop.</note></p>
            <p>Combined with other evidence, it seems likely that the Turnbull “Crayon Board” used
              for mounts was made by the brothers Turnbull, who advertised themselves as makers of
              this kind of product. A post-1819 date for the mounts, of course, means that they were
              added years after the drawings were purchased. This does not necessarily mean that the
              drawings were not displayed on the walls of Butts’s house. While works in washline
              mounts were usually stored in portfolios, the mounts also encouraged display. Perhaps
              the systematic remounting of the Blakes in a uniform style was prompted by the
              original washline mounts having been pinned to walls or boards, hence the need to trim
              the original margins.</p>
            <p>As noted, Butts left some watercolors untrimmed and thus presumably unmatted; at
              least three were in this style in the March 1852 auction (Butlin 463, 494, 506) and
              three more in Butts’s June 1853 auction (Butlin 495, 500, 639). But clearly he
              drum-mounted most of his Blake watercolors, though this fact is no longer apparent
              because so many of the watercolors have been rematted and/or framed. Many of these,
              however, are recorded in sale catalogues by quotations (see lots 161 and 174 in
              Appendix 1, and Butlin 469, 470), or by Butlin as having inscribed mounts just 20 or
              30 years ago.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref> Though
only eight of the 23
              biblical watercolors in Ford’s June 1852 auction are still in their original,
              Butts-style mounts, all 23 are trimmed to the image, which is why 
                <pb id="p29-51" n="51"/>
I assume that probably all were once uniformly mounted in this inlaid
style
              and thus originally from the Butts collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">37</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> It is to such front window mats, and
                not Butts’ mounts, that Butlin refers to when he notes that title and text are “now
                concealed by the mount” (e.g., 458).</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi><hi
                  rend="i"> St. Paul shaking off the Viper</hi> in lot 175 of the Ford sale is
                probably Butlin 510 (see Appendix 1). Though it is in a private collection and
                unexamined, its inscription is said to read: “Acta XVIII c. 6.v.” This is Blake’s
                form, but there are two reasons I assume that this work was also once mounted in the
                Butts style and that the inscription is not Blake’s. The inscription should read
                “Acts XXVIII c. 6.v.,” and the work was once owned by Quaritch, who bound eight
                similar Butts watercolors in a portfolio, now in the Boston Museum of Fine Arts,
                using the same style of notation on the contents page (see n59).</note></p>
            <p>Butts may have acquired the crayon boards to mat the watercolors himself, or had a
              local stationer mat them using such boards. The latter seems more likely, because the
              mounts appear professionally cut. Their calligraphic texts, however, appear more
              amateurish, as is suggested by the presence of unerased ruling lines on some of the
              mounts and the exclusive use of pencil rather than pen. As chief clerk in the office
              of the Commissary General of Musters, Butts had developed a fine copperplate hand and
              would have been able to write the text. The similarity of the “the” and other letters
              in the texts of <hi rend="i">Sealing the Stone</hi> (illus. 2) and <hi rend="i">The
                Great Dragon</hi> (illus. 5) may be due to a shared letter style, but it may also be
              due to the same hand. However the mounts were prepared, the reasons for Butts’s having
              one watercolor mounted but not another lie with the patron and not the artist.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Charles Ford and the June 1852 Sale</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake’s biblical watercolors at the Ford auction in June 1852 were mounted in the
              Butts style. These works appear certainly to have belonged at one time to Butts. Who
              owned them in June 1852, however, is the question. The title page of the sale
              catalogue reads: Catalogue / of the / Valuable Collection / of / Water-Colour
              Drawings[,] / The Property of / Charles Ford, Esq. of Bath, / Comprising / 
                <hi rend="i">Beautiful Examples of the Productions of</hi> / Barrett, Cox, Chambers,
              Cattermole, De Wint, Lewis, Copley Fielding, Harding, Hunt, F. Tayler, Topham, Roberts
              / and / J. M. W. Turner. / Fine Characteristic Drawings by / William Blake, / Together
              With / A Few Paintings, &amp;c. / The Property of an Amateur” (illus. 1). Auctions
              often included works from more than one collection or vendor, but, as noted, this fact
              was almost always recorded somewhere in the catalogue, either on the title page or as
              a subheading in the catalogue itself, or at the very least in annotated file copies.
              The convention, then, strongly suggests that Ford and the Amateur were the auction’s
              only two vendors. The convention for title pages seems to have been to separate
              artists and titles of works within one vendor’s collection by commas and semi-colons,
              but to separate different collections by periods. Thus the period after “Turner” in
              the Ford sale catalogue is unexpected, forcing us to read “Fine Characteristic
              Drawings by 
              <figure n="TurnbullsCrayonBoard.29.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="370">
                <head>6 “Turnbull’s Crayon Board.”</head>
                <figDesc>Blind embossed stamp in the mount of <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and
                    the Beast from the Sea</hi>, c. 1803-05.</figDesc>
              </figure> 
              William Blake, together with A Few Paintings, &amp;c. the Property of an
              Amateur.” as one sentence. The syntax indicates that the Blakes—together with a few
              paintings, by which is meant oil paintings rather than watercolors—belonged to the
              “Amateur.”</p>
            <p>Can the syntax be trusted? In the March 1852 auction at Sotheby’s, the heading
              “Property of the Late Thomas Moule, Esq.” is one page 17, immediately following lot
              349. On the title page of this auction, however, the two collections are separated by
              a semicolon instead of a period. The semicolon was used for this purpose in many
              Sotheby sale catalogues, including the auction immediately following Ford’s.<ref
                target="n38" type="note">38</ref> The title page of the sale catalogue of <corr type="emend">William
              Monck Mason,</corr> whose auction preceded Ford’s only by a few weeks, used a period inside
              the list of Mason’s 
              collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref> 
              The sale
              catalogue of Butts’s June 1853 auction did the same: “. . . and many other fine
              pictures. Also, A Collection of Pictures 
<pb id="p29-52" n="52"/>
and Drawings, by the
              late William Blake. . . .” The frequent use of the semicolon in place of the expected
              period, and the occasional period in place of the semicolon or comma prevents one from
              relying exclusively on the cataloguer’s punctuation—or compositor’s eyesight. The
              period and comma in the title page of the Ford catalogue may have been mistakenly
              transposed. This, at least, is exactly what the placement of the Blake watercolors
              within the auction and sale catalogue indicates. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">38</hi>
                The collection of Mr. R. W. Silvestre sold at Sotheby’s on 28 June 1852 with an
                anonymous collection. The two collections are separated by a semicolon, followed by
                “to which is added.” The coin collection of Thomas Moule sold at Sotheby’s on 7 June
                1852 with two anonymous collections and the collection of J. W. Harrison, which are
                all separated by semicolons and not periods, despite the fact that all four
                collections were substantial enough to require separate sale days.</note>	
                <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">39</hi> “Catalogue of the Valuable and Important Philological
                and General Library of William Monck Mason, Esq. . . . including A copy of Bartsch
                Peintre Graveur, Revised and Amended as to the Italian Department, and Augmented
                with two Volumes of Supplemented Matter in Manuscript. Also Capital Bookcases,
                Library Tables, etc.”</note></p>
            <p>The Blake watercolors are followed by a ruled line (illus. 7), which usually
              indicates the end of one property and the start of the next. But Ford’s property does
              not end with Blake, for following him are lots 183 to 194, which consist of four works
              by J. F. Lewis, seven by F. W. Topham, and one by Turner, all of whom are mentioned
              unambiguously on the catalogue’s title page as part of Ford’s collection.<ref
                target="n40" type="note">40</ref> Structurally, the Blakes are grouped within Ford’s
              collection instead of the Amateur’s. Up to and including the Turner (lot 194), the
              lots are almost exclusively of British late eighteenth- and early nineteenth-century
              works on paper. The Blake watercolors are all c. 1803-08 and fit more comfortably
              within Ford’s collection than within what follows. Lots 195 to 206 consist of 16
              items, including five “Drawings on Patent Mounts” by Simeon, Gaman (Gamain?), Le Roy,
              and two anonymous artists, and 11 “Paintings” by Zuccarelli, Moroni, Wilson,
              Heemskeerk, and four unknown artists. Only Wilson is an English artist, but the fact
              that his “Landscape, with Castle, Figures in foreground” (lot 203) sold for a mere
              seven shillings strongly suggests that this is a misattribution.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
                type="note">41</ref> Moreover, these are not the artists or kinds of art that
              Butts—as reflected in his son’s and grandson’s auctions—collected. The June 1853
              auction at Foster’s, for example, contains no works by Heemskeerk, Moroni, Le Roy,
              Gaman, or Simeon, <figure n="SothebySaleCatalogue.29.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="513">
                <head>7 Page 10, Sotheby’s sale catalogue for Charles Ford’s collection, 26 June
                  1852.</head>
              </figure> or any “Drawings on Patent Mounts,” or any Topham or Lewis, or paintings by
              Wilson or Zuccarelli, though two drawings attributed to Zuccarelli were included.
              Although the March 1852 auction was probably not Butts Jr.’s, it is worth pointing out
              that it too contained none of these artists or matting styles except for five pencil
              drawings attributed to Wilson and five wash drawings attributed to Zuccarelli. The
              break between Ford and Amateur appears to begin with lot 195, with different artists
              (continental), different mode of presenting art (“Patent Mounts”), and different media
              (paintings). The absence of a catalogue subheading also suggests that the Amateur’s
              collection really was a mere 16 items in 12 lots, tacked on at the end of the sale and
              catalogue, where its shape and content are self-evident. 
                  <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">40</hi> Of the eight Topham drawings in the auction, seven (lots
187-93) were
                grouped after the Blake works; all four J. F. Lewis works were also grouped after
                Blake (183-86).</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Simeon is probably Pierre
                Simeon, a nineteenth-century French architectural artist; Gaman is probably Louis
                Gamain, a nineteenth-century French marine artist; LeRoy is probably Pierre Francois
                Le Roy, the elder, a nineteenth-century Flemish animal and battle painter. Moroni
                probably refers to Giovanni Battista Moroni, whose painting is a “Portrait of
                Aretino,” no doubt Pietro Aretino, the satirist (1492-1556). Moroni was a portrait
                painter who died in 1578, but he is not known to have painted a portrait of Aretino
                (Gregori). More likely, this portrait is a small copy of one by Titian (1545) in the
                Pitti Gallery and is wrongly attributed to Moroni. The fact that it sold for only
                one pound in a decade when five of his portraits sold from 28 to 246 pounds (James
                2: 263) suggests that the work was not taken as authentic. The paintings by
                Zuccarelli, Wilson, and Heemskeerk (probably Maerten) are probably not originals
                either; this is suggested by the extremely low prices they brought in (less than a
                pound each). Unfortunately, none of the works belonging to the Amateur can be
                traced, because the titles are either generic or the attributions are
                incorrect.</note></p>
            <p>Somewhere there is a mistake. Either the typesetter transposed a period and comma on
              the catalogue’s title page—or house style was less consistent and meaningful than we
              imagine—, in which case the Blakes belonged to Ford. Or the cataloguer accidentally
              nested the Amateur’s Blake collection within the Ford lots. One could argue that
              Sotheby’s may have included Blakes from another collection—the Amateur’s—in the Ford
              auction because aesthetically they fit so perfectly and would appeal to the same
              audience as the works in Ford’s collection. But inclusion in the sale does 
                <pb id="p29-53" n="53"/>
not require nesting the works <hi rend="i">within</hi> Ford’s
              collection. The auction was only a one-day sale consisting of 212 lots; had the Blakes
              belonged to the Amateur, they could have followed the Topham, Lewis, and Turner like
              the Amateur’s other works, which would have marked his property while also seamlessly
              continuing the kinds of work central to the sale. One would also think that Sotheby’s
              need to keep accounts, if not also provenances, distinct would make nesting
              unlikely.</p>
            <p>More to the point, Ford did own at least two works by Blake. Lot 11 consists of “The
              Transfiguration, <hi rend="i">coloured</hi>; and Time with the hour glass,” which may
              have been proofs from <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> [Appendix 1]. The separation of
              lot 11 from the watercolors does not necessarily indicate separate collectors, since
              lot 11 is among lots with multiple items, most of which are listed as “sketches” and
              “studies.” The single-item lots begin in earnest on page 5, with lot 50, and the
              subsequent works are primarily watercolor drawings, with descriptions like “finely
              finished,” “very fine,” “a beautiful sketch,” and “powerfully painted” appearing
              regularly. The two Blake works in lot 11 may be outside the main Blake section because
              they are not “Original Drawings in Colours” but prints or sketches, the kinds of works
              that started the auction. Other artists whose works are grouped together, like Hunt,
              Topham, Cox, Duncan, and Wilkie, also have a few works outside their main groups. The
              presence, then, of two Blakes in Ford’s collection increases the likelihood that the
              watercolors were also part of his collection.</p>
            <p>The historical, technical, and national coherencies of the Ford collection support
              the idea that the Blakes belonged to Ford and not the Amateur. Like the unknown
              collector of the March 1852 auction, Ford appears to have acquired Blakes from the
              Butts collection from an unknown source and added them to his collection. Such
              transactions did take place; that is, some collectors did acquire Blakes from the
              Butts collection either directly from Butts or, according to Briggs, from Butts Jr.
              Briggs states that “the son . . . is believed to have hated Blake; at any rate he
              disposed of as many of the drawings as he could as soon as they became his own
              property” (96). She says that “after his father’s death [he] either gave away or sold
              for a mere trifle a great many of the pictures, and notably the Inventions to the Book
              of Job, which was sold by Lord Crewe at Sotheby’s on March 30th, 1904, for £5,600, the
              highest price, it is believed, ever paid for any comparatively modern book” (93). The
              Book of Job watercolors were acquired by Richard Monckton Milnes, later Lord Houghton
              (father of Lord Crewe), presumably from Butts Jr. between 1845 and 1862 (the death of
              Butts and Butts Jr.) for an unknown sum. The idea that Butts Jr. sold the series and
              other of Blake’s works for demeaning sums is based entirely on post-Gilchrist prices.
              As we will see, when Butts Jr.’s auctions are contextualized, the prices reflect
              Blake’s then fair market value. Butts Jr. was neither giving the stuff away nor,
              apparently, in any hurry to rid himself of Blake. Indeed, he insists in his will that
              his children retain the collection, which included his father’s Blakes, “in
              affectionate remembrance of me by whom they are prized by reason of family
              recollections.” Moreover, the sale that is assuredly his occurred at Foster’s a full
              eight years after Butts died (and one and a half years after Mrs. Butts, his
              stepmother, died, for which see my “Green House”). The Foster sale may have been
              prompted by his “Removing from his Residence”—itself possibly prompted by the
              enlistment of his 20-year old son Frederick in the army on 18 March 1853 (see n26).
              Nevertheless, while the motivation behind that auction and the others may be in
              question, the idea that Butts Jr.—or some other member of the family—may have
              privately sold single works before resorting to auctions is borne out by the
              historical record.</p>
            <p>F. T. Palgrave, for example, acquired the temperas <hi rend="i">The Body of Christ
                Borne to the Tomb</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Virgin Hushing the Young Baptist</hi>
              (Butlin 426, 406), inscribing the former: “Bought of Mr. Butts of Fitzroy Square—about
              1852. F. T. Palgrave.” The color print of <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing to the
                Apostles</hi> and the tempera <hi rend="i">The Nativity</hi>, the latter of which
              failed to sell at Butts Jr.’s 1853 and 1854 auctions, were acquired by J. C. Strange
              by 1863 (Butlin 325, 401). The <hi rend="i">Whore of Babylon</hi> was acquired by the
              British Museum in 1847 through “Evans” (Butlin 523), though when and how it left the
              Butts collection is unknown. Milnes acquired <hi rend="i">Jacob’s Dream</hi>, the Job
              watercolors, and <hi rend="i">The Holy Family</hi> by 1863 (Butlin 438, 550, 671).<ref
                target="n42" type="note">42</ref> Dante Gabriel and William Michael Rossetti
              acquired temperas (<hi rend="i">Lot and his Daughters</hi> and <hi rend="i">St.
                Matthew</hi>) that are recorded as coming from Mr. Butts (Rossetti 223, #111; 204,
              #28; Butlin 381, 396), though no sales are known (see also Butlin 428) and, as noted,
              no mention of Butts Jr. is made in either of their correspondence, which raises the
              possibility that they acquired the works from a third party, who acquired it from
              either Butts or Butts Jr.—or from another member of the family. 
                  <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">42</hi> Butlin suspects that Milnes acquired <hi rend="i">The
Repose</hi>
                from Butts, “this watercolour [cannot] be found in the known Butts sales, but at
                least one sale remains untraced” (472). Rossetti records <hi rend="i">The
                  Repose</hi> as belonging to Milnes and not Butts (209, #69)—which is
                understandable since Butts owned the tempera version (Butlin 405). Even Butlin finds
                duplicates in Butts’s collection suspicious, nothing that the watercolor is a “late
                addition to the series of watercolours of Biblical subjects” and “may well have been
                painted with another, or no, patron in mind” (472). On the other hand, there is
                precedent for Milnes’s acquiring works from the Butts collection by private sale and
                for Butts’s owning tempera and watercolor of the same subjects (see Butlin 415, 474,
                and Lot 167 in Appendix 1).</note></p>
            <p>Blakes did leave the Butts collection through private sale; Butts Jr., however, was
              not necessarily the only one behind those sales. Indeed, recent discoveries about
              Thomas Butts’s residences and family strongly support the idea that other members of
              the Butts family had access to and possibly acquired and sold the Blakes from the
              Butts collection in the March and June 1852 auctions (see Viscomi, “Green House”). The
              presence of Blakes from the Butts collection in auctions whose vendors might not have
              been Butts Jr. suggests that the Butts collection began to be dispersed before 1852
              and that interest in collecting Blake was wider and the number of Blake collectors
              larger than previously realized. And this, combined with an extended family and
              numerous residences, suggests that Butts Jr. may have not been the first to disperse
              publicly the Butts Blake collection. But the idea that Butts Jr. was at the Ford
              auction in June 1852 <hi rend="i">buying</hi> Blakes once owned by his father raises
              other problems.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p29-54" n="54"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Another Unknown Blake Collector and Sale</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The Blakes in Ford’s June 1852 auction thus appear to have belonged to Ford, who
              acquired them from a Butts family member; or, less likely, they may have belonged to
              the Amateur, who either did the same or was a Butts descendant other than Butts Jr.
              The fourth and most unlikely possibility is that they belonged to the Amateur who was
              Butts Jr. Admittedly, the idea that Butts was at the auction selling Blakes is easier
              to believe than his buying them, because the Blakes involved were once his father’s.
              But this seemingly logical conclusion requires that the Blakes were incorrectly nested
              in Ford’s collection and that Blake failed to sell, something the other auctions of
              1852 and 1853 make unlikely (see below). Equally significant, such a conclusion is
              challenged by Sotheby’s accounting nomenclature and a heretofore unknown precedent of
              <corr type="emend">Butts Jr.’s</corr> acquiring other Blakes at auction.</p>
            <p>Typically, auction catalogues that record prices and buyers have corresponding
              columns drawn in the right margin of the page, or the catalogue page is inlaid into an
              account book with such columns drawn in (illus. 7 and 8). In a normal transaction,
              price and buyer were recorded in their proper columns. If an item was withdrawn, the
              lot number was crossed out and no price or buyer was recorded. Items bought in were
              recorded in various ways. In Sotheby’s catalogues, like those of March and June 1852,
              the buy-in price was listed in the price column, no buyer’s name was recorded, and the
              price was repeated to the right of the buyer’s column. The buy-in price is the final
              bid reached from the floor but which falls below the reserve price, the price that the
              vendor informs the auctioneer is the lowest acceptable bid and which is kept secret.
              The buy-in price, repeated far right in a column of its own, identifies the item that
              failed to sell and is the price upon which the commission paid by the unsuccessful
              vendor is accessed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref> In
Butts Jr.’s June 1853
              auction at Foster and Son, the buy-ins are recorded differently but the objective is
              the same. In the annotated copy of the catalogue at the Victoria and Albert Art
              Library, the buy-in price was recorded in the buyer’s column, in place of a name, and
              the price column was left blank; in the annotated catalogue in the Frick Art Library,
              the price column was left blank, the buyer is recorded as “Thomas,” a pseudonym
                <figure n="SothebySaleCatalogue9.29.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="511">
                <head>8 Page 9, Sotheby’s sale catalogue for Charles Ford’s collection, 26 June
                  1852.</head>
              </figure> for Butts Jr., and the buy-in price is listed right of the buyer’s column,
              as in the Sotheby catalogues. <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">43</hi> In Sotheby
                catalogues, some buyers have the purchase prices repeated in the buy-in column.
                Because the duplication is used for the same buyers throughout a sale, the repeated
                price with a buyer’s name appears to indicate a credit (see illus. 7).</note></p>
            <p>Auction houses often bid prices up to their reserve by bouncing fictive bids “off the
              chandelier.” But at Foster’s, Butts Jr. appears to have bid the prices up himself, as
              “Thomas,” at the risk of “buying” those lots when he was not outbid. The wide range in
              prices for the Blake material that “Thomas” bought suggests that Butts Jr. was bidding
              per lot rather than relying on a uniform reserve, say of £1 for mounted works of
              similar size and media.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">44</ref> He bought in a 27 × 38
              cm tempera on copper (<hi rend="i">The Nativity</hi>) for 6s., but then let two
              temperas twice that size (<hi rend="i">Eve Naming the Birds</hi> and <hi rend="i">Adam
                Naming the Beasts</hi>), each approximately 75 × 62 cm, go for a mere 5s. apiece to
              William Stirling-Maxwell. For 19s. he bought in <hi rend="i">Moses and Pharoah’s
                Daughter</hi>, a nicely mounted watercolor of 32 × 32 cm, but he let the watercolors
                <hi rend="i">Moses and the Burning Bush</hi>, 39 × 30.4 cm, and <hi rend="i">Saul
                and Samuel</hi>, 32 × 33.4 cm, which were also professionally mounted, go for 7s.
              each. A few works were bought in for as 
<pb id="p29-55" n="55"/>
little as 2s. (lots
              84 and 141, each lot containing three temperas(?) now untraced), while others cost
              Butts Jr./“Thomas” as much as 19s. and 17s. (lots 126 and 132). 
                  <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">44</hi> Reserves, of course, are never made public, but not all
auctions
                have reserves; a few auctions at Foster and Son, for example, included properties
                advertised as being “without reserve” (see 2 July 1845, for example).</note></p>
            <p>Was Butts Jr. attempting to do the same at the Ford auction, to bid prices up at
              Sotheby’s in June 1852? Did he buy-in <hi rend="i">19</hi> watercolors? The accounting
              nomenclature clearly states that the Blakes sold as normal transactions, that they
              were bought and not bought in (illus. 7). Prices and buyer are listed in their proper
              columns and no prices are listed right of the buyer. If the Blakes were bought in,
              then how was Sotheby’s auctioner or accountant to know that? Three works in the Ford
              auction appear to have been bought in (lots 6, 28, and 108), and they were
              conventionally recorded: no buyer is listed and the price is recorded twice, in the
              price column and right of the buyer’s column, and they were added up separately.</p>
            <p>What indicates that the accounting nomenclature for Ford’s auction can be trusted is
              the precedent of Butts Jr.’s buying <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> at Sotheby’s on 5 July
              1852, just nine days after the Ford sale, when he would surely have been informed
              about the upcoming July sale. The sale was four days long and included four vendors,
              but the first and primary vendor was Edward Vernon Utterson (1776?-1856), a well known
              and successful book and art collector.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">45</ref> He is not
              mentioned in Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> or <hi rend="i">Blake
                Records</hi>, or in Butlin, yet he owned two illuminated books 
                (<hi rend="i">America, Book of Ahania</hi>), two illustrated books (<hi rend="i">The
Grave</hi>,
              two copies of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>), and the second set of the 
                <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustrations (see Appendix 2 for an annotated list of the
              Blakes sold in this auction), which Butts Jr. sold at Foster’s in June 1853 and which,
              consequently, is assumed to have been commissioned by his father. 
                  <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">45</hi> Three other vendors, whose properties are clearly
identified in
                the catalogue, also participated in this four-day sale. The Blakes sold on the first
                day and were listed under “Quarto”; they belonged to the first and largest
                collection (lots 1-682), which is identified as Utterson’s on the microfilm’s
                introductory label, an identification supported by the inclusion of limited editions
                published by private clubs, like Abbotsford Club Books (lots 217-20) and Bannatyne
                Club Books (231-41), which Utterson assiduously collected. Lowndes misdates the
                auction as “1855,” but he records the illuminated books and prices correctly (1:
                216).</note></p>
            <p>Utterson was a barrister practicing in the court of chancery. He was also an editor
              of early English works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">46</ref> He was elected fellow of
              the Society of Antiquaries in 1807 and was an original member of the Roxburghe Club,
              founded in 1812, a few of whose members and friends also owned original works by
                Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">47</ref> After 1835 he
resided on the Isle of
              Wight, where he set up the Beldornie Press, 1840-43. “The Principal Portion of [his]
              Valuable Library” was sold at Sotheby’s on 19-26 April, 29 April-1 May, and 3 May
              1852. The Blake works, though, were auctioned at Sotheby’s on 5 July 1852, lots
              248-53, as part of a “Catalogue of a Valuable Assemblage of Choice and Fine Books:
              including Some Rare Old English Poetry, and other interesting works, from the Library
              of an Eminent Collector, Omitted in the Previous Sale; Some Profusely Illustrated
              Books. . . .” <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">46</hi> For a list of books written and
                edited by Utterson, see his auction at Sotheby’s, 20 March 1857, which is not listed
                in Lugt.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">47</hi> James Boswell owned 
                  <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy U, the Duke of Devonshire owned
                  <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> copy S, Thomas Dibdin acquired a copy of 
                  <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence, The Book of Thel</hi> copy J, and 
                  <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> copy G, Richard Heber owned 
                  <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> copy F, Earl Spencer acquired copy Q of 
<hi rend="i">Night
                  Thoughts</hi> (a colored copy) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> of 1802, and
                Francis Douce acquired <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> copy B.
                Utterson may have learned of Blake through his friend Thomas Dibdin, whom Blake
                visited in 1816 to discuss the minor poems of Milton (see n74). It is interesting to
                note, though, that the lawyers John and George Shaddick, who in 1817 shared an
                office with George Butts, Butts’s youngest son, worked in Utterson’s office (Six
                Clerks Office, Chancery Lane) in 1819, according to <hi rend="i">Robson’s
                  Directory</hi> for that year.</note></p>
            <p>Butts Jr. purchased Utterson’s copy of the 1808 edition of <hi rend="i">The
                Grave</hi> (lot 248) and the eight illustrations of Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>
              (lot 253). He did not purchase anything else from this four day sale, despite its
              inclusion of other illustrated books, an omission which is inconsistent with the
              hypothesis that Butts Jr. was the vendor of the print collection auctioned in March
              1852. (The purchase of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> is particularly odd if Butts Jr.
              had been the vendor, because he would have sold a copy of the same edition for only
              five shillings and was now paying 13 shillings more than his own copy realized.) He
              paid £4 6s. for <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and sold it and <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> in
              June 1853 for a profit, the latter going to Wood for £2 2s. (lot 143) and the former
              to J. C. Strange for £6 6s. (lot 98). The first <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> series was
              finished c. 1801, commissioned and purchased by the Rev. Joseph Thomas (Butlin 527).
              The second series is assumed to have been executed for Butts because it was sold by
              his son, even though stylistic features suggest a c. 1815 date (Butlin 528), a period
              when Butts is conspicuously absent from Blake’s affairs and no receipts for works are
              extant (see Viscomi, “Green House”). Could <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> have once belonged
              to Butts and been sold privately to Utterson? While this theory cannot be ruled out
              completely, it seems unlikely because the manner in which <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>
              designs were mounted differed considerably from the one usually used by Butts. They
              are now trimmed to the image and in modern mats, but they appear never to have been
              inlaid into larger window mounts like the biblical watercolors. The purchase and
              physical evidence (for more of which see below) suggest that the second series of 
                <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> was not executed for Butts, but possibly for Utterson himself or
              for an unknown collector from whom Utterson acquired it. Rossetti records the
              provenance of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> as “Mr. Strange, from Mr. Butts” (232, #205),
              apparently unaware of the Utterson sale. He was also unaware of Rev. Thomas’s 
                <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, as well as his <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> (see below).</p>
            <p>Butts Jr.’s presence at the 5 July 1852 auction, his purchase of works by Blake, and
              his selling those works the following year support the idea that he had been a buyer
              at the June 1852 auction as well. For a Butts to buy Blakes at auction, however, was
              not unprecedented. A “Butts” acquired four 
<pb id="p29-56" n="56"/>
illuminated books
              and a copy of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> from the George Cumberland sale of 6 May
              1835 at Christie’s. These books sold in the March 1852 auction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
                type="note">48</ref> The “Butts” who bought them was most likely Thomas Butts
              (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 657); he was 75 years old at the time and was
              apparently in the habit of presenting his second wife, Elizabeth Delauney, with gifts
              (see Viscomi, “Green House”). Of course, Butts Jr., who was 47, might have been
              “Butts,” as he was at the Utterson sale 17 years later. In any event, the act of
              buying Blake’s books and watercolors in 1835 and 1852, years after Blake and Mrs.
              Blake died, means that Butts and/or his son were collecting Blake, that is, acquiring
              Blakes not out of the desire to help Blake financially but out of the desire to create
              or enrich a Blake collection. <note id="n48"><hi rend="s">48</hi> A Butts receipt
                records the purchase of a copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                  Experience</hi> from Blake for £6 6s. in September 1806 (Bentley, 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 575). This copy (E) is assumed to be the one sold in the
26-27
                March 1852 auction. There are no similar receipts for the copies of <hi rend="i">The
                  Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (F) and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> (L)
                sold in the March 1852 auction (see n27). The four illuminated books from the
                Cumberland sale of 1835 are <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy F, <hi rend="i">Visions
                  of the Daughters of Albion</hi> copy B, <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy D, and 
                  <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> copy D, which were bound together and sold with a copy
                of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (lot 60). “Butts” purchased the lot for £3 18s.
                (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 657). The four illuminated books were sold
                in the March 1852 auction (lot 54) to Palgrave for £11; <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>
                sold to Toovey for five shillings (lot 61).</note></p>
            <p>Is it possible, then, that Butts Jr. was at the Ford auction buying Blakes that once
              belonged to his father in order to add them to his collection—a collection that was no
              longer synonomous with his father’s? At first, the idea of his purchasing works seems
              suspect because he sold them just one year later along with similar kinds of Blakes.
              And buying Blakes seems especially suspect if he was selling them just a few months
              earlier, at the March 1852 auction. But, as noted, except for the Blakes, the
              collection sold in March 1852 does not appear to have been assembled by Butts Sr. or
              sold by Butts Jr. In other words, the June 1853 auction—the only auction that
              identifies Butts Jr. as the vendor—may have been his first. Its explicit cause was his
              “Removing from his Residence,” a decision presumably made after the June 1852 auction,
              and possibly motivated by the enlistment of his son Frederick into the army in the
              spring of 1853.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">49</ref>
Indeed, the March and June sales
              of 1852 may have given him the idea to put part of his Blake collection up for auction
              the following year. In short, he may have believed that Blake now had a public market.
                <note id="n49"><hi rend="s">49</hi> I am not sure where Butts Jr. moved in 1852; he
                is recorded in directories after 1856 and in his will at 20 Chester Terrace, Regent
                Park.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Market for Blake in 1852</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The question of whether Butts Jr. was at Ford’s auction in June 1852 as vendor or
              buyer can be answered by considering the sale catalogue’s structure and its accounting
              nomenclature, the unlikelihood of Butts Jr.’s being the vendor of the March 1852
              auction, and the precedent of Butts Jr.’s buying Blakes at other auctions: he was
              there as buyer. And as buyer, he bid presumably to acquire Blakes, though he may also
              have bid to ensure that Blake’s watercolors did not sell for too little, that is, to
              create the appearance of a Blake market, an illusion especially important to a
              collector who owned the world’s largest Blake collection. But this fact was
              undoubtedly little known at the time, and the idea of manipulating the market for the
              future sale of Blakes raises serious questions, not the least of which is whether such
              a market existed.</p>
            <p>The March 1852 auction, with 25 Blake watercolors realizing £48 7s.6d., was the first
              major sale of a collection of diverse Blake designs since Blake’s own 1809 exhibition.
              It was followed by the Ford auction in June 1852, with 29 watercolors realizing £23
              5s.6d., the Utterson auction of 5 July 1852, with eight <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>
              designs, two illuminated books, and three illustrated books realizing £11.18s. All
              three sales were at Sotheby’s, where copy G of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, Blake’s most
              elaborately colored copy of this 28-page book, sold on 20 January 1852 for £8 15s. to
              Milnes (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 182). Apparently, word was out: Blake
              could sell. The following year saw the Butts auction in June 1853 at Foster and Son,
              with 117 drawings and paintings, followed by a previously unrecorded auction at
              Sotheby’s on 19 December 1853, in which copies of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
                and Hell, Book of Thel, Jerusalem</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi> sold
              for £15 2s. from the collection of John Hugh Smyth Pigott (see Viscomi, 
                <hi rend="i">Book</hi> 352). The next year saw the Joseph Hogarth auction of 7-30 June 1854 at
              Southgate and Barrett, with 78 works. The next extensive Blake collection that came to
              market included over 200 sketches, color prints, and watercolors, and two post-humous
              copies of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, which sold at Sotheby’s on 29 April 1862. This
              auction is believed by Butlin to be Tatham’s (“William Rossetti” 40 and throughout the
              catalogue raisonné), though Bentley always gives Tatham a question mark when referring
              to this auction (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, passim). Tatham is a logical choice
              because the auction included drawings and sketches, the very kind of works that might
              have remained in Blake’s studio and that he would have inherited from Mrs. Blake. The
              problem is that in 1862 Tatham was corresponding with Rossetti, but Rossetti, who went
              to press after the Bicknell sale of 29 April - 1 May 1863 (which he refers to on 201,
              #5), does not know about this auction or many of the collectors there purchasing
              Blakes, like the painter Rowbotham. Clearly, he never saw a copy of the sale
              catalogue, recording only those works from the auction that had been purchased by
              dealers that he knew, like Palser and Harvey, who did not divulge the source of the
              material (see n12). The attribution of the 1862 auction to Tatham, like the
              attribution of the March 1852 to Butts Jr., makes sense until examined closely, when
              it begins to suggest yet another Blake collector unknown to us.</p>
            <p>Blake’s paintings apparently began changing hands publicly around 1852. Until the
              March 1852 sale at Sotheby’s, <pb id="p29-57" n="57"/>
the Blake works that sold
              through auctions and dealers were primarily illuminated and illustrated books. Indeed,
              as Dorfman demonstrates, Blake was known—so far as he had any reputation at all—more
              as an illustrator than a painter. “During the 1850s in England a well-informed art
              critic of the younger generation would have known of William Blake only from Allan
              Cunningham’s generally unsympathetic account in his <hi rend="i">Lives of the
                Painters</hi> and the engraved designs to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The
                Grave.</hi> Blake . . . seemed to be making his way to oblivion; those who
              remembered the man or had bought his works were settling into old age” (1). According
              to Cunningham, Blake “was a most splendid tinter, but no colourist, and his works were
              all of small dimensions, and therefore confined to the cabinet and the portfolio. His
              happiest flights, as well as his wildest, are thus likely to remain shut up from the
              world” (qtd. in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 503). To Cunningham, Blake
              was a minor artist, ranked below Flaxman and Fuseli, of interest for his strange turn
              of mind, his engravings of Job, lyrical poetry, prophecies, and visionary heads. As
              noted, Gilchrist did not himself know of Blake or start on the biography until 1854,
              and there were no public exhibitions of Blake’s works or reproductions to challenge
              Cunningham.</p>
            <p>With so little public knowledge and exchange of Blake’s paintings and drawings,
              Blake’s market value in March 1852 was still a mystery. Had Butts Jr. or Sotheby’s
              known in 1851 of previous auctions of Blake watercolors, which is unlikely, they might
              have been discouraged. Blake failed to sell his paintings at his exhibition of 1809.
              Likewise, Thomas Edwards of Halifax attempted and failed to sell the 537 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs, which were comparable in size (42 × 32 cm) and
medium
              to Butts’s biblical watercolors. These, the first watercolors brought to market by
              someone other than Blake, were offered in 1821 as one item for L300 (Butlin 330),
              which is approximately 11s. 11d. per design. They were put up for auction in 1826 and
              1828 and bought in both times, the latter time for only £52 10s. (Bentley, 
                <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 655), which means they failed to bring in even 2s. per
              design.</p>
            <p>Also in 1828, Blake’s 117 illustrations to Gray’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, the same
              size, medium, and period as the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs, were sold at
              Flaxman’s auction for a mere £8 8s. (Butlin 335), which is about 1s.6d. per design. On
              21 May 1830, however, two late and highly finished watercolors, <hi rend="i">The
                Vision of Queen Katherine</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>,
              both c. 1825 (Butlin 549, 481), sold at the Thomas Lawrence auction at Christie’s for
              £4 6s. and £8 15s respectively. These high prices are in part due to the splendor of
              these late designs, but may also be to the very good provenance of Lawrence himself,
              as well as to the high number of collectors and dealers in attendance.<ref
                target="n50" type="note">50</ref> But that was the last public sale of Blake
              watercolors until the auction in March 1852. During that 22 year hiatus, a few more
              illuminated books sold—and did not sell. Bohn acquired <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
              copy F in 1837 for £3 18s. and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> copy D bound with 
                <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> copy O in 1838 for £5 12s.6d. (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
              130). These works were first listed in Bohn’s catalogue for 1841 but not sold till
              after 1847. <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">50</hi> The prices paid for the Blakes are
                especially high relative to pencil and chalk drawings by Fuseli, Flaxman,
                Gainsborough, Cosway, and Lawrence himself in this and Lawrence’s 17 June 1830
                auction.</note></p>
            <p>The size and shape of the market for Blake’s watercolors, then, began to emerge in
              March 1852. Nearly all the Blakes sold for over a pound, and a few sold for over two
              pounds, prices that may have prompted other collectors—or Butts Jr.—to sell their
              Blakes, not because these prices are high for Blake, since the absence of recent sales
              made that impossible to gauge, but because they sold for what other works comparable
              in size, medium, and age, as is evinced by the auctions of March and June 1852, as
              well as those of 21 and 29 June 1853 at Sotheby’s. These auctions included watercolors
              and wash drawings by Rowlandson, Martin, Evans, Cotman, Turner, DeWint, Gainsborough,
              Bonington, Prout, and Cox (see lots 82-85, 91, 92, 78, 79, 94, 105, 113, 123, 124 of
              the Ford auction). For example, in the Ford auction, “Landscape Composition in sepia,
                <hi rend="i">highly finished</hi>,” by J. Martin (lot 85) sold for 5s.; “A Landscape
              Sketch, in colours” by DeWint (lot 78) sold with a work by Vickers for 5s. If the
              March and June 1852 auctions are the context, then Briggs is certainly mistaken to
              accuse Butts Jr. of disliking Blake and selling “for a mere trifle a great many of the
              pictures” (93). Apparently, she inferred that Butts Jr. disliked Blake from his having
              sold Blakes for what seemed to be paltry sums. Relative to the prices commanded by
              watercolors by Blake’s contemporaries, though, the prices realized by Blake’s
              watercolors were fair.</p>
            <p>With the Blake lots selling at the end of the Ford auction, with the tenor of the day
              established, with only three Ford items bought in, and with Blakes selling for as much
              as the other drawings and watercolors, would Butts Jr. buy-in 19 of 29 works? If he
              did, then clearly Blake failed to sell. If, however, as I believe is the case, Butts
              Jr. was buying, then Blake sold but for lower prices relative to March. Had Butts Jr.
              known about the March sale, he would have been in an advantageous position in the June
              1852 sale, either as vendor or buyer. If there as vendor, then he bought in hoping
              that Blake could realize higher prices at a later date. If there as buyer, then he
              purchased works knowing that they were at good prices and might prove to be an
              investment. Speculating so, either as vendor or buyer, would have been risky—unless
              Butts Jr. suspected why the prices were lower than before.</p>
            <p>At the March 1852 auction, four collectors and six dealers who were or would become
              interested in Blake were present: Arthington, Milnes, Palgrave, Dilke, Toovey, Bohn,
              Colnaghi, Evans, Palser, and Hogarth.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">51</ref> At Butts’s
              June 1853 auction, <pb id="p29-58" n="58"/>
nine collectors and dealers were present:
              Bohn, Sterling-Maxwell, Strange, Robinson, Mills, C. Martin, Money, Wood, and
              Colnaghi. Bohn was the main buyer in both these auctions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">52</ref> He and most of the other collectors appear to have been
absent from Ford’s
              June 1852 auction. Present, though, were Palser, W. Evans, Hogarth, Fuller, and
              Hickeson, who bought two Blake works from Ford (lot 11). So some competition was
              present, but clearly less than in March 1852 and June 1853.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
                type="note">53</ref> None of these buyers purchased anything at Butts’s March 1854
              auction, which suggests that they were probably absent and may explain why the Blakes
              bought in by “Thomas” in June 1853 remained unsold. In any event, Butts may have
              reasoned in June 1852 that the low prices were not due to Blake but to the audience,
              and that the solution was to alter it. Apparently, this was done for the June 1853
              auction, since, as noted, at least nine reputable collectors and dealers attended the
              auction and the prices, though not as high as the March 1852 sale, were higher by a
              few shillings per item than those of the Ford June 1852 sale. 
                  <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">51</hi> Arthington and Toovey bought illuminated books but no
                watercolors; Palser and Hogarth, dealers who acquired Blakes later in the decade,
                bought many Rowlandson drawings and other works but no Blakes that day. Still, they
                may have been part of the bidding.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">52</hi>
                Relatively few of Bohn’s Blake acquisitions had been resold by 1863, since Rossetti
                examined most of them in Bohn’s collection. Whether this reflects the market,
                prohibitive prices, or an unwillingness to sell the works is not known.</note>	
                <note id="n53"><hi rend="s">53</hi> Palser, who bought a number of Blake works from the 29
                April 1862 auction at Sotheby’s, bought 22 works at Ford’s 26 June 1852 auction, but
                no Blakes. Only twice did he spend more than a pound; he bought over 24 items in
                March 1852, but again was very conservative, spending more than a pound only four
                times. He was usually picking up what could be had for less than 10 shillings—which
                was considerable.</note></p>
            <p>Prices for Blake were a bit lower in June than March 1852 for similar works, probably
              due to the absence of serious buyers rather than to a severe revaluation of Blake.
              Prices were relatively low at the Utterson sale of 5 July 1852 as well, where Bohn and
              Evans were absent (or at least silent) on the day the Blakes sold. Utterson’s
              illuminated books sold for prices close to those in March 1852, but his eight designs
              of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> sold for less than the similarly-sized six designs of 
                <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> (£4 6s. versus £6 6s.). Given these low prices, the fact that
              Fuller paid more than a pound for each of his purchases in June 1852, while Butts paid
              less than a pound for his, may signify a more determined buyer instead of an owner
              secretly buying in. Whatever our opinion of the relative worth of Blake’s works,
              Fuller clearly bought those works that were identified in the catalogue as being in
              Blake’s “finest manner,” works described as “very powerful and characteristic” and
“of
              grand conception and highly characteristic.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The June 1852 Vendor Redux</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Comparing Butts Jr.’s June 1853 auction with the March and June auctions of 1852 may
              not provide conclusive answers, but it brings into sharper focus the shape and size of
              Blake’s emerging market before Gilchrist.</p>
            <p>In Butts Jr.’s June 1853 sale, the Blakes were grouped in a very orderly manner. Lots
              70-87 were temperas of various sizes; lots 88-92 were vertical watercolors; lots 93-97
              were horizontal temperas; lots 98-139 were watercolors, and lots 140-42 were temperas.
              The main group of watercolors (lots 100-38) were bracketed by Milton illustrations,
                <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il
                Penseroso</hi> (lots 98-99) and nine from <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (lot 139).
              The biblical watercolors acquired from Ford’s June 1852 auction were not dispersed
              within the Butts collection—as one might expect if these works were returning home—but
              remained together. Though not in the same lot order as in the Ford auction, they
              formed a group within a group, like a series of recent acquisitions, selling in lots
              103-15 (116? see lot 182x in Appendix 1).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">54</ref> The
              watercolors sold for more, on average, than the temperas: only three of possibly 35
              temperas sold for more than £1 apiece, whereas 31 (including nine 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations) out of 82 watercolors (including 20 Milton
              illustrations) sold for more than £1 apiece. <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">54</hi> The
                only work of the 19 watercolors from June 1852 not put up for auction in June 1853
                was <hi rend="i">Touching the Garment</hi> (see Appendix 1, lot 156), now known as
                  <hi rend="i">Christ Healing the Woman with an Issue of Blood</hi> (Butlin
                482).</note></p>
            <p>The differences between the auctions of March and June 1852 and Butts Jr.’s auctions
              of June 1853 and March 1854 reflect different vendors and selling strategies. Only six
              items in the March 1852 auction were withdrawn and another four to eight bought in
              (see n20), which is less than 1%. Only three items appear to have been bought in in
              the June 1852 auction, which is less than 1%. In the June 1853 auction, 22% of the
              entire collection was bought in.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">55</ref> The Amateur’s
              share of the June 1852 auction was at least the last 12 lots (16 items). If the 29
              Blake watercolors belonged to the Amateur, then that property had at most 41 lots (46
              items). To assume that this Blake-owning Amateur was Butts Jr. is to assume not only
              that buy-ins were recorded differently for this one sale and that precedent is
              inconsequential, but also that Butts Jr. bought in 65% of the Blakes he put up for
              sale but none of the non-Blake material. <note id="n55"><hi rend="s">55</hi> In the 29
                June 1853 auction, 69 drawings and paintings by various artists were sold in the
                first 62 lots, and 117 Blakes were sold in the subsequent 75 lots (see n14). Butts
                Jr. bought in 26 items from the first group (37%) and 17 from the second (14%), and
                two of these were theatre portraits believed to have been by Blake (see
              n16).</note></p>
            <p>All the material belonging to Butts Jr. in March 1854 came from his June 1853
              auction, and nearly all of the items again failed to sell. The 17 Blakes sold in six
              lots (13-18), presumably to increase their chances of selling. Only two (now untraced)
              temperas sold (Butlin 397, 399), and those for only 5s.6d. apiece. The other works
              were bought in, at usually half the 1853 buy-in prices. Lowering the reserve for an
              item the second time it is auctioned was standard procedure. But it would not have
              been followed if Butts Jr. were the vendor of the June 1852 auction. In that auction,
              he bought <hi rend="i">Satan in His Former Glory</hi> for 10s.; if this were a 
                <pb id="p29-59" n="59"/>
buy-in instead of a purchase (see Appendix 1, lot 157), then
              his buying it in June 1853 for 11s., i.e., at a higher reserve, makes little sense. In
              1854 this drawing was again bought in, along with two others, for an average of
              7s.</p>
            <p>In the 1854 sale, the 17 Blakes unsold from the year before were given lower
              reserves, most failed to sell, but all kept the same titles. In the 1853 sale, 18
              Blakes came from the June 1852 auction, all but one sold, nearly all realized higher
              prices than in 1852, and at least seven were retitled.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n56" type="note">56</ref> Titles are given to the auction house by the vendor; if Butts was the
              vendor of both the June 1852 and June 1853 sales, then why did he change titles of
              works bought in? If to conceal the earlier sale, then why change only a few and not
              all? Why not also change titles of the works resold in March 1854?<ref target="n57"
                type="note">57</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">56</hi> The work that failed to sell
                was <hi rend="i">Satan in His Former Glory</hi>; works whose titles were changed
                included <hi rend="i">Witch of Endor</hi>, changed to <hi rend="i">Saul and
                  Samuel</hi>, and “<hi rend="i">Her Sins Are Forgiven</hi>,” changed to 
                  <hi rend="i">Jesus and Martha.</hi> (See Appendix 1, lots 157, 158, 161, 166, 168,
                172, 175.) <p>In March 1852, five works were titled by the quotes on their mounts;
                  in June 1852, 12 (including six Milton designs) were so titled; but only one title
                  is quoted from the mount in June 1853. Another similarity between the March and
                  June auctions of 1852—which set them apart from Butts Jr.’s June 1853 auction—is
                  the absence of temperas and color prints.</p></note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">57</hi> The descriptions given to lots in these auctions also differ, though
                these may have been supplied by the auction house. Even so, they reveal how Blake
                was perceived at the time. In Butts Jr.’s 1853 auction, four Blakes are described
                minimally: (88) <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi>, “an elaborate work”; (89) 
                  <hi rend="i">The Fall of Man</hi>, “a capital drawing”; (91) <hi rend="i">Death on the
                  Pale Horse</hi>, “spirited”; and (137) <hi rend="i">Queen Catherine’s Dream</hi>,
                “very fine.” In the March 1852 auction, eight of 20 Blake lots were described, a few
                effusively: (147) Milton’s <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi>, “six very beautiful and
                highly finished drawings”; (149) <hi rend="i">The Blasphemer</hi>, “sketched with
                great power and effect”; (163) <hi rend="i">The Devil is Come Down</hi>, “a fine
                characteristic example of the vigour and talent of the artist”; (165) 
                  <hi rend="i">The Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>, “admirably designed, and very fine”;
(166) 
                  <hi rend="i">The Vision of Queen Katherine</hi>, “an elaborate and most beautifully
                finished drawing, the fantastic grouping of the flying figures being of the most
                admirable execution, and altogether a CHEF D’OEUVRE OF THIS EXTRAORDINARY ARTIST.”
                The descriptions in Ford’s June 1852 auction are closer to those of March than to
                those of June 1853. (See Appendix 1, lots 155, 156, 157, 162, 163, 164, 167, 169,
                176.)</note></p>
            <p>Behavior so different from that shown in the June 1853 auction strongly supports the
              bibliographical evidence supplied by the Ford catalogue, that Butts Jr. attended the
              Ford auction to buy Blakes that once belonged to his father (and possibly sold by
              another member of his family) for his own collection.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>The Milton Illustrations in the Butts Collection</title>
            </head>
            <p>Six of the 12 1808 <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs were in the Ford auction
              (lots 177-82). They were placed under the subheading: “The six following Designs, by
              Blake, are illustrative of Milton’s ‘Paradise Lost.’” Three were acquired by Fuller
              and three by Butts (see Appendix 1). Their presence in the auction raises the question
              of initial provenance. Were these watercolors also once part of the original Butts
              collection, or were they acquired from other collectors? The evidence connecting the
              1808 <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> set with Butts is strong though mostly
              circumstantial, not documentary. They were executed when Butts was Blake’s “almost
              solitary purchaser” and sold in his son’s June 1853 auction. Linnell commissioned
              Blake to reproduce the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> drawings, recording on 9 April
              1822 that Blake had begun to make them (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 275).
              But no mention is made of an owner. Blake is assumed to have borrowed them from Butts,
              because it was from Butts that he borrowed the Job watercolors (and other works) so
              Linnell could prepare tracings for a second set.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">58</ref>
              The original style used to mount the nine <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs
              supports this assumption. These nine sold in June 1853 to J. C. Strange (lot 139 for
              £17 6s.6d.), who also acquired the eight <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> designs and nine
              biblical watercolors, along with the seven Shakespeare miniatures. 
                  <note id="n58"><hi rend="s">58</hi> Though there are no records, Butts must have lent Blake 
                  <hi rend="i">The Vision of Queen Katherine</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Wise and Foolish
                  Virgins</hi> (Butlin 548, 478) as well, because the late versions executed for
                Lawrence and Linnell (Butlin 549, 479) are based on tracings from them.</note></p>
            <p>Strange’s entire Blake collection was acquired by Bernard Quaritch and sold in 1890
              to the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, presented in three large red leather portfolios.
              Though the works have been trimmed of their original mounts, the mounting style of the
              larger works was almost certainly Butts’s, as is evinced by the sizes of their
              portfolios and a few other factors. The original mounts were large sheets of thick
              paper that were tipped into the stubs of the portfolios; the portfolio for the
              biblical watercolors is the size of Turnbull mounts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n59" type="note">59</ref> The biblical and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> watercolors had been
              trimmed to the image and inlaid into windows cut in larger sheets, remnants of which
              are still visible, for the sheets were trimmed to about a quarter inch from the image.
              Although trimming would have removed any Turnbull stamp, biblical inscription, or
              text, traces of pencil in the lower right corner, where the inscription was written on
              the biblical watercolors, are visible on a few of the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
              mounts. The titles recorded by Rossetti for most of these designs were quotations from
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (see Appendix 1, lots 177-82), which implies that
              inscriptions and verse references were once present on the mounts. These textual
              echoes, pencil traces, and the inlaying style itself strongly suggest that the six 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations sold by Ford were from the Butts
                collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">60</ref>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">59</hi>
                In Quaritch’s advertisement of November 1886, the biblical watercolors are recorded
                as “mounted to the size of 22 in. by 17.1/2 in.” (55.7 × 44.4 cm), which is the size
                of the Turnbull mounts on the other biblical watercolors (see n19); the 
                  <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs were “mounted to the size of 28 in. by 20 in.”
(70.9 ×
                50.6 cm). The <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> designs were “mounted to the size of 11 in. by
                8.1/2 in.” (27.2 × 21.4 cm); there are no traces on the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>
                designs to indicate they had previously been drum mounted.</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi
                  rend="s">60</hi> The three designs acquired by Fuller have been removed from their
                original mats.</note></p>
            <pb id="p29-60" n="60"/>
            <p>The sale of the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs at the Ford auction helps to
              explain why critics like Rossetti and Joseph Wittreich have assumed that Blake
              intended the series to be just nine instead of 12 designs. Rossetti records Fuller’s
              three acquisitions in the order and with the titles of the Ford sale, but places them
              among the <hi rend="i">Poetic and Miscellaneous</hi> works (255, #16-18), outside the
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> series. Butts Jr. apparently added his three 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs to six he already had, for in June 1853 he sold
              “Nine from Milton.” Rossetti records them in slightly more detail: “Nine Designs from
              ‘Paradise Lost’ [Mr. Strange, from Mr. Butts]” (209, #75). He appears to identify the
              nine designs as constituting the entire series, or at least not to have recognized the
              true size of the series. He had not seen the Fuller designs and was unaware of the
              1807 <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> that belong to the Rev. Joseph Thomas (Butlin
                529).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">61</ref> Gilchrist,
however, may have known that
              the series had been dispersed. He states: “the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>,
              executed for Mr. Butts, . . . are now scattered in various hands” (1: 335). 
                <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">61</hi> When Fuller’s three designs from <hi rend="i">Paradise
                  Lost</hi> sold at Munro’s auction at Christie’s 22-24 April 1868 (lots 502, 501,
                500), they were titled as in the June 1852 and Rossetti catalogues, that is, by
                quotations, but their connection to the series was again overlooked.</note></p>
            <p>While the 1808 series originally consisted of 12 designs, like the smaller set of
              1807, Butlin believes that <hi rend="i">Satan, Sin, and Death</hi> may have been “done
              on its own before Blake thought of doing his two series of illustrations,” because the
              “form of the signature, a near monogram, is common in works up to 1806 but rare later”
              (536.2). Wittreich, however, has argued that this design, along with 
                <hi rend="i">Satan Arousing the Rebel Angels</hi> and probably <hi rend="i">The Judgment of
Adam
                and Eve</hi>—the three designs acquired by Fuller—were never intended by Blake to be
              part of the series. Wittreich, in other words, like Rossetti, identifies the series as
              the nine designs that Butts Jr. sold in his June 1853 auction, and thus argues that
              the series remained intact and was never dispersed (“Illustrator” 99-103; 
                <hi rend="i">Angel</hi> 92-97).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">62</ref> It seems, however, that
              the nine designs sold by Butts Jr. may have been <hi rend="i">reassembled</hi> by
              Butts Jr. after the series had already been dispersed and cannot be regarded as the
              size of the series intended by Blake. <note id="n62"><hi rend="s">62</hi> Wittreich
                now concedes that <hi rend="i">The Judgment of Adam and Eve</hi> in the Houghton
                Library can be added to the nine designs of Butts’s in the Boston Museum (Butlin,
                “Minute Particular” 44).</note></p>
            <p>Butlin supposes that Butts Jr. dispersed the set by selling Fuller three designs from
              an “untraced sale” (536; see also “Minute Particular” 45). But that assumes what seems
              increasingly unlikely, that Butts Jr. was the vendor of the Blake works in Ford’s June
              1852 auction. If Butts Jr. was the vendor in June 1852, why did he auction only six
              and not the whole set? That is, why would he have withheld six in 1852 but put up
              nine—all that he had—the following year? More troubling still, why sell them as
              individual designs (lots 177-82) instead of as a series in one lot, as he did in 1853
              (lot 139)? The former auction was at Sotheby’s and the latter was at Foster and Son,
              but the decision to sell as one lot was probably made by the vendor and not the
              auction house. The six <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> designs, for example, sold as one
              lot at Sotheby’s in March 1852 (lot 147). Dividing a series of 12 large illustrations
              may be yet another sign that the Butts collection had been partly dispersed before
              1852 and not inherited in its entirety by Butts Jr.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n63" type="note">63</ref>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">63</hi> A similar situation occurred with the
                Linnell copies of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained.</hi> These brilliantly and
                persuasively executed works are attributed to James T. Linnell, though they may be
                by John Linnell (see Essick, “Marketplace, 1994” 141). Six descended through James
                Linnell’s family and six descended through the family of John Linnell Jr., though
                five of these are now untraced.</note></p>
            <p>While the 1808 <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs were part of the original
              Butts collection, the late series of Milton illustrations executed c. 1816 may not
              have been. After December 1810, there are no receipts or documentary evidence to prove
              that Butts continued his patronage of Blake (see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                Records</hi> 578). Indeed, Gilchrist states that Butts eventually “grew cool” to
              Blake and that he “employed him but little now, and during the few remaining years of
              Blake’s life they seldom met” (1: 282). The absence of receipts by a professional
              clerk, whose other receipts from Blake appear to have been meticulously kept, does
              lend credence to Gilchrist’s theory. No implied or explicit reference to Butts is made
              in Blake’s correspondence until Blake borrowed the Job watercolors from Butts for
              Linnell, for which Butts received a discount on a proof copy of the engravings in 1826
              (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 599). Blake also noted that Butts had paid
              him a visit in the spring of 1826 (Erdman 777).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n64" type="note">64</ref>
              Yet the presence of <hi rend="i">Comus, Nativity, L’Allegro</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Il
                Penseroso</hi> (Butlin 528, 542, 543) in the Butts collection appears to refute
              Gilchrist. Consequently, these works are believed, “in the absence of concrete
              evidence to the contrary,” to have been designed for and/or commissioned by Butts
              (Butlin 550). But given that <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> was acquired by Butts Jr. from
              Utterson’s auction, the hypothesis that Butts commissioned the other series of Milton
              illustrations is also suspect. <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">64</hi> Copy A of 
                  <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>, presumably bound with copies of <hi rend="i">On
                  Homers Poetry [&amp;] On Virgil</hi> and <hi rend="i">Man Sweeping the
                  Interpreter’s Parlour</hi>, sold in the 26-27 March 1852 auction (Bentley, 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 209). Because they were part of this sale, they are
                assumed to be Butts’s copies. Blake had completed all three works c. 1822 and may
                have given them to Butts (there are no receipts for the purchase) in appreciation
                for his lending the Job watercolors in 1821, or three of the <hi rend="i">Paradise
                  Lost</hi> designs in May 1822 (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi>
                105-06). The most one can say, perhaps, is that after 1820 Butts and Blake were on
                good terms but Butts seems not to be actively adding to his collection or trying to
                support Blake financially.</note></p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> sold in the March 1852 auction. Most of the Blake items in
              this auction appear to have been originally purchased by Butts directly from Blake. At
              least five items, however, were not purchased directly; these were the four
              illuminated books and a copy of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> that “Butts” purchased at
              the 1835 Cumberland sale (see n48). Other Blake works purchased from a third party,
              possibly by the vendor 
<pb id="p29-61" n="61"/>
rather than by Butts, include a
              posthumous copy of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and probably the copies of 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi> engravings.<ref
                target="n65" type="note">65</ref> Given such precedent, it seems reasonable to
              suspect that the vendor may also have acquired the <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> designs
              from a collection other than Butts’s, or that they were another late addition to the
              Butts collection, purchased by the Butts who attended the Cumberland sale or by Butts
              Jr., who attended the Utterson sale. <note id="n65"><hi rend="s">65</hi> There are no
                good reasons to believe that Butts owned duplicates of <hi rend="i">Night
                  Thoughts</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi>—or that the vendor of the
                March 1852 auction, whose Blake holdings constituted a very small portion of his
                collection, had not acquired his copies from someone other than Butts. Butts Jr.
                sold a copy of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> in his June 1853 auction (lot 143)
                and another copy remained in Captain Butts’s collection (Butts 164), though this
                copy may have been the “20 pages of proofs in various states, some written on by W.
                Blake” that sold in the Captain’s 1903 auction (lot 22). Linnell records Butts as
                having acquired one proof copy of <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi> for half price
                “because he lent the Drawing to Copy,” but it is the only copy of <hi rend="i">The
                  Book of Job</hi> he is recorded as having acquired (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                  Records</hi> 599). This copy is presumably the one that sold in the 1903 auction
                (lot 21), which was described as “the superb india proof copy (no. 1), morroco.”
                Blake did not number copies of Job, but the Butts’s copy may have been numbered by
                Butts or a descendant to signal his having received preferential
              treatment.</note></p>
            <p><hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> seem to be the only
              uncontested set of late Milton illustrations in the Butts collection. But these
              companion pieces are not all that they seem. They sold with the Butts collection in
              Butts Jr.’s June 1853 auction, which included <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> from the Utterson sale and 17 watercolors once belonging to his
              father but probably purchased at the Ford auction. The precedent of a Butts purchasing
              Blakes after Blake’s death and of Butts Jr. at Utterson’s and apparently Ford’s
              auctions raises the possibility that these Milton illustrations were not commissioned
              for Butts but acquired by Butts Jr. or a family member from another, unknown collector
              or patron. The omission of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> from the Butts
              collection suggests as much. Its omission is curious, as Butlin acknowledges (550),
              since it was executed in the same style and with the same materials as these other
              late series.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Paradise Regained, L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso,
                Nativity</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> are dated between c. 1815 and 1820. An
              examination of the paper used in these series, however, strongly indicates that it
              came from the same stack of sheets, which in turn suggests that the four series were
              executed as a group very near in time to one another. The 14 leaves of 
                <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> and <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> are without watermarks and are trimmed
to
              the images, approximately 15.8 × 12.3 cm and 15.4 × 12 cm respectively. Six of the 12
              leaves of <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> and three of
              the 12 leaves of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> are watermarked M &amp; J LAY
              1816, approximately 16 × 12 cm and 17 × 13 cm respectively. The six marked leaves in
                <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Peneroso</hi> indicate six sheets,
              which quartered yield 24 leaves in four stacks (6 leaves per quarter stack). Two
              stacks of quarter leaves—one with the watermark—were apparently used. The other two
              stacks of (12) unmarked quarter leaves plus two leaves from a seventh sheet (the leaf
              with the watermark was used elsewhere) were used for <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">Nativity.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">66</ref> The 12 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> designs were probably executed last but to match the
earlier
              designs. Their place in the sequence of production is suggested by the facts that
              their 12 leaves came from three sheets quartered and all three watermarked quarters
              are in this series. The paper for this project, in other words, appears to have been
              purchased especially for it, whereas the 24 quarters of the six sheets used in the
              other three series were intermixed. <note id="n66"><hi rend="s">66</hi> The Milton
                illustrations are now trimmed to the image, but six sketches with the same watermark
                and same image size are on paper measuring 22.7 × 19.4 cm (8.15/16 × 7.1/2 inches)
                (see Butlin 712, 715, 768, 830, 832). This larger measurement is probably the size
                of an untrimmed quarter leaf used for the Milton illustrations. The size of the
                untrimmed sheet may have been 18.5 × 14.5 inches, which corresponds to “Pinched
                Post” drawing paper (see Labarre 251).</note></p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> are the same size and were
              signed “WBlake,” features which seem intentional, which in turn suggests that they
              were executed as companion works for the same patron. The same may be true of the
              other two series, which are both “WBlake inv” and 12 designs each. The image size of
                <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>, however, appears to
              have been determined by <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi>,
              presumably the first two series executed, and is slightly smaller than its companion
              series, <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, whose 12 designs have “a second drawn
              border” (Butlin 544), making them appear slightly larger. It is also the only one of
              the series that has no record of having been accompanied by descriptions or poems.<ref
                target="n67" type="note">67</ref>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">67</hi><hi rend="i">
                  Nativity</hi> was lot 147 of the 26-27 March 1852 auction and sold “with the poem
                in MS.” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> sold as lot 98 in the 29 June 1853 auction “with the
                artist’s descriptions”; and <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il
                  Peneroso</hi> sold in the same auction as lot 99 as “ditto.” What is meant by
                “ditto” is unclear; poems in manuscript and not descriptions are extant, and they
                are the only accompanying texts extant from the series. There is no record of 
                  <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> having accompanying descriptions or texts. There
                is a record, made by Thomas Dibdin, of a visit paid to him by Blake in 1816 to
                discuss “‘the minor poems of Milton’” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
                242). Perhaps this was the stimulus to reproduce <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and 
                  <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> and to execute the new series. In this light, it is
                interesting to note that Dibdin and Utterson were friends, both original members of
                the Roxburghe Club.</note></p>
            <p>Butts may have known of the Thomas series of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>,
              executed in 1807. Thomas (1765-1811) was a friend of Flaxman and resided in Epsom (see
              Parris 1390), where Butts appears to have had a cottage or summer home by 1809.<ref
                target="n68" type="note">68</ref> Butts certainly knew of Flaxman, since Blake
              mentions him often in his letters, and probably had met him as well, since Flaxman
              lived at 7 Buckingham Street, Fitzroy Square and Butts moved to the Square in 1808. If
              Butts knew Thomas and his collection, then the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs
              of 1808, a year after the Thomas set was executed, may have been Butts’s idea and not
              Blake’s. But if so, why would Butts have waited until c. 1816 to order copies of 
                <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi>, both of 
<pb id="p29-62" n="62"/>
              which were in Thomas’s collection by 1801 and 1809 respectively? 
                  <note id="n68"><hi rend="s">68</hi> Butts Jr. wrote his mother on 14 August 1809 to tell her
that he
                visited the Blakes, as “you wished me to do so while you and my Father are out of
                Town. Mr. and Mrs. Blake are very well. . . . they intend shortly to pay the
                promised visit at Epsom” (qtd. in Wilson 96n).</note></p>
            <p>The designs of the 1808 <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> are 50.7 × 38.2 cm, twice the
              size of the 1807 designs. While the first and second sets of <hi rend="i">Paradise
                Lost</hi> differ in many compositional details, Blake clearly had the 1807
              compositions in mind (though probably no longer in the studio) when redrawing the
              series for Butts. The increased size was probably influenced by the patron, whose
              collection consisted primarily of large biblical watercolors and color prints, and who
              acquired works the same size in 1806 and 1807 (see Butlin 639, 641). Given the large
              size of the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs, it seems unlikely that the 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> designs, at one quarter the size, were initially
              produced for Butts. Blake, or a patron other than Butts, of course, would not have
              perceived the new <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> designs as the companion of
              another series of designs. The c. 1816 <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> designs, which are clearly new compositions based on the texts, are
              smaller than the Thomas sets. They too seem equally out of place in the Butts
              collection, and much smaller than the Butts watercolors.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> appears at first to be oddly missing from the
              Butts collection, or to be a work rejected by Butts (Bindman, 
                <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> 38). But it may never have been intended for Butts. 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> remained with Blake, presumably because it was executed on
              speculation and not by commission. Linnell purchased the series for 10 pounds in
              October and November 1825 (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 604), apparently
              to assist Blake financially.</p>
            <p>How much later <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> was executed than 
                <hi rend="i">Comus, Nativity</hi>, and <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il
                Penseroso</hi> is not known. The shared style and materials suggest that it was not
              very long and that it was meant to be part of a Milton project. Yet it seems clearly
              not designed for Butts. Its omission from the Butts collection seems to reflect
              Blake’s decision not to offer or design it for Butts. Had Butts acquired the other
              four Milton series, then the absence of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> would
              indeed be surprising, since the series would then have matched in size and subject
              works he had been assiduously collecting. Conversely, the absence of 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> from the collection suggests that the matching Milton
              illustrations may also have been for another collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n69" type="note">69</ref> No hard evidence exists, however, to prove that Butts was the patron.
              Instead, he is assumed to have commissioned the c. 1816 Milton illustrations because
              they sold with his collection at auction. As an examination of Isaac D’Israeli’s Blake
              collection proves, ownership is not identical with commission (Viscomi, “Myth”
              passim). <note id="n69"><hi rend="s">69</hi> That the second set of 
                  <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> initially had descriptions reinforces Butlin’s argument that
this
                series is after, and not, as C. H. Collins Baker, Robert Wark, and Stephen Behrendt
                believe, before the Thomas series (see Butlin 538). But the size and materials alone
                place it with the later illustrations. The c. 1816 <hi rend="i">Nativity,
                  L’Allegro</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> have been cleaned and remounted
                and evidence of the original mounts is missing.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Conclusion</title>
            </head>
            <p>The sale of Blake watercolors long suspected as being from an untraced Butts auction
              occurred at Sotheby’s on 26 June 1852, but the vendor appears to have been Charles
              Ford and not Butts Jr. The Blakes in the sale included two unrecorded drawings or
              sketches (lot 11) that may have been proofs from <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, 23
              biblical watercolors, and six watercolors from the 1808 <hi rend="i">Paradise
                Lost</hi> series. The watercolors were once part of the Butts collection, as
              receipts between Blake and Butts and a mounting style characteristic of the Butts
              collection indicate. Nineteen of the Blake watercolors were acquired by Butts Jr.; the
              structure of the sale and the accounting nomenclature of the Ford sale catalogue
              strongly suggest that these transactions were purchases and not buy-ins. Eighteen of
              these works were sold with a large portion of the Butts collection the following year,
              on June 1853 at Foster and Son.</p>
            <p>For Ford’s previously unrecorded auction to have material from the Butts collection
              indicates that the collection was dispersed earlier than 1852 (Butlin p. 336) and not
              necessarily by Butts Jr. It also indicates that Ford collected Blake and may have
              acquired his Blakes from a member of the Butts family. The presence of Blakes once
              belonging to Butts in Ford’s collection forces a reexamination of the much larger
              auction of 26-27 March 1852 at Sotheby’s, which was of a “Valuable Collection . . .
              From the Portfolio of An Amateur,” who has heretofore been identified as Butts Jr.
              because the sale included Blakes that once belonged to his father. If the Blakes were
              put up for sale by Butts Jr., then that fact, or the fact that these particular works
              constituted another property, would have been acknowledged on the title page, in the
              catalogue, or in Sotheby’s annotated catalogue. The works not belonging to the
              anonymous “Amateur” were so acknowledged. Hence, it is reasonable to suppose that the
              Amateur’s collection once belonged to Butts and Butts, Jr. If so, then our idea of
              Butts’s relation to Blake is very mistaken. His taste was more diverse and his art
              collection far more extensive than Blake’s biographers have realized. If, however,
              Butts was as Gilchrist and Briggs depicted him, a man devoted more to Blake than to
              his art or to art in general, then Butts was not the person who assembled the
              collection. To assume that Butts Jr. was the vendor not by inheritance but by nature
              of his passion for collecting ignores his taste as demonstrated in his auction of June
              1853. Apparently, Butts’s illuminated books and biblical watercolors began to be
              dispersed before 1852, and Blake may have had major collectors unknown to us,
              including Charles Ford and the anonymous “Amateur” of the March 1852 auction.</p>
            <p>One such previously unknown collector is E. V. Utterson, at whose sale on 5 July 1852
              Butts Jr. acquired the second series of <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> This purchase, along
              with four illuminated books from the Cumberland sale of 1835, indicates that Butts Jr.
              and/or another member of the family continued to collect Blake, which in turn
              challenges the theory that Butts 
<pb id="p29-63" n="63"/>
commissioned directly from
              Blake “replicas of Blake’s Milton series” (Butlin p. 336). The last five series of
              Milton illustrations were executed c. 1816 and possibly for the same patron. That
              patron, however, was not necessarily Butts.</p>
            <p>Did Rossetti know something about the Ford auction that we do not? He knew the sale
              catalogue but he did not identify the vendor. By “Mr. Fuller, from Mr. Butts,”
              Rossetti acknowledged only that the works sold once belonged to Butts, which is true.
              He did not necessarily mean that they passed from Butts to Butts Jr. to Fuller, or
              that the auction in which they sold had been Butts Jr.’s. His stated intention was “to
              specify which were once [Butts’s], even in the instances where they have passed out of
              the family” (Gilchrist 2: 199). He was, in other words, interested in listing first
              owners and, when possible, present owners, but not intermediate owners. Had he known
              that Ford or the Amateur owned the Blakes in 1852, he would not have noted it; nor
              would Rossetti have noted the ownership of Butts Jr. or another member of the family,
              since he equated relatives and descendants with Butts. His recording Fuller’s
              acquisitions as being “from Mr. Butts” reveals only that he knew the provenance of the
              Blakes sold by Ford. He may have been told this by Gilchrist or Haines, whose lists of
              Blake’s works he inherited, or he may have inferred Butts’s ownership from the
              biblical subjects of the watercolors and from titles that echo those in Butts’s
              account (Gilchrist 2: 256). As noted, these features alone connect the June 1852
              watercolors to Butts, whether the vendor was Ford or the Amateur. Or he may have used
              an annotated copy of the sale catalogue and assumed that the “Butts” listed in the
              buyer’s column was Butts Jr. buying in. We cannot be sure that he made this
              assumption, but, if he did, it needs to be pointed out that it is only an assumption,
              for Rossetti appears to have had no correspondence with Butts Jr., nor, it seems, did
              Gilchrist, Anne Gilchrist, Dante Rossetti, or Haines. As we have seen, the assumption
              is as problematic as it is appealing.</p>
            <p>Examining the three auctions at Sotheby’s in March, June, and July of 1852
              simultaneously reveals and challenges several basic assumptions about the manner in
              which Blake worked and was collected. Revealed as well is how little we know about
              Butts and his family, despite their importance in sustaining Blake in his lifetime
              and, through the dispersal of Blakes from Butts’s remarkable and splendid collection,
              his aesthetic reputation afterwards. The “facts” that lie behind the construction of
              provenances often reveal themselves to be tenuous assumptions when examined closely. I
              think that the attribution of the anonymous and Ford auctions of March and June 1852
              to Butts Jr. is one such assumption.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Appendix 1</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The following is an annotated list of the Blake works sold at Sotheby’s on 26 June
              1852.</p>
            <p>Lot 11. W. Blake. The Transfiguration, <hi rend="i">coloured</hi>; and Time with the
              hour glass.</p>
            <p>The works were bought for 1s.6d. by a “Hickeson.” Rossetti and Butlin list no such
              person, though Butlin lists a Mrs. E. J. Hickson, daughter of Albin Martin, a pupil of
              Linnell who emigrated to New Zealand (p. 409). Hickeson or Hickson bought 16 other
              lots in the auction and may have been a dealer, though no picture or printdealer by
              that name is listed in the <hi rend="i">London Post Office Directory</hi> for 1852. A
              stationer-bookseller named Edward Hickson, however, is listed.</p>
            <p>This lot differs from lots 155-82x in consisting of two items and in being listed
              outside that group of watercolors. A watercolor entitled <hi rend="i">The
                Transfiguration</hi>, c. 1800, had sold in the auction of March 1852, lot 153, to
              Sir Charles Wentworth Dilke, who, according to Rossetti, still owned it in 1863 (226,
              #140). What sold in the Ford auction may have been another version, now untraced. It
              is probably not the untraced “rough suggestion for a design of the 
                <hi rend="i">Transfiguration</hi>,” which Rossetti notes was on the back of “Jacob and the
              Angel” (246, #71; Butlin 332), since that was apparently an uncolored sketch. The
              second item, <hi rend="i">Time with the hour glass</hi>, is not described as colored
              and may have been a pencil drawing, perhaps the untraced pencil drawing shown in 1876
              at the Burlington Fine Arts Club exhibit (#245), listed as “A Life Study: Time”
              (12.3/4 × 17.1/2 in., lent by A. Macmillan). Butlin refers to this work as 
                <hi rend="i">A Life Study: Time</hi> (866); Rossetti does not list it in 1863, but in
              1880 he lists this work as “Time” and “A Life-study” (274, #189 and #190).</p>
            <p>But lot 11 also differs from the others (except lots 173, 174, and 182x) in being the
              only works in the “Sale-catalogue” omitted (as opposed to renamed, which 173 and 182x
              may have been) by Rossetti. This omission, and their being grouped together and set
              apart, along with the very low price of 1s.6d for two works, suggest that they may
              have been sketches for or proofs of etchings from <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
              (16.1/2 × 12.7/8 inches). Page 65 of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> pictures the
              resurrected Christ, which could understandably be interpreted as the transfiguration.
              (A proof of this plate was used in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, p. 114). Page 24 of 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> pictures the allegorical figure of Time and an hour
              glass. (Proofs of this plate were used in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, pages 53 and
              71).</p>
            <p>Lot 155. “He cast him into the bottomless pit”—<hi rend="i">very powerful and
                characteristic</hi></p>
            <p>C. 1803-05. Purchased by Fuller for £1 5s. (Rossetti 229, #174). Butlin refers to it
              as “<hi rend="i">He Cast Him into the Bottomless Pit, and Shut Him Up</hi>” (524). See
              lots 162-64.</p>
            <p>Lot 156. Touching the Garment—<hi rend="i">many figures</hi></p>
            <p>C. 1803-05. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 10s., but not sold at either of his subsequent
              auctions. It was acquired by William Smith by 1863, presumably from the Butts family
              by private sale, and given to the Victoria and Albert Museum in 1871. Rossetti refers
              to it as <hi rend="i">The Woman touching Christ’s Garment</hi>, and he describes it as
              “A composition of many figures, disfigured by lankiness. Not a superior specimen”
              (227, #149). Butlin refers to the work as <hi rend="i">Christ Healing the Woman with
                an Issue of Blood</hi> (482).</p>
            <pb id="p29-64" n="64"/>
            <p>Lot 157. “Thou wast perfect till iniquity was found in thee”— <hi rend="i">very
                fine</hi></p>
            <p>C. 1805. Purchased by Butts for 10s. and offered in his June 1853 and March 1854
              auctions as <hi rend="i">Satan in his former Glory</hi>, but bought in both times,
              first by “Thomas” for 11s. and then for 10s. with two other works (Butlin 497, 498).
              In 1863 it belonged to Captain Butts. Rossetti records the work twice, by the title in
              the Butts’s June 1853 auction (255, #13 [“Mr. Thomas, from Mr. Butts”]) and by the
              title in the June 1852 sale. The latter he describes as “bright in colour and
              extremely grand” (230, #181). The title as inscribed on the mount, though, was “Thou
              wast perfect in thy ways from the day that thou was created, till iniquity was found
              in thee” (Robertson 60). Butlin gives the title as <hi rend="i">Satan in His Original
                Glory: “Thou Wast Perfect Till Iniquity was Found in Thee”</hi> (469). Of the 18
              works from this sale put up for auction in June 1853, this was the only one bought
              in.</p>
            <p>Lot 158. Samson bursting his bonds</p>
            <p>C. 1800-03(?). Purchased by Butts Jr. for 11s. and presumably sold at his June 1853
              auction, lot 105, as <hi rend="i">Samson and Delilah</hi>, for 12s. to J. C. Strange.
              Butlin refers to it as <hi rend="i">Samson breaking his bonds</hi> (453). In his
              account with Butts, 12 May 1805, Blake mentions <hi rend="i">Samson break[in]g
                bonds</hi> [#8], which was paired with <hi rend="i">Samson subdu’d</hi> [#9]
              (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 572). Lot 158 and Butts’s lot 105 are
              probably different titles for the same work, now in the Pierpont Morgan Library, which
              seems, “for stylistic reasons, to have been executed earlier, c. 1800-03,” than its
              presumed 1805 delivery date (Butlin 453). On the other hand, one or the other may have
              been the untraced watercolor referred to by Keynes as <hi rend="i">Samson breaking his
                bonds</hi> (<hi rend="i">Bible</hi> 51b) and by Butlin as <hi rend="i">Samson and
                the Philistines</hi> (454). It has been untraced since 1905, when it belonged to
              Marsden J. Perry, the printer at the Kelmscott Press.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n70" type="note">70</ref> Butlin acknowledges that this untraced painting may have been the
              watercolor listed c. 1865 by the dealer Francis Harvey as <hi rend="i">Samson breaking
                his bonds</hi> (454). Rossetti does not mention <hi rend="i">Samson and the
                Philistines</hi>, or <hi rend="i">Samson and Delilah</hi>; he refers to a watercolor
              by the June 1852 sale catalogue title, dating it 1805 and noting that “Delilah . . .
              stares in dismay at the upshot of her conspiracy” (208, #59). If <hi rend="i">Samson
                and Delilah</hi> was the work Ford sold in June 1852, then the untraced version
              acquired by Perry may have been the <hi rend="i">Samson break[in]g bonds</hi>
              delivered to Butts in 1805—and another of his works that was sold privately.<ref
                target="n71" type="note">71</ref>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">70</hi> Three other
                works once belonging to Perry and shown at the Grolier Club exhibition of 1905 are
                also untraced: Butlin 181, 860, 861. Perry also acquired from Quaritch after 1900
                  <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> copy H, 
                  <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy G, and <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> copy C (Bentley, 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 475).</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">71</hi> Perry
                also acquired <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi>, c. 1809, another work that can be
                traced to Butts but to no intermediate owners or sales (Butlin 645).</note></p>
            <p>Lot 159. The Burning Bush</p>
            <p>C. 1800-03. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 10s. and sold at his June 1853 auction, lot
              104, to Bohn for 7s. Butts refers to the watercolor by the June 1852 title; Rossetti
              and Butlin refer to it as <hi rend="i">Moses at the Burning Bush</hi> (224, #116;
              441).</p>
            <p>Lot 160. The Man of God and Jeroboam</p>
            <p>C. 1803-05. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 6s. and sold at his June 1853 auction, lot
              106, to Bohn for 7s. Butts and Rossetti refers to it by the June 1852 title (225,
              #129); Butlin refers to it as <hi rend="i">Jeroboam and the Man of God</hi>, since
              “the Man of God’s only action was in fact to entreat the Lord to restore Jeroboam’s
              arm” (460).</p>
            <p>Lot 161. “Her sins are forgiven”</p>
            <p>C. 1803-05. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 6s. and sold at his June 1853 auction, lot
              115, to Bohn for 11s. Butts listed it as <hi rend="i">Jesus and Martha</hi>, but
              Rossetti refers to it by the June 1852 title, adding “for she loved much” to the title
              and listing Bohn as owner (227, #146). Butlin refers to it as <hi rend="i">Mary
                Magdalene Washing Christ’s Feet</hi> (488).</p>
            <p>Lot 162. Scene from the Apocalyptic Vision—<hi rend="i">of grand conception and
                highly characteristic</hi></p>
            <p>Lot 163. “The Number of the Beast is 666”—<hi rend="i">of the same characteristic
                merit</hi></p>
            <p>Lot 164. “And power was given him over all kindreds, and tongues, and nations”—<hi
                rend="i">equally characteristic</hi></p>
            <p>Three of the four paintings depicting the Red Dragon of the Apocalypse purchased by
              Fuller for £1 2s., £1 1s., and £1 1s. respectively. Rossetti records them as “Mr.
              Fuller, from Mr. Butts” and “Described in the Sale-catalogue as ‘of grand conception,
              and highly characteristic’” and “of the same characteristic merit” and “equally
              characteristic” (229, #175, 177, 176). Lot 162 is commonly known as <hi rend="i">The
                Great Red Dragon and The Woman Clothed with the Sun</hi> (Butlin 519); lot 163 is
              still called <hi rend="i">The Number of the Beast is 666</hi> (Butlin 522); lot 164 is
              now entitled <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and The Beast from the Sea</hi> (Butlin
              521). These three watercolors, along with <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the
                Woman Clothed with the Sun: “The Devil is Come Down”</hi> (Butlin 520), “seem to
              have been painted as a separate sub-group within the series of Biblical watercolours
              for Thomas Butts,” c. 1803-05. Bindman dates them c. 1805-09 (164-65). Butlin further
              suggests that numbers “520 and 522 also form a pair of matching designs within the
              group of four” (519). Lot 155 of the June 1852 auction, “<hi rend="i">He Cast Him into
                the Bottomless Pit</hi>” (Butlin 524), which pictures Michael binding the Dragon, is
              also associated with this group and was also purchased by Fuller.</p>
            <p>Lot 165. Woman taken in Adultery</p>
            <p>C. 1805, was purchased by Butts Jr. for 5s. and sold at his June 1853 auction, lot
              114, to J. C. Strange for 11s. (Rossetti 227, #147; Butlin 486).</p>
            <p>Lot 166. Witch of Endor</p>
            <p>C. 1800. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 7s. and is probably the version sold at his June
              1853 auction, lot 112, to Bohn for 7s., as <hi rend="i">Saul and Samuel.</hi> Rossetti
              refers to the Foster item as <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Samuel appearing to Saul</hi>,
              but notes that “the Witch of Endor is wonderfully fine” (225, #124). Butlin refers to
              it by the same title as Rossetti (458). Two other less likely possibilities for lot
              166 are <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</hi>, 1783, and
                <hi rend="i">Saul and the Ghost of Samuel</hi>, c. 1775-80. The provenances of these
              works are not known before 1854 (Butlin 74, 75).</p>
            <p>Lot 167. The Baptism of Christ—<hi rend="i">finely conceived</hi></p>
            <p>C. 1803. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 5s. In his June 1853 auction, two works with this
              title were sold: lot 113 to J. C. Strange for 19s., and lot 73 to Strange for £1 2s.
              (Butlin 475, 415). The second version was painted in tempera, which 
                <pb id="p29-65" n="65"/>
Rossetti refers to as <hi rend="i">The Baptism of Christ</hi> (226,
#138);
              he refers to the watercolor version as “The same” (226, #139). Apparently, one of
              these two works came from the June 1852 sale. Rossetti saw both versions of 
                <hi rend="i">The Baptism of Christ</hi> in Strange’s collection, which enabled him to
              identify media. Given that all the other “Original Drawings in Colours, by Blake” in
              the June 1852 auction were watercolors, lot 167 probably followed suit.</p>
            <p>Lot 168. Creation of Light</p>
            <p>C. 1800-05(?). Purchased by Butts Jr. for 6s. and sold at his June 1853 auction, lot
              111, to C. Martin for 18s. as <hi rend="i">The Creation.</hi> Untraced since 1853.
              Rossetti lists it as <hi rend="i">Creation of Light</hi>, but does not describe it or
              record an owner (223, #104), presumably because he never saw it. Rossetti apparently
              used the June 1852 sale catalogue for the title and provenance, since he fails to
              record Martin as owner.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">72</ref>
	<note id="n72"><hi
                  rend="s">72</hi> George Richmond painted a tempera in 1826 with this title, now in
                the Tate Gallery (see Paley 115-16 and color plate XII). The painting elicited this
                question from Robert Essick: “Might there be some compositional relationship between
                Blake’s design, untraced since 1853, and Richmond’s? There is no record of Richmond
                having access to Butts’s collection, where Blake’s drawing would have been by the
                time Richmond met Blake” (“Marketplace 1986” 13). Richmond also executed a drawing
                in graphite and colored chalk entitled <hi rend="i">Adam and Eve in the Garden of
                  Eden</hi>, which raises similar questions regarding lot 173 of the June 1852 sale,
                  <hi rend="i">Adam and Eve in Paradise.</hi></note></p>
            <p>Lot 169. Baptism—<hi rend="i">very fine</hi></p>
            <p>Dated 1805. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 8s. and presumably sold at his June 1853
              auction, lot 110, to Bohn for £1 15s., as <hi rend="i">Baptism.</hi> The painting
              described by Rossetti (207, #52) and Butlin (485) depicts Christ baptizing (as opposed
              to being baptized), which is the title of the design Blake delivered to Butts 12 May
              1805 (<hi rend="i">Christ Baptizing</hi>, #7). But the work delivered to Butts in 1805
              was possibly a tempera, matching his tempera of <hi rend="i">The Baptism of
                Christ.</hi> The medium of tempera is suggested by Blake’s touching up the work
              later that year for £1 1s.—which is what an original watercolor cost (Bentley, 
                <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 573). The reworking and price suggest a painting more
              substantial than pen and watercolor—and more susceptible to cracking and peeling,
              particularly if it were painted on copper. Rossetti seems equally puzzled about the
              extant watercolor version: the “colour is pale and sweet,” yet Blake’s “account”
              (i.e., the reworking for £1 1s.) “seems to show that more than usual pains were
              bestowed upon this water-colour” (207, #52), implying that the watercolor does not
              reflect this special attention, which in turn suggests that the work delivered to
              Butts in 1805 was a tempera now untraced (or completely deteriorated) and that the
              watercolor was lot 167.</p>
            <p>Lot 170. War</p>
            <p>Dated 1805. Purchased by Fuller for £1 3s. Recorded by Butlin as “Thomas Butts;
              Fuller by 1863; H. A. J. Munro, sold Christie’s 22-4 April 1868 . . . Fogg Museum”
              (195). <hi rend="i">War</hi> is the third version of <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City
                Wall The Morning after the Battle</hi>; the two earlier versions are both c. 1784
              and have provenances unknown before 1863 (Viscomi, “A Breach” 44 passim). The version
              of the subject sold in lot 170 is probably the one delivered to Butts on 12 May 1805
              (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 572; Butlin 195), the period for all the
              other works in the auction.</p>
            <p>Lot 171. Moses striking the Rock</p>
            <p>Purchased by Butts Jr. for 4s.6d. and presumably sold at his June 1853 auction, lot
              108, for 15s. to Bohn (Rossetti 207, #53; Butlin 445). Blake delivered a watercolor
              with this title to Butts on 12 May 1805, which is most likely the extant version, now
              in the collection of the Lutheran Church in America, and signed “WB inv [in monogram]
              1805.”</p>
            <p>Lot 172. The Seven Golden Candlesticks</p>
            <p>C. 1800-05? Purchased by Butts Jr. for 5s. and sold at his June 1853 auction, lot
              109, to Bohn for £1 11s. as <hi rend="i">The Seven Candlesticks.</hi> This untraced
              work was not seen by Rossetti, who lists it by the June 1852 and not Butts title (229,
              #171), as does Butlin (514).</p>
            <p>Lot 173. Adam and Eve in Paradise</p>
            <p>C. 1800-06? Purchased by Butts Jr. for 19s. No work with this title is recorded by
              Rossetti or other sales. Butlin records an untraced “drawing in colours” with this
              title, which passed from Flaxman to his sister-in-law, Maria Denham, before being sold
              at Christie’s 26 April 1876 (Butlin 835). More likely it was a version of 
                <hi rend="i">Satan Watching the Endearments of Adam and Eve.</hi> One such version was dated
              1806 and listed in Butts’s June 1853 catalogue (lot 100) as <hi rend="i">Adam, Eve and
                Serpent</hi> (Butlin 531; Rossetti 209, #71). Arguing against this supposition is
              the fact that the June 1852 material was grouped together in the June 1853 auction as
              lots 103-115 (116?) and <hi rend="i">Adam, Eve and Serpent</hi> was lot 100.</p>
            <p>Lot 174. “But hope rekindled only to illume”</p>
            <p>C. 1805. Purchased by Evans for £1 1s., presumably the bookdealer, either R. H. or
              W., and acquired by Mrs. Anne Gilchrist by 1863 (Rossetti 235, #210). The work is one
              of the illustrations to Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, otherwise known as 
                <hi rend="i">The Descent of Man into the Vale of Death: “But Hope Rekindled, Only to
                Illume the Shades of Death, and Light Her to the Tomb”</hi> (Butlin 238). Gilchrist
              claims that it was “formerly in Mr. Butts’s collections” and is “a duplicate,
              probably, of one of the unengraved designs from Young” (1: 223). The claim, as Butlin
              notes, is apparently based on the similarity in style to the watercolors painted for
              Butts c. 1800-05. Butlin also notes that “though related in subject and composition to
              plate 7 of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> it seems to be an independent, perhaps slightly
              earlier, design” (638).</p>
            <p>Lot 175. St Paul shaking off the Viper</p>
            <p>C. 1803-05. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 5s. There are two similar versions of this
              painting (Butlin 509, 510), both assumed to have been executed for Butts. Nearly all
              the works Butts acquired from the June 1852 auction were put up for sale the following
              year, lots 103-15 (116?). Given this pattern, the version bought at the June 1852
              auction is probably the one sold at Foster’s 29 June 1853, lot 107, for 12s. to Bohn
              as <hi rend="i">St Paul and the Viper</hi> (Butlin 510) and the second version the one
              sold by Captain Butts’s widow in 1906 (Butlin 509).</p>
            <p>Lot 176. The Assumption—<hi rend="i">an elaborate and exquisitely finished work in
                the finest manner of this extraordinary artist and genius</hi></p>
            <p>Dated 1806. Purchased by Fuller for £4 2s., the largest price paid for any of the
              Blake works at the June 1852 auction. Rossetti records the June 1852 title and
              paraphrases the description as “Described in the Sale-catalogue as an elaborate and
              exquisitely finished work in Blake’s finest manner” (231, #195). Butlin refers to the
              work as <hi rend="i">The Assumption of the Virgin</hi> (513).</p>
            <p>Lots 177-82 are preceded by the subheading:</p>
            <pb id="p29-66" n="66"/>
            <p>The six following Designs, by Blake, are illustrative of Milton’s “Paradise
              Lost.”</p>
            <p>Lot 177. “So judged he man”</p>
            <p>Dated 1808. Purchased by Fuller for £1 7s. Butlin records it as <hi rend="i">The
                Judgment of Adam and Eve: ‘So Judged He Man’</hi> (536.10). Rossetti placed this
              work and the two others purchased by Fuller (lots 180, 182) outside the 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> group, recording them in <hi rend="i">Poetic and
                Miscellaneous</hi> works (255, #16-18) in the order and with the titles of the June
              1852 sale catalogue, though identifying only the first and third as illustrations of
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, which, coincidentally, are two of the three designs
              that Linnell had traced in 1822.</p>
            <p>Lot 178. “Father! thy word is past”</p>
            <p>Dated 1808. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 17s. and resold in his June 1853 auction, lot
              139 (“Nine from Milton”), to Strange for £17 6s.6d. Rossetti quotes the whole line as
              its title: “Father, Thy word is passed, Man shall find grace” (210, #75c); Butlin
              refers to it as <hi rend="i">Christ Offers to Redeem Man</hi> (536.3).</p>
            <p>Lot 179. “Ah! gentle pair”</p>
            <p>Dated 1808. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 10s, resold in 1853 in June 1853 auction, lot
              139. Rossetti and Butlin record it as <hi rend="i">Satan Watching the Endearments of
                Adam and Eve</hi> (Rossetti 210, #75d; Butlin 536.4).</p>
            <p>Lot 180. “Awake! arise! or be for ever fallen”</p>
            <p>Dated 1808. Purchased by Fuller for £1 11s. Butlin records it as <hi rend="i">Satan
                Arousing the Rebel Angels</hi> (536.1). See lot 177.</p>
            <p>Lot 181. “But to the cross he nails the enemies”</p>
            <p>Dated 1808. Purchased by Butts Jr. for 10s. and sold in his June 1853 auction, lot
              139. Quote is from <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> 12.415. Butlin records it as 
                <hi rend="i">Michael Foretells the Crucifixion</hi> (536.11). Rossetti records it as 
                <hi rend="i">Michael Foretells the Crucifixion to Adam</hi> and quotes lines
              12.415-17.</p>
            <p>Lot 182. “Oh, Father! what extends thy hand, she cry’d, against thy only Son”</p>
            <p>C. 1808. Purchased by Fuller for £1 11s. Butlin records it as <hi rend="i">Satan, Sin
                and Death: Satan Comes to the Gates of Hell</hi> (536.2). Rossetti records it by the
              June 1852 title, followed by “(Satan, Sin, and Death, from ‘Paradise Lost’). [Mr.
              Fuller, from Mr. Butts.]” (255, #18).</p>
            <p>Lot 182x.</p>
            <p>This lot number was written in pen, but no title is given. The work was purchased by
              Butts Jr. for 11s. It seems certainly to have been a Blake design. Was it a 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustration, or another biblical watercolor? Given that
              all the material except Milton designs from the June 1852 sale remained together as a
              group in the June 1853 sale (lots 103-15), it seems reasonable to assume that either
              lot 102 or 116 of the 1853 sale may have been lot 182x. Lot 102 in 1853 was 
                <hi rend="i">The Sacrifice of Isaac</hi> and seven Shakespeare drawings; the first is
              biblical in subject, but, like the Shakespeare drawings, is much earlier in technique
              and at 19 × 24.5 cm, quite smaller in size than the biblical watercolors, all about 40
              × 35 cm. Lot 116 was <hi rend="i">The Ten Commandments</hi>, which is the same size,
              medium, and date as the other watercolors in the June 1852 auction.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Appendix 2</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The following is an annotated list of the Blake works sold at Sotheby’s on 5 July
              1852 as part of the E. V. Utterson collection.</p>
            <p>Lot 248. Blake (William) Twelve Illustrations of “Blair’s Grave,” engraved by
              Schiavonetti, portrait 1808.</p>
            <p>Purchased by Butts Jr. for 18s. and sold at his 29 June 1853 auction, lot 143, for £2
              2s. to Wood.</p>
            <p>Lot 249. Blake (W.) <hi rend="i">Young’s Night Thoughts</hi>, designed and etched by
              himself, original impressions imp. 4to, 1797.</p>
            <p>Purchased by James Toovey for £1 5s.</p>
            <p>Lot 250. Blake, <hi rend="i">Another Copy</hi>, fine impressions[;] half green
              morocco, gilt top ib. 1797.</p>
            <p>Purchased by James Toovey for £1 9s. This and the copy in lot 249 were probably
              uncolored; neither fit the descriptions of the known colored copies (see Bentley, 
                <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 642-47). Butts may have passed because he already had a
              copy, which he sold with a copy of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (presumably Utterson’s
              copy) at his 29 June 1853 sale. Captain Butts sold “twenty pages of proofs in various
              states” in his 1903 auction (lot 21); these are probably the <hi rend="i">Night
                Thoughts</hi> designs Mary Butts refers to as being in her father’s collection in
              the late nineteenth century (Butts 164).</p>
            <p>Lot 251. Blake (W.) <hi rend="i">America, a Prophecy.</hi> with Eighteen 
                <hi rend="i">Singular Designs</hi>, printed in tints by the artist himself, rare ib. 1793.</p>
            <p>Purchased by Holmes for £2 7s. Possibly John Holmes the antiquary and senior keeper
              of the Department of Manuscripts at the British Museum (1800-54), or James Holmes
              (1777-1860), a watercolorist and miniaturist. Linnell records in his journal for 20
              August 1819: “with Mr Holmes to Mr Blake, Evg” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records
                Supplement</hi> 104). The British Museum purchased <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy H
              in 1856 and copy F in 1859 (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 103, 102). Both
              copies were printed in black ink and unwashed, and thus neither seems likely to have
              been Utterson’s copy—which suggests that the Holmes who purchased the works may have
              been the painter and not the curator. “Singular” does not really identify format,
              since it could mean rare as well as separate (i.e., designs on single leaves). In this
              case it appears to mean the former, which suggests the possibility of a recto/verso
              copy. That the designs were “printed in tints” as opposed to colored suggests copy R,
              printed on both sides of the leaf in bluish and greenish black ink as well as blue and
              green (Essick, “Resurrection” 139).</p>
            <p>Lot 252. Blake (W.) <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, with Three Illustrations,
              etched and coloured by himself, rare, and One other Etching by him Lambeth, 1795</p>
            <p>Purchased by Richard Monckton Milnes (the future Lord Houghton) for £1 13s. Bentley
              does not list an owner of copy A before Milnes and assumes that the copy Lowndes
              records as being sold in the “1855” auction (1: 216) was copy Bb and not copy A, as
              Keynes states (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 114 n1; <hi rend="i">Census</hi> 95). But
              Lowndes was referring to Utterson’s copy, as is evinced by his recording the correct
              price. Copy A was sold with “three illustrations” (plates 1, 2, 6), which indicates
              that it was complete when acquired by Milnes. When sold by Milnes’s son, the Earl of
              Crewe, at Sotheby’s on 30 March 1903, it consisted only of “5 engraved plates, with a
              coloured vignette on the first and last pages” e.g. plates 2 and 6 (lot 7). Its
              initial frontispiece 
<pb id="p29-67" n="67"/> (plate 1), now known as copy Ba, was
              sold separately in the same auction as “An Allegorical Subject of a Giant with a nude
              female figure, in colours,” along with a few set loose impressions (lot 18). As
              Bentley notes, the date the original frontispiece was extracted and whether it was
              known to Gilchrist and Swinburne are unclear (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 114n1).
              The complete six-plate work, however, was reproduced by Yeats and Ellis in 1893.<ref
                target="n73" type="note">73</ref>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">73</hi> The
                frontispiece now in copy A is from another, presumably lost, copy. It may have been
                the impression sold anonymously on 11 May 1895 at Sotheby’s to R. Ward (Bentley, 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 114). The “one other etching” that accompanied 
                  <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> in the Utterson sale may have been one of the prints that
                sold with the <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> frontispiece in lot 18 of the Crewe sale at
                Sotheby’s on 30 March 1903. These loose impressions consisted of an “Ancient of
                Days” proof, “A plate from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> in drab,” <hi rend="i">For the
                  Sexes</hi> plate 3, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> title plate,
                and the frontispiece to Burger’s <hi rend="i">Leonora.</hi> The last item was
                designed but not etched by Blake; the second <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> plate has not
                been identified, but “in drab” suggests that it was printed in olive or
                brown.</note></p>
            <p>Lot 253. Blake (W.) Illustrations of Milton’s “Comus.” <hi rend="i">The Eight
                Original Designs</hi>, drawn and coloured by himself, in his peculiar and unique
              style.</p>
            <p>C. 1816. Purchased by Butts Jr. for £4 6s. and sold at his June 1853 auction, lot 98,
              for £6 6s. to Strange. <hi rend="i">The</hi> Eight <hi rend="i">Original</hi> Designs”
              may imply that the designs are original drawings, as opposed to prints or copies, but
              it may also reflect Utterson’s awareness of the Thomas set and perhaps his opinion
              about which set was executed first. Butts sold <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> with “the
              artist’s descriptions” (lot 98), which are not mentioned in the Utterson catalogue
              (and are untraced), but were presumably included in the series as owned by Utterson
              and may have been why Utterson considered his set first and the model for the
              other.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E. Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1988.</p>
            <p>—. “The Daughters of Albion and the Butts Household.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 18
              (1984): 116.</p>
            <p>—. “Thomas Butts, White Collar Maecenas.” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> 71 (1956):
              1052-66.</p>
            <p>Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the
                Fitzwilliam Museum.</hi> Cambridge: W. Heffer and Sons, 1970.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">Colour Versions of William Blake’s Book of Job Designs from the Circle of
                John Linnell.</hi> London: William Blake Trust, 1987.</p>
            <p>Briggs, Ada E. “Mr. Butts, the Friend and Patron of Blake.” 
                <hi rend="i">Connoisseur</hi> 19 (1907): 92-97.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Burke’s Landed Gentry of Great Britain.</hi> 12th edition. 1914.</p>
            <p>Bury, Adrian. <hi rend="i">Richard Wilson, R.A. The Grand Classic.</hi> Leigh-On-Sea:
              F. Lewis, 1947.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2
              vols. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1982.</p>
            <p>—. “A ‘Minute Particular’ Particularized: Blake’s Second Set of Illustrations to 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 22 (1972):
              44-46.</p>
            <p>—. The Physicality of William Blake: The Large Color Prints of ‘1795.’” 
                <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 52 (1989): 1-18.</p>
            <p>—. Review of the William Blake Trust edition of <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi>,
              ed. David Bindman. <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 22 (1988/89): 105-10.</p>
            <p>—. “William Rossetti’s Annotations to Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William
                Blake.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 2 (1968): 39-40.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin and Evelyn Joll. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Turner.</hi> 2 vols.
              Rev. ed. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1984.</p>
            <p>Butts, Mary. <hi rend="i">The Crystal Cabinet: My Childhood at Salterns.</hi> London:
              Methuen &amp; Co. 1937.</p>
            <p>Constable, W. G. <hi rend="i">Richard Wilson.</hi> London: Routledge Kegan Paul,
              1953.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi>
              Rev. ed. New York: Anchor, 1988.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1986.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 21
              (1987): 4-13.</p>
            <p>—. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1994.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 28 (1995): 120-41.</p>
            <p>—. “Blake’s 1812 Exhibition.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 27 (1993): 36-42.</p>
            <p>—. “The Resurrection of <hi rend="i">America</hi> Copy R.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 21
              (1988): 138-42.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi> Princeton:
              Princeton University Press, 1983.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake’s ‘The Phoenix’: A Problem in Attribution.” 
                <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 67 (1988): 365-84.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake in the Huntington Collections.</hi> San
              Marino: Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1985.</p>
            <p>Foskett, Daphne. <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of British Miniature Painters.</hi>
              London: Faber and Faber, 1972.</p>
            <p>Gaskell, Phillip. <hi rend="i">A New Introduction to Bibliography.</hi> New York:
              Oxford University Press, 1972.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. London:
              Macmillan, 1863.</p>
            <p>Graves, Algernon. <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of Artists who have exhibited works in
                the principal London exhibitions from 1760 to 1893.</hi> 2 vols. 3rd edition.
              London, 1901. Kingsmead Reprints, 1969.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Society of Artists of Great Britain 1760-1791; The Free Society
                of Artists 1761-1783.</hi> London, 1907. Kingsmead Reprints, 1969.</p>
            <p>Gregori, Mina. <hi rend="i">Giovan Battista Moroni: Tutte le Opere.</hi> Bergamo:
              Poligrafiche Bolis, 1979.</p>
            <p>Hayes, John. <hi rend="i">The Drawings of Thomas Gainsborough.</hi> 2 vols. New
              Haven: Yale University Press, 1971.</p>
            <p>James, Ralph N. <hi rend="i">Painters and Their Works.</hi> 3 vols. London: Upcott
              Gill, 1897.</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake</hi>, 3rd edition. 
                <pb id="p29-68" n="68"/>
Oxford: Clarendon Press. 1980.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Bible.</hi> London: Blake Trust,
              1957.</p>
            <p>Labarre, E. J. <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of Paper and Paper-Making Terms.</hi>
              Amsterdam: N. V. Swets &amp; Zeitlinger, 1937.</p>
            <p>Long, Basil S. <hi rend="i">British Miniaturists.</hi> London: The Holland Press,
              1929.</p>
            <p>Lowndes, W. T. <hi rend="i">The Bibliographer’s Manual of English Literature.</hi> 11
              vols. London, 1857-61.</p>
            <p>Lugt, Fritz. <hi rend="i">Repertoire des Catalogues de Ventes Publiques.</hi> La
              Haye: M. Nijhoff, 1938-64.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton. “The Art of ‘The Ancients.’” <hi rend="i">William Blake and His
                Circle. Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 52 (189): 97-124.</p>
            <p>Parris, Leslie. “William Blake’s Mr. Thomas,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary
                Supplement</hi> (5 Dec. 1968): 1390.</p>
            <p>Reynolds, Graham. <hi rend="i">The Later Paintings and Drawings of John
                Constable.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 1984.</p>
            <p>Robertson, W. Graham. <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of W. Graham Robertson,
                Described by the Collector.</hi> Ed. Kerrison Preston. London: Blake Trust,
              1952.</p>
            <p>Rossetti, W. M. <hi rend="i">The Diary of W. M. Rossetti 1870-1873.</hi> Ed. Odette
              Bornand. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers 1862 to 1870.</hi> Comp. by William Michael Rossetti.
              London: Sands, 1903.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Selected Letters of William Michael Rossetti.</hi> Ed. Roger W.
              Peattie. University Park: Pennsylvania State University Press, 1990.</p>
            <p>Selincourt, Ernest de. <hi rend="i">Letters of William and Dorothy Wordsworth: The
                Later Years.</hi> 2nd ed. Rev. by Alan G. Hill. Parts 1-4. Oxford: Oxford University
              Press, 1978-88.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> Princeton:
              Princeton University Press, 1993.</p>
            <p>—. “<hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi>: Lost or
              Found?” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 28 (1994): 44-61.</p>
            <p>—. “A ‘Green House’ for Butts? New Information on Thomas Butts, his Residence, and
              Family.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (forth-coming).</p>
            <p>—. “The Myth of Commissioned Illuminated Books: George Romney, Isaac D’Israeli, and
              ‘ONE HUNDRED AND SIXTY designs. . . of Blake’s.’” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989):
              48-74.</p>
            <p>Wilson, Mona. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> 3rd edition. Oxford:
              Oxford University Press, 1971.</p>
            <p>Wilton, Andrew. <hi rend="i">J. M. W. Turner: His Art and His Life.</hi> New York:
              Rizzoli International, 1979.</p>
            <p>Wilton, Andrew, and Anne Lyles. <hi rend="i">The Great Age of British Watercolours,
                1750-1880.</hi> London: Royal Academy of Arts, 1993.</p>
            <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of
                Milton.</hi> Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1975.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake: Illustrator-Interpreter of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained.</hi>”
                <hi rend="i">Calm of Mind: Tercentary Essays on</hi> Paradise Regained 
                <hi rend="i">and</hi> Samson Agonistes <hi rend="i">in Honor of John S. Diekhoff.</hi> Ed. J.
A.
              Wittreich, Jr. Cleveland and London: Press of Case Western Reserve Univ., 1971.
              93-132.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
