<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.2.clark</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Harvey Birenbaum, Between Blake and Nietzsche: The Reality of Culture</title>
        <author n="Clark">Stephen Clark</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Clark</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
	<pb id="p29-68" n="68"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEW</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Harvey Birenbaum. <hi rend="i">Between Blake and Nietzsche: The Reality of
Culture.</hi> Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press and London and Toronto: Associated University Presses,
1992. Pp. xvi + 159; $26.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Stephen <name>Clark</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Harvey Birenbaum’s study of Blake and Nietzsche has both the strengths and weaknesses of its
comparative format. It combines a broad characterization of intellectual affiliation with illuminating
tessellations of detail, and has the considerable merit of attempting to situate Blake within the context of
European romanticism. This is achieved, however, at the expense of an habitual recourse to composite
generalization. The focus ceases to be making sense of the work of the individual author: problems of internal
coherence and evolution are downgraded, if not altogether bypassed, to allow points of similarity and contact
to be emphasized. But as the two thinkers have been yoked together since Yeats and Symons, it is welcome to
have an extended treatment of their relation.</p>
          <p>Birenbaum, however, has bigger fish to fry. After the reflex linguistic pyrrhonism of the past
decades, the time may well be ripe for a contemporary reformulation of the neo-Kantian doctrine of symbolic
forms associated with Cassirer and Langer, whose closest analogue in the field of Blake studies remains
Northrup Frye. Birenbaum’s ambition to rehabilitate this body of work deserves respect, and later in this
review I wish to take up some of its premises in detail. First, however, some more general indication of the
ground covered by Birenbaum may be helpful.</p>
          <p>Both Blake and Nietzsche are characterized in terms of their “critique of all culture” (4),
and on numerous occasions we are assured of their “almost identical pairs of psychological targets” (15).
This lack of differentiation is indicative of a larger tendency to abstract from any specifiable cultural
context. One might have expected, for example, some discussion of common intellectual genealogies, such as the
critique of causality via Hume, the degree of adjustment before and after Darwin, and the extent of the
continued dependence on a sentimentalist idea of innate impulse in both writers. When Bakhtin is invoked in
the third chapter, there is no consideration of issues of power in the carnivalesque, of whether licensed
transgression subverts or reconfirms hierarchies, and no attempt to identify the immanent speech-communities
out of which the dialogic text is constructed. Such historical perspective as we encounter comes in terms of
“European civilization precariously balanced
<pb id="p29-69" n="69"/>
between predicament and opportunity” (40), or “cultural history” as a movement towards comprehension of
the archetype (xvi).</p>
          <p>Second, both writers are presented in terms of an “energetic explosion of the irrational”
(4). This claim is partially rescinded in the case of Nietzsche, who, it is immediately acknowledged,
“challenges customary reasoning out of logical necessity” (4) but continues to result in a highly
reductive characterization of Blake’s work. The presence of rationalist elements in his thoughts remains
much more complex than this suggests: in terms of continuous intellectual preoccupation, Blake may even be
said to have been to Urizen’s party without knowing it. Such obvious examples come to mind as the heroic
dimension of Urizen’s struggle to create a world out of chaos, and the “sweet Science” that “reigns”
after the “Spectre of Prophesy” has “Departed” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 139.5-10 [IX 850-55], E 407), and
the allocation of a ringside seat at the resurrection to “Bacon &amp; Newton &amp; Locke 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 98:9). Furthermore, it is patently inadequate to assume that his work may somehow be exempted
from “conventional rational interpretation” (7). As Blake himself reminds us, it is “a most pernicious
Falshood” of Plato’s that “Poets &amp; Prophets do not know or Understand what they write or Utter”
for “If they do not pray is an inferior Kind to be calld Knowing” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi> E 554).</p>
          <p>Birenbaum moves without apparent qualm from Blake as a proponent of the irrational to a somewhat
hackneyed version of the neglected visionary who was “virtually on his own” (53). From here it is a short
step to insisting that he is a “shaman or a tribal artist” who must “be taken at his word” in his
testimony of a spirit world (49-50). No original evidence is used to support this claim, and it is simple
enough to refute. If we regard Blake in terms of his career as an en-graver, a “professional among
professionals,” as Birenbuam himself puts it (50), he remains in continuous and productive interchange with
a contemporary audience throughout his career. To discuss his work in terms of liminal states introduces an
unnecessary element of melodrama and distracts attention away from the more interesting issue of the parodic,
or at least dramatically contextualized use of the histrionic, in the prophesies.</p>
          <p>The status of the psychological per se remains obscure. Both Blake and Nietzsche, we are told,
possess an “absolute sense of themselves as persons” (4), but the obvious query as to how can we “read a
text for the person in it” (6) when we construct that self from our encounter with that text is never
adequately addressed. Such invocations would carry considerably more weight if some detailed considerations
was given to the notion of personal identity implied by the “fortuitous concourse of memories accumulated
&amp; lost” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 29:8). Instead we are offered a broadly therapeutic and wholly
anachronistic ideal of self-expression.</p>
          <p>“Culture,” it is declared, “is a problem of personal psychology” (15). At the very least,
several interim stages of argument need to be inserted in order to justify such a transposition. Bakhtin is
invoked to perform this unification of private and public spheres, but as the title of the third chapter,
“The solitary carnival,” suggests, the effect is to internalize the cultural rather than socialize the
psychic.</p>
          <p>To “reinvent discourse” (6), Birenbaum argues, would transform both the self and the symbolic
forms which it inhabits. This implies the recovery of an occluded mythopoeic dimension that simultaneously
transcends and refutes “the leveling, abstracting, and objectifying force of conventional language” (6).
Leaving aside the contentious nature of this characterization (does it include metaphor, for example?), it
will be helpful to begin by considering its relevance to Nietzsche.</p>
          <p>The more obviously mythic elements of the German philosopher’s thought—the superman, eternal
recurrence, the Apollonian and the Dionysiac—are precisley what the contemporary reader tends to find least
satisfactory: Birenbaum himself finds them “sometimes forced and excessively conscious” (87). The problem
is not that we have too few myths, but that we have too many, each claiming a self-authenticating priority.
“As myths, they simply do not make logical contact” (82); consequently, there can be no rational grounds
for preferring positions with which we might sympathize, say, the assault on slave morality to the arrogant
elitism of a “myth of the nobler nobleman” (85). Birenbaum is left in the uncomfortable position of
refusing to commit himself to the biologistic affirmation of the Will to Power, with all its respective
historical contamination, while still resisting a reading in terms of semiotic demystification in favor of a
putative mythic plentitude.</p>
          <p>The problem lies primarily in Birenbaum’s insistence on the successive rather that
contemporaneous nature of the conflict of interpretations. Blake and Nietzsche must not “simply undo the
language and the culture given to them,” but must instead “bring both closer to the logic of directly
perceived relationships and the nature of immediate experience alive with feeling’” (6-7). One does not
have to be a card-carrying deconstructor to accept that the mediation of language itself precludes access to
any such realm. Here, and throughout the book, the moment of affirmation is defined so nebulously as to be
virtually meaningless. Birenbaum’s analysis, by situating itself on the plane of the ontological, proves
incapable of envisaging a hermeneutic level on which doubt may be seen as not merely the prelude to but
synonymous with energetic creation.</p>
          <p>The manifest shortcomings of his argument at this point do, however, have the virtue of drawing
attention to a key issue: how may we conceptualize interpretation as a moment of denial and resistance without
reverting to a philosophical concept of negativity or a glib and impoverished proclamation of the ludic?</p>
          <p>With Blake, comparable problems arise. Although the early polemics on behalf of energy and
delight tend to be more
<pb id="p29-70" n="70"/>
favorably received than Nietzsche’s adoration of power, the same interchange of dogmatism and
self-reformulation is apparent. When Los proclaims, “I must Create a System or be enslav’d by another
Mans” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 10:20), should the emphasis fall on the “System” or on the desire to
“Create”? Birenbaum is by no means exceptional in claiming for Blake’s writing the freedom of open-ended
process while basing his exposition on locally doctrinaire pronouncements. There is virtually no attention to
the narrative and dramatic structures of the later prophesies, nor consideration of their textual
complexities. “Specialists” are somewhat disparagingly opposed to “new readers” (41), but
Birenbaum’s readings of the lyrics are deeply flawed by their apparent unconcern with the basic debates
concerning viewpoint and persona: the narrator of “London,” for example, is confidently classified as the
“same voice of Blake”; the speaker of “The Fly” as affirming his “essential innocence” (63). One
may feel broadly sympathetic to the aim of reading the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> “without the defense of
irony” (73) without preemptively dismissing all attempts to understand them “ironically or
sociologically” as merely a “cyclical trap” (70); at the very least, some consideration of the generic
inversion of hymn and children’s song is required, and also their relation to Swedenborg’s theory of
correspondences. Furthermore there is little or no analysis of the specifically epistemological claims made by
Blake. It may be more persuasive to regard the realm of imagination as founded upon a theory of constitutive
metaphor than upon a quasi-Berkeleyan idealism, but the vocabulary in which it is articulated suggests the
latter.</p>
          <p>It would be clearer and more honest if Birenbaum were prepared to distinguish between levels of
reality and to declare an investment in an ulterior, opaque dimension. Instead, he claims to be offering a
secular account of cultural symbolism when his arguments at their most plausible pull in precisely the
opposite direction. The move to the ontological without adequate prior consideration of the semantic all too
easily becomes a mode of dogmatism: all that restrains Birenbaum is a humanist vocabulary of culture which is
clearly at variance with the assertions designed to support it.</p>
          <p>Two questions cannot be avoided if one is to resuscitate a vocabulary of symbolic forms: what is
the relation of the mythic to the related but distinct phenomena of metaphor and symbol? and secondly, how are
we to arbitrate between competing or contradictory manifestations? Birenbaum’s terminology shifts
confusingly on the first issue: sometimes the symbol appears to be verbal; at others it is opposed to the
merely figural. It “provides a focus to comprehend the unity of author, audience, thought, and the
world—in the work of imagination, where they all meet naturally” (xii), a process supported by analogy
with the “process of projection” (xiv), an oddly Lockean conjunction of screen and darkened room. Even if
one accepts that there is an initial state of “fragmentation” to be overcome, it remains to be seen
whether “integration” is likely to be forthcoming in the texts of Blake and Nietzsche.</p>
          <p>The symbol “holds various impulses in tension, and involves itself in conflict with other
points of view” (xiv), a capacity designated “quasiousness” (xii). Although myth has previously been
defined “as an instrument to know what is valid” (xi), it now transpires that it is “powerfully
meaningful because it is also going to be wrong” (xiii). The term “collusion,” in the sense of playing
with, is used to define this relation (xiii): “we grant them their own charm and eagerly fall under their
spell.” Thus the authority of the symbol derives from an active forgetting of its origin, exactly the
process which the myth of Albion and Vala dramatizes and one would have thought exposed.</p>
          <p>Birenbaum is clearly vulnerable to the familiar charge laid against the phenomenology of
religion: that its descriptive (and arguably implicitly prescriptive) method is devoid of the element of
conflict contained within a properly hermeneutic stance. It can serve as no more than a confirmatory mode,
willing to divulge its enigmas only to those who have already decided what they can find. There is no element
of risk or uncertainty in “this way of knowing that requires appreciation, if not awe” (xvi).</p>
          <p>Birenbaum’s specific against deconstructive approaches are unimpressive: it seems peculiar to
treat Derrida’s “Spurs” rather than “White Mythology” on the issue of philosophical metaphor
(108-11); and to dismiss de Man’s reading of Nietzsche for treating signs as “binary substitutions”
rather than “unifying participations” ignores his assiduous demonstrations of the dependence of the one on
the other (107-08). Above all, Birenbaum underestimates the sheer productivity of a semiotic model, even
though his own infrequent close analyses of Blake’s language are clearly indebted to it (e.g., 54-59). But
in terms of its basic hermeneutic stance, it may be seen as continuous with rather than antithetical to the
ubiquitous skepticism of recent methodologies. Their frequently exemplary rigor and finesse have been
customarily expanded on behalf of Blake, whose decentered universe and habitual indeterminacy of text provide
convenient corroboration of their supposedly subversive analyses.</p>
          <p>Birenbaum provides a helpful introductory commentary on the relation of Blake and Nietzsche, but
if we take his larger ambitions seriously, his book may be seen as mirroring what it claims to displace. It
cannot disbelieve enough, but attains a representative significance in this failure. The contrast with 
<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> may be illuminating. Whereas Birenbaum makes no attempt to circumscribe the
domain of myth, Frye insists upon both an internal dynamism within its concentric levels and perhaps, more
importantly, a judicious sense of what it could not incorporate. The euphoria of Frye’s exposition is at all
times tempered by a residual astringency, and it is perhaps this quality from which Blake studies in the 1990s
can learn most.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
