<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.2.net</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Romanticism on the Net</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1995</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Clark</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <pb id="p29-71" n="71"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi>
              </hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The announcement of a new Web page and electronic journal:
<q>
Hello and welcome to Romanticism On the Net. The first issue of this new electronic journal will be launched
in a couple of months. In the meantime, here is an outline of the purpose of this new international journal
entirely devoted to Romantic Studies. Why a new electronic journal? With the expansion of electronic media and
the increasing success of the Internet, I think it is time for an electronic journal entirely devoted to
Romantic Studies to be created. There are already a few journals developed by departments of English across
the world but none so far dedicated to the Romantic Period only. The Internet is a source of information for
academic purpose as the latest edition of the MLA Handbook for Writers of Research Papers (4th edition, 1995)
shows since it explains how to cite material from electronic journals. What purpose? My purpose is similar to
that of a “conventional” journal in offering articles and reviews but the limitless amount of space in the
Internet allows me to advertise other journals or conferences, as well as graduate courses, or offer some
links to other Romantic-related sites on the World Wide Web, such as the on-line database of Romantic Poetry.
One does not have the limitations imposed by publishers when working with the Internet. Any questions? For any
enquiries or suggestions, send me an e-mail:<lb/>
<lb/>
michael.laplace-sinatra@stcatz.ox.ac.uk<lb/>
Michael Laplace-Sinatra, Editor of Romanticism On the Net
</q></p>
          <p>The editor reports that the first issue will be out in January. Submissions can be sent to
Michael Laplace-Sinatra, St. Catherine’s College, Oxford OX1 3UJ or to Michael Gamer, Department of English,
119 Bennett Hall, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia PA 19104-6273.</p>
          <p>The page also has information about and links to conferences, journals (including Blake), sites
related to romaticism, and associations. The URL is http://info.ox.ac.uk:80/~scat0385/.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>