<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.warner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Steven Vine, Blake’s Poetry: Spectral Visions</title>
        <author n="Warner">Janet Warner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0006">
      	<pb id="p29-96" n="96"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Steven Vine, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry: Spectral Visions.</hi> New York:
St. Martin’s Press, 1993. xv + 194 pp., 16 pls. $45.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Janet <name>Warner</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>We’ve had the Visionary Blake, the Dangerous Blake, and now the Ambiguous Blake. Steven Vine
states at the outset that his book examines Blake as a poet of contradiction and contrariety, and focuses on
the elusive spectre, its shadowy ironies, and “the divided energies of Blake’s poetics.” Vine criticizes
the idealist approaches to Blake of Frye and Erdman, who insist on the integrity of Blake’s prophetic voice.
He sees instead a Blake who relentlessly confronts the failure of visionary power, whose poetics are “ever
building, ever falling.”</p>
          <p>In Vine’s words, “. . . a spectral rhythm of continual building and falling is installed at
the heart of Blake’s account of visionary poetry, and it is the argument of this book that the poetic
dramatisation of such inquiet energies is the measure of Blake’s poetic daring and his rigour.” This is
nicely put; however, what emerges is a book emphasizing Blake’s failure and the paradoxes of his doctrine.
Vine gives illuminating close readings of selected passages of Blake’s major poems, quite often for the
purpose of pointing out the ambiguities and contradictions and presumable failures. Yet paradox works both
ways, and often the critic is undermined by the energy and mystery of his poet.</p>
          <p>Vine’s book charts a chronological path through Blake’s work, and the second chapter
considers Blake’s critique of Edmund Burke’s theory of the sublime by exploring Blake’s revolutionary
poems of the 1790s. Vine argues that Blake’s “aesthetic of vision” fails to escape the paradoxes that
bedevil it, essentially because in spite of his criticism of Burkian obscurity, Blake’s is itself the
language of mystification. Most importantly, there are “spectres” in these poems who are both kingly and
revolutionary, and a general mistiness prevails which clouds the imagination in spite of Blake’s avowed aim
to the contrary.</p>
          <p>Vine thinks Burke is successfully criticized in certain designs in <hi rend="i">Job</hi>,
particularly the design “Behemoth and Leviathan” (1805-06; the design appears in plate XV of Blake’s
engraved collection). Because Burke used Eliphaz’s vision as an example of sublime obscurity, Vine contends
that the clarity of Blake’s line renders these beasts less terrible than laughable and that Burke’s vision
of the sublime is being overturned by mockery. He then asks the key questions which the rest of the book
examines: “. . . if these designs expose the collapse of a certain kind of sublimity, what of Blake’s
sublime of ‘vision?’ Is the Blakean sublime free of the blindness which darkens the visions of Burke,
Eliphaz, and the God of Job?” Ambivalence is the answer here, as it is for vine’s reading of the Lambeth
Prophecies, with their conjunction of the sublime and satiric modes.</p>
          <p>When Vine carries his study of ambiguity into a consideration of the idea of form in 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> he becomes really interesting, though I think it is here that he goes astray, for
he suggests that the veil of Enion (“Hide me some shadowy semblance” [<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 1, 4: 24])
becomes in Beulah a “metaphor of redemptive form.” This idea can only be valid if one rather willfully
misreads the veils of Beulah as positive. By insisting upon ambiguity in Blake’s idea of form, Vine misses
the distinction in Blake between Eternal Form and Fallen Form. (Critical discussions of veils and form are not
mentioned in Vine’s references.)</p>
          <p>Of course, Vine’s point of view would not allow an idealist concept like Eternal Form, so I was
interested to see what he would do to the idea of the Spectre in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Somehow the approach that seemed confusing in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> works
brilliantly in Vine’s concise discussions of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> There
<hi rend="i">is</hi> creative ambiguity in these poems and Vine’s close readings of key sections are
illuminating. His chapter on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> focuses on language, and also takes up the theme of
the garment to argue that the ambiguous nature of apocalyptic language dissolves into a kind of chaos. As he
writes at one point, “The language here makes and unmakes its revelations . . . .” Although the Spectre is
annihilated, he is still in the play, so to speak. The energy of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> belongs to the
Spectre, and Blake is of the Spectre’s party without knowing it.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
