<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.read</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi, eds., William Blake, 
Milton a Poem and the Final Illuminated Works: The Ghost of Abel, on Homer’s Poetry 
[and] On Virgil, Laocoön</title>
        <author n="Read">Dennis M. Read</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0006">
        <pb id="p29-91" n="91"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi> and the Final Illuminated Works:
<hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>[,] <hi rend="i">on Homer’s Poetry</hi> [and] <hi rend="i">On
Virgil</hi>[,] <hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi> Edited with Introductions and Notes by Robert N. Essick and Joseph
Viscomi. Princeton: William Blake Trust/Princeton University Press, 1993. Blake’s Illuminated Books Volume
5. General Editor David Bindman. 286 pp. $65.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Dennis M. <name>Read</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>From the 1950s to the early 70s, the William Blake Trust published more than a dozen beautiful
facsimile volumes of Blake’s works. This labor of love, carried out by the Trianon Press under the direction
of Arnold D. Fawcus, made available for the first time the corpus of Blake’s verbal-visual art as he had
created it. The volumes, however, were published in very limited editions and carried price tags of hundreds
and even thousands of dollars. Consequently, their purchasers were, by and large, college and university
libraries. Most Blake scholars today cut their eyeteeth on these volumes in the rare books rooms of their
graduate school libraries.</p>
          <p>Now, in the 90s, we have from the William Blake Trust, in collaboration with Princeton University
Press, a new series of Blake’s works in photo-offset reproduction. While they are not as hand-crafted and
bibliophilisticly precious as the first series, they are more affordable—certainly not cheap, but within the
range of most Blakeans. <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is the fifth volume. The others are 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (1991, reviewed in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> fall 1992), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
and Experience</hi> (1991, reviewed in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> fall 1992), <hi rend="i">All Religions are One,
There is No Natural Religion, Book of Thel, Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi> (1993), and <hi rend="i">Urizen, Ahania, Book of Los, America, Europe</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (forthcoming in two volumes, 1995). The recent release of <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and Experience</hi> in paperback induces the hope that the other volumes will follow suit; then even
grad students will be able to buy them and instructors will be able to use them as texts without a guilty
conscience. The entire project, with its uniform volumes, meticulously edited texts, extensive commentary, and
glosses on critical studies, might be likened to the huge Library of America.</p>
          <p>The editors of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi, are well
credentialed for this undertaking. Essick is an accomplished commentator on Blake’s meaning and method and
the hands-down expert on Blake’s engraving techniques, as well as a major Blake collector. Viscomi has
established himself as the pre-eminent historian of Blake’s artistic production, and the fruits of his
landmark study, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>, enrich this project. One example is in the
discussion on pages 35-41 of the date of publication for <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and the ordering of its
plates. The upshot of this discussion is that Blake may not have printed a complete <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
until 1810-11, much later than previously postulated.</p>
          <p>Only four copies of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> are known to exist, and each is at least slightly
different from the others in the number and arrangement of its plates. In 1967 the William Blake Trust chose
to reproduce copy D, now in the Library of Congress, for its Trianon Press edition. As the alphabetical letter
implies, it was thought to be the latest of the four, probably printed in 1818. Essick and Viscomi have chosen
to reproduce copy C, now in the New York Public Library, and they argue that it is the final 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>; furthermore, because he did not sell it until 1826, that it embodies “Blake’s final
intentions” (41). (Kay Parkhurst Easson and Roger R. Easson reproduced copy B, now in the Huntington
Library, for an edition published by Shambhala/Random House in 1978. Although the plates are less than full
size, the volume is handy for quick comparisons. It still can be found in used bookstores.)</p>
          <p>With its 40-odd to 50 plates, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is a hefty work, second in length only to
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> It is also a dense and confounding work. With its confusing narrative structure,
constantly shifting cast of characters, and geographical and cosmological leapfrogging, it challenges the
reader, sometimes beyond patience. Few, if any, in Blake’s own day were up to this challenge. In our day,
however, readers have become more accustomed to discontinuous narratives. No longer do commentators attempt to
crack the code or come up with <hi rend="i">the</hi> definitive reading of this work. In their introduction,
Essick and Viscomi provide a summary of the story in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>:
<q>
Book 1. Milton leaves heaven and returns to earth to do battle with forces opposed to art and the human
spirit.<lb/>
Book 2. Milton’s female counterpart, Ololon, returns to earth to unite with Milton in preparation for
apocalypse. (9)
</q></p>
          <p>Those who have struggled with the meaning of the work might even argue about these descriptions
of its actions. But none can deny that they are helpful. Also helpful is the discussion about biblical
allegory and Blake’s mythological creations (such as Ololon). The introduction gives the neophyte reader a
foothold and the experienced reader a review of salient matters concerning the work.</p>
          <p>Essick and Viscomi also provide an elucidating discussion of the genesis and history of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, as well as a careful analysis of the dating and pagination of the surviving copies. The
reproduced plates of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> follow. One can argue that the paper should be less glossy and
more matte, like the paper Blake himself used; one can maintain that the dimensions of the pages should be the
same as the original and
<pb id="p29-92" n="92"/>
not larger; one can quibble over the authenticity of the coloring. No matter; the reproductions serve well and
probably bring most of us as close to the original as we ever will be. The plates are supplemented with plates
from other copies of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> that Blake chose to exclude from copy C, as well as several
sketches and engravings of related figures and designs.</p>
          <p>Following the plates is the text of the poem in letterpress. Essick and Viscomi have minutely
examined Blake’s engraved text and consequently have dissented from David V. Erdman’s version in 
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> on numerous small matters, for instance 
<hi rend="i">ann</hi>, not <hi rend="i">can</hi> on 42:30. (This difference, Essick and Viscomi note, comes from
an inadvertence in etching, which Blake corrected in ink on copy B.) Other differences involve capitals
instead of lowercase letters and colons instead of exclamation points. Along with the text are voluminous
notes, which often surpass in length the page they accompany. They are impressively inclusive of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> scholarship, and they are evenhanded, favoring no critical approach over others. A small
oversight is the omission of Paul Youngquist’s <hi rend="i">Madness and Blake’s Myth</hi> (Pennsylvania
State University Press, 1989) from “Works Cited,” although the study is referred to on page 163.</p>
          <p>A bonus to the volume are reproductions of three late Blake works: the two-plate 
<hi rend="i">Ghost of Abel</hi> and the single plates, <hi rend="i">On Homers Poetry</hi> [and] <hi rend="i">On
Virgil</hi> and <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, along with associated paintings, engravings, drawings, and
sketches. These are slight works when compared with <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, but worthy of study
nevertheless. Essick and Viscomi find in <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> Blake’s themes of vengeance,
atonement, and apocalypse writ small and assert it “is about the ramifications of the murder, about the
various responses to the material fact of death—that is, to ‘Nature’ (1:2-4) itself” (222). They are
more tentative in identifying the figures on the plates; the commentary is thick with such qualifiers as
“may,” “perhaps,” “suggests,” and “appears.” In <hi rend="i">On Homers Poetry</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">On Virgil</hi> Essick and Viscomi find Blake ambivalent toward Homer and disparaging of Virgil. 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> has to do with “the contrast between what we think we know and what we are being
told” (232). Essick and Viscomi choose to arrange the inscriptions swirling around the figures on the plate
in an order quite different from Erdman’s, attempting to approximate a clockwise arrangement. Erdman’s is
a “roughly thematic sequence” (E 814). The effort is similar to mapping the globe on a flat piece of
paper—that is, not entirely a success. More successful is their argument that the date of composition of 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> should be 1826, not 1820.</p>
          <p>All in all, there is much to praise, little to question, and less to criticize in this splendid
volume. Its greatest virtue is in making available to a larger audience something remarkably close to
Blake’s own hand. And yet there is an irony in this effort. Most of this volume is taken up with the work of
the editors; perhaps one-sixth of it is unadulterated Blake. Blake, of course, engraved and published his
works in order to reach his audience directly, without the agencies of editors, publishers, and booksellers.
Yet that, we find, is the only way almost all of us can ever hope to know him. Under such conditions, we must
be grateful to Essick and Viscomi for providing such an excellent interface.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
