<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.cox</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Jeanne Moskal, Blake, Ethics, and Forgiveness</title>
        <author n="Cox">Stephen Cox</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
	<pb id="p29-97" n="97"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Jeanne Moskal, <hi rend="i">Blake, Ethics, and Forgiveness.</hi> Tuscaloosa and
London: University of Alabama Press, 1994. 240 pp., $32.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Stephen <name>Cox</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>On the first page of her book, Jeanne Moskal suggests that consideration of Blake as an ethicist
is a challenge to fashionable opinion. Literary scholars, she says, are reluctant to entertain ethical issues,
because they are afraid of being led down the garden path to the abyss of “logocentric ‘meanings.’”
The public, meanwhile, has become convinced that Blake was a great “immoralist.”</p>
          <p>Moskal clearly exaggerates. The public, insofar as it is acquainted with Blake at all, regards
him as the poet of certain commonly anthologized <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, poems
which, as presented in most high-school and college classrooms, probably seem far from antinomian. And
literary scholarship is in no danger at all of relinquishing its traditional moralism. Even when it claims to
relinquish moralism for some higher purpose, such as the subversion of logocentrism, it seldom fails to
insinuate that the pursuit 
<pb id="p29-98" n="98"/>
of this goal is itself morally bracing. Scholars of Blake have always been moralistic. No one has ever written
on Blake without providing a moralizing gloss on what is obviously, though often unconsciously, regarded as
Blake’s moralizing text. (I include myself in that “no one.”) The morality thus recommended is never the
kind that would shock anyone likely to encounter it. No one has ever hesitated to pick up a book on Blake out
of fear of reading something scandalous.</p>
          <p>It is refreshing, however, to see a book on Blake that addresses moral questions
straightforwardly, instead of representing its moral commentary as mere interpretation of Blake’s attitudes
toward Druids, the French Revolution, or the theology of Emanuel Swedenborg. Moskal focuses clearly on the
ethical issues that arise in Blake’s work, with special emphasis on his prophecies; and she places his ideas
in relationship to a number of twentieth-century ethical theories. She pays Blake’s moral ideas the
compliment of searching criticism, exploring the various and at times incompatible ways in which he uses
them.</p>
          <p>Of special interest in this respect is her treatment of the difference between the
“intersubjective” and the “intrapsychic” functions of those ideas. Forgiveness, in her account, is a
central ethical concept for Blake because it is a means of adjusting both relations among people (the
intersubjective function) and relations among the psychological forces within people (the intrapsychic
function). Blake’s assumption is that one’s ability to forgive other persons depends on one’s ability to
deal with the accusing person within oneself.</p>
          <p>This is an apparently simple idea. Complications arise when it is associated with another simple
but powerful idea, Blake’s doctrine of states.</p>
          <p>If I want to stop accusing people of sin, I can try to remember that there is a difference
between a person and what that person is currently doing or suffering, the “state” that he or she
currently inhabits. When I make that distinction, I quiet the accuser inside me and forgive the sinners (or
supposed sinners) outside. Blake’s character Erin expounds the doctrine clearly:
<q>
Learn therefore O Sisters to distinguish the Eternal Human<lb/>
That walks about among the stones of fire in bliss &amp; woe<lb/>
Alternate! from those States or Worlds in which the Spirit travels:<lb/>
This is the only means to Forgiveness of Enemies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Blake, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 49.72-75, in <hi rend="i">The Complete
Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, newly rev. ed. (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday,
1982) 199. Subsequent references to this edition cite it as “E,” followed by page number.</note></q></p>
          <p>Here is a bold and generous conception, one that invites the forgiving spirit to discern eternity
through every cloud of temporal imperfection and preoccuptation.</p>
          <p>But Moskal argues, with reason, that the doctrine of states has one kind of effect when it is
applied to intersubjective relationships and another when it is applied to intrapsychic ones. When Blake
applies it intersubjectively, it helps him to recognize and appreciate the diversity of human beings,
visualizing their difficulties as temporary results of the states that they are passing through: “Like
parents who forgive their children because they are ‘going through a phase,’ Blake’s potential forgiver
looks forward to the journey’s continuance to a better destination” (81). But when Blake applies the
doctrine of states intrapsychically, he is tempted to write as if everyone were one person and to reduce all
relationships to one relationship, manifested in “the decision of just one party to forgive himself.”
Blake sometimes “implies that all instances of . . . intersubjective forgiveness depend solely upon the
intrapsychic self-annihilation, or renunciation of accusation” (121-22). The tendency is both to hold
everyone to the same standard of self-annihilation and to deplore variations as effects of people’s
involvement in a state of accusation.</p>
          <p>“In Blake’s emergent view,” Moskal says, “it is no longer one party’s 
<hi rend="i">offense</hi> that provides the occasion to be forgiven, but <hi rend="i">the very fact of his
otherness</hi> from the forgiver”—an otherness that is “overcome” in the act of “forgiveness”
(69). This is a radical and abstract statement of the problem. Read literally, perhaps too literally, it may
imply that Blake resented people simply for being different from him; and that’s not exactly the way Blake
was. But Blake’s own processes of abstraction are radical indeed; the pressure in his work toward subsuming
variety in universality is very great; and, as Moskal sees, the pressures of his own life must often have made
it difficult for him to see the “celebration” of human variety as a major ethical imperative.</p>
          <p>Moskal suspects that Blake’s concern with self-forgiveness gained emphasis from feelings of
guilt over his trial for sedition, when he was unable to acknowledge a vision that actually was, in some
sense, subversive. She also suspects that forgiveness appeared especially important to him because of his
conflicting feelings about William Hayley, a would-be benefactor for whom Blake had contempt (6-7, 86, 89).
Hayley was about as different from Blake as a person could be; Hayley’s otherness, viewed in close quarters,
would certainly be difficult to forgive. Moskal notices that in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Blake aims at
forgiving Hayley and ends up forgiving Milton, who was a good deal easier to forgive (94). Milton had the
intrapsychic advantage of seeming to resemble Blake himself much more closely than Hayley ever could.</p>
          <p>Moskal’s treatment of all these issues is well worth studying. Unfortunately, however, her book
is a much harder study than it needs to be. Like many other books on Blake, it gives no help to the general
reader and less help than it should to the specialist. If you think you may be interested in Blake’s ideas
about ethics but you don’t know what the Spectre of 
<pb id="p29-99" n="99"/>
Urthona is or how John Milton ever got involved with something called Ololon, you will not get far with this
book. If you do know these things, your progress will still be impeded by the author’s unnecessary summaries
and repetitions, her preference for wordy explanations of simple concepts (especially when those explanations
can be quoted from alleged authorities), her frequent resistance to putting the clearest evidence for an
hypothesis anywhere near the hypothesis itself, and her steady suppression of a sense of humor. In its
rhetoric, in other words, <hi rend="i">Blake, Ethics, and Forgiveness</hi> is a typical academic book, and
that is a pity.</p>
          <p>The book’s problems are not all stylistic and organizational. Some of Moskal’s intellectual
positions have not been thought through carefully enough. Consider, for example, one of her arguments about
“alterity.”</p>
          <p>Discussing the idea that Blake finds it easier to illustrate forgiveness between characters who
are alike than between characters who are different, she asserts that “he consistently (but not always)
excludes the more radical versions of alterity (sexual alterity, generational alterity, and human-divine
alterity) in order to clear the decks for a forgiveness between two versions of the same, for it is
forgivenesses between men (who are parts of One Man) that Blake considers normative” (106). Moskal’s point
about Blake’s treatment of otherness carries some force, but she is inclined to make it still more forceful
by reading such terms as “Man” and “brotherhood” as obvious synonyms for “males” and “male
relationships.” Granted, many of Blake’s attitudes toward women deserve criticism on ethical grounds, but
he cannot be interpreted fairly by the application of modern-American inclusive-language norms.</p>
          <p>Meanwhile, Moskal leaves several interesting aspects of the “alterity” issue unexplored.
Why, one might ask, is sexual or generational “alterity” necessarily more “alter” than other kinds of
“alterity”? Is it really true that the difference between males and females is harder for Blake to forgive
than the difference manifested by males who think in ways that he does not agree with? And, speaking of
differences among people, why did Blake write that “[i]t is easier to forgive an Enemy than to forgive a
Friend” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 91.1, E 251)? Moskal quotes this passage (103). We all quote it. But
why did he write it? What happens to the remark when it is put beside another hard saying, which Moskal also
quotes (142): “Friendship cannot exist without Forgiveness of Sins continually” 
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 52, E 201)? I’m not sure that any of us has an answer to this now, but it would be
interesting to have one, and it seems to lie in Moskal’s field of inquiry.</p>
          <p>Moskal’s analysis might also benefit from a more thorough exploration of the historical
relations of Blake’s ideas. In describing his historical context, she relies so heavily on the conventions
of Blake scholarship that a reader unfamiliar with those conventions might easily conclude that she had
forgotten what century he was born <corr type="emend">in. She</corr> refers, for example, to Blake’s
“contemporaries, the heterodox Ranters and other religious sects” (4). But didn’t such
“contemporaries” flourish a hundred years before Blake’s birth? Well, yes, but what Moskal calls “the
current consensus about Blake’s antinomianism” (4) positions him as close to those worthies as possible,
and this despite the fact that he never refers to them and in no sense required their influence—or the
influence of any of their eighteenth-century intellectual heirs—for the development of his ideas.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">2</ref> You don’t need to school yourself in an
antinomian tradition in order to become an antinomian; every age offers enough laws and commandments to rebel
against. And every age can find those interesting crossroads in the Pauline epistles where one can, if one
wishes, take an antinomian turn. <note id="n56"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The antinomians who may have influenced
Blake can be tracked through the scholarly literature from A. L. Morton’s <hi rend="i">The Everlasting
Gospel: A Study in the Sources of William Blake</hi> (London: Lawrence and Wishart, 1958)—a thin and thinly
argued book, still routinely cited as an authority—to E. P. Thompson’s vastly better informed 
<hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast: William Blake and the Moral Law</hi> (New York: The New Press, 1993); but
the quarry has never quite been captured. There are a good many cross-trails, too. “Antinomians” have a
way of getting mixed up with “millenarians,” or “radicals,” or opponents of “hegemony” (Thompson,
108-109), or people who simply had peculiar ideas. There is the optimistic sense, in this scholarly
literature, of an encounter with people who in one way or another <hi rend="i">might</hi> have influenced
Blake—provided, of course, he didn’t derive the influences in question directly from some more prominent
source, such as the Bible.</note></p>
          <p>Moskal argues that Blake finally rejects antinomianism, if antinomianism entails a conviction
that defiance of law is valuable in itself. Blake realized that such a position would simply be a reactive
concession to the significance of law. But what was Blake’s reaction to ethical ideas that, unlike
antinomianism, actually permeated his culture? Here Moskal discovers a curious view of the nature of
late-eighteenth-century ideas. The era, she believes,
<q>
was singularly arid in its exclusive emphasis on duty, obligation, and reason. Some of the eccentric twists in
Blake’s treatment of human forgiveness were caused historically, I think, by the domination of ethical
discourse in his time by theories of duty, obligation, and universal law over theories of sympathy and
benevolence. (4)
</q></p>
          <p>Surely, if there was ever a time when “sympathy” and “benevolence” were in vogue, it was
the later eighteenth century, which gave those moral concepts their typically modern forms and disseminated
them with all its might. Moskal is apparently operating in the old tradition of scholarship that sees Blake as
rebelling against “reason” and therefore projects an imperious cult of reason for him to rebel against.
She misses the fact that for the eighteenth century, sympathy and benevolence, and the “sensibility” in
which they were supposed to originate, were themselves a duty and an obligation.</p>
          <pb id="p29-100" n="100"/>
          <p>It is hard to overemphasize the impression, both favorable and unfavorable, that the ethic of
sensibility made on Blake.</p>
          <p>Blake could satirize sensibility as effectively as he satirized anything else:
<q>
[H]e saw that life liv’d upon death<lb/>
The Ox in the slaughter house moans<lb/>
The Dog at the wintry door[.]<lb/>
And he wept, &amp; he called it Pity<lb/>
And his tears flowed down on the winds.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> 23.27, 25.1-4, E 81-82)
</q></p>
          <p>Urizen’s tears are those of thwarted benevolence and futile sympathy. But sympathy and
benevolence are ethical values for Blake, too. The <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and the great prophetic works are
fully, if fractiously, at home in the beginning of the first historical era that was sympathetically concerned
and then morally indignant about poverty, slavery, and the oppression of women.</p>
          <p>There is a tendency in Blake scholarship to prefer the radical affiliation or influence to the
bourgeois-liberal one, to emphasize the Ranters, say, rather than the preachers of sympathy and sensibility.
Moskal follows this tendency, unaware of the fact that some of her own ideas are similar to those of the
late-eighteenth-century liberal moralists. Describing the process of forgiveness, she says:
<q>
When we see the other, who has offended us, as a suffering human being, we project outward our own experience
of suffering, an experience that we know intimately only when it is our own suffering, onto the other. Then we
feel compassion for him as for ourselves. (9; see also 117)
</q></p>
          <p>This passage reflects Moskal’s own thinking, inspired by remarks of Hannah Arendt and Reinhold
Niebuhr. It could also pass for an outline of Adam Smith’s argument, in his <hi rend="i">Theory of Moral
Sentiments</hi>, about the mechanism of compassion. It is certainly more useful than most of the passages
Moskal cites from her long list of twentieth-century authorities (besides Arendt and Niebuhr, the list
includes Martin Buber, Martin Heidegger, Alasdair MacIntyre, Luce Irigaray, Emmanuel Levinas, and others). It
is useful because it identifies the problematic nature of the moral act with which Moskal is most concerned:
the act of forgiving other people without losing a sharp sense that they are, in fact, <hi rend="i">other
people.</hi></p>
          <p>Let me explain. Moskal is bothered (as Blake was) by ethical codes that neglect the individuality
of the persons involved with them. She therefore derives her “basic definition of forgiveness” from
Arendt’s statement that “<hi rend="i">what</hi> was done is forgiven for the sake of <hi rend="i">who</hi>
did it”; the idea, as Moskal says, is that “forgiveness establishes an eminently personal relationship”
(7). Moskal is attracted, in addition, to the far less perspicuous comments of Levinas, who writes about
“redefining the other as exterior and excessive, ‘a form of exteriority, separate from and unpredicted by
the subject,’ and ‘the site of excess, an unabsorbable, indigestible residue the subject is unable to
assimilate to itself’” (105). This says nothing, however, about how we can establish an eminently personal
relationship with the “exteriority” of all those people whom we are supposed to know and forgive but with
whom we try to sympathize through the medium of our own experience, an experience that we imaginatively
“project outward . . . onto the other.”</p>
          <p>Adam Smith saw the difficulty with this approach. Imaginative projection has its limitations:
<q>
As we have no immediate experience of what other men feel, we can form no idea of the manner in which they are
affected, but by conceiving what we ourselves should feel in the like situation. Though our brother is upon
the rack, as long as we ourselves are at our ease, our senses will never inform us of what he suffers. They
never did, and never can, carry us beyond our own person, and it is by the imagination only that we can form
any conception of what are his sensations. Neither can that faculty help us to this any other way, than by
representing to us what would be our own, if we were in his case.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Adam Smith, <hi rend="i">The Theory of Moral Sentiments</hi>, ed. D. D.
Raphael and A. L. Macfie (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1976) 9.</note></q></p>
          <p>It is quite possible, as any good late-eighteenth century moralist (or novelist) can tell you,
that when I think I am sympathizing with you, I am actually just imagining how I would feel 
<hi rend="i">if</hi> I <hi rend="i">were</hi> you.</p>
          <p>Blake saw this difficulty. He embodied it in his characters. Urizen is a good example: he thinks
that all the other Eternals suffer as he does and that they should therefore submit to his special treatments
of “love” and “forgiveness”:
<q>
Why will you die O Eternals?<lb/>
Why live in unquenchable burnings?<lb/>
..............................<lb/>
Lo! I unfold my darkness: and on<lb/>
This rock, place with strong hand the Book<lb/>
Of eternal brass, written in my solitude.<lb/>
<lb/>
Laws of peace, of love, of unity:<lb/>
Of pity, compassion, forgiveness.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> 4.12-13, 31-35, E 71-72)
</q></p>
          <p>Blake’s symbolism offered him a chance to escape the limitations of projective emotional
sympathy. It offered him a chance to transcend his narrowly personal experience so as to see the great world
beyond and try to forgive it. Every “alterity” could, at least theoretically, be expressed in symbols and
make itself determinately known, both to his audience
<pb id="p29-101" n="101"/>
(if any) and to himself. Yet the symbolism that emerged was all too clearly the projection of an
extraordinarily powerful mind’s own priorities upon all “others.” Real, recognizably living “others”
are so scarce in Blake’s work that Moskal, looking assiduously for one such other, can produce none more
“powerfully individualized” than Milton, in Blake’s poem of that name (135). And even this claim may not
carry much weight; Blake’s Milton speaks as Blake would presumably speak and acts as Blake would presumably
act under the various circumstances that Blake creates for him.</p>
          <p>Blake’s ability to create a universal symbolism permits him to imagine everyone at last
“put[ting] off by forgiveness, every sin,” in Albion’s reunion with Jesus (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
96.19, E 255). Moskal believes, however, that it also permits Blake to “minimize or deny altogether the
intractable otherness,” the individuality, of the people by whom forgiveness is achieved (10).</p>
          <p>She has a point. Blake’s symbolic forgiveness of his characters is often far from what Smith or
Arendt or anyone else would regard as forgiveness of living, breathing, individual people. It is not the kind
of forgiveness that Blake seems to request for himself when he addresses the readers of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Here he is interested in a personal relationship, with Jesus and with his audience:
<q>
I am perhaps the most sinful of men! I pretend not to holiness! yet I pretend to love, to see, to converse
with daily, as man with man, &amp; the more to have an interest in the Friend of Sinners. Therefore [Dear]
Reader, [forgive] what you do not approve, &amp; [love] me for this energetic exertion of my talent. 
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 3, E 145)
</q></p>
          <p>As Moskal observes, Blake begs his audience to forgive him, while deftly implying that he has the
moral standing to forgive his audience (95). And there is a universalizing tendency even here. The audience
is, potentially, everyone, all the members of Albion, the universal form, who neglected him, tried him for
sedition, accused him of madness, and committed even worse sins against its own soul. Forgiving “Albion”
was difficult. From the passage quoted above, Blake removed the words in brackets. His audience wasn’t
necessarily “Dear,” and it wouldn’t necessarily “love” and “forgive” him in return for his own
offers of forgiveness. But forgiving Albion as a whole was much easier for Blake than forgiving some of the
individual persons of whom Albion was composed.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, Blake’s willingness to universalize comes off a good deal worse, in Moskal’s
analysis, than it deserves to do. She is worried not only about his universalizing symbolism but also about
its connection with a universal “ethics of obligation,” especially of the kind recommended by
Christianity; and she is worried about this despite the fact that a sense of moral obligation, based on
principles considered universally applicable, would appear to offer Blake another, quite promising means of
transcending “the selfhood” and forgiving other people.</p>
          <p>Blake’s Jesus recognizes the difficulty of forgiveness and love; he declares that “every
kindness to another is a little Death.” Still, he says, Man can only “exist . . . by Brotherhood” 
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 96.27-28, E 256). It’s hard, but it’s an ethical imperative for everyone. Moskal,
however, seems to see Christianity’s universal ethic as something that necessarily reduced Blake’s regard
for the individuality of other people. She argues that in his early writings he attacked conventional notions
of moral duty, exalting “contrariety” over the “universalizability” of moral precepts; but in his
later, essentially Christian works, he “in a sense, defected, by practicing a version of the fault in
obligation-based ethics that he earlier deplored—that is, its emphasis on the universalized individual”
(9). She implies that no ethics of obligation can provide a fair treatment of “alterity.”</p>
          <p>This is a currently fashionable and superficially plausible assumption, but it is an assumption
that undermines the very idea of ethics. The truth, in plain terms, is that there is no ethics that is not an
ethics of obligation. Ethics does not merely describe all the things that various people are inclined to do;
it prescribes what they ought to do, whether or not they are inclined to do it. An ethics without an
“ought”—without a sense of obligation—would simply lack the distinctive quality of ethics. It would be
scrambled eggs without the eggs.</p>
          <p>Almost as hard to imagine is an ethics that excludes any reference to universally applicable
ideas. Such an ethics would hardly be able to provide a coherent reason for its particular prescriptions; it
would be a collection of double, triple, or multiple “standards.” Adapt ethics as much as you like to
individuality or (to use the Blakean term that Moskal prefers) “contrariety”; declare as loudly as you
like that “One Law for the Lion &amp; Ox is Oppression” (<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
24, E 44); the sense of universal obligation remains, if only in the implication that all people, whoever they
are, ought to respect individual freedom and refrain from imposing one law on both the lion and the ox. When
we judge Blake as unfair to the individual human objects who get swept up in his universalizing symbolism, we
judge him against a universal principle, a presumed obligation to show regard for individual differences of
character.</p>
          <p>Ethical relativists may pursue their line of reasoning to the boundaries of paradox, and beyond,
without ever being able to lose the sense of obligation that inheres in the basic concept of ethics. Even
orthodox and dogmatic moralists, however, ordinarily recognize the fact that fundamental moral obligations
need to be fulfilled in different ways by different individuals. Jesus preached generosity and simplicity as
general principles, but he did not tell everyone he met, “Sell all that thou hast, and distribute unto the
poor” (Luke 18:22).</p>
          <pb id="p29-102" n="102"/>
          <p>A universal ethics of obligation may actually promote fair play for “alterity” by insisting
that everyone, no matter how “other,” is on the same moral footing. Blake’s contemporary, the novelist
Elizabeth Hamilton, made this point when she had one of her characters remark that Jesus was the first
philosopher who taught respect for women, because he preached a truly universal ethic, one that decreed no
special moral rules for women:
<q>
Women, we learn from the gospels, frequently composed a great part of his audience: but to them no particular
precepts were addressed, no sexual virtues recommended....His morality was addressed to the judgment without
distinction of sex. His laws went not to fix the boundaries of prerogative, and to prescribe the minutiae of
behaviour, but to fix purity and humility in the heart.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Elizabeth Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Memoris of Modern Philosophers</hi>
(1800; rpt. New York: Garland, 1974) I:199-200.</note></q></p>
          <p>Blake’s Christianity may not have prompted him to worry very much about other people’s
“unabsorbable, indigestible residue”; but neither did it prompt him to prescribe the minutiae of their
behavior. He thought that the commandment to love and forgive other people implied a commandment to let them
be free: “Jerusalem is called Liberty among the Children of Albion” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 54.5, E
203). Liberty was grounded on moral principles that could be recommended to everyone.</p>
          <p>The complexities of this kind of Christianity are not quite captured by Moskal’s reference to
Blake’s Jesus as “an alternative way of looking at the moral life from the grid of obligations and duties
used by promulgators of universal laws” (32). Still less helpful is Moskal’s characterization, derived
from Stanley Hauerwas, of ethics as it is ordinarily understood: “in its emphasis on duty and obligation as
they pertain to all individuals interchangeably, the standard account [of ethics] alienates each individual
from his plans, metaphors, and stories” (2).</p>
          <p>Moskal tends to measure Blake’s success as an ethicist by his (imperfect) success in forming
ethical conceptions that escape the terms of the “standard account.” But her idea of the “standard
account” is needlessly reductive. The notion that people are morally obligated, for instance, to love their
neighbors as themselves doesn’t imply that they have to alienate themselves from their own plans, metaphors,
and stories; it doesn’t even imply that they have to <hi rend="i">like</hi> their neighbors. (Indeed,
one’s sense of the neighbors’ otherness will probably be sharpened considerably by one’s sense of an
obligation to forgive them.) Every great system of belief associates its ethic of obligation with a rich
variety of metaphors, stories, and plans of life. This richness is surely one of the reasons for Blake’s
attraction to Christianity and for his ability to adapt its ethical narratives and metaphors to his own
literary and intellectual plans.</p>
          <p>It is regrettable that Moskal brings current intellectual assumptions to bear on Blake without
subjecting them to the kind of criticism to which she subjects his own ideas. In this respect, however, she is
by no means unusual; few contemporary critics interrogate their framework assumptions as skeptically as they
interrogate their primary texts. Moskal’s subject, however, is of unusual interest, and what she says about
it is also of unusual interest, both for its own sake and for its ability to provoke debate.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
