<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Rare Group of Early Twentieth-Century Watercolors by a Follower of
          William Blake</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <pb id="p29-76" n="76"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Rare Group of Early Twentieth-Century Watercolors by a Follower of
              William Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>One of the most extraordinary examples of the influence of William Blake on an English
            artist working in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries was demonstrated by
            a group of watercolors sold at Christie’s in November 1994.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Paradoxically, the most noticeable feature of these
watercolors was their
            totally un-Blakean style, derived from G. F. Watts and through him Titian and Rubens.
              <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Fine Victorian Pictures, Drawings and
                Watercolours</hi>, Christie’s 4 November 1994, lots 56-64, with two additional works
              by Stock, lots 66 and 68, all illustrated, all in color except lot 66. The information
              in this article is mainly derived from the introductory note on pp. 42-43 of the
              Christie’s catalogue.</note></p>
          <p>The painter of these watercolors was Henry John Stock (1853-1930). Born like Blake in
            Soho, London he made a somewhat unusual start as an artist by going blind in childhood
            but recovered his sight on going to live at Beaulieu in the New Forest. Fully recovered,
            he studied at the St. Martin’s School of Art and at the Royal Academy Schools and was
            befriended by the engraver W. J. Linton, who, perhaps significantly, had engraved the
            illustrations to Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 1863. He exhibited
            at the Royal Academy between 1874 and 1910 and also at the Royal Institute of Painters
            in Water Colours, becoming a member in 1881, as well as at commercial galleries such as
            the Fine Arts Society. During the first half of his career he mainly painted portraits,
            often of upper class and fashionable sitters as in the group of portraits in the fancy
            dress worn at the Devonshire House Ball of 1897. However, later in his life he
            concentrated more on subject paintings and in 1909 moved to Felpham, with all its
            associations with William Blake.</p>
          <p>His subject pictures included a number on musical themes such as <hi rend="i">A
              Musician’s Reverie</hi> of 1888, <hi rend="i">Listening to Brahms</hi>, 1901, and 
              <hi rend="i">In the Night—Schumann</hi> of which he exhibited three versions between 1908
            and 1927. He also illustrated the Bible and literature including Shakespeare,
            Wordsworth, Coleridge, Goethe, Browning, William Morris and Walt Whitman, and, in a more
            Blakean context, Dante. Closer to Victorian genre were the painting of <hi rend="i">The
              Kiss</hi> and a related drawing, dated 1894 and 1891 respectively, also included in
            the Christie’s sale.</p>
          <p>The unprecedented group of works sold at Christie’s was however more noticeable for the
            10 watercolors of imaginative <figure n="StockAngel.29.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="713">
              <head>1 Henry John Stock (1853-1930), <hi rend="i">The Angel standing in the Sun</hi>,
                pencil and watercolor heightened with body color and touches of white, 33.3 ×
                23.2cm., signed and dated 1910, sold Christie’s 4 November 1994, Lot 61.</head>
            </figure> subjects. These included one subject close to Watts, <hi rend="i">Pain
              bringing Wings to a Soul</hi>, signed and dated 1900, and an illustration to Dante’s
              <hi rend="i">Inferno, Dante and Virgil encounter Lucifer in Hell</hi> of 1923. More
            specifically Blakean were the eight illustrations to the Book of Revelation: 
              <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi>, 1902, “<hi rend="i">And I saw a Star fall from
              Heaven</hi>,” 1902, <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Woman clothed with the
              Sun</hi>, 1902, <hi rend="i">The Beast cast into the Lake of Fire</hi>, 1904, 
              <hi rend="i">The Angel standing in the Sun</hi>, 1910, “<hi rend="i">And the Moon became
              as Blood</hi>,” 1910, <hi rend="i">The Four and Twenty Elders</hi>, 1911, and 
              “<hi rend="i">God shall wipe away all Tears from their Eyes</hi>,” 1912. Some of the
            compositions, such as <hi rend="i">The Angel standing in the Sun</hi> (illus. 1) and 
              <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Woman clothed with the Sun</hi> are Blakean at
            least in their airborne figures and spiral compositions. All however are painted in a
            manner far from the linear, crystaline style of William Blake, a manner of rich textures
            and blurred outlines derived from Watts. The obese figure of <hi rend="i">The Beast cast
              into the Lake of Fire</hi> (illus. 2) is Rubensian in its fleshiness and
            substance.</p>
          <pb id="p29-77" n="77"/>
          <figure n="StockBeast.29.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="732">
            <head>2 Henry John Stock (1853-1930), <hi rend="i">The Beast cast into the Lake of
                Fire</hi>, pencil and watercolor heightened with body color, 33.3 × 23.2 cm., signed
              and dated 1904, sold Christie’s 4 November 1994, Lot 60.</head>
          </figure>
          <p>A further link with William Blake, and perhaps at least a partial explanation for this
            paradoxical illustration of Blakean subjects in totally un-Blakean style, was the
            commissioner of these watercolors, Francis P. Osmaston (1857-1925), an accomplished
            musician and author (including a translation of Hegel’s <hi rend="i">Philosophy of Fine
              Art</hi> and two books on Tintoretto) and a patron of many struggling painters of his
            time. Osmaston owned a number of works by Blake: a copy of <hi rend="i">The Book of
              Thel</hi> and a color-printed copy of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
              Hell</hi>, together with three individual works, the watercolor of <hi rend="i">Christ
              raising the Son of the Widow of Nain</hi>, the tempera <hi rend="i">Bathsheba at the
              Bath</hi> and the color-printed <hi rend="i">Dream of Thiralatha</hi> (Butlin nos.
            483, 390 and 267 respectively). It is possible that the textures of the color-printed
            works and the tempera may have helped to justify Stock in his combination of Blakean
            subjects and un-Blakean richness of effect.</p>
          <p>The Blakean watercolors were sold for prices ranging from £1,100 to £5,500 with the
            exception of the perhaps overly porcine <hi rend="i">Beast cast into the Lake of
              Fire</hi> which was bought in.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
