<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.linkin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Molly Anne Rothenberg, Rethinking Blake’s Textuality</title>
        <author n="Linkin">Harriet Linkin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
	<pb id="p29-92" n="92"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Molly Anne Rothenberg, <hi rend="i">Rethinking Blake’s Textuality.</hi>
Columbia and London: University of Missouri Press, 1993. $34.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Harriet <name>Linkin</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Given the deconstructive approach Molly Anne Rothenberg takes in her informed discussion of
Blake’s textuality, her first sentence appropriately points to a gap: “In the past decade a gap has opened
up in Blake studies between commentators who continue to read Blake’s poetry as a <hi rend="i">work</hi> and
those who read it as a <hi rend="i">text</hi>, to use Roland Barthes’ distinction” (1). While this gap
still looms in some critical circles, it is no longer the most telling one in Blake studies or other fields of
literary analysis, where the greater gulf that divides the deconstructive approaches of the 70s and 80s from
the new historical/cultural-materialist approaches of the 80s and 90s now provokes alternate readings of
literary works as <hi rend="i">texts</hi> or <hi rend="i">sites. Rethinking Blake’s Textuality</hi> makes an
admirable effort to bridge this gulf by demonstrating how Blake as “poststructuralist” responds to and
critiques the late eighteenth-century philosophical assumptions that subsequently shape twentieth-century
schools of thought. Rothenberg distinguishes her project from comparable endeavors to locate poststructuralist
tenets in Blake’s texts by looking at contemporary documents Blake would have known to historicize what she
defines as his position: “Like the chaos theory of present-day science, Blake’s philosophical inquiry into
the conditions by which texts/subjects/objects are constituted as meaningful subverts linear and totalizing
rationality” (2).</p>
          <p>The introduction carefully situates Rothenberg’s work in the school of Blake criticism most
congenial to her approach, that practiced by Nelson Hilton, Thomas Vogler, Donald Ault, Paul Mann, and Jerome
McGann.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">1</ref> Her contribution seeks to
provide for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> what Ault furnishes for <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, though in
less “exhaustively minute” a fashion, offering close readings of local examples from 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to reveal the poem’s strategic subversion of all absolutisms instituted
<pb id="p29-93" n="93"/>
by the Enlightenment’s project of rationalization. She rightly cautions that we not view the sources
introduced (such as Alexander Geddes, Thomas Gray, or F. A. Nitsch) as authorities who stabilize meaning but
rather as participants in a discursive arena. She also asserts we need not read Blake’s poem (or be overly
familiar with Blake scholarship) to follow her argument, which strikes me as unfortunate, as then we must rely
on her authority, but she means, of course, to underscore her own non-reading:
<q>
Ultimately, then, my argument seeks to make a contribution to contemporary poststructuralist thought as it
engages questions of agency and political implication by means of a reading of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
rather than to proffer an “interpretation” of the poem or an account of what Blake actually intended. (4)
</q>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The text itself, however, most frequently refers to Leslie Tannenbaum,
Joseph Wittreich, Leopold Damrosch, and Peter Otto, as if without these Bacon Newton Locke contraries there is
no progression.</note></p>
          <p>This statement is followed by one that insists Blake is neither an advocate of liberationist
politics nor a prophet of utopian Christian fellowship, and that Blake critics should recognize how Blake
rejects all such positions:
<q>
critics who claim that Blake aims to redeem human society through the transformation of the consciousnesses of
individual readers have not taken into account Blake’s analysis of the evils produced by utopianism and have
misunderstood his evaluations of “possessive selfhood.” (4)
</q></p>
          <p>Despite the series of caveats, such statements do require authority to pass judgment (and veer
into the quicksand that fills the pit of intentionality).</p>
          <p>Rather than back away from the edge, Rothenberg ventures further out: “So I part company with
most Blake scholars, including many poststructuralist critics of Blake, who insist that Blake wishes to give
his readers access to a transcendental realm” (4). Whether or not this oppositional framing of her position
indicates true friendship or an overdetermined gesture, she casts her challenge with a reckless defiance I
respect, despite my own desire to part company at this juncture as just such a critic; time and again I
resisted this book, which I view as a measure of its value. All the more courageous that she follows this
assertion with a repudiation of her own previously published self in the best Blakean mode of casting out
error.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">2</ref> Most important of all is her
stipulating that she is only looking at <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to showcase Blake’s refusal of all
authorities, even those we liberally think of as “good.” One question never addressed, however, is this:
if she is not reading <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> but offering methodology, does she mean us to extend her
argument to all of Blake’s texts? And does such extension effect a totalizing absolutism? 
<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Of the three longer sections that rework material from articles published in <hi rend="i">Word
and Image</hi> (1987), and <hi rend="i">Genre</hi> (1990), two now arrive at different conclusions.</note></p>
          <p>The argument itself opens with a quote from <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (on
Milton as “a true Poet and of the Devils party without knowing it” E 35) to establish that “the
distinguishing characteristic of true Poets is their ignorance of the source and authority of their work”
(9). So too <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> on the matter of authority and origin, where Rothenberg points to
Blake’s typical narrative deflections to show his constructive problematizing of authority: Blake’s
preface claims the poem was dictated, a narrative voice identifies the savior dictating a song, the narrator
says a theme calls him, and the text’s last words identify some or all of the preceding as a song of
Jerusalem, which recursively complicates the preface’s discussion of tone and stylistic choice. More
innovative than the insightful display of narrativity is the instructive turn to historicized religious and
philosophical debates. She outlines the significance contemporary biblical criticism holds for Blake, when the
basis for scriptural authenticity shifts from prophetic truth guaranteed by divine revelation to inspired
interpretation marked by artful construction. Once Higher Criticism conjoins inspiration with rhetorical
strategies, Blake sees “the Bible [as] a historical record of the means by which ‘sacred’ texts are
constructed to oppress” (18). Rothenberg draws usefully and generously from prior arguments and primary
sources offered by Tannenbaum, Wittreich, and McGann to document Blake’s familiarity with Higher
Criticism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">3</ref> The strength of her
analysis manifests more powerfully in her own inspired interpretations, such as the lively reading of Matthew
on Jesus’s authority, where the parable of the sheep and goats assists Blake’s theory of authorship by
undercutting the idea of totalizing authority, because the parable authorizes a kind of individual
participatory interpretation that unfixes universal authority. <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">3</hi> I find it
troubling that some primary materials are cited from secondary sources, such as Wittreich citing Pareus or
Newton (25), or Tannenbaum citing Howes (22-23); while the bibliography does offer a primary source for Howes,
none such is proffered for Newton or Pareus. As I give voice to my pedantic spectre, I will add that the
bibliography not only contains erros (Thomas Frosch is renamed “Douglas”) but also cites far too many
works that receive no mention in or appear to have an impact on the text. Most works cited date from 1987 or
earlier (except for Peter Otto’s 1991 <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision and Visionary Deconstruction</hi> and
Katherine Hayles’s 1990 <hi rend="i">Chaos Bound: Entropy, Information and Complexity in Contemporary
Literature</hi>); one cannot help but wonder what effect Robert Essick’s 1989 <hi rend="i">William Blake and
the Language of Adam</hi> or Vincent De Luca’s 1991 <hi rend="i">Words of Eternity</hi> might have
had.</note></p>
          <p>Blake rejects the guarantee of transcendent authority to authenticate interpretation as well as
the Dissenter belief in an immanent experience of God’s intention through the individual’s perceptual
faculties; instead,
<q>
the individual can learn to perceive the mediations that make perceptions seem not only natural and unmediated
but possible at all . . . . that perception <hi rend="i">could not</hi>
	<pb id="p29-94" n="94"/>
	<hi rend="i">take place</hi> without the prior mediation of ideologically constituted interpretations—in
effect, that all perception traces the lineaments of its constitutive ideological assumptions—provides the
key to Blakean textuality. (37)
</q></p>
          <p>Even so fine a critic as Northrop Frye fails to understand how ideological interpretation effects
perception when he designates Blake’s Hallelujah-Chorus perception of the sun as more imaginative than the
duller seeing of the sun as like a guinea: for Rothenberg (and Otto), both heavenly host and lowly guinea
establish metaphoric comparisons that emanate from ideological systems (44). While Blake views perception as
ideological interpretation, he never loses sight of his bounding line’s essentializing capacity to create
form. Rothenberg’s excellent exposition of several techniques Blake employs to disrupt his bounding line’s
potential for authorizing absolutisms, via punctuation, for instance, or intertextuality, brings the first of
the book’s two parts to conclusion. Part One/De-Signing Authority (9-61) focuses most carefully on Blake’s
projection of himself as inspired author in terms of changing definitions of inspiration and scriptural
authenticity, so that Blake’s intertextual citations of Gray’s “The Bard” reflect on scriptural
authors who establish assumptive authenticity through citation.</p>
          <p>Part Two/The Subject of Discourse (65-137) situates Blake’s subversive tactics among such
architects of thought as Augustine, Kant, Husserl and Hume to consider how Blake undermines the totalizing
effects of hermeneutics, epistemology, phenomenology, typology, and narrativity. A comparison of Blake and
Augustine suggests “Blake’s practice is Augustine’s without God” (65) functioning as guarantor of
transcendental signification to stabilize meaning. Rothenberg’s elegant discussion of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s opening as demonstration contends that most Blake criticism traditionally reads
the scene as a dialogue between a savior and Albion, whereas local textual disruptions show the potentiality
of multiple vantage points. More specific attention to other readers of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> might have
substantiated this broad claim in helpful ways. As Augustine, so Kant: Blake affirms the “Kantian insight
that mind resembles world because mind constitutes world” (82) but whereas Kant fends off charges of
solipsism through a “turn to transcendent subjectivity and universal moral laws” (82-83), Blake presents a
discursive formation of mind that produces transformative subjectivity. Rothenberg’s treatment of plate 97
to evidence transformative subjectivity displays her fine critical imagination at work in identifying the
plate as a scene of reading the viewer reads, with variant light sources that both suggest and offset
centralized perspective: “The plate thematizes and dramatizes the necessity for a continual movement of
displacement in order to subvert the bid for ultimate determinacy that attends the centralized subject’s
repression of its own limitations” (96).</p>
          <p>Another superior local reading shows how typology’s defense against the solipsism of
phenomenalism employs “Augustinian tropological strategies to interpret Christ’s life as the 
<hi rend="i">forma perfecta</hi> of every life” (98) but thereby depends on circular reasoning, when Rothenberg
looks at plates 61-62 for the story of Joseph and Mary told to Jerusalem as a means of her understanding
herself (even as Jerusalem’s story serves as paradigm for Joseph and Mary). Jerusalem not only sees the
tautology of typological configuration, but also the range of types available that might supply and thereby
destabilize meaning: “In biblical typology the value of the event proposed as the paradigm is known in
advance, while in Blake’s view that value changes with each reader, with each context” (106). The
individual’s seeming dependence on memory for personal identity is equally fictive or narrativized, as the
two “authorized” locations for plate 29/33 suggest in undermining the referent for the opening identity
pronoun “He.” Rothenberg begins the kind of “exhaustive” but playful reading of indeterminacies that
brings out the best in Hilton, Ault and Vogler to demonstrate the sorts of tautologies or complex circular
reasonings that effect narrative causalities: “The ‘authority’ of the voice requires that ‘causes,’
which are in fact a product of the activity of the authoritative voice, appear to predate the narrative”
(124).</p>
          <p>These few important close readings beautifully ground Rothenberg’s astute but sometimes
theory-thick discussion of philosophical and religious contemporary contexts to compensate for whatever
imperfections the book contains. Perhaps I betray my own hopeless desire for meaning when I confess what I
would like from Rothenberg is an extended reading of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that displays her sound
method at work, decoding and recoding Blake’s complex textual subversions of authority. She is indeed a
sensitive “Reader! [lover] of books!” whose interpretive focus would bring us further along the road of
understanding, even or especially a nontotalizing one, as we come to understand how Blake’s textuality
exposes the search for mastery as 
<q>
a narrative of “errors”: this is the “story” of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> At any moment in the
search, the reading subject can acknowledge the structure of what it has produced, a structure that
articulates disjunct, incommensurable, or competing systems as though they derive from a transcendental
subject and form a coherent totality. (132)
</q></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
