<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.lincoln</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">George Anthony Rosso, Jr., Blake’s Prophetic Workshop: A Study of The Four
Zoas</title>
        <author n="Lincoln">Andrew Lincoln</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0006">
        <pb id="p29-95" n="95"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">George Anthony Rosso, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Workshop: A Study
of</hi> The Four Zoas. Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press; London and Toronto: Associated University
Presses, 1993. 208 pp., 9 pls. $36.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Andrew <name>Lincoln</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>This is the first extensive study of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> to relate the prophetic form
of the narrative methodically to developments in the mainstream of eighteenth-century British and European
culture. Rosso argues that the contending strands of Blake’s narrative embody the divisions of a culture and
society “adrift in a world without economic or transcendental guarantees.” His study identifies two areas
of contemporary thought as having special relevance: the struggle between biblical and scientific models of
creation in the religious poetry of the eighteenth century; and the Enlightenment critique of the Bible’s
prefigurative form and language. It treats these two areas separately, moving in each case from a general
discussion of the historical context to a detailed reading of the narrative.</p>
          <p>Rosso’s exploration of the first area focuses on the long poem of eighteenth-century Christian
apologetics, which he sees as a “neglected but seminal” field for the study of Blake’s poem. In a survey
which includes Thomson’s <hi rend="i">The Seasons</hi>, Pope’s <hi rend="i">Essay on Man</hi>, and
Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, he considers the importance of the Newtonian cosmology in the
poets’ theology, and briefly identifies some of the developments that “put eighteenth-century apologetics
on the road to the internalized creation of Blake and the Romantic poets” (in particular Lowth’s study of
the poetics of biblical prophecy, and Alexander Geddes’s account of Genesis as a “composite” text).
Blake, writing in the wake of these and other (less clearly identified) factors, inherited “a cosmological
system in collapse.” Accordingly, he adopts the biblical cosmology as his model but “problematizes his
source, repeating the Creation in various frames, depicting it from multiple perspectives, to indicate its
‘fallen,’ i.e., time-bound status.”</p>
          <p>In examining the second area, Rosso outlines a history of “the crucial seventeenth- and
eighteenth-century religious debates that shape Blake’s use of biblical typology.” The survey considers
the pressure exerted on the prefigurative language of the Bible by figures such as Bayle and the English
Deists, and then touches on the responses of those who defended and modified typology, including antiquarians
(such as William Stukeley and Jacob Bryant) and the German “higher critics.” In Rosso’s view, Blake
resembles his German contemporaries (notably Herder) who “avoid reducing history to the empirical by raising
the fact-claim of an event into the higher category of <hi rend="i">understanding.</hi>” Since the
“fact-claim” is transformed rather than abandoned, an “emphasis on historical actuality remains crucial
to Blake,” whose narrative at times closely follows the linear development of biblical history (so that, for
example, the temple building in Night II “ranges over Old Testament history from the rise of monarchy to
Solomon’s reign, roughly the period from 1200 to 900 B.C.”). But although this linear development is
discernable, the narrative is actually a “simulacrum of sequence,” because “typological repetition
neutralizes chronology and abandons causal links between events in favor of repeated type scenes.” Such
repetitions are part of “Blake’s strategy for approximating simultaneity in his narrative.” And so at
one point Jerusalem may represent “not only the biblical Jerusalem of 1000 B.C. and, perhaps, 70 A.D., but
also the contemporary eighteenth-century ‘heavenly city’ to be built among England’s dark satanic
mills.” Past events are presented so as “to trigger their typical or figural meaning,” activating the
past “through the <hi rend="i">kerygmatic</hi> or transactive nature of prophetic rhetoric: readers must
‘witness’ the intrusion of spiritual agency within the text, within their own lives, and within
history.”</p>
          <p>This view of the poem’s method clearly determines Rosso’s view of its conclusion:
“Blake’s hope is that, once his audience (re)learns to read history figuratively, the power of Rahab, or
the whole system of natural religion, will self-destruct”—an event shown in the conclusion of Night VIII.
In Night IX, accordingly, the representations of violence lose something of their actuality, since Blake
continually emphasizes their symbolic nature, “translating the literal war of nations into a war of
contending perspectives.” It is an interpretation that seems to hand history over almost entirely to the
process of writing and reading.</p>
          <p>Rosso is theoretically informed, and handles complicated ideas deftly. Few who read his account
of his chosen contexts will doubt their general relevance to Blake’s poem. But some of the assumptions and
methods involved seem questionable. The long poem that he cites as “seminal” does not assume as much
importance in his detailed reading as we are led to expect, in spite of a determined attempt to establish the
“generic relation” of Blake’s narratives’ “to the graveyard tradition of Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” Perhaps this is not really surprising, given the manifestly encyclopedic
nature of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> The discussion of biblical typology is developed with considerable
subtlety—but the comparison with the higher critics seems to me pressed too hard. Against Rosso’s claim
that in approaching the Bible an “emphasis on historical actuality remains crucial to Blake,” one might
set some of Blake’s own comments:
<q>
If Moses did not write the history of his acts. it takes away the authority altogether it ceases to be history
&amp; becomes a Poem of probable impossibilities fabricated for pleasure as moderns say but I say by
Inspiration (E 616). I cannot concieve the Divinity of the . . . Bible to consist . . . in the historical
evidence which may be all
<pb id="p29-96" n="96"/>
false in the eyes of one man &amp; true in the eyes of another. (E 618)
</q></p>
          <p>The statements will no doubt bear more than one interpretation. To me they don’t suggest a need
to emphasize “historical actuality” in order to transform it; instead they suggest that the
“fact-claim” of the Bible is an irrelevance. They seem to undermine, that is, one of the foundations on
which Rosso has based his reading.</p>
          <p>There will always be differences of opinion about such statements, and about the most rewarding
way of reading Blake’s narratives (let’s hope so). One of the agreeable features of Rosso’s book is its
flexibility and tolerance of other views. The flexibility of his method appears in his adaptation of, among
other things, Northrop Frye’s theory of the “Orc cycle,” Jackie DiSalvo’s application of the social
history of Old Testament culture, and David Erdman’s method of relating the poem to contemporary events.
Apart from this incidental introduction to the larger field of <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> criticism,
Rosso’s book has other features that will make it useful to new readers. It begins with a lucid explanation
of the special problems associated with the manuscript; it provides a succinct account of the critical
reception of the poem; it ends with a brief commentary on the drawings. It is a study which makes Blake’s
narrative seem less eccentric, more clearly of its time, and in doing so it should help readers to make up
their own minds about Blake’s visions of creation and history.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
