<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.browne</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Blake Source for von Holst</title>
        <author n="Browne">Max Browne</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0005">
        <div2>
          <pb id="p29-78" n="78"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Blake Source for von Holst</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Max <name>Browne</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>An important sheet of figure drawings by the English romantic painter Theodor von Holst
            (1810-44) has recently come to light to reveal Blake as a stronger iconographic source
            for Fuseli’s pupil than has previously been evident and hence further confirm Dante
            Gabriel Rossetti’s view of Holst; “. . . in many of whose most characteristic works the
            influence of Blake, as well as that of Fuseli, has probably been felt.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
              type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Supplementary chapter 39 in A.
              Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 1863, 1: 379. Rossetti was Holst’s
              greatest admirer and the inclusion of this short account of his one-time hero was both
              testimony to the romantic sympathy that he felt with Holst’s work and the importance
              that he placed on his role as a disciple of the earlier generation of romantic
              artists.</note></p>
          <p>As with Fuseli and Rossetti, Holst’s family background was also rooted in continental
            Europe. His father, Matthias von Holst, had been a professor of music and taught members
            of the imperial family in St. Petersburg. He returned to Riga with his young Russian
            wife but, amidst the upheavals of the Napoleonic wars, found that his political ideas
            had become so unwelcome that he was forced to flee with his family and they settled in
            London in 1807. Theodor was born there three years later and by the age of 10 his
            prodigious talent for drawing had attracted the attention of both Fuseli and Sir Thomas
            Lawrence, who was later criticized for leading Holst astray with commissions for erotic
            drawings of which several were destined for the portfolios of King George IV.</p>
          <corr type="emend" rend="plain">
            <figure n="vonHolstJerusalem.29.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="493">
              <head>1 Theodor von Holst, Figure Studies from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and
                other sources,</head>
              <figDesc><corr type="emend">pencil, pen and ink on laid paper with a watermark of
                  Brittania with her shield bearing the cross of St. George, 7 3/4 × 12 inches (20 ×
                  30.7 cm.), Private Collection, England.</corr></figDesc>
            </figure>
          </corr>
          <p>Holst steadfastly maintained an adherence to the artistic values of his Royal Academy
            masters throughout his short life but developed his own highly eclectic manner of
            stylistic and subject improvisation far beyond what was generally acceptable to the
            changing nature of English patronage during the age of reform. His vivacious,
            supernatural and daemonic pictures must have made many of the rising middle-class
            patrons blanch as they strolled along the exhibition walls of London looking for
            suitable scenes of religious and domestic genres to hang in their sittingrooms. In this
            way Holst was subjected to the same rejection and neglect 
<pb id="p29-79" n="79"/>
            <figure n="vonHolstKeyDiagram.29.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="432">
              <head>2 Key diagram to figures from the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plates in illus
                1.</head>
            </figure> that had affected the reputations of both Blake and Fuseli until their
            resurrection in the present century.</p>
          <p>Fortunately a sufficiently representative sample of works had become available for a
            sesquicentenary exhibition of Holst’s paintings, drawings, and prints to take place last
            year—at Hazlitt, Gooden and Fox in London and at Cheltenham Art Gallery. Prior to this
            the very limited knowledge of Holst’s work had greatly hindered both appraisal of him
            and confirmation of Rossetti’s proposal of Holst as “one of the few connecting links”
            from the art of Fuseli and Blake to that of the Pre-Raphaelites. My catalogue of the
              exhibition,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">2</ref> I believe,
establishes this connection
            at last but nevertheless provides only limited evidence of Blake’s influence on Holst.
            However, subsequent to the exhibition and publication of the catalogue, I was delighted
            to discover that a group of six drawings by Holst in a private collection in England
            contains one that establishes this line of influence without a doubt.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
              type="note">3</ref> As can be clearly seen from the pen and pencil studies on this
            sheet (illus. 1), the majority of the prominent figures are copies of those from Blake’s
              <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The key to this identification is the well-known figure
            of Los entering the gothic doorway from the frontispiece plate. The source for at least
            six further figures can be found in plates 19, 21, and 23 from the first chapter of 
              <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (illus. 2). Holst has copied these with varying degrees of
            freedom but their source is unmistakable. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i">
                The Romantic Art of Theodor Von Holst 1810-1844</hi>, published by Lund Humphries,
              London 1994 (Distributed in the USA by the Antique Collectors Club).</note>	
              <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">3</hi> All these drawings were orignally contained in the “Rolls
              Album” which was purchased by Colnaghi’s in 1959 and later dispersed (see Appendix II
              in my Holst catalogue). This particular sheet appears to have been purchased
              separately by Peter Pears sometime after the other five drawings were given to
              Benjamin Britten and Peter Pears by Imogen Holst in the early 1960s. Imogen Holst was
              the daughter and biographer of the composer Gustav Holst, a great-nephew of the
              artist. I would like to take this opportunity of offering my warmest thanks to
              Rosamund Strode for bringing these drawings to my attention and for her most generous
              and enthusiastic support for the publication of the Holst catalogue last
            year.</note></p>
          <p>Unfortunately I have not been so successful in identifying the source for several other
            figures on the sheet of which at least one appears stylistically closer to Fuseli rather
            than Blake. With regard to the “seated man with his head in his hands,” Martin Butlin
            has kindly pointed out to me the similarity to Blake’s figure in plate 3 of 
              <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> Holst was certainly familiar with <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> as can be
            seen from his borrowing of figures from plates 1 and 9 used in a drawing—known as 
              <hi rend="i">Dream of Marguerite</hi> (illus. 3)—executed in 1833. This was probably while
            on a visit to his elder brother, Gustavus, <pb id="p29-80" n="80"/>
            <figure n="vonHolstMarguerite.29.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="977">
              <head>3 Theodor von Holst, “Dream of Marguerite,” 1833, pen and pencil on buff paper,
                14 1/4 × 9 7/8 inches, Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino CA.</head>
            </figure>
<pb id="p29-81" n="81"/>
a musician then employed by an aristocratic patron
            near Eastbourne.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">4</ref> It
remains to be ascertained if
            Holst, at this time, had access to original copies of Blake’s books, or separate plates,
            or had made copies of figures from them at some earlier date. It would certainly seem
            remarkable, although perhaps not impossible, for him to have retained these motifs from
              memory.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See
              Imogen Holst, <hi rend="i">Gustav Holst</hi>, Oxford 1938 (2nd. ed. 1969) 2-4. I must
              admit some doubt as to this title since the composition appears closer to the subject
              of Francesca Da Rimini and the “whirlwind of lovers” from Dante’s 
                <hi rend="i">Inferno.</hi> Holst is known to have executed several sketches inspired by Dante
              about this time and particularly while on at least one trip to Eastbourne.</note>	
              <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">5</hi> If Holst possessed such a retentive faculty it may explain
              how he had, perhaps unconsciously, retained the figure of Adam by Michelangelo which
              he had subsequently employed in a sketch and claimed as original when challenged by
              William Young Ottley. This anecdote was reported by Holst’s emigré engraver friend
              John Sartain nearly 70 years later in <hi rend="i">The Reminiscences of a Very Old Man
                1808-1897</hi> (New York 1899, p. 118) although he doubted if such a feat of memory
              was possible.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is also of special interest since it was the one work by
            Blake singled out for inclusion in a review for the <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> by
            Holst’s close friend the dilettante artist and writer Thomas Griffiths Wainewright
            (1794-1847). This characteristically jocular piece appeared in the issue for September
            1820 and was considered by Gilchrist<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">6</ref> to be a “feeler
            for a possible subsequent full article on Blake. At this point in time Wainewright was
            best know under his <hi rend="i">nom-de-plume</hi> as Charles Lamb’s “light-hearted
            Janus [Weathercock]” and he was still several years away from the suspicion of his
            criminal activity which included strychnine poisoning and the Bank of England check
            forgery that finally led to his conviction and transportation “for life” to the penal
            colony of Hobart, Tasmania in 1837.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n7"><hi
                rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Life of William Blake</hi> 1: 278-79.</note>	
              <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">7</hi> For the fullest account of Wainewright see J. Curling, 
                <hi rend="i">Janus Weathercock</hi>, London 1938.</note></p>
          <p>Like Holst, Wainewright was a fervent follower of Fuseli and was also an admirer and
            patron of Blake. Gilchrist reported that Wainewright had purchased several of the
            illuminated books among which was one of the finest colored copies of the 
              <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> and the only known copy of 
<hi rend="i">The
              Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> embellished with gold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">8</ref> Such admiration was reciprocated in some degree for Blake was recorded as
            singling out Wainewright’s picture of <hi rend="i">The Milk-Maid’s Song</hi> as “very
            fine” while walking round the Royal Academy exhibition of 1823 with Samuel Palmer.<ref
              target="n10" type="note">9</ref> So, given the strength of these relationships, it
            seems very probable that it was Wainewright who introduced Holst to Blake’s designs,
            although several other artist and connoisseur acquaintances of Holst were also friends
            or patrons of Blake during his last years including John Varley, William Young Ottley
            and Sir Thomas Lawrence. It would be most desirable to be able to pinpoint which copies
            of Blake’s designs Holst employed as source material since this could shed further light
            on their provenance and also the circle of artists that the younger romantic associated
            with. However the rather free manner of the copying of the present sheet seems to
            preclude such identification.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">10</ref> This is in marked
            contrast to some of Holst’s copies after Fuseli which are sometimes almost impossible to
            distinguish from the original drawings, as the late Gert Schiff discovered when
            re-attributing the works of both these artists during his monumental work on Fuseli in
            the 1960s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Ibid.
              277. I am grateful again to Martin Butlin for referring me to Joseph Viscomi’s recent
              study <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> which provides details of
              Wainewright’s patronage of Blake and his purchase of several of the prophetic books
              (perhaps with the proceeds from his check forgery in 1826). In addition to 
                <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (copy X) and <hi rend="i">The
                Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (copy I), Wainewright’s collection was also know to
              contain <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (copy C), a set of proof <hi rend="i">Illustrations
                to the Book of Job, Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> and possibly 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (monochrome copy D).</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Ibid.
              278.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">10</hi> However it may be possible to eliminate
              certain copies of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as a source. Morton D. Paley points out
              several iconographic differences in various copies of the frontispiece design (see 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, William Blake Trust/Tate Gallery, 1991 [130] and additional
              plate illus. i-iii) and comparison with Holst’s drawing would seem to preclude colored
              copy E (Paul Mellon’s Collection) from the running. This is indicated in details such
              as Los’s finger shapes and non-sandaled feet and the absence of full plate-sized rays
              emanating from the “globe of Light.” Holst has his copy of this latter detail actually
              in front of the archway upright and this only appears to occur in colored copy B,
              although in this case it is not identical and the fingers that hold it are different.
              However the retouching of the garment and body shape below Los’s left armpit in copy B
              is closer than the monochrome copies to Holst’s figure as is the more curved shape of
              Los’s hat brim. Such inconsistency is both puzzling and unfortunately inconclusive at
              present, particularly as Wainewright appears to have provided the most likely source
              for Holst but is believed to have owned monochrome copy D (see n8). Of course an
              alternative possibility may be that Holst was following the copying of another artist
              as intermediary.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See G. Schiff, 
                <hi rend="i">Echtheits-und Zuschreibungsprobleme bei Johann Heinrich Füssli</hi>,
              Schweizerisches Institut für Kunstwissenschaft, Annual Report, Zurich 1965 and my
              catalogue, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Art of Theodor Von Holst.</hi></note></p>
          <p>At present only about a quarter of Holst’s documented work has appeared so far. We can
            thus look forward to further discoveries in the future with the possibility that more
            may also contain further evidence of the influence of Blake.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
