<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.hayes</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Elliott Hayes, Blake: Innocence and Experience, dir. Valerie Doulton</title>
        <author n="Lincoln">Andrew Lincoln</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0006">
        <pb id="p29-97" n="97"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Blake: Innocence and Experience</hi> by <corr type="emend">Elliott Hayes,</corr> 
with Michael Loughnan as William Blake. Directed by Valerie Doulton; designed by Gary Thorne; music for songs by Loreena
McKennitt. At the Tristan Bates Theatre, Tower Street, London, 12-18 June 1995.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Andrew <name>Lincoln</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The one-person show is an apt vehicle for representing Blake, since it allows the voice so much
freedom to determine the experience of time and space. In this production, the outward eye is repeatedly
unsettled by the ear. The lights come up on an elderly man of shabby-genteel appearance—frock-coated,
open-shirted, stubbled, balding and unkempt. Before long Blake announces that he is three months from his
seventieth birthday, which would put him on (if not beyond) the brink of his death—“an Old Man feeble and
tottering.” Illness and weakness are figured by the medicine bottle and the occasional grimace, but the
vigorous voice negates such evidence. At one point he appears to “fade away” in a chair, wrapped in a
sheet—a winding sheet from which there is a semi-comic resurrection. This Blake is at once elderly and
youthful, able to travel through the course of his own life at will, a man whose words are drawn in part from
letters and poems spanning five decades.</p>
          <p>In the restricted space of the Tristan Bates theatre, Michael Loughnan was able to use his full
vocal range in making the invisible visible—as when expelling Joshua Reynolds’s ghost in thunderous rage,
or allowing us to overhear intimate exchanges with Catherine Blake. His enthralling delivery of lines from 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> suddenly transformed the tiny stage into a stormy Atlantic from which Orc arose
“Intense! naked! a Human fire”—a vivid demonstration of the voice’s ability to govern the eye, and
overwhelming proof, should anyone need it, that Blake’s prophetic books demand to be heard as well as read.
A few of the songs were sung, unaccompanied, to specially composed melodies that Blake himself might have been
pleased with. For me, the only point at which the direction faltered was when, as Loughnan recited “The
Tyger,” he wandered over the stage as if looking for something—a point at which the visual effect was
allowed to compete with, and distract from, the voice.</p>
          <p>Paradoxically, the very freedom of the voice can help to enforce a sense of the speaker’s
isolation and self-absorption. This Blake, devoted to recollection and recrimination, asserting his own
convictions without fear of interruption (except from the visionary world), confronting and succumbing to his
own driving envy, often seems to be addressing a mirror rather than the audience. In this context the familiar
stories—of warning Paine to fly to France, of playing at Adam and Eve with Catherine in the garden—appear
as manifestations of a persistent tendency towards self-dramatization. Loughnan develops a convincing portrait
of a passionate, tormented and unclubbable individual—one who might even become a hot-eyed bore—always
ready to air his own ideas, but less ready to lend an ear to others.</p>
          <p>The setting of the play allows the frustration and anger to be seen as manifestations of the
selfhood that desire and vision must struggle to overcome. At the back of the stage three paint-covered easels
stand like crosses. On the left is Blake’s portrait of Catherine, on the right an empty sheet of paper—the
focus for a tirade against portrait painting which prompts an exposition of the importance of the bounding
line. In the center is Blake’s painting “The Angel Rolling the Stone from the Tomb,” in which the
angel’s outstretched arms enact the triumph over the cross. By the end of the play Blake has defined the
limits of his own caverned existence: in the final stage picture, he stands with arms outspread, mirroring the
angel in the painting behind him.</p>
          <p>Any dramatization of Blake must inevitably exclude much. There is little room here for Blake the
vulgarian; for the man who claimed to love laughing; for the man given to what is not too explicit
(“London” is sung in an early version because, presumably, it seems easier for an audience to absorb).
There is little room for the man immersed in the engraver’s work, its negotiations and deadlines, its messy
physical processes. But the limits of the play, and Valerie Doulton’s expert handling of them, make for a
portrait that is definite, determinate, and impossible to forget.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
