<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <front>
      <pb id="p29-73-74" n="73-74"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.029.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="334">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            VOLUME 29<lb/>
            NUMBER 3<lb/>
            WINTER 1995/96</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="14" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>CONTENTS</title>
        	  </head>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particulars</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.butlin">A Rare Group of Early Twentieth-Century Watercolors
by a Follower of William Blake</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by Martin Butlin</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">76</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.browne">A Blake Source for von Holst</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by Max Browne</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">78</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.imaizumi">G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Studies in
Japan: A Bibliography of Works on William Blake Published in Japan 1893-1993</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Yoko Ima-Izumi</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">82</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.ferber">William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated
Books</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Michael Ferber</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">88</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.read">William Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi> and the
Final Illuminated Works: <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>[,] <hi rend="i">on Homer’s Poetry</hi> [and]
<hi rend="i">On Virgil</hi>[,] <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Dennis M. Read</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">91</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.linkin">Molly Anne Rothenberg, <hi rend="i">Rethinking
Blake’s Textuality</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Harriet Linkin</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">92</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.lincoln">George Anthony Rosso, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Prophetic Workshop: A Study of</hi> The Four Zoas</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Andrew Lincoln</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">95</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.warner">Steven Vine, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry: Spectral
Visions</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i"> Reviewed by Janet Warner</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">96</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><corr type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="29.3.hayes">Elliott Hayes, <hi rend="i">Blake: Innocence and
Experience</hi></ref></corr><lb/>
<hi rend="i"> Reviewed by Andrew Lincoln</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">97</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.cox">Jeanne Moskal, <hi rend="i">Blake, Ethics, and
Forgiveness</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i"> Reviewed by Stephen Cox</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">97</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="29.3.davies">Exhibition: “The Genitals are Beauty”</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Keri Davies</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">102</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p29-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Max Browne is a Fuseli, Blake and Holst enthusiast and collector. He recently organized the first
exhibition devoted to Holst and wrote the catalogue <hi rend="i">The Romantic Art of Theodor Von Holst</hi>
(Lund Humphries, 1994).</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin was formerly Keeper of the Historic British Collection at the Tate Gallery, where he
was in charge of the notable groups of works by Blake and Turner. He is now a consultant at Christie’s.</p>
        <p>Stephen Cox, Professor of Literature at the University of California, San Diego, is the author of
<hi rend="i">“The Stranger Within Thee”: Concepts of the Self in Late-Eighteenth-Century Literature</hi>,
and of <hi rend="i">Love and Logic: The Evolution of Blake’s Thought.</hi></p>
        <p>Keri Davies is Chair of the Blake Society at St James’s. He is currently researching Blake’s
contemporary collectors.</p>
        <p>Michael Ferber is Professor of English at the University of New Hampshire. His most recent books
are the Blake and Shelley volumes of the Penguin Critical Studies series.</p>
        <p>William F. Halloran, Professor of English, University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, has returned full
time to teaching and research on Blake, Yeats, William Sharp (“Fiona Macleod”) and others after an
inordinate number of years as dean.</p>
        <p>Yoko Ima-Izumi, Associate Professor of English at the University of Tsukuba in Japan, has published
essays on Blake, romantic literature, and film. She is currently working on three books: 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Re-Vision of the Female</hi> (in Japanese), <hi rend="i">Romantic Poetry and Postmodern
Film</hi> (in Japanese) and <hi rend="i">Women in Japanese Film</hi> (in English).</p>
        <p>Andrew Lincoln teaches in the School of English and Drama at Queen Mary and Westfield College,
University of London. His book, <hi rend="i">Spiritual History: A Reading of William Blake’s The Four
Zoas</hi> was recently published by Oxford University Press.</p>
        <p>Harriet Kramer Linkin teaches courses in Blake, romanticism, and gender at New Mexico State
University. She is currently co-editing <hi rend="i">Approaches to Teaching British Women Poets of the
Romantic Period</hi> for the MLA and writing a study on the poetry of Mary Tighe.</p>
        <p>Dennis M. Read is an associate professor at Denison University, where he teaches courses in
literature and writing.</p>
        <p>Janet Warner is Professor Emerita of English, Glendon College, York University, Toronto. She is now
living on five acres near Vancouver, British Columbia, and studying garden design.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Patricia Neill, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY
14627</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Patricia Neill<lb/>
TELEPHONE 716/275-3820<lb/>
FAX 716/442-5769<lb/>
PRODUCTION OFFICE EMAIL: pnpj@db1.cc.rochester.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Morris Eaves</hi>, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627<lb/>
Email: meav@db1.cc.rochester.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Morton D. Paley</hi>, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA
94720<lb/>
Email: P72735@garnet.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</hi>, University College, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario
M5S 1A1 Canada<lb/>
Email: gbentley@epas.utoronto.ca</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Nelson Hilton</hi>, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA
30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@uga.cc.uga.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">David Worrall</hi>, St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill, Waldegrave Road, Twickenham
TW1 4SX England<lb/>
Email: 101510.2141@compuserve.com</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester.</p>
        <p>SUBSCRIPTIONS are $50 for institutions, $25 for individuals. All subscriptions are by the volume (1
year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be
applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and Mexico) require an $8 per
volume postal surcharge for surface, an $18 per volume surcharge for air mail delivery. U.S. currency or
international money order necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi>
Address all subscription orders and related communications to Patricia Neill, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>,
Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627.</p>
        <p>BACK ISSUES are available at a reduced price. Address Patricia Neill for a list of issues and
prices.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to forms suggested in 
<hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of
Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA
94720.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A
Selective and Critical Bibliography</hi> (ed. David V. Erdman et al.), American Humanities Index, Arts and
Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover illustration: Henry John Stock (1853-1930), <hi rend="i">The Beast cast into the Lake of
Fire.</hi>
	<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1995 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
