<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>29.3.ferber</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, eds., 
William Blake, The Early Illuminated Books</title>
        <author n="Ferber">Michael Ferber</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1995/96</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1995/96</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">29.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Max Browne</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Stephen Cox</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>William F. Halloran</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1995/96"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_29">
    <body>
	<pb id="p29-88" n="88"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-29-3-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books.</hi> Edited with
introductions and notes by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi. Princeton: The William Blake
Trust/Princeton University Press, 1993. Blake’s Illuminated Books Volume 3. General Editor David Bindman.
286 pp. $75.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Michael <name>Ferber</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>This is an altogether splendid volume of plates and commentary. It covers all of Blake’s
“illuminated” work from 1788 to 1793 except for the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, which made up Volume 2. Of
the three volumes I have seen (there will be six in all, not five, as originally announced), this is the most
interesting and original in its commentary, though like the others it tries to be catholic and fair in its
citations of scholarship. Unlike the first two volumes, however, it escapes serious damage from sleepy
compositors and proofreaders. It gives us several of the works we are most likely to teach after the 
<hi rend="i">Songs: Thel, Marriage</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, as well as the early tracts 
<hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> and <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion.</hi> It is too expensive to
assign to students, but for almost any course on Blake professors must see that their library has it on
reserve; for specialists the commentary alone is worth the price.</p>
          <p>I have not tried to compare the plates with the originals, but they seem about as faithful as one
could ask. Color variations are subtle, and nothing seems either too bright or too subdued. And the publishers
have been generous. Besides the eight plates of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> copy J, for example, we are given six
supplementary plates: two proof copies of plates 2 and 3, plate 6 of copy K, plate 7 of copy I, plate 8 of
copy N, and pencil sketches of plates 6 and 7. There are particular reasons for including these (a bit of
design or text is added), but it is also good to have them just for the differences in coloring, so a student
will see that even in general impact Blake’s versions of the same work differ dramatically. So with the
other works: there are 14 extra plates for <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> and 11 for <hi rend="i">Visions.</hi> We
get four versions of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 21, the wonderful nude male who reappears in 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> 8, and three versions of the great frontispiece of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, one of
which is reproduced at about twice the original size on the dust jacket of the volume. Even with no scholarly
questions in mind it is rewarding to gaze at the different versions of these designs.</p>
          <p>The introduction presents the most lucid and succinct summary of Blake’s methods of book
production that I have seen. It stresses that Blake composed designs directly on the plate and thus did not
need a fair copy, though he manifestly had pencil sketches of many if not all of them. The fundamental unit of
production was not the individual copy of a work but the printing and coloring “session,” which typically
involved two copies and sometimes more. Different ink colors might be used in one session. “The products of
each printing session correspond to an ‘edition’ of a book, while each ink colour can be considered a
different ‘issue’ of the edition” (11). These categories reflect the brilliant reconstructive research
of Joseph Viscomi, who elaborates his argument in <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (Princeton,
1993).</p>
          <p>One result of his researches is a new approach to <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion.</hi>
“Viscomi’s recent discoveries” (22), as detailed in his book, showed that 50 of the 153 known
impressions of the 20 plates of <hi rend="i">NNR</hi> were not done by Blake. The authentic ones represent
just two sessions, one c. 1794 and one c. 1795. From the six copies that Viscomi determined stem from the
first session, the same eight plates are lacking (that is, the bulk of the “b” series as usually printed
now: b1-2, 5-11, including the one missing from all copies, b5). In other words, Blake printed and colored six
sets with the same 12 plates, a1-9, b3, b4, and b12. It strongly appears that Blake’s intention, at that
time, was to make an independent work out of the two sequences he had engraved as early as 1788. Viscomi et
al. go on to argue that there is no sharp inconsistency in combining the three “b” plates with the “a”
plates, and that indeed “The ‘a’ part cannot stand alone; without its second half, the irony would not
be apparent and Blake would have appeared to contemporary readers as an advocate of the very position he is
attacking,” namely the rational empiricism of Bacon and Locke (25). We are given a new work, and the plates
are here so arranged. (The c. 1795 printing is the “b” series with the “a” title page.)</p>
          <p>It is not to question Viscomi’s research to wonder if it is so clear that the “a” series
cannot stand alone. <hi rend="i">A reductio ad absurdum</hi> argument can be quite straight-faced; it
needn’t
<pb id="p29-89" n="89"/>
pounce on a conclusion as in b3 and b4. The fourth through sixth propositions (a7-9), involving thought and
desires (e.g., “Mans desires are limited by his perceptions”), might well have struck a contemporary as
evidently false without explicit prompting. The “a” series might (originally) have been intended to convey
through a mixture of plausibly Lockean ideas and ironic distortions of them the sheer paltriness of such a
philosophy, giving us not so much a logical absurdity as an outrage to the human spirit. This is all we can
grind out of Locke’s mill, it seems to say: Are you satisfied? The editors later concede, somewhat
inconsistently, that “Blake exaggerates (and thereby parodies) their method [Bacon’s and Locke’s]”
(28) and that “Even a reader favourably disposed toward Bacon and Locke might begin to suspect [with a8 and
a9] that this strait jacket has been fitted a bit too tightly” (32). I agree. By 1794, it may be, Blake lost
his nerve a little, and added the three “b” plates to make sure his readers got the point. In any case we
do seem to have an evolving intention, and if we are to respect that intention then future editions of Blake
should print three sequences, the “a” and “b” sequences (as in Erdman 1982) and the 1794 sequence.</p>
          <p>With the otherwise very helpful commentary on <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> I have only
one quibble. The editors take the “Argument” as a statement no empiricist would question—for they take
“experiment” and “experiences” to be used in the modern (Baconian) sense—concerning “the true
method of knowledge”; “but Blake immediately begins to overturn that easy assumption by introducing as his
first principle ‘the Poetic Genius’” (29). I think Blake is slyer here, and is not exactly overturning
his assumption. He may be trying to lure an empiricist to agree with his argument, but Blake can agree with
it, too, for he is also using “experiment” and “experience” in the older and broader sense found in
the language of religious enthusiasm. As William Haller writes, “the Preachers made experiment a familiar
word on the plane of religion and morals long before it became supreme on that of natural science” 
(<hi rend="i">The Rise of Puritanism</hi> [NY: Columbia, 1938] 299). As an example from the radical sects, take
Gerrard Winstanley, who wrote in 1649 that the Scriptures are a record of the “pure experience” of the
prophets and apostles, and in reading them we gain “an experimental persuasion, grounded upon sight and
feeling of the spirit of truth” (George Sabine, ed., <hi rend="i">The Works of Gerrard Winstanley</hi>
[Ithaca: Cornell, 1941] 128-29). Methodists in Blake’s day had “experience meetings” where people gave
personal testimonies. Though Blake does not say that the Poetic Genius experiences anything, it is not
inconsistent with his formulation to say that the Poetic Genius enables us to experience things not dreamt of
in the philosophy of Bacon and Locke. The empiricists experience through the chinks of their caverns: we, at
our best, experience through fourfold vision.</p>
          <p>Most Blake scholars, I suspect, are closet commentators, near kin to classicists and medievalists
who dream of producing the Great Commentary on their cherished author, line by line and word by word. I for
one have had to struggle, not always successfully, against an impulse to shovel gobbets out of my notebook of
hard-earned annotations into my articles and books. What fun to have the license to fill 15 large pages with
comments on <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>! But you thereby expose yourself to the jealous scrutiny of the commentary
guild. Let me say, then, before I put forth my own additions and corrections, that the commentaries on 
<hi rend="i">Thel, Visions</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> are all excellent; I might have done them a little
differently, but I could not have done them better.</p>
          <p>I was a little surprised to see the point that “By referring to herself in the third person
(4:11; see also 5:3), Thel also separates herself from herself, as though consciousness without identity leads
to a grammatical expression of alienation” (75). (The plate numbers here are two higher than the standard
numbering, and there are four instances, not two, of Thel’s calling herself “Thel.”) Aside from the fact
that my two-year-old daughter, not yet self-alienated, calls herself by her name, I find this very
far-fetched. What do we say about Lyca, then, who calls herself “Lyca” four times in a shorter poem, and
uses “her” to mean “my”? Or Oothoon, who calls herself “Oothoon” six times? It is also awkward
that Thel drops that habit in the latter three plates. This idea should have been laid to rest, not preserved
in a commentary that will be much consulted for a long time.</p>
          <p>The discussion of the titlepage design for <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> leaves out something important
about the willow, and it strikes me as misleading to say that the “entwined vine forms a traditional emblem
of marriage or education” (81). That may be true (though marriage and education are quite different things),
but it ignores the symbolism of the willow by itself. The willow means just the opposite of marriage. In a
tradition going back to Homer, the willow is “worne of forlorne Paramours,” in Spenser’s phrase 
(<hi rend="i">FQ</hi> 1.1.9). It is described thus throughout Shakespeare: the report of Ophelia’s drowning, for
example, begins with a willow, and Desdemona sings of a willow before she is murdered by Othello. In Blake’s
day, “she is in her willows” meant “she is mourning her husband or betrothed.” Willows were also
frequently carved on tombstones; thus the tombstone shape that the willow describes on the title page is
probably not our fancy. Indeed the sole willow in Homer is at the entrance to Hades.</p>
          <p>In the “Notes” to <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (108f) I would add the following:</p>
          <p>4.4 (=2.4) “crave” deserves a note. It means “ask” or “beg”; the “voiceless” are
those who “cannot crave.” See <hi rend="i">King Edward the Third</hi> 6:45-46: “nor shall the young /
Crave or be heard” (E 438). Joseph of Arimathea “craved the body of Jesus” from Pilate (Mark 15.43).
Yeats may have been inspired by Blake’s line in “To the Rose upon the Rood of Time”: “Lest I no more
hear the common things that crave; / The weak worm hiding down in its small cave, / The field mouse running by
me in the grass.”</p>
          <p>4.7 (=2.7) “taints”: cf. <hi rend="i">Lycidas</hi> 46: “Or Taint-worm to the weanling Herds
that graze.” “Taint” by itself could mean “taint-worm.”</p>
          <pb id="p29-90" n="90"/>
          <p>6.6 (=4.6) “cherish” means “make warm” or “keep warm.” Cf. <hi rend="i">PL</hi>
10.1068-69 (“some better warmth to cherish / Our limbs benumbed”) and several occurrences in the AV.</p>
          <p>8.1 (=6.1) “northern bar”: cf. Job 17.16 (“the bars of the pit”); also 
<hi rend="i">Auguries</hi> 42 (“polar bar”) and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 23.42 (“Satans Bar”). Perhaps
also relevant are the “exclusive bars” of “membrane, joint, or limb” in <hi rend="i">PL</hi> 8.625;
the editors cite this for the final line of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> but treat “bars” as if it were a
verb.</p>
          <p>The editors make a good case against the standard view that the final plate of 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, which seems different in tone and imagery from the others, was engraved two years after
they were. The evidence rests in part on the changing shapes of the letter “g,” David Erdman’s
discovery, and the editors show that Erdman’s argument as to dating <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> can no longer be sustained. There is also no direct evidence of an alternative ending.
They acknowledge that Blake may have had difficulty coming up with an ending to the poem, but they deny there
was an appreciable delay. We do not have a case like Wordsworth’s “Intimations” ode. Those for whom the
process of production, as evidence of Blake’s intentions, is crucial to interpreting the work must take
note. Those for whom it is the final product that counts (perhaps following Blake’s intention there as
well!), are left where they were, trying to make sense of a somewhat baffling ending.</p>
          <p>The editors, following more work by Viscomi, argue that <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> was begun and very likely completed in 1790; Blake did not take until 1793 to do it, as most
scholars have argued or assumed. He worked within discrete textual units, such as plates 16-20, probably did
not produce them in the final order (departed from in copy G in any event), and could have assembled them in
almost any order. In a recent talk at the “Blake 1794/1994” conference at St. Mary’s College, Viscomi
gave more details of the production of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, and made a case that Blake may have
intended one or more parts of it as a separate pamphlet or broadside. I couldn’t help feeling a little surge
of satisfaction, as I have recently claimed that <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> has very little structure despite
many ingenious efforts to reveal it. As an anti-intentionalist I would not rest my claim on evidence from the
production process, but those who do not draw the line where I do should take careful note of the new
evidence. (Viscomi is at work on a second book, which will expand and occasionally correct his first.) The
editors do find a category for the form of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, the “category called Menippean or
Varronian satire” (118), but it is safe to say that no one has ever found a structure common to these
satires.</p>
          <p>The “Contexts and Themes” section of the introduction to <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> is
terrific. Among other merits it has a rich though concise discussion of just what it was in Swedenborg’s
style and beliefs that roused Blake’s faculties to act. Their notes on the “Memorable Fancy” of plate
15, the “Printing house in Hell,” are interesting, if not quite convincing, as they have a good go at
reading it as an allegory of the phases of Blake’s printing method. In the commentary the point I missed
most (perhaps they felt it was too obvious) is that the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> is not really a marriage
after all, whatever the titlepage design may suggest. It is certainly not a marriage of two equals, resulting
in a higher synthesis: it is more like a spiritual war, where the Angels lose every encounter or (once)
convert to Devilhood. I thought the editors went over the top in suggesting that the titlepage design
describes a large human face (131), but the road of excess, after all, leads you know where.</p>
          <p>There are no surprises in the discussion of the production of <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi>, but the commentary is exemplary. I only missed an acknowledgment of the importance
of the subject of epistemology, and of the startling turn in Oothoon’s speech (at 5:30 = 2:30) from her
claim to be pure after her rape to a tirade against empiricism and the five senses. To work out what these
seemingly unconnected topics are doing in the same speech, I think, is pretty much to work out the whole
poem.</p>
          <p>Throughout their commentaries and notes the editors are generous in acknowledging scholarship and
admitting many incompatible points as worth considering. Such hospitableness does not demand that we embrace
“interpretive multiplicity” and refuse to resolve it into a unity. “The conclusion that 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> offers no such unity would be unsettling for readers of logical arguments,” the editors
conclude, “but need not be for readers of poems” (81), as if Blake deployed his logical arguments for the
aesthetic delectation of poem readers. Undecidable interpretive multiplicity is now so ubiquitous a touchstone
of literary criticism that it has grown invisible. This is not the place to argue it out, but I would at least
ask the editors what Blake would think of it. Or of this: “ambivalence, both visual and linguistic, is one
of Blake’s most effective satirical tools [in <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>]—an infernal tool, because heaven
is not built on ambivalence” (130). I think Blake’s response to this would not be ambivalent at all.
Fortunately the editors don’t hesitate to pass positive judgements and to rule out some interpretations as
mistaken, and in this more Blakean spirit they have produced an outstanding commentary.</p>
          <p>I have noticed the following typographical errors:</p>
          <p>p. 56: texts for plates b4 and b12 are transposed.</p>
          <p>p. 79: the Greek word should end in a nu, not an upsilon (and “Thalia” the noun is not
strictly speaking <hi rend="i">from</hi> the verb form “thallein”).</p>
          <p>p. 225 near the bottom: a line (or more) has dropped out.</p>
          <p>p. 228, 1. 22: “entagled” for “entangled.”</p>
          <p>p. 231, 1. 13 from bottom: the accent is wrong.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
