<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.1.erdman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Dating Blake’s Script: the “g” hypothesis</title>
				<author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>June 15, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-1-0004">
                <pb id="p03-8" n="8"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">4. DATING BLAKE’S SCRIPT: the “g” hypothesis</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>David V. <name>Erdman</name>
                        </docAuthor> SUNY (Stony Brook) and NYPL</byline>
                    <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., has urged me, at a welcome time and in the 
                    public interest, to spell out in more detail the grounds for the 
                    theory I advanced in a summary note in <hi rend="u">Studies in
                    Bibliography</hi> in 1964 (pp. 51-54) and, even more cryptically, in 
                    1966 in the textual notes of the Doubleday Blake (pp. 738, 744, 745), 
                    the theory based on the discovery that one of Blake’s “accidentals,”
                    the shape of the letter <hi rend="u">g</hi> in his script, had twice 
                    undergone such deliberate change as to be anything but accidental.</p>
                    <p>I observed that up to about 1790 Blake in the lettering of his
                    Illuminated Books or engraved inscriptions employed a lower-case 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi> of the conventional kind, with the serif (“the
                    little nubbin at the top” as Bentley calls it) pointing to the right 
                    (ǵ); that he invented a different letter, with the serif pointing 
                    idiosyncratically to the left (g̀) “in about 1791, employed [it] with
                    unwavering consistency for fourteen years, and then as suddenly and
                    with ruthless consistency discarded” it in 1805:</p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="u">Thel</hi>, dated 1789 but containing (as others have 
                    observed) a Motto and a concluding plate that seem late additions, 
                    uses the conventional and manuscript <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s—except in 
                    the Motto and the last plate [pl. 1, 8], where the new [left-facing]
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi> takes over. <hi rend="u">The Marriage</hi> . . . 
                    was the product of several years [as most scholars agree]. The old 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi> rules up through Plate 3, and in 5-6, 11-13, 21-24
                    [here I correct a numerical error in <hi rend="u">SB</hi>]; the new
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi> in 4, 7-10, 14-20, and in the ‘Song of Liberty’ 
                    (25-27). This overlap narrows the date of change to late 1790 or early
                    1791. Every serified <hi rend="u">g</hi> thereafter points leftward, 
                    even in inscriptions made for Cumberland or Hayley, including the 
                    inscription ‘June 18, 1805 . . . Bridge Street’ in the plates for
                    Hayley’s <hi rend="u">Ballads.</hi> After that date Blake not only
                    abandoned the leftward <hi rend="u">g</hi> but corrected it in
                    reissues! In the 1807 reissue of these <hi rend="u">Ballads</hi> the
                    date is not changed, but the <hi rend="u">g</hi> in ‘Bridge Street’ 
                    has a new rightward serif. Blake’s <hi rend="u">Gates of
                    Paradise</hi>, etched ‘For Children’ in 1793, with leftward g’s, was 
                    reissued many years later with some further etching, during which the
                    g’s [on pl. 13, 14, 16] were given new, right-facing serifs, opposite
                    visible remains of the old. In late issues of <hi rend="u">Songs of
                    Experience</hi>, for example in the Rosenwald and Fitzwilliam copies 
                    [copies Z, AA, to be seen in the Blake Trust facsimile and in color
                    slides, respectively], when Blake retouched the lettering he added new 
                    serifs beside the old.”</p>
                    <p>Bentley is puzzled at my claim to see conventional 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s in the main part of <hi rend="u">Thel.</hi> I 
                    should have explained more analytically that the lowercase 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s in <hi rend="u">Thel</hi> are of a rather 
                    neutral kind that can be found occasionally in any period, with no 
                    serif and no loop in the tail and an oval head (9), but that in plates 
                    3-5, 7 of <hi rend="u">Thel</hi> occur hybrid <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s 
                    with more rounded head and a slight but rightward serif (g). These I 
                    counted in with the conventional <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s, but perhaps
                    the argument should be put, here, as resting on the absence of the 
                    new, leftward <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s. Another type of serif-less 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s, with curled tail and round—but bald—head (g) 
                    will puzzle us later on.</p>
                    <p>To fill out the picture, Bentley suggests a table of evidence to 
                    see whether it is accurate to say that there are “no exceptions” to my 
                    hypothesis in any clearly dated work—and to see what applications may 
                    be made that clarify the dating of uncertainly dated work. A first 
                    step, partly supplied by Bentley in correspondence, would be a 
                    tabulation of all writings containing <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s of any
                    kind, according to dates traditionally assigned, on however little 
                    authority. But since an immediate second step would be the elimination 
                    of items containing only serif-less <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s (Bentley
                    sketched out a list of engraved captions containing only neutral 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s which shows <corr type="emend">them</corr>
                	<pb id="p03-9" n="9"/>
                	as available to Blake in all periods—though seldom in captions that 
                	may not have been lettered by someone else), and a third step the 
                	removal for separate treatment of items of infirm date or of ambiguous 
                	serif, I’ve chosen to begin at <hi rend="u">this</hi> point, with a 
                	table of unambiguous and fairly certainly (if not always pinpointably) 
                	dated exhibits, followed by a table of works or inscriptions of 
                	uncertain date and/or ambiguously drawn <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s.</p>
                    <p>It should be understood that no writing by Blake, in pencil, pen, 
                    burin, or graver, has been excluded from this survey. If few instances 
                    of pen or pencil writing are listed, it is because they are the only 
                    occurrences of serifed <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s I have found in all 
                    Blake’s manuscripts.</p>
                    <table rows="36" cols="2">
                        <head>Table 1</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>RIGHT-SERIF ǵ (Conventional)</cell>
                            <cell>LEFT-SERIF g̀ (Idiosyncratic)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>No Natural Religion [1788]</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>All Religions are One [1788]</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Innocence (tp 1789) pl 2-27, 34-36, 53, b</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Thel (tp 1789) pl 3-5, 7 
                            	(hybrid <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s)</cell>
                            <cell>Thel pl 1 (Motto), 8 (Finis)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Marriage pl 2, 3[1790], 5-6, 11-13, 21-24</cell>
                            <cell>Marriage pl 4, 7-10, 14-20, 25-27</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Visions (tp 1793)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>For Children (1793) pl 2, 13-14, 16</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Job (18 Aug 1793)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Edward &amp; Elenor (18 Aug 1793)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>America (tp 1793)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Experience (tp 1794) 30-33, 37-51</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Europe (tp 1794)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Urizen (tp 1794)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Ahania; Song of Los; Bk of Los (tps 1795)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Cumberland: Thoughts on Outline (Jan 1795) 
                            	pl 2, 3, 5-16, 18, 19, 22</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Moore &amp; Co carpet adv [1797-98]</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Naval Pillar (1799)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Little Tom (Oct 5 1800)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Designs to . . . Ballads, fp (June 1 1802), 
                            	Lion (August 3 1802)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hayley <hi rend="u">Cowper</hi> III 
                            	(25 March 1804)</cell>
                            <cell>Hayley <hi rend="u">Cowper</hi> II (1803) fp,
                            	Weatherhouse (Nov 5 1802) (1st, 2nd, 3rd eds)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hayléy <hi rend="u">Ballads</hi>(1805), 
                            	Eagle [revised?], Lion, Horse 
                            	(all inscr. June 18 1805)</cell>
                            <cell>Hayley <hi rend="u">Ballads</hi> (1805), 
                            	Eagle (June 18 180 [reprod. in Russell; 
                            	Lion and Horse not seen]</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Milton (tp 1804, no <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s)</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Jerusalem (tp 1804, no <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s)</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Title page design for 
                            	<hi rend="u">The Grave</hi> (1806)</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hoare <hi rend="u">Inquiry</hi> (1806)</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Canterbury Pilgrims (Oct 8 1810)</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hervey [ca 1810]</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Joseph of Arimathea, 2nd state [ca 1810]</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Mirth [1816-20] 2nd state</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Laocoon</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>On Homers Poetry, on Virgil</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Ghost of Abel (1822)</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>The Hiding of Moses [ca 1823]</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Wilson Lowry (1825)</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Illustrations of the Book of Job (1826)</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <pb id="p03-10" n="10"/>
                    <p>The general pattern, as Bentley agrees, is clear enough. While 
                    <hi rend="u">Thel</hi> and <hi rend="u">The Marriage</hi> were in 
                    progress, Blake switched from conventional to leftward serifs, and
                    while at work on the 1805 <hi rend="u">Ballads</hi> he switched back.
                    Even this chart omitting uncertain cases, however, contradicts my 
                    assertion of June 1805 as a moment of sudden and ruthless reversal. 
                    Indeed only one copy, not now located, has a left serif; the latest 
                    leftward serifs fully in evidence are in the three 1803 editions of 
                    Hayley’s <hi rend="u">Cowper</hi>, in plates inscribed Nov 5 1802 in 
                    vol II; the “moment” of change is the 16-month interval between that 
                    date and March 25 1804, the date inscribed on right-serif plates in 
                    vol III. Yet the 1805 Eagle plate demonstrates the ruthlessness I 
                    spoke of. Blake did not simply mend the serif on the one 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi> concerned; he re-engraved the whole line, “Publ. 
                    June 18 1805 by R. Phillips. N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 6 
                    Brid<hi rend="u">g</hi>e Street Black Friers,” to get it 
                    <hi rend="u">right.</hi> Possibly this was a single errant plate, 
                    revised not for the 1807 reissue but at once; I wish I knew.) This 
                    second state of the plate is also more highly finished if comparison 
                    of the Russell plate with a B.M. copy is valid.</p>
                    <p>The dubious evidence of a <hi rend="u">g</hi> in the frontispiece 
                    of volume I of the Cowper, inscribed Nov 5 1802, points to a 
                    distinction that complicates matters. It is serifless (bald:
                    <inline-image n="003-01-p10-g-bald">
                        <figTranscr>g</figTranscr>
                    </inline-image>) in the 1st edition; in the second (NYPL copy) under 
                    scrutiny it reveals a trace of an entering stroke on the right side 
                    (here exaggerated: 
                    <inline-image n="003-01-p10-g-stroke">
                            <figTranscr>g</figTranscr>
                    </inline-image>) not made as the usual serif by a separate stroke but 
                    a fine line made as the burin approached to cut the loop of the 
                    letter. (It is Bentley who reports the first edition bald; perhaps the 
                    only change is in deeper inking of the plate.) In any event, I take 
                    this as an instance of the neutral <hi rend="u">g</hi>, not a firm and 
                    determinate right serif. But the distinction I refer to as illustrated 
                    here is that between Blake’s relief etching, where the lettering was 
                    first drawn in ground (varnish), thick in line including serifs, and 
                    his (or other engravers’) incised inscriptions, cut directly into the 
                    copper. Bald or almost bald <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s occur occasionally 
                    in all periods, in both media<supplied type="emend">.</supplied>
                    The serif requires an extra stroke of the pen, burin, or needle, 
                    apparently easier to forget with the tools of incising than with the 
                    pen or brush. In Blake’s final period, when he was printing from 
                    relief plates made in his leftward, Lambeth period, he did not tamper 
                    with the copper plates but simply retraced the letters on the paper 
                    after printing, leaving the old serifs at the left, as printed, but 
                    inserting new ones at the right. (I do not mean to imply that he did 
                    this in all post-Felpham copies; many he printed without retouching. 
                    I should have said that whenever he retouched, he changed the 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi> serifs.) Such retracing was not satisfactory, or 
                    necessary with intaglio printing, however; the easy and more 
                    attractive method there was to burnish the plate and recut the 
                    letters. This process left more or less faint traces of the earlier 
                    shapes, as we see in mended inscriptions in <hi rend="u">For the 
                    Sexes</hi> [ca 1818]: remnant left serifs and added right serifs, 
                    plates 13-14, 16. Still simpler was to close up the copper where the 
                    serif had been, leaving them bald. (Though bald <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s 
                    never serifed are common in inscriptions, from those in “Original 
                    Shavin<hi rend="u">g</hi>” in <hi rend="u">May-Day in London</hi>, 
                    June 1 1784, to those in the 1811 Chaucer.)</p>
                    <p>Two problem inscriptions may be discussed in this connection, 
                    before we return to the question of dating the beginning and ending of 
                    the left-serif period. <hi rend="u">The Accusers</hi>, originally 
                    inscribed “Our End is Come . . . 1793,” in its latest state has 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s in “Judge” and “Judgment,” which in some copies 
                    appear to be bald. But in some a clear left serif is visible in Judge
                    (<inline-image n="003-01-p10-g-clear-left-serif">
                    	<figTranscr>g</figTranscr>
                    </inline-image>) and a slight left serif in Judgment 
                    (<inline-image n="003-01-p10-g-slight-left-serif">
                    	<figTranscr>g</figTranscr>
                    </inline-image>). The implication is that the inscription was incised 
                    during the leftward period and the serif removed in later printings. 
                    I would like to believe that the outcry against the Judgment of 
                    Accusers was Blake’s response to his accusation and having to stand 
                    trial for sedition; i.e., that the Notebook “Grey Monk” lines and the 
                    inscription of this plate were made in August 1803 or thereabouts.
                    This will fit into that 16-month moment.</p>
                    <pb id="p03-11" n="11"/>
                    <p>The inscriptions of <hi rend="u">Albion rose</hi> (the date of 
                    which I have been guilty of moving about impulsively) has one 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>, in “Giving,” quite bald in some prints but 
                    showing a faint trace of a right serif in others. This is maddeningly 
                    ambiguous, though it does seem to put the inscription outside the 
                    Lambeth-Felpham era. When Blake <hi rend="u">added</hi> right serifs, 
                    he did it firmly. But to posit a deleted serif would require putting 
                    the original inscription impossibly early (pre-Lambeth, so to speak). 
                    I have been guilty of this anachronism, in my Doubleday notes, 
                    forgetting the <hi rend="u">language</hi> of the inscription (but see 
                    <hi rend="u">SB</hi>, p. 54). It is not only that dancing the dance of 
                    Eternal Death and giving oneself for the Nations are concepts and 
                    language of the <hi rend="u">Milton</hi> period (see esp. pl 14:14) 
                    but that the concept of Albion as a person does not otherwise precede 
                    <hi rend="u">Milton.</hi> Up through the works of 1795 Albion is a 
                    <hi rend="u">land</hi>; only in additions to the ms of 
                    <hi rend="u">Vala</hi> does the “Eternal Man” change to “Albion.”
                    Appealing again to biography, Albion’s rise, with the dated 
                    recollection that the drawing was made in or of “1780” (riots for
                    America), would nicely fit the bread-riot year 1800, with rumors of 
                    peace—and the Blakes’ “rising” to Felpham? One would need to examine 
                    bald-<hi rend="u">g</hi> copies to see if they represent an earlier 
                    state of the engraving and test this hypothesis, which requires that 
                    the right stroke was added in a later state.</p>
                    <p>The most surprising discovery of conventionally serifed 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s where they would not be expected bears also on 
                    the question of the time of return from leftward 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s. These are the six left-serif 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s on pp. 8, 10, 12, 67 of the 
                    <hi rend="u">Vala</hi> manuscript. They occur in different layers of 
                    the script (defined as copperplate hand and modified copperplate hand; 
                    not in Blake’s usual manuscript hand, which never employs serifed 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s of either kind), thought to be wide apart in 
                    date. (This is unclear; no <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s with serifs, except 
                    these few, occur in the copperplate hands either, but a serifed 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi> is not out of keeping in hands that imitate print 
                    as these do.) Presumably they show work on the ms toward the end of or 
                    after the Felpham period—but this is much less startling than my 
                    initial, mistaken deduction that their date had to be post June 1805. 
                    For discussion of the complications of the problem, see pp. 738, 744, 
                    745 in the Erdman-Bloom text (and Bentley’s edition of the ms and my
                    critique of it in <hi rend="u">Library</hi> 1964[1968]). Finding the 
                    Cowper inscriptions (which Bentley and I did independently in pursuit 
                    of more data of <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s) is a great relief; I mean to 
                    say, the revised date of transition (back from June 1805 to 1803-04) 
                    makes the whole <hi rend="u">g</hi> hypothesis a lot easier to live 
                    with.</p>
                    <p>I still think it important that most of our assumptions about the 
                    <hi rend="u">Vala</hi> ms need to be blown sky high before we can 
                    understand the nature of the “evidence” we have concerning its 
                    inscription let alone its composition. One assumption was Bentley’s, 
                    that “once Blake had abandoned his beautiful, rounded copperplate 
                    hands for his more hurried usual hand, he never reverted to the
                    earlier style of writing” (p. 159). 1805 was an impossible date for 
                    copperplate hand preceding all usual hand ms; 1803 is still an 
                    improbable one, Nov 5 1802 (but there he was, in a long inscription 
                    under Cowper’s Weather-house, using sturdy leftward 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s over that date). I see him returning to the fine
                    hand in fine spirit, after his triumphant acquittal but determined on 
                    conquering from within the conventional ways, and introducing these 
                    rightward <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s into his beautiful, rounded 
                    copperplate.</p>
                    <p>To turn now to the first turning to leftward <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s 
                    in our table, it is hardly disputable that the Motto and last plate of 
                    <hi rend="u">Thel</hi> are in a different style of lettering from the 
                    rest of the work; nor is it against expectation to find that the 
                    “1790” page of <hi rend="u">MHH</hi> (pl 3) is in earlier style than 
                    “A Song of Liberty” (25-27); it is surprising to find a scatter of 
                    plates in both styles all through the work. Against the explanation 
                    that Blake was trying both kinds of <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s is the fact 
                    that no individual plate contains a mixture of kinds. Just as analysis 
                    of the script and content of <hi rend="u">Thel</hi> (which I’ll not go 
                    into here) bears out the assumption that the left-<hi rend="u">g</hi> 
                    plates
                    <pb id="p03-12" n="12"/>
                    are the latest parts, so analysis of <hi rend="u">MHH</hi> (hard to 
                    communicate, since it involves much looking and comparing) lends 
                    support to a similar assumption. We have not to do (as we may have in 
                    the case of <hi rend="u">Thel</hi>) with any marked thematic or tonal 
                    change, nor with much appreciable stylistic change except in the 
                    letter <hi rend="u">g.</hi> What happened, I suggest, is that after 
                    Blake had a complete version of <hi rend="u">The Marriage</hi> 
                    (probably minus the “Song”) on copper, he began thinking of 
                    improvements and amplifications—all his Illuminated works show this 
                    sort of revision—and made them by inserting new plates, onto which old 
                    and new matter were inscribed (at a time when he had changed his 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>). Consider Plate 4 is inserted to introduce the 
                    Devil, already required by the texts of 3 &amp; 5 but perhaps lacking 
                    at first; pl 7 begins as straight continuation of 6, where the 
                    Proverbs began; presumably the remaking of 7-10 was to accommodate 
                    additional proverbs. Plates 14-20 consist of four self-contained 
                    sections, the Printing House of 14 being a development of material in 
                    the Memorable Fancy of pl 6-7. What one must suppose about the new 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi> is either that some technical accident produced 
                    one, and he adopted it, or that he created it as part of the design of 
                    some contemporaneous work, perhaps <hi rend="u">Songs of 
                    Experience</hi> or <hi rend="u">America</hi>, and carried it over into 
                    other “repair” jobs in his workshop—<hi rend="u">Thel</hi> and 
                    <hi rend="u">MHH.</hi></p>
                    <p>Suggesting the first possibility is the curious glancing horizontal 
                    stroke above the serif of the first <hi rend="u">g</hi> on pl 7. Since 
                    Blake in the text at this point is being self-descriptive of his 
                    etching of this plate, could this mark his first new serif, a fresh, 
                    idiosyncratic fling, created and adopted at once? (Plate 4, amplifying 
                    the introduction to these Proverbs, can easily be a subsequent 
                    insertion.) As I have suggested, there is no ambiguity or indication 
                    of possible wavering in the lettering of this period such as there 
                    appears to be in the engraved inscriptions of 1802-05. Wherever it
                    appears the new style is clear, consistently adhered to; there seems 
                    to me every indication that Blake committed himself to it at once. But 
                    can we date the moment of commitment?</p>
                    <p>Taking late 1790 (Blake was born in November) or early 1791 as
                    firmly given by the date reference in <hi rend="u">MHH</hi> 3 
                    (supported as a reference to 1790 by marginal inscription in the Butts
                    copy), we have a date we cannot push back for the continuance of 
                    conventional <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s. On the other side a date probably 
                    not earlier than mid-1791 for the leftward plates 15, 17-20 is
                    established, I think, by the strong evidence of use in these plates of 
                    passages in Swedenborg’s <hi rend="u">Apocalypse Revealed</hi> (1791; 
                    the time of year can be found when we locate contemporary
                    advertisements of its publication: does anyone know?). (The passages 
                    noted by Désirée Hirst in <hi rend="u">Hidden Riches</hi>,
                    pp. 218-223, have more extensive echoes in <hi rend="u">MHH</hi> than 
                    Miss Hirst calls attention to.) These arrows point to 1791 (or later) 
                    as the time of the shift; it would be very convenient biographically 
                    to find it coincided with the move to Lambeth (which we now know 
                    occurred in early 1791). A date for Thel’s Motto etc as late as this 
                    does not seem improbable.</p>
                    <p>Another document that fits in here is <hi rend="u">A Divine 
                    Image</hi>, a sort of Song of Experience that first turned up when 
                    someone was, after Blake’s death, printing a set of the 
                    <hi rend="u">Songs</hi> and found this poem on the back of one of the 
                    plates. Keynes’s printing it after the <hi rend="u">Songs</hi> as an 
                    “Additional Poem” has obscured the fact that it is really a rejected 
                    poem; and indeed it turns out to have conventionally serifed 
                    <hi rend="u">g</hi>’s. Robert Gleckner, in <hi rend="u">PMLA</hi> Sept 
                    1961, without benefit of the <hi rend="u">g</hi> theory, made a strong 
                    case for an early date of composition by studying the evolution of 
                    texts from “The Divine Image” (TDI) to “I heard an Angel singing” 
                    (Angel) to “The Human Image” (THI) to “The Human Abstract” (THA), 
                    fitting <hi rend="u">A Divine Image</hi> (ADI) between the first two. 
                    I doubt if the sequence is that clear; ADI could come between Angel
                    and THI: but then Gleckner mistook the dates of Notebook use as 1793 
                    (they should be 1791-92 for the poems concerned). His sequence would 
                    put ADI in 1791; the alternative would put it in early 1792. In any 
                    case, here is a plate in conventional style well into 1791, it
                    <pb id="p03-13" n="13"/>
                    would seem. Add a further document, the canceled plates of 
                    <hi rend="u">America</hi>, in style and composition and symbolic 
                    drawing surely many months earlier than the final 
                    <hi rend="u">America</hi>: but with leftward g’s.</p>
                    <p>If you have been following, patient reader, the tug and push of the 
                    evidence, I believe you will see that we are pretty tightly wedged 
                    into a date somewhere in the middle of 1791 for the change. I think 
                    that a survey of other elements of Blake’s graphic style from 
                    <hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence</hi> through <hi rend="u">Songs of 
                    Experience</hi> would show <hi rend="u">Thel</hi>, even the original 
                    part, later than all Innocence songs but the Bard; <hi rend="u">A 
                    Divine Image</hi> contemporaneous with the revised plates of 
                    <hi rend="u">MHH.</hi></p>
                    <p>And if we now take the hypothesis of <hi rend="u">g</hi> as 
                    confirmed, with a first switch in 1791 and a second in 1803 (or 
                    1802-04-05), the remaining uncertainly dated works or inscriptions may
                    be located in tabular form. Let me include in it those we have been 
                    discussing.
                    <table rows="6" cols="2">
                            <head>
                                <title>Table 2</title>
                            </head>
                            <row>
                                <cell>a.</cell>
                                <cell>CONVENTIONAL <hi rend="u">g</hi> 
                                	probably PRECEDING mid-1791</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>A Divine Image</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>b.</cell>
                                <cell>CONVENTIONAL <hi rend="u">g</hi> 
                                	probably FOLLOWING 1803(ca)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>To Tirzah<lb/>
                                	Vala i pp 8, 10, 12; Night VI title<lb/>
                                	Joseph of Arimathea inscription</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>c.</cell>
                                <cell>IDIOSYNCRATIC <hi rend="u">g</hi> 
                                	between mid-1791 and 1803</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="u">Job</hi> undated 1st state 
                                    (precedes state dated Aug 18 1793)<lb/>
                                    America, 3 canceled plates<lb/>
                                    Thiralatha<lb/>
                                    Accusers inscription (first state)<lb/>
                                    The Reposing Traveller (Hagstrum pl 17)</cell>
                            </row>
                    </table>
					You will see that I have been unable to settle the case of 
					<hi rend="u">Albion rose</hi>, inclining to a straddle of 1800-1803. 
					Another lost item, of a very different nature, is the reported 
					conventional <hi rend="u">g</hi> in the Latin inscription of the plate 
					for Catullus, <hi rend="u">Poems</hi> (1795 which I have not seen: 
					without examination I can only express the hopeful confidence that GEB 
					is right in calling the inscription one for which Blake may not have 
					been responsible.</p>
                    <p>Are there any questions? Any additional points?</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>