<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.1.stevenson</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="query">Blake and William Frend</title>
				<author n="Stevenson">W. H. Stevenson</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>June 15, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <pb id="p03-19" n="19"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-1-0007">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="i">
                            <hi rend="u">QUERIES</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Blake and William Frend</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>John Adlard’s reference to Frend [<hi rend="i">BNL</hi> #8, p. 73] is very
interesting; but I wonder if the influence is not the other way round? Blake uses the idea in several places,
and it arises in the first place from his belief that in the perfect world perception would be infinite and
unlimited:</p>
					<q>
Earth was not: nor globes of attraction<lb/>
The will of the Immortal expended<lb/>
Or contracted his all flexible senses. (Urizen 3: 36-38)
</q>
                    <p>Blake seems slightly ambivalent in his treatment of the idea. Sometimes he contrasts
the infinite variability of the vision of eternity with the restricted sight of natural man, who can only see
and understand “globes of attraction.” Sometimes he uses the vision of different worlds as globes as one of
the possible attitudes of infinite vision; and this seems to be the point that Frend has taken. In the passage
quoted by John Adlard, Blake says that it is a man’s subjective viewpoint that counts, not his generalising
rationalisations about the universe. Unexpectedly, Blake vindicates the telescope and microscope against their
scientific users. These instruments assist the mortal eye, and open living worlds that had previously been
hidden. Newtonic generalisation closes them again, against the evidence of experience.</p>
                    <p>There are other passages, however, with a rather difficult angle. Also in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, plate 15, Blake describes the universe, not in terms of Newtonian globes, but of
Cartesian vortices:</p>
					<q>
when once a traveller thro’ Eternity<lb/>
Has passd that Vortex, he perceives it roll backward behind<lb/>
His path, into a globe itself infolding; like a sun:<lb/>
Or like a moon, or like a universe of starry majesty,<lb/>
While he keeps onwards in his wondrous journey on the earth<lb/>
Or like a human form, a friend with whom he livd benevolent.<lb/>
As the eye of man views both the east &amp; west encompassing<lb/>
Its vortex; and the north &amp; south, with all their starry host;<lb/>
Also the rising sun &amp; setting moon he views surrounding<lb/>
His corn-fields and his valleys of five hundred acres square.<lb/>
Thus is the earth one infinite plane, and not as apparent<lb/>
To the weak traveller confin’d beneath the moony shade.<lb/>
Thus is the heaven a vortex passd already, and the earth<lb/>
A vortex not yet pass’d by the traveller thro’ Eternity.
</q>
                    <p>The world of a man’s present, living experience, is opened out to him like the open
world of a flower. When he passes beyond it, and ceases to experience it directly, it rolls up into a
globe.</p>
                    <p>Again, in “The Mental Traveller,”</p>
					<q>
The Cottage fades before his sight<lb/>
The Garden &amp; its lovely Charms<lb/>
                        <lb/>
The Guests are scattered thro’ the land<lb/>
For the Eye altering alters all.<lb/>
The Senses roll themselves in fear<lb/>
And the flat Earth becomes a Ball<lb/>
                        <pb id="p03-20" n="20"/>
The Stars Sun Moon all shrink away<lb/>
A desert vast without a bound . . .
</q>
                    <p>Again the emphasis is on the difference between close acceptance of life, and fearful
shrinking from it: there is a common image in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> of a sort of “exploding universe” in
which not only the stars and plan but even the countries of the earth (notably Israel and Britain), are
alienated from each other (e.g. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 66: 40ff). In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 83: 33ff
this restricted vision becomes acceptable to Los after all, as a duty of the now repentant daughters of Albion
(82: 72-80) to give some kind of shadowy understanding of the truth to “the weak traveller confin’d beneath
the moony shade:”</p>
					<q>
An outside shadowy Surface superadded to the real Surface<lb/>
Which is unchangeable for ever &amp; ever Amen so be it!<lb/>
(83: 47-48)
</q>
                    <p>In short, Frend’s idea seems to be drawn from Blake, rather than vice versa, and this
explains the late date. Frend has watered it down, and turned it to a use which Blake would not accept; but
that is, unfortunately, a common fate of Blake’s particular and more original ideas.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>W.H. <name>Stevenson</name>
                        </docAuthor> University of Ibadan Nigeria</byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>