<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.2.essick</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">A Finding List of Reproductions of Blake’s Art</title>
				<author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>September 26, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-2-0003">
				<pb id="p03-24" n="24"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">A FINDING LIST OF REPRODUCTIONS OF BLAKE’S ART</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Compiled by <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>The following list is not intended as a bibliography of Blake’s art, but rather as an
aid to the researcher in finding reproductions of Blake’s works In those books and Journals (about 200
surveyed for this list) usually found in college and university libraries with good Blake collections. I have
made no attempt to establish the provenance, date, or medium of each work, and only include this information
when necessary for proper Identification. All reproductions listed are monochrome unless otherwise noted.
Reproductions are listed by the book (Identified by author’s or editor’s last name and short title) or
journal (name; volume, and year) in which they may be found, and located by the plate number (preceded by
“pl.”) or by the page (preceded by no abbreviation) on which they appear or are most closely contiguous.
Preliminary sketches, proof impressions, and other related materials are listed following the finished
engraving or painting with which they are associated. All drawings from Blake’s “Notebook” are reproduced in
Keynes’ facsimile of 1935. The list is divided into four main alphabetized sections, covering the
illuminated books, illustrations to Blake’s non-illuminated writings, illustrations in series to others’
writings (including book illustrations engraved but not designed by Blake), and all drawings, paintings, and
engravings not part of any series.</p>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>Part 1: The Illuminated Books</title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Complete facsimiles listed in Part 1 of the Bentley and Nurmi Bibliography or the
recent supplement issued by the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> are not included. Except for Songs of
Innocence and Songs of Innocence and of Experience (listed alphabetically by title following prefatory
plates), all plates are numbered and, whenever possible, copies identified (in parentheses at end of the
entry) according to the Keynes and Wolf Census. The plates in “A Small Book of Designs” and “A Large Book of
Designs” described in the Census are here listed as “separate plates” following the entry for the illuminated
plate from which they were taken, but of course copy identification for these separate plates refers to the
appropriate design book. Plates in the two design books not taken from the illuminated books are listed under
the propor title in section IV of this list.</p>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Keynes, Bibliography of Blake, 94.</p>
                            <p>7 (Principle 4). Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. VC.</p>
                            <p>9 (Principle 6). Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. VD.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">America</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete, Microfilm by Micro Methods Ltd. (color, O).</p>
                            <p>i (frontispiece). Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXXIV; Binyon, Engraved Designs of
Blake, pl. 50 (H); Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 262 and Blake’s Engravings, pl. 83; Figgis,
Paintings of Blake, pl. 95 (O); Langridge, Blake, 108 (H); Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 28 (O).</p>
                            <pb id="p03-25" n="25"/>
                            <p>ii (title page). Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXXIII; Chesterton, Blake, 60;
Selincourt, Blake, 138; Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 292; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet,
61 (color, M).</p>
                            <p>1. Chesterton, Blake, 66; upper design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 13 bottom;
Erdman, Prophet Against Empire, 236; Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LIVA (I); Raine, Blake and
Tradition, Pl. 112 (E). Saurat, Blake and Modern Thought, 178.</p>
                            <p>2. Wright, Blake for Babes, pl. 4; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pls. 84 (early
state) and 85 (as usually printed); Erdman, Prophet Against Empire, 237; Studies in Romanticism, VI (Autumn,
1966), 48 (P, and lower design only of a, K, F, L, H, I, E).</p>
                            <p>3. Sketch, rising figure. Brion, Romantic Art, 46.</p>
                            <p>4. Upper Design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 52 (E).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, similar to descending figure. Brion, Romantic Art, 46.</p>
                            <p>5. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 113 (1863), 110 (1880).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, two lower figures. Brion, Romantic Art, 46.</p>
                            <p>Sketch, similar to figure above snake. Notebook, 75 top right; Ellis and Yeats,
Works of Blake, 111, middle right of third page of reproductions from the Notebook.</p>
                            <p>6. Tinker, Poet and Painter, 116.</p>
                            <p>7. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXXV; Langridge, Blake, 20 (H); Binyon, Engraved
Designs of Blake, pl. 51 and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 21 (both H); Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s
Life of Blake, 112; Philadelphia Catalogue, 32; Frye, Selected Poetry and Prose of Blake, 226 (A); Keynes,
Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 63 (color, M); Ralne, Blake and Tradition, pl. 80 (E).</p>
                            <p>8. Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 86; upper design, Digby, Symbol and Image
in Blake, pl. 26 (O); Hilles and Bloom, eds., From Sensibility to Romanticism, 318, pl. IV; Keynes, Blake:
Poet, Printer, Prophet, 65 (color, M).</p>
                            <p>9. Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 87; lower design, Digby, Symbol and Image
in Blake, pl. 37 (O); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LIVB (1).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, similar to suplne figure. Notebook, 77 bottom.</p>
                            <p>10. Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 88; Erdman, Poetry and Prose of Blake,
pl. 1; Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 113 (E).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, similar to the figure. Notebook, 108; Wicksteed, Blake’s Innocence
and Experience, 244.</p>
                            <p>11. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 112(1863), 108(1880); Cary, Art of Blake, pl.
XXXVI; Garnett, Blake, 42; Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 52 and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl.
20 (both H); lower design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 12 top and Blake for Bebes, pl. 1; Keynes, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. 89; upper design, Margoliouth, Blake, 85; Woods, ed., English Poetry and Prose of the Romantic
Movement, 180; Bronowski, Blake and the Age of Revolution, pl. 2 (H).</p>
                            <p>12. Tinker, Poet and Painter, 114.</p>
                            <p>13. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXXVII; Langridge, Blake, 110 (H); Garnett, Blake,
48; lower design, Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 76 (O); Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 67
(color, M).</p>
                            <p>14. Center design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 15 bottom; Keynes, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. 90; Frye, Foarful Symmetry, 140 (A); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LVA (1); Beer,
Blake’s Humanism, pl. 29 (O).</p>
                            <p>16. Upper design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 15 top; Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and
Painter, pl. LVB (1).</p>
                            <pb id="p03-26" n="26"/>
                            <p>c. Keynes and Wolf, Census, 42 (a*).</p>
                            <p>d, printed as a separate plate in A Large Bk. of Designs. Binyon, Engraved
Designs of Blake, pl. 53 (color, A) and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 35 (A); Keynes and Wolf, Census,
90 (B); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 73 (B).</p>
                            <p>Sketch of a diving figure, associated with America. Selincourt, Blake, 248;
Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 11.</p>
                            <p>Sketches for figures in America. Brion, Romantic Art, 46.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Book of Ahania</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Frontispiece. Wilson, Life of Blake (1927), 94 (B*); Philadelphia Catalogue, 50
(A).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Keynes, Blake’s Drawings, second series, pl. 7.</p>
                            <p>i (title page). Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXXVIII (probably A); Sampson,
Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 340 (A); Philadelphia Catalogue, 52 (A); figure only, Raine, Blake and
Tradition, pl. 68 (A).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Book of Los</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>1 (frontispiece). Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 332.</p>
                            <p>2 (title page). Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 334; Binyon, Engraved
Designs of Blake, pl. 60.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Microfilm by Micro Methods Ltd. (color, G).</p>
                            <p>ii (title page). Swinburne, Blake, 200 (probably D, color in first ed.,
monochrome in 1967 reprint); Garnett, Blake, 33 (color); Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XIV; Sampson, Blake’s
Poetical Works (1913), 240; Plowman, Introduction to Blake, 49; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 91;
Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. XLVIII (L); Huntington Library Calendar of the Exhibitions, Nov.-Dec.
1965 (L); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 44 (color, D).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of
Blake, pl. 10 (color); Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 172 bottom.</p>
                            <p>1. Lettering of “Thel” only, Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11, 71 (1863), 77
(1880).</p>
                            <p>2. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XV; Selincourt, Blake, 18; Chesterton, Blake, 10;
Wright, Blake for Babes, pl. 6.</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925),
1, 172 top.</p>
                            <p>4. Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 11 (D).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake,
pl. 47 and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 12 (both color); Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 174
top; Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 20a.</p>
                            <p>5. Philadelphia Catalogue, 14; lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 51
(color, G).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Selincourt, Blake, 100; Keynes,
Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 174 bottom.</p>
                            <p>6. Garnett, Blake, 36 (color); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. XLIXB
(L); lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 54 (G).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, figures associated with Thel. Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl.
4.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <pb id="p03-27" n="27"/>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Book of Urizen</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Emery, ed., The Book of Urizen (G).</p>
                            <p>1 (title page). Langridge, Blake, 116; Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works
(1913), 312; Percival, Blake’s Circle of Destiny, 20 left; Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 16 top (B); Frye,
Selected Poetry and Prose of Blake, 226; Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. 1 (G); Keynes, Blake: Poet,
Printer, Prophet, 71 (color, G); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 145 (G).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Keynes and Wolf, Census, 85
(B).</p>
                            <p>2. Chesterton, Blake 108 (probably D); Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 33 (G).
Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs, inscribed “Teach these Souls to Fly” in copy B. Selincourt,
Blake, 30 (A); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 55 (color, A) and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl.
24 (A); Butlin, Tate Catalogue of Blake, pl. 3 (B); Keynes, The Masters: Blake, pl. VI (color, enlarged, B);
slide by American Library Color Slide Co. (color, B).</p>
                            <p>3. Upper design, Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 32 (G).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate. Langridge, Blake, 120 (from A Small Bk. of Designs, A);
Preston, Blake Collection of Robertson, pl. 64 (from A Small Bk. of Designs, B, inscribed “Oh! Flames of
Furious Desires” in a modern hand on the mount); Butlin, Tate Catalogue of Blake, pl. 6 (not part of any
design bk., inscribed, not by Blake, “Oh! Flames of Furious Desires”).</p>
                            <p>4. Lower design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 16 bottom (perhaps a separate print
not part of any copy).</p>
                            <p>5. Percival, Blake’s Circle of Destiny, 26 left.</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs, inscribed “The Book of my
Remembrance” in B. Greenough, Home Bible, 340 first section (B).</p>
                            <p>6. Hirst, Hidden Riches, 193 (D); lower design, Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl.
37 (G); lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 146 (G).</p>
                            <p>7. Langridge, Blake, 118.</p>
                            <p>8. Percival, Blake’s Circle of Destiny, 20 right.</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Garnett, Blake, 34; Binyon,
Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 25.</p>
                            <p>9. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 56 (color, D) and Drawings and
Engravings of Blake, pl. 26 (D); Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 308; Réalités, Jan. 1968, 16 (separate
print, perhaps a in the Census, page 86).</p>
                            <p>10. Upper design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 148 (G).</p>
                            <p>11. Lower design, Pinto, ed., William Blake, pl. 3 (G).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Saurat, Blake and Modern Thought,
37 (A).</p>
                            <p>12. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 312 and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet,
73 (color, G); Blackstone, English Blake, pl. V (D); Blunt, Art of Blake, 23a (D); de Keyser, The Romantic
West, 74 (G).</p>
                            <p>13. Blackstone, English Blake, pl. 11 (D); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter,
pl. XXIII (G).</p>
                            <p>14. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 306 and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet,
75 (color, G); Philadelphia Catalogue, 43 (G); Gardner, Blake the Man, 108 (D); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and
Painter, pl. XXVIIIB (G).</p>
                            <p>15. Lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, 158 (G).</p>
                            <pb id="p03-28" n="28"/>
                            <p>16. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 310 and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet,
79 (color, G); Wilson, Life of Blake (1927), 91.</p>
                            <p>17. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 314; Blackstone, English Blake, pl. VI
(D).</p>
                            <p>19. Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Saurat, Blake and Modern
Thought, 169 (A).</p>
                            <p>20. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 57 (color, D) lower design, Raine,
Blake and Tradition, pl. 3 (G).</p>
                            <p>21. Langridge, Blake, 26; Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 58 (color, D)
and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 27 (D); Bronowski, Blake and the Age of Revolution, pl. 4 (D);
Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 111 (G).</p>
                            <p>22. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 320 second plate and Blake: Poet,
Printer, Prophet, 77 (color, G); Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 28 (D); Gardner, Blake the Man,
106 (D); Percival, Blake’s Circle of Destiny, 26 middle; Philadelphia Catalogue, 42 (G); Hagstrum, Blake:
Poet and Painter, pl. LVIIA (G); RAine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 14 (G).</p>
                            <p>23. Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. XXI (G); lower design, Raine, Blake
and Tradition, pl. 90 (G).</p>
                            <p>24. Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 17 top (B) and bottom (D); Beer, Blake’s
Humanism, pl. 11 (G); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 147 (G).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, lower left of plate 24 only, from A Small Bk. of Designs.
Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 318; Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 59 (color).</p>
                            <p>25. Upper design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 17 (G).</p>
                            <p>26. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 320 first plate.</p>
                            <p>27. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 322.</p>
                            <p>28. Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 29 (D); Percival, Blake’s
Circle of Destiny, 26 right.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Microfilm by Micro Methods, Ltd. (color, K). (frontispiece).
Chesterton, Blake, 38 (probably D); Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 380 (D, with Cumberland’s
inscriptions); Gardner, Blake the Man, 100 (probably D); Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 30
(color, K); Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 19 top (D); Greenough, Home Bible; frontispiece to first section
(color, G); Pinto, ed., William Blake, pl. 4 (D); Digby, Symbol and image in Blake, pl. 53 (D); Beer,
Blake’s Humanism, pl. 24 (K); slide included in Stillman, English Art (color, probably E, but may be a
separate print); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 144 (color, probably E, but may be a separate print).</p>
                            <p>Separate print, “The Ancient of Days.” Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1,
294, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 92, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 59 (color, Keynes copy), and Engravings by
Blake: Separate Plates, pl. 16 (color, Keynes copy); Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XIX; Garnett, Blake, 38 (Br.
Museum copy with right arm appearing); Wright, Life of Blake, II, frontispiece (color, Whitworth copy);
Figgis, Paintings of Blake, pl. 1 (color, Whitworth copy); Langridge, Blake, 112. (copy with right arm
appearing); Van Sinderen, Blake: The Mystic Genius, frontispiece; Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 24a (Whitworth
copy); Percival, Blake’s Circle of Destiny, 20 middle; Raine, Writers and Their Work;
<pb id="p03-29" n="29"/>
Blake, 22 (Whitworth copy); Bronowski, Blake and the Age of Revolution, pl. 5 (Whitworth copy); Frye, Fearful
Symmetry, pl. 3 (Morgan copy); Pinto, ed., The Divine Vision, 208 (an uncolored Br. Museum copy); Réalités,
Jan. 1968, 86 (color).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 96.</p>
                            <p>ii (title page). Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXVII; Selincourt, Blake, 234 (D);
Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 302 (probably K); Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 28 (K).</p>
                            <p>Proof, with figure (Cameron, Crawford and Balcarres copy). Keynes, Bibliography
of Blake, 139.</p>
                            <p>1. Upper design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 18 bottom; upper design, Erdman,
Prophet Against Empire, pl. Va (H).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, figure with dagger. Notebook, 97.</p>
                            <p>Sketch, grotesque head. Notebook, 74 left bottom and 75 left top; Ellis and
Yeats, Works of Blake, III, top section of third page of reproductions from the Notebook.</p>
                            <p>2. Keynes and Wolf, Census, 77 (b*).</p>
                            <p>Water color, with two extra figures. Figgis, Paintings of Blake, pl. 96
(probably not wholly by Blake—see Keynes, TLS, Dec. 17, 1925, page 883).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, struggling figure. Notebook, 8.</p>
                            <p>3. Chesterton, Blake, 74; Langridge, Blake, 114.</p>
                            <p>5. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXVIII; Erdman, Prophet Against Empire, pl. VI
(H).</p>
                            <p>6. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 300 and Blake’s Engravings, pl. 93
(first state).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, left figure. Figgis, Paintings of Blake, 82 of the text; Keynes,
Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 10.</p>
                            <p>7. Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 128 (not part of any copy);
Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 298 and Blake’s Engravings, pls. 94 (first state) and 95 (second
state); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 54 (D); Preston, Blake Collection of Robertson, pl. 63 (not
part of any copy); Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 23b.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 25.</p>
                            <p>8. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXIX.</p>
                            <p>Sketch, figures. Figgis, Paintings of Blake, 82 of the text; Keynes, Drawings
by Blake (1927), pl. 10.</p>
                            <p>9. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 126 (1863), 124 (1880); Robertson, ed.,
Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 130; Langridge, Blake, 24; Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 19 bottom (D); Clark, The
Nude, pl. 164; Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 47 (K).</p>
                            <p>10. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXX.</p>
                            <p>11. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXXI; Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. III
(K).</p>
                            <p>12. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 129 (1863), 126 (1880); Digby, Symbol and
image in Blake, pl. 33 (D); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 115 (E).</p>
                            <p>13. Lower design, Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 44 (D); lower design,
Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 49 (K).</p>
                            <p>14. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XXXII.</p>
                            <p>15. Philadelphia Catalogue, 38 (the Rosenwald proof—see the Census, page
79).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Ghost of Abel</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Sloss and Wallis, Blake’s Prophetic Writings, 1, 644.</p>
                            <p>2. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. L; Keynes, Bibliography of Blake, 172 (B).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <pb id="p03-30" n="30"/>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Microfilm by Micro Methods Ltd. (color, E).</p>
                            <p>1. (frontispiece). Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 111, 166, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. 103, and Blake Studies, pl. 30 (Keynes proof, with text); frontispiece to the Blake Trust
facsimile of copy C (Keynes proof, with text); Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 35 (A); Hagstrum, Blake:
Poet and Painter, pl. LXIIA (E) and Blake’s Blake in Bluhm, ed., Essays . . . Presented . . . to Stanley
Pargellis, pl. VIA (F); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 89 (E).</p>
                            <p>2. (title page). Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 384; Wicksteed,
Blake’s Jerusalem, pl. XVI (E); Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 91 (color, E); Raine, Blake and
Tradition, 1, frontispiece (color, E).</p>
                            <p>4. Upper design, Plowman, Introduction to Blake, 97.</p>
                            <p>5. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 65 (color, E).</p>
                            <p>6. Lower design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 12 bottom and Blake for Babes, pl.
3; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 104; lower design, Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 39 (A);
Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LX (E); lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 128 (E). Saurat,
Blake and Modern Thought, 172.</p>
                            <p>8. Lower design, Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 59 (A).</p>
                            <p>11. Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 66; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 93
(color, E).</p>
                            <p>14. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 66 (color, E); lower design, Digby,
Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 36 (E); lower design, Margoliouth, Blake, 152 (A); lower design, Pinto, ed.,
William Blake, 167 (C).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 37.</p>
                            <p>18. Design only, Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 65 (E); design only,
Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 86 (E); design only, Rosenfeld, ed. Blake: Essays for Damon, pl. XXVI (D).</p>
                            <p>19. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 67 (color, E).</p>
                            <p>22. Lower design, Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 27 (E); lower design,
Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 164 (E).</p>
                            <p>24. Upper third, Todd, Tracks in the Snow, 39; upper design, Digby, Symbol and
Image in Blake (E); upper design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 97 (I).</p>
                            <p>25. Design only, Todd, Tracks in the Snow, 53; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings,
pl. 25; Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 52 (E); Frye, Selected Poetry and Prose of Blake, 226 (F);
Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LVIIIA (E); design only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 187 (color,
B*). Saurat, Blake and Modern Thought, 115.</p>
                            <p>26. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 111, 200; Digby, Symbol and Image in
Blake, pl. 71 (E).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 38.</p>
                            <p>28. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 68 (color, E) and upper design,
Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 60 (A); Frye, Fearful Symmetry, 300 (F); Wicksteed, Blake’s Jerusalem,
pls. XXI (E) and XXII (F); upper design, Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 70 (E); upper design, Damon,
Blake Dictionary, pl. V bottom (F) and top (D); upper design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 46 (E); upper
design, Rosenfeld, ed., Blake: Essays for Damon, pl. XXIV bottom (F) and top (D).</p>
                            <p>31. Lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 39 (E).</p>
                            <pb id="p03-31" n="31"/>
                            <p>32. Design only, Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 193 (1863), 236 (1880); design
only, Selincourt, Blake, 281 (E); Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 206; Philadelphia Catalogue, 70
(probably F); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 69 (C); Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 106; design
only, Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 66 (A); detail, Wicksteed, Blake’s Jerusalem, pl. XXIII (E);
detail, Lister, Beulah to Byzantium, pl. IV; Irwin, English Neo-classical Art, pl. 100; Hagstrum, Blake: Poet
and Painter, pl. LVIIIB (E); design only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 85 (color, B*).</p>
                            <p>33. Chesterton, Blake, 138 design only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 180
(E).</p>
                            <p>35. Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 210; Binyon, Engraved Designs
of Blake, pl. 70 (E) and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 61 (A); Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet,
95 (color, E).</p>
                            <p>37. Swinburne, Blake, 282 (probably A); Langridge, Blake, 128; Cary, Art of
Blake, pl. VI; Chesterton, Blake, 150; Philadelphia Catalogue, paper cover (probably F); Binyon, Engraved
Designs of Blake, pl. 71 (C); Keynes and Wolf, Census, 106 (early proof); Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake,
pl. 40 (E); Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 97 (color, E); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LIX
(E); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 191 (E).</p>
                            <p>39. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 194 (1863), 238 (1880); Selincourt, Blake, 192
(E); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 72 (color, E); Percival, Blake’s Circle of Destiny, 160; Keynes,
Blake’s Engravings, 110.</p>
                            <p>Sketch, the bowman. Philadelphia Catalogue, 72; Keynes, Blake’s Drawings,
second series, pl. 28.</p>
                            <p>41. Lower design, Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 111, 226, Poetry and Prose,
627 (1927), 448 (1939), and Complete Writings (1957, 1966), 669; lower design, Erdman, Poetry and Prose of
Blake, 182.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Keynes, Blake’s Drawings, second series, pl. 29.</p>
                            <p>44. Upper design, Todd, Tracks in the Snow, 40; upper design, Raine, Blake and
Tradition, pl. 94 (E).</p>
                            <p>46. Selincourt, Blake, 195 (E); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 73 (E)
and lower design, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 63 (A); Sloss and Wallis, Blake’s Prophetic
Writings, 1, 530 (A); Keynes, Bibliography of Blake, 163 (C) and Blake’s Engravings, pl. 107; lower design,
Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 50b; Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 181 (E).</p>
                            <p>47. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 74 (C); Keynes, Bibliography of
Blake, 164 (C) and Blake’s Engravings, pl. 108; design only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 171 (E).</p>
                            <p>48. Lower portion of text, BNYPL, 64 (1960), 594 (C and F).</p>
                            <p>50. Lower figure, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 65 right bottom.</p>
                            <p>51. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 230 (1880); Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s Life
of Blake, 198; Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 111, 240 and Blake’s Engravings, pl. 109; Figgis, Paintings
of Blake, pl. 93 (not part of any copy); Schorer, Blake: Politics of Vision, 334, 234 in paperback (D).</p>
                            <p>53. Upper design, Selincourt, Blake, 185 (probably not part of any copy);
Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 75 (color, not part of any copy); Frye, Selected Poetry and Prose of
Blake, 226 (F); upper design,
<pb id="p03-32" n="32"/>
Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 50d; upper design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 87 (E); upper design, Rosenfeld,
ed., Blake: Essays for Damon, pl. XXV (D).</p>
                            <p>54. Upper central section, Keynes, WRitings of Blake (1925), 111, 246, Poetry
and Prose, 651 (1927), 501 (1939), and Complete Writings (1957, 1966), 685; upper central section, Erdman,
Poetry and Prose of Blake, 201; upper central section, Hilles and Bloom, eds., From Sensibility to
Romanticism, 312, pl. 1B; lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 133 (E).</p>
                            <p>57. Selincourt, Blake, 159 (A); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 76
(color, E); Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 111; Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. XXXIII (F).</p>
                            <p>58. Design only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 96 (E).</p>
                            <p>59. Upper design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 31 (E).</p>
                            <p>63. Middle design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 42 bottom; middle design, Erdman,
Prophet Against Empire, 429 (D).</p>
                            <p>69. Lower design, Erdman, Prophet Against Empire, 435 (D); Wicksteed, Blake’s
Jerusalem, pl. XXV (E); lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 106 (E).</p>
                            <p>70. Swinburne, Blake, frontispiece (color in first ed., monochrome in 1967
reprint); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 77 (color, E) and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 64
(A); Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, frontispiece and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 99 (color, E); Todd, Tracks
in the Snow, 51; Frye, Selected Poetry and Prose of Blake, 226 (F); Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 48b.</p>
                            <p>72. Central and lower designs, Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 111, 278-9,
Poetry and Prose, 695-6 (1927), 530-1 (1939), and Complete Writings (1957, 1966), 712; central and lower
designs, Erdman, Poetry and Prose of Blake, 225; central design, Hilles and Bloom, eds., From Sensibility to
Romanticism, 312, pl. 1A.</p>
                            <p>75. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 78 (color, E); Keynes, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. 112; Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 32 (E).</p>
                            <p>76. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 194 (1863), 240 (1880); Chesterton, Blake,
156; Selincourt, Blake, 231 (A); Cary, Art of Blake, pl. V; Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 214;
Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pls. 79 (C) and 80 (E) and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 65 (A);
Keynes, Bibliography of Blake, 166 (E, color in first ed., monochrome in 1969 reprint), Writings of Blake
(1925), 111, 282, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 113, and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, frontispiece (color, E);
Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 48a; Gardner, Blake the Man, 144 (A); Greenough, Home Bible, 184 second section (D);
Hirst, Hidden Riches, pl. 3 (C); Hughes, ed., Jerusalem, frontispiece; Hilles and Bloom, eds., From
Sensibility to Romanticism, 318, pl. V (probably C); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 173 (E).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, figure of Albion. Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 2; Blunt, Art
of Blake, pl. 6c.</p>
                            <p>77. Criticism, VIII (1966), 116 figure 1 (E).</p>
                            <p>78. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 182 (1863), 226 (1880); upper design, Wright,
Life of Blake, pl. 6 top and Blake for Babes, pl. 2; upper design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 55 (E).</p>
                            <p>79. Swinburne, Blake, 276 (probably A); lower design, Keynes, Writings of Blake
(1925), 111, 293, Poetry and Prose, 715 (1927), 543 (1939), Complete Writings (1957, 1966), 724, and Blake:
Poet, Printer, Prophet, 101 (full plate, color, E); lower design, Erdman, Poetry and Prose of Blake, 236.</p>
                            <pb id="p03-33" n="33"/>
                            <p>84. Wicksteed, Blake’s Jerusalem, pl. XXVI (E).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, child and old man. Notebook, 54; Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl.
14 and Blake Studies, pl. 6. See also “London” In Songs of Experience.</p>
                            <p>85. Lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 166 (E).</p>
                            <p>87. Wicksteed, Blake’s Jerusalem, pl. XXVII (E); upper design, Raine, Blake
and Tradition, pl. 103 (E).</p>
                            <p>91. Design only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 188 (E).</p>
                            <p>93. Upper design, Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 111, 313, Poetry and Prose,
740 (1927), 560 (1939), and Complete Writings (1957, 1966), 740; upper design, Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 65
top; upper design, Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 51c; upper design, Erdman, Prophet Against Empire, 425 (D) and
Poetry and Prose of Blake, 250.</p>
                            <p>97. Selincourt, Blake, 26 (A); Wright, Life of Blake, 1, frontispiece (color,
E) and lower design, Blake for Babes, pl. 5; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 114; Hagstrum, Blake’s Blake
in Bluhm, ed., Essays . . . Presented . . . to Stanley Pargellis, pl. VIB (F) and Blake: Poet and Painter, pl.
LXIIB (E); Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 43 (H).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 39.</p>
                            <p>99. Selincourt, Blake, 55 (E); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 81 (E);
Blackstone, English Blake, pl. VIII (E); Wicksteed, Blake’s Jerusalem, pl. XXVIII (E); Gaunt, Arrows of
Desire, 177; Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 49a; design only, Pinto, ed., William Blake, 177 (C); Keynes, Blake:
Poet, Printer, Prophet, 103 (color, E); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LXI (E); Raine, Blake and
Tradition, pl. 81 (E). Saurat, Blake and Modern Thought, 185.</p>
                            <p>100. Chesterton, Blake, 126; Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 111, 320; Todd,
Tracks in the Snow, 49; Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 77 (F); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl.
LVIIB (E); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 18 (E). Saurat, Blake and Modern Thought, 53.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Microfilm by Micro Methods Ltd. (color, 1); Emery, ed., The Marriage
of Heaven and Hell (1).</p>
                            <p>1. (title page). Swinburne, Blake, 204 (color in first ed., monochrome In 1967
reprint); Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 246; Blunt, Art of Blake, 22a; Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and
Painter, pl. L (H); Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 53 (color, D); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 118
(D).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, embracing figures. Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 7 left
top.</p>
                            <p>2. Rosenfeld, ed., Blake: Essays for Damon, pl. XXVLI (A).</p>
                            <p>3. Langridge, Blake, 90; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 53 (color, D);
lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 110 (D).</p>
                            <p>4. Lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 119 (D).</p>
                            <p>See also “The Good and Evil Angels.” Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XLVIII (Whitney
color print); Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 142 (Tate color print); Figgis, Paintings of Blake,
pl. 71 (Tate color print); Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 182 (Tate color print); Philadelphia
Catalogue, 137 (Whitney color print); Blunt, Art of Blake, pls. 32a (water color) and 32b (Tate color print);
Preston, Blake Collection of Robertson, pl. 6 (Tate color print); Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 36
(Tate color print); Butlin, Tate Catalogue of Blake, pl. 13 (color, Tate color print); slide by
<pb id="p03-34" n="34"/>
American Library Color Slide Co. (color, Tate color print); Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 30 top (Tate color
print) and bottom (water color); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 120 (color, Tate color print).</p>
                            <p>5. Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 53 (color, D).</p>
                            <p>8. Swinburne, Blake, 208 (color in first ed., monochrome in 1967 reprint);
Keynes, Bibliography of Blake, 112 (H, color in first ed., monochrome in 1969 reprint).</p>
                            <p>9. Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 53 (color, D).</p>
                            <p>10. Philadelphia Catalogue, 21.</p>
                            <p>12. Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer. Prophet, 55 (color, D).</p>
                            <p>15. Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 55 (color, D); design only, Raine,
Blake and Tradition, pl. 56 (D).</p>
                            <p>16. See the following associated items:</p>
                            <p>Sketch, “Is All Joy Forbidden?” Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 7.</p>
                            <p>Gates of Paradise, pl. 12. Russell, Engravings of Blake, pl. 5; Binyon,
Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 9-(1); Philadelphia Catalogue, 61.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 59; Keynes, Gates of Paradise, 1.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 9.</p>
                            <p>Dante drawing 68. Illustrations to the Divine Comedy of Dante by Blake (1922,
1968); Roe, Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine Comedy.</p>
                            <p>Tempera, “Ugolino in Prison,” Keynes, Letters of Blake, 204 (first ed.), 176
(second ed.) and Tempera Paintings of Blake, pl. XI.</p>
                            <p>20. Swinburne, Blake, 224 (color in first ed., monochrome in 1967 reprint);
Keynes, Bibliography of Blake, 108 (H, color in first ed., monochrome in 1969 reprint).</p>
                            <p>21. Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 55 (color, D) and Bibliotheca
Bibliographici, pl. XII (E); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LIA (H); Lister, Blake, pl. 6 (D).</p>
                            <p>24. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XLIV; Frye, Selected Poetry and Prose of Blake, 226
(C); Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 55 (color, D); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LIB (H);
design only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 156 (D).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 44; Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XLIII; Keynes, Drawings by Blake
(1927), pl. 13.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 48.</p>
                            <p>See also the color print, “Nebuchadnezzar.” Keynes, Blake’s illustrations to
the Bible, pls. 84a (Butts copy) and 84c (Richmond copy), Blake (Faber Gallery), pl. 3 (color, Butts) and The
Masters: Blake, pl. 11 (color, Butts); Selincourt, Blake, 244 (Butts); Robertson, ed., Gilchrist’s Life of
Blake, 90 (Butts); Figgis, Paintings of Blake, pl. 77 (color, Butts); Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 31c (Butts);
Erdman, Prophet Against Empire, pl. VIIb (Butts); Preston, Blake Collection of Robertson, pl. 4 (Butts);
Butlin, Tate Catalogue of Blake, pl. 11 and Blake: Tate Gallery, pl. 11 (both Butts); slide by American
Library Color Slide Co. (color, Butts).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Microfilm by Micro Methods Ltd. (color, A).</p>
                            <p>1. (title page). Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 368; Sloss and
Wallis, Blake’s Prophetic Writings, 1, frontispiece (C); Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 98 and Blake:
Poet, Printer, Prophet, 83 (color, D); Wicksteed, Blake’s Jerusalem, pl. XIV (A); Hagstrum,
<pb id="p03-35" n="35"/>
Blake’s Blake in Bluhm, ed., Essays . . . Presented . . . to Stanley Pargeilis, pl. VIIA (B) and Blake: Poet
and Painter, pl. XXIV (B).</p>
                            <p>2. Wicksteed, Blake’s Jerusalem, pl. XIII (A); added to Blake Trust facsimile
of copy D (A).</p>
                            <p>4. Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 56 (A); Sloss and Wallis,
Blake’s Prophetic Writings, 1, 358 (A); Blackstone, English Blake, pl. VII (A); Wicksteed, Blake’s
Jerusalem, pl. XIX (A); Bronowski, Blake and the Age of Revolution, pl. 3 (A).</p>
                            <p>8. Swinburne, Blake, 258 (probably A, color in first ed., monochrome in 1967
reprint); Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 11, 318.</p>
                            <p>13. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 62 (A); Keynes, Writings of Blake
(1925), 11, 324; Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 49 (A); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 184 (C).</p>
                            <p>15. Chesterton, BLake, 174; Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 63 (A);
Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 11, 326, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 99, and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 85
(color, D); Philadelphia Catalogue, 64 (D); Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 25 (A); Raine. Blake and
Tradition, pl. 142 (D).</p>
                            <p>21. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 11, 336; Philadelphia Catalogue, 68, pl.
47 (D); Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 47 (A); Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 25 (A); Raine, Blake and
Tradition, pl. 91 (C).</p>
                            <p>24. Upper section, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 114 (D).</p>
                            <p>29. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 11, 350 and Blake’s Engravings, pl.
100; Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 47 top; Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 50 (A); Hagstrum, Blake’s
Blake in Bluhm, ed., Essays . . . Presented . . . to Stanley Pargeilis, pl. IV (B).</p>
                            <p>30. Upper design, Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 11, 352, Poetry and Prose,
524 (1927), 415 (1939), and Complete WVitings (1957, 1966), 518; upper design, Erdman, Poetry and Prose of
Blake, 128.</p>
                            <p>32. Lower design, Maclaglan and Russell, eds., Milton, 57; lower design,
Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 11, 358, Poetry and Prose, 524 (1927), 421 (1939), and Complete Writings
(1957, 1966), 523; lower design, Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 30 (A); lower design, Erdman, Poetry
and Prose of Blake, 132; lower design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 168 (D).</p>
                            <p>33. Garnett, Blake, 47; Langridge, Blake, 134; Keynes, Writings of Blake
(1925), 11, 356; Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 47 bottom.</p>
                            <p>36. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 198 (1863), 245 (1880); Binyon, Drawings and
Engravings of Blake, pl. 57 (A); Philadelphia Catalogue, 64, pl. 40 (D); Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl.
101; Hagstrum, Blake’s Blake in Biuhm, ed., Essays . . . Presented . . . to Stanley Pargeilis, pl. VIIB
(B).</p>
                            <p>38. Chesterton, Blake, 144; Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 11, 364,
Blake’s Engravings, pl. 102, and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 87 (color, D); Binyon, Engraved Designs of
Blake, pl. 64 (not part of any copy) and Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 58 (A); Digby, Symbol and Image
in Blake, pl. 64 (A). Rudd, Organiz’d Innocence, frontispiece (A).</p>
                            <pb id="p03-36" n="36"/>
                            <p>41. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 11, 368.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 33.</p>
                            <p>43. Chesterton, Blake, 132.</p>
                            <p>45. Ralne, Blake and Tradition, pl. 69 (D).</p>
                            <p>a. Keynes and Wolf, Census, 102 (D).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, “The Bowman,” perhaps to be associated with Milton. Keynes, Blake’s
Drawings, second series, pl. 22; Preston, Blake Collection of Robertson, pl. 62.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Microfilm by Micro Methods Ltd. (color, D).</p>
                            <p>1. (frontlspiece). Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 338; Philadelphia
Catalogue, 48 (B).</p>
                            <p>2. (title page). Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 330; Hagstrum,
Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. VI (E).</p>
                            <p>4. Chesterton, Blake, 114.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 60.</p>
                            <p>5. Selincourt, Blake, 35 (A or D); Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake,
pl. 33 (A or D); Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 340.</p>
                            <p>Sketch, perhaps by Robert Blake. Notebook, 13; Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XL;
Wilson, Life of Blake (1927), 36; Keynes, Blake Studies, pl. 4.</p>
                            <p>Water color, “Oberon and Titania on a Lily.” Brown and Harris, eds., Early
Shakespeare (Stratford-Upon-Avon Studies), 168, pl. 3b; Merchant, Blake’s Shakespeare, In Apollo, 79 new
series (April, 1964), 322, pl. 7.</p>
                            <p>6. Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. VII (E).</p>
                            <p>8. Selincourt, Blake, 168 (A or D); Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 342;
Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 93 (B, but here mis-titled “Book of Los”).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. See Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</p>
                            <p>Frontispiece. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. VIII; Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925),
1, 148 and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 31 (color, Z of Innoc. &amp; Exp.); Gaunt, Concise History of
English Painting, pl. 108; Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 2.</p>
                            <p>Title Page. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Cary, Art of Blake, pl.
X; Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 64; Woods, ed., English Poetry and Prose of the Romantic
Movement, 168; Keynes, Blake Studies, 106, pl. A (Gilchrist electrotype) and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 31
(color, Z of Inno. &amp; Exp.); Blunt, Art of Blake, 14a.</p>
                            <p>“Introduction.” Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 16a; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer,
Prophet, 33 (color, Z of Inno. &amp; Exp.).</p>
                            <p>“The Blossom.” Binyon, Drawings <corr type="emend">and Engravings</corr> of
Blake, pl. 6 (color, AA of Inno. &amp; Exp.); Wicksteed, Blake’s Innocence and Experience, 76 (color, AA of
Inno. &amp; Exp.); Philadelphia Catalogue, 11; Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 18b; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer,
Prophet, 35 (color, Z of Inno. &amp; Exp.); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. XLV (B of Inno.).</p>
                            <p>“A Cradle Song,” first plate. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype);
Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. XVIII (Gilchrist electrotype).</p>
                            <pb id="p03-37" n="37"/>
                            <p>“The Divine Image.” Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Langridge,
Blake, 16; Chesterton, Blake, 18; Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 7; Keynes, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. XIX (Gilchrist electrotype) and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 37 (color, Z of Inno. &amp;
Exp.); Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 18a; Hilles and Bloom, eds., From Sensibility to Romanticism, 313, pl. 11;
Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. XLIV (B of Inno.).</p>
                            <p>“The Eccholng Green,” both plates. Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 33
(color, Z of Inno. &amp; Exp.); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pls. XXXIV, XXXV (B of Inno.); Gardner,
Blake (Lit. in Perspective), 72.</p>
                            <p>First plate. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Keynes, Blake Studies,
106, pl. B (Gilchrist electrotype).</p>
                            <p>Second plate. Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 19a.</p>
                            <p>“Holy Thursday.” Blunt, Art of Blake, pl. 19b.</p>
                            <p>“Infant Joy.” Garnett, Blake, 20 (probably Gilchrist electrotype); Langridge,
Blake, 100; Wicksteed, Blake’s Innocence and Experience, 76 (color, B of Inno. &amp; Exp.); Blunt, Art of
Blake, pl. 15a; Frye, Selected Poetry and Prose of Blake, 226 (probably K of Inno.); Pinto, ed., William
Blake, pl. 2; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 37 (color, Z of Inno. &amp; Exp.); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet
and Painter, pl. XLIII (B of inno.); slide by American Library Color Slide Co. (color, probably C of Inno.
&amp; Exp.); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 49 (color, Z of Inno. &amp; Exp.).</p>
                            <p>“The Lamb.” Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Garnett, Blake, 20
(probably Gilchrist electrotype); Langridge, Blake, 86; Chesterton, Blake, frontlspiece (color); Keynes, Blake
Studies, 106, pl. C (Gilchrist electrotype) and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 33 (color, Z of Inno. &amp;
Exp.); Philadelphia Catalogue, 10; Woods, ed., English Poetry and Prose of the Romantic Movement, 169.</p>
                            <p>“Laughing Song.” Woods, ed., English Poetry and Prose of the Romantic Movement,
172; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 35 (color, Z of Inno. &amp; Exp.).</p>
                            <p>“The Little Black Boy,” first plate. Chesterton, Blake, 24; design only, Raine,
Blake and Tradition, pl. 4.</p>
                            <p>Second plate. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. VII.</p>
                            <p>“The Little Boy lost” and <corr type="emend">“The</corr> Little Boy found,” 
both plates. Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 35 (color, Z of Inno, &amp; Exp.); PMLA, LXXXII 
(May, 1967), 259, 260 (T of Inno. &amp; Exp.); designs only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 6.</p>
                            <p>“The Little Girl Lost” and “The Little Girl Found”—see under Songs of
Innocence and of Experience.</p>
                            <p>“Nurse’s Song.” Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Keynes, Blake
Studies, 106, pl. D (Gilchrist electrotype).</p>
                            <p>“On Another’s Sorrow.” Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Keynes,
Blake’s Engravings, pl. XX (Gilchrist electrotype).</p>
                            <p>“The School Boy”—see under Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</p>
                            <p>“The Shepherd.” Langridge, Blake, 80; Blunt, Art of Blake, 17b; Woods, ed.
English Poetry and Prose of the Romantic Movement, 170.</p>
                            <p>“Spring,” both plates. Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 37 (color, Z of
Inno. &amp; Exp.).</p>
                            <p>Second plate. Lister, Blake, pl. 3.</p>
                            <p>“The Voice of the Ancient Bard”—see under Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</p>
                            <p>MS of Innocence. Three pages from “An Island in the Moon” MS, with some Songs
of Innocence, In Wicksteed, Blake’s Innocence and Experience, 208.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <pb id="p03-38" n="38"/>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Microfilm by Micro Methods Ltd. (color, B and AA); Wicksteed,
Blake’s Innocence and Experience (plates from A, B, T, AA).</p>
                            <p>General Title Page. Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XI; Wicksteed, Blake’s Innocence
and Experience, 76 (color, B); Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 64; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer,
Prophet, 31 (color, Z); Bateson, Selected Poems of Blake, frontispiece (color, B); slide by American Library
Color Slide Co. (color, probably C).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="u">Note</hi>: Songs of Experience only listed here. For Songs of
Innocence, including plates from copies of Innocence and Experience, see preceding section.</p>
                            <p>Frontispiece. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 68 (1880 ed. only); Langridge,
Blake, 84; Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 22 (color, probably T); Keynes, Writings of Blake
(1925), 1, 278 and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 31 (color, Z); Tinker, Poet and Painter, 101; Raine, Blake
and Tradition, pl. 1.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 74 right bottom.</p>
                            <p>Title Page. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Sampson, Blake’s
Poetical Works (1913), 80; Blunt, Art of Blake, 14b; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 39 (color, Z);
Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 59. Keynes, Blake Studies, 106, pl. E (Gilchrist electrotype); Rosenblum,
Transformations in Late Eighteenth Century Art, pl. 186.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 43.</p>
                            <p>Introduction. Binyon, Drawings and Engravings of Blake, pl. 23 (probably T);
Philadelphia Catalogue, 25; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 39 (color, Z); Raine, Blake and Tradition,
pl. 67.</p>
                            <p>“Ah! Sun Flower”—see “My Pretty Rose Tree.”</p>
                            <p>“The Angel.” Sketch. Notebook, 65; Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl.
15.</p>
                            <p>“The Chimney Sweeper.” keynes, Blake Studies, pl. 28 (A) and Blake: Poet,
Printer, Prophet, 39 (color, Z); Margoliouth, Blake, 33 (A); Brownowski, Blake and the Age of Revolution, pl.
7; Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 8.</p>
                            <p>“The Clod &amp; the Pebble.” Cary, Art of Blake, pl. IX; Keynes, Blake: Poet,
Printer, Prophet, 39 (color, Z); Hagstrum, Blake’s The Clod and the Pebble, in Camden, ed., Restoration and
Eighteenth-Century Literature, pl. 1 (Z).</p>
                            <p>“A Divine Image.” Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 118; Keynes and Wolf,
Census, 54 (Keynes copy); Keynes, ed., Songs of Inno. and Exp., supp. pl.</p>
                            <p>“The Fly.” Garnett, Blake, 24; Philadelphia Catalogue, 27; Woods, ed., English
Poetry and Prose of the Romantic Movement, 183; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 41 (color, Z);
Rosenfeld, ed., Blake: Essays for Damon, pl. XXVIII (A).</p>
                            <p>“The Garden of Love.” Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 41 (color, Z);
Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 9.</p>
                            <p>“Holy Thursday.” Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Chesterton, Blake,
94; Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 45 (color, T); Wicksteed, Blake’s Innocence and Experience, 76
(color, T); Keynes, Blake Studies, 106, pl. F (Gilchrist electrotype); Frye, Fearful Symmetry, 74 (K); Woods,
ed., English Poetry and Prose of the Romantic Movement, 182.</p>
                            <pb id="p03-39" n="39"/>
                            <p>“The Human Abstract.” Gilchrist, 11 (electrotype); Keynes, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. XXIII (Gilchrist electrotype) and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 43 (color, Z); design only,
Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, 75; Hilies and Bloom, eds., From Sensibility to Romanticism, 318, IIIA;
Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 139.</p>
                            <p>“Infant Sorrow.” Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Keynes, Blake
Studies, 107, pl. H (Gilchrist electrotype)</p>
                            <p>“The Lilly”—see “My Pretty Rose Tree.”</p>
                            <p>“The Little Girl Lost” and “The Little Girl found,” first plate. Gilchrist,
Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Langridge, Blake, 12; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. XXI (Gilchrist
electrotype); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 65.</p>
                            <p>Second plate. Upper design, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 63.</p>
                            <p>Third plate. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Keynes, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. XXV (Gilchrist electrotype); Bronowski, Blake and the Age of Revolution, pl. 6 (perhaps a);
Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 64.</p>
                            <p>“The Little Vagabond.” Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 43 (color, Z);
Hilles and Bloom, eds., From Sensibility to Romanticism, 318, 111B.</p>
                            <p>“London.” Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Keynes, Blake Studies,
106, pl. G (Gilchrist electrotype) and Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 43 (color, Z); woods, ed., English
Poetry and Prose of the Romantic Movement, 184.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 54; Keynes, Drawings by Blake (1927), pl. 14 and Blake
Studies, pl. 6. See also Jerusalem, pl. 84.</p>
                            <p>“My Pretty Rose Tree,” “Ahl Sun Flower,” and “The Lilly.” Gilchrist, Life of
Blake, 11 (electrotype); Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. XXII (Gilchrist electrotype): “Ahl Sun Flower”
section only, BNYPL, 64 (1962), 616; Rosenfeld, ed., Blake: Essays for Demon, pl. XXIII (0).</p>
                            <p>“Nurse’s Song.” Garnett, Blake, 22 (T); Margollouth, Blake, 59 (A).</p>
                            <p>“A Poison Tree.” Woods, ed., English Poetry and Prose of the Romantic Movement,
185; Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. XLVI (Z); Lister, Blake, pl. 9; Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl.
135.</p>
                            <p>“The School Boy.” Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11 (electrotype); Keynes, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. XXIV (Gilchrist electrotype); Frye, Selected Poetry and Prose of Blake, 226.</p>
                            <p>“The Sick Rose.” Frye, Fearful Symmetry, 74 (K); Blunt, Art of Blake, 15b;
Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 41 (color, Z); Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. XLVII (Z); Raine,
Blake and Tradition, pl. 47.</p>
                            <p>Sketch, similar to lower design. Notebook, 21; Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl.
47.</p>
                            <p>“To Tirzah.” Lower design, Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925), 1, 292, Poetry and
Prose, 80 (1927), 79 (1939), and Complete Writings (1957, 1966), 220; lower design, Erdman, Poetry and Prose
of Blake, 30; Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 71.</p>
                            <p>“The Tyger.” Garnett, Blake, 24; Langridge, Blake, 98 (T); Chesterton, Blake,
88 (T); Keynes and Wolf, Census, 53 (P); Woods, ed., English Poetry and Prose of the Romantic Movement, 183;
Grant, Discussions of Blake, 77 (0); Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 41 (color, Z); Hirsh, The World of
Turner (Time-Life Library of Art), 24 (color, T).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 6.</p>
                            <pb id="p03-40" n="40"/>
                            <p>“The Voice of the Ancient Bard.” Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 43
(color, Z).</p>
                            <p>Tailpiece. Keynes, Bibliography of Blake, 116 (C) and Writings of Blake (1925),
1, 292; Wicksteed, Blake’s Innocence and Experience, 206 (B).</p>
                            <p>MS of Experience. Notebook, 99-115, reproduced in Wicksteed, Blake’s
Innocence and Experience.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, first series</title>
                            </head>
                            <p>1. (title page). Philadelphia Catalogue, 2.</p>
                            <p>2. (frontispiece). Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111; Keynes, Blake’s
Engravings, pl. 77.</p>
                            <p>3. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111; Philadelphia Catalogue, 2; Keynes,
Blake’s Engravings, pl. 78.</p>
                            <p>4. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl.
79.</p>
                            <p>5. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl.
80.</p>
                            <p>6. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111.</p>
                            <p>7. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111; Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl.
81.</p>
                            <p>8. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111; Chesterton, Blake, 32; Selincourt,
Blake, 105 (A); Keynes, Blake’s Engravings, pl. 82.</p>
                            <p>9. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, second series</title>
                            </head>
                            <p>3. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111.</p>
                            <p>4. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111.</p>
                            <p>9. Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. VB (G*).</p>
                            <p>10. Keynes, Bibliotheca Bibliographici, pl. XI (L*).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, “God Creating the Universe.” Keynes, Blake’s Drawings, second series,
pl. 34.</p>
                            <p>11. Ellis and Yeats, Works of Blake, 111; Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl.
154.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Complete. Microfilm by Micro Methods Ltd. (color, P).</p>
                            <p>i (frontispiece). Langridge, Blake, 106 (A); Philadelphia Catalogue, 30 (a);
Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LII (E*); Lister, Blake, pl. 7 (P).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Large Bk. of Designs. Keynes, Writings of Blake (1925),
1, 254; Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 14 (A); Digby, Symbol and image in Blake, pl. 67 (B); Butlin, Tate
Catalogue of Blake, pl. 7 (B) and Blake: Tate Gallery, pl. 2 (color, B); Bronowski, Blake and the Age of
Revolution, pl. 8 (A); Réalités, Jan. 1968, 79 (color, B); Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 76 (B).</p>
                            <p>ii (title page). Sampson, Blake’s Poetical Works (1913), 284; Plowman,
Introduction to Blake, 96; Blunt, Art of Blake, 22b; Keynes, Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, 47 (color, C);
Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LIIIA (E*).</p>
                            <p>Sketch, upper right figure. Notebook, 81.</p>
                            <p>Sketch, similar to figures in the clouds and running figure. Keynes, Drawings
by Blake (1927), pl. 6.</p>
                            <pb id="p03-41" n="41"/>
                            <p>iii Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XVII; Selincourt, Blake, 190; Keynes, Blake: Poet,
Printer, Prophet, 49 (C).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Small Bk. of Designs. Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 1, 105
(1863), 103 (1880); Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake, pl. 48 (color) and Drawings and Engravings of Blake,
pl. 19; Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 13 top; Blunt, Art of Blake, 20b.</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 28; Cary, Art of Blake, pl. XVI.</p>
                            <p>3. Sketch. Notebook, 32.</p>
                            <p>4. Chesterton, Blake, 46; design only, Beer, Blake’s Humanism, pl. 31
(probably P); design only, Raine, Blake and Tradition, pl. 75 (J).</p>
                            <p>Separate plate, from A Large Bk. of Designs. Binyon, Engraved Designs of Blake,
pl. 49 (color,A); Digby, Symbol and Image in Blake, pl. 68 (B); Butlin, Tate Catalogue of Blake, pl. 6
(B).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 92.</p>
                            <p>Sketch, seated figure. Notebook, 74 right middle.</p>
                            <p>5. Chesterton, Blake, 52.</p>
                            <p>6. Detail, Erdman, Prophet Against Empire, 218.</p>
                            <p>7. Water color of the design. Wright, Life of Blake, pl. 62 top.</p>
                            <p>8. Figure in flame only, Gilchrist, Life of Blake, 11, 376 (1880 ed. only);
Hagstrum, Blake: Poet and Painter, pl. LIIIB (E*).</p>
                            <p>Sketch. Notebook, 78.</p>
                        </div4>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>