<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.2.periodicals</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Exhibitions, periodicals, and the MLA seminar</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>September 26, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-2-0003">
                <pb id="p03-23" n="23"/>
                <p>The Blake Trust sponsored an exhibition at Edinburgh this past summer; we hope to have a
report in the next <hi rend="i">Newsletter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Gleanings from periodicals: Kathleen Nott reviewed <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> by
Kathleen Raine in the Aug. 17, 1969 issue of the <hi rend="i">Observer</hi> (“Symbols and Sources,” p. 21). In
the <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> for June 27, 1968, there is a news item and photograph with the caption “Homage
to William Blake” (p. 6). The subject is the unveiling of a memorial relief sculpture of Blake—a triptych
measuring 13 ft. by 9 ft.—at William Blake House, Marshall Street, London, W. 1. The sculptor is John W.
Mills; two panels are in cast aluminum, one in bronze; the head is based on the life mask in the National
Portrait Gallery.</p>
                <p>The August 1969 number of <hi rend="i">Art and Artists</hi> magazine is devoted to “Art and
Revolution”; it includes “William Blake: Revolutionary or Rebel?” by John Christopher Battye (pp. 24-25).<gap
type="emend"/></p>
                <pb id="p03-41" n="41"/>
                <p>
                    <gap type="emend" rend="plain"/><hi rend="i">The Nation</hi> for April 28, 1969 published
“William Blake and Nonviolence” by John Sutherland (pp. 542-544).</p>
                <p>Two of the new pulls from Blake’s Dante plates produced for Mr. Lessing J. Rosenwald are
on display among recent acquisitions at the Victoria and Albert Museum.</p>
                <p>There is to be another “Seminar” on Methods of Interpreting Blake’s Illuminations (last
year it was called “Seminar 55” but we don’t yet know number or exact time and place) at the Denver meeting
of <hi rend="i">MLA.</hi> It will be announced in <hi rend="i">PMLA.</hi> Persons wishing to attend should
write to John E. Grant, English Department, State University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, 52240, Topic suggested:
The Arlington Court picture.</p>
                <p>A two-part article on “An Island in the Moon” begins in the September <hi rend="i">Bulletin
of The New York Public Library</hi> (vol. 73, pp. 440-65), Illustrated by Blake’s drawings on the last page
of the manuscript. It is “The satiric Blake: Apprenticeship at the Haymarket?” by Martha W. England. Part 2 in
October.</p>
                <p>Some of the Berg Collection Blakes will be in the forthcoming NYPL Berg Collection
exhibition, “Pen and Brush: The Author as Artist.” Catalogue on sale Opening Day, October 2 (and by mail: 53
prepaid).</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>