<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.3.paley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">William Wells, William Blake’s “Heads of the Poets”; 
William Blake: Illustrations to The Divine Comedy of Dante, from Da Capo Press</title>
				<author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-3-0007">
				<pb id="p03-62" n="62"/>
				<div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main"><hi rend="i">William Blake’s “Heads of the Poets”</hi> (by William Wells).
Manchester: City Art Gallery (1969) 43 pp . . . No price listed.</title>
						<title type="main"><hi rend="i">William Blake: Illustrations to</hi> The Divine Comedy 
<hi rend="i">of Dante.</hi> New York: Da Capo Press, pp. iii + 109 plates. $100.00.</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>These two publications, one a large portfolio, the other a booklet, both reproduce
series of pictures by Blake not otherwise available at present, although in neither case is the series
reproduced for the first time. The Dante series is a “second edition” of the facsimile produced for the
National Art-Collections Fund in 1922,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">1</ref> (see announcement in <hi rend="i">BNL</hi> 11, no. 4 [whole #8], p. 61). The Manchester
booklet includes photographic reproductions of a series to be found complete only in a long out-of-print Blake
Society pamphlet of 1925. 
                        <note id="n20">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> The Dante illustrations are also reproduced from this
facsimile in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to</hi> The Divine Comedy by Albert S. Roe (Princeton,
1953), along with the seven engravings.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The name of William Wells, Keeper of the Burrell Collection, Glasgow, does not appear
on the cover of the Manchester pamphlet, and there is no title page; the author is identified only in the
foreward to the booklet. This is regrettable, for Mr. Wells deserves credit for giving us a valuable little
study of Blake’s least-known series of pictures. This booklet, prepared in conjunction with a Blake-Hayley
exhibition<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">2</ref> at the City Art Gallery,
includes reproductions of all eighteen heads, thirty subsidiary reproductions, and a handsome cover drawing of
Hayley’s Turret. In almost all respects, this <hi rend="i">Heads of the Poets</hi> is superior to the Blake
Society’s 1925 production. The latter had only a cursory introduction by Thomas Wright, while in this one
Mr. Wells presents twenty-five pages of concise information. Five Heads given incorrect titles in 1925 are
retitled now, following the corrections made by the late Kenneth Povey. Much detail appears only in the new
reproductions: for example, the figure of Ugolino in “Dante” is virtually invisible in the Blake Society’s
reproduction but well defined in Mr. Wells’s; in the earlier “Spenser” the delightful figures on the left
side of the picture cannot be seen at all. In one respect, however, the earlier reproductions have an
advantage — in being printed one to a page. They have considerably more effect this way than they do in the
present booklet, where they are crowded two to a page. 
                        <note id="n21">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> “For Friendship’s Sake” <corr type="emend">29 April – 18 May 1969.</corr></note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p03-63" n="63"/>
                    <p>Since the new edition of Blake’s Dante illustrations is not a fresh reproduction of
the originals but rather a reproduction of the Emery Walker collotype facsimile of 1922<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">3</ref>, it might be thought that the new production
would be necessarily less accurate than its antecedent. Having had the opportunity, through the kindness of
Mr. Martin Butlin, to compare the two sets page for page, I can report that in most respects this is not so.
In each set detail comes through with about equal clarity; handwriting is equally legible. In fact, the darks
of 2 seem at times to show more sensitive variation than those of 1 — the rock in plate 22 (“The
Minotaur”<corr type="emend">),</corr> for example; and the darks of plate 16 (“Goddess of Fortune”) are
sharper in 2 than in 1. As far as outline and detail are concerned, one gets about as good an idea of
Blake’s drawings from 2 and from 1, and there are even times when 2 is preferable: in plate 5 (“The
Vestibule of Hell . . . ”) the frieze of figures at the top is if anything clearer in 2. Nevertheless, there
are two important respects in which the Da Capo edition is decidedly less satisfactory than the Emery Walker
one. 
                        <note id="n22">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> For the sake of brevity, I will refer to the Walker and Da
Capo editions as 1 and 2 respectively.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The whites of I are very close to Blake’s. In 2, however, there is frequently a
strangely yellowish tone which creates an effect far different from that of Blake’s originals. This makes a
tremendous difference in the tone of some of the pictures — 10, for example (“The Circle of the Lustful”).
In 54 (“Donati Transformed into a Serpent”), the picture as a whole seems decidedly darker as a result, while
in 72 (“The Angelic Boat . . . ”) the radiance of the angelic presence is entirely lost by the absence of
white. Similarly, in 80 (“The Rock Sculptured . . . ”) the contrast between dark sea and light rock is
spoiled. Whether intentional or accidental, the failure to reproduce white as white in these pictures is a
serious one.</p>
                    <p>A second point: the texture of the hand-made laid paper of the Emery Walker set is very
similar to that of the drawing-paper Blake actually used. The paper of 2, however, has no visible texture, but
as the texture of 1 is reproduced in the facsimile the result is an anomaly: the drawings appear to have
texture but the white borders do not. 2 <hi rend="u">looks</hi> like a reproduction, while in 1 the effect of
versimilitude is further increased by edges cut with slight, but discernible, irregularity.</p>
                    <p>It should be said that in one respect <hi rend="u">both</hi> facsimiles leave something
to be desired. Someone who knew these pictures only through facsimile would have no idea of the role color
plays in the originals. Of the nineteen Dante illustrations displayed at the Tate Gallery, not one is without
some important use of color. The loss is of course greatest in finished or almost finished water colors like
“Beatrice Addressing Dante” or “The Serpent Attacking Buso Donati.” (I does include a single color
illustration, “The Inscription Over Hell-Gate”). The loss is not only of artistic effect but of symbolic
meaning as well — it would be unfortunate if someone were to rely on a black-and-white facsimile in
interpreting a picture like “Beatrice Addressing Dante.” And even in pictures in which only a little color has
been used, it can make a tremendous difference, as in “The Ascent of the Mountain of Purgatory,” where Virgil
wears a pale blue garment, Dante a rose-colored one. Or consider “Dante and Virgil approaching the Angel who
guards the Entrance of Purgatory,” where deep red clouds contrast strikingly with green grass in
<pb id="p03-64" n="64"/>
the foreground. At this stage of the study of Blake, should we settle for less than full-color reproductions
of major works?</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>