<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.3.tolley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">The Auckland Fuselis</title>
				<author n="Tolley">Michael J. Tolley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-3-0005">
                <pb id="p03-51" n="51"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">2. The Auckland Fuselis</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Michael J. <name>Tolley</name>
                        </docAuthor> The University of Adelaide South Australia</byline>
                    <p>The editor has asked me to comment on the Fuseli drawings that were purchased in
January 1965 from a private source in Dunedin, New Zealand, by the Auckland City Art Gallery. The illustrated
catalogue, <hi rend="i">A Collection of Drawings by Henry Fuseli</hi>, Auckland: Auckland City Art Gallery
(1967), 100 pp., reproduces the 37 main drawings and also several of the verso sketches. The work for the
catalogue seems to have been almost entirely the responsibility of P.A. Tomory, who contributes a brief
introduction. The drawings are carefully annotated. The collection itself is, I suppose, still on tour: I saw
it on exhibition in Cork Street, London, March 1968 (it was mentioned in several newspapers). Unfortunately,
the catalogue seems to be little known by Blake scholars. A case in point is Albert S. Roe’s article,
“‘The Thunder of Egypt’”, in <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H.
Rosenfeld, Providence (1969), pp. 158-195. On p. 160, Professor Roe argues that the illustration to Darwin’s
<hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> entitled “Fertilization of Egypt”, which is stated to be designed by Fuseli
and engraved by Blake, may have been Blake’s inspiration. Against Roe’s argument is other written
evidence, as well as two other Fuseli designs that have figures unmistakably similar to that of Anubis in the
Darwin illustration, acknowledged by Roe on p. 444. In the Auckland collection, however, there is a third
sketch with (basically) this figure, incidentally on a subject that would have appealed to Blake, “Hephaestus,
Bia and Crato securing Prometheus on Mount Caucasus” (c 1810) from Aeschylus, <hi rend="i">Prometheus
Bound.</hi> In the catalogue is a note explaining that the figure we are concerned with “is initially taken
from the executioner in Andrea del Sarto’s <hi rend="i">Decapitation of St. John</hi> (Courtyard of the
Scalzo, Florence)” (p. 68). (The del Sarto painting is conveniently illustrated in Heinrich Wollflin’s 
<hi rend="i">Classic Art</hi>, now a Phaidon paperback.)</p>
                    <p>P.A. Tomory concludes his introduction with some remarks on Fuseli’s connection with
Blake:
<q>
The connection is illustrated here in nos 4, 18, 24, 30, 36. The evidence of nos 4, 30 and 36 seems to support
Mason’s opinion that Blake used the older artist as a figurative source, even though his final conceptions
were entirely individual. Todd . . .
<pb id="p03-52" n="52"/>
suggests it was Fuseli whom Stothard accused when he ‘ . . . allowed he [Blake] had been misled to
extravagances in his art and he knew by whom’. While Fuseli freely admitted that Blake was ‘ . . . d—d
good to steal from’, one must agree with Mason that it is difficult to find any direct reference to Blake in
Fuseli’s work. It would appear that if Fuseli ‘stole’ from Blake it was a ‘painterly’ borrowing. For
instance, in general Fuseli’s colour and tones are very similar to Blake’s (cf: <hi rend="i">The Four and
Twenty Elders</hi>, c. 1800-5: Tate, London). More specifically, Fuseli adapts Blake’s yellow aura behind a
head (cf: <hi rend="i">Glad Day</hi>, c. 1780: British Museum) in such a drawing as no. 25 and Blake’s
scallopped cloud from (cf: <hi rend="i">Elohim Creating Adam</hi>, c. 1795: Tate, London) is found in less
precise form in nos. 34 and 36. As he confessed, it was colour that eluded Fuseli; and there was none better
to turn to than Blake in this field.
</q>
No. 4, “Subject from Milton’s L’Allegro” (c1780), has a figure of Laughter “not unlike, in spirit and
pose” the figure of Laughter in Blake’s “Mirth” (c1815). No. 18, “Chriemhild throwing herself on the body of
Siegfried, assassinated by Trony” (1815) has a central group “found also at the foot of Blake’s title page
to <hi rend="i">America</hi>” — a woman embracing a warrior’s body. No. 24 is the Aeschylus illustration
already mentioned. No. 30, “Vergil, Dante and Geryon” (1811) is very different from Blake’s conception in
his later Dante illustration. Not much can be made of Blake’s following Fuseli here and Tomory points the
difference: Fuseli’s Geryon is “a <hi rend="i">terribilità</hi> image and yet accurately drawn from the
text — Blake’s, a creature of gentle deceit and more arbitrarily conceived”. No. 36, “Death and Sin
bridging the ‘Waste’ of Chaos and met by Satan on his return from Earth” (c1819-21) also follows Blake:
“The same figure of Satan also appears in Blake’s Argument from <hi rend="i">The Daughters of Albion</hi> of
1793 [the figure springing from the sunflower], and in the top section of the title page to his 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>”. That Fuseli follows Blake in this and no. 18 seems to contradict Tomory’s assumption
that Fuseli was little indebted to Blake for other than “painterly” qualities.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>