<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.3.hughes</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Kathleen Raine, Blake and Tradition</title>
				<author n="Hughes">Daniel Hughes</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-3-0007">
				<pb id="p03-57" n="57"/>
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> <supplied type="emend">(by Kathleen
Raine).</supplied> The Bollingen Series: XXXV: II Princeton, Vol. I, 460 pp., Vol. 11. 367 pp., $22.50 the
set</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>What Blake would you have? The “wild pet for the super cultivated” whom Eliot warned us
about, the blazing humanitarian in love with mankind’s heuristic life, the guru of the body and physician of
the ailing intellect, the hero of the counter-culture? None of these? None. But Blake as 
<hi rend="i">mystagogos</hi> can be too easily dismissed by the anxious humanist or the technical critic of
language and line. Mylonas in his book on Eleusis defines the <hi rend="i">mystagogos</hi> as “the sponsor of
a <hi rend="i">mystes</hi>, the person who introduced the initiate and even performed some of the rites of
preparation and initiation” and, as the Blakean <hi rend="i">mystai</hi> continue their search for hidden
source and secret ceremony, one begins to understand that, for whatever reasons, there is something in Blake
himself of the mystagogue despite his detestation of mystery. His allegory addressed to the intellectual
powers demands not only the
<pb id="p03-58" n="58"/>
resources of literary history and criticism but other rites and ranges of meaning. The long-delayed
publication of Kathleen Raine’s <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> sets forth more acutely and
problematically than any previous book the problem of who you are and what you are doing when you experience
Blake, and what Blake you want him to be. If Miss Raine herself sometimes adopts the mystagogic role, she does
so only in imitation of Blake, and her central ritual is, finally, no more remote than the elucidation of
poetry itself. This book, with its labor of years, its learning, the battles it fights and the skirmishes it
avoids, offers essentially a <hi rend="i">poet’s</hi> view of Blake, not as the critical technocrats would
limit it: to a knowledge of verse and hints from the workshop, but a poet’s book in terms of its
participation in and sensitivity to a poet’s likely motivations and meanings; these are very wide and very
mysterious and what we are shown about them will likely do us good.</p>
                    <p>Like some other Blakeans, then, Miss Raine has more to do than add another explication,
vast or little, to the roaring industry of Blake hermeneutics. Her wider motive is probably best approached in
her later collection of essays, <hi rend="i">Defending Ancient Springs</hi>, 1967, a series of passionate yet
graceful studies of English visionary poets in relation to the very Tradition: Platonic, Neo-Platonic,
Gnostic, etc. in which, in her larger work, she seeks to place Blake. Miss Raine’s concern with the quality
of consciousness as this is maintained in Blake, Coleridge, Shelley, Yeats and a few other modern poets is
further illuminated by more general essays which, I think, serve as excellent preparation for 
<hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>: “On the Symbol,” “On the Mythological,” and “The Use of the Beautiful”,
endeavors best summed up in her title; she is defending those ancient sources — the continuing power of
symbols — from modern demythologized naturalism and materialism. Miss Raine has a mission; she would not
merely get Blake right or read him in the context of the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries and in
the perspective of English literature; she would <hi rend="i">use</hi> Blake as he himself saw his prophetic
role. His words, her interpretation of those words — mark them well! — are of your eternal salvation.</p>
                    <p>So <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, in addition to bearing the normal load of
controversial explication and embattled interpretation asks a larger commitment yet: to visionary poetry as
Miss Raine understands it and writes it herself. I, for one, am sympathetic to this envelope and find Miss
Raine refreshing: profound without hysteria, serious without rancor, and somehow freed from the nervous
claustrophobia of the current American academic marketplace; let’s say her reading of Blake raises the
spiritual level and improves the tone of Blake studies one noticeable notch. But this does not mean that her
book, so handsomely produced by Princeton in two impressive volumes, is conclusive or resolving or absolutely
new in its position; as a document of belief it is one thing; as a definitive study of Blake, it is another.
Grave problems abound. For one thing, the delayed appearance of this book, first finished in 1961, but not
published until last year, means that some of the scholarship seems already out of date, and the critical
interpretation sometimes lags behind new readings and discoveries. Just what the overwhelmed scholar should
attend to will remain a matter of debate and difficult choice, but one sometimes has the sense in reading Miss
Raine that what she writes is neither new or startling or particularly hers. This is a familiar problem in
scholarship and criticism — have you seen so-and-so’s latest and where can you fit it in? — but it
becomes more complicated when the endeavor is as comprehensive as this one. In studying the lyrics
particularly, including
<pb id="p03-59" n="59"/>
such central works as “The Mental Traveller” or “The Tyger”, Miss Raine ignores much valuable explication that
would, one feels, enforce or clarify her position; to the reader knowing this other work, her indifference may
seem excessively blithe on the one hand or cursorily arrogant on the other, even though one recognizes that
she has more to do than to protect tenderly established reputations. A more serious problem in assessing the
work — not as a private and poetic document in the tradition of Swinburne’s Blake, but as a contribution
to Blake scholarship in its own right — is an examination of just what is meant by tradition in this book
and just what place it is supposed to have in Blake’s work.</p>
                    <p>One knew where Miss Raine stood from the articles she has published over the years:
firmly within the camp of which George Mills Harper is the other leading representative: this “tradition” is
Greek, it is Platonic and Neo-Platonic; it opts for the mystagogue and his mysteries, and the Perennial
Philosophy itself. Knowing this, this reviewer must nonetheless admit to purprise at the importance given to
Thomas Taylor in <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition.</hi> Although Miss Raine locates Blake’s greatest
interest in Taylor’s translations and adaptations from the Greek in his work of the 1780’s and 1790’s,
the influence of Taylor on Blake is certainly regarded as pervasive and significant throughout his career. She
is definite: “Without the aids of Plotinus and Porphyry, the <hi rend="i">Pymander</hi> of Hermes, and, above
all, Taylor, Blake’s Christianity itself would have been a more limited and lesser matter.” One might assent
to that more readily if one knew more or believed more about Taylor himself, but the concurrent publication of
the Raine-Harper <hi rend="i">Thomas Taylor the Platonist</hi>, which fills an undoubted gap in our knowledge
of this obscure figure, still will not convince many students that he is a crucial missing piece in the
intricate puzzle of the backgrounds of English Romanticism. One senses readily the identification that is made
between the beleaguered Platonist of the late eighteenth century and the oppressed poet-critic of our own
time, but, in reading Taylor’s crabbed and deliberately obscurantist writings (including his less than
awesome translation of the Orphic hymns), one balks at finding him an important source for Blake. Admittedly,
many artists have found fructifying materials in strange places, but did Blake find motivations in Taylor?
Miss Raine’s emphatic claims for the Taylor-Blake relationship, does prevent one from fully accepting 
<hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> as the clarifying and central work it is intended to be. I am less concerned
with the actual “facts,” although we must note that Blake nowhere refers to Taylor in his work, including his
letters; Gilchrist is silent on Taylor in any edition; probably Taylor is Sipsop the Pythagorean in 
<hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, but it is hard to see how that satiric portrait demonstrates a personal
and intellectual bond between the men. It is unlikely, perhaps, that Blake did not attend Taylor’s lectures
on Platonism in Flaxman’s house but he may not have. Finally, however, such nigglings will only mystify some
and anger others; he who would deny any connection between Taylor and Blake for lack of concrete historical
evidence would lose Miss Raine’s important poetic and philosophical understanding of Blake; he who would
insist too much on Blake the Platonist (as a welcome relief from Blake the Hebraist) has a difficult case to
prove. The issue becomes not scholarly but critical. What does the juxtaposition of Thomas Taylor and William
Blake do for our understanding of Blake’s difficult work? If that is enhanced and we come to a more precise
appreciation of what kind of poet and artist Blake was, then the rescue of Taylor’s work and reputation will
have been worth while.</p>
                    <pb id="p03-60" n="60"/>
                    <p>According to Miss Raine, “Taylor’s greatest service to the romantic poets was in
teaching the use of symbolic discourse as the language of metaphysical thought.” This indeed is an important
contribution — even if Thomas Taylor did not make it. In recent years critical interest in the Romantics has
moved away from the political and the historical to the study of those methods of composition and structuring
of symbologies that lead to such extraordinary and still imperfectly described works as 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound.</hi> The poem as “an essay in mythological
composition”, argues Miss Raine, required the structural levels of myth which Taylor, in his <hi rend="i">A
Dissertation on the Eleusinian and Bacchic Mysteries</hi>, set forth from Sallust. The levels of fable
suggested by Sallust and adopted by Taylor in his exposition of the Mysteries: the fable itself, the physical
interpretation of the fable (Proserpina as blossoming earth), the animastic level (<corr type="emend">Proserpina</corr> as the descent
of the soul), and the theological-metaphysical level (“who knows if to live is not to die, and to die to
live?”) — these give the “fullest possible content” to the poet’s material. The raising of curtains here
is swift and subtle: one has to assume, for example, that the Neo-Platonic allegorizing of Homer gives us the
richest view of the Homeric poems, that Thomas Taylor’s resuscitation of Homeric commentaries by Proclus and
Porphyry is valuable in itself and of even greater value in showing Blake how to write symbolic verse.
Finally, Miss Raine seems to aver, in recognizing the abstracting and Platonizing impulse of Blake’s mind we
come closer to his basic poetic Method than we have before. Yes and no. Miss Raine’s marked ability to write
uncluttered exposition of uncertain visibilities makes nearly all her material attractive in itself, but
whether it is all relevant to Blake is a different and often controversial matter. She is at her best, I
think, in offering possible but undogmatic resonances to Blake’s work when that work itself seems
particularly to require extension and comparison as in her interpretation of the late painting at Arlington
Court, “The Sea of Time and Space” or in her reading of “The Little Girl Lost” and “The Little Girl Found.”
The painting is examined as an illustration of Porphyry’s treatise on Homer’s <hi rend="i">Cave of the
Nymphs</hi>, translated by Taylor in 1788-1789, although neither Geoffrey Keynes nor George Digby agrees that
Blake is illustrating Porphyry’s view of Homer in this beautiful and complicated work, nor does a careful
reading of Taylor’s translation of <hi rend="i">De Antro Nympharum</hi> in its new appearance resolve the
issue. What Miss Raine establishes by these speculations is, I think, the appropriate spiritual and symbolic
level on which Blake was operating most of the time. Once again, the range of “abstraction” must be
appreciated. The episode in Book Thirteen of <hi rend="i">The Odyssey</hi> in which Odysseus returns to Ithaca
through the Cave of the Nymphs must assume a symbolic meaning; Porphyry in a typical Neo-Platonic allegorizing
must see Odysseus as the soul crossing and freeing itself from the stormy sea of generation; Taylor’s
translation must convey the full arching weight of an arguable interpretation and Blake, of course, must read
Taylor in a sympathetic spirit. If any one these steps is a misadventure, does Miss Raine’s further
Platonizing fail? I think not.</p>
                    <p>Paradoxically, the linking of Blake to the Tradition as Miss Raine understands it helps
in rescuing Blake’s complex poems and pictures from the charges of the private and the arbitrary that have
been lodged against them. The poet who may seem self-indulgent, the reader who may appear anxious and cultish
both gain from Miss Raine’s reading. What has sometimes seemed overdetermined, too casually allusive, and
certainly hard to discover in Blake’s course is revealed, at the least, to be part of, indeed, clarified and
ennobled
<pb id="p03-61" n="61"/>
by a tradition of speculative thought that shaped itself in the second and third centuries of our era, found
new life in the fifteenth century and continues to run in a significant if underground current through the
present time of troubles. Miss Raine’s reading of the Lyca poems can serve, I think, as a good example of
the enriching range she brings to Blake studies even as we hem and haw. Once again the route is perilous, for
we have to believe that Blake was drawing on his knowledge of the Portland Vase whose figures he engraved for
Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> in 1791, that the vase does depict the Mysteries of Eleusis, and
that Blake is drawing on Taylor’s exposition of the Mysteries. It is true, as Irene Chayes has pointed
out,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p61u1" type="note">*</ref> that Kathleen Raine, in her
reading of these poems, fails to distinguish between the primordial image of the Lost Maiden, the Kore
<corr type="emend">Proserpina,</corr> and the Neo-Platonic allegory of what the Kore means, but that “fullest possible content” Miss
Raine is anxious to discover for Blake depends heavily on a tradition in which Neo-Platonic extrapolations
play an important part. I know of no other discussion of these crabbed and teasing stanzas that better
accounts for the poetic process in these poems. What, at first, may seem confused or even careless in
Blake’s “allegorical waver”, as Edwin Honig would call it, takes on body and meaningful connection with
other poems by Blake; “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, “Earth’s Answer”, and the fallen
Ahania of <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> assume new meaning in Blake’s various and elaborate
presentation of the archetype. This graceful density continues to operate through Miss Raine’s presentation
of motifs, sources, and analogues in the Prophetic Books, where we can even see Thomas Taylor start to fade
into his significant and interesting but not conclusive role. 
                        <note id="p61u1">* “Little Girls Lost: Problems of a Romantic Archetype”, 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public Library</hi>, LXVII, 9 (November 1963) 579-92. Reprinted in 
<hi rend="i">Blake: A Collection of Critical Essays</hi>, ed. Northrop Frye (Spectrum Books 1966), 65-78.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> is a far more personal work than it might look
at first — the quality and commitment of Kathleen Raine’s mind and imagination must be engaged at every
point. But the subtle boundary between the personal: the alert and steady pressure of a particular outreaching
mind and the eccentric: the half-glimpsed display of hidden sources and events — this line is not always as
well defined as it should be in a work of undoubtedly major intentions. Yet the comprehensive works on Blake,
starting with Ellis-Yeats, have inevitably swung between the personal and the eccentric and away from the
strictly literary-academic because Blake’s position in literary and cultural history, a wholly ambiguous
matter in his own time, has been only slightly better defined in this century. The “big” books like Foster
Damon’s and Northrop Frye’s did not and could not seek neatly sanctioned solutions to be passed on to the
Oxford Histories. Damon, in his time, performed the essential first task of showing that Blake might, after
all, be intelligible; Frye, in what is still the best study, demonstrates how consistent in itself and how
challenging to our whole view of literature that intelligibility might be; yet both authors, while never
losing sight of their larger purposes are often “personal” in the sense in which I have defined the term.
Kathleen Raine belongs here but to what degree and to what end is likely to stir the
<pb id="p03-62" n="62"/>
passions for some time to come. I want to come back to the poet, <hi rend="i">sui generis</hi>, not as
handbooks and workshops understand him, but as Shelley did, “the hierophant of an unapprehended inspiration.”
Miss Raine’s Blake is no dogmatic geometer-humanist whose wheels, within or without, were set in motion for
the critic and propagandist of a terrible time; he is a poet, obsessed with line and verb, requiring and
making symbols to which his interpreter must be true. After the elucidation of the Mysteries, we yet remain in
the presence of secrets honored, secrets kept.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Daniel <name>Hughes</name>
                        </docAuthor> Wayne State University</byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>