<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.3.wittreich</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Further Observations on William Rossetti’s Annotations to Gilchrist’s
Life of Blake</title>
				<author n="Wittreich">Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <pb id="p03-48" n="48"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-3-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="i">
                            <hi rend="u">NOTES</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">1. Further Observations on William Rossetti’s Annotations to
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Joseph Anthony <name>Wittreich</name>, Jr.</docAuthor> Summer Fellow Henry
E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</byline>
                    <p>Martin Butlin has recently drawn attention to William Michael Rossetti’s copy of
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1863), now in the Houghton Library, Harvard University,
Catalogue No. *EC75 / B5815 / W863g (B);<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref> and he has suggested, on the basis of annotations to the “Descriptive Catalogue” in Volume
II, that these notes — perhaps written over a period of years<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref> — were begun before 1872 and completed by 1876. Rossetti’s annotations to
the biography and poems provide evidence in support of different time-limits for these marginalia. A note on
“The Crystal Cabinet,” referring to Swinburne’s explanation of the poem, indicates that these jottings were
begun after the appearance of <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Critical Study</hi> in 1868. The fact that the
annotation to Volume II, p. 106, is printed almost verbatim in Rossetti’s <hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of
William Blake</hi> and that the annotation to the same volume, p. 77, is greatly expanded in this edition
suggests that the marginalia to the biography and poems, at least, were completed by the Autumn of 1873 when
<corr type="emend">Rossetti’s</corr> edition with “Prefatory Memoir” was being put together.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
                        <note id="n1">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> Rossetti’s marginalia are printed here for the first time by
permission of the Harvard College Library. For Mr. Butlin’s description of Rossetti’s copy of Gilchrist,
see “William Rossetti’s Annotations to Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake,” Blake
Newsletter</hi>, II (1968), 39-40.</note>
                        <note id="n2">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Mr. Butlin’s conjecture is borne out by the fact that when
Rossetti annotates Volume I, p. 335, he is aware of only the Butts-Strange set of illustrations to 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, now in the Boston Museum of Art; when he annotates Volume II, p. 210, however, he
is conversant with the Aspland set now in the possession of the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art
Gallery.</note>
                        <note id="n3">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> It seems likely that the corrections and emendations to the
biography and text were done over a very short period of time with Tatham’s MS in hand; those to
“Descriptive Catalogue” occur over a much longer span of time.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>A librarian’s note, inserted into the Houghton copy, indicates that “some annotations
&amp; revisions” from the first volume are “included in ed. 2; many more not” (the marginalia referring to
Tatham’s manuscript are uniformly ignored); also ignored are the many emendations to the second volume,
although “revisions in the Descriptive Catalogue of Blake’s pictures” are “generally included; and these
marginalia are very numerous.” Moreover, Rossetti’s annotation to Volume II, p. 243, provides a clue as to
what occasioned him to reread and heavily annotate this copy. He says, “It would be as well in a second
edition, to put these heads into something a little more like order.” The librarian’s inference that these
marginalia “arise from someone’s request for advice concerning a possible 2nd edition” seems
correct.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> The annotations are clearly
suggestions, and indeed very few were carried into execution. For the most part, Rossetti is concerned with
textual emendation and correction of printing errors and some biographical facts; however, a very few of his
marginalia have a critical orientation, and those are printed below.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> When one considers the use made of these annotations in
Rossetti’s edition of Blake, it seems likely that the immediate occasion for reading and correcting
Gilchrist was the preparation of Rossetti’s “Prefatory Memoir” and edition.</note>
                        <note id="n5">
                            <hi rend="s">5</hi> Rossetti’s remarks are printed in ordinary type; the
passages in Gilchrist to which they refer in italics. Editorial comments are bracketed.</note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p03-49" n="49"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="i">Gilchrist, I, 335.</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
						<q>
                            <hi rend="i">While, in 1825,
                            the designs from Dante were progressing, I find Mr.
                            Linnell a purchaser also of twelve drawings from Milton’s</hi> 
                            Paradise Regained, <hi rend="i">a sequel to
                            those from</hi> Paradise Lost, <hi rend="i">executed for 
                            Mr. Butts, which are now scattered in various
                            hands.</hi> [<hi rend="i">“a <corr type="emend">sequel” 
                            and</corr> “which . . . hands” are underscored by 
                            Rossetti</hi>]
						</q>
                        <p>I don’t know how far this may be correct. Strange (alone to my knowledge) has a
set which may or may not be complete — much <hi rend="i">larger</hi> than the <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regained</hi> designs — some subjects noted p. 255 vol. 2, <hi rend="i">may</hi> belong to the Strange ed.
— I don’t know.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
                            <note id="n6">
                                <hi rend="s">6</hi> Rossetti’s comment explains his reservations regarding
the second passage but not the first. A letter to Mrs. Gilchrist, dated 13 Decr. [1862] is suggestive,
however; Rossetti writes, “I will consider about the Paradise Regained. The designs were shown to me by John
Linnell as being more than usually beautiful, &amp; I do not directly <hi rend="i">dissent</hi> from the terms
used in the slip you send me; only my feeling is that Blake has here been less inspired than usual, and the
result comparatively tame” (<hi rend="i">Letters of William Michael Rossetti Concerning Whitman, Blake, and
Shelley</hi> [Durham, N.C., 1934], p. 11).</note>
                        </p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="i">Gilchrist, I, 343.</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
						<q>
[<hi rend="i">In response to Henry Crabb Robinson’s report of Blake saying</hi>,] <hi rend="i">“He</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>] <hi rend="i">wished me to expose the falsehood of his doctrine taught in the</hi>
Paradise Lost <hi rend="i">that sexual intercourse arose out of the Fall.”</hi>
						</q>
                        <p>He did not</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="i">Gilchrist, II, 77.</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
						<q>
                            <hi rend="i">This enigmatic-looking poem</hi> [<hi rend="i">“The Crystal
Cabinet”</hi>] <hi rend="i">probably does no more than symbolize in a new way the world-old phenomena of a
lover’s transfiguration of his mistress and of all things through her, and the reaction when the dream is
broken by a too ardent effort to embody it.</hi>
						</q>
                        <p>I differ here, being pretty confident that the poem describes figuratively the
physical phenomena of birth: this explanation would probably be repulsive to most readers.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="i">Gilchrist, II, 88.</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
						<q>
                            <hi rend="i">THE CRYSTAL CABINET.</hi>*<lb/>
						</q>
						<p>*This poem seems to me to represent under a very ideal form the phenomena of gestation and birth. Mr.
Swinburne has suggested a different explanation; and another again is offered in the 2nd vol. of Gilchrist’s
book.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="p03-50" n="50"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="i">Gilchrist, II, 106.</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
						<q>
                            <hi rend="i">THE AGONY OF FAITH.</hi> [<hi rend="i">“AGONY OF FAITH” deleted;
“Grey Monk</hi><hi rend="s">1</hi>” <hi rend="i">written above it.</hi>] 
						</q>
                        <p><hi rend="s">1</hi> See the verses <hi rend="i">To the Deists,</hi> with which the
present poem corresponds to some extent.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="i">Gilchrist, II, 199.</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
						<q>
[<hi rend="i">At the bottom of the page on which the headnote to “Descriptive Catalogue” begins, Rossetti
writes:</hi>]
</q>
                        <p>I shd be disposed to add a sentence somewhat to the following effect: —</p>
                        <p>A Catalogue [“such” deleted] on the plan of the ensuing is peculiarly necessary in
the case of Blake. His life consisted in imaginative insight &amp; in the embodiment of that insight in the
form of art. The list of his paintings &amp; designs is therefore a most important part of his life. I am in
hopes that the extraordinary amount of original thought &amp; invention which belongs to these works will be
to some extent sensible even thro’ so imperfect a medium as that of an annotated Catalogue, &amp; will
render the looking thro’ this somewhat less tedious than would be the case with almost any other artist.</p>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p03-51" n="51" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>