<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.4.johnson</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">The Devil’s Syntax and the O.E.D.</title>
				<author n="Johnson">Mary Lynn Johnson</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>May, 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt> 
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <pb id="p03-94" n="94"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-4-0008">
                <head>
                    <title type="section"><hi rend="u">DISCUSSION</hi></title>
                </head>
                <head>
                    <title type="section-subtitle">“With Intellectual Spears and Long-winged Arrows of
Thought”</title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">1. The Devil’s Syntax and the O.E.D.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Mary Lynn <name>Johnson</name>
                        </docAuthor> Department of English Georgia State University</byline>
                    <p>How should we parse “Damn. braces: Bless relaxes”.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">1</ref> Does this proverb mean that damning braces [the one who
damns] and blessing relaxes [the one who blesses]? Or are braces to be damned and relaxes to be blessed? The
arguments on both sides are intriguing. 
                        <note id="n34">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> All quotations are from <hi rend="u">The Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City, N.Y., 1965).</note>
                    </p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <hi rend="u">The act of damning is stimulating; the act of blessing is
enervating.</hi> Although <hi rend="u">Damn</hi> and <hi rend="u">Bless</hi> are awkward nouns, the fact that
they are capitalized, as well as the placing of a pause-period after <hi rend="u">Damn</hi>, strengthens the
impression that they are nevertheless the subjects of balanced declarative clauses. The colon after 
<hi rend="u">braces</hi> and the period after <hi rend="u">relaxes</hi> further suggest the declarative sentence,
the indicative mood, as in other paired statements among the Proverbs of Hall—“Excess of sorrow laughs.
Excess of joy weeps” or “The cistern contains: the fountain overflows,” for example. Thus the pronouncing of
the word “damn” or the act of damning anything deserving of an honest man’s indignation is healthy, toning
up the nerves and girding one for battle. The weak, “angelic” act of blessing, on the other hand, weakens
<pb id="p03-95" n="95"/>
and debilitates. Or if the verbs are intransitive, “Damn” itself becomes resolute and “Bless” becomes
slack.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <hi rend="u">Curse everything that braces; bless everything that relaxes</hi>
(or curse restrains; bless releases). A more vigorous aphorism, in the imperative mood, is this command to
condemn whatever holds in and to bless whatever lets go. The punctuation does not suggest an oath or an
ejaculation (several other proverbs do end in exclamation points), however, and <hi rend="u">relaxes</hi> is
an even odder noun than <hi rend="u">Damn</hi> or <hi rend="u">Bless.</hi> Yet the formula “Damn —; Bless
—” in ordinary English word order leads us to expect nouns. Other proverbs begin with such imperatives as
“Drive,” “Dip,” “Bring,” “Think,” “Expect,” and “Listen.” The OED definitions of <hi rend="u">brace</hi> as a
noun which are relevant to this proverb are “that which clasps, tightens, secures, connects” and “that which
imparts rigidity or steadiness.” Since—fortunately—the use of <hi rend="u">braces</hi> to mean 
<hi rend="u">suspenders</hi> does not appear until 1816, the noun <hi rend="u">braces</hi> is a good synonym for
the Urizenic laws, “mindforg’d manacles,” Newtonian systems, the thou-shalt-nots under which priests are
“binding with briars my joys and desires.” Blessed by angels, all such “braces” are damned by the Devil.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The noun form of <hi rend="u">relax</hi> is rare, but it is used by Milton, and the OED
records it as late as 1773. It has even been known to occur in the plural form, in Owen Felltham’s 
<hi rend="u">Resolves</hi> between 1627 and 1677. It means “relaxation, or that which causes relaxation.” The
legal meaning of <hi rend="u">relaxation</hi>, “partial (or complete) remission of some penalty, burden, duty,
etc.,” would certainly be considered praiseworthy by the Devil’s party. Another definition, 
“<corr type="emend">diminution</corr> of, release or freedom from, strictness or severity,” should be equally
attractive to the apostles of exuberance. The religious would consider such “relaxes” a threat to the angelic
code and its enforcement, but the Devil heartily blesses them.</p>
                    <p>Evidence from Blake’s own usage elsewhere is inconclusive. According to David V.
Erdman’s <hi rend="u">Concordance</hi> (Ithaca, N.Y., 1967), <hi rend="u">relax</hi> appears nowhere else in
Blake. <hi rend="u">Brace</hi>, in its three other appearances, is a noun modified by iron:
<q>
A. Nought can deform the Human Race<lb/>
Like to the Armours iron brace.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
(Auguries of Innocence, 11. 99-100)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
B. The “golden builders” form Golgonooza from such materials as stones of pity, bricks of affections, tiles of
merciful labor, beams and rafters of forgiveness, and<lb/>
the nails,<lb/>
And the screws &amp; iron braces, are well wrought blandishments<lb/>
And well contrived words, firm fixing, never forgotten,<lb/>
Always comforting the remembrance.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
(<hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> 12:33-36)
<pb id="p03-96" n="96"/>
C. Los’s sons Rintrah, Palamabron, Theotormon, and Bromion have endured long periods of anguish in the
Furnaces at which they now labor. The machinery there includes<lb/>
iron rollers, golden axle-trees &amp; yokes<lb/>
Of brass, iron chains &amp; braces &amp; the gold, silver &amp; brass<lb/>
Mingled or separate: for swords; arrows; cannons; mortars<lb/>
The terrible ball: the wedge: the loud sounding hammer of destruction.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
(<hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> 73:9-12)
</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="u">Damn</hi> and <hi rend="u">Bless</hi> are always verbs, although the
direct objects of <hi rend="u">Bless</hi> are consistently ironic: Tiriel’s bald pate or the seventh day on
which the children of Urizen rest after having shrunk up from existence. <hi rend="u">Damn</hi>, on the other
hand, is used as a straightforward expletive, as in “damn sneerers” in the annotations to Lavater (Keynes, p.
67, Erdman, p. 574).</p>
                    <p>It seems highly likely that “Damn. braces: Bless relaxes”: has more than one infernal
or diabolical meaning. E. J. Rose has commented on “Blake’s synchronization of parts of speech with his
symbolism.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">2</ref> In “Mental forms
Creating,” for instance, “Creating” is both a participle and a verb. When corrosives have melted away apparent
grammatical surfaces, Blake’s ambiguity of syntax (Empson’s second type of ambiguity) emerges. Both the
first and second meanings, at the very least, are simultaneously communicated in a double-edged statement of
infernal wisdom. 
                        <note id="n35">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Edward J. Rose, “Visionary Forms Dramatic: Grammatical and
Iconographical Movement in Blake’s Verse and Designs,” <hi rend="u">Criticism</hi>, VIII (1966),
111-125.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>