<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.4.betz</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Wordsworth’s First Acquaintance with Blake’s Poetry</title>
				<author n="Betz">Paul F. Betz</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>May, 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt> 
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-4-0005">
                <pb id="p03-84" n="84"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">2. Wordsworth’s First Acquaintance With Blake’s Poetry</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Paul F. <name>Betz</name>
                        </docAuthor> Georgetown University</byline>
                    <p>It is relatively well known that William Wordsworth’s Commonplace Book (Dove Cottage
MS. Prose 31) contains four of Blake’s early poems: “Holy Thursday” and “Laughing Song” from the 
<hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence</hi>, “The Tyger” from the <hi rend="u">Songs of Experience</hi>, and “I love the
jocund dance” from <hi rend="u">Poetical Sketches.</hi>
                        <ref target="n22" type="note">1</ref> One might have hoped to discover that these
transcripts had been taken directly from the rare primary sources, or indirectly from these sources through
the agency of Southey, Lamb, or Crabb Robinson. But Mary Moorman, in an interesting article on “Wordsworth’s
Commonplace Book” in the September 1957 issue of <hi rend="u">Notes and Queries</hi> (pp. 400-405), has
pointed out that the poems probably have been taken from Benjamin Heath Malkin’s <hi rend="u">A Father’s
Memoir of his Child</hi> (1806), where six of Blake’s short poems were printed for the first time.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">2</ref> G. E. Bentley, Jr., in <hi rend="u">Blake
Records</hi>, has recently confirmed the Malkin source of the entries.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n24" type="note">3</ref>
                        <note id="n22">
                                <hi rend="s">1</hi> I am grateful for encouragement and advice given by
Professors Morton D. Paley, Mark L. Reed, and David V. Erdman; and I wish to thank the Trustees of Dove
Cottage for permission to examine Ms. Prose 31. Wordsworth’s Commonplace Book is complicated by the
confusion of hands which so often plagues scholars working on Wordsworth manuscripts, and which has lead to
frequent examples of mis-attribution in the past. While the drafts of Wordsworth’s verse notebooks have
often not been entered chronologically, with the possible exception of pasted-in entries there seems almost
always to be a steady chronological progression in the Commonplace Book entries.
                            <p>Leaf numbers as given above refer only to the original leaves of the notebook,
not to the slips and full leaves which have been pasted to those original leaves. All material cited here has
been written directly on original leaves.</p>
                            <p>Entries in the notebook run from both ends toward the middle. All entries of a
primarily literary interest are at one end. The few pages with entries at the other end are entirely taken up
with household lists, accounts, medical remedies, and a page of notes by Dorothy about the infant language and
activities of John, Wordsworth’s first son, born in 1803.</p>
                            <p>My disagreement with F. W. Bateson’s suggestion that Wordsworth may well have
encountered some of Blake’s poems as early as 1797 will be seen from the title of this note; although, of
course, evidence to that effect may someday be discovered. Mr. Bateson’s statement (pp. 133-134), that
“Susan is one of the country girls in ‘Laughing Song’ and it may not be simply a coincidence that
Wordsworth’s poem is ‘The Reverie of Poor Susan,’” is surprising. There is no indication that
Wordsworth’s lack of invention in choosing names, to which Mr. Bateson alludes, ever extended this far. In
addition, the title itself is a translation or Bürger’s “Das Arme Süsschens Traum,” a poem which
Wordsworth praised (see Mary Moorman, <hi rend="u">William Wordsworth: The Early Years, 1770-1803</hi>, p.
428), although it must be added that when first published the poem was called only “Poor Susan.”</p>
                        </note>
                        <note id="n23">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Moorman, “Wordsworth’s Commonplace Book,” p. 403.</note>
                        <note id="n24">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="u">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford,
1969), p. 430n.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>However, the question of when the poems were read and transcribed into the Commonplace
Book still remains to be settled. F. W. Bateson, in <hi rend="u">Wordsworth: A Re-Interpretation</hi> (second
edition, 1956), writes that the entries were made “in or about 1804.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n25" type="note">4</ref> He has perhaps been misled by the presence, several pages before the Blake
poems, of seven pages of extracts (leaves 38 recto to 41 recto) from Sir John Barrow’s <hi rend="u">Travels
in China</hi>; at the top of lead 38 recto, above the title of the
<pb id="p03-85" n="85"/>
book, the Poet’s grandson Gordon Graham Wordsworth has written: “First Published in 1804.” But this is not
to say that the Wordsworths read the book when it was first published; and as Mrs. Moorman has established
Malkin as the source of the verses, a date before 1806 is almost impossible. <note id="n25">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> Bateson, <hi rend="u">Wordsworth: A Re-Interpretation</hi>
(London, 1956), p. 133.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Mrs. Moorman does not attempt to specify the date of the Blake entries, although in
another context she points out that what appears to be the final entry in the Commonplace Book is a part of
Wordsworth’s June 5, 1808, letter to Francis Wrangham.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">5</ref> This narrows the probable date of the Blake transcripts to a period of approximately two
years. 
                        <note id="n26">
                            <hi rend="s">5</hi> Moorman, “Wordsworth’s Commonplace Book,” p. 400. The entire
letter appears in <hi rend="u">The Letters of William and Dorothy Wordsworth: The Middle Years</hi>, I, ed.
Ernest de Selincourt, rev. Mary Moorman (Oxford, 1969), pp. 246-251.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>It now appears that the four Blake entries can be placed with some certainty within the
period of six and one-half months between February 12, 1807 and August 25, 1807. Within this period, the most
likely dates of transcription seem to be from mid-March to mid-April, and from mid-May to June 10.</p>
                    <p>On February 15, 1807, from the temporary home of the Wordsworths at Coleorton, Dorothy
wrote to Lady Beaumont that “We received the Books a week ago” which had been lent by the Beaumonts, and that
“I shall next begin with Barrow’s Travels.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">6</ref> Most and probably all of the literary extracts in the Commonplace Book seem likely to have
been made at William’s request, so that he might again consult passages or poems from books which he did not
then own. As William would have needed to read the book first, Mary Wordsworth’s seven extracts from Barrow
were probably made after Dorothy’s reading, and could not have been made earlier than two or three days
before it. The Barrow entries are followed by John Mayne’s poem “Logan Braes” (leaves 41 verso-42 recto) in
the hand of Sara Hutchinson, a brief passage “From Aristotle’s Synopsis of the virtues and vices” (leaf 42
recto) in Dorothy’s hand, and excerpts from J. L. Buchanan’s <hi rend="u">Travels in the Western
Hebrides</hi> (leaves 42 recto-43 verso) in William’s hand. Only then come Blake’s “Holy Thursday” (leaf
43 verso), “Laughing Song” (leaf 44 recto), and the first quatrain of “The Tyger” (leaf 44 recto) in
William’s hand, followed by the rest of “The Tyger” (leaf 44 verso) and “I love the jocund dance” (leaf 45
recto) in Mary’s hand. If one considers the time necessary for William to have read the works mentioned
earlier, as well as other books quite probably read but not represented in the Commonplace Book (see
Dorothy’s letter to Lady Beaumont for three possibilities), a date earlier than mid-March for the Blake
entries seems unlikely. 
                        <note id="n27">
                            <hi rend="s">6</hi>
                            <hi rend="u"> Letters: The Middle Years</hi>, I, p. 133. The Wordsworths arrived
at Coleorton in Leicestershire at the beginning of November, 1806, and did not depart to return to Grasmere
until June 10, 1807. They stayed in the Coleorton farm house as the guests of Sir George Beaumont,
Wordsworth’s patron, while the Beaumonts themselves spent most of this period in London. Sara Hutchinson was
at Coleorton from the beginning until mid-April; while Coleridge and his son Hartley arrived on December 21
and also remained until mid-April. It is certainly possible that Coleridge may have seen <hi rend="u">A
Father’s Memoir</hi>, with its Blake verses, during this stay.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>On August 25, 1807, William and Mary set out for a short stay at Eusemere at the foot
of Ullswater. This would have been the Poet’s first opportunity to see Thomas Wilkinson the Quaker poet, who
lived nearby, since before the Wordsworths had moved to Coleorton during the previous autumn. During November
1806, when already at Coleorton, Wordsworth had written to Wilkinson:
<q>
I was prevented by a most severe cold from seeing you as I intended . . . what shall I say in apology for your
<pb id="p03-86" n="86"/>
Journal, which is now locked up with my manuscripts at Grasmere . . . unluckily, most unluckily, in the hurry
of departure I forgot it, together with two of my own manuscripts which were along with it . . . it may be
procured, for I can write to Grasmere to that effect; it is there in perfect safety . . . . If you do not want
it, it is in a place where it can take no injury, and I may have the pleasure of delivering it to you myself
in the spring.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">7</ref>
                            <note id="n28">
                                <hi rend="s">7</hi>
                                <hi rend="u"> Letters: The Middle Years</hi>, I, p. 104.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The “Journal” mentioned is the Scottish section of Wilkinson’s <hi rend="u">Tours to
the British Mountains</hi>, parts of which circulated in manuscript long before actual publication in 1824.
Wordsworth had seen this section of the journal before 1806; he had based the final lines of “The Solitary
Reaper,” composed on November 5, 1805, upon a short passage from it. This very passage (“Pass’d by a Female
who was reaping alone, she sung in Erse as she bended over her sickle, the sweetest human Voice I ever
heard[.] Her strains were tenderly melancholy and felt delicious long after they were heard no more”) has been
entered retrospectively by Wordsworth at the top of leaf 45 verso, directly after the Blake entries. It is
followed by a second passage from Wilkinson which Wordsworth draws upon in <hi rend="u">The Excursion</hi>,
IV, 489-504.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">8</ref> There is no indication
that Wilkinson asked for the immediate return of his manuscript, and it would not have been in character; but
Wordsworth would surely have taken the first opportunity to return the overdue loan in person. Since the
manuscript had been in Grasmere, Wordsworth would have entered these passages in his Commonplace Book between
the family’s return to Grasmere during July 1807 and the departure for Eusemere on August 25. 
                        <note id="n29">
                            <hi rend="s">8</hi> The first passage appears in Thomas Wilkinson, 
<hi rend="u">Tours to the British Mountains, with the Descriptive Poems of Lowther, and Emont Vale</hi> (London,
1824), p. 12. The second passage, also clearly from the Scottish tour, never appeared in the published
version.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>How did Wordsworth encounter <hi rend="u">A Father’s Memoir of his Child</hi>? It may
have been through Dorothy Wordsworth’s friend, Catherine Clarkson. On August 26 (or 27), 1809, Dorothy wrote
to Mrs. Clarkson:
<q>
We saw in the paper the other day that Mr. Malkin is elected to the Mastership of Bury School. I am afraid he
will not fill the place so well as the late Master for I am told he is a coxcomb, and indeed it is plain
enough from the manner in which that account of his Son is written.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n30" type="note">9</ref>
                            <note id="n30">
                                <hi rend="s">9</hi>
                                <hi rend="u"> Letters: The Middle Years</hi>, I, p. 368.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Dorothy seems to assume that Catherine Clarkson also is familiar with the book, and
indeed the Clarksons lived in Bury St. Edmonds. If this is the source, then the book might have come
ultimately from Henry Crabb Robinson. Crabb Robinson indicates that prior to his attendance at Blake’s 1809
exhibition he had encountered Blake’s work only through Malkin,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n31" type="note">10</ref> and while not yet personally acquainted with the Wordsworths, he had been on
terms of close friendship with Catherine Clarkson for some time. 
                        <note id="n31">
                            <hi rend="s">10</hi> See Crabb Robinson’s account of this is <hi rend="u">Blake,
Coleridge, Wordsworth, Lamb, Etc., being Selections from the Remains of Henry Crabb Robinson</hi>, ed. Edith
J. Morley (Manchester, 1922), pp. 17-19.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>However, a more likely source seems to be the Beaumonts, either through their library
at Coleorton or through books sent on personal loan.</p>
                    <pb id="p03-87" n="87"/>
                    <p>While there is no evidence that the Wordsworths were receiving books from the Clarksons
during this period, they definitely were receiving books from the Beaumonts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">11</ref> If Malkin’s book came to them through the Beaumonts, then
in line with the limitations already established, the Blake entries were probably made within either of two
short periods: from mid-March to mid-April, when Wordsworth left Coleorton for London; and from mid-May, when
Wordsworth returned to Coleorton, to June 10, when the family left Coleorton for an extended journey which was
to take them at last back to Grasmere. 
                        <note id="n32">
                            <hi rend="s">11</hi> See <hi rend="u">Letters: The Middle Years</hi>, I, pp. 129,
133, and 186. Of course, they may have first heard of the book from Catherine Clarkson, and may have asked the
Beaumonts for the book or chosen it from the library at Coleorton for that reason.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Important questions remain to be answered. Why did Wordsworth select these poems while
omitting the other two printed by Malkin: “The Divine Image” and “How sweet I roam’d”? Did Wordsworth have
in mind the possibility of publishing the poems himself in a collection of poetry he appears to have
contemplated making at this time?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">12</ref> If
he had actually done so, this would quite possibly have introduced Blake’s poetry to a wider audience than
it ever enjoyed during his lifetime. And what influence, if any, did Wordsworth’s awareness of these poems
have on his own work? <note id="n33">
                            <hi rend="s">12</hi> The only evidence for this proposed collection is Mary
Lamb’s comment, in a letter written to Mrs. Clarkson on December 25, 1806, that “my brother sometimes
threatens to pass his holidays in town hunting over old plays at the Museum to extract passages for a work (a
collection of poetry) Mr. Wordsworth intends to publish.” <hi rend="u">The Letters of Charles and Mary
Lamb</hi>, II, ed. E. V. Lucas (London, 1935), p. 33.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p03-88-89" n="88-89" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>