<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.4.reed</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake, Wordsworth, Lamb, Etc.: Further Information from Henry Crabb
Robinson</title>
				<author n="Reed">Mark L. Reed</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>May, 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt> 
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
			<pb id="p03-76" n="76"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-4-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">NOTES</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">1. Blake, Wordsworth, Lamb, Etc.: Further Information from Henry
Crabb Robinson</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Mark L. <name>Reed</name>
                        </docAuthor> University of North Carolina Chapel Hill, North Carolina</byline>
                    <p>A significant link in the literary correspondence of Henry Crabb Robinson with Edward
Quillinan, the widowed son-in-law of revered friend Wordsworth, as presented in Edith J. Morley’s 
<hi rend="u">Correspondence of Henry Crabb Robinson with the Wordsworth Circle</hi> (London, 1927) is supplied by
the following letter at the Dove Cottage Library. These comments from the barrister to Quillinan, who was
still an intimate of the poet’s household, include revealing remarks on the
<pb id="p03-77" n="77"/>
medallion of Wordsworth by Leonard Charles Wyon (1826-1891), but rather more excitingly contain Robinson’s
part of a short but explicit discussion of William Blake hitherto known only on quillinan’s side 
(<hi rend="u">Correspondence</hi>, pp. 675-77). They thus add a new item to what is properly reckoned “in many ways
. . . the best contemporary record we have of Blake.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref> More particularly, they add definition to Robinson’s and Wordsworth’s opinions of
Blake and report amusingly if ambiguously on Charles Lamb’s opinion of both Blake and Wordsworth. 
                        <note id="n1">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., in G. E. Bentley, Jr., and M. K. Nurmi,
<hi rend="u">A Blake Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis, 1964), p. 9. For valuable assistance and advice in the
preparation of this note I am grateful to Professor Paul F. Betz, Professor Bentley, and Mr. John Creasey,
Deputy Librarian of the Dr. Williams Library.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>A few words on the background of Robinson’s statements will provide perspective. The
event in which the exchange on Blake originated was a visit paid by Quillinan at Wordsworth’s home, Rydal
Mount, on 27 July 1848. There Quillinan noticed a parcel of books just arrived from the Poet Laureate’s
publisher Moxon, and later in the day he wrote to Robinson a letter containing these remarks:
<q>
I observed C. Lamb’s Letters, &amp; <hi rend="u">Blake’s</hi> Poems - &amp; as I was glancing over them
for an hour or two, it seemed to me that both publications had the fault of <hi rend="u">too much.</hi> In
Lamb’s <hi rend="u">too much</hi> (for some may be well enough) of childish fun, or rather that strain at
fun which is the trivial imitation of child’s fun; - And <hi rend="u">some</hi> of Blake’s verses,
illustrated in the book you possess, want in this publication the poetry of painting to support them. They
seemed to sound very like nonsense-verses, as we read them aloud. <hi rend="u">Some</hi> of them, I say; for
others have a real charm in their wildness and oddness. Do not suppose I undervalue the man. I have on the
contrary a sort of tenderness for him that makes me disposed perhaps to over-estimate the value of many of his
verses.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
                            <note id="n2">
                                <hi rend="s">2</hi> T. N. Talfourd’s <hi rend="u">Final Memorials of Charles
Lamb</hi>, dedicated to Wordsworth, was published by Moxon 22 July 1848 (London <hi rend="u">Times</hi> of 17
and 30 July). Robinson’s Diary shows that he read the book between 24 July and 5 August. As 
“<hi rend="u">Blake’s</hi> Poems” lacked pictorial embellishment, Quillinan’s reference is plainly to the
edition of <hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> of J. J. Garth Wilkinson published by
Pickering and Newbery in 1839, the only unillustrated collection then extant of verses of Blake’s of which
an illustrated collection was also extant. Robinson had met Wilkinson on 16 April 1848, and by 27 April had
received from him a copy of his edition of Blake and ordered more from Moxon. His Diary records four further
meetings in May and June. The “book you possess” was probably Robinson’s copy of the 
<hi rend="u">Songs</hi>, Keynes and Wolf copy Z, apparently purchased from Blake 18 February 1826. Robinson also
owned copies of <hi rend="u">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, pl. 21-24 (K), <hi rend="u">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi> (O), and <hi rend="u">America</hi> (D). Probably all were acquired from Blake, and
the first two were certainly, the last probably, in Robinson’s possession at this time. (Geoffrey Keynes and
Edwin Wolf 2nd, <hi rend="u">William</hi> Blake’s Illuminated Books, New York, 1953, pp. 32, 39, 65;
information from Professor Bentley derived primarily from John Pearson Catalogue no. 62, ?1886, item 70. See
also note 18 below.) Robinson possibly received another copy of <hi rend="u">Songs</hi> from Miss Denman on 1
Oct 1842. See E. J. Morley, ed., <hi rend="u">Henry Crabb Robinson on Books and Their Writers</hi> (London,
1938), p. 625. (The phrasing of his 1848 references to the Garth Wilkinson volume does not suggest earlier
familiarity with the book.)</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The diarist’s answer was delayed by his travels, but he replied as follows from Bury
St. Edmunds on 10 August. His letter, comment on which will be basically confined to portions directly
relating to Blake and Wordsworth, is here published with the kind permission of the Dove Cottage Trustees.
Superscript letters have been brought down to the line and accompanying subscript periods omitted.
Misspellings are reproduced without comment. The dash-like periods with which Robinson habitually closes his
sentences are transcribed as points.</p>
                    <p>Bury St. Emunds</p>
                    <p>10th Augt 48</p>
                    <p>My dear Sir.</p>
                    <p>It was not forgetfulness of your letter so mu[ch] as of my not having replied to it
[tha]t I am to be reproached with: There was time for a rejoinder had the time [time del.] occasion been
given.</p>
                    <p>I have now a cluster of letters to be thankful for.</p>
                    <pb id="p03-78" n="78"/>
                    <p>But it suits [suits del. and rewritten] the scantiness of my materials to jumble
together some notice of all. Tho’ indeed the greater portion of what you &amp; Mrs. W: have written calls
only for &amp; sometimes admits only of an acknowledgment.</p>
                    <p>As I was driving in an Omnibus to Hampstead on Saturday I fell in with young Wyon. He
told me he was on his road to the North. There was a time when he had wished to have another Sitting from Mr.
W: in order to complete his exercise on the poets physiognomy. There is no form of plastic work that I like so
much as bas-relief <hi rend="u">Medallion</hi> (<hi rend="u">Italice Medalone</hi>) The small medal certainly
fails [fails <hi rend="u">del.</hi>] as a likeness is a - failure But the expression is pure And the sadness
will be understood. The next generation will be delighted with it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
                        <note id="n3">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> Robinson had written to Wordsworth on 18 April 1847 to arrange
a sitting for Wyon, who made a pencil and chalk drawing of the poet on 21 April. Wordsworth sat again on 26
April for the model of his head on which Wyon based the profile medal which he cast in early 1848. Robinson
ordered two silver medals. During the second sitting Wordsworth was called from the room to hear bad news
about the health of his daughter Mrs. Quillinan, who died on 9 July. Wyon called at Rydal Mount probably on 9
or 10 August. See <hi rend="u">Henry Crabb Robinson on Books</hi>, pp. 664-65, 674; 
<hi rend="u">Correspondence</hi>, II, pp. 662, 677; Francis Blanchard, <hi rend="u">Portraits</hi>
                            <hi rend="u">of Wordsworth</hi> (Ithaca, 1959), pp. 18, 99-100, 173-74, plates
30a, 30b.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>You speak more 
slightingly<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> 
than I should expected of <hi rend="u">Blake.</hi> Recollect they are not to be considered
as works of art. but as fragments of a shattered intellect. Lamb used to call him a “mad Wordsworth” Enquire
of Mrs. W: Whether she has not a copy of his <hi rend="u">Catalogue.</hi> If she has not, enquire of me
hereafter. Many years ago Mr. W: read some poems which I had copied and made a remark on them which I would
not repeat to every one. “There is no doubt that this man is mad, but there is something in this madness which
I enjoy more than the <hi rend="u">Sense</hi> of W: Sc: or Lord B:—I had lent him when he died the 8vo Edit
in 2 Vols: of W. W’s poems. They were sent me by his widow with the pencil marginalia which I inked over. He
admired W:W: “tho’ an atheist” And when I protested against this sentence it was thus supported. “Who ever
worships nature denies God, for nature is the Devils work.” I succumbed, for he always beat me in argument. He
almost went into a fit of rapture at the platonic ode.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> “Slightingly” underlined and annotated by Quillinan in pencil:
“as usual a mistake of friend Crabbe’s[.]”</note>
                        <note id="n5">
                            <hi rend="s">5</hi> On the loan of Wordsworth’s Poems (1815) see E. J. Morley,
ed., <hi rend="u">Blake, Coleridge, Wordsworth, Lamb, Etc.</hi> (Manchester and London, 1922), p. 24. This
letter confirms Erdman’s conjecture (<hi rend="u">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, New York,
1965, p. 802) that the inking-over was done by Robinson. Blake’s most direct comments (apart from his
marginalia) on Wordsworth as a worshipper of Nature and the voice of the Devil appear in Robinson’s Diary
under the dates of 24 December 1825 and 18 February and 12 May 1826. Robinson wrote to Dorothy Wordsworth
about Blake’s views of her brother as an atheist in February 1826 (see <hi rend="u">Blake, Coleridge</hi>,
[etc.], pp. 14-16). He read the <hi rend="u">Ode</hi> to Blake on 24 December 1826, probably the occasion upon
which Blake responded to the passage “But there’s a tree . . . ” with almost “hysterical rapture” (ibid.,
pp. 15, 23).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>I enjoyed our Lincoln trip: It was a mere social enjoyment. I shall continue to
accompany the learned body, until I am become quite intolerable And considered as a burthen. I cannot now even
<hi rend="u">learn</hi> on such an excursion. <hi rend="u">Teaching</hi> was never by [by 
<hi rend="u">del.</hi>] my forte. My single contribution consisted in repeatedly reciting
<q>
“How profitless the relics that they [they del.] we cull!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
                            <lb/>
                            <lb/>
&amp;c &amp;c &amp;c <note id="n6">
                                <hi rend="s">6</hi> Wordsworth, “Roman Antiquities,” 1. 1.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>We made among others, a wild trip to Tattershall-Castle and Boston Stump [Stump 
<hi rend="u">repeated</hi>]. The R:R: Comp: treated us with the journey over an unfinished road in iron sand
trucks. And gave us a luncheon to boot. We had bishops deans lords &amp; barronets And I enjoyed the excursion
mightily. I shall stay here about a month. And how spend [sic] the other idle months will depend on accidents.
I had meant to go to Germany, but really the uncertain, perhaps perillous state of the country is a sufficient
reason for abandoning the scheme: As to France; I have really no inclination whatever to go thither again. I
mean in a few days to go to Playford.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
And that journey will I trust supply materials for a short letter to Mrs. Wordsworth. You will have
<pb id="p03-79" n="79"/>
seen Mrs. Reid by this time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> her great
worth lies in her perfect disinterestedness &amp; great benevolence rather than in the judgement which directs
that benevolence. When you fall in with her, just say I am <hi rend="u">here.</hi> She may favor me with a
line. Indeed I am looking for one. To my dear friends at Rydal Mount The Miss Qus: Miss M: Mrs. D &amp; Mrs. F
&amp; Lady R: The Doctor<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> &amp;c &amp;c
&amp;c . . . my Kind regards 
                        <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">7</hi> Residence of Catherine Clarkson.</note>
                        <note id="n8">
                            <hi rend="s">8</hi> See <hi rend="u">Correspondence</hi>, II, pp. 674-77.</note>
                        <note id="n9">
                            <hi rend="s">9</hi> Jemima and Rotha Quillinan; Miss Martineau; Mrs. John Davy;
Mrs. Fletcher; Lady Richardson; probably Doctor Christopher Wordsworth, Jr.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Most truly yours</p>
                    <p>H. C. Robinson</p>
                    <p>E. Quillinan Esqr</p>
                    <p>Quillinan apparently completed the exchange on Blake in his response of 12 August, of
which it is sufficient to note that the writer denies having spoken slightingly of Blake, one of his “pet
spoiled children of genius.” Robinson’s more valuable comments are of course in large part variants of
anecdotes or information recorded in hitherto published writings of the diarist. His remark that Blake “always
beat” him in argument, however, although possibly intended to convey no more than “beat down,” implies a
recollection of Blake as more effective in rational dispute than he elsewhere acknowledges: His usual
explanation of his failures to explain himself to, or convince, the poet, such as “I tried to twist this
passage into a sense corresponding with Blake’s own theories, but failed,” or, “Objections were seldom of
any use,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> is the poet’s
singularity. Robinson’s less ambiguous pronouncement on Blake’s sanity, for all its suggestions of
cataclysmic historiography, provides a new confirmation of the barrister’s basic attitude on this subject as
later reported, with concern, by Gilchrist: “Among those who think Blake to have been an ‘insane man of
genius’ or at any rate a victim of monomania, [Robinson] is the only one to think so of all I have met with
who actually knew anything of him.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
Earlier remarks by Robinson on the subject were not uniformly unqualified—he told Dorothy Wordsworth in
1826, for example, that Blake “will interest you . . . whatever character you give to his mind”; in 1836 he
reassured Samuel Palmer that “in calling Blake insane I was not repeating the commonplace declamation against
him.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Here he apparently settles
conclusively on a description that fixes the pattern for the phrasing of his 1852 Reminiscences, on which
Gilchrist’s description of Robinson evidently draws in turn, where Blake is again described as an “insane
man of genius” and victim of “that form of insanity or lunacy called Monomania.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
                        <note id="n10">
                            <hi rend="s">10</hi>
                            <hi rend="u"> Henry Crabb Robinson on Books</hi>, p. 327; Blake, Coleridge,
[etc.], p. 7.</note>
                        <note id="n11">
                            <hi rend="s">11</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="u">The Life of William
Blake</hi> (London and Cambridge, 1863), I, 338.</note>
                        <note id="n12">
                            <hi rend="s">12</hi> Blake, Coleridge, [etc.], p. 14; <hi rend="u">Henry Crabb
Robinson on Books</hi>, p. 498.</note>
                        <note id="n13">
                            <hi rend="s">13</hi> Blake, Coleridge, [etc.], p. 18. Robinson, commenting on
Gilchrist’s biography on 11 November [1863], a few days after its publication, adds a remark on “one of
Blake’s coloured drawings, which was headed <hi rend="u">America</hi>”: “When I attempted to read it some
years since I thought it Sheer-Madness.” (Letter to Mrs. F. W. Fields, Osborn Collection, Yale University
Library; quoted with permission of the owner and Professor Bentley, who called my attention to Robinson’s
comment.) As early as 1810, in his essay on the poet for the <hi rend="u">Vaterländisches Museum</hi>, he had
characterized Blake (whom he met on 10 December 1825), as demonstrating “the union of genius and madness.”
(See K. A. Esdaile, “An Early Appreciation of William Blake,” <hi rend="u">The Library</hi>, V, 1914, p. 236:
Mrs. Esdaile’s re-translation from the German.)</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The immediate sequel of these comments in the 1852 Reminiscences is a repetition, again
in phrasing almost identical to that of the 1848 letter, of Wordsworth’s pronouncement upon Blake to
Robinson after “reading” of a number of the poems: “There is no doubt this poor man was mad, but there is
something in the madness of this man which interests me more than the sanity of Lord Byron or Walter
Scott!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Wordsworth’s alleged
comment calls for scrutiny. Possibly it is reported accurately, but it differs radically from other of his
comments on Byron’s own mental condition. On 18 April 1816 the poet wrote
<pb id="p03-80" n="80"/>
bluntly to John Scott that Byron was “insane; and will probably end his career in a mad-house.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Earlier, on 24 May 1812, he is recorded in
Robinson’s Diary as remarking that he believed Byron “somewhat cracked.” This comment, however, accompanied
another of the same day, when, upon hearing Robinson read some of Blake’s poems, Wordsworth said that he
“considered Blake as having the elements of poetry a thousand times more than either Byron or Scott.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> In the absence of further evidence, it seems
probable that this incident is the actual basis of the 1848-1852 recollection. Robinson’s comment to
Quillinan may thus represent a casual but, in the event, decisive misformulation of a recollection of an
occasion “many years ago”—on 24 May 1812—when Wordsworth in fact expressed appreciation of Blake’s
powers and doubts of the sanity of Byron. 
                        <note id="n14">
                            <hi rend="s">14</hi> Blake, Coleridge, [etc.], p. 18.</note>
                        <note id="n15">
                            <hi rend="s">15</hi> Ernest de Selincourt, ed., <hi rend="u">The Letters of
William and Dorothy Wordsworth. The Middle Years</hi> (Oxford, 1937), p. 734. A more temperate view of Byron
by Wordsworth is recorded in <hi rend="u">Henry Crabb Robinson on Books</hi>, pp. 486-87, but is too late
(1836) to bear upon the present discussion.</note>
                        <note id="n16">
                            <hi rend="s">16</hi>
                            <hi rend="u"> Henry Crabb Robinson on Books</hi>, p. 85.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Wordsworth, whom Blake regarded as “the <hi rend="u">only</hi> poet of the age,” and of
whose <hi rend="u">Ode</hi> Blake “most enjoyed” the parts that Robinson “least” liked or comprehended, had
probably known all of the poems of Blake’s printed by Malkin in <hi rend="u">A Father’s Memoir of His
Child</hi> (1806) by 25 August 1807.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref>; and whether Wordsworth read or listened on 24 May 1812, Robinson then possessed
transcripts of at least nineteen poems or excerpts from Blake, of which sixteen had not appeared in
Malkin.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> It would thus be
inappropriate, in view of the possible extent of Wordsworth’s contact with Blake’s work by this date, to
overlook a last anecdote bearing on Wordsworth’s opinions of Blake’s mental balance, Gilchrist’s rather
vague report that he “spake in private of the <hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence and Experience</hi> . . . as
‘undoubtedly the production of insane genius’ . . . but as to him more significant than the works of many
a famous poet.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> Gilchrist
immediately afterward cites Robinson as the source of his repetition of the late story of Wordsworth on
Blake’s madness, and thus seems to distinguish the diarist from his source for this previous quotation. But
the phrasing of the undocumented quotation is so Robinsonian that it must nonetheless be regarded on present
evidence as most likely derivative from Robinson—possibly ultimately from the same events of 24 May 1812.
The record in any event is hearsay. The case for Wordsworth’s having termed Blake insane would appear to
stand unproven. 
                        <note id="n17">
                            <hi rend="s">17</hi>
                            <hi rend="u"> Blake, Coleridge</hi>, [etc.], p. 15; <hi rend="u">Henry Crabb
Robinson on Books</hi>, pp. 330-31; Paul F. Betz, “Wordsworth’s First Acquaintance with Blake’s Poetry,”
elsewhere in this issue of <hi rend="u">Blake Newsletter.</hi> Poems of Blake’s published in Malkin are
“Laughing Song,” “Holy Thursday” (<hi rend="u">Innocence</hi>), “The Divine Image,” “How sweet I roamed,” “I
love the jocund dance,” “The Tiger.”</note>
                        <note id="n18">
                            <hi rend="s">18</hi> Transcripts of or from poems not in Malkin included at least:
“To the Muses,” “Night,” “The Little Black Boy,” “The Chimney Sweeper” (<hi rend="u">Innocence</hi>), “A
Dream,” “The Sunflower,” “Introduction” (<hi rend="u">Experience</hi>), “Earth’s Answer,” “The Garden of
Love,” “A Little Boy Lost,” “The Poison Tree,” “The Sick Rose,” “The Human Abstract,” the “Dedication” of the
designs for Blair’s <hi rend="u">Grave</hi> (1808), America, pl. 10, 11. 5-10, and <hi rend="u">Europe</hi>,
pl. 1, 11. 12-15. Robinson’s 1810 Vaterlandisches Museum article (see note 13 above) had included one poem
not among these transcripts, “Introduction” (<hi rend="u">Innocence</hi>); and Robinson also possessed
transcripts from the Exhibition <hi rend="u">Advertisement</hi> (1809): See Esdaile, pp. 224-56. Mrs. Esdaile
saw the transcripts which she describes at the Dr. Williams Library. An “old letter” upon which Robinson
copied the excerpts from <hi rend="u">America, Europe</hi>, and the <hi rend="u">Advertisement</hi> seems to
have disappeared since Mrs. Esdaile’s examination. The lyric transcripts are in Bundle 1.VI.29 of the
Robinson papers. I am indebted to Professor Bentley and Mr. John Creasey for information of these materials.
Mr. Creasey has advised me, since the completion of this note, that “Introduction” 
(<hi rend="u">Innocence</hi>) is also found among a set of transcripts, otherwise containing no poems of Blake’s
not in Malkin or the copies already cited, in a pocket book of Robinson’s also in the Dr. Williams
Library.</note>
                        <note id="n19">
                            <hi rend="s">19</hi> Gilchrist, I, pp. [1]-2.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Lamb’s reported comment on Blake, perhaps the earliest direct suggestion, facetious
or otherwise, by a critic of resemblances between the minds or purposes of Blake and Wordsworth, might add a
minute, speculative measure to the other side of the balance. To characterize Blake as a “mad Wordsworth” is
of course to characterize Wordsworth as well, and not necessarily to his praise: The positive qualities of the
Wordsworthian sanity remain wickedly undefined. One readily recalls Lamb’s irony when, in 1808, he
understood remarks of the poet to be a claim of ability to write like Shakespeare if he “had a mind”: “It is
clear, then, nothing is wanting but the mind.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref> One might also be tempted to imagine Lamb (who died in 1834) responding, long before
Robinson’s account to Quillinan, to a conversational report that Wordsworth regarded Blake as a madman with
a remark like “So he is—a mad Wordsworth!” 
                        <note id="n20">
                            <hi rend="s">20</hi> E. V. Lucas, ed., <hi rend="u">The Letters of Charles Lamb,
to Which Are Added Those of His Sister Mary Lamb</hi> (London, 1935), II, p. 51. See also <hi rend="u">Henry
Crabb Robinson on Books</hi>, pp. 466-67.</note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p03-81" n="81"/>
                    <p>Whether a copy of the <hi rend="u">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, of which Robinson had
purchased four copies in 1809 and perhaps received another copy as a gift from Miss Denman in 1842, was either
already at Rydal Mount or later sent to Mary Wordsworth, is uncertain. No surviving copy is known, in any
case, to have belonged to the Wordsworths. The trail possibly ends in another Catalogue, of the Sale of the
Rydal Mount Library in July 1859, in which lot 635, sold on 21 July, is described as containing “Sundry
Gallery Guides, etc.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
                        <note id="n21">
                            <hi rend="s">21</hi>
                            <hi rend="u"> Blake, Coleridge</hi>, [etc.], p. 17; <hi rend="u">Henry Crabb
Robinson on Books</hi>, p. 625. For the Catalogue see <hi rend="u">Transactions of the Wordsworth
Society</hi>, VI [1884], pp. 195-257. The same catalogue offers as one of the twelve items in lot 523 “Songs
of Innocence, by W. Blake.” The lot was sold for £ 1/18 [?0], a good price by the Sale’s standards. The
anonymous recorder of the price in the “Queen’s Hotel” copy (see <hi rend="u">Correspondence</hi>, II, pp.
873-74) also wrote between “and six others” (the conclusion of the description) and “12” (the total number of
items) the word “pamphlets.” While the Garth Wilkinson volume was issued cloth-bound, and I know no
information suggesting that it was issued otherwise, a casual use of the term pamphlet could have included
this small book. The catalogue entry must on present evidence be regarded as a short title for the copy of the
Garth Wilkinson edition that prompted Quillinan’s uninspired but usefully evocative criticism in 1848.
(Information on the annotations kindly provided by Professor Betz from G. G. Wordsworth’s transcripts in a
copy of the Catalogue at Dove Cottage. Keynes, <hi rend="u">A Bibliography of William Blake</hi>, New York,
1921, p. 264, quotes C. J. Wilkinson, Memoir of J. J. Garth Wilkinson, London, 1911, London, 1911, p. 25: “The
edition, a thin cloth-bound octavo, was published jointly by Pickering and Newbery on July 9, 1839.” Professor
Bentley tells me of his copy of the volume that “even though it is in herd covers, its height and thickness
are such that ‘pamphlet’ might be an appropriate description.”)</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p03-82-84" n="82-84" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>