<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.4.works</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">Works in Progress</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>May, 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt> 
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <pb id="p03-106" n="106"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-4-0010">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="u">WORKS IN PROGRESS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <p>ADLARD, John: a book on the folklore sources of William Blake, to be published in the near
future by Cecil and Amelia Woolf, London.</p>
                <p>AULT, Donald: book-length study: “Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton;” and a
shorter study of perspective ontology in <hi rend="u">The Four Zoas.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb id="p03-107" n="107"/>
                <p>BENTLEY, G. E., Jr.: 1) an edition of <hi rend="u">The Writings of William Blake</hi>
(Clarendon Press), with bibliographical apparatus; 2) a revision of the <hi rend="u">Blake Bibliography</hi>,
corrected and enlarged. Articles in the press: 1) on a new, minor Blake MS (<hi rend="u">The Library</hi>); 2)
on new Blake engravings (<hi rend="u">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi> in <hi rend="u">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>); 3) on Blake’s copperplates, particularly <hi rend="u">Job</hi>; 4) on pre-1827 facsimiles
of Blake’s <hi rend="u">Songs</hi>; 5) on new contemporary references by the Ancients to Blake 
(<hi rend="u">Blake Studies</hi>); 6) on Blake and Cromek, dealing with new contemporary references; 7) the Blake
section of the <hi rend="u">New CBEL.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BOYAJIAN, Aram: work on a half-hour film for television (WILLIAM BLAKE, to be shown on
ABC’s <hi rend="u">Directions</hi> in October, 1970), including short sequences on Carnaby Street,
Westminster Abbey, Felpham; greater part of the film will be done from transparencies of plates from the
illuminated books.</p>
                <p>BROGAN, Howard O: a book on English verse satire from Churchill to Byron, including a
chapter on Burns and Blake, in which the two are compared and contrasted as peasant and artisan struggling
against class barriers in a revolutionary era.</p>
                <p>BUTLIN, Martin: 1) a fully revised catalogue of the works by William Blake in the Tate
Gallery (first published 1957); 2) a complete Blake catalogue; working on a <hi rend="u">catalogue
raisonné</hi> of Blake’s paintings, water colors, drawings, and separate color prints.</p>
                <p>CHAYES, Irene H.: a study, probably book-length, of Blake’s designs; part of a larger
project on his “modes and themes.”</p>
                <p>EAVES, Morris: 1) an index for S. Foster Damon’s <hi rend="u">A Blake Dictionary</hi>; 2)
dissertation, “Blake’s Artistic Strategy and His Medium, and the Evolution of His Early Narrative Art<supplied type="emend">”</supplied>
(Tulane University); 3) article, “Adam’s Fall and the Evangelical Revival’s Mythical Triangle;” a review
of Allen Ginsberg’s recording of the <hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence and Experience</hi> for the 
<hi rend="u">Blake Newsletter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ESSICK, Robert: a study of the designs in Blake’s illuminated books, for the present
excluding <hi rend="u">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="u">Jerusalem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GLECKNER, Robert: 1) a revised edition of <hi rend="u">Selected Writings of William
Blake</hi> (Crofts Classics); 2) a critical study of <hi rend="u">Island in the Moon</hi> and its backgrounds.
Dissertation directed: Jim S. Borck, <hi rend="u">William Blake: A Prophetic Tradition.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb id="p03-108" n="108"/>
                <p>GRANT, John E.: Books: 1) <hi rend="u">Blake’s Designs for Young’s Night Thoughts</hi>,
with E. J. Rose and M. J. Tolley, in association with David V. Erdman (Clarendon Press, 5 vols.); 2) 
<hi rend="u">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, co-edited with David V. Erdman (Princeton, 1970); an
anthology of twenty essays on his work in various media; 3) <hi rend="u">Blake’s Designs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>, an interpretation of the pictures and a discussion of the poems. Articles: 1) “Blake and the
Trojan War,” an essay on form and politics; 2) “The Substance of Things Seen by Earth,” on a persistent
difficulty in communication; 3) “Blake and Prophetic Tradition,” a chapter in a book called 
<hi rend="u">Expositions in Apocalypse: Dante to Beckett</hi>; 4) “The Golden Bow,” an essay on symbolism; 5) “The
Order of the ‘Auguries of Innocence’.”</p>
                <p>HARPER, George Mills: a study on numerology in the prophetic books; an article on “The
Unholy Trinity in Blake’s Prophetic Books.”</p>
                <p>HEPPNER, Christopher: dissertation completed: an attempt to define the problem of form in
Blake’s prophecies in terms of a multi-level view of form, emphasizing narrative structures and the mixed
medium Blake created.</p>
                <p>KIRALIS, Karl: books: 1) a critical study and annotated edition of 
<hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi>, including a history of the criticism of the poem; 2) a critical study of Blake as a
literary critic. Articles: “More on Chaucer’s Fairies that the Poet Be Understood;” “Blake, the Beatles, and
Ornette Coleman: A New Trip with ‘The Mental Traveller’ ”.</p>
                <p>KREMEN, Kathryn: dissertation: <hi rend="u">The Imagination of the Resurrection: The Poetic
Continuity and Conversion of a Religious Motif in Donne, Blake, and Yeats</hi>; article: “The ‘Second
Writing’: Jesus’ Forgiving the Woman Taken in Adultery,” on the watercolor “Women Taken in Adultery” and
parallel passages in <hi rend="u">John</hi>, “The Everlasting Gospel,” and “The Gates of Paradise.”</p>
                <p>LEFCOWITZ, Barbara: dissertation: <hi rend="u">Self, Nature, and Madness in the Poetry of
Christopher Smart and William Blake</hi> (in progress).</p>
                <p>LISTER, Raymond: a new and complete edition of the letters of Samuel Palmer (Clarendon
Press, Oxford), many of which concern Blake.</p>
                <p>MELLOR, Anne Kostelanetz: book-length study, “Blake’s Human Form Divine,” on Blake
developing theory of form in his poetry and prose in relation to his use of formal compositions and
<pb id="p03-109" n="109"/>
iconography in art.</p>
                <p>METCALF, Francis W.: article: “Blake’s <hi rend="u">Tiriel</hi> and 
<hi rend="u">Job</hi>: the Symmetry of the First and Last,” maintaining that both works are constructed not only
as verbal or pictorial narratives, but also as spatial configurations of radial or reflexive symmetry.</p>
                <p>MINER, Paul: book: <hi rend="u">Blake’s London</hi>, to be illustrated with about 250
cuts.</p>
                <p>MINNICK, Thomas L.: dissertation: On Blake and Milton, considering the way in which Blake
came to terms with Milton, through an examination both of Blake’s writings and of the Milton available to
Blake (through Hollis, Hayley, Warton, etc.). In progress.</p>
                <p>PALEY, Morton D.: book-length critical study of <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi>, to include a
consideration of both text and illustrations.</p>
                <p>PELFREY, Patricia: dissertation: a study of Blake’s prophetic works, especially 
<hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi>, in the context of the utopian tradition. (In progress).</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS, Michael: <hi rend="u">Blake’s Poetical Sketches</hi>: A Definitive Text, the
Printing and Reputation of the Poems 1783 - 1969, and a Critical Interpretation.</p>
                <p>PIERCE, Hazel: dissertation: a critical analysis of <hi rend="u">Europe.</hi>
                </p>
				<p><corr type="emend">SAMUEL, George: dissertation: <hi rend="u">Blake’s Opinions of Milton and Edward
Young</hi> (in progress); directing the dissertation of Cecil Anthony Abrahams, <hi rend="u">The Fourfold Man
in William Blake.</hi></corr>
                </p>
                <p>SIMMONS, Robert: an article on Blake’s <hi rend="u">Arlington Court Picture</hi> (with
Janet Warner); an article on “The Mental Traveller.”</p>
                <p>STEVENSON, W. H.: book: <hi rend="u">A Critical Introduction to Blake</hi>; articles: 1)
“Centre and Circumference in Blake;” 2) on Blake’s kind of symbolism.</p>
                <p>STEVENSON, Warren: book: <hi rend="u">The Creation Motif in Blake and Coleridge</hi>;
directing a dissertation by Marney McLaughlin on text and design in Blake.</p>
                <p>TAYLER, Irene: book: <hi rend="u">Blake’s Gray: A Visionary Reading</hi> (Princeton
University Press), studies Blake’s interpretive criticism of the poetry of Thomas Gray as delineated in his
116 illustrations to Gray’s poems.</p>
                <p>TEBBETTS, Terrell L.: dissertation: <hi rend="u">A Critical Study of Blake’s America</hi>
(in progress).</p>
                <p>WARNER, Janet: a study of systems of structure and iconography in selected Blake designs
(with Robert Simmons); an
<pb id="p03-110" n="110"/>
article on “Blake and the Wirey Bounding Line:” a script for a videotape of <hi rend="u">America</hi> to be
produced and directed at Glendon College by Robert Wallace (with John Sutherland).</p>
                <p>WATSON, Alan: articles: 1) “<hi rend="u">Tiriel</hi>: The Fundamentals of Blake’s Sublime
Epic,” emphasizing the theory behind illustrated epic; 2) “William Blake’s Illustrated Poetry: A Typical
Instance,” a close look at the frontispiece to the <hi rend="u">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITEHEAD, Fred: dissertation: <hi rend="u">Blake and the Communist Tradition</hi> (in
progress).</p>
                <p>WITTREICH, Joseph: essays: 1) “The Epic Designs of Hayley and Blake” (a re-assessment of
the Blake-Hayley relationship); 2) “William Blake: Illustrator-Interpreter of <hi rend="u">Paradise
Regained</hi>” (a study of Blake’s illustrations as a form of non-verbal criticism); book, <hi rend="u">Calm
of Mind: Tercentary Essays on Paradise Regained and Samson Agonistes</hi>, ed. Joseph Wittreich, containing
two appendices: 1) a catalogue of Blake’s Milton illustrations and 2) a list of illustrators and subjects
for PR before Blake (Case Western Reserve University Press). The book also contains the essay 
“<hi rend="u">Paradise Regained</hi> and the Four-Book Epic in the Romantic Period,” by Stuart Curran.
Introductions: 1) <hi rend="u">Early Accounts of William Blake</hi>; 2) William Hayley’s <hi rend="u">The
Life of Milton</hi>, second edition (1796), both to be published by Scholars’ Facsimiles and Reprints.<gap
type="emend"/></p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>