<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.4.news</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">The Wordsworth Circle, intended Fitzwilliam Museum catalogue, Job ballet,
Blake graffiti</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>May, 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt> 
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-4-0004">
                <div2>
                    <pb id="p03-76" n="76"/>
                    <p>A new newsletter, THE WORDSWORTH CIRCLE, is being edited by Marilyn Gaull and Charles
Mauskopf (Dept. of English, Temple University, Philadelphia, Penn.) The subscription price is three dollars
for one year (four issues).</p>
                    <p>M. Cormack informs us that the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, intends to publish a
catalogue of their extensive Blake collection, edited by David Bindman, sometime in the autumn, provisionally
to be in early October. It is intended to mark the publication of the catalogue (which will have 72 plates)
with an exhibition of their Blake collection, and a small subsidiary exhibition of portraits of Blake.</p>
                    <p>The Royal Ballet (Touring Section) has revived the ballet <hi rend="u">Job</hi>, based
on Blake’s designs, and will give six performances of it at Covent Garden this Spring.</p>
                    <p>And the tabloid <hi rend="u">Express</hi> ran a picture article on London graffiti
several months ago, with photographs and comments by passers-by. On a wall in Notting Hill Gate - THE ROAD OF
EXCESS LEADS TO THE PALACE OF WISDOM. A “Warehouseman, about forty” says: “ . . . I’m sure it’s filth.
It’s best to look the other way in this district. You’re not safe anywhere nowadays.” While someone
identified as “Irishman who declined to give his name” comments: “If it’s true, I’m in the palace of
wisdom all right.”</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>