<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>3.4.chayes</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Deborah Dorfman, Blake in the Nineteenth Century</title>
				<author n="Chayes">Irene H. Chayes</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>May, 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">03.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt> 
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_03">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-03-4-0007">
				<pb id="p03-91" n="91"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">2. <hi rend="u">Blake in the Nineteenth Century: His Reputation as
a Poet from Gilchrist to Yeats</hi>, by Deborah Dorfman. Yale Studies in English, Vol. 170. Yale University
Press, 1969. Pp. vx + 314. $8.75.</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Exactly how, after Blake’s death, the nineteenth century tried to come to terms with
what remained of his work and what could be learned about his life: this is a subject on which a major
publication has been long overdue. Previously, according to Miss Dorfman, there was only a 1953 dissertation;
except for her footnote references, it seems to have sunk without a trace. The present study apparently began
as a dissertation also, and the author has been faithful to the genre in approach and organization as well as
in the paradigmatic title. Although the immense amount of material she has to draw on might have lent itself
to any one of several emphases when the dissertation became a book, intended for a new audience, Miss Dorfman
keeps almost exclusively to the main line of chronology, the shortest distance between the earliest date and
the latest, and compromises with the other options as she goes. One result, as the footnotes threaten to rise
into the text, is that we are aware of how much is being left out, a larger and more complex world of
documents, personalities, cultural attitudes, and ideas, which is hinted in the citations at the bottom of the
page but which the author is not able to explore in her dutiful march through the decades. Only in the
relatively less compressed and more unified chapters on Gilchrist’s <hi rend="u">Life</hi> and the
Ellis-Yeats edition is there more than a glimpse of the kind of book that may have been one revision away.</p>
                    <pb id="p03-92" n="92"/>
                    <p>Although the subtitle—also from the conventions of the dissertation—makes
“reputation” the key word, the account is concerned mainly with nineteenth-century editions of the poetry and
the evolution of a Blake criticism. Qualitative judgments are inescapable, and here Miss Dorfman is most
disappointing, not only because of her chronological approach and her exclusions. Her individual comments,
though brief, are perceptive, pointed, often witty; but when she steps back for a general view, she allows her
heterogeneous company of early Blakeans to fade together in a mist of retrospective compliment. There is no
reason, certainly, to object to the statement that, starting from “nothing—no printed texts, no reading
public, no confidence in a man presumed insane—Blake’s nineteenth-century editors cleared a narrow path
for readers to approach him.” The pioneer commentators, as well—and this is a point not sufficiently
stressed, I think—were capable of incidental critical insights which are a vindication of the power of
literary meanings to communicate themselves, even at an unpropitious time. Nevertheless, side by side with
legitimate curiosity and admiration and a sense of scholarly responsibility, there was something else at work
in the age which Miss Dorfman’s own evidence suggests, although she does not follow it up.</p>
                    <p>It was not only that, as she observes, the critics tried to recreate Blake in images of
themselves: Swinburne’s arch-rebel, Smetham’s “religio-aesthetic monk,” Arthur Symons’ precursor of
Nietzsche, Ellis’ Kabbalist initiate, Yeats’<hi rend="i">s</hi> Irish poet. What Miss Dorfman calls the
“educational diversion” of rewriting Blake’s poems—Cunningham, Swinburne, the Rossettis, Edwin Ellis, and
W. B. Yeats all indulged—was of a piece with the cavalier editorial practice of “improving” his texts for
publication; William Rossetti was, again, a particular offender. Tatham’s sacrifice by fire and Ruskin’s
mutilations were more dramatic, but it is difficult to regard them as different except in form and degree from
the other expressions of what at best was an ambivalence among Blake’s professed champions. Prophetically,
Blake himself had supplied the terms to describe what happened to the body of work he left behind. In the
ideal contrariety of <hi rend="u">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, which was also the ideal relation
between artist and public, the Prolific was inexhaustible and active, the Devourer insatiable but passive. But
the precondition of their creative tension was that both should be “always upon earth”; by implication, if
either disappeared, the other would lose his function and hence his identity. Blake did not foresee that when
the Prolific ceased to produce, the Devourer would cease to be passive and would try to play both roles.</p>
                    <p>Edwin Ellis, in the edition whose character he appears to have done more than his
collaborator to determine, also rewrote and recast some of the poems, as Miss Dorfman points out, and dated
and rearranged those that were being published according to what he understood as their “technical vocabulary
of symbols.” The symbols belonged to the explicitly named occult “system” (unfortunately, the same word is
used in the famous speech by Los, so that it is subject to double confusion) which was expounded by Ellis and
Yeats in their first volume—no less
<pb id="p03-93" n="93"/>
an arbitrary “improvement” of Blake than the textual and editorial changes; another example of the Devourer at
his usurping work. But Miss Dorfman has changed the direction of her comparisons; in the last pages of her
last chapter she is already backing away from the nineteenth century toward a vantage point of her own. She
quotes Northrop Frye on the obvious critical faults of the Ellis-Yeats commentary, and she herself calls
attention to the failure by both editors to recognize Blake’s vitality and combativeness as a creator and
thinker. Yet her estimate of the contribution of the Ellis-Yeats edition as a whole—that it laid the
groundwork for serious later study of Blake’s longer poems—ends as a selective acceptance of the
Ellis-Yeats “system.” Why? Because such an acceptance is what actually has occurred: “Once the existence of
the four Zoas, the principle of fourfold meaning, the dialectical progression, and the theory of symbol had
been absorbed, the ‘System’ was open to addition, qualification, documentation, and comparative
studies.”</p>
                    <p>A number of twentieth-century expositions of Blake, major and minor, have of course
been related to the Ellis-Yeats interpretation in the ways listed by Miss Dorfman, even without direct
influence by anything actually written by either man. But continuity is not necessarily progress, and the fact
of the relationship may as well raise, or confirm, doubts about the twentieth-century commentators as elevate
Ellis and Yeats. The number of years since the publication of the Ellis-Yeats edition in 1893 is now greater
than that between 1893 and the date of Blake’s death; even allowing for an unusual conservatism among many
of those writing about Blake, the developments in the study of literature during the past three decades have
had their effect on how his poetry too is approached. More accurate texts, new studies of his intellectual
background and his literary and pictorial sources, and improved techniques of reading the poems themselves are
making any overall, “systematic” interpretation unnecessary, even for the longer works; on the contrary, it
may be a hindrance. Merely to try to imagine a Blake scholarship or criticism still limited to variations on
Miss Dorfman’s formula is to be reminded of the changes that have been taking place since mid-century, our
mid-century. Practically, at least, the trend is away from diagrams and doctrine and more and more toward
investigations of the language and the forms Blake actually used, in both his poetry and his designs.</p>
                    <p>Nowhere, however, does Deborah Dorfman indicate what the situation in Blake studies is
today, or even what it was when she started on her own project. Except for a few documentary references and
appeals to contemporary scholars in matters of opinion (but almost never opinion on Blake’s poetry, and not
their own interpretations), she might be writing at some indeterminate time in the middling past, demonstrably
later only than 1924. When in a two-page “Afterword” she quotes from Blake’s “first truly modern
commentator,” it is S. Foster Damon she means, and she cites him twice again before concluding. The particular
quotations chosen sound “humanistic” enough, but ironically (and unavoidably, considering when he began his
work), it is Damon who probably has been most responsible for keeping nineteenth-century views of Blake
<pb id="p03-94" n="94"/>
at least formally alive. Most of the books listed in <hi rend="u">William Blake: His Philosophy and
Symbols</hi> were published before 1900, and the commentators Damon calls on are among those Miss Dorfman
discusses. In one instance, the much later <hi rend="u">Blake Dictionary</hi> (s. v. “Thel”) preserves as
biographical fact what she shows to have been Edwin Ellis’ invention: the supposed unborn child of the
Blakes, supposedly lost by a miscarriage.</p>
                    <p>The small irony that involves the author herself does not affect the genuine scholarly
value of her researches, which also enable us to see that the subject does not belong wholly to the past and
that neither 1893 nor 1924 really marked the beginning of the “modern” in Blake studies. If Blake’s story
is, as Miss Dorfman sums it up, “peculiarly a history of reclamation,” it would seem that the greater part of
the task—reclaiming the man and his work from his Victorian heirs and exegetes—is barely under way.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Irene H. <name>Chayes</name>
                        </docAuthor> Silver Spring, Maryland</byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>