<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.1.vultee</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Apollonian Elephant?</title>
        <author n="Vultee">Denise Vultee</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1996</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley</name>
              <name>David Caplan</name>
              <name>Michael Gamer</name>
              <name>Paul Wayne Rodney</name>
              <name>Nanora Sweet</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Denise Vultee</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <pb id="p30-22" n="22"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Apollonian Elephant?</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Denise <name>Vultee</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi>, G. E. Bentley, Jr. includes part of a 20 June 1802
letter to William Hayley from his friend Edward Garrard Marsh, an Oxford student who had met Blake at Felpham
(21). In the letter, Marsh offers Hayley and Blake his translation from the <hi rend="i">Argonautica</hi> of
Apollonius of Rhodes, wishes Blake success “on his elephant” (i.e., his engravings for Hayley’s Elephant
ballad), and suggests that the elephant “from its rider might (I think) be called the Apollonian
elephant.” As Bentley points out in a footnote, however, “There is no reference to elephants in Apollonius
of Rhodes” (21). Nor does Robert N. Essick, in his article on Marsh’s letters, see anything
“particularly ‘Apollonian’ about Blake’s design” (69).</p>
          <p>The confusion here results from Marsh’s mental leap from one Apollonius to another. The
“Apollonian elephant” refers to Philostratus’s <hi rend="i">Life of Apollonius of Tyana</hi>, a highly
embroidered tale of the travels and purported miracles of a Neopythagorean philosopher who lived during the
first century A.D. In the second book of that work, Apollonius and his sidekick Damis travel to India, where
they encounter a number of elephants. (This, by the way, is the same Apollonius who spoils Lamia’s fun in
Keats’s poem.)</p>
          <p>If Bentley is right (and I think he is) in suggesting that the “rider” is Blake, Marsh
appears to be comparing Blake, however facetiously, to Apollonius of Tyana. What’s more, he clearly expects
Hayley to see the resemblance without further explanation and to enjoy his little joke. <hi rend="i">Why</hi>
Marsh thought the comparison apt is a tantalizing—and probably unanswerable—question. Perhaps Marsh was
simply alluding to Blake’s lack of worldliness rather than to any specifically Pythagorean tendencies in his
thought or work.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1988.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake, Hayley, and Edward Garrard Marsh: ‘An Insect of Parnassus.’”
<hi rend="i">Explorations</hi> 1 (1987): 58-84.</p>
            <p>Philostratus. <hi rend="i">The Life of Apollonius of Tyana.</hi> Trans. F. C. Conybeare. 2
vols. Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP, 1960.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
