<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.1.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1996</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley</name>
              <name>David Caplan</name>
              <name>Michael Gamer</name>
              <name>Paul Wayne Rodney</name>
              <name>Nanora Sweet</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Denise Vultee</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <front>
      <pb id="p30-1-2" n="1-2"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.030.01.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="335">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            VOLUME 30<lb/>
            NUMBER 1<lb/>
            SUMMER 1996</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-1-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="10" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>CONTENTS</title>
        	  </head>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.1.viscomi">A “Green House” for Butts? New Information on
Thomas Butts, His Residences, and Family</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by Joseph Viscomi</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">4</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particular</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.1.vultee">Apollonian Elephant?</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by Denise Vultee</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">22</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Poetry</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.1.caplan">Blake in Boca Raton</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by David Caplan</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">22</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.1.gamer">David Simpson, <hi rend="i">Romanticism, Nationalism,
and the Revolt against Theory</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Michael Gamer, Paul Wayne Rodney, and Nanora Sweet</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">23</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.1.bentley">Donald Fitch, <hi rend="i">Blake Set to Music: A
Bibliography of Musical Settings of the Poems and Prose of William Blake</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr.</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">25</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p30-3" n="3"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-1-0002">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley wrote this review in 1991, but it went astray. He retired from the University of
Toronto in 1996 and is writing a biography of Blake.</p>
        <p>David Caplan received an M.F.A. from the University of Florida and is currently working toward a
doctorate in English from the University of Virginia.</p>
        <p>Michael Gamer is an Assistant Professor at the University of Pennsylvania. He is currently working
to complete a book manuscript on the relation of romantic poetry and Gothic romance, entitled “‘This
Pageantry of Fear’: Making Poetry Romantic in the Age of Radcliffe and Lewis.”</p>
        <p>Paul Wayne Rodney is completing his Ph.D. at the University of Michigan. His dissertation examines
the development of domestic tourism in Britain in the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries as it
relates to the definition of national and individual identity.</p>
        <p>Nanora Sweet teaches romanticism and poetry at the University of Missouri at St. Louis. She
publishes on Felicia Hemans and her circle.</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi teaches English at the University of North Carolina and is the author of 
<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> He is currently coeditor, along with Robert N. Essick and Morris
Eaves, of the electronic Blake archive.</p>
        <p>Denise Vultee, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, is working on Blake and romantic
Hellenism.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-1-0003">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Patricia Neill, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY
14627</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Patricia Neill<lb/>
TELEPHONE 716/275-3820<lb/>
FAX 716/442-5769<lb/>
PRODUCTION OFFICE EMAIL: pnpj@db1.cc.rochester.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Morris Eaves</hi>, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627<lb/>
Email: meav@db1.cc.rochester.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Morton D. Paley</hi>, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA
94720<lb/>
Email: P72735@garnet.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</hi>, University College, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario
M5S 1A1 Canada<lb/>
Email: gbentley@epas.utoronto.ca</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Nelson Hilton</hi>, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA
30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@uga.cc.uga.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">David Worrall</hi>, St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill, Waldegrave Road, Twickenham
TW1 4SX England<lb/>
Email: worralld@mailnt.smuc.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-1-0004">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester.</p>
        <p>SUBSCRIPTIONS are $50 for institutions, $25 for individuals. All subscriptions are by the volume (1
year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be
applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and Mexico) require an $8 per
volume postal surcharge for surface, an $18 per volume surcharge for air mail delivery. U.S. currency or
international money order necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi>
Address all subscription orders and related communications to Patricia Neill, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>,
Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627.</p>
        <p>BACK ISSUES are available at a reduced price. Address Patricia Neill for a list of issues and
prices.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to forms suggested in 
<hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of
Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA
94720.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A
Selective and Critical Bibliography</hi> (ed. David V. Erdman et al.), American Humanities Index, Arts and
Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover Illustration: A selection of <hi rend="i">Bs, s</hi>, and <hi rend="i">us</hi> from the 1805
receipt, see page 9. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1996 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D.
Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
