<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.2.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Death of Blake’s Partner James Parker</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1996</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Lane Robson</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
	<pb id="p30-49" n="49"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Death of Blake’s Partner James Parker</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>James Parker was a good friend to William Blake all his life; the two men served their
apprenticeships together, they were arrested together on a sailing expedition about 1780, they were in
partnership in 1784-85 and lived over the shop in Broad Street together, and in the last years of Parker’s
life Blake was still consulting him about professional matters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">1</ref> However, very little is known of Parker’s domestic circumstances except
that he was married to Ann Serjeantson in the same month that Blake was married to Catherine Boucher, in
August 1782, and that he died suddenly on 16 May 1805. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See “The
Journeyman and the Genius: James Parker and His Partner William Blake with a List of Parker’s Engravings,”
<hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 59 (1996): 208-23. Parker’s Will was discovered just as this essay
was going through the press but too late to be included in it.</note></p>
          <p>A significant amount of information about James Parker’s life may be derived from his
Will<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">2</ref> which has recently been noticed
in the Public Record Office in Chancery Lane, London. This indicates that Parker’s sister Sarah Parker kept
house for him 1787 to 1805 and implies that his wife was dead by then. Perhaps the break-up of the
Blake-Parker printshop was related to the ill-health and death of Ann Serjeantson Parker. 
<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">2</hi> PROB 11 14333, 342-43, transcribed from the Public Record Office microfilm of the original. At
the end of a page, there is often a duplication of one or more words with the beginning of the next page,
though the to-be-repeated words at the foot of the page are not dropped, as in ordinary catch-words. This
duplication is ignored in the transcription above.
                            <p>Wills were probably rather unusual among Parker’s class; at any rate, no Will
has been traced for Blake’s father James Blake (d. 1784), his mother Catherine Blake (d. 1792), for his
brother James Blake (d. 1827), for the poet himself (d. 1827) or his wife Catherine (d. 1831), for Henry
Fuseli (d. 1825), for John Flaxman (d. 1826), or for Thomas Stothard (d. 1834), though Thomas Armitage, the
first husband of the poet’s mother, did leave a will (1746), as did Blake’s patron Thomas Butts
(1845).</p></note></p>
          <p>The Will was made in somewhat curious circumstances. Apparently Parker discovered suddenly in
April 1805 that he had a disease which was likely to prove quickly fatal, and he made his will somewhat
casually and perhaps hastily, writing in pencil, omitting the date beyond “April 1805,” and neglecting to
have it witnessed, though he did show it to his sister Sarah in the presence of this apprentice Richard
Golding, who was then about 20. Though Parker lived another month, he made no effort to give the Will a more
official cast, and when the Will came to be proved, a good
<pb id="p30-50" n="50"/>
deal of testimony was required from Sarah Parker, from Richard Golding, and from the servant Ann Pickering to
demonstrate its authenticity.</p>
          <p>According to the Will, which was made in April 1805 and proved six months later on 6 November,
<q>
In the Name of God Amen. I James Parker of Spring Place Ken[<hi rend="i">tish</hi>]. Town in the parish of
Pancras and County of Middlesex Engraver being in perfect health and in full possession of the faculties it
has pleased God to bless me with do make and write with my own hand this my last will and Testament in the
following Manner[:] I give and bequeath my household Goods Prints Debts Mortgages to my dear Sister Sarah
whose unremitted Care Love and Attention I have received through Life[.] I also devise give and bequeath to my
said Sister my freehold Cottage and Land on the west Side of Highgate Hill in the said County late in the
occupation of M.<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Mary Rust[.] I also give and bequeath to my said Sister my ffreehold
property in Little Drury Lane and occupied by M.<hi rend="s">r</hi> Astly and Williamson and my Will Intention
and Devise is that my Sister Sarah may enjoy through her Life the Profits of my before-mentioned ffreehold and
copyhold Estates without the Let or hindrance of any person whatever but that after her decease they shall be
equally divided between the children of my late Sister Mary late the wife of Thomas Nixon now or late of
Betterwell in the County of Leicester Carpenters and Joiners and finally I institute and appoint my said
Sister Sarah the sole Executrix of this my last Will and Testament made and written in perfect health and with
my own hand and also signed by me the [<hi rend="i">space</hi>] day of April in the year of our Lord one
thousand eight hundred and five James Parker.
</q>
On 5 July 1805 it was proved by:
<q>
Sarah Parker of Spring Place Kentish Town in the County of Middlesex Spinster Ann Pickering Servant of the
same place Spinster and Richard Golding of Saint Bartholomews Hospital London Engraver . . . Sarah Parker . .
. is the natural and lawful Sister and only next of kin of James Parker . . . who departed this Life on the
sixteenth Day of May now last past a Batchelor without a parent leaving her the deponent and also Ann Nixon
Lavinia Nixon and Mary Nixon Spinsters his lawful heirs by a Second Sister the only persons intitled in the
distribution of his personal Estate . . . and this deponent saith that she lived and resided with her said
Brother for upward of eighteen years before and to the time of his death and managed his household Concerns
and that on Tuesday Morning [<hi rend="i">14 May</hi>] preceding his Death he the said deceased produced and
read to this deponent in his Garden the paper writing now hereto annexed written in pencil and bearing date
the [blank] Day of April one thousand eight hundred and five and which paper he then declared to be his will
and she further saith that on the Morning of the day of the deceaseds death but previous thereto she this
Deponent on looking in her deceased’s Brothers pocket found the said will therein and saith that the said
paper is now in the same plight and condition as when read by the deceased to her the Deponent as aforesaid
And the said Ann Pickering Servant for herself saith that she knew and was well acquainted with the said James
Parker for upwards of nine years before and up to the Time of his death which happened on Thursday the
sixteenth day of May now last past and that during all that time the said Sarah Parker Spinster his Sister
resided with him and this deponent saith that the said deceased did not tell his Bod[?] of the Illness whereof
he died until the afternoon of the day preceding his death and saith that on the Morning of Thursday the day
on which the said deceased told the deponent that he was verily sensible he was dying and begged[?] deponent
not to weep that she the deponent thereupon asked him if he had settled his affairs to which he replied “I
have made my will my Sister is every Thing to me[”] or he then expressed himself in words precisely to that
Effect and was then of perfect sound Mind and Capacity And this deponent Richard Golding for himself saith
that he knew and was well acquainted with the said James Parker for upwards of Eight Months before and up to
the Time of his Death living both with him the said James Parker during that period as a pupil in the Business
of an Engraver And this deponent saith that he the said deceased was in the constant habit of using his Black
Lead pencil for almost every Purpose even to the Keeping of his Accounts and this Deponent saith that on the
Morning of Tuesday the fourteenth Day of May he saw the said deceased in his Garden with his Sister Sarah
Parker and he this said deceased was then reading a paper to his said Sister and adjourned therewith into the
Summer House and this deponent further saith that on the Morning of Thursday being the day on which the
deceased died But before his death the said Sarah Parker showed the deponent the Will of the said deceased now
hereunto annexed bearing date the [<hi rend="i">blank</hi>] day of April one thousand eight hundred and five
and which had the appearance of being and which was as he verily believes the very paper he so saw the said
deceased reading to his said Sister and which paper she the said Sarah Parker then informed the said deponent
she had taken out of the [<hi rend="i">said deceased’s del</hi>] [<hi rend="i">word illeg</hi>] Brothers
pocket and this deponent Ann Pickering Servant and Richard Golding jointly and severally say and depone that
they have several times seen the said deceased write and also [<hi rend="i">word illeg</hi>] his name and
particularly so with his pencil and having now carefully viewed and perused the paper writing hereunto annexed
purporting to be and contain the last Will and Testament of the said deceased beginning thus “In the Name of
God Amen I James Parker of Spring Place” and ending thus “and with my own hand and also sealed by me the
[<hi rend="i">blank</hi>] day of April in the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and five” and has
subscribed “James Parker” and being written in pencil they the sd[?] Deponents do say they verily and in
their Consciences 
<pb id="p30-51" n="51"/>
believe the whole Body Series[?] and Contents thereof to be all of the proper hand writing and Subscription of
the said James Parker deceased / Sarah Parker Hse[?] Servant Richard Golding The same day the said Sarah
Parker Spinster Ann Pickering Servant Spinster and Richard Golding were duly sworn to the Truth of this
affidavit before me S Parson Surrogate pros.<hi rend="s">t</hi> Geo: Bogg Not. Pub.<lb/>
<lb/>
This Will was proved at London on the nineteenth Day of November in the Year of our Lord one thousand eight
hundred and five before the worshipful [<hi rend="i">three names illeg</hi>] Doctor of Laws Surrogate of the
Right Honourable Sir William Eyres Knight Doctor of Laws Master [<hi rend="i">word illeg</hi>] Commissary of
the Prerogative Court of Canterbury lawfully instituted by the oath of Sarah Parker Spinster the Sister of the
Deceased and his sole Executrix named in the Said Will to whom administration of all and singular the Goods
Chattels and Credits of the deceased was granted she having before first sworn duly to administer.
</q></p>
          <p>The Will demonstrates that James Parker was a man of some substance (unlike his sometime partner
William Blake), with two rental properties plus his house in Spring Place, Kentish Town, with a Summer House.
He apparently had no wife or children surviving, his married sister Mary Nixon was dead, and his only
relatives were his spinster sister Sarah Parker and his nieces Ann, Lavinia, and Mary Nixon. And he was
sufficiently prosperous to have a servant, Ann Pickering, who was with him for nine years. (William and
Catherine Blake had a servant when they lived in Lambeth but soon gave her up.)</p>
          <p>Notice, however, that among his “household Goods Prints Debts Mortgages” specified in the
Will there is no reference to a rolling press. William Blake certainly had a rolling press on which he printed
his own engravings, and it has been supposed that he acquired it by the time that he and Parker set up their
print-selling business in 1784.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">3</ref> Blake
was apparently unusual in owning his own rolling press. <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake
Records</hi> (1969) 29.</note></p>
          <p>Parker’s Numerous Assemblage of Prints, together with his Coins and Medals, were sold at
auction by Thomas Dodd on 18 February 1807.</p>
          <p>It is likely that Blake visited Parker and his sister Sarah at their home in Spring Place,
Kentish Town, and it is pleasant to think that Blake may have accompanied the Governors of the society of
Engravers to the grave in St Clement Danes<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">4</ref> when James Parker was buried. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Obituary of James Parker
in <hi rend="i">The Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> 75 (June 1805) 586.</note></p>
          <p>James Parker’s Will throws a good deal of domestic light upon a man who was very important in
the life of William Blake.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
