<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.2.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">William Blake, Jacob Ilive, and the Book of Jasher</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1996</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Lane Robson</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-2-0006">
      	<pb id="p30-51" n="51"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake, Jacob Ilive, and the Book of Jasher</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>William Blake was, as we know, very interested in research on and speculation about the
            Bible, including matters such as Hebrew prosody, theories of composition, and the
            constitution of texts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">1</ref> He
was also, aware of the
            tradition that there were lost books of the Bible as is shown in plate 12 of 
              <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">2</ref> as
            well as by his eagerness to illustrate the Book of Enoch after its publication in
              1821.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">3</ref> In Swedenborg’s
<hi rend="i">True Christian
              Religion</hi>, Blake would have read that one of these, the Book of Jasher, was extant
            “amongst the People who live in Great Tartary.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n30" type="note">4</ref>
            Blake did not, of course, respond to ideas on such subjects as a scholar but rather as a
            poet and artist, placing himself in relation to new knowledge by assimilating it. The
            fact that a work purporting to be the lost book of Jasher (or Jashar) had been published
            in his own century must have been known to him, especially as it had been produced by a
            man well known in the printing profession, one whose heterodox religious ideas had some
            common ground with his own. The fact that this work was widely considered a forgery
            would hardly have <corr type="emend">deterred</corr> Blake, whose characteristic view was that not
the literal fact
            of production but the inner meaning of a work determines its authenticity. As he wrote
            in his annotations to Bishop Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology for the Bible</hi>, “I cannot
            concieve the Divinity of the &lt;books in the&gt; Bible to consist either in who they
            were written by or at what time or in the historical evidence which may be all false in
            the eyes of one man &amp; true in the eyes of another but in the Sentiments &amp;
            Examples which whether true or Parabolic are Equally useful . . . .” 
              (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 618). In the 1751 <hi rend="i">Book of Jasher</hi> Blake may well have
found
            useful sentiments and examples, as well as a model for the layout of part of his own
            Bible of Hell, <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen.</hi>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Leslie Tannenbaum, <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early
                Prophecies</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1982) 25-54; Morton D. Paley, 
                <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1983) 45-48); and Jerome J.
McGann,
                <hi rend="i">Social Values and Poetic Acts</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1988)
              152-72.</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> The Complete Poetry and
                Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, rev. ed. (New York: Doubleday,
              1988) 39, hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">E</hi> followed by the page
              number.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The
                Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale UP, 1981)
              1:595.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See my “‘A New Heaven Is Begun’: Blake
              and Swedenborgianism,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 13 (1979): 80.</note></p>
          <p>The Book of Jasher is considered a lost source for parts of other books in which it is
            named, including Joshua 10-13, 
<pb id="p30-52" n="52"/>
<figure n="BookOfJasher.30.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="447">
              <head>1 <hi rend="i">The Book of Jasher</hi> [by Jacob Ilive].</head>
              <figDesc>British Library.</figDesc>
            </figure> 2 Samuel 1:18, and the Septuagint version of 1 Kings 8: 53.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
              type="note">5</ref> In 1751, a printer named Joseph Ilive published what he claimed
            was an English version by the monk Alcuin: <hi rend="i">The Book of Jasher, with
              Testimonies and Notes explanatory of the Text.</hi> Ilive himself is a figure of some
            interest. The son of a printer, he set up a letter-foundry in Aldersgate c. 1730.<ref
              target="n32" type="note">6</ref> In 1733 he gave an oration at Joyner’s Hall in Thames
            Street, pursuant to the will of his late mother, Jane Ilive, who may have been one of
            the Philadelphian circle around Jane Leade. In this discourse, which he published that
            same year, he maintained four principal theses: 
			<q> I The Plurality of Worlds<lb/>
 II
              That this Earth is Hell.<lb/>
 III That the Souls of Men are Apostate Angels. And<lb/>
              IV That the fire which will punish those who shall be confined to this Globe after the
              Day of Judgment will be immaterial.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">7</ref></q><note
              id="n31"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “Book of Jashar,” <hi rend="i">The New Standard Jewish
                Encyclopedia</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Wigoder (New York and Oxford: Facts on File, 7th
              ed., 1992), <hi rend="i">s.v.</hi> “Jashar” is not a name (as is sometimes supposed)
              but Hebrew for “the upright one.”</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">6</hi> H. R.
              Plomer, in <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of the Printers and Booksellers Who Were At Work
                in England[,] Scotland[,] and Ireland from 1726 to 1775</hi> (Oxford: Printed for
              the Bibliographical Society at the Oxford University Press, 1932 [for 1930])
              136.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> The Oration Spoke at
                Joyners hall in Thames Street on Monday, Sept. 24, 1733</hi>, t.p.</note></p>
          <p>In 1750, addressing his fellow master printers, he said “It may with Great Veracity be
            affirmed, that there is no Art, Science, or Profession in the World, but what owes its
              <hi rend="i">Origin</hi>, at least its Progress and present 
              <hi rend="i">Perfection</hi>, to the free Exercise of the <hi rend="i">Art of Printing</hi>,”
and
            he went on to defend “the <hi rend="i">Liberty</hi> of the Press.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
              type="note">8</ref> Prosecuted in 1756 for printing his own <hi rend="i">Modest
              Remarks upon the Discourses of the Bishop of</hi>
	<pb id="p30-53" n="53"/>	
              <hi rend="i">London</hi> (Dr. Sherlock),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">9</ref> Ilive was imprisoned
            for over a year, during which he took the opportunity to write and publish 
              <hi rend="i">Reasons offered for the Reformation of the House of Correction in Clerkenwell</hi>
            (1757). We may well imagine that William Blake would have found Ilive’s story of some
            interest. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> The Speech of Mr. Jacob Ilive
                to His Brethren the Master-Printers</hi> (1750).</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> The History and Antiquities of Dissenting Churches and
Meeting
                Houses, in London, Westminster, and Southward</hi>, 4 vols. (London, 1808) 2:
              290-92.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Book of Jasher</hi> was recognized as a forgery from the first. 
              <hi rend="i">The Monthly Review</hi> declared it was “a palpable piece of contrivance
            intended to impose on the credulous, and the ignorant, and to sap the credit of the
            books of <hi rend="i">Moses</hi>, and blacken the character of Moses 
              <hi rend="i">himself.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">10</ref> The circumstances of the hoax
            were recounted in 1778 by Edward Rowe-Mores, in his <hi rend="i">Dissertation Upon
              English Typographical Founders and Foundries</hi>: 
			<q> . . . Of the publication we can
              say from the information of the Only-One who is capable of informing us, because the
              business was a secret between the Two: <hi rend="i">Mr. Ilive</hi> in the night-time
              had constantly an <hi rend="i">Hebr.</hi> bible before him (<hi rend="i">sed. q. de
                hoc</hi>) and cases in his closet. He produced the copy for 
              <hi rend="i">Jasher</hi>, and it was composed in private, and the forms worked off in a private
              pressroom by these Two after the men of the printing-house had left their work. (65)
			</q>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">10</hi> 5 (December 1751): 520.</note></p>
          <p>That this exposure did not cause <hi rend="i">The Book of Jasher</hi> to disappear
            entirely from view is shown by the republication of Ilive’s text in 1829.<ref
              target="n37" type="note">11</ref> Blake, with his interest in biblical antiquities and
            his connections with the printing trade, would have had ample opportunity to know the
            first edition. It is interesting to consider what distinctive features might have
            interested him most. <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See Thomas Hartwell Hone, B.D.,
                <hi rend="i">Bibliographical Notes on the Book of Jasher</hi> (London, 1833). S. T.
              Coleridge, commenting on this edition, thought it was based on one of the “slovenly
              Eutropius-like Abridgements of the Pentateuch &amp; the books of Joshua &amp; Judges
              by some ignorant Monk” (<hi rend="i">The Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor
                Coleridge</hi>, ed. E. L. Griggs [Oxford: Oxford UP, 1956-72] 6: 900).</note></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Jasher</hi> 3: 19 Abraham is talked out of sacrificing Isaac by Sarah,
            who says “The holy voice hath not so spoken.” As a result, “Abraham repented him of the
            evil he purposed to do unto his son: his only son Isaac.” The Egyptians do not pursue
            the Hebrews into the Red Sea but go home instead (10: 24). Moses is frequently depicted
            as acting <corr type="emend">tyrannically.</corr> When Miriam opposes his appointing of judges, Moses hides her for
            seven days until she is released by the demand of the congregation, who prefer her view
            to his; but after Miriam’s death Moses appoints 70 elders to rule the people (15). In
            the course of establishing the priesthood of the Levites, Moses has 250 who oppose him
            killed (22). When Shelomith protests against the laws Aaron gives to the people, he is
            stoned to death by order of Moses. Achan too 
<figure n="urizen.c.p3" id="urizen.c.illbk.03" work-copy="urizen.c" rend="db" width="692" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Chap: I<lb/>
	1. Lo, a shadow of horror is risen<lb/>
	In Eternity! Unknown, unprolific?<lb/>
	Self-closd, all-repelling; what Demon<lb/>
	Hath form’d this abominable void<lb/>
	This soul-shudd’ring vacuum?. Some<lb/>
	said<lb/>
	It is Urizen“, But unknown, abstracted<lb/>
	Brooding secret, the dark power hid.<lb/>
	2, Times on times he divided, &amp; measur’d<lb/>
	Space by space in his ninefold darkness<lb/>
	Unseen, unknown; changes appeard.<lb/>
	Like desolate mountains rifted furious<lb/>
	By the black winds of perturbation<lb/>
	3. For he strove in battles dire<lb/>
	In unseen conflictions with shapes<lb/>
	Bred from his forsaken wilderness.<lb/>
	Of beast, bird, fish, serpent &amp; element<lb/>
	Combustion, blast, vapour and cloud.<lb/>
	4. Dark revolving in silent activity:<lb/>
	Unseen in tormenting passions;<lb/>
	An activity unknown and horrible;<lb/>
	A self-contemplating shadow,<lb/>
	In enormous labours occupied<lb/>
	5. But Eternals beheld his vast forests:<lb/>
	Age on ages he lay, clos’d, unknown,<lb/>
	Brooding shut in the deep; all avoid<lb/>
	The petrific abominable chaos<lb/>
	6. His cold horrors silent. dark Urizen<lb/>
	Prepar’d; his ten thousands of thunders<lb/>
	Rang’d in gloom’d array stretch out across<lb/>
	The dread world. &amp; the rolling of wheels<lb/>
	As of swelling seas, sound in his clouds<lb/>
	In his hills of stor’d snows, in his mountains<lb/>
	Of hail &amp; ice; voices of terror,<lb/>
	Are heard, like thunders of autumn,<lb/>
	When the cloud blazes over the harvests<lb/>
	Chap: II.<lb/>
	1. Earth was not: nor globes of attraction<lb/>
	The will of the Immortal expanded<lb/>
	Or contracted his all flexible senses,<lb/>
	Death was not, but eternal life sprung<lb/>
	2 The sound of a trumpet the heavens<lb/>
	Awoke &amp; vast clouds of blood roll’d<lb/>
	Round the dim rocks of Urizen, so nam’d<lb/>
	That solitary one in Immensity<lb/>
	3. Shrill the trumpet: &amp; myriads of Eternity</figTranscr>
              <head>2 William Blake, <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Copy C. Plate 3. Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon
                Collection.</figDesc>
            </figure> is stoned to death, not because of his sin in appropriating part of the spoil
            of Jericho devoted to God (as in Joshua 7) but because he challenged the giving of the
            spoils to the tribe of Levi (28: 20-23). At the end of the book, Joshua makes peace with
            the kings of Canaan. This altered narrative, emphasizing humanitarian values, casting
            Moses as an authoritarian power-figure, and endorsing rebellion against tyrannical law,
            would have found a sympathetic reader in Blake. Of course not all of Ilive’s recasting
            of biblical material is of this nature. For example, his account of the parting of the
            Red Sea is rationalistic: Moses says, “It is now midnight, and by the time of the
            cock-crow the Red Sea will be dried up: and peradventure we may cross over dry-shod into
            the wilderness” (10: 24). Blake preferred miracles, but that did not prevent him from
            defending the deist Thomas Paine against Bishop Watson. In such instances he was more
            conscious of similarities than of differences.</p>
          <p>A further point of comparison may be made between the format of <hi rend="i">The Book
              of Jasher</hi> and that of <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen.</hi> Both works,
            as can be seen in the illustrations (illus. 1 and 2), exploit the familiar layout of the
            Authorized Version and some other English Bibles: a double-columned page divided into
            chapters and verses. Of course Blake is 
<pb id="p30-54" n="54"/>
unique in his
            combination of design and calligraphic text; Ilive’s decorated initial capital is his
            only gesture in this direction. Nevertheless, both play upon the reader’s experience of
            opening a conventional Bible, only to present a text subversive of such a Bible.
            Finally, just as <hi rend="i">Jasher</hi> concludes after its last verse (37: 32) 
              “<hi rend="i">The End of the Book of</hi> Jasher,” <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> concludes “The
            End of the [<hi rend="i">first</hi>] book of Urizen” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 83), both in
            imitation of colophons in medieval texts. Did Blake recognize Ilive’s private press-room
            as a forerunner of his own Printing House in Hell?</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
