<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
        <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
                <idno>30.2.robson</idno>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title type="article">Blake’s Death</title>
                                <author n="Robson">Lane Robson</author>
                                <author n="Viscomi">Joseph Viscomi</author>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>Fall 1996</edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <date>1996</date>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <biblFull>
                                        <titleStmt>
                                                <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                                                <biblScope unit="volIss">30.2</biblScope>
                                                <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
                                                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                                                <respStmt>
                                                  <resp>Editors</resp>
                                                  <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                                                  <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                                                  <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                                                  <name>Patricia Neill</name>
                                                  <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                                                  <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                                                  <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                                                  <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                                                  <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                                                  <name>David Worrall</name>
                                                  <resp>Contributors</resp>
                                                  <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                                                  <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                                                  <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                                                  <name>Lane Robson</name>
                                                  <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
                                                  <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                                                  <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
                                                </respStmt>
                                        </titleStmt>
                                        <publicationStmt>
                                                <publisher>Department of English, University of
                                                  Rochester</publisher>
                                                <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
                                                <date value="1996"/>
                                                <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                                        </publicationStmt>
                                </biblFull>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <langUsage>
                                <language id="eng">English</language>
                        </langUsage>
                </profileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text id="volume_30">
                <body>
                        <pb id="p30-36" n="36"/>
                        <div1 id="BQ-30-2-0005">
                                <head>
                                        <title type="main">
                                                <hi rend="b">Blake’s Death</hi>
                                        </title>
                                </head>
                                <byline>by <docAuthor>Lane <name>Robson</name></docAuthor> and
                                                <docAuthor>Joseph
                                        <name>Viscomi</name></docAuthor></byline>
<q> But first the notion that man has a body distinct from his soul,
                                        is to be expunged; this I shall do, by printing in the
                                        infernal method, by corrosives, which in Hell are salutary
                                        and medicinal, melting apparent surfaces away, and
                                        displaying the infinite which was hid.<lb/>
<hi rend="i">The
                                                Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, plate 14 </q>
                                <p>Between the spring of 1824 and July 1827, the month before he
                                        died, William Blake regularly visited John Linnell and his
                                        family at their cottage, Collins Farm, in Hampstead, missing
                                        the visits only when ill, which was an increasing problem
                                        during his last year.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref> On
                                        Tuesday, 3 July 1827, Blake thanked Linnell “for the Ten
                                        Pounds” he had just sent and informed him that his “journey
                                        to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a relapse which is lasted
                                        till now. I find I am not so well as I thought I must not go
                                        on in a youthful Style—however I am upon the mending hand to
                                        day &amp; hope soon to look as I did for I have been yellow
                                        accompanied by all the old Symptoms.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
                                                type="note">2</ref> This news would not have
                                        surprised Linnell; he knew that Blake often blamed the
                                        Hampstead air for bringing about his “old Symptoms,” which
                                        included fever and stomach pains (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 306;
                                                <hi rend="i">E</hi> 775). And, no doubt, since
                                        Blake’s health was the subject of 17 of his 19 extant
                                        personal letters to Linnell over the last 29 months (Keynes
                                        156-70), Linnell was accustomed to Blake’s optimistic and
                                        reassuring diagnoses. But Linnell must have suspected the
                                                worst.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> Indeed,
                                        from the summer of 1818, when the two artists met, to early
                                        1825, there is no record of personal letters, only business
                                        transactions, because they met regularly, going to
                                        exhibitions, galleries, plays, and various social gatherings
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 256-310). The letters were
                                        occasioned by Blake’s illness, and when read together they
                                        reveal a pattern of illness waxing and waning and a man more
                                        anxious about his work being disrupted than his life ending.
                                        Linnell had already expressed serious concern about Blake’s
                                        health by the summer of 1826, when he had hoped to move
                                        Blake to Hampstead so that he would be nearby 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 338; Gilchrist 1: 350), and he did so
again
                                        on 7 February 1827, when he encouraged Blake to live at
                                        Cirencester Place (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 338), an idea that
                                        Blake refused after much anxious reflection 
                                                (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 782).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
                                        Now, with this new letter of 3 July 1827, despite Blake’s
                                        optimism and good cheer, Linnell must have been alarmed, for
                                        the “old Symptoms” were accompanied by something new and
                                        frightening: the yellowing of Blake’s skin. 
                                                  <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Linnell moved his family
to
                                                Hampstead on 6 March 1824; Blake’s first recorded
                                                visit is 18 May 1824. A. H. Palmer said that his
                                                father Samuel and Blake “often walked up to the
                                                village together” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                                                  Records</hi> 286, 292; hereafter cited as 
                                                  <hi rend="i">BR</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi
                                                  rend="s">2</hi> Erdman, David V., ed. 
                                                  <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
                                                  Blake</hi> (New York: Doubleday, 1988) 785.
                                                Hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">E.</hi></note>	
                                                <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> In addition to these 19
                                                letters and notices, Blake wrote in his last two
                                                years two short notes to Mrs. Linnell, one to Maria
                                                Denman, another to Mrs. Aders excusing himself from
                                                one of her salons due to illness, and a long letter
                                                to Cumberland (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 774, 776, 781,
                                                783). The only full-length study of Blake’s letters,
                                                by David Wells, virtually ignores the last letters,
                                                spending only three paragraphs on them (120-21).
                                                  <p>Based on extant letters, Blake’s epistolary
                                                  efforts during his last years were slight compared
                                                  to those exerted during the period of 1800 to
                                                  1805, which includes 54 letters, but they were
                                                  more extensive than those for the periods of 1791
                                                  to 1799 and 1806 to 1819, which includes only six
                                                  and nine letters respectively (excluding receipts
                                                  to Butts and including two letters to magazines).
                                                  Letters from 1800 to 1805 reveal a Blake either
                                                  “Emit[ting] sparks of fire” (<hi rend="i">E</hi>
                                                  709) or entering “a Deep pit of Melancholy,
                                                  Melancholy without any real reason for it, a
                                                  disease which God keep you from and all good men”
                                                  (2 July 1800, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 706). Blake was
                                                  aware of depression’s effect on his work and wife,
                                                  and, though puzzled over its cause, always
                                                  prescribed work as the antidote 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 706, 719-20, 724, 756, 767). From these
                                                  letters comes the speculation that Blake’s
                                                  artistic and spiritual crises were forms of
                                                  depression, filled with anxiety and self-doubt
                                                  (Wells 82-85, Jamison 92-95).</p></note>	
                                                <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Linnell wrote in his
                                                journal: “February 7. To Mr Blake to speak to him @
                                                living at C[irencester] P[lace].” But Cirencester
                                                Place was the name of a street near Fitzroy Square,
                                                where Blake’s brother James lived and where Linnell
                                                had his London studio/residence. As Bentley
                                                explains, the “reference does not make clear whether
                                                the Blakes were to move into Linnell’s studio, into
                                                independent lodgings, or into the building where
                                                Blake’s brother James lived” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                                338 and n3). Given that Linnell’s objective appears
                                                to have been to keep a closer eye on Blake, it seems
                                                reasonable to assume that he hoped to move Blake
                                                closer to him and other of his friends in that
                                                neighborhood, which included Flaxman and Thomas
                                                Butts.</note></p>
                                <p>The letter was Blake’s last; he died six weeks later. The yellow
                                        skin signified jaundice, a yellowish discoloration of tissue
                                        and bodily fluids with bile pigment, which is caused by a
                                        variety of pathological conditions that interfere with the
                                        normal processing of bile—the liquid secreted by the liver
                                        and stored in the gallbladder. J. T. Smith and Frederick
                                        Tatham both attributed Blake’s death to “gall [i.e., bile]
                                        mixing with the blood” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 475, 528); Mona
                                        Wilson attributed it to “gall-stones” (297); and Sir
                                        Geoffrey Keynes, the esteemed Blake scholar who was also a
                                        respected fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons of London,
                                        attributed it to “gallstones and inflammation of the
                                        gallbladder” (156n1). Most recently, Aileen Ward attributed
                                        Blake’s death to “a ruptured gallbladder with attendant
                                        peritonitis” (15). The latter part of her diagnosis, as we
                                        argue here, is probably incorrect, whereas the less detailed
                                        diagnoses about the gallbladder are nearer the truth, in
                                        that they attribute Blake’s death to a problem in the liver
                                        and bile ducts. Recent improvements in our understanding of
                                        the diseases of the biliary tract, however, allow a more
                                        precise speculation regarding the cause of Blake’s death. A
                                        modern and more <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">We
                                                would like to thank Aileen Ward, Morton Paley, and
                                                G. E. Bentley Jr. for reading earlier versions of
                                                this paper and for their helpful
                                                suggestions.</note>
	<pb id="p30-37" n="37"/>
specific
                                        description of the cause might be liver failure due to
                                        biliary cirrhosis. Cirrhosis is an irreversible alteration
                                        of the liver architecture consisting of hepatic fibrosis and
                                        areas of nodular regeneration (Wyngaarden, Smith, and
                                        Bennett 786). A variety of disease processes can lead to
                                        cirrhosis. When it develops due to obstruction in the
                                        biliary system, it is called biliary cirrhosis. A review of
                                        the available information on Blake’s illness and a close
                                        reading of Blake’s and his contemporaries’ descriptions of
                                        his illness suggests that among the currently recognized
                                        causes of biliary cirrhosis the most likely is sclerosing
                                        cholangitis.</p>
                                <p>Ascertaining the probable cause of Blake’s death, while of
                                        significant biographical importance in itself, can provide
                                        relevant information about the man as well as his
                                        biographers, for it enables us to assess Frederick Tatham’s
                                        account of Blake’s final illness being accompanied with
                                        “agonies of pain” and Ward’s recent challenge to the legend
                                        that Blake burst into song on his deathbed (14-15). It also
                                        provides a clearer picture of when and how Blake managed to
                                        produce his last paintings and illuminated books despite a
                                        recurring illness that kept him bedridden for days at a
                                        time. Of significant interest are reports that sclerosing
                                        cholangitis might be caused or aggravated by chronic copper
                                        intoxication (LaRusso 901, Weisner 204-05, Gross 277),
                                        raising the possibility that Blake died from a lifetime
                                        exposure to copper, or, more specifically, to the fumes from
                                        the chemical reaction of nitric acid and copper—the
                                        “corrosives” of his own “infernal method.”</p>
                                <p>Sclerosing cholangitis occurs most commonly in individuals with
                                        inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), a chronic diarrheal
                                        disease (Sherlock 249, Shorter 311). Alexander Gilchrist,
                                        Blake’s first biographer, states that Blake “was a perpetual
                                        sufferer from intermittent attacks of cold and dysentery”
                                        (1: 347). The modern interpretation of a “cold” is an upper
                                        respiratory infection, “an inflammatory condition of the
                                        mucous membranes of the respiratory organs, accompanied by
                                        catarrh, hoarseness, and cough” (OED). In the eighteenth
                                        century, however, the term was more flexible, referring also
                                        to “an indisposition of the body caused by exposure to cold”
                                        (OED). Blake appears to have used the term in both these
                                        senses. In a letter sent on 30 January 1803 from Felpham to
                                        his brother James, Blake says: “I have no Ague but have had
                                        a Cold this Winter”; he also claimed that “the air tho warm
                                        is unhealthy” and acknowledged that “I was really very ill
                                        when I wrote [Butts] the last time” (i.e., 10 January 1803).
                                        When he returned to London, he wrote Hayley of his “violent
                                        cold which confind me to my bed 3 days &amp; to my chamber a
                                        week” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 725-26, 740). But in a letter to
                                        John Linnell on 1 February 1826, Blake referred to a “cold
                                        in my stomach” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 775), indicating a
                                        gastrointestinal illness. Gastrointestinal “colds” and
                                        dysentery are consistent with the speculation that Blake had
                                        IBD, a chronic (Gilchrist’s “perpetual”) diarrheal disease
                                        characterized by exacerbations and remissions (Gilchrist’s
                                        “intermittent”).</p>
                                <p>Unfortunately, with only nine known letters between 1 July 1806
                                        and March 1825 (and only four or five of these could be
                                        called personal), the documentary evidence necessary to
                                        trace a pattern in his health during these years is absent.
                                        However, to Henry Crabb Robinson, apparently on their first
                                        visit at the Aders on 10 December 1825, Blake spoke of “a
                                        bowel complaint which nearly killed him.” The cause,
                                        according to Blake, was Wordsworth’s “preface to the
                                        Excursion” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 325).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
                                                type="note">5</ref> When Blake read the 
                                                <hi rend="i">Excursion</hi>, published in 1814, is not known,
                                        but Flaxman had been similarly offended by the same passage,
                                        as he told Robinson on 19 December 1814. As Bentley
                                        surmises, “it would not be surprising if Flaxman and Blake
                                        had talked about the offensive passage” 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 312n3). If so, then Blake’s IBD may
have
                                        been present this early. Blake himself, though, seems to
                                        admit that his stomach colds were present even earlier,
                                        while he was “young,” and that they had been precipitated
                                        not by literature but by all points north of London. In his
                                        1 February 1826 letter, he tells Linnell: 
<q> I am forced to
                                                write because . . . I am again laid up by a cold in
                                                my stomach the Hampstead Air as it always did. so I
                                                fear it always will do . . . I believe my
                                                Constitution to be a good one but it has many
                                                peculiarities that no one but myself can know. When
                                                I was young Hampstead Highgate Hornsea Muswell Hill
                                                &amp; even Islington &amp; all places North of
                                                London always laid me up the day after &amp;
                                                sometimes two or three days with precisely the same
                                                Complaint &amp; the same torment of the Stomach.
                                                Easily removed but excruciating while it lasts &amp;
                                                enfeebling for some time after . . . . 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 775)<ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> In his
                                                  diary, Robinson records Blake as saying that “he
                                                  had been much pained by readg the introduction to
                                                  the excursion It brought on a fit of illness” 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 312); in his 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi>, he states that “The
Preface
                                                  to the Excursion especially the Verses quoted from
                                                  book I. of the Recluse, so troubled him as to
                                                  bring on a fit of illness” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                                  545); but to Dorothy Wordsworth he identified the
                                                  illness as a “bowel complaint.” The offending
                                                  passage expressed the idea of passing Jehovah
                                                  “unalarmed.”</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> In response to Mrs. Linnell’s statement
                                                  that Hampstead was a healthy place, Blake
                                                  asserted: “It is a lie! It is no such thing” 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 306). Perhaps Gilchrist had this
                                                  response and letter in mind when he said that
                                                  Blake “cherished a wilful dislike to Hampstead,
                                                  and to all the northern suburbs of London” (1:
                                                  353). <p>The subject of Blake’s compass symbolism
                                                  is too complex to pursue here, but note that
                                                  Urizen was banished to the north by the eternals
                                                  and that Blake describes bowels negatively (“To
                                                  Klopstock”) and positively. Bowlahoola, in 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, puns on bowels and
                                                  corresponds to stomach, heart, and lungs; as it
                                                  houses Los and the imagination, it is the positive
                                                  side to the fourth stage of humanity, which is
                                                  Or-Ulro, situated in “the Stomach and Intestines,
                                                  terrible, deadly, unutterable” 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 134) Further study of Blake’s health
may
                                                  provide surer grounds for such biological and
                                                  anatomical passages.</p></note></q></p>
                                <p>What the 68 year-old Blake means by “young” is uncertain, but a
                                        reasonable guess would be his twenties and thirties, that
                                        is, in the 1780s and 1790s. This would be consistent 
                                                <pb id="p30-38" n="38"/>
with Tatham’s statement that
                                        Blake “and his Wife” went on very long walks “in his youth”
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 527). Blake’s walks to
                                        villages north of London may have continued to at least
                                        1808, when Thomas Butts appears to have moved from a house
                                        in Dalston to Fitzroy Square (Viscomi “Green House” 12).</p>
                                <p>When signs of IBD first began to reveal themselves is not known,
                                        but they appear to have been chronic or “perpetual,” as
                                        Gilchrist says. If Blake suffered from IBD in his “youth,”
                                        then it was probably still present at the end of his life,
                                        which would be consistent with Blake’s behavior, for, while
                                        he regularly speaks of his health improving and of his
                                        ability to continue working, he also says he dare not leave
                                        the house. That it was intermittent is evinced by Linnell’s
                                        journal, which records his and Blake’s going to Lahee’s, the
                                        City, and an exhibition in March, April, and May 1825 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 301).</p>
                                <p>If Blake had IBD complicated by sclerosing cholangitis, the final
                                        stages of his illness began about 29 months before his
                                        death, as indicated by Blake’s undated letter to Linnell,
                                        which appears to have been written in early March 1825,
                                        making it the first extant personal letter to Linnell: 
<q> A
                                                return of the old Shivering Fit came on this Morning
                                                as soon as I awaked &amp; I am now in Bed—Better
                                                &amp; as I think almost well If I can possibly I
                                                will be at Mr Lahees tomorrow Morning. these attacks
                                                are too serious at the time to permit me to be out
                                                of Bed. but they go off by rest which seems to be
                                                All that I want . . . . (<hi rend="i">E</hi>
                                                  773)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref>	
                                                  <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> This letter was
                                                  written on “12 O Clock Wednesday,” which may have
                                                  been 2 March 1825. The letter informs Linnell that
                                                  Blake will try but may miss the appointment with
                                                  Lahee, the printer of the 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job.</hi> Linnell
                                                  records a meeting with Lahee and Blake for
                                                  Saturday 5 March 1825 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 300),
                                                  which suggests that Blake’s letter was written 2
                                                  March and the meeting was put off for two more
                                                  days due to Blake’s illness. Erdman dates the
                                                  letter “March” (773) while Keynes merely places it
                                                  before the next letter, dated 7 June 1825 (156).
                                                  Both editors, though, consider it the first known
                                                  letter to Linnell. It is also Blake’s first extant
                                                  letter since 11 October 1819; all correspondence
                                                  between these dates consists of receipts and the
                                                  contract with Linnell for <hi rend="i">Job.</hi>
                                                  The unaddressed letter of 11 October 1819 may have
                                                  been to Linnell, as Erdman and Keynes speculate,
                                                  but this seems unlikely, given its tone and a
                                                  provenance in which Linnell or Samuel Palmer
                                                  (Linnell’s son-in-law) do not figure (there is
                                                  only one Linnell document of 32 that fits this
                                                  description; see Keynes 225 #173). In October of
                                                  1819, Blake was frequently seeing John Varley, of
                                                  Visionary Heads fame (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 259),
                                                  and in the letter he mentions meeting up with the
                                                  engraver and watercolorist Thomas Heaphy, who in
                                                  1807 became a member of the Old Watercolor
                                                  Society, of which Varley was a founding member.
                                                  The two men must have known one another, whereas
                                                  there is no evidence that Heaphy and Linnell were
                                                  friends. Whoever the recipient, though, the letter
                                                  is of interest regarding Blake’s health, for Blake
                                                  ends it with: “hoping that I may meet you again in
                                                  perfect Health &amp; Happiness.” Is Blake alluding
                                                  to his health or that of the
                                        addressee?</note></q></p>
                                <p>A shivering fit is the nineteenth-century description of fever
                                        and chills (Elliotson 140), symptoms that can occur in
                                        individuals with IBD and particularly in those with
                                        sclerosing cholangitis (Wyndgaarden, Smith, and Bennett 701,
                                        Schiff 1312). Chills and fever develop in about fifty
                                        percent of individuals with sclerosing cholangitis (Schiff
                                        1312). That the “old” symptoms “returned” suggests that
                                        Blake experienced similar problems for some time,
                                        reconfirming the chronic and intermittent nature of the
                                        illness.</p>
                                <p>In his second letter to Linnell, Blake described his problem as
                                        “ague.” On 7 June 1825, he wrote that 
<q> on account of this
                                                abominable Ague or whatever it is I am in Bed &amp;
                                                at Work my health I cannot speak of for if it was
                                                not for Cold weather I think I should soon get about
                                                again . . . I can draw as well a Bed as Up &amp;
                                                perhaps better but I cannot Engrave I am going on
                                                with Dante &amp; please myself . . . 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 773-74)<ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The 102
                                                  Dante drawings, in varying degrees of completion,
                                                  and the seven unfinished engravings figure
                                                  prominently in Blake’s last letters, between March
                                                  1825 and July 1827. They apparently overlapped
                                                  with other work, like late temperas, watercolors,
                                                  the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> engraving, the
                                                  unfinished <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>
                                                  drawings, and reprintings of the 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (copies U, X, Y, W, Z, AA), 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (copy I), and 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (copy F) (see Butlin 1: 481,
                                                  775-77, 798-802, 805-07, 811, 812.1-102, 813-26,
                                                  827.1-5, 828.1-11, 829.1-29, 830-34; Essick and
                                                  Viscomi 240-43; Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                                                  chap. 35). The 102 drawings were not, in other
                                                  words, completed in a forthnight in October of
                                                  1824, while Blake was in bed due to a scalded
                                                  foot, as Palmer recalled many years later 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 291). Indeed, if Blake had begun
                                                  the Dante drawings that early, then they
                                                  overlapped with the <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
                                                  engravings. If so, perhaps this is another sign of
                                                  Blake’s intermittent illness, which placed him in
                                                  bed and prevented him from engraving the 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Job.</hi> Linnell did not begin paying
                                                  for the Dante by name until 28 January 1825
                                                  (Keynes 152), but perhaps he had been paying for
                                                  it “on acct” since 2 February 1824 (Keynes
                                                  148).</note></q></p>
                                <p>In the nineteenth century, “ague” was a term used to describe a
                                        feverish illness with chills and sweating (Clutterbuck 756,
                                        Elliotson 140-41).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> If
                                        Catherine Blake’s ague during the Felpham years is any
                                        evidence, this could be a debilitating condition;
                                        nevertheless, Blake characteristically refused to be
                                        disrupted and actually found work therapeutic.<ref
                                                target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi
                                                  rend="s">9</hi> According to the OED, “ague”
                                                refers now “more usually to the cold or shivering
                                                stage” of a fever, but initially it referred to “the
                                                burning or feverish stage.”</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi
                                                  rend="s">10</hi> Blake’s complaints about his and
                                                Catherine’s health seem genuine and not designed
                                                either to elicit sympathy from his brother James or
                                                justify to Hayley his leaving Felpham. Catherine was
                                                especially bothered there, suffering from “Agues
                                                &amp; Rheumatisms” apparently during most of her
                                                stay and the fall of 1803 back in London 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 725, 738). Catherine remained sick
                                                through January 1804: “My poor wife has been near
                                                the Gates of Death” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 740).
                                                Little wonder that Blake believed that “if sickness
                                                comes all is unpleasant,” and “only illness makes
                                                all uncomfortable &amp; this we must prevent by
                                                every means in our power” (<hi rend="i">E</hi>
                                                726-27).</note></p>
                                <p>Blake may have spent much of the summer of 1825 in bed; there are
                                        no documents extent from July 1825 to prove or disprove
                                        this, but on 6 August 1825, Linnell received a letter from
                                        Edward Thomas Daniell, who stated: “I am sorry to hear poor
                                        Mr Blake is so unwell but hope he may recover, again to use
                                        [h]is pencil and graver” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 301). Daniell
                                        got his wish, for Linnell and Blake visited the Aders on
                                        that day. Clearly, the illness continued to come and go,
                                        raising 
<pb id="p30-39" n="39"/>
Blake’s hopes only to
                                        disappoint him with further relapses. In September, he may
                                        have visited Palmer in Shoreham (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 302
                                        and n2); in October, he visited the Linnells at Hampstead at
                                        least twice. He wrote Mrs. Linnell on 11 October to say “I
                                        hope to see you on Sunday morning as usual,” and he did so,
                                        on 16 October, as her journal for 18 October records: “Mr
                                        Blake came as usual” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 305). But on 10
                                        November, Blake wrote Linnell that 
<q> I cannot get Well
                                                &amp; am now in Bed but seem as if I should be
                                                better tomorrow rest dose me good—Pray take care of
                                                your health this wet weather &amp; tho I write do
                                                not venture out on such days as today has been. I
                                                hope a few more days will bring us to a conclusion .
                                                . . . (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 774-75) </q></p>
                                <p>By December, Blake’s health appears to have improved
                                        substantially. On 10 December, he attended a dinner party at
                                        the Aders, where he met Robinson, who paid him long visits
                                        on 17 and 24 December and 6 January 1826. But, as noted,
                                        Blake told Linnell on 1 February 1826 that he was “again
                                        laid up by a cold in [his] stomach,” supposedly because of
                                        “the Hampstead Air” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 775). Seventeen
                                        days later, Blake received Robinson for a morning chat 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 321), and though Robinson makes no
                                        mention of Blake’s health, it seems that it was
                                        deteriorating. On 31 March 1826, Blake described his
                                        condition: 
<q> I have been very ill since I saw you but am
                                                again well enough to go on with my work but not well
                                                enough to venture out. the Chill of the weather soon
                                                drives me back into that shivering fit which must be
                                                avoided till the Cold is gone . . . . if the weather
                                                should be warm I will endeavour to come to you
                                                before Tuesday but much fear that my present
                                                tottering state will hold me some time yet. 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 776) </q></p>
                                <p>Blake sounds much as he did exactly one year earlier, when he
                                        first described his condition as a “return of the old
                                        Shivering Fit,” but now he compounds his description with
                                        the phrase “tottering state,” which reveals Blake’s
                                        awareness of himself as significantly weakening.</p>
                                <p>The illness continued to wax and wane, but through it all Blake
                                        continued to work. In April, he wrote Linnell: “I am still
                                        far from recoverd &amp; dare not get out in the cold air.
                                        Yet I lose nothing by it Dante goes on the better which is
                                        all I care about” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 777).<ref
                                                target="n11" type="note">11</ref> On 12 May, Blake
                                        attended a party at Robinson’s, but on 19 May, he wrote
                                        Linnell to cancel his upcoming Sunday visit to Hampstead
                                        because of the “shivering fits.” This time, though, he also
                                        described “forcing sweats,” a nineteenth-century treatment
                                        for fever (Clutterbuck 760): 
<figure n="Encyclopedie1767.30.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="701">
                                                <head>1 Etching the copper plate in a trough;
                                                  detail.</head>
                                                <figDesc><hi rend="i">Encyclopedie</hi>,
                                                  1767.</figDesc>
                                        </figure>
<q> I have had another desperate Shivring Fit. it
                                                came on yesterday afternoon after as good a morning
                                                as I ever experienced. It began by a gnawing Pain in
                                                the Stomach &amp; soon spread. a deathly feel all
                                                over the limbs which brings on the shivring fit when
                                                I am forced to go to bed where I contrive to get
                                                into a little Perspiration which takes it quite
                                                away. It was night when it left me so I did not get
                                                up but just as I was going to rise this morning the
                                                shivring fit attackd me again &amp; the pain with
                                                its accompanying deathly feel I got again into a
                                                perspiration &amp; was well but so much weakend that
                                                I am still in bed. (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 777)
                                                </q>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Keynes
                                                mistakenly dates this letter April 1827 (168). It
                                                can be dated a year earlier because Blake mentions
                                                that “Mr. Butts is to have a Proof Copy for Three
                                                Guineas,” which Linnell duly recorded in his cash
                                                account book for 29 April 1826 (Keynes
                                        148).</note></p>
                                <p>There are no letters from June, but Robinson paid Blake a visit
                                        on the 13th and found him “as wild as ever” and contending
                                        that “wives should be in common” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 548).
                                        The rest of the summer, though, was miserable, as Blake’s
                                        letters clearly reveal. On 2 July 1826, Blake described
                                        progressive symptoms and signs of weakness: 
<q> I also feel
                                                Myself weaker than I was aware, being not able as
                                                yet to sit up longer than six hours at a time. &amp;
                                                also feel the Cold too much to dare venture beyond
                                                my present precincts. . . . But I get better &amp;
                                                stronger every day, tho weaker in muscle &amp; bone
                                                than I supposed. . . . I intend to bring . . . My
                                                Book of Drawings from Dante &amp; one Plate shut up
                                                in the Book . . . [but] 
                                                  <pb id="p30-40" n="40"/>
<figure n="Encyclopedie1751.30.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="335">
                                                  <head>2 Etching the copper plate diked in wax and
                                                  feathering away gas bubbles; detail.</head>
                                                  <figDesc><hi rend="i">Encyclopedie</hi>,
                                                  1751-52.</figDesc>
                                                </figure> I fear I could not go thro [the coach’s
                                                “rumble”] So . . . conclude another Week must pass
                                                before I dare Venture upon what I ardently
                                                desire—the seeing you with your happy Family once
                                                again &amp; that for a longer Period than I had ever
                                                hoped in my health full hours. (<hi rend="i">E</hi>
                                                778) </q></p>
                                <p>A letter written three days later, on 5 July 1826, describes a
                                        remission: 
<q> I am getting better every hour my Plan is
                                                diet only &amp; if the Machine is capable of it
                                                shall make an old man yet: I go on Just as If
                                                perfectly well which indeed I am except in those
                                                paroxysms which I now believe will never more
                                                return. (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 778)<ref target="n12"
                                                  type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> By “Machine,” Blake seems ironically to
                                                  mean his body, in the sense that “whatever enters
                                                  . . . the Ulro” or material world, “Becomes
                                                  Sexual, &amp; is Created, and Vegetated, and Born
                                                  . . . the Spectrous Uncircumcised Vegetation. /
                                                  Forming a Sexual Machine: an Aged Virgin Form”
                                                  (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 44: 21-25, 
                                                  <hi rend="i">E</hi> 186-87).</note></q></p>
                                <p>The illness, which appeared to be in remission for at least 11
                                        days, left him weaker but hopeful. He writes on 14 July: “I
                                        am so much better that I have hopes of fulfilling my
                                        expectation &amp; desire of Visiting Hampstead I am
                                        nevertheless very considerably weakend by the last severe
                                        attacks” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 778). The relentless nature of
                                        his illness led Blake, though hopeful, to obtain new medical
                                        advice, but his letter from 16 July 1826 is the only mention
                                        of a specific therapy for his illness apart from diet, rest,
                                        and forcing sweats: 
<q> I have been ever since taking Dr
                                                Youngs Addition to Mr Finchams Practise with me
                                                ([It] &lt;The Addition&gt; is dandelion) In a
                                                Species of Delireum, &amp; in Pain too much for
                                                Thought It is now passed as I hope. . . . 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 779)<ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> On 29
                                                  April 1826, Linnell sold a copy of the 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings to “Mr George Young,
                                                  surgeon brother of [Charles Mayne] Young the
                                                  actor” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 600). But George is
                                                  probably not the Young of the letter, since he is
                                                  a surgeon and the designation “Doctor” suggests a
                                                  physician, as is still customary. The Young who
                                                  treated Blake was probably Dr. James Forbes Young,
                                                  a physician living in Lambeth, about 30 years old
                                                  at the time of Blake’s death. He was also a
                                                  licensed apothecary and an eminant botanist, which
                                                  is consistent with a prescription of dandelion, as
                                                  well as a print collector (<hi rend="i">Medical
                                                  Times</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> 46).
                                                  Fincham was probably Mr. George Fincham, a surgeon
                                                  who worked at Bartholomew’s Hospital and later
                                                  Westminister Hospital (<hi rend="i">The London and
                                                  Provincial Medical Directory</hi> 134). In a
                                                  postscript to his letter, Blake identifies him as
                                                  a “Pupil of Abernathy’s,” which gave him “great
                                                  pleasure” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 780). John
                                                  Abernathy was a prominent surgeon of the time at
                                                  St. Bartholomew’s Hospital and wrote a variety of
                                                  books on surgery. <p>A report in the 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Lancet</hi> recommends copper sulphate for the
                                                  treatment of dysentery (vol. 11, 524-25), which
                                                  raises the possibility that Blake may have been
                                                  treated with copper sulphate, since this treatment
                                                  was current during the final years of his
                                                  life.</p></note></q></p>
                                <p>Dandelion is a folk remedy used to stimulate the liver or to
                                        treat gallstones. The medicinal use of dandelion suggests
                                        that a liver or biliary problem might have been diagnosed as
                                        the cause of Blake’s symptoms prior to the development of
                                        the jaundice.</p>
                                <pb id="p30-41" n="41"/>
                                <p>Blake’s hopes for a visit were soon dashed by a new affliction.
                                        On 29 July 1826—about one year before his death—he described
                                        the new symptom: 
<q> Just as I had become Well. that is
                                                subdued the disease. tho not its Efects Weakness
                                                &amp;c Comes Another to hinder my Progress calld The
                                                Piles which when to the degree I have had them are a
                                                most sore plague &amp; on a Weak Body truly
                                                afflictive. These Piles have now also as I hope run
                                                their Period. &amp; I begin to again feel returning
                                                Strength. on these accounts I cannot yet tell when I
                                                can start for Hampstead like a young Lark without
                                                feathers. Two or Three days may be suficient or not,
                                                all now will depend on my bones &amp; sinews Muscle
                                                I have none but a few days may do &amp; have done
                                                miracles in the Case of a Convalescent who prepares
                                                himself ardently for his return to Life &amp; its
                                                Business among his Friends. (<hi rend="i">E</hi>
                                                780) </q></p>
                                <p>The development of hemorrhoids (piles) suggests that the
                                        sclerosing cholangitis has progressed to biliary
                                                cirrhosis.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> One of
                                                the consequences of cirrhosis is obstruction to the
                                                flow of blood through the liver. This leads to
                                                increased pressure and enlargement of the veins that
                                                drain into the liver. Because the hemorrhoidal veins
                                                drain into the liver, hemorrhoids are common in
                                                cirrhosis (Wyngaarden 792).</note></p>
                                <p>Blake’s optimistic diagnosis notwithstanding, he would never
                                        again return to his old vigorous self. He did, however, feel
                                        strong enough to visit the Linnells the following week. On 1
                                        August, he informs Linnell that he will set out on Thursday
                                        (3 August) in a 
<q> Cabriolet. for tho getting better &amp;
                                                stronger I am still incapable of riding in the Stage
                                                &amp; shall be I fear for some time being only bones
                                                &amp; sinews All strings &amp; bobbins like a
                                                Weavers Loom. Walking to &amp; from the Stage would
                                                be to me impossible tho I seem well being entirely
                                                free from both pain &amp; from that Sickness to
                                                which there is no name. Thank God I feel no more of
                                                it &amp; have great hopes that the Disease is Gone.
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 780-81) </q></p>
                                <p>It wasn’t. But even with his illness in remission, Blake had lost
                                        much weight and was left significantly weakened in body,
                                        though not in mind or inspiration. He brought the Dante
                                        drawings and continued to work on them 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
<figure n="MarriageEtching.30.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="693">
                                                <head>3 <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> plate 10 executed
                                                  as an etching, 15.3 × 10.1 cm; the design cut
                                                  through the ground with a needle.</head>
                                        </figure> 333). The use of a cabriolet—a two-wheeled,
                                        one-horse carriage with two seats and a folding top—was
                                        certainly out of character, but apparently necessary because
                                        it could provide door-to-door delivery and perhaps a more
                                        comfortable ride than the “rumble” and bouncing of the
                                        larger stage he so feared. In light of these concerns and
                                        his condition, the speculation that Blake visited Edward
                                        Calvert in Brixton the following month (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                        333) ought to give pause—or did Blake make similar
                                        arrangements for transportation?</p>
                                <p>By his own account, in letters and to Robinson on 7 December,
                                        Blake had been “very ill during the Summer” of 1826, and
                                        when Robinson told him of Flaxman’s recent death, Blake
                                        said: “I thought I should have gone first” 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 337). The fall held no improvement. No
                                        letters or documents from the fall of 1826 (September,
                                        October, and November) are extant, but a letter to Linnell
                                        from Edward Denny on 20 November regarding the 
                                                <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings acknowledges Linnell’s
concern
                                        for Blake’s health: “I am very sorry to hear that Mr Blake
                                        has been in danger, and sincerely hope that he is now in
                                        perfect health” (Keynes 165). The serious deterioration of
                                        Blake’s health was now apparent to himself and his friends.
                                        Indeed, the last year of his illness was a great physical
                                        challenge for Blake. Tatham writes: 
                                                <pb id="p30-42" n="42"/><q> About a year before he died he was
seized with
                                                a species of Ague, (as it was then termed[)], of
                                                which he was alternately better &amp; worse. He was
                                                at times very ill but rallied and all had hopes of
                                                him, indeed such was his energy that even then, tho’
                                                sometimes confined to his Bed, he sat up Drawing his
                                                most stupendous Works. (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 527)
                                        </q></p>
                                <p>Gilchrist comments that during the last year of his illness,
                                        Blake was “suffering from diarrhoea, or, perhaps, dysentery”
                                        (1: 353). As noted, Blake described himself as
                                        emaciated—“only bones and sinews All strings and bobbins
                                        like a Weavers Loom”—in his letter to Linnell on 1 August
                                        1826, one year before he died. Emaciation is a feature of
                                        sclerosing cholangitis, and weight loss develops in up to
                                        seventy-nine percent of individuals with this disease
                                        (Sherlock 250).</p>
                                <p>The long, final illness seems to have offered Blake little
                                        respite. To an invitation from Mrs. Aders, Blake responded
                                        on 29 December 1826: 
<q> . . . the least thing brings on the
                                                symptoms of the original complaint. he does not dare
                                                to leave his room by any means. he had another
                                                desperate attack of the Aguish trembling last night
                                                &amp; is certain that at present any venture to go
                                                out must be of bad perhaps of fatal consequence.
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 781) </q></p>
                                <p>Although his body was broken, his spirit never flagged. In
                                        response to Linnell’s request (on 7 February 1827) that he
                                        move to Cirencester Place, Blake wrote that he was 
<q>
                                                getting better every Morning but slowly. as I am
                                                still feeble &amp; tottering. tho all the Symptoms
                                                of my complaint seem almost gone as the fine weather
                                                is very beneficial &amp; comfortable to me I go on
                                                as I think improving my Engavings of Dante more
                                                &amp; more &amp; shall soon get Proofs. . . .<lb/>
 I
                                                have Thought &amp; Thought of the Removal. &amp;
                                                cannot get my Mind out of a State of terrible fear
                                                at such a step. the more I think the more I feel
                                                terror at what I wishd at first &amp; thought it a
                                                thing of benefit &amp; Good hope you will attribute
                                                it to its right Cause Intellectual Peculiarity that
                                                must be Myself alone shut up in Myself or Reduced to
                                                Nothing . . . . (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 782) </q></p>
                                <p>In refusing to move nearer Linnell, Blake seems more anxious
                                        about his work than his health. He also seems to want to
                                        reassure Linnell. A few days later, he walked to Cirencester
                                        Place carrying four large Dante plates, ostensibly “to
                                        prevent the trouble of [Linnell’s] Coming thro Curiosity to
                                        see what I was about,” and stated that he was “getting
                                        better or [he] could not have Come at all” 
                                                (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 782). The next letter, on 15 March, notes
                                        that he had received a letter from Cumberland, that Tatham
                                        senior paid him a visit, and that he was “getting on with
                                        the [Dante] Engravings,” but it does not mention his health
                                                (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 782).</p>
                                <p>He did not respond to Cumberland, who evidently posted his letter
                                        5 March (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 340), until 12 April 1827,
                                        writing his longest extant letter in over 20 years, one
                                        which reflects remarkably Blake’s awareness of his mortality
                                        and his tenacious belief in the imagination: 
<q> I have been
                                                very near the Gates of Death &amp; have returned
                                                very weak &amp; an Old Man feeble and tottering, but
                                                not in Spirit &amp; Life not in The Real Man The
                                                Imagination which Liveth for Ever. In that I am
                                                stronger &amp; stronger as this Foolish Body decays.
                                                  (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 783) </q></p>
                                <p>During these days, Blake “was frequently bolstered up in his bed”
                                        to work (Gilchrist 1: 359). But he must have had relatively
                                        long periods out of bed as well, since engraving the Dante
                                        plates required a table or workbench, as did Cumberland’s
                                        calling card, which he assured Cumberland he would “do as
                                        soon as Possible,” using his poor health as an excuse for
                                        the delay: “when you Consider that I have been reduced to a
                                        Skeleton from which I am slowly recovering you will I hope
                                        have Patience with me” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 784).</p>
                                <p>And Blake continued to print a few illuminated books. As he told
                                        Cumberland: “I am now Printing a Set of the Songs of
                                        Innocence &amp; Experience for a Friend at Ten Guineas which
                                        I cannot do under Six Months consistent with my other Work,
                                        so that I have little hope of doing any more of such things”
                                                (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 784). Nevertheless, Blake
                                        enclosed a list of books he was willing to reprint and their
                                        prices. The copy of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> was probably
                                        copy X, which Thomas G. Wainwright had ordered in February
                                        1827 through Linnell (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 339). Blake was
                                        working on it “consistent with . . . other work,” which
                                        probably included copy I of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                                                Heaven and Hell</hi>, also for Wainwright, and the
                                        Dante drawings and engravings. Blake did not list 
                                                <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> or mention the Dante
                                        engravings, but he mentioned <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
                                        “the Last Work [he] produced,” observing that to print and
                                        finish it like the one he had (i.e., 
                                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E) would “Cost [in] Time
the
                                        amount of Twenty Guineas” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 784). Though
                                        “reduced to a Skeleton,” Blake visited the connoisseur and
                                        collector William Young Ottley with Linnell five days after
                                        writing Cumberland, on 17 April, in the hope of securing a
                                        commission. The following week, on 25 April, he thanked
                                        Linnell “for the prospect of Mr Ottleys advantageous
                                        acquaintance,” and assured him that he is “going on better
                                        Every day . . . in hea[l]th &amp; in Work,” but also admits
                                        that he goes 
<q> on without daring to count on Futurity.
                                                which I cannot do without Doubt &amp; Fear that
                                                ruins Activity &amp; are the greatest hurt to an
                                                Artist such as I am . . . . I am too much attachd to
                                                Dante to think much of any thing else . . . [and]
                                                count myself sufficiently Paid If I live as I now do
                                                &amp; only fear that I may be unlucky to my friends
                                                . . . . (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 784) </q><pb
                                                id="p30-43" n="43"/> Ottley came through,
                                        commissioning copy F of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, a
                                        monochrome copy for which he paid £5 5s.0d. Linnell records
                                        receiving this payment and giving the money to Mrs. Blake on
                                        11 August (Keynes 149, <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 594)—one day
                                        before Blake died, and one day after Linnell had visited
                                        Blake and recorded in his journal that he was “Not expected
                                        to live” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 341). Apparently, Blake was
                                        either too weak or perhaps not awake to make the business
                                        transaction, as he normally did.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
                                                type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Linnell always insisted on payment before
                                                the delivery of goods, which in this case may have
                                                proved especially fortuitous, because £5 5s.
                                                combined with the £5 Mrs. Blake borrowed from
                                                Linnell on the day Blake died (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                                606) would have covered almost all of the £10 18s.
                                                cost of Blake’s funeral (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 343).
                                                Linnell records giving Mrs. Blake this sum on 26
                                                January 1828 for the funeral (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                                595), but it is not clear if he is reimbursing her
                                                or paying the bill over five months after services
                                                were rendered. There is no evidence that the bill
                                                was deferred by the undertaker, though that is
                                                certainly plausible, nor is it clear why Linnell
                                                would pay such a bill indirectly and thereby require
                                                Mrs. Blake to play messenger. <p>Linnell retrieved
                                                  <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy F only partially
                                                  numbered but clearly in 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s “first order,” and he
proceeded
                                                  to order its 100 unbound leaves according to his
                                                  copy (C), which was in the “second order.”
                                                  Preparing the copy for Ottley required Linnell to
                                                  erase and change some of Blake’s numbers as well
                                                  as add those missing, thereby inadvertently
                                                  altering Blake’s intentions (Viscomi, 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> chap. 34).</p></note></p>
                                <p>There are no extant letters from Blake in May and June, and
                                        perhaps that is a good sign, pointing to the period in which
                                        he printed <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and finished
                                        Wainwright’s commissions. He did feel healthy enough to
                                        visit Hampstead at the end of June—the visit that Blake
                                        believed “brought on a relapse” and the jaundice that he
                                        described on 3 July 1827. Blake was bedridden during his
                                        last days. According to Tatham, “In August he gradually grew
                                        worse &amp; required much more of his Wife’s attention,
                                        indeed he was decaying fast; his patience during his agonies
                                        of pain is described to have been exemplary” 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 528). By 10 August, he was completely
                                        bedridden. According to Gilchrist, “his illness was not
                                        violent, but a gradual and gentle failure of physical
                                        powers, which no wise affected the mind. The speedy end was
                                        not foreseen by his friends.” When it came, on 12 August,
                                        Blake “lay chaunting Songs to Melodies, both the inspiration
                                        of the moment. . . . To the pious Songs followed, about six
                                        in the summer evening, a calm and painless withdrawal of
                                        breath; the exact moment almost unperceived by his wife, who
                                        sat by his side (Gilchrist 1: 360-61). The first obituary,
                                        published on 18 August 1827 in the <hi rend="i">Literary
                                                Gazette</hi> (and republished five times with minor
                                        variations; see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 350n1), reported that
                                        Blake “died as he had lived, piously, cheerfully, talking
                                        calmly, and finally resigning himself to his eternal rest
                                        like an infant to its sleep” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 355).<ref
                                                target="n16" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi
                                                  rend="s">16</hi> Three days after Blake died,
                                                Richmond related a slightly different account of his
                                                last moments to Samuel Palmer: “Just before he died
                                                His countenance became fair—His eyes Brighten’d and
                                                He burst out in singing of the things he saw in
                                                Heaven” (Keynes 165).</note></p>
                                <figure n="MarriageBitingFacsimile.30.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="311">
                                        <head>4 Biting the facsimile etching of 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> plate 10 in nitric acid and
                                                feathering away gas bubbles.</head>
                                </figure>
                                <p>Needless to say, these various accounts of Blake’s last days
                                        raise more questions than they answer. Was Blake’s final
                                        illness as nonviolent and its culmination as peaceful as
                                        Gilchrist and the obituary notice suggest, or was it, as
                                        Tatham states, accompanied with “agonies of pain,” with only
                                        the last hours peaceful, when his “spirit departed like the
                                        sighing of a gentle breeze” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 528)? Did
                                        he find the energy and inspiration one last time to compose
                                        and sing melodies just before dying?</p>
                                <p>Tatham’s and Gilchrist’s descriptions are probably both correct,
                                        though they are of different stages of the illness. And both
                                        biographers are almost certainly incorrect about the
                                        deathbed scene. As noted, Linnell visited Blake two days
                                        before he died and knew that he was “Not expected to live.”
                                        From this journal entry and her belief that Blake died from
                                        a ruptured gallbladder (15), Ward infers that Blake was
                                        probably in a semi-comatose state (14). If correct—and we
                                        think it is, though not for the reasons Ward gives—that
                                        condition alone casts suspicion on the legend that Blake
                                        burst into song on his deathbed. In a provocative article
                                        examining the effect that stereotypes and archetypes of
                                        artists and heroes have had on Blake biographers (including
                                        Carlyle’s idea of the artist-as-hero on his disciple,
                                        Gilchrist), Ward argues that the legend is a version of the
                                        “myth of the death of the hero” (14). She traces its various
                                        forms—through Richmond, Smith, Cunningham, Tatham, and
                                        Gilchrist—to the same source, Catherine Blake, who, Ward
                                        argues, may have been the only witness, despite Richmond’s
                                        description of an unidentified person standing by (14 and
                                        n28). Ward is particularly suspicious of Tatham, as a person
                                        and biographer. At a full page, Tatham’s conflation of other
                                        deathbed accounts “pulled out all the stops,” with Blake
                                        coloring a print of the Ancient of Days, then sketching a
                                        portrait of Catherine, then singing hallelujahs and songs of
                                        joy “loudly &amp; with true extatic energy” 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 528), and then suggesting to Catherine
that
                                        Tatham ought to manage her affairs, to which Ward responds:
                                        “This of a man 
<pb id="p30-44" n="44"/>
dying of a ruptured
                                        gallbladder with attendant peritonitis!” (15).</p>
                                <p>While her skepticism of Tatham’s account for medical reasons is
                                        justified, Ward’s unreferenced diagnosis is mistaken and
                                        actually contradicts her claim that Blake was semi-comatose
                                        during his last few days. After the gall bladder ruptures,
                                        the bacteria in the gall bladder spill out into the
                                        abdominal cavity and cause peritonitis (the <corr type="emend">inflammation</corr> or
                                        infection of the membrane lining the walls of the abdominal
                                        cavity). Neither a ruptured gallbladder nor peritonitis
                                        accounts for the piles or the emaciation, but both would be
                                        very painful. Untreated, the patient develops septic shock,
                                        blood pressure falls, blood perfusion to the brain
                                        decreases, and unconsciousness (coma) intervenes for several
                                        hours, not days, prior to death.</p>
                                <p>Blake likely died of complications due to biliary cirrhosis
                                        possibly caused by sclerosing cholangitis, and not a
                                        ruptured gallblader with peritonitis. If we return to the
                                        obituary notice, we can discern a few important but
                                        overlooked clues about Blake’s final illness supporting this
                                        hypothesis. The notice states that Blake’s 
<q> . . . .
                                                ancles frightfully swelled, his chest [was]
                                                disordered, old age striding on, his wants
                                                increased, but not his miserable means and
                                                appliances: even yet was his eye undimmed, the fire
                                                of his imagination unquenched, and the preternatural
                                                never-resting activity of his mind unflagging. 
                                                  (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 349) </q></p>
                                <p>The swollen ankles and the disordered chest were likely due to
                                        fluid retention in the legs and lungs, respectively, a
                                        common terminal event which occurs in individuals with liver
                                        failure from any cause. The disordered chest suggests
                                        breathing difficulties likely due to pulmonary edema. Blake
                                        was 69 years old with old coronary arteries and old lungs
                                        (perhaps abnormal from the etching fumes), and he probably
                                        developed the pulmonary edema slowly over weeks or months,
                                        likely adjusting his activities and sleeping position to
                                        accommodate the fluid accumulating in his lungs. A
                                        semi-comatose state is consistent with this diagnosis, and
                                        it would likely have set in a day or two before Blake died,
                                        which is also consistent with Linnell’s comments on 10
                                        August. If this were Blake’s condition, then it is unlikely
                                        that he awoke in his last hours with the energy to color,
                                        draw, sing, and talk. Far more likely, he entered “his
                                        eternal rest like an infant to its sleep,” and, while
                                        asleep, experienced “a calm and painless withdrawal of
                                        breath.” A believable scenario is that Blake went to sleep,
                                        his breathing slowed, an episode of apnea developed, and he
                                        never breathed again. Alternatively, Blake went to sleep,
                                        his breathing slowed, his blood oxygen level decreased, he
                                        experienced a heart attack, and he never woke up.</p>
                                <p>Hence, Gilchrist’s description of a peaceful death is probably
                                        accurate, whereas Tatham’s phrase “agonies of pain”
                                        describes not the last days but much of the last year of
                                        Blake’s 
<figure n="MarriageReliefEtching.30.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="697">
                                                <head>5 Facsimile of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>
                                                  plate 10 as relief etching, 15.2 × 10 cm; pouring
                                                  acid onto the diked plate.</head>
                                        </figure> life, particularly the weeks and months leading to
                                        the final days. Blake’s “gnawing Pain in the Stomach” (19
                                        May 1826), “paroxysms” (5 July 1826), “Species of Delireum,”
                                        and “Pain too much for Thought” (16 July 1826) are not what
                                        killed him; they are the “old Symptoms” he talks about six
                                        months before he died and which accompany IBD or sclerosing
                                        cholangitis, or both (see Table).</p>
                                <p>Pulmonary edema was probably the final or absolute cause of
                                        death, but it resulted from liver failure due to biliary
                                        cirrhosis, itself probably caused by sclerosing cholangitis.
                                        But what caused the sclerosing cholangitis?</p>
                                <p>As we have seen, with the exception of Wordsworth’s offending
                                        passages, Blake appears consistently to have blamed his poor
                                        health, both in youth and old age, on the northern air. But
                                        Tatham gave another, even more peculiar, cause. He states
                                        that “it has been supposed that [Blake’s] Excessive labour
                                        without the exercise he used formerly to take, (having
                                        relinquished the habit of taking very long Walks) brought on
                                        the complaint which afterwards consumed him” 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 527). Tatham appears to confuse effects
                                        with cause, since Blake postponed his relatively long walk
                                        to Hampstead only when physically incapable of making it.
                                        Moreover, what Tatham means by “very long Walks” is not
                                        clear. He states that 
<pb id="p30-45" n="45"/>
<figure n="MarriageReliefFacsimile.30.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="688">
                                                <head>6 Facsimile of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>
                                                  plate 10 as relief etching; feathering the plate
                                                  in the nitric acid bath to remove gas bubbles;
                                                  detail.</head>
                                        </figure>
<q> in his youth [Blake] and his Wife would start
                                                in the Morning early, &amp; walk out 20 miles &amp;
                                                dine at some pretty &amp; sequestered Inn &amp;
                                                would return the same day home having travelled 40
                                                miles. Mrs Blake would do this without excessive
                                                fatigue. Blake has been known to walk 50 Miles in
                                                the day, but being told by some Physician, that such
                                                long walks were injurious, he discontinued them,
                                                &amp; went so far to the other extreme, that it has
                                                been said he remained in the House, so long that
                                                [it] was considered far from extraordinary his days
                                                were shortened. (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 527) </q></p>
                                <p>As noted, by “youth” Tatham seems to refer to the same period
                                        Blake spoke of in 1826, when Blake recalled that “When [he]
                                        was young Hampstead Highgate Hornsea Muswell Hill &amp; even
                                        Islington &amp; all places North of London always laid me up
                                        the day after . . . [with] the same Complaint &amp; the same
                                        torment of the Stomach.” All of these locales, though, are
                                        well within a 20-mile radius of Blake’s home. While it is
                                        apparent that he enjoyed long walks for most of his life, it
                                        seems unlikely that Blake, who boasted that he “never
                                        suspended his Labours on Copper for a single day” 
                                                (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 568), would have ever made a “habit”
                                        of walking 40 or more miles in a day, which translates,
                                        minimally, into 10 to 14 hours of hiking. Even the young
                                        Wordsworth, an exceptionally strong walker, covered 20-25
                                        miles per day on his Tintern Abbey tour (Hayden 78). Tatham
                                        probably exaggerates the length, if not also the frequency,
                                        of Blake’s hikes, exaggerating perhaps not as much as in the
                                        deathbed scene but for the same reason, to present Blake as
                                        transcending normal physical as well as mental
                                        limitations.</p>
                                <p>Tatham’s implication that Blake had discontinued long walks late
                                        in his life is clearly refuted by Blake’s trips to
                                        Hampstead. So is his implication that Blake “remained in the
                                        House, so long that [it] was considered far from
                                        extraordinary his days were shortened.” Tatham clearly
                                        places Blake’s housebound period close to his death, which
                                        suggests that he may have wanted to hide the fact that Blake
                                        regularly visited Linnell, from whom Tatham was estranged.
                                        Smith is presumably referring to the same period in Blake’s
                                        life, though he does not date it, when he states: “so
                                        steadfastly attentive was he to his beloved tasks, that for
                                        the space of two years he had never once been out of his
                                        house; and his application was often so incessant, that in
                                        the middle of the night, he would, after thinking deeply
                                        upon a particular subject, leap from his bed and write for
                                        two hours or more” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 475). The idea of
                                        Blake staying indoors for two years is, as Bentley notes, an
                                        unconfirmed “extraordinary story,” which, if true, may have
                                        occurred in “1813-14, when almost nothing is known about
                                        Blake” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 475n2). But it seems more
                                        plausible that Smith is alluding to the same period that
                                        Tatham describes. Smith’s description of Blake’s writing
                                        process echoes Blake’s own version of it as told to
                                        Robinson, 18 February 1826 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 322), and
                                        this too suggests that he had old Blake in mind. If so,
                                        Smith uncharacteristically exaggerated, or perhaps merely
                                        misunderstood Mrs. Blake’s summary of Blake’s last two
                                        years, when long walks to Hampstead were seriously curtailed
                                        but work was not. To a widowed care-taker and a biographer,
                                        perhaps Blake appeared housebound relative to his earlier
                                        peripatetic and social self.</p>
                                <p>As causes of Blake’s illness, we can rule out the air of London’s
                                        northern villages and the combination of excessive work and
                                        lack of exercise. We cannot rule out Blake’s profession as
                                        an engraver, however, because of the theoretical connection
                                        between sclerosing cholangitis and copper intoxication. As
                                        noted, Blake confirmed his considerable exposure to copper,
                                        stating in 1809 that he had never, “during a Period of Forty
                                        Years . . . suspended his Labours on Copper for a single
                                        day” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 568). This claim is somewhat
                                        hyperbolic, since Blake did not take up engraving until 1772
                                        and appears to have had a hiatus in 1799 
                                                (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 704). But given that some of the 
                                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plates may be as late as c.
                                        1820 and that the 22 plates of the <hi rend="i">Book of
                                                Job</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, and the
                                        seven incomplete Dante engravings were executed between 1823
                                        and 1827, it is no exaggeration to say that Blake was
                                        exposed to copper for 55 of his 69 years. But surely, other
                                        engravers were exposed to copper for extensive 
                                                <pb id="p30-46" n="46"/>
periods as well. In the absence
                                        of epidemiological studies on nineteenth-century engravers
                                        and data on their livers and deaths, is this theoretical
                                        connection worth pursuing? We believe it is, because it will
                                        provide the grounds for further research on Blake’s death
                                        and because it will illuminate where and how Blake differed
                                        from his fellow engravers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> It is
                                                controversial whether chronic copper intoxication
                                                can cause or aggravate sclerosing cholangitis.
                                                Although a recent review does not mention the role
                                                of copper in the pathogenesis of sclerosing
                                                cholangitis, there are numerous reports of excess
                                                copper in the livers of patients with this disease
                                                and several authors who speculate that excess copper
                                                might at least aggravate the condition. To our
                                                knowledge, there is no data to prove or disprove the
                                                possible role of copper in sclerosing cholangitis.
                                                There is data to support the role of chronic copper
                                                ingestion as the cause of Indian Childhood
                                                Cirrhosis, a cause of liver failure in Indian
                                                children believed to be acquired by drinking water
                                                from inadequately tinned copper vessels. Cirrhosis
                                                develops in patients with Vineyard Sprayer’s
                                                Disease, which is considered to be due to the
                                                inhalation of copper salts in fungicides. There are
                                                several animal models of liver failure that develop
                                                due to chronic exposure to copper, including sheep
                                                and Bedlington Terriers. <p>There are numerous
                                                  reports of acute copper intoxication due to the
                                                  inhalation of copper. Metal fume fever is caused
                                                  by the inhalation of copper by welders and
                                                  presents itself with fever, chills, nausea,
                                                  vomiting, cough, muscular pain, headache,
                                                  weakness, and a metallic taste. The symptoms
                                                  usually abate in 24 to 72 hours (Armstrong). An
                                                  early report describes Brass Founder’s Ague, using
                                                  the same terminology Blake used to describe his
                                                  “old symptoms” or “original complaint”
                                                  (Burstein).</p></note></p>
                                <p>On 4 August 1772, at 14 years of age, Blake began his seven year
                                        apprenticeship to the engraver James Basire 
                                                (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 9).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
                                        Like all others of his craft, he learned all the stages of
                                        engraving and, because during this period original and
                                        reproductive engravings began as etchings, executed in a
                                        technique known as “mixed-method,” Blake learned all the
                                        steps of etching as well. He learned to draw for the
                                        printmakers, to cut plates out of sheets of copper, prepare
                                        the plates to accept etching grounds, to transfer drawings
                                        onto plates, to make inks and stop-out varnishes, to use and
                                        sharpen diversely shaped burins and needles, to prepare
                                        paper for printing, and to use a rolling press. And he
                                        learned how to mix, dilute, and use nitric acid. By the time
                                        he invented relief-etching in 1788, he had over 16 years of
                                        experience in engraving and etching. This means 16 years of
                                        handling copper and being exposed to the fumes from the
                                        chemical reaction of nitric acid and copper. Other engravers
                                        were exposed to these fumes as well, and in normal
                                        etching—if done correctly—the fumes were weak. Their
                                        potential for harm, however, increased substantially with
                                        relief etching. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> For
                                                information about Blake’s apprenticeship and the
                                                techniques of engraving, etching, and relief
                                                etching, see Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake,
                                                  Printmaker</hi> (3-38) and Viscomi, 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> chaps. 1-15.</note></p>
                                <p>In standard practice, the hand-hammered copper plate is prepared
                                        for engraving by being first planed to a smooth surface with
                                        water and charcoal, pumice stones, and metal burnishers. It
                                        is then polished with a tightly rolled piece of felt using
                                        oil as the lubricant. The plate is then cleaned of oily
                                        residue by being thoroughly rubbed with whiting or
                                        breadcrumbs mixed with water. The “degreased” plate can now
                                        accept an etching ground, an acid-resistent mixture of wax
                                        and resins melted onto the plate and spread into a thin
                                        film. The design’s outline is transferred onto this covering
                                        ground and then scratched through with a needle. The metal
                                        beneath the ground is now exposed and can be etched with
                                        acid. The purpose of the etch is to place the lines lightly
                                        into the plate to facilitate the engraver’s burin. In the
                                        seventeenth-century, the ground was very hard and the acid
                                        was vinegar-based, and the needle used to cut lines had an
                                        oval tip that could cut lines that swelled like those cut
                                        with burins. The plate was etched by being placed on an
                                        easel or trough and having acid poured over it (illus. 1).
                                        These materials and etching technique, however, were long
                                        out of fashion when Blake began to learn the trade. They
                                        were replaced with a softer, more supple ground and pointed
                                        etching needles, with true nitric acid, and with a new way
                                        of applying the acid. Plates were diked with wax to hold
                                        acid, which was poured on its surface (illus. 2). This new
                                        method required that the plate be watched carefully while
                                        being etched, because nitric acid cuts laterally as well as
                                        vertically, which means that it can cut under lines and
                                        thereby ruin fine line work or hatching. Nitric acid can
                                        also ruin the design by <corr type="emend">coarsening</corr>
                                        lines or pitting or lifting (“foulbiting”) parts of the 
                                        etching ground. To prevent these effects, an etcher or 
                                        assistant passed a feather over the design to release 
                                        the gas bubbles or “the froth or scum, which gather upon 
                                        . . . strokes of hatchings whilst the water performs its operation” 
                                        (<hi rend="i">Sculptura</hi> 91; Faithorne 35). Even in pure
                                        etchings, like caricature prints or aquatints, the amount of
                                        copper exposed to nitric acid was relatively minimal (illus.
                                        3, 4), and the acid was diluted at least three to one and
                                        carefully regulated. Depending on the acid’s strength and
                                        the etcher’s objective, the plate would have remained in the
                                        acid continuously for 15 to 40 minutes.</p>
                                <p>Like his contemporaries, Blake would have been exposed to copper
                                        particles and dust that were released into the air by
                                        cutting plates from sheets and from preparing plates by
                                        planing, burnishing, and polishing. These amounts, like
                                        those from etching plates in the normal manner, were
                                        probably negligible. Blake’s exposure to copper dust and
                                        fumes, however, as well as to nitric oxide and dioxide,
                                        increased enormously when he etched plates in relief.
                                        Blake’s technique required a stronger acid and a much longer
                                        bite, upwards of eight hours or more, while still requiring
                                        a fairly constant check. Furthermore, because only the lines
                                        of the design are covered in an acid-resistant ground, the
                                        amount of copper exposed to the acid was many times that of
                                        normal etching (illus. 5, 6). The more metal acid bites, the
                                        hotter and more active it becomes and thus the greater the
                                        chance of foulbiting. Blake’s “corrosives,” or “corroding
                                        fire,” lay on the walled-in plate about “half a finger’s
                                        breadth all over” (Faithorne 33), turned blue, and bubbled
                                        along 
<pb id="p30-47" n="47"/>
the relief lines. This kind
                                        of active bite would have prevented the plate “from being
                                        seen” (Dossie 2: 166). Given the amount of metal exposed,
                                        the bite must have been very active, probably enough to have
                                        become cloudy and emitted much higher than usual amounts of
                                        nitric oxide and dioxide, “which in hell” may be “salutary
                                        and medicinal,” but on earth are potentially hazardous.
                                        Blake may be alluding to such fiery biting when he asserts
                                        that “melting apparent surfaces away, and displaying the
                                        infinite which was hid” characterized “printing in the
                                        infernal method” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 39). To prevent his
                                        plates from being pockmarked by the strong acid, Blake may
                                        have added sal ammoniac to his nitric, which “has the
                                        peculiar property of causing the aquafortis to bite more
                                        directly downwards and less laterally” (Fielding 212).
                                        Nitric diluted with sulphuric acid (“oil of vitriol”) 10
                                        parts to one, and then five parts water to two parts acid,
                                        makes “an aquafortis that will consume the copper more
                                        keenly and cleanly than a purer spirit of nitre, without
                                        leaving any roughness or frosted appearance in the lines”
                                        (Dossie 2: 150). But none of these additives eliminates the
                                        need to feather the plate while it is being etched. Blake
                                        appears to allude to feathering plates in the “Printing
                                        house in Hell,” where this stage—and, metonymically,
                                        etching—occurs in the third chamber: “Eagles with wings and
                                        feathers of air . . . caused the inside of the cave to be
                                        infinite” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 40). But a constant watch and
                                        careful feathering could also have been disadvantageous to
                                        Blake’s health, for it meant inhaling noxious fumes for
                                        hours at a time (illus. 2).</p>
                                <p>That Blake singled out the etching stage of his new technique in
                                                <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
                                        suggests that he knew he was working without precedent. He
                                        certainly was working in homes with poor ventilation (see
                                        illustrations in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 560 and 562, and
                                        Keynes plate 23). His plates required a new kind of etch,
                                        which Blake could have perfected only through trial and
                                        error, learning “what is enough” by knowing “what is more
                                        than enough” (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> plate 9). Blake’s
                                        “infernal method” assured excessive exposure to the noxious
                                        fumes produced by the chemical reaction between nitric acid
                                        and copper. This exposure was not continuous, but it was
                                        intense for brief periods; hence, supposing that it may have
                                        weakened his immune system and contributed to his IBD seems
                                                reasonable.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> We hope
                                                to supplement the current study with data drawn from
                                                testing air samples from the various stages in the
                                                etching and relief etching processes for copper dust
                                                and fumes and nitric oxide and dioxide. We intend to
                                                compare these samples with those established by
                                                environmental agencies like EPA and thereby refute
                                                or confirm scientifically our supposition that Blake
                                                inhaled dangerous amounts of copper dust and fumes
                                                and nitric dioxide.</note></p>
                                <p>Between 1788 and 1790, Blake etched <hi rend="i">All Religions
                                                are One, There is No Natural Religion, Songs of
                                                Innocence, The Book of Thel</hi>, and 
                                                <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> plus 
                                                <table rows="3" cols="3">
                                                <head>Table: Blake’s symptoms and the various
                                                  diseases to which they are related.</head>
                                                <row>
                                                  <cell><hi rend="b">Disease</hi> Inflammatory Bowel
                                                  Disease (IBD)</cell>
                                                  <cell><hi rend="b">Blake’s Symptoms</hi> Abdominal
                                                  pain, diarrhea, weight loss, occasionally can
                                                  cause fever</cell>
                                                  <cell><hi rend="b">Comment</hi></cell>
                                                </row>
                                                <row>
                                                  <cell>Sclerosing cholangitis (SC)</cell>
                                                  <cell>Abdominal pain, chills and fever, weight
                                                  loss, emaciation, jaundice</cell>
                                                  <cell>develops commonly in patients with
                                                  IBD</cell>
                                                </row>
                                                <row>
                                                  <cell>Biliary cirrhosis</cell>
                                                  <cell>Piles, jaundice</cell>
                                                  <cell>develops commonly in patients with SC</cell>
                                                </row>
                                        </table> three or four separate plates for a total of about
                                        100 plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref> After a
                                        two-year hiatus, Blake executed <hi rend="i">Visions of the
                                                Daughters of Albion, America, a Prophecy, Europe, a
                                                Prophecy, The Book of Urizen</hi>, and 
                                                <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> between 1793 and 1795 for a
                                        total of 84 mostly large plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
                                                type="note">21</ref> Blake appears to have etched
                                        plates in batches; he did not have to wait till all the
                                        plates of a book were executed, nor did he need to etch one
                                        plate at a time as soon as it was executed (Viscomi,
                                        “Evolution,” forthcoming). Etching plates in groups greatly
                                        increased Blake’s exposure to the copper and noxious fumes
                                        released by a strong and long etch. 
                                                  <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> The separate plates
include 
                                                  <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> and possibly
                                                  <hi rend="i">Joseph Preaching to the Inhabitants
                                                  of Britain</hi> (both c. 1788); “The Divine Image”
                                                and possibly “To Tirzah” both c. 1790 (Viscomi,
                                                “Evolution” n17).</note></p>
                                <p>During the first period of illuminated book production Blake was
                                        31-33 years old, and during the second he was 36-38. Is
                                        this, the Blake of the late 1780s and early 1790s, the
                                        “young” Blake who regularly experienced “the same Complaint
                                        &amp; the same torment of the Stomach” as the 68-year-old
                                        man reflecting on 1 February 1826? Perhaps to an old man it
                                        is, and Tatham’s account of Blake’s long walks with his wife
                                        supports that hypthosis. There is no documentary evidence to
                                        prove it, though. Neither of the two personal letters extant
                                        before 1797 (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 699-700) mentions his
                                        health, and Blake claims on 11 December 1805 that he “was
                                        alive &amp; in health &amp; with the same Talents” in the
                                        1790s, “the time of Boydell’s Macklins Boyers &amp; other
                                        Great Works” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 766-67). On the other
                                        hand, “in health” must be read in light of his saying that
                                        his “Constitution” was “a good one” despite its having “many
                                        peculiarities,” like stomach cramps, that no one” but
                                        himself could know (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 775).</p>
                                <pb id="p30-48" n="48"/>
                                <p>Blake may have experienced episodes of acute copper intoxication
                                        after intense periods of etching, and some of Blake’s
                                        symptoms—“the same Complaint &amp; the same torment of the
                                        Stomach” that laid him up “the day after &amp; sometimes
                                        [for] two or three days”—could fit with the delayed effects
                                        of acute copper intoxication (see n17). It is tempting to
                                        speculate that Blake’s walks to the villages north of London
                                        were prompted by his need for fresh air after etching plates
                                        in strong acid all day long for a week or more. It is
                                        tempting because the symptoms of acute copper intoxication
                                        include nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhea, blood in
                                        the urine, and jaundice. Some of the symptoms (nausea,
                                        vomiting, abdominal pain) develop in the first day, but
                                        others develop after one (diarrhea, blood in the urine) or
                                        even several days (jaundice).</p>
                                <p>Blake took a long rest before etching relief plates again. The
                                        next two projects, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
                                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, contain between them 50 mid-size
                                        and 100 large plates, but they were done over a number of
                                        years. Both are dated 1804, but the former was probably not
                                        finished until c. 1811 and the latter not until c. 1820
                                        (Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> chap. 32, 34). Cumberland,
                                        however, reported in the summer of 1807 that Blake had “engd
                                        60 Plates of a new Prophecy!” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 187). Is
                                        he referring to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> or a mixture of
                                        the two books? Apparently, Blake had etched at least 60
                                        plates of one or both works in three years, which would have
                                        been a period of etching as sustained as the previous two.
                                        After that, he appears not to have been in any hurry to
                                        finish <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
                                <p>The relatively vast amounts of copper exposed to acid in
                                        illuminated plates differentiates Blake’s technique from all
                                        others and subjected Blake to more noxious fumes than any of
                                        his contemporary printmakers. Another difference between
                                        Blake and other engravers is his late engraving style. The
                                        22 plates to <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and the seven Dante
                                        plates are pure engravings, which means that Blake worked
                                        directly into the metal without the aid of preliminary
                                        etching. The <hi rend="i">Job</hi> plates, contracted in
                                        March 1823 and finished in March 1826 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                        277, 327), are all extensively engraved, providing Blake
                                        with his most extended and sustained exposure to copper in
                                        his last years and probably in more than a dozen years. Is
                                        it mere coincidence that Blake’s health began to decline
                                        while he was engraving them? Could they have exacerbated the
                                        illness that had lain <corr type="emend">dormant</corr> for years? 
                                        Or were the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and Dante engravings executed as
                                        pure engravings, without preliminary etching, because Blake
                                        had made a connection between the noxious fumes and his “old
                                        symptoms”? Was the choice of technique, in other words,
                                        determined by Blake’s desire to avoid etching or to emulate
                                        the style of the “ancient” engravers whom he was then
                                        re-examining with Linnell?<ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> This
                                                number includes the four rejected plates of 
                                                  <hi rend="i">America</hi> but counts <hi rend="i">Song
                                                  of Los</hi> as six instead of eight plates,
                                                because its plates 3 and 4 were the left and right
                                                sides of an uncut oblong folio-size plate, as were
                                                plates 6 and 7 (Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                                                414n25).</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi>
                                                Essick has argued in <hi rend="i">William Blake,
                                                  Printmaker</hi> that Blake’s late style of pure
                                                engraving was influenced by his and Linnell’s study
                                                of early Italian and German engravings (219 passim).
                                                In private correspondence, he raises the possibility
                                                of the choice being driven by health.</note></p>
                                <p>On 27 January 1804, Blake predicted to William Hayley that “if
                                        God blesses me with health [I] doubt not yet to make a
                                        Figure in the Great Dance of Life that shall amuse the
                                        Spectators in the Sky” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 741). That he
                                        has done, and would have even if all he produced were those
                                        “stupendous Works” of his last years, when his health had
                                        significantly declined. The available evidence suggests that
                                        Blake might have had IBD, a condition that commonly precedes
                                        sclerosing cholangitis, and that he probably died from
                                        biliary cirrhosis caused by sclerosing cholangitis. Chronic
                                        copper intoxication is a theoretical cause or aggravating
                                        factor in the pathogenesis of sclerosing cholangitis,
                                        raising the possibility that Blake died due to a disease
                                        acquired during his years of relief-etching.</p>
                                <div2>
                                        <head>
                                                <title>
                                                  <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
                                                </title>
                                        </head>
                                        <p>Anon. “Case Reports at St. Thomas Hospital,” 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Lancet</hi> 11(1826): 534-??.</p>
                                        <p>Armstrong, C. W. et al. “An Outbreak of Metal Fume
                                                Fever.” <hi rend="i">Journal of Occupational
                                                  Medicine</hi> 25 (1983): 886-88.</p>
                                        <p>Bentley, G. E. Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi>
                                                Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1969.</p>
                                        <p>Burstein, A. “Brassfounders’ Ague.” <hi rend="i">Journal
                                                  of Industrial Hygiene</hi> 7 (1925): 110.</p>
                                        <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings
                                                  of William Blake.</hi> New Haven: Yale University
                                                Press, 1981.</p>
                                        <p>Clutterbuck, Henry. “Of Complicated Fever.” 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Lancet</hi> 11 (1826): 756.</p>
                                        <p>—. “Periodical Fever.” <hi rend="i">Lancet</hi> 11
                                                (1826): 760.</p>
                                        <p>Dossie, Robert. <hi rend="i">The Handmaid to the
                                                  Arts.</hi> 2nd ed. 2 vols. London, 1764.</p>
                                        <p>Elliotson, John. “Ague.” <hi rend="i">Lancet</hi> 12
                                                (1827): 140-141.</p>
                                        <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry
                                                  and Prose of William Blake.</hi> New York:
                                                Doubleday, 1988.</p>
                                        <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake,
                                                  Printmaker.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University
                                                Press, 1980.</p>
                                        <p>Essick, Robert N. and Joseph Viscomi, eds. 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Milton, a Poem and the Last Illuminated
                                                  Works.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                                                1993.</p>
                                        <p>Faithorne, William. <hi rend="i">The Art of Graveing and
                                                  Etching.</hi> 2nd ed. London, 1702.</p>
                                        <p>Fielding, T. H. <hi rend="i">The Art of Etching.</hi>
                                                London, 1844.</p>
                                        <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William
                                                  Blake.</hi> London: MacMillan, 1863.</p>
                                        <p>Gross, John B., et al. “Abnormalities in Tests of Copper
                                                Metabolism in Primary Sclerosing Cholangitis.” 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Gastroenterology</hi> 89 (1985):
                                                272-78.</p>
                                        <p>Hayden, Donald E. <hi rend="i">Wordsworth’s Travels in
                                                  Wales and Ireland.</hi> Tulsa, Oklahoma:
                                                University of Tulsa Press, 1985.</p>
                                        <p>Jamison, Kay R. <hi rend="i">Touched by Fire:
                                                  Manic-Depressive Illness</hi><pb id="p30-49"
                                                  n="49"/><hi rend="i">and the Artistic
                                                  Temperament.</hi> New York: Free Press, 1993.</p>
                                        <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William
                                                  Blake.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                                                1980.</p>
                                        <p>LaRusso, Nicholas F., et al. “Primary Sclerosing
                                                Cholangitis.” <hi rend="i">New England Journal of
                                                  Medicine</hi> 310 (1984): 899-903.</p>
                                        <p><hi rend="i">London and Provincial Medical
                                                  Directory.</hi> London, 1861.</p>
                                        <p><hi rend="i">Medical Times &amp; Gazette</hi>, Obituary
                                                for Dr. James Forbes Young, 14 July 1860, 46.</p>
                                        <p>Schiff, L. and E. R. Schiff. <hi rend="i">Diseases of the
                                                  Liver.</hi> 6th ed. Philadelphia: J. B.
                                                Lippincott, 1987.</p>
                                        <p><hi rend="i">Sculptura Historico-Technica: or the History
                                                  and Art of Engraving.</hi> 4th ed. London,
                                                1770.</p>
                                        <p>Sherlock, S., and J. Dooley, eds. <hi rend="i">Diseases
                                                  of the Liver and Biliary System.</hi> Oxford:
                                                Blackwell Scientific Productions, 1993.</p>
                                        <p>Shorter, R. G. “Sclerosing Cholangitis.” 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Inflammatory Bowel Disease.</hi> 3rd ed.
                                                Philadelphia: Lea &amp; Febiger, 1988.</p>
                                        <p>Smith, J. T. <hi rend="i">Nollekens and his Times.</hi> 2
                                                vols. London: Henry Colburn, 1828. Essay on Blake in
                                                2: 454-88; rpt. in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                                                  Records</hi>, 455-76.</p>
                                        <p>Tatham, Frederick. <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> (MS),
                                                c. 1832. Rpt. in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                                                  Records</hi>, 507-36.</p>
                                        <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the
                                                  Book.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                                                1993.</p>
                                        <p>—. “The Evolution of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The
                                                  Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>” 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>
                                                (forthcoming).</p>
                                        <p>—. “A ‘Green House’ for Blake? New Information on Thomas
                                                Butts, His Residences, and Family.” 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 30 (1996): 4-21.</p>
                                        <p>Ward, Aileen. “William Blake and the Hagiographers.” 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Biography and Source Studies.</hi> Ed. by
                                                Frederick R. Karl. New York: AMS Press, 1994.</p>
                                        <p>Weisner, Russell H, and Nicholas F. LaRusso.
                                                “Clinicopathologic Features of the Syndrome of
                                                Primary Sclerosing Cholangitis.” 
                                                  <hi rend="i">Gastroenterology</hi> 79 (1980): 200-06.</p>
                                        <p>Wells, David. <hi rend="i">A Study of William Blake’s
                                                Letters.</hi> <corr type="emend">Tübingen, Germany:</corr> Stauffenburg
                                                Verlag, 1987.</p>
                                        <p>Wilson, Mona. <hi rend="i">The Life of William
                                                  Blake.</hi> London: Rupert Hart-Davis, 1948.</p>
                                        <p>Wyngaarden, James B, Lloyd H. Smith, and J. Claude
                                                Bennett, eds. <hi rend="i">Cecil Textbook of
                                                  Medicine.</hi> 19th ed. Philadelphia: W. B.
                                                Saunders Co., 1992.</p>
                                </div2>
                        </div1>
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI.2>
