<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.3.hollis</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Seeing Thel as Serpent</title>
        <author n="Hollis">Hilda Hollis</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1996/7</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996/97</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Hilda Hollis</name>
              <name>Marc Kaplan</name>
              <name>Deborah McCollister</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996/97"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
	<pb id="p30-87" n="87"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Seeing Thel as Serpent</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Hilda <name>Hollis</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Thel’s motto remains one of the most enigmatic aspects of William
                        Blake’s short <hi rend="i">Book of Thel.</hi> It is composed of a
                        series of questions, the intent of which is unclear, and which only seem to
                        provoke more questions: 
						<q> Does the Eagle know what is in the pit?<lb/>
 Or
                            wilt thou go ask the Mole:<lb/>
 Can Wisdom be put in a silver rod?<lb/>
                            O Love in a golden bowl?<lb/>
 (i.1-4, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) </q>
Most
                        discussion focuses on the second pair of questions, and my argument begins
                        with this set. Two major sources are widely suggested for these lines:
                        Ecclesiastes and Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> The former refers
                        to the issue of mortality which is of paramount concern to Thel, and the
                        latter bears a relation to Thel’s virginal and frightened chastity. I
                        suggest that, while contributing to our understanding of these lines,
                        neither Ecclesiastes nor <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> comprehends the full or
                        multiple meaning of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and its motto. Blake first
                        composed these lines in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> in a section which he
                        subsequently deleted, and this original context suggests another metaphor
                        which has implications for the whole of the later book.</p>
          <p>When Tiriel first utters the questions about the rod and bowl, there is no
                        clear reference to sexuality and certainly no allusion to <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi>
Tiriel’s concern with his old age and mortality
                        echoes Ecclesiastes: “before the silver cord is snapped, or the
                        golden bowl is broken” (12:6). But there are significant differences.
                        Cord is replaced by rod, and neither wisdom nor love is associated with
                        these objects in Ecclesiastes. Originally a single line, “Can wisdom
                        be put in a silver rod or love in a golden bowl” (deleted from 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> 8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 815), these questions occur
                        in Tiriel’s final venting of rage against his father. The anger
                        expressed by Tiriel against power supported by a hypocritical religion is a
                        familiar theme in Blake’s work. Here Tiriel questions the
                        universalizing myth of “Thy God of love thy heaven of joy”
                        (del., <hi rend="i">E</hi> 815) invoked by a natural religion which turns
                        Tiriel into a serpent. As a child, Tiriel claims that he was not given
                        nourishment and milk by his mother, and that his father scourged him into
                        weak infant sorrow. This treatment bred hypocrisy—“the idiots
                        wisdom &amp; the wise mans folly” (del., <hi rend="i">E</hi> 815).
                        Elizabeth Stieg identifies Tiriel as a false prophet, “one who speaks
                        in God’s name to tyrannize over others” (296). Tiriel is
                        brought to that hypocritical and limiting religion which Blake elsewhere
                        identifies as feminine: “Compelld to pray repugnant &amp; to humble
                        the immortal spirit / Till I am subtil as a serpent in paradise”
                        (8.23-24, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
	<pb id="p30-88" n="88"/>
285). I suggest the transformation into a serpent
                        that Tiriel undergoes is identical to Blake’s intention in the
                        drawing of a serpent at the end of Thel.</p>
          <p>When Tiriel asks “Can wisdom be put in a silver rod or love in a
                        golden bowl,” he appears to allude to his father’s scourging
                        “off all youthful fantasies” (8.18, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 285)
                        and to the replacement of his mother’s milk and nourishment
                        presumably by food served in a dish. As a metaphor extending Tiriel’s
                        personal experience, the silver rod and golden cup have wider reference to
                        abusive political and religious authorities which can be identified with the
                        sceptre and the chalice. Blake’s condemnation and linking of King and
                        Priest occur throughout his work. For instance, in “The Chimney
                        Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, Blake connects
                        “God &amp; his Priest &amp; King / Who make up a heaven of our
                        misery” (11-12, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 23). This identification is also
                        seen clearly in the alliance between the Archbishop and the sceptre-wielding
                        King in <hi rend="i">The French Revolution.</hi> Tiriel thus inquires
                        whether wisdom can come from a silver sceptre and if love can be found in a
                        golden chalice. The gold and silver symbolize the hypocrisy with which these
                        symbols are overlaid. In particular, the image of the golden bowl is
                        striking since it recalls the Eucharistic cup representing Christ’s
                        sacrificial offering. But the golden chalice of a wealthy and selfish church
                        in the face of poverty creates an image of contradiction. While wisdom and
                        love are declared, their opposite is evinced. Gold and precious jewels are
                        used in the same way in “I saw a chapel all of gold.” Just as
                        Tiriel is transformed into a serpent, this chapel breeds a serpent who
                        vomits “his poison out / On the bread &amp; on the wine”
                        (13-14, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 467).</p>
          <p>I suggest that we read Thel as a type of the Female Will, and, as such, as a
                        metaphor for the limiting natural religion enforced by priest and king.
                        Thel’s name is itself a Greek pun on <hi rend="i">female</hi>
                        <corr type="emend">(thel) and</corr> <hi rend="i">will</hi> (thel).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">1</ref> Susan Fox argues that in 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> Blake depicts a
                        feminine failure which 
						<q> foreshadows the genderless failure of active
                            desire Blake will develop in later poems: in the context of his other
                            works Thel suggests not just the frailty of women, but the
                            “feminine” frailty of all human beings. In <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794),
engraved five years after the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> songs and <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, female characters
                            represent not only the darker propensities Blake feared in women, but
                            the technically genderless tyrannies of nature and religion as well.
                            (511) </q>
In later works, Blake consolidates his idea of Female Will
                        and develops it in an explicit opposition to an active Will. While there is
                        no male Will in this early poem, Blake depicts in Thel the attributes that
                        he will later give to the separated female emanation. 
<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">1</hi> E. B. Murray draws attention to the popular
                            contemporary recognition of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> as Greek for 
<hi rend="i">woman</hi> after the publication in 1780-81 of Martin
                            Madan’s notorious polemic, <hi rend="i">Thelyphthora</hi> (see
                            esp. 276 and n4).</note></p>
          <p>Foster Damon draws our attention to two traditional ways of understanding
                        Thel. While Damon argues that Thel’s fear of maturation and
                        motherhood is an “obvious” interpretation of the poem, he also
                        suggests that Thel represents a soul fearful of entering the world and
                        hypothesizes that the <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> is an elegy for a
                        possible stillborn child of the Blakes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">2</ref>
                        In either case, Damon contends that Thel never reappears in any of
                        Blake’s later poetry, either because she is “far too nice a
                        girl” (<hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> 401) or because the poem lacks a
                        universal application since “most souls do not refuse to be
                        born” (“Blake and Milton” 94). In contrast to Damon, I
                        argue that we do see a reincarnation of Thel in Blake’s development
                        of a fearful Female Will. The “Thel” who reappears is the one
                        who corresponds to the first interpretation of Thel acknowledged by Damon to
                        be obvious, but I place a more sinister interpretation on this girl who is
                        “too nice.” In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Los’s
                        thunderous query, “O Albion why didst thou a Female Will
                        Create?” (56.43, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 206), is uttered in response to
                        the Albion women’s declaration of timidity: “We Women tremble
                        at the light therefore: hiding fearful/The Divine Vision with Curtain &amp;
                        Veil &amp; fleshly Tabernacle” (56.39-40, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 206).
                        The women’s statement of prohibitive fear recalls the near final
                        lines of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>: “Why a tender curb upon the youthful
                        burning boy! / Why a little curtain of flesh on the bed of our
                        desire?” (6.19-20, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 6). Limited by her mortality,
                        Thel separates herself from her fellow creatures and, by refusing to give,
                        she becomes symbolic of self-oriented religion. <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">2</hi>
Damon finds support for this hypothesis in what he contends
                            is yet another allusion to a miscarriage in Los’s words to the
                            Albion women in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>:
<q> To the golden Loom of
                                Love! to the moth-labourd Woof<lb/>
 A Garment and Cradle weaving for
                                the infantine Terror:<lb/>
 For fear; at entering the gate into our
                                World of cruel<lb/>
 Lamentation: it flee back &amp; hide in
                                Non-Entitys dark wild.<lb/>
 (56.13-16, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 206) </q>
                            Damon makes this argument in <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (401)
                            and “Blake and Milton” (94).</note></p>
          <p>Rather than seeing an infinite world, Thel is bound by death, wanting to
                        “hear the voice / Of him that walketh in the garden in the evening
                        time” (1.14, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). In Genesis, when God is heard
                        walking in the garden in the evening time, Adam and Eve hide themselves
                        because they have disobeyed, and then God curses them with their own
                        mortality: “for dust thou art, and unto dust shalt thou
                        return” (Genesis 3:19). The voice which speaks in the garden is
                        punitive and utters death; Thel desires to be bound by this voice which
                        insists on mortality.</p>
          <p>Some recent critics read Thel in a positive light and see in her a rebellious
                        female—a type of proto-feminist, years beyond Mary
                            Wollstonecraft.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">3</ref> Applauding
                        Thel’s refusal to 
<pb id="p30-89" n="89"/>
submit to masculine
                        demands, sexual or otherwise, they suggest that Blake approved of Thel. It
                        is important, however, to distinguish a feminist sympathy with Thel from
                        Blake’s attitude, and I would avoid the danger of falsely attributing
                        a feminist agenda to Blake. Blake’s work is not written in support of
                        the 1990s hard won recognition of a woman’s right to say <hi rend="i">no</hi>, but
rather identifies the nay-saying virgin with natural
                        religion. Alicia Ostriker’s comment that “Thel is selfish, and
                        a coward” (151), while not representative of most current feminist
                        readings of Thel’s actions, is probably closer to Blake’s own
                        reading of his creation. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">3</hi> For example,
                                Gerda Norvig argues,
                            <p>For despite the evidence that Blake later on adopted a revisionary
                                form of these same Christian ideals, my contention is that in 
<hi rend="i">this</hi> text he represented and endorsed a liminal
                                view of the desiring self for the purpose of critiquing a philosophy
                                detrimental to the energies of real women even as it served the
                                so-called feminine values of an empirical, deistical patriarchal
                                order. (271)</p></note></p>
          <p>Throughout the book, images identify Thel as a parody or false Christ. In the
                        frontispiece, Thel is depicted as a shepherdess without sheep. Originally
                        she is not without a caring role, but like the leaders of the church or
                        false prophets, she is a false shepherd and abandons her sheep. In each of
                        the illustrations, Thel does not act, but merely presents a formal imitation
                        of her interlocutors’ activities. In the second plate, the lily bows
                        deeply because she is weighed down by her fruit—representing her
                        generative powers and her gifts. Thel, in contrast, engages in a shallow
                        ritual bow. While the cloud in plate 4 spreads his arms to drop his
                        moisture, Thel spreads her arms over the baby worm at a safe distance from
                        which she can give nothing to him. David Erdman comments that in plate 5
                        Thel “almost makes a cradle of her arms” (39). This empty
                        cradle parodies the clod of clay lying on the ground and perhaps playing
                        with the baby. Thel is like a golden bowl, for like it, she is a
                        hypocritical imitation of loving kindness. While Thel does eventually enter
                        the earth, she does not engage experience; she only observes, listens and
                        then flees.</p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, the verses concerning the silver rod and golden
                        bowl are preceded by two other questions: “Does the Eagle know what
                        is in the pit? / Or wilt thou go ask the Mole” (i.1-2, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). The
reference to the Mole, in connection with gold and
                        silver symbols of religion and authority, recalls the only mole who appears
                        in the Bible. Because of Blake’s immersion in the Bible’s
                        prophetic books, this passage in Isaiah should be viewed as an important,
                        though previously neglected, intertext: 
						<q> And they shall go into the holes
                            of the rocks, and into the caves of the earth, for fear of the Lord, and
                            for the glory of his majesty, when he ariseth to shake terribly the
                            earth. In that day a man shall cast his <hi rend="i">idols of
                                silver</hi>, and his <hi rend="i">idols of gold</hi>, which they
                            made each one for himself to worship, to the moles and to the bats.
                            (Isaiah 2:19-20; my emphasis) </q>
This passage speaks of powerful
                        leaders taking refuge in the ground when “the day of the Lord”
                        comes and of their realization that their limiting natural religion is not
                        large enough. In particular, “The Lord will enter into judgement with
                        the ancients of his people, and the princes thereof: for ye have eaten up
                        the vineyard; the spoil of the poor is in your houses” (Isaiah 3:14).
                        Thel’s visit to the caves of the earth is prompted by a personal fear
                        of death or her own “day of the Lord” rather than a universal
                        and apocalyptic one, but in these caves she also encounters terror in the
                        face of insistent and unrelenting questioning. The silver and gold
                        idols—the silver sceptre which pretends to wisdom, but really is a
                        sign of self serving power, and the gold chalice which symbolizes not love,
                        but self-love—are undermined by the questions which are asked.</p>
          <p>The series of questions emphasizes Thel’s dependence on her eyes and
                        ears—her mortal senses. They query the bounds placed on love. In
                        contrast to the motto’s silver rod, Isaiah introduces a rod which is
                        not limited and bound, and which will contain wisdom: “there shall
                        come forth a rod out of the stem of Jesse . . . And the Spirit of the Lord
                        shall rest upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding” (Isaiah
                        11:1-2). In contrast to Thel whose “Ear cannot be closed to its own
                        destruction/ Or the glistning Eye to the poison of a smile” (6.11-12,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 6), he “shall not judge after the sight of
                        his eyes, neither reprove after the hearing of his ears” (Isaiah
                        11:3). Thel, however, is concerned with self, and she will not face the
                        challenge posed by the questions which she encounters under the earth.
                        Rather than entering into an active love which will confront natural
                        religion, she flees. Thel attempts to escape her own mortality by entering
                        the holes of the earth, but eventually she opts to return to her own
                        enclosing, safe and dissembling world.</p>
          <p>Donald Pearce argues that Thel’s mistake was to have inquired of moles
                        rather than eagles. He comments that the lily, the cloud, and the clod only
                        encourage Thel towards a limiting natural religion since they do not have
                        prophetic and spiritual vision. Similarly, Gerda Norvig asserts that
                        Thel’s “represented desire for a real female subjectivity is
                        meant to undermine the powerful calls from her interlocutors to embrace a
                        philosophy of repetitive and uncreative self sacrifice” (271). But
                        the poem actually suggests that none of the characters of whom Thel inquires
                        feels limited by their activities. All see their work within a wider and
                        infinite spiritual framework: the lily looks towards eternal vales; the
                        cloud lives on though vanishing to mortal sight; and the clod has an eternal
                        crown. While these creatures are not bound by their physicality, Thel, in
                        contrast, by engaging in imitative gestures, places herself under mortal
                        bounds and within the “same dull round” (<hi rend="i">There is
                            No Natural Religion</hi>, b, IV, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 2) so loathed by
                        Blake.</p>
          <pb id="p30-90" n="90"/>
          <p>Each of the creatures encountered by Thel—the lily, the cloud and the
                        clod—is initiated into love. As Michael Ferber points out, the lily
                        and the clod become brides of Christ while the cloud is united with the dew.
                        The lily is visited from heaven, and the clod is bound with “his
                        nuptial bands” (5, 2, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 5). Ferber argues that the
                        cloud’s marriage, although more oblique, also suggests a transcendent
                        marriage to God (45-48). Thel, however, remains a virgin and refuses to
                        enter into this bridal role. The <hi rend="i">Bride of Christ</hi> is a
                        title which the church claims for itself,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n31" type="note">4</ref> but Blake’s assessment of official religion suggests
                        that the church has not actually fulfilled this role. Likewise, Thel
                        imitates love, but does not love. This false pretense reminds us of
                        Tiriel’s self-description: “subtil as a serpent” (8.37,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 285). In order to achieve his ends he must
                        dissimulate. Is this also the meaning of the enigmatic serpent at the end of
                        Thel? As commentators have noted, Thel is not the child riding the serpent.
                        Her disappearance from the illustration suggests the possibility that she,
                        like Tiriel, has been transformed into a serpent. Eugenie Freed argues that
                        the children riding the serpent may represent the lady and her two brothers
                        from <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> If Thel is understood to represent the moral
                        law, then this identification is apt. Thel, as the moral law, carries the
                        three children on her serpent-back. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See
                            Ephesians 5:31-32.</note></p>
          <p>By employing in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> the pair of enigmatic questions from
                        the deleted section in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, Blake is able to take
                        advantage of their wide allusive potential in the new setting. Rod and cup
                        are clearly sexual images, and the magician of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> is
                        recalled. The silver cord and golden bowl, symbols of mortality from
                        Ecclesiastes, become important in the context of Thel’s preoccupation
                        with death. But Blake also uses the image of rod and bowl, as sceptre and
                        chalice, in order to introduce Thel as a metaphor for a hypocritical and
                        limiting religion. Thel’s refusal to engage in an active giving role
                        becomes clear as the depictions of her imitative and inactive stance
                        progress throughout the poem. Her transformation into the serpent finally
                        confirms her identity as Thel—<hi rend="i">Female Will.</hi></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Damon, Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of
                                William Blake.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves. Rev. ed. Hanover: University
                            Press of New England, 1988.</p>
            <p>—. “Blake and Milton.” <hi rend="i">The Divine
                                Vision: Studies in the Poetry and Art of William Blake born November
                                28th, 1757.</hi> Ed. Vivian de Sola Pinto. London: Victor Gollancz,
                            1957. 89-96.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
                                William Blake.</hi> Newly rev. ed. Garden City, NY: Anchor
                            Press/Doubleday, 1982.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake: William Blake’s
                                Complete Works with a Plate-by-Plate Commentary.</hi> Garden City,
                            NY: Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1974.</p>
            <p>Ferber, Michael. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and the
                            Bride of Christ.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 9 (1980):
                            45-56.</p>
            <p>Fox, Susan. “The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s
                            Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 3 (1977): 507-19.</p>
            <p>Freed, Eugenie. “‘Sun-Clad Chastity’ and
                            Blake’s ‘Maiden Queens’” <hi rend="i">Comus,
                                Thel</hi>, and ‘The Angel.’” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 25 (1991-92):
104-16</p>
            <p>Murray, E.B. “Thel, <hi rend="i">Thelyphthora</hi>, and the
                            Daughters of Albion.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 20
                            (1981): 275-97.</p>
            <p>Norvig, Gerda. “Female Subjectivity and the Desire of Reading
                            In(to) Blake’s Book of Thel.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Romanticism</hi> 34 (1995): 255-71.</p>
            <p>Ostriker, Alicia. <hi rend="i">Vision and Verse in William Blake.</hi>
                            Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1965.</p>
            <p>Pearce, Donald. “Natural Religion and the Plight of Thel.”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 8 (1978): 23-35.</p>
            <p>Stieg, Elizabeth. “Reinterpreting the Old Testament:
                            Blake’s Tiriel as Prophet.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Romanticism</hi> 29 (1990): 273-96.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
