<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.3.romantic</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Romantic Circles Web Site</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1996/7</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996/97</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Hilda Hollis</name>
              <name>Marc Kaplan</name>
              <name>Deborah McCollister</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996/97"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0008">
      	<pb id="p30-95" n="95"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Romantic Circles Web Site</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>This is to announce a new web site for research, Romantic Circles: Byron,
                        Keats, the Shelleys and Their Contemporaries. Its prototype can be found at
                        the following URL:</p>
          <p>http://www.inform.umd.edu/RC/rc.html</p>
          <p>According to the editors, Romantic Circles is organized as a meta-resource
                        that will be openended, collaborative, and porous—maintaining and
                        encouraging many potential links to other sites on the Web. As currently
                        conceived, the site will be divided into three main entities: Electronic
                        Editions, Scholarly Resources, and Critical Exchange. The last of these will
                        include a real-time, interactive MOO, the Villa Diodati.</p>
          <p>Two general principles will guide the development of the site: “We
                        will value quality over quantity, mounting only resources produced and
                        maintained according to high scholarly standards; and we will give priority
                        to innovative, creatively-conceived resources that take advantage of the
                        electronic medium in ways that could not be duplicated easily in print. We
                        invite you to visit the site, read the prospectus, and see what we and our
                        co-editors have planned for the coming months. Romantic Circles will be
                        formally launched in November, to coincide with the NASSR conference in
                        Boston. Until then, users are welcome to watch the site develop as we
                        construct it and to try out features as they become available, including our
                        NASSR ’96 Conference pages.” [Neil Fraistat, Steve E. Jones,
                        and Donald H. Reiman, General Editors; and Carl Stahmer, Design and
                        Technical Editor.]</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
