<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.3.dorrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Veils, Infinity, a Roof, and “One thought” in Contemporary Art: A Note
          on Four Exhibitions</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1996/7</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996/97</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Hilda Hollis</name>
              <name>Marc Kaplan</name>
              <name>Deborah McCollister</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996/97"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
	<pb id="p30-82" n="82"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEW</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Veils, Infinity, a Roof, and “One thought” in Contemporary Art<lb/>
            A Note on Four Exhibitions</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>D. W. <name>Dörrbecker</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>At the brink of the new millennium, Blake still hasn’t found that large readership in
            the German-speaking countries which Henry Crabb Robinson had expected to grow so rapidly
            when drafting the essay he contributed to the <hi rend="i">Vaterländisches Museum</hi>
            in 1811. Therefore, it comes as a surprise to find that over the past few years Blake’s
            works have inspired a series of exhibitions by contemporary artists in Austria, Germany,
            and Switzerland which may warrant a brief report.</p>
          <p>Supposedly, only few of the visitors who came to see Verena Immenhauser’s installation
            “Beneath the Veil of Vala” at the Berner Galerie in 1988 were fully aware of the Swiss
            artist’s understanding of the symbol of Vala’s veil/vale and its complex meaning in the
            poetry and art of William Blake. And yet, anybody ready to engage with the aesthetic
            experience offered by that installation must have felt the urge to question the
            relationship between the veil and the veiled, center and circumference, form and
            formlessness, the cycle of natural growth and decay (reigning in Vala’s vale) and the
            ideas of stability and of eternity (governing a realm that lies beyond it). Employing
            soft transparent wrapping foils, Immenhauser created an environment inside the small
            gallery space which at first sight seemed devoid both of calculated form and all
            specific content. However, the movements of the visitors quite literally breathed life
            into the room which was filled with draped “veils” (illus. 1) hanging from the ceiling
            and hiding the measured dimensions of the walls. The softly whispering and everchanging
            folds of the thin and shining plastic veils remained entirely abstract in shape, but
            functioned as an appropriate representation of Vala’s veil of nature. Their
            rippling-rustling texture lured the sense of touch and the ear, while their utter
            refusal of all representational concreteness, the complete lack of linear (and optical)
            solidity, and their shimmering, silvery reflections, irritated and fascinated the
            eye.</p>
          <p>In a sense, this finely tuned metaphor of Vala’s art of seduction seemed related to
            Marcel Duchamp’s famous “spider-web” installation for the Surrealist exhibition at 451
            Madison Avenue in 1942. But it also anticipated such “physical sculptures” as the
            “Bodycheck” contributed by Flatz to the documenta IX in 1992, or the labyrinth of
            measured time made from hundreds of clocks, hanging folding rules, 
              <pb id="p30-83" n="83"/>
            <figure n="ImmenhauserUntitled.30.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="621">
              <head>1 Verena Immenhauser, “Untitled,” a figural veil/a veiled figure, executed in
                preparation of the installation shown at Berne, Switz., dimensions vary,
                1988.</head>
              <figDesc>Collection of the artist.</figDesc>
            </figure> and “lost” digits that was shown by Cildo Meireles on the same occasion in
            Kassel. The magic and attractiveness which Blake and most of his (male?) readers fear in
            Vala was reflected by the artistic sorcery with which Immenhauser handled the
            insubstantiality of the translucent yet blinding and suffocating quality of her simple
            materials.</p>
          <p>For his “1992 Infinite Painting on A Vision of the Last Judgment by William Blake
            1808,” shown in Berlin at the Zwinger Galerie, Nikolaus Utermöhlen mounted enlarged
            photocopies of Blake’s “Vision” on thirteen aluminum panels (200 × 80 cm. each). The
            reproductions had been produced on a color photocopying machine which was manipulated by
            the artist so that a sequence of color variations resulted. Each panel (or, as
            Utermöhlen prefers to call them, each “spectre”) displayed a different layering of the
            primary colors, blurring and distorting the clarity of Blake’s original watercolor. Its
            design was thus supplanted with the cool glow of industrial colors which had been
            heightened by additional hand-tinted patterns and which produced the effect of a giant
            kaleidoscope. Utermöhlen’s interest in the openness and mechanical “infinity” of
            possible color variations and in the configurations which can be assembled by grouping
            the aluminum panels on the gallery walls, produced 
              <figure n="LochleStonyRoof.30.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="692">
              <head>2 Dieter Löchle, “Stony Roof,” pencil and encaustic painting, 50 × 35 cm.,
                1994.</head>
              <figDesc>Collection of the artist.</figDesc>
            </figure> a decorative color rhythm quite appropriate for a postmodern ice cream parlor.
            Sure enough, Utermöhlen’s project may pass as yet another artistic experiment with the
            representational implications of technical reproduction and repetition. Moreover, the
            artist may well have hoped for a meaningful contrast between “classical form” and
            “modern technique” similar to the one achieved by, say, Jim Dine’s appropriation of the
            Venus of Melos. However, I failed to trace any deeply felt conceptual relation between
            Utermöhlen’s “Infinite Painting” and Blake’s understanding of infinity or his idea of a
            Last Judgment. Rather, Blake’s watercolor painting apparently had been chosen more or
            less at random, and the artist’s references to a Blakean model served, in the end, as no
            more than a fairly banal attempt to dignify with iconographical content what was merely
            another more or less interesting experiment in replacing the old-fashioned brush with a
            xerox machine.</p>
          <p>If Utermöhlen’s central concern was that of a formalist, one will have to locate the
            works of Dieter Löchle at the other end of the spectrum. Under the title “Roof’d in from
            Eternity,” his Blakean drawings, prints, and paintings were on show at the Tübingen
            university library in 1995. Almost devoid of color, Löchle’s paintings relied on the
            simple opposition of darkness and light, created by black, white, 
              <pb id="p30-84" n="84"/>
            <figure n="LochleMilton.30.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="663">
              <head>3 Dieter Löchle, “Milton,” pencil on encaustic ground, 64.0 × 47.5 cm.,
                1995.</head>
              <figDesc>Collection of the artist.</figDesc>
            </figure> and thinly saturated yellowish washes. These almost unstructured encaustic
            color fields provide the backdrop for the artist’s similarly simplified linear
            adaptation of Blake’s figural language. Drawing with the brush, with pen and ink, or
            with black and white chalks in what seems a consciously retrospective manner, Löchle
            reinvents the imagery of the illuminated books. Visitors to the exhibition were allowed
            to gauge this reference to Blake’s relief-etched designs in the modernized versions by
            means of a generous selection from the Trianon Press facsimiles of the illuminated books
            which was on show in the library’s vestibule. Löchle handles his lines with great
            clarity and achieves solid, almost “architectural” compositions that are all based on
            only one or two figures (as in many of Blake’s own illuminated pages). For example, the
            German painter has translated figural motifs from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 41, 
              <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 21, the frontispiece for <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>, and plates 10
            and 17 from <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> into his own pictorial idiom (illus. 2-3).</p>
          <p>Occasionally, when confronted with the symbolic portrait heads and some of the
            eroticized designs which were included in the show, I felt struck by what seems a
            curiously straightforward approach to the problems and functions of contemporary visual
            representation, an approach bordering on the naive. However, Löchle’s linear
            abbreviations of the “human form divine” generally work well enough as a modern
            interpretative response to Blake. Because the expressive use of bodily movements in
            Blake’s designs is perpetuated in Löchle’s pictorial homage, his images seem highly
            charged with symbolic energy and meaning. And it is here that they provide an antithesis
            to Utermöhlen’s dominantly formalist concerns. At the same time, the austerity and
            abstract quality of Löchle’s 
<pb id="p30-85" n="85"/>
draughtsmanship steer clear of the
            preoccupation with those “sublime,” “fantastic,” “weird,” and more narrative aspects
of
            the art of Blake and Fuseli which have previously attracted the attention of other
            Austrian and German artists such as Günter Brus, Alfred Hrdlicka, or Horst Janssen in
            some of their exhibitions of the 1970s and 1980s.</p>
          <p>Löchle’s stylistic choices lead towards a relative independence of his images from
            their Blakean blueprints. But they draw the viewer’s attention to such characteristics
            as the white-line technique—first in Löchle’s own prints, drawings, and paintings, but
            then, on the way out and through the show-cases lined up in the entrance hall, also in
            Blake’s illuminated prints. In this sense, “Roof’d in from Eternity” was a group
            exhibition, ideally suited for an academic library. Löchle not only paid homage to
            Blake, he also invited the visitors to find out for themselves what he had seen in
            Blake’s colored relief-etchings, and how he had seen it.</p>
          <p>An entirely different and certainly non-didactic approach was chosen for a fourth
            exhibition which presented a far more radical, avantgardist, and in its own way very
            exciting use of the raw materials provided by Blake for the making of contemporary art.
            The first major one-man show in Germany for the Spanish sculptor and installation artist
            Jaume Plensa was organized by the Städtische Galerie Göppingen in the summer of 1995.
            Plensa’s art often combines the visual and the verbal in a surprising, some may say an
            absurd manner. While this relationship of image and text cannot be described as
            “narrative” in any common sense of the word, it succeeds in making familiar objects seem
            strange, and it creates “new” and challenging combinations which provoke the senses and
            the imagination. His recent work exposes the spectator to environments assembled from
            prosaic objects of the artist’s own everyday life and from inscribed panels, boxes, or
            cages which are cast in synthetic resin. Together with two other installations, the
            Göppingen exhibition introduced Plensa’s (as yet unfinished) project on Blake’s
            “Proverbs of Hell” from <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (illus. 4-5).
            Similar to Immenhauser’s veils, but adding Blake’s own words in blind-stamped letters on
            his polyester panels, Plensa’s “Proverbs” provide a highly personal interpretation of
            Blake, the rich associations of which remain valid (or at least intellectually
            fascinating) even for an onlooker who is entirely unacquainted with the British
            poet-artist’s works.</p>
          <p>Most of the 1995 “Proverbs” consist of three elements, which are usually mounted at a
            right angle on the gallery’s walls. The first of these elements is an object from the
            “hell” of the artist’s studio work, such as a red plastic bucket which had been used in
            the preparation of the plaster Plensa employs in an early stage of his casting
            technique, or a cheap metal wastepaper basket which, one imagines, had once been filled
            with discarded sketches and studies for the artist’s projects. The second element is a
            pillar, protruding <figure n="PlensaProverbs.30.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="620">
              <head>4 Jaume Plensa, “Proverbs of Hell 73: ‘Enough or too much’,” wall piece made
                from synthetic resin and a plastic bucket, 65 × 130 × 144 cm., 1995.</head>
              <figDesc>Private collection, Barcelona, Spain; photo: Lluis Bover.</figDesc>
            </figure> about three feet from the wall into the exhibition space. Attached to the top
            of this pillar, sometimes standing, sometimes dangling headlong, is a small statue of a
            naked child. Both the pillar and the statuette are cast from semi-transparent polyester
            resin. The naked child is placed in a position which seems to defy the law of gravity
            and often suggests that it is contemplating the object from everyday life and the third
            element, a cast polyester panel with Blake’s proverb inscribed in relief. By
            reading/viewing, for example, “The busy bee has no time for sorrow” in the panel mounted
            on top of one of the waste-baskets, the small figures on their pillars supply the
            visitors with directions for the use of the entire installation.</p>
          <p>At the same time the transparent three-dimensional figures prompt us to muse about the
            relationship between the various elements that have been combined for each of the
            “Proverbs” and outward reality—to ponder on the practical usefulness of a red plastic
            bucket, a usefulness which is lost once it is made part of a work of art—to realize that
            thereby it may, however, achieve a different function, and may as such become useful in
            a different sense—to contemplate the representation of the human figure in its relation
            to the abstract stereometry of the pillar-cube it is attached to—and, of course, to
            think about the continuing relevance of what Blake’s devils have to say concerning the
              <pb id="p30-86" n="86"/>
nature, the social conditions and conditioning, and the role
            of the imagination in this world. One thing I didn’t like about the exhibition at
            Göppingen: its title, “One thought fills immensity.” In Plensa’s work, just as in many
            other instances of contemporary installation and concept art (and even in Blake), formal
            repetitions, the reduplication of a specific motif or shape are of essential importance.
            I doubt, however, that an irony was intended, and that the title was meant to draw the
            spectator’s attention to the filling of the “immensity” of the gallery space with just
            “One thought.” Even if it was, “The road of excess leads to the palace of wisdom,” and
            “Enough! or Too much” would have described Plensa’s secular modernization of Blake more
            appropriately.</p>
          <p>Each of these four exhibitions tells us about specific modes and possibilities of the
            creative appropriation of Blake’s words and images. What Michelangelo was to Blake,
            Blake is to Löchle who—in the group of works discussed in the present
            note—literally/visually cites the elder artist’s figural language and/or entire
            compositional arrangements. Not only is the artist consciously transforming Blakean
            models, he also wants the viewer to recognize his citations as such. Just as an editor
            or a critic of Blake’s works might do, Löchle asks for the meaning which Blake’s art may
            have for an audience separated from its initial production by two centuries. The tension
            between the historicity of the pictorial inventions and the actuality of their rendering
            in Löchle’s “cover version,” between the identity of the motifs and the discrepancy of
            the formal qualities of their representation is exactly where the “meaning” of these
            paintings and prints from 1994-95 appears to be situated. Löchle’s insistence on
            visually confronting Blake’s images (by means of the facsimiles included in the
            exhibition) with his own works demonstrates a historical awareness which in turn allows
            for linking his art with certain techniques of scholarly interpretation.</p>
          <p>If Löchle’s art is inspired by the “historical approach,” Immenhauser’s seems to
            provide a parallel with gender criticism. Those of the visitors to her installation who
            were alert to the Blakean connotations of Vala’s veil, will have glimpsed at a critical
            and revisionist view of the role assigned to Vala in the poem which was named after her,
            in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and in almost any learned commentary on these works.
            Immenhauser, it seems, “reads” Blake against the masculine grain, and by doing so she
            opens up an alternative understanding of Vala and her veil which attempts to visually
            “explain” some of the fascination which Blake himself apparently felt when creating the
            mythic character. To take this just one step further, one might classify Plensa’s
            sculptural montage of the “Proverbs” as an example of a “deconstructive” or a
            “hypermedia” art, the creation of an unstable artistic reality from seemingly unrelated
            textual elements, which in a continual flux combine and dissociate to form a variety of
            meaningful, yet “open” constellations.</p>
          <figure n="PlensaProverbs3.30.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="601">
            <head>5 Jaume Plensa, “Proverbs of Hell 3: ‘The road of excess leads to the palace of
              wisdom’,” wall piece made from synthetic resin and a brass object, 98 × 71 × 50 cm.,
              1995.</head>
            <figDesc>Städtische Galerie, Göppingen, Germany; photo: Lluis Bover.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Now, does this mean that these contemporary artists work with scholarly methodologies
            in mind? Or that scholars unconsciously are creating their texts along the same lines
            that artists create their works? Though Immenhauser and Löchle have indeed written
            academic theses on Blake, such a conclusion would seem rather ludicrous to me. The
            construction of abstract analogies between art and scholarship as two “fruits” of the
            human mind still seems synonymous with comparing apples to peaches. However, to look at
            contemporary artists’ reactions to Blake’s words and images, and to draw such parallels,
            may still be a heuristically useful exercise, one that will remind the critic of the
            plurality of legitimate and potentially meaningful engagements with Blake’s works.</p>
          <pb id="p30-87" n="87"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Artists, Exhibitions, and Catalogues</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Verena Immenhauser (b. 1939), <hi rend="i">Vala: Arbeiten zu Blake</hi>, Berner
              Galerie, Berne, Switz., 1-24 Nov. 1988. On show were the installation “Beneath the
              Veil of Vala” (as reviewed above), as well as a selection of the artist’s “Vala”
              photographs and oil paintings (the latter somehow reminiscent of Cy Twombly’s “Wilder
              Shores of Love”). There was no catalogue, but the exhibition was previously reviewed
              in <hi rend="i">Der Bund</hi> and by Ester Adeyemi, <hi rend="i">Berner Zeitung</hi>,
              12 Nov. 1988.</p>
            <p>Dieter Löchle (b. 1952), <hi rend="i">William Blake—Roof’d in from Eternity</hi>,
              Universitätsbibliothek, Tübingen, Ger., 3 Apr.-25 May 1995. The catalogue, with a note
              on the artist by Susanne Padberg, translations from Blake’s poetry, and a commentary
              on Blake’s prophecies by the artist, is being distributed by the Galerie Druck &amp;
              Buch (Nauklerstrasse 7, D-72074 Tübingen, Ger.). The show was previously reviewed by
              Kurt Oesterle, <hi rend="i">Schwäbisches Tagblatt</hi>, 6 Apr. 1995: 27. On the
              occasion of the exhibition, and under the same title, two portfolios with
              reproductions of Löchle’s designs and his prints in offset lithography were issued in
              a limited edition of 50 copies each (Tübingen, Ger.: Galerie Druck &amp; Buch,
              1995).</p>
            <p>Jaume Plensa (b. 1955), “<hi rend="i">One thought fills immensity</hi>,” Städtische
              Galerie, Göppingen, Ger., 2 July-6 Aug. 1995. The exhibition catalogue contains
              Blake’s “Proverbs of Hell” and contributions by the artist, Werner Meyer, and Alain
              Charre (parallel texts in German and English).</p>
            <p>Nikolaus Utermöhlen (b. 1958), <hi rend="i">1992 Nikolaus Utermöhlen “An Infinite
                Painting” on A Vision of the Last Judgment by William Blake 1808</hi>, Zwinger
              Galerie, Berlin, Ger., 5 Sept.-10 Oct. 1992. In lieu of a catalogue, the gallery
              issued an “artist’s book” in an exceedingly small (and expensive) edition. The
              exhibition has been briefly reviewed in <hi rend="i">Die Tageszeitung</hi>, 15 Sept.
              1992.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
