<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.3.mccollister</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Seduction of Self-Abnegation in The Book of Thel</title>
        <author n="McCollister">Deborah McCollister</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1996/7</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996/97</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Hilda Hollis</name>
              <name>Marc Kaplan</name>
              <name>Deborah McCollister</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996/97"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
	<pb id="p30-90" n="90"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Seduction of Self-Abnegation in <hi rend="i">The Book of
                                Thel</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Deborah <name>McCollister</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In his 1961 analysis of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Thel</hi> and Tiriel, critic Peter F. Fisher comments: 
<q> Thel is
                            represented as a woman because she succumbs to mortality in a feminine
                            way—that is to say, passively—by a retreat into
                            wish-fulfilling fantasy. Tiriel is represented as a man because he
                            succumbs in a masculine way, and actively pursues the lure of tyrannical
                            power. . . . Both lose themselves—Tiriel by the path of tyranny,
                            and Thel by the way of suicide. She gives way to the indolence which
                            refuses to desire a human life, and he gives way to that aggression
                            which fails to understand and realize it. (206) </q></p>
          <p>In these characterizations, Fisher’s assignment of gender traits is
                        intriguing: “the feminine way” is “passive,” and
                        Thel’s refusal to enter human life is attributed to
                            “indolence.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">1</ref>
                        Similarly, despite his revolutionary spirit, William Blake reflected his
                        culture—one that believed woman’s essential worth lay in her
                        ability to procreate and nourish others.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n33" type="note">2</ref> As Thel searches to discover meaning in the vapor 
<pb id="p30-91" n="91"/>
						<supplied type="emend">of mortal life, personified natural elements demonstrate</supplied> 
						to her their own worth in the life cycle, a worth
                        achieved through self-abnegation. My purpose here is not simply to translate
                        the myth of Thel, but rather to discuss arguments for a mortal life of
                        self-abnegation as presented in <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Interestingly, in a 1989 assessment of
                                <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, Paul Youngquist says that
                                “<hi rend="i">an adolescent fear</hi> of sexual experience. .
                            .precipitates the denial of life” [emphasis mine] in <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi> On
the other hand, Urizen withdraws from eternity due to
                            “something in the organization of the mind itself, some <hi rend="i">principle
of self-preservation</hi> that paradoxically
                            wills death rather than submit to the contingencies of existence”
                            [emphasis mine] (90).</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Contemporary handbooks exhorted young
                            ladies to sweetly accept their roles “of servitude to masculine
                            desires and expectations” (Eaves et al. 80).</note></p>
          <p>Since the name “Thel” is derived from the Greek word for
                        “will” or “desire,” the implications for
                        Thel’s characterization are manifold. Some readers might see her as
                        willful, while others might attribute her name to the desire for knowledge
                        about life that motivates her.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">3</ref> At any
                        rate, early in the poem, Blake presents her as ripe for seduction from the
                        safe Vales of Har, which Foster Damon defines as “the state of
                        Self-love” (401). Her motto (i.1-4, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) reveals
                        her desire to know—but only from secondhand sources at first. A. G.
                        Den Otter, who classifies the forms of questions in <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Thel</hi>, observes that on the title page, the plate contains a bud
                        that “slithers up to her knee,” suggesting the temptation of
                        Eve (646). The motto “hooks Thel’s interest, managing
                        successfully to guide her to the altar of sacrifice” (647).
                        Blake’s pictures of Thel present her as an adolescent; her incessant
                        questions in the motto and throughout the work likewise convey a childish
                        and innocent nature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">4</ref> In her innocence,
                        she seeks to know what is in the pit, just as the Eagle and the Mole know,
                        but she trusts a predator and a blind, limited creature for her answers. Her
                        questions about Wisdom and Love, with their respective containers, a rod and
                        a bowl, suggest her naive eagerness to explore a contained, mortal life. But
                        in her innocence, she does not realize that both containers represent the
                        necessity of procreation in the cycle of mortal existence. 
<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Michael Ferber identifies many of the names in
                            the poem by showing connections with other Blakean works and myths
                            outside Blake; at the same time, he postulates that Blake may have
                            alluded to traditional myths only to make fresh suggestions from those
                            associations.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
                            Joseph Viscomi point to Blake’s “subtle uses of the
                            interrogative [in his illuminated books] as a way to confound common
                            assumptions, suggest alternatives, and engage the reader’s
                            imagination” (14).</note></p>
          <p>Thel is also ripe for seduction because of her willingness to separate from
                        her sisters, while not knowing who she is. The other Daughters of Mne
                        Seraphim know their place—tending the flocks (1.5, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). Their
dwelling, The Vales of Har, receives more attention in
                        Blake’s complementary work, <hi rend="i">Tiriel.</hi> It is a
                        peaceful valley, ruled by the senile Har and his sister/wife, Heva, who
                        “dwell in an extreme and childish old age, tended by Mnetha”
                        (their mother/nurse). Har is “the God of Moral Law” who holds
                        to “uninspired wisdom to enforce restrictive morality upon
                        man.” In fact, the dotard himself has authored the code (Sloss and
                        Wallis 275-76). Although this pastoral setting offers relative safety, Thel
                        is restless.</p>
          <p>Thel’s description of herself reveals another problem that contributes
                        to her vulnerability to seduction: although she is essentially selfish, she
                        does not possess identity. Refering to lines 10-18, Nelson Hilton observes:
                        “Thel displays an essential aspect of lamentation: not going
                        anywhere, not standing firm, but assimilating everything to its vision.
                        Narcissus-like, lamentation centers on itself and so defeats its
                        fulfillment” (30). Her description of herself in comparison to
                        objects—typical of Blake’s intentional
                        ambiguity—further reveals a female who does not realize her essence.
                        While she bemoans her destiny—should she be born—she first
                        compares herself with “a wat’ry bow” (1.8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). Such an
object is beautiful, but exists only because of the
                        light. “A parting cloud” (1.8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) collects
                        life-giving moisture, as Blake mentions later, but paradoxically, its
                        absence is usually heralded by humans since it obscures the favored
                        sunshine. “A reflection in a glass” is only a representation
                        of the real object, just as “shadows in the water” (1.9, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3)
are not solid entities and can change with the
                        ripples of the waves. The “dreams of infants” are not actual
                        events; even their smiles (1.10, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) are pointless,
                        since, as she has lamented earlier, they are “born but to smile
                        &amp; fall” (1.7, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). As she continues to
                        catalog transient forms, the ambiguities continue. A “dove’s
                        voice” is sweet, but mournful; “transient day”
                        enlightens, but grows dark; “music in the air” may be either
                        joyful or funereal (1.11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). In brief, even after Thel
                        has described herself, we know that she will fade, but we do not know how or
                        if the world will change when she does.</p>
          <p>Finally, Thel may be easily seduced into the mortal world because she is
                        ignorant of the harshness outside the Vales of Har. She uses
                        “gentle” (ll. 16-17) to describe the act of dying/rebirth and
                        the euphemism “sleep of death”; however, the vision she later
                        experiences in the land of the dead (plate 8) shatters these expectations.
                        Similarly, her expectations of “him that walketh in the garden in the
                        evening time” (l. 18) reveal her naivete. Genesis 3:8 uses this
                        phrase immediately after the fall of Adam and Eve and immediately before God
                        reprimands the pair and casts them out of the Garden of Eden. Ironically,
                        the voice she later hears in the land unknown is her own “voice of
                        sorrow” (l. 117).</p>
          <p>Blake has thus created a naive woman who asks questions restlessly, refuses
                        to accept her place in the Vales of Har passively, sees herself only in
                        vague terms, and expects to be treated consistently with gentleness.
                        Moreover, the Lilly, the Cloud, the Worm, and the Clay each attempts to
                        seduce Thel into mortal existence by appealing to her most outstanding
                        characteristic—her need to have a unique and lasting place in the
                        universe. In addition to the lines with which she has described her
                        transience (II. 12-15), an echoing refrain is formed by such lines as the
                        following: “I vanish from my pearly throne, and who shall find my
                        place?” (l. 41). “I complain, and no one hears my
                        voice” (l. 51). “And all shall say, ‘Without a use this
                        shining woman liv’d’” (l. 69). Morris Eaves, Robert
                        Essick, and Joseph Viscomi aptly note that “<hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Thel</hi> is Blake’s version of Ecclesiastes, with an innocent
                        woman substituted for the melancholy patriarch for whom ‘all is
                        vanity’” (78).</p>
          <pb id="p30-92" n="92"/>
          <p>Thel’s primal need, then, to feel significant in the universe, is
                        itself universal and thus common to both genders. Mindful of the culture of
                        Blake’s day, one can easily speculate as to the solutions the four
                        natural beings would have offered a young male in Thel’s state of
                        mind: perhaps that he win a battle, or make his voice eternal through poetic
                        expression, or accomplish some other substantial feat. However, the male
                        Cloud, the male Worm, the female Lilly, and the female Clay offer her
                        eternal life in exchange for what she can give to the earth in spite of, and
                        because of, her feminine gender. As Den Otter comments: “Rather than
                        satisfying Thel’s concern for the meaning of things, these small
                        educators [he mentions all but the Worm] redirect her focus to the 
<hi rend="i">use</hi> of things” (640).</p>
          <p>An examination of the designs highlights the consequential tensions: In some,
                        Thel “responds to her companions with imitative or sympathetic
                        gestures [see pls. 4 and 6], much as she speaks about her similarity to
                        them” (Eaves et al. 81). This very tendency to imitate and identify
                        with her potential seducers is thus in conflict with her reluctance to
                        acquiesce to their definition of her role, as is evident in plate 2, where
                        “she stands apart as a spatial expression of her separateness and
                        role as an observer more than an actor” (Eaves et al. 81).</p>
          <p>The Lilly of the valley is the first entity to address Thel’s problem.
                        Quite simply, she suggests that Thel imitate her by sacrificing herself and
                        accepting the cycle of life passively and even thankfully. Not only does the
                        Lilly accept her lowly position, but she loves it (ll. 19-21). The Lilly,
                        “So weak, the gilded butterfly scarce perches on [her] head”
                        (l. 22), is like Thel in that she is a virgin (l. 31). But she gives herself
                        to everything around her and rejoices to do so because “he that
                        smiles on all” has told her to do so (ll. 23-25). She is
                        “clothed in light” (l. 27) only to be melted later in the heat
                        produced by the light (l. 28). She will dwell in “eternal
                        vales” (l. 29) that are fertile, but remain in the place of
                        death.</p>
          <p>Thel sees irony in the Lilly’s gift of self. The bloom that makes her
                        beautiful and sweet-smelling attracts the innocent lamb, who devours her
                        while she “sittest smiling in his face, / Wiping his . . .
                        mouth” (ll. 36). But Thel admires the power that the Lilly’s
                        gift includes—the power to purify, revive, and tame, while being
                        consumed (ll. 37-39). The last line about the Lilly reinforces her role as
                        nurturer/giver: “[She] went to mind her numerous charge among the
                        verdant grass” (l. 47).</p>
          <p>Swinburne said that the Lilly, Cloud, and Worm teach that “the secret
                        of creation is sacrifice; the very act of growth is a sacrament . . . each
                        thing is redeemed from perpetual death by perpetual change” (quoted
                        in Sloss and Wallis 2:267). Thel is impressed by the flower, but is not
                        comforted and is not seduced quite yet into sacrificing herself. She has
                        seen the example, but still laments her own uselessness (Bloom 56).</p>
          <p>Compared with the obsequious female Lilly, the Cloud—a male
                        figure—is quite bold and impressive. His “golden head”
                        and “bright form” hover and “glitter” over Thel
                        as he addresses her, and the import of the Cloud’s exhortation to
                        Thel lies in its sexual meaning. The Cloud supplies the moisture for the
                        rivers where Luvah’s horses drink. In other Blakean mythology, Luvah
                        is the “mythical embodiment of the passional and sexual aspect of man
                        [who] repairs to the Vales of Har simply in order to rest and water his
                        horses” (Abrams 64). The Cloud seems to feel important largely
                        because he serves a god of eros.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, seeing Thel’s need to be significant in eternity, the
                        Cloud describes his union with the dew and what it produces. He makes Thel
                        identify with the female dew, whom he calls a “weeping virgin”
                        (l. 61). After all, Thel’s “gentle lamentation falls like
                        morning dew” (l. 9). The Cloud’s lofty language describes the
                        union explicitly: “And [I] court the fair-eyed dew to take me to her
                        shining tent: / The weeping virgin, trembling, kneels before the risen sun,
                        / Till we arise link’d in a golden band and never part, / But walk
                        united, bearing food to all our tender flowers” (ll. 60-63). In other
                        words, the dew is seduced into an ecstatic experience, she is never alone
                        again, and—most importantly—her ability to nurture tender
                        flowers is validation for her being. The Cloud thus suggests that if Thel
                        would yield herself to her proper function, she too could have the joy of
                        fruitful existence.</p>
          <p>Thel, however, recognizing that she has never nurtured, remains depressed
                        (ll. 64-68). She asks the Cloud what she intends as a rhetorical question:
                        “Or did [Thel] only live to be at death the food of worms?”
                        (l. 70). Echoing the heavenly being who has earlier told the Lilly to
                        rejoice in her ephemeral state (l. 25), the Cloud instructs Thel relative to
                        the “blessing” of the Worm (l. 73). Just before the Cloud goes
                        to find “his partner in the vale” (l. 78), he reminds her:
                        “Everything that lives / Lives not alone nor for itself” (ll.
                        73-74). But before she can be useful, Thel must abandon her fear of the
                        Worm. Brenda S. Webster acknowledges that critics often overlook “the
                        implicit degradation and forced submission of the woman. . . . In the
                        speeches of both Thel and the Cloud, the theme of degradation is condensed
                        in the opposition of high and low, shining virgin and earth worm”
                        (52).</p>
          <p>The thought of the Worm—associated symbolically with both death and
                        procreation—frightens the virgin Thel. So the Cloud shows her a worm
                        that will woo her without frightening her. Appearing as a naked, helpless
                        infant, the Worm immediately appeals to her repressed maternalism (Bloom
                        57). She speaks to it, but it can only weep in return (ll. 80-84). Of
                        course, these cries touch her more than any of the speeches she has heard
                        previously. The worm’s seductive powers are so strong that,
                        ironically, she sympathizes with the very entity that will devour her.</p>
          <pb id="p30-93" n="93"/>
          <p>The Clod of Clay that appears and nourishes the infant worm further arouses
                        Thel’s maternal drive and her search for significance. Modeling
                        self-sacrifice, the Clay exhales “her life. . ./In milky
                        fondness” (ll. 86-87). Her first words to Thel exhort the ideals of
                        sacrificial motherhood: “we live not for ourselves” (l. 88).
                        Moreover, the Clay describes a relationship derived from the account in
                        Genesis of the creation of man in which God began the human race by forming
                        Adam from clay and breathing into him the breath of life. Though a humble
                        entity, the Clay has gained eternity by joining God and bearing His
                        children: “My bosom of itself is cold, and of itself is dark; / But
                        he, that loves the lowly, pours his oil upon my head, / And kisses me, and
                        binds his nuptial bands around my breast, / And says: ‘Thou mother of
                        my children, I have loved thee, / And I have given thee a crown that none
                        can take away’” (ll. 90-94). The Clay does not understand this
                        relationship; she simply lives and loves (l. 96). Thus, the Clay models the
                        following message for Thel: Accept your role on earth, and do not
                        question.</p>
          <p>In plate 7, Thel’s hidden face suggests the loss of identity implicit
                        in maternal sacrifice, and as she cries again, she wipes her tears on her
                        white veil (l. 97). Blake is apparently playing upon the phrase “vale
                        of tears,” for the virgin draws closer here to a vision of the end of
                        life. Ironically, she cries to learn that God cares for the worm (l. 100),
                        but the glimpse she soon receives of her ultimate destiny as a mortal
                        reveals no benevolent God. The Worm and the Clay present danger for Thel,
                        although they appear as innocent entities coming to the aid of a wandering
                        innocent. Note, however, how the Clay’s appeal to Thel gradually
                        evolves from an invitation, to a suggestion, to a command: “Wilt
                        thou, O Queen, enter my house? ’Tis given thee to enter / And to
                        return: fear nothing, enter with thy virgin feet” (ll. 106-07). The
                        last line is deceitful: Thel has much to fear because she is indeed a
                        vulnerable virgin.</p>
          <p>The Clod of Clay, who has modeled benevolent motherhood and told Thel about a
                        benevolent God, is able to bring her to the brink of mortal
                        experience—but only with the condition that the virgin can return to
                        the vales of Har (l. 107). Here at last Thel sees her destiny: After
                        entering earthly existence, she will indeed be eternal, but eternally dying,
                        mournful, and—despite her usefulness as mate and mother—alone.
                        Simply put, her sacrifice (in following the example of the female Lilly,
                        dew, and Clay) will not bring her eternal peace. The intention of the Clay
                        (and Blake) is ambiguous here. Although the Clay has seduced her into a
                        terrible place, the revelation of that place allows Thel to know the truth
                        and to reject her destiny on earth.</p>
          <p>In the “land unknown” (l. 109), Thel witnesses the corrupted
                        forms of two of her advisors. Before, the Cloud was “golden,”
                        “bright,” and “glittering” (ll. 52-53), but the
                        “land of clouds” is dark and foreboding (l. 113). The dew had
                        once united with the Cloud, to “never part” and to bear food
                        (ll. 62-63). Here the dew rests on graves (l. 114). These ironies have been
                        foreshadowed, however, as early as on plate 2, where a vine “forms a
                        traditional emblem of marriage or education” but in outline also
                        suggests a tombstone, and the figure of Thel observes two other figures,
                        either in a moment of happy union or of rape, thus symbolizing Thel’s
                        own uncertainties about sexuality (Eaves et al. 81-82).</p>
          <p>For the first time in the poem, Thel dares to listen to her own voice, now
                        coming from her grave (ll. 116-17). It laments the sorrowful fact that her
                        senses have “whirled her to destruction” (Bloom 61). The
                        sensory images gradually grow darker and more sexual. The first sensory
                        organ mentioned is the Ear (l. 118). After all, she has listened to
                        others’ voices. Brenda Webster observes: “A further image of
                        the ear as a whirlpool that fiercely ‘draws creation in’ is
                        linked to the Clod’s womb-grave and foreshadows Blake’s view
                        of the ravenous earth . . . who tries to draw all existence into her
                        voice” (56). Next is the Eye, and Thel asks why it cannot be closed
                        “to the poison of a smile” (ll. 118-19). This question
                        reflects the foolishness of the “pitying tears” (l. 97) that
                        once trusted the benevolence of God (ll. 98-101). Other temptations to the
                        Eye are then listed (ll. 120-22), along with the honeyed Tongue and
                        responsive Nose (ll. 123-25). Finally, the mention of touch boldly reveals a
                        daunting picture of sexual union: “a little curtain of flesh on the
                        bed of our desire”—one that can place “a tender curb
                        upon the youthful burning boy” (ll. 126-27)—is not the
                        pleasant image that the united Cloud and dew earlier suggested to Thel. She
                        learns that even in experience, she will find no fulfillment (Bloom, in
                        Erdman 809).</p>
          <p>The truth about her mortal initiation into the sexual experience has this
                        result: “The Virgin started from her seat, &amp; with a shriek /
                        Fled back unhinder’d till she came into the vales of Har” (ll.
                        129-30). Alicia Ostriker says “She discovers that her fate is far
                        worse than she imagined. Instead of merely fading away and dying gracefully,
                        she will have to undergo a storm of passions and restraints”
                        (154).</p>
          <p>Blake’s decision concerning Thel’s fate was made after at least
                        two years of incubation. Although the title page reads “1789,”
                        the same date as <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, textual critics
                        believe that plate 6 was actually completed two years later, along with 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> During this time, Blake decided that
                        Thel would wander into the “land unknown” at the Clay’s
                        invitation, but that she would lose her courage upon hearing her own voice
                        from the grave. Unlike Oothoon of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion</hi>, she does not fly to her lover (Ferber 52-53).</p>
          <p>A decade ago, G. E. Bentley, Jr. remarked upon a recently discovered sketch
                        for <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi> The sketch indicates Blake’s plan for two
                        designs facing each other, with lines indicating text. On the left is a
                        sketch of the brooding Thel that later became plate 7. On the right is a
                        figure with outstretched arms, resembling the figure of Thel later printed
                        as plate 6. Obviously, the designs were reversed for printing, and a
                        structure 
<pb id="p30-94" n="94"/>
resembling a Greek temple was discarded
                        from above the Thel with outstretched arms, probably because this manmade
                        object distracts from the context of the pastoral setting. Bentley
                        postulates that in the early sketch, “Thel appears to be on the
                        threshold of the Temple of the Earth, about to enter without fear”
                        (139). But in the course of crafting this illustrated poem, Blake chose to
                        have Thel enter reluctantly, only to flee in fear.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">5</hi> For a detailed discussion of the
                            controversial dating of the plates in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, see Joseph
                            Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 234-37 and
                            252-58.</note></p>
          <p>Critics have noted the different ages of children riding upon the serpent in
                        plate 8, suggestive of the process of maturation “in accordance with
                        the use of snakes as emblems of natural life and mortality . . . [and] in
                        the context of phallic symbolism, the design would seem to indicate a
                        control over sexual experience by playful innocence.” The reins also
                        suggest “prudence controlling desire” (Eaves et al. 85). If
                        the female driving the snake is Thel, she looks not so much frightened as
                        determined, with a steady, forward gaze. Whereas Michael Ferber posits that
                        the pictured serpent and children allude to Blake’s early play <hi rend="i">King
Edward the Third</hi>, where the prince says that his
                        recklessness is like “the innocent child” who
                        “unthinking, plays upon the viper’s den” (62-63), I
                        suggest that the serpent recalls the one in Eden that tempts Eve. Unlike
                        Eve, however, Thel has harnessed and controlled the serpent and uses it to
                        take her “unhinder’d . . . [to] the vales of Har” (l.
                        129).</p>
          <p>Because she has been allowed to see the truth, the attempted seduction of
                        Thel into the cycle of a mortal woman’s life fails at last. She will
                        not surrender her haven of virginity in order to live eternally in such a
                        dark world. The sacrifice of her present self for a utilitarian, earthly
                        self would be a mistake. Disappointed by her adventurous quest away from the
                        valley, Thel chooses to live in a world governed by the dotard Har and his
                        restrictive codes, rather than enter into a mortal body, encumbered by
                        sensory temptations and death. In the vale, she faces the future of becoming
                        like the eternally aging Har and Heva in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (Ostriker
                        151).</p>
          <p>Or is her life in the Vales of Har necessarily full of dread? One critic has
                        speculated that “Thel” is an anagram of “Lethe,”
                        the river of forgetfulness. Perhaps Thel will forget her cares and become
                        more like her sisters. W. J. T. Mitchell suggests still another possibility:
                        When Thel returns to the Vales of Har and to the “Daughters of Mne
                        Seraphim,” is she returning to “a land of infantile regression
                        [with] . . . daughters of ineffectual memories (Mnemosyne) rather than
                        inspiration?” Or could the prophetic Blake be predicting an age where
                        “Daughters of Memory shall become the Daughters of
                        Inspiration?” (83). Just as Thel has raised incessant questions, the
                        conclusion of the poem and the enigmatic emblems in the illustrative plates
                        raise questions and offer few resolutions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">6</hi> In their edition of <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake: The Early Illuminated Books</hi>, Eaves, Essick and Viscomi
                            contextualize the ending of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, noting the outcome
                            of other female figures in Blakean works, and comparing what Thel
                            learns—or fails to learn—with the doctrines expressed in
                            Blake’s annotations to Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                                Heaven and Hell, There is No Natural Religion</hi>, the botanical
                            poems of <corr type="emend">Langhorne</corr> and Darwin, and cultural ideologies of the day
                            (80-81).</note></p>
          <p>One matter is resolved, however. Although Blake shows that Thel’s only
                        alternative to relative obscurity in the Vales of Har is for her to listen
                        to the voices of Earth that tell her to yield herself to the cycle of life,
                        he does give her a choice. With a loud shriek, his heroine, in effect, cries
                        “No!” to the experience of the earthly woman.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Abrams, M. H., ed. <hi rend="i">The Norton Anthology of English
                                Literature.</hi> 3rd ed. 2 vols. New York: Norton, 1968.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “From Sketch to Text in Blake: The Case of The
                            Book of Thel.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19 (1986): 128-41.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic
                                Argument.</hi> Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1963.</p>
            <p>Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols
                                of William Blake.</hi> Providence: Brown UP, 1965.</p>
            <p>Den Otter, A. G. “The Question and The Book of Thel.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 30 (1991):633-55.</p>
            <p>Eaves, Morris, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Early
Illuminated Books.</hi> Princeton:
                            Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake.</hi> Commentary by Harold Bloom. Garden City, N.Y.:
                            Doubleday, 1965, cited hereafter as <hi rend="i">E.</hi></p>
            <p>Ferber, Michael. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Blake.</hi> London:
                            Penguin, 1991.</p>
            <p>Fisher, Peter F. <hi rend="i">The Valley of Vision: Blake as Prophet and
                                Revolutionary.</hi> Ed. Northrop Frye. Toronto: U of Toronto,
                            1961.</p>
            <p>Hilton, Nelson. <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision
                                of Words.</hi> Berkeley: U of California, 1983.</p>
            <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of
                                the Illuminated Poetry.</hi> Princeton: Princeton, 1978.</p>
            <p>Ostriker, Alicia. <hi rend="i">Vision and Verse in William Blake.</hi>
                            Madison: U of Wisconsin, 1965.</p>
            <p>Sloss, D. J. and Wallis, J. P. R. <hi rend="i">The Prophetic Writings of
                                William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon, 1926.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi>
                            Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>Webster, Brenda S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology.</hi>
                            Athens: U of Georgia, 1983.</p>
            <p>Youngquist, Paul. <hi rend="i">Madness and Blake’s Myth.</hi>
                            University Park: Pennsylvania UP, 1989.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
