<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.3.kaplan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Jerusalem and the Origins of Patriarchy</title>
        <author n="Kaplan">Marc Kaplan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1996/7</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996/97</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Hilda Hollis</name>
              <name>Marc Kaplan</name>
              <name>Deborah McCollister</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996/97"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <pb id="p30-68" n="68"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and the Origins of Patriarchy</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Marc <name>Kaplan</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>“O Albion why wilt thou Create a Female Will?” Los wails in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
30:31.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> The term
                    “Female Will” here makes its first appearance in Blake’s
                    poetry, though for years critics have used it retroactively to explicate prior
                    works, because it ties together so many of the sinister actions of the women
                    characters of the earlier poetry.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> Critics
                    who elaborate on Blake’s notion of the Female Will usually make the case
                    that Blake does not intend a criticism of actual women by the term, but rather
                    of nature and Natural Religion, or else that his criticism is not of
                    woman’s empowerment but of the perverse exercise of that power. On the
                    other hand, feminist readings like those of Susan Fox and Anne K. Mellor have
                    pointed out that Blake seems uneasy about <hi rend="i">any</hi> display of
                    willfulness on the part of the female, and that he almost invariably portrays
                    such situations negatively, while simultaneously idealizing female
                    self-sacrifice as embodied in characters like Ahania and Oothoon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
                    <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is no exception to this latter rule. 
<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> David V. Erdman and Harold Bloom, eds., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi> (New York:
                        Doubleday, 1988) 176. Subsequent references to this text will be designated
                        by <hi rend="i">E</hi> followed by the page number. Plate and line numbers
                        will accompany the page numbers where appropriate.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Lengthy critical works on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are few, probably due
to the difficulty of the poem,
                        which presumes a thorough familiarity with Blake’s earlier poetry.
                        Most studies remain at the level of establishing the epic’s coherence
                        and making it scrutable. Such works include Morton D. Paley’s <hi rend="i">The
Continuing City</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1983), Minna
                        Doskow’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Jerusalem</hi> (East
                        Brunswick, N.J.: Associated University Presses, 1982), Joseph
                        Wicksteed’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Jerusalem</hi>
                        (London: Trianon Press, 1953), a work that has been criticized for its
                        eccentric and erroneous interpretations, and Joanna Witke’s <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Epic: Imagination Unbound</hi> (London:
                        Croom Helm, 1986). Works dealing with gender in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        include Thomas D. Frosch’s <hi rend="i">The Awakening of Albion</hi>
                        (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1974), discussed in the text, and Brenda
                        Webster’s <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology</hi>
                        (Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1983). Webster contends: “The
                        chief psychological problem posed by the poem is how to reconcile the
                        father, Albion, with the son, Los. The difficulty is their mutual suspicion
                        and hatred, which are linked for their desire for exclusive possession of
                        the mother, Jerusalem.” As the argument of this chapter indicates, I
                        agree with Webster that the poem’s central struggle is that of son
                        against patriarch and patriarchy, but disagree with her implication that
                        Blake is unconscious of his poem’s theme.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Susan Fox, “The Female as Metaphor in
                        William Blake’s Poetry,” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 3
                        (1977): 508-13, and Anne K. Mellor in “Blake’s Portrayal of
                        Women,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16 (1982-83): 148-55, advance the
                        basic propositions involving Blake’s sexism around which subsequent
                        debate has revolved. Alicia Ostriker in “Desire Gratified and
                        Ungratified: William Blake and Sexuality,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16
                        (1982-83): 156-65, concurs with Fox and Mellor that in Blake’s ideal
                        universe “to be female is to be dependent” (162) and notes
                        that “In <hi rend="i">Milton and Jerusalem</hi> . . . female figures
                        are either powerful or good; never both” (162-63). Other works which
                        deal with Blake’s sexual politics include Webster, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic
Psychology</hi> (see above) and her article,
                        “Blake, Women and Sexuality” in Donald Ault, Mark Bracher and
                        Dan Miller, eds., <hi rend="i">Critical Paths: Blake and the Argument of
                            Method</hi> (Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press, 1987): 204-24;
                        Margaret Storch, <hi rend="i">Sons and Adversaries: Women in Blake and D.H.
                            Lawrence</hi> (Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 1991); and
                        Diana Hume George, <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell
                        University Press, 1980). Webster, Storch and George constitute a wing of
                        Blake criticism that is both Freudian and at times feminist as well, but
                        George, ostensibly using the same Freudian paradigms and often looking at
                        the same poems as Storch and Webster, comes to an almost opposite judgment
                        of Blake. Both Webster and George see Blake’s views as similar to
                        those of Freudian radicals like Norman O. Brown, but whereas George
                        champions Brown’s and Blake’s revolutionary sexual ethos,
                        Webster finds such strategies dangerous and regressive, and Storch, after
                        Webster, has a similar view. David Punter, “Blake, Trauma and the
                        Female,” <hi rend="i">New Literary History</hi> 15 (1984): 475-90,
                        suggests that the trauma of Oothoon in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
                            of Albion</hi> is really the projected displacement of the trauma felt
                        by Blake and males in general at a time when gender roles were in flux.
                        Nelson Hilton in “An Original Story” in <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and
Textuality</hi>, Hilton and Thomas
                        Vogler, eds., (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1986) 69-104,
                        provides one of the most interesting recent defenses of Blake and 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, making the argument that Blake’s eye (his
                        text) saw more than his heart knew—a familiar poststructuralist
                        strategy, but Hilton’s knowledge of the background material on Mary
                        Wollstonecraft (see n15) helps him fashion a convincing case.</note></p>
        <p>There is more to the above statement of Los than the sexism that might
                    immediately meet the eye, however. Los clearly implies that the evil Female Will
                    is the creation of Albion, the fallen patriarch of British civilization, and not
                    something brought about by woman herself. Los later reiterates, “O Albion
                    why didst thou a Female Will Create?” (56:43, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 206). A
                    close scrutiny of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> reveals, I believe, that Blake
                    offers a perceptive critique of masculine gender-roles without a similar
                    rethinking of the role of the female.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> criticizes male power as it is embodied in the
                    structures of a society specifically identified by the poet as 
<hi rend="i">patriarchal.</hi> This term has for Blake many of the same pejorative
                    connotations as it does for contemporary feminist discourse: in both instances,
                    “patriarchal” connotes an oppressive masculinist system that
                    perpetuates itself through the definition and control of <hi rend="i">property.</hi></p>
        <p>The word “patriarch” and other terms derived from it appear but a
                    single time in Blake’s work prior to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, an
                    incidental reference in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> to “a throne
                    &amp; a pavement / Of precious stones surrounded by twenty four venerable
                    patriarchs” (123:35, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 393). In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, however,
Blake uses the terms eight times, each time in a
                    highly significant context. It first appears in the prose section “To the
                    Jews” that precedes chapter 2 (27, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 171): “Was
                    Britain the Primitive Seat of the Patriarchal Religion?” Blake here 
<pb id="p30-69" n="69"/>
means Patriarchal Religion to be taken in a double
                    sense: as referring both to the eternal truths of the Judeo-Christian culture
                    and to the degenerated Natural Religion which is the actual practice of that
                    same culture. It becomes clear that Blake identifies the patriarchal element in
                    that heritage with its fallen or erroneous aspect when he links patriarchy to
                    Druidism a few lines later: “Your Ancestors derived their origin from
                    Abraham, Heber, Shem, and Noah, who were Druids: as the Druid Temples (which are
                    the Patriarchal Pillars &amp; Oak Groves) over the whole Earth witness to this
                    day” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 171). Druidism is the prehistoric form of
                    Natural Religion; in one quatrain of the poem that follows the prose on plate
                    27, Blake addresses the “Spectre of Albion”: 
					<q> Is this thy soft
                        Family-Love<lb/>
 Thy cruel Patriarchal pride<lb/>
 Planting thy Family
                        alone<lb/>
 Destroying all the World beside.<lb/>
 (27:76-80, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 173) </q></p>
        <p>The criticism of patriarchy enters <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> proper further on
                    in chapter 2, when the twelve sons of Albion corroborate their father’s
                    fall by “Rearing their Druid Patriarchal rocky Temples around his
                    limbs” (46:14, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 196). Later, Jerusalem hears the
                    Divine Voice asking “Wilt thou make Rome thy Patriarch Druid”
                    (61:50, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 212). Jerusalem subsequently laments the death of
                    her beloved “Along the Valley of Destruction, among these Druid Temples /
                    Which overspread all the Earth in patriarchal pomp &amp; cruel pride”
                    (79:66-67, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 235). Urthona, the Eternal form of Los,
                    characterizes himself as acting “Against the Patriarchal pomp and
                    cruelty, labouring incessant” (83:4, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 241). Finally,
                    in the apocalyptic burst of song that concludes the work, the poet exultantly
                    asks “Where is the Tree of Good &amp; Evil that rooted beneath the cruel
                    heel / of Albions Spectre the Patriarch Druid!” (98:47-48, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 258). The
return of humankind to the unfallen state is clearly
                    linked to the abolition of patriarchy.</p>
        <p>Blake does not stop at mere condemnation of patriarchy; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> contains the
poet’s most sophisticated analysis of
                    institutionalized masculinism. The critique of conventional masculine roles and
                    authority figures is a consistent theme in Blake’s poetry from early on.
                    Helen Bruder, in “The Sins of the Fathers: Patriarchal Criticism and <hi rend="i">The
Book Of Thel</hi>,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
                    finds Blake already engaged in a critique of patriarchy in <hi rend="i">The Book
                        of Thel</hi>, one of the first illuminated books, in which she describes the
                    poet as “exclaiming against the patriarchal fetishizing of the hymen as
                    an oppressive curb to an erotics of mutual delight” (156). She likewise
                    finds the poet preaching against phallocentrism in the creation of a
                    “young woman (Thel) who is so unimpressed by . . . displays of the
                    phallus” (156). The anti-phallocentrism, the attack on conventional (that
                    is, Urizenic) masculinity, and the repudiation of repression and virginity are
                    indeed constant preoccupations of Blake’s writing and art. But Bruder is
                    in error to say that the presentation of these themes in themselves constitutes
                    “a neglected feminist dimension to Blake’s long-acknowledged
                    radicalism” (147). A critique of masculinity is not per se a critique of
                    gender, and an insistence on woman’s sexual freedom is not necessarily a
                    feminist position when that erotic freedom is, as it is so often in
                    Blake’s myth, the only new freedom that the poet will allow his female
                        characters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is perhaps the most dramatic example of the true
                    character of Blake’s sexual politics: never has the poet’s
                    condemnation of traditional masculine authority in the form of patriarchy been
                    more overt and forceful, yet Blake’s solution to the problem in no way
                    presumes an increase in female empowerment. <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
                        Helen Bruder, in <hi rend="i">Historicizing Blake</hi>, Steve Clark and
                        David Worrall, eds. (New York: St. Martin’s, 1994) 147-59.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Nor am I convinced by Bruder’s attempts
                        to establish a counter-tradition of Blake criticism that vindicates the
                        poet’s radical feminism. The authors she cites, like Bruder herself,
                        make a case for Blake as an opponent of phallocentrism and a champion of
                        woman’s sexual freedom, but not a case for the poet as an advocate of
                        genuine female empowerment. Vernon E. Lattin, in “Blake’s Thel
                        and Oothoon: Sexual Awakening in the Eighteenth Century” in <hi rend="i">The
Literary Criterion</hi> 16 (1981): 11-24, notes the way
                        “Blake speaks very clearly about the centrality of woman’s
                        sexual awakening as the way of vision” (12) and finds Oothoon, unlike
                        Thel, gaining liberation “by confronting her desire” (22);
                        Lattin doesn’t consider the extent to which female sexual license
                        benefits male power structures. K. D. Everest, in “Thel’s
                        Dilemma” in <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 37 (1987): 193-208,
                        similarly describes the way “nominal virtue in Thel is gradually
                        subverted by an insurgent sexuality of superb energy and abandonment”
                        (206). Catherine L. McClenahan, in “‘No Face Like the Human
                        Divine?’: Women and Gender in Pickering Manuscript,” in G. A.
                        Rosso and Daniel P. Watkins, eds., <hi rend="i">Spirits of Fire: English
                            Romantic Writers and Contemporary Historical Methods</hi> (London:
                        Associated University Presses, 1990) 189-208, demonstrates how Blake shares
                        Wollstonecraft’s critique of sexual modesty, but fails to note that
                        the rationality that Blake so dislikes is the fundamental principle of
                        Wollstonecraftian feminism. Another of McClenahan’s arguments, that
                        Blake learned subversive techniques and voices from marginalized woman
                        writers, sounds suspiciously like the exploitative appropriation of feminine
                        characteristics that Alan Richardson has termed a
                        “colonization” of the feminine and found to be typical of male
                        romantic writers as a group (see n17). David G. Reide, in “The
                        Symbolism of the Loins in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” in 
<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi>
                        21 (1981): 547-64, convincingly shows how the poem rates Blake’s
                        contempt for “mere genital sexuality” (549), and Elizabeth
                        Langland in “Blake’s Feminist Revision of Literary Tradition
                        in ‘The Sick Rose’” in Donald Ault, Mark Bracher and
                        Dan Miller, eds., <hi rend="i">Critical Paths: Blake and the Argument of
                            Method</hi> (Durham, NC and London: Duke Univ. Press, 1987) 225-43,
                        demonstrates how that poem’s ironic language exposes the
                        speaker’s violation of the rose by phallic psychological projections;
                        as noted in the text however, anti-phallocentrism does not automatically
                        constitute feminism.</note></p>
        <p>The critique of patriarchy advanced by Blake in his final epic is, however, in
                    many ways strikingly similar to the argument of feminist historian Gerda Lerner
                    in her contemporary 
<pb id="p30-70" n="70"/>
study, <hi rend="i">The Creation of
                        Patriarchy.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> Lerner maintains that
                    the control by males of women’s sexual behavior and reproductive capacity
                    is the very cornerstone of our civilization. She contends that this
                    appropriation occurred prior to the institution of private property, and in fact
                    was the very foundation of private property (in Western history, Lerner locates
                    this event during the period of the early Sumerian and Mesopotamian
                    civilizations, 2200-1800 B.C.). Later, male subjugation of woman’s
                    sexuality resulted in class structure, and finally in slavery, the ultimate
                    commodification of the human (well underway by the time of the Babylonian Code
                    of Hammurabi, 1752 B.C.). According to Lerner, men in the earliest societies
                    were divided into classes relative to the amount of
                    “wealth”—potentially fertile women - over whom they had
                    hegemony. In this same historical period, men divided all women into two groups,
                    one “respectable” or “honorable,” meaning under the
                    protection of a male, and the other “not respectable,” meaning
                    unattached to a male. The two kinds of women were frequently distinguished by
                    the presence or absence of a veil, the wearing of which denoted the
                    “good” woman and also marked this “honorable” woman
                    as an article of property, which accounts for her protected status.
                    Male-dominated society moved toward an increasingly abstract and increasingly
                    masculine idea of God, culminating finally in the invisible-but-male Hebrew
                    deity, who ordains that the expression of woman’s sexuality for other
                    than reproductive purposes is sinful (Lerner places the beginning of the writing
                    of the Book of Genesis in the tenth century B.C., but believes the stories
                    within it to be parts of an oral myth several centuries older). 
<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Gerda Lerner, <hi rend="i">The Creation of
                            Patriarchy</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1986), 8-10. The
                        pages indicated present a summary of Lerner’s argument and indicate
                        chapters in which points are elaborated further.</note></p>
        <p>Lerner’s theory is frankly, admittedly, speculative. Her work has drawn
                    criticism for what has been deemed a too-willful projection of contemporary
                    feminist polemic onto a body of inconclusive (and inadequately researched)
                    empirical evidence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> However damaging such
                    criticism may be to Lerner’s credibility as a historian, it in no way
                    lessens the value of her work as an instrument for the interpretation of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, for Blake’s poem, avowedly mythic and even
                    anti-empirical in its construction of history, is openly polemical.
                    Blake’s epics retain an engagement with literal history by virtue of the
                    poet’s implicit belief that utopian fantasy, by the suggestion of
                    unrealized human possibilities, can provoke real change in the social/political
                    world (in this respect, the poet’s strategy remains unchanged since the
                        <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>). <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi>
                        Scholar Sarah B. Pomeroy, writing in the <hi rend="i">New York Times Book
                            Review</hi>, 20 April 1986, voices the common concerns of
                        Lerner’s critics when she complains of Lerner’s
                        “subordination of principles of historical investigation to feminist
                        politics.” She objects to Lerner’s construction of “a
                        grandiose paradigm demonstrating the continually deteriorating position of
                        women.” Pomeroy takes Lerner to task for grouping “societies
                        as different as the Sumerians, Babylonians, Assyrians, 
                        <corr type="emend">Amorites,</corr> Hebrews and
                        Greeks as though they existed on a historical continuum and evolved from one
                        another,” and she complains that Lerner is led into some crucial
                        misunderstandings because of her dependence on works in translation and
                        secondary sources. In a review in <hi rend="i">History: Reviews of New
                            Books</hi> (Jan.-Feb. 1987 [66-67]), however, it is precisely
                        Lerner’s “intellectual boldness, her bluntness and penchant
                        for polemic” that Bernard Essen praises. Calling her work
                        “vastly ambitious and admirable, even heroic,” Essen goes on
                        to laud Lerner for “her flair for theorizing and generalizing,
                        sometimes outrageously,” which would serve equally well as a
                        description of Blake at his best.</note></p>
        <p>Lerner traces the development of patriarchy in a historical sequence. Blake in
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> displays a remarkable anticipation of the
                    initial stages of Lerner’s model. Blake, like Lerner, locates the
                    beginning of “fallen” history in the patriarchal suppression and
                    control of women’s sexual behavior. He develops a notion implicit in
                    Lerner’s model into a cardinal point of his myth: the destructive
                    dualisms of Western thought, which the poet has been bent on exposing ever since
                        <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, are in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
revealed to be rooted in the primal separation of women into
                    two camps, “good” (chaste) women and whores. The division of
                    females into good women and bad women provoked the development of the moral code
                    that Blake hates, with its radical separation of good and evil, heaven and hell,
                    holy and profane, pure and defiled. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the initial
                    moment of this separation is depicted in Albion’s separation of the
                    “good” woman Vala, who is actually sinister, from the
                    “bad” Jerusalem, whose only sins are her sexual openness and her
                    capacity for self-sacrifice. The veil of Vala is perhaps the poem’s
                    central trope; it becomes in Blake’s hands the symbol of everything that
                    separates humankind from its salvation. In the end, Jerusalem and Vala are
                    rejoined as a “whole” woman, Brittannia.</p>
        <p>The latter stages of Lerner’s model, however, diverge from and even oppose
                    Blake’s vision. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake would replace the
                    patriarchy with a (male) brotherhood bonded by a covenant. The covenant of
                    brothers is indeed a part of Lerner’s structure, but for her it
                    represents not the overthrow of patriarchy, but its ultimate consolidation.
                    Blake’s ideal brotherhood, in which women are shared among the brothers,
                    contains all the qualities to which Lerner objects. Further, Blake
                    doesn’t appropriate female procreativity outright, but in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
as in his earlier poetry, he denigrates
                    “merely” natural and biological creation and seeks to subsume it
                    under a “higher” creativity, that of artistic inspiration, a
                    quality which is portrayed as decisively masculine, because it involves the (for
                    Blake) quintessentially masculine ability to organize a “female”
                    and passive perceptual world.</p>
        <p>Lerner’s sequential model of patriarchal history has as its culmination
                    the production of a type of metaphorical construct that in her view has
                    fundamentally distorted all Western thought. She describes this body of tropes as
                    configuring “the symbolic devaluing of women in relation to the
                    divine” (10). For Blake in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, this hierarchical
                    relationship 
        <pb id="p30-71" n="71"/> 
        			is not considered a metaphor, but rather
                    the principle by which the poet’s mythic universe is organized; it is
                    ultimately the one element in the Blakean cosmos that seems <hi rend="i">not</hi> to be
trope, but a categorical imperative. The devaluing of the
                    feminine is everywhere implicit in Blake’s construction of the
                    relationship of masculine self to female Emanation, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
concludes with a vision of a post-apocalyptic world in which
                    this hierarchy of self and Emanation is still firmly in place. Blake’s
                    vision is anti-patriarchal while still being hierarchically masculinist. In
                    contemporary terms, Blake has made gender-as-a-social-construction identical
                    with gender-as-essence. This is precisely the sort of transformation of a
                    metaphor into a fundamental principle of existence which Blake in other
                    situations recognizes immediately as Natural Religion.</p>
        <p>Having struck a tone critical of Blake, let me rush momentarily to his defense.
                    It would be disingenuous to take Blake to task for not meeting the standards of
                    a later era in his treatment of gender, or to suggest that he was in some way
                    worse on the issue than most other writers of the time (in fact, I am going to
                    imply the opposite). To single Blake out for special personal condemnation would
                    indeed undermine any sort of feminist argument predicated upon a belief in the
                    socially-constructed nature of attitudes about gender. The purpose of this essay
                    then, is not to establish Blake’s sexism (that has been done by Fox,
                    Mellor and others) or even to criticize it, so much as to demonstrate what a
                    crucial role the notion of gender-hierarchy plays in the form and functioning of
                    Blake’s visionary cosmos. If it proves impossible in this analysis to
                    suppress an occasional note of late-twentieth-century dismay, it is only because
                    the poet <hi rend="i">does</hi> reject so many of the attitudes of his era that
                    encounters with his sexist formulations, even after repeated readings, are
                    always slightly startling. The fact that gender seems to be an exception to a
                    general rule perhaps tells us less about Blake than about his and our
                    culture.</p>
        <p>However, if gender inequality is accepted as an organizing principle in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, I believe the poem can be rescrutinized to yield up
                    new insights. Blake’s sexism is no less intricately imaged than the other
                    parts of his myth, and his depiction of female characters, while by contemporary
                    standards perhaps less progressive than other parts of his artistic world, is no
                    less powerful. Indeed, I will imply below that, as with Picasso in our own era,
                    these female portraits represent some of the most intensely rendered of
                    Blake’s “Visionary Forms Dramatic” precisely because of the
                    anxiety they inspire in the poet.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>I</title>
          </head>
          <p>The patriarch whose fall and redemption are the subject of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is Albion,
Blake’s Universal Man. His fall was
                        also described in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, but there the Zoas
                        themselves (the components of Albion’s unfallen self) took center
                        stage. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the Zoas are relatively minor
                        players, and the focus is on Albion himself, his sons and daughters, and
                        Jerusalem, “the Emanation of the Giant Albion,” as the
                        poem’s title informs us. The first half of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> deals with
Albion’s fall into “Eternal
                        Death.” One of the most important models for the story of
                        Albion’s fall is the Book of Job, which Blake in fact illustrated
                        near the end of his life. Like Albion, Job is a patriarch who loses his
                        family and then has it restored to him. S. Foster Damon, in his book on the
                        Job engravings, maintains that Blake’s images interpret the Job story
                        as an internal, psychological drama: Job doesn’t lose his children to
                        physical catastrophe, rather he loses their affection and respect due to his
                        self-righteous morality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref>
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> operates on a similarly psychological level:
                        when Albion’s Spectre and Emanation come to the Divine Humanity
                        saying “We alone are escaped” (43:29, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                        191), a direct reference to Job 1:15, they are not fleeing a massacre (as in
                        the Bible story), but rather from Albion’s own darkened psyche and
                        the fallen world it generates around itself, “Albions darkning
                        [r]ocks” (43:28, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 191). For Blake, as always,
                        psychology constitutes geography. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> S.
                            Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> (Providence: Brown
                            University Press, 1966) 3. This has become the generally accepted
                            interpretation of the Job engravings. The Job series is also linked to
                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> by the “Druid” trilithons
                            (Blakean symbols of Natural Religion) that appear in both sets of
                            illustrations.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> begins with the fall of Albion already in
                        progress. The Divine Vision calls out: 
						<q> return Albion! return!<lb/>
 Thy
                            brethren call thee, and thy fathers, and thy sons,<lb/>
 Thy nurses, and
                            thy mothers, thy sisters and thy daughters<lb/>
 Weep at thy souls
                            disease, and the Divine Vision is darkend:<lb/>
 (4:10-13, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 146) </q>
Albion, like Job, has lost his family and been
                        afflicted with disease. The problem, ironically, is patriarchy: in seeking
                        to hold and protect his family, Albion has in fact lost them spiritually,
                        because of his tyrannical possessiveness. Albion’s specific error is
                        to hide his Emanation from the Divine Humanity—that is, to restrict
                        her sexual favors to him alone, the act which Lerner theorized was the
                        crucial first move in the creation of patriarchy (the Emanation in this poem
                        has characteristics of both a wife and a daughter). With this event,
                        jealousy comes into the world: “So spoke Albion in jealous fears,
                        hiding his Emanation” (4:33, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 147).</p>
          <p>So <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> begins <hi rend="i">in medias res</hi>, as
                        does a classical epic. The fall of Albion will be recapitulated throughout
                        the poem. In asserting patriarchal control, Albion has lost control; his
                        sons, the products of patriarchy, now control England while Albion lies
                        helpless in a dream of Eternal Death. The illustration at the bottom of
                        plate 9 shows the fallen Albion prostrate on the 
                        ground.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> 
                        As Erdman notes, however, Albion’s 
<pb id="p30-72" n="72"/>
						eyes are open, leading us to believe that his
                        stupor is self-willed. The next plate depicts the fallen rule of
                        Albion’s sons, who are characterized by Morton Paley as “the
                        objects of [Albion’s] aggression disguised as 
                        justice”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>:
                        <q> 
                        	And this is the manner of the Sons of Albion in their strength<lb/>
                        	They take the Two Contraries which are calld Qualities, with which<lb/>
                        	Every Substance is clothed, they name them Good &amp; Evil<lb/>
                        	From them they make an Abstract, which is a Negation<lb/>
                        	(10:7-10, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 152-53)
                        </q>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The reference is to Copy D, as reproduced
                            in David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden
                            City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1974) 288. All plate numbers refer to the 
<hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> reproduction. In other copies, Blake
                            changed the order of some of the plates in chapter 2. The order in the
                            reproduction in <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> corresponds to the
                            order in <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi></note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">The
                                Continuing City</hi> 221.</note></p>
          <p>The separation of the “good” from the “evil”
                        woman (in Lerner’s terms, the veiled is opposed to the unveiled
                        woman; in Blake’s terms, Vala—her name, of course, punning on
                        “veil”—is separated from Jerusalem) has led to a moral
                        code of good and evil that becomes increasingly abstract, and which
                        characterizes everything regarding the body as sinful. Vala and Jerusalem,
                        body and spirit, are properly dynamic contraries; the Sons have separated
                        them into negating opposites. These historical developments find their
                        culmination in a god who is male and totally abstract/transcendent. The
                        transformation of the patriarch into an abstract father-god means that
                        patriarchy can live on even though the patriarch himself (or an overtly
                        patriarchal religion) may appear to be dead, like the paralyzed Albion.
                        Patriarchy continues to operate, reproducing itself with mechanical
                        persistence: this is one significance of the turning of the “Starry
                        Wheels,” the activity of Albion’s Sons. The Twelve Sons form
                        themselves into “Three Immense Wheels” (18:8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163), because
they are “Jealous of Jerusalems
                        children” (18:6, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163), and covetous of their
                        heritage as Albion’s lawful sons by Vala.</p>
          <p>The Sons want Jerusalem to be cast out because, in the words of Harold Bloom,
                        “if she is reunited to man, their reign ends” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 934):
<q> Cast!
Cast ye Jerusalem forth! The Shadow of
                            delusions!<lb/>
 The Harlot daughter! Mother of pity and dishonourable
                            forgiveness<lb/>
 Our Father Albions sin and shame!<lb/>
 (18:11-13, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163) </q>
The Sons complain that their father has
                        destroyed the patriarchal family by his indiscretions with Jerusalem. With
                        their cry for punishment, they think they are redressing their
                        father’s crimes; in fact, they are repeating them, because it was
                        Albion who first declared Jerusalem sinful. In this ironic way, the sins of
                        the fathers are visited on the children, and patriarchy replicates itself
                        though the cycle of guilt and repression. The Sons pledge allegiance to: 
						<q>
                            Babylon the City of Vala, the Goddess Virgin-Mother.<lb/>
 She is our
                            Mother! Nature! Jerusalem is our Harlot-Sister<lb/>
 Return’d with
                            Children of pollution, to defile our House,<lb/>
 With Sin and
                            Shame.<lb/>
 (18:29-32, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163) </q>
Vala and Jerusalem
                        were originally one, in the form of Brittannia. In casting Jerusalem out,
                        the Sons are only furthering the initial act of Albion, who separated the
                        two and covered Vala with the veil of patriarchal property.</p>
          <p>This issue of property underlies Albion’s plight: 
		<q> His Children
                            exil’d from his breast pass to and fro before him<lb/>
 His birds
                            are silent on his hills, flocks die beneath his branches<lb/>
 His tents
                            are fall’n! his trumpets, and the sweet sound of his harp<lb/>
                            Are silent on his clouded hills, that belch forth storms &amp;
                            fire.<lb/>
 His milk of Cows, &amp; honey of Bees, &amp; fruit of
                            golden harvest,<lb/>
 Is gather’d in the scorching heat, &amp; in
                            the driving rain:<lb/>
 (19:1-6, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163-64) </q></p>
          <p>Albion’s loss is here, as in Blake’s Job illustrations, both
                        internal and external. Albion’s wealth is at once the true riches of
                        the realized spirit and senses, and the material, projected forms in which
                        the patriarch tries unsuccessfully to capture and hold those riches. The act
                        of projection is in itself a loss: in creating wealth, Albion in fact loses
                        it. His loss becomes a loss of riches as well as family (Albion’s
                        children are similarly both the disowned parts of himself and the real
                        children whom he alienates by that act of disowning). Blake here anticipates
                        Lerner’s view that all wealth comes not from labor, as in Marx, but
                        from male control of woman’s sexuality, the act which for Lerner is
                        the very origin of private property. The same imagery of loss of wealth
                        pervades Albion’s own description of his situation: 
						<q> Shame divides
                            Families. Shame hath divided Albion in sunder!<lb/>
 First fled my Sons,
                            &amp; then my Daughters, then my Wild Animations<lb/>
 My Cattle next,
                            last ev’n the Dog of my Gate. the Forests fled<lb/>
 The
                            Corn-fields, &amp; the breathing Gardens outside separated<lb/>
                            (21:6-9, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 166) </q></p>
          <pb id="p30-73" n="73"/>
          <p>Albion’s complaint, earlier in the same lament, that “The
                        disease of Shame covers me from head to feet: I have no hope / Every boil on
                        my body is a separate &amp; deadly Sin” (21:3-4, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                        166), again links him to Job, who was likewise afflicted with boils. The
                        boils of Blake’s Albion/Job are really an inner “disease of
                        Shame”; the loss of his children is not their physical death but the
                        loss of their love and respect, and the loss of wealth and property is not
                        only a material loss but, as noted above, the loss of the full realization
                        of the spirit and of the senses in all their abundance. These losses come to
                        pass as a result of Albion’s desire to control the sexuality and
                        fertility of woman. Albion now has control over woman, but has lost the
                        capacity for sexual joy because sin and guilt are the vehicle of that
                        control. He mourns “Vala! O that thou wert pure! / That the deep
                        wound of Sin might be clos’d up with the Needle” (21:12-13,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 166), but it was he himself who made the vagina
                        sinful when he made it the source of wealth. Albion eventually comes to look
                        back nostalgically on a time when “Albion coverd the whole
                        Earth” (24:44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 170) because woman’s
                        sexuality had not been divided and apportioned.</p>
          <p>As Paley points out, Albion in Jerusalem “takes on many of the
                        characteristics assigned to Urizen-figures in Blake’s earlier
                            works.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> A plea by Jerusalem
                        makes it clear that Albion has both Urizen’s sense of sin and his
                        capacity for reductive over-analysis: 
						<q> Then spoke Jerusalem O Albion! my
                            Father Albion<lb/>
 Why wilt thou number every little fibre of my
                            Soul<lb/>
 Spreading them out before the Sun like stalks of flax to
                            dry?<lb/>
 The Infant Joy is beautiful, but its anatomy<lb/>
 Horrible
                            ghast &amp; deadly!<lb/>
 (22:19-23, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 167) </q>
Blake
                        has actually made two significant switches here: not only has Albion been
                        described in Urizenic terms, but Jerusalem speaks the same words with which
                        Tharmas accuses Enion in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> 4:29-33 (<hi rend="i">E</hi>
302). There, the (male) Tharmas complained of
                        Enion’s (female) jealousy. Blake’s transfer of the speech to
                        the female Jerusalem makes clear the paranoia behind Tharmas’s
                        declaration in the earlier poem: his need to dominate, rather than
                        woman’s jealousy, is the ultimate source of sexual guilt. 
<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Paley 198.</note></p>
          <p>As with Urizen in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, the masculine triumph of
                        Albion is actually a triumph of Vala. Albion pleads: 
						<q> But come O Vala
                            with knife &amp; cup: drain my blood<lb/>
 To the last drop! then hide
                            me in thy Scarlet Tabernacle<lb/>
 For I see Luvah whom I slew. I behold
                            him in my Spectre<lb/>
 (22:29-31, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 167-68) </q>
He
                        has accepted the veil of Vala, which he himself imposed, as a final reality,
                        and he is afflicted with an unbearable sense of guilt because his
                        institution of sin has “slain” humankind’s passional
                        life. Albion can think of no remedy but to elevate Vala into a
                        virgin-goddess and to offer himself as a human sacrifice. In terms of
                        Lerner’s historical model, Albion here is at the stage where
                        patriarchy institutionalizes and encourages the worship of the
                        mother-goddess; Babylon was such a civilization. Whereas Lerner sees the
                        religion of the goddess as having both positive and negative aspects (the
                        goddess is a powerful female, but her power is restricted to sexuality and
                        fertility), Blake can see any goddess-worship only as a form of Natural
                        Religion, demanding human sacrifice.</p>
          <p>In order to replace this constant blood-sacrifice, Albion takes Vala’s
                        veil and uses it as a “Veil of Moral Virtue, woven for Cruel
                        Laws” (23:22, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 168). This corresponds to a stage
                        in Lerner’s model where the religion of the goddess is suppressed and
                        supplanted by the moral religion of the abstract and invisible father-god.
                        This has the advantage for Albion of changing his position from that of
                        accused to that of accuser: “every Act a Crime, and Albion the
                        punisher &amp; judge” (28:4, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 174). He can now
                        condemn his offspring instead of vice versa: the patriarch has resumed his
                        position of authority. The Cities of England make a last effort to redeem
                        him, asking 
						<q> What is a Wife &amp; what is a Harlot? What is a Church?
                            &amp; What<lb/>
 Is a Theatre? Are they Two &amp; not One? can they
                            Exist Separate?<lb/>
 Are not Religion &amp; Politics the Same Thing?
                            Brotherhood is Religion<lb/>
 O Demonstrations of Reason Dividing
                            Families in Cruelty &amp; Pride!<lb/>
 (57:8-11, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                            207) </q></p>
          <p>The separation of “Wife” from “Harlot,” in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and in Lerner’s
model, is the source, the
                        first separation from which other divisions spring. The patriarchal family
                        is broken by this same chain of separations, but however broken, divided,
                        “dysfunctional” in the current parlance, the patriarchal
                        family still perpetuates itself through the mechanistic power of guilt.
                        Albion, his fall complete, sinks down to the Rock of Ages, where he remains
                        until the apocalypse.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>II</title>
          </head>
          <p>Jerusalem and Vala represent Blake’s most sophisticated development of
                        positive and negative female figures, yet a problem inherent in this
                        dichotomy from its first appearance in the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
                            and of Experience</hi> remains: to use Paley’s words,
                        “Blake’s ranging of female figures along the lines of the
                        Jerusalem-principle and the Vala-principle 
<pb id="p30-74" n="74"/>
                        threatens to become congruent with the old cultural bifurcation” that
                        Blake ostensibly wants to protest.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
                        Almost all the women in the poem are subsumed as “surrogates”
                        (Paley’s term) of Jerusalem or Vala. As surrogates of Jerusalem,
                        Paley lists Erin, Dinah, Rosamund, Oothoon and Mary, each of whom represents
                        “an aspect of redemption through female love.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Vala’s camp includes Rahab and
                        Tirzah, familiar from the earlier poetry, and the malevolent Daughters of
                        Albion, chief among them Cambel and Gwendolen (the one important female
                        figure not connected to either Jerusalem or Vala is Enitharmon, about whom
                        more later). In <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Blake was
                        intent upon questioning the validity of oppositional thinking altogether
                        (“Excess of sorrow laughs. Excess of joy weeps” [8:26, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 36]).
The opposition of the two groups of women is a
                        similarly false dualism, created by the deluded Albion. However,
                        Blake’s presentation of the inversion of the dualism as an
                        apocalyptic revelation—Jerusalem, the bad woman is really good; the
                        chaste Vala is really evil—has the effect of making the opposition
                        seem authoritative, with only the specific terms of the dichotomy brought
                        into question. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Paley 194.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Paley 185.</note></p>
          <p>In dividing Jerusalem from Vala, Albion invents sin and accuses Jerusalem of
                        its commission: 
						<q> Jerusalem! dissembler Jerusalem! I look into thy
                            <corr type="emend">bosom:</corr><lb/>
 I discover thy secret places: Cordella! I behold<lb/>
 Thee
                            whom I thought pure as the heavens in innocence &amp; fear:<lb/>
                            (21:18-20, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 166) </q>
The echoes of Lear and Cordelia
                        are appropriate (one of the Daughters of Albion is named Ragan as well):
                        Lear was another mistaken patriarch involved in the division of property and
                        the desire to possess <hi rend="i">all</hi> of his daughters’ love.
                        Vala is the real dissembler and hider of secrets; her secret is that the
                        patriarchal division of women into virgins and whores is a deception. Albion
                        accedes to the demands of Vala and his sons and daughters and casts
                        Jerusalem out. Los later encounters her as he wanders the night streets of
                        London, the domain of the impoverished (45:39-43, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 195).
                        This is Jerusalem’s appropriate place, because in casting out
                        Jerusalem, Albion created private property and social classes (as in
                        Lerner’s theory), dividing rich and poor.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> here links the division of women into two camps
                        with the division of humanity into impoverished and wealthy classes. Vala
                        wears the veil which is an ancient signifier of both the married woman and
                        the priestess or nun (often spoken of as being married to the deity).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> The veil denotes that the woman is
                        property, an item of wealth, but as such she is also under the protection of
                        patriarchal power in either its secular or ecclesiastical form, and
                        therefore enjoys certain privileges. The unveiled woman has no protector, no
                        connection with wealth and consequently no status. Jerusalem therefore
                        dwells among the wretched, where the Daughters of Los are building
                        Golgonooza in the midst of the squalor of the fallen city of London: 
						<q>
                            Terrible their distress &amp; their sorrow cannot be utterd<lb/>
 And
                            another Daughter of Los sat at the Spinning Wheel<lb/>
 Endless their
                            labour, with bitter food. void of sleep,<lb/>
 Tho hungry they labour:
                            they rouze themselves anxious<lb/>
 Hour after hour labouring at the
                            whirling Wheel<lb/>
 Many Wheels &amp; as many lovely Daughters sit
                            weeping<lb/>
 (59:28-33, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 209) </q>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> David G. Riede, “The Symbolism of
                            the Loins in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” (see n5)
                            links the veil to the physical hymen “and . . . its simultaneous
                            meaning as the cover of mystery” (553). The veil of the wife or
                            the nun is a kind of permanent hymen, which signifies the control and
                            protection of the woman’s sexuality by patriarchal institutions.
                            “Once the veil is torn, the loins lose their all-obsessing
                            importance,” Riede goes on to say (557), describing
                            Blake’s apocalypse as a deliverance from the tyranny of
                            genitality. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake establishes the
                            connection between this fallen genitality and the obsession with
                            material wealth.</note></p>
          <p>The Daughters weave to re-form the ancient work of Vala, who wove the veil of
                        fallen nature. The spinning wheels they turn indicate the source of their
                        suffering in the Starry Wheels of patriarchal Deism turned by
                        Albion’s Sons. Never before, except perhaps in
                        “London,” has Blake so clearly based his portrayal on real
                        scenes of the exploitation of women in the London of his day. The Divine
                        Voice searches for Jerusalem and finds her 
						<q> closd in the Dungeons of
                            Babylon<lb/>
 Her Form was held by Beulahs Daughters. but all within
                            unseen<lb/>
 She sat at the Mills, her hair unbound her feet naked<lb/>
                            Cut with the flints: her tears run down, her reason grows like<lb/>
 The
                            Wheel of Hand. incessant turning day &amp; night without rest<lb/>
                            (60:39-43, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 210) </q></p>
          <p>This is the fate of women without a “veil,” without the
                        protection of a male.</p>
          <p>Jerusalem dwells here because the oppressed necessarily know the reality of
                        the spirit, the spirit being all they have because their physical life is
                        bondage. Yet the suffering can become so intense that even the consolations
                        of the spirit are lost: “Insane she raves upon the winds hoarse,
                        inarticulate” (60:44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 210). In despair, Jerusalem
                        questions the existence of God, the “Human Imagination”
                        (60:57, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 211). To comfort her, the Divine Voice tells her
                        Blake’s revisionist version of the story of Joseph and Mary, in which
                        Mary 
<pb id="p30-75" n="75"/>
has been impregnated not by God but simply by
                        a man other than her husband. Joseph at first throws her out as a harlot,
                        but he hears the Divine Voice in a dream and realizes he must forgive Mary
                        and take her back. Jerusalem realizes her essential humanity is still
                        unsullied within her and takes heart: “Every Harlot was once a
                        Virgin: every Criminal an Infant Love!” (61:52, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                        212).</p>
          <p>Blake has affirmed woman’s right to a sexual freedom commensurate with
                        that of man; but more importantly, Joseph has not only forgiven Mary, but
                        renounced as well the fundamental privilege of all patriarchy: he has
                        accepted as his own offspring the impending child of his wife by another
                        man. Mary’s song of freedom is a chant of female sexuality unleashed:
						<q> Then Mary burst forth into a Song! she flowed like a River of<lb/>
                            Many Streams in the arms of Joseph &amp; gave forth her tears of
                            joy<lb/>
 Like many waters, and Emanating into gardens &amp; palaces
                            upon<lb/>
 Euphrates &amp; to forests &amp; floods &amp; animals wild
                            &amp; tame from<lb/>
 Gihon to Hiddekel, &amp; to corn fields &amp;
                            villages &amp; inhabitants<lb/>
 (61:28-32, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 212)
						</q>
						Blake’s symbolism corroborates Lerner’s view that
                        patriarchal society is founded upon the control of female sexuality: the
                        rushing torrent of Mary’s freed libido in effect reclaims all the
                        institutions and products of the society built upon the repression of that
                        sexual force.</p>
          <p>However, Blake, as much as any patriarch, <hi rend="i">identifies</hi> woman
                        with sexuality, and treats the liberation of that sexuality as
                        woman’s total liberation. Blake envisions a good woman as either an
                        ardent lover or nurturing mother. It is in the form of maternity that Mary
                        offers consolation to Jerusalem: “Jerusalem recieved / The Infant
                        into her hands in the Visions of Jehovah” (61:47-48, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 212). The
long lament which is Jerusalem’s last major
                        speech in the poem makes clear her longing for the unfallen state which she
                        experienced as a kind of universal maternity: 
						<q> The Fifty-two Counties of
                            England are hardend against me<lb/>
 As if I was not their Mother, they
                            despise me &amp; cast me out<lb/>
 London coverd the whole Earth.
                            England encompassd the Nations:<lb/>
 And all the Nations of the Earth
                            were seen in the Cities of Albion:<lb/>
 My pillars reachd from sea to
                            sea: London beheld me come<lb/>
 From my east &amp; from my west; he
                            blessed me and gave<lb/>
 His children to my breasts, his sons &amp;
                            daughters to my knees<lb/>
 (79:20-26, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 234-35) </q></p>
          <p>In this state, the roles of lover and mother were apparently conjoined: 
		<q>
                            the Lamb of God met me there.<lb/>
 There we walked as in our secret
                            chamber among our little ones<lb/>
 They looked upon our loves with joy:
                            they beheld our secret joys:<lb/>
 With holy raptures of adoration<lb/>
                            (79:41-44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 235) </q>
Jerusalem in the illustration
                        on plate 46 is depicted as just such an ideal conjunction of lover and
                        mother. There Vala covers herself with the veil of mystery, and would cover
                        the naked beauty of Jerusalem, who stands apart surrounded by three
                        children.</p>
          <p>Unlike Jerusalem, Vala is interested in power. Just as Blake does not imagine
                        a good woman as other than a mother or lover, he likewise seems unable to
                        see a willful female as other than evil. There are no women in Jerusalem who
                        are strong-willed yet positive with which to balance the negativity of Vala
                        and her surrogates. Blake does, however, integrate the malevolence of Vala
                        with his analysis of the evils of patriarchy. Immediately after he separates
                        Vala from Jerusalem, Vala is described as “spreading her scarlet Veil
                        over Albion” (21:50, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 167). She is smart enough to
                        see that the veil that disempowers also empowers; she can turn the
                        patriarchal creation of sin against its author. Vala condemns Albion with
                        his own invention, using the same words Enion spoke to Tharmas in <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi>: “I have looked into the secret Soul
                        of him I loved / And in the dark recesses found Sin &amp; can never
                        return” (22:14-15, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 167).</p>
          <p>Vala celebrates her power in the aggregate form of the Daughters of Albion:
						<q> She cries: The Human is but a Worm, &amp; thou O Male: Thou
                            art<lb/>
 Thyself Female, a Male: a breeder of Seed: a Son &amp;
                            Husband: &amp;<lb/>
 Lo.<lb/>
 The Human Divine is Womans Shadow, a Vapor
                            in the summers heat<lb/>
 Go assume Papal dignity thou Spectre, thou Male
                            Harlot!<lb/>
 Arthur<lb/>
 Divide into the Kings of Europe in times remote
                            O Woman-born<lb/>
 And Woman-nourishd &amp; Woman-educated &amp;
                            Woman-scorn’d!<lb/>
 (64:12-17, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 215) </q>
On
                        one level, this speech is an apt and even feminist mockery of the
                        pretensions of patriarchy (“Papal dignity;”
                        “Arthur;” “the Kings of Europe”) to some sort of
                        divinely ordained masculine authority. Vala reminds Los that the edifice of
                        his civilization is built upon the control of female sexuality. However, in
                        the context of the entire poem, <pb id="p30-76" n="76"/>
we can see that the
                        poet shares the patriarch’s terror of being “feminized”
                        by passive (i.e. “womanly”) dependence on a woman for nurture
                        and sexual gratification (“a Son &amp; a Husband”).</p>
          <p>For instance, anxiety about the sexual power of woman predominates in
                        Blake’s depiction of the sacrificial altar of Natural Religion: 
						<q>
                            they sit naked upon the Stone of trial.<lb/>
 the Knife of flint passes
                            over his howling Victim: his blood<lb/>
 Gushes &amp; stains the fair
                            side of the fair Daug[h]ters of Albion.<lb/>
 . . . . .<lb/>
 They pour
                            cold water on his brain in front, to cause.<lb/>
 Lids to grow over his
                            eyes in veils of tears: and caverns<lb/>
 To freeze over his nostrils,
                            while they feed his tongue from cups<lb/>
 And dishes of painted clay.
                            Glowing with beauty &amp; cruelty:<lb/>
 They obscure the sun &amp; the
                            moon; no eye can look upon them.<lb/>
 (66:19-21, 30-34, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 218) </q></p>
          <p>This is the agony of Albion tormented by woman as depicted in plate 26, where
                        Vala, Rahab and Tirzah wind his umbilical cord (or his bowels) into a ball.
                        Woman is indicted as the agent of Natural Religion; her rejection of man
                        causes the fall of the senses. In scenes like this, the indictment of the
                        patriarchy recedes and woman seems to act as an independent agent of the
                        fall.</p>
          <p>Blake further condemns the female as the cause of war; the Daughters of
                        Albion are 
						<q> Ashamed to give Love openly to the piteous &amp; merciful
                            Man<lb/>
 Counting him an imbecile mockery: but the Warrior<lb/>
 They
                            adore: &amp; his revenge cherish with the blood of the Innocent<lb/>
                            (67:19-21, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 220) </q></p>
          <p>The Warriors then sing a song of homage: 
		<q> I am drunk with unsatiated
                            love<lb/>
 I must rush again to War: for the Virgin has frownd &amp;
                            refusd<lb/>
 Sometimes I curse &amp; sometimes bless thy fascinating
                            beauty<lb/>
 (68:62-64, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 222) </q>
Certainly woman
                        throughout history has been dangled before men as a prize of war, but Blake
                        makes her the willful initiator of the conflict. Gwendolen, the Emanation of
                        Hyle, confesses to as much a bit later: “I have mockd those who
                        refused cruelty &amp; I have admired / The cruel Warrior” (81:1-2,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 238).</p>
          <p>The entire drama of the Daughters of Albion triumphant takes place after
                        Albion has collapsed onto the Rock of Ages. Blake seems to imply that with
                        the patriarch unconscious, Vala, or the Female Will, runs amok. Still, the
                        poet does juxtapose this nightmarish portrayal of female power against the
                        sufferings of Jerusalem in the Dungeons of Babylon, and holding the two in
                        balance, one could argue that Blake has in sum presented a myth that
                        symbolizes the contention of Mary Wollstonecraft and other female writers of
                        the era: while real women are exploited, men engage in the violent and
                        tormented pursuit of ideal female beauty and the glittering wealth produced
                        by woman’s enslavement.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref>
                        Blake’s remedy for this situation, however, is a problematic one: 
						<q>
                            they refuse liberty to the male; &amp; not like Beulah<lb/>
 Where every
                            Female delights to give her maiden to her husband<lb/>
 The Female
                            searches sea &amp; land for gratification to the Male Genius:<lb/>
                            (69:14-17, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 223) </q>
This passage is the culmination
                        in Blake’s poetry of a long series of declarations, beginning with
                        Oothoon’s famous speech in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion</hi> (7:23-29, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 50) in which the female
                        tolerance of male promiscuity is posited as a condition of the paradisal
                        state. Oothoon at least claims a corresponding sexual freedom for herself,
                        but in subsequent poems (see, for example, Milton 33:1-9 [<hi rend="i">E</hi> 132]),
where the Divine Voice reproaches the Daughters of
                        Beaulah for cutting off his sexual pleasures with jealousy) promiscuity is
                        depicted as an exclusively masculine prerogative. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi>
Mary Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">A Vindication of
                                the Rights of Woman</hi> (New York: Norton, 1988). Wollstonecraft
                            succinctly refutes the canard that the beauty of women gives them a
                            power over individual men that compensates for their powerlessness in
                            society, commenting: “I do not wish women to have power over men,
                            but over themselves” (62). Nelson Hilton in “An Original
                            Story,” 69-78 (see n3), provides a thorough summary of the
                            circumstantial case that indicates Blake and Wollstonecraft might have
                            known each other personally. Other female writers of the period who
                            shared Wollstonecraft’s condemnation of the cult of beauty were
                            Mary Anne Radcliffe, <hi rend="i">The Female Advocate</hi> (New York: G.
                            Olms, 1980): Mary Hays, <hi rend="i">An Appeal to the Men of Great
                                Britain on Behalf of Women</hi> (New York: Garland, 1974), and even
                            the later and much more conservative Priscilla Wakefield in 
<hi rend="i">Reflections on the Present Condition of the Female Sex</hi>
                            (London: Darton, 1817). Blake shares these writers’ disdain for
                            the cult of female beauty, but not their parallel exaltation of
                            woman’s rational powers.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s sexual paradise, Beulah, is a lower state than Eden, but still
                        an ostensible improvement over our fallen world of Generation. In the latter
                        world, Blake expresses an alternative to fallen reality through the actions
                        of the character Los.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>III</title>
          </head>
          <p>Los is for Blake the anti-patriarch, the character whose actions are meant to
                        undo the negative heritage of patriarchy. In order to redeem Albion, Los
                        must persuade him to put aside his patriarchal pride; to become a member of
                        a brotherhood of (male) equals, as in the message of the Divine Vision:
                        “I am not a God afar off, I am a brother and a friend” (4:18,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 146). Because “Los was the friend of Albion
                        who most lov’d him” (35:12, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 181), Los
                        calls the cities of 
<pb id="p30-77" n="77"/>
England to help him restore
                        Albion: “Brotherhood is Religion,” (57:10, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                        207), the Cities declare. In the poem’s apocalyptic climax, Albion
                        sees Los and Jesus become the same person, saying to Jesus, “I see
                        thee in the likeness &amp; similitude of Los my Friend” (96:22, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
256), and Jesus declares, “nor can Man exist but
                        by Brotherhood” (96:28, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 256).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> The most extensive recent discussion of
                            Blake’s notion of brotherhood is in Michael Ferber’s <hi rend="i">The Social
Vision of William Blake</hi> (Princeton:
                            Princeton University Press, 1985) 69-88. Ferber notes that “The
                            prime source of Blake’s ideas about brotherhood, as about so much
                            else, is the New Testament” (69) so that “Spiritual
                            brotherhood is a state where none are inferior or superior and all
                            equally share in the benevolence and joy, a state of unity founded on,
                            and symbolized by, the Eternal Man who walks among us, Jesus the
                            Imagination or Albion the collective man himself” (84). However,
                            Ferber notes that Blake was deeply interested in liberty and fraternity
                            but “had almost nothing to say . . . about equality” (68),
                            an idea whose implications for the female become clear when Ferber
                            remarks that the Christian fraternity upon which Blake modeled his own
                            idea of brotherhood “is a fraternity in the literal sense: the
                            only full participants are male” (86), and that, though
                            “Blake’s fraternity seems not to exclude women,”
                            still “Blake was content to deploy the traditional symbols and
                            analogies, which bore indelibly the stamp of the patriarchal society
                            where they were established” (87).</note></p>
          <p>In Gerda Lerner’s model of history, however, brotherhood did not
                        overthrow patriarchy; it refined and sustained it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> In the Western tradition, this historical
                        development is represented by the covenant made by God with Israel in
                        Genesis and Exodus. Lerner argues that “The decisive change in the
                        relationship of man to God occurs in the story of the covenant, and it is
                        defined in such a way as to marginalize women.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> Women are definitively excluded from the access to
                        God shared by members of this brotherhood. <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Lerner
180-99.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Lerner 188.</note></p>
          <p>Blake never uses the word “covenant” before <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, yet there it appears
six times, including four
                        occasions on plate 98, the poem’s apocalyptic conclusion. The poet
                        declares: 
						<q> And I heard Jehovah speak<lb/>
 Terrific from his Holy Place
                            &amp; saw the Words of the Mutual Covenant Divine<lb/>
 . . . . . .<lb/>
                            In the Forgiveness of Sins according to the Covenant of Jehovah. They
                            Cry<lb/>
 Where is the Covenant of Priam, the Moral Virtues of the
                            Heathen<lb/>
 (98:40-41, 45-46, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 258). </q>
For Blake
                        this new covenant fulfills the true covenant of the Bible, but cancels the
                        covenant of morality, which he regards as heathen. The emphasis of the new
                        covenant on the forgiveness of sins is consonant with traditional
                        Christianity. Nowhere does Blake imply that this new covenant includes
                        women.</p>
          <p>Lerner notes that the key ritual by which the Judaic covenant was reaffirmed,
                        circumcision, by its very nature excludes women. She maintains that it marks
                        the male as the older of procreative power, countering the goddess-religions
                        in which priests were either castrated or else forced to give the fruit of
                        their sexual couplings to the goddess.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
                        “Circumcision” is another word that never appears in
                        Blake’s earlier poetry; in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, as Edward J.
                        Rose points out, it appears nine times, always as a positive symbol.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> As Rose also notes, Blake goes to
                        great lengths in the poem “to contrast circumcision with
                        Virginity” (16), portraying the latter negatively: the Eternals cry
                        out, “Establishment of Truth depends on destruction of Falshood
                        continually / On Circumsion: not on Viginity, O Reasoners of Albion”
                        (55:65-66, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 205). Virginity for Blake relates to the
                        religion of the goddess in its castrating mode; its modern incarnation is
                        the cult of female modesty and chastity. The same “female”
                        religion is condemned when Los’s Spectre and Emanation, observing
                        Albion’s fall, see “the Sexual Religion in its embryon
                        Uncircumcision” (44:11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 193). In the apocalypse,
                        the Divine Vision is seen “Circumscribing &amp; Circumcising the
                        excrementitious / Husk &amp; Covering into Vaccuum evaporating revealing
                        the lineaments of Man” (98:18-19, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 257). 
<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Lerner 191-92.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Edward J. Rose, “Circumcision
                            Symbolism in Blake’s Jerusalem,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Romanticism</hi> 8 (1968) 16-25.</note></p>
          <p>It is not surprising that the female in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is
                        frequently portrayed as the barrier to this new brotherhood that Los would
                        create: Vala attempts to delude Albion that she is the true Jerusalem,
                        declaring that “the Divine appearance is Brotherhood, but I am Love /
                        Elevate into the Region of Brotherhood with my red fires” (29:52 -
                        30:1, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 176). Albion shrinks from the revelation Los would
                        show him, “Rending the fibres of Brotherhood &amp; in Feminine
                        Allegories / Inclosing Los” (44:18-19, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 193). In
                        the poem’s ultimate crisis, Los posits the impossibility of male
                        brotherhood without the submission of woman: “How then can I ever
                        again be united as Man with Man / While thou my Emanation refusest my Fibres
                        of dominion” (88:12-13, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246). Implicit here and
                        elsewhere is the notion that the ideal brotherhood would involve the sharing
                        of women, a development that might at first appear to abolish woman’s
                        status as property but actually compounds it. Jerusalem, Blake’s
                        ideal female, yearns for the ancient times when she was shared in this
                        manner: 
						<q> Italy saw me, in sublime astonishment: France was wholly
                            mine:<lb/>
 As my garden &amp; as my secret bath; Spain was my heavenly
                                <pb id="p30-78" n="78"/>
couch:<lb/>
 I slept in his golden hills:
                            the Lamb of God met me there.<lb/>
 (79:39-41, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 235)
						</q></p>
          <p>Jerusalem maintains that <hi rend="i">she</hi> was the owner of these places,
                        but in fact her act of ownership was to yield herself up to one and all as a
                        lover. Blake here means this woman-sharing to be pure metaphor, but it is a
                        metaphor founded on the derogation of the feminine in relation to the
                        masculine, in contrast to the democratic, egalitarian metaphor of sharing
                        brothers that characterizes the ideal relations of males to other males in
                        the poem.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>IV</title>
          </head>
          <p>On plate 86 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Los struggles with Enitharmon in
                        what Harold Bloom calls “Los’s own crisis with his
                        Emanation” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 944). The crisis is in fact the
                        crisis of Blake’s entire mythic structure; a crisis provoked by the
                        contradictions inherent in the concept of gender on which the poet has based
                        his visionary universe.</p>
          <p>There are hints throughout the first three chapters of the epic that Blake is
                        directing the poem toward a revelation about the sexes. There are in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> more usages of the word “sex” and
                        its derivatives than in all of Blake’s earlier writings combined. The
                        word is sometimes employed in a sense subtly different than contemporary
                        usage: in these instances, sex and the sexual are pejorative terms, as when
                        Los’s Spectre and Emanation perceive “the Sexual Religion in
                        its embryon Uncircumcision” (44:11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 193), or when
                        the “Spectrous Uncircumcised Vegetation” of the Ulro forms
                        “a Sexual Machine: an Virgin Form” (39:24-25, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 186-87) or when
Los denounces Vala as “The Sexual Death
                        living on accusation of Sin &amp; Judgment” (64:22, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 215). When
Blake speaks of the sexual here, he in fact means the
                            <hi rend="i">anti</hi>-sexual (Milton O. Percival points out that the
                        fall into sex is for Blake a fall into chastity<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>. The Sexual Religion is the patriarchal religion of chastity
                        and the repression of sex; that is why it appears in the form of an aged
                        virgin. Blake calls the anti-sexual “Sexual” because he
                        believes that the sexual personality as we know it is the product of
                        repression. The sexual “Garment,” or persona, is for Blake put
                        off in the act of sex, in which the two participants momentarily become one.
                        Hence, by engaging in unrepressed sex, we become less
                        “Sexual”; this is why Los can say of Beulah, the realm of
                        sexual consummation, “Humanity knows not of Sex: wherefore are Sexes
                        in Beulah?” (44:33, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 193). <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi>
Milton O. Percival, <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake’s Circle of Destiny</hi>, 117.</note></p>
          <p>This unrepressed sex is for Blake necessarily polymorphous, not centered upon
                        genitality. Los therefore denounces “Sexual Organization,”
                        which is a false organization of the body around genitality: “O worm
                        of sixty winters said Los / Consider Sexual Organization &amp; hide thee in
                        the dust” (30:57-58, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 177). Sexual organization is
                        overcome in embraces which are properly “Cominglings: from the Head
                        even to the Feet; / And not a pompous High Priest entering by a Secret
                        Place” (69:43-44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 223). Blake’s oft-quoted
                        denunciation of the phallic here links the phallic to the patriarchal
                        “Sexual” Religion in which the male hierophant presides over a
                        mystery which is really the hidden and subjugated sexuality of woman.</p>
          <p>At first, the Blakean “Sex” may sound like the contemporary
                        “gender”: a culturally-defined set of differences, often
                        arbitrary and unjust. However, Blake also seems to believe that beneath this
                        false, culturally-constituted set of differences there is a real and
                        essential system of difference. Blake, as much as the patriarchy he
                        condemns, fears the collapse of sexual difference, an event that he believes
                        will throw humanity into the chaos of Ulro—the hell-realm that Blake
                        associates with hermaphroditism. The separation of male and female becomes
                        part of the eternal artistic labor of Los, with whom Blake is more closely
                        identified in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> than ever before. In order that
                        “Rational Philosophy” and “Mathematic
                        Demonstration” might be removed from the realm of abstraction where
                        they possess the power of religious mystery, Los splits them into gendered
                        forms: 
						<q> And Los fixes them on his Anvil, incessant his blows:<lb/>
 He
                            fixes them with strong blows. placing the stones &amp; timbers.<lb/>
 To
                            Create a World of Generation from the World of Death:<lb/>
 Dividing the
                            Masculine &amp; Feminine: for the comingling<lb/>
 Of Albions &amp;
                            Luvahs Spectres was Hermaphroditic.<lb/>
 (58: 16-20, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                            207) </q>
It is highly significant that Los here is depicted as a
                        “divider.” Almost everywhere else in the poem, it is Albion
                        who divides and Los who seeks to unify.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n22" type="note">22</ref> The maintenance of male and female identities is essential to
                        the world of Generation; sexual ambiguity hints not of a higher world but of
                        a fall into the “hermaphroditic” hell of Ulro. <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi>
There is only one other instance where
                            division is used in a positive sense associated with Los: on 91:52, 
<hi rend="i">E</hi> 252, where Los alters his Spectre “Till he
                            had completely divided him into a separate space.” This
                            separation of the Spectre is analogous to the necessary separation of
                            the two genders in Blake’s myth, each to its own “separate
                            space.”</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> uses the hermaphroditism trope extensively, and
                        Blake links hermaphroditism directly to the anti-sexual
                        “Sexual” of the Sexual Religion (I will presently deal with
                        the difference between Blakean “hermaphroditism” and
                        “androgyny”): 
						<q> Albions Emanation which he had hidden in
                            Jealousy<lb/>
 Appeard now in the frowning Chaos prolific upon 
<pb id="p30-79" n="79"/>
the Chaos<lb/>
 Reflecting back to Albion in
                            Sexual Reasoning Hermaphroditic<lb/>
 (29:26-28, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 175)
						</q>
						Albion, like Satan in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, has become
                        “feminized” by his jealous failure to project his Emanation,
                        which he then internalizes. Without the crucial difference produced by
                        gender, Blake’s system collapses into “frowning Chaos prolific
                        upon the Chaos.” It is therefore appropriate to see anxiety about
                        gender underlying Los’s tirades against the Female Will: 
						<q> What may
                            Man be? who can tell! but what may Woman be?<lb/>
 To have power over Man
                            from Cradle to corruptible Grave.<lb/>
 There is a Throne in every Man,
                            it is the Throne of God<lb/>
 This woman has claimd as her own &amp; Man
                            is no more!<lb/>
 Albion is the Tabernacle of Vala &amp; her Temple<lb/>
                            And not the Tabernacle &amp; Temple of the Most High<lb/>
 O Albion why
                            wilt thou Create a Female Will?<lb/>
 (30:25-31, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 176)
						</q>
						The female survives, hidden beneath the orthodox surface of modern
                        patriarchal religion, which through repression makes female sexuality seem
                        even more mysterious and secret than the ancient religions of the goddess. A
                        bit later, the same Female Will is indicted for the latest development of
                        Natural Religion, an anti-sexual, mechanistic Deism: “Is this the
                        Female Will O ye lovely Daughters of Albion. To / Converse concerning Weight
                        &amp; Distance in the Wilds of Newton &amp; Locke” (30:39-40, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
177).</p>
          <p>Blake can only see any degree of female willfulness as a negative,
                        “hermaphroditic” mingling of genders. However, he does seem to
                        see the apparent contradiction between his ostensibly egalitarian beliefs
                        and a visionary universe that derives its structure from a dualistic
                        hierarchy of gender, in which one gender is central and primary and the
                        other “emanated” and secondary. He briefly makes an attempt at
                        a resolution of this contradiction near the end of chapter 3, in his
                        exploration of the “Eternal States” of the Blakean universe,
                        Ulro, Generation, Beulah and Eden/Eternity, previously charted in detail
                        (and in terms of gender) in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> The poet mentions that
                        Albion’s Sons and Daughters “intermarry in Beulah / For all
                        are Men in Eternity” (71:14-15, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 225). In this
                        otherwise insignificant passage, Blake states outright something that his
                        imagery has long implied: Eden/Eternity, the ultimate fulfillment of the
                        human, is an entirely masculine realm. For the first time, Blake tells us
                        the fate of women in paradise: they may enter, but only as males, leaving
                        all female traits behind in the lower realms. This declaration does seem to
                        indicate that Blake sees the need for some form of female equality in a
                        redeemed, fully human universe. The problems, however, are fairly obvious:
                        anything feminine or female is implicitly an indicator of the fallen state.
                        Blake possibly has in mind a strategy that Alan Richardson has identified as
                        characteristic of male romantic writers: the attempt to
                        “colonize” the feminine by appropriating traditionally female
                        characteristics as a part of a new “higher” masculine
                            self.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Alan Richardson, “Romanticism and
                            the Colonization of The Feminine” in Anne K. Mellor, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Feminism</hi> (Bloomington: Indiana
                            University Press, 1988) 13-26. It can be demonstrated that Blake has
                            indeed employed Richardson’s “colonization”
                            strategy in earlier poems: in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, for instance,
                            Blake maps a metaphysics that in a traditional fashion defines time as
                            masculine (Los) and space as female (Enitharmon). However, Los declares
                            in 22:17 (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 117) that “both Time &amp; Space
                            obey my will” indicating that in Blake’s apocalypse, male
                            time <hi rend="i">subsumes</hi> female space. Again in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,
masculine Time is the redeemer; he is “the
                            mercy of Eternity,” (24:72, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 121), while the
                            female’s place is vital but subordinate: “And between
                            every two Moments stands a Daughter of Beulah / To feed the Sleepers on
                            their Couches with maternal care.” (28:48-49, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                            126). The redeeming quality of female space comes into being only as a
                            consequence of the creation of Moments of Time by Los.</note></p>
          <p>One can understand, then, the reluctance of Enitharmon to accept Los’s
                        “proposition” at the climax of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
                        The most human of Blake’s females, and the one most identified with
                        Catherine Blake, Enitharmon has been strangely absent from the poem since
                        her separation from the body of Los in 17:49-55 (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 162).
                        For the second time in the poem, Enitharmon divides away from Los, implying
                        an even deeper rift between male and female: “Two Wills they had; Two
                        Intellects: &amp; not as in times of old” (86:61, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 245). A state
which in fact sounds like a condition of equality
                        is lamented by the poet.</p>
          <p>Los and Enitharmon begin a game of sexual hide and seek that recalls
                        “The Mental Traveller.” Finally, Los speaks his love: 
						<q> O
                            lovely Enitharmon: I behold thy graceful forms<lb/>
 Moving beside me
                            till intoxicated with the woven labyrinth<lb/>
 Of beauty &amp;
                            perfection my wild fibres shoot in veins<lb/>
 Of blood thro all my
                            nervous limbs. soon overgrown in roots<lb/>
 I shall be closed from thy
                            sight. sieze therefore in thy hand<lb/>
 The small fibres as they shoot
                            around me draw out in pity<lb/>
 And let them run on the winds of thy
                            bosom: I will fix them<lb/>
 With pulsations. we will divide them into
                            Sons &amp; Daughters<lb/>
 To live in thy Bosoms translucence as in an
                            eternal morning<lb/>
 (87:3-11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246) </q></p>
          <p>Los is asking Enitharmon to help him control the “fibres” of
                        sexual desire, to convert sexual energy into the “Sons &amp;
                        Daughters” of creative work. This is the offer that Enitharmon
                        accepted at the climax of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>; to 
<pb id="p30-80" n="80"/>
assist Los in the creation of redemptive
                        “counterparts” to the minute particulars of the fallen world.
                        This time Enitharmon has a different answer: 
						<q> No! I will sieze thy Fibres
                            &amp; weave<lb/>
 Them: not as thou wilt but as I will, for I will
                            Create<lb/>
 A round Womb beneath my bosom lest I also be overwoven<lb/>
                            With Love; be thou assured I never will be thy slave<lb/>
 Let Mans
                            delight be love; but Womans delight be Pride<lb/>
 In Eden our loves were
                            the same here they are opposite<lb/>
 I have Loves of my own<lb/>
                            (87:12-18, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246) </q></p>
          <p>Blake allows Enitharmon’s voice considerable autonomy, and she speaks
                        well, perhaps even better than the poet realizes. For the first time, one of
                        Blake’s women speaks not merely willfully but in a manner akin to a
                        modern feminist polemic; indeed, in a manner akin to Mary Wollstonecraft:
                        “be thou assured I never will be thy slave.” When Enitharmon
                        vows to “Create a round Womb” from the fibres of Los, she
                        means that she would “naturalize” the sexual energies to deal
                        with the needs of this world, not Los’s ideal world of art. She
                        subsequently gives a rationale for this: “In Eden our loves were the
                        same here they are opposite.” She concisely informs Los that the
                        needs of men and women in an unjust world may be quite different. The prior
                        statement of Enitharmon, “Let Mans delight be love; but Womans
                        delight be Pride,” echoes Gwendolen’s earlier statement of
                        81:6. Blake begins to sound like the Restoration authors (whom he disliked
                        intensely) who never tired of accusing woman of pride; he never suggests
                        that pride might be woman’s understandable response to a situation in
                        which the female’s only path to power is through beauty.</p>
          <p>Enitharmon is meant to seem perverse in rejecting Los, but she sounds
                        altogether reasonable. Her best arguments are saved for last: 
						<q> thou
                            hidest Vala<lb/>
 From her these fibres shoot to shut me in a Grave.<lb/>
                            You are Albions Victim, he has set his Daughter in your path<lb/>
                            (87:22-24, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246) </q>
Enitharmon’s analysis is
                        superior to that of Los, who thinks he opposes Vala, but in fact practices a
                        covert Natural Religion in the form of sexism. Los is not the foe of
                        patriarchy, but rather, as “Albions victim,” he has fallen
                        into its trap: he thinks he will overturn patriarchy by replacing
                        traditional legalistic authority with an authority linked to a principle of
                        masculinity; in fact, this will only perpetuate the abuses of patriarchy in
                        a new guise.</p>
          <p>Los attempts to plead his case: 
		<q> Man cannot unite with Man but by their
                            Emanations<lb/>
 Which stand both Male &amp; Female at the Gates of each
                            Humanity<lb/>
 How then can I ever again be united as Man with Man<lb/>
                            While thou my Emanation refusest my Fibres of 
<corr type="emend">dominion.</corr><lb/>
 When
                            Souls mingle &amp; join thro all the Fibres of Brotherhood<lb/>
 Can
                            there be any secret joy on Earth greater than this?<lb/>
 (88:10-15, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246) </q>
Line 11 is key to the argument of those
                        who maintain that Blake in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is advocating
                        androgyny; I will have more to say about it when I discuss Blake’s
                        concept of androgyny. That one very ambiguous line aside, Los is offering
                        Enitharmon a bad bargain. She must receive his “Fibres of
                        dominion,” acknowledge his dominance, so that he can join with other
                        men in “Fibres of Brotherhood”—in other words,
                        Lerner’s all-male society of the covenant, with women shared out
                        among the brothers.</p>
          <p>Enitharmon’s response is redolent of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>: as in that earlier
work, the world is portrayed as a
                        female hell, with woman as a demiurge, “This is Womans World”
                        (88:16, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 247). The triumph of the Female Will brings
                        about the final manifestation of Vala as “A terrible indefinite
                        Hermaphroditic form” (89:3, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 248), the ultimate
                        consolidation of the monstrous hermaphrodites of Blake’s myth: the
                        Covering Cherub. The Cherub amalgamates Rahab-Tirzah, the Whore of Babylon,
                        and all of the “female-males” and “male-females”
                        who block entry into paradise.</p>
          <p>On the heels of this revelation, Blake makes a direct attempt to resolve the
                        contradictions in his sexual myth. This he would do putting forth a concept
                        of gender as a fallen state, ultimately to be replaced by an androgyny that
                        is to be distinguished from this fallen hermaphroditism. The fall is first
                        described: “The Feminine separates from the Masculine &amp; both
                        from Man, / Ceasing to be His Emanations, Life to Themselves
                        assuming!” (90:1-2, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 249). If “Man”
                        is read as humanity, the statement might be read as a very contemporary
                        formulation of the problem of gender as a reductive division of all that is
                        human into a binary set of characteristics. Blake finds the source of this
                        problem in the appropriation of what he calls “Universal
                        Characteristics” by individuals: 
						<q> 
                        	For Los said: When the Individual appropriates Universality<lb/>
                        	He divides into Male &amp; Female: &amp; when the Male &amp; Female,<lb/>
                        	Appropriate Individuality, they become an Eternal Death.<lb/>
                        	Hermaphroditic worshippers of a God of cruelty &amp; law!<lb/>
                        	(90:52-55, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 250) 
						</q>
                        This doctrine of Universal Characteristics is an
                        extension of the of States as presented in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>:
                        individuals pass through States, but must avoid identification with any 
            <pb id="p30-81" n="81"/> 
                        single State. To identify with a State is to freeze
                        ourselves into a fixed, immutable Selfhood and to lose touch with our total
                        humanity. Gender is one of these States; to over-identify with a single
                        gender ironically makes us “hermaphroditic”: we end up
                        internalizing the sexual Other rather than finding it outside our selves.
                        However, I believe that the “androgyny” that Blake would set
                        against this negative hermaphroditism can be demonstrated to be nothing more
                        than the personification of the familiar androcentric voice of Western
                        literature, that voice which feminist critics have repeatedly accused of
                        representing a masculinist agenda in the guise of an ungendered
                        universalism.</p>
          <p>Earlier, Los declared “Man cannot unite with Man but by their
                        Emanations / Which stand both Male &amp; Female at the Gates of each
                        Humanity” (88:10-11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246). Thomas D. Frosch, a
                        champion of Blake as a proponent of androgyny, interprets the lines: 
						<q>
                            This is a difficult passage and line 11 is capable of supporting
                            contradictory interpretations. Each man might have four gates, for
                            instance, as paradise does, and his emanations might be both
                            “both Male &amp; Female,” or themselves androgynous. As I
                            understand the lines, however, the suggestion seems to be that each
                            Edenic Humanity emanates what we might consider to be two sexual
                            persons, a male and a female, at its points of communication with other
                            human forms, as if each Edenic being, then, appeared to others a
                            radically unified couple.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Thomas D. Frosch, <hi rend="i">The
                                    Awakening of Albion</hi>, 174.</note></q></p>
          <p>The difficulty that Frosch has in describing Blake’s concept of
                        androgyny is typical of critical attempts to define this elusive
                            proposition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">25</ref> Frosch is probably
                        close to the truth in describing the individual in the awakened Edenic
                        Humanity as a “radically unified couple,” but it is a couple
                        in which the male has (in Los’s words) “dominion” over
                        and in fact <hi rend="i">subsumes</hi> the female. At the climax of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Ololon is in fact incorporated into
                        Blake-Los-Milton. The subsumption of the female by the male in
                        Blake’s poetry has been remarked upon by Alicia Ostriker, while the
                        same motif in Blake’s visual art has been noted by Anne K.
                            Mellor.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
The closing plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> show this same strategy at work, and Alan
                        Richardson’s principle of the “colonization” of the
                        feminine by male romantic writers again seems to be an entirely appropriate
                        characterization of Blake’s narrative. <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Camille
Paglia in <hi rend="i">Sexual Personae</hi> (New
                            York: Viking Press, 1991) 291-92, comments that in <hi rend="i">A Blake
                                Dictionary</hi>, S. Foster Damon “makes a distinction between
                            hermaphrodite and androgyne that makes no sense whatever to me. Damon
                            and Percival believe that the sexes are equal in the androgyne but that
                            the female dominates in the hermaphrodite,” and she adds a bit
                            later, “The words hermaphrodite and androgyne should be
                            synonymous.” In point of fact, any figure in the poetry that
                            seems at all androgynous is labelled hermaphroditic and condemned. The
                            beings described as androgynous, in the positive sense invoked by Damon
                            and Percival, are figured as masculine.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Ostriker (see n3) 163; Mellor,
                            “Blake’s Portrayal of Women,” 151. The two
                            articles, taking similar critical stances toward Blake’s sexual
                            politics, appeared in the same issue of <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Los at the climax of the poem never directly resolves his crisis with
                        Enitharmon; instead he turns to confront the Spectre. Spectre and Emanation
                        have been linked since the beginning of the poem; they were the two
                        survivors who escaped Albion’s fall in chapter 2, and plate 44 shows
                        them flying side by side into the arms of Los. The effect of this connection
                        is to link the female with that which is most negative in the (male) psyche:
                        fear, anger, vanity, phallocentrism. Los subdues his Spectre in the famous
                        “It is easier to forgive an Enemy than to forgive a Friend”
                        (91:1, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 251) speech that occupies the whole of plate 91.
                        Los’s victory comes from the renunciation of personal vanity,
                        “In unpitying ruin driving down the pyramids of pride” (91:43,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 252). Through the abdication of pride, “Los
                        alterd his Spectre” (91:50, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 252), and he triumphs
                        over Spectre and Emanation simultaneously.</p>
          <p>There is no corresponding scene in which Los deals with the challenge of
                        Enitharmon. After his contest with the Spectre, she reappears, already
                        defeated and lamenting: “The Poets Song draws to its period &amp;
                        Enitharmon is no more” (92:8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 252). The female
                        will be subsumed in the masculine identity of the awakened Albion. Los
                        informs her that “Sexes must vanish &amp; cease / To be, when Albion
                        arises from his dread repose O lovely Enitharmon” (92:13-14, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
252), but what he really means is that <hi rend="i">woman</hi> (traditionally designated as “the sex”)
will
                        vanish; there is no indication that Los’s masculine characteristics
                        will disappear or in any way be transformed. In Blake’s myth, woman
                        resists the end of sexual division because it means a loss of power for her.
                        Since in Blake’s redeemed universe the mending of sexual division
                        means the subsumption and containment of the female by the male, it is easy
                        to see why woman would resist.</p>
          <p>The last element of woman to vanish is her maternity. Enitharmon wails to her
                        sons Rintrah and Palamabron, “The Mothers love of obedience is
                        forgotten &amp; you seek a Love / Of the pride of dominion” (93:4-5,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 253). Enitharmon’s comments again seem a
                        disturbingly accurate critique of Blake’s own project. The poet will
                        overturn the traditional patriarchal control of woman’s sexuality by
                        subsuming that sexuality into a masculine creativity that is
                        “higher” than mere “natural” procreativity. Los,
                        the new patriarch, reassures his Sons: “Fear not my Sons this Waking
                        Death. he is become One with me / Behold him here! We shall not Die! we
                        shall be united in Jesus” (93:18-19, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 253).</p>
          <p>The rest of the poem deals with the awakening of Albion. Brittannia, the
                        reunified form of Jerusalem and Vala, lies across his prone body and
                        attempts to rouse him. She moans in contrition, “In dreams of
                        Chastity &amp; Moral Law I have Murdered Albion! Ah! / . . . behold ye the
                        Jealous Wife” (94:23-26, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 254). It is this wail of
                        female self-abnegation 
<pb id="p30-82" n="82"/>
that wakes Albion, at which
                        point 
						<q> England who is Brittannia enterd Albions bosom rejoicing,<lb/>
                            Rejoicing in his indignation! adoring his wrathful rebuke.<lb/>
 She who
                            adores not your frowns will only loathe your smiles<lb/>
 (95:22-24, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 255) </q>
This, alas, is the apotheosis of Blakean
                        woman. Brittannia is subsumed by the male: her entry into
                        “Albion’s bosom rejoicing,” as depicted on plates 96
                        and 99,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref>
implies an incorporation into
                        the male body. Brittannia does not reappear in the poem. 
<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Mellor, “Blake’s Portrayal of
                            Women,” 151-52, sees subsumption at work in Plate 99 in the
                            masculine characteristics of the body of Jerusalem. I see the
                            Jerusalem-figure as female, and attribute its masculine musculature to
                            Blake’s problematic draftsmanship and his too-assiduous copying
                            of Michelangelo, but I see a clearer suggestion of subsumption in the
                            way that Albion/Jehovah/Urizen gathers Jerusalem in, coupled with her
                            disappearance from the poetry.</note></p>
          <p>The depiction of a postapocalyptic world in the remainder of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> bears
out the earlier pronouncement that in
                        Eden/Eternity “all are Men.” The poet hears the “Vision
                        of Albion” speak; the Vision of Albion is, as Blake’s faculty
                        of “Vision” has always been since the <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi>, an irreducibly masculine ability to organize perception.
                        The Vision of Albion is identified with “The Universal Father”
                        (97:6, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 256): patriarchy is not wiped out; rather,
                        authority has been apportioned “universally” among the male
                        members of a brotherhood; it is the final stage in Lerner’s
                        developmental model of patriarchal history.</p>
          <p>There is, however, a hint of the persistence of the female at the
                        poem’s conclusion: 
						<q> All Human Forms identified even Tree Metal
                            Earth &amp; Stone. all<lb/>
 Human Forms identified, living going forth
                            &amp; returning wearied<lb/>
 Into the Planetary lives of Years Months
                            Days &amp; Hours reposing<lb/>
 And then Awaking into his Bosom in the
                            Life of Immortality.<lb/>
<lb/>
 And I Heard the Name of their Emanations
                            they are named Jerusalem<lb/>
 (99:1-5, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 258-59) </q>
                        It seems fitting that, in the very last line of the epic that the poet
                        intended to be his greatest statement, Blake’s proliferating myth
                        should come to rest upon its central contradiction, a contradiction that
                        remains unresolved: a system that wishes to unify and equalize all persons
                        is founded upon the principle of the dominance of a masculine subject over
                        an emanated and secondary female object.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
