<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>30.4.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
1996</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
        <author n="Aoyama">Keiko Aoyama</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1997</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1997</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1997"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-4-0005">
        <pb id="p30-121" n="121"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
1996</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor><lb/>
			<hi rend="i">With the Assistance of <docAuthor>Keiko <name>Aoyama</name></docAuthor> for Japanese
Publications</hi>
          </byline>
          <p>The annual checklist of scholarship and discoveries concerning William Blake and his circle
records publications for the current year (say, 1996) and those for previous years which are not recorded in
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995). The organization of
the checklist is as follows:</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <table rows="8" cols="2">
              <row>
                <cell>Part I:</cell>
                <cell>Editions, Translations, and Facsimiles of Blake’s Writings</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Section A:</cell>
                <cell>Original Editions and Reprints</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Section B:</cell>
                <cell>Collections and Selections</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part II:</cell>
                <cell>Reproductions of his Art</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part III:</cell>
                <cell>Commercial Book Engravings</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part IV:</cell>
                <cell>Catalogues and Bibliographies</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part V:</cell>
                <cell>Books Blake Owned</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part VI:</cell>
                <cell>Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <p><hi rend="i">Note:</hi> Collections of essays on Blake and issues of periodicals devoted
entirely to him are listed in one place, with cross-references to their authors.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>This division is organized by individual (say, William Hayley or John Flaxman), with works by
and about Blake’s friends and patrons, living individuals with whom he had significant direct and
demonstrable contact. It includes Thomas Butts, Thomas Hartley Cromek, George Cumberland, John Flaxman and his
family, Henry Fuseli, Thomas and William Hayley, John Linnell and his family, Samuel Palmer, James Parker,
George Richmond, Thomas Stothard, and John Varley. It does <hi rend="i">not</hi> include important
contemporaries with whom Blake’s contact was negligible or non-existent such as John Constable and William
Wordsworth and Edmund Burke; such major figures are dealt with more comprehensively elsewhere, and the light
they throw upon Blake is very dim.</p>
            <p>Reviews listed here are only for books which are substantially about Blake, not for those with
only, say, a chapter on Blake. These reviews are listed under the book reviewed; the authors of the reviews
may be recovered from the index.</p>
            <p>In general, Keiko Aoyama is responsible for works in Japanese, and I am greatly indebted to her
for her meticulous accuracy and her patience in translating the words and conventions of Japan into our very
different context.</p>
            <p>I take <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>
(1995), <hi rend="i">faute de mieux</hi>, to be the standard bibliographical authorities on Blake<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> and have noted significant differences from
them. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Except for the states of the plates for Blake’s commercial book
engravings, where the standard authority is R. N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
Illustrations</hi> (1991).</note></p>
            <p>N.b. I have made no attempt to record manuscripts, typescripts, computer printouts, radio or
television broadcasts, calendars, music, pillows,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> posters,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> published
scores,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> recorded readings and
singings, rubber stamps,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> T-shirts,
tatoos,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> video recordings, or email
related to Blake. <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> For one with part of “The Tyger,” see R. N. Essick,
“Blake in the Marketplace, 1996,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXX (1997), hereafter cited as Essick,
Marketplace, 1996.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> E.g., *<hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi> (Ashington, Northumberland: MidNAG [c.
1976]) Poster No. 35, c. 12 × 18.”</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> For example, §Dmitri Smirnov, <hi rend="i">Jacob’s Ladder:</hi>
Blake’s Pictures for 16 Players, Op. 58 (N.Y., 1993); §Dmitri Smirnov, <hi rend="i">Shest’
Stikhoyvorenii</hi> . . . Six Poems by William Blake: For Voice and Organ (1981); §Dmitri Smirnov, 
<hi rend="i">Vremena Goda</hi> . . .: <hi rend="i">The Seasons</hi> for Violin, Flute, Viola, and Harp
(1986).</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> For stamps of <hi rend="i">America</hi> and Essick’s portrait of Blake
made by a Santa Barbara firm, see Essick, Marketplace, 1996.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For a tattoo (1993) of “The Ancient of Days” on the left leg of Charles
A. Bufalino, see Essick, Marketplace, 1996.</note></p>
            <p>The chief indices used to discover what relevant works have been published were (1) 
<hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature</hi>, LXVIII for 1993 (1995), pp. 374-77
(#5816-5772); (2) <hi rend="i">BHA:</hi> Bibliography of the History of Art, Bibliographie d’Histoire de
l’Art (1995); (3) <hi rend="i">Books in Print</hi> (October 1996); (4) <hi rend="i">British Humanities Index
1995</hi> (1996); (5) <hi rend="i">English and General Literature Index 1900-1933</hi> (1934), pp. 178-79; . .
. <hi rend="i">1934-1940</hi> (1941), p. 121; . . . <hi rend="i">1941-1947</hi> (1948), pp. 156-57; . . . 
<hi rend="i">1948-1954</hi> (1955), pp. 193-94; . . . <hi rend="i">1955-1959</hi> (1960), 122-23; . . . 
<hi rend="i">1960-1964</hi> (1965), pp. 135-36; . . . <hi rend="i">1965-1969</hi> (1970), pp. 131-32; . . . 
<hi rend="i">1970-1974</hi> (1975), pp. 150-52; . . . <hi rend="i">1975-1979</hi> (1980), pp. 160-61; . . . 
<hi rend="i">1980-1984</hi> (1985), pp. 181-82; . . . <hi rend="i">1985-89</hi> (1990), 164-65; . . . 
<hi rend="i">1990-1994</hi> (1995), pp. 180-81;(6) <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement:</hi> A Selective and
Critical Bibliography for 1993 (1994), pp. 65-73, and (7) <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English
Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996) (by David Worrall).</p>
            <p>I am grateful to more friends and correspondents than I can conveniently name, but I must offer
special thanks to Julia G. Bentley (for translations from Chinese), John Byrne, D.W. Dörrbecker, Robert N.
Essick, Arthur Freeman, William Halloran, Giles Harvey, Nelson Hilton, Ted Hoffman, Heather Howell,
Marlborough Rare Books, Michael Millgate, Jeanne Moskal, James Northrup, Michael O’Neill, Oxford University
Press, Morton D. Paley, Margaret Sharman, Joseph Viscomi, Xianyi Yang, and especially to Keiko Aoyama and Dr.
E. B. Bentley.</p>
            <pb id="p30-122" n="122"/>
            <p>I should also like to express my gratitude for and joy in a Visiting Research Fellowship at
Hatfield College, where much of the work on this checklist was done in the autumn of 1996, and to my
colleagues there in the English department of Durham University.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Symbols</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>*Works prefixed by an asterisk include one or more illustrations by Blake or depicting him. If
there are more than 19 illustrations, the number is specified. If the illustrations include all those for a
work by Blake, say <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> or <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, the work is identified.</p>
            <p>§Works preceded by a section mark are reported on second-hand authority.</p>
            <p>18 Numbers prefixed to Blake’s manuscripts, original editions, and commercial engravings are
the standard ones which identify them in <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <table rows="3" cols="2">
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                </cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Introduction</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The number of publications recorded on Blake in this checklist for 1996 is very considerable:
over 160 essays, 136 reviews, 13 books on Blake, 14 editions of his poetry, and 10 exhibitions and catalogues
of his work in languages as diverse as Catalan, Chinese, Czeck, English, French, German, Hebrew, Italian,
Japanese, Korean, Polish, Portuguese, Russian, Scotch, Spanish, and Swedish. However, the flood of new
publications is not nearly so great as this implies, for there are only 54 essays, 67 reviews, and nine books
from 1996 recorded here. The even larger number of essays and reviews dating from 1784 to 1995 were first
noticed in a variety of sources, chiefly <hi rend="i">English and General Literature Index</hi> for 1900-94
and the on-line catalogue of the Research Libraries Group.</p>
            <p>The 14 editions of Blake’s poetry newly noted here are mostly of small significance; editions
of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> translated into Spanish (1987) and Chinese (1988), collections in Chinese
(1973), Latvian (1981), Portuguese (1977), Russian (1993), and Scotch (1988), three broadsides (1930, 1968,
1980), and an “Office Drawn from” the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> and elsewhere in Blake “for Use of St.
Mark’s in-the-Bourie” (1920). <hi rend="i">Selected Poems</hi> (1996) and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
&amp; Experience</hi> [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] (1996) are insufficiently original for the publisher to bother
to record the name of the editor. The only likely exception seems to be the two volumes of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, edited and translated by Marcello Pagnini (1994), which neither its Italian nor its
English publisher seems to be able to supply and on which I can therefore scarcely comment.</p>
            <p>In terms of Blake’s original works, the most tantalizing is the discovery of a broken pair of
spectacles in Blake’s cottage in Felpham which could have belonged to the poet.</p>
            <p>A good deal of new information about the earliest series of colored facsimiles of Blake’s
works in illuminated printing by William Muir has been discovered in the Crookshank Collection in the West
Sussex Record Office in Chichester. These give details of when copies were sold and which originals were
reproduced. They also include fascinating inscriptions attributed to Blake from <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (A) and
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (F) and the allegation that <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (F) once
belonged to Dante Gabriel Rossetti.</p>
            <p>Blake’s designs for Bunyan’s <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> have been sold by the
Frick Collection in New York, where they were for half a century, and they are now in a private collection in
England.</p>
            <p>Among Blake’s commercial book engravings, there are a good many new locations recorded here,
and a facsimile has been published of George Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Attempt to Describe Hafod</hi>
(1996), though with no new information as to whether Blake had a hand in the engravings in it. And a great
store of information about Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, in the archive of John Murray,
not only demonstrates the conditions in which one of the most distinguished illustrated books of the century
was produced but records what Blake was paid for his small part in the enormous undertaking.</p>
            <p>The most impressive and significant of the catalogues recorded here is Robin Hamlyn’s 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: visiones de mundos eternas</hi> for the 1996 exhibition in Madrid. Most of the essays
except for Hamlyn’s are curiously irrelevant to Blake and to the pictures and books exhibited, but the works
shown are extensive and of the first class, and the 180 color plates include complete reproductions of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (X), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (B), and Job. As there has been very little
publication about Blake in Spanish before 1996, this is an astonishing accomplishment.</p>
            <p>A large proportion of the essays and reviews published on Blake in 1996<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> appeared in <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>,
in <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society at St James</hi>, and in volumes of reprinted essays edited by
Noriko Kawasaki and David Punter. One of the most rewarding of the new essays is that by Joseph Viscomi in 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, displaying a vast range of new information about Blake’s faithful patron Thomas Butts.
Among the fascinating conclusions derived from these facts is that when Butts ordered duplicates of Blake’s
designs, he may have intended them for different houses he owned, one of them used for a school for a young
ladies, and that the biblical subjects of many of these designs may have had a pedagogical function. 
<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> N.b. As usual, I cannot, through linguistic ignorance, comment on the 25 essays
published in Japan and the two in Korea.</note></p>
            <pb id="p30-123" n="123"/>
            <p><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> also serves Blake scholarship with its extensive reports of “Blake in
the Marketplace” by Robert Essick and of “Blake and His Circle,” to which a whole issue is devoted.</p>
            <p>One especially rewarding essay is the one by Stuart Peterfreund in 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi> (1994) with its argument about “Blake—Prophet Against Ideology.”
Another is Stephen Prickett’s argument in his <hi rend="i">Origins of Narrative</hi> (1996) concerning
“Swedenborg and Blake: The Privatisation of Angels.” And Karen Shabatai’s argument concerning
“Blake’s Hostility Towards the Jews” in <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> (1996) raises disturbing issues which
warrant serious reflection, though “Blake appears at best uninterested in the ‘Jewish question.’”
Michael Grenfell makes an attractive though much overstated case in the <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake
Society of St James</hi> (1996) that “A Gnostic view is ‘the’ key to understanding Blake’s dense
mythologies,” and G. E. Bentley, Jr. provides illuminating parallels between the careers of “James Parker
and His Partner William Blake” in <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> (1996).</p>
            <p>There are the usual quota of attempts to consider Blake in terms of modern intellectual
fashions like feminist theology, as well as a number of agreeable diversions. These include James Bogan’s
“centrifugal lark” in “Blake on a Bike,” the “electronic concert dedicated to the life and work of
William Blake,” and the Blake “Xword” (all in <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society at St
James</hi>). A few arguments seem particularly labored or perverse, such as Peter Ackroyd’s claim in 
<hi rend="i">The Independent</hi> (1993) and elsewhere that Blake was a “Cockney” (in the novel sense that he
“expressed the true nature and spirit of London”). I should relish hearing that great London-lover Dr.
Johnson respond to the allegation that he was a Cockney. Some arguments seem to be expiring, like Laocoön, in
the grip of irresistible critical jargon, such as the claims that “Blake appropriates the homology between
biological and non-biological creativity to address the politics of the copied text” (Julia Wright), that
Molly Anne Rothenberg’s book is written “in post-structuralist and ‘post-post-structuralist’ terms,”
and that in Jeanne Moskal’s book “the intrapsychic wins out over the intersubjective.”</p>
            <p>Though a number of critical books are newly recorded here, few have much pretension to novelty.
Noriko Kawasaki’s <hi rend="i">Eden wa Kitaka:</hi> William Blake Ronshu: <hi rend="i">On the Location of
Eden:</hi> Studies on William Blake (1996) reprints five of her essays in Japanese (1988-95), one of them
translated from English for the purpose, and David Punter’s <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (1996) reprints
10 essays of 1970-87 by various authors. Victor Paananen’s <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (1996) is an
“Updated Edition” of a modest little book first published in 1977. I have not been able to see, and
therefore cannot comment on, Richard O’Keefe’s <hi rend="i">Mythic Archetypes in Ralph Waldo Emerson:</hi>
A Blakean Reading (1995) (except to say that it is presumably a revised version of his dissertation),
François Piquet’s <hi rend="i">Blake et le Sacré</hi> (1996) (ibid.) or William Richey’s 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Altering Aesthetic</hi> (announced for November 1996).</p>
            <p>Violet Tengberg’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s “The Tyger”:</hi> En konstvelenskaplig
analys och tolkning (1994) is a study in Swedish of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, reproduced from typescript
and of modest dimensions and pretensions.</p>
            <p>The two most substantial new critical books recorded here are Frank Vaughan’s 
<hi rend="i">Again to the Life of Eternity:</hi> William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Thomas Gray
(1996), with 139 folio pages and 116 plates, and Andrew Lincoln’s <hi rend="i">Spiritual History:</hi> A
Reading of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1995), a very
substantial work though strangely unillustrated. Vaughan’s book, which reproduces all Blake’s watercolors
for Gray in reduced size and monochrome, concludes very oddly that “Blake was not much interested in
illustrating” Gray (7), even though he must have spent a great deal of the time on his designs for his good
friend John Flaxman. Even more curiously, the Gray designs are said to have been intended to implant “not
knowledge but a radical burning doubt” (18). These are strange conclusions for the poet who wrote:
<q>
He who shall teach the Child to Doubt<lb/>
The rotting Grave shall neer get out. . . .<lb/>
He who Doubts from what he sees<lb/>
Will neer Believe do what you Please.<lb/>
If the Sun &amp; Moon should doubt<lb/>
Theyd immediately go out.
</q>
One may suspect that the purpose discovered in the Gray designs. “To educate one to rebel” (116) and “to
free the mind-forged manacles” (rather than “to free the manacled mind”) tells us more of what the
critic wishes than of what the artist intended.</p>
            <p>Andrew Lincoln’s <hi rend="i">Spiritual History</hi> is an altogether more substantial and
rewarding book, the most valuable critical work newly recorded here. It is a detailed “staged reading” of
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> designed for “new readers of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>” (v, ix) but rewarding for critics of all levels of experience and sophistication. One of its most
valuable features is its analysis of the poem as “a universal history” (1), with the aid of illumination
from contemporary historians such as Gibbon. The Last Judgment in the poem reveals that man’s prison “in a
finite vision of the natural world” is a “prison locked from the inside” (190); we are the inmates of
ourselves, and the key to escape is in our own hands. Andrew Lincoln’s <hi rend="i">Spiritual History</hi>
is a work to which one can return repeatedly for light upon Blake’s poem—and upon the nature of
humanity.</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">Completed this 27th Day of January 1997 at East Lake Apartments, Dongzhimenwai
Dajie, Beijing</hi>
            </p>
            <pb id="p30-124" n="124"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part I Editions, Translations and Facsimiles</hi>
                    <ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
                    <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> N.b. In this checklist, “facsimile” is taken to mean
“an exact copy” attempting very close reproduction of an original named copy including size of image,
color of printing (and of tinting if relevant), and size, color, and quality of paper, with no deliberate
alteration as in page-order or numbering or obscuring of paper defects.</note>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Section A: Original Editions</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794[-1831])</p>
                  <p>Copy B</p>
                  <p>History: . . . Copy B from Glasgow University is reproduced in the 1996 2 February-7
April catalogue of the Fundación “la Caixa” in Madrid, plates 28a-q.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> (1794[-1815?])</p>
                  <p>Plate 1</p>
                  <p>History: . . . Lent by “The Keynes Family Trust on deposit at the Fitzwilliam Museum”
to the 1996 2 February-7 April exhibition of the Fundación “la Caixa” in Madrid, No. 30a.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> (1820-1831?)</p>
                  <p>Edition</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> [B]. (London: Frederick Hollyer,
1925) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #47&gt;.</p>
                  <p>According to a prospectus (?1925), ordinary copies of this facsimile of the copy of Miss
C. Carthew were for sale at 15<hi rend="i">s</hi> and 55 copies (only 50 of which were for sale) on
“platinotype paper” at £4.4.0.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> A copy of the prospectus for all Hollyer’s Blake reproductions is with
the Muir facsimile of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi> in the West Sussex Records Office; the prospectus
presumably pre-dates Hollyer’s reproduction of <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> (1926), which is not
mentioned there.</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (1804[-20?][-1832?])</p>
                  <p>Copy E</p>
                  <p>History: It was reproduced again in color in the Italian facsimile (1994).</p>
                  <p>Plate 1</p>
                  <p>History: . . . Lent by “The Keynes Family Trust on deposit at the Fitzwilliam Museum”
to the 1996 2 February-7 April exhibition of the Fundación “la Caixa” in Madrid, No. 53a.</p>
                  <p>Edition</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, ed. M. D. Paley (Blake Trust, 1991) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 88&gt;.</p>
                  <p>The same ektachromes were apparently used in the facsimile edited by Marcello Pagnini
(1994).</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>11 §Jon Mee, <hi rend="i">Australian Journal of Art</hi>, X (1993), 105-06 (with the
Blake Trust <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>).</p>
                  <p>12 §Daniel Mark Epstein, “The Two William Blakes,” <hi rend="i">New Criterion</hi>,
XIII, No. 2 (October 1994), 10-22 (with Viscomi’s <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> [1993]
and the other Blake Trust volumes).</p>
                  <p>13 Iain Sinclair, “Customising Biography,” <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi>,
22 February 1996, 16-19 (with Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1995], and the Blake Trust reproductions
of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [1991], <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated
Books</hi> [1993], <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi> [1995], <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> [1993], and
<hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi> [1995]) (there is no indication that Sinclair has looked at 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>—for a protest, see John Commander, below).</p>
                  <p>§*<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Ed. &amp; tr. Marcello Pagnini. 2 vols. (Florence: Giunti
Gruppo Editoriale, 1994) ISBN: 88-09-20507-3.</p>
                  <p>Vol. I is a facsimile of copy E, apparently using the same ektachromes as in the 1991
Blake Trust edition.</p>
                  <p>Receipt</p>
                  <p>1805 July 5</p>
                  <p>History: Bought with the Joseph Holland Collection by John Windle in 1995 and (according
to Essick, Marketplace, 1996) and sold in June 1996 to the autograph dealer Kenneth Rendell.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789[-1808?])</p>
                  <p>Copy X &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 120-21&gt;</p>
                  <p>History: Pl. 9-10 from the Fitzwilliam and pl. 13-14, 16-19, 23-25, 27, 34-36, 53-54 (the
rest) from the National Gallery of Victoria (Melbourne) are reproduced together in the 1996 2 February-7 April
catalogue of the Fundación “la Caixa” in Madrid, editions 17a-q.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Announcing the Felpham Edition of Songs of Innocence by William
Blake</hi>: An <corr type="emend">Intaglio</corr> Plate Book Designed &amp; Printed in Colour at the Pear Tree
Press and Now Offered for Subscription. (Flansham, Bognor Regis, Sussex: Pear Tree Press, 1937) 4 leaves.</p>
                  <p>There seems to be no record of the publication of such an edition.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Canciones de inocencia y de experiencia.</hi> Ed. J. L. Caramés y S. G.
Corugedo (Madrid, 1987).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Les Chants de l’Innocence.</hi> Tr. Alain Suied (1993) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>1 §François Hàn, <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, No. 772 (1994), 206-07.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1794[-1831?])</p>
                  <p>Pls. 42, 47 (“The Tyger” and “The Human Abstract”)</p>
                  <p>History: . . . Lent by “The Keynes Family Trust on deposit at the Fitzwilliam Museum”
to the 1996 2 February-7 April exhibition of the Fundación “la Caixa” in Madrid, No. 27a-b.</p>
                  <pb id="p30-125" n="125"/>
                  <p>Editions</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (1970)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> # &gt;.</p>
                  <p>The plates are reproduced in Gray, and Keynes’s Introduction is translated by Yang Yi
in <hi rend="i">Tianzhen yu jing yan zhige</hi> [<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>]
(1988).</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Tianzhen yu jing yan zhige</hi> [<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>]. Tr. Yang Yi [i.e., Jinru Yang]. (Changsha: Hunan Renmin Chuban Shi [Hunan Peoples Publishing
House], May 1988) 8°, pp. 7, 210; ISBN: 7-217-00342-3 (hardback) and 7-217-00343-1 (paperback).</p>
                  <p>G. Kaiensi [G. Keynes], “Yinhan [Introduction]” (1-8); T.S. Ailuete [T.S. Eliot],
“Weillian Bulaike [William Blake]” (1-8 [bis]); “Fan zhe de hua [Translator’s comments],” dated the
Fiftieth Anniversary of the War of Resistance Against Japanese Aggression, 13 August 1937 (204). The text
consists of faint pale Gray reproductions of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> from the reproduction edited by
Geoffrey Keynes (1970) of the Blake Trust facsimile (19) of copy, with facing translations into Chinese and
followed by short comments.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, ed. Andrew Lincoln (1991) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 136&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>11 §Jon Mee, <hi rend="i">Australian Journal of Art</hi>, X (1993), 105-06 (with the
Blake Trust <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [1991]).</p>
                  <p>12 §Daniel Mark Epstein, “The Two William Blakes,” <hi rend="i">New Criterion</hi>,
XIII, No. 2 (October 1994), 10-22 (with Viscomi’s <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> [1993]
and the other Blake Trust volumes).</p>
                  <p>13 Iain Sinclair, “Customising Biography,” <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi>,
22 February 1996, 16-19 (with Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1995], and the Blake Trust reproductions
of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [1991], <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi> [1993], <hi rend="i">The
Continental Prophecies</hi> [1995], <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> [1993], and <hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi>
[1995]) (there is no indication that Sinclair has looked at <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>—for a protest, see John
Commander, below).</p>
                  <p>New Entry</p>
                  <p>Spectacles at Felpham (illus. 1)</p>
                  <p>Half a pair of nineteenth-century spectacles, found about 1928 in a piece of rotting wood
when the floor of Blake’s cottage in Felpham was relaid, may have been the poet’s about 1803. They have
simple magnification of 1.75 (1.0 being neutral). The spectacles, which fit neatly on the life-mask of Blake,
belong to Mrs. Heather Howell, the owner of the cottage.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> The spectacles Blake owned when he died are in the Fitzwilliam Museum
(see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1996]).</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> (1794-95)</p>
                  <p>Copy E</p>
                  <p>History: (5) From Mrs. Ramsay Harvey, it passed by inheritance
                    <figure n="HalfSpectacles.30.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="354">
	<head>1 Half of a pair of gold-framed spectacles which were found about 1928 in Blake’s cottage in Felpham
and which may have belonged to Blake.</head>
	<figDesc>They now belong to the owner of Blake’s cottage on Blake’s Road, Felpham, who courteously
supplied these photographs. Photo courtesy of Devereux Photography, Felpham. If any Blake readers should want
a print of these photos, Mrs. Heather Howell writes that she would be happy to obtain them through Devereux
Photography. Please contact her at Blake’s Cottage, Blake’s Road, Felpham, Bognor Regis, West Sussex, PO22
7 EB.</figDesc>
</figure>
to (6) Mr. Giles Harvey.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> It was withdrawn from the Christie sale of the other Harvey Blakes (30
Nov 1993) when its authenticity was questioned on the basis of the discoveries of Joseph Viscomi.</note></p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Section B: Collections and Selections</hi>
                      <ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
                      <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Here and below I ignore mere reprints.</note>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Poems</hi>, ed. W. H. Stevenson, second edition
(1989).</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>1 François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Etudes Anglaises</hi>, XLVII (1994), 478 (an account of
the “nouveautés” in the second edition).</p>
                  <p>§*<hi rend="i">Blake: Selected Poems.</hi> Ed. Mike Davis &amp; Alan Pound. (Oxford:
Heinemann Educational, 1996) Heinemann Poetry Bookshelf. viii, 168 pp.</p>
                  <p>Blake’s Illuminated Books (The William Blake Trust).</p>
                  <p>Volume I: <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, ed. M. D. Paley (1991) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
88&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Volume II: <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, ed. Andrew Lincoln
(1991) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 136&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Volume III: <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves, Robert N.
Essick, &amp; Joseph Viscomi (1993) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Volume IV: <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi>, ed. D. W.</p>
                  <pb id="p30-126" n="126"/>
                  <p>Dörrbecker (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Volume V: <hi rend="i">Milton a Prophecy and the Final Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. Robert
N. Essick &amp; Joseph Viscomi (1993) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Volume VI: <hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi>, ed. David Worrall (1995) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi>, ed. D. W. Dörrbecker (1995) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>1 Iain Sinclair, “Customising Biography,” <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi>,
22 February 1996, 16-19 (with Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1995], and the Blake Trust reproductions
of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [1991], <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi> [1993], <hi rend="i">The
Continental Prophecies</hi> [1995], <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> [1993], and <hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi>
[1995]) (there is no indication that Sinclair has looked at <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi>—for
a protest, see John Commander, below).</p>
                  <p>2 Barthélémy Jobert, <hi rend="i">Revue de l’Art</hi>, No. 112 (1996), 78 (with
Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> [1993], and <hi rend="i">The Urizen
Books</hi>, ed. David Worrall [1995]) (barely mentioned).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
Joseph Viscomi (1993) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>3 §Daniel Mark Epstein, “The Two William Blakes,” <hi rend="i">New Criterion</hi>,
XIII, No. 2 (October 1994), 10-22 (with Viscomi’s <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> [1993]
and the other Blake Trust volumes).</p>
                  <p>4 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> for 1993 (1996), 322
(“splendid”).</p>
                  <p>5 Michael Ferber, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> XXIX, 3 (Winter 1995-96), 88-90 (“an
altogether splendid volume,” with “the most lucid and succinct summary of Blake’s methods of book
production that I have ever seen” [88]).</p>
                  <p>6 Iain Sinclair, “Customising Biography,” <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi>,
22 February 1996, 16-19 (with Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1995], and the Blake Trust reproductions
of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [1991], <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [1991], 
<hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi> [1995], <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> [1993], and <hi rend="i">The Urizen
Books</hi> [1995]) (there is no indication that Sinclair has looked at <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated
Books</hi>—for a protest, see John Commander, below).</p>
                  <p>7 S. L. M., <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>, 138<hi rend="s">e</hi> Année
(1996), 19 (with <hi rend="i">Milton a Prophecy and the Final Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick
&amp; Joseph Viscomi [1993]) (the series is “une magnifique collection”).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Earth’s Answer</hi> (Madley, Hereford: Five Seasons Press [1980s])
Broadside.</p>
                  <p>“The Edition of the Works of Wm. Blake” printed by William Muir at “The Blake Press
at Edmonton,” England (1884-1936) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #249, <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 152-55&gt;.</p>
                  <figure n="BlakeMaskSpectacles.30.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="613">
                    <head>2 Life mask of William Blake wearing the half-pair of spectacles. When the mask was
made, the clay pinned his ears to his head, so the spectacle-frame had to be fixed to his head with
anachronistic sellotape.</head>
                    <figDesc>Photo courtesy of Devereux Photography, Felpham.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>The Rev. Mr. Arthur Chichester Crookshank (1889-1958) acquired from Quaritch most of the
Muir facsimiles, many of them identified as “M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Muirs Master Copy,” which he bequeathed
to the West Sussex Record Office &lt;WSRO&gt;. All these Master Copies have notes made in Quaritch’s shop
(“Q”), and some have notes by Muir (“M”) as well. In the record below, the details not in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Book Supplement</hi> are given in bold face, and the copy reproduced is given within
parentheses “(A).”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">America</hi> (A)</p>
                  <p>Q: “copied from an original [A] lent to Mr Muir by M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Quaritch in
1905. It is now in the U.S.A. <hi rend="b">24 copies were sold by Mess<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Quaritch.</hi>”
&lt;WSRO&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Ancient of Days [<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 1] (D)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> The note appears on the verso of the last leaf of the first version of
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> with which it is bound. A duplicate uncolored copy of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 1 is
marked “rough proof” “Corrected from life” (WSRO = West Sussex Record Office).</note></p>
                  <p>M: “Fifty copies . . . were sold by Mr Quaritch (at 21/- each—All numbered) 
<hi rend="b">between 18<hi rend="s">th</hi> May 1885 and 14<hi rend="s">th</hi> August 1919[.] | P.S. Reference to
documents shows me that the above statement is not quite correct, M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Pearson had sold nine
copies before M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Quaritch began”; “Coloured from an original by Blake in the British
Museum.”</hi> &lt;WSRO&gt;.</p>
                  <pb id="p30-127" n="127"/>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> [first version] (D)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> With it is a much-corrected “Rough proof” of Muir’s “Proposal for
the Prophetic Books and the Songs of Innocence and of Experience by W Blake.”</note></p>
                  <p>M: “Copied from British Museum Copy [D]”; “Fifty Copies of this Book (all numbered)
were produced and sold in 1884-90 at £2.2 0[.] M<hi rend="s">r</hi>_Pearson sold the first twenty copies
between October 1884 and April 1885. At that date he retired from business because ‘he found that he had
£20,000 and he did not want more’[.] He introduced me to M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Quaritch, who continued the
work[.] He received and sold the remaining thirty copies between 27<hi rend="s">th</hi> April 1885 and 8<hi
rend="s">th</hi> September 1890[.]” &lt;WSRO&gt;.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> [second version] (J)</p>
                  <p>Q: “24 copies have been sold”; M: “This copy of Thel [J] is coloured from one that
M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Bernard Quaritch lent to me in 1885-6. He sold it afterwards to an American [Amy Lowell
c. 1900], so it is now in the U.S.A.” With it are duplicates of pl. 2, 4, 6-7, identified (M) on a separate
leaf: “The four pages just before this are from originals [<hi rend="i">from the Small Book of Designs</hi>]
in the B. M. print Room | They were coloured by [<hi rend="i">Miss]</hi> E. J. Druitt” as in color-printing.
&lt;WSRO&gt;.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> [third version] (A)</p>
                  <p>“The Beckford copy” (i.e., A), bought by Quaritch at the Beckford sale in 1883, sold
to E. W. Hooper in 1891. Both the second and third versions in the WSRO have inscriptions on the designs: Pl.
2 (titlepage): “Lives [?Loves] of the plants<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> in Summer”; pl. 4: “Flowers personified”; pl. 6: “Spring”; pl. 7: “Fallen
seeds protected by the earth Autumn.” The third version facsimile also has a note: “Perhaps Beckford got
these titles from Blake when buying the Book,” though this copy of the book was in the Cumberland sale of
1835 before Beckford obtained it. &lt;WSRO&gt;. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Part II (1789) of Erasmus
Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> was called “The Loves of the Plants.”</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (A, D, c]</p>
                  <p>Q: “with 2 pp. added from Blakeana . . . 50 copies were sold by Messrs Quaritch
|‘Blakeana’ was a vol of scraps[;] the Macgeorge fragment is now in U.S.A.” Part of this volume of
Blakeana &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #125&gt; was sold by Quaritch in 1886 to William Muir, and the rest was sold
by Quaritch to B. B. MacGeorge by 1906 and acquired by George C. Smith of the United States by 1927.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> &lt;WSRO&gt;. 
<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Another copy of Muir’s <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is inscribed: “This is an uncolored copy
of Europe | It is of no special value | M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Muir offers it for your acceptance.”
&lt;WSRO&gt;</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> (F)</p>
                  <p>M: “About 20 copies have been made and sold[,] the Text [<hi rend="i">is</hi>] printed
W Muir” (the text is in fact printed from movable type). &lt;WSRO&gt;.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> [second version] (F) M, “Forest Gate May
1920”: “This is a careful copy of a copy by Chatto &amp; Windus c. 1864 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #99&gt;
From the Original [F] that belonged to D.G. Rossetti.” “This copy is facsimiled after the Dante Gabriel
Rossetti Copy—The titles given to the plates are after the Beckford copy [A].”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> “20 copies have been sold.” The inscriptions are: Pl. 1
(titlepage): “Union of the Elements”; pl. 2: “Earth”; pl. 3: “Fire”; pl. 4: “Water”; pl. 5:
“Air”; pl. 11: “Dawn”; pl. 14: “The Body of Hector”; pl. 15: “Genius”; pl. 16: “Ugolino”;
pl. 20: “A Dream”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> pl. 21:
“Satan addressing the Sun”; pl. 24: “Arbitrary Power.” It is reproduced from a color-printed copy, and
the only color-printed copy is F, which was bought by R. M. Milnes in 1852 and sold by his son in 1903. There
seems to be no other evidence that copy F (or any other copy) “belonged to D.G. Rossetti.” &lt;WSRO&gt;.
<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The Crookshank Collection also has a copy of the First Version of Muir’s
facsimile of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> made from copy A.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Inscribed at the bottom in Muir’s Brown ink: “The Background should
be quite smooth| The reds in the Serpent should be brighter.”</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> [third version] (I)</p>
                  <p>M: “M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Muirs <hi rend="i">Master Copy</hi> of the Fitzwilliam Heaven
&amp; Hell | about five copies were sold[.] The original is in the FitzWilliam Museum Cambridge.” “Copied
in April 1886 by J. D. Wallis from the original in the Fitzwilliam Museum at Cambridge. | Note the letter
press should all be printed in red, not in yellow.” The titlepage verso in inscribed in pencil “Richard
Edward Kerrick | August 31<hi rend="s">st</hi> 1856” as in copy I. “Coloured thus £4.4.0.” It bears
annotations from the Beckford copy. &lt;WSRO&gt;.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (A)</p>
                  <p>M: “This is M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Muir’s Master Copy of the Song of Los copied from
the original in the British Museum [A] | 21 copies were sold by Mess<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Quaritch.”
&lt;WSRO&gt;.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> (A, H, L)</p>
                  <p>“M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Muirs Master Copy of No Nat Relig | 50 copies were sold | I do
not know where the original is now.” Facing pl. b12 (“God becomes as we are that we may be as he is”) is
a quotation from Irenaeus about the phrase (see <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> [1978], 14). On
the first flyleaf is a transcription of <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> with a note: “This little
book is copied from illustrated leaves in the possession of the Linnell family . . . W Muir”; Muir never
made a facsimile of <hi rend="i">All Religions are One.</hi> &lt;WSRO&gt;.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Eternity.</hi> (Berkeley, California: Mayacamas Press, 1993) Broadside 35
× 28 inches.</p>
                  <p>It is “He Who Binds to Himself a Joy.”</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Fellow Labourers in the Great Vintage.</hi> ([Buffalo, N.Y.: Institute of
Further Studies, 1968) Broadside.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">If the Doors of Perception Were Cleansed.</hi> ([Mount Carmel,
Connecticut:] Ives Street Press, 1983) 4 pp. A broadside.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell:</hi> Office Drawn from the Lyric and
Prophetic Work of William Blake (1727-1827) for Use of St. Mark’s in-the-Bourie. (N.Y.: 1920s).</p>
                  <pb id="p30-128" n="128"/>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Milton a Poem and the Final Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick
&amp; Joseph Viscomi (1993) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>3 §Daniel Mark Epstein, “The Two William Blakes,” <hi rend="i">New Criterion</hi>,
XIII, No. 2 (October 1994), 10-22 (with Viscomi’s <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> [1993]
and the other Blake Trust volumes).</p>
                  <p>4 Dennis M. Read, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXIX, 3 (Winter 1995-96), 91-92 (“there is
much to praise, little to question, and less to criticize in this splendid volume” [92]).</p>
                  <p>5 Iain Sinclair, “Customising Biography,” <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi>,
22 February 1996, 16-19 (with Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1995], and the Blake Trust reproductions
of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [1991], <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [1991], 
<hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi> [1993], <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi> [1995], and 
<hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi> [1995]) (there is no indication that Sinclair has looked at <hi rend="i">Milton
. . . and the Final Illuminated Books</hi>—for a protest, see John Commander, below).</p>
                  <p>6 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> for 1993 (1996), 323
(“splendid”).</p>
                  <p>7 S. L. M., <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>, 138<hi rend="s">e</hi> Année
(1996), 19 (with <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, &amp;
Joseph Viscomi [1993]) (the series is “une magnifique collection”).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Pesni Nevinnosti opyta.</hi> [Tr. Sergeia Stepanova into Russian,
Kommentari Aleksandry Glebouskoi.] (Sankt-Peterburg: Severo-Zapad, 1993) 270 pp.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Poems of William Blake</hi> ed. Peter Ackroyd (1995) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>1 *Alberto Manguel, “Genius of Blake revealed: Ackroyd makes it clear we owe the poet a
great many revelations about our senses,” <hi rend="i">Globe and Mail</hi> [Toronto], 13 January 1996, p.
C20 (with Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1995]).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Poesía completa.</hi> Prólogo, Pablo Mañe [Garzon]; introducción,
Mariano Vázquez Alonso; correción y revisión, E. Caracciolo Trejo (Barcelona: Ediciones 29, 1986), Río
nuevo, 2 vols., 452 pp. ISBN: 84-7175-186-0 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS; Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;. . . . D.
§(Barcelona, 1995).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, ed. John Sampson (1913) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#302&gt;. The Penguin edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Selected Poems</hi> (1996) was apparently selected
from John Sampson’s edition (1913).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">A Printing House in Hell.</hi> (Pittsburgh: The Laboratory Press, 1930)
Students’ Project (Carnegie Institute of Technology Library Press) Specimen No. 103. Broadside 35 × 20.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Proverbs of Hell.</hi> Translated to Scotch by William Henshaw.
([Markinch:] Scrievens Press, 1988) 8 pp.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Pu-lai-k’o shih hsuan:</hi> Chou Wen-ping i. (Taipei: Wu Chou, mia 62,
1973) 121 pp. In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Selected Poems.</hi> Ed. P. H. Butter. (London, Melbourne, Toronto: Dent,
1982) B. §1986. C. §1988. D. §1989. E. *London &amp; Rutland, Vermont, 1991.</p>
                  <p>An “abridged edition,” omitting the editor’s name, was published as *<hi
rend="i">Songs of Innocence &amp; Experience</hi> (London: Phoenix, 1996).</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Selected Poems.</hi> (London, N.Y., Ringwood [Victoria, Australia],
Toronto, Auckland: Penguin Books, 1996) Penguin Popular Classics 12°, ×, 242. ISBN: 0-14-062219-5.</p>
                  <p>Lyric poems plus <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> and <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> apparently selected
from <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, ed. John Sampson (1913) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #302&gt;.</p>
                  <p>§*<hi rend="i">Selected Works.</hi> Ed. David Stevens. (Cambridge: Cambridge University
Press, 1995) 144 pp.</p>
                  <p>§*<hi rend="i">The Shepherd.</hi> ([Berkeley Heights, New Jersey: The Oriole Press,
?1932]) 4 pp. “with cordial greetings of the season 1932-3.”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence &amp; [of] Experience.</hi> (London: Phoenix, 1996)
Square 16°, [vi], 58 pp., ISBN: 1-85799-541-4.</p>
                  <p>The text of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and poems from the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> and
the Pickering MS is apparently taken from <hi rend="i">Selected Poems</hi> [ed. P. H. Butter] (1981) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 164&gt; [which in turn is taken from <hi rend="i">Poems &amp; Prophecies</hi>, ed. Max
Plowman (1927) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #287&gt;].</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">The Tyger: O tygres.</hi> Tr. Augusto de Campos. (Sao Paulo: [no
publisher], 1977) 8 pp. In English and Portuguese.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi>, ed. David Worrall (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1996)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>1 Iain Sinclair, “Customising Biography,” <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi>,
22 February 1996, 16-19 (with Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1995], and the Blake Trust reproductions
of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [1991], <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [1991], 
<hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi> [1993], <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi> [1995], and 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> [1993]) (there is no indication that Sinclair has looked at <hi rend="i">The Urizen
Books</hi>—for a protest, see John Commander, below).</p>
                  <p>2 Barthélémy Jobert, <hi rend="i">Revue de l’Art</hi>, No. 112 (1996), 78 (with
Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> [1993], and <hi rend="i">The Continental
Prophecies</hi>, ed. D.W. Dörrbecker [1995]) (barely mentioned).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">The Voice of the Ancient Bard.</hi> (London: Spoon Print Press, 1994) 4
leaves.</p>
                  <p>Illustrated by Linda Ann Landers.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">William Blake Od mi-shire ve-Keats</hi> [<hi rend="i">More Poems by Blake
and Keats</hi>]. [Tr. Joshu Kochov.] (Tel Aviv: Ofir, 1980) 32 pp.</p>
                  <pb id="p30-129" n="129"/>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Yongguk Nangnam sisa = Selected English Romantic Poems</hi>—William
Blake oe. Ed. Sisa Yongosa. (Seoul: T’ukpyols: Sisa Yongosa, 1990) 247 pp.</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Zemirtes Koka</hi> [<hi rend="i">Under the Myrtle Tree</hi>]. [Tr. Olga
Lisovska into Latvian.] (Riga: Liesma, 1981) 203 pp.</p>
                  <p>Tamara Zalite, “Viljams Bleiks” (5-14); O. Lisovska, “Komentari” (103-04).</p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part II Reproductions of Drawings and Paintings</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Section A: Illustrations of Individual Authors</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Bible</p>
                  <p>§<corr type="emend">Bhaktipada,</corr> Swami. <hi rend="i">The Bible Illuminated:</hi>
Illustrated by William Blake and Francisco de Hollanda. Ed. Krzysztof Cieszkowski. (New Vrindaban, W. Va.:
Palace Pub, 1994).</p>
                  <p>Bunyan, John, <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi></p>
                  <p>Blake’s Bunyan designs (see illus. 1-4) were offered by the Frick Collection (N.Y.)
(along with a design for <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>) at §Sotheby’s (London), 14 November 1996, Lot
243 (estimate £260,000-£340,000), bought in, and sold to an Anonymous British collector. For behind the
scenes details, see Essick, Marketplace, 1996.</p>
                  <p>Gray, Thomas, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi></p>
                  <p>Blake’s 116 watercolors for Gray are reproduced in reduced size and monochrome in Frank
A. Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Again to the Life of Eternity</hi> (1996).</p>
                  <p>Milton, John, <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi></p>
                  <p>“The First Temptation” from the <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> series (see
illus. 5) was sold by the Frick Collection to an Anonymous British collector—see Bunyan (above).</p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Section B: Collections and Selections</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p><hi rend="i">William Blake at the Huntington</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick (1994) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995) under Art&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>1 S. L. M., <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>, 138<hi rend="s">e</hi> Année
(1996), 19-20 (the book is edited by “l’un des principaux spécialistes actuels de Blake” and produced
“en couleurs de grande qualité”).</p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part III Commercial Book Engravings</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Bible—<hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi> (1826, 1874)</p>
                <p>New Location: Felsted School (Felsted, Essex) (reproduced in the 1996 2 February-7 April
(catalogue of the Fundación “la Caixa” in Madrid, plates 64a-x).</p>
                <p>Edition</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi> Invented &amp; Engraved by William Blake
1825. (London: Frederick Hollyer, 1923) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #430&gt;.</p>
                <p>According to a prospectus (?1925), 225 copies were produced at £3.3.0.</p>
                <p>Cumberland, George, <hi rend="i">An Attempt to Describe Hafod</hi> (1796)</p>
                <p>New Location: Princeton.</p>
                <p>Edition</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">An Attempt to Describe Hafod</hi> by George Cumberland. A Bicentenary Edition
Edited and Introduced by Jennifer Macve &amp; Andrew Sclater, Illustrated with Drawings from a sketchbook of
Thomas Jones of Pencerrig introduced by Donald Moore. (Aberystwyth: Ymddiriedolaeth Yr Hafod—Hafod Trust,
1996) 8°, ISBN: 0-9527941-0-1.</p>
                <p>This is a facsimile of the copy in the National Library of Wales, with Jennifer Macve &amp;
Andrew Sclater, “Introduction” (1-10, 15-16), and Donald Moore, “The artist Thomas Jones at Hafod”
(11-14, 16). A section on “Hafod in 1795 and Blake’s Map” (9-10) concludes that “One must . . . keep
an open mind” as to what part Blake had in the map.</p>
                <p>Cumberland, George, <hi rend="i">Outlines from the Antients</hi> (1829) New Locations:
Brown, California (Santa Barbara), Edinburgh.</p>
                <p>Cumberland, George, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> (1796)</p>
                <p>New Locations: California State Library, Getty, Harvard, Iowa.</p>
                <p>Dante, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations of Dante</hi> (1838)</p>
                <p>New Location: Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery.</p>
                <p>Darwin, Erasmus, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> (1791, 1791, 1795, 1799, 1806)</p>
                <p>C 1795 (Third Edition) New Location: Ushaw College (Durham).</p>
                <p>Euler, Leonard, <hi rend="i">Elements of Algebra</hi> (1797)</p>
                <p>Blake was probably referring to his engraving (c. 6.8 × 11.0 cm) for Euler’s 
<hi rend="i">Elements of Algebra</hi> when he told the Revd. Dr. Trusler on 23 August 1799: “I had Twelve 
[<hi rend="i">Guineas</hi>] for the [<hi rend="i">small engraved</hi>] Head I sent you.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> He could alternatively but less plausibly be referring to his engraving
of the head of John Brown (c. 11 × 13 cm) for Brown’s <hi rend="i">Elements of Medicine</hi> (1795) or to
one of the heads of Catullus and Cornelius Nepos (each c. 10 × 17 cm) for <hi rend="i">Poems of Caius
Valerius Catullus</hi> (1795).</note></p>
                <p>Flaxman, John, <hi rend="i">Compositions from . . . Hesiod</hi> (1817)</p>
                <p>New Locations: Edinburgh, Newcastle Literary and Philosophical Society, NYPL (2),
Pennsylvania State, Rochester, Syracuse.</p>
                <pb id="p30-130" n="130"/>
                <p>Flaxman, John, <hi rend="i">The Iliad of Homer</hi> (1805)</p>
                <p>New Locations: American Academy (Rome), Art Institute (Chicago), Brown, California
(Berkeley; Davis), California State Library, Cleveland Museum, Edinburgh, Florida State, Getty, Harvard,
Metropolitan Museum, Michigan, Minnesota (2), Pierpont Morgan, NYPL, New York University, Pennsylvania State,
Rochester, Ushaw College (Durham).</p>
                <p>Gay, John, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793, [1811])</p>
                <p>A 1793 New locations: Newcastle Literary and Philosophical Society; Toronto Public Library
(Osborne Collection of Early Children’s Books); Ushaw College (Durham).</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805)</p>
                <p>New Locations: California (Berkeley), Cornell, Free Library of Philadelphia, Iowa,
Michigan, NYPL, Stanford.</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi> (1800)</p>
                <p>New Location: Brown, California (Berkeley), Minnesota, Newcastle Literary and Philosophical
Society, Pennsylvania.</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">The Life . . . of William Cowper, Esq.</hi> (1803-04)</p>
                <p>New Locations: A (1803-04) Athenaeum (Philadelphia), Brown, California (Berkeley; Santa
Barbara), Cornell, Edinburgh, Iowa, LC, Michigan, Mills College, Minnesota, National Gallery (Washington),
National Library of Scotland, NYPL (2), Northwestern, Pennsylvania State, Southern California, Stanford, State
University of New York (Stony Brook).</p>
                <p>B Second Edition (1804) Rochester.</p>
                <p>New Entry</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">The Life . . . of William Cowper</hi> (N.Y., 1803)</p>
                <p>The wood-engraving in William Hayley, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of
William Cowper</hi> (New York: T. &amp; J. Swords, 1803), Vol. II, at p. 245, of “The Weather-house” and
“Cowper’s Tame Hares” (8.3 × 11 cm) signed Alexander “Anderson F[<hi rend="i">ecit</hi>]” was
copied from the design signed “Blake d &amp; sc” in the edition of London: J. Johnson, 1803, as R. N.
Essick was the first to point out in Marketplace, 1996, illus. 8. The plates engraved by Peter Maverick of
Cowper and of Cowper’s mother (Vol. I, frontispiece and at p. 3) are copied from Blake’s engravings after
George Romney and D. Heins.</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi> (1809)</p>
                <p>New Locations: Art Institute (Chicago), Boston Museum, Brown, California (Berkeley [2],
Davis, Santa Barbara), Clarke Art Institute, Edinburgh, Emory, Florida, Folger, Getty, Kimbell Art Museum,
Metropolitan Museum, Minnesota (2), National Library (Ottawa), Nelson Atkins Museum, Stanford, Yale.</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi> (1807)</p>
                <p>THE | TRIUMPHS OF TEMPER [not THE | TRIUMPHS | OF | TEMPER, as in <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi>]</p>
                <p>New Locations: (1803) Brown, California (Berkeley), Cornell, Emory (Theology), Iowa, LC,
Michigan, Mills College, Minnesota, NYPL, Northwestern, Pennsylvania, State University of New York
(Buffalo).</p>
                <p>(1807) Brown.</p>
                <p>Josephus, Flavius, <hi rend="i">Genuine and Complete Works</hi> ([?1785-90]) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 228-29&gt;</p>
                <p>Josephus, Flavius, <hi rend="i">The Whole Genuine and Complete Works</hi>, ed. Maynard
&amp; Kimpton (London: C. Cooke and . . . Ireland, n.d.).</p>
                <p>E (1792-93) New Location: Ushaw College (Durham).</p>
                <p>Lavater, J. C., <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> (1788, 1789, 1794)</p>
                <p>The copy of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> (1788)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> signed and annotated by “Thos: Butt | 23 Aug<hi
rend="s">t</hi> 1789—” &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt; almost certainly has nothing to do with
Blake’s London patron Thomas Butts; rather it belonged to a contemporary, perhaps of Bridgmouth, Shropshire,
with a coincidentally similar name, who annotated it (as Lavater directed) with symbols indicating his likes
and dislikes and with occasional notes such as that for Aphorism #539 concerning four women with virtues so
rare that there will scarcely be found one in each quarter of the world:
<q>
Such are The Marchioness of Stafford—Trentham<lb/>
Stafford<lb/>
M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Berry of y<hi rend="s">e</hi> Mill Stamford—Worcestershire<lb/>
M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Butt of Bridgmouth<lb/>
Shropshire<lb/>
Miss Butt —
</q></p>
                <p>Lavater, J. C., <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> (1789-98; 1810; 1792 [i.e.,
1817])<lb/>
1810 New Locations: Edinburgh; National Library of Scotland. <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Seen 15 May
1996 through the courtesy of Arthur Freeman and Ted Hoffman at Quaritch’s (London).</note></p>
                <p>Plate 4: The plate signed “Blake sculp” below and to the right of the image also has
“Blake Sc” “very lightly scratched immediately below, and on the same diagonal as, the line defining the
lower margin of the figure’s neck” (as was first recorded in Essick, Marketplace, 1996).</p>
                <p>The Quality of the Engravings</p>
                <p>According to the engraver Thomas Holloway, who supervised the plates for Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>,
<q>
It was not long before TH found that in spite of all his Care &amp; even expostulations with most of the
Artists—
<pb id="p30-131" n="131"/>
the work they brought home was distressingly inaccurate—many plates were destroyd totally—and those which
were the best executed were frequently so errone[<hi rend="i">o</hi>]us both in outline &amp; expression that
many parts were obligd <hi rend="i">to be hammerd out</hi> &amp; reproduced—a piece of work this the most
painful &amp; the most mortyfying imaginable to TH— . . .<lb/>
A great number of the plates were necessarily repaird in some instances twice in a few instances 3 times
making the plates equal to duplicates—which was the case with the Venus de Medicis &amp; others—without
this attention the major part of the Impressions wou[l]d have been weak &amp; the Reputation of the work most
materially injured . . .<lb/>
The work executed by TH &amp; others was in its Kind unique .... Without Vanity it is presumed that for
Correctness as well as for execution it Stands unequalld-<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> “Observations Submitted to the Consideration of Doct Hunter M<hi
rend="s">r</hi> Johnson—two of the proprietors of Lavater—and the Execs of the late M<hi rend="s">r</hi>
[<hi rend="i">John</hi>] Murray” dated January 1802 in the archive of the publisher John Murray, printed
here (like the other Murray Archive papers) by permission of John Murray.</note></q></p>
                <p>Payment for the Engravings</p>
                <p>In Holloway’s list of “Expenses attending the Engravings of Lavater . . . during the
years 1787 to 1799” is “Blake ..... [£]39.19.6,” a somewhat moderate payment for three small plates and
one large one.</p>
                <p>Holloway’s figures indicate the following prices for Lavater:</p>
                <table rows="4" cols="2">
                  <row>
                    <cell>Cost of Copper</cell>
                    <cell>£ 88. 4.—</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Engraving Titles on Plates</cell>
                    <cell>£ 26.15.—</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Total Cost of Engravings<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> This is the total given in Holloway’s list of what he paid to
individual engravers; the total in his list of what he paid year-by-year is £2,683.13.6 [this is mis-added by
Holloway; it should be £2,628.13.6].
                                                <p>Of the 37 engravers for Lavater named in Holloway’s list,
only 24 names are recorded on the engravings themselves (113 plates), <hi rend="i">“Holloway Direxit”</hi>
is on 156 of them, and 267 are anonymous.</p></note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£2,558.17.—</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Cost of Printing and Hotpressing Plates</cell>
                    <cell>£2,500.—.—</cell>
                  </row>
                </table>
                <p>Sale of the Copperplates</p>
                <p>The 537 copperplates for Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> were sold to John
Stockdale, who published an edition in 1810. After Stockdale’s death (1814), “<hi rend="i">the Remaining
Stock of the Estate of the Late Mr. John Stockdale</hi>; consisting chiefly of Copper Plates, together with
the Copyrights to the Works, to which they belong” was offered for sale at auction by Robert Saunders on 3
January 1818, and the “Five hundred and thirty-seven [copperplates]—Lavater’s Physiognomy, by Hunter,
4°, <hi rend="i">and Copyright</hi>” were sold for £210 (according to the marked copy in the British
Library; no buyer is listed for any of the lots).</p>
                <p>Silent Reprint of the Book</p>
                <p>The plates were subsequently printed on paper watermarked as late as 1817 but dated 1792 on
the titlepages and bearing the names of the original publishers but not that of the 1817 buyer of the
copperplates. Perhaps the new owner discovered belatedly that the copyright he had acquired was for the plates
only and did not include the copyright of Dr. Henry Hunter’s translation of Lavater. He may therefore have
decided that it was safest to conceal the date and to pretend that this was the original edition.</p>
                <p>Malkin, B. H., <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of his Child</hi> (1806) New Location:
Toronto Public Library (Osborne Collection of Early Children’s Books).</p>
                <p>Mora, José Joaquin de, <hi rend="i">Meditaciones Poeticas</hi> (1826) New Location:
Biblioteca Nacional (Madrid): R35836 and ER2444.</p>
                <p>Salzmann, C. G., <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>, tr. [Mary Wollstonecraft] (1791,
1792, 1799, 1805, ?1815)</p>
                <p>A 1791 New Location: Toronto Public Library (Osborne Collection of Early Children’s
Books).</p>
                <p>Shakspeare, William, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi> (Boydell, 1802) New Location: Ushaw College
(Durham).</p>
                <p>Stedman, J. G., <hi rend="i">Narrative of a five years’ expedition, against the Revolted
Negroes of Surinam</hi> (1796, 1806, 1813)</p>
                <p>1796 New Locations: Newcastle Literary and Philosophical Society, Stanford.</p>
                <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary, <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> (1791, 1796) A 1791 New Location:
Toronto Public Library (Osborne Collection of Early Children’s Books).</p>
                <p>Young, Edward, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 271; 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;</p>
                <p>New Locations: Library of Congress, *Muhlenberg College.</p>
                <p>Census of Colored Copies</p>
                <p>Addenda</p>
                <p>Copy G</p>
                <p>History: . . . (6) The Lutheran Church of America in 1986 passed it, with the Florence
Foerderer Tonner print collection, to (7) The Frank Martin Gallery, Muhlenberg College.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Ten plates from copy G are reproduced in color in Grant F. Scott, “A
Clash of Perspectives: Blake’s Illustrations to the Poem <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> . . .,” 
<hi rend="i">Muhlenberg</hi>, V (1993), 10-16.</note></p>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Appendix Books with Engravings Implausibly Attributed to Blake</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Minor’s Pocket Book</hi> (1813)</p>
                  <p>Fuller details of the plate attributed to Blake in [Ann Taylor et al.], <hi rend="i">The
Minor’s Pocket Book, for the Youth of Both</hi>
	<pb id="p30-132" n="132"/>
	<hi rend="i">Sexes</hi> ([London:] Darton, Harvey, and Darton, 1813) are recorded and the Blake connection
rejected in Essick, Marketplace, 1996.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Plutarch’s Lives:</hi> Abridged, Selected and Adapted for Youth . . . as
an Introduction to Classic Reading for the Use of Schools by J[ohn] Faucit Saville. ([London:] Printed for R.
Hill, 1823) 116 pp.</p>
                  <p>It is claimed to have a “Frontispiece by William Blake.”</p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part IV Catalogues and Bibliographies</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>1954</p>
                <p>*<hi rend="i">William Blake, The Romantic Poets, The Nineteenth Century:</hi> The Brick Row
Book Shop, Inc., Catalogue No. 41. (N.Y.: Brick Row Book Shop, 1954).</p>
                <p>The Blake lots are 1-70, 668-70, including Blake’s copy of Barry’s <hi rend="i">Account
of a Series of Pictures</hi> (1783) and nine works inscribed “Original Drawings by William Blake” [?now in
the New York Public Library], “an interesting imposture.”</p>
                <p>1959, 1995</p>
                <p>Robert F. Metzdorf. <hi rend="i">The Tinker Library:</hi> A Bibliographical Catalogue of
the Books and Manuscripts collected by Chauncey Brewster Tinker. (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1959)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #683&gt; B. (1995).</p>
                <p>1960</p>
                <p>Steer, Francis W. “William Blake.” Pp. 6-14 of <hi rend="i">The Crookshank Collection
in the West Sussex Record Office:</hi> A Catalogue. Ed. Francis W. Steer. (Chichester: West Sussex County
Council, 1960) See also xii-xvi and passim.</p>
                <p>The collection by the Rev. Arthur Chichester Crookshank (1889-1958) focuses on Blake (No.
90-201), Hayley, and Chichester printing (viii).</p>
                <p>1976 2-5 March</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> [of the University of California (Santa Barbara) Art Galleries
exhibition for the Blake conference 2-5 March 1976].</p>
                <p>Fifteen mimeographed leaves with 99 entries (most of the original Blakes from the
collection of R. N. Essick). The catalogue was expanded (to 94 pp.), annotated, and illustrated in the
catalogue of <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of His Time</hi> (24 February-27 March 1976) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 293&gt;.</p>
                <p>1989</p>
                <p>Martin Butlin &amp; Ted Gott. <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Collection of the National
Gallery of Victoria</hi> (Melbourne, 1989) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 306&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 §David B. Brown, “Blake in Australia,” <hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi>, XII, 1
(March 1995), 87-88.</p>
                <p>1990</p>
                <p>Fitch, Donald. <hi rend="i">Blake Set to Music</hi> (1990) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
309-10&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 G. E. Bentley, Jr., in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXX (1996), 25-31 (“Fitch’s search
for music set to Blake texts seems to have been wonderfully comprehensive” [27]; the Appendix here [28-31]
lists addenda and corrigenda).</p>
                <p>1991 October</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Records of the William Blake Bicentenary Celebrations (1955-59)</hi>, MS 615
Department of Manuscripts and Special Collections, Hallward Library, University of Nottingham. ([Nottingham:
University of Nottingham, October 1991]).</p>
                <p>A five-page printed catalogue of “minutes, correspondence, photographs of Blake’s
paintings, news cuttings, agreements and financial material . . . given to the Library in 1991 by Mr John
Pyke, whose wife, then Miss D. Vaughan, assisted the committee in its work.”</p>
                <p>1991</p>
                <p>Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (1991)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 310&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 §David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, N.S. LIV (January 1993),
115-19 (with <hi rend="i">Blake and His Bibles</hi>, ed. D. V. Erdman [1990]).</p>
                <p>1993 1 May-26 June</p>
                <p>§<hi rend="i">William Blake and His Circle</hi>. Hunterian Library, [University of]
Glasgow, [exhibition] 1 May-26 June 1993. (Glasgow, 1993).</p>
                <p>1994</p>
                <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., with the assistance of Keiko Aoyama, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies in
Japan</hi> (1994) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 Yoko Ima-Izumi, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXIX, 3 (Winter 1995-96), 82-88 (mostly a useful
“necessary historical explanation” concerning the Japanese Blake scholars discussed in the “valuable
introduction” to <hi rend="i">Blake Studies in Japan</hi> [82]).</p>
                <p>2 Noriko Kawasaki, <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu Romanha Gakkai: 
<hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English Romanticism, No. 19-20 (1996),
178-80. In Japanese. (Highly esteemed.)</p>
                <p>1995 6-17 February</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">The Genitals are Beauty</hi>, exhibition at The House of William Blake 6-17
February 1995 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Keri Davies, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXIX, 3 (Winter 1995-96), 102-03 (the genitalia
exhibition “tied together a roomful of genitals with some of the kitschy inheritance of St. Valentine’s
Day”).</p>
                <p>1996 2 February-7 April; 17 April-2 June <hi rend="i">William Blake: visiones de mundos
eternos (1757-1827).</hi> [Exhibition]
<pb id="p30-133" n="133"/>
2 de febrero-7 de abril de 1996 [at the] Sala de Exposiciones de la Fundación “la Caixa,” Madrid. [Tr.
Gabriel Sánchez Espinosa, Russell B. Sacks, &amp; Elvira Villena.] (Madrid: Fundación “la Caixa,” 1996)
4°, 262 pp., 180 plates; ISBN: 84-7664-537-6. B. §<hi rend="i">William Blake: visions de mons eterns,
1757-1827:</hi> [Exhibition by Robin Hamlyn] 17 d’abril-2 de juny de 1996 Centre Cultural de la Fundacio
“La Caixa.” (Barcelona: Centre Cultural de la Fondacion” la Caixa,” 1996) 226 pp. In Catalan.</p>
                <p>Robin Hamlyn is the Comisaro or Curator of the exhibition.</p>
                <p>The book (A) consists of:</p>
                <p>1 Luis Monreal (Director General, Fundación “la Caixa”), “Presentación” (11),
“Foreword” (217): A prime reason for organizing the Blake exhibition is “the fact that his work is not
present in any Spanish museum or collection.”</p>
                <p>2 Robin Hamlyn, “William Blake (1757-1827)” (12-29 in Spanish; 219-28 in English): A
general account for a Spanish audience.</p>
                <p>3 Francisco Calvo Serraller, “Blake y Goya: convergencias y divergencias entre dos
mundos” (31-42); “Blake and Goya: Convergence and Divergence between Two Worlds” (229-35): Concerns
“Flaxman’s possible influence on Goya” (231), with an aside on Fuseli and a paragraph on Blake.</p>
                <p>4 Estella de Diego, “La invención de William Blake” (43-52); “The Invention of
William Blake” (237-42): “Blake is pervaded by life,” and “it is hard to tell just how much the
Surrealists actually read of Blake” (240, 237).</p>
                <p>5 *[Adela Morán &amp; Montserrat Gómez], “Catalogo” (53-210, with descriptions only
of the 180 color plates reproduced, which include <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> [X], <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
[B], and the Job engravings [1826]); “Catalogue” (243-59 in English of all 188 items exhibited).</p>
                <p>6 “Bibliografia” (211-13); “Literature” (261-62).</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 *Shantigarbha. “Visions of Eternity: Blake in Madrid: Exhibition at Fundacion ‘la
Caixa’, Madrid, February-April 1996,” <hi rend="i">Urthona</hi>, No. 6 (1996), 83 (“an important
event”).</p>
                <p>1996 9 July-6 October</p>
                <p>§<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to Young’s</hi> Night Thoughts.
[Exhibition at the] Tate Gallery, 9 July-6 October 1996. (London: Tate Gallery, 1996) 8 pp.</p>
                <p>1996 4-5 December</p>
                <p>. . . <hi rend="i">Periodicals, Manuscripts &amp; Ephemera, etc.</hi> [auction sale by
Foncie] Mealy. (Dublin, 1996).</p>
                <p>The Blakes included Lots 263-64, 297, 302, 303, 331, 385, 564-66, 579-88, 635, 637, 729,
797, 1247. Perhaps the most remarkable entry was that for Bewick’s Virgil (1821) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#504&gt;, Vol. I (?All published), estimate £150-£200 [sold for £3,000].</p>
                <p>1996?</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi> [Sale catalogue of] R. A. Gilbert. (Bristol: R. A.
Gilbert, [?1996]).</p>
                <p>An 11-page list of 330 Blake items for sale en bloc (without price).</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part V Books Blake Owned</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Barry, James, <hi rend="i">An Account of a Series of Pictures</hi> (1783) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 315-16&gt;.</p>
                <p>History: (1) It belonged to Samuel Palmer (see below), (2) Whose son inscribed the sketch:
“This is a portrait of Barry by Blake A H Palmer”; (3) Acquired by H. Buxton Forman, who added his
bookplate and a note about it and sold it posthumously at Anderson Galleries, 15 March 1920, Lot 36 [for
$205]; (4) Acquired by G. C. Smith, Jr., described in his anonymous catalogue (1927) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#631&gt;, and sold posthumously at Parke-Bernet, 2 November 1938 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #644&gt;, Lot 94
[for $250]; (5) Sold anonymously at Parke Bernet Galleries, 18 February 1942, #68 (“ORIGINAL WRAPPERS”);
(6) <hi rend="b">Offered in Brick Row Book Shop Catalogue 41</hi> (1954), Lot *1, for $200; (7) Bought from
Jacob Zeitlin of Los Angeles in 1962 by (8) Sir Geoffrey Keynes, who described it in his catalogue (1964)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #687&gt;, No. 721, and sold it posthumously with the rest of his type-printed books
in 1986 to (9) Cambridge University Library.</p>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Appendix Books Owned by the Wrong William Blake</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Johnson, Samuel</p>
                  <p>THE | LIVES | OF THE MOST EMINENT | ENGLISH POETS;| WITH | CRITICAL OBSERVATIONS | ON
THEIR| WORKS.| By SAMUEL JOHNSON.| IN FOUR VOLUMES.| |- | VOLUME I[-IV]. |  LONDON: | PRINTED FOR C. BATHURST,
J. BUCKLAND, W. STRAHAN, J. RIVINGTON AND SONS, T. DAVIES, T. PAYNE, L. DAVIS, W. OWEN, B. WHITE,| S. CROWDER,
T. CASLON, T. LONGMAN, B. LAW, C. DILLY,| J. DODSLEY, J. WILKIE, J. ROBSON, J. JOHNSON, T. LOWNDES,| G.
ROBINSON, T. CADELL, J. NICHOLS, E. NEWBERY, | T. EVANS, P. ELMSLY, J. RIDLEY, R. BALDWIN, G. NICOL, | LEIGH
AND SOTHEBY, J. BEW, N. CONANT, W. NICOLL,| J. MURRAY, S. HAYES, W. FOX, AND J. ROWEN.| M DCC LXXXI
[1781].</p>
                  <p>A copy with the black stamp in each volume of “W:BLAKE” and with paper labels
bordered by hand in red ink on each front paste-down with a brown ink (shelf-list?) number “N° 40[-43].”
to be offered in Marlborough Rare Books Catalogue 165 (1996). No such stamp or number is in any book
demonstrably owned by the poet, nor is such a system or the size of library it implies characteristic of him.
Probably the books belonged to one of the many contemporaries of the poet who bore his name.</p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <pb id="p30-134" n="134"/>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part VI Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Ackroyd, Peter, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>An excerpt from chapter 5 was reprinted in <hi rend="i">Lonsdale</hi>, II, No. 1 (January
1996), 12-13.</p>
                <p>For his account of writing the book, see <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society</hi>
(1996), 3-4.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>8 *Jonathan Bate, “William Blake in the new Jerusalem: Jonathan Bate admires Peter
Ackroyd’s biography of the great London visionary,” <hi rend="i">Sunday Telegraph</hi>, 3 September 1995,
p. 9 (“a biography of Blake which is lucid and measured, but also intuitive and empathetic. The scholarship
is impeccable, yet at the same time the novelist has got under his man’s skin”).</p>
                <p>9 §John Bemrose, “Burning bright,” <hi rend="i">Macleans</hi>, 6 November 1995. B.
Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Lonsdale</hi>, II, No. 1 (January 1996), 7-8 (“Ackroyd has given the artist a more
palpable, detailed presence than he has enjoyed at any time since his death”).</p>
                <p>10 Anon. “Anti-Enlightenment visionary,” <hi rend="i">Economist Review</hi>, 11
November 1995, pp. 4-5 (Ackroyd “sympathises deeply with Blake’s struggles” and takes Blake’s
“visions as seriously and soberly as he did,” but he is “badly served by the book’s designer” and
editor for tolerating muddy plates and prolix “displays of erudition”).</p>
                <p>11 *Alberto Manguel, “Genius of Blake revealed: Ackroyd makes it clear we owe the poet a
great many revelations about our senses,” <hi rend="i">Globe and Mail</hi>, [Toronto] 13 January 1996, p.
C20 (with <hi rend="i">Poems of William Blake</hi> ed. Peter Ackroyd [1995]).</p>
                <p>12 Iain Sinclair, “Customising Biography,” <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi>, 22
February 1996, pp. 16-19 (with the Blake Trust reproductions of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [1991], 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [1991], <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi>
[1993], <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi> [1995], <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> [1993], and 
<hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi> [1995]) (an enormous, and enormously self-indulgent, meander through what he
thinks are current intellectual avant-garde matters, commenting incidentally that Ackroyd’s 
“<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> is decently crafted fiction over-whelmed by an excess of tyrannical facts” “with
perhaps a little too much fondness for local colour” [18]).</p>
                <p>13 Paul Cantor, “William Blake, Capitalist,” <hi rend="i">Weekly Standard</hi>, 22
April 1996, pp. 29-32 (Ackroyd’s “<hi rend="i">new</hi> biography of Blake” stresses insufficiently that
Blake shows “the dogged spirit of the English small businessman” but that Blake “constantly 
<hi rend="i">misreads</hi> the market; he didn’t ignore or abjure it” [31, 30]).</p>
                <p>14 George Gurley (<hi rend="i">Kansas City Star</hi>), “Illuminating the visions of
William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Chicago Tribune</hi>, 23 April 1996, Section 2, p. 3 (Ackroyd’s “stylish
writing [<hi rend="i">is</hi>] lyrical and illuminating without being intrusive”—and Gurley has discovered
that Blake “could swear in nine languages”).</p>
                <p>15 Michael Dirda, <hi rend="i">International Herald Tribune</hi>, 21 May 1996, p. 10
(“Peter Ackroyd makes Blake live for the modern reader”).</p>
                <p>16 *Kennedy Fraser, “Piper Pipe that Song Again: Peter Ackroyd finds a William Blake for
our time,” <hi rend="i">New Yorker</hi>, 27 May 1996, pp. 126-31 (“This is a book with bounce and push”
about a man whose “work just glows, somehow”).</p>
                <p>17 §Colin Steel, <hi rend="i">Australian Book Collector</hi> (April 1996) (with
Viscomi’s <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> [1993]).</p>
                <p>18 Anon., <hi rend="i">Lonsdale</hi>, II, No. ii (April 1996), 11-[15] (review of chapters
8-14) (“That which made Blake a truly gifted man was his abilities and talents as a tradesman” [12]).</p>
                <p>19 Tim Heath, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society</hi> (1996), pp. 77-79 (Ackroyd
“builds up a life, slowly, with care and with detail”).</p>
                <p>20 *Dharmachari Ananda, “A Grain of Sand in Lambeth,” <hi rend="i">Urthona</hi>, No. 5
[1996], 43-46 (it is “a rich and closely observed biography” with a sharp focus on “tiny but telling
detail,” but “Ackroyd has a tendency to be dogmatic,” and “the whole man manages to elude us”).</p>
                <p>*Ackroyd, Peter. “Cockney Visionaries.” <hi rend="i">Independent</hi> [London] 18
December 1993, p. 27 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>“I want . . . to describe those London luminaries and Cockneys [chiefly “that Cockney
visionary William Blake,” Dickens and J. M. W. Turner] who in their art have expressed the true nature and
spirit of London. “Cockney” here appears to mean someone who epitomizes London.</p>
                <p>*Ackroyd, Peter. “To the rescue of a cockney prophet: Peter Ackroyd tells Giles Coren why
William Blake is unjustly neglected.” <hi rend="i">Times</hi>, 11 September 1995, p. 17.</p>
                <p>“Blake is a much better poet than people think”; “There has never been a substantial
biography of Blake”; “in fiction you have to tell the truth. In biography you can make things up.”</p>
                <p>Adams, Hazard. “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s Didactic and Mimetic-Narrative
Experiment: In Happy Memory of Northrop Frye.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, XXXII (1993),
627-54.</p>
                <p>“In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Blake sets contraries to the task of building an order in
disorder and disorder in order at the same time—and in the same place”—<corr type="emend">“an</corr>
introduction to a reading” (627), with a survey of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> criticism (651-54).</p>
                <p>§Ahlstrom, Chrispin. “Poet-Profet och konstnar.” <hi rend="i">Göteborgs-Posten</hi>,
27 April 1974. In Swedish.</p>
                <p>Allison, John. “Charioteer of fire: A huge choral setting of William Blake comes to
London on Sunday: A three-hour epic previewed.” <hi rend="i">Times</hi>, 15 November 1996, p. 36.</p>
                <p>Chiefly an interview with William Bolcom about a performance on 17 November 1996 at South
Bank of his setting of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi></p>
                <p>Annwn, David, <hi rend="i">Hear the Voice of the Bard</hi>! (1995) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <pb id="p30-135" n="135"/>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Sarah Joyce, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society</hi> (1996), 65-67 (it is a
“perceptive reading” of the “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>).</p>
                <p>Anon. “Expert on poet William Blake to lecture group.” <hi rend="i">Sunday
Chronicle</hi> [Muskegon, Michigan], 18 September 1996.</p>
                <p>Lecture by G. E. Bentley, Jr., on “The Artist and the Prophet: The Art of William
Blake,” related to the minor Blake collection at the Muskegon Museum of Art.</p>
                <p>Anon. “Felpham Has a Stamp Bible, Tobacco, and a Poet’s Cottage.” 
<hi rend="i">Southern Weekly News</hi>, 20 December 1952, p. 15.</p>
                <p>Partly about Blake’s cottage at Felpham.</p>
                <p>*Anon. “A Note on Four Water-Colours by William Blake.” <hi rend="i">International
Studio</hi>, LXXIV, No. 294 (September 1921), xxxvii.</p>
                <p>A comment, presumably by the editor, Guy C. Eglinton, on reproductions (on the cover and
xxxvii, xxxviii, xl) “from a small but very choice exhibition recently on view at the Metropolitan Museum”
[which is otherwise unknown].</p>
                <p>Anon. “Scene of a fairy funeral.” <hi rend="i">Evening Argus</hi>, 28 October 1962.</p>
                <p>Chiefly a photograph of Blake’s Cottage at Felpham.</p>
                <p>Anzai, Keiko. “<hi rend="i">Albion no Musumetachi no Genso</hi> ni okeru Hana Imejari no
Shoso: Aspects of Flower Imagery in <hi rend="i">The Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Showagakuin Tankidaigaku Kiyo: Bulletin of Showagakuin Junior College</hi>, No. 28 (1991), 83-95. In
Japanese.</p>
                <p>§Anzai, Keiko. “Blake, Lambeth Shohon ni okeru ‘Namida’ to ‘Kozui’: Tears and
Deluge in Blake’s Lambeth Books.” <hi rend="i">Showakaguin Tankidaigaku Kiyo: Bulletin of Showagakuin
Junior College</hi>, No. 22 (1990). In Japanese.</p>
                <p>Anzai, Keiko. “Blake ‘Yameru Bara’ ni okeru Jenda no Imi: The Gender of the Worm in
Blake’s ‘The Sick Rose.’” <hi rend="i">Ningen Bunka Kenkyu Nenpo, Ochanomizu Joshi Daigaku</hi>,
Ningen Bunka Kenkyuka: <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Doctoral Research Course in Human Culture</hi> [Ochanomizu
Women’s University], No. 15 (1991), 95-106. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>§Anzai, Keiko. “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> ni okeru Enion to Jumoku no Imejari:
Symbolic Trees and Enion in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Showakaguin
Tankidaigaku Kiyo: Bulletin of Showagakuin Junior College</hi>, No. 31 (1994). In Japanese.</p>
                <p>§Anzai, Keiko. “‘Kyojun’ no Anbivarensu—<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> no Leutha Zo:
Ambivalence of Submission: Leutha in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Showakaguin
Tankidaigaku Kiyo: Bulletin of Showagakuin Junior College</hi>, No. 29 (1992). In Japanese.</p>
                <p>*Anzai, Keiko. “Yokuatsu no Katachi—William Blake <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> no
Shinborizumu: A Depraved Form—The Symbolism of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Newton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Ningen
Bunka Kenkyu Nenpo, Ochanomizu Joshi Daigaku</hi>, Ningen Bunka Kenkyuka: <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the
Doctoral Research Course in Human Culture</hi> [Ochanomizu Women’s University], No. 14 (1990), 101-14. In
Japanese.</p>
                <p>Aoyama, Keiko. “Imi wa dokokara kuruno ka—Blake no <hi rend="i">Urizen [Daiichi] no
Sho</hi> ni okeru Imi-seisei no Purosesu: How Are the Meanings Generated?—William Blake’s Political Stance
in the 1790’s and <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>,
Igirisu Romanha Gakkai: <hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English
Romanticism, No. 19-20 (1996), 41-48. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>§Arakawa, Mitsuo. “Bungaku no naka no Toshi—William Blake to William Wordsworth no
Baai [Cities in Literature—In the Cases of William Blake and William Wordsworth].” <hi rend="i">Tohoku
Gakuin Daigaku Ronshu</hi>, Ningen Gengo, Joho, Tohoku Gakuin Daigaku Gakujutsu Kenkyukai: <hi rend="i">The
Tohoku Gakuin University Review</hi>, Human, Linguistics, and Information Sciences, The Research Association,
Tohoku Gakuin University, No. 110 (1995), 73-91. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>Baldwin, Michael. “Between Agues and the Muse: Blake would recognize the old place
....” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi>, 10 August 1991.</p>
                <p>About Blake’s cottage at Felpham.</p>
                <p>Barry, Kevin. “Autonomous song: [<hi rend="i">Michel-Paul Guy de</hi>] Chabanon and
Blake.” Pp. 65-78 of chapter 2: “William Blake and William Cowper” (56-93, 198-203) of his 
<hi rend="i">Language, music, and the sign:</hi> A study in aesthetics, poetics and poetic practice from Collins
to Coleridge. (Cambridge, N.Y., New Rochelle, Melbourne, Sydney: Cambridge University Press, 1987).</p>
                <p>A survey of “the most important ideas about music in the later poetry of the eighteenth
century” (56).</p>
                <p>*Beer, John. “Prophetic Affluence in the 1790s.” Chapter 2 (23-48, 257-62 of his 
<hi rend="i">Romantic Influences Contemporary-Victorian-Modern.</hi> (N.Y.: St Martin’s Press, 1993).</p>
                <p>Concerns especially Blake, Wordsworth, and Coleridge. Blake is also dealt with in
“Flowings” (chapter 1, 1-22, 156-57).</p>
                <p>Behrendt, Stephen C., <hi rend="i">Reading William Blake</hi> (1992) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 364&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 §James O. Allsup, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, XXV (1994), 219-
<pb id="p30-136" n="136"/>
21 (“a golden string that leads us in at the gate of a cleansed perception of not only literature but
criticism”).</p>
                <p>*Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Journeyman and the Genius: James Parker and His Partner William
Blake With a List of Parker’s Engravings.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, XLIX (1996), 208-31
plus 6 plates.</p>
                <p>“The career of James Parker demonstrates what that of William Blake might have been like
had he been a steady, reliable workman like Parker—and had he not been a genius” (220).</p>
                <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “<hi rend="i">Rex v. Blake:</hi> Sussex Attitudes toward the Military
and Blake’s Trial for Sedition in 1804.” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>, LVI (1993), 83-89
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 R[obert]. F. G[leckner], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994)
(“Interesting additions to what we know already (largely from Bentley)”).</p>
                <p>2 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> for 1993 (1996), 324
(“written fascinatingly”).</p>
                <p>*Bindman, David. “Blake, William.” Vol. IV, pp. 116-23 of <hi rend="i">The Dictionary
of Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries; London: Macmillan Publishers Limited, 1996).</p>
                <p>A good standard account.</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume XXVI, Number 2 (Fall 1992)</p>
                <p>1 Marsha Keith Schuchard. “The Secret Masonic History of Blake’s Swedenborg Society.”
Pp. 40-51.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
326 (it manifests “thorough researching”).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume XXVI, Number 4 (Spring 1993)</p>
                <p>1 John Vice, “William Blake—A Man Without Marx.” Pp. 162-65.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 72 (a
summary).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume XXVII, Number 1 (Summer 1993):</p>
                <p>1 G. E. Bentley, Jr. “‘Blake . . . Had No Quaritch’: The Sale of William Muir’s
Blake Facsimiles.” Pp. 4-13.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
328 (“well-documented, comprehensively researched”).</p>
                <p>2 *Keri Davies. “William Muir and the Blake Press at Edmonton with Muir’s letters to
Kerrison Preston.” Pp. 14-25.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
328 (“well-documented, comprehensively researched”).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> XXVII, Number 2 (Fall 1993)</p>
                <p>1 Robert N. Essick, “Blake’s 1812 Exhibition.” Pp. 36-42.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 67 (a carping
summary).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume XXVII, Number 3 (Winter
1993-94)</p>
                <p>2 Paula R. Feldman, “Felicia Hemans and the Mythologizing of Blake’s Death.” Pp.
69-72.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1994 (1995), 43-44 (a
summary).</p>
                <p>3 Warren Stevenson, “The Image of Canada in Blake’s <hi rend="i">America a
Prophecy.</hi>” Pp. 72-74.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1994 (1995), 45 (“Another
argument from coincidence”).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume XXVIII, Number 2 (Fall 1994)</p>
                <p>2 Chris Orr, “The Life of W. Blake.” Pp. 35-38.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1994 (1995), 44 (“The six
scenes reproduced are lively, allusive, and Hogarthian”).</p>
                <p>1 Joseph Viscomi, “<hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle:</hi>
Lost or Found?” Pp. 44-61.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1994 (1995), 46 (“highly
detailed,” “enlightened” and “instructive”).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume XXVIII, Number 2 (Fall 1994)</p>
                <p>6 David Simpson, “Which Newton for the British Library?” Pp. 77-78.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1994 (1995), 45 (a
summary).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume XXVIII (1994-95)</p>
                <p>1 Aileen Ward, “Who Was Robert Blake?” Pp. 84-89.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1994 (1995), 46 (“A very
thorough reconsideration of the confused and confusing evidence”).</p>
                <pb id="p30-137" n="137"/>
                <p>
                  <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Volume XXIX, Number 3 (Winter 1995/96 [4 April 1996]) 1 Martin Butlin. “A Rare Group of
Early Twentieth-Century Watercolors by a Follower of William Blake.” Pp. 76-77. (Henry John Stock
[1853-1930] was “befriended by W.J. Linton,” moved to Felpham, and painted from Revelation “Blakean
subjects in totally un-Blakean style.”)</p>
                <p>2 Max Browne. “A Blake Source for von Holst.” Pp. 78-81. (Theodor von Holst [1810-44]
copied figures from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [B?] pl. 1, 19, 21, 23.)</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>3 Yoko Ima-Izumi. Review of G. E. Bentley, Jr. [with Keiko Aoyama], <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies in Japan</hi> (1994&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake 1995</hi>&gt;), under Catalogues&gt;. Pp. 82-88. (Mostly a
useful “necessary historical explanation” concerning the Japanese Blake scholars discussed in the
“valuable introduction” to <hi rend="i">Blake Studies in Japan</hi> [82].)</p>
                <p>4 Michael Ferber. Review of <hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. Morris
Eaves, Robert N. Essick, &amp; Joseph Viscomi (1993). Pp. 88-90. (“An altogether splendid volume,” with
“the most lucid and succinct summary of Blake’s methods of book production that I have seen” [88].)</p>
                <p>5 Dennis M. Read. Review of <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem and the Final Illuminated
Books</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick &amp; Joseph Viscomi (1993). Pp. 91-92. (“There is much to praise, little
to question, and less to criticize in this splendid volume” [92].)</p>
                <p>6 Harriet Linkin. Review of Molly Anne Rothenberg, <hi rend="i">Rethinking Blake’s
Textuality</hi> (1993). Pp. 92-94. (A “few important close readings beautifully ground Rothenberg’s astute
but sometimes theory-thick discussion of philosophical and religious contemporary contexts to compensate for
whatever imperfections the book contains” [94].)</p>
                <p>7 Andrew Lincoln. Review of George Anthony Rosso, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic
Workshop</hi> (1993). Pp. 95-96. (“Some of the assumptions and methods involved seem questionable”
[95].)</p>
                <p>8 Janet Warner. Review of Steven Vine, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry:</hi> Spectral Visions
(1993). P. 96. (“Often the critic is undermined by the energy and mystery of his poet,” but “the
approach that seemed confusing in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> works brilliantly in Vine’s concise
discussions of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”)</p>
                <p>9 Andrew Lincoln. Review of the production of <hi rend="i">Blake’s Innocence and
Experience</hi> by Elliot Hayes [1983 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 503&gt;], with Michael Loughnan as William
Blake. Directed by Valerie Doulton; designed by Gary Thorne; music for songs by Loreena McKennitt. At the
<corr type="emend">Tristan</corr> Bates Theatre, Tower Street, London, 12-18 June 1995. P. 97. (“The limits of the play, and Valerie
Doulton’s expert handling of them, make for a portrait that is definite, determinate, and impossible to
forget.”)</p>
                <p>10 Stephen Cox. Review of Jeanne Moskal, <hi rend="i">Blake, Ethics, and Forgiveness</hi>
(1994). Pp. 97-102. (“A typical academic book” whose “problems are not all stylistic and
organizational,” for “Some of <corr type="emend">Moskal’s</corr> intellectual positions have not been thought through carefully
enough” [97, 102].)</p>
                <p>11 Keri Davies. Review of “‘The Genitals are Beauty.’ Exhibition of ‘An Interior of
William Blake.’ House of William Blake, London. July-August, 1994.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> Pp. 102-03. (The genitalia exhibition “tied together a
roomful of genitals with some of the kitschy inheritance of St. Valentine’s Day.”) 
<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> The title here is confused. The exhibition of “An Interior for [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]
William Blake” &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt; was on 1-14 August 1994; that of “The Genitals are
Beauty” &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt; (reviewed here) was on 6-17 February 1995, as the review
makes clear.</note></p>
                <p>
                  <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Volume XXIX, No. 4 (Spring [July] 1996)</p>
                <p>1 *Robert N. Essick. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1995, Including a Survey of Blakes in
Private Ownership.” Pp. 108-30. (A masterfully detailed catalogue, including as an “Appendix: New
Information on Blake’s Engravings” [130].)</p>
                <p>2 *G. E. Bentley, Jr., With the Assistance of Keiko Aoyama for Japanese Publications.
“William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 1995.” Pp. 131-68.</p>
                <p>Newsletter<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Omitting items irrelevant to William Blake.</note></p>
                <p>3 Anon. “William Blake Collection Moves Home.” P. 168. (The Preston Blake Collection
has been moved from a branch of the Westminster Public Library [at 35 St Martin’s Street] to the City of
Westminster Archives Centre [at 20 St Anne Street].)</p>
                <p>4 Anon. “Blakean Art News: Milton.” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> [i.e., “The Bard’s
Song”] will be performed twice, apparently by Golgonooza Productions, in Boulder, Colorado, in November
1996, with “a virtual universe based on Blake’s artwork.”)</p>
                <p>
                  <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Volume XXX, Number 1 (Summer [September] 1996)</p>
                <p>1 Joseph Viscomi. “A ‘Green House’ for Butts? New Information on Thomas Butts, His
Residences, and Family.” Pp. 4-21. (An enormous mass of valuable detail about the family and residences of
Thomas Butts’s family suggests that his son Thomas Butts [Jr.] may not have been the anonymous vendor of the
Blakes in the Sotheby sales of 26-27 March and 26 June 1852 [20].)</p>
                <p>2 Denise Vultee. “Apollonian Elephant?” P. 22. (The “Apollonian elephant,” as E.G.
Marsh in 1802 identifies Blake’s engraving for Hayley’s Elephant Ballad, derives not from the
elephant-free <hi rend="i">Argonautica</hi> of Apollonius of Rhodes referred to in the same letter but from
Philostratus’ <hi rend="i">The Life of Apollonius of Tyana</hi>, a neo-Pythagorean philosopher of the first
century A.D.)</p>
                <p>3 David Caplan. “Blake in Boca Raton.” P. 22. (A poem.)</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>4 Michael Gamer, Paul Wayne Rodney, &amp; Nanora Sweet. Review of David Simpson, 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism, Nationalism, and the Revolt against Theory</hi> (1993). Pp. 23-25. (It is “an
embodiment
<pb id="p30-138" n="138"/>
of the romantic ‘methods’ of Germaine de Staël and Samuel Taylor Coleridge” [23].)</p>
                <p>5 G. E. Bentley, Jr. Review of Donald Fitch, <hi rend="i">Blake Set to Music</hi> (1990).
Pp. 25-31. (“Fitch’s search for music set to Blake texts seems to have been wonderfully comprehensive”
[27]; the Appendix here [28-31] lists addenda and corrigenda.)</p>
                <p>§Bowra, Cecil Maurice. “On Blake’s ‘The Tiger [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>].’” Vol.
II, p. 84, of <hi rend="i">Readings for Liberal Education.</hi> Ed. Louis Glenn Locke, William Merriam Gibson,
&amp; George Warren Arms. (Rinehart, 1948) B. Revised edition. (1952).</p>
                <p>§Bradford, Richard. “Blake and the Arbitrary Use of Language.” In his <hi rend="i">A
Literary History of English Poetry.</hi> (London &amp; N.Y.: Routledge, 1993).</p>
                <p>Brammer, Marsanne Carolee. “Poetics of the Incommensurable: Classical Scientific
Epistemology and Mystical Discourse in Nineteenth and Twentieth Century British Literature.” 
<hi rend="i">DAI</hi>, LVI (1995), 353A. California (San Diego) Ph.D.</p>
                <p>The thesis “focuses on the ways in which the illuminated writings of William Blake and
James Joyce’s Ulysses develop a poetics of the incommensurable”; Blake is in chapter 3-4.</p>
                <p>Brown, Marshall. “Stealing a Self: Schiller and Blake.” Pp. 104-12 of chapter 5
(81-112), “The Economy of Sensibility,” in his <hi rend="i">Preromanticism.</hi> (Stanford: Stanford
University Press, 1991).</p>
                <p>Bull, Malcolm. “Blake and Watts in <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">N&amp;Q</hi>, CCXLI [N.S., XLIII] (1996), 27-29.</p>
                <p>In “I saw a chapel all of gold” and “The Garden of Love,” Blake is alleged to be
“clearly rewriting Watts,” “The Church the Garden of Christ.”</p>
                <p>Bungey, Margurite. “Well-loved family hymns: No. 6: Jerusalem by William Blake
(1757-1827).” <hi rend="i">This England</hi>, XVIII, No. 1 (Spring 1985), 26-29.</p>
                <p>With photographs of Blake’s cottage and the Fox Inn at Felpham.</p>
                <p>Butt, William. “Robert Gourlay’s <hi rend="i">Millennial Vision: A Reader’s
Guide.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Journal of Canadian Studies: Revue d’études canadiennes</hi>, XXIV (1989),
66-80.</p>
                <p>It is about the vague “correspondence between Gourlay’s writing and that Blake” (68),
though Gourlay (d. 1863), a Canadian reformer, never mentions Blake.</p>
                <p>§Castoren, Gunnar. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Svenska Dagbladet</hi>, 11, 14
January 1909. In Swedish.</p>
                <p>*Chauvin, Danièle. <hi rend="i">L’Œuvre de William Blake</hi> (1992) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Robert Davreu, <hi rend="i">Romantisme</hi>, No. 83 (1994), 115-16 (“lumineuse et
convaicante”).</p>
                <p>Chayes, Irene H. “Picture and Page, Reader and Viewer in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> Illustrations.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, XXX (1991), 439-71 &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 436&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 D. V. E[rdman], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 64-65 (“A valuable
program from which all Blakeists can benefit”).</p>
                <p>Clark, Steve, &amp; David Worrall, ed. <hi rend="i">Historicizing Blake</hi> (1994) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995&gt;.</p>
                <p>7 Andrew Lincoln. “Blake and the ‘Reasoning Historian.’” Pp. 73-85.</p>
                <p>Material from it is incorporated in revised form in his <hi rend="i">Spiritual
History:</hi> A Reading of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
(1995).</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 §Jason Whittaker, <hi rend="i">BARS Bulletin and Review</hi>, No. 9 (November 1995),
19.</p>
                <p>Clarke, Lorraine, <hi rend="i">Blake, Kierkegaard, and the Spectre of Dialectic</hi> (1991)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 438&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 §Michael Fischer, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, XXIV (1993), 230-32.</p>
                <p>2 François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Etudes Anglaises</hi>, XLVII (1994), 478-79 (a work of
“érudition précise”).</p>
                <p>Commander, John. “Dereliction.” <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi>, 21 March
1996, p. 5.</p>
                <p>He deplores the absence of “critical comment on, or response to” the scholarship in the
Blake Trust volumes which Iain Sinclair was purporting to review.</p>
                <p>§Courthope, William John. “Democracy and Lyric Poetry, Scottish and English.” Vol. VI,
52-83 of his <hi rend="i">A History of English Poetry.</hi> (London &amp; N.Y.: Macmillan, 1895-1910). B.</p>
                <p>§(London: Macmillan &amp; Co., 1922-1925) C. §(N.Y.: Russell &amp; Russell, 1962).</p>
                <p>Said to concern Blake.</p>
                <p>Cox, Stephen, <hi rend="i">Love and Logic:</hi> The Evolution of Blake’s Thought (1992)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 444&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>2 Kathleen Lundeen. <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi>, V (1994), 127-31
(“challenging, controversial” [131]).</p>
                <p>Cranston, Maurice. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement.</hi> (Oxford &amp; Cambridge
[U.S.A.]: Blackwells, 1994). Pp. 52-56.</p>
                <p>Crisman, William. “Songs named ‘Song’ and the Bond of the Self-Conscious Lyricism in
William Blake.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, LXI (1994), 619-33 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <pb id="p30-139" n="139"/>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1994 (1995), 43 (a summary).
Curran, Stuart, &amp; Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., ed., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi> (1973)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #A1437 5&gt;.</p>
                <p>Jean H. Hagstrum. “Babylon Revisited, or the Story of Luvah and Vala.” B. “Slightly
abbreviated” in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. David Punter (1996), 36-53.</p>
                <p>Davie, Donald. “Conclusion.” Pp. 155-58 of his <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth-Century Hymn
in England.</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993).</p>
                <p>Blake’s “point of view [<hi rend="i">was</hi>] unChristian” and his “Jerusalem”
from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is not a hymn, partly because it “has no <hi rend="i">argument</hi> at
all.”</p>
                <p>Davies, J. M. Q. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Milton Designs</hi> (1993) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 65-66 (a
carping summary).</p>
                <p>2 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
325 (“learned readings of Blake’s Milton designs”).</p>
                <p>Davreu, Robert. “Londres, Blake et Wordsworth: genèse poétique d’une vision moderne
de la ville.” <hi rend="i">Romantisme</hi>, No. 83 (1994), 38-48.</p>
                <p>See especially “W. Blake: Londres, ville maudite, promesse de cité sainte”
(40-42).</p>
                <p>Day, Aidan. <hi rend="i">Romanticism.</hi> (London &amp; N.Y.: Routledge, 1996) The New
Critical Idiom.</p>
                <p>Blake is particularly on pp. 17-26 in a section called “Enlightenment or Romantic.”</p>
                <p>De Luca, V. A., <hi rend="i">Words of Eternity</hi> (1991) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
450&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>9 Jonathan Lamb, <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>, LVI (1993), 191-207.</p>
                <p>Den Otter, A. G. “True, Right, and Good: Blake’s Argument for Vision in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.” Philological Quarterly</hi>, LXXII (1993), 73-96 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
327 (“interesting”).</p>
                <p>Dörrbecker, D. W. “Blake, <hi rend="i">William.</hi>” Vol. XI, 359-66 of 
<hi rend="i">Allgemeines Künstler-Lexikon:</hi> Die Bildenden Künstler aller Zeiten und Völker.
(München-Leipzig: K.G. Saur, 1995).</p>
                <p>A densely-packed essay, with extensive bibliographical references; there are also entries
by the same author on Catherine Blake (the poet’s wife [353]) and Robert Blake (his brother [358]).</p>
                <p>It is a kind of replacement for A. G. B. Russell, “Blake, William,” Vol.IV, pp. 84-88
of <hi rend="i">Allgemeines Lexicon der Bildender Künstler</hi>, ed. Ulrich Thieme &amp; Felix Becker (1910)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>&gt;.</p>
                <p>Eaves, Morris, <hi rend="i">The Counter-Arts Conspiracy</hi> (1992) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1993)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 §Tim Cloudsley, <hi rend="i">History of European Ideas</hi>, XVIII (1994), 1042-44.</p>
                <p>2 §Mark Hallett, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, XVIII (1995), 608-09.</p>
                <p>3 Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi>, XXV (1995), 299-300 (it
shows “considerable erudition” and “great imaginative power”).</p>
                <p>4 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
326 (“an original and very significant contribution”).</p>
                <p>Eaves, Morris, &amp; Michael Fischer, ed., <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary
Criticism</hi> (1986) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 576&gt;.</p>
                <p>W. J. T. Mitchell. “Visible Language: Blake’s Wond’rous Art of Writing.” B.
Reprinted without the section on calligraphy, “Human Letters,” in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed.
David Punter (1996), pp. 123-48.</p>
                <p>Eliot, T. S. “Mad Naked Blake.” (1920) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> # &gt;.</p>
                <p>Translated into Chinese by Yi Yang with her <hi rend="i">Tianzhen yu jing yan zhige</hi>
[<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>] (1988).</p>
                <p>*Endo, Toru. “Blake ni okeru Ryutai Imegi—18-seiki Kagaku Shiso to Blake: Images of
Liquid in Blake’s Poetry [—Science in the 18th Century and Blake].” <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha
Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu Romanha Gakkai: <hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of
English Romanticism, No. 19-20 (1996), 49-58. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>*Engetsu, Katsuhiro. “Meikyu no Blake—<hi rend="i">Mil/ton</hi> Zen [1]2 kan o yomu:
Blake in the Labyrinth—Reading <hi rend="i">Mil/ton</hi> in [1]2 Books.” <hi rend="i">Doshisha Daigaku
Eigo Eibungaku Kenkyu: Doshisha Studies in English, the Literary Association, Doshisha University</hi>, No. 65
(1995), 19-50. In Japanese, with an English abstract on 51-52.</p>
                <p>Erdman, David V., ed., <hi rend="i">Blake and His Bibles</hi> (1990) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 462-63&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 §David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, N.S. LIV (January 1993),
115-19 (with Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> [see
1991]).</p>
                <p>2 Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi>, XXIII (1993), 351-52
(praise).</p>
                <p>Erdman, David V., &amp; John E. Grant, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic</hi>, (1970) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1580 A&gt;.</p>
                <p>George Quasha. “Orc as a Fiery Paradigm of Poetic Torsion.” B. “Reproduced in a
slightly abbreviated form” in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. David Punter (1996), 16-35.</p>
                <pb id="p30-140" n="140"/>
                <p>§Ernst, C. “The Vocation of Nature.” Pp. 59-73 of <hi rend="i">The Limits of Human
Nature:</hi> Essays Based on a Course of Lectures Given at the Institute of Contemporary Arts, London. Ed.
Jonathan Benthall. (London: Dutton, 1974).</p>
                <p>Said to concern Blake.</p>
                <p>Esterhammer, Angela. “The Constitution of Blake’s Innocence and Experience.” 
<hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi>, X (1993), 151-60.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
328 (it shows “elegant clarity”).</p>
                <p>Fausset, Hugh I’anson. “William Blake.” Chapter 6 (152-64) of his 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Idealism.</hi> (London &amp; N.Y., 1923) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>&gt; B. §(Port
Washington [N.Y.], Kennikat, 1965).</p>
                <p>§Freeman, Kathryn S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Nostos:</hi> Fragmentation and Non-Dualism in
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> (State University of New York, 1977) SUNY Series in Western Esoteric
Traditions. 192 pp. ISBN: 0-7914-3298-X.</p>
                <p>Freeman, Kathryn S. “Narrative Fragmentation and Undifferentiated Consciousness in
Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi>, V (1995),
178-92.</p>
                <p>Furtwangler, Albert. “Jefferson’s Trinity.” Pp. 115-37 of his <hi rend="i">American
Silhouettes:</hi> Rhetorical Identities of the Founders. (New Haven &amp; London: Yale University Press,
1987).</p>
                <p>Bacon, Newton, &amp; Locke were reverenced by Jefferson and deplored by Blake (128-34).</p>
                <p>Glausser, Wayne. “Atomistic Simulacra in the Enlightenment and in Blake’s
Post-Enlightenment.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century:</hi> Theory and Interpretation, XXXII (1991), 73-88
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Spectres and emanations can both trace their lineage back through 
[<hi rend="i">Epicurean</hi>] atomism” (75).</p>
                <p>Glendening, John. “Ezra Pound and Ezra Pound’s Blake: Method in Madness, Madness in
Method.” <hi rend="i">Paideuma</hi>, XX (1991), 95-106.</p>
                <p>In Canto 16, “the apparent madness of the Blake passage reflects, parodies, and hence
resists the madness Pound saw not only in Blake’s method, but also, quite possibly, in himself” (107).</p>
                <p>Goyder, George, <hi rend="i">Signs of Grace</hi> (1993) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Tim Heath, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society</hi> (1996), 75-77 (it is a “clear
and orderly” autobiography).</p>
                <p>Groves, David. “‘W—M B—E, A Great Original’: William Blake, The Grave, and James
Hogg’s <hi rend="i">Confessions.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Scottish Literary Journal</hi>, XVIII, No. 2 (November
1991), 27-45 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 496&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 R. F. G[leckner], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 67 (the claim that
the W—M B—E is William Blake evokes a succinct “Oh my!”).</p>
                <p>*Grundy, Thomas E. “An Eye of gifts &amp; graces: A Reading of Blake’s <hi rend="i">The
Book of Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Nagoya Daigaku Bungakubu Kenkyu Ronshu</hi>, Bungaku 41: <hi rend="i">The
Journal of the Faculty of Letters, Nagoya University</hi>, Literature 42, No. 124 (1996), 49-78.</p>
                <p>Gurney, Stephen. “William Blake.” Chapter 2 (26-41, 318) of his <hi rend="i">British
Poets of the Nineteenth Century.</hi> (N.Y.: Twayne Publishers; Toronto: Maxwell Macmillan Canada; N.Y.,
Oxford, Singapore, Sydney: Maxwell Macmillan International, 1993).</p>
                <p>A general account.</p>
                <p>Haigwood, Laura. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion:</hi>
Revising an Interpretive Tradition.” <hi rend="i">San Jose Studies</hi>, XI, No. 2 [1985] &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 498&gt;. B. Reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. David Punter (1996),
94-107.</p>
                <p>§Hampton, Christopher. “Blake’s Dialectic: The Prolongation of Mental War.” In his
<hi rend="i">Socialism in a Crippled World.</hi> (London: Penguin, 1981).</p>
                <p>§Hampton, Christopher. <hi rend="i">The Ideology of the Text.</hi> (The Open University,
1990).</p>
                <p>It contains a chapter on Blake.</p>
                <p>*Harbison, Robert. “The Cult of Death.” Chapter 2 (25-62) of his 
<hi rend="i">Deliberate Regression.</hi> (London: André Deutsch Ltd, 1980) B. §(N.Y. Knopf, 1980).</p>
                <p>Blake is dealt with particularly on pp. 40-45.</p>
                <p>*Harman, Clare. “Revealed: Blake’s vision of a British statue of liberty: A millenium
monument? It won’t match a towering idea they had 200 years ago.” <hi rend="i">Independent on Sunday</hi>,
20 October 1996, p. 7.</p>
                <p>On Flaxman’s design for a Naval Monument (1800), scarcely related to either a revelation
or Blake.</p>
                <p>Harris, R. W. “The New Jerusalem of William Blake.” Chapter 8 (149-69) of his 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and the Social Order 1780-1830.</hi> (London: Blandford Press, 1969) Blandford History
and Literature Series.</p>
                <p>A very general introduction to the poetry; “he was less interested in politics as such
than in the moral problems and conflicts within his own breast” (149).</p>
                <p>Hayes, Elliot, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Innocence and Experience</hi> (1983), play
performance &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 503&gt;.</p>
                <pb id="p30-141" n="141"/>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXIX, 3 (Winter 1995-96), 97 (“the limits of
the play, and Valerie Doulton’s expert handling of them, make for a portrait that is definite, determinate,
and impossible to forget”).</p>
                <p>§*Henderson, Jeff. “Right License: Blake’s Reading/Painting of the Canterbury
Pilgrims.” <hi rend="i">Publications of the Arkansas Philological Association</hi>, XVIII, 2 (1992),
1-14.</p>
                <p>Hilton, Nelson. <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination</hi> [1983] &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
507).</p>
                <p>“Blake in the Chains of Being” is reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed.
David Punter (1996), 71-93.</p>
                <p>Hilton, Nelson, &amp; Thomas Vogler, ed. <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms</hi> (1986) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 508&gt;.</p>
                <p>Gavin Edwards. “Repeating the Same Dull Round.” B. The “first half” is reprinted in
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. David Punter (1996), 108-22.</p>
                <p>David Simpson. “Reading Blake and Derrida—Our Caesars neither Praised nor Buried.” B.
Reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. David Punter (1996), 149-64.</p>
                <p>Hobson, Christopher Z. “‘The Chained Boys’: Orc and Blake’s Idea of Revolution.”
<hi rend="i">DAI</hi>, LVI (1995), 1367A. City University of New York Ph.D. (1995).</p>
                <p>Hoerner, Fred. “Prolific Reflections: Blake’s Contortion of Surveillance in 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, XXXV (1996),
119-50.</p>
                <p>About Oothoon and Locke.</p>
                <p>§Holten, Ragnar von. “Profet och bildmakare.” <hi rend="i">Svenska Dagbladet</hi>, 22
April 1978. In Swedish.</p>
                <p>James, David E. “Angels out of the Sun: Art, Religion and Politics in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, XVIII (1979) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
524&gt; B. Reprinted in “abbreviated” form in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. David Punter (1996),
54-70.</p>
                <p>James, G. Ingli. “William Blake and Feminist Theology: Some Observations on the
Affinities.” <hi rend="i">Feminist Theology</hi>, No. 11 (January 1996), 72-85.</p>
                <p>Chiefly concerned with “how much there is in Blake which particularly resonates with
feminist theology, both . . . Christian and post-Christian,” “even if he was an mcp” (73, 85).</p>
                <p>James, Joan E., &amp; G. Ingli James. “Blake’s ‘The Clod and the Pebble’: Some
Christian-Feminist Observations.” <hi rend="i">Feminist Theology</hi>, No. 6 (May 1994), 48-52.</p>
                <p>Perhaps “love, properly understood, is neither exclusively passive nor exclusively
active” (52).</p>
                <p>§Jossua, Jean-Pierre. <hi rend="i">Pour une histoire religieuse de l’expérience
littéraire.</hi> Vol. II: <hi rend="i">La Poésie moderne.</hi> (Paris: Beauchesne, 1990).</p>
                <p>Said to be about Blake.</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society at St James</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>10 Jim Dewhurst, “Is The Tyger All About IT?” Pp. 3-6. See <hi rend="i">Journal of the
Blake Society</hi> (1996) for a letter of agreement by Thomas F. Dillingham and an account by Dewhurst of the
origin of his essay.</p>
                <p>*<hi rend="i">The Journal of the Blake Society at St. James</hi> (1996).</p>
                <p>1 The Editors [Jim Dewhurst &amp; ?Pauline Wilson<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n26" type="note">26</ref>]. “Editorial.” P. 2. (An invitation for “contributions on any work
that is conceived within a Blakean spirit, however that may be defined.”) 
<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Jim Dewhurst is said to be “Co-designer of this journal interior with Pauline Wilson”
(80).</note></p>
                <p>2 Peter Ackroyd. “The Writing of Blake.” Pp. 3-4. (A general account of the writing of
his biography called <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi>)</p>
                <p>3 *G. E. Bentley Jr. “‘I Hear a Voice You Cannot Hear’: William Blake’s
Audiences.” Pp. 5-18. (“The world was not much interested in William Blake . . . the audience he most
valued was in heaven and in his own mind” [18].)</p>
                <p>4 *Michael Grenfell. “Blake And Gnosis.” Pp. 19-29. (“Working notes” on Gnosticism
with the premise that “A Gnostic view is ‘the’ key to understanding Blake’s dense mythologies” [20,
19].)</p>
                <p>5 *James Bogan. “Blake on a Bike: Following the Footsteps of Los’ Epic Ramble in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Pp. 30-47. (An amusing “centrifugal lark” [45].)</p>
                <p>6 Jason Whittaker. “Blake and the Native Tradition.” Pp. 48-56. (An attempt “to
sketch briefly the significance of the giant Albion and two groups of his sons, the bards and druids, for
Blake’s religious vision” [48].)</p>
                <p>7 Chris Rubinstein. “Xword.” Pp. 57-60. (With Blake-context clues such as “Scoundrel
who knew. Mary Wollstonecraft,” five letters presumably for Imlay, the lover of Mary Wollstonecraft.)</p>
                <p>8 Chris Rubinstein. “” An Imaginative Exercise: Blake Writes London.” P. 60. (A
poem.)</p>
                <p>Correspondence</p>
                <p>9 Thomas F. Dillingham. “Blake and The Tyger.” Pp. 60-61. (Agrees with Jim Dewhurst,
“Is The Tyger All About IT?,” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society</hi> [1995], 33-36, “that the
tiger is, at least in part, an embodiment of the sexual energy of the phallus”; with a “Note from Jim
Dewhurst” [61] about the origin of his essay.)</p>
                <p>10 Michael Edwards. “William Blake on Tape.” P. 61. (Would anyone like to finance and
promote his tape of a reading by a Dartington College student from the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> “with my music score”?)</p>
                <p>Information</p>
                <p>11 Chris Rubinstein. “Memorabilia (2).” P. 62. (The Finch Foundry, which “dates from
around 1800,” is at Sticklepath.)</p>
                <pb id="p30-142" n="142"/>
                <p>12 Kevin Kewell. “Blake on the Internet.” Pp. 62-63. (“blake@albion.com . . . is an
‘electronic concert dedicated to the life and work of William Blake’,” and
“http:library.utoronto.ca/www/utel rp/authors blake.html” has “much to say on Blake and English
poetry.”)</p>
                <p>13 Anon. “The Hammer of Los—‘I remember! I remember!’” P. 63. (There were four
performances in October 1996, and “Any financial contributions welcomed!”)</p>
                <p>14 Anon. “The Blake Society and Blake Journal.” P. 64. (General accounts.)</p>
                <p>15 Anon. “Depression is a Gift.” P. 64. (Solicitation for contributions to the next
exhibition at the House of William Blake.)</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>16 Sarah Joyce. Review of David Annwn, <hi rend="i">Hear the Voice of the Bard</hi>!
(1995). Pp. 65-67. (The book is a “perceptive reading” of the “Introduction” to 
<hi rend="i">Experience.</hi>)</p>
                <p>17 Sunao Vagabond [stage name of Andrew Vernède]. Review of Andrew Solomon, 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> (1995). Pp. 67-69. (A “marvellous book,” “astoundingly
well-informed.”)</p>
                <p>18 Peter Cadogan. Review of Jon Mee, <hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm</hi> (1992). P. 70.
(“<hi rend="i">A</hi> notice rather than a review” of “a brilliant book,” “most interesting.”)</p>
                <p>19 Peter Cadogan. Review of George Goyder, <hi rend="i">The Just Enterprise.</hi> Pp.
70-72. (The book, by the President of the Blake Society, is about what happens “if we treat human beings as
human beings” in industry.)</p>
                <p>20 Andrew Vernède. Review of Elliott Hayes, <hi rend="i">Blake—Innocence and
Experience:</hi> A Play. Pp. 72-75. (A review of a performance at Tristan Bates Theatre, n.d.)</p>
                <p>21 Tim Heath. Review of George Goyder, <hi rend="i">Signs of Grace</hi> (1993). Pp. 75-77.
(It is a “clear and orderly” autobiography.)</p>
                <p>22 Tim Heath. Review of Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995). Pp. 77-79. (Ackroyd
“builds up a life, slowly, with care and with detail.”)</p>
                <p>Kaplan, Marc A. “Weeping woman/weaving woman: gender roles in Blake’s mythology.” 
<hi rend="i">DAI</hi>, LVI (1995), 369A. California (Los Angeles) Ph.D. (1993).</p>
                <p>“Sexism is not incidental to Blake’s system, but fundamental.”</p>
                <p>Kawasaki, Noriko. “Blake ni okeru Ifuku no Imi [The Symbolic Meanings of Clothing in
William Blake].” <hi rend="i">Echudo</hi>, Ochanomizu Joshi Daigaku Daigakuin Eibungakkai: 
<hi rend="i">Etude</hi> [Society of English Literature, Graduate School of Ochanomizu Women’s University], No.
19 [1989], 40-52 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 532&gt;. B. Reprinted as chapter 3 (67-89) of her <hi rend="i">Eden
wa Ki taka:</hi> William Blake Ronshu: <hi rend="i">On the Location of Eden:</hi> Studies on William Blake.
(Tokyo: Kindai Bungeisha, 1996) In Japanese.</p>
                <p>§Kawasaki, Noriko. “Eden wa Kita ka: Damon no <hi rend="i">Blake Dikushonari</hi> Saiko:
On the Location of Eden: Reconsidering S.F. Damon’s <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Ningen Bunka Kenkyu Nenpo, Ochanomizu Joshi Daigaku: Bulletin of the Doctoral Research Course in
Human Culture</hi> [Ochanomizu Women’s University], No. 17 [1994]. B. Reprinted in chapter 2 (5-38) of her
<hi rend="i">Eden wa Kitaka:</hi> William Blake Ronshu: <hi rend="i">On the Location of Eden:</hi> Studies on
William Blake. (Tokyo: Kindai Bungeisha, 1996) In Japanese.</p>
                <p>*Kawasaki, Noriko. <hi rend="i">Eden wa Kita ka:</hi> William Blake Ronshu: <hi rend="i">On
the Location of Eden:</hi> Studies on William Blake. (Tokyo: Kindai Bungeisha, 1996) 149 pp. ISBN:
4-7733-5907-2 C0095. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>The book consists of reprinted essays:</p>
                <p>1 “Eden wa Kita ka: Damon no <hi rend="i">Blake Dikushonari</hi> Saiko: On the Location
of Eden: Reconsidering S.F. Damon’s <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary.</hi>” Pp. 5-38. (Reprinted from 
<hi rend="i">Ningen Bunka Kenkyu Nenpo, Ochanomizu Joshi Daigaku: Bulletin of the Doctoral Research Course in
Human Culture</hi> [Ochanomizu Women’s University], No. 17 [1994].)</p>
                <p>2 “Maigo no Imeji ni tsuite: William Blake to Makuranososhi ‘Mino Mushi’ no Dan no
Hikaku Kenkyu: On the Imagery of the Lost Child: Starting from a Comparative Study of William Blake’s Poetry
and the ‘Minomushi’ Passage of <hi rend="i">Makura-no-Soshi.</hi>” Pp. 39-66. (Reprinted from 
<hi rend="i">Ningen Bunka Kenkyu Nenpo, Ochanomizu Joshi Daigaku: Bulletin of the Doctoral Research Course in
Human Culture</hi> [Ochanomizu Women’s University], No. 12 [1988], 75-89.)</p>
                <p>3 “Blake ni okeru Ifuku no Imi: The Symbolic Meanings of Clothing in William Blake.”
Pp. 67-89. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">Echudo</hi>, Ochanomizu Joshi Daigaku Daigakuin Eibungakkai: 
<hi rend="i">Etude</hi> [Society of English Literature, Graduate School of Ochanomizu Women’s University], No.
19 [1989], 40-52.)</p>
                <p>4 “Kozetsu no Iso—Blake no ‘Maigo no Otokonoko’: Phases of Alienation: William
Blake’s ‘The Little Boy Lost.’” Pp. 91-105. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">Romanha Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu
Romanha Gakkai: <hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English Romanticism, No.
14 [1990], 8-15.)</p>
                <p>5 “William Blake ni okeru ‘Mushi’ to ‘Katachi’: Form and Worm in William
Blake.” Pp. 107-45. (Translated by the author into Japanese from pp. 96-113 of her essay in 
<hi rend="i">Centre and Circumference:</hi> Essays in English Romanticism [by members of the] Association of
English Romanticism in Japan. Ed. Kenkichi Kamijima. [Tokyo: Kirihara Shoten, 1995].)</p>
                <p>*Kawasaki, Noriko. “Maigo no Imeji ni tsuite: William Blake to Makura-nososhi ‘Mino
Mushi’ no Dan no Hikaku Kenkyu: On the Imagery of the Lost Child: Starting from a Comparative Study of
William Blake’s Poetry and the ‘Minomushi’ [Bagworm] Passage of <hi rend="i">Makura-no-Soshi.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Ningen Bunka Kenkyu Nenpo, Ochanomizu Joshi Daigaku: Bulletin of the Doctoral Research Course in
Human Culture</hi> [Ochanomizu Women’s University], No. 12 [1988], 75-89 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 532&gt;.
B. Reprinted in chapter 1 (39-66) of her <hi rend="i">Eden</hi>
	<pb id="p30-143" n="143"/>
	<hi rend="i">wa Kita ka:</hi> William Blake Ronshu: <hi rend="i">On the Location of Eden:</hi> Studies on
William Blake. (Tokyo: Kindai Bungeisha, 1996) In Japanese.</p>
                <p>Minomushi passage is one of 300 passages in Sei Shonagon, <hi rend="i">Makura-no-Soshi</hi>
[<hi rend="i">Pillow Talk</hi>] (early 11th Century).</p>
                <p>Kawasaki, Noriko. “Satan no Chokoku—Blake no <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> ni tsuite
([1]-7)] [Transcending Satan-Self in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Gifu Shiritsu Joshi
Tankidaigaku Kenkyu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Gifu City Women’s Junior College</hi>], No. 39
(1989), 39-46 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 532&gt;; No. 40 (1990), 49-55; No. 41 (1991), 149-55; No. 42 (1992),
27-32; No. 43; No. 44 (1994), 15-20; No. 45 (1995), 9-16. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>No. 3 is sub-titled “‘pity’ to ‘shizumu Hi’ [‘pity’ and ‘the setting
Sun’]”; from No. 44 (1994), both journal and essay titles appear also in translation.</p>
                <p>Kawasaki, Noriko. “William Blake ni okeru ‘Mushi’ to ‘Katachi’: Form and Worm in
William Blake.” Pp. 96-113 of <hi rend="i">Centre and Circumference:</hi> Essays in English Romanticism [by
members of the] Association of English Romanticism in Japan. Ed. Kenkichi Kamijima. (Tokyo: Kirihara Shoten,
1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;. B. Translated by the author into Japanese as chapter 5 (107-45)
of her <hi rend="i">Eden wa Kitaka:</hi> William Blake Ronshu: <hi rend="i">On the Location of Eden:</hi>
Studies on William Blake. (Tokyo: Kindai Bungeisha, 1996).</p>
                <p>Kazin, Alfred. “An Introduction to William Blake.” Pp. 36-88 of his <hi rend="i">Inmost
Leaf:</hi> A Selection of Essays. (N.Y., 1941) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>&gt; B. Pp. 1-55 of <hi rend="i">The
Portable Blake</hi>, ed. Alfred Kazin. (N.Y., 1946) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>&gt; C. §(N.Y.: Harcourt,
1955).</p>
                <p>§Kim, Ok Yub. “Blake eui <hi rend="i">Milton:</hi> jungshinjeok tujaeng eul wihan
saeroun chutbal [Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: A New Start for Mental Conflict].” <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi> [of Seoul University], XVII (1993), 31-43. In Korean.</p>
                <p>§Kim, Young Shik. “William Blake eui yokmang geungiung [Blake’s Eulogy on Human
Desire].” <hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and Literature</hi> [of Chongjun, Korea], XXXIV (1993),
25-50. In Korean.</p>
                <p>King, James. <hi rend="i">William Blake His Life</hi> (1991) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
535-36&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>4 Hatsuko Niimi, <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature 1994</hi> ([English Literary
Society of Japan, ?1994]), 99-105.</p>
                <p>Kovel, Joel. “Some Lines from Blake.” Chapter 14 (277-87) of his <hi rend="i">The
Radical Spirit:</hi> Essays on Psychoanalysis and Society. (London: Free Association Books, 1988).</p>
                <p>The lines from <hi rend="i">The Marriage:</hi> “Man has no Body distinct from his soul .
. . Energy is Eternal Delight” “are an almost exact enunciation of what Freud held to be most essential
about the psyche” (277).</p>
                <p>Lambo, John. “The Imagination as Unifying Principle in the Works of Blake and
Wordsworth.” <hi rend="i">Diogenes</hi>, XLI, No. 4 (1993), 59-72 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1995)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Blake and Wordsworth . . . essentially share the same world view” (59).</p>
                <p>Leavis, F. R. “Justifying One’s Evaluation of Blake.” <hi rend="i">Human World</hi>,
VI (May 1972), 58. B. Pp. 66-85 of <hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi> Essays in honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes.
Ed. Morton D. Paley &amp; Michael Phillips (1973) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2350 4&gt; C. §Pp. 1-23 of 
<hi rend="i">The Critic as Anti-Philosopher:</hi> Essays &amp; Papers. Ed. G. Singh. (Athens &amp; London:
University of Georgia Press, 1982).</p>
                <p>Lincoln, Andrew. “Blake and the Natural History of Creation,” <hi rend="i">Essays and
Studies 1986</hi>, N.S. XXXIX (1986), 94-103 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>&gt;.</p>
                <p>Material from it is incorporated in revised form in his <hi rend="i">Spiritual
History:</hi> A Reading of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
(1995).</p>
                <p>Lincoln, Andrew. “Blake’s Lower Paradise: The Pastoral Passage in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, LXXXIV (1981), 470-78
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>&gt;.</p>
                <p>Material from it is incorporated in revised form in his <hi rend="i">Spiritual
History:</hi> A Reading of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
(1995).</p>
                <p>Lincoln, A.W. J. “A history of the composition of William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as revealed by a study of the surviving manuscript.”
<hi rend="i">Index to [British] Theses</hi>, XXV (1977), 7 (#5470). Wales (Bangor) Ph.D. &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>It is clearly related to his <hi rend="i">Spiritual History:</hi> A Reading of William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1995).</p>
                <p>Lincoln, Andrew. <hi rend="i">Spiritual History:</hi> A Reading of William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995) 8°, xviii + 322 pp.
ISBN: 0-19-818314-3.</p>
                <p>An elaborate, detailed, and rewarding “staged reading” for “new readers of 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” “that moves, as Blake himself moved, from simpler to more complex forms of
writing” and stresses that <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> is “a universal history” with reference to
contemporary historians such as Gibbon; Blake’s presentation of the Last Judgment suggests that “although
Man has been imprisoned in a finite vision of the natural world, the prison is locked from the inside” (v,
ix, 1, 190).</p>
                <p>The “book incorporate[<hi rend="i">s</hi>] material revised from” his (1) “Blake’s
Lower Paradise: The Pastoral Passage in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth,” 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, LXXXIV (1981), 470-78; (2) “Blake and the Natural
History of Creation,” <hi rend="i">Essays and Studies 1986</hi>, N.S. XXXIX (1986), 94-103; (3) “Blake and
the ‘Reasoning Historian’,” 73-85 of <hi rend="i">Historicizing Blake</hi>, ed. Steve Clark &amp; David
Worrall (London, 1994) (xiv), and it is clearly related to his University
<pb id="p30-144" n="144"/>
of Wales (Bangor) doctoral dissertation entitled “A history of the composition of William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as revealed by a study of the surviving manuscript”
(c. 1977).</p>
                <p>*Löchle, Dieter. <hi rend="i">William Blake—Roof’d in from Eternity:</hi> Erschienen
als Begleitheft zur Ausstellung vom 3. April bis zum 25. Mai 1995 in der Universitätsbibliothek Tübingen.
(Tübingen: Universitätsbibliothek Tübingen, 1995) 4°, 32 pp. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>The text consists of 10 excerpts from Blake in English and German plus reproductions plus
comments. It is accompanied by 10 plates with designs loosely based on Blakean figures (first exhibited at
Tübingen University Library, April-May 1995) enclosed in a portfolio entitled Dieter Löchle. 
<hi rend="i">William Blake—Roof’d in from Eternity.</hi> (Tübingen, Germany: Fockenberg 6/1994 [sic], 1995)
Folio, 10 plates, no text.</p>
                <p>Mackenzie, J. S. “Conventional Morality.” Chapter 6 (133-61) of his <hi rend="i">Arrows
of Desire:</hi> Essays on Our National Character and Outlook. (London: George Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd,
1920).</p>
                <p>About Blake’s attacks on Puritan morality (143-56).</p>
                <p>Maeda, Yoshihiko. “Blake ni yoru <hi rend="i">Yaso</hi> Suisai Sashie No. 68 no Zuzo o
megutte: Notes on the Iconography of Blake’s Design No. 68 for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Rikkyo Daigaku Kenkyu Hokoku, Jinbunkagaku: St. Paul’s Review: Arts and
Letters, College of General Education, Rikkyo University</hi>, No. 54 (1995), 41-96. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>Matsushima, Shoichi. “Blake to Kindai Nippon—Yanagi Soetsu to Oe Kenzaburo no Baai
[Blake and Modern Japan—Soetsu Yanagi and Kenzaburo Oe].” <hi rend="i">Gakushuin Daigaku Bungakubu Kenkyu
Nenpo: The Annual Collection of Essays and Studies, Faculty of Letters, Gakushuin University</hi>, XLII
(1995), 159-74. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>Mee, Jon. <hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm</hi> (1992) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
571&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>3 §Michel Baridon, <hi rend="i">Dix-Huitième Siècle</hi>, XXV (1993), 601. 4 François
Piquet, <hi rend="i">Etudes Anglaises</hi>, XLVII (1994), 339-40 (Mee is an “excellent connaisseur de la
litérature radicale du temps”).</p>
                <p>5 Peter Cadogan, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society</hi> (1996), 70 (“a notice
rather than a review” of “a brilliant book,” “most interesting”).</p>
                <p>Meller, Horst. “Lucifer Rearing from off the Pool: Revolutionary Romanticism and the
Evolution of Satan.” Pp. 9-38 of <hi rend="i">Romantic Continuities:</hi> Papers Delivered at the Symposium
of the ‘Gesellschaft für englischen Romantik’ held at the Catholic University of Eichstätt (October
1990). Ed. Günther Blaicher &amp; Michael Gassenmeier. (Essen: Blaue Eule, 1992) Studien zur englishcen
Romantik 4.</p>
                <p>About illustrations of Milton’s Satan, especially by Blake, with 35 reproductions.</p>
                <p>Merton, Thomas. “Blake and the New Theology.” <hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi>, LXXVI
(1968), 673-82 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 572&gt;. B. §Pp. 3-11 of <hi rend="i">The Literary Essays of Thomas
Merton.</hi> Ed. Brother Patrick Hart. (New Directions, 1981).</p>
                <p>Miller, Dan, Mark Bracher, &amp; Donald Ault, ed. <hi rend="i">Critical Paths</hi> (1987)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 574&gt;.</p>
                <p>David Aers. “Representations of Revolution: From <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>
to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” B. Reprinted in much shorter form in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>,
ed. David Punter (1996), 165-87.</p>
                <p>Brenda S. Webster. “Blake, Women, and Sexuality.” B. Reprinted in <hi rend="i">William
Blake</hi>, ed. David Punter (1996), 188-206.</p>
                <p>Morse, David. “The Figure of the Artist in English Romantic Poetry.” Chapter 6 (228-92)
of his <hi rend="i">Romanticism:</hi> A Structural Analysis. (London &amp; Basingstoke: Macmillan Press, 1982)
B. §(N.Y.: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1982).</p>
                <p>Blake is particularly on pp. 234-46.</p>
                <p>*Morton, A. L. <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel:</hi> A Study in the Sources of William
Blake (1958) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2251&gt;. B. <hi rend="i">Blake to [and] Ranters:</hi> Blake Shiso no
Gensen [Sources of Blake’s Thoughts]. Tr. Shoichi Matsushima into Japanese. (Tokyo: Hokuseido Shoten, 1996)
155 pp. ISBN: 590-10105-1 C3098.</p>
                <p>The Japanese version includes “Blake Nenpu [Blake Chronicle]” (123-36), “Nihon ni
okeru Blake Bunken [Blake Bibliography in Japan]” (137-48), and “Yakusha Atogaki [Translator’s
Afterword]” (149-55).</p>
                <p>Moskal, Jeanne, <hi rend="i">Blake, Ethics, and Forgiveness</hi> (1994) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 Anon., <hi rend="i">Chronicle of Higher Education</hi> (June 1994) (a onesentence
summary).</p>
                <p>2 Kay Kimbrough, <hi rend="i">Harbinger</hi> (it is “outstanding” for
“demonstrating” the “evolution” of Blake’s ethical views and for illuminating Blake as an
“original visionary prophet”).</p>
                <p>3 J. T. Lynch, <hi rend="i">Humanities:</hi> Language &amp; Literature—English &amp;
American, XXXII, No. 4 (December 1994) (“the focus is narrow without always being sharp; the readings are
sometimes belabored; and the importance of her topic is overstated”).</p>
                <p>4 David L. Clark, <hi rend="i">Christianity and Literature</hi>, XLIV, No. 3-4 
[<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] (Spring-Summer 1995), 397-400 (“even-handed” and “powerfully illuminating”).</p>
                <p>5 Thomas L. Cooksey, <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Review</hi>, LX, No. 3 (September 1995),
123-25 (a “useful contribution,” “thorough and well-informed, if at times monotonous” which shows
<pb id="p30-145" n="145"/>
that “the intrapsychic wins out over the intersubjective”). 6 Steven Cox, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXIX, 3
(Winter 1995-96), 97-102 (“a typical academic book” whose “problems are not all stylistic and
organizational,” for “Some of Moskal’s intellectual positions have not been thought through carefully
enough” [97, 102]).</p>
                <p>7 D. Bg, <hi rend="i">Academic Library Books Review</hi> (April 1996) (“It contributes to
our understanding of Blake’s struggle to represent human forgiveness in his work”).</p>
                <p>8 Jason Whittaker, <hi rend="i">BARS Bulletin &amp; Review</hi>, No. 10 (May 1996), 12-13
(almost entirely summary).</p>
                <p>9 Doug Thorpe, <hi rend="i">Religion &amp; Literature</hi>, XXVIII, No. 1 (Spring 1996),
129 (with E. P. Thompson, <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast</hi> [1993]) (a summary).</p>
                <p>10 §Margaret Storch, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, XCI, No. 2 (1996), 458-59
(with Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> [1994]).</p>
                <p>11 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Byron Journal</hi> (Summer 1996), 96 (“a brave and
important study”).</p>
                <p>Muhlestein, Daniel K. “(Re)Reading ‘The Chimney Sweeper’: Western Marxism, Christian
Faith, and a Negative Hermeneutics of Critical Demystification.” <hi rend="i">Literature and Belief:</hi>
Center for the Study of Christian Values, Brigham Young University, XIII (1993), 69-94.</p>
                <p>Three readings of “The Chimney Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, one
Marxist.</p>
                <p>Murry, John Middleton. “William Blake and Revolution.” <hi rend="i">New Adelphi</hi>,
N.S. IV (1932), 536-43 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2237&gt;. B. Tr. Bunsho Jugaku, <hi rend="i">Blake to
Whitman</hi>, II (1932), 489-91 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1219 25&gt;. C. §Pp. 55-66 of <hi rend="i">Essays
of the Year 1931-1932.</hi> (Fort Lee [New Jersey]: Argonaut, 1932).</p>
                <p>§Nemerov, Howard, “Poetry, Prophecy, Prediction.” Pp. 208-21 of his 
<hi rend="i">Reflexions on Poetry &amp; Poetics.</hi> (New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press, 1972).</p>
                <p>Said to be about Blake.</p>
                <p>Nemerov, Howard. “Two Ways of Imagination: Blake &amp; Wordsworth.” 
<hi rend="i">Carlton Miscellany</hi>, V (1964), 18-41 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2280&gt;. B. §Pp. 102-23 of his
<hi rend="i">Reflexions on Poetry &amp; Poetics.</hi> (New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press, 1972) C. §Pp.
140-60 of his <hi rend="i">New and Selected Essays.</hi> (Carbondale: Southern Illinois Press, 1985).</p>
                <p>§Niikura, Shunichi. “Blake to Seisho [Blake and the Bible].” <hi rend="i">Meiji Gakuin
Daigaku Kirisutokyo Kenkyujo Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Bulletin of the Research Association of Christianity,
Meiji Gakuin University</hi>], No. 28 (1995), 51-69. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>Niimi, Hatsuko. “Blake no ‘Yameru Bara’ no Hi-Genteisei (1): The Indefinability of
Blake’s ‘The Sick Rose’ (1).” <hi rend="i">Nihon Joshi Daigaku Eibeibungaku Kenkyu: Studies in English
and American Literature, The English Literary Society of Japan Women’s University</hi>, No. 31 (1996), 1-14.
In Japanese. Norvig, Gerda S. <hi rend="i">Dark Figures in the Desired Country</hi> (1993) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>5 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> for 1993 (1996), 324
(the book “is highly compromised by the neglect of the materiality of the pictures . . . unnerving at best
and questionable at worst”).</p>
                <p>§Odden, Danile. “Blake, Wordsworth, and the French Revolution.” <hi rend="i">Humanist
Dagarna:</hi> Att Först å Europa [<hi rend="i">Humanities Days:</hi> To Understand Europe], ([University of
Uppsala] 1994), 147-51.</p>
                <p>O’Keefe, Richard Robert. “Mythic archetypes in Ralph Waldo Emerson: A Blakean
Reading.” Pennsylvania State Ph.D. 1991 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 591&gt;.</p>
                <p>Presumably it is the basis for his book with the same title (1995).</p>
                <p>§O’Keefe, Richard. <hi rend="i">Mythic Archetypes in Ralph Waldo Emerson:</hi> A Blakean
Reading. ([Kent, Ohio:] Kent State University Press, 1995) ISBN: 0-87338-518-7.</p>
                <p>Presumably it derives from his 1991 Pennsylvania State dissertation with the same title
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 591&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 §P. J. Ferlazzo, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, XXXIII (1996), 1312-13.</p>
                <p>O’Keefe, Vincent. “Debunking the Romantic Ideology: A Re-View of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.” European Romantic Review</hi>, VII (1996), 40-48.</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is a socially engaged work of literature” (40).</p>
                <p>O’Neill, Michael. “Blake and the Self-Conscious Poem.” Pp. 145-59 of 
<hi rend="i">Trends in English and American Studies:</hi> Literature and the Imagination: Essays in Honour of
James Lester Hogg. Ed. Sabine Coelsch-Foisner, Wolfgang Görtschacher, &amp; Holger M. Klein.
(Lewiston/Queenston/Lampeter [Wales]: The Edwin Mellen Press, 1996).</p>
                <p>“I wish to claim for Blake, then, a simultaneous ability to affirm and question the
poet’s role” (149).</p>
                <p>Paananen, Victor N. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> (Boston, 1977) Twayne English Authors
Series 202 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 597&gt; B. *<hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi> Updated Edition. (N.Y.:
Twayne Publishers; London, Mexico City, New Delhi, Singapore, Sydney, Melbourne: Prentice Hall International,
1996) Pp. xxi, 185.</p>
                <p>B has an added “Preface to Updated Edition” (ix-xii).</p>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake and the Ideology of the Natural.” 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi>, N.S., XVIII (1994), 92-119.</p>
                <p>The heart of the matter is “Blake—Prophet Against Ideology” (104-14): “Embodied
humanity does not live by matter alone; spirit, not by matter at all” (114).</p>
                <pb id="p30-146" n="146"/>
                <p>*Phillips, Michael. “Blake and the Terror 1792-93.” <hi rend="i">Library</hi>, 6 S, XVI
(1994), 263-97 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 R. F. G[leckner], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1994 (1995), 44-45 (“A
splendid piece of detective work, careful discrimination, and scholarly imagination”).</p>
                <p>§*Piquet, François. <hi rend="i">Blake et le Sacré.</hi> ([Paris:] Didier Erudition,
1996) Etudes Anglaises 98. 450 pp., 23 reproductions; ISBN: 2-86460-270-9.</p>
                <p>Presumably it is descended from his Doctorat ès lettres of the same title (1981) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 606&gt;.</p>
                <p>Piquet, François. “Entre chiliasme et épiphanie: Blake et l’espérance
millénariste.” Pp. 143-52 of <hi rend="i">Évolution et Révolution(s) dans le Grande-Bretagne du XVIII<hi
rend="s">e</hi> siècle</hi>: Actes des colloques tenues 1989-1990 á la Sorbonne [organisés par le] Centre
d’Etudes anglaises du XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> siècle, Université de Paris III—Sorbonne nouvelle. Ed.
Paul Gabriel Boucé. (Paris: Publications de la Sorbonne, 1993) Langues et Langages 24.</p>
                <p>§Porée, Marc. “Marges/cadres: l’exemple du romantism anglais.” Pp. 177-88 of 
<hi rend="i">Cadres et Marges:</hi> Actes du quatrième colloque du CICADA: 2, 3, 4 décembre 1993. Ed. Bertrand
Rougé. (Paris: Publication de l’université de Paris, 1995).</p>
                <p>It is especially about Blake.</p>
                <p>Porée, Marc. “Poétique d’une forme brève: Les proverbes de l’enfer Blakiens.”
<hi rend="i">Etudes Anglaises</hi>, XLVIII (1995), 395-406.</p>
                <p>An intricate argument about the <hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi></p>
                <p>*Prickett, Stephen. “Swedenborg and Blake: The Privatisation of Angels.” Pp. 215-21 of
his <hi rend="i">Origins of Narrative:</hi> The Romantic Appropriation of the Bible. (Cambridge: University
Press, 1996).</p>
                <p>In Blake’s watercolor of “Jacob’s Ladder,” the presence of angelic females and
children suggests a Swedenborgian context. The book is about “the way in which the Romantics read the
Bible” (xi).</p>
                <p>Punter, David. “Legends of the Animated Body: Blake’s Albion and the Body and Soul of
the Nation.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism</hi>, I (1995), 161-76.</p>
                <p>Punter, David, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> (Basingstoke &amp; London: Macmillan
Press Ltd, 1996) New Casebooks 8°, ISBN: 0-333-54596-6 (hardcover) and 0-333-54957-4 (paperback).</p>
                <p>The book consists of John Peck &amp; Martin Coyle, “General Editors’ Preface” (ix);
David Punter, “Introduction” (1-15) plus</p>
                <p>1 George Quasha. “Orc as a Fiery Paradigm of Poetic Torsion.” Pp. 16-35. 
(“<hi rend="i">R</hi>eproduced in a slightly abbreviated form” from <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman &amp; John E. Grant [1970].)</p>
                <p>2 Jean H. Hagstrum. “Babylon Revisited, or the Story of Luvah and Vala.” Pp. 36-53.
(“Slightly abbreviated” from <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi>, ed. Stuart Curran &amp; Joseph
A. Wittreich, Jr. [1973].)</p>
                <p>3 David E. James. “Angels out of the Sun: Art, Religion and Politics in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America.</hi>” Pp. 54-70. (“Abbreviated” from <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, XVIII
[1979].)</p>
                <p>4 Nelson Hilton. “Blake in the Chains of Being.” Pp. 71-93. (Reprinted from his 
<hi rend="i">Literal Imagination</hi> [1983].)</p>
                <p>5 Laura Haigwood. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion:</hi>
Revising an Interpretive Tradition.” Pp. 94-107. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">San Jose Studies</hi>, XI, No.
2 [1985].)</p>
                <p>6 Gavin Edwards. “Repeating the Same Dull Round.” Pp. 108-22. (Reprinted from “the
first half” of his essay in <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms</hi>, ed. Nelson Hilton &amp; Thomas Vogler
[1986].)</p>
                <p>7 W. J. T. Mitchell. “Visible Language: Blake’s Wond’rous Art of Writing.” Pp.
123-48. (Reprinted without the section on calligraphy, “Human Letters,” from <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Contemporary Criticism</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves &amp; Michael Fischer [1986].)</p>
                <p>8 David Simpson. “Reading Blake and Derrida—Our Caesars neither Praised nor Buried.”
Pp. 149-64. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms</hi>, ed. Nelson Hilton &amp; Thomas Vogler
[1986].)</p>
                <p>9 David Aers. “Representations of Revolution: From <hi rend="i">The French
Revolution</hi> to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Pp. 165-87. (Reprinted from the “much longer” form
in <hi rend="i">Critical Paths</hi>, ed. Dan Miller, Mark Bracher, &amp; Donald Ault [1987].)</p>
                <p>10 Brenda S. Webster. “Blake, Women, and Sexuality.” Pp. 188-206. (Reprinted from 
<hi rend="i">Critical Paths</hi>, ed. Dan Miller, Mark Bracher, &amp; Donald Ault [1987].)</p>
                <p>Purinton, Marjean D. “An Act of Theological Revisioning: William Blake’s Pictoral
Prophecy.” <hi rend="i">Colby Quarterly</hi>, XXIX, 1 (March 1993), 33-42 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1995)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
325 (“profoundly disorienting”).</p>
                <p>§Raine, Kathleen. “C. G. Jung—A Debt Acknowledged.” <hi rend="i">Harvest:</hi>
Journal for Jungian Studies, XXXIV (1988-89), 7-22. B. Chapter 13 (167-76) of <hi rend="i">Jungian
Criticism.</hi> Ed. Richard Sugg. (Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 1992) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1995)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>“I would not call myself a ‘Jungian’—Blake is my master,” but “a follower of
Blake must be, if not a follower of Jung, at all events a fellow traveler” (B, 168, 167).</p>
                <p>Raine, Kathleen. “The Underlying Order: Nature and the Imagination.” Chapter 15
(198-216) of <hi rend="i">Fragments of Infinity:</hi> Essays in Religion and Philosophy: A Festschrift in
Honour of Professor Huston Smith. Ed. Arvind Shaara. (Bridport, Dorset: Prism Press; Garden City Park, N.Y.:
<pb id="p30-147" n="147"/>
Avery Publishing Group; Lindfield, Australia: Unity Press, 1991).</p>
                <p>Blake is especially on pp. 201-10; “Let us examine what he is in reality saying” in his
myth (206).</p>
                <p>§Rexroth, Kenneth. “Poets, Old and New: William Blake.” Pp. 208-09 of his 
<hi rend="i">Assays.</hi> (New Directions, 1962).</p>
                <p>§Richey, William. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Altering Aesthetic.</hi> (University of Missouri
Press, 1996) 216 pp., ISBN: 0-8262-1077-5.</p>
                <p>§Richey, William. “Neoclassical Gothicism of Blake’s Early Poetry and Art.” 
<hi rend="i">Poetica</hi>, XXXIX-XL for 1993 (Shubun International Co., Ltd., 1994), 73-91.</p>
                <p>Richey, William. “Not Angles but Angels’: Blake’s Pictorial Defense of English
Art.” <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi>, VII (1996), 49-60.</p>
                <p>Blake’s design of “Non Angeli Sed Angli,” based on James Barry’s 
<hi rend="i">Inquiry</hi> (1775), refutes the idea that “British artists were incapable of artistic
excellence” (49).</p>
                <p>Richey, William. “‘One must be master’: Patronage in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Vala.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature 1500-1900</hi>, XXXIII (1993), 705-24.</p>
                <p>The account of the fall of Los in Night I reflects Blake’s experience that “By trying
to please one patron [<hi rend="i">William Hayley</hi>], he risks offending another [<hi rend="i">Thomas
Butts</hi>]” (708).</p>
                <p>Riede, David G. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: On Membership in the Church Paul.”
In <hi rend="i">Re-membering Milton</hi>: Essays in the Texts and Traditions. Ed. Mary Nyquist &amp; Margaret
W. Ferguson. (London: Methuen, 1987) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 623&gt; B. Reprinted “in revised form” as
“Blake and the Church Blake.” Chapter 1 (33-91) of his <hi rend="i">Oracles and Hierophants</hi>:
Constructions of Romantic Authority. (Ithaca &amp; London: Cornell University Press, 1991) Also pp. 4-12 and
passim.</p>
                <p>Ries, Frank W. D. “Sir Geoffrey Keynes and the Ballet <hi rend="i">Job.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Dance Research</hi>, II, No. 1 (Spring 1984), 19-34 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>An interview with Keynes—all the words are those of Keynes and his collaborators Gwen
Raverat (his sister-in-law) and Vaughan Williams (her cousin)—about the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> ballet 
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2049), with “the original scenario” (30-33).</p>
                <p>Rix, Donna S. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Blake’s Reading of Second Isaiah.” Chapter 7
(106-18, 203-06) of <hi rend="i">Poetic Prophecy in Western Literature.</hi> Ed. Jan Wojcik &amp; Raymond-Jean
Frontain. (Teaneck, Rutherford, Madison: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press; London &amp; Toronto:
Associated University Presses, 1984).</p>
                <p>An argument that “on the first six plates of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Blake not only
employs almost all of the themes and images of Second Isaiah [<hi rend="i">Isaiah 40-55</hi>], but he also
arranges them in an order parallelling the order of their appearance in the prophecy. Most striking of all,
perhaps, are the similarities between Blake’s portrait of Milton and Second Isaiah’s portrait of the
servant” (106).</p>
                <p>§Rogal, Samuel J. “Blake’s ‘And did those feet’ as Congregational Hymn.” 
<hi rend="i">Hymn</hi>, XLIV, No. 3 (July 1993), 22-25.</p>
                <p>Includes a history of its composition and performance.</p>
                <p>§*Roob, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Das hermetische Museum</hi>: Alchemie und Mystik.
(Cologne: Benedikt Taschen Verlag, 1996) ISBN: 3-8228-8803-6.</p>
                <p>Blake is reproduced and explained on pp. 69, 119, 161, 163-64, 174, 182, 192, 201-02,
213-14, 229-31, 259, 296-97, 429, 433, 437, 461, 482, 489, 491, 523, 531, 551, 553, 577, 626, 632-33, 649,
652, 663, 692-93, 696-97.</p>
                <p>An English edition is scheduled for 1997.</p>
                <p>Rosso, George Anthony, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Workshop</hi> (1993) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H.C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 69 (a
summary).</p>
                <p>2 Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXIX, 3 (Winter 1995-96), 95-96 (“some of the
assumptions and methods involved seem questionable” [95]).</p>
                <p>3 Philip Cox, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, N.S., XLVIII (1996), 425-26 (the
book “will be of use to new students” of Blake but “fails to contribute in a sustained way to an
advancement of our understanding of Blake’s most puzzling epic”). 4 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s
Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996), 326-27 (“genuinely humanist in its sympathies”).</p>
                <p>5 Margaret Storch, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi>, XXVI (1996), 292 (it is
“welcome” and “lucid”).</p>
                <p>Rothenberg, Molly Anne. <hi rend="i">Rethinking Blake’s Textuality</hi> (1993) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 69-70 (a
“remarkable <hi rend="i">tour de force</hi>,” “an individual though depersonalized response to Blake in
post-structuralist and ‘post-post-structuralist’ terms”).</p>
                <p>2 Harriet Linkin, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXIX, 3 (Winter 1995-96), 92-94 (a “few
important close readings beautifully ground Rothenberg’s astute but sometimes theory-thick discussion of
philosophical and religious contemporary contexts to compensate for whatever imperfections the book
contains” [94]).</p>
                <p>3 Kathryn S. Freeman, <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi>, VII (1996), 87-90 (the
book “offers keen insight” [87]).</p>
                <p>4 Margaret Storch, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi>, XXVI (1996), 292-93
(“challenging and penetrating”).</p>
                <p>5 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
327 (“a subtle book but not a wilful one”).</p>
                <pb id="p30-148" n="148"/>
                <p>§Rothery, Agnes Edwards. “Four Poets and Four Gardens.” Pp. 51-166 of her 
<hi rend="i">Joyful Gardener.</hi> (Dodd, 1949).</p>
                <p>Probably it is related to her “Mad Poets in the Spring,” <hi rend="i">Virginia
Quarterly Review</hi>, III (1927), 250-63 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2583&gt; about John Clare, Blake, Mangan,
and Dowson.</p>
                <p>Sato, Hikari. “Oothoon no Koe to Kafuchosei Shakai—Blake no <hi rend="i">Albion no
Musumetachi no Genso no Ichikosatsu</hi>: The Voice of Oothoon and Patriarchy [On <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu Romanha Gakkai: 
<hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English Romanticism, No. 19-20 (1996),
31-39. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>*Sayers, Lesley-Ann. “An enigma more than a landmark.” <hi rend="i">Dance Now</hi>, II,
No. 3 (Autumn 1993), 40-47, 49.</p>
                <p>The Birmingham Royal Ballet revival of Ninette de Valois’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> ballet
based on Blake’s designs &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2049&gt; “is nothing less than a revelation.”</p>
                <p>Schock, Peter A. “<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>: Blake’s Myth of
Satan and its Cultural Matrix,” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, LX (1993), 441-70 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1995&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 70-71 (“the
information he has assembled here on the political and intellectual milieu of the time is valuable in
itself”).</p>
                <p>2 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> for 1993 (1996), 323
(admiring).</p>
                <p>*Schwenger, Peter, “Blake’s Box, Coleridge’s Circles, and the Frame of Romantic
Vision.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, XXXV (1996), 99-117.</p>
                <p>Focuses on Blake’s drawing of “Elisha in the Chamber on the Wall” and “the power of
the frame” (116).</p>
                <p>*Scott, Grant F. “A Clash of Perspectives: Blake’s Illustrations to the Poem 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>: At once monumental and elastic, Blake’s powerful images inhabit a world of
their own.” <hi rend="i">Muhlenberg</hi>: The Magazine of Muhlenberg College, V, No. 1 (Fall 1993),
10-16.</p>
                <p>“Blake often turns Young’s most characteristic features . . . against him” (14). The
10 reproductions are from the Muhlenberg colored copy (C) of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
                <p>Shabetai, Karen. “The Question of Blake’s Hostility Toward the Jews.” 
<hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, LXI (1996), 139-52.</p>
                <p>“I remain puzzled and disturbed by the many examples of hostility that pepper his
works,” especially in the debate about Deism, though “Blake appears at best uninterested in the ‘Jewish
question’” (139, 149).</p>
                <p>Simpson, David. “The Struggle with Albion’s Angels: William Blake.” Pp. 159-67 of his
<hi rend="i">Romanticism, Naturalism and the Revolt Against Theory.</hi> (Chicago &amp; London: University of
Chicago Press, 1993).</p>
                <p>Simpson, Matt. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and [of] Experience.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Critical Survey</hi>, IV, No. 1 (1992), 20-27.</p>
                <p>“Blake demands . . . that we experience <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> . . . as visionary”
(22).</p>
                <p>Smith, L. E. W. “The Sick Rose.” Part 6 (61-68) of his <hi rend="i">Twelve Poems
Considered.</hi> (London: Methuen &amp; Co Ltd, 1963) B. (1964).</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="i">I</hi>t is the sounds rather than the meanings of the words in this poem
that make us feel what it is about” (A, 68).</p>
                <p>Solomon, Andrew, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Sunao Vagabond [stage name of Andrew Vernède], <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake
Society</hi> (1996), 67-69 (a “marvellous book,” “astoundingly well-informed”).</p>
                <p>§Stephens, James. “William Blake.” Pp. 195-201 of his <hi rend="i">James, Seumas, and
Jacques</hi>: Unpublished Writings of James Stephens. Ed. Lloyd Frankenberg. (N.Y.: Macmillan, 1964).</p>
                <p>*Stevenson, Warren. “Blake’s Myth of Divine Analogy.” Chapter 1 (23-48) of his 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and the Androgynous Sublime.</hi> (Madison &amp; Teaneck: Fairleigh Dickinson University
Press; London: Associated University Press, 1996).</p>
                <p>Storch, Margaret, <hi rend="i">Sons and Adversaries</hi> (1990) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
647&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 §Adela Pinch, <hi rend="i">Signs</hi>, IX (1993), 264-68.</p>
                <p>Sturrock, June. “Protective Pastoral: Innocence and Female Experience in William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and Christina Rossetti’s <hi rend="i">Goblin Market.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Colby Quarterly</hi>, XXX (1994), 98-108.</p>
                <p>“Both <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> and <hi rend="i">Goblin
Market</hi> present versions of pastoral [<hi rend="i">in the sense of an</hi> idyllic, rural setting] . . .
to suggest the state of youthful innocence” (105).</p>
                <p>Suzuki, Masashi. <hi rend="i">Genso no Shigaku</hi>: William Blake Kenkyu: 
<hi rend="i">Visionary Poetics</hi>: A Study of William Blake. (Kyoto: Aporonsha, 1994) ISBN: 4-87041-058-3 C3098
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995), 181&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Shigeru Taniguchi, <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu Romanha Gakkai: 
<hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English Romanticism, No. 19-20 (1996),
149-52. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>*Suzuki, Masashi. “‘We censure Nature for a Span too short’: William Blake and 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> II, 115-20.” Pp. 305-26 of <hi rend="i">Enlightened Groves</hi>: Essays in
Honour of Professor Zenzo Suzuki. Ed. Eiichi Hara, Hiroshi Ozawa, &amp; Peter Robinson. (Tokyo: Shohakusha,
1996) ISBN: 4-88198-858-1.</p>
                <pb id="p30-149" n="149"/>
                <p>Swann, Joseph. “The Breaking of Language: Blake and the Development of Yeats’s
Imagery.” Pp. 217-31, 344-45 of <hi rend="i">The Internationalism of Irish Literature and Drama.</hi> Ed.
Joseph McMinn, with Anne McMaster, &amp; Angela Welch. (Gerrards Cross: Colin Smythe, 1992) Irish Literary
Studies, 41 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Blake’s whole poetic drift [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] was to attack and break” “the
aesthetic unity of the poem,” and “This was the way Yeats was to think and write” (220, 223).</p>
                <p>§Takemura, Masayuki. “Views of the Human Imagination—Blake, Poe [and] Swedenborg.”
<hi rend="i">Eibeibunka</hi> [<hi rend="i">English and American Literature</hi>], No. 26 (1996), 41-51.</p>
                <p>*Tengberg, Violet. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s “The Tyger”:</hi> En
konstvelenskaplig analys och tolkning. C-uppsats vid Konstvelenskapliga Institutionen Göteborgs Universitet.
(Handledare: Lars Stockel, Höstterminen, 1994) 66 leaves printed on one-side-only from typescript in Swedish,
plus 23 reproductions.</p>
                <p>Ff. 20-44 are about the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, including a translation of “The Tyger”
(f. 60).</p>
                <p>Thompson, E. P., <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast:</hi> William Blake and the Moral
Law (1993) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>7 Peter Bradshaw, “Return to dissent,” <hi rend="i">Evening Standard</hi>, 16 December
1993, p. 40 (it shows the “vigour and distinctive Englishness” of Blake and of E. P. Thompson).</p>
                <p>8 §Terry Eagleton, <hi rend="i">NSS</hi>, XXVI (1993), 39-40 (cautious praise).</p>
                <p>9 §Colin Welch, <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi>, 18-25 December 1993, pp. 70-71.</p>
                <p>10 §Alfred Kazin, “The Vision Thing,” <hi rend="i">New Republic</hi>, 21 March 1994,
pp. 38-40.</p>
                <p>11 J[ohn] P[eter] L[undman], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 70-71
(“an essential corrective to Blake studies which are, far too often, as fantastical as Blake’s own
works”).</p>
                <p>12 §Nigel Smith, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century</hi>, XLIV (1994), 147-55.</p>
                <p>13 François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Etudes Anglaises</hi>, XLVIII (1995), 195-98 (this
“étude captivante” demonstrates that “Thompson est un admirable connaisseur du monde complex des
sectes” [498]).</p>
                <p>14 Doug Thorpe, <hi rend="i">Religion &amp; Literature</hi>, XXVIII, No. 1 (Spring 1996),
129 (with Jeanne Moskal, <hi rend="i">Blake, Ethics, and Forgiveness</hi> [1994]) (a summary).</p>
                <p>15 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993
(1996), 328-29 (“at a stroke, <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast</hi> makes Blake
understandable”).</p>
                <p>*Treadwell, James, “Blake, John Martin, and the Illustration of <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Word &amp; Image</hi>, IX (1993), 363-82 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 I[rene] H. C[hayes], <hi rend="i">Romantic Movement</hi> for 1993 (1994), 72 (a
summary).</p>
                <p>*Vaughan, Frank A. <hi rend="i">Again to the Life of Eternity:</hi> William Blake’s
Illustrations to the Poems of Thomas Gray. (Selinsgrove: Susquehanna University Press; London: Associated
University Presses, 1996) Folio, 139 pp., 116 plates, ISBN: 0-945636-74-1.</p>
                <p>“Blake was not much interested in illustrating” Gray; instead, “he fought to free the
mind-forged manacles,” “To educate one to rebel,” to implant “not knowledge but a radical burning
doubt” (7, 116, 18). Blake’s 116 watercolors for Gray are reproduced in reduced size and monochrome.</p>
                <p>Vine, Steven, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry:</hi> Spectral Visions (1993) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Janet Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, XXIX, 3 (Winter 1995-96), 96 (“often the critic
is undermined by the energy and mystery of his poet,” but “the approach that seemed confusing in 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> works brilliantly in Vine’s concise discussions of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”).</p>
                <p>Viscomi, Joseph, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (1994) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>9 §Daniel Mark Epstein, “The Two William Blakes,” <hi rend="i">New Criterion</hi>,
XIII, No. 2 (October 1994), 10-22 (with the five Blake Trust volumes).</p>
                <p>10 §Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, XXV (1994), 198-99
(“revolutionary” and “indispensable”).</p>
                <p>11 Thomas G. Tanselle, <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Literature</hi>, XLIX (1995), 534-37
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996&gt;§&gt; (a “magnificent achievement” which “will profoundly
influence future studies,” but “there could . . . be greater clarity in Viscomi’s use of bibliographical
terminology” such as “edition” for “printrun”).</p>
                <p>12 §Anon.. <hi rend="i">Dix-Huitième Siècle</hi>, No. 27 (1995—Revue Annuelle).</p>
                <p>13 §Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi>, LIII, No. 4
(Fall 1995).</p>
                <p>14 §Jeffrey D. Parker, <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Review</hi>, January 1995, 174-76.</p>
                <p>15 §Sarah Symmons, <hi rend="i">British Journal of Aesthetics</hi>, XXXV, No. 3 (July
1995), 308-09.</p>
                <p>16 Barthélémy Jobert, <hi rend="i">Revue de l’Art</hi>, No. 112 (1996), 78 (with 
<hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi>, ed. D. W. Dörrbecker [1995]), and <hi rend="i">The Urizen
Books</hi>, ed. David Worrall [1995]) (“magistrale”).</p>
                <p>17 §Colin Steel, <hi rend="i">Australian Book Collector</hi> (April 1996) (with
Ackroyd’s <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1995]).</p>
                <p>18 §Margaret Storch, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, XCI, No. 2 (1996), 458-59
(with Jean Moskal, <hi rend="i">Blake, Ethics, and Forgiveness</hi> [1994]).</p>
                <p>19 S. L. M., <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>, 138<hi rend="s">e</hi> Année
(1996), 20 (a summary).</p>
                <pb id="p30-150" n="150"/>
                <p>20 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> for 1993 (1996),
521-22 (it displays “staggering logic”).</p>
                <p>Wada, Ayako. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala/The Four Zoas</hi>: The Genesis of Night I as a
Preludium.” <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu Romanha Gakkai: <hi rend="i">Essays in English
Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English Romanticism, No. 19-20 (1996), 5-14.</p>
                <p>The Preludium (Night I, 3-7) “reversed this archetypal vision of the Fall . . . in the
<hi rend="i">America</hi> Preludium,” and in its further revision “The poem suffered the fatal structural
wounds when it had hardly been given shape” (11, 12).</p>
                <p>Ward, Aileen. “The Forging of Orc: Blake and the Idea of Revolution.” 
<hi rend="i">Tri-Quarterly</hi>, XXIII-XXIV (1972), 204-07 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #A1918&gt;. B. §Pp. 204-27 of
<hi rend="i">Literature in Revolution.</hi> Ed. George Abbott &amp; Charles Hamilton Newman. (N.Y.: Holt,
1972).</p>
                <p>Ware, Tracy. “Bring ‘Gladness out of Sorrow’: <hi rend="i">By the Aurelian
Wall.</hi>” Pp. 111-27 of <hi rend="i">Bliss Carman:</hi> A Reappraisal. Ed. Gerald Lynch. (Ottawa, London,
Paris: University of Ottawa Press, 1990) Reappraisals: Canadian Writers &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1994)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Carman’s indebtedness to Blake is obvious and extensive”; in “The Country of Har:
For the Centenary of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> (1890)
reprinted in <hi rend="i">By the Aurelian Wall</hi> (1898), “Har is the ideal of England” (119, 118).</p>
                <p>§Wemyss, Henry. “Blake Watercolours from The Frick Collection.” 
<hi rend="i">Sotheby’s Preview</hi> (November 1996), 18-19.</p>
                <p>§Williams, John. “Place of William Blake in Relationship to the Growth of Radical
Thought in England.” York University D.Phil., 1974.</p>
                <p>Wilmott, Richard; Brian Alderson; Colin A. St John Wilson; Michael Saunders. “Newton
statue.” <hi rend="i">Times</hi>, 10 August 1992, p. 11 (Wilmott &amp; Alderson), 13 August 1993, p. 11
(Wilson &amp; Saunders).</p>
                <p>Paolozzi’s statue of Newton after Blake’s design for the new British Library is “a
cultural gaffe” (Wilmott), “demonstrates the BL’s failure to apprehend the artist’s meaning”
(Alderson), is creditable because “ambivalent” and “equivocal” (Wilson, a member of the BL committee)
and because “whereas Blake’s figure is impotent and exposed to the elements, Paolizzi’s is immensely
strong and powerful [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]” (Saunders, chairman of the British Library board).</p>
                <p>§Winegarten, R. “The Apocalyptic Vision of William Blake.” Pp. 3-19 of his 
<hi rend="i">Writers and Revolution:</hi> The Fatal Lure of Action. (New Viewpoints, 1974).</p>
                <p>§Wolf, Edwin. <hi rend="i">William Blake as an Artist</hi></p>
                <p>The unpublished book was offered with Wolf’s Blake papers by §Jonathan Hill, Catalogue
98 (1996), Lot 54, for $7,500 (see Essick, Marketplace, 1996). Wolf’s sometime collaborator Ruthven Todd
published his own book called <hi rend="i">William Blake as an artist.</hi></p>
                <p>Wright, Julia M. “‘And None Shall Gather the Leaves’: Unbinding the Voice in
Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>” <hi rend="i">European Romantic
Review</hi>, VII (1996), 61-84.</p>
                <p>“Blake appropriates the homology between biological and non-biological creativity to
address the politics of the copied text” (77).</p>
                <p>Young, Gerard. “Blake’s Felpham paintings on exhibition in Manchester.” 
<hi rend="i">Post</hi>, 17 May 1969.</p>
                <p>Review of the exhibition of Blake’s Heads of the Poets for Hayley’s Library at the City
Art Gallery (Manchester) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #697&gt;.</p>
                <p>Youngquist, Paul. “Reading the Apocalypse: The Narrativity of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, XXXII (1993), 601-25.</p>
                <p>The “contingent narrativity of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” works by “ramification
and incursion” (613).</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, LXXIV for 1993 (1996),
327.</p>
                <p>Zamir, Shamoon. “The Artist as Prophet, Priest and Gunslinger: Ishmael Reed’s 
<hi rend="i">Cowboy in the Boat of Ra.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Callaloo:</hi> A Journal of Afro-American and African
Arts and Letters, XVII (1994), 1205-35.</p>
                <p>Partly about the contexts of Blake and Yeats in Reed’s poem “I am a cowboy in the boat
of Ra.”</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Cromek, Robert Hartley (1770-1812)</p>
              <p>Entrepreneur, Patron and Exploiter of Blake David Alexander. “Cromek, Robert Hartley.”
Vol. VIII, p. 186 of <hi rend="i">The Dictionary of Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries;
London: Macmillan Publishers Limited, 1996).</p>
              <p>Cumberland, George (1754-1848)</p>
              <p>Polymath, Blake’s Friend, Correspondent, and Collaborator</p>
              <p>David Rodgers. “Cumberland, George.” Vol. VIII, p. 264 of <hi rend="i">The Dictionary of
Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries; London: Macmillan Publishers Limited, 1996). Thomas
Johnes. <hi rend="i">A Land of Pure Delight:</hi> Selections from the Letters of Thomas Johnes of Hafod,
Cardiganshire (1748-1816). Ed. Richard J. Moore-Colyer. (Llandysul: Gomer Press, 1992).</p>
              <p>An account of “George Cumberland” (62-65) precedes letters from Johnes to him of
1784-1815. In a letter to Robert Anderson of 29 January 1808, Johnes says that in Malkin’s 
<hi rend="i">Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi> (1806) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #482&gt;</p>
              <pb id="p30-151" n="151"/>
              <p>“You will see an account of Blake and an eulogium of your humble servant. Blake is
certainly verging on the extravaganza” (230).</p>
              <p>Flaxman, John (1756-1826)</p>
              <p>Sculptor, Friend of Blake</p>
              <p>David Bindman. “Flaxman, John.” Vol. XI, pp. 161-63 of <hi rend="i">The Dictionary of
Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries; London: Macmillan Publishers Limited, 1996).</p>
              <p>Fuseli, John Henry (1741-1825)</p>
              <p>Artist, Friend of Blake</p>
              <p>David Blayney Brown. “Fuseli, Henry [Johann Heinrich Füssli].” Vol. XI, p. 862 of 
<hi rend="i">The Dictionary of Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries; London: Macmillan
Publishers Limited, 1996).</p>
              <p>Linnell, John (1792-1882)</p>
              <p>Painter and Engraver, Blake’s Patron</p>
              <p>Christina Payne. “Linnell, John (ii).” Vol. XIV, pp. 426-28 of <hi rend="i">The
Dictionary of Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries; London: Macmillan Publishers Limited,
1996).</p>
              <p>Palmer, Samuel (1805-81)</p>
              <p>Artist, Blake’s Disciple</p>
              <p>David Blayney Brown. “Palmer, Samuel.” Vol. XXIII, pp. 844-47 of <hi rend="i">The
Dictionary of Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries; London: Macmillan Publishers Limited,
1996).</p>
              <p>Richmond, George (1809-96)</p>
              <p>Artist, Blake’s Disciple</p>
              <p>David Blayney Brown. “Richmond, George.” Vol. XXVI, pp. 353-54 of <hi rend="i">The
Dictionary of Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries; London: Macmillan Publishers Limited,
1996).</p>
              <p>Varley, John (1778-1842)</p>
              <p>Artist, Astrologer, Friend of Blake</p>
              <p>Anne Lyles. “Varley, John.” Vol. XXXI, pp. 908-09 of <hi rend="i">The Dictionary of
Art.</hi> Ed. Janet Turner. (N.Y.: Grove’s Dictionaries; London: Macmillan Publishers Limited, 1996).</p>
              <p>Abbott, George 150</p>
              <p>Ackroyd, Peter 123, 128, 134, 141, 142</p>
              <p>Adams, Hazard 134, 149</p>
              <p>Aers, David 144, 146</p>
              <p>Ahlstrom, Chrispin 134</p>
              <p>Alderson, Brian 150</p>
              <p>Alexander, David 150</p>
              <p>Allsup, James O. 135</p>
              <p>Alonso, Mariano Vázquez 128</p>
              <p>Ananda, Dharmachari 134</p>
              <p>Annwn, David 134, 142</p>
              <p>Anzai, Keiko 135</p>
              <p>Aoyama, Keiko 121, 132, 135, 137</p>
              <p>Arakawa, Mitsuo 135</p>
              <p>Ault, Donald 144, 146</p>
              <p>Baldwin, Michael 135</p>
              <p>Baridon, Michel 144</p>
              <p>Barry, Kevin 135</p>
              <p>Bate, Jonathan 134</p>
              <p>Becker, Felix 139</p>
              <p>Beer, John 135</p>
              <p>Behrendt, Stephen 135</p>
              <p>Bemrose, John 134</p>
              <p>Benthall, Jonathan 140</p>
              <p>Bentley, E. B. 121</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 121, 123, 132, 136, 137, 138, 141</p>
              <p>Bentley, Julia G. 121</p>
              <p>Bg, D. 145</p>
              <p>Bindman, David 136, 151</p>
              <p>Blaicher, Günther 144</p>
              <p>Bogan, James 123, 141</p>
              <p>Boucé, Paul Gabriel 146</p>
              <p>Bowra, Cecil Maurice 138</p>
              <p>Bracher, Mark 144, 146</p>
              <p>Bradford, Richard 138</p>
              <p>Bradshaw, Peter 149</p>
              <p>Brammer, Marsanne Carolee 138</p>
              <p>Brown, David B. 132</p>
              <p>Brown, David Blayney 151</p>
              <p>Brown, Marshall 138</p>
              <p>Browne, Max 137</p>
              <p>Bull, Malcolm 138</p>
              <p>Butlin, Martin 132, 137</p>
              <p>Butt, William 138</p>
              <p>Butter, P. H. 128</p>
              <p>Byrne, John 121</p>
              <p>Cadogan, Peter 142, 144</p>
              <p>Cantor, Paul 134</p>
              <p>Caplan, David 137</p>
              <p>Caramés, J. L. 124</p>
              <p>Castoren, Gunnar 138</p>
              <p>Chauvin, Danièle 138</p>
              <p>Chayes, Irene H. 136, 138, 139, 147, 148</p>
              <p>Chou, Wen-ping i 128</p>
              <p>Cieszkowski, Krzysztof 129</p>
              <p>Clark, David L. 144</p>
              <p>Clark, Steve 138, 143</p>
              <p>Clarke, Lorraine 138</p>
              <p>Cloudsley, Tim 139</p>
              <p>Coelsch-Foisner, Sabine 145</p>
              <p>Commander, John 124, 125, 126, 128, 138</p>
              <p>Cooksey, Thomas L. 144</p>
              <p>Corugedo, S. G. 124</p>
              <p>Courthope, William John 138</p>
              <p>Cox, Philip 147</p>
              <p>Cox, Stephen 137, 138, 145</p>
              <p>Cranston, Maurice 138</p>
              <p>Crisman, William 138</p>
              <p>Curran, Stuart 139, 146</p>
              <p>Davie, Donald 139</p>
              <p>Davies, J. M. Q. 139</p>
              <p>Davies, Keri 132, 136, 137</p>
              <p>Davis, Mike 125</p>
              <p>Davreu, Robert 138, 139</p>
              <p>Day, Aidan 139</p>
              <p>de Campos, Augusto 128</p>
              <p>de Diego, Estella 133</p>
              <p>Den Otter, A. G. 139</p>
              <p>Dewhurst, Jim 141</p>
              <p>Dillingham, Thomas F. 141</p>
              <p>Dirda, Michael 134</p>
              <p>Dörrbecker, D. W. 121, 126, 128, 139, 149</p>
              <p>Doulton, Valerie 137</p>
              <p>Eagleton, Terry 149</p>
              <p>Eaves, Morris 125, 126, 128, 137, 139, 146</p>
              <p>Edwards, Gavin 141, 146</p>
              <p>Edwards, Michael 141</p>
              <p>Eglinton, Guy C. 135</p>
              <p>Eliot, T. S. 139</p>
              <p>Endo, Toru 139</p>
              <p>Engetsu, Katsuhiro 139</p>
              <p>Epstein, Daniel Mark 124, 125, 126, 128, 149</p>
              <p>Erdman, David V. 132, 138, 139, 146</p>
              <p>Ernst, C. 140</p>
              <p>Espinosa, Gabriel Sánchez 133</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert N. 121, 123, 125, 126, 128, 129, 130, 132, 136, 137</p>
              <p>Esterhammer, Angela 140</p>
              <p>Fausset, Hugh I’anson 140</p>
              <p>Feldman, Paula R. 136</p>
              <p>Ferber, Michael 126, 137</p>
              <p>Ferguson, Margaret W. 147</p>
              <p>Ferlazzo, P. J. 145</p>
              <p>Fischer, Michael 138, 139 146</p>
              <p>Fitch, Donald 132, 138</p>
              <p>Frankenberg, Lloyd 148</p>
              <p>Fraser, Kennedy 134</p>
              <p>Freeman, Arthur 121</p>
              <p>Freeman, Kathryn S. 140, 147</p>
              <p>Frontain, Raymond-Jean 147</p>
              <p>Fuller, David 132, 139</p>
              <p>Furtwangler, Albert 140</p>
              <p>Gamer, Michael 137</p>
              <p>Gassenmeier, Michael 144</p>
              <p>Gilbert, R. A. 133</p>
              <p>Glausser, Wayne 140</p>
              <p>Gleckner, Robert F. 136, 140, 146</p>
              <pb id="p30-152" n="152"/>
              <p>Glendening, John 140</p>
              <p>Gómez, Monserrat 133</p>
              <p>Görtschacher, Wolfgang 145</p>
              <p>Gott, Ted 132</p>
              <p>Goyder, George 140, 142</p>
              <p>Grant, John E. 139, 146</p>
              <p>Grenfell, Michael 123, 141</p>
              <p>Groves, David 140</p>
              <p>Grundy, Thomas E. 140</p>
              <p>Gurley, George 134</p>
              <p>Gurney, Stephen 140</p>
              <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. 139, 146</p>
              <p>Haigwood, Laura 140, 146</p>
              <p>Hallett, Mark 139</p>
              <p>Halloran, William 121</p>
              <p>Hamlyn, Robin 122, 133</p>
              <p>Hampton, Christopher 140</p>
              <p>Hàn, Francois 124</p>
              <p>Hara, Eiichi 149</p>
              <p>Harbison, Robert 140</p>
              <p>Harman, Clare 140</p>
              <p>Harris, R. W. 140</p>
              <p>Hart, Patrick 144</p>
              <p>Harvey, Giles 121</p>
              <p>Hayes, Elliot 137, 140</p>
              <p>Heath, Tim 134, 140</p>
              <p>Henderson, Jeff 141</p>
              <p>Henshaw, William 128</p>
              <p>Hilton, Nelson 121, 141, 146</p>
              <p>Hobson, Christopher Z. 141</p>
              <p>Hoerner, Fred 141</p>
              <p>Hoffman, Ted 121</p>
              <p>Holten, Ragnar von 141</p>
              <p>Howell, Heather 121, 125</p>
              <p>Ima-Izumi, Yoko 132, 137</p>
              <p>James, David E. 141, 146</p>
              <p>James, G. Ingli 141</p>
              <p>James, G. Ingli. 141</p>
              <p>James, Joan E. 141</p>
              <p>Jobert, Barthélémy 126, 128, 149</p>
              <p>Johnes, Thomas 151</p>
              <p>Jones, Thomas 129</p>
              <p>Jossua, Jean-Pierre 141</p>
              <p>Journal of the Blake Society at St James 122, 141</p>
              <p>Joyce, Sarah 135, 142</p>
              <p>Kaiensi, G. 125</p>
              <p>Kamijima, Kenkichi 142</p>
              <p>Kaplan, Marc A. 142</p>
              <p>Kawasaki, Noriko 123, 132, 142</p>
              <p>Kazin, Alfred 143, 149</p>
              <p>Kewell, Kevin 142</p>
              <p>Keynes, Geoffrey 125</p>
              <p>Kim, Ok Yub 143</p>
              <p>Kim, Young Shik 143</p>
              <p>Kimbrough, Kay 144</p>
              <p>King, James 143</p>
              <p>Klein, Holger M. 145</p>
              <p>Kochov, Joshu 128</p>
              <p>Kovel, Joel 143</p>
              <p>Lamb, Jonathan 139</p>
              <p>Landers, Linda Ann 128</p>
              <p>Leavis, F. R. 143</p>
              <p>Lincoln, A. W. J. 143</p>
              <p>Lincoln, Andrew 123, 125, 137, 138, 141, 143, 147</p>
              <p>Linkin, Harriet 137, 147</p>
              <p>Lisovska, Olga 129</p>
              <p>Löchle, Dieter 144</p>
              <p>Locke, Louis Glenn 138</p>
              <p>Loughnan, Michael 137</p>
              <p>Lundeen, Kathleen 138</p>
              <p>Lundman, John Peter 149</p>
              <p>Lyles, Anne 151</p>
              <p>Lynch, Gerald 150</p>
              <p>Lynch, J. T. 144</p>
              <p>Mackenzie, J. S. 144</p>
              <p>Macve, Jennifer 129</p>
              <p>Maeda, Yoshihiko 144</p>
              <p>Mañe, Pablo 128</p>
              <p>Manguel, Alberto 128, 134</p>
              <p>Matsushima, Shoichi. 144</p>
              <p>McKennitt, Lorena 137</p>
              <p>McMaster, Anne 149</p>
              <p>McMinn, Joseph 149</p>
              <p>Mee, Jon 124, 125, 142</p>
              <p>Meller, Horst 144</p>
              <p>Merton, Thomas 144</p>
              <p>Metzdorf, Robert F. 132</p>
              <p>Miller, Dan 144, 146</p>
              <p>Millgate, Michael 121</p>
              <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. 139, 146</p>
              <p>Monreal, Luis 133</p>
              <p>Moore, Donald 129</p>
              <p>Moore-Colyer, Richard J. 151</p>
              <p>Morán, Adela 133</p>
              <p>Morse, David 144</p>
              <p>Morton, A. L. 144</p>
              <p>Moskal, Jeanne 121, 123, 137, 144</p>
              <p>Muhlestein, Daniel K. 145</p>
              <p>Muir, William 126</p>
              <p>Murry, John Middleton 145</p>
              <p>Nemerov, Howard 145</p>
              <p>Newman, Charles Hamilton 150</p>
              <p>Niikura, Shunichi 145</p>
              <p>Niimi, Hatsuko 143, 145</p>
              <p>Northrup, James 121</p>
              <p>Norvig, Gerda S. 145</p>
              <p>Nyquist, Mary 147</p>
              <p>Odden, Danile 145</p>
              <p>O’Keefe, Richard 123, 145</p>
              <p>O’Keefe, Richard Robert 145</p>
              <p>O’Keefe, Vincent 145</p>
              <p>O’Neill, Michael 121, 145</p>
              <p>Orr, Chris 136</p>
              <p>Ozawa, Hiroshi 149</p>
              <p>Paananen, Victor N. 123, 145</p>
              <p>Pagnini, Marcello 124</p>
              <p>Paley, Morton D. 121, 124, 125, 143, 149</p>
              <p>Parker, Jeffrey D. 149</p>
              <p>Payne, Christina 151</p>
              <p>Peterfreund, Stuart 123, 145</p>
              <p>Phillips, Michael 143, 146</p>
              <p>Pinch, Adela 148</p>
              <p>Piquet, Franćois 123, 125, 138, 144, 146, 149</p>
              <p>Plowman, Max 128</p>
              <p>Porée, Marc 146</p>
              <p>Pound, Alan 125</p>
              <p>Prickett, Stephen 123, 146</p>
              <p>Punter, David 122, 123, 139, 146</p>
              <p>Purinton, Marjean D. 146</p>
              <p>Quasha, George 139, 146</p>
              <p>Raine, Kathleen 146</p>
              <p>Read, Dennis M. 128, 137</p>
              <p>Rexroth, Kenneth 147</p>
              <p>Richey, William 123, 147</p>
              <p>Riede, David G. 147</p>
              <p>Rix, Donna S. 147</p>
              <p>Robinson, Peter 149</p>
              <p>Rodgers, David 150</p>
              <p>Rodney, Paul Wayne 137</p>
              <p>Rogal, Samuel J. 147</p>
              <p>Roob, Alexander 147</p>
              <p>Rosso, George Anthony, Jr. 137, 147</p>
              <p>Rothenberg, Molly Anne 123, 137, 147</p>
              <p>Rothery, Agnes Edwards 148</p>
              <p>Rougé, Bertrand 146</p>
              <p>Rubinstein, Chris 141</p>
              <p>Russell, A. G. B. 139</p>
              <p>Sacks, Russell B. 133</p>
              <p>Sampson, John 128</p>
              <p>Sato, Hikari 148</p>
              <p>Sayers, Lesley-Ann 148</p>
              <p>Schock, Peter A. 148</p>
              <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith 136</p>
              <p>Schwenger, Peter 148</p>
              <p>Sclater, Andrew 129</p>
              <p>Scott, Grant F. 148</p>
              <p>Serraller, Francisco Calvo 133</p>
              <p>Shaara, Arvind 147</p>
              <p>Shabatai, Karen 123, 148</p>
              <p>Shantigarbha 133</p>
              <p>Sharman, Margaret 121</p>
              <p>Simpson, David 136, 141, 146, 148</p>
              <p>Simpson, Matt 148</p>
              <p>Sinclair, Iain 124, 125, 126, 128, 134</p>
              <p>Singh, G. 143</p>
              <p>Smirnov, Dmitri 121</p>
              <p>Smith, L. E. W. 148</p>
              <p>Smith, Nigel 149</p>
              <p>Solomon, Andrew 148</p>
              <p>Steel, Colin 134, 150</p>
              <p>Steer, Francis W. 132</p>
              <p>Stepanova, Sergeia 128</p>
              <p>Stephens, James 148</p>
              <p>Stevens, David 128</p>
              <p>Stevenson, W. H. 125</p>
              <p>Stevenson, Warren 136, 148</p>
              <p>Storch, Margaret 145, 147, 148, 150</p>
              <p>Sturrock, June 148</p>
              <p>Sugg, Richard 146</p>
              <p>Suied, Alain 124</p>
              <p>Suzuki, Masashi 148</p>
              <p>Swann, Joseph 149</p>
              <p>Sweet, Nanora 137</p>
              <p>Symmons, Sarah 149</p>
              <p>Takemura, Masayuki 149</p>
              <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru 148</p>
              <p>Tanselle, Thomas G. 149</p>
              <p>Tengberg, Violet 123, 149</p>
              <p>Thieme, Ulrich 139</p>
              <p>Thompson, E. P. 145, 149</p>
              <p>Thorne, Gary 137</p>
              <p>Thorpe, Doug 145, 149</p>
              <p>Todd, Ruthven 150</p>
              <p>Treadwell, James 149</p>
              <p>Turner, Janet 136, 150</p>
              <p>Vagabond, Sunao 142</p>
              <p>Vaughan, Frank A. 123, 129, 149</p>
              <p>Vernède, Andrew 142, 148</p>
              <p>Vice, John 136</p>
              <p>Villena, Elvira 133</p>
              <p>Vine, Steven 137, 149</p>
              <p>Viscomi, Joseph 121, 122, 125, 126, 128, 136, 137, 149</p>
              <p>Vogler, Thomas 141, 146</p>
              <p>Vultee, Denise 137</p>
              <p>Wada, Ayako 150</p>
              <p>Ward, Aileen 136, 150</p>
              <p>Ware, Tracy 150</p>
              <p>Warner, Janet 137, 149</p>
              <p>Webster, Brenda S. 144, 146</p>
              <p>Welch, Angela 149</p>
              <p>Welch, Colin 149</p>
              <p>Wemyss, Henry 150</p>
              <p>Whittaker, Jason 138, 141, 145</p>
              <p>Wilkie, Brian 139</p>
              <p>Williams, John 150</p>
              <p>Wilmott, Richard 150</p>
              <p>Wilson, Colin A. St John 150</p>
              <p>Wilson, Pauline 141</p>
              <p>Windle, John 124</p>
              <p>Winegarten, R. 150</p>
              <p>Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. 139, 146</p>
              <p>Wojcik, Jan 147</p>
              <p>Wolf, Edwin 150</p>
              <p>Worrall, David 121, 126, 128, 136, 138, 139, 141, 143, 145, 148, 149, 150</p>
              <p>Wright, Julia M. 123, 150</p>
              <p>Yang, Xianyi 121</p>
              <p>Yang, Yi 125</p>
              <p>Yongosa, Sisa 129</p>
              <p>Young, Gerard 150</p>
              <p>Youngquist, Paul 150</p>
              <p>Zalite, Tamara 129</p>
              <p>Zamir, Shamoon 150</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
