<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>31.1.clark</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Angela Esterhammer, Creating States: Studies in the Performative Language of John
Milton and William Blake</title>
        <author n="Clark">David L. Clark</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1997</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1997</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">31.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Lorenz Becher</name>
              <name>Wes Chapman</name>
              <name>David L. Clark</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>James McKusick</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>R. Paul Yoder</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1997"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_31">
    <body>
	<pb id="p31-29" n="29"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-31-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Angela Esterhammer, <hi rend="i">Creating States: Studies in the Performative
Language of John Milton and William Blake.</hi> Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1994. xvii + 245 pp.
$45.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>David L. <name>Clark</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In a book described as the concluding chapter of a decade long investigation of the aesthetic
ideology, Jerome McGann argues that Blake is exemplary for radically resisting the “formal” and “organic
principles of poetry and imagination” entrenched by Kant and Coleridge, principles unreflectively reproduced
by a certain high romantic criticism ever since.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">1</ref> Blake’s poems and designs are not, or not merely, “a dance of forms,” McGann
insists, but “the textual ‘performances’ of his imaginative communications” (32); they are “deed[s]
of language” (18) and “a set of actions carried out in the world” (4), whose “‘great task’” it
is to effect “social and psychic overthrow” (25). Significantly, the critical rhetoric with which McGann
brings out this
<pb id="p31-30" n="30"/>
resistance to the aesthetic ideology is drawn largely from speech-act theory. The point is that Blake’s
texts <hi rend="i">do things with words</hi>, disruptive and self-consciously “gestural” and
“performative” (12) things, and, as such, they “must be grasped [<hi rend="i">pace</hi> Habermas] as a
type of communicative action.” Their “truth-experience” (7)—McGann does not say “truth”—lies 
<hi rend="i">entirely</hi> in the lively social transaction that they create, complicate, and to which they are
contingently exposed. The year that McGann’s study was published also saw the appearance of Robert N.
Essick’s <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Adam</hi>, a signally important book that, like McGann’s,
evokes speech-act theory in the context of a broader hermeneutical argument. And like McGann, Essick shifts
the emphasis from what Blake’s texts <hi rend="i">mean</hi> to their productive or illocutionary force
within a social context. But it is there that the similarity ends. Far from exploiting the absences and
differences inhabiting his own performances, as in McGann, Essick’s Blake strives for an ideal speech
situation in which all semiotic things—sign, referent, recipient—are identified. For Essick, Blake
certainly recognizes the differential and arbitrary nature of conventional signification, but remains
committed to a radicalized literal expression patterned after the “kerygmatic or ‘performative’
gesture” of Christ’s blessing hand or Adam naming the beasts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">2</ref> In speech-act terms, the complete uptake of Blake’s signs and the
realization of their saving significance are at least theoretically possible within “the community of
faithful recipients” (26). Under these conditions, “Jerusalem” would be what Alphonso Lingis calls, in a
quite different context, a “city of communication maximally purged of noise,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">3</ref> the site of an absolutely felicitous performance in which the
shared apocalyptic competencies of speaker and listener ensure the realization of meaningfulness without
remainder. As a preface to his evocation of this perfected linguistic “State,” Essick reads Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts</hi>, where he espies two mutually exclusive ways of doing things with words:
on the one hand, the privileged performative that names the <hi rend="i">zoa</hi> into existence; on the other
hand, the slippery coils and recoils of unmotivated language games that Essick identifies with “Nietzsche,
Sartre, and Derrida” (16)—presumably the postmodern equivalent to Blake’s “Bacon, Newton, &amp;
Locke.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Jerome McGann, <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Towards a Literature of Knowledge</hi></corr>
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1989). Page numbers hereafter cited in the body of the review.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Robert Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of Adam</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1989). Page numbers hereafter cited in the body of the review.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> The Community of Those Who Have Nothing in Common</hi>
(Bloomington and Indianapolis: Indiana UP, 1994) 86.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">4</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, rev. ed. (Berkeley: U of California P, 1982) 218. Hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">E</hi>
followed by the page number.</note></p>
          <p>The fact that the principles of speech-act theory insinuate themselves into these quite
divergent, if similarly strong readings of Blake says as much about the complex fate of that theory in
contemporary criticism as it does about the artist’s linguistic practice. McGann’s and Essick’s studies
form important critical pretexts—acknowledged as such—for Angela Esterhammer’s lucidly argued and
elegantly written book, the first to take up the question of performativity in Blake’s work in a sustained
and explicit fashion. As an inaugural study, the book can only introduce us to this very large subject, but
what it does say is consistently illuminating and often provocative. (Esterhammer’s study is nominally about
speech-acts in Milton <hi rend="i">and</hi> Blake, but I do not think that it is unfair to the book to claim
that its focus and its most engaged negotiations lie with Blake.) For Esterhammer, speech-act principles offer
a clarifying precision to the discussion of Blake’s texts, texts that forthrightly seek to create and
recreate worlds with words, and that challenge (but, also, in some cases, reproduce) the forms of
authoritative speech that police and produce the social body. That Blake was fascinated by the effectual
nature of language and visionary art is of course nothing new. What is sharply original about Esterhammer’s
study is its emphasis not only on the variety of performativities in Blake’s texts, but also on the ways in
which the question of doing things with words goes to the heart of a number of related issues and problems:
the constitution of the creative subject, the limits of aesthetic representation, the hermeneutics of
prophetic discourse, and the poet’s negotiations with origins and originality.</p>
          <p>Paradoxically enough, from a certain perspective speech act theory would seem to find unpromising
ground in Blake. It is true that he creates texts that deliberately eschew constative statements—“forms of
worship” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 38), he would call them—preferring instead to conceive of his work as a
performance “where meaning emerges in and through the encounter between reader and text” (175); but he is
also the notorious builder of those “wall[s] of words”— to use De Luca’s memorable phrase<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">5</ref>—whose “despotism in symbols”—as
Coleridge once said<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">6</ref>—threatens the
very basis of performativity; by short-circuiting what J. L. Austin calls “audience uptake,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">7</ref> Blake’s utterances always run the risk of
failing to do anything, as most of his contemporaries and many of my struggling students could well attest.
Blake’s vision of words and deeds is almost always self-complicating. For example, the English visionary
calls for freedom from the coercive force of conventional speech acts; yet he also recognizes that
revolutionary subjects—epitomized by Orc—are actants who play roles in social and psychic scripts that can
exceed and precede them. When Los’s song is described as “‘uttered with Hammer &amp; Anvil’”
<pb id="p31-31" n="31"/>
(206), Blake’s alter ego clearly embodies the power of speech that has become act; yet Blake reserves his
most vivid visual depiction of him in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (plate 6) with his tools standing silent
beneath the smothering presence of the Spectre. As an idealist, Blake can pattern his creative work after
God’s <hi rend="i">fiats</hi>, even though as a more suspicious cultural critic he condemns the scurrilous
ways in which “societal institutions take words like ‘God’ and ‘eternal,’ which in other contexts
would convey transcendent authority and evoke a realm of language in which saying and doing are the same, and
appropriate them into a logic of human laws and conventions” (157). Finally, as Esterhammer argues, Blake is
conspicuously uncomfortable with the notion of an other-worldly authority speaking on behalf of humankind, and
knows, like Nietzsche, that “cognition requires restriction and knowledge is never knowledge of a whole”
(147); yet the redemptive plot of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> depends for its denouement—if that is what it
is—on the outside intervention of the “Divine Voice” whose purely effectual utterances authoritatively
announce an escape from the prison house of language. <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Vincent Arthur De
Luca, <hi rend="i">Words of Eternity: Blake and the Poetics of the Sublime</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP,
1991) 89.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">6</hi> “To C.A. Tulk,” in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, ed. G.E. Bentley,
Jr., (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969) 252.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Cited by Sandy Petrey, <hi rend="i">Speech Acts and Literary Theory</hi>
(New York and London: Routledge, 1990) 5.</note></p>
          <p>Esterhammer begins her examination by in effect refining the hierarchized opposition between
motivated and unmotivated language that underwrites Essick’s study. In its place, she works up a distinction
between the “sociopolitical performative” and the “phenomenological performative,” each of which tends
to generate its own mode of interpretation. Sociopolitical performatives explicitly obtain their illocutionary
power from the cultural and historical circumstances of their utterance, and are associated with speech-acts
made by figures <hi rend="i">within</hi> Blake’s texts. The moralizing declarations of the Priest in “A
Little Boy Lost” are a case in point: here, normative terms like “holy” and “fiend” are much more
than mere descriptions; they are disciplinary <hi rend="i">acts</hi> that <hi rend="i">subject</hi> the child,
fitting him to the regulatory ideal of the theological regime. As Esterhammer demonstrates in close readings
of selected passages from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience, The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, The Book of
Urizen</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, what drives Blake’s social work is the far-reaching
“recognition that societal institutions only exist in so far as they are created by speech acts (charters,
vows, declarations of independence) and kept in existence by the exercise of verbal performativity” (27).
The phenomenological performative, on the other hand, grants a certain privilege to the speaker, and prompts
an analysis that focuses on the way the utterance (re)produces the power and originality of the speaker or
poet. The paradigm for this kind of creative and effectual language is the divine creation by the Word, the
originary speech-act, as it were, that Blake mimics by creating illuminated texts that derive “authority
from private visionary consciousness” (25). For this reason, Esterhammer argues, visionary poetry “in its
entirety may be regarded as performative discourse in that it is a sustained act of asserting authority”
(33) on the part of the poet. Where the function of sociopolitical performatives is to control 
<hi rend="i">and</hi> to disempower the listener, phenomenological performatives serve the purpose of constituting
and empowering the speaker.</p>
          <p>Esterhammer argues that Blake’s Bardic admonitions—like <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>’s
“‘Mark well my words’” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 100)—constitute both a construction of subjectivity and
an assertion of the subject’s authority. Or in her neat paraphrase: “‘The one who is saying this is I,
and I am the one authorized to say it’” (33). As the circular logic of this phrasing suggests, however,
the visionary’s authority comes at a price, for it “risks being exposed as always and only a function of
language” (33). This is a risk that Esterhammer acknowledges but perhaps underplays in her book, since she
is clearly drawn—as are so many Blakeans—to the heroic image of Blake creating a world “in defiance of
the existing one, to demonstrate the poet’s imaginative independence from the social conditions of his or
her utterance” (25). From the perspective of contemporary language theory, this independence is an illusion,
for performative acts are always at a certain level reenactments, the reiterative or citational effect of
socially sanctioned practice. In as much as phenomenological performatives refer to utterances that are
“non-conventional, extra-societal, deriving from the will or intentionality of the speaker 
<hi rend="i">alone</hi>” (13; emphasis mine), they are, strictly speaking, a contradiction in terms: an
utterance spoken without reference to <hi rend="i">any</hi> social context would be what Derrida calls “the
vocative absolute,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">8</ref> and
unintelligible as such. Blake does not see performative language as always already sociopolitical, an argument
that Esterhammer makes with such vigor that her position would at times appear to be indistinguishable from
that of her subject. Consistently wary of contemporary readers making Blake over into their own
(“post-structuralist”) image, Esterhammer insists that Blake, especially the vatic, inspired Blake, boldly
lays claim to the presentist notion that he is the exclusive origin of what he says. Here, the uptake of
prophetic meaningfulness is presumably more a matter of shared <hi rend="i">belief</hi> (or faith) than
linguistic competency, and, as literary critics we do not talk about such things because they make Blake too
dangerous by half. Perhaps we could say that the pure phenomenological performative functions not so much as
an a achieved fact—we can <hi rend="i">say</hi> that it happens, but how would we know it had
happened?—and more as a figure of visionary <hi rend="i">desire</hi>, no less powerful for being that. It is
the image of linguistic perfection, whether we believe in it or not, that throws the contingent and often
coercive nature of fallen speech-acts into sharp relief. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Of
Grammatology</hi>, trans. Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP, 1978) 112.</note></p>
          <p>For Esterhammer, the sociopolitical performative and phenomenological performative interact and
contradict each other by turns throughout Blake’s work. The artist
<pb id="p31-32" n="32"/>
comes by this dichotomy naturally, however, since, as Esterhammer shows, the same thing is to be found in
Blake’s two great precursors, the Bible and Milton. In a manner reminiscent of some of the work of Kenneth
Burke, Esterhammer reads Genesis as a pretext for both the argument and the rhetoric of modern language
theory. In the “Priestly” or “P” myth of creation in Genesis 1, we of course witness the most vivid
example of a vision of language “which can create things from nothing so that the resulting world is
co-existent and perfectly correspondent with the words” (52). Against this spectacularly effectual but
asocial (or pre-social) instance of doing/saying, Esterhammer contrasts the “Jahwist” or “J” text of
Genesis 2 and 3, in which God’s prohibiting, cursing, and naming—speech-acts all of them—organize and
regulate an already existent life-world through the power of authoritative utterance. Explicitly oriented
towards a present and future disciplinary social context that is at once instituted and dominated by speech
acts, the “J” text thus represents the inaugural example of the sociopolitical performative. Not unlike
what Blake provides in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Esterhammer’s reading of Genesis
amounts to a genealogy of morals that brings out how the Judeo-Christian culture naturalizes its socially
circumscribed norms: in so far as God’s speech-acts “establish domination and subordination as the
characteristic terms of relationships” between men and women, humans and animals, humans and the natural
world, they provide a kind of theological alibi for the human, all too human, history of suffering,
inequality, and “power relationships” (57) that follow.</p>
          <p>The conflictual nature of the performative emerging from the Genesis account has important
implications for texts claiming visionary or inspirational status. Esterhammer begins by pointing to tensions
inhabiting some of Milton’s prose works as well as <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, where his “desire to
represent and imitate the phenomenological performative, as it appears in divine creation, is repeatedly
threatened by the intrusion of the sociopolitical performative” (67). Interestingly, for Esterhammer this
threat does not come from any explicit sense that <hi rend="i">all</hi> utterances are conventional, even and
especially those that naturalize their authority by affecting to be purely “creative” or “expressive”
in the manner of God’s <hi rend="i">fiats.</hi> That is a knowledge about performative language that must
await Blake and romanticism, although why precisely the late eighteenth century would possess it where the
late seventeenth did not is a question that could stand a little clarification in the book. Instead, the
hazard that Milton confronts is displaced into a kind of hubristic embarrassment about presuming that one’s
work is or can be truly self-originating. This is never more sharply legible than at those points where Milton
reflects upon the origins and nature of his own visionary power, as in the invocations to 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> Milton starts with explicit gestures towards firstness but finally figures
himself “in the position of one who comes second, a revisor and reshaper of received material” (77). In
Books 1 and 3, Milton reveals his desire for and faith in the performative ability of his language to summon a
world of phenomena into existence, but by Book 7 this desire is overtaken by a counter-sense that creative
utterances are also a matter of arbitrary, violent impositions and articulations spoken out of a limited
position whose inspirational authority rests in large part with the consent of a community of
believers—i.e., language acts that more closely resemble the conventionalized utterances of the
sociopolitical world than the protected inward realm of the phenomenological performative. This crossing
between what Milton desires and what he knows, or between what he says and what he does, represents an
important—though underthought—moment in literary history, for here Milton takes “a first step toward
implicating creative utterance in a structure of repetition” (89).</p>
          <p>The same questions of authority, performativity, and representation pre-occupy Blake, whom
Esterhammer characterizes as “much more conscious of, and therefore anxious about, the dichotomy between
language which derives its creativity from individual will and language which wields by common consent”
(64). Curiously, the Blake that actually emerges from Esterhammer’s discussion does not come across as
particularly anxious, and, indeed, seems most often in command of his vision of words, coolly manipulating the
performative dichotomy in which he is also said to be caught. Nevertheless, the ways in which the
phenomenological and the sociopolitical performatives interact in Blake’s texts varies considerably over the
course of the production of the illuminated works. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
stage them as a non-dialectical opposition: “Innocence” names a condition of felicitious speech-acts in
which the Child’s illocutionary force and perlocutionary effects are immediate and forceful;
“Experience” is the realm in which speech acts either fail, as in the case of the Bard’s summons to
Earth, or succeed only too well, as is the case with the social discourses that subjugate their auditors.
Against the almost canonical position in Blake studies to interpret <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
through the ironic lens of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, Esterhammer thus presses for a reading that
“more fully” appreciates the significance of the “idealized scene of discourse” (130) being envisioned
there.</p>
          <p>I take Esterhammer’s point; part of recovering a more dangerous Blake may well lie in allowing
him to have a vision of words wholly different from that of the late twentieth century. But the question
remains why it is <hi rend="i">necessarily</hi> the case that the communicative action of the Bard is in
effect ironized by the felicity of the Child, but not vice versa. In other words, aside from our firm
persuasion that it is not so, why can’t the Child’s performative success be read as a dreamy projection
about language rather than an ideal against which to measure the infelicities of spoken experience? I am not
sure if this question can be dismissed simply
<pb id="p31-33" n="33"/>
as one emerging out of “a Derridean anxiety imposed onto the Blakean text” (129), especially since
Esterhammer’s subsequent discussion of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi> fully demonstrates Blake’s extreme sensitivity to the fact that phenomenological
performatives, with their claim to authority and efficacy, can instantly become the alibi for speech-acts of
sociopolitical violence. (We might further ask what a phenomenological performative <hi rend="i">is</hi> and
must be <hi rend="i">in the first place</hi> if it is supplementally open to such violent “appropriation”
(157) by its demonized other? Does the phenomenological performative suffer this appropriation as a kind of
accident, or does its susceptibility to corruption point to its always already being sociopolitical in nature?
Is it possible that the sociopolitical realm produces the conceit of an appropriated or repressed
“creativity” in the realm of the phenomenological in order to rationalize its own strategies?) Even if
Blake held out the possibility of a truly ideal speech situation when he produced the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>,
the subsequent reprinting of that text alongside <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
Marriage</hi> exposes it to a hermeneutics of suspicion that inevitably reframes its idealistic claims about
an “innocent” performative language of individual vision.</p>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>—which Esterhammer characterizes as the Blakean text most open to
speech-act analysis—would seem to be a text that is framed by the linguistic problematic it frames,
unwilling to dwell on either side of the performative dichotomy that organizes <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi>
Through his parody of “the Bible’s various language games, including prophecy, wisdom literature, law, and
history” (160), Blake denounces the authoritarian claims of those utterances that claim universality but in
fact expressly perform the disciplinary labor of Church and State. Against the systematizing codes of the
Priests, Blake opposes the creative language of the Poet; but he does so even though the 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>’s pervasively dialogical form reminds us that <hi rend="i">all</hi> utterances are
dependent upon context and perspective, even as every quantum of energy relies upon its circumference to make
it legible. The title of the text nicely captures the problem: the marriage ceremony evokes the primary
example of sociopolitical performativity in language theory, the exemplary instance of an utterance whose
illocutionary power and perlocutionary effect rely upon a certain minimal agreement between speaker and
audience; yet Blake makes his marital declaration, like all the other declarations in the poem, “utterly
without the authority or the societal consensus that would give him the right to make such a pronouncement”
(170). The (un)solemn union of “Heaven &amp; Hell” asserted by the poem is thus not the effect of a
collective accord, but an imposition—even an act of rhetorical violence—whose authority is produced only
in and through its own performance. How to account for this curious contradiction in speech-act terms? Or as
Geoffrey Hartman once asked, “Where does Blake get his authority from?” (216). Esterhammer implies that
while intellectually Blake recognizes that his devilishly individualistic and non-conventional claims are made
without any substantiating authority, emotionally he remains attracted to the self-grounding power of
phenomenological performative, especially since the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> marks the “turning point”
(172) in which Blake begins to lose “whatever interpretive community he was ever able to address” (173).
At the conclusion of her discussion of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, Esterhammer recuperates the situation
somewhat by suggesting that even without an audience to make his utterance felicitious, Blake “performs” a
“marriage . . . in the writing of the poem itself, and we instantiate it in reading” (172). Yet her own
suggestive reading of the poem rightly complicates what this instantiation could mean. Far from simply
realizing the communicative action of Blake’s performative utterance, Esterhammer’s instantiation of
Blake’s work in her <hi rend="i">own</hi> study helps to bring out how the problem of performative
legitimacy is complexly symptomatic of a cleft inhabiting declarative discourse in general. As Derrida has
shown with regard to declarations of independence, revolutionary assertions involve a strangely duplicitous
twist in thinking: they create the very state that they must already be in in order to bring that state
about.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">9</ref> Lacking any consensual
authority, the force and efficacy of Blake’s visionary utterance is derived from its own declaration in the
form of his text. Yet in order to <hi rend="i">have</hi> a vision and to <hi rend="i">make</hi> his
pronouncements, Blake must already in some sense <hi rend="i">be</hi> visionary. Or in Geoffrey Bennington’s
terms, “there is no performative which does not also involve an at least implicit description of the state
of affairs it produces.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">10</ref> The
authority of Blake’s declaration of independence from conventional speech-acts—again, not unlike all
declarations—is thus scandalously unstable, since it is grounded in its own act of grounding. The circular
and recursive logic of the illocutionary force of Blake’s poem is this: it must verbally effect what it
requires to be effectual. As such, the performance always lags slightly behind itself, never a purely
phenomenological utterance springing from the creative will because of the hidden way in which it derives its
authority from an always earlier speech act extending “backwards” towards an irrecoverable “past.” To
pick up on Esterhammer’s language: visionary speech is “a <hi rend="i">hybrid</hi> of the phenomenological
and the sociopolitical performative” (177; emphasis mine), that is, a <hi rend="i">grafting</hi> of an act
upon a description. <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">9</hi> See, for example, “Declarations of Independence,”
trans. Thomas Keenan and Thomas Pepper, <hi rend="i">New Political Science</hi> 15 (1986): 7-15.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> Jacques Derrida</hi> (Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1993)
233.</note></p>
          <p>Esterhammer divides her concluding chapter on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> into two movements.
Beginning with an analysis of different speech-act strategies adopted by figures within the text, she shows
how those utterances provide a means by which to apprehend the visionary performance of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
	<pb id="p31-34" n="34"/>
as a whole. True to the teleological assumptions underwriting her account of Blake’s development as an
artist, Esterhammer treats Blake’s epic as the culmination of a lifelong negotiation with performativity. It
is here, in the act of “creating states,” that Blake finally finds a “compromise” to the problem of
transcendent and convention-based ways of doing things with words. “Jerusalem” is the pre-eminent example
of this settlement, a socio-political and visionary “State” that is said to be named—and framed?—into
existence by the poem’s first and last words. Between these apocalyptic pronouncements, the narrative is
noisy with unhappy speech acts—lamentations, exhortations, and curses—almost as if the true performative
can emerge only when all the false have exhausted themselves. Albion’s sorrowful cry at the end of chapter 1
marks a critical moment in this progress: “What have I said? What have I done? O all-powerful Human
Words!” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 169). Albion’s apostrophe to signs registers his self-conscious awareness
that language harbors an articulate life of its own, and that the authority of his words is thus not of his
own doing. (Today, we would call this overwhelmingly mighty language <hi rend="i">discourse.</hi>) Esterhammer
contrasts the agonistic and derived nature of Albion’s speech acts to the forcefulness of the “Divine
Voice” that anticipates the redemptive outcome of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and brings this outcome about
in the form of the poem itself. The “Divine Voice” may be the direct expression of the creative will of
the “Divine Family,” but the rhetoric and the strategies of its redemptive utterances are resolutely
social. As an accommodation to the inhabitants of Albion’s Land, the “Divine Voice” awakens Albion by
creating and recreating “States,” a word, Esterhammer astutely emphasizes, that possesses important
political and communal resonances. Although Esterhammer does not describe it in these terms, a “State”
possesses a formal rather than substantive integrity; as the sum of its speech-acts, it is an ongoing
articulation and rearticulation of itself that has its “permanence” (as Blake puts it) in the continuity
of this process. Blakean “States,” like nation states, are thus more or less provisional arrangements with
the express purpose of “continually” staging a redeemed social universe. Esterhammer characterizes this
felicitious outcome as a truce between the two forms of performativity, but it is perhaps more accurately a
linguistic apocalypse in which the distinction no longer obtains because language itself has somehow been
redeemed. It is precisely this transformation that Esterhammer sees being described (or perhaps even effected)
in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s concluding plates.</p>
          <p>Esterhammer identifies herself with those for whom Blake is interestingly resistant precisely
because he is <hi rend="i">not</hi> postmodern, even if his insights illuminate and reproduce elements of
contemporary language theory. In addition to its readings of individual texts, the strength of this book is
that it opens up so many possibilities in other areas of Blake studies. For example, how do the principles of
speech-act theory help us investigate Blake’s vexed representation of the feminine? At a recent Romantics
conference, I heard Anne K. Mellor roundly declare that Blake “was sexist to the core.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">11</ref> but one of the things that speech-act theory
has done—especially in the work of Judith Butler<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">12</ref>—is to demonstrate how no one is anything “to the core,” not even 
<hi rend="i">gendered.</hi> Speech act theory might well prove useful in moving us past the critical impasse
created by Mellor’s curiously dismissive and preemptive statement. In critically discerning how ideological
and gendered positions are produced and reproduced in performative acts of authoritative speech, we will
perhaps understand more clearly what “sex” and “sexism” mean in Blake’s texts. In other words,
speech-act theory encourages us to continue the task of <hi rend="i">reading</hi>—rather than
dismissing—Blake as a complex speaker in a shifting cultural context. In this regard, Esterhammer’s book
is exemplary. To be sure, Esterhammer offers us a melioristic interpretation of Blake, as perhaps befits a
book dedicated to Northrop Frye. Yet she also emphasizes a Blake who was resolutely pragmatic, a Blake who
might have said that although all speech is equal, some is more equal than others. Blake dispels the peculiar
legal-constitutional hallucination that speech is free, and that what one says is entirely divorced from what
one does. As Esterhammer concludes, “One could say that the aim of Blake’s art, like that of 
<hi rend="i">How To Do Things with Words</hi>, is to demonstrate the illocutionary force of constative statements,
or to emphasize that all speech <hi rend="i">acts</hi>” (207). Speech does not simply happen; it is made by
individuals in specific social contexts, in which some speak with authority, and thus with real consequences
for those who are compelled to listen. The fractious and strangled cries that resound through Blake’s texts
repeatedly show and tell us two things: words are never <hi rend="i">only</hi> words, and those who are not in
a position to speak effectually are kept in that position of inequality by those who are.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Mellor made this remark during the discussion period following the
session on “Framing the Subject: Portraits and Frontispieces,” at the conference on 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and the Ideologies of Genre</hi>, University of Western Ontario, London, Canada, 26
August 1993.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">12</hi> See, for example, <hi rend="i">Bodies that Matter: On the Discursive
Limits of “Sex”</hi> (New York and London: Routledge, 1993) 223-42.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">13</hi> I am thinking here, of course, of the argument that Catharine MacKinnon
makes in <hi rend="i">Only Words</hi> (Cambridge, MA.: Harvard UP, 1993) 71-110.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
