<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>31.1.mckusick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">George Coates, 20/20 Blake</title>
        <author n="McKusick">James McKusick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1997</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1997</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">31.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Lorenz Becher</name>
              <name>Wes Chapman</name>
              <name>David L. Clark</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>James McKusick</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>R. Paul Yoder</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1997"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_31">
    <body>
	<pb id="p31-38" n="38"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-31-1-0006">
        <div2>
          <figure n="20-20-Blake.31.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="221" height="337"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">20/20 Blake.</hi> Written and Directed by George Coates. North
American Premiere: Civic Center Theater, San Francisco, 17 January 1997. World Premiere: Teatro Sérgio
Cardoso, Sao Paulo, Brazil, 4 September 1996.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>James <name>McKusick</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p><hi rend="i">20/20 Blake</hi>, a dramatic and musical performance based on the life and work of
William Blake, recently concluded a production at the Civic Center Theater in San Francisco. Perhaps the most
innovative feature of this lush scenic production, written and directed by George Coates, is its digital
manipulation of Blake’s paintings and engravings to create the illusion of three dimensions when viewed by
the audience through special 3-D glasses. Familiar images from Blake’s illuminated books are magnified to
enormous size and projected onto the stage, thus enabling the performers to walk into, through, and behind the
engravings. This technique, initially somewhat disorienting to the observer, is nevertheless effective in
drawing the audience
<pb id="p31-39" n="39"/>
into and across the uncertain boundaries between Blake’s lived and imagined worlds.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">20/20 Blake</hi> does not attempt a linear narrative of Blake’s life story, but
rather presents a series of climactic moments that are vividly realized in choral music performed by the San
Francisco Chamber Singers and represented in dance and pantomimic gesture by the actors. The music is
challenging and eclectic, weaving together traditional plainsong and orchestral music with elegantly
embroidered lyrics from Blake’s poetry, and even at times incorporating a fourpiece rock-and-roll band with
Urizen playing the bass guitar. There is very little spoken dialogue, although Robert G. Kennedy gives a
fierce and compelling portrayal of William Blake as a strenuously embattled poet-artist at odds with the
universe; he rattles off Proverbs of Hell and related apothegms in a pithy counterpoint to the lush visual and
musical texture of each set-piece. The other characters portrayed on stage are his wife Catherine (who doubles
as Enitharmon), Mr. Wedgwood (appearing mainly as a villainous enforcer of bourgeois artistic standards),
Thel, and Los. The latter two characters provide a lavishly choreographed rendition of their eponymous books,
allowing an escapist and frankly erotic fantasy to emerge briefly before it is beaten back into submission by
the nay-saying likes of Wedgwood and Urizen.</p>
          <p>This production is unlikely to appeal to those Blake scholars who insist on a faithful adherence
to Blake’s subtlety of design and meaning, since the ethos of his life and work is painted here with rather
broad strokes. But this production is both innovative and appealing in its own right, and it does comprise a
sustained effort to represent the passionate intensity of Blake’s poetry in a dynamic contemporary medium.
It certainly reaches out to new audiences who might otherwise never encounter the rich imagery of Blake’s
illuminated books.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
