<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>31.3.carretta</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Meheux?</title>
        <author n="Carretta">Vincent Carretta</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1997/98</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1997/98</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">31.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Vincent Carretta</name>
              <name>A. Harris Fairbanks</name>
              <name>Sarah Joyce</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Shelia A. Spector</name>
              <name>Frank A. Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1997/98"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_31">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-31-3-0006">
      	<pb id="p31-84" n="84"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Meheux?</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Vincent <name>Carretta</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Among the plates executed by Blake after designs by other artists is Robin Hood &amp; Clorinda,
“J. Meheux delint.,” published by T. Macklin in London on 30 March 1783. Robert N. Essick, in The Separate
Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1983) 133, observes that
“[n]othing is known of ‘J. Meheux, other than his designing ‘Robin Hood and Clorinda,’” and notes
that “Samuel Redgrave, A Dictionary of Artists of the English School, 2nd ed., London, 1878, p. 292, gives
the artist’s name as ‘John Meheux.’” The John Meheux in question was probably the John Meheux
(1749?-1839) who corresponded during the 1770s with Ignatius Sancho (1729-80), the black Westminster grocer
whose posthumously published Letters (London, 1782) I have edited: <hi rend="i">Letters of the Late Ignatius
Sancho, an African</hi> (Penguin Putnam Inc, 1998).</p>
          <p>Meheux’s obituary in The Gentleman’s Magazine (December 1839) 662, says, “In his 90th year,
John Meheux, esq. of Hans Place, formerly many years Secretary to Board of Control. He has bequeathed 5000£.
to Indigent Blind School, 200£. to Deaf and Dumb Institution, and 100£. each to St. George’s Hospital,
Westminster Lying-in Hospital, and Society of Arts, all duty free.” During the 1770s, Meheux was an amateur
writer and artist, submitting essays to the newspapers and designs to print sellers through Sancho. Sancho had
many contacts in the art world. His portrait had been painted in 1768 by Thomas Gainsborough, and his friends
included the artists John James Barralet, William Henry Bunbury, Matthew and Mary Darly, Daniel Gardner, John
Hamilton Mortimer, Joseph Nollekens, and William Stevenson. Besides Mr. and Mrs. Darly, who frequently etched
and published prints after the designs of amateurs, Sancho also knew the print and booksellers John Ireland
and John Wingrave.</p>
          <p>In a letter misdated 21 March 1770 but written in 1776, Sancho sends Meheux “a proof print”;
in one of 4 January 1776, Sancho asks about Meheux’s sketches; and on 3 September 1777, Sancho asks Meheux,
<q>
How do you like the print?—Mr. D[arly] says, and his wife says the same, that you are exceedingly
clever—and they shall be happy to do any thing which is produced by the same hand which did the
original—and if Mr. D[arly] can be of any service to you in the etching, you may command him when you
please.
</q></p>
          <p>Given the history of Sancho’s John Meheux as an amateur artist providing designs for prints
executed and published by others during the late 1770s, he is probably Blake’s “J. Meheux” of 1783 as
well.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
