<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>31.3.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Marvin D. L. Lansverk, The Wisdom of Many, The Vision of One: The Proverbs of
William Blake</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1997/98</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1997/98</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">31.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Vincent Carretta</name>
              <name>A. Harris Fairbanks</name>
              <name>Sarah Joyce</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Shelia A. Spector</name>
              <name>Frank A. Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1997/98"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_31">
    <body>
	<pb id="p31-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-31-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Marvin D. L. Lansverk, <hi rend="i">The Wisdom of Many, The Vision of One: The
Proverbs of William Blake.</hi> American University Studies, Series IV, vol. 142. New York: Peter Lang, 1994.
215 pp. $38.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Unknown gnomes mine. pro-verbal proverbs. but, ah! men, Wisdom’s awful theopanatives love her.
language bombs</p>
          <p>Or so one might imagine from recent, stimulating work by Marvin D. L. Lansverk. Beginning with
“the puzzle that Blake would use proverbs at all” (2), given the oppressing conformity often found in such
“wisdom of the many,” Lansverk traces a path to Blake’s invention of “a new type of proverb” (3) or
prophetic performative in which speech acts. Along the way he revives for us an image with profound
implications for Blake’s emanations, the figure of the divine female consort in the “Wisdom Books” of
Hebrew scripture.</p>
          <p>The first part of his book, a literary history of Blake’s relations to proverb literature,
opens with a comparison of the themes, forms, and functions of the Book of Proverbs and of Blake’s
“Proverbs of Hell.” Timely criticism this, for “the only major English writer himself to have composed a
<pb id="p31-85" n="85"/>
whole collection of proverbs”—as John Holloway observed over 28 years ago (<hi rend="i">Blake: The Lyric
Poetry</hi> [London: Edward Arnold, 1968]). Lansverk shows that while Blake “rejects the Book of Proverbs’
external law of distributive justice” (188) with satire and transformation, he adapts its binary forms which
“draw together two phrases or versets into a parallelism” (15)—e.g., “Joys impregnate. Sorrows bring
forth.” So, the thesis being driven hard, we are asked to see that “Blake converts the biblical ‘A wise
king scattereth the wicked, and bringeth the wheel over them’ (20:26) into a command as well: ‘Drive your
cart and your plow over the bones of the dead’” (23).</p>
          <p>Lansverk notes also how the introductory chapters of the Book of Proverbs, 8 and 9 in particular,
would have attracted Blake, “with their sustained mythic personification of the virtues of Lady Wisdom.”
This figure “is most commonly imaged as a superior goddess who is both a possession of God and a childhood
companion with him. As she says in an early poetic exposition of the myth,”
<q>
The Lord possessed me in the beginning of his way,<lb/>
before his works of old . . .<lb/>
When [God] appointed the foundation of the earth:<lb/>
Then I was by him, <hi rend="i">as</hi> one brought up <hi rend="i">with him:</hi> and I was<lb/>
daily <hi rend="i">his</hi> delight, rejoicing always before him.<lb/>
(8:22, 29-30) (18)
</q></p>
          <p>Remarking Blake’s “attention to and exploitation of . . . typographic details’ ability to
carry additional meaning,” Lansverk appropriately retains the use of italics in the King James Version for
“words merely implied in the original Hebrew” (34). Attention to the original Hebrew would have been
appropriate as well, as the AV translation of “one brought up” for the Hebrew (‘<hi rend="i">amon</hi>)
can be challenged by readings of “‘<hi rend="i">amôn</hi> as ‘master architect’ or else ‘little
child’” or both at once (Judith M. Hadley, “Wisdom and the Goddess,” in <hi rend="i">Wisdom in Ancient
Israel</hi>, eds. John Day et al. [Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995] 238). These references can begin to suggest
that a Bible-reader like Blake could have pondered, with the most recent scholarship, how, “from a
literary-theological point of view, personified Wisdom is simply unequalled in the entire Old Testament”
(Roland E. Murphy, “The Personification of Wisdom,” in Day et al. eds. 232).</p>
          <p>The second chapter, on “Blake and Bunyan’s Allegorical Proverbs” argues that “[t]he
pervasive use of proverbs by Bunyan cannot have escaped Blake’s attention, nor the fact that Bunyan adopts
and extends the very aspects of biblical proverbs that Blake despised” (38). This, then, is an allegorical
use of proverbs” which Blake rejects, “yet also a model for the variety and power of proverbs in
imaginative literature” (188). While Swedenborg’s works do not offer many proverbs, they supply Blake with
a vocabulary and a “symbolic theory in the doctrine of correspondences” to be transformed “from a
divinely revealed, fixed hermeneutic into a heuristic for the creation of [Blake’s] own wisdom” (188).
“Almost every term used in the Proverbs of Hell,” from the many animals to the abstract nouns, “is given
discussion in Swedenborg’s dictionary of correspondences,” Lansverk reports (65).</p>
          <p>The book’s first part concludes with a study of “Blake’s and Milton’s Paradoxical
Proverbs,” the title pointing to the poet’s co-creation of “a radically new type of proverb” (5) which
exhorts rejection of the tradition of law, Milton’s “custome,” as grounds of authority and affirms
instead liberty and “the tradition of prophecy.” For Lansverk, “[t]he importance of Milton as an
analogue of Blake’s proverbs cannot be overestimated. In fact, this link is so close that if it were not for
Blake’s subsequent transformations, Milton might be said to cross the boundary between analogue and actual
source. . . . Blake’s readers should recognize that the late eighteenth century poet does not create his
paradoxical proverbs <hi rend="i">ex nihilo</hi>” (84).</p>
          <p>Milton’s crucial contribution, according to this argument, can be exemplified through a passage
in <hi rend="i">The Reason of Church Government</hi>, where Milton combines several verses from the Book of
Proverbs which “emphasize the function of proverbs as exhortations. Quoting Solomon’s personification of
wisdom as a woman, Milton writes: ‘as Salomon saith, “<hi rend="i">She crieth without, she uttereth her
voice in the streets, in the top of high places, in the chief concours, and in the openings of the
Gates</hi>”’” (79). This emphasis on “exhortation” takes Lansverk to Stanley Fish’s familiar
argument that “the purpose of Milton’s prose is to get his readers to ‘exchange one way of knowing for
another,’ to exchange their reliance on reason for a reliance on vision” (81): “an example of how to do
things with proverbs” (89), in other words.</p>
          <p>The second part of the book turns to textual interpretation of five of Blake’s productions,
focusing both on his use of proverbs as performative rather than affirmative utterances and on his
“systematic revision” of Hebrew Wisdom literature. It is worth recalling that these texts include not only
Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, Ecclesiasticus, and Wisdom, but also that work whose importance for Blake requires no
rehearsal, Job. The discussion of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> as “Blake’s
Performative Book of Proverbs” hinges on those verbal utterances named (or, performed) by J. L. Austin in
<hi rend="i">How to Do Things with Words</hi>, in which to say is to perform and so engender a new
psychological or social reality. This function of occasioning “a change in reality in the act of speaking .
. . lies at the heart of Blake’s use of proverbs” (98). As this effect gives performatives “the force of
utterances of God,” Lansverk coins for them the name “<hi rend="i">theopanatives</hi>,” drawing on
“the Greek root of our word prophecy—<hi rend="i">phanai</hi>, or to speak—and . . . related to the term
<hi rend="i">theopany</hi>—or the visible manifestation of God” (102). They are used, he writes elsewhere,
“as textual language bombs to create the reality they refer to” (<hi rend="i">Northwest Society for
Eighteenth-Century</hi>
	<pb id="p31-86" n="86"/>
	<hi rend="i">Studies</hi> 19 [1991-94] 182). The neologism serves to emphasize the oddity that “Blake even
uses the term <hi rend="i">proverb</hi> rather than the many alternatives available”— gnome, dictate,
maxim, apothegm—“given that his aphorisms are not the restatement of general, popular wisdom” (113;
these would be <hi rend="i">theopalliatives</hi>, perhaps). Lansverk’s intriguing suggestion is that
Blake’s act of “naming his sententia <hi rend="i">proverbs</hi> . . . in opposition to the social
conventions of language which serve to define the term, is itself a performative,” and that, more
importantly, the etymology allows an author fixated on naming to denominate an attempt at meaning both
“before” and “on behalf of” (<hi rend="i">pro</hi>) words (<hi rend="i">verbum</hi>) (113).</p>
          <p>Chapter 6 presents <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, with its memorable
proverbial epigraph, as “Blake’s Book of Job,” “a parable of proper sententious utterance” (117).
The influence of biblical story appears in the poem’s “dialogue format, in its presentation of a battle
between two types of wisdom” (120-21)—and “two ways of expressing it” (122)—and foremost “in its
use of proverbial questions” (121). Bromion’s and Theotormon’s repeated questions, like those of Job and
his comforters, embody “panicked efforts to maintain a semblance of order in a world on the brink of
confusion” (120) (owing to loss of faith, for the Hebrew story, in the actuality of “distributive
justice”), and their questions represent futile attempts “to gain rhetorical ascendancy” (120). Lansverk
notes how Theotormon’s concluding outcry, “Tell me what is the night or day to one o’erflowd with
woe,” doubles Job’s “most characteristic lament of woe” (125). To Oothoon, however, is reserved the
use of “the proverbial questions from Job” to express the “theopanative wisdom” of her understanding
of an imaginative wisdom unknown to her antagonists. The tight, steady focus of the discussion here shows one
of the limitations of the author’s method, as when he writes that “to emphasize that her learning is not
the rote following of a commandment but the generation of her own theopanatives—Oothoon maintains that her
soul is ‘pure transparent’ and not ‘defiled’” (122). But any construction of Oothoon’s supposed
intention is complicated by the full context:
<q>
Rend away this defiled bosom that I may reflect.<lb/>
The image of Theotormon on my pure transparent
breast.<lb/>
(2.15-16)
</q></p>
          <p>Not only is the implication of defilement not rejected here, but the notion of pure
transparency’s reflecting raises questions about the speaker’s (psycho-)logic. Oothoon here plucks, again,
a “flower” of rhetoric (<hi rend="i">OED</hi> “flower,” 6d), but in its seeming entire neglect of the
wisdom of many who have written specifically on <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (not to mention Blake and
performatives, like Robert Essick in <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of Adam</hi> [1989, 25-26]),
Lansverk’s vision misses opportunities to ground itself more substantially. It misses, as well, occasions to
express itself with greater felicity—things seem recurrently “more” or “most” important, or
“actually” so (117); Blake has “finely tuned proverbial hands” (117).</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> appears in this book as “Blake’s Vision of Ecclesiastes,”
and with his concern, Lansverk can build on Brian Wilkie and Mary Lynn Johnson’s puzzled observation that
“‘[t]he kind of paradoxical epigram, reminiscent of Blake’s Proverbs of Hell, occurs more often in 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> than one might expect in a work so grand in scale’” (131). For a Blake
involved in “continued experiments with reforming biblical Wisdom books” (132), however, a full blown
dramatization and transformation of “Ecclesiastes’s cyclical world view, its structure, and its
proverbs” seems par for the course. Apropos of that “structure,” however, Lansverk reports that
“[b]iblical scholars have not been able to find much identifiable progression of ideas” (140). (The book
here has structural difficulties of its own, as a doubling of footnote 17 throws the remaining 10 out of
sync.) Donald Ault’s work on embedded structure in <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound</hi> (1987) could usefully
be linked here (and to the discussion of “Blake’s Narrative Bound Proverbs” [173]). Lansverk argues that
the two passages from John with which Blake glosses <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>’s opening
“proverbs”—
<q>
Four Mighty Ones are in every man; a Perfect Unity<lb/>
Cannot Exist. but from the Universal Brotherhood of
Eden,<lb/>
The Universal Man, to Whom be Glory Evermore. Amen.
</q></p>
          <p>—together “comprise the central Gospel reference, the <hi rend="i">locus classicus</hi> . . .
to the power of performatives, and thus they can be seen to serve as a ‘functional key’ if not a
‘content key’ to Blake’s work” (151). John 17:21-23 and 1:14 read:
<q>
That they all may be one; as thou, Father, art in me, and I
in thee, that they also may be one in us: that the world
may believe that thou hast sent me.<lb/>
And the glory which thou gavest me I have given them;
that they may be one, even as we are one.<lb/>
I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect
in one; and that the world may know that thou hast sent
me, and hast loved them, as thou hast loved me.<lb/>
And the Word was made flesh, and dwelt among us . . .
</q></p>
          <p>I note here that Blake writes out the last phrase in the Greek, without accents or breathings,
“καιι εςκηνωςεν εν, ημιν” which sets up a multi-lingual clinch with the nearest word of
the poem proper, “Amen” (ημιν [“us”] could be transliterated “amin”): Hebrew ‘<hi
rend="i">amên</hi>, cognate with Wisdom as the “master architect”/ “little child,” 
<hi rend="i">‘amon.</hi> Being “just &amp; true to our own Imaginations” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Preface),
we become like unto “the Amen, the faithful and true witness”
<pb id="p31-87" n="87"/>
(Rev. 3:14) with a name “that no man knew” but which “name is called The Word of God” (Rev. 19:12,
13). The Johannine texts, writes Lansverk, “outline how Blake can lay claim to the performative power of God
demonstrated in Genesis,” and indicate “the importance of speech act to Blake’s use of proverbs”
(151). I will add that the pertinence of Wisdom’s <hi rend="i">eman</hi>ative name Amen for this argument
can be illustrated by Gustaf Dalman’s comment that, “Amen is affirmation, Amen is curse, Amen is making
something one’s own” (in <hi rend="i">Theological Dictionary of the Old Testament</hi>, eds. G. Johannes
Botterweck and <corr type="emend">Helmer Ringgren,</corr> trans. John T. Willis, vol. 1 [Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 1974] 322).</p>
          <p>So, in <hi rend="i">MIL/TON</hi>, “Blake’s Book of Infernal Wisdom,” such textual fiats
express the polymorphously erotic “sports of Wisdom in the Human Imagination” (3.3):
<q>
And it is thus Created. Lo the Eternal Great Humanity<lb/>
To whom be Glory &amp; Dominion Evermore Amen<lb/>
Walks among all his awful Family seen in every face<lb/>
As the breath of the Almighty, such are the words of man to man<lb/>
In the great Wars of Eternity, in fury of Poetic Inspiration<lb/>
To build the Universe stupendous: Mental forms Creating<lb/>
(30[33]. 15-20)
</q></p>
          <p>This is only one of many passages which allow Lansverk to characterize <hi rend="i">MIL/TON</hi>
as “a freestanding collection of proverbs, with the narrative parts simply providing a frame for the wisdom
statements as in the Book of Proverbs and Ecclesiastes” (173). Such statements are themselves thematized in
the poem’s references to “Dictates,” “a proverb in Eden,” “a prophecy in Eden,” and perhaps most
curiously, “gnomes.” In a provocative paper presented to the 1995 meeting of the Northwest Society for
Eighteenth-Century Studies, Lansverk notes S. Foster Damon’s suggestion that “‘Blake may have known that
a gnome also means a wise but cryptic saying,’” and argues that Blake surely knew the dominant reference
of “gnome” in his age. Indeed, in marking well <hi rend="i">MIL/TON</hi>’s words about the “servants
            of the Harrow, / The Gnomes” (7.18-19), it is striking to discover that <corr type="emend">subterranean</corr> gnomes only appear in
English with Pope’s <hi rend="i">Rape of the Lock</hi>, while the older reference flourishes in
“gnomic,” “gnomical,” “gnomographer,” “gnomologic,” and “gnomology”—as in Milton’s 
<hi rend="i">Tetrachordon</hi>: “Which art of powerful reclaiming, wisest men have also taught in their ethical
precepts and gnomologies” (<hi rend="i">OED</hi>, s.v.). <hi rend="i">MIL/TON</hi>’s depiction of
Palamabron
<q>
Curbing his living creatures; many of the strongest Gnomes<lb/>
They bit in their wild fury, who also madden’d like wildest beasts<lb/>
(7.46-47)
</q>
echoes strongly the language of the speaker of the deuterocanonical “Book of Wisdom” or “Wisdom of
Solomon,” who claims to be taught by wisdom and to know “[t]he natures of the living creatures, and the
furies of wild beasts” (7:20, AV version). (One would have thought that this quotation would also find some
bearing on Lansverk’s discussion [144] of “the Natures of those Living Creatures” at the opening of 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>) In my <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination</hi> (Berkeley: U of California P, 1983),
I posited a Blakean “ear/earth,” and it would seem that it is in such ground, “in the Auricular Nerves
of Human life / Which is the Earth of Eden” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 4.1-2), that the Gnomes labour to bring
forth, like Zen koans, the performative nature of wisdom.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The word “koan,” from Japanese <hi rend="i">ko</hi>, “public,” and
<hi rend="i">an</hi>, “matter, material for thought,” denotes “a paradox put to a student” to
stimulate the mind (<hi rend="i">OED Supplement</hi>)—like the image of Los’s response to the wild Gnomes,
when he “took off his left sandal placing it on his head, / Signal of solemn mourning” 
(<hi rend="i">M</hi> 8.11-12). In which context, the following koan, from the famous thirteenth-century Chinese
collection, <hi rend="i">Wumenguan</hi> or “The Bolt on a Nonexistent Door,” may not be amiss:
<q>
Because the monks of the eastern and western halls were fighting over a cat, Master Nanquan picked it up and
said, “If you can speak, I’ll spare the cat. If not, I’ll kill it.”<lb/>
No one replied, so Nanquan killed it.<lb/>
That evening Zhaozhou came back from somewhere else and Nanquan told him what had happened. Zhaozhou then took
off his sandals, put them on his head, and walked out. Nanquan said, “Had you been here, you could have
saved the cat.”
</q><p>In the course of his commentary on this koan, Thomas Cleary observes, “Zhaozhou’s farcical act
silently remarks that to be enslaved by something that originally was supposed to foster liberation is like
being worn by a pair of shoes instead of wearing them” (Thomas Cleary, trans., comm., <hi rend="i">No
Barrier: Unlocking the Zen Koan: A New Translation of the Zen Classic Wumenguan</hi> [New York: Bantam Books,
1993] 66, 68).</p></note></p>
          <p>Lansverk writes that “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is the study of how Blake’s central character
Milton learns to leave behind the affirmative utterances too characteristic of his Puritan works for the more
powerful and visionary performative utterances” (164) which he voices at the poem’s conclusion and which,
Lansverk feels, “comprise the climactic moment of the work: ‘Obey thou the Words of the Inspired Man . .
.’” (172). As if Satan, “To pervert the Divine voice in its entrance to the earth” (9.23), hadn’t
been spouting “obey my principles” (9.26) from the beginning. Lansverk should be more wary of so-called
“climax”: Milton talks the talk, but the walk he forces still, again, on Ololon. To apply the “moral”
which Lansverk finds earlier in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, we must attend to “what [the] prophets do
and not what [they] say, even though what [they] say is correct” (103). It’s not <hi rend="i">Ololon</hi>,
as Lansverk argues, who must “realize that she is Lady Wisdom” (170), but Milton and ourselves who read
her, as a result of his lack of recognition, in the “Double Six-fold Wonder” (42[49].4) of 
<hi rend="i">MIL/TON a Poem in 12</hi>
	<pb id="p31-88" n="88"/>
	<hi rend="i">Books.</hi> These objections can serve to exemplify Lansverk’s contention that “[t]he only
doctrine which . . . can fruitfully be said to underlie [<hi rend="i">MIL/TON</hi>] . . . is the doctrine of
contraries . . . here both as the opposition between . . . two ways of reading and in the very form of the
performative proverb, which ultimately amount to the same thing” (182-83).</p>
          <p>The Book of Wisdom says that “she is the breath of the power of God [cf. <hi rend="i">M</hi>
30[33]. 18, above], and a pure influence flowing from the glory of the Almighty: therefore can no defiled
thing fall unto her” (7:25; Lansverk fumbles this crucial quotation through misattribution and omission of
the central phrase [194])—that is, as the New Jerusalem Bible has it, “she is a breath of the power of
God, pure emanation of the glory of the Almighty” (and, for Blake, “all bionic” existence). The Greek of
the Septuagint has “aporroia” also as common in the neo-Platonists and translated, literally, as
“outflow,” “emanation.” Lansverk sees the plot of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem The Emanation of The Giant
Albion</hi> as “the story of Albion’s learning to treat Jerusalem as Lady Wisdom, his consort from the
very beginning, and not as the harlot she becomes when externalized from him as a sexual object” (193). This
entails the reader’s learning that “the Treasures of Heaven” are none other than “Mental Studies &amp;
Performances” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77). Lansverk comments that, “[t]hough the speech act theory to
identify Blake’s use of language would not be created for a hundred and fifty years, Blake could still point
the way, whether coincidentally or not . . . that to perform is ‘to do something,’ ‘to fulfill a
command,’ and most importantly ‘to present a literary work of art’” (196-97).</p>
          <p>Students and lovers of Blake can be grateful to Marvin Lansverk for this awakening call to the
rich fields of the poet’s sport with Wisdom and performative language.</p>
          <p>Unknown gnomes mine. pro-verbal proverbs. but, ah! men, Wisdom’s awful theopanatives love her.
language bombs</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
