<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>31.3.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s First Arrest, at Upnor Castle</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1997/98</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1997/98</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">31.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Vincent Carretta</name>
              <name>A. Harris Fairbanks</name>
              <name>Sarah Joyce</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Shelia A. Spector</name>
              <name>Frank A. Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1997/98"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_31">
    <body>
      <pb id="p31-82" n="82"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-31-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s First Arrest, at Upnor Castle</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>William Blake was a notably peaceable citizen, for all his radical, antinomian views. He may have
believed that “One Law for the Lion &amp; Ox is Oppression,’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">1</ref> and that “All Penal Laws court Transgression &amp; therefore are cruelty
&amp; Murder,’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">2</ref> but he lived
quietly within the laws. Only twice, so far as we know, did he offend the majesty of the law, and both times
he was released without a stain upon his character—though some scholars suspect that on the second occasion,
when he was tried for sedition in 1804, he may have escaped through a technicality rather than through genuine
innocence. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Marriage (?1790), pl. 24 (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Writings</hi> [1978], 27).</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Annotation to Watson (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> [1978],
1419).</note></p>
          <p>The second arrest, in 1804, is moderately well known because Blake himself wrote about it and a
good number of documents survive.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">3</ref> The
first however, is more slightly known, the facts are altogether sparser, and a new fact has recently appeared
which allows us for the first time to set it firmly in context. <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi
rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> (1969), 121-149, and <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> (1988)
24-28.</note></p>
          <p>When Blake was in his early twenties, he made friends with number of rising young artists such as
Thomas Stothard, the book-illustrator, John Flaxman, the sculptor, and George Cumberland, the inventor and
artist. It was perhaps about September 1780 that this first incident occurred. According to Stothard’s
daughter-in-law, Stothard would occasionally spend a few days with his friends in sailing up the Medway,
landing and sketching as they pleased. In one of these excursions he was accompanied by his old friend Mr.
Ogleby,
<q>
and Blake, . . . Whilst the trio were one day engaged with the pencil on shore, . . . some soldiers . . . very
unceremoniously made them prisoners, under the suspicion of their being spies for the French government; as
this country was then at war with France. . . . There were they detained, with a sentinel placed over them,
until intelligence could be received from certain members of the Royal Academy, to whom they appealed to
certify they were really peaceable subjects of his Majesty King George, and not spies for France.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Mrs. [A.E.] Bray, <hi rend="i">Life of Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London,
1851), 20-21, reprinted in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 19-20.</note></q></p>
          <p>Stothard made an etching of his sketch which is very rare. One copy is in the Balmanno Collection
of Stothard in the
                        <figure n="stothard-sketch-medway.031.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="931" height="818">
	<head>1 Thomas Stothard’s etching of his own design representing occasion when he, Blake, and another
friend were arrested while on a sketching expedition on the Medway.</head>
	<figDesc>This copy, from the collection of Robert N. Essick, emphasizes that the incident took place at Upnor
Castle.</figDesc>
</figure>
British Museum Print Room,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">5</ref> another is
in the Rosenwald Collection of the U.S. National Gallery of Art,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n13" type="note">6</ref> a third is with a collection of prints and drawings by Stothard formed by
George Cumberland in the Fitzwilliam Museum, and a fourth was recently acquired by Robert N. Essick.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">7</ref> This last previously unknown copy has an
inscription of some importance, though its authorship and authority are unknown:
<q>
This relates to Stothard and Blake who went on a sketching ramble and while they . . . [illegible] Upnor
Castle on the Medway were taken Prisoners as spies and detained by the garrison till they heard from London
the truth of the story [see pl. 1].
</q>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">5</hi> This is probably the copy reproduced by Mrs. Bray.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For its very puzzling inscription, see <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
(1969), 19 n.4; its identification of the third member of the sketching party as “Parkes” may refer to
Blake’s fellow-apprentice and later partner James Parker.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Described and reproduced in Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace,
1994,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 28 (1995), generously shown me in typescript.</note></p>
          <p>This is, of course, a much abbreviated account but it emphasizes the vital detail of where they
were arrested, and this in turn helps to explain why they were arrested. Until we knew where the incident took
place, it seemed a somewhat wanton abuse of military power, that such peaceable artists should have been so
rudely accused and confined.</p>
          <p>The Medway flows 60 miles east-north-eastward, mostly through Kent and if the sailing artists
were “sailing up the Medway” they must have begun at or near the mouth, at
<pb id="p31-83" n="83"/>
the estuary of the Thames. They had not travelled very far when they were arrested, for Upnor Castle, on Upnor
Reach, is only a few miles from the Channel, just east of Rochester, on the north bank of a sharp bend of the
Medway. The river here was wide and bucolic, and Upnor Castle was certainly picturesque, but the military
significance of Upnor Castle and its neighborhood would have been plainly visible to the most unworldly
artist. Chatham Docks, “the chief arsenal of the Royal Navy of Great Britain . . . one of the most
considerable in the world,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">8</ref> is just
across the river from Upnor Castle, and on occasion as many as 40 men-of-war might be seen moored there
together. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Anon., <hi rend="i">The Picturesque Beauties of Great Britain:
Illustrated by . . . Original Designs Taken upon the Spot: Kent</hi> (London: George Virtue . . . [1830])
19-20.</note></p>
		<q>
UPNOR-Castle, is . . . about over against the famous Dock in <hi rend="i">Chatham</hi>; it was built by Queen
<hi rend="i">Elizabeth</hi>, in the Third Year of her Reign [1561], for the Defence of the River 
<hi rend="i">Medway</hi>; where the greatest Part of the Royal Navy usually lye at their Moorings, and for the
Security of the aforesaid Dock.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">9</hi> John Harris, <hi rend="i">The History of Kent</hi>, Vol. I (London: D.
Midwinter, 1719) 1: 386. According to Harris, “In the Castle are about 37 Guns,” and down river are
several other batteries, but eighty years later the armaments of the Castle had been allowed to deteriorate to
a pathetic state.</note></q>
          <p>The docks were established in the reign of Charles II, and they were vigorously extended during
Blake’s youth and early manhood. Anyone reading the newspapers in London a few miles away was likely to have
been aware of such developments.</p>
		<q>
In 1758, when this country was threatened by invasion from the French, the elaborate fortification, called the
<hi rend="i">Lines</hi>, were commenced, extending from the Medway, above the Ordnance Wharf, measuring half a
mile in width and a mile in breadth, extending beyond the limits of the Dock-yard, where they again unite with
the river. Within this area, besides the naval establishments, are included the <hi rend="i">Upper</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Lower Barracks</hi>, the church of Chatham, and the hamlet of Brompton; containing about five
hundred dwellings. Various important additions have since been made, as in 1782 an Act passed for the purchase
of lands, for the further security of this great natural depôt.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Anon., <hi rend="i">The Picturesque Beauties of Great Britain:
Illustrated by . . . Original Designs Taken upon the Spot: Kent</hi> (London: George Virtue . . . [1830])
21.</note></q>
          <p>However, Stothard and Blake were not the only artists to ignore the presence of military power at
Upnor Castle, to their peril. In 1791 Samuel Ireland made a series of <hi rend="i">Picturesque Views on the
River Medway</hi> from the Nore to the Vicinity of its Source, and when he came to Upnor Castle he had an
experience strikingly similar to that of Blake and Stothard some 10 years before. He made a sketch of Upnor
Castle with impunity, but his next sketch was fraught with peril.</p>
		<q>
Upnor castle, considered as a pleasing object of the picturesque kind, on the banks of the river, draws our
warmest commendation, but, as a place of natural defence, I fear, has never answered any purpose whatever; yet
it must be allowed to have its merits as a place of snug security for the governor, storekeeper, clerk of the
cheque, &amp;c. &amp;c. The governor has command of all the forts on the river except Sheerness. . . .<lb/>
Such was the shamefully neglected state of the castle that there were only four guns fit for use, mounted
within it, at the time the Dutch made their bold attempt up the river in the reign of Charles II. At present
it has no platform, nor yet one gun mounted, which, for the author of this work, was probably a fortunate
circumstance, as he had fixed his station very near it while making the annexed sketch of the castle.<lb/>
Other mischiefs, however, seemed to await him, for, while he was peaceably situated beneath the stern of a man
of war, to keep under the wind, he was visited by a person from on board, who claimed the privilege of taking
him before the Commissioner in Chatham yard, to answer for his rash attempt on this noble place of
defence.<lb/>
Having satisfied Commissioner Probyn that he had no insidious design against the navy, he was suffered to
depart in peace ....<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Samuel Ireland, <hi rend="i">Picturesque Views on the River Medway from
the <corr type="emend">Nore to</corr> the Vicinity of its Source</hi> (London: T. &amp; J. Egerton, 1793) 36-37.</note></q>
          <p>It is perhaps little wonder that while Ireland was sheltering from the wind under the stern of a
man-of-war his bona fides were suspected.</p>
          <p>In Stothard’s sketch there is no indication of Upnor Castle, but presumably it is just out of
sight. There are only two figures there, one of them apparently still sketching, but of course Stothard
himself, who made the sketch, is invisible.</p>
          <p>But what are these artists doing making landscape-sketches at all? Stothard was a figure painter,
whose forte was (or became) charming book-illustrations on a small scale, and Blake is scarcely known to have
made landscapes. How curious that these young men whose penchant was so strongly for the human figure should
have been out sketching landscapes at all.</p>
          <p>But perhaps they were carrying out a student assignment for the Royal Academy Schools. It is
striking that when Ireland was haled before the authorities he talked himself out of his difficulty but that
Blake, Stothard, et al. had to have their stories verified by members of the Royal Academy. If they had
claimed that they were sketching for the Royal
<pb id="p31-84" n="84"/>
Academy Schools, it would have been natural for the story to be confirmed from the Royal Academy itself. And
indeed the military may have wondered why the Royal Academy was sending its students to represent military
installations.</p>
          <p>Of course the Academy had not done anything of the kind. But the unworldliness of these young
men, blithely making careful sketches (like that in Stothard’s etching) of military fortifications of the
greatest naval base in the world in time of war, almost surpasses comprehension. At least it might appear so
to naval intelligence, if that is not an oxymoron.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
