<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>31.3.joyce</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Thomas, dir., South Bank Show Documentary on Blake</title>
        <author n="Joyce">Sarah Joyce</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1997/98</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1997/98</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">31.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Vincent Carretta</name>
              <name>A. Harris Fairbanks</name>
              <name>Sarah Joyce</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Shelia A. Spector</name>
              <name>Frank A. Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1997/98"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_31">
    <body>
	<pb id="p31-102" n="102"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-31-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">South Bank Show Documentary on Blake. Directed by David Thomas. ITV (U.K.), 17
September 1995.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Sarah <name>Joyce</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>On 17 September 1995, ITV’s South Bank Show screened a one-hour documentary on William Blake.
It was directed at newcomers or rather, since no one in the British Isles is exempt from knowledge of at least
one Blake lyric, at those who had only encountered his most famous productions. Accordingly, the program
included biographical material, broad discussions of Blake’s beliefs, and brief consideration of some of his
writings, paintings and prints. It could easily have been disappointing for the already initiated scholar, but
in fact it was a very appealing program, made with a great enthusiasm for Blake, and an impulse to celebrate
as well as to inform.</p>
          <p>One manifestation of this enthusiasm was the ebullient claims made for Blake’s literary status
by Peter Ackroyd, who was an important presence throughout the film. He praised Blake “the greatest
religious poet England has ever produced” as well as “the greatest poet of London,” finally placing him
in the ultimate English canon: “His vision is so prescient, his poetry and painting, so marvelous, that he
is of the same stature as Milton, as Chaucer, as Shakespeare.” Whilst the scope of the program did not
enable it to reward such eulogy with careful analysis, it did succeed in presenting what seemed to me an
accurate and moving account of some of the reasons why Blake is so cherished by his twentieth century
public.</p>
          <p>At the heart of the documentary was the vision of Blake as the lonely, unrecognized genius,
dramatically represented by Michael Loughnan, who performed extracts from Elliot Hayes’s play, 
<hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience</hi> [see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 29 (1995/96): 97]. Amidst drying
impressions of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plates, Loughnan’s Blake worked alone in his studio, frequently
bursting into prophetic monologue although unvisited but for the brief appearance of the Archangel Gabriel.
Ackroyd insisted that Blake’s isolated labors were not the work of “some solitary visionary in a
garret,” but of an ordinary Londoner with extraordinary commitment: “earning his living all his life and
only able to work on his own time.”</p>
          <p>Blake’s ability to complete works that were doomed to near obscurity in his own lifetime was
much admired in the film, and is indeed one of the most fascinating aspects of his achievement. In Ackroyd’s
estimation, this prodigious triumph over isolation was made possible by the very phenomenon that caused it:
the visions. Blake’s engrossing private spirit world certainly caused him professional problems, condemning
him to poverty and much neglect, but, if Blake is to be believed, it also compelled his creativity utterly,
providing him with both the substance of his works and the strength to beat down despair and labor upwards
into futurity.</p>
          <p>Ackroyd also argued that it was Blake’s alienation, intensified after the catastrophe at
Felpham, that gave him his insightfulness about the society that had rejected him, and his deep compassion
towards the suffering that he saw throughout that society. He considers the inclusiveness of Blake’s social
vision as one of his truly prescient insights, which would not find a popular echo until our own century. He
cited the egalitarian stance of “The Little Black Boy,” as well as the following couplet from “Auguries
of Innocence” in which Blake insists upon the ethical relevance of animal suffering:
<q>
Each outcry of the hunted Hare<lb/>
A fibre from the Brain does tear.
</q></p>
          <p>In the same poem, Allen Ginsberg finds a startling precedent for a modern critique of the
societies responsible for producing widespread destitution as well as the damage to the ozone layer:
<q>
The Beggar’s Rags, fluttering in Air,<lb/>
Does to Rags the Heavens tear.
</q></p>
          <p>Much of the documentary was filmed in London’s streets and open spaces, strongly suggesting
that Blake’s vision “London, a Human awful wonder of God!” a vision of our London. This sense of
continuity was powerfully communicated by the director’s combining panoramic photography of London’s modem
skyline, with Loughnan’s delivery of Blake’s poetry about the city. The powerfully compassionate poem
“London” was spoken over a silent film of familiar London streets with their traffic of cars and ordinary
people bearing the “Marks of weakness, mark of
<pb id="p31-103" n="103"/>
Woe” of our own period. Blake’s joyful epiphanies were also rehearsed in modern London: the innumerable
heavenly host crying “Holy Holy Holy is the Lord God Almighty,” and the tree full of glistening angels on
Peckham Rye.</p>
          <p>The program’s use of Blake’s own words was a very successful strategy. Performances of his
poetry by Loughnan and by Allen Ginsberg did justice to Blake in a way that some of the invented monologues
did not. Ginsberg’s delivery of Blake was fascinating and oddly compelling. Reading the words from a
facsimile, he sang the “Introduction” to the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and “The Tyger,” in
an improvised recitative style with a rhythmic accompaniment from a hand-held pump organ. The effect was
completely unlike an ordinary folk ballad, such as “The Maid of Islington,” which was featured in the
program: it was much more direct and intense, more bardic perhaps. The performance of “The Tyger” was
surprisingly pacy and joyful, dispensing with the fear which the poem can evoke when spoken aloud, but
retaining the sense of awe.</p>
          <p>As well as Blake admirers from the literary and artistic worlds, the film featured
representatives of modern science and commerce: the biologist Rupert Sheldrake and the industrialist Peter
Parke. Sheldrake echoed Blake’s critique of Newtonian abstraction, blaming this kind of science for causing
radical damage to our civilization: “It has split the sciences from the arts. It has split science from
religion. It has fragmented our whole culture.” He predicted that the science of the future would validate
Blake’s objection to the dead mechanistic universe posited by Newton. The world of future science would be
“a living world. A world permeated by consciousness and spirit, full of life and quality.”</p>
          <p>Peter Parker said that “The Sick Rose” had changed his life, opening up a channel of Blakean
influence throughout his career. This has amounted to a conviction that Blake’s anti-materialist stance, his
determination to see through the eye, not with it, is “crucial to the health of modern society.” In the
spring 1995 inaugural edition of <hi rend="i">The Journal of the Blake Society at St James’s</hi>, he wrote
that Blake’s refusal to be dominated by reductive rationalistic thinking had fed directly into his own
attitude to management: “His purpose was not to generalise, but to raise the faculties of the individual to
action against poverty, privilege, cruelty and inequalities to sex or race, intolerance - in short,
unimaginativeness.” Blake’s rejection of Newton’s dead world has become an ethical imperative to see
human situations as particularly and minutely as possible. The documentary both began and ended with the hymn
usually known as “Jerusalem” (And did those feet”) Ackroyd pointed out the incongruity between the
patriotic emotions usually associated with the hymn and Blake’s own attitude to the monarchy and the
Established Church. However, as Parry’s music soared to its final crescendo and the camera came to rest upon
the rapt features of the engraved Blake portrait after Phillips, I felt that this most famous lyric may have
attained its hold on the British public partly through Blakean merits of its own, similar to those which the
documentary had celebrated. What we find in Blake is a yearning for vision, a capacity for faith, and a mighty
determination to transcend the empty cruelty of nature and create a world full of meaning and value, to build
Jerusalem amongst the dark satanic mills.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
