<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.1.groves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake, the Edinburgh Literary Journal, and James Hogg</title>
        <author n="Groves">David Groves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1998</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
      <pb id="p32-14" n="14"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake, the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi>, and James Hogg</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>David <name>Groves</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi> was a weekly magazine of 1828-1832, founded by a
25-year-old law student named Henry Glassford Bell.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">1</ref> It normally ran to 14 pages plus advertisements, and it claimed a circulation of about
2000.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">2</ref> Published by the Constable
firm, the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi> was in some ways a continuation of Constable’s
defunct <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi>, where an important review of Blake had appeared in 1808.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">3</ref> Although Bell’s <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>
has been largely ignored by scholars, it was a colorful, sprightly magazine, which carried short works by
Shelley<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">4</ref> and other British authors
like John Lockhart (editor of London’s <hi rend="i">Quarterly Review)</hi>, Allan Cunningham (the friend of
Thomas De Quincey), Robert Morehead (a former editor of the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi>), the dramatist
James Sheridan Knowles, and poets Alexander Balfour and William Tennant.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">5</ref> The <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> became controversial among
Scottish periodicals by its outspoken attacks on the Scots novelist John Galt,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">6</ref> and on <hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</hi> and
the powerful Blackwood firm in general.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Bell (1803-74) edited the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> until the middle of
1830 (see W. Norrie, <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Newspapers Past and Present</hi> [Edinburgh: Waverley, 1891] 19).
From 1830 to 1839, Bell worked as a lawyer, and from then to 1868 he was Sheriff-Substitute in Glasgow. His
correspondence would likely be interesting, if it could be found. The best account of his life is an obituary
in the <hi rend="i">Journal of Jurisprudence</hi> (18 (1874]: 97-103: see also anon., <hi rend="i">Memoirs and
Portraits of One Hundred Glasgow Men</hi>, 2 vols. [Glasgow; Maclehose, 1886] 1: 29-32).</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “The circulation of every number has . . . exceeded fifteen hundred
copies, whilst that of several has extended to . . . twenty-five hundred” (anon., “A Few Words Concerning
our own Affairs,” <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi>, 1 (14 March 1829): 241-43).</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">3</hi> A review in the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> of 27 February 1830 describes
the Constable firm as “our own publishers” (3:123n.). The 1808 review of Blake in Constable’s 
<hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> is reprinted in my article, “Blake, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and Edinburgh
Literary Society” (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 24 [1991] 251-52).</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The link with Shelley illustrates the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s ties
with the old <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine.</hi> In 1810, Shelley sent his poem “A Wandering Jew” to
Archibald Constable, but it was still unpublished when the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> folded in 1826.
Somehow the poem was transferred to Bell’s <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>, where excerpts from it appeared on 27
June 1829 (2: 43-45). See <hi rend="i">The Letters of Percy Bysshe Shelley</hi> ed. F. L. Jones (Oxford:
Clarendon, 1964) 1: 17n-18n. This connection between the two journals may perhaps shed light on the
coincidence of their two articles on Blake, separated by almost the same long interval.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">5</hi> A list of contributors appeared in the article cited in note 2
(above).</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">6</hi> The attacks reached a zenith in 1830, when the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>
charged Galt with “disgrac(ing) the history of English literature” (4:165). Dislike of Galt’s pedestrian
prose may help to explain the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s interest in Blake and Hogg.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">7</hi> In the article cited in note 2 (above), readers were told that William
Blackwood declined sending “any further review copies of his books to the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>;
“unless we consent to praise every one of (his] publications,” the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> added
sarcastically, “we shall receive no support from him!”</note></p>
          <p>But the Journal’s most famous contributor was the poet and novelist James Hogg, “the Ettrick
Shepherd.” Although Hogg would turn 60 in 1830, he was a close friend of Bell’s<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">8</ref> and his tales, poems, and essays made Hogg the 
<hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s most frequent contributor of signed works. During the three-and-a-quarter years of
its existence, the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi> published more pieces by Hogg than did any
other publication. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Their friendship is discussed in my booklet, 
<hi rend="i">James Hogg and the St Ronan’s Border Club</hi> (Dollar [Scotland]: Mack, 1987).</note></p>
          <p>There are reasons to suspect that the “Ettrick Shepherd” played something of an advisory or
quasi-editorial role in the <hi rend="i">Journal.</hi> Henry Bell’s youth, and the fact that he was never
again an editor, nor at any time a figure of much literary importance, invites the suspicion that Hogg was a
guiding spirit. Moreover, the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s very first issue carried a letter of support from
Hogg, praising its independence, and promising to support it with his writings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">9</ref> The new periodical probably owed much of its success to this
and other contributions by Hogg. <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The letter also criticized 
<hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Magazine</hi> for being “devoted to party, not only in politics,” but also “in
literature” (“A Letter from Yarrow; The Ettrick Shepherd to the Editor,” 1 [15 Nov. 1828]: 9-10). At the
time, Hogg needed an ally in his simmering dispute with Blackwood. John Wilson, who was the chief writer for
<hi rend="i">Blackwood’s</hi>, told Blackwood that Hogg “deserved punishment” for siding with the
“enemy,” Bell; “I would see [Hogg] damned before I ever again printed one article of his” (undated
letter, National Library of Scotland MS 4028, folio 333; cited by permission of the Trustees of the NLS). Hogg
perhaps needed to keep his behind-the-scenes influence with the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> a secret, in order
to avoid a final rift with Blackwood.</note></p>
          <p>In 1830, the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi> published three favorable, anonymous
reviews of the second and third volumes of Allan Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British
Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi>, The second of the three discusses Cunningham’s account of the
painters Benjamin West, James Barry, and William Blake. Although the remarks on Blake are not illuminating,
they at least show that he was a figure of some interest in literary Edinburgh:
<q>
To Barry succeeds Blake—a poet-painter, whose enthusiastic imagination taught him to believe that he held
converse with the world of spirits, and who painted not so much from existing nature, as from the shapes which
were continually presenting themselves to him in his daydreams. He was nevertheless one of the happiest of his
race; and, whether it be singular or not, this happiness is mainly to be attributed to his wife, concerning
whom we have the following particulars: . . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">10</ref><lb/>
This excellent woman—whose character partly reminds
<pb id="p32-15" n="15"/>
us of Klopstock’s Meeta—was true to him to the last, and, after a long life of mutual affection. we find
her soothing him on his death-bed: . . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">11</ref><lb/>
The affection and fortitude of Mrs Blake, entitle her to much respect. “She shared her husband’s lot,”
says Mr Cunningham, “without a murmur,—set her heart solely upon his family and soothed him in those hours
of misgiving and despondency, which are not unknown to the strongest intellects. She still lives to lament the
loss of Blake, and <hi rend="i">feel</hi> it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">10</hi> An excerpt consisting of two paragraphs from Cunningham’s book
follows—The excerpt begins, “When he was six-and-twenty years,” and ends, “whenever he chose to see
them” (see <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi>, 6 vols.
(London: Murray, [1829], 2: 147-48). In the review, the excerpt is given the title “BLAKE’S COURTSHIP AND
MARRIAGE.” Each of the excerpts in this review has minor changes of punctuation and capitalization.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">11</hi> An excerpt of three paragraphs from Cunningham follows. it begins, “He
had now reached,” and ends “when he ceased breathing” (<hi rend="i">Lives</hi>, 2: 175-76). In the
review, the excerpt is entitled “BLAKE’S LAST ILLNESS AND DEATH.” “Meeta” was the wife of the Danish
poet Immanuel Klopstock.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Anon. rev. in The <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal: Or, Weekly
Register of Criticism and Belles Lettres</hi>, 2 (20 Feb. 1830): 112-15 (113-14).
                                <p>The quotation about Catherine Blake is from Cunningham’s 
<hi rend="i">Lives</hi> (2: 179). The other reviews of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> appeared in the 
<hi rend="i">Journal</hi> on 25 July 1829 (2: 101-04), 13 Feb. 1830 (3: 101-02), 12 June 1830 (4: 338-39), and 12
Feb. 1831 (6: 106-07). No other volumes by Cunningham received comparable attention in the 
<hi rend="i">Journal.</hi></p></note></q></p>
          <p>No one will learn much about Blake’s art here. But the comments are interesting for their
sympathetic account of his temperament, “enthusiastic imagination,” and spiritual beliefs. The information
that Blake was both poet and painter, may have been news to some northern readers in 1830.</p>
          <p>Nothing in the review betrays the identity of its author. Bell himself was probably the 
<hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s most frequent critic,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">13</ref> and a likely candidate, therefore, for the authorship of this one. But some external
evidence suggests that James Hogg may have played a part, either in writing the notices of Cunningham, or at
least in seeing that they appeared in the <hi rend="i">Journal.</hi> Hogg was certainly one of the 
<hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s reviewers,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">14</ref>
and, unlike Bell and its other regulars, he had been a friend and correspondent of Allan Cunningham’s for
almost three decades.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">15</ref> The evidence
which seems to link Hogg to the lines on Blake begins with an accusation, by an English critic in 1831, that
Hogg was in the habit of supplying the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> with anonymous panegyrics for Cunningham. The
accusation was as follows: “See Hogg’s praise of Cunningham in the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary
Journal</hi>, &amp;c.; and Allan’s praise of the Shepherd [i.e., Hogg] in the [London] Athenaeum,
etc.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Bell “did the editorial work” for the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>, and
his “contributions . . . in prose . . . were constant and varied” (Obituary, cited in note 1 [above] 98).
A contemporary review of the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> found that “Mr Bell [has] few rivals” “In the
critical department” (anon., <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Observer</hi>, 1 Jan. 1830 (p. 41).</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Its review of <hi rend="i">The Life of Alexander Alexander</hi>, “By
the Ettrick Shepherd” (4 [1830] 280-82) was the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s only signed review.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Cunningham (1784-1832) moved to London around 1810. He never returned to
Scotland, until his visit to Hogg in 1831. It is unlikely that Cunningham knew many of the 
<hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s writers (most of whom were much younger, and little-known outside Scotland).
Hogg’s reminiscence, “My first Interview with Allan Cunningham,” appeared in the 
<hi rend="i">Journal</hi> on 16 May 1829 (1: 374-75).</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Alaric A. Watts, note to his poem “The Conversazione,” in 
<hi rend="i">The Literary Souvenir</hi> for 1832, ed. Watts (London: Longman, 1831) 224n.</note></p>
          <p>Although the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> denied this hint, it did so in a rather ingenious way, by
pretending that the charge referred solely to a paragraph about a public dinner given to Cunningham.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">17</ref> “Hogg did not write the paragraph,” the
<hi rend="i">Journal</hi> replied; “his accuser could have no reason to believe that he did, but his own
dirty suspicions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">18</ref> That statement
raises more questions than it answers. It does not by any means refute the claim that Hogg used his influence
in the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> to praise Allan Cunningham. Moreover, the paragraph about Cunningham’s
dinner was merely an impartial account,—whereas the complaint from England referred explicitly to
“praise” and “panegyric”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">19</ref> of
Cunningham. In pretending that the English critic was referring to this paragraph, the 
<hi rend="i">Journal</hi> side-stepped his challenge, in a way that seems a little suspicious. A reply so evasive
leaves us free to wonder if Hogg did indeed have a hand in the paragraphs about Blake. 
<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The untitled, unsigned paragraph appeared in the “Literary Chit-Chat and Varieties”
column, 6 (30 July 1831): 71.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Anon., “Mr Alaric Watts,” <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary
Journal</hi> 6 (29 Oct. 1831): 260.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Watts, note to “The Conversazione” 223n.</note></p>
          <p>Some readers of Bell’s <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> may have noticed that much of the passage on
Blake would have applied with equal justice to the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>’s own main poet, James Hogg.
Hogg, too, maintained (as the review says of Blake) “that he held converse with the world of spirits.” In
a poem of the same year, Hogg inveighed against the rationalism that was turning “people now-a-days” into
“mere machines,”
<q>
Pruned vegetables—flowers of formal cut;<lb/>
A class of nature wholly by itself;<lb/>
And <hi rend="i">not</hi> as relatives of heaven and hell,<lb/>
And all the mighty energies between . . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">20</hi> “A Real Vision: By the Ettrick Shepherd,” 
<hi rend="i">Blackwood’s</hi> 28 (July 1830): 63-65.</note></q></p>
          <p>Hogg also enjoyed (as the review says of Blake) a happy marriage. His good spirits (again like
Blake, according to the review) were almost proverbial, in spite of discouraging treatment from publishers and
critics. Finally, Hogg somewhat resembled Blake in cultivating an image of himself as a writer unrestrained by
“cold ungenial rules,” and free to explore the “boundless wilderness” of existence, like a “meteor
of the wild”:
<q>
To gleam to tremble and to die<lb/>
’Tis Nature’s error—so am I<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">21</hi> “To Miss M.A.C — E” (1832; rpt. in <hi rend="i">James Hogg:
Selected Poems and Songs</hi>, ed. D. Groves [Edinburgh: Scottish Academic Press, [1986]: 203-04
(204).</note></q></p>
          <pb id="p32-16" n="16"/>
          <p>If any readers in 1830 considered these affinities between Blake and Hogg, they may also have
recalled the cryptic allusion to “W — m B — e, a great original,” in the ending of Hogg’s greatest
novel, six years earlier.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Hogg, <hi rend="i">The Private Memoirs and Confessions of a Justified
Sinner</hi>, ed. D. Groves (Edinburgh, Canongate, 1991) 202. Some connections between Blake and Hogg are
suggested in my articles “Blake, Thomas Boston, and the Fourfold Vision” (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19
[1986]: 142) and “‘W — m B — e, a Great Original’; William Blake, The Grave, and James Hogg’s 
<hi rend="i">Confessions</hi>” (<hi rend="i">Scottish Literary Journal</hi>, 18 [1991]: 27-45).</note></p>
          <p>Yet in spite of tempting evidence, none of the reviews of Cunningham in the 
<hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi> can be proved to be Hogg’s. The most that may safely be claimed is
that Hogg probably saw, and enjoyed, those reviews, and he probably read their comments on Blake. Like some
readers of the <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>, he may also have noticed the similarities between himself and Blake
which that passage seems to suggest.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
