<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.1.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">“Dear Generous Cumberland”: A Newly Discovered Letter and Poem by William
Blake</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1998</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
      <pb id="p32-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Dear Generous Cumberland”: A Newly Discovered Letter and Poem by William
Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor> and <docAuthor>Morton D.
<name>Paley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The discovery of a letter by William Blake to one of his more intimate correspondents is a rare
and signal event. In the 1960s, two letters to William Hayley came to light. Both, however, had been recorded,
with brief summaries and extracts, in a Sotheby’s auction catalogue of 1878.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> It has been many more decades since a wholly unrecorded letter
has emerged. The present essay announces just such a discovery: a previously unknown letter by Blake to his
friend of many years, George Cumberland, posted on 1 September 1800, just three weeks before Blake and his
wife Catherine moved from the London suburb of Lambeth to Felpham on the Sussex coast. This letter was first
brought to the attention of Morton D. Paley by its previous owner, a private British collector, in the summer
of 1997. With the help of the San Francisco dealer John Windle, the letter was acquired by Robert N. Essick in
November of the same year. A transcription follows:
<q>
[addressed as follows]<lb/>
<lb/>
M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Cumberland<lb/>
Bishopsgate<lb/>
Windsor Great Park<lb/>
<lb/>
[<hi rend="i">Written sideways in pencil at left in another hand</hi>] W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake 1800<lb/>
<lb/>
My Dear Cumberland<lb/>
<lb/>
To have obtained your friendship is better than to have sold ten thousand books. I am now upon the verge of a
happy alteration in my life which you will join with my London friends in Giving me joy of — It is an
alteration in my situation on the surface of this dull Planet I have taken a Cottage at Felpham on the Sea
Shore of Sussex between Arundel &amp; Chichester. M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Hayley the Poet is [<hi rend="i">next 3
words inserted</hi>] soon to be my neighbour he is now my friend. to him I owe the happy suggestion for it was
on a visit to him that I fell in love with my Cottage. I have now better prospects than ever The little I want
will be easily supplied he has given me a twelvemonths work already. &amp; there is a great deal more in
prospect I call myself now Independent. I can be Poet Painter &amp; [<hi rend="i">written over f</hi>]
Musician as the Inspiration comes. And now I take this first oppor [<hi rend="i">line break</hi>] -tunity to
Invite you down to Felpham we lie on a Pleasant shore it is within a mile of Bognor to which our Fashionables
resort My Cottage faces the South about a Quarter of a Mile from the Sea, only corn Fields between. tell M<hi
rend="s">rs</hi> Cumberland that my Wife thirsts for the opportunity to Entertain her at our Cottage<lb/>
Your Vision of the Happy Sophis I have devourd. O most delicious book how canst thou Expect any thing but Envy
in Londons accursed walls. You have my dear friend given me a task which I have endeavourd to fulfill I have
given a sketch of your Propo[<hi rend="i">line break</hi>] -sal to the Editor of the Monthly Magazine desiring
that he will [<hi rend="i">page ends</hi>] give it to the Public hope he will do so. I have shown your
Bonasoni to M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Hawkins my friend desiring that he will place your Proposal to the account of
its real author. wherever he goes<lb/>
How Sorry I am that you should ever be Ill. it also gives me pain to hear that you intend to leave Bishopsgate
&amp; it would give me more pleasure to hear that Sussex was preferred by you to Somersetshire But wherever
you Go God bless you.<lb/>
Perhaps I ought to give you My Letter to the Editor of the Monthly Mag. It is this<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
<lb/>
Your Magazine being so universally Read induces me to recommend to your notice a Proposal made some years ago
in a Life of Julio Bonasoni which Proposal ought to be given to the Public in Every work of the nature of
yours. It is. For the Erection of National Galleries for the Reception of Casts in Plaster from all the
Beautiful Antique. Statues Basso Relivos &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> that can be procured at home or abroad.
Which Galleries may be built &amp; filled by Public Subscription To be open to The Public. Their Use would be
To Correct &amp; Determine Public Taste as well as to be Treasures of Study for Artists. If you think 
[<hi rend="i">page ends</hi>] that this Proposal is of the Consequence that it appears to me to be, You will
Extract the Authors own words &amp; give them in your valuable Magazine. The Work is Intitled “Some
Anecdotes of the Life of Julio Bonasoni &amp; [<hi rend="i">next 3 words inserted</hi>] by George Cumberland
Publishd by Robinsons Paternoster Row 1793<lb/>
<lb/>
Yours W. B.<lb/>
<pb id="p32-5" n="5"/>
I so little understand the way to get such things into Magazines or News papers that if I have done wrong in
Merely delivering the Letter at the Publishers of the Magazine beg you will inform me<lb/>
My Wife joins with me in Love &amp; Respect to yourself &amp; familly<lb/>
<lb/>
I am Your devoted artist<lb/>
Will<hi rend="s">m</hi> Blake
</q>
PS. I hope to be Settled in Sussex before the End of September it is certainly the sweetest country upon the
face of the Earth
<q>
Dear Generous Cumberland nobly solicitous for a Friends welfare. Behold me<lb/>
Whom your Friendship has Magnified: Rending the manacles of Londons Dungeon dark<lb/>
I have rent the black net &amp; escap’d. See My Cottage at Felpham in joy<lb/>
Beams over the Sea, a bright light over France, but the Web &amp; the Veil I have left<lb/>
Behind me at London resists every beam of light; hanging from heaven to Earth<lb/>
Dropping with human gore. Lo! I have left it! I have torn it from my limbs<lb/>
I shake my wings ready to take my flight! Pale, Ghastly pale: stands the City in fear
</q>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Catalogue of a Valuable Collection of Autograph Letters,
Forming the Hayley Correspondence</hi>, Sotheby, Wilkinson, and Hodge, 20-22 May 1878, lot 21, letter of 16
July 1804 (£.3.1s. to Naylor); and lot 26, letter of 4 December 1804 (£4 to Naylor). These two letters were
first printed in full in George Mills Harper, “Blake’s Lost Letter to Hayley, 4 December 1804,” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Philology</hi> 61 (1964): 573-85; and Frederick W. Hilles, “A ‘New’ Blake Letter [of
16 July 1804],” <hi rend="i">Yale Review</hi> 57 (1967): 85-89.</note></p>
          <p>The subject of this letter was a momentous one for Blake, a change in residence that would begin
a new phase of his life. The references to Felpham in this letter are the first to appear in his writings. As
is well known, he had decided to move there in order to be employed as an artist and engraver for William
Hayley’s various projects, the most important of which was his biography of William Cowper. Blake had come
on an extended visit early in July 1800, and by 11 August we find Hayley writing that “the ingenious Blake .
. . appeared the happiest of human Beings on his prospect of inhabiting a marine Cottage in this pleasant
village. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> In a letter of 12
September, Blake would inform John Flaxman that “every thing is nearly completed for our removal [from]
&lt;to&gt; Felpham.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Letter to John Hawkins, printed in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969) 72. This letter was previously published in a book of
correspondence by and to Hawkins: <hi rend="i">I am, my dear Sir</hi>. . ., ed. Francis W. Steer (Chichester:
privately printed, 1959) 4.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David
V. Erdman (Garden City, New York: rev. ed., 1988) 756. This edition is hereafter cited as E.</note></p>
          <p>The move to Felpham was, as we see in Blake’s letter, associated in his mind with artistic
independence. He would begin with a commission from Hayley for “a twelvemonths work.” This was probably
the series of heads of poets for Hayley’s library, on which Blake reported himself well engaged on 26
November 1800.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Interestingly, in this
passage Blake confers equal status to his activities as “Musician” to those as poet and painter. This both
confirms the importance music had for Blake and establishes that he did compose music, though presumably he
did not know musical notation. That Blake wrote music for his poems has long been reported. John Thomas Smith,
author of <hi rend="i">Nollekens and His Times</hi> (1828), heard Blake sing his songs early in his career,
when he frequented the gatherings of the Rev. and Mrs. Anthony Mathew:
<q>
Much about this time, Blake wrote many other songs, to which he also composed tunes. These he would
occasionally sing to his friends; and though, according to his confession, he was entirely unacquainted with
the science of music, his ear was so good, that his tunes were sometimes most singularly beautiful, and were
noted down by musical professors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Letter to Hayley, E 714. In the event, the 18 heads, interspersed with
other projects, may have taken more than a year to complete. Martin Butlin dates them c. 1800-03; see 
<hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1981)
1: 297.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 457. Allan Cunningham
(1784-1842), who did not know Blake, reported on the basis of an unknown authority that composing music was
integral to Blake’s creative process in the later 1780s:
<q>
In sketching designs, engraving plates, writing songs, and composing music, he employed his time. . . . As he
drew the figure he meditated the song which was to accompany it, and the music to which the verse was to be
sung, was the offspring of the same moment. Of his music there are no specimens . . .
</q>
—<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 482, from <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters,
Sculptors, and Architects</hi> (1830).
                            </note></q></p>
          <p>That Blake did indeed spend some of his time at Felpham as “Musician” when the
“Inspiration” came is attested by the Oxford student Edward Garrard Marsh in a letter to William Hayley in
which Marsh mentions “The hymn, which inspired our friend, whom I have some idea, I mistitled a poetical
sculptor instead of a poetical engraver. . . .” This must refer to Blake, though the hymn that inspired may
not have been written by Blake. However, Marsh goes on to say in the same letter:
<q>
I long to hear M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Blake’s devotional air, though I should have been very aukward 
[<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] in the attempt to give notes to his music. His ingenuity will however (I doubt not)
discover some method of preserving his compositions upon paper, though he is not very well versed in bars and
crotchets.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Original letter in the collection of Robert N. Essick. First published in
Essick, “Blake, Hayley, and Edward Garrard Marsh: ‘An Insect of Parnassus,’” 
<hi rend="i">Explorations: The Age of Enlightenment</hi> 1 (1987): 58-94 (quotation cited from 66). The Blake
references in this letter are also quoted in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1988) 18-19.</note></q><pb id="p32-6" n="6-7"/>
<figure n="lt1sept1800.1.1+2.rm" id="lt1sept1800.1.ltr.01" work-copy="letters" rend="db" width="958" height="617">
	<figTranscr>Wm. Blake 1800 Mr Cumberland Bishopsgate Windsor Great Park C. 1 SE[PTEMBER 1]800 My Dear
Cumberland To have obtained your friendship is better than to have sold ten thousand books. I am now upon the
verge of a happy alteration in my life which you will join with my London friends in Giving me joy of - It is
an alteration in my situation on the surface of this dull Planet I have taken a Cottage at Felpham on the Sea
Shore of Sussex between Arundel &amp; Chichester. Mr Hayley the Poet is soon to be my neighbour he is now my
friend. to him I owe the happy suggestion for it was on a visit to him that I fell in love with my Cottage. I
have now better prospects than ever The little I want will be easily supplied he has given me a twelvemonths
work already. &amp; there is a great deal more in prospect I call myself now Independent. I can be Poet
Painter &amp; Musician as the Inspiration comes. And now I take this first opportunity to Invite you down to
Felpham we lie on a Pleasant shore it is within a mile of Bognor to which our Fashionables resort My Cottage
faces the South about a Quarter of a Mile from the Sea, only corn fields between. tell Mrs Cumberland that my
Wife thirsts for the opportunity to Entertain her at our Cottage Your Vision of the Happy Sophis I have
devourd. O most delicious book how canst thou Expect any thing but Envy in Londons accursed walls. You have my
dear friend given me a task which I have endeavourd to fulfill. I have given a sketch of your Proposal to the
Editor of the Monthly Magazine desiring that he will</figTranscr>
	<head>1 Address and page 1 of Blake’s letter to Cumberland, postmarked 1 September 1800.</head>
	<figDesc>Collection of Robert N. Essick. Pen and ink, except for the later pencil inscription in another hand
above the address, “W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake 1800.” Laid paper, approx. 19.5 × 32 cm., chain lines 2.5
cm. apart, showing a large crown and shield watermark in the center of the sheet. The postmark lower left
indicates the month, abbreviated as “S E,” the day (1) in the inner circle, and the year as “[1]800.”
From 1800 through 1822, only the last 3 numbers of the year were given in English postmarks—see John G.
Hendy, <hi rend="i">The History of the Early Postmarks of the British Isles</hi> (London: Gill, 1905) 6-7. The
letter “C” designates the “table or division in the Inland [post office] branch where the letter was
stamped” (Hendy 6). The double outer rim of the mark indicates the “evening” (i.e., late afternoon)
shift at the post office. Another, poorly-printed stamp can be seen about 4 cm. above the postmark; its right
end, upside-down, appears just left of the fold between the address and the first page of the letter. We can
decipher from this stamp only the letters G, E, S, e, and r. Fortunately, these fragments accord very closely
with a clearly printed stamp, “BRIDGE/Westminster A.S.E.,” on Blake’s letter to Hayley of 16 September
1800, now in the Huntington Library. Bridge Street, running across Westminster Bridge over the Thames, was
only a few blocks from Blake’s home in Hercules Buildings, Lambeth.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p32-8" n="8-9"/>
<figure n="lt1sept1800.1.3+4.rm" id="lt1sept1800.1.ltr.03" work-copy="letters" rend="db" width="958" height="615">
	<figTranscr>give it to the Public hope he will do so. I have shewn your Bonasoni to Mr Hawkins my friend
desiring that he will place your Proposal to the account of its real author, wherever he goes How Sorry I am
that you should ever be Ill. it also gives me pain to hear that you intend to leave Bishopsgate &amp; it would
give me more pleasure to hear that Sussex was preferred by you to Somersetshire But where ever you Go God
bless you. Perhaps I ought to give you My Letter to the Editor of the Monthly Mag. It is this Sir Your
Magazine being so universally Read induces me to recommend to your notice a Proposal made some years ago in a
Life of Julio Bonasoni which Proposal ought to be give to the Public in Every work of the nature of yours. It
is. For the Erection of National Galleries for the Reception of Casts in Plaster from all the Beautiful
Antique Statues Basso Reli[e]vos &amp;c that can be procured at home or abroad. Which Galleries may be built
&amp; filled by Public Subscription To be open to The Public. Their Use would be To Correct &amp; Determine
Public Taste as well as to be Treasures of Study for Artists. If you think that this Proposal is of the
Consequence that it appears to me to be, You will Extract the Authors own words &amp; give them in your
valuable Magazine. The Work is Intitled “Some Anecdotes of the Life of Julio Bonasoni &amp; by George
Cumberland Published by Robinsons Paternoster Row 1793 Yours W.B. I so little understand the way to get such
things into Magazines or News papers that if I have done wrong in Merely delivering the Letter at the
Publishers of the Magazine beg you will inform me My Wife joins with me in Love &amp; Respect to yourself
&amp; familly I am Your devoted artist Willm Blake PS. I hope to be settled in Sussex before the End of
September it is certainly the sweetest country upon the face of the Earth Dear Generous Cumberland nobly
solicitous for a Friends welfare. Behold me Whom your Friendship has Magnified: Rending the manacles of
Londons Dungeon dark I have rent the black net &amp; escap’d. See My Cottage at Felpham in joy Beams over
the sea, a bright light over France, but the Web &amp; the Veil I have Left Behind me at London resists every
beam of light; hanging from heaven to Earth Dropping with human gore. Lo! I have left it! I have torn it from
my limbs I shake my wings ready to take my flight! Pale, Ghostly pale: stands the City in fear</figTranscr>
	<head>2 Pages 2 and 3 of Blake’s letter to Cumberland, postmarked 1 September 1800.</head>
	<figDesc>Collection of Robert N. Essick. The initials (page 3) at the conclusion of Blake’s letter to the
editor of the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> look at first glance like “A. B.” But this letter within
the letter to Cumberland is clearly Blake’s, and thus we believe that a slip of the pen created the
appearance of an “A” when “W” was meant. Blake is not known to have used “A.B.” as pseudonymous
initials. Letters signed “A.B.” were printed in the 1 October 1800, 1 December 1800, and 1 June 1801
issues of the the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine.</hi> These are on botanical and meteorological topics; the
1801 letter is addressed from “Portsea.” They clearly have no connection with Blake.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p32-10" n="10"/>
Alexander Gilchrist, on the basis of information from John and Mary Ann Linnell, wrote of Blake at North End
in 1825: “He himself still sang, in a voice tremulous with age, sometimes old ballads, sometimes his own
songs, to melodies of his own.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> George
Richmond, who was present at Blake’s death, wrote that “Just before he died . . .He burst out Singing of
the things he saw in Heaven[.]”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
Smith, Marsh, the Linnells, and Richmond are reliable witnesses, but up to now we have not had a statement by
Blake himself expressing how important being a “Musician” along with “Poet” and “Painter” was to
him. We can now see the personal element in the triadic arrangement of statements like that on plate 3 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: “Nations are Destroy’d, or Flourish, in proportion as Their Poetry Painting and
Music, are Destroy’d or Flourish!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
Blake knew himself to be a creator of all three. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Life of
William Blake</hi>, ed. Ruthven Todd (London: J. M. Dent, rev. ed., 1945) 297.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> 347, from a letter to Samuel Palmer dated
15 August 1827.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> E 147. In <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> “Poetry
Painting &amp; Music” are “the three Powers &lt;in Man&gt; of conversing with Paradise which the flood did
not sweep away” (E 559).</note></p>
          <p>In his sanguine mood, Blake introduces the name of “M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Hawkins my friend,”
indicating the reappearance in his life of someone who had once tried to advance his career in a very
significant way. John Hawkins (1758?-1841)was a wealthy art collector and a writer on antiquarian
subjects.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Their original connection
was John Flaxman. On 18 June 1783, Flaxman wrote to his wife, Nancy, that Hawkins “at my desire has employed
Blake to make him a capital drawing for whose advantage in consideration of his great talents he seems
desirous to employ his utmost interest.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> Then, on 26 April 1784, Flaxman reported to William Hayley: “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>:
Hawkins a Cornish Gentleman has shewn his taste &amp; liberality in ordering Blake to make several drawings
for him, &amp; is so convinced of his uncommon talents that he is now endeavouring to raise a subscription to
send him to finish [<hi rend="i">his</hi>] studies in Rome. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Being a younger son, Hawkins, as Flaxman explained, could not meet the
entire expense himself; evidently he was unable to raise the necessary money, and Blake was not to have his
time in Rome. Nevertheless, Blake obviously remembered Hawkins’s interest with gratitude, and his fortuitous
reappearance must have impressed Blake, always a believer in signs, as auspicious. Hawkins had met William
Hayley at the Flaxmans’ in London only in May 1799, and he had then visited Hayley, who addressed a poem to
him, at Eartham in September 1799.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
On 11 August1800, Hayley wrote to Hawkins that “that worthy Enthusiast, the ingenious Blake” would be made
even happier if Hawkins should move to Sussex.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> Hawkins was later to be associated in Blake’s mind with one more significant event.
Blake’s account of his inner renewal the day after visiting the Truchsessian Gallery is immediately preceded
by the words: “Our good and kind friend Hawkins is not yet in town — hope to soon have the pleasure of
seeing him, with the courage of conscious industry, worthy of his former kindness to me.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> DNB</hi> 9: 221; and <hi rend="i">I am, my dear Sir.</hi>..,
ix-xxi.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> 24. Neither this nor any of Hawkins’s
other commissions for Blake have been traced.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> 27-28. Butlin suggests that three outline
drawings after Blake that Flaxman drew from memory when in Rome may be based on the pictures mentioned. See
<hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> 1: 57-8 (no. 152), 2: plate 170.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> See Morchard Bishop, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Hayley</hi> (London:
Gollancz, 1951) 243, 245.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> 72 and n1. As Bentley notes, Hawkins did
eventually move to Sussex, but not until 1806.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Letter to William Hayley, 23 October 1804, E 756. For the significance of
this linkage, see Morton D. Paley, “The Truchsessian Gallery Revisited,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 16 (1977): 165-77.</note></p>
          <p>Much of the letter is devoted to the projects of George Cumberland, whose friendship with Blake
may have begun as early as 1784.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref>
Blake’s mention of “Your Vision of the Happy Sophis” refers to Cumberland’s novel <hi rend="i">The
Captive of the Castle of Sennaar</hi>, printed in 1798.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> Although <hi rend="i">Sennaar</hi> was suppressed by Cumberland in 1798 and only
published in revised form in 1810, Cumberland sent copies of it to some of his friends, and this volume may
have been the “kind present” for which Blake had previously neglected to thank Cumberland, an omission for
which Blake apologized profusely in his letter to Cumberland dated 2 July 1800 (E 706). The core of the tale
concerns Sophis, a utopian society in Africa where property is limited to immediate personal use, energy is
considered the divine principle, there is no shame about the naked human body, and gold is despised except for
its use in art.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> Blake’s remark
that <hi rend="i">Sennaar</hi> has encountered “Envy in Londons accursed walls” may be a way of saying
that even Cumberland’s friends had considered the book too daring for publication. 
<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> See Sir Geoffrey Keynes, “George Cumberland and William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies: Essays on His Life and Work</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 2nd ed., 1971) 230-52.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> For historical and bibliographic details, see G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed.,
<hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar</hi> (Montreal and Kingston: McGill-Queen’s University
Press, 1991).</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> For a number of parallels between Blake’s ideas and those in this
novel, see Bentley’s Introduction xxxvi-xli.</note></p>
          <p>Blake next takes up the proposal for a National Gallery, previously broached by Cumberland in his
preface to <hi rend="i">Some Anecdotes of the Life of Julio Bonasoni</hi> (1793), entitled “A Plan for
Improving the Arts in England.” Blake’s letter is an accurate representation of Cumberland’s “Plan.”
The latter proposes “that a subscription be commenced . . . for the declared purposes . . . of commencing
<hi rend="i">two galleries</hi>, and filling them, as fast as the interest <corr type="emend">accrues,</corr>
with <hi rend="i">plaister</hi> casts from antique statues, bas-reliefs, . . . &amp;c. collected not only from
<pb id="p32-11" n="11"/>
Italy, but from all parts of Europe.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref> Blake’s advocacy of Cumberland’s neoclassicism shows his continued high
regard—although perhaps prompted more by friendship than by conviction—for that aesthetic. This letter
makes clear that Blake’s praise of “the immense flood of Grecian light &amp; glory which is coming on
Europe” (letter to Cumberland, 2 July 1800; E 706) continued at least until just before his removal to
Felpham. For some reason unknown to us, Blake thought that Cumberland’s plan was close to gaining acceptance
in high places at this time. On 2 July 1800, he had even congratulated Cumberland “on your plan for a
National Gallery being put into Execution” (E 706). His letter to the editor (John Aikin) of the 
<hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> was
part of a campaign that Blake (and presumably Cumberland) thought was close to fruition. The 
<hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> may have been chosen because Blake had an entrée there through Joseph Johnson,
who has been characterized as the “mentor and assistant” of the <hi rend="i">Monthly</hi>’s publisher,
Richard Phillips.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Phillips’s
premises at no. 71 St. Paul’s Churchyard were next door to Johnson’s, and Phillips did publish a letter of
Blake’s a few years later.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
However, neither Blake’s letter to the editor nor Cumberland’s proposal ever appeared in the magazine, and
while Cumberland may have contributed to an atmosphere that nurtured the idea of a National Gallery, he had no
role in the actual founding of the National Gallery, which may be dated from the acquisition of the Angerstein
collection for the nation in 1824. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Some Anecdotes
of the Life of Julio Bonasoni</hi> (London: G. G. J. and J. Robinson, 1793) 14-15.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> For Aikin’s editorship from 1796 to c. 1806, see Lucy Aikin, 
<hi rend="i">Memoir of John Aikin, M. D.</hi> (Philadelphia: Abraham Small, 1824) 109-44. Lucy Aikin states that
“all the original correspondence [to the magazine] came under his [John Aikin’s] inspection; articles were
inserted or rejected according to his judgment, and the proof sheets underwent his revision” (110).</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> See Gerald P. Tyson, <hi rend="i">Joseph Johnson: A Liberal
Publisher</hi> (Iowa City: University of Iowa Press, 1979) 168 and 258n81. Cumberland himself evidently had
considerable direct correspondence with the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>, beginning in April 1800, and
he published letters to the editor in the April 1800 and March 1803 issues. The first is about sugar
substitutes; the second is a defense of Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, for which Blake
had engraved some of the plates, and which contains a passing reference to Blake. (See G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">A Bibliography of George Cumberland</hi> [New York and London: Garland, 1975] 3n1 and 57).</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Published in the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> for 1 July 1801 (E
768-69), this letter defends Henry Fuseli against adverse critics. A subsequent letter (14 October 1807, E
769) ) to the <hi rend="i">Monthly</hi>, protesting against the arrest of an astrologer, was not
published.</note></p>
          <p>In several letters of 1800 to close friends just before and after his move to Felpham, Blake
expressed his ebullient feelings in verse. This newly discovered letter contains the first in this cluster of
epistolary poems. It is a brief but important addition to the corpus of Blake’s poetry. In a letter to John
Flaxman of 12 September (E 707-08), Blake included a poem in long lines of a type we also find in this poem, a
type familiar to readers of Blake’s “Prophetic” works from <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (c. 1789) to 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (completed c. 1820). The next poem, included in a letter of 14 September from Mrs.
Blake to Mrs. Flaxman, is in much shorter lines (E 708-09). The last extant text in this group, sent to Thomas
Butts on 2 October, is in short, rhymed couplets (E 712-13). Only the poem addressed to John Flaxman directly
invokes the “terrors” and “horrors” (E 707-08) that are so much a part of the poem printed here for
the first time. In their prosody and imagery, these seven lines are particularly evocative of the poem Blake
was then writing under the title of <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi> The most regular line is the fourth, which
comprises a spondee followed by six anapests:</p>
          <p>¯ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ |</p>
          <p>However, the only other seven-foot line is the first, which has only four anapests among its
seven feet:</p>
          <p>¯ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ˘ | ˘ ˘ ¯ | ˘ ¯ |</p>
          <p>These two lines have much in common with Blake’s septenaries elsewhere, but in this passage as
elsewhere Blake is frequently irregular in his long lines. As Alicia Ostriker remarks:
<q>
. . . Blake did not always confine himself to seven-beat lines. Alexandrines play an increasingly important
distaff part in his verse, and octometer also becomes frequent. Sometimes there are lines of four or five
beats, and sometimes there are lines nine beats long or longer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi><hi rend="i"> Vision and Verse in William Blake</hi> (Madison and
Milwaukee: University of Wisconsin Press, 1965) 137.</note></q>
Lines 2, 3, 5 and 6 are octometric, while line 7 has nine feet. It is difficult to scan some of these lines
because of their irregularity. Ostriker’s observations are again pertinent:
<q>
The octometers and other line-lengths give more trouble. They, along with the alexandrines, are of course
subject to as many rhythmical peculiarities as Blake imposes on his septenaries. And these odd-size lines
appear unpredictably, so that we can never be certain how many beats a line is going to have until we finish
reading it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi><hi rend="i"> Vision and Verse in William Blake</hi> 137-38.</note></q>
Line 9, for example, is an anthology of poetic feet, beginning with two iambs followed by a dactyl and a
trochee, then a spondee, a trochee, another spondee, an iamb and an anapest. Yet the passage as a whole is
dominated by rising feet, anapest and iamb, a rhythmical pattern that matches the rising spirits
expressed.</p>
          <p>In its development of the theme of freedom from bondage the passage uses a number of images
familiar to us from
<pb id="p32-12" n="12"/>
other contexts. Key words like manacles, Dungeon, net, Web, Veil, and gore, elsewhere applied to mythical or
fictitious figures, are here used to display Blake’s personal situation. The “manacles of Londons Dungeon
dark” cannot fail to remind us of the “mind-forg’d manacles” of “London” (8, E 27) of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> “Rending the manacles,” Blake is like Orc in <hi rend="i">America</hi>,
whose shoulders “rend the links” that bind his wrists (2: 2, E 52), or the figure in “The Mental
Traveller” who “rends up his Manacles” (23, E 484). Blake is also like “the inchained soul” of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, whose “dungeon doors are open” (6: 10, E 53). The “black net” is reminiscent of
Urizen’s “dark net of infection” in <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen</hi> 26: 30 (E 82), closely
associated with the “Web dark and cold” that follows Urizen’s footsteps (25: 14, E 82) and that
reappears at the end of Night VI of <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi> “Veil,” yoked with the “Web” and
“Dropping with human gore,” had not previously had the sense of the obfuscation of vision that it does
here and in <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi> “Human gore” had appeared as early as in “An Imitation of
Spen[s]er” 32 (E 421) in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783). These nightmarish images of fear and
entrapment express the deep depression Blake had fallen into by the end of the 1790s. Counter-balancing them
is Blake’s cottage, which “Beams over the Sea, a bright light over France,” behind which are perhaps
Jesus’s words from the Sermon on the Mount: “Ye are the light of the world. A city that is set on a hill
cannot be hid” (Matt. 5.14).</p>
          <p>In its short compass the poem moves from the horrific sublime, embodied in the London that Blake
was leaving, towards a renewed vision of light. Read with our retrospective knowledge of Blake’s Felpham
years and his misery under Hayley’s condescending patronage, the lines strike in us a note of pathos.
Blake’s hopes were so high, their realization so unattained. London turned out to be only one objective
correlative for Blake’s inner demons and professional distresses. Despite his bold announcements to the
contrary, “the Web &amp; the Veil” followed him to Felpham and there took on the psychic and poetic forms
populating “The Bard’s Song” in <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem.</hi> In 1803 Blake returned to “Londons
Dungeon dark,” soon after rechristened “a City of Assassinations” (letter to Hayley, 28 May 1804; E
751). The letter to Cumberland enriches our sense of Blake’s enthusiasm in the late summer and autumn of
1800, but it also provides a prelude to the disappointment and despair to come.</p>
          <pb id="p32-13" n="13"/>
          <figure n="lt1sept1800.1.3+4.rm.detail" id="lt1sept1800.1.ltr.04" work-copy="letters" rend="file" width="958" height="298">
            <figTranscr>Dear Generous Cumberland nobly solicitous for a Friends welfare. Behold me Whom your
Friendship has Magnified: Rending the manacles of Londons Dungeon dark I have rent the black net &amp;
escap’d. See My Cottage at Felpham in joy Beams over the sea, a bright light over France, but the Web &amp;
the Veil I have Left Behind me at London resists every beam of light; hanging from heaven to Earth Dropping
with human gore. Lo! I have left it! I have torn it from my limbs I shake my wings ready to take my flight!
Pale, Ghostly pale: stands the City in fear</figTranscr>
            <head>3 Detail of the poem, “Dear Generous Cumberland,” page 3 of Blake’s letter to
Cumberland.</head>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
