<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.2.worrall</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">G. E. Bentley, Jr., Blake Books Supplement</title>
        <author n="Worrall">David Worrall</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1998</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Thomas Dillingham</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
	<pb id="p32-46" n="46"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-2-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">G.E. Bentley, Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement: A Bibliography of
Publications and Discoveries about William Blake 1971-1992 being a Continuation of Blake Books (1977).</hi>
Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995. xvii + 789 pp. 13 plates. $135.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>David <name>Worrall</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Bentley’s labors, both here and in <hi rend="i">Blake Books, Blake Records and Blake Records
Supplement</hi>, have been hugely important to the expansion of Blake studies. It’s surely not too fanciful
to trace back to Bentley’s foundations the original impulses behind the new “Superbibliography” of
Essick
<pb id="p32-47" n="47"/>
<figure n="bentley-blake-books-supplement.032.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="475" height="773">
	<figTranscr>G. E. Bentley, Jr. Blake Books Supplement A Bibliography of Publications and Discoveries about
William Blake 1971-1992 being a Continuation of Blake Books (1977) Clarendon Press Oxford 1995</figTranscr>
</figure>
and Viscomi (although their scholarship has always been more than that, of course). Such is the complexity of
Blake’s work (drawings, watercolors, oils, various processes of engraving, manuscripts, multiple
“originals” of illuminated books, etc.), and so rapid has been the expansion of romanticism’s centrality
within English studies during the 1960s and now the 1990s, that it always had urgent need of being firmly
grounded in critical empiricism. If it becomes the case that the six or seven canonical writers diminish to a
rump as future critical interest in them dwindles, Blake may endure as the only one whose complex textual
materiality will be certain to ensure that he remains unco-opted into any newer, broader and more democratic
cultural histories of the period. What might make sense as an argument about Blake’s life as a writer may
make less sense about his work as an artist, and vice versa. However that develops in the future, Bentley’s
two <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> volumes enable us to visualize, at a glance, not only the totality of Blake
study but also to glimpse its developmental process. It will be no surprise that the column of index inches
(<hi rend="i">centimeters</hi> if you must) devoted to Keynes and Erdman are now much reduced, their primacy
overtaken (“neck and neck” as horseracing commentators would have it) by Essick and Bentley himself. But
our colleagues do not <hi rend="i">jockey</hi>, for it has long been thanks to the collective labors of
Bentley, Essick, Dörrbecker (and many others), that the <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> themselves have been
continually updated by the rapid annual bibliographies and checklists which appear here in 
<hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> As a community of scholars we continue to have much to be grateful for.</p>
          <p>As Bentley realized a long time ago, and the rest of us somewhat later, the study of Blake is a
uniquely complex activity because the abundance, technical complexity and material diversity of Blake’s
original artifacts is combined with a dearth of “literary” information about his life. We have all, at one
time or another, leapt upon a dated “WB inv” monogram to bolster some favorite—if more or less
shaky—hermeneutic about his life or work, but the materiality of the artifact, the principal domain of the
bibliographer, has increasingly tended to trounce us. We all now know, for example, that only 
<hi rend="i">some</hi> of the big Tate Gallery color prints dated by Blake “1795” might be dateable to
1795—since some of the paper is watermarked 1803—but now, it seems, in the absence of anything more
convincing, we must also learn not to call <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> “Hecate.” Such are the things
bibliographers (and gallery curators) do to us, and it hurts. Although <hi rend="i">Blake Books
Supplement</hi> confines itself explicitly to primary and secondary written records, the adjacent domain of
art history will frequently converge with the literary bibliographies when the act of interpretation confronts
the status of the archive. Ultimately, what we need is a <hi rend="i">Supplement</hi> to the 
<hi rend="i">Supplement</hi>, with Butlin and Bentley butted end to end, so to speak, collating the array of
materialities connected with Blake. As it is, Bentley’s book is our latest (and best) stab at attaining this
essential empirical control over Blake. And such control is needed if we are to have some chance of curbing
our own excesses, errors and omissions as scholars.</p>
          <p>How professional were we that we missed noticing that copies E-H and H-K of <hi rend="i">There is
No Natural Religion</hi> were Victorian facsimiles (139)? Or, if confirmed, how did we—until 1991—fail to
notice a whole set of 1809 silver buttons with Blake’s portrait appearing amidst those of Nelson, Pitt and
other luminaries in that crucial <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> year (3)? And what of the so-called
“Felpham Rummer” inscribed “Blake in Anguish Felpham August 1803” (70-72, pl. 2)? A glass goblet is
solid enough, surely? Yet we missed it, and much else. Unless you have at your elbow a complete run of 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>’s back to 1977 (with past bibliographers Thomas Minnick and Detlef Dörrbecker giving
way to Bentley himself), then <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> will be essential at your desk keeping
you informed about the totality of artifacts involved in modern Blake studies. Its user will even extract
oddments of innocent humor such as finding, for example, that (exotically), the <hi rend="i">Journal of
Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi> is indexed next to the <hi rend="i">Journal of Aoyama Gakuin Women’s
Junior College.</hi> Much like Bentley’s photographic dressing, in a recent issue of 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, of Blake’s life
<pb id="p32-48" n="48"/>
mask with his recently discovered spectacles (<hi rend="i">speculative</hi> spectacles, strictly), we can
never be quite sure of the extent of this impish fun.</p>
          <p>One of the most valuable sections of <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> is that devoted to
newly recorded and newly traced copies of the illuminated books. The former includes, for example, a census of
information on the German and Austrian “Lambeth” books discovered by Dörrbecker in the 1980s while the
latter includes many new details of Blake’s mid nineteenth-century provenance. In the light of the
“Superbibliography” with its careful interpellation from artifacts, it is now of significance that Bentley
records as “Newly Recorded Copies” no less than seven individual plates and one “Newly Traced” copy of
plates from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy J. Similarly, if less dramatically, Bentley methodically records
new editions of books containing Blake’s commercial engravings and gives, for example, new locations of
editions of his Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, including details of contemporary announcements about its
publication. On their own these are matters of minor moment but cumulatively, when enriched with other similar
notes, they enable us to gauge the extent of Blake’s contemporary circulation and help us visualize
Blake-the-craftsman as well as Blake-the-visionary. Further help, usually in the form of addenda to the 1977
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, is also provided in the form of tables of new Blake titles and copies, lists of
stab holes, collections, details of location and ownership, plate sizes, watermarks and reproductions
(including reprints before 1863). Of course, this information is augmented, <hi rend="i">inter alia</hi>, by
details of dimensions, color, binding orders etc.</p>
          <p>As one might expect, over half of <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> is given over to a
straightforward bibliography of Blake criticism, mostly postdating the first <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> but
also filling in many of that volume’s bibliographical escapees. The global coverage is impressive with
articles, books and theses recorded in most of the major and minor European languages (viz., Catalan as well
as Spanish) in addition to emergent but identifiable Indian and Japanese bodies of scholarship. As one might
expect, although the entries include newspaper and other ephemeral publications, the core of the bibliography
of criticism consists of the mainstream output of academically oriented books and journal articles with the
listings frequently bearing Bentley’s own annotations. Many of these are short synoptic quotations from the
works themselves but he quite often provides his own analytical comments, sometimes including evaluative
judgements about style (e.g., “rambling,” “severe”) or content (“wonderfully inaccurate,”
“masterful,” “conventional,” “highly sophisticated,” “rudimentary”). More frequently, however,
Bentley’s comments (not nearly as starkly reductive as I have presented here) provide a true analytical
annotation, by which I mean that they elucidate information from otherwise unrevealing titles. For example,
Robert Essick’s 1978 <hi rend="i">Notes &amp; Queries</hi> piece, economically titled “William Blake and
Sir Thomas Lawrence,” is annotated by Bentley to reveal the core of its information (in this case the
existence of an 1830 William Etty letter stating that Lawrence sent Blake £100). By also providing analytical
entries for Blake chapters in books not otherwise signally, or obviously, concerned with him, as well as
cumulative annotated entries for long running journal volumes such as <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, the 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> will cut down much speculative searching and retrieval.</p>
          <p>Ours is an age of information, the age of IT. My first action on entering a library is not to go
to the catalogue but to padlock my laptop within range of an electricity socket. In considering how 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> might be used in the future, it seems extraordinarily shortsighted of
Oxford University Press not to have presented the academic market with the possibility of having (as
antiquarian booksellers are fond of saying) the “very scarce” 1977 <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
electronically merged with <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> and to sell them both on CD-ROM (I am
presuming that the latter, if not the former, would have been presented to the Press on disk). While
Bentley’s index is very good (he indexes watermarks, for example—even if “J Whatman” comes
inexplicably under “J”) and includes some attempt to index significant title words (e.g.,
“Enlightenment,” “Body,” “Self” etc.), what today’s scholarly community requires is
“Electronic Searchability.” The indexing of names and places is exemplary (I’ve tried faulting the index
but haven’t yet managed to do so) but, given the increasingly artifact-based nature of Blake studies, what
if I wished to search out, for example, all leaf dimensions of 24.3 cm in the illuminated books? Or what if I
wished to collect all Blakeana relating to, say, 1890 (e.g., sales, exhibitions, editions, articles, books)?
Or, quite simply, to find all references to “woodcut,” both in the section on original works and in the
titles or annotations of the critical bibliography? While I recognize that the physicality of modern scholarly
practices are often curiously asymmetrical (why is it that I always padlock my laptop but never my Bentley?),
the types of research <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> might potentially support is far greater than
the abilities of a paper index to serve. It is also difficult, but necessary, to incorporate information from
the old <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> and merge it with the <hi rend="i">Supplement</hi> (I am thinking, in
particular, of provenance details and physical descriptions of the illuminated books). The 
<hi rend="i">Supplement</hi> tends to assume ownership or sight of <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> exactly at those
points where other databases (e.g., MLA, ABELL) cannot be of much help. To such wistful electronic mergers we
might also add <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Blake Records and Supplement.</hi> It seems a pity that such a
Herculean set of labors, and such wonderful achievements as <hi rend="i">Blake Books/Records/Supplements</hi>
should be confined to the archaic and undemocratic world of print. Perhaps enlightened opportunism at Oxford
University Press might persuade them of the economic potential of selling, either in CD-ROM format or over the
internet, not just <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
	<pb id="p32-49" n="49"/>
	<hi rend="i">Books Supplement</hi> but the now dormant <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>: three OUP incomes for
two copyrights. Just as the Blake internet sites have shown so splendidly, we have at our disposal the means
to lead our discipline in the digitalization of literary studies: Bentley’s four Blake books ought to be
there in the vanguard. Blake studies, and romanticism in general, should count itself fortunate to have been
so well served, and for so long, by the dedicated (if not precisely devout) scholarship of Jerry and Beth
Bentley.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
