<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.3.gourlay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Worrall, ed., William Blake, The Urizen Books</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander S. Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1998/99</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998/99</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998/9"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
	<pb id="p32-76" n="76"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Urizen Books.</hi> Edited with introductions
and notes by David Worrall. Princeton: The William Blake Trust/Princeton University Press, 1995. Blake’s
Illuminated Books Volume 6. General Editor David Bindman. 231 pp. $65. Paper $29.95 [1998].</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Alexander S. <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>David Worrall’s contribution to the new series of Blake Trust editions of the illuminated books
is a thoroughly creditable performance—like the other volumes, this well-constructed book offers a set of
thoughtful introductions, carefully edited texts with informative but not exhaustive pictorial, critical, and
textual notes, and colorful and minutely detailed images of the illuminated pages themselves. <hi rend="i">The
Urizen Books</hi> includes <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book
of Los</hi>, but not <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, which was (appropriately) included in Detlef W.
Dörrbecker’s edition of <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies.</hi> Worrall has successfully negotiated
the difficult path that one enters when editing a book in which the usefulness of the pictures will outlast
that of most of the critical apparatus. Any editor might be tempted to retreat into the mode usually adopted
by Sir Geoffrey Keynes in his slight commentaries in the even more glorious Trianon Press facsimiles. Worrall
has done better than that. His introductions to the difficult Urizen books offer coherent and sensible
interpretive suggestions that reflect a broad grasp of recent scholarship, and his critical, technical and
bibliographical information is up to date. Inevitably, readers will find that he has neglected things they
wish he had explained or at least mentioned, but most, now and for years to come, will find his apparatus to
be a helpful, readable and reliable accompaniment to the illustrations.</p>
          <p>In his acknowledgments Worrall cites the influence of the great learned lefties David V. Erdman
and E. P. Thompson; he shares their interest in the ways that Blake responded to his times, especially
contemporary politics, and his introductions reiterate and expand upon their work. Like them, he is especially
good at showing how politics and religion were intertwined in the period, and adduces a score of political,
philosophical, and religious writers and artists whose works are variously analogous or at least relevant to
Blake’s, some of them well known to Blakeans, like Spence, Paine, Mallet and (more recently) Geddes, and
some less familiar ones that Jon Mee, Iain McCalman, and Worrall himself have recently uncovered. Worrall is
judicious in selecting these analogues and in his assessment of their relevance. As usually happens when
studying Blake in context, even identifying materials or phenomena that the author was undoubtedly thinking of
as he wrote (and expected his audience to know) helps the struggling modern reader only so much. As the
analogues and potential allusions proliferate, it often becomes harder rather than easier to imagine how Blake
could have expected his readers to negotiate these intertextual jungles. None of the contemporary analogues
seems satisfactory to me as a rhetorical model for Blake’s procedure in these books—something that
Worrall, like most of us, usually calls a parody, even though we all know that the term is insufficient to
describe the wide range of ways in which Blake’s work is related to his most likely targets. When Spence or
Paine (or Cruikshank or Gillray) did things like Blake’s it is clear that they were operating as parodists
of a complex but not particularly mysterious kind, but I still cannot clearly envision a reader for whom these
books of Blake’s would have been anything but opaque, however richly evocative, wittily suggestive, and
potentially subversive we can show them to be.</p>
          <p>Worrall is only a little less assured in treating the textual and related technical aspects of
these books than in clarifying their political and social contexts. He is familiar with the latest
developments in understanding Blake’s means of production in general and the history of producing the Urizen
books in particular, and throughout his apparatus Worrall shows that he understands the implications of the
work of Joseph Viscomi and others for those trying to make sense of multiple versions of an illuminated Blake
text. The assorted editorial notes are helpful and fairly efficient. The pictorial notes are much more
carefully chosen than, for instance, the luxuriant tangle of implications and possibilities catalogued in
David Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi>, but Worrall nevertheless includes some ephemeral remarks
by others on minute particulars that mean little outside the context of the discussion in which they
originally appeared.</p>
          <p>The facing-page letterpress texts presumably record the text as it appears in the page that is
reproduced (as in the earlier volumes), and they are therefore somewhat different from the more familiar
editorial texts (such as Bentley’s or Keynes’s) and also from the collated “largest printed mark”
texts invented by Erdman. I couldn’t find any explicit claim here about the editorial principle used, but
Paley’s rationale in the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> volume of this series is persuasive (126-27). A
judicious and uncluttered record of the text of the copy reproduced is a useful thing to have and is not
available elsewhere, even if it is not the best imaginable
<pb id="p32-77" n="77"/>
reconstruction of what Blake meant to write. And as transcriptions of the words and punctuation on the
finished pages these texts seem to be very reliable: working from the reproductions in the book I found no
apparent errors. In general the compositors did an excellent job of reproducing the format and lineation (and
even the word-spacing) of Blake’s pages—the only problem I can see is that when Blake inserted the end of
a broken line above rather than below the line it completes, the typesetter (or the typesetting program)
adjusted the line spacing so that the fragment is placed closer to the line above than to the broken line that
it completes.</p>
          <p>I can’t testify about the color accuracy of the reproductions in this volume, for I have not
examined them side by side with the originals. But because so many of the original pages are color-printed in
thick smears of ink, the images here cannot be facsimiles of Blake’s pages but rather very plausible
color-offset reproductions of very sharp and carefully lit photographs. The reproductive processes used cannot
even approximate the look of most of Blake’s originals, which often feature richly textured impasto effects
and other unreproducible elements such as gold leaf, but they do provide a reliable record of most of what is
there to be seen. The photographs used were very sharp, and the offset screens so fine that it is impossible
to perceive with the naked eye the tiny dots of ink that make up the image. In all seven copies that I have
examined the printing plates were perfectly registered, so that the printing colors were applied exactly where
they should be. As a result of all these circumstances, the images are exceptionally beautiful and very useful
for scholars. The hairline features of the intaglio-etched texts of <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, for instance, are almost as clearly reproduced as in the photo-collotype
Trianon Press facsimiles, and all pages are sharper and more subtly colored than in any other reproductions
now available except the best color slides and, perhaps, the digital images that will eventually be available
from the electronic Blake Archive. This resource (http://www.iath.virginia.edu/blake), still under
construction, presently offers a dazzling glimpse of the technology that will revolutionize the reproduction
of Blake’s pictures for scholarly purposes, and will undoubtedly (and unfortunately) forestall any future
publishing projects like the one that produced the volume under review. (On the other hand, it seems likely
that an electronic archive coupled to advanced printers could eventually be used to produce high-quality paper
copies on demand, so all the romance of the printed page may not be lost forever.)</p>
          <p>The problem of choosing copies to reproduce and determining the ordering of pages in them is
simple for <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, since the complete
copies are unique, but devilishly difficult for <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, which is ordered and
constituted differently in almost every copy. Blake made twenty eight printing plates for 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, all at roughly the same time, but except for copies A and B he didn’t use all the
pages that the plates could print, and while some pages may have been extracted (or added) by later owners,
Blake’s foliation and other evidence suggest that he regarded several different forms of the book as
complete and satisfactory. Indeed, the copy reproduced as a whole in this new edition, Copy D, lacks not only
plate 16, but also plate 4, which includes about a tenth of all the text. Flawed but plausible cases could be
made for several of the more complete copies as the “best” text to reproduce, but as long as one must
choose an exemplar—and for paper editions of the illuminated books, I guess one must—Copy D of 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> is an attractive copy and a sound choice. Worrall includes a generous sampling of variant
pages (among them the two missing from Copy D) and indicates the variety of alternative orderings.</p>
          <p>I am still slowly working my way through these new Blake Trust editions systematically, but I
have been using them unsystematically for some time as my primary reference texts for the illuminated books.
The whole series seems to me a resounding success—the level of the scholarship is high, the overall
editorial approach sound, and the execution of the volumes very good. There is always room for caviling—such
a magnificent presentation should be attended by both careful color-checking of the illustrations and
perspicuous proofreading (and graceful editing for style), and some volumes didn’t receive enough attention
in these respects. But no serious Blake scholar can do without these books, and the Blake Trust, the Tate
Gallery, Princeton University Press, and the editors should all be proud of all of them. David Worrall’s
contribution to the series is consistent with the high standard that prevails throughout.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
