<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.3.freed</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">“In the Darkness of Philisthea”: The Design of Plate 78 of Jerusalem</title>
        <author n="Freed">Eugenie R. Freed</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1998/99</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998/99</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998/9"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
      <pb id="p32-60" n="60"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“In the Darkness of Philisthea”: The Design of Plate 78 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Eugenie R. <name>Freed</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>With the hint of a tear in its eye, a hunched figure sits on a cliff sloping towards a dark sea.
It has the body of a man and the profiled head of a bird, surmounted by a crest like a cock’s comb, but with
a hooked predatory beak like that of an eagle or even a vulture. The bird-head stares gloomily towards the
viewer’s left, past a quartered sun appearing on the horizon against the background of a clouded sky. Thus
Blake opens the fourth chapter of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (see illus. 1 and 2).</p>
          <p>The scene on plate 78 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (henceforth <hi rend="i">J</hi>), and
especially the figure dominating it, is a controversial one.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref> As Morton Paley comments, few of Blake’s images have received more varied
interpretations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Various identities
have been proposed for the figure: Joseph Wicksteed (226), W. J. T. Mitchell (211), Judith Ott (48), W. H.
Stevenson (803) and Joanne Witke (180) see him as Los, S. Foster Damon ([1924]473) as Egypt, David Erdman 
(<hi rend="i">IB</hi> 357) and Henry Lesnick (400-01) as Hand. Erdman, Wicksteed and Lesnick perceive the head as
that of a cock; John Beer (253), Mitchell, Witke, Stevenson and Ott see the head of an eagle; Paley ([1983]
89) suggests that Blake was inspired by the hawk-headed Osiris. Opinions differ as to whether the sun in the
scene is rising or setting; for instance, while Paley (describing copy E, the unique colored version) sees
“an angry sunset” (261) and Erdman (surveying all extant versions) “plainly the setting material sun—a
signal for the rising of a more bright sun,” to Beer, looking at the same version as Paley, the sun is
“rising in splendour,” and in Witke’s view the bird-headed figure “looks towards a great globe of
light reascending on the horizon in expectation of Albion’s redemption.” <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
Blake texts are quoted from the Erdman edition, cited as E followed by the page numbers. Blake’s illuminated
plates other than those of copy E of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are cited from Erdman, <hi rend="i">The
Illuminated Blake</hi>, referred to as <hi rend="i">IB</hi> followed by the page number. Copy E of Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is discussed with reference to the facsimile edited by Morton Paley.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Paley summarizes critical opinion in a note to the facsimile edition of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, 261.</note></p>
          <p>Anyone surveying the agglomeration of conflicting critical views may well exclaim, with Blake
himself, “But thou readst black where I read white” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 524). Obviously these are matters
on which ultimately readers will have to agree to differ from one another. But I would like, in what follows,
to draw attention to one element in the context of this enigmatic image that may have been overlooked: that of
“disease”—the “spiritual disease” referred to by the “Watcher” of the vision just preceding,
when he directs the poet, as Jesus commanded his disciples, to “cast out devils in Christs name / Heal thou
the sick of spiritual disease” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:24-25, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 233).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> No doubt this adds a further complication to a
question already vexed enough, but it may go a little way towards articulating, if not clarifying, some of the
ambiguities surrounding this scene. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Matthew 10:8: “Heal the sick, cleanse
the lepers, raise the dead, cast out devils . . . .” See also note 13 below.</note></p>
          <p>The strongly hooked beak of the bird-head on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78, the upper part overhanging
the lower, suggests that of a predatory bird, like an eagle, or a bird of carrion, a vulture. Amongst the
numerous eagles that hover and swoop through Blake’s works are some whose heads can be clearly seen: for
instance, on plate 15 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (<hi rend="i">IB</hi> 112), on
plate 3 of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (<hi rend="i">IB</hi> 131), on plate 42 [38]
of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (<hi rend="i">IB</hi> 258), and in the upper left corner of Blake’s 1805
painting “War” (Butlin, cat. no. 195, pl. 193; and see also cat. no. 189, pl. 195), where the bird (more
like a raven or a crow than an eagle) seems to be attracted to carrion flesh. None of these has a 
<hi rend="i">crest</hi> like the bird-head on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78—nor, moreover, do the two eagle-headed men
riding man-faced bulls in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 46[41]. Blake made several sketches (presumably in 1802)
illustrating William Hayley’s ballad “The Eagle” (Butlin cat. nos. 360-63, pl. 467 and 470-72). Two of
these (361 <hi rend="i">recto</hi> and 362 <hi rend="i">recto</hi>) show a neck-ruff of raised feathers behind
the eagle’s head, but 360 and especially 363, the most advanced of the sketches (tentatively dated by Butlin
1805) show Blake’s usual smooth-headed eagle with a hooked upper beak. Paley (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
261) points out that the gryphon pulling the car of Beatrice in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Paradiso</hi>
illustration “Beatrice addresses Dante from the Car” (Butlin cat. no. 812 88, pl. 973) resembles the head
of the figure in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78. But I would argue that the way in which the crest is deliberately
extended <hi rend="i">forward</hi> in the figure on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 to meet the nostrils just above the
beak differentiates it from the swept-back crest of the gryphon harnessed to Beatrice’s car. The head of
this bird-man is not <hi rend="i">obviously</hi> that of a crested eagle, but something more like a domestic
fowl with a crest or comb that suggests (to me, at any rate) a modification of the rooster’s head seen under
the right arm of Comus at the banqueting table in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustration of c. 1801,
<hi rend="i">The Magic Banquet with the Lady Spell-Bound</hi>, from the Thomas set (Butlin cat. no. 527 5, pl.
620) (illus 3).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Pace</hi> Judith Ott, who uses this same comparison to support
her assertion that the bird’s head in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 is <hi rend="i">not</hi> that of a cock (51n1).
Blake has given the bird-head in the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustration both the comb and the pendent
wattles of a barnyard cock, whereas the beak and <hi rend="i">lower</hi> part of the bird-head in 
<hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 are definitely eagle-like, having no sign of wattles.</note></p>
          <p>It would be appropriate—as Wicksteed (226) argued—for a cock to figure in the symbolism on
this plate. Blake
<pb id="p32-61" n="61"/>
<figure n="jerusalem-d-78.032.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="734">
	<figTranscr>78<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Jersualem. C 4<lb/>
	<lb/>
	The Spectres of Albions Twelve Sons revolve mightily<lb/>
	Over the Tomb &amp; over the Body: ravning to devour<lb/>
	The Sleeping Humanity. Los with his mace of iron<lb/>
	Walks round: loud his threats. loud his blows fall<lb/>
	On the rocky Spectres, as the Potter breaks the potsherds;<lb/>
	Dashing in pieces Self-righteousnesses: driving them from Albions<lb/>
	Cliffs; dividing them into Male &amp; Female forms in his Furnaces<lb/>
	And on his Anvils: lest they destroy the Feminine Affections<lb/>
	They are broken. Loud howl the Spectres in his iron Furnace<lb/>
	<lb/>
	While Los laments at his dire labours. viewing Jerusalem,<lb/>
	Sitting before his Furnaces clothed in sackcloth of hair;<lb/>
	Albions Twelve Sons surround the Forty-two Gates of Erin,<lb/>
	In terrible armour, raging against the Lamb &amp; against Jerusalem,<lb/>
	Surrounding them with armies to destroy the Lamb of God.<lb/>
	They took their Mother Vala, and they crown’d her with gold:<lb/>
	They namd her Rahab. &amp; gave her power over the Earth<lb/>
	The Concave Earth round Golgonooza in Entuthon Benython.<lb/>
	Even to the stars exalting her Throne, to build beyond the Throne<lb/>
	Of God and the Lamb. to destroy the Lamb &amp; usurp the Throne of God<lb/>
	Drawing their Ulro Voidness round the Four-fold Humanity<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Naked Jerusalem lay before the Gates upon Mount Zion<lb/>
	The Hill of Giants, all her foundations levelld with the dust:<lb/>
	Her Twelve Gates thrown down: her children carried into captivity<lb/>
	Herself in chains: this from within was seen in a dismal night<lb/>
	Outside, unknown before in Beulah. &amp; the twelve gates were fill’d<lb/>
	With blood; from Japan eastward to the Giants causway. west<lb/>
	In Erins Continent: and Jerusalem wept upon Euphrates banks<lb/>
	Disorganizd; an evanescent shade, scarce seen or heard among<lb/>
	Her childrens Druid Temples dropping with blood wanderd weeping!<lb/>
	And thus her voice went forth in the darkness of Philisthea.<lb/>
	<lb/>
	My brother &amp; my father are no more! God hath forsaken me<lb/>
	The arrows of the Almighty pour upon me &amp; my children<lb/>
	I have sinned and am an outcast from the Divine Presence!</figTranscr>
	<head>1 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 78, copy D.</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of the Houghton Library, Harvard University.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p32-62" n="62"/>
<figure n="jerusalem.e.p78" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.78" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="785" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>78<lb/>
	<lb/>
	The Spectres of Albions Twelve Sons revolve mightily<lb/>
	Over the Tomb &amp; over the Body: ravning to devour<lb/>
	The Sleeping Humanity. Los with his mace of iron<lb/>
	Walks round: loud his threats. loud his blows fall<lb/>
	On the rocky Spectres, as the Potter breaks the potsherds;<lb/>
	Dashing in pieces Self-righteousnesses: driving them from Albions<lb/>
	Cliffs; dividing them into Male &amp; Female forms in his Furnaces<lb/>
	And on his Anvils: lest they destroy the Feminine Affections<lb/>
	They are broken. Loud howl the Spectres in his iron Furnace<lb/>
	<lb/>
	While Los laments at his dire labours. viewing Jerusalem,<lb/>
	Sitting before his Furnaces clothed in sackcloth of hair;<lb/>
	Albions Twelve Sons surround the Forty-two Gates of Erin,<lb/>
	In terrible armour, raging against the Lamb &amp; against Jerusalem,<lb/>
	Surrounding them with armies to destroy the Lamb of God.<lb/>
	They took their Mother Vala, and they crown’d her with gold:<lb/>
	They namd her Rahab. &amp; gave her power over the Earth<lb/>
	The Concave Earth round Golgonooza in Entuthon Benython.<lb/>
	Even to the stars exalting her Throne, to build beyond the Throne<lb/>
	Of God and the Lamb. to destroy the Lamb &amp; usurp the Throne of God<lb/>
	Drawing their Ulro Voidness round the Four-fold Humanity<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Naked Jerusalem lay before the Gates upon Mount Zion<lb/>
	The Hill of Giants, all her foundations levelld with the dust:<lb/>
	Her Twelve Gates thrown down: her children carried into captivity<lb/>
	Herself in chains: this from within was seen in a dismal night<lb/>
	Outside, unknown before in Beulah. &amp; the twelve gates were fill’d<lb/>
	With blood; from Japan eastward to the Giants causway. west<lb/>
	In Erins Continent: and Jerusalem wept upon Euphrates banks<lb/>
	Disorganizd; an evanescent shade, scarce seen or heard among<lb/>
	Her childrens Druid Temples dropping with blood wanderd weeping!<lb/>
	And thus her voice went forth in the darkness of Philisthea.<lb/>
	<lb/>
	My brother &amp; my father are no more! God hath forsaken me<lb/>
	The arrows of the Almighty pour upon me &amp; my children<lb/>
	I have sinned and am an outcast from the Divine Presence!</figTranscr>
	<head>2 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 78, copy E.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p32-63" n="63"/>
wishes here to remind the reader of an event recounted in all four of the Gospels,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> the crowing of a cock that reminded the apostle Peter of
Christ’s prophecy in the Garden of Gethsemane that he, Peter, would thrice deny him before cockcrow at
sunrise. The cock thus becomes a symbol of <hi rend="i">the denial of Jesus</hi>, “bright Preacher of
Life” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:21, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 232), by those who claim to follow his teachings,
“the Christians” to whom this chapter is addressed. Because of its association with the sunrise, the cock
is also traditionally a symbol of <hi rend="i">resurrection.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Perhaps Blake’s mind flashed back to the opening lines of Night the Second
of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, in which Young brings these elements together:
<q>
“When the cock crew, he wept”—smote by that eye<lb/>
Which looks on me, on all; that power, who bids<lb/>
This midnight centinel, with clarion shrill,<lb/>
Emblem of that which shall awake the dead . . .<lb/>
(lines 1-4)
</q>
In the 1790s Blake had chosen to illustrate these lines with the powerful image of a trumpeting angel
commanding the dead to arise.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Matthew 26:34, 57-58 and 69-75, Mark 14:30 and 53-72, Luke 22:34 and 54-62,
John 13:36-38, 18:15-18, 25-27.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> The “crested Cock” is mentioned in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 28[30]:24,
<hi rend="i">E</hi> 126. Kathleen Raine associates the image with a myth of resurrection and reincarnation
linked to the Scandinavian war-god Odin, and also quotes from Thomas Taylor’s <hi rend="i">Plato</hi> (1804)
a passage from Proclus’s <hi rend="i">Dissertation on Magic</hi> that attributes special powers to the cock
because of its relationship with the “solar divinity.” (Kathleen Raine, “The Crested Cock”, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 1 (1967-68):9-10.) In my view, the cock-headed figure on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78
reflects these concepts ironically. (Special thanks to Morris Eaves for drawing my attention to Raine’s
note, and to Patricia Neill for sending it to me.)</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Bindman, <hi rend="i">Complete Graphic Works</hi>, 348. Blake modified the
figure of the angel in this emblem of resurrection and used it again in 1808 on the titlepage of Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (Bindman, 465).</note></p>
          <p>Erdman (<hi rend="i">IB</hi> 357) identifies the crest of the figure on Plate 78 as “a cock’s
comb—a signal of the morning,” linking it with the dawning of the apocalyptic day of the resurrection of
Albion. He also quotes Wicksteed’s association of the image with “the Christian symbol upon Church
steeples recalling Peter’s denial of his Lord and the bitter repentance that was to make him the ‘Rock’
upon which the church itself was founded” (226). The sorrowful mien and suggestion of a tear in the eye of
the bird-headed man could imply the “bitter repentance” Peter expressed by weeping.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Matthew 26:75, Mark 14:72, Luke 22:62.</note></p>
          <p>Peter’s triple denial of Christ was uttered at the palace of the High Priest, Caiaphas, who had
led the chief priests and Pharisees in plotting against Jesus and had counseled them to have him put to
death.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> It was in Caiaphas’s palace,
before daylight, that Jesus was arraigned, reviled and buffeted immediately after his betrayal and arrest in
the Garden of Gethsemane. Peter, who had followed his master “afar off unto the high priest’s palace, went
in, and sat with the servants, to see the end” (Matthew 26:58). He was warming himself at a coal fire “in
the midst of the hall” (Luke 22:55) and trying to mingle unobtrusively with the household staff—in effect,
he was hoping to pass himself off unnoticed as another of the High Priest’s servitors—when, one after
another, three of the servants recognized him as “one of <hi rend="i">them</hi>” (Mark 14:69-70). He
responded to each by denying his association with Jesus of Nazareth. He was still within the palace of
Caiaphas when he heard the cock crow, for after hearing it he “<hi rend="i">went out</hi>, and wept
bitterly.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> The cock and its
symbolic crowing can thus also be associated with “Caiaphas, the dark Preacher of Death / <hi rend="i">Of
sin, of sorrow, &amp; of punishment</hi>” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:18-19, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 232 [my
emphasis]). In fact Caiaphas embodies what Blake elsewhere calls “the infection of Sin &amp; stern
Repentance,” a “dread disease” from which “none but Jesus” can save Albion (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
38[43]:75, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 186, <hi rend="i">J</hi> 40[45]:16, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 187). The name
“Caiaphas” is given to the “Wheel / Of fire” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:2-3, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 232) of
the poet’s vision in the blank-verse lyric on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 77. Its movement “From west to east
against the current of / Creation” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:4-5, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 232)—and against the
apparent movement of the <hi rend="i">sun</hi>—suggests that in this force opposed to Jesus, this “Wheel
of Religion” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:13, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 232) Blake chooses to call by Caiaphas’s
name, he approaches the concept of an “Antichrist” in Northrop Frye’s sense of “the form which the
social hatred of Jesus creates out of Jesus” (387). <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Matthew 26:3-4, Mark
14:1, Luke 22:2, and especially John 11:47-53.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Matthew 26:75, Luke 22:62; emphasis mine.</note></p>
          <p>The keynote for the theme of the denial of Jesus is sounded by the quotation from the Acts of the
Apostles etched on the previous plate, plate 77: “Saul Saul” / “Why persecutest thou me.” These quoted
words of Christ recall that, before he heard them, Saul of Tarsus had set out for Damascus, “breathing out
threatenings and slaughter against the disciples of the Lord” (Acts 9:1), intending to suppress the
teachings of Jesus and destroy his following. In Blake’s view, the failure to give to the “Mental Gifts”
of Genius their due recognition amounts to exactly that—the rejection, persecution and mockery of Jesus:
<q>
O ye Religious discountenance every one among you who shall pretend to despise Art &amp; Science! . . . expel
from among you those who pretend to despise the labours of Art &amp; Science, which alone are the labours of
the Gospel . . . And remember: He who despises &amp; mocks a Mental Gift in another . . . mocks Jesus the
giver of every Mental Gift, which always appear to the ignorance-loving Hypocrite, as Sins. 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 231-32)
</q></p>
          <p>The last sentence quoted restates a lifelong conviction of Blake’s, affirmed by a Devil in the
final “Memorable Fancy”
<pb id="p32-64" n="64"/>
<figure n="but527.1.5.wc" id="but527.1.wc.05" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="821" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
	<head>3 One of Blake’s illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> (1801 series): “The Magic
Banquet with the Lady Spell-bound.”</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</figDesc>
</figure>
of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> of 1790 (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 22-23, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
43) and reiterated in peals of thunder by Los in a metrical paraphrase in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 91:5-12 
(<hi rend="i">E</hi> 251):
<q>
. . . Go to these Fiends of Righteousness . . .<lb/>
Go, tell them that the Worship of God, is honouring his gifts<lb/>
In other men: &amp; loving the greatest men best, each according<lb/>
To his Genius: which is the Holy Ghost in Man; there is no other<lb/>
God, than that God who is the intellectual fountain of Humanity;<lb/>
He who envies or calumniates: which is murder &amp; cruelty,<lb/>
Murders the Holy-one: Go tell them this . . .<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 91:4-12, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 251)
</q></p>
          <p>Through its association with the denial and persecution of Christ, the image of the cock thus
hints as well at the
<pb id="p32-65" n="65"/>
<figure n="jerusalem-d-93-detail.032.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="497">
	<figTranscr>93<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Anytus<lb/>
	Melitus<lb/>
	&amp; Lycon<lb/>
	thought Socrates<lb/>
	a very Pernicious<lb/>
	Man<lb/>
	<lb/>
	So Caiphas<lb/>
	thought Jesus<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Enitharmon heard. She raisd her head like the mild Moon<lb/>
 	<lb/>
 	O Rintrah! O Palamabron! What are your dire &amp; awful purposes<lb/>
 	Enitharmons name is nothing before you: you forget all my Love!<lb/>
 	The Mothers love of obedience is forgotten &amp; you seek a Love<lb/>
 	Of the pride of dominion. that wilt Divorce Ocalythron &amp; Elynittria<lb/>
 	Upon East Moor in Derbyshire &amp; along the Valleys of Cheviot<lb/>
 	Could you Love me Rintrah, if you Pride not in my Love<lb/>
 	As Reuben found Mandrakes in the field &amp; gave them to his Mother<lb/>
 	Pride meets with Pride upon the Mountains in the stormy day<lb/>
 	In that terrible Day of Rintrahs Plow &amp; of Satans driving the Team.<lb/>
 	Ah! then I heard my little ones weeping along the Valley:<lb/>
 	Ah! then I saw my beloved ones fleeing from my Tent<lb/>
 	Merlin was like thee Rintrah among the Giants of Albion<lb/>
 	Judah was like Palamabron: O Simeon! O Levi! ye fled away<lb/>
 	How can I hear my little ones weeping along the Valley<lb/>
 	Or how upon the distant Hills see my beloveds Tents.</figTranscr>
	<head>4 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 93 (detail), copy D.</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of the Houghton Library, Harvard University.</figDesc>
</figure>
gnawing private anguish Blake suffered because his own work had never achieved the recognition it deserved.
Especially during the later period of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s composition, Blake must have agonized
over the obscurity and neglect in which his art 
languished.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> 
In particular, he brooded upon the failure of his exhibition of 1809, and
the critical derision it had attracted—notably in the excoriating review by Robert Hunt published in 
<hi rend="i">The Examiner</hi> in September 1809. Blake was still smarting from that when he executed the later
plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, for in the design of <hi rend="i">J</hi> 93 he explicitly links
Caiaphas’s persecution of Christ to the stinging criticism of his own work by Robert Hunt and his two
brothers, co-editors of <hi rend="i">The Examiner</hi> (illus. 4). On the upper part of <hi rend="i">J</hi> 93
three male figures bend forward, each with one hand ostentatiously pointing ahead, as though in
accusation,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> and the other pointing
downward in condemnation. The name of Blake’s “Hand,” who—like Caiaphas—wishes “to Destroy the
Divine Saviour” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 18:37, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163), is derived from the pointing hand used
by the three Hunt brothers as their editorial siglum in <hi rend="i">The Examiner</hi>, and obviously
caricatured in this design. Perhaps Blake also associates other “false friends” (“Blakes apology” 12,
<hi rend="i">E</hi> 505) with these three figures, on which he has inscribed the words “Anytus / Melitus /
&amp; Lycon / thought Socrates / a Very Pernicious Man // So Caiaphas / thought Jesus” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
93).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> The word “Pernicious,” as
Erdman
<pb id="p32-66" n="66"/>
has shown,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> is quoted from Robert
Hunt’s review, both hostile and intolerably condescending in its tone, of 1809. In it Hunt diagnosed Blake
as mentally ill, calling him “an unfortunate lunatic,” his paintings “the ebullitions of a distempered
brain,” and the catalogue he published for the 1809 exhibition “the wild effusions of a distempered
brain.” In effect Hunt declared that any critic of art who praised Blake’s work must have been infected
with his “malady.” He wrote:
<q>
when the ebullitions of a distempered brain are mistaken for the sallies of genius the malady has indeed
attained a pernicious height, and it becomes a duty to endeavour to arrest its progress. Such is the case with
the productions and admirers of William Blake, an unfortunate lunatic, whose personal inoffensiveness secures
him from confinement.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref></q>
“Hand,” one of the most powerfully oppressive of the Sons of Albion, is Blake’s imaginative
characterization of what he perceived as the threat to art and indeed to <hi rend="i">humanity</hi> posed by
such outrageous Philistinism as that displayed in critiques of his work published in <hi rend="i">The
Examiner.</hi>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Paley comments: “In the circumstances of his life from 1810 to 1818,
years which Gilchrist rightly termed ‘Years of Deepening Neglect,’ it must have been difficult for Blake
to soldier on with a work which no one might ever buy or even read” (<hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi>,
6.).</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> “The Accuser” (or “the Adversary”) translates the Hebrew word
“Satan,” as Blake very well knew. The name “Satan” is used in this sense in the Book of Job and
elsewhere in the Old Testament. Blake perceived these critics as “accusers” and “adversaries,” the
enemies of creative humanity.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> The second sentence of this inscription appears on the rear end of the
central figure. It is tempting to associate it with Blake’s satirical “apology” in reply to the Hunts’
searing criticism of his <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> for his 1809 exhibition. Blake’s reply
concludes “This is my sweet apology to my friends / That I may put them in mind of their latter Ends”
(Notebook 65, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 505). Another vitriolic verse apparently related to this, addressed to
“Cosway Frazer &amp; Baldwin of Egypts lake . . .,” ends with the line “And all the Virtuous have shewn
their backsides” (Notebook 37, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 505). The latter poem incorporates a reference to Matthew
10:8, the text Blake also quotes in the blank-verse poem of <hi rend="i">J 77</hi>: “This Life is a Warfare
against Evils / They heal the sick he casts out Devils . . .” (3-4; Notebook 37, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 505).
Though in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> the context of the quotation is serious, it seems to me that Blake is
there concerned with exactly the same issues of betrayal as in the satirical outbursts.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 454.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Robert Hunt’s comments on Blake and his art are reproduced in full by
Bentley 215-18. The historical background is documented and discussed by David Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake:
Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 455-61.</note></p>
          <p>This is Blake’s concern in the first few lines of the text on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78. Los
wields his “mace of iron,” hitting out at “the rocky Spectres, as the Potter breaks the potsherds; /
Dashing in pieces Self-righteousnesses . . . driving them from Albions / Cliffs . . .” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
78:5-7, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 233). The lines refer to Isaiah 30:14, in which the prophet declares that the Lord
will shatter the iniquity of the Children of Israel “as the breaking of the potters’ vessel that is broken
in pieces . . . so that there shall not be found in the bursting of it a sherd to take fire from the hearth or
to take water withal out of the pit.” The verse Blake recalls is a rebuke to those “which say to the
seers, See not; and to the prophets, Prophesy not unto us right things” (Isaiah 30:9-10). Blake’s text,
and indeed, his whole book, enact the Lord’s command to Isaiah to issue a warning to those who despise the
prophet’s vocation and his message: “write it before them in a table, and note it in a book, that it may
be for the time to come” (Isaiah 30:8). The theme of the despising and mocking of “Mental Gifts,” and
most of all the prophetic gift of the visionary, is clearly uppermost in Blake’s mind as he sends Los to
drive “Self-righteousnesses . . . from Albions / Cliffs” in the text beneath his image of a bird-man
perched on those cliffs.</p>
          <p>Morton Paley points out, significantly, that “it would be uncharacteristic of Blake to present
a human body with an animal head as a positively charged image.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">16</ref> The scene on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 is filled with “negatively charged”
signs. I agree with Paley and those others who maintain that the sun <hi rend="i">is</hi> setting in this
scene. Twice in the text on subsequent plates we are told that “the night falls thick” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 83:61, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 242, 84:20, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 243), and when Los walks amongst
his Furnaces at <hi rend="i">J</hi> 85, he does so “in the deadly darkness” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 85:10,
<hi rend="i">E</hi> 244). Perhaps, like the “Wheel of Religion,” this sun is moving “against the current
of / Creation”; and perhaps Blake intended the gathering darkness to be the ironic antithesis of the
“light from heaven” (Acts 9:3) that miraculously surrounded Saul of Tarsus when, at high noon on the road
to Damascus, he heard the voice of Jesus uttering the words Blake inscribed at the head of <hi rend="i">J</hi>
77. In copy E the atmosphere of the sunset is not peaceful and luminous, but threatening. The sun is circled
by a black aura, and Blake even obliterated the heading “Jerusalem. C 4” that appears against a white
cloud in the black-and-white copies (for instance copy D, <hi rend="i">IB</hi> 357), painting over it in dark
purplish-black tones, “as though” Erdman comments, Blake “did not want anybody to be sure” 
(<hi rend="i">IB</hi> 357). The sun’s disk in copy E is flecked with black, contributing to the pervading gloom
reflected in the birdman’s sorrowful, even agonized, “expression” as he looks back on the preceding
three-quarters of the work: for the quarter of the sun visible on the horizon here also represents the last
quarter of the epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that is about to unfold. 
<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> Jerusalem</hi>, 261. Blake’s reading of Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>,
which he twice illustrated, may well have influenced his basic viewpoint. His second visual interpretation of
Milton’s masque was executed c. 1815, while work on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> was in progress. See
especially his rendering of the “ugly-headed monsters” (line 694), Comus’s dissolute followers, in 
<hi rend="i">The Magic Banquet with the Lady Spell-Bound</hi>, in the versions of both c. 1801 (reproduced above)
and c. 1815 (Butlin, cat. no. 528 5, pl. 628).</note></p>
          <p>The darkness and generally oppressive atmosphere could be attributed to the association of the
cock with the denial of Christ. A human figure with a head suggesting that of a cock, herald of the dawn and
symbol of resurrection, sadly, or angrily, contemplates a sun that appears to be <hi rend="i">setting</hi>,
when, according to tradition, the cock should look toward the <hi rend="i">rising</hi> sun.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> But it seems to me that another factor enters
into the image as well: one that expresses the concept of the “spiritual disease” which the poet is
commanded to heal in the blank-verse lyric on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 77, and at the same time
<pb id="p32-67" n="67"/>
lashes back at the diagnosis of mental illness that Robert Hunt had applied broadly both to Blake and his art
in his review of 1809. Perhaps, in one quite basic strand of meaning, Blake asserts that his detractors were
“cock-brained” in their judgement.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Lesnick rightly describes the design as “basically ironic. The cock’s
comb might suggest . . . that the figure is announcing the rising of the sun. In fact, the sun at the left is
setting, and the setting of the sun marks the beginning of the deepest night of Ulro” (400).</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> O.E.D. “Cock-brained: <hi rend="i">a.</hi> Having little judgement,
foolish, lightheaded.” The latest example of usage is dated 1856.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s design on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 has certain features in common with an illustration in
a sixteenth-century medical text, <hi rend="i">Feldtbůch der Wundartzney</hi>, by Hans von Gerssdorff, a
physician of Strassburg. I offer this illustration as a parallel only, since although it is well known that
Blake was drawn to old alchemical and scientific texts, valuing especially their emblems and illustrative
material,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> I have no means of proving
that he ever saw this particular work. But neither have I any doubt that he saw and noted pictorial
representations <hi rend="i">like</hi> this one, which is “generic” in its nature, as I will explain.
<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Kathleen Raine offers multiple instances of Blake’s interest in such
writings in <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition.</hi></note></p>
          <p>The first edition of von Gerssdorff’s work was published in Strassburg by Joannẽ Schott in
1517. It was well enough received to run into at least one subsequent edition, which appeared in
1532.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> The work is plentifully
illustrated with woodcuts. Many of these show, with a degree of scientific accuracy, anatomical dissections,
surgical instruments, and parts of the human body being subjected to their use by contemporary surgeons
attempting to repair injuries, especially those received in battle. This category of illustrations may well
have been “specific,” printed from blocks prepared especially for this work. But other illustrations seem
to be “generic,” related in only a general manner to the text—for instance, the handsome frontispiece
illustration showing the patron saints of medicine, Cosmas and Damian. The illustration I wish to discuss
seems to fall into this second category. It appears in the third “Tractat” of the work, in a section of
the text dealing with leprosy, but actually shows a victim of either smallpox or syphilis.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> This illustration, like the frontispiece
portrait of Cosmas and Damian, may also have been used by the same or another printer in other books (a
practice not uncommon at this period), and in contexts not necessarily medical. 
<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> The version I have used for reference is a facsimile of the first edition (1517), reproduced
from two original copies, one in the Universitätsbibliothek Heidelberg, and the other in a private
collection. I have also consulted a microfilm of a copy of the 1517 edition in the British Library in London.
The illustration I discuss appeared in both the 1517 and the 1532 editions. Though the work is divided into
numbered sections, the printer did not number individual pages. I am especially indebted to Professor
Hildegard Stielau of the Department of German of the Rand Afrikaans University, Johannesburg, for translating,
and for her scholarly guidance in reading, parts of this work. My thanks are due as well to Dr. Michael
Milway, Curator of the Center for Reformation and Renaissance Studies at the E. J. Pratt Library of Victoria
University, University of Toronto, for his patient assistance in providing information and a
photograph.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Jolande Jacobi (xiii; see note 24 below for reference) suggests that the
disease represented may be syphilis; Hildegard Stielau (personal communication) believes that the word 
<corr type="emend">“blonẽ”</corr> in the couplet on the frame (discussed in the body of this essay) may
indicate that whoever composed the couplet believed that the personage in the picture was afflicted with
smallpox. The consensus is that the disease depicted in the illustration is <hi rend="i">not</hi> the one
discussed by von Gerssdorff in the surrounding text. It seems unlikely that this respected physician, who
evidently wrote from extensive practical experience, would have confused leprosy with the symptoms and
development of these other two diseases, both all too familiar at the time—which implies that the choice of
illustration was not the author’s but (probably) the printer’s, and that it was not put in to illustrate a
specific scientific point.</note></p>
          <p>Von Gerssdorff describes in detail the manifestations of various forms of leprosy, drawing
heavily on such standard authorities as Galen, Avicenna, Averroes and Gordonius. He makes it clear that the
physician can do little or nothing for the patient suffering from this affliction, beyond amputating members
of the body that have become gangrenous in the course of the relentless degeneration characteristic of the
disease. Though von Gerssdorff himself eschews philosophic reflections, his illustrious contemporary
Paracelsus (with some of whose writings Blake had long been familiar<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n22" type="note">22</ref>) reminds both physician and patient that such a disease must be regarded as
a scourge of God. Paracelsus articulates a widely held view that accords with Marsilio Ficino’s concept of
the “priest-physician”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> when he
divides the diseases of man into “those which arise in a natural way, and those which come upon us as
God’s scourges.” For, he admonishes his colleagues,
<q>
God has sent us some diseases as a punishment, as a warning, as a sign by which we know that all our affairs
are naught, that our knowledge rests upon no firm foundation, and that the truth is not known to us, but that
we are inadequate and fragmentary in all ways, and that no ability or knowledge is ours.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref></q>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> S. Foster Damon writes that Blake found in the works of Paracelsus “a
preliminary sketch of his own universe” (Damon [1973], 322). In a poetic recapitulation of major influences
in his own intellectual development, Blake implies that he first read Paracelsus before “the American War
began”—that is, prior to 1776 (Letter to Flaxman, 12 September 1800, lines 7 and 9, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
707-08). See note 24 below.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> See Désirée Hirst’s account of Ficino’s influence on Paracelsus in
chapter 2 of <hi rend="i">Hidden Riches</hi> (44-75).</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Paracelsus, <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Werke.</hi> II. Abteilung. Die
theologischen und religionsphilosophischen Schriften. Ed. Karl Sudhoff and Wilhelm Matthiessen. Vol. 1.
(Munich: O.W. Barth, 1923) 12: 226. Trans. Norbert Guterman in <hi rend="i">Selected Writings</hi>, ed.
Jolande Jacobi, 81. Most of the major philosophical, medical and alchemical writings of Paracelsus had been
translated into English in the latter half of the seventeenth century. There was widespread interest in them
in England at this time, as there also was in the works of Jakob Boehme. Blake was equally interested in
Boehme’s work and also read it in seventeenth-century translations. Two of Paracelsus’s works in
translation that Blake is likely to have read are listed below under Works Cited. Jacobi uses the woodcut
under discussion, reproduced from the 1532 edition of von Gerssdorff’s book, to illustrate the passage from
Paracelsus cited in my text.</note></p>
          <pb id="p32-68" n="68"/>
          <figure n="hans-von-gerssdorff-feldtbuch-der-wundartzney.032.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="786">
          	<figTranscr>Got gab / got nã huss / hoff / kind / gůt /<lb/>
          	Und satzt mich unders teüfels růt.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Mein weyb / uñ blonẽ peingten mich /<lb/>
          	Noch lydt ichs alles gdultigslich.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Benedic <lb/>
          	deo, et <lb/>
          	morere.</figTranscr>
            <head>5 Woodcut from Hans von Gerssdorff’s <hi rend="i">Feldtbůch der Wundartzney</hi>
(1517).</head>
            <figDesc><supplied type="emend">Strassburg: Joannẽ Schott, 1517; Tractat iii. Reproduced from
the facsimile of the 1517 edition produced for Editions Medicina Rara Ltd. under the supervision of Agathon
Presse, Baiersbronn, West Germany, 1970. Photograph courtesy of the Centre for Reformation and Renaissance
Studies, E.J. Pratt Library; Victoria University, Toronto.</supplied> See note 20.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p32-69" n="69"/>
          <figure n="duerer-melencolia-i.032.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="774">
            <figTranscr>MELENCOLIA I<lb/>
            <lb/>
            VIIII X XI XII I II III IIII V<lb/>
            <lb/>
            16   3   2   13<lb/>
             5  10  11    8<lb/>
             9   6   7   12<lb/>
             4  15  14    1<lb/>
             <lb/>
             15[14]<lb/>
             AD<lb/>
            </figTranscr>
            <head>6 Albrecht Dürer’s <hi rend="i">Melencolia I.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the New York Public Library.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p32-70" n="70"/>
          <p>Opposite the beginning of von Gerssdorff’s section on leprosy, the printer has placed a woodcut
showing a sufferer who evidently represents the biblical Job, sitting on a hillside that slopes quite sharply
down from right to left (illus. 5). He is seen in profile on the viewer’s right, facing into the picture, in
an attitude comparable to that of Dürer’s <hi rend="i">Melencolia I</hi> and of Blake’s bird-man (illus.
6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> His right leg is bent, with his
right elbow resting on it, left hand under the right elbow, head slightly bowed and resting against his right
hand. He has no covering apart from a cloth draped across his loins, revealing that his whole body is covered
with blisters. Above his head a creature resembling a cockatrice hovers on dragon-like wings. This
“teüfel” has the head of a rooster, with the thin, sharply hooked beak of a fighting-cock or even a
predatory bird. It has the tail of a dragon or serpent, but its trunk with sagging belly and its muscular arms
and hands are those of a man. The creature grasps in each hand a long, bifurcated whip or scourge. It is
engaged in lashing the hapless victim on his back with the scourge held in the right hand, while that in the
left hand is drawn back to follow up swiftly with another cut. (The attitude of the partly serpentine
“teüfel” and its positional relationship to its victim suggest those of Blake’s serpent-entwined
Satanic “Elohim” in his painting “Job’s Evil Dreams,” c. 1805-06 [illus. 7].<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>) The victim’s wife stands before him at the viewer’s
left, primly elegant in a tight-sleeved high-necked dress and elaborate headgear. She piously urges her
husband “Benedic deo, et morere”—“Bless God, and die.” Job’s wife gave her husband this advice
when the Lord afflicted him “ulcere pessimo, a planta pedis usque ad verticem eius”—“with a very
grievous ulcer, from the sole of his foot even to the crown of his head” (Job 2:7-9). At the top of the
engraving two couplets are inscribed (no doubt by the printer), in German.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> In the first of these the victim speaks, in a loose
translation of Job 1:21, saying “Got gab / got <corr type="emend">nã</corr> huss / hoff / kind / 
<corr type="emend">gůt</corr> / // Und satzt mich unders teüfels růt” (“God gave / God took away / property /
children / goods // And set me under the devil’s rod . . .”), while in the second he refers to his
wife’s additions to his sufferings—implying the context of the quotation included within the frame of the
illustration: “Mein weyb / <corr type="emend">uñ</corr> <corr type="emend">blonẽ</corr> peingten mich //
Noch <corr type="emend">lydt</corr> ichs alles gdultigslich”— “My wife / and my blisters afflict me //
Yet I suffer all things in patience.” The artist has emphasized this saintly submission by surrounding the
sufferer’s head with a double aureole, extending all the way to the border of the engraving on all sides.
The visual effect is that of a sun, whose center is the profiled face of the sick man. 
<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Samuel Palmer, who visited Blake often in the rooms at Fountain Court in which he and his
wife lived after 1821, recalled that Blake kept a print of this work “close by his engraving table”
(Bentley 565n3). Judith Ott (49) first pointed out the parallel between the pose of Dürer’s “melancholy
angel” and Blake’s bird-man; but see Hirst’s discussion of the contextual significance of Dürer’s
image (44-48).</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Butlin cat. no. 550 <hi rend="i">11</hi>, pl. 707.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Many of the other woodcut illustrations are surmounted by couplets in a
similar tone, though those showing surgical procedures and instruments usually have explanatory prose
inscriptions, in German.</note></p>
          <p>My guess is that this design was produced originally to illustrated a text of the Book of Job.
Blake, whose preoccupation with the Book of Job extended throughout his creative life,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> would have paid attention to such a representation in any
context because of these specific associations. Kathleen Raine notes: “From an early stage Blake seems to
have identified the sickness of Albion with the sickness of Job,” and quotes from <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, Night the Third, p.41, lines 15-16 (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 328): “the dark Body of Albion left
prostrate upon the crystal pavement / Coverd with boils from head to foot.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Blake’s earliest Job illustrations date back to c. 1785; the latest,
the set of engravings commissioned by John Linnell, were executed in 1825, shortly before his death.
Quotations from, and echoes of, the Book of Job abound in Blake’s works from the earliest extant fragments
to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake and Tradition</hi> 2: 256.</note></p>
          <p>To return to <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78: one element of Blake’s creation is undoubtedly, I believe,
the Christian emblem of the cock. On the one hand it stands for the <hi rend="i">affirmation</hi> of life,
since it utters “that Signal of the Morning” of resurrection, here implied only through ironic
association. On the other hand, the cock can represent the <hi rend="i">denial</hi> of Jesus “the bright
Preacher of <hi rend="i">Life</hi>” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:21, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 232) by those hypocrites
who claim to follow him, but actually serve “Caiaphas, the dark Preacher of <hi rend="i">Death</hi>” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:18, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 232). But I suggest that another element of Blake’s composite
figure may be represented by the monstrous cockatrice, which yet is partly human—for he is an aspect of
“the Antichrist accursed . . . a Human Dragon terrible” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 89:10-11, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
248). The creature embodies the “infection” transmuted by Blake from a physical to a “spiritual
disease” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:25, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 233), the “infection of Sin &amp; stern
Repentance” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 38[43]:75, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 186). It is a scourge that causes the
sufferer to long for death. If Blake did have in mind an emblem like the one included in von Gerssdorff’s
book, then he replaced the head of the seated personage with that of his cockatrice-like persecutor—thus
casting the victim in the role of the disease itself—and removed the sun-like aureole from the head of the
sufferer in order to place it on the horizon. Paracelsus wrote: “The imagination is . . . the sun of man . .
. It irradiates the earth, which is man. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">30</ref> The sun in the scene on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 becomes a symbol of man’s 
<hi rend="i">diseased</hi> imagination, sinking in an aura of deep melancholy and about to be engulfed by “the
darkness of Philisthea” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 78:30, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 234), from which the voices of both
Jerusalem and the artist William Blake are heard lamenting. In the blank-verse poem on the preceding plate, a
heavenly “Watcher” commands the poet to heal those afflicted
<pb id="p32-71" n="71"/>
with this “spiritual disease.” The “Holy-One” who guided the prophet Daniel (Daniel 4:13) and has now
come to instruct the poet foresees that, through the “self-denial &amp; forgiveness of Sin” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:23, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 232) preached and practiced by Jesus, Albion may be cured of the
moralistic malaise bringing down all the “seven diseases of the Soul” (the traditional “Seven Deadly
Sins”) that “settled around [him] . . . as he builded onwards / On the Gulph of Death in
self-righteousness” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 19:26-27, 30-31, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 164). The diminishing sun in
the scene on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 sets beneath a “dark incessant sky” as the bird-man contemplates the
“Gulph of Death” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 19:22, 31, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 164).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> The bird-headed figure is both Philistine “ignorance with
a rav’ning beak!” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 19:13, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 152) and the “ignorance-loving
Hypocrite” persistently misrepresenting “Mental Gift[s] . . . as Sins” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77, 
<hi rend="i">E</hi> 232), who compels Jesus to die on the cross just as surely as did Caiaphas at the head of his
council of “Crucifying” Pharisees (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:28-30, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 233). The figure on
<hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 embodies the “disease forming a Body of Death around the Lamb / Of God, to destroy
Jerusalem &amp; to devour the body of Albion” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 9:9-10, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 152). In copy
E the malaise seems to erupt on the sun’s disk in black marks suggestive of the plague-sores covering the
body of the suffering Job-figure in von Gerssdorff’s book. The sick sun reflects the “corruptibility”
that Los sees upon the limbs of Albion (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 81:84 - 82:1, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 241), the
“spiritual disease” the poet is called upon to heal <hi rend="i">by revitalizing the imagination</hi>,
which Blake identified with Jesus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref>
Like other contemporary accounts of leprosy, von Gerssdorff’s description of the disease defines its
symptoms conventionally in terms of the medieval theory of humours, and stresses repeatedly the physical and
psychological role of “melancholy” or “black bile” in the development and progress of the illness. For
Blake too, as both Ott and Mitchell have observed, “melancholy” is a notable theme of the scene on 
<hi rend="i">J</hi> 78. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi><hi rend="i"> Paracelsus his Archidoxies</hi> (London,
1661), quoted by Damon (1965) 322.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Perhaps Blake associated the dark expanse of sea over which the bird-man
gazes with the “Sea of Rephaim” which eventually “oerwhelm[s] . . . all” in the revelation of the
“Covering Cherub” on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 89:50-51, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 249. Since this overwhelming
“Sea” extends to “Irelands furthest rocks where the Giants builded their Causeway,” the bird-man of
<hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 may be looking westwards across the Irish Sea (the “Giant’s Causeway” is on the
north coast of Antrim, Ireland). There is no mention of a “Sea of Rephaim” in the Bible (as Stevenson
points out [829]), but since Philistines encamped repeatedly in the <hi rend="i">Valley</hi> of Rephaim (2
Samuel 5:18, 22 and 23:13), Blake may have coined the phrase to describe the invasion of Philistinism. Blake
is pessimistically viewing the whole scene at this moment as the landscape of “Philisthea.”</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> “The Eternal Body of Man is The IMAGINATION./God himself/ that is / The
Divine Body / <hi rend="i">Y’shu’a</hi> JESUS we are his Members” (Blake, <hi rend="i">The Laocoön,
E</hi> 273).</note></p>
          <p>Albion is still “sick to death” as Blake opens this fourth chapter of his epic 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 36 [40]:12, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 182). He suffers “the torments of Eternal Death” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 36 [40]:25, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 182), dying piecemeal like the miserable leper whose physical
deterioration the good doctor of Strassburg records in ghastly detail in his text. The “Watcher” from
heaven calls upon the poet himself on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 77 to assume an apostolic and prophetic role like
that of Peter and later Paul, “in Christs name” to “cast out [the] devils” that scourge Albion in his
afflicted state, to “heal” the inhabitants of Albion of their “spiritual disease” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
77:24-25, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 233). On <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78, Albion has not yet achieved the condition
prophetically enacted on the chapter divider, <hi rend="i">J</hi> 76, in which he stands in the darkness of
his benighted island before Jesus, crucified upon the “deadly Tree . . . [of] Moral Virtue” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 28:15, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 174), and takes upon himself Christ’s divine humanity.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> But <hi rend="i">J</hi> 76 is a “visionary
study.” On <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78, Blake shows us symbolically the <hi rend="i">actual</hi> situation at
this pivotal point of his epic. Albion at this moment is “shrunk to a narrow rock in the midst of the sea”
(<hi rend="i">J 79:17, E</hi> 234) and is dominated—in fact, literally “sat upon”—by
“Self-righteousnesses” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 78:6, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 233), epitomized in the monstrous
figure of the bird-headed man, “Self-righteousness / In all its Hypocritic turpitude” 
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 38 [43]:43-44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 139). As Caiaphas himself may have contemplated the
dawning of that Friday on which he knew with certainty that the forces he had set into motion were to bring
about the death of Jesus, so this figure contemplates a horizon on which a sun that should be rising as a
bright source of life and light appears to be sinking into “deadly darkness.” The parallel is an exact
one. The bird-headed man embodies everything that Caiaphas, as the summation of the forces opposing Jesus,
represents for Blake: the Pharisaic hypocrisy, and the Philistinism, of individuals who—like Saul of Tarsus
and Robert Hunt—zealously persecute the spiritually gifted and vilify “Mental Gifts” like Blake’s own,
“which always appear to the ignorance-loving Hypocrite as Sins.” These are all to “become One with the
Antichrist” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 89:62, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 249). Blake may well, as Erdman asserts, have
meant this figure to represent “the sons of Albion . . . condensed . . . into Hand, with ‘rav’ning’
beak” (<hi rend="i">IB</hi> 357). But he also incorporates Caiaphas, the predator who preys on
creative—which is to say, <hi rend="i">meaningful</hi>—human life, “ravning to devour / The Sleeping
Humanity” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 78:2-3, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 233). He embodies the “spiritual disease” of
self-righteous morality from which Albion yet suffers, and expresses the immobilizing “melancholy” which
is one of its most destructive symptoms throughout the epic Jerusalem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">34</ref> The same melancholy afflicts the artist of genius whose gifts are reviled
and refused recognition—by which Jesus the Savior is denied as Peter denied him in a fearful, though in his
case momentary, fit of the “Hypocritic
<pb id="p32-72" n="72"/>
<figure n="but550.1.11.wc" id="but550.1.wc.11" work-copy="but550.1" rend="db" width="958" height="787">
	<figTranscr>אלהיך נתנ<lb/>
	<lb/>
	שםיה        לא תרצח<lb/>
	<lb/>
	לא תנאף<lb/>
	<lb/>
	תגנב<lb/>
	<lb/>
	inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
	<head>7 One of Blake’s illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi> (1805-06), “Job’s Evil
Dreams.”</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the Pierpont Morgan Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
turpitude” habitual to many of those of Blake’s own time and place who <hi rend="i">call</hi> themselves
“Christians,” but are in effect serving the arch-enemy of Christ, Caiaphas. 
<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> See Paley’s summary of conflicting critical interpretations of <hi rend="i">J</hi> 76 in
<hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi>, 113-18. Paley’s own conclusion, which I completely accept, is that
“the ‘naïve’ view of this picture, deriving from its immediate affect, fully accords with the central
doctrine of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> . . . which we find almost everywhere in Blake’s works. ‘Therefore
God becomes as we are, that we may be as he is’ (<hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> [b], 
<hi rend="i">E</hi> 2) . . .” (117). See also Mitchell, 209-11.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Compare <hi rend="i">J</hi> 36 [41]:59-60, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
183.</note></p>
          <p>True enlightenment <hi rend="i">will</hi> come—both the cock as an emblem of the sunrise and
St. John’s eagle with its apocalyptic associations imply that the “New Age” will dawn at last. So,
towards the end of his life, Blake was to reassure a future audience, and himself, in an inscription on his
engraving of “Job’s Evil Dreams” (1825): “the triumphing of the wicked is short, the joy of the
hypocrite is but for a moment” (Job 20:5).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">35</ref> By hinting at the visionary evangelist whose symbol was the eagle, the bird-man asserts
the visionary and prophetic role of the artist. And even though the figure in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 78 sits
before a sun that appears, ironically, to be setting, Blake implies a latent hope by suggesting the 
<hi rend="i">positive</hi> symbolic aspect of the cock, whose call signalled the awakening to renewed life:
“England! awake! awake! awake!” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 77:1, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 233). It is this hope of
spiritual renewal that Blake is to display as <hi rend="i">fulfilled</hi> in his prophetic conclusion to
Jerusalem, when the diseased “Body of death” is driven out, and all the birds and beasts in his broad
range of symbolism “. . . Humanize / In the Forgiveness of Sins” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 98:20, 44-45, 
<hi rend="i">E</hi> 257-58). <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the
Book of Job</hi> (London, 1825) 11; reproduced by Bindman, pl. 636.</note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Works Cited</title>
            </head>
            <p>Beer, John. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Universe.</hi> Manchester: Manchester University
Press, 1969.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G.E. Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, 1969.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Biblia Vulgata.</hi> Madrid: Biblioteca de Autores Cristianos, 1965.</p>
            <p>Bindman, David, comp. <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake.</hi> Assisted
by Deirdre Toomey. London: Thames and Hudson, 1978.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake.</hi> A Photographic and Typographic
Facsimile. Edited by David V. Erdman with the assistance of Donald K. Moore. Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1973.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman,
commentary by Harold Bloom. New York: Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New
Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1981.</p>
            <pb id="p32-73" n="73"/>
            <p>Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, 1924.
Gloucester, MA: Peter Smith, 1958.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary.</hi> 1965. Ed. Morris Eaves. London: Thames and Hudson,
1973.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire.</hi> 3rd ed. New York: Dover
Publications, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> London: Oxford University Press, 1975.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. and John E. Grant, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic.</hi>
Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1970.</p>
            <p>Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press,
1947.</p>
            <p>Hirst, Désirée. <hi rend="i">Hidden Riches.</hi> London: Eyre and Spottiswoode, 1964.</p>
            <p>Holy Bible, Douay-Rheims translation. Birmingham: C. Goodliffe Neale, 1955.</p>
            <p>Holy Bible, King James Version. New York: American Bible Society, 1967.</p>
            <p>Lesnick, Henry. “Narrative Structure and the Antithetical Vision of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” In <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, 391-412.</p>
            <p>Milton, John. <hi rend="i">The Poems.</hi> London: Longman, 1968.</p>
            <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of the Illuminated
Poetry.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1978.</p>
            <p>Ott, Judith. “The Bird-Man of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 10 (1976): 48-51.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press,
1983.</p>
            <p>—, ed. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> By William Blake. London: William Blake Trust / Tate
Gallery, 1991.</p>
            <p>Paracelsus. <hi rend="i">Selected Writings.</hi> Ed. with an Introduction by Jolande Jacobi.
Trans. Norbert Guterman. Bollingen Series 28. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1951-1988.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Archidoxes.</hi> Trans. J.H. [?James Howell]. London, 1661. 2 parts.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Philosophy Reformed &amp; Improved in four Profound Tractates.</hi> Trans. R.
Turner. London, 1657.</p>
            <p>Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition.</hi> Bollingen Series 35:11. 2 vols.
Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1968.</p>
            <p>—. “The Crested Cock.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 1 (1967-68): 9-10.</p>
            <p>Stevenson, W. H., ed. <hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> 2nd ed. London: Longman,
1989.</p>
            <p>von Gerssdorff, Hans. <hi rend="i">Feldtbůch der Wundartzney.</hi> Strassburg: Joannẽ
Schott, 1517. 2nd ed., 1532. Facsimile of 1517 edition reproduced for Editions Medicina Rara Ltd. under the
supervision of Agathon Presse, Baiersbronn, West Germany, 1970.</p>
            <p>Wicksteed, Joseph. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem. London: Trianon Press,
1954.</p>
            <p>Witke, Joanne. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Epic: Imagination Unbound.</hi> London: Croom
Helm, 1986.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
