<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.3.mertz</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">An Unrecorded Copy of Blake’s 1809 Chaucer Prospectus</title>
        <author n="Mertz">J. B. Mertz</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1998/99</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998/99</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998/9"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
	<pb id="p32-73" n="73"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">An Unrecorded Copy of Blake’s 1809 Chaucer Prospectus</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>J. B. <name>Mertz</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In August 1830, shortly after his visit to Oxford in the company of his friend Isaac D’Israeli,
the antiquarian and collector Francis Douce made his will, directing that his extensive collection of printed
books, drawings, prints, illuminated manuscripts, coins and medals should be left to the Bodleian
Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">1</ref> After his death in 1834 the
library received one of its most valuable bequests, which included several works by Blake: <hi rend="i">The
Book of Thel</hi> (I), <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (B), <hi rend="i">A Descriptive
Catalogue</hi> (H), and the print <hi rend="i">Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> (impression 3D).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">2</ref> Douce kept a record of his purchases in a set
of three notebooks entitled “Collecta,” which show that he acquired “Blake’s marr. of heaven &amp;
hell’ in April 1821 from “Dyer”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">3</ref>
and “Blake’s print of Canterbury pilgrimage” in November 1824 from the publishers and printsellers
“Hurst [and Robinson].”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">4</ref> Four
months later, in March 1825, Douce returned to Hurst and Robinson’s shop, recording the acquisition of
“Blake’s Canterbury Pilgr.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">5</ref>
Joan Stemmler suggests that this is “probably a double entry” for the print of the Canterbury
Pilgrims,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">6</ref> but more likely it refers
to the hitherto unknown second copy of Blake’s 1809 Chaucer Prospectus in the Bodleian Library. Douce pasted
the prospectus onto the fly-leaf inside the back cover of his copy of the first volume of <hi rend="i">The
Canterbury Tales of Chaucer</hi> (edited by Thomas Tyrwhitt and published in 1798).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">7</ref> Like the sole copy (A) in the British Museum Print Room
recorded by G. E. Bentley, Jr., the Bodleian copy is a broadsheet approximately 18.65 × 22.7 cm., printed on
the recto with the verso blank.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">1</hi> [Samuel Weller Singer], “Francis Douce, Esq. F. S. A.,” 
<hi rend="i">The Gentlemen’s Magazine</hi> 156 (1834): 216-17.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">2</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford, 1977) 128, 134
and 298, and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (Princeton,
1983) 63. Only <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> are listed in the 
<hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Printed Books and Manuscripts Bequeathed by Francis Douce, esq., to the Bodleian
Library</hi> (Oxford, 1840) 32.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Bodleian Library, MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 40<hi rend="s">v</hi>.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">4</hi> MS. Douce e. 68, fol. 2<hi rend="s">v</hi>. The “Collecta” do not
indicate when or from <corr type="emend">whom</corr> he acquired <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> or <hi rend="i">A Descriptive
Catalogue.</hi></note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">5</hi> MS. Douce e. 68, fol. 3<hi rend="s">v</hi>.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">6</hi> “Undisturbed above once in a Lustre’: Francis Douce, George Cumberland
and William Blake at the Bodleian Library and Ashmolean Museum,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 26 (1992):
18n145.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See the <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Printed Books and Manuscripts
Bequeathed by Francis Douce</hi>, 63, and G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi>
(Oxford, 1988) 132.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s Writings</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr.
(Oxford, 1978) ii, 823-24 and 1692.</note></p>
          <pb id="p32-74" n="74"/>
          <p>We also have evidence that Douce’s interest in illustrations of Chaucer extended beyond
Blake’s print. Facing Blake’s prospectus in Douce’s Chaucer (i.e., pasted on the inside of the back
cover) is the prospectus for a rival project: Robert Hartley Cromek’s print after Stothard’s “The
Procession of Chaucer’s Pilgrims to Canterbury.” This prospectus is dated “<hi rend="i">London,
Feb.</hi> 10<hi rend="i">th</hi>, 1807.” Douce praised Stothard’s painting in his book 
<hi rend="i">Illustrations of Shakspeare, and of Ancient Manners</hi>, claiming that the “attention to accuracy
of costume which it displays has never been exceeded, and but very seldom so well directed.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">9</ref> In a notebook listing books received, he also
records in 1809 that “Cromeck” gave him a copy of “Carey’s description of Stodart’s picture of the
pilgrimage to Canterbury,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">10</ref> but
Douce apparently never purchased the print. Should he have desired a copy, Douce certainly had the means,
especially after his receipt in 1827 of an estimated £50,000 as residuary legatee of the estate of his friend
Joseph Nollekens. He was clearly aware of Cromek and Blake’s projects, even placing their prospectuses
facing one another in a volume of Chaucer. But perhaps he concluded, on the basis of his antiquarian
expertise, that Blake’s print was the more historically accurate representation and (like Charles Lamb)
“preferred it greatly to Stoddart’s.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">11</ref> There is a small engraving (approximately 5.1 × 17.6 cm.)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">12</ref> by W. H. Worthington after Stothard’s painting pasted onto
the titlepage of the same copy of Chaucer, but it is obviously not the print “3 Feet 1 Inch long, and 10 1/2
Inches high” that Cromek undertook to deliver to his subscribers. Although no definitive catalogue of the
prints bequeathed by Douce to the Bodleian has been compiled, there appears to be no copy of Cromek’s print
after Stothard’s painting in the present collection. Most of Douce’s print collection (as well as some of
the manuscripts and drawings he owned) was transferred to the Ashmolean Museum in 1863, and more prints and
drawings were added from the Bodleian holdings in 1915.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Francis Douce, <hi rend="i">Illustrations of Shakspeare, and of Ancient
Manners: with Dissertations on the Clowns and Fools of Shakspeare; on the Collection of Popular Tales Entitled
Gesta Romanorum; and on the English Morris Dance</hi> (London, 1808) ii, 285 fn.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">10</hi> MS. Douce e. 69, fol. 9<hi rend="s">v</hi>. William [Paulet] Carey, 
<hi rend="i">Critical Description of the Procession of Chaucer’s Pilgrims to Canterbury, Painted by Thomas
Stothard, Esq. R.A.</hi> (London, 1808) 11, reprints Douce’s commendatory remarks on Stothard’s painting.
Cromek circulated Carey’s essay to promote the sale of the print. See <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, 777 and
G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (Oxford, 1995) 431-32.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">11</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford, 1969)
538.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">12</hi> This engraving was published by “W. Pickering &amp; R. &amp; S. Prowett
London 1822.”</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">13</hi> See Arthur Cornwallis Madan and George Rodney Scott’s rough handlist
<hi rend="i">A Catalogue of the Collection of Engravings, &amp;c. in Portfolios bequeathed by Francis Douce in
1835</hi>, 2 vols. (1913-15, 1916). Douce’s copies of <hi rend="i">Thel, The Marriage</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> remain in the Bodleian collection. I would like to thank Ursula
Mayr-Harting of the Ashmolean Museum for her kind assistance.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
