<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.3.donald</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Diana Donald, The Age of Caricature: Satirical Prints in the Reign of George
III</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander S. Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1998/99</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998/99</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998/9"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
	<pb id="p32-74" n="74"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Diana Donald, <hi rend="i">The Age of Caricature: Satirical Prints in the Reign
of George III.</hi> New Haven: Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1996. viii + 248 pp.
$65/cloth;$30/paper [Yale University Press, 1998].</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Alexander S. <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Upon seeing it, most scholars of Blake and Romanticism will immediately want to read and even to
own this book, which promises to cover a lot of material, little of it easily available elsewhere, that is
essential background for any literary or art-historical study of the period. The book includes 210
high-quality reproductions of satirical prints, many in color and most in a large enough scale to permit
study, and the text is extensive. Once one starts reading it, it becomes clear that Donald knows a great deal
about these prints and that she thinks about them in sophisticated and original ways. But many readers are
likely to be somewhat frustrated, not so much by shortcomings of the book as by the fact that the topic is
simply too large and too complex to be susceptible to summary on this scale, however astute the summarizer.
Each of the chapters could have been a lavishly illustrated book in itself, and while it is obvious that
Donald has enough good ideas to fill a dozen volumes, this book provides only tantalizing and sometimes
exasperating glimpses of the main topics. Donald knows well that works in popular culture embody and convey
meaning in extremely complicated ways, and she tries gamely to indicate how various audiences would have
responded to these works, but the result is barely adequate even as an overview. Other recent books that
investigate the role of popular culture in Georgian political and literary discourse, such as those by Vincent
Carretta, Iain McCalman and David Worrall, have been more satisfying and more coherent, mostly because they
address similar material from well defined if comparatively limited perspectives. Donald’s broader approach
permits only cursory examination of the way a given constituency might read a few aspects of a given piece. As
a result, we rarely get much feeling for the work as a whole, much less its place in the vast web of relevant
contexts that inform it. It is captious to criticize a book for not being what it is not meant to be, but a
narrower or a longer book would have been a better one.</p>
          <p>A related problem is that the work of Gillray so thoroughly dominates the illustrations and the
discussion of them. This is understandable—Gillray was the most powerful caricaturist of the period (perhaps
of any period), and his works remain much more interesting than those of his
<pb id="p32-75" n="75"/>
contemporaries. His fierce approach to caricature went to molecular depth: each form—animal, vegetable, and
even mineral—appears to have a completely imagined grotesque anatomy, with hideous bones below the skin and
nasty little corpuscles coursing through the veins. Further, Gillray’s extraordinary command of the
languages of high and low art, combined with his intellectual depth, broad learning (and that of his
collaborators), profound political cynicism, and well documented susceptibility to influence and bribery from
all quarters, permit (even require) every etching to be read in at least a half-dozen ways. His work is so
powerful, so rich, and so influential that he inevitably dominated the scene, just as he continues to dominate
modern studies of it. But as Donald tries to show, he was only one of many influential caricaturists: to
understand the Age of Caricature, one must also be steeped in the work of James Sayers, Isaac Cruikshank,
Richard Newton, William Dent, Thomas Rowlandson, and many others. And to understand even one work by Gillray
or these secondary artists one must usually place it in the whole bubble of prints (and other ephemera) that
arose about each public issue; most prints, even those by one-hit wonders and amateurs, respond elaborately to
both immediate and broader contexts. A similar claim could be made about almost any work of art, and
especially of such elaborately cross-referential works as Renaissance sonnets, but I am persuaded that
caricature prints of this period are uniquely interdependent: they respond so intricately to each other and to
the cultural currents around them that the essential context for a given print often seems limitless. Donald
offers a pretty good selection of non-Gillray material—the work of all the artists listed above are
represented by several good examples—and she even ventures beyond the world of satirical prints to show how
they respond to other media and cultural forms. But one can’t get a proportionate sense of Gillray’s
contribution to the caricature tradition unless one is willing to read this book while juggling M. Dorothy
George’s fat volumes of the British Museum’s <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Personal and Political Satires</hi>
and simultaneously rolling through the thousands of images in the Chadwyck-Healey microfilms of the British
Museum collection.</p>
          <p>Because most readers of this journal are likely to approach this book as an adjunct to studying
Blake and his circle, it makes sense to consider it in those terms. David Erdman and others have demonstrated
that Blake borrowed widely from contemporary caricatures, especially in his illuminated books, and although
Blake famously claimed that excessive exposure to Rowlandson’s caricature prints had “perverted” the eye
of Dr. Trusler, there is plenty of evidence that Blake himself studied and responded to the work of both major
and minor caricaturists. Donald is aware of all this, and at various times she reads the prints as a
sophisticated artist of the 1790s might have done, but few will come away from reading this book with a
substantially different sense of the context of Blake’s work. That is not to say there is nothing of
interest to Blake scholars. Although the ideas are not developed very thoroughly, Donald comments suggestively
about Gillray’s debt to Lavater and current physiognomical literature, which were of great interest to
Blake. Further, she outlines several ways in which modes of caricature that are not obviously political or
personal—such as the low comic “drolls” by “Tim Bobbin” [John Collier]—could have varying
political implications. Her insights on this point are also important for Blake scholars because they can help
us in thinking about the significance of Blake’s only foray into the caricature print trade, the work he did
in engraving after Stothard (who couldn’t quite get the hang of it) and Collings for <hi rend="i">The
Wit’s Magazine</hi> in 1784, when it was edited by the radical Thomas Holcroft. Blake’s mixed-method
etching/engravings after Collings’s loopy drawings are firmly within the shaggy tradition of “Bobbin,”
Isaac Cruikshank and others, even if they seem very odd when we come upon them among his other commercial
works.</p>
          <p>Donald is particularly successful when she brings to bear her training as an art historian, which
is probably why she is so good at spotting the many ways in which Gillray and to a lesser extent the others
responded to higher art. She is deeply learned about Hogarth, and often notes that a particular device or
theme in a caricature print is a crib or an homage—and that the later artists are often aware of the sources
to which Hogarth himself was responding. Especially because the Tory wing of Hogarth criticism still howls
whenever Ronald Paulson argues for a political and subversive Hogarth, it is instructive to see that the
subtle mechanisms of conveying meaning that Paulson has elucidated were also recognized by artists only a
generation away from Hogarth, and that they repeated them, often without his subtlety.</p>
          <p>This is a well made book. The reproductions are usually large enough to reveal the features to
which Donald’s text refers, and while a few are too small to study even with a magnifying glass, most are
very good. The paper is a little too glossy for comfortable reading, but it is fairly opaque, the typeface is
small but readable, and the quality of the printed images is very good indeed. If the format, the
illustrations, or the typeface had been larger, the book would have cost much more, and if the illustrations
had been massed at the back and the text printed on less glossy paper it would have been much more difficult
to follow Donald’s exposition.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Carretta, Vincent. <hi rend="i">George III and the Satirists from Hogarth to Byron.</hi>
Athens, GA: U of Georgia P, 1990.</p>
            <p>George, M. Dorothy. <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Political and Personal Satires Preserved in the
Department of Prints and Drawings</hi>
	<pb id="p32-76" n="76"/>
	<hi rend="i">in the British Museum</hi>, vols. 5-11. London: British Museum, 1940-54.</p>
            <p>McCalman, Iain. <hi rend="i">Radical Underworld: Prophets, Revolutionaries, and Pornographers
in London, 1795-1840.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, 1993.</p>
            <p>Worrall, David. <hi rend="i">Radical Culture: Discourse, Resistance, and Surveillance,
1790-1820.</hi> Detroit: Wayne State UP, 1992.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
