<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.3.hoagwood</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Wayne Glausser, Locke and Blake: A Conversation across the Eighteenth
Century</title>
        <author n="Hoagwood">Terence Allan Hoagwood</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1998/99</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998/99</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998/9"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
	<pb id="p32-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Wayne Glausser, <hi rend="i">Locke and Blake: A Conversation Across the
Eighteenth Century.</hi> Gainesville, FL: University Press of Florida. 1998. xi + 201pp. $49.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Terence Allan <name>Hoagwood</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Despite its title, this is not a philosophical book;<ref target="n55" type="note">1</ref>
instead, it is “a composite critical biography . . . neither continuous nor complete” (ix), narrating and
discussing episodes for comparison. The incompleteness of the biographical accounts results in part from a
shortage of evidence (“records are scarce from [Locke’s] years in political exile” [3], and “neither
man said much of anything about his mother” [13], but to a greater degree it results from a selectivity in
favor of coincidence. <note id="n55"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For accounts of the philosophical issues that are
important for a comparison of Locke with Blake, see Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>
(Princeton UP, 1947), which Glausser mentions briefly, and also two books which Glausser does not mention:
Morton Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and Imagination</hi> (Oxford, Clarendon, 1970); and Terence Allan Hoagwood,
<hi rend="i">Prophecy and the Philosophy of Mind</hi> (Tuscaloosa, U of Alabama P, 1985).</note></p>
          <p>An introductory chapter states the book’s aim to suggest a conversation between Locke and
Blake, in imitative or rhetorical accordance with Locke’s remark that “‘Difference of Opinions in
conversation’ brings about ‘the greatest Advantage of Society’” (3, quoting Locke’s 
<hi rend="i">Some Thoughts Concerning Education</hi>). The second chapter affirms that “both [Locke and Blake]
participated in conventional representations of gendered desire, yet both of them resisted traditional
romantic plots and looked for alternatives to ordinary marriage” (12); this chapter narrates some of
Locke’s “amorous relationships” (15) and “Blake’s feelings about conjugal love” (43) that involved
challenging Locke’s representation of the body. Chapter 4 shows that Locke condemned slavery and also
“participated in the slave trade” (62), whereas Blake’s opposition to slavery was not similarly
contradictory. In chapter 5, the book explains that “both were accused of sedition” but “neither was
convicted” (92). A chapter on the topic of possessions and theory of property proceeds by comparing the
anger that each man expressed when he thought that someone had stolen a picture from him. Another chapter
explains “Locke’s immersion in print consciousness and Blake’s reaction against it” (145). The
concluding chapter compares Locke’s epitaph (“ . . . A scholar by training, he devoted his studies wholly
to the pursuit of truth”) with Blake’s inscription in an autograph album (“. . . what is done without
meaning is very different from that which a Man Does with his Thought &amp; Mind”), and Glausser
paraphrases: “artists try to create meaningful structures against the reign of ‘Nature’ and
‘Chance,’ full of hogs and humans, signifying nothing” (165).</p>
          <p>Some of the research is primary, referring to Locke’s papers that are now in the Bodleian
Library, but most draws on familiar sources—e.g., Maurice Cranston’s biography of Locke, E. S. DeBeer’s
edition of Locke’s letters, and Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">2</ref> Some of the research and argumentation is both interesting
and important—on, for example, the contradictions in Locke’s responses (in writing and in his own
financial investments) to slavery, and on Locke’s involvement in the print trade, literally and in his
development of print metaphors. Sometimes, however, the reliance on secondary research leads to problems, as
it almost inevitably will: Glausser attributes to a personal letter written by Damaris Cudworth a passage
about “an Active Sagacitie in the Soul whereby something being Hinted to Her she runs out into a More Cleare
and large Conception,” whereas that passage was written by Henry More, her father’s fellow Cambridge
Platonist; Damaris Cudworth is merely quoting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Maurice Cranston, <hi rend="i">John Locke: A Biography</hi> (Oxford:
Oxford UP, 1957); E. S. DeBeer, <hi rend="i">The Correspondence of John Locke</hi>, 8 vols. (Oxford: Oxford
UP, 1976-83); G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1969); Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1989).</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The sentence, from Henry More’s <hi rend="i">Antidote Against
Atheism</hi>, is both quoted and attributed to More in Hoagwood’s <hi rend="i">Prophecy and the Philosophy
of Mind</hi> 14.</note></p>
          <pb id="p32-85" n="85"/>
          <p>Given the readership of <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, I should point out that
the discussions of Blake’s writings are thematic in what was once a conventional manner, as in the important
books by S. Foster Damon,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">4</ref> translating
Blake’s signifiers into abstract ideas: for example, in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, “Blake used ‘female
space’ to mean an illusory infinity that makes someone feel small and impotent” (5). Clearly, some of the
topics discussed in <hi rend="i">Locke and Blake</hi>—slavery, gender, sedition—are shared among studies
much more recent than Damon’s,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">5</ref> but
the interpretive method and project in this book are often apparently innocent of theoretical sophistication:
“The speaker is Leutha, Satan/Hayley’s emanation, who tells of his feminization and consequent attraction
to Palambron/Blake.” A note discredits the biographical equivalence (“no Blakean character should ever be
reduced to its biographical referent” [171n90]), but there the discredited interpretation sits. 
<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">4</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (New York: P. Smith, 1924); and
Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi> (Providence: Brown UP,
1965).</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See, e.g., John Mee, <hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm: William Blake and
the Culture of Radicalism in the 1790s</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1992); E. P. Thompson, <hi rend="i">Witness
Against the Beast: William Blake and the Moral Law</hi> (New York: New Press, 1993); Terence Allan Hoagwood,
<hi rend="i">Politics, Philosophy, and the Production of Romantic Texts</hi> (DeKalb: Northern Illinois UP,
1996).</note></p>
          <p>Sometimes the interpretive reductions involve an apparent exploitation of a coincidence, or an
apparent attempt rhetorically to invent a connection between Locke and Blake: for example, in comparing
Blake’s putatively therapeutic mission with Locke’s actual work as a physician, Glausser writes that Blake
“liked to represent England as a single body (Albion), whose health . . . would be restored” (53).
Observing that “Locke’s philosophy had turned the body from ‘the human form divine’ into an atomized
material object” and that “Blake’s renovated imagination would undo the damage,” Glausser produces
this passage (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 26: 31-33) as an illustration of the supposedly shared interest in
healing a physical body: “And every Generated Body in its inward form, / Built by the Sons of Los in
Bowlahoola and Allamanda.” I would suggest, however, that, rather than resembling Locke’s work as a
physician, that passage might be susceptible of a figurative interpretation. Sometimes the interpretive
reductions in <hi rend="i">Locke and Blake</hi> express what might appear to be naive intentionalism, saying,
for example, that “Blake wanted to reenchant the body by finding primary spiritual causes” (53); after a
few decades of rigorously antifoundational theorizing, many of us would be shy of saying, on the basis of a
literary text, what the author “wanted” thereby. To think of the author as a function, for instance, as
Foucault suggests, dissolves the terms of the question; any variety of deconstruction (e.g., Kenneth
Burke’s, or Derrida’s, or DeMan’s) would see that the terms of the question <hi rend="i">are terms</hi>
and not persons; Marxists have been loudly critical of the bourgeois construction of the individual on which
that interpretive remark about what Blake “wanted” is based; and I (or you) could go on: it is very late
in the theoretical day to affirm, as if with confidence, and merely on the basis of a poem’s text, what
“Blake wanted.” Even the desire to write in that way is starting to look obsolete.</p>
          <p>What is best about the book, then, is not its scholarship or its interpretations, and not (to my
mind) the sometimes far-fetched or merely rhetorical constructions of analogy, but rather its easy-going
anecdotalism, which is most enjoyable when one no longer has to worry about whether the research is original,
derived, or mixed, or whether the interpretations are rigorous. The chapter on seditious plots, for example,
narrates Locke’s possible involvement in conspiracies and comments interestingly on the legally seditious
character of some passages in the manuscript of <hi rend="i">Two Treatises of Government</hi> as well as
radical texts that may or may not have been written by Locke; and, noticing that Locke destroyed his letters
that pertained to conspiracies against the king, Glausser infers sensibly that “Locke, like other radicals,
may have encrypted his references to plots with metaphors of gardening, medicine, business, and so forth”
(95). (I will add that the practice of encryption that Glausser describes was in fact so commonplace that
Swift was able to satirize it hilariously in part 3 of <hi rend="i">Gulliver’s Travels</hi>, where
decryption experts in political employment decode the remark, “Our brother Tom has got the piles.”)</p>
          <p>Literary studies have been showing a great deal of interest in several of the topics mentioned in
this clearly written book, including slavery, gender, and sedition; and further, the “conversation” model
has been gathering interest as well, though <hi rend="i">Locke and Blake</hi> is innocent of the sort of
theoretical complications associated with Jerome McGann’s dialogues or the work of Bakhtin on which
McGann’s dialogism is largely based.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">6</ref> Further still, the book is free of the sort of sentences that one’s undergraduate
students will profess an inability to understand. For Blakeans unfamiliar with Locke or for Lockeans
unfamiliar with Blake, there is probably interesting biographical material here with some likewise interesting
discussion of its implications in intellectual history. While one cannot foresee the book’s having an effect
in the scholarly fields, it is, for all those reasons, likely to interest those with sufficient leisure to
read it. <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For one example, see George Mannejc, Ann Mack, J. J. Rome, and
<corr type="emend">Joanne McGrem,</corr> “A Dialogue on Dialogue,” <hi rend="i">Postmodern Culture: An Electronic Journal of
Interdisciplinary Criticism</hi> 2 (1991). On McGann’s interest in Bakhtin, see Anne Mack and Jay Rome,
“Marxism, Romanticism, and Postmodernism: An American Case History,” in <hi rend="i">Dialogue and Critical
Discourse: Language, Culture, Critical Theory</hi>, ed. Michael Macovski (New York: Oxford UP,
1997).</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
