<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.3.animated</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">The Animated Blake</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1998/99</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998/99</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998/9"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
      <pb id="p32-86" n="86"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">The Animated Blake</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>James Jay is creating a juggling show, “The Animated Blake,” which will premiere at the
Seattle Fringe Festival in March, 1999. Blake’s work will be illuminated by a variety of physical arts:
juggling, movement, staff spinning, incense burner swinging, puppetry, and book manipulation. The audience
will be served a fortune cookie communion featuring the Proverbs of Hell. From Jay’s webpage:
<q>
    William Blake was considered a Freak during his lifetime and a Genius after his death. “The Animated
Blake” embraces both the freak and the genius, illuminating the artist’s visionary poetry with juggling
and manipulation.<lb/>
<lb/>
    The show follows the “routine” format of a poetry reading or musical revue. It has no plot line, but
is shaped by an aesthetic and conceptual progression. An opposition between Innocence and Experience gives way
to subtle blends of good and evil through the “Marriage of Heaven and Hell.” To underscore this thematic
arrangement of the texts, the host has a split personality (a la <corr type="emend">Dr. Jekyll</corr> and Mr.
Hyde) which merges into a single character during the marriage.<lb/>
<lb/>
    In addition to recitations, Blake’s poetry will be presented in musical accompaniment. The Proverbs of
Hell will be dispensed in fortune cookies during a “communion” ceremony. Slide projections will bring
Blake’s visual art into the show, and may convey his texts, as well.<lb/>
<lb/>
This literary freakshow will be created and performed by James Jay, the inventor of the high-tech Juggling
Jukebox. The director is Jenny Iacobucci.
</q></p>
          <p>For a complete description, see www.jamesjay.com/wordup.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
