<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.3.update</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">William Blake Archive Update</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1998/99</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1998/99</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1998/9"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
      <pb id="p32-86" n="86"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">William Blake Archive Update</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The editors of the William Blake Archive 
                    &lt;http://www.iath.virginia.edu/blake/&gt; are pleased to announce the opening of a major
new wing of the site, devoted to documentation and supplementary materials “About the Archive.” Available
as the first entry on our main table of contents page from the URL above, the “About the Archive”
materials consist of:</p>
          <p>A brief overview of the Archive for first-time or hurried users, entitled The Archive at a
Glance; a statement of Editorial Principles and Methodology; a technical summary of the Archive’s design and
implementation; a Frequently Asked Questions list; a reference page listing articles by members of the project
team, as well as reviews and notices of the Archive by others; an updated and expanded version of the
article-length Plan of the Archive, providing additional detail about our intentions with regard to Blake’s
non-illuminated works.</p>
          <p>Also included are information about the editors, an account of the editors’ collaboration with
the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, and a link to our extensive Help documentation. In
addition, we will shortly be adding a Tour of the Archive to these materials (combining textual narration,
graphical screenshots, and suggestions as to how to use the Archive). A complete update can be found at the
Archive website. [Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi]</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
