<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.4.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
1998</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
        <author n="Aoyama">Keiko Aoyama</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1999</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1999</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <title/>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Patrick Noon</name>
              <name>Ian Singer</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1999"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-4-0006">
        <pb id="p32-114" n="114"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
1998</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor><lb/>
            <hi rend="i">With the Assistance of <docAuthor>Keiko <name>Aoyama</name></docAuthor> for Japanese
Publications</hi>
		  </byline>
		  <p>The annual checklist of scholarship and discoveries concerning William Blake and his circle records
publications for the current year (say, 1998) and those for previous years which are not recorded in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995), and “William Blake and
His Circle” (1994-98). The organization of the checklist is as follows:</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <table rows="6" cols="2">
              <row>
                <cell>Part I:</cell>
                <cell>Editions, Translations, and Facsimiles of Blake’s Writings<lb/>
Section A: Original Editions and Reprints<lb/>
Section B: Collections and Selections</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part II:</cell>
                <cell>Reproductions of his Art</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part III:</cell>
                <cell>Commercial Book Engravings</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part IV:</cell>
                <cell>Catalogues and Bibliographies</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part V:</cell>
                <cell>Books Blake Owned</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Part VI:</cell>
                <cell>Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Note:</hi> Collections of essays on Blake and issues of periodicals devoted entirely to him are
listed in one place, with cross-references to their authors.</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <p>Reviews listed here are only for books which are substantially about Blake, not for those with
only, say, a chapter on Blake. These reviews are listed under the book reviewed; the authors of the reviews
may be recovered from the index.</p>
            <p>I take <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>
(1995), faute de mieux, to be the standard bibliographical authorities on Blake<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> and have noted significant differences from them. 
<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Except for the states of the plates for Blake’s commercial book engravings,
where the standard authority is R. N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
Illustrations</hi> (1991).</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>This division is organized by individual (say, William Hayley or John Flaxman), with works by
and about Blake’s friends and patrons, living individuals with whom he had significant direct and
demonstrable contact. It includes Thomas Butts, Robert Hartley Cromek, George Cumberland, John Flaxman and his
family, Henry Fuseli, Thomas and William Hayley, John Linnell and his family, Samuel Palmer, James Parker,
George Richmond, Thomas Stothard, and John Varley. It does <hi rend="i">not</hi> include important
contemporaries with whom Blake’s contact was negligible or non-existent such as John Constable and William
Wordsworth and Edmund Burke; such major figures are dealt with more comprehensively elsewhere, and the light
they throw upon Blake is very dim.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">N.b.</hi> I have made no systematic attempt to record manuscripts and typescripts,
chinaware,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> computer print outs, radio
or television broadcasts,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> calendars,
festivals and lecture series,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
furniture with inscriptions, microforms, music, pillows, poems, posters, published scores, recorded readings
and singings, rubber stamps, T-shirts, tattoos, video-recordings, or email related to Blake. 
<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> For example, the white bone china bud vase decorated with “The Sick Rose” apparently
produced by Coalport for the 1978 Tate exhibition (see R. N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 1998,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [1999]).</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See Sarah Joyce, review of “South Bank Show Documentary on Blake.
Directed by David Thomas. ITV (U.K.), 17 September 1995,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 102-03.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> E.g., (1) “Blake and the Book,” Strawberry Hill (England), 18 April
1998; (2) “Blake Course at the Tate Gallery” (London, England), 12 May-9 June 1998; (3) “William Blake
&amp; His Circle,” exhibition and lecture series at the Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery (England), 22
June-6 Sept 1998; (4) Blake Festival as part of the annual Olavfestdagene (Trondheim, Norway), 25-28 July
1998.</note></p>
            <p>The status of electronic “publications” becomes increasingly vexing. Some such works seem
to be merely electronic versions of physically stable works, such as <hi rend="i">Colliers Encyclopedia-CD
Rom</hi> (1996), with essays by Charles P. Parkhurst, Jr., on Fuseli and Flaxman and by Geoffrey Keynes on
Blake (1966) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2040, which replaced that by Mark Schorer and Charles P. Parkhurst,
Jr., <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2673&gt;. Some electronic publications, however, suggest no more knowledge than how
to operate a computer, such as reviews invited for the listings of the book-sale firm of Amazon.com, which are
divided into those by (1) the author, (2) the publisher, and (3) other, perhaps disinterested, remarkers. I
have not searched for electronic publications, and I report here only those I have happened upon which appear
to bear some authority.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> E.g., Baulch, David M. “The Sublime of the Bible.” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism On the Net 3</hi> (August 1996). (“When Blake writes [<hi rend="i">in MILTON</hi>]
about ‘the Sublime of the Bible,’ it is not the Bible itself that functions as a sublime object: instead,
the Bible becomes the site of the sublime experience for a Redeemed or Reprobate reader.”)</note></p>
            <p>The chief indices used in compiling this Checklist were <hi rend="i">Books in Print
1998-99</hi> (New Providence [New Jersey], 1998) (160 Blake entries under subjects, 52 under titles, 58 under
authors), <hi rend="i">Book Review Index 1998 Cumulation</hi> (received 13 November 1998, copyright 1999), 
<hi rend="i">Catalogo dei libri in commercio 1998</hi> (Milano, 1998) (20), [<hi rend="i">English Literature in
Russian Critique:</hi> Bibliography Part 1: Middle Ages-XVIII
<pb id="p32-115" n="115"/>
Century] (Moscow: Russian Academy of Sciences Institute for Scientific Information on Social Sciences
(I.N.I.O.N.), 1994), <hi rend="i">Livres disponibles 1998: French Books in Print</hi> (Paris, 1997) (14), 
<hi rend="i">MLA on-line bibliography</hi> (seen 28 November 1998), <hi rend="i">Verzeichnis Lieferbarer Bücher:
German Books in Print 1997-98</hi> (München, 1997) (5), <hi rend="i">Whitaker’s Books in Print 1998</hi>
(London, 1998) (36), and <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, 75 for 1994 (1997) and 76 for
1995 (1998).</p>
            <p>I am indebted for help of many kinds to Associated University Presses, Donald Ault, Dr. E. B.
Bentley, Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery, Cambridge University Press, Shirley Patricia Dent, Duke University
Press, Robert N. Essick, Alexander Gourlay, Heather Howell, Irina Kukota (for help with Russian works),
Christopher Marsden, Joseph Viscomi, and John Windle.</p>
            <p>I should be most grateful to anyone who can help me to better information about the unseen (§)
items reported here, and I undertake to thank them prettily in person and in print.</p>
            <p>Research for “William Blake and His Circle” (1998) was carried out chiefly in the Bodleian
Library, the British Library, the British Museum Print Room, the Huntington Library, and the University of
Toronto Library.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Symbols</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>* Works prefixed by an asterisk include one or more illustrations by Blake or depicting him. If
there are more than 19 illustrations, the number is specified. If the illustrations include all those for a
work by Blake, say <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> or his illustrations to <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>, the work is
identified.</p>
            <p>§ Works preceded by a section mark are reported on second-hand authority.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <table rows="3" cols="2">
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                </cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Blake Publications and Discoveries in 1998</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The languages of recent Blake criticism are remarkably various. Besides English, American,
Australian, and Canadian, these languages include Catalan (1), French (8), German (2), Italian (9), Japanese
(12), Latvian (1), Norwegian (3), Russian (15—1900-97), and Spanish (2), plus four English essays in Korean
journals and one in a Japanese journal.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Blake’s Writings</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The “new” editions of Blake’s writings include <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>
(1998), <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> in French and English (1996), <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> in French (1993), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> in French (1994), <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi> in English (1998), French (1997), and Norwegian (1997), plus reproductions of
Blake’s letter of 1 September 1800, <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (L), and 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (I, b), plus the fascinating text of Blake’s letter of 1
September 1800 printed and reproduced for the first time in an essay by Robert Essick and Morton Paley in 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998).</p>
            <p>There are also variously titled collected editions of his poems in English (1996, 1997, 1998),
Italian (1991 [2], 1996, 1997), and Russian (1978), plus fragments such as <hi rend="i">Auguries of
Innocence</hi> (1997), <hi rend="i">I asked [a Thief]</hi> (1989), <hi rend="i">A Poison Tree</hi> (1989), and
<hi rend="i">Proverbs of Hell</hi> in French (1996). Of these, the most curious is <hi rend="i">Auguries of
Innocence</hi>, produced by the Ziggurat Press with non-representational designs embossed on copper.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Blake’s Art</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The Larger Blake-Varley Sketchbook is no longer on loan at the Tate Gallery and now belongs to
an unidentified collector, rumored to be David Thompson (of Toronto), son of Lord Thompson of Fleet.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Exhibition Catalogues</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>There was no major Blake exhibition in 1998, though there were modest shows in Birmingham
(England) and Kanagawa (Japan). Perhaps the most interesting new catalogue information is to be found in the
1923 sale of the egregious Richard C. Jackson.</p>
            <p>However, there were several significant public events associated with Blake: The conference on
“Blake and the Book” at Strawberry Hill (England) on 18 April 1998; the series of lectures called “Blake
Course at the Tate Gallery” in London (England) on 12 May-9 June 1998; the lecture series on “William
Blake &amp; His Circle” at the Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery (England) on 22 June-6 September 1998; and
the Blake Festival as part of the annual Olavfestdagene in Trondheim (Norway) on 25-28 July 1998.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Scholarship and Criticism</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The scholarship and criticism recorded here cover 1830-1998; indeed one “1998” publication
appeared in 1999.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Essays</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The number of newly recorded works about Blake is substantial. These include 147 essays of
1835-1998, plus 39 reprinted essays, eight doctoral dissertations, and 58 reviews (1835-1998), 25 of them by
David Worrall in <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies.</hi></p>
            <p>“Dialectical” seems to be a term whose time has come, especially among
dissertation-writers, as in Bryan Nemo
<pb id="p32-116" n="116"/>
Alexander, “Dialectical Nightmares: The Historicity of the Romantic-Era Doppelganger in the Works of Godwin,
Hogg, Blake, Burney, and the Shelleys” (Michigan Ph.D., 1997), John Sebastian Howard, “Romantic Dialectics
and the Politics of the Subject” (Saint Louis Ph.D., 1997), Susan Ann Weaver, “Dialectical Formulations
and Covert Language in Coleridge, Blake, and [Mary] Robinson,” (Texas A&amp;M Ph.D., 1997), plus of course
Fred Dortort, <hi rend="i">The Dialectic of Vision</hi> (1998). The fact that a term is critically popular
does not, of course, mean that it is critically abused, but some of its uses here seem to be unfamiliar
ones.</p>
            <p>Other popular subjects are gender, maternity (but not matriarchy), patriarchy (but not
paternity), and the sexual machine.</p>
            <p>This list records eight doctorates on Blake in institutions from St. Petersburg to St. Louis to
Calicut (India). The number of dissertations seems to be about the same as in recent years, but the
geographical range is a good deal wider.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> alone carried nine essays, 10 reviews, and
eight newsletter snippets. The most important of these are Robert Essick’s “Blake in the Marketplace”
and the essay by Essick and Morton Paley on the newly discovered Blake letter of 1 September 1800.</p>
            <p>In what is essentially a 27-page essay, Richard Outram’s <hi rend="i">Notes on William
Blake’s “The Tyger”</hi> (1997) explores ground gratifyingly unfamiliar to most Blake scholars,
particularly on the influences of bestiaries and heraldry on “The Tyger.”</p>
            <p>The 19 essays collected in <hi rend="i">Blake, Politics, and History</hi>, ed. Jackie DiSalvo,
G. A. Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson (1997) cover much of the spectrum of political interest which has
informed much of the best Blake scholarship of the last 50 years. One of the most lastingly valuable of these
is the essay by Jon Mee about the vocabulary of violent republicanism and radical protestantism shared by
William Blake and Richard Lee, called “Citizen Lee,” the author of <hi rend="i">King Killing</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">The Happy Reign of George the Last.</hi> In passing Mee remarks most promisingly: “we have to be
circumspect about claiming that Blake was ever a member of the [<hi rend="i">Joseph</hi>] Johnson
circle.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Jon Mee, “‘The Doom of Tyrants’: William Blake, Richard ‘Citizen’
Lee, and the Millenarian Public Sphere,” <hi rend="i">Blake, Politics, and History</hi>, ed. Jackie
DiSalvo, G. A. Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson (1998) 103.</note></p>
            <p>Similarly, the background details of radical regency political agitation provided by David
Worrall shed a fundamentally new light on Blake’s somewhat conventional engraving of the conventionally
pretty “Mrs Q,” the Prince Regent’s sometime mistress whom he had cast off as he was trying in 1820 to
cast off Queen Charlotte.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> David Worrall, “The Mob and ‘Mrs. Q’: William Blake, William Benbow,
and the Context of Regency Radicalism,” <hi rend="i">ibid</hi>, 169-84.</note></p>
            <p>Another essay which is likely to draw attention is that by Christopher Hobson in which he
argues that the often-cited “Orc cycle” is a myth in the pejorative sense rather than in the sense of
Northrop Frye.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Christopher Z. Hobson, “The Myth of Blake’s ‘Orc Cycle,’” 
<hi rend="i">ibid</hi>, 5-36.</note></p>
            <p>The most densely argued essay recorded here, and probably the one which will prove most
lastingly influential, is that by Joseph Viscomi about the genesis of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>, the second-to-be-published section of a three-part study of the <hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi> In
particular, he assembles very persuasive evidence that pl. 21-24 of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> formed
“an autonomous text preceding the composition of . . . [<hi rend="i">the rest of</hi>] the 
<hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Joseph Viscomi, “The Lessons of Swedenborg; or, The Origin of William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Lessons of Romanticism:</hi> A
Critical Companion, ed. Thomas Pfau and Robert F. Gleckner (1998) 174.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Books</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>There are 15 books on Blake newly recorded here, six of them in French, German (2), Italian,
Japanese, and Russian. Linguistic poverty inhibits me from evaluating two of them,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> and inability to see a copy prevents me from commenting on
five more.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Two other new books are
collections of unrevised essays and fragments of books which have the same merits as when they were originally
printed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> A. Elistratova, [<hi rend="i">William Blake (1757-1827)</hi>] (1957) (in
Russian) and Akinobu Okuma, <hi rend="i">William Blake Kenkyu:</hi> “Yonju no Ningen” to Seiai, Gisei,
Kyusai o megutte: [<hi rend="i">Sexuality, Brotherhood, Sacrifice, and Salvation:</hi> A Study of William
Blake’s “Fourfold Man”] (1997) (in Japanese).</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> James Hogg, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Recreation of Gnostic
Myth:</hi> Resolving the Apparent Incongruities (1995), Roberto Sanesi, <hi rend="i">Blake &amp; Newton</hi>
(1993) (in Italian), Daniela Tandecki, <hi rend="i">Tygerbrand:</hi> das unbequeme Genie William Blake (1997)
(in German), and Eric Verhoest &amp; Jean-Luc Cambier, <hi rend="i">Blake et Mortimer</hi> (1996) (in
French).</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake</hi>, ed. John Lucas (1998), and Stuart
Peterfreund, <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World:</hi> Essays on Literature As Art and Science
(1998). Two other books are noticed under essays above: Richard Outram’s <hi rend="i">Notes on William
Blake’s “The Tyger”</hi> (1998) and <hi rend="i">Blake, Politics, and History</hi>, ed. Jackie DiSalvo,
G. A. Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson (1998).</note></p>
            <p>Two books were reprinted in 1998 with no new matter: Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
of William Blake</hi> (1863), ed. W. Graham Robertson (1907) and G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">William
Blake:</hi> The Critical Heritage (1975).</p>
            <p>Eleanore Frauke Pieper’s <hi rend="i">“Imitation Is Criticism”:</hi> Dante Gabriel
Rossetti und William Blake (1997) is an examination in German of how Dante Gabriel Rossetti used his
misunderstanding of Blake as a symbol of his own feeling of alienation from Victorian society. As with all
such psychological interpretations, one wonders where the author’s alienation ends and that of the subject
begins.</p>
            <p>Henry Summerfield, <hi rend="i">A Guide to the Books of William Blake for Innocent and
Experienced Readers</hi> (1998), is a useful and enormous (874-page) digest of Blake scholarship and
criticism, a kind of variorum edition of Blake which omits the texts themselves.</p>
            <pb id="p32-117" n="117"/>
            <p>Nicholas M. Williams, <hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William Blake</hi>
(1998), is greatly concerned with critical theory and with “readings” of Blake’s writings, particularly
concerning Blake’s “program for social change” (xiv).</p>
            <p>Wayne Glausser, <hi rend="i">Locke and Blake:</hi> A Conversation across the Eighteenth Century
(1998) is a remarkable exercise in discovering affinities between two men who are usually treated as polar
opposites. The connections are often fascinating, ingenious, and ephemeral, as in the section on “Locke and
Blake as Physicians.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Wayne Glausser, <hi rend="i">Locke and Blake:</hi> A Conversation across
the Eighteenth Century (1998); the original title of chapter 3 was “Locke and Blake as Physicians Delivering
the Eighteenth-Century Body.”</note></p>
            <p>The most important of the books on Blake published in 1998 are those by Stanley Gardner, John
Pierce, and Fred Dortort.</p>
            <p>Certainly the most challenging, and perhaps the one which will prove over the years to be the
most rewarding, is Fred Dortort, <hi rend="i">The Dialectic of Vision:</hi> A Contrary Reading of William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (1998). The book appropriates, adapts, and extends the terms and methods
of Donald Ault’s challenging <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound:</hi> Re-Visioning William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1987), which alone will be enough to frighten off all but the most dauntless
readers. But dauntlessness will be rewarded. Dortort posits two warring meanings in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, one of radical English Christianity and the other exposing and correcting the
oppression of the former. These two elements are not so much cunning authorial devices to enmesh the reader as
manifestations of internal conflicts in Blake himself. Readers who struggle through the extraordinarily dense
and self-reflexive argument are likely to conclude that Dortort has made a far stronger case than they
expected when beginning the book.</p>
            <p>John B. Pierce, <hi rend="i">Flexible Design:</hi> Revisionary Poetics in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1998) has surprising affinities to Dortort’s work on
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> but is far more accessible. The chief difference is probably Pierce’s emphasis
upon the deliberateness of Blake’s shifting narrative strategies; Blake uses “conscious adaptations of
sequential disruptions as a fundamental element in narrative experiment” (xxii). Pierce pays very careful
attention to the physical characteristics of the manuscript, and he makes a plausible case that “the
synoptic and synchronic tendencies of Blake’s poetics are the result of conscious revision and correction of
an essentially diachronic narrative” (xvii-xviii). This is a valuable study of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, and its arguments about narrative method and intention have important implications for each of
Blake’s long Prophecies, particularly for <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
            <p>The book which is likely to be most frequently read is the late Stanley Gardner’s 
<hi rend="i">The Tyger, the Lamb, and the Terrible Desart: Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> in its times
and circumstance (1998). In the first place, the book is beautiful, with color reproductions of 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copies I and b, the former watercolored, the latter posthumously-printed and in
monochrome. In the second place, it deals in a straight-forward way with Blake’s most widely appealing
poems. And in the third place it provides generous and often very original evidence that the 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> are vitally related to the reforms concerning destitute and
orphan children established and then dismantled in Blake’s own very enlightened parish of St. James,
Westminster. The infants in the poems are often foundlings, the caring women are parish nurses, not mothers,
and the village scenes are often in Wimbledon where the St. James Parish authorities for a time sent the
charity-supported children to get them out of the literally-deadly poor-houses when they were very young.
Stanley Gardner’s <hi rend="i">The Tyger, the Lamb, and the Terrible Desart</hi> is a visual, critical, and
scholarly delight.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Roads Not Taken</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Some of the roads not taken in recent scholarship are wonderfully alluring. Jon Mee argues that
Blake’s poem from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> called “The Sick Rose” alludes to the powerful
and powerfully corrupt politician George Rose, a secretary of the Treasury, who was convicted in 1791 of
having paid “bludgeon men” to persuade unconvinced voters to support the government in the 1788
Westminster election.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Mee marshalls
the historical and political facts with wonderfully tempting skill. The problem is that neither “The Sick
Rose” nor any of the other poems in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> feel like
personal caricatures or political diatribes. Blake’s art and poetry work in fundamentally different ways
from those of Cruikshank and Gillray. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Jon Mee, “The ‘insidious poison
of secret Influence’: A New Historical Context for Blake’s ‘The Sick Rose,’” <hi rend="i">Studies in
the Eighteenth Century 10</hi> 22 (1998): 111-22.</note></p>
            <p>Others make claims which seem to have little to do with the poet William Blake. There is no
reason known to me to believe that William Blake was any more “a <corr type="emend">disenfranchised</corr>
citizen”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> than were his brothers
James and John, his father James, and his partner James Parker, and one or more of them voted in the elections
of 1749, 1774, 1780, 1784, 1788, and 1790,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> though the poet chose not to do so. And the attempt to associate Blake with the
fraternity and symbols of the Masons is often supported by evidence no more persuasive than that “‘James
Blake’ appears (with other shopkeepers and artisans) on an Ancient lodge register in 1757”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref>
	<pb id="p32-118" n="118"/>
—as if any of the dozens of James Blakes living in London in 1757 must be either William Blake’s father
James or his brother James, then age four. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Catherine C. McClenahan,
“Albion and the Sexual Machine: Blake, Gender and Politics, 1780-1795,” <hi rend="i">Blake, Politics, and
History</hi>, ed. Jackie DiSalvo, G. A. Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson (1998) 302.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> (1969) 551, 553-54, 558.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Marsha Keith Schuchard, “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> and the
Regency Crisis: Lifting the Veil on a Royal Masonic Scandal,” <hi rend="i">Blake, Politics, and
History</hi>, ed. Jackie DiSalvo, G. A. Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson (1998) 116.</note></p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division I:<lb/>
                  William Blake</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part I<lb/>
                    Editions, Translations, and Facsimiles<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">18</ref></hi>
                    <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> N.b. In this Checklist, “Facsimile” is taken to
mean “an exact copy” attempting very close reproduction of an original named copy including size of image,
color of printing (and of tinting if relevant), and size, color, and quality of paper, with no deliberate
alteration as in page order or numbering or obscuring of paper defects.</note>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Section A: Original Editions</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Watermarks in Paper Used by Blake Crown and Shield</p>
                  <p>Letter of 1 September 1800</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">America</hi> (1793[-1831?])</p>
                  <p>Copy N (bound with <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> [I])</p>
                  <p>History: (1) Perhaps <hi rend="i">America</hi> (N) and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (I) were
among the “three or four of the Engraved books” which Catherine Blake sold about 1831 to the artist James
Ferguson (1791-1871), “a gentleman in the far north”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref> (2) Acquired by Sir George Grey (1779-1882) of Falloden, Northumberland, who wrote in it:
“I purchased this book at the sale of the effects of a deceased artist, (I now forget his name), who had
obtained it direct from Blake” (the posthumous character of the printing of <hi rend="i">America</hi>
suggests that it was obtained from Catherine after Blake’s death).... <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi>
Gilchrist (1863) 366 (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969] 363-64).</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> (1809)</p>
                  <p>Manuscript</p>
                  <p>In a letter of 5 August 1914, Richard C. Jackson said that “My Father 
[<hi rend="i">Francis Jackson</hi>] had Blake’s M/S of this [<hi rend="i">DESCRIPTIVE CATALOGUE</hi>], and I may
have it still” (Victoria and Albert Museum Archives), but no other record is known of the manuscript of the
<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue.</hi> Jackson also said in a letter of 14 June 1913 to Palmer (V&amp;A
Archives) that
<q>
many of his [<hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi>] relics are here which my father acquired of M<hi rend="s"><hi
rend="u">rs</hi></hi> Blake &amp; Tatham—and here are his Clock and watch &amp; chain &amp; Seal—Still
going &amp; keeping fairly good time—
</q></p>
                  <p>It seems possible that all these Blake treasures are the products of the fertile
imagination of Jackson (father or son).</p>
                  <p>Copy U</p>
                  <p>History: The title page, p. 33, and Cumberland’s note are reproduced in 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 117, 119, 120.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794[-1831?])</p>
                  <p>Copy I</p>
                  <p>History: For the possibility that it was first bought by James Ferguson, see 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> (N) with which it is bound.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi> (1793)</p>
                  <p>Newly Recorded Print</p>
                  <p>Plate 18</p>
                  <p>History: (1) Offered and reproduced in Folio Fine Art Ltd Catalogue 5 (January 1968),
#22, “second or third state . . . with 1” margins” for £38; Untraced.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> (?1818)</p>
                  <p>A copy of pl. 18 offered at §Swann Galleries, “Works of Art on Paper” (12 November
1998), #185 (called “Second state,” platemark 11.5 × 9.0 cm, estimate: $1,200-$1,800, not sold) is shown
by R. N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 1998,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1999) to be an imitation.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> (?1784)</p>
                  <p>Edition</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon.</hi> Ed. and Decorated by Gavin O’Keefe. ([Newport
Ness (Virginia), later in 1998 Lilburn, Georgia:] Purple Mouth Press, 1998) 8o, iv, 28 pp.; ISBN:
0-9603-300-5-4.</p>
                  <p>In “The Work” (28), O’Keefe says that he has tried <corr type="emend">“to</corr>
present as readable a version of the story as is possible”; some of his designs show a moon-scape.</p>
                  <table rows="3" cols="4">
                    <head>Letters Newly Recorded Letter</head>
                    <row>
                      <cell>Date</cell>
                      <cell>Postmark</cell>
                      <cell>Watermark</cell>
                      <cell>Collection</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>1800 Aug</cell>
                      <cell/>
                      <cell/>
                      <cell>Untraced</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>1800 Sept 1</cell>
                      <cell>SE[PT] [1] 800 fragments of BRIDGE Westminster A.S.A.</cell>
                      <cell>Crown and shield</cell>
                      <cell>Essick</cell>
                    </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>1800 August?</p>
                  <p>History: (1) Sent by Blake to [John Aiken], the editor of <hi rend="i">The Monthly
Magazine</hi> (who did not publish it) and quoted by Blake in his letter to Cumberland of 1 September 1800;
(2) Untraced.</p>
                  <p>1800 September 1</p>
                  <p>History: The letter is reproduced in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 32 (1998): 6-9 (illustrating
Robert N. Essick and Morton D. Paley, “‘Dear Generous George Cumberland’: A Newly Discovered Letter and
Poem by William Blake”).</p>
                  <p>1807 May. The copy sent by Cromek to Blake has disappeared. However, Cromek’s
“duplicate copy” was (1) “found . . . amongst his father’s papers by the late T.H. Cromek,” who (2)
“knowing Mr. Allan Cunningham personally, and as an old friend of his father, lent it to him at his request
. . . in
<pb id="p32-119" n="119"/>
<figure n="BB134.8.1.MS" rend="file" width="958" height="384">
	<figTranscr>9 Sept. 1806 Received of W. Butts six Pounds, six Shillings for Drawings, Songs of Innocence
&amp;c £6, 6 William Blake</figTranscr>
	<head>1 Blake’s receipt of 9 September 1806 for £6.6.0 from Thomas Butts (courtesy of the Huntington
Library, which acquired it in 1998).</head>
	<figDesc>Notice that the receipt itself is made out in an elegant clerkly hand, presumably that of Thomas
Butts, while Blake’s signature is in a distinctly different hand. This receipt is unusual in specifying what
the money was for; most of the Butts receipts say merely “on further account.” Not only did Butts make out
in advance the receipt for Blake to sign, but he paid in advance for works not specified. The surviving
receipts cover 1803-1810, but Butts certainly bought works from Blake both before and after this time, such as
the illustrations for Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus, L’Allegro</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> (c.
1816).</figDesc>
</figure>
1833 .... The letter he was never able to get back”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref> (3) The letter was lent by Peter Cunningham, for publication in Anon., “The Life and
Works of Thomas Stothard, R.A.,” <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, N.S. 38 (1852): 146-50; (4)
Untraced. <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> John Bell, “Blake and Cromek,” <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi>
836 (1882): 1411.</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> ([?1790]-[?1827])</p>
                  <p>Copy L</p>
                  <p>History: It is reproduced in Robert N. Essick, “Representation, Anxiety, and the
Bibliographic Sublime,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 59 (1998): 503-28, Figures 9-10.</p>
                  <p>Copy M</p>
                  <p>History: It is reproduced in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 116, 139, 144.</p>
                  <p>Editions</p>
                  <p>§*<hi rend="i">Matrimonio del cielo e dell’inferno.</hi> (n.d.) Piccola enciclopedia
100. ISBN: 88-7710-288-8. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Le Mariage du Ciel et de l’Enfer.</hi> Postface de Giuseppe Ungaretti.
Tr. Alain Suied. (Paris: Arfuen, 1996) Arfuen Textes anglais cahier no 106. 8o, 72 pp.; ISBN:
2-9088-25-49-X.</p>
                  <p>English and French texts are on facing pages; “Petit glossaire du Ciel et de
l’Enfer” (61-62); Ungaretti, “Sur William Blake,” tr. Gerard Pfister 63-66); “Note Biographique”
(67-70).</p>
                  <table rows="2" cols="4">
                    <head>Receipts signed by Blake (see illus. 1)</head>
                    <row>
                      <cell>Payer</cell>
                      <cell>Date</cell>
                      <cell>Sum</cell>
                      <cell>Location of MS</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                      <cell>9 Sept 1806</cell>
                      <cell>£6.6.0</cell>
                      <cell>Huntington<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> The MS, which had been owned by Ruthven Todd, was sold from Marvin Sadik
Fine Arts, Catalogue 1 (April 1998) to John Windle and by him to the Huntington Library in May 1998, with
funds provided by Robert N. Essick.</note>
	</cell>
                    </row>
                  </table>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (1794[-1802])</p>
                  <p>Edition</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Les chants de l’expérience.</hi> Tr. Alain Suied. (Paris: Arfuen, 1993)
Arfuen Textes anglais cahier no 91. 8o, 94 pp.: ISBN: 2-908825-295.</p>
                  <p>English and French texts are on facing pages; “Abstrait humain, concret divin”
(83-88).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789[-1808?])</p>
                  <p>Edition</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Les chants de l’innocence.</hi> Tr. Alain Suied. (Paris: Arfuen, 1992)
Arfuen Textes anglais cahier no 83. 8o, 80 pp.; ISBN: 2-9088-242-01 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1994)§&gt;.</p>
                  <p>English and French texts are on facing pages. “Révélation et Révolution” (71-74);
biography of Blake (75-79).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1794[-1831?])</p>
                  <p>Copy F</p>
                  <p>History: (1) Cumberland may have acquired <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (F) in August 1800. On
2 July 1800, Blake wrote to Cumberland
<pb id="p32-120" n="120"/>
                    <figure n="vizetelly-ecchoing-green.032.04.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="517">
	<head>2 (a) Headpiece and (b) tailpiece, both perhaps by H. Vizetelly who signed the second, for Blake’s
“The Ecchoing Green” (here called “A Summer Evening on a Village Green” and shorn of its first stanza)
as printed in <hi rend="i">Pictorial Calendar of the Seasons</hi>, ed. Mary Howitt (1854) &lt;Collection of R.
N. Essick&gt;.</head>
	<figDesc>Blake’s “Ecchoing Green” in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789) also has a headpiece
and a tailpiece (see illus. 3a-b). The headpiece, of children playing “under the oak” round which sit
“the old folk” is related sufficiently closely to the headpiece of the <hi rend="i">Pictorial
Calendar</hi>, with children dancing round a huge oak tree, to make one wonder whether the designer had seen
Blake’s plate.<lb/>
An even closer analogy in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Pictorial Calendar</hi> head-piece
of dancing on the green is in the tailpiece for “Nurse’s Song” (illus. 3c).<lb/>
Blake’s tailpiece of children walking homeward (illus. 3b) is quite unlike the <hi rend="i">Pictorial
Calendar</hi> tailpiece of handkerchief dancing in a village street (illus. 2b).</figDesc>
</figure>
about the “deep pit of Melancholy” from which “I begin to Emerge.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> Cumberland may have tried to lift Blake from his depression
by offering to sell Blake’s books and by buying <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (F), which was “prepared by him
[<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>] expressly for an intimate friend [<hi rend="i">Cumberland</hi>],”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> and with which Blake’s thankful letter of 1
September 1800 was apparently kept. Cumberland may even have acquired at the same time the copies of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> (F), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (C), <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (D), 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (B) (these four works bound together), <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (A), and <hi rend="i">For
Children</hi> (C) which he also owned.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">24</ref> In August Cumberland apparently told Blake of his ill-success in trying to sell Blake’s
works, and on 1 September Blake replied: “To have obtained your friendship is better than to have sold ten
thousand books.” <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s Writings</hi>
1535.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Kerslake’s Catalogue (after Dec 1857), Lot 733. However, 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (F) is fairly clearly a made-up copy, for the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> leaves are
printed (early?) on both sides of the leaves and watercolored in a late style, while those in 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> are color-printed on only one side of the leaf.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Cumberland owned no work of Blake in Illuminated Printing written after
1800, though he did acquire <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> (U) in 1809 and <hi rend="i">Job</hi> in
1828.</note></p>
                  <pb id="p32-121" n="121"/>
                  <figure n="ecchoing-green-william-blakes-writings.032.04.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="559"/>
                  <figure n="nurses-song-william-blakes-writings.032.04.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="793">
                    <head>3 (a) Headpiece and (b) tailpiece of “The Ecchoing Green,” and (c) tailpiece to
“Nurse’s Song,” pl. 6-7, 24 from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789) [all three as reproduced in
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> (1978) 26-27, 47].</head>
                    <figDesc>The headpiece to “The Ecchoing Green” and the tailpiece to “Nurse’s
Song” seem to be significantly related to the headpiece to the version of “The Ecchoing Green” printed
in Mary Howitt’s <hi rend="i">Pictorial Calendar of the Seasons</hi> (1854) (see illus. 2a).</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1794[-1831?])</p>
                  <p>Copy I</p>
                  <p>History: Reproduced in Stanley Gardner, <hi rend="i">The Tyger, the Lamb, and the
Terrible Desart</hi> (1998).</p>
                  <p>Copy W</p>
                  <p>History: Reproduced from the Blake Trust reproduction (1991) in <hi rend="i">Eskyldens og
Erfaringens sanger</hi>: som viser menneskes: elens to motstridende tistander, tr. Geir Uthaug (1997).</p>
                  <p>Copy b</p>
                  <p>History: Reproduced in Stanley Gardner, <hi rend="i">The Tyger, the Lamb, and the
Terrible Desart</hi> (1998).</p>
                  <p>Editions</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1991), Blake Trust &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 136&gt;.</p>
                  <p>The Blake Trust reproductions of copy W are reproduced in Geir Uthaug’s Norwegian
translation (1997).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Chansons d’innocence et d’expérience: Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</hi> Tr. Armand Sedaine. Ill. Sam Jones. (La Tilv, 1997) 86 pp., ISBN: 2-909159-19-1. In
French.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Eskyldens og Erfaringens sanger</hi>: som viser menneskes: elens to
motstridende tistander. Ed. and tr. Geir Uthaug. Med komplette gjengivelse av William Blakes etsninger, 20 I
farger. (Oslo: Aschehoug, 1997) 4o, 144 pp., ISBN: 82-03-17794-8.</p>
                  <pb id="p32-122" n="122"/>
                  <p>“Forord” (5-6); “William Blake” (7-23); Norwegian translation facing
reproductions in black-and-white and color from the Blake Trust facsimile (W); “Kommentarer til de enkelte
dikt” (15-144).</p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Section B: Collections and Selections</hi>
                      <ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref>
                      <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Here and below I ignore most reprints.</note>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Reprints of Blake’s Works Before 1863</p>
                  <p>(Addenda)</p>
                  <p>1854</p>
                  <p>“The Ecchoing Green” [called “A Summer Evening on a Village Green”], 
<hi rend="i">Pictorial Calendar of the Seasons</hi>, ed. Mary Howitt, 274-75.</p>
                  <p>1862</p>
                  <p>“The Ecchoing Green,” <hi rend="i">Pictorial Calendar of the Seasons</hi>, ed. Mary
Howitt, 274-75.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Auguries of Innocence</hi>: A Poem. (Providence [Rhode Island]: Ziggurat
Press, 1997)</p>
                  <p>Walter Feldman, “Introduction.” The prime feature of this edition produced in 20
copies is the series of non-representational designs on embossed copper.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake</hi>: Selected Poems. Ed. Mike Davis and Alan Pound. (Oxford:
Heinemann Educational Publishers, 1996) Heinemann Poetry Bookshelf. 12o, viii, 168 pp.; ISBN: 0-435-150082-0
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)§&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Davis and Pound, “Introduction” (v-vi)—it is aimed at A-level students. The text is
on the right with notes on facing versos. “Background” (132-37), “Chronological Table” (138-39),
“Cultural and Literary Background” (140-47), “Critical Approaches” (148-57), topics for “Essays”
(158-59), “Writing an Essay on Poetry” (160-61), Virginia Graham, “A Note from a Chief Examiner”
(162-63), and “Select Bibliography” (164-66).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Blake Project</hi>: Spring, ed. Finn Coren (1997) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>1 Thomas Dillingham, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 32 (1998): 49-50 (in his settings of
Blake’s poems to rock music, Finn’s “responses to Blake are . . . complex and interactive”).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi>, ed. D. W. Dörrbecker (1995) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>2 Irene Chayes, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 27 (1996): 200-01 (with Christopher
Heppner, <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s Designs</hi> [1995]) (“Needless to say, Dörrbecker’s work in his
several editorial roles is admirable” [201]).</p>
                  <p>3 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 (1998):
397-98 (quotes the comment in “William Blake and His Circle . . . 1995,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 29
[1996]).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves, R. N. Essick, and Joseph
Viscomi (1993) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;. B. §(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1998)
ISBN: 0-691-00147-2 (paperback).</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>10 Paul Cantor, <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 59 (1998): 557-70 (with
<hi rend="i">MILTON A POEM and the Final Illuminated Books</hi> and Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the
Idea of the Book</hi>) (“The reproductions . . . are as good as modern technology will allow,” and the
“editions have been prepared” with commendable “care and thoughtfulness” [558, 570]).</p>
                  <p>[“The Ecchoing Green,” called] “A Summer Evening on a Village Green” by William
Blake the Painter. Pp. 274-75 of <hi rend="i">Pictorial Calendar of the Seasons</hi> Exhibiting the Pleasures,
Pursuits, and Characteristics of Country Life for Every Month in the Year and Embodying the Whole of Aikin’s
Calendar of Nature Embellished with Upwards of One Hundred Engravings on Wood. Ed. Mary Howitt. (London: Henry
G. Bohn, 1854) &lt;<hi rend="i">R. N. Essick</hi>&gt; B. (1862) &lt;<hi rend="i">R. N. Essick</hi>&gt;</p>
                  <p>The first stanza of the poem is omitted. This printing of “The Ecchoing Green” has
designs related to Blake’s (see illus. 2-3) but no indication of where Mary Howitt saw an original copy.</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">The Essential Blake.</hi> Ed. Stanley Kunitz. (N.Y.: Ecco Press, 1987) The
Essential Poets Volume 4. 12o, ix, 92 pp., ISBN: 0-88001-138-6 and 0-8801-139-4 (paperback) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 155&gt;. B. §(N.Y.: Fine Communications, 1996) 112 pp., ISBN: 1-56731-159-8.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">I asked</hi> [a thief . . .]. (Stoke Ferry, Norfolk: Daedalus Press [c.
1989]) Poemcard Six.</p>
                  <p>The poem is printed on pink post-card size stiff paper.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Lamb.</hi> Designed and printed by Linda Anne Landers. ([London:] Spoon
Print Press, [1998]) Narrow 8o, 6 decorated leaves in a decorated cover.</p>
                  <p>100 copies printed.</p>
                  <p>§*<hi rend="i">Libri Profetici.</hi> Tr. Roberto Sanesi. (Milano, 1986) Tascabili
Bombiani 400. 16o, 224 pp., ISBN: 88-452-1303-X. In Italian. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 157&gt;. B. §<hi
rend="i">Libri profetici.</hi> Testo inglese a fronte. Ed. R. Sanesi. (1995) 16o, 234 pp., ISBN:
88-452-2611-5.</p>
                  <p>A bilingual English-Italian edition based on Sampson (1913), with “Repertorio”
(vii-xxvii), biography (xxix-xxxii), and notes on the text (215-25).</p>
                  <pb id="p32-123" n="123"/>
                  <p>* <hi rend="i">Libri Profetici.</hi> [Tr. Roberto Sanesi.] (Milano, 1987) L’Altra
Bibliotheca 13. 8o, 184 pp., ISBN: 88-7710-048-6. In Italian. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 157&gt;. B. §<hi
rend="i">Libri profetici.</hi> (1997) conoscenza religiosa. ISBN: 88-7710-356-6.</p>
                  <p>Roberto Sanesi, “Repertorio” (155-72), “Nota ai Testi” (173-80). The text
consists of facing English and Italian pages of <hi rend="i">Thel, Marriage, Visions, America, Europe, Urizen,
Ahania, Song of Los</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Book of Los.</hi></p>
                  <p>The paucity of information available about the 1995 edition makes it difficult to
determine how or whether it is related to any of the other <hi rend="i">Libri profetici.</hi></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Milton A Poem and the Final Illuminated Books</hi>, ed. R. N. Essick and
Joseph Viscomi (1993) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;, B. §(Princeton: Princeton University Press,
1998) ISBN: 0-691-00148-0 (paperback).</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>9 Paul Cantor, <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 59 (1998): 557-70 (with 
<hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi> and Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the
Book</hi>) (“The reproductions . . . are as good as modern technology will allow,” and the “editions
have been prepared” with commendable “care and thoughtfulness” [558, 570]).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Obra Poetica.</hi> Tr. [Pablo Mañé Garzön. Intro. Mariano Vazquez
                    Alonso. Rev. E. Caracciolo Trejo. (Barcelona: Ediciones 29, 1992) Coleccion <corr type="emend">“Ucieza,”</corr> Vol. [3] 8o, 261
pp., ISBN: 84-7175-341-3.</p>
                  <p>Garzön, “Prologo” (13-19); Alonso, “Introduccion” (21-38); it includes 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches, Tiriel, Songs</hi>, Notebook, <hi rend="i">French Revolution, Marriage</hi>, and
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, plus “Nota cronologica,” and a very few notes.</p>
                  <p>The pagination and ISBN suggest that it is not the same as *<hi rend="i">Obra
Poética</hi>, tr. Pablo Mañé Garzön (Barcelona: Ediciones 29, 1997), 166 pp., 19 cm, ISBN: 84-7175-426-6
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)&gt;.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Poems.</hi> (N.Y. &amp; Toronto: Alfred A. Knopf, 1994) Everyman’s Library
Pocket Books. 283 pp.</p>
                  <p>§[<hi rend="i">Poems</hi>]. (Moscow, 1978) In Russian.</p>
                  <p>A. Zveryev, “[The Greatness of Blake]” (5-32); G. Yakovleva (reprinted in 
[<hi rend="i">Literary Review</hi>] 5 [1979]: 75-76); N. Starosel’skaya, “[Between the Epochs]” (reprinted in
<hi rend="i">Inostrannaya [Foreign] Literatura</hi> 12 [1980]: 232-33).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Poems &amp; Prophecies of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Max Plowman. (1927)
Everyman’s Library. B. §(1934) C. <hi rend="i">Poems and Prophecies.</hi> [Ed. Max Plowman.] (1950) D. 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Poems and Prophecies.</hi> Ed. Max Plowman. (1954) E. Supplementary Notes, Select
Bibliography, and Revisions to the Notes by Geoffrey Keynes. (1959) F. (London: Dent; N.Y.: Dutton, 1963)
Everyman’s Library No. 792. 12o &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #287, not including the 1963 edition&gt;.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Poems and Prose.</hi> Introduction by Robert Van de Weyer. (London: Fount,
1997) 12o, xii, 123 pp.; ISBN: 0-00-628031-5.</p>
                  <p>“Introduction” (vii-x).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Poesie.</hi> Tr. G. Conserva. (1991) 8o, 208 pp. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Poesie e visioni:</hi> Maledizione e veggenza dell’ultimo dei bardi.
(1996) 8o, 144 pp., ISBN: 88-7122-914-2. In Italian.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">A Poison Tree.</hi> (Stoke Ferry, Norfolk: Daedalus Press [c. 1989])
Poemcard 21.</p>
                  <p>The poem is printed on post-card size stiff paper.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Proverbes de l’enfer:</hi> calligraphie Lalou. Tr. Angela Esdaile.
(1996) ISBN: 2-84103-060-1. Text from the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> in French and English.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Selected Poems.</hi> (London, N.Y., Ringwood, Toronto, Auckland: Penguin
Books, 1996) Penguin Popular Classics. 12o, ×, 242 pp.; ISBN: 0-14-062219-5.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Selected Poems:</hi> Scelta dei testi e traduzione francese di Georges
Bataille. <hi rend="i">Poèmes choisis:</hi> Versione italiana di Giuseppe Ungaretti: Poesie scelte. A cura di
Annamaria Leserra. (Milan: Arnoldo Mondadori, 1996) Scrittori tradotti da scrittori Serie trilingue 69 12o,
226 pp.; ISBN: 88-06-13921-5.</p>
                  <p>English and French texts are on facing pages with Italian in footnotes. Georges Bataille,
“William Blake,” tr. Andrea Zanzotto (85-114); Georges Bataille, “Frommenti su William Blake”
(149-63); Georges Bataille, “Lettore e traduttore di William Blake,” tr. Annamaria Leserra (165-217); A.
L., “Nota bibliographica” (218-20).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Selected Poetry.</hi> Ed. Michael Mason. (Oxford &amp; N.Y.: Oxford
University Press, 1996) World’s Classics. B. (1998) Oxford World’s Classics. 12o, xvi, 311 pp.; ISBN:
0-19-283489-4.</p>
                  <p>“Introduction” (vii-xii: “How should the modern reader approach William Blake?”
[vii]); “Notes” (270-303).</p>
                  <p>This seems to be the same as his <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (1994) in the Oxford
Poetry Library &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Trentadue poesie.</hi> (1997) I miti poesia 44. ISBN: 88-04-43222-5. In
Italian.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi>, ed. David Worrall (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1996)&gt;. B. §(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1998) ISBN: 0-691-00146-4 (paperback).</p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <pb id="p32-124" n="124"/>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part II<lb/>
                    Reproductions of Drawings and Paintings</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>Section A<lb/>
                    Illustrations of Individual Authors</title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Blake-Varley Sketchbook (larger)</p>
                  <p>History: (1) Sold posthumously for William Mulready (John Varley’s brother-in-law) at
§Christie’s, 28 April 1864, Lot 86 [to Kempton for £5.5.0]; (2) Acquired by Lionel Robinson from whom it
passed “by descent” to (3) An Anonymous Owner, who offered it at Christie’s, 21 March 1989,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> the whole catalogue devoted to this work, all
the Blake drawings reproduced (estimate: £450,000), not sold, loaned it to the Tate Gallery 1992-98, and sold
it at Sotheby’s, 8 April 1998, *Lot 151 (estimate: £200,000-£300,000) for £216,000 to an Anonymous
Owner.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Not 1983 as in <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 178, though the date is correct in
the main entry on 306. The connection of Mulready and Robinson is recorded in the 1998 catalogue.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> In the trade, the new owner is rumored to be “David Thompson, the son
of Lord Thompson of Fleet and hitherto known primarily as a collector of drawings by John Constable. Thompson
may also be the new owner of Blake’s watercolors illustrating Bunyan’s <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s
Progress</hi>,” according to R. N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 1998,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1999).</note></p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part III<lb/>
                    Commercial Book Engravings</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p><hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826)</p>
                <p>1826 New Locations: Kanagawa Kindai Bijutsukan [Kanagawa Modern Fine Art Museum, Japan],
Santa Barbara Museum.</p>
                <p>Blair, Robert, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808, 1813, . . .)</p>
                <p>1808 New Locations: Kanagawa Kindai Bijutsukan [Kanagawa Modern Fine Art Museum, Japan],
Victoria College (University of Toronto—Northrop Frye’s copy).</p>
                <p>B. H. Malkin’s important letter of 4 January 1806 (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>,
421-31), showing the variety of Blake’s talents (like the “Advertisement” to <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches</hi> [1783]) and praising Blake’s watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> and Fuseli’s
encomium of them printed in the two prospectuses for it of November 1805 (<hi rend="i">Blake Records
Supplement</hi> 31, 35), which is of such tenuous relevance as printed in Malkin’s <hi rend="i">Father’s
Memoirs of His Child</hi> (1806), may have been drafted as the “Preface . . . by BENJAMIN HEATH MALKIN”
advertised in the November 1805 Prospectus to <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> The part of the “Preface
Containing an Explanation of the Artist’s View in the Designs” (November 1805) probably became the essay
“Of the Designs” in <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808), 33-36.</p>
                <p>For Thomas Sivright’s sale of a “Volume of Drawings by Blake, Illustrative of Blair’s
Grave, entitled ‘Black Spirits and White, Blue Spirits and Grey,’” see 1-19 February 1836.</p>
                <p>Dante, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations of Dante</hi> (1838)</p>
                <p>New Location: Kanagawa Kindai Bijutsukan [Kanagawa Modern Fine Art Museum, Japan].</p>
                <p>Donne, John, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> (1779)</p>
                <p>The unpublished proof for Bell’s Edition of The Poets of Great Britain of a winged figure
flying from the viewer is tentatively ascribed in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> A1450 to Bell’s edition of Donne’s
<hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> and in Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William
Blake</hi> (1983), 236-37, Figure 105, to Bell’s edition of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi></p>
                <p>There are two copies of the print in the British Museum Print Room, Essick has acquired a
copy, and another is in John Windle’s <hi rend="i">List Twenty-Nine</hi> (1998), #73.</p>
                <p>Flaxman, John, <hi rend="i">Compositions from . . . Hesiod</hi> (1817)</p>
                <p>New Locations: Detroit Mercy, Minnesota.</p>
                <p>Flaxman, John, <hi rend="i">The Iliad of Homer</hi> (1805)</p>
                <p>New Location: Detroit Mercy.</p>
                <p>Gay, John, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793, [1811])</p>
                <p>Set of Unrecorded Date New Location: Detroit Public.</p>
                <p>Hartley, David, <hi rend="i">Observations on Man</hi> (1791)</p>
                <p>A proof of Blake’s frontispiece before signature, on wove paper, was acquired by R. N.
Essick in 1998.</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805)</p>
                <p>New Location: Fogg Museum (Harvard University).</p>
                <p>An examination of the probable costs, sales, and profits or losses of the publication of
Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805) may elucidate the obscurity of this crucial period of Blake’s
life.</p>
                <p>The expenses of the volume would have been:</p>
                <table rows="3" cols="2">
                  <head>Costs of Text</head>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Copyright—30 copies given to Hayley in lieu of royalties<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Hayley to Phillips, 28 Feb 1805 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 159). The
cost-per-copy is the total manufacturing cost (£238.4.6) divided by the number of copies printed (1,000) =
4<hi rend="i">s</hi> 9<hi rend="i">d.</hi></note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£7.2.6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Setting 216 8o pp. (13 3/4 sheets) of text by Seagrave at £7.12.0 per
sheet<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> In 1799, Bensley estimated that for Du Roveray’s Gray, 1,000 ordinary +
250 large paper copies in 8° would cost £12.12.0 per sheet, and 1,250 + 250 large paper copies would cost
£14.10.0 (MS in the Huntington; see G. E. Bentley, Jr., “F. J. Du Roveray, Illustrated-Book Publisher
1798-1806: II: The Amateur and the Trade,” <hi rend="i">Bibliographical Society of Australia and New Zealand
Bulletin</hi> 12 [1990]: 69); therefore 250 ordinary copies would cost £1.18.0 (£14.0.0 less £12.12.0), and
1,000 would cost £7.12.0 (4 times £1.18.0) per sheet. I presume that this cost includes setting the text,
paper (27 1/2 reams at £2.10.0 per ream), printing, labels, hotpressing, and sewing and boarding. The cost of
paper derives from that in Malkin’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> (Jan 1806) (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 595]).
                                                <p>In correspondence with Phillips, Seagrave insisted that he
should be paid at the rates of London Printers.</p></note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£104.10.0</cell>
                  </row>
                </table>
            	<pb id="p32-125" n="125"/>
                <table>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Total Cost of Text<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">30</ref>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> All expenses for 1,000 duodecimo copies of the 21 sheets of George
Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Original Tales</hi> (1810), including 19 advertisements, came to £147.18.9
(British Library Add. MSS 36,503, ff. 240-241; see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of George
Cumberland (1754-1848)</hi> [N.Y. &amp; London: Garland Publishing, 1975] 27).</note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£111.12.6</cell>
                  </row>
                </table>
                <table rows="4" cols="2">
                  <head>Costs of Engraving</head>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Engraving 5 designs at £21 each<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n31" type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Letter of 22 March 1805 (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi>
[1978] 1624). The costs of the copyright of the designs, copper, captions, and corrections were presumably
included in Blake’s fee.</note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£105.0.0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>1 1/2 reams of unwatermarked paper at £4.8.0<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> for 1,000 copies of 5 8o plates 
<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> As in Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> (April 1805) (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 561). Prints
could be pulled as needed.</note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£6.12.0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Printing 1,000 copies of 5 plates at 6s per 100<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi><hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi> Note that the cost of printing 8° plates may
have been substantially less than for the folio plates in Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Iliad.</hi></note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£15.0.0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Total Cost of Engravings</cell>
                    <cell>£126.12.0</cell>
                  </row>
                </table>
                <table rows="3" cols="2">
                  <head>Cost of Distribution</head>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Advertising<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">34</ref> including 20 review copies<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">35</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> As in Malkin’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> (Jan 1806) 
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 595). There were puffs and ads for Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> in (1-2) Phillips’
<hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> (1 April, 1 July 1805), (3) <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Review</hi> 6 (July
1805): 495, (4) Bent’s <hi rend="i">Monthly Literary Advertiser</hi> (Aug 1805), and (5) a Phillips Short
List (n.d.).</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi> It was reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Critical Review</hi> 3 S, 5 (1805):
439, (2) <hi rend="i">Literary Journal</hi> 5 (1805): 884, (3) <hi rend="i">Guardian of Education</hi> 4
(1805): 416-26, (4) <hi rend="i">Monthly Mirror</hi> 20 (1805): 184-85, (5) <hi rend="i">British Critic</hi>
26 (1805): 563-64, (6) <hi rend="i">Eclectic Review</hi> 1 (1805): 923, (7) <hi rend="i">Flowers of
Literature</hi> 4 (1805): 417, (8) <hi rend="i">New Annual Register</hi> 26 (1805): 355, (9) 
<hi rend="i">Annual Review</hi> 4 (1806): 576-77, (10) Phillips’ <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> 20
Supplement (1806): 614-15, and (11) <hi rend="i">Poetical Register</hi> for 1805 5 (1807): 489.</note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£14.18.7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>10 copies to Blake at cost<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">36</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> Blake is known to have given copies of the <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>
(1805) to Mr. Weller and to Lady Hesketh (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>, 163, 162), and doubtless there were more which
cannot now be identified.</note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>£2.17.6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>Total Distribution Costs</cell>
                    <cell>£17.16.1</cell>
                  </row>
                </table>
                <p>On the publication in June 1805 of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805), Blake
became liable for his share (c. £23<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">37</ref>) of the publication costs, and, though he expected to receive half the proceeds from the
sales,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">38</ref> this was slow in coming in
and probably never equalled his investment in cash and kind. To pay his debt to Phillips, Blake may have had
to borrow money, and the sacrifices he had to make to repay his debt may well have reduced him to living on a
pittance. Perhaps after all Cromek was right that in the autumn of 1805 the Blakes “were reduced so low as
to be obliged to live on half-a-guinea a week!” <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi> Blake’s share was half
the total publication cost (£256.0.7) minus the £105 credit for his engravings.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">38</hi> The price given in the <hi rend="i">Eclectic Review</hi> 1 (1805): 923,
was 10<hi rend="i">s</hi> 6<hi rend="i">d.</hi> (Phillips’ <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> [1805]: 583,
must be in error in giving the price as 6<hi rend="i">s.</hi>) Of this 10<hi rend="i">s</hi> 6<hi
rend="i">d</hi>, the bookseller’s discount was 16 2/3% (1<hi rend="i">s</hi> 9<hi rend="i">d</hi>), leaving
8<hi rend="i">s</hi> 9<hi rend="i">d</hi> for the publishers.
                                        <p>Sixty copies, given to Hayley (30), to Blake (10), and for review
(20), were not available for sale.</p></note></p>
                <p>We can only guess how many copies of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805) were
sold—probably not many. Had the number been large, Phillips would surely have published another edition.</p>
                <p>Profit and Loss Related to Copies Sold</p>
                <p>In order to make a profit, 564 copies of the <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> had to be sold, and
almost certainly the total sales were fewer than this.</p>
                <table rows="7" cols="4">
                  <row>
                    <cell>Copies Sold</cell>
                    <cell>Costs<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Prints could be pulled and copies boarded as they were called for, but
the other costs are constant.</note>
	</cell>
                    <cell>Receipts</cell>
                    <cell>Profit or Loss</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>200</cell>
                    <cell>£238.16.2</cell>
                    <cell>£87.10.0</cell>
                    <cell>−£ 151. 6.2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>400</cell>
                    <cell>£243. 2.3</cell>
                    <cell>£175. 0.0</cell>
                    <cell>−£ 68. 2.3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>564</cell>
                    <cell>£246.10.7</cell>
                    <cell>£246.15.0</cell>
                    <cell>+£ 4.5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>600</cell>
                    <cell>£247. 8.4</cell>
                    <cell>£262.10.0</cell>
                    <cell>−£ 15. 1.8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>800</cell>
                    <cell>£251.14.5</cell>
                    <cell>£350. 0.0</cell>
                    <cell>+£ 98. 5.7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell>940</cell>
                    <cell>£256. 0.7</cell>
                    <cell>£395.10.6</cell>
                    <cell>+£139. 9.11</cell>
                  </row>
                </table>
                <p>It seems very likely that Blake received no profit from the sales of the 
<hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, though he did receive credit for £105 for his engravings—from which, of course, he
had to deduct the 10s for the copper.</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Designs to A Series of Ballads</hi> (1802) We do not know how
many copies of the <hi rend="i">Designs</hi> were printed or what Seagrave’s charges were for printing and
paper, but we may make estimates based upon Blake’s statement that he paid Seagrave £30<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">40</ref> and on contemporary printing prices. On 10
October 1800 Thomas Bensley estimated that the cost of printing 1,000 quarto copies of Thomson’s 
<hi rend="i">Seasons</hi> (5 sheets) for F.J. Du Roveray would be £15.15.0 per sheet (£78.15) for paper,
printing, and hotpressing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">40</hi> On 28 December 1804 Blake thanked Hayley for “the Twelve Guineas which
you Lent Me when I made up 30 Pounds to pay our Worthy Seagrave in part of his Accounts” 
(<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> [1978] 1619). I take the “part” of Seagrave’s account to be
£12.12.0 rather than the £30. Hayley said Blake had “paid a Bill of 30£ for paper” (letter of 3 April
1803 [<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969] 114) which I take to represent payment to Seagrave for paper 
<hi rend="i">and printing of the Designs.</hi><p>When Blake wrote on 11 Dec 1805 that he “should be able to
Settle with him [<hi rend="i">Seagrave</hi>] Soon what is between us” (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Writings</hi> 1631), he was presumably referring to his indebtedness not for the <hi rend="i">Designs</hi>
(1802) but for the <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805), for which the publisher Richard Phillips “will go equal
shares with me in the expense and the profits, and . . . Seagrave is to be the printer” (letter of 22 Jan
1805 [<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> 1631]).</p></note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Quoted from the MS in the Huntington Library; see G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
“F.J. Du Roveray, Illustrated-Book Publisher 1798-1806: The Amateur and the Trade,” 
<hi rend="i">Bibliographical Society of Australia and New Zealand Bulletin</hi> 12 (1988): 70.</note></p>
                <p>At this rate, £29.10.8 would pay for 250 quarto copies of the 7½ sheets of Hayley’s
first four Ballads. Assuming that Seagrave’s provincial rates were lower than those of the metropolitan fine
printer Bensley, and that Seagrave did not hotpress the <hi rend="i">Designs</hi>, his charges for 250 copies
would have been somewhat lower than £29.10.8. On the other hand, the paper on which Blake printed the
whole-page plates (the same as for the text, watermarked “1802”) are not included in this cost. The 312½
sheets for the five whole-page engravings at £5 per ream of 500 sheets would have come to about £3 more.</p>
                <pb id="p32-126" n="126"/>
                <p>Presumably Seagrave printed 250 copies of each Ballad and sent them to Blake; Blake and his
wife then printed three designs on text plates plus a frontispiece and a separate print for each Ballad—but
they printed them only as the need arose, not all at once. When there proved to be demand for no more than a
few score copies (only 12 copies of the first Ballad have been traced in public collections), Blake was left
with perhaps 200 copies (1500 sheets) of the <hi rend="i">Designs.</hi> These were of no commercial value, but
the paper alone had cost about £15. Blake cannily kept these sheets, even taking them back to London with him
in 1803, at considerable trouble, and he drew on them for the rest of his life, including designs for
Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1805), Malkin’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> (1806), Job and Dante (c.
1824).</p>
                <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Life . . . of William Cowper, Esqr</hi> (1803-04)</p>
                <p>A 1803-4 New Location: Wayne State.</p>
                <p>Blake said that
<q>
My Wife has undertaken to Print the whole number of the Plates for [<hi rend="i">the first two volumes
of</hi>] Cowpers work which She does to admiration &amp; being under my own eye the prints are as fine as the
French prints &amp; please every one. . . . The Publishers are already indebted to My Wife Twenty Guineas for
work deliverd [<hi rend="i">letter of 30 January 1803.</hi>]
</q></p>
                <p>However, after the Blakes had printed 12 proof sets of the two plates for Vol. 3 of 
<hi rend="i">Cowper</hi>, Blake had to “send the Plates to [<hi rend="i">Joseph</hi>] Johnson who wants them to
set the Printer to work upon” (letter of 31 March 1804). R. N. Essick remarks that
<q>
The plates for vols. 1-2 are much more clearly and darkly printed in the second edition .... One hesitates to
blame Mrs Blake for the poor impressions of the first states, but that may indeed be the case 
[<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations (1991)</hi>].
</q></p>
                <p>Malkin, Benjamin Heath, <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi> (1806)</p>
                <p>New Location: Minnesota.</p>
                <p>For evidence that the prefatory essay on Blake may have originated as the “Preface . . .
by BENJAMIN HEATH MALKIN” advertised in the November 1805 Prospectus to Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
(1808), see Blair (above).</p>
                <p>Edition</p>
                <p>Malkin, Benjamin Heath. <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His Child 1806.</hi> (Poole
&amp; Washington, D.C.: Woodstock Books, 1997) ISBN: 1 85477 210 4.</p>
                <p>J[onathan] W[ordsworth], “Introduction) (7 pp.).</p>
                <p>Scott, John, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> (1782)</p>
                <p>New Location: Minnesota.</p>
                <p>Stedman, J. G., <hi rend="i">Narrative of a five years expedition against the Revolted
Negroes of Surinam</hi> (1796, 1806, 1813) 1796 New Location: Detroit Public.</p>
                <p>Young, Edward, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797)</p>
                <p>New Locations: Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery, Kanagawa Kindai Bijutsukan [Kanagawa
Modern Fine Art Museum, Japan], Victoria College, (University of Toronto—Northrop Frye’s copy. Given to
him in 1954 by Jay Macpherson).</p>
                <p>A copy in “original boards with ‘printed label on upper cover’” in §Sotheby
(London) catalogue (7 May 1998), #30, exhibits a label not recorded elsewhere.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part IV<lb/>
                    Catalogues and Bibliographies</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>1-19 February 1836</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Extensive and Valuable Collections of Books, Pictures,
Drawings, Prints, and Painters’ Etchings, Ancient Bronzes and Terracottas, Etruscan Vases, Marble Busts,
Antique Carvings and Chasings in Wood and Metal, Coins, Minerals, Gems and Precious Stones, Philosophical
Instruments, Wines, Spirits, &amp;c. &amp;c. of the late Thomas Sivwright Esq. of Meggetland and
Southouse</hi>, Which Will Be Sold by Auction by Mr. C.B. Tait, In His Great Room, 11, Hanover Street, on
Monday, February 1, and Sixteen following lawful days, at One O’Clock (Edinburgh: Printed by Thomas
Constable, M.DCCC.XXXVI [1836])</p>
                <p>Lot 1835 was a “Volume of Drawings by Blake, Illustrative of Blair’s Grave, entitled
‘Black Spirits and White, Blue Spirits and Grey’” [sold for £1.5.0].<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">42</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">42</hi> The quotation is from Thomas Middleton’s <hi rend="i">The Witch</hi>,
V, ii (often appropriately interpolated into eighteenth-century performances of <hi rend="i">King Lear</hi>,
IV, 1).
                                        <p>For a fuller account of the sale, see “Thomas Sivright and the
Lost Designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 29 [1984-85]: 103-06; the
information here did not make its way into <hi rend="i">BBS.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>This “Volume of Drawings by Blake” for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (still
untraced) presumably consisted of the 20 finished drawings which Cromek chose in 1805 from the 40 designs
Blake had made for <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">43</ref> Only two finished drawings have survived, both listed in the first 1805 Prospectus but
neither engraved: “The Widow Embracing her Husband’s Grave” (Yale Center for British Art) and “Death
Pursuing the Soul through the Avenues of Life” (collection of Robert N. Essick). We know the subjects of two
further Blair designs, both untraced: “Friendship” (listed in the first prospectus of November
<pb id="p32-127" n="127"/>
                  <figure n="blake-bastien-la-nouvelle-maison-rustique.032.04.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="667">
	<head>4 Title page of J. F. Bastien’s <hi rend="i">La Nouvelle Maison Rustique</hi> (Paris: Deterville
&amp; Destray, 1798) with the signature of “W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Blake” who is almost certainly one of the
numerous contemporaries who bore his names, presumably a land-owner or tenant-farmer.</head>
	<figDesc>The signature is disconcertingly similar to the one dated 29 May 1773 on the title page of anon.,
<hi rend="i">A Political and Satirical History of the Years 1756 and 1757</hi> (London: E. Morris, [?1757])
(see the reproduction in <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> [1995]) 315).</figDesc>
</figure>
1805), and “The Gambols of Ghosts according with their affections previous to the final Judgment”
(mentioned admiringly by Flaxman in his letter). <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">43</hi> According to Flaxman’s
letter of 18 Oct 1805 (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969] 165-66).</note></p>
                <p>Nothing at all is known of the other six finished designs for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> which Cromek bought from Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">44</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">44</hi> However, there are preliminary sketches for all but pl. 2, 8, 10, 12,
plus four alternative versions of the title page.</note></p>
                <p>No surviving drawing or book by Blake has been traced to the collection of Cromek or
Sivright.</p>
                <p>However, Allan Cunningham evidently saw the design described in the first 1805 Prospectus
as “Death Pursuing the Soul through the Avenues of Life.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">45</ref> Cunningham had good opportunity to see Cromek’s watercolors for Blair’s
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, for he lived with Cromek when he first came to London in 1810, and Cromek’s son
later lent him Cromek’s copy of his letter to Blake of May 1807 (q.v.). Apparently the designs for Blair’s
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> were still in the Cromek family as late as 1830 and passed thereafter to Thomas
Sivright of Meggetland. <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">45</hi> Cunningham (1830) paragraph 21 (<hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> 487), a reference generously pointed out to me by Essick. However, Cunningham thought the drawing
an illustration for <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>; one of Urizen’s “exploits is to chase a
female soul through a narrow gate and hurl her headlong down into a darksome pit.” No such action is
described or depicted in <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi></note></p>
                <p>23-25 July 1923</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Catalogue of . . . R.C. Jackson</hi> (London: Goddard &amp; Smith, 1923)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Additional information about R. C. Jackson’s Blake collection is given in Thomas Wright,
<hi rend="i">The Life of Walter Pater</hi> (N.Y.: G. P. Putnam’s Sons’ London: Everett &amp; Co., 1907);
Vol. 2 is largely based on information from R. C. Jackson, information which subsequent Pater scholars have
controverted<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">46</ref> or, more commonly,
ignored. For instance, Wright claimed that Jackson is the original of Pater’s <hi rend="i">Marius the
Epicurean</hi> and that Pater “spent far more of his time in the company of Mr. Jackson than in that of any
other friend” (21, 42). <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">46</hi> For example, Jackson is a “bizarre
halluciné” whose “témoigne est . . . profondément suspect à nos yeux” (Germaine d’Hangest, 
<hi rend="i">Walter Pater:</hi> L’Homme et l’Œuvre [Paris: Didier, 1961] 287); Jackson “never seems to have
realised the boundary between the world of his dreams and the realities of his situation,” and none of
Pater’s known friends had apparently heard of Jackson (Samuel Wright, “Richard Charles Jackson,” 
<hi rend="i">Antigonish Review</hi> 1 [1971]: 82, 86). There is no reference to Jackson in the indices to Samuel
Wright, <hi rend="i">An Informative Index to the Writings of Walter Pater</hi> (West Cornwall, Connecticut:
Locust Hill Press, 1987), or in <hi rend="i">Letters of Walter Pater</hi>, ed. Lawrence Evans (Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1970).</note></p>
                <p>On the other hand, Wright does present some hard evidence in the form of photographs
representing Jackson c. 1882 (as “Brother a Becket”), c. 1886 (as “Marius the Epicurean”), c. 1890,
and August 1906 (“in Mr. Wright’s study at Olney”) (53, 78, 172, 233) as well as Jackson’s richly
cluttered rooms in Camberwell (181, 185, 189, though with no table like the one owned by Gainsborough and
Blake).</p>
                <p>Jackson’s library may not have been, as Wright claimed, “one of the most valuable
private libraries in England,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">47</ref> but
it was sufficiently extensive to allow Jackson to give 850 books on Dante to Southwark Public Library in
1900,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">48</ref> and Wright’s book reproduces
from it photographs of (1) Virgil, Sebastian Brandt’s edition, commentary by Christophoro Landino (Argent:
Johannis Gruninger, 1502) (255, 258, 261), (2) Homer (Venice, 1525) with over 100 woodcuts (265, 269, 273,
276), (3) Dante, <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi> (Venice, 1529) (248), (4) <hi rend="i">The Workes of our
Antient and learned English Poet Geoffrey Chaucer</hi> (London: Bonham Norton, 1598) (237, 241, 245), and (5)
John Guillim, <hi rend="i">Display of Heraldry</hi>, Fourth Edition (London: Richard Bleme, 1660) with
“every coat . . . properly colored at the time of publication” (268). Wright
<pb id="p32-128" n="128"/>
also refers to “an early edition of Caxton and a pre-Caxtonian copy of the Golden Legend, with beautiful
binding and clasps” and “first editions of Carlyle and Blake” (174). <note id="n47"><hi rend="s">47</hi>
Thomas Wright 81.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">48</hi> Samuel Wright, “Richard Charles Jackson,” <hi rend="i">Antigonish
Review</hi> 1 (1971): 87.</note></p>
                <p>In particular, the “Blake treasures” which Jackson showed to Pater consisted of
<q>
an engraving of the Canterbury Pilgrims, Blake’s original oil-colour sketch for Chaucer, several copies of
Blake’s works in proof state, including the plates to the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>, Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, and Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>—all in uncut states, and a copy of the
famous ‘Marriage of Heaven and Hell,’ coloured in water-colours by Blake’s own hand.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">49</ref>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">49</hi> Wright 180. Wright does not mention a number of works associated with
Blake in the 1923 catalogue: portraits of Dante and Chaucer (#182), a pen-and-ink drawing (#245), a “letter
from Blake to Flaxman” (#293), Blake’s chair (#465), his painting table (#579f), and 37 volumes from
“The Library of William Blake” (#812)—perhaps Jackson acquired these after Pater’s death in 1894 or
after Wright’s book was published in 1907.</note></q></p>
                <p>Of these works by Blake, the only one which appears in the 1923 sale is the engraving of
the Canterbury Pilgrims (#293, not attributed to Blake)—perhaps the others had been.</p>
                <p>Published “Proofs” of Job (1826) and Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1808) are not
uncommon, but no other copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797) is known to be “in proof
state.” “Blake’s original oil-colour sketch for Chaucer” which Wright says Jackson owned is not
otherwise known.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">50</ref> Of the eight known
colored copies of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, copies F-I could not have belonged to Jackson, and it is
exceedingly unlikely that A, C-E did. <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">50</hi> Blake’s tempera for the Canterbury
Pilgrims has been in the Stirling-Maxwell family since 1853 (Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and
Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven &amp; London: Yale University Press, 1981) 475), and the uncolored
pencil sketch has been in the Cunliffe family since 1895 (476). It is exceedingly unlikely that Blake ever
made a sketch for Chaucer <hi rend="i">in oil</hi>, as opposed, say, to watercolors.</note></p>
                <p>Almost certainly Jackson did not own a proof copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> (1797), “Blake’s original oil-colour sketch for Chaucer,” or a copy of <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, though he could have had the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> facsimile of Hotten
(1868) or of Muir (1884).</p>
                <p>September 1949</p>
                <p>§Maggs Bros Catalogue 117, <hi rend="i">Mercurius Britannicus.</hi></p>
                <p>Sixteen Blake drawings are recorded in R. N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 1998,”
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1999).</p>
                <p>1983</p>
                <p>*Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake:</hi> A Catalogue
(1983) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 301&gt;.</p>
                <p>For “New Information about Blake’s Engravings” for <hi rend="i">The Separate
Plates</hi>, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 136.</p>
                <p>1991</p>
                <p>*Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (1991)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 310&gt;.</p>
                <p>For “New Information about Blake’s Engravings” for <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Commercial Book Illustrations</hi>, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 136.</p>
                <p>1995</p>
                <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement:</hi> A Bibliography of
Publications and Discoveries about William Blake 1971-92 being a Continuation of <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
(1995).</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>5 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 32 (1998): 46-48 (“<hi rend="i">Blake
Books/Records/Supplements</hi>” are “such a Herculean set of labors, and such wonderful achievements”
that they should be merged and published on CD-ROM [48]).</p>
                <p>6 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 (1998):
396-97 (“encyclopaedic and indispensable”).</p>
                <p>2 April-16 July 1997</p>
                <p>Patrick Noon, <hi rend="i">The Human Form Divine</hi> (1997)</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>3 §Robert Orme, <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi> 5 (1998): 44-45.</p>
                <p>22 June-6 September 1998</p>
                <p>*<hi rend="i">William Blake and his Circle:</hi> Exhibition Guide, Birmingham Museum and
Art Gallery, 22 June -6 September 1998. (Birmingham: Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery, 1998) 4o, 8 pp., 47
entries.</p>
                <p>The exhibition consists of 17 Blakes and 26 works by Calvert, Francis Oliver Finch, Fuseli,
Linnell, Palmer, Richmond, James Smetham, Stothard, and Varley.</p>
                <p>Reviews, Announcements, &amp;C.</p>
                <p>1 *Dave Freak, <hi rend="i">What’s On:</hi> Birmingham and Central England, 13-26 June
1998, 28.</p>
                <p>2 Anon., “Midlands &amp; North West Previews,” <hi rend="i">Art Review</hi>,
July/August 1998 (“A programme of theatrical events, readings, lectures and children’s workshops has been
organised by the Museum to complement this significant exhibition”).</p>
                <p>3 *Terry Grimley, “Visions of a new Jerusalem: Terry Grimley welcomes a rare public
showing for Birmingham’s William Blake collection,” <hi rend="i">Birmingham Post</hi>, 30 June 1998
(“The heart of Birmingham’s Blake collection consists of six” Dante watercolors).</p>
                <p>4 *Anon., “William Blake &amp; His Circle,” <hi rend="i">What’s On:</hi> Your Leading
Leisure Guide, July 1998, 35 (“All but four of the images on show in this exhibition . . . are owned by
Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery”).</p>
                <p>11 July-11 October 1998</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">William Blake Hangaten</hi> [<hi rend="i">Exhibition of William Blake’s
Engravings</hi>]. Kanagawa Kindai Bijutsukan Bekkan. (Kanagawa, Japan, 1998) In Japanese.</p>
                <pb id="p32-129" n="129"/>
                <p>A sheet folded in three with:
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1 Hidefumi Hashi. “Blake no Hanga ni miru Jukosa to Shinpisei [Depth and Mystery in Blake’s
Engravings].”</p></item>
	<item><p>2 “Sakuhin Kaisetsu [Works Commentary].”</p></item>
	<item><p>3 “William Blake Ryakunenpu [Short Chronicle of William Blake].”</p></item>
	<item><p>4 “Shuppin Risuto [List of Exhibits].”</p></item>
</list></p>
                <p>The works exhibited were Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797), Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, Virgil’s <hi rend="i">Pastorals</hi> (1977), <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1826), and Dante
(1838), all from the Kanagawa Modern Fine Art Museum.</p>
                <p>Autumn 1998</p>
                <p>*John Windle, Antiquarian Bookseller. <hi rend="i">List Twenty-Nine:</hi> William Blake.
(San Francisco: John Windle, Autumn [November] 1998) 8o, [50] pp., 221 lots, no ISBN.</p>
                <p>Chiefly books with Blake’s commercial illustrations, reprints of his art and poetry, and
books about him.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part V<lb/>
                    Books Blake Owned<lb/>
                    Newly Recorded Title</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>CUMBERLAND, George</p>
                <p>= | THE CAPTIVE OF THE | CASTLE OF SENNAAR | AN AFRICAN TALE: | CONTAINING VARIOUS |
ANECDOTES OF THE | SOPHIANS HITHERTO | UNKNOWN TO MANKIND | IN GENERAL. | = | BY GEORGE CUMBERLAND. | = |
LONDON: PRINTED FOR THE AUTHOR; AND SOLD| BY MESS. EGERTON, OPPOSITE THE ADMIRALTY. | M DCC XCVIII [1798].</p>
                <p>Collection:: <hi rend="i">Untraced.</hi></p>
                <p>Description: The novel, set in the island of Sophis in central Africa, concerns a Utopian
community embodying the best qualities of classical Greece but with radically liberated sexual customs.
Cumberland gave copies to his friends, but one of them warned him that, as Cumberland reported, it would be
“dangerous under Mr Pitts’ maladministration, to publish it,” and therefore “it was never published or
a single copy sold to any one.” Only six copies are known, in Australian National University, Bodley
(corrected), Bristol Central Library (corrected), British Library, John Rylands Library of the University of
Manchester (corrected), and Yale (see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of George
Cumberland</hi> [1975], 20-23).</p>
                <p>Blake almost certainly received one of the gift copies, for on 1 September 1800 he wrote to
Cumberland: “Your Vision of the Happy Sophis I have devourd. O most delicious book.”</p>
                <p>Newly Recorded Title</p>
                <p>CUMBERLAND, George</p>
                <p>SOME ANECDOTES | OF THE LIFE OF | JULIO BONASONI, | <hi rend="i">A BOLOGNESE ARTIST</hi>, |
WHO FOLLOWED THE STYLES OF THE BEST | SCHOOLS IN THE SIXTEENTH CENTURY. | 
<hi rend="smallcaps"><corr type="emend">Accompanied</corr> By a</hi> CATALOGUE OF THE | ENGRAVINGS, WITH THEIR MEASURES, OF THE | WORKS
OF THAT TASTEFUL COMPOSER. | AND REMARKS ON THE GENERAL CHARACTER | OF HIS RARE AND EXQUISITE PERFORMANCES. |
= | <hi rend="i">TO WHICH IS PREFIXED</hi>, | A PLAN FOR THE IMPROVEMENT OF THE | ARTS IN ENGLAND. | = | BY
GEORGE CUMBERLAND. | = |—I’ll write it straight; | The Matter’s in my Head, and in my Heart. | 
<hi rend="i">Shakspeare’s As You Like It.</hi> | = | LONDON | Printed by W. Wilson, Ave-Maria Lane; | And sold
by G. G. J. and J. Robinson, Paternoster-Row. | M DCC XCIII [1793].</p>
                <p>Collection: <hi rend="i">Untraced.</hi></p>
                <p>Description: Cumberland almost certainly gave a copy to Blake, for Blake urged the editor
of the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> to “notice a Proposal made some years ago in a Life of Julio
Bonasoni . . . [<hi rend="i">concerning</hi>] the Erection of National Galleries for the Reception of Castes
in Plaster from all the Beautiful Antique Statues Basso Relievos &amp;c that can be procured” (quoted in his
letter to Cumberland of 1 September 1800).</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>Appendix<lb/>
                  Books Owned by the Wrong William Blake</title>
                </head>
                <p>BASTIEN, J.-F.</p>
                <p>LA NOUVELLE | MAISON RUSTIQUE,| OU | ÉCONOMIE RURALE, | PRATIQUE ET GÉNÉRALE | DE TOUS
LES BIENS DE CAMPAGNE. | Nouvelle Édition, entièrement refondue, considérablement augmentée, | et mise en
ordre, d’après les expériences les plus sûres, les auteurs les | plus estimés, les mémoires et les
procédés de cultivateurs, amateurs, et artistes, chacun dans les parties qui les concernent; Par J.-F.
BASTIEN: | AVEC 60 FIGURES. | TOME PREMIER[-TROISIEME]. | - | A PARIS, | Chez DETERVILLE, libr., rue du
Battoir, no. 16, près celle de l’Éperon. | DESRAY, libraire, rue Hautefeuille, no. 36, près
S.-André-des-Arcs.| -| AN VI.—M. DCC. XCVIII [1798]. (Beinecke Library, Yale University) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #755&gt;</p>
                <p>The signature of “W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Blake” in old brown ink at the top of each
quarto volume (see illus. 4) is similar to that of the poet but is almost certainly that of one of the score
or more of contemporaries who bore his names, presumably one of the “propriétaires de terres” or
cultivateurs” to whom the book is addressed. The volume has been at Yale since at least 1941.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Part VI<lb/>
                    Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>§Abramovitch, N.Y. “[Aestheticism and Eurotics [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>], . . . Blake].”
<hi rend="i">Obrazovanye</hi> 5 (1906): 21-51, section 2. In Russian.</p>
                <p>Ackroyd, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>54 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995
<pb id="p32-130" n="130"/>
(1998): 398 (“a careful assemblage of the narrative from his highly eclectic sources”).</p>
                <p>Alexander, Bryan Nemo, “Dialectical Nightmares: The Historicity of the Romantic-era
Doppelganger in the Works of Godwin, Hogg, Blake, Burney, and the Shelleys.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 58
(1998): 3927A. Michigan Ph.D., 1997, 147 pp.</p>
                <p>“Blake (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>) and Shelley (<hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi>)
offer a eucatastrophic double, whose characters deliberately will doubt as a weapon.”</p>
                <p>§Allen, Graham. <hi rend="i">Romantic Allegory.</hi> (London: Routledge, 1996)</p>
                <p>Compares “The Ancient Mariner” with <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion.</hi></p>
                <p>Anon. “Blake House.” <hi rend="i">Daily Telegraph</hi>, Wednesday 7 October 19[ ].</p>
                <p>About Blake’s South Molton Street residence which is for sale to “William Blake
enthusiasts” for £1,500,000.</p>
                <p>Anon. “Blake, John.” Vol. I (1835), p. 522 of Neues allgemeines | Künstler-Lexicon |
oder | Nachrichten | von dem | Leben und den Werken | der | Maler, Bildhauer, Baumeister, Kupferstecher, |
Formschneider, Lithographen, Zeichner, Me- | dailleure, Elfenbeinarbeiter, etc.|= | Bearbeitet von | Dr. G.K.
Nagler.| - | <hi rend="i">Erster Band.</hi>| A—Boe.| - | München,| 1835. | Verlag von E.A. Fleischmann.
&lt;Getty Library, Malibu&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Blake, John, Bruder William’s, ebenfalls Zeichner and Kupferstecher, arbeitete
mehreres für literarische Erzeugnisse. Im Jahre 1817 stach er die Umrisse zu Hesiod’s Theogonie nach
Flaxmann. Die näheren Lebensverhältnisse dieses Künstler sind uns nicht bekannt.”</p>
                <p>The reason why nothing more could be found about this engraver named John Blake is that he
did not exist. William Blake did have a brother named John, but he was a baker and soldier and
ne’er-do-well.</p>
                <p>Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> (1817) is said on the title page to be “Engraved by
William Blake,” but it was advertised in <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Review</hi> 28 (1817): 261, and 
<hi rend="i">New Monthly Magazine</hi> 7 (1817): 246 as having plates “Engraved by J. Blake” 
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 560), and the plates are also said to be “by J. Blake” in Friedrich Adolph Ebert, 
<hi rend="i">Allgemeines Bibliographisches Lexikon</hi> 2 (Leipzig: F.A. Brockhaus, 1821): 199 &lt;<hi
rend="i">BR</hi> #535&gt;.</p>
                <p>Anon., “Blake, William,” the preceding article in <hi rend="i">Neues allgemeines
Kunstler-Lexicon</hi>, is recorded under “Nagler” in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2267.</p>
                <p>Anon. “Blake-Lovers Walked In: Cottage Owner’s Complaint.” <hi rend="i">Bognor Regis
Post</hi>, 16 October 1965.</p>
                <p>Dorothy Howell complains about the plaque the Council put on her cottage in Felpham.</p>
                <p>*Anon. “Blake’s Cottage to be allowed to retire.” <hi rend="i">Evening News</hi>, 12
October 1965, 15.</p>
                <p>Because tourists invaded the Felpham Cottage when a plaque was put on it, the Council has
agreed to remove the plaque.</p>
                <p>*Anon. “Council Remove Sign to Restore Blake’s ‘Heaven.’” <hi rend="i">Evening
Argus</hi>, 12 October 1965, 18.</p>
                <p>The plaque on Blake’s Felpham cottage seemed to invite unwanted invasions of
tourists.</p>
                <p>*Anon. “Mrs. Howell hopes to be left alone.” <hi rend="i">Observer</hi> [Bognor Regis],
15 October 1965, 24.</p>
                <p>The owner of Blake’s Cottage in Felpham hopes tourists will go away.</p>
                <p>Anon. “<hi rend="i">The Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and
Architects.</hi> By Allan Cunningham. Vol. II. Being No. X of the Family Library. London. John Murray. 1830.
12mo. Pp. 320.” <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi> 67 (1830): 112-15 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
347&gt;.</p>
                <p>The review may have been written by Henry Glassford Bell, or by his good friend James Hogg,
according to David Groves, “Blake, the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi>, and James Hogg,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 32 (1998): 14-16.</p>
                <p>*Anon. “Roof of Rusted Gold.” ‘<hi rend="i">The Post</hi>’ [Bognor Regis], 20 April
1957, 5.</p>
                <p>The thatching on Blake’s Felpham cottage is being replaced.</p>
                <p>Anon. “Strange Pictures at the Secular Hall.” <hi rend="i">Free Press</hi> [Leicester],
20 October 1900.</p>
                <p>This may have been the first occasion when Blake’s designs (photographed by Mr. A. J.
Essex) were “projected on to the magic-lantern screen.”</p>
                <p>Anon. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Free Press</hi> [Leicester], 13 October 1900.</p>
                <p>About Gould’s lecture on “Blake’s career and achievements” at the Leicester Secular
Hall, followed by pictures “on the lantern-sheet” from photographs by A. J. Essex.</p>
                <p>Aoyama, Keiko. “<hi rend="i">Blake Studies in Japan:</hi> A Bibliography of Works on
William Blake Published in Japan 1893-1993.” <hi rend="i">Shoshi Sakuin Tenbo: Journal of Japan Indexers
Association</hi> 19 (1995): 19-27 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996): 149&gt;. B. Reprinted on 223-38 of Vol.
I of <hi rend="i">Shoshi o tsukuru</hi> [<hi rend="i">How to Make Bibliographies</hi>]. Ed. Shun Unno,
<corr type="emend">Mitsuhiro Oda,</corr> Kazuaki Kishida, and Shinichi Toda. (Tokyo: Nichigai Associates, 1997) In Japanese.</p>
                <p>§*Arbuthnot, May Hill. “William Blake 1757-1827.” Pp. 166-71 of her 
<hi rend="i">Children’s Books.</hi> (Chicago, Atlanta, Dallas, Palo
<pb id="p32-131" n="131"/>
Alto, Fair Lawn [N.J.]: Scott, Foresman and Company [1957]. B. §(?) C. Third Edition. (1964) D. §Fourth
Edition. (1972).</p>
                <p>About how to teach about children’s books; “<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> is a
landmark in English literature as well as in children’s literature” (66).</p>
                <p>See also “Woodcuts and Engravings Before 1800” (55-56) and “William Blake
1757-1827” (55).</p>
                <p>*Baker, Marcia. <hi rend="i">If Only You Imagine!</hi> The Wondrous World of William Blake.
Illustrated by Todd Hermann. (London: Minerva Press, 1996) 8o, [58 pp.], ISBN: 1-85863-837-2. &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Interactive” narratives for children of what Blake saw, derived from his poems and his
biography, each concluding: “You can [<hi rend="i">see the same things</hi>], if you only imagine!”</p>
                <p>A shorter version appeared in <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society of St James</hi>
(1995): 26-30 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Barrell, John. “A Blake Dictionary.” Chapter 3 (22-57, 353-54) of his <hi rend="i">The
Political Theory of Painting From Reynolds To Hazlitt</hi>: “The Body of the Public” (1986) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 360&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John Lucas (1998) 101-16, omitting the
section on “‘Public.’”</p>
                <p>Batten, Guinn. “Spectral Generation in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: ‘Indolence and
Mourning Sit Hovring.’” Chapter 2 (72-118) of her <hi rend="i">The Orphaned Imagination</hi>: Melancholy
and Commodity Culture in English Romanticism. (Durham &amp; London: Duke University Press, 1988)</p>
                <p>“Blake has prepared us to understand that the poetry of Romantic melancholy recognizes
that the humble body itself . . . reincarnates, in a radically Christian sense, the dead” (118).</p>
                <p>*Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: The Critical Heritage. (London
&amp; Boston: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1975) The Critical Heritage Series. ISBN: 0 7100 8234 7. 8o, xix,
294 pp., 20 plates. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #A1181&gt; B (London &amp; N.Y.: Routledge, 1995) ISBN:
0-415-13441-2.</p>
                <p>B (1995) is a mere reprint of A (1975).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 22, Number 3 (1988-89)</p>
                <p>489 John B. Pierce. “The Shifting Characterization of Tharmas and Enion in Pages 3-7 of
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Pp. 93-102 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#403&gt;. (It was reprinted as part of chapter 3 of his <hi rend="i">Flexible Design</hi> [1998].)</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 27, Number 4 (1994) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BIQ</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>1 *Robert N. Essick. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1993, Including a Report on the Sale of
the Frank Rinder Collection.” Pp. 103-29 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, (1995)&gt;. (Review by David Worrall,
<hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 [1997]: 391: “highly authoritative.”)</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 28, Number 1 (1994) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BIQ</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>1 G. E. Bentley, Jr., With the Assistance of Keiko Aoyama for Japanese Publications.
“William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 1992-1993.” Pp. 4-34 &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi>, (1995)&gt;. (Review by David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>
75 for 1994 [1997]: 391: “useful.”)</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 28, Number 2 (1994 [i.e., 1995])
&lt;<hi rend="i">BIQ</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>1 *Joseph Viscomi. “<hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle</hi>:
Lost or Found?” Pp. 44-61 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;. (Review by David Worrall, 
<hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 [1997]: 392: a “fine essay,” “technically
accomplished”).</p>
                <p>6 David Simpson. “Which Newton for the British Library?” Pp. 77-78 &lt;<hi
rend="i">BIQ</hi> (1995)&gt;. (Review by David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75
for 1994 [1997]: 393: “startlingly original and provocative.”)</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 28, Number 4 (1995)</p>
                <p>1 *Robert N. Essick. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1994.” Pp. 120-41. (A
“Corrigendum,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 [1998]: 135, says that the Essick copies of 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 11, 17 are not from copy c.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 29, Number 1 (1995 [i.e.,
1996])</p>
                <p>1 Lauren Henry. “Sunshine and Shady Groves: What Blake’s ‘Little Black Boy’ Learned
from African Writers.” Pp. 4-11. (Review: David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>
76 for 1995 [1998]: 40 (“fascinating”).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 29 (1996)</p>
                <p>1 *Robert N. Essick. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1995, Including a Survey of Blakes in
Private Ownership.” Pp. 108-30. (A masterfully detailed catalogue, including as an “Appendix: New
Information on Blake’s Engravings” [130].) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt; (Review: David Worrall,
<hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 [1998]: 397).</p>
                <p>2 *G. E. Bentley, Jr., With the Assistance of Keiko Aoyama for Japanese Publications.
“William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 1995.” Pp. 131-68. &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt; (Review: David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76
for 1995 [1998]: 397: “an essential supplement to the [<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>] 
<hi rend="i">Supplement</hi>”).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 31, Number 3 (1997/98)</p>
                <p>1 A. Harris Fairbanks. “Blake, Burke, and the Clanrickard Monument.” Pp. 76-81. (Blake
may have seen the monument
<pb id="p32-132" n="132"/>
of Ann, Countess of Clanrickard [d. 1732], in Westminster Abbey with its motto “Un Roy, un Foy, un Loy”
[shared with Edmund Burke, who came from the same family] and echoed it in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 4:
“One King, one God, one Law.”)</p>
                <p>2 G. E. Bentley, Jr. “Blake’s First Arrest, at Upnor Castle.” Pp. 82-84. (“The
unworldliness of these young men, blithely making careful sketches . . . of military fortifications of the
greatest naval base in the world in time of war, almost surpasses comprehension. At least it might appear so
to naval intelligence, if that is not an oxymoron” [84].)</p>
                <p>3 Vincent Carretta. “Blake’s Meheux?” P. 84. (The J. Meheux who designed “Robin
Hood &amp; Clorinda” engraved by Blake is probably the amateur artist John Meheux [1749?-1839].)</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>4 Nelson Hilton. Review of Marvin Lansverk, <hi rend="i">The Wisdom of Many, The Vision of
One</hi> (1994). Pp. 84-88. (“Students and lovers of Blake can be grateful to Marvin Lansverk for this
awakening call to the rich fields of the poet’s sport with Wisdom and performative language” [88].)</p>
                <p>5 Frank A. Vaughan. Review of Christopher Heppner, <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s
Designs</hi> (1996). Pp. 88-91. (“His warnings should be accepted as necessary and lucid guidelines, and as
a challenge to read Blake by better evidentiary rules” [91].)</p>
                <p>6 Jennifer Davis Michael, review of <hi rend="i">Speak Silence</hi>, ed. Mark Greenberg
(1996). Pp. 92-94. (“It is refreshing to see such meticulous attention given to poems once dismissed as
‘rude’ and ‘clumsy’” [92]. For a “Correction,” see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 [1998]: 175.)</p>
                <p>7 G. E. Bentley, Jr. Review of Peter Isaac, <hi rend="i">William Bulmer: The Fine Printer
in Context 1757-1830</hi> (1994). Pp. 94-97. (“An admirable biographical and commercial history of Bulmer”
[95].)</p>
                <p>8 Sheila A. Spector. Review of Kathryn S. Freeman, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Nostos</hi>
(1997). Pp. 97-102. (“Despite her formidable interpretive abilities, Freeman never really establishes her
own critical stance,” and “her reliance on Eastern mysticism is inconsistent and ahistorical” [101,
99].)</p>
                <p>9 Sarah Joyce. Review of “South Bank Show Documentary on Blake. Directed by David Thomas.
ITV (U.K.), 17 September 1995.” Pp. 102-03. (“A very appealing program, made with a great enthusiasm for
Blake, and an impulse to celebrate as well as to inform” [102].)</p>
                <p>Newsletter</p>
                <p>10 Anon. “Twenty-First Century Blake: Call for Papers.” P. 103. (For the 1998 Modern
Language Association meeting.)</p>
                <p>11 Anon. “Blake and the Book: The Materiality of Books in the Life and Times of William
Blake: Call for Papers, St. Mary’s University College, 18 April 1998.” P. 103.</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 31, Number 4 (1998)</p>
                <p>1 *Robert N. Essick. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1997.” Pp. 108-37. (A masterly survey,
with a “Corrigendum” for “Blake in the Marketplace, 1994,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 28 [1995]: 135,
“Appendix 1: New Information on Blake’s Engravings” for his <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William
Blake</hi>: A Catalogue [136] and <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> [136], and
“Appendix 2: Current Ownership of the Preliminary Drawings for, and Proofs and Relief Etchings of, Blake’s
Wood Engravings Illustrating Thornton’s Virgil” [136-37].)</p>
                <p>2 *G. E. Bentley, Jr., with the Assistance of Keiko Aoyama for Japanese Publications.
“William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 1997.” Pp. 137-75. (With an
“Appendix: Watermarks: A Cumulative Table” [171-73].)</p>
                <p>Newsletter</p>
                <p>3 Anon. “Blake Course at the Tate Gallery.” P. 175. (12 May-16 June.)</p>
                <p>4 Anon. “Correction.” P. 175. (The title of Jennifer Davis Michael’s unpublished book
is <hi rend="i">Cities Not Yet Embodied</hi>, not <hi rend="i">Cities Not Yet Entombed</hi>, as in 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 [1997-98].)</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 32, Number 1 (1998)</p>
                <p>1 *Robert N. Essick and Morton D. Paley. “‘Dear Generous Cumberland’: A Newly
Discovered Letter and Poem by William Blake.” Pp. 4-13. (Text, reproductions, and essay on Blake’s letter
of 1 September 1800.)</p>
                <p>2 David Groves. “Blake, the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi>, and James
Hogg.” Pp. 14-16. (A review of Cunningham’s life of Blake in the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary
Journal</hi> [1830] may be by its editor, Henry Glassford Bell, or by his good friend James Hogg.)</p>
                <p>3 Michael Ferber. “The Orthodoxy of Blake Footnotes.” Pp. 16-19. (Protests against the
needless speculations, often masquerading as well-known facts, in “recent student anthologies” [1979-95],
particularly concerning irrelevant etymologies.)</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>4 Nelson Hilton. Review of Helen P. Bruder, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Daughters of
Albion</hi> (1997). Pp. 20-25. (The book is “at times interesting and provocative” [20].)</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 32, Number 2 (1998 [1999])</p>
                <p>1 *Morton D. Paley. “‘To Defend the Bible in This Year 1798 Would Cost a Man His
Life.’” Pp. 32-43. (“Why should Blake want to defend Thomas Paine [<hi rend="i">from Bishop
Watson</hi>]. . . so unequivocally?” [32].)</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>2 Sheila A. Spector. Review of Robert M. Ryan, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Reformation:</hi>
Religious Politics in English Literature, 1789-1824 (1997). Pp. 43-46.</p>
                <p>3 David Worrall. Review of G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement:</hi> A
Bibliography of Publications and Discoveries about William Blake 1971-92 being a Continuation of 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1995). Pp. 46-48. (“<hi rend="i">Blake Books/Records/Supplements</hi>”
<pb id="p32-133" n="133"/>
are “such a Herculean set of labors, and such wonderful achievements” that they should be merged and
published on CD-ROM [48].)</p>
                <p>4 *Thomas Dillingham. Review of Finn Coren, <hi rend="i">The Blake Project:</hi> Spring
(Bard Records, BACD-1) and <hi rend="i">The Blake Project:</hi> Spring: Appendix (Bard Records, BACD-2). Pp.
49-50. (In his settings of Blake’s poems to rock music, Finn’s “responses to Blake are . . . complex and
interactive.”)</p>
                <p>Newsletter</p>
                <p>5 Anon. “<hi rend="i">The Blake Journal.</hi>” P. 51. (A statement of the editorial
policy of what was previously named the <hi rend="i">Journal of the Blake Society of St James.</hi>)</p>
                <p>6 Anon. “<hi rend="i">Pioneers of the Spirit—William Blake.</hi>” P. 51. (Description
of a television program which “will air early next year” [presumably in 1999].)</p>
                <p>7 Anon. “Cruikshank at Princeton.” (Description of an exhibition of George Cruikshank
prints on the web.)</p>
                <p>8 Anon. “Romantic Revelations.” P. 51. (A description of “the 6th International
Residential Conference of the British Association for Romantic Studies” at Keele University in the summer of
1999.)</p>
                <p>§Boime, Albert. “William Blake’s Graphic Imagery and the Industrial Revolution.” 
<hi rend="i">Art Magazine</hi> (June 1985): 107-19. B. *Reprinted as 414-61 of <hi rend="i">A History of Book
Illustration:</hi> 29 Points of View. Ed. Bill Katz. (Metuchen [N.J.] &amp; London: Scarecrow Press, 1994) The
History of the Book, No. 1. C. An expanded version was printed as *“William Blake” (349-70, 505-08) in
chapter 4: “The Industrial Revolution: Post-American Independence Phase” in his <hi rend="i">Art in an Age
of Revolution 1750-1800.</hi> (Chicago &amp; London: University of Chicago Press, 1987) A Social History of
Art Volume I &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 420 for 1987 only&gt;.</p>
                <p>Bradford, Richard. “Blake and the Arbitrary Use of Language.” Pp. 111-18 of his 
<hi rend="i">A Linguistic History of English Poetry.</hi> (London &amp; N.Y.: Routledge, 1993) The Interface
Series. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>Bruder, Helen P., <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1997)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 32 (1998): 20-25. (The book is “at times
interesting and provocative” [20].)</p>
                <p>§Bulckaer, D. “‘Apocalypse Now’: Blake and Millenialism.” Pp. 103-12 of 
<hi rend="i">Millenialism and Utopianism in Anglo-Saxon Countries—Millenarism et Utopie dans les Pays
Anglo-Saxons.</hi> Ed. W. Rotge. ([ ]: Presse universitaire Mirail [1998]) Anglophonia 3; ISBN:
2-85896-351-0.</p>
                <p>*Bungey, Marguerite. “William Blake: The Man who saw ‘Heaven’ in England’s green
and pleasant land.” <hi rend="i">This England</hi> 18 (1985): 28-29.</p>
                <p>§Burwick, Frederick. “Blake’s Laocoon and Job: On the Boundaries of Painting and
Poetry.” Pp. 125-55 of <hi rend="i">The Romantic Imagination:</hi> Literature and Art in England and
Germany. Ed. Frederick Burwick and Jurgen Klein. (Amsterdam: Rodolpi, 1996).</p>
                <p>*C., G. “Blake’s Cottage, Felpham, Sussex.” <hi rend="i">Country Life</hi>, 4 August
1917, 119.</p>
                <p>A letter to the editor remarking that Blake’s Cottage “has lately changed hands.”</p>
                <p>§Chong, Cue-huan. “‘Bard’s Song’: Blake, Hayley, and the Milton Connection.” 
<hi rend="i">Milton Studies</hi> 7 (1997 [Korea]): 257-95.</p>
                <p>Clark, S. H. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as Empiricist Epic: ‘Weaving the Woof
of Locke.’” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 26 (1997): 457-82.</p>
                <p>Blake’s references to Locke “may be seen as part of a more general reinstatement of an
empiricist perspective in the poem . . . ultimately Lockean in origin” (458).</p>
                <p>Cox, Philip. “Blake, Hayley and Milton: A Reassessment.” <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi> 75 (1994): 430-42 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 (1997):
391-92 (Cox corrects Wittreich).</p>
                <p>Crafton, Lisa Plummer. “The ‘Ancient Voices’ of Blake’s <hi rend="i">The French
Revolution.</hi>” Pp. 41-57 of <hi rend="i">The French Revolution Debate in English Literature and
Culture.</hi> Ed. Lisa Plummer Crafton. (Westport [Connecticut]: Greenwood Press, 1997) Contributions to the
Study of World Literature, Number 87.</p>
                <p>About “verbal warfare” in <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> (48).</p>
                <p>§Crafton, Lisa Plummer. “Blake’s ‘Swinish Multitude’: The Response to Burke in
Blake’s <hi rend="i">The French Revolution.</hi>” <hi rend="i">The Friend:</hi> Comment on Romanticism 2
(1993): 1-12.</p>
                <p>Crehan, Stewart. <hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> (1984) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
444&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Producers and Devourers” is reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John
Lucas (1998) 60-79.</p>
                <p>Cunningham, Allan. <hi rend="i">The Cabinet Gallery of Pictures</hi> (Vol. I, 1833; Vol.
II, 1834) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1431A&gt;. B. (Both? volumes 1834). C. (London: George Virtue, [?1835])
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1432B&gt;.</p>
                <p>De Luca, Vincent, <hi rend="i">Words of Eternity</hi> (1991) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
450&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>10 Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Literature &amp; Theology</hi> 7 (1993): 408-09 (with Otto,
<hi rend="i">Constructive Vision and Visionary Deconstruction</hi> [1991]): De Luca “throws light on a
surprisingly wide range of Blake’s poetic practises” (408).</p>
                <pb id="p32-134" n="134"/>
                <p>§Demidova, O. R. “[Some Particular Features in the Stylistics of the K. Balmont’s and
S. Marshak’s Translations of Blake’s Poem ‘The Tyger’].” [<hi rend="i">Analysis of Styles in Foreign
Fiction and Scientific Literature</hi>] 5 (Leningrad, 1987): 126-33. In Russian.</p>
                <p>Den Otter, A. G. “Displeasing Women: Blake’s Furies and the Ladies of Moral Virtue.”
<hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 9 (1998): 35-58.</p>
                <p>“Many of the patriarchal biases normally associated with men were indulged and presented
by middle- and upperclass [eighteenth century] women themselves” (36).</p>
                <p>*DiSalvo, Jackie, G. A. Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake, Politics,
and History.</hi> (N.Y. &amp; London: Garland Publishing, 1998) Wellesley Studies in Critical Theory, Literary
History, and Culture Volume 17; Garland Reference Library of the Humanities Volume 1842. 8o, xxxii, 386 pp.,
27 Blake plates; ISBN: 0-8153-1679-8.</p>
                <p>It consists of</p>
                <p>1 Jackie DiSalvo. “Introduction.” Pp. xiii-xxxiii. (A survey of Blake criticism:
“So—is Blake dead” politically? [xiii].)</p>
                <p>2 Christopher Z. Hobson. “The Myth of Blake’s ‘Orc Cycle.’” Pp. 5-36. (“The
‘Orc cycle’ is almost entirely a product of Frye’s imagination, not Blake’s,” a “liberal venture
into conservative political theory” [6, 29].)</p>
                <p>3 Stephen C. Behrendt. “Blake’s Bible of Hell: Prophecy as Political Program.” Pp.
37-52. (About the “political dimensions” of <hi rend="i">Urizen, Book of Ahania</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Book of Los</hi>; “William Blake’s works stand as powerful testimony to the proposition that all
writing—indeed all art—is inherently political” [37].)</p>
                <p>4 Eric V. Chandler. “The Anxiety of Production: Blake’s Shift from Collective Hope to
Writing Self.” Pp. 53-79.</p>
                <p>5 James E. Swearingen. “William Blake’s Figural Politics.” Pp. 80-94. (Reprinted from
<hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 59 [1992]: 125-44 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 652&gt;.)</p>
                <p>6 Jon Mee. “‘The Doom of Tyrants’: William Blake, Richard ‘Citizen’ Lee, and the
Millenarian Public Sphere.” Pp. 97-114. (Mee “develops a parallel between Blake’s brand of millenarian
radicalism and the politics of Richard ‘Citizen’ Lee” who combined “intense religious feeling and
violent republicanism” [97, 106].)</p>
                <p>7 Marsha Keith Schuchard. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> and the Regency Crisis:
Lifting the Veil on a Royal Masonic Scandal.” Pp. 115-35. (She is persuaded that “<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>
emerges as a dangerously accurate exposé of the clandestine intrigues of the King’s rebellious brothers and
sons . . . which bordered on treason” [115].)</p>
                <p>8 Joseph Wittreich. “Laboring Into Futurity: A Response.” Pp. 136-43. (In recent Blake
criticism, “The Blake of popular culture is all but ignored,” and such ignorance “threatens to . . .
displace him from the canon” [138].)</p>
                <p>9 Joseph Hutton. “‘Lovers of Wild Rebellion’: The Image of Satan in British Art of
the Revolutionary Era.” Pp. 150-68. (“Blake . . . did not so much revise the image of Satan in according
with his revolutionary sympathies as shatter it out-right and reconstruct the pieces in a new way”
[159].)</p>
                <p>10 David Worrall. “The Mob and ‘Mrs. Q’: William Blake, William Benbow, and the
Context of Regency Radicalism.” Pp. 169-84. (Fascinating details of the radical political context of
Blake’s engraving of Mrs. Quentin, the mistress of the Prince of Wales.)</p>
                <p>11 William Richey. “‘The Lion &amp; Wolf shall cease’: Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> as a Critique of Counter-Revolutionary Violence.” Pp. 196-211.</p>
                <p>12 Michael Ferber. “The Finite Revolutions of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>” Pp.
212-34.</p>
                <p>13 Peter Otto. “Re-Framing the Moment of Creation: Blake’s Re-Visions of the
Frontispiece and Title Page to <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>” Pp. 235-46. (“Each revision thematises elements
present in (or implied by) the frontispiece and title page but previously overlooked or treated as
incidental” [234].)</p>
                <p>14 G. A. Rosso. “Empire of the Sea: Blake’s ‘King Edward the Third’ and English
Imperial Poetry.” Pp. 251-72. (In “King Edward the Third” from <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>,
Blake is parodying his “Shakespearean model to attack the empire panegyric tradition” in the context of
“the imperial crisis of 1778-79” [251, 268].)</p>
                <p>15 Anne Rubenstein and Camilla Townsend. “Revolted Negroes and the Devilish Principle:
William Blake and Conflicting Visions of Boni’s Wars in Surinam, 1772-1796.” Pp. 273-98. (They attempt
“to unravel the varying discourses from the <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, . . . to see precisely how they
acted upon each other to change the nature of the argument as a whole, even against the will of the different
speakers” [273].)</p>
                <p>16 Catherine C. McClenahan. “Albion and the Sexual Machine: Blake, Gender and Politics,
1780-1795.” Pp. 301-24. (Blake “represents . . . imagination . . . as shaped by the sexual machine while
it exposes this machinery in order to resist and change it” [304].)</p>
                <p>17 Harriet Kramer Linkin. “Transfigured Maternity in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi>: Inverting the ‘Maternity Plot’ in ‘A Dream.’” Pp. 325-38. (“Blake’s
representation of maternity in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> offers a more subtle and perhaps
sympathetic recognition of a greater variety of maternal positions than contemporary cultural idealizations of
the mother allow” [327].)</p>
                <p>18 June Sturrock. “Maenads, Young Ladies, and the Lovely Daughters of Albion.” Pp.
339-49.</p>
                <p>19 Anne K. Mellor. “Blake, Gender, and Imperial Ideology: A Response.” Pp. 350-53.
(“Blake was deeply—if unselfconsciously—complicit in the racist and sexist ideologies of his culture”
[351].)</p>
                <p>*Dortort, Fred. <hi rend="i">The Dialectic of Vision:</hi> A Contrary Reading of William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Foreword by Donald Ault. (Barrytown [N.Y.]: Station Hill Arts, 1998)
The Clinamen Studies Series. 8o, xxviii, 468 pp.; ISBN: 1-886449-49-X.</p>
                <pb id="p32-135" n="135"/>
                <p>Donald Ault, “Foreword” (xv-xxviii): Dortort’s book, the “first full-length
appropriation of the methods and terms I developed specifically for the study of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>” in <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound</hi> (1987), is “certainly one of the most unorthodox books
ever written on Blake” (xvii, xv).</p>
                <p>The book is an attempt to “resolve the riddle of the poem” by positing “two totally
contradictory sets of meanings” in it, one of “radical English Christianity” and one which “exposed .
. . [<hi rend="i">the former’s</hi>] potential contradictions and ultimately oppressive manifestations,”
the conflicting attitudes perhaps originating in “an internal conflict . . . [<hi rend="i">in Blake’s
own</hi>] personality” (11, 22, 38, 13).</p>
                <p>“Event Catalogues” (explained on 85-86) constitute a summary of the texts of the four
chapters page-by-page (85-91; 155-63; 256-71; 384-400).</p>
                <p>Appendix A, “A Critical Review” gives critics’ views of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
(421-48).</p>
                <p>*Drinkwater, John. “Solitary Genius: John Drinkwater’s Poem for Saturday: William Blake
1757-1827.” <hi rend="i">Evening Standard</hi> [19] 17.</p>
                <p>Prints the “Jerusalem” lyric from <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi></p>
                <p>§Edgar, Brian Windsor. “Pity and Anger in the Poetry of William Blake from ‘Poetical
Sketches’ to ‘Milton.’” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 58 (1998).</p>
                <p>§Elistratova, A. [<hi rend="i">William Blake (1757-1827)</hi>]. (Moscow: Znanye, 1957) In
Russian.</p>
                <p>Ellis, Edwin J. <hi rend="i">The Real Blake</hi>: A Portrait Biography. (London, 1907)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1547&gt; B. (N.Y.: McClure, Phillips &amp; Co., 1907)</p>
                <p>Erdman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Prophet Against Empire</hi>, Third Edition (1977)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 463&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Infinite London” is reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John Lucas
(1998) 51-57.</p>
                <p>*Essick, Robert N. “Representation, Anxiety, and the Bibliographic Sublime.” 
<hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 59 (1998): 503-28.</p>
                <p>The “bibliographic sublime” is the “response to semiotic uncertainty, when inscribed
within the physical features of a book” (513). The essay ranges agreeably through <hi rend="i">Tristram
Shandy, Pat the Bunny</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (511-13, 523-27). <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (L)
pl. 25-27 (“A Song of Liberty”), “almost certainly printed as a small, independent pamphlet” (523-24),
is reproduced entire.</p>
                <p>*Esterhammer, Angela. <hi rend="i">Creating States</hi>: Studies in the Performative
Language of John Milton and William Blake (1994) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995, 1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>2 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 (1997): 396
(it contains “some of the sharpest readings of Blake I have seen in a long time”).</p>
                <p>Evans, B. Ifor. “Thomas Gray and William Blake.” Chapter 7 (99-108) of his 
<hi rend="i">Tradition and Romanticism.</hi> (London, 1940) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1584&gt; B. 
<hi rend="i">Tradition and Romanticism</hi>: Studies in English Poetry from Chaucer to W.B. Yeats. (Hamden
[Connecticut]: Archon Books, [c. 1964]).</p>
                <p>§Fabre, Silvia Diaz. “Rewriting the Blakeian ‘Invisible Worm’ in the Work of
Jennifer Johnston.” <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Cuadernos de Literatura Inglesa Norteamericana</hi></corr> 2 (1997 [Aires,
Argentina]): 39-52.</p>
                <p>Apparently about Johnston’s novel called <hi rend="i">The Invisible Worm.</hi></p>
                <p>§Flory, Wendy Stallard. “‘The Diving and Ducking Moralities’: Sendak’s 
<hi rend="i">Pierre</hi>, Blake, and the Vulnerabilities of the Artist.” <hi rend="i">Melville Society
Extracts</hi> #111 (December 1997): 7-17.</p>
                <p>Foote, G. W. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">National Reformer</hi>, 14, 21, 28 February,
21 March 1875, 100-01, 114-15, 131-32, 181-82.</p>
                <p>A biographical account, with sections on his visions (they “were but developed
subjectivities objectively extruded” [131]) and his achievement (“He is a star of first magnitude in the
constellations of poetry and art” [182]).</p>
                <p>*Freed, Eugenie R. “<hi rend="i">A Portion of His Life</hi>”: William Blake’s
Miltonic Vision of Woman ([?1994]) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 [1997]:
393-93 (“recaptures something of the holistic Blakean study we are in danger of losing”).</p>
                <p>*Freed-Isserow, Eugenie. “‘Building the Stubborn Structure of the Language’: The
Dynamic of Blake’s Poetic Art.” <hi rend="i">English Studies in Africa</hi> 41 (1998): 11-28.</p>
                <p>It deals especially with the images of women weaving on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl.
59.</p>
                <p>Freeman, Kathryn S., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Nostos</hi> (1997) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1998)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Sheila A. Spector, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 97-102 (“Despite her formidable
interpretive abilities, Freeman never really establishes her own critical stance,” and “her reliance on
Eastern mysticism is inconsistent and ahistorical” [101, 99]).</p>
                <p>2 §<hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century Literature</hi> 52 (1997): 398+.</p>
                <p>3 §<hi rend="i">Reference and Research Book News</hi> 12 (1997): 158.</p>
                <p>*Fuhr, Bodil. “Engelsk mystik i trøndersk landskap: William Blake, engelsk mystiker,
poet og billedkunstner fra 1700-tallet, blir frontfigur under Olavsfestdagene.” 
<hi rend="i">Aftenposten</hi> [Oslo], 18 July 1998. In Norwegian.</p>
                <p>The Olaf-Festival at Trondheim cathedral will focus on William Blake, with lectures,
exhibitions, and performance of music by Gunnar Jess based on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
                <pb id="p32-136" n="136"/>
                <p>Fuller, David. “William Blake.” Pp. 27-44 of <hi rend="i">Literature of the Romantic
Period</hi>: A Bibliographical Guide. Ed. Michael O’Neill. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1998).</p>
                <p>A sound and straightforward guide designed especially for undergraduates, with essays on
“Texts and Facsimiles” (27-28), “Literary Scholarship and Criticism” (29-37), and “Art Scholarship
and Criticism” (37-40).</p>
                <p>*Gardner, Stanley. <hi rend="i">The Tyger, the Lamb, and the Terrible Desart: Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi> in its times and circumstance Including facsimiles of two copies. (London:
Cygnus Arts; Madison &amp; Teaneck: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 1998) 4o, xi, 256 pp., 107
illustrations; ISBN: 0-8386-3566-0 and 1-900541-35-1.</p>
                <p>The biographical account (1-157) concentrates on 1757-94 and stresses local details,
particularly those relating to charity toward children in the Parish of St. James, with frequent
cross-references to his <hi rend="i">Blake’s Innocence and Experience Retraced</hi> (1986) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 482&gt;. The reproductions include <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (I, b) (161-214), followed by a
“Commentary” (216-47) on each plate dealing primarily with the designs.</p>
                <p>*Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi> . . . (1863). . . . C.
Ed. with an Introduction by W. Graham Robertson and Numerous Reproductions from Blake’s Pictures Many
Hitherto Unpublished . . . (1907) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1680&gt; . . . N. Ed. W. Graham Robertson.
(Mineola [N.Y.]: Dover Publications, 1998).</p>
                <p>The 1998 edition is “an unabridged republication” of the 1907 Bodley Head edition,
except, perhaps, in the title page.</p>
                <p>W. R. G. (1906), “Introduction” (v-xi); Anne Gilchrist (1863), “Preface to the First
Edition” (xiii-xv); W. M. Rossetti, “Annotated Lists of William Blake’s Paintings, Drawings, and
Engravings” (413-90) and “Supplementary List” (491-96) and the text of <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi> (457-526). There are 53 plates, many still marked “from the collection of Mr. W. Graham
Robertson.”</p>
                <p>Glausser, Wayne. “Atomistic Simulacra in the Enlightenment and in Blake’s
Post-Enlightenment.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century</hi>: Theory and Interpretation 32 (1991): 73-88
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 485&gt;.</p>
                <p>“A few passages” from it are adapted in chapter 7 (“Printing”) of his 
<hi rend="i">Locke and Blake</hi> (1998).</p>
                <p>Glausser, Wayne. <hi rend="i">Locke and Blake</hi>: A Conversation across the Eighteenth
Century. (Gainesville, Tallahassee, Tampa, Boca Raton, Pensacola, Orlando, Miami, Jacksonville: University
Press of Florida, 1998) 8o, pp. xi, 201, ISBN: 0-8130-1570-7.</p>
                <p>It is “a composite critical biography, organized by topics of cultural significance ....
Each chapter begins with a biographical connection between Locke and Blake” (ix).</p>
                <p>“A version of chapter 3” (“Two English Physicians”) was printed as “Locke and
Blake as Physicians Delivering the Eighteenth-Century Body” in <hi rend="i">Reading the Social Body</hi>
(1993); the first half of chapter 4 is reprinted from “Three Approaches to the Slave Trade,” 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi> 60 (1990): 197-216 (which is entirely about Locke); and chapter
7 “adapts a few passages” from his “Atomistic Simulacra in the Enlightenment and in Blake’s
Post-Enlightenment,” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century</hi>: Theory and Interpretation 32 (1991): 73-88
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 485&gt;.</p>
                <p>Glausser, Wayne. “Locke and Blake as Physicians Delivering the Eighteenth-Century
Body.” Chapter 11 (218-43) of <hi rend="i">Reading the Social Body.</hi> Ed. Catherine B. Burroughs and
Jeffrey David Ehrenreich. (Iowa City: University of Iowa Press, 1993).</p>
                <p>“I want to . . . complicate some of our conventional ideas about Locke, Blake, and the
period” (218).</p>
                <p>“A version” of it was printed as “Two English Physicians” in chapter 3 of his 
<hi rend="i">Locke and Blake</hi> (1998).</p>
                <p>Greenberg, Mark L., ed. <hi rend="i">Speak Silence</hi>: Rhetoric and Culture in Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1996) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;.</p>
                <p>3 Susan J. Wolfson. “Sketching Verbal Form: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches.</hi>” Pp. 27-70. (It is a version of “Blake’s Politics in Rhyme and Blank Verse,” 195-205 of
<hi rend="i">Aesthetics and Ideology</hi>, ed. George Levine [1994], and another version was printed as
chapter 2 [32-62, 249-55] of her <hi rend="i">Formal Changes</hi>: The Shaping of Poetry in British
Romanticism [1997].)</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Jennifer Davis Michael, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 92-94 (“it is refreshing to
see such meticulous attention given to poems once dismissed as ‘rude’ and clumsy’” [92].)</p>
                <p>§Gridninsky. [sic] “[William Blake].” [<hi rend="i">Monthly Edition</hi>] 20 (1900):
238-42. In Russian.</p>
                <p>Hadfield, Andrew. “William Blake, Edmund Spenser, and William Kent.” <hi rend="i">Notes
and Queries</hi> 242 [N.S. 45] (1997): 207-10.</p>
                <p>Blake may have known the edition of Spenser edited by Thomas Birch with 32 plates after
William Kent (1751) as shown by the “possible parallels” in his own designs.</p>
                <p>*Haresnape, Geoffrey. “William Blake and South Africa.” <corr type="emend">South African National
Gallery/Suid Afrikaanse Nasionale Kunsmuseum</corr> <hi rend="i">Quarterly Bulletin</hi> (September 1980): 5-10.</p>
                <p>It is especially about “The Little Black Boy,” Negroes, slavery, and state religion:
“In South Africa today Blake is disquieting.”</p>
                <p>§Harriston, J. R. “‘Empire is no more’: William Blake, Tom Paine, and the American
Revolution.” <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi>, 3 S, 7 (1998): 16-32.</p>
                <p>Heppner, Christopher, <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s Designs</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>3 Irene Chayes, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 27 (1996): 200-01 (with
<pb id="p32-137" n="137"/>
	<hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi> [1995]) (“There is . . . much to disagree with” and “much
to be commended in the book as a whole” [201]).</p>
                <p>4 David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> 47 (1997): 405-06.
(“Heppner’s scholarship is excellent .... The book should stimulate more work on Blake’s illustrations
on sounder interpretative bases” [406]).</p>
                <p>5 Frank A. Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 88-91. (“His warnings should be
accepted as necessary and lucid guidelines, and as a challenge to read Blake by better evidentiary rules”
[91]).</p>
                <p>6 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 (1998):
401-02 (“careful and cautiously powerful” and “most witty”).</p>
                <p>Higgins, Michael. <hi rend="i">Heretic Blood</hi>: The Spiritual Geography of Thomas
Merton. (Toronto &amp; N.Y.: Stoddart, 1998) Passim.</p>
                <p>“The key to his spiritual biography is . . . William Blake”; “Thomas Merton is the
William Blake of our time” (3, 4). Chapter 2 is “Tharmas: The Rebel” (67-118), chapter 3 “Urizen: The
Marginal Critic” (119-92), chapter 4 “Luvah: The Lover” (193-232), and chapter 5 “Urthona: The Wise
One” (233-74).</p>
                <p>§Hogg, James. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Recreation of Gnostic Myth:</hi> Resolving
the Apparent Incongruities (Lewiston/Queenston/Lampeter [Wales]: The Edwin Mellen Press, 1995) 155 pp.; ISBN:
0-7734-4188-3.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 (1998): 400
(“a book about which it is difficult to be positive,” “all fairly ramshackle”).</p>
                <p>Howard, John Sebastian. “Romantic Dialectics and the Politics of the Subject.” 
<hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 58 (1998): 3143A. Saint Louis Ph.D., 1997.</p>
                <p>“Two types of romantic politics (of Los and Prometheus) in Blake and Shelley suggest a
subjective consciousness built on anti-dialectical concepts and movements.”</p>
                <p>Howell, Henry. “To the Editor.” <hi rend="i">Bognor Regis Post</hi>, 11 September
1937.</p>
                <p>His design for “a small thatched entrance hood” for Blake’s Felpham Cottage has been
rejected by the local Council.</p>
                <p>*Hults, Linda C. “England: Barry, Stubbs, and Blake.” Pp. 358-79. <hi rend="i">The
Print in the Western World:</hi> An Introductory History. (Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1996).</p>
                <p>“Both as a poet and as a printmaker, Blake was a curious and grand anomaly” (375).</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 58 No. 3-4 (1996)</p>
                <p>2 Viscomi, Joseph, “The Evolution of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell.</hi>” Pp. 281-344. (This is the first of a three-part essay; the second is “The Lessons of
Swedenborg; or, The Origin of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>” Pp.
173-212 of <hi rend="i">Lessons of Romanticism:</hi> A Critical Companion. Ed. Thomas Pfau and Robert F.
Gleckner [1998], and the third is “The Caves of Heaven and Hell: Swedenborg and Printmaking in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>” to be published in <hi rend="i">Blake in the Nineties</hi>, ed. David Worrall and
Steve Clark [1998].)</p>
                <p>Jesse, Jennifer. “The Binding of Urizen: The Role of Reason in William Blake’s
Religious Thought.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 58 (1998): 2668A. Chicago Ph.D., 1997. 288 pp.</p>
                <p>The thesis gives “a wide-angled view of where Blake stands,” concluding that “Blake
is neither anti-rational nor antinomian in his religious thought.”</p>
                <p>§Jose, Fr. C. P. “William Blake’s Interpretation of the Bible through his Poems &amp;
Paintings.” University of Calicut [India] Ph.D. (1991).</p>
                <p>Jose, Chiramel P. “Blake Decoding <hi rend="i">The Book of Job.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 19 (1997): 1-24.</p>
                <p>“The present study confines itself to . . . a close analysis of all the . . . plates . .
. [<hi rend="i">and</hi>] of how far and exactly Blake followed the Sacred Text” (3).</p>
                <p>§Kamyishnikova, N. M. “[<hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory.</hi>]” 
<hi rend="i">Referatyvnii [Abstract] Zhournal</hi> 3 (1975): 132-36. In Russian.</p>
                <p>Perhaps an abstract of Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi> (1973) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1437&gt;.</p>
                <p>§Kaplan, Nancy. “Blake’s Problem and Ours: Some Reflections on the Image and the
Word.” <hi rend="i">Readerly Writerly Texts</hi> 3 (1996): 115-33.</p>
                <p>*Kawasaki, Noriko. <hi rend="i">Eden wa Kita ka:</hi> William Blake Ronshu: <hi rend="i">On
the Location of Eden:</hi> Studies on William Blake. (Tokyo: Kindai Bungeisha, 1996) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997): 142&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Toshihsa Kono, <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu Romanha Gakkai: 
<hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English Romanticism 22 (1998): 83-85.</p>
                <p>Kawasaki, Noriko. “Satan no Chokoku—Blake no <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> ni tsuite
([1]-9)] [Transcending Satan-Self in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Gifu Shiritsu Joshi
Tankidaigaku Kenkyu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Gifu City Women’s Junior College</hi>], No. 39
(1989), 39-46 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 532&gt;; No. 40 (1990), 49-55; No. 41 (1991), 149-55; No. 42 (1992),
27-32; No. 43 (1993); No. 44 (1994), 15-20; No. 45 (1995), 9-16; No. 46 (1996), 25-42; No. 47 (1997), 29-34.
In Japanese.</p>
                <p>No. 3 is sub-titled “pity’ to ‘shizumu Hi’ [‘pity’ and ‘the setting
Sun’],” and No. 9 is sub-titled “Milton’s Incarnation Descending to the Mundane World”; from No. 44
(1994), both journal and essay titles appear also in translation.</p>
                <pb id="p32-138" n="138"/>
                <p>*Kelly, Therese M. “Romantic Ambivalences.” Chapter 5 (93-134) of her 
<hi rend="i">Reinventing Allegory.</hi> (Cambridge: University Press, 1997) Cambridge Studies in Romanticism,
22.</p>
                <p>Especially about the Gray designs (96-107).</p>
                <p>§Khang, Kyeong-huan. “Time and Eternity in Milton.” <hi rend="i">Milton Studies</hi> 7
(1997 [Korea]): 25-46.</p>
                <p>Apparently about Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi></p>
                <p>§Kim, Hee-sun. “The Paradoxical Task of Blake/Los in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>:
System-Building and System-Breaking.” <hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and Literature</hi> 42 (1996
[Korea]): 761-76.</p>
                <p>§Kim, Okyub. “Blake’s Art.” <hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and
Literature</hi>, 43 (1997 [Korea]): 27-49.</p>
                <p>Especially about the treatment of Los in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
                <p>Kobayashi, Keiko. “Oe Kenzaburo to Blake: Blake and Oe Kenzaburo (1[-3]).” 
<hi rend="i">Ritsumeikan Bungaku: Journal of cultural Science, Ritsumeikan University</hi> 506 (1988) 483-95; 517
(1990): 39-56 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 539&gt;; <hi rend="i">Ritsumeikan Bungaku: Miscellaneous Essays in
Commemoration of the 70th Anniversary of the Faculty of Letters of Ritsumeikan University</hi> 551 (1997):
381-402. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>In the English translation, the novelist’s name is spelled “Ohe” in parts 1-2 and
“Oe” in part 3.</p>
                <p>*Kobayashi, Keiko. “William Blake no Romanshugi [William Blake’s Romanticism].”
Chapter 8 (225-57) of <hi rend="i">Romanshugi no Hikaku Kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Comparative Studies of
Romanticism</hi>]. Ed. Nagao Nishikawa, Hideharu Matsumiya, and Kiyoshi Suekawa. (Tokyo: Yuhikaku, 1989) In
Japanese.</p>
                <p>Kuwayama, Takako. “Blake no Shinwa ni okeru Eien to Ryushutsu: The Concept of Eternity
and Emanations in Blake’s Prophetic Writings.” <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu Romanha
Gakkai: <hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English Romanticism, 22 (1998):
11-19. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>§Langford, Ryan Dale. “William Blake’s Minor Literature.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 58
(1998). Georgia Ph.D.</p>
                <p>Lansverk, Marvin, <hi rend="i">The Wisdom of Many, The Vision of One</hi> (1994) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31 (1998): 84-88 (“Students and lovers of Blake
can be grateful to Marvin Lansverk for this awakening call to the rich fields of the poet’s sport with
Wisdom and performative language” [88].)</p>
                <p>*Larson, Turid. “En himmelsk dikter pao norsk: Geir Utaugs nærkamp med William Blake.”
<hi rend="i">Arbeiderbladet</hi>, 10 April 1997, 24.</p>
                <p>About Uthaug’s edition of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
                <p>Lincoln, Andrew. <hi rend="i">Spiritual History:</hi> A Reading of William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 (1998): 399
(“a fine book,” “sure footed”).</p>
                <p>*Linnell, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.:</hi> The Life of John Linnell
(1994) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>2 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 (1997): 392
(“Fascinating” but “severely compromised by its lack of anything approaching a modern scholarly
apparatus”).</p>
                <p>*Lucas, John, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> (London &amp; N.Y.: Longman, 1998)
Longman Critical Readers 2101, Critical Readers Series. 8o, ix, 210 pp.; ISBN: 0-582-23711-4 and 0-582-23710-6
(paperback).</p>
                <p>The collection consists of
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1 John Lucas. “Introduction.” Pp. 1-26. (A survey of trends in Blake criticism.)</p></item>
	<item><p>2 E. P. Thomson. “‘The Divine Image.’” Pp. 27-42. (Reprinted from his <hi rend="i">Witness
Against the Beast</hi> [1993].)</p></item>
	<item><p>3 John [sic] Mee. “Dangerous Enthusiasm.” Pp. 43-49. (Reprinted from Jon Mee, 
<hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm</hi> [1992] 3-11.)</p></item>
	<item><p>4 *David Erdman. “Infinite London.” Pp. 51-57. (Reprinted from his <hi rend="i">Blake, Prophet
Against Empire</hi> [third edition] [1977].)</p></item>
	<item><p>5 Stewart Crehan. “Producers and Devourers.” Pp. 60-79. (Reprinted from his <hi rend="i">Blake
in Context</hi> [1984].)</p></item>
	<item><p>6 Susan Matthews. “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and Nationalism.” Pp. 81-100. (Reprinted from 
<hi rend="i">Beyond Romanticism</hi>, ed. Stephen Copley and John Whale [1992]&gt;.)</p></item>
	<item><p>7 John Barrell. “‘Original’, ‘Character’ and ‘Individual.’” Pp. 101-16. (Reprinted
from his <hi rend="i">The Political Theory of Painting From Reynolds To Hazlitt</hi> [1986].)</p></item>
	<item><p>8 *Kathleen Raine. “A New Mode of Printing.” Pp. 117-29. (Reprinted from her 
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> [1971].)</p></item>
	<item><p>9 Brenda S. Webster. “Blake, Women, and Sexuality.” Pp. 130-47. (Reprinted from 
<hi rend="i">Critical Paths</hi>, ed. Dan Miller, Mark Bracher, and Donald Ault [1987].)</p></item>
	<item><p>10 Gerda S. Norvig. “Female Subjectivity and the Desire of Reading In(to) Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Book of Thel.</hi>” Pp. 148-66. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 34
[1995].)</p></item>
	<item><p>11 Michael Simpson. “Who Didn’t Kill Blake’s Fly: Moral Law and the Rule of Grammar in
‘Songs of Experience.’” Pp. 167-88. (A “reader-response” examination of grammatical ambiguities in
“The Fly” suggests the possibility that the fly does not die; the essay is reprinted from 
<hi rend="i">Style</hi> 30 [1996].)</p></item>
	<item><p>12 Matt Simpson. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and [of] Experience.</hi>” Pp.
189-200. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">Critical Survey</hi> 4 [1992].)</p></item>
</list></p>
                <p>MacLean, Robert. “The Influence of Chaucer’s Dream-Vision Poetry upon William Blake:
The Dream as Poem.”
<pb id="p32-139" n="139"/>
	<hi rend="i">Ritsumeikan Bungaku: Miscellaneous Essays in Commemoration of the 70th Anniversary of the
Faculty of Letters of Ritsumeikan University</hi> 551 (1997): 100-31.</p>
                <p>MacNish, Robert. <hi rend="i">The Philosophy of Sleep.</hi> (N.Y., 1834). Pp. 227-28. B.
Second Edition. (Glasgow: W.R. M’Phun, 1834) Pp. 256-57. C. §(1836) D. (Glasgow &amp; London, 1838) Pp.
258-60. E. (Glasgow, London, &amp; Edinburgh, 1845) Pp. 296-98. F. (Glasgow &amp; London, 1859) Pp. 152-53.
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2174, not recording the second edition of 1834&gt;.</p>
                <p>*Makdisi, Saree. “William Blake and the Universal Empire.” Chapter 7 (154-72) of her
<hi rend="i">Romantic Imperialism</hi>: Universal Empire and the Culture of Modernity. (Cambridge: University
Press, 1998) Cambridge Studies in Romanticism, 27.</p>
                <p>For Blake, “the ‘Universal Empire’ had to be understood on a planetary scale”
(172).</p>
                <p>§Marshak, S. “[About the Poems of William Blake].” <hi rend="i">Severnye Zapiski</hi>
10 (1915): 73. In Russian.</p>
                <p>Matthews, Susan. “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and Nationalism.” Chapter 5 (79-100) of
<hi rend="i">Beyond Romanticism</hi>: New approaches to texts and contexts 1780-1832, ed. Stephen Copley and
John Whale [1992] &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;. B. Reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed.
John Lucas (1998) 81-100.</p>
                <p>Mee, Jon. <hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm</hi> (1992) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
571&gt;.</p>
                <p>“Dangerous Enthusiasm” (1-11) is reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John
Lucas (1998) 43-49.</p>
                <p>*Mee, Jon. “The ‘insidious poison of secret Influence’: A New Historical Context for
Blake’s ‘The Sick Rose.’” <hi rend="i">Studies in the Eighteenth Century 10 22</hi> (1998):
111-22.</p>
                <p>Blake’s poem may be addressed to George Rose, a secretary of the Treasury, who was
successfully sued in 1791 for not paying a bill for, inter alia, “bludgeon men” at the 1788 Westminster
election.</p>
                <p>§Meller, Horst. “The Parricidal Imagination: Schiller, Blake, Fuseli and the Romantic
Revolt against the Father.” Pp. 76-94 of <hi rend="i">The Romantic Imagination</hi>: Literature and Art in
England and Germany. Ed. Frederick Burwick and Jurgen Klein. (Amsterdam: Rodolpi, 1996).</p>
                <p>Meyers, Victoria. “The Dialogue as Interpretive Focus in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 56 (1977): 221-39.</p>
                <p>Miller, Dan, Mark Bracher, and Donald Ault, ed. <hi rend="i">Critical Paths</hi> (1987)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 573-74&gt;.</p>
                <p>9 Brenda S. Webster. “Blake, Women, and Sexuality.” Pp. 204-24, 352-53. (Reprinted in
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John Lucas [1998], 130-47.)</p>
                <p>*Mills, Vanessa. “Bygone Bognor: William Blake’s idyllic visit to Felpham, ended in
trial for sedition: Famous poet escaped prison.” <hi rend="i">Bognor Regis Observer</hi>, 1 September 1994,
13.</p>
                <p>Miyamachi, Seiichi. “Blake Kenkyu no Aratana Shiza — Dotoku Haiki Ronsha to Rantazu: A
New Perspective on Blake Studies: Antinomians and Ranters.” <hi rend="i">Sapporo Gakuin Daigaku Jinbungakkai
Kiyo: Journal of the Society of Humanities, the Society of Humanities, Sapporo Gakuin University</hi> 62
(1998): 237-47. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>*Moskal, Jeanne. <hi rend="i">Blake, Ethics, and Forgiveness</hi> (1994) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BIQ</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>16 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 (1997):
394 (“a brave and important study”).</p>
                <p>§Nekrasova, E. “[William Blake].” <hi rend="i">Iskusstvo</hi> 8 (1957): 58-59 &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> A2289&gt;. B. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Sovremennaya Kultura</hi> (28 November 1957).
In Russian.</p>
                <p>Nemerov, Howard. “Two Ways of the Imagination: Blake &amp; Wordsworth.” 
<hi rend="i">Carlton Miscellany</hi> 5 (1964): 189-41. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2286&gt; B. §<hi
rend="i">Graduate Journal</hi> (Spring 1967) C. Pp. 103-23 of his <hi rend="i">Reflexions on Poetry &amp;
Poetics.</hi> (New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press, 1972) D. §Pp. 140-60 of his <hi rend="i">New and
Selected Essays.</hi> (Carbondale: Southern Illinois Press, 1985) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Norvig, Gerda S. “Female Subjectivity and the Desire of Reading In(to) Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Book of Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 34 (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
1996&gt;. B. Reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John Lucas (1998) 148-66.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 (1998):
400-01 (“challenging”; “Norvig’s approach is a strong one”).</p>
                <p>*Nuttall, A. D. <hi rend="i">The Alternative Trinity</hi>: Gnostic Heresy in Marlowe,
Milton, and Blake. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1998) xiii, 282 pp., ISBN: 0-19-818462-X.</p>
                <p>The Blake sections consist of chapters</p>
                <p>1 “Blake: The Son Versus the Father.” Pp. 4-21. (“The tendency of my argument is to
suggest that, long before William Blake, Gnosticism implies an alternative Trinity in which the Son opposes
the Father” [15].)</p>
                <p>2 “Blake.” Pp. 192-272. (“The similarities, sometimes intricate, between his thought
and that of the Gnostics whom (dare we say it) he could not possibly have read is [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]
quite inescapable”; “The more one reads, the clearer it becomes that . . . we are dealing with a 
<hi rend="i">philosophia perennis . . .</hi>” [200, 208].)</p>
                <p>O’Flinn, Paul. “Studying a Blake Poem.” Chapter 2 (12-30) of his <hi rend="i">How to
Study Romantic Poetry.</hi> (Basingstoke &amp; London:
<pb id="p32-140" n="140"/>
Macmillan, 1988) Macmillan How to Study.</p>
                <p>On “The Clod &amp; the Pebble.”</p>
                <p>O’Keefe, Richard R. <hi rend="i">Mythic Archetypes in Ralph Waldo Emerson</hi>: A Blakean
Reading. (Kent &amp; London: Kent State University Press, 1995) 8o, viii, 228 pp; ISBN: 0-87338-518-7.</p>
                <p>“The archetypal models have been chosen from Blake precisely because there is no direct
influence in involved” (3) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)§&gt;.</p>
                <p>*Okuma, Akinobu. <hi rend="i">William Blake Kenkyu</hi>: “Yonju no Ningen” to Seiai,
Gisei, Kyusai o megutte: [<hi rend="i">Sexuality, Brotherhood, Sacrifice, and Salvation</hi>: A Study of
William Blake’s “Fourfold Man”]. (Tokyo: Sairyusha, 1997) 434 pp.; ISBN: 4-88202-445-4 C0098. In
Japanese.</p>
                <p>The book consists of:</p>
                <p>Introduction: “Blake no Shiso no Patan—‘Yonju no Ningen’ to Seiai, Gisei, Kyusai
[Patterns of Blake’s Thought—‘Fourfold Man,’ Sexuality, Brotherhood, Sacrifice, and Salvation].” Pp.
9-29.</p>
                <p>Chapter 1: “Shinwa no Katarite o megutte [On Speakers in Blake’s Myth].” Pp.
31-60.</p>
                <p>Chapter 2: “Bunkon—Blake Shinwa no Kosei Genri [Soul Divided in Four—Principle of
Composing Blake’s Myth].” Pp. 61-89.</p>
                <p>Chapter 3: “Reikon no Unmei—Blake Shinwa no Sekai to Takei [Destiny of Human Souls—A
World and System in Blake’s Myth].” Pp. 91-120.</p>
                <p>Chapter 4: “Ryosei Guyu—Seiai to Yuai [Hermaphrodite—Sexuality and Brotherhood].”
Pp. 121-73.</p>
                <p>Chapter 5: “Keimo Shiso to Blake [Blake and Enlightenment].” Pp. 175-200.</p>
                <p>Chapter 6: “Orc Densetsu to Yottsu no Zoa no Gui [The Orc Cycle and Allegory in 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>].” Pp. 201-62.</p>
                <p>Chapter 7: “Gisei o koete—Jinruigakuteki Sozoryoku to Tairitsu no Ronri [Beyond
Sacrifice—Anthropological Imagination and the Logic of Contraries].” Pp. 263-308.</p>
                <p>Chapter 8: “‘Shirei’ to Guigateki Shuho [‘The Poetic Genius’ and Allegorical
Method].” Pp. 309-71.</p>
                <p>Chapter 9: “Kyusai—Blake no Jiku [Salvation—Blake’s Time and Space].” Pp.
373-408.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>1 Mitsuru Watanabe, <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>, Igirisu Romanha Gakkai: 
<hi rend="i">Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, Japan Association of English Romanticism, 22 (1998): 100-03.</p>
                <p>2 Masashi Suzuki, <hi rend="i">Eibungaku Kenkyu</hi>, Nihon Eibungakkai: 
<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi>, the English Literary Society of Japan 75 (1998): 94-98.</p>
                <p>§Olson, D. W., and M. S. Olson. “William Blake and August’s Fiery Meteors.” 
<hi rend="i">Sky and Telescope</hi> 78 (1989): 192-99.</p>
                <p>It is presumably related to Donald W. Olson and Marilynn S. Olson, “William Blake and
August’s Fiery Meteors,” <hi rend="i">Astronomical Computing</hi> (1989): 192-94 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
593-94&gt;.</p>
                <p>*Olson, Roberta J., and Jay M. Pasachoff. “The Comets and Meteors of Blake and His Circle
and the Great Comet of 1811.” Pp. 109-30 of their <hi rend="i">Fire in the Sky</hi>: Comets and Meteors, the
Decisive Centuries, in British Art and Science. Epilogue by Colin Pillinger. (Cambridge: Cambridge University
Press, 1998).</p>
                <p>Deals especially with Linnell’s meticulous drawings of the 1811 comet.</p>
                <p>*Olson, Roberta J., and Jay M. Pasachoff. “The Comets and Meteors of William Blake.”
Pp. 80-95 of their <hi rend="i">Fire in the Sky</hi>: Comets and Meteors, the Decisive Centuries, in British
Art and Science. Epilogue by Colin Pillinger. (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998).</p>
                <p>Note also “Telescopes and Blake’s and Sandby’s Contemporaries: William and Caroline
Herschel” (96-101) and “The Comets and Meteors of Later Visionaries” Samuel Palmer, Francis Danby, and
John Martin (163-66).</p>
                <p>Ooka, Shohei. “Blake o yomu Tominaga Taro [Taro Tominaga Who Reads Blake].” 
<hi rend="i">Bungei [Literature]</hi> 19 (1980): 344-48 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 594&gt;. B. Reprinted on 361-67
of Vol. 17 of his <hi rend="i">Ooka Shohei Zenshu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Complete Writings of Shohei Ooka</hi>].
(Tokyo: Chikuma Shobo, 1995) In Japanese.</p>
                <p>Otto, Peter. <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision and Visionary Deconstruction</hi> (1991)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 596&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>3 Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Literature &amp; Theology</hi> 8 (1993): 408-09 (with De
Luca, <hi rend="i">Words of Eternity</hi> [1991]): Otto “brings a new sophistication” to the study of
Blake, but readers will find “that it places them in the grip of a system they will be glad to
deconstruct” (408). (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)§&gt;</p>
                <p>*Outram, Richard. <hi rend="i">Notes on William Blake’s “The Tyger:”</hi> A Paper
Read . . . at The Arts and Letters Club of Toronto 4 February 1997. ([Toronto:] Printed at the Gauntlet Press,
December 1997) 4o, iv, 27 pp.; no ISBN.</p>
                <p>“In the hope of sharing an enthusiasm and perhaps starting a few hares,” Outram offers
“a number of what might be termed ‘the field-notes of a poem watcher,’ from childhood to the present”
(1), including wonderfully original speculations on the influence of Montaigne, heraldry, and bestiaries on
“The Tyger.”</p>
                <p>Paley, Morton D. “Apocalypse and Millennium.” Chapter 47 (470-85) of <hi rend="i">A
Companion to Romanticism.</hi> Ed. Duncan Wu. (Oxford: Blackwell, 1998) Esp. 470-75.</p>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake and Anti-Newtonian Thought: The Problem with Prescriptive
Though.” <hi rend="i">Beyond the Two Cultures</hi>, ed. Joseph W. Slade and Judith Yaross Lee (1990) 141-60
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 602&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in his <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World</hi> (1998) 38-57,
200-02.</p>
                <pb id="p32-141" n="141"/>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake and Newton: Argument as Art, Argument as Science.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi> 10 (1981): 205-26 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 602&gt;.)</p>
                <p>Reprinted in his <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World</hi> (1998) 19-37,
197-200.</p>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake and the Ideology of the Natural.” 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi>, N.S. 18 (1994): 91-119 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in his <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World</hi> (1998) 139-68,
221-28.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 [1997]: 393
(“repays careful reading”).</p>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake, Freemasonry, and the Builder’s Task.” 
<hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi> 17 (1984): 35-57 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 602&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in his <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World</hi> (1998) 58-84,
202-04.</p>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake on Charters, Weights, and Measures as Forms of Social
Control.” <hi rend="i">Studies in the Literary Imagination</hi> 22 (1989): 37-59 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
602&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in his <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World</hi> (1998) 105-25,
212-16.</p>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake, Priestley, and the ‘Gnostic Moment.’” 
<hi rend="i">Literature and Science: Theory and Practice</hi>, ed. Stuart Peterfreund (1990) 139-66 &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> 603&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in his <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World</hi> (1998) 85-04,
204-12.</p>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “The Din of the City in Blake’s Prophetic Books.” 
<hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 64 (1997): 99-130 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in his <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World</hi> (1998) 169-91,
228-40.</p>
                <p>Peterfreund, Stuart. “Power Tropes: ‘The Tyger’ as Enacted Critique of Newtonian
Metonymic Logic and Natural Theology.” <hi rend="i">New Orleans Review</hi> 28 (1991): 27-35 &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in his <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World</hi> (1998) 126-38,
216-21.</p>
                <p>*Peterfreund, Stuart. <hi rend="i">William Blake in a Newtonian World:</hi> Essays on
Literature As Art and Science. (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1998) Oklahoma Project for Discourse and
Theory, Volume 2. 8o, xv, 255 pp., ISBN: 0-8061-3042-3.</p>
                <p>A collection of essays consisting of
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1 “Preface.” Pp. xi-xv. (Summaries of what follows.)</p></item>
	<item><p>2 “Introduction: Blake and the Case for Situated Knowledge.” Pp. 3-18, 193-97.</p></item>
	<item><p>3 Chapter 1: “Blake and Newton: Argument as Art, Argument as Science.” Pp. 19-37, 197-200.
(Reprinted from <hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi> 10 [1981]: 205-26.)</p></item>
	<item><p>4 Chapter 2: “Blake and Anti-Newtonian Thought: The Problem with Prescriptive Thought.” Pp.
38-57, 200-02. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">Beyond the Two Cultures</hi>, ed. Joseph W. Slade and Judith
Yaross Lee [1990], 141-60.)</p></item>
	<item><p>5 *Chapter 3: “Blake, Freemasonry, and the Builder’s Task.” Pp. 58-84, 202-04. (Reprinted from
<hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi> 17 [1984]: 35-57.)</p></item>
	<item><p>6 Chapter 4: “Blake, Priestley, and the ‘Gnostic Moment.’” Pp. 85-104, 204-12. (Reprinted
from <hi rend="i">Literature and Science: Theory and Practice</hi>, ed. Stuart Peterfreund [1990],
139-66.)</p></item>
	<item><p>7 Chapter 5: “Blake on Charters, Weights, and Measures as Forms of Social Control.” Pp. 105-25,
212-16. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">Studies in the Literary Imagination</hi> 22 [1989]: 37-59.)</p></item>
	<item><p>8 Chapter 6: “Power Tropes: ‘The Tyger’ as Enacted Critique of Newtonian Metonymic Logic and
Natural Theology.” Pp. 126-38, 216-21. (Reprinted from <hi rend="i">New Orleans Review</hi> 18 [1991]:
27-35.)</p></item>
	<item><p>9 Chapter 7: “Blake and the Ideology of the Natural.” Pp. 139-68, 221-28. (Reprinted from 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi> N.S. 18 [1994]: 91-119.)</p></item>
	<item><p>10 Chapter 8: “The Din of the City in Blake’s Prophetic Books.” Pp. 169-91, 228-40. (Reprinted
from <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 64 [1997]: 99-130.)</p></item>
</list></p>
                <p>*Pfau, Thomas. “Introduction. Reading beyond Redemption: Historicism, Irony, and the
Lessons of Romanticism.” Pp. 1-37 of <hi rend="i">Lessons of Romanticism:</hi> A Critical Companion. Ed.
Thomas Pfau and Robert F. Gleckner. (Durham &amp; London: Duke University Press, 1998).</p>
                <p>He is concerned (11-18) with “the ambiguous temporal logic prevailing in Blake’s early
prophecies” (11).</p>
                <p>*Phillips, Michael. “Blake and the Terror 1792-93.” <hi rend="i">Library</hi> 6 S, 16
(1994): 263-97 &lt;<hi rend="i">BIQ</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>2 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 (1997):
395-96 (“first-rate historical research,” “One of the year’s best excursions into contextual
recovery”).</p>
                <p>*Pieiller, Evelyne. “William Blake: Satan, prince du monde.” <hi rend="i">magazine
littéraire</hi> 356 (1997): 50-51.</p>
                <p>A general account of Blake.</p>
                <p>*Pieper, Eleanore Frauke. <hi rend="i">“Imitation Is Criticism”:</hi> Dante Gabriel
Rossetti und William Blake. (Frankfurt am Main, Berlin, Bern, N.Y., Paris, Wien: Peter Lang, 1997)
Europäische Hochschulshriften: Publications Universitaires Européennes: European University Studies Reihe
XIV: Angelsächischer Sprache und Literature: Langue et littérature anglo-saxonnes: Anglo-Saxon Language and
Literature Vol. 330. 8o, 428 pp., ISBN: 3-631-31899-5. In German.</p>
                <pb id="p32-142" n="142"/>
                <p>According to the English “Summary” (421-28), Rossetti’s appropriation of the
Victorians’ misunderstanding of Blake was used “as a powerful symbol of the Victorian artist’s own
feelings of alienation” (428).</p>
                <p>Pierce, John B. “Blake’s Writing of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>: A Study of Textual Development” (Toronto Ph.D., 1986) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #605&gt;.</p>
                <p>The dissertation matured as his <hi rend="i">Flexible Design</hi> 1998).</p>
                <p>Pierce, John B. “The Changing Mythic Structure of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Study of the Manuscript, Pages 43-84,” <hi rend="i">PQ</hi> 68 (1989): 485-50
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #605&gt;.</p>
                <p>The essay is reprinted in chapter 4 of his <hi rend="i">Flexible Design</hi> (1998).</p>
                <p>*Pierce, John B. <hi rend="i">Flexible Design:</hi> Revisionary Poetics in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> (Montreal, Kingston, London, Buffalo: McGill-Queen’s
University Press, 1998) 8o, xxviii, 206 pp., 9 plates; ISBN: 0-7735-1682-4.</p>
                <p>“In <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, Blake’s shifting of narrative strategies gives the poem a
flexible design, one whose outline . . . gains its flexibility through conscious adaptations of sequential
disruptions as a fundamental element in narrative experiment. . . . the poem is revised to enact its own
meaning through emergent forms” (xxii, xxvi.)</p>
                <p>Appendix A: “The Copperplate Text of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>” (151-65, 188-91) is a
fresh transcription of pp. 7-42. Chapter 4 (“Completing <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>”) is reprinted
from “The Changing Mythic Structure of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>:
A Study of the Manuscript, Pages 43-84,” <hi rend="i">PQ</hi> 68 (1989): 485-508, and part of chapter 3
(“Recasting the Copperplate”) appeared as “The Shifting Characterization of Tharmas and Enion in Pages
3-7 of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas,” Blake</hi> 22 (1988-89): 93-102. The
book plainly grew out of his dissertation on “Blake’s Writing of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Study of Textual Development” (Toronto, 1986).</p>
                <p>*Piper, David. “Blake.” Pp. 123-26 of his <hi rend="i">Painting in England
1500-1870</hi> (London: Privately Published by the Book Society, 1960). B. “Blake.” Pp. 123-29 of his 
<hi rend="i">Painting in England 1550-1800:</hi> An Introduction. (Cambridge, 1965) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2409, not reporting the 1960 edition&gt;.</p>
                <p>*Piquet, François. <hi rend="i">Blake et le Sacré.</hi> (Lyon: Didier Erudition, 1996)
Etudes Anglaises 98. 8o, 452 pp., 23 plates; ISBN: 2-86460-270-9 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)§&gt;. In
French.</p>
                <p>“Ce travail s’est donné pour objectif de dégager le mythe personnel de Blake à
partir de la problématique du sacré” (417).</p>
                <p>§Porée, Marc. “‘Ruinous Fragments of Life’, ou le livre d’Urizen A á Z (ou
presque).” <hi rend="i">QUERTY</hi> 6 (1996): 97-106. In French.</p>
                <p>Punter, David. “Legends of the Animated Body: Blake’s Albion and the Body and Soul of
the Nation.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism</hi> 1 (1995): 161-76. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 (1998): 401
(“a rich and widely ranging argument,” “bold and original”).</p>
                <p>*Punter, David. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience Notes.</hi> (Longman:
York Pres, 1998) York Notes. 8o, 96 pp. (84-94 bear merely the word “Notes”); ISBN: 0-582-32932-92.</p>
                <p>“Introduction: How to Study a Poem” (7-9); poem-by-poem commentary (10-45); “Critical
Approaches” (50-64); “Textual Analysis” of “The Chimney Sweeper” (from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>),
“The Tyger,” and “London” (50-84), “Background” (65-70), and “Critical History” (71-83).</p>
                <p>Purslove, Glyn. “Alexander Gilchrist (25 April 1828-30 November 1861).” Pp. 108-16 of
<hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi> Volume One Hundred Forty-Four: Nineteenth-Century British
Literary Biographers. Ed. Steven Serafin. (Detroit, Washington, London: Gale Reearch, 1994).</p>
                <p>Primarily an appreciation and criticism of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William
Blake, “Pictor Ignotus”</hi> (1863).</p>
                <p>Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (1971) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2499&gt;.</p>
                <p>“A New Mode of Printing” is reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John
Lucas (1998) 117-29.</p>
                <p>*Reinhart, Charles. “William Blake (28 November 1757-12 August 1827).” Pp. 16-58, with
51 plates, in <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi> Volume Ninety-Three: British Romantic Poets,
1789-1832 first series. Ed. John R. Greenfield. (Detroit, N.Y., London: Gale Research, 1990).</p>
                <p>The work was mistakenly listed in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995) under “Reinart.” For
other Blake biographies in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi>, see Alan Richardson
(British Children’s Writers, 1800-1880) and Ruth Robbins (The British Literary Book Trade, 1700-1820).</p>
                <p>Richardson, Alan. “Blake, Children’s Literature, and Colonialism.” Part 4 of chapter
3 (“Children’s literature and the work of culture,” 109-66, 298-300) in his <hi rend="i">Literature,
Education, and Romanticism:</hi> Reading as Social Practice, 1780-1832. (Cambridge: University Press, 1994)
Cambridge Studies in Romanticism 8.</p>
                <p>In “The Little Black Boy,” the child tries to “challenge a crippling ideology through
creative subversion . . . a rare lesson in radical dissent” (166).</p>
                <p>*Richardson, Alan. “William Blake (28 November 1757-12 August 1827).” Pp. 21-29 of 
<hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi> Volume One Hundred and Sixty-Three: British Children’s
Writers, 1800-1880. Ed. Meena Khorana. (Detroit, Washington, London: Gale Research, 1996).</p>
                <p>Especially about children’s books, of course.</p>
                <pb id="p32-143" n="143"/>
                <p>For other Blake biographies in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi>, see
Charles Reinhart (British Romantic Poets, 1789-1832 first series) and Ruth Robbins (The British Literary Book
Trade, 1700-1820).</p>
                <p>Richardson, Alan. “Wordsworth, Blake, and Catechistic Method,” Part [2] (64-77, 286) of
chapter 2 (“School time,” 44-108) in his <hi rend="i">Literature, Education, and Romanticism:</hi> Reading
as Social Practice, 1780-1832. (Cambridge: University Press, 1994) Cambridge Studies in Romanticism 8.</p>
                <p>In “The Lamb,” the child’s “answer to his own question” would have “shock[<hi
rend="i">ed</hi>] most eighteenth century parents” (74, 76).</p>
                <p>Richey, William. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Altering Aesthetic</hi> (1996) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> 1998&gt;.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>2 Ahmad, Siraj, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 28 (1997): 211-12 (with Edward J.
Ahearn, <hi rend="i">Visionary Fictions:</hi> Apocalyptic Writing from Blake to the Modern Age [1996]).</p>
                <p>3 §<hi rend="i">Reference and Research Book News</hi> 12 (1997): 131+.</p>
                <p>*Robbins, Ruth. “William Blake ([<hi rend="i">worked in</hi>] London: 1784-1827.” Pp.
26-32 of <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi> Volume One Hundred Fifty-Four: The British
Literary Book Trade, 1700-1820. Ed. James K. Bracken and Joel Silver. (Detroit, Washington, London: Gale
Research, 1995)</p>
                <p>An account of Blake’s work in the book trade.</p>
                <p>For other Blake biographies in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi>, see
Charles Reinhart (British Romantic Poets, 1789-1832 first series) and Alan Richardson (British Children’s
Writers, 1800-1880).</p>
                <p>§*Roob, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Das hermetische Museum:</hi> Alchemie und Mystik.
                  (Cologne: Benedikt <corr type="emend">Taschen</corr> Verlag, 1996) ISBN: 3-8228-8803-6. Pp. 69, 119, 161, 163-64, 174, 182, 192, 201-02,
213-14, 229-31, 259, 296-97, 429, 433, 437, 461, 482, 491, 523, 531, 553, 577, 626, 632-33, 649, 652, 663,
692-93, 696-97 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;B. *<hi rend="i">The Hermetic Museum:</hi> Alchemy &amp;
Mysticism. [Tr. Shaun Whiteside.] (Köln, Lisboa, London, N.Y., Paris, Tokyo: Taschen, 1997) Pp. 8, 21-23, 55,
67, *69, 99, 118-*19, 126, *163-*64, 166, *174, *182, *192, *201-*02, *213, *229-*31, 253, *296-*97, 338, 341,
417, *429, *433, *437, 460-*61, *482-83, *489, *491, *523, 530-*31, 550-*53, 570, *577, 616, *626, *632-34,
646, *649, *652-53, *662, *692-*93, 696-*97.</p>
                <p>The volume consists of annotated illustrations from alchemical texts, many from 
<hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen.</hi> “Blake developed the character of Los from various Paracelsian
concepts” (483).</p>
                <p>Rothery, Agnes. “Mad Poets in the Spring.” <hi rend="i">Virginia Quarterly Review</hi>
3 (1927): 250-63. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2583&gt; <corr type="emend">B. §“Four</corr> Poets and Four
Gardens.” Pp. 151-66 of her <hi rend="i">Joyful Gardener.</hi> (Dodd, 1949) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1997)&gt; C. New and Revised Edition. (London, N.Y., Melbourne, Sydney, Cape Town: Andrew Melrose Ltd, 1951)
157-74.</p>
                <p>Blake’s plants and animals are visionary (1951, 164-68).</p>
                <p>Rowland, William G. “Religious Vocation and Blake’s Obscurity.” Chapter 3 (63-88,
199-201) of his <hi rend="i">Literature and the Marketplace:</hi> Romantic Writers and their Audiences in
Great Britain and the United States. (Lincoln &amp; London: University of Nebraska Press, 1996).</p>
                <p>“Blake in some ways courted oblivion” (75).</p>
                <p>*Ryan, Robert. “Blake’s Orthodoxy.” Chapter 2 (43-79, 243-48) of his <hi rend="i">The
Romantic Reformation:</hi> Religious politics in English Literature, 1789-1824. (Cambridge: University Press,
1997).</p>
                <p>He seems to think that Blake was orthodox according to the religious standards of his
time.</p>
                <p>§Samorodov, B. “[The 225th Anniversary of Blake’s Birthday].” <hi rend="i">Pamyatnie
Khizhnie Dati [Commemoration of Literary Dates], 1982</hi> (Moscow, 1982): 137-40. In Russian.</p>
                <p>§Samorodov, B. “[William Blake, Poet and Printer: to the 225th Anniversary of his
Birthday].” [<hi rend="i">Polygraphia</hi>] 7 (Moscow, 1982): 36-37. In Russian.</p>
                <p>§*Sanesi, Roberto. <hi rend="i">Blake &amp; Newton:</hi> appunti per una lezione. (Castel
Maggiore: Book Editori, 1993) Collezione di Poetica, Critica, Estetica: Minute. 8o, 55 pp. In Italian.</p>
                <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith. “William Blake and the Promiscuous Baboons: A Cagliostroan
Séance Gone Awry.” <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1995): 185-200
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>I David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 76 for 1995 (1998):
398-99 (“richly researched” and “extremely important”).</p>
                <p>§Sedyich, Elina Vladimirovna. “[Contact in Poetry as a Mode of Expression: On the
Example of the Blake’s Poetic Cycles ‘Songs of Innocence’ and ‘Songs of Experience’].” St.
Petersburg Ph.D., 1997, 206 pages. In Russian.</p>
                <p>Senaha, Eijun. “Autoeroticism and Blake: O Rose Art Thou Sick!?” Chapter 1 (11-28) of
<hi rend="i">Sex, Drugs, and Madness in Poetry from William Blake to Christina Rossetti:</hi> Women’s Pain,
Women’s Pleasure (1996) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998&gt;. B. <hi rend="i">Hokkaido Daigaku Bungakubu
Kiyo: The Annual Report of Cultural Science, The Faculty of Letters of Hokkaido University</hi> 46-1 (1997):
85-109.</p>
                <p>§Shilinya, Brigita Karlovna. [<hi rend="i">William Blake and English Pre-Romanticism:</hi>
Handbook for Optional Courses.] (Riga: P. Stuhkas Latvijas Valsts Univ. [Latvian State University],
<pb id="p32-144" n="144"/>
1982) 56 pp. In Latvian and English. (The author’s name is Jilina in Latvian.)</p>
                <p>Simpson, Matt. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and [of] Experience.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Critical Survey</hi> 4 (1992): 20-27 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;. B.</p>
                <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John Lucas (1998) 189-200.</p>
                <p>Simpson, Michael. “Who Didn’t Kill Blake’s Fly: Moral Law and the Rule of Grammar in
‘Songs of Experience.’” <hi rend="i">Style</hi> 30 (1996): 224-46 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1998)§&gt;. B. Reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John Lucas (1998) 167-88.</p>
                <p>“Reader-response criticism” and “affective stylistics” suggest “a dual
audience” coping with “the versatile grammar of the poem and the self-monitoring reading persona” (1996,
220, 238).</p>
                <p>*Smith, Jessica Todd. “Hogarth, Blake, and <hi rend="i">The Beggars’ Opera.</hi>’”
Pp. 80-84 of “<hi rend="i">Among Whores and Thieves</hi>”: William Hogarth and <hi rend="i">The Beggars’
Opera.</hi> Ed. David Bindman and Scott Wilcox. (New Haven: Yale Center for British Art; The Lewis Walpole
Library, 1997).</p>
                <p>Accompanying an exhibition of 1 February-6 April 1997.</p>
                <p>Sontag, Frederick. <hi rend="i">Truth and Imagination:</hi> The Universes Within. (Lanham
[Maryland], N.Y., Oxford: University Presses of America, 1998) 8o, xv, 92 pp., ISBN: 0-7618-0921-X.</p>
                <p>The “PREFACE: Blake on the Origin of Creativity and Understanding” (ix-xiii) invites us
to “see if they [Blake’s key concepts] help us to reveal the Modern World’s Achilles heel” (ix-x), but
Blake serves as little more than the source of quotations.</p>
                <p>§Sorenson, Peter. “Freemasonry and ‘Greek Mysteries’ in William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Classical and Modern Literature</hi> 15 (1995): 153-75.</p>
                <p>Steinkjer, Mode. “William Blake på cd.” <hi rend="i">Arbeiderbaldet</hi>, 10 April
1997, 24. In Norwegian.</p>
                <p>About Finn Coren’s CD of Blake.</p>
                <p>Stewart, David. “The Context of Blakean Contraries in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
and Hell.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi> 21 (1994): 43-53 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1995)&gt;.</p>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 (1997): 393
(Boehme is behind Blake’s attack on Swedenborg).</p>
                <p>§Sukharev (Murishkin) S. “[Two “Tygers’, Mastery of Translation].” 
<hi rend="i">Collected Articles</hi> 2 (Moscow, 1977): 296-317. In Russian.</p>
                <p>*Summerfield, Henry. <hi rend="i">A Guide to the Books of William Blake for Innocent and
Experienced Readers</hi> with notes on interpretive criticism 1910-1984. (Gerrards Cross: Colin Smythe, 1998)
8o, 874 pp., ISBN: 0-86140-408-4.</p>
                <p>“The primary purpose of this book is to provide [<hi rend="i">guidance</hi>] for the
serious reader of poetry, for the student, and for the scholar who is not a Blake specialist” (11).</p>
                <p>Part 1, “The Books of William Blake: An Introduction” (27-320) gives “an account of
Blake’s beliefs, concepts and development and an exposition of those of his productions that can reasonably
be classified as books” (11).</p>
                <p>Part 2, “Notes on Criticism” (321-836) poem-by-poem and sometimes line-by-line, a kind
of variorum edition without the texts of the poems.</p>
                <p>Swearingen, James E. “William Blake’s Figural Politics.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 59
[1992]: 125-44 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 652&gt;. B. Reprinted in 80-94 of <hi rend="i">Blake, Politics, and
History</hi>, ed. Jackie DiSalvo, G. A. Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson (N.Y. &amp; London: Garland
Publishing, 1998).</p>
                <p>§*Tandecki, Daniela. <hi rend="i">Tigerbrand:</hi> das unbequeme Genie William Blake.
(Frankfurt am Main: O. Lembeck, 1997) 310 pp.; ISBN: 3-87476324-2. In German.</p>
                <p>§Thompson, E. P. “Anti-Hegemony: the Legacy of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">New Left
Review</hi> 201 (1993): 26-33.</p>
                <p>Thompson, E. P., <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast</hi> (1993) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <p>“‘The Divine Image’” is reprinted in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, ed. John
Lucas (1998) 27-42.</p>
                <p>Thompson, Marc Alan. “Romantic Representation and the Rhetoric of Unfinished Design.”
<hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 58 (1998): 4285A. Cincinnati Ph.D., 1997. 225 pp.</p>
                <p>Examines, inter alia, <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi></p>
                <p>Toriumi, Hisayoshi. “Hebe to Romanha no Sonen (2)—Blake no Baai [Serpent and Romantic
Concepts (2)—In the Case of Blake].” <hi rend="i">Wayo Joshi Daigaku Eibungakkaishi: Language and
Literature, Wayo Women’s University</hi>, 32 (1998): 31-46. In Japanese.</p>
                <p>*Upstone, Robert. “Fantasy and Imagination.” Pp. 152-56 of his <hi rend="i">Sketchbooks
                  of the Romantics.</hi> (<corr type="emend">Secaucus,</corr> N.J.: The Wellfleet Press, 1991). 27 Blake plates.</p>
                <p>A book about romantic artists generally, not much related to their sketchbooks.</p>
                <p>van Lieshout, Jules, <hi rend="i">Within and Without Eternity:</hi> The Dynamics of
Interaction in William Blake’s Myth and Poetry (1994) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;.</p>
                <pb id="p32-145" n="145"/>
                <p>Review</p>
                <p>1 David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 (1997):
394-95 (a “novel and refreshing way of thinking about Blake’s text”).</p>
                <p>§Vasilieva, T. N. “[Blake and English Poetry of the XVIIIth Century, Literary Process
and Creative Individuality].” <hi rend="i">Kishinev</hi> (1990) 115-25.</p>
                <p>§Verhoest, Eric, and Jean-Luc Cambier. <hi rend="i">Blake et Mortimer</hi> (1996). 120 pp.
ISBN: 2-87097-045-5l. In French.</p>
                <p>It contains “Blake et Mortimer, histoire d’un retour.”</p>
                <p>§Vesely, S. A. “The Daughters of 18th-century Science: A Rationalist and Materialist
Context for William Blake’s Female Figures.” <hi rend="i">Colby Quarterly</hi> 34 (1998): 5-24.</p>
                <p>*Vine, Stephen. “‘That Mild Beam’: Enlightenment and enslavement in William Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>” Pp. 40-63 of <hi rend="i">The Discourse of
Slavery:</hi> Aphra Behn to Toni Morrison. Ed. Carl Plasa and Betty J. Ring. (London &amp; N.Y.: Routledge,
1994).</p>
                <p>Vine “examines the critical energies in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>’ account of the body,
sexuality and slavery, and maps the struggle of the poem to expose structures of sexual and colonial
enslavement in the name of visionary enlightenment” (41).</p>
                <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (1993) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>24 Theresa M. Kelley, <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 7 (1997): 197-200 (a
“monumental study” dealing masterfully with “a daunting array of evidence” [197]).</p>
                <p>25 Paul Cantor, <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 59 (1998): 557-70 (with 
<hi rend="i">The Early Illuminated Books</hi> and <hi rend="i">MILTON A POEM and the Final Illuminated Books</hi>)
(“On the whole I am convinced by the case Viscomi makes” [559]).</p>
                <p>26 §<hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi> 105 (1997): 38+</p>
                <p>27 §<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 26 September 1997, 18.</p>
                <p>*Viscomi, Joseph. “The Lessons of Swedenborg; or, The Origin of William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>” Pp. 173-212 of <hi rend="i">Lessons of Romanticism:</hi> A
Critical Companion. Ed. Thomas Pfau and Robert F. Gleckner. (Durham &amp; London: Duke University Press,
1998).</p>
                <p>An examination of “the primary Swedenborgian texts and themes that Blake” deals with in
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> pl. 21-24, “an autonomous text preceding the composition of . . . the 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>” (174).</p>
                <p>Weaver, Susan Ann. “Dialectical Formulations and Covert Language in Coleridge, Blake, and
[Mary] Robinson.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 58 (1998): 4285A. Texas A&amp;M Ph.D., 1997. 330 pp.</p>
                <p>“William Blake also used dialectical formulations and covert language to conceal his
radical political inclinations.”</p>
                <p>*Williams, Nicholas M. <hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William
Blake.</hi> (Cambridge: University Press, 1998) Cambridge Studies in Romanticism 28. 8o, xviii, 250 pp. ISBN:
0-521-62050-3.</p>
                <p>A theory-charged “series of readings of Blake’s texts” in order “to portray a Blake
whose program for social change was always situated in an historical context” (xiv).</p>
                <p>§*Wilson, Simon. “William Blake and his Followers.” Pp. 65-73 of his <hi rend="i">Tate
Gallery:</hi> An Illustrated Companion. (London: Tate Publishing, 1990) B. §Second Edition. (1991) C.
§(1993) D. §(1994) E. §(1995) F. §(1996) G. (1997) H. Translated into Japanese (1996).</p>
                <p>Wolfreys, Julian. “Blake’s London: London’s Blake: an Introduction to the Spirit of
London or, on the way to Apocalypse.” Pp. 32-58, 213-19 of his <hi rend="i">Writing London:</hi> the trace
of the urban text from Blake to Dickens. (Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1998).</p>
                <p>About “the ways in which William Blake writes himself into his vision of London”;
“Blake <hi rend="i">is</hi> London: London <hi rend="i">is</hi> Blake” (31, 34).</p>
                <p>Wolfson, Susan J. “Blake’s Politics in Rhyme and Blank Verse.” Pp. 195-205 of
“‘Romantic Ideology’ and the Values of Aesthetic Form,” 188-218 of <hi rend="i">Aesthetics and
Ideology.</hi> Ed. George Levine. (New Brunswick, New Jersey: Rutgers University Press, 1994). B. “Sketching
Verbal Form: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi>” Pp. 27-70 of <hi rend="i">Speak Silence:</hi>
Rhetoric and Culture in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, ed. Mark L. Greenberg (Detroit: Wayne
State University Press, 1996) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)&gt;. C. Chapter 2 (32-62, 249-55) of her 
<hi rend="i">Formal Charges:</hi> The Shaping of Poetry in British Romanticism (Stanford: Stanford University
Press, 1997).</p>
                <p>B and C are said to be different versions of A.</p>
                <p>Worrall, David. <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1994 (1997):
391-96.</p>
                <p>Careful evaluations of many works on Blake.</p>
                <p>Worrall, David. <hi rend="i">Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 75 for 1995 (1998):
396-402.</p>
                <p>Admirable surveys of publications about Blake in 1995.</p>
                <p>§Yakovleva, G. V. “[Blake’s Polemics with Reynolds, Literary Traditions in Foreign
Literature of the XIX-XX Centuries].” <hi rend="i">Perm</hi>’ (1983): 11-19. In Russian.</p>
                <p>§Yakovleva, G. V. “[‘Prophecies of Innocence’ in the Context of W. Blake’s
Philosophy].” Pp. 24-25 of [<hi rend="i">First All-Union Conference of the Specialists in the Studies of
English Literature</hi>]. (Moscow, 1991) In Russian.</p>
                <pb id="p32-146" n="146"/>
                <p>Yasuda, Masayoshi. “Blake no Sozo no Kannen no Keisei—Shoki Yogensho ni okeru: The
Formation of W. Blake’[s] Idea of Creation in the Earlier Prophetic Books.” <hi rend="i">Takushima Bunri
Daigaku Kenkyu Kiyo: Research Bulletin of Takushima Bunri University</hi> 55 (1998): 1-10. In Japanese, with
an English abstract on 10.</p>
                <p>Yeats, W. B. “Academy Portraits, XXXII.—William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Academy</hi> 51
(1897): 634-35 . . . &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #3047, <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 691&gt; R. §<hi rend="i">Blake e
l’immaginazione.</hi> Tr. L. Gallesi. (1992) 8o, 70 pp., ISBN: 88-85387-683. In Italian.</p>
                <p>§Zhirmunsky, V. M. “[William Blake].” Pp. 175-87 of his [<hi rend="i">The History of
Western European Literatures</hi>]. (Leningrad, 1981) In Russian.</p>
                <p>§Zimmerman, Sarah M. “Charlotte Smith’s Lessons.” Pp. 121-28 of 
<hi rend="i">Approaches to Teaching British Women Poets of the Romantic Period.</hi> Ed. Stephen C. Berendt and
<corr type="emend">Harriet Kramer Linkin.</corr> (N.Y.: Modern Language Association, 1997).</p>
                <p>Blake and Wordsworth are compared with Charlotte Smith.</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division II<lb/>
                  Blake’s Circle</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Cumberland, George (1754-1848)</p>
              <p>Blake’s Friend, Correspondent, and Collaborator</p>
              <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr. “The Suppression of George Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Captive of the
Castle of Sennaar</hi> (1798): Liberty vs Commerce.” <hi rend="i">Yale University Library Gazette</hi> 71
(1997): 155-58.</p>
              <p>Flaxman, John (1756-1826)</p>
              <p>Sculptor, Friend of Blake</p>
              <p>§<hi rend="i">Flaxman:</hi> La difusion del models clasico Homero, Esquilo, Hesiodo, Dante.
<corr type="emend">Ex calcografía Nacional,</corr> Real Accademia de Bellas Artes de San Fernando, Madrid. ([Madrid: ? 1995]) 70 pp.,
in Spanish.</p>
              <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr. “The Unrecognized First Printing of Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi>
(1793).” <hi rend="i">A &amp; B:</hi> Analytical &amp; Enumerative Bibliography, N.S. 9 (1995 [i.e., Spring
1998]): 102-20.</p>
              <p>“The unrecognized first printing of the first edition . . . [<hi rend="i">was</hi>] printed
in Rome on Italian paper for Flaxman to send to his patrons” (117).</p>
              <p>Fuseli, John Henry (1741-1825)</p>
              <p>Artist, Friend of Blake</p>
              <p>Heinrich Sieveking. <hi rend="i">Fuseli to Menzel:</hi> Drawings and Watercolors in the Age
of Goethe from a German Private Collection. (Munich &amp; N.Y.: Prestel, 1998).</p>
              <p>It is the catalogue of an exhibition shown at the Busch-Reisinger Museum, Cambridge (4
April-7 June 1998), the Frick Collection, N.Y. (23 June-30 August 1998), and the J. Paul Getty Museum, Los
Angeles (15 September-29 November 1998). The collector is Alfred Winterstin. “Fuseli to Menzel: Aspects of
German Drawing in the Age of Goethe” is on 13-35; the Fuseli entries are #10-11.</p>
              <p>David H. Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Prints and Engraved Illustrations by and after Henry
Fuseli:</hi> A Catalogue Raisonné (1994) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;.</p>
              <p>Review</p>
              <p>1 C. S. Matheson, <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 59 (1998): 571-75 (“One is
very grateful for access to information painstakingly culled from prints housed in British, American, and
Swiss collections” [575]).</p>
              <p>Hayley, William (1754-1820)</p>
              <p>Poet, Patron, Employer of Blake</p>
              <p>Herbison, Vida. “Felpham: fit for Immortals, Vida Herbison visits the Sussex village of
Felpham, home of the late writer, poet and patron of the arts William Hayley.” <hi rend="i">Sussex
Life</hi>, September [after 1980], 36-37.</p>
              <p>Hogg, James. “William Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Marcella</hi> and Thomas Middleton and
William Rowley’s <hi rend="i">The Changeling:</hi> A Watered-Down Jacobean Masterpiece.” Pp. 319-61 of 
<hi rend="i">Jacobean Drama as Social Criticism.</hi> Ed. James Hogg. (Lewiston [N.Y.] &amp; Salburg: Edwin Mellen
Press, 1995) Salzburg University Series.</p>
              <p>*Nisse, Neville. “Felpham Provided Help, Vision and Inspiration.” <hi rend="i">‘The
Post’</hi> [Bognor Regis], 29 September 1979.</p>
              <p>Hayley’s Turret House was demolished in 1961 for a block of flats.</p>
              <p>Johnson, Joseph (1738-1809)</p>
              <p>Bookseller, Employer of Blake</p>
              <p>Carol Hall, “Joseph Johnson ([<hi rend="i">Worked in</hi>] London: 1761-1809).” Pp.
159-63 of <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi> Volume One Hundred Fifty-Four: The British
Literary Book Trade, 1700-1820. Ed. James K. Bracken and Joel Silver. (Detroit, Washington, London: Gale
Research, 1995).</p>
              <p>Palmer, Samuel (1805-81)</p>
              <p>Artist, Blake’s Disciple</p>
              <p>Brian Keble. “Samuel Palmer’s Vision of Nature.” Pp. 41-60 of his <hi rend="i">Art for
Whom and for What?</hi> (Ipswich: Golgonooza Press, 1998).</p>
              <p>Especially about six Shoreham works.</p>
              <p>Richmond, George (1809-96)</p>
              <p>Artist, Blake’s Disciple</p>
              <p>A watercolor “Recollection of William Blake” by George Richmond on wove paper watermarked
[J WH]ATMAN [TURKE]Y MILL [18]36, 10 3/4” × 7 1/4,” offered and reproduced in the Sotheby catalogue of 8
April 1998, Lot 105, is clearly a sketch from the life-mask, with eyes closed and lips sealed [see the
reproduction in Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace (1998)”].</p>
              <pb id="p32-147" n="147"/>
              <p>The Royal Academy</p>
              <p>C. S. Matheson, “The Royal Academy and the Annual Exhibition of the Viewing Public.” Pp.
280-303 of <hi rend="i">Lessons of Romanticism:</hi> A Critical Companion. Ed. Thomas Pfau and Robert F.
Gleckner. (Durham &amp; London: Duke University Press, 1998).</p>
              <p>A generously illustrated account of audiences at the Royal Academy exhibitions 1771-1808.</p>
              <p>Stothard, Thomas (1755-1834)</p>
              <p>Artist, Friend of Blake</p>
              <p>Blewitt, David, “The English Rediscovery of Defoe: Stothard,” chapter 2 (45-64) of his
<hi rend="i">The Illustration of ROBINSON CRUSOE 1719-1920.</hi> (Gerrard’s Cross: Colin Smythe, 1995) Also
196-98 listing editions of <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe</hi> with Stothard designs.</p>
              <p>Varley, John (1774-1842)</p>
              <p>Painter, Astrologer, Friend of Blake</p>
              <p>Eighteen pencil drawings including portraits (on paper watermarked 1815-1832) “collected by
E. Sterry” and mounted in a contemporary red roan oblong 4o album were offered in Ken Spelman Catalogue 38
(1998), Lot 203 (£2,200).</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Index</title>
            </head>
            <p>Abramovitch, N. Y. 129</p>
            <p>Ackroyd, Peter 129</p>
            <p>Ahmad, Siraj 143</p>
            <p>Alexander, Bryan Nemo 116</p>
            <p>Allen, Graham 130</p>
            <p>Alonso, Mariano Vazquez 123</p>
            <p>Aoyama, Keiko 90, 114, 130, 131, 132</p>
            <p>Arbuthnot, May Hill 130</p>
            <p>Ault, Donald 115, 117, 135, 139</p>
            <p>Baker, Marcia 131</p>
            <p>Barrell, John 131, 138</p>
            <p>Bataille, Georges 123</p>
            <p>Batten, Guinn 131</p>
            <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. 134</p>
            <p>Bentley, Dr. E. B. 115</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 90, 114, 128, 131, 132, 146</p>
            <p>Berendt, Stephen C. 146</p>
            <p>Bindman, David 144</p>
            <p>Blewitt, David 147</p>
            <p>Boime, Albert 133</p>
            <p>Bracher, Mark 139</p>
            <p>Bradford, Richard 133</p>
            <p>Bruder, Helen P. 132, 133</p>
            <p>Bulckaer, D. 133</p>
            <p>Bungey, Marguerite 133</p>
            <p>Cambier, Jean-Luc 145</p>
            <p>Cantor, Paul 122, 123, 145</p>
            <p>Carretta, Vincent 132</p>
            <p>Chandler, Eric V. 134</p>
            <p>Chayes, Irene 122, 136</p>
            <p>Chong, Cue-huan. 133</p>
            <p>Clark, S. H. 133</p>
            <p>Coren, Finn 122, 133</p>
            <p>Cox, Philip 133</p>
            <p>Crafton, Lisa Plummer 133</p>
            <p>Crehan, Stewart 133, 138</p>
            <p>Davis, Mike 122</p>
            <p>De Luca, Vincent 133</p>
            <p>Demidova, O. R. 134</p>
            <p>Den Otter, A. G. 134</p>
            <p>Dent, Shirley Patricia 115</p>
            <p>Dillingham, Thomas 122, 133</p>
            <p>DiSalvo, Jackie 116, 134</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker, D. W. 122</p>
            <p>Dortort, Fred 116, 117, 134</p>
            <p>Drinkwater, John 135</p>
            <p>E. P. Thomson 138</p>
            <p>Eaves, Morris 122</p>
            <p>Edgar, Brian Windsor 135</p>
            <p>Elistratova, A. 135</p>
            <p>Ellis, Edwin J. 135</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. 135, 138</p>
            <p>Esdaile, Angela 123</p>
            <p>Essex, A. J. 130</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. 115, 116, 122, 123, 128, 131, 132, 135</p>
            <p>Esterhammer, Angela 135</p>
            <p>Evans, B. Ifor 135</p>
            <p>Fabre, Silvia Diaz 135</p>
            <p>Fairbanks, A. Harris 131</p>
            <p>Feldman, Walter 122</p>
            <p>Ferber, Michael 132, 134</p>
            <p>Flory, Wendy Stallard 135</p>
            <p>Foote, G. W. 135</p>
            <p>Freak, David 128</p>
            <p>Freed, Eugenie R. 135</p>
            <p>Freeman, Kathryn S. 132, 135</p>
            <p>Fuhr, Bodil 135</p>
            <p>Fuller, David 136, 137</p>
            <p>Gardner, Stanley 117, 121, 136</p>
            <p>Garzön, Pablo 123</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander 136</p>
            <p>Glausser, Wayne 117, 136</p>
            <p>Gourlay, Alexander 115</p>
            <p>Graham, Virginia 122</p>
            <p>Greenberg, Mark L. 132, 136, 145</p>
            <p>Gridninsky 136</p>
            <p>Grimley, Terry 128</p>
            <p>Groves, David 132</p>
            <p>Hadfield, Andrew 136</p>
            <p>Hall, Carol 146</p>
            <p>Haresnape, Geoffrey 136</p>
            <p>Harriston, J. R. 136</p>
            <p>Hashi, Hidefumi 129</p>
            <p>Henry, Lauren 131</p>
            <p>Heppner, Christopher 122, 136</p>
            <p>Herbison, Vida 146</p>
            <p>Higgins, Michael 137</p>
            <p>Hilton, Nelson 132, 133, 138</p>
            <p>Hobson, Christopher Z. 116, 134</p>
            <p>Hogg, James 137, 146</p>
            <p>Howard, John Sebastian 116, 137</p>
            <p>Howell, Heather 115</p>
            <p>Howell, Henry 137</p>
            <p>Howitt, Mary 122</p>
            <pb id="p32-148" n="148"/>
            <p>Hults, Linda C 137</p>
            <p>Hutton, Joseph 134</p>
            <p>Isaac, Peter 132</p>
            <p>Jesse, Jennifer 137</p>
            <p>Jose, Chiramel P. 137</p>
            <p>Jose, Fr. C. P. 137</p>
            <p>Joyce, Sarah 132</p>
            <p>Kamyishnikova, N. M. 137</p>
            <p>Kaplan, Nancy 137</p>
            <p>Kawasaki, Noriko 137</p>
            <p>Keble, Brian 146</p>
            <p>Kelley, Teresa M. 145</p>
            <p>Kelly, Therese M. 138</p>
            <p>Khang, Kyeong-huan 138</p>
            <p>Kim, Hee-sun 138</p>
            <p>Kim, Okyub 138</p>
            <p>Kobayashi, Keiko 138</p>
            <p>Kono, Toshihsa 137</p>
            <p>Kukota, Irina 115</p>
            <p>Kunitz, Stanley 122</p>
            <p>Kuwayama, Takako 138</p>
            <p>Landers, Linda Anne 122</p>
            <p>Langford, Ryan Dale 138</p>
            <p>Lansverk, Marvin 132, 138</p>
            <p>Larson, Turid 138</p>
            <p>Levine, George 145</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew 133, 140</p>
            <p>Linkin, Harriet Kramer 134, 146</p>
            <p>Linnell, David 138</p>
            <p>Lucas, John 133, 138</p>
            <p>MacLean, Robert 138</p>
            <p>MacNish, Robert 139</p>
            <p>Makdisi, Saree 139</p>
            <p>Marsden, Christopher 115</p>
            <p>Marshak, S. 139</p>
            <p>Mason, Michael 123</p>
            <p>Matheson, C. S. 146, 147</p>
            <p>Matthews, Susan 138, 139</p>
            <p>McClenahan, Catherine C. 134</p>
            <p>Mee, Jon 117, 134, 138, 139</p>
            <p>Meller, Horst 139</p>
            <p>Mellor, Anne K. 134</p>
            <p>Meyers, Victoria 139</p>
            <p>Michael, Jennifer Davis 132, 136</p>
            <p>Miller, Dan 139</p>
            <p>Mills, Vanessa 139</p>
            <p>Miyamachi, Seiichi 139</p>
            <p>Moskal, Jeanne 139</p>
            <p>Nekrasova, E. 139</p>
            <p>Nemerov, Howard 139</p>
            <p>Nisse, Neville 146</p>
            <p>Noon, Patrick 128</p>
            <p>Norvig, Gerda S. 138, 139</p>
            <p>Nuttall, A. D. 139</p>
            <p>O’Flinn, Paul 139</p>
            <p>O’Keefe, Gavin 118</p>
            <p>O’Keefe, Richard R. 140</p>
            <p>Okuma, Akinobu 140</p>
            <p>Olson, D. W. 140</p>
            <p>Olson, M. S. 140</p>
            <p>Olson, Roberta J. 140</p>
            <p>Ooka, Shohei 140</p>
            <p>Orme, Robert 128</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter 134, 140</p>
            <p>Outram, Richard 116, 140</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. 115, 118, 132, 140</p>
            <p>Pasachoff, Jay M. 140</p>
            <p>Peterfreund, Stuart 140</p>
            <p>Pfau, Thomas 141</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael 141</p>
            <p>Pieiller, Evelyne 141</p>
            <p>Pieper, Eleanore Frauke 116, 141</p>
            <p>Pierce, John B. 117, 131, 142</p>
            <p>Piper, David 142</p>
            <p>Piquet, François 142</p>
            <p>Plowman, Max 123</p>
            <p>Porée, Marc. 142</p>
            <p>Pound, Alan 122</p>
            <p>Punter, David 142</p>
            <p>Purslove, Glyn 142</p>
            <p>Raine, Kathleen 138, 142</p>
            <p>Reinhart, Charles 142, 143</p>
            <p>Richardson, Alan 142</p>
            <p>Richey, William 134, 143</p>
            <p>Robbins, Ruth 143</p>
            <p>Roob, Alexander 143</p>
            <p>Rosso, G. A. 116, 134</p>
            <p>Rothery, Agnes 143</p>
            <p>Rowland, William G. 143</p>
            <p>Rubenstein, Anne 134</p>
            <p>Ryan, Robert M. 132, 143</p>
            <p>Samorodov, B. 143</p>
            <p>Sanesi, Roberto 122, 143</p>
            <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith 134, 143</p>
            <p>Sedaine, Armand 121</p>
            <p>Sedyich, Elina Vladimirovna 143</p>
            <p>Senaha, Eijun 143</p>
            <p>Shilinya, Brigita Karlovna 143</p>
            <p>Sieveking, Heinrich 146</p>
            <p>Simpson, David 131</p>
            <p>Simpson, Matt 138, 144</p>
            <p>Simpson, Michael 138, 144</p>
            <p>Sivright, Thomas 124</p>
            <p>Smith, Jessica Todd 144</p>
            <p>Sontag, Frederick 144</p>
            <p>Sorenson, Peter 144</p>
            <p>Spector, Sheila A. 132, 135</p>
            <p>Steinkjer, Mode 144</p>
            <p>Stewart, David 144</p>
            <p>Sturrock, June 134</p>
            <p>Suied, Alain 119</p>
            <p>Sukharev (Murishkin) S. 144</p>
            <p>Summerfield, Henry 116, 144</p>
            <p>Suzuki, Masashi 140</p>
            <p>Swearingen, James E. 134, 144</p>
            <p>Tandecki, Daniela 144</p>
            <p>Thomas, David 132</p>
            <p>Thompson, E. P. 144</p>
            <p>Thompson, Marc Alan 144</p>
            <pb id="p32-149" n="149"/>
            <p>Toriumi, Hisayoshi 144</p>
            <p>Townsend, Camilla 134</p>
            <p>Ungaretti, Giuseppe 119</p>
            <p>Upstone, Robert 144</p>
            <p>Uthaug, Geir 121</p>
            <p>Van de Weyer, Robert 123</p>
            <p>van Lieshout, Jules 144</p>
            <p>Vasilieva, T. N. 145</p>
            <p>Vaughan, Frank A. 132, 137</p>
            <p>Verhoest, Eric 145</p>
            <p>Vesely, S. A. 145</p>
            <p>Vine, Stephen 145</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph 115, 116, 122, 123, 131, 137, 145</p>
            <p>Watanabe, Mitsuru 140</p>
            <p>Weaver, Susan Ann 116, 145</p>
            <p>Webster, Brenda S. 138, 139</p>
            <p>Weinglass, David H. 146</p>
            <p>Whiteside, Shaun 143</p>
            <p>Wilcox, Scott 144</p>
            <p>Williams, Nicholas M. 117, 145</p>
            <p>Wilson, Simon 145</p>
            <p>Windle, John 115, 129</p>
            <p>Wittreich, Joseph 134</p>
            <p>Wolfreys, Julian 145</p>
            <p>Wolfson, Susan J. 136, 145</p>
            <p>Worrall, David<lb/>
116, 122, 123, 128, 132, 134, 135, 137, 138, 139, 141, 142, 144, 145</p>
            <p>Wright, Thomas 127</p>
            <p>Yakovleva, G. V. 145</p>
            <p>Yasuda, Masayoshi 146</p>
            <p>Yeats, W. B. 146</p>
            <p>Zanzotto, Andrea 123</p>
            <p>Zhirmunsky, V. M. 146</p>
            <p>Zimmerman, Sarah M. 146</p>
            <p>Zveryev, A. 123</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
