<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>32.4.noon</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="remembrance">Paul Mellon, 1908-1999</title>
        <author n="Noon">Patrick Noon</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1999</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1999</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">32.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <title/>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Patrick Noon</name>
              <name>Ian Singer</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1999"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_32">
    <pb id="p32-152" n="152"/>
    <back>
      <div1 id="BQ-32-4-0009">
  		<div2>
  			<div3 type="in-memoriam">
        		<head>
          			<title type="main">
            			<hi rend="b">Paul Mellon<lb/>
						1908-1999</hi>
          		</title>
        		</head>
        	</div3>
        </div2>
        <p>Paul Mellon became interested in collecting William Blake at the comparatively early date of 1941.
Of the major eighteenth-century British artists, George Stubbs alone preceded (and to the very end superseded)
the poet in his affections. The largest exhibition of Blake’s work ever organized in North America had just
closed at the Philadelphia Museum of Art and had done much to generate enthusiasm among a new generation of
collectors. His first purchase was an album of 22 watercolor illustrations for the Book of Job, most
frequently referred to in the literature as “The New Zealand Set” and no longer accepted as autograph. It
was an inauspicious start, but a more significant and, ultimately, precursory acquisition of the same year was
copy B of Blake’s first illuminated book, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, from the heirs of
William A. White. From this celebrated source would eventually derive <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
(copy G), <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (copy I), and <hi rend="i">America a
Prophecy</hi> (copy M).</p>
        <p>After 1941, hardly a year passed without Paul Mellon’s acquiring some Blake opus. The harvest is
impressive: four tempera paintings, one monotype, several hundred prints and watercolors, and several dozen
volumes with engraved illustrations; however, it is the 12 illuminated books that truly elevated him to
preeminence among Blake admirers. Between 1947 and 1949, the acquisitions included Philip Hofer’s 
<hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> (copy B); Benjamin D’Israeli’s <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi> (copy A);
the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (copy F) that George
Cumberland, Blake’s generous patron, had bound together in 1794; and a complete <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi> (copy L) that has no known marvelous pedigree despite its quiet excellence.
In the 1950s, the three previously cited titles from the White collection were added, as were a second 
<hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> (copy R) and one of the few copies of <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen</hi>
(copy A) with a full complement of 28 plates. The final illuminated book to enter the collection, in 1972, was
a second copy, quite differently colored, of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (copy C), thus bringing together two of
only eight known printings of that magnificent prophetic work.</p>
        <p>When Paul Mellon began to amass a comprehensive collection of British art in the 1960’s, he was
plunging into a field that was much undervalued internationally. Conversely, 20 years earlier, he had been
anticipated in his passion for Blake by a very acquisitive group of distinguished bibliophiles that included
Henry E. Huntington, Lessing J. Rosenwald, and Mrs. Landon K. Thorne in America, and W. Graham Robertson and
Sir Geoffrey Keynes in England. Exceptional objects were rare and the competition was aggressive. The Mellon
collection could never achieve, at that date, the comprehensiveness of those other collections, but it
ultimately ranks with them primarily because of two stellar acquisitions: the 116 watercolor illustrations for
the poems of Thomas Gray, and the most coveted of Blake’s composite art of poetry, painting, and
printmaking, the unique colored copy of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (copy E).<gap type="emend"/></p>
        <pb id="p32-151" n="151"/>
        <p>Paul Mellon purchased <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in 1953 from the collection formed by Sir William
Stirling-Maxwell. From the same source and in the same year, he acquired, and immediately donated to the
Victoria and Albert Museum, the tempera of <hi rend="i">The Virgin and Child in Egypt</hi> (1810). This was
not his first Blake donation to a public institution. In 1949 he and Mrs. Thorne had made possible the
purchase by the Morgan Library of twelve watercolor illustrations for Milton’s <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso.</hi> The illustrations to Gray were purchased in 1966 by private treaty, thus
preventing their likely dispersal by the trade.</p>
        <p>Prior to that date, in March 1949, Geoffrey Keynes and others had founded the William Blake Trust
to promote the continued study of the poet through the publication of accurate color reproductions of his
greatest works. The unique copy E of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which had not yet entered the Mellon
collection, was the first major project undertaken for the Trust by Arnold Fawcus and his Trianon Press in
Paris. In 1962, Paul Mellon was elected an Associate American Trustee, and from 1966 to 1970 he supported
financially, and with matchless patience, the exacting production of the jewel of the Trust’s collotype and
stencil replications, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Water-Colour Designs for the Poems of Thomas Gray</hi>
(1971). This was merely one of many instances of his financial and intellectual support for the publications
and exhibitions of the Blake Trust. It is quite likely, in fact, that without his subventions the Trust would
not have been able to effect its most important projects. Martin Butlin’s magnificent catalogue raisonné,
to cite but one example, owes its second, invaluable volume of illustrations to Paul Mellon’s
generosity.</p>
        <p>As a novice curator only recently arrived at the British Art Center after its opening in 1977, I
was immediately dispatched to Upperville to reconnoiter what remained of the British paintings and drawings
not yet transferred to Yale. The Brick House was still resplendent with its dazzling collection of Ben
Marshall and Stubbs set on pastel walls. The Degas waxes and <hi rend="i">Fallen Jockey</hi> seemed an
exquisite anomaly in this seat of Georgian decorum. The Degas <hi rend="i">Self-Portrait</hi>, literally
affixed to a nearby powder room door, playfully exposed the unique wit of a man who was fastidious about the
installation of his collection. The majestic library, however, had had its shelves seriously denuded of its
many treasures—the color-plate books that comprised the Abbey collection, for instance. I first met Paul
Mellon in this library. It was the briefest of encounters. He had come to assess and to welcome, but he made
the point of introducing me to a very special group of books and folios that occupied an inconspicuous nine
square feet of this cavernous cabinetry. On the nearby tables rare sixteenth-century globes, flawless
porcelain, and the trophies and bronzes of Mill Reef proved little distraction as he pulled a volume from the
shelf and left me to my private meditations. It was <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plates 1-20.</p>
        <p>Although much of the Blake material had gone to Yale in 1977, Paul Mellon retained the cream of the
collection, for obvious personal reasons, until its permanent transfer to the British Art Center in 1992. At
his death, he owned only a single work by Blake. Identical in size to the small engraved illustration for
Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805) that it reproduces, <hi rend="i">The Horse</hi>, a precious
tempera on copper, is indisputably the gem of the entire collection. If it is one of the “little high
finished Pictures the size the Engravings are to be” mentioned by Blake in a letter to Hayley of March 1805,
it is the only surviving example. Intimate in scale, exquisite in execution, perfection in its state of
preservation, and thematically so sympathetic to the varied tastes of a literary scholar, connoisseur, and
sportsman, it is not surprising that this philanthropist, who gladly relinquished to the public domain
countless works of art in his lifetime, was reluctant to do so in this one instance.</p>
        <p>In 1997, I organized an exhibition of the entire Mellon Blake collection. Many of the works had
been seen publicly over the years in the most important Blake exhibitions, especially those organized by
Martin Butlin for the Tate in 1978 and David Bindman for Yale in 1984, but never had they all been shown
together. While still in his possession, Paul Mellon had had the illuminated books and the Gray disbound with
the thought of their public exhibtion and ease of study in mind. Consequently, it was possible to exhibit for
the first time all one hundred plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and to juxtapose the multiple sets of 
<hi rend="i">Songs, Thel</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi> A staggering display of over 350 sheets, the
exhibition paid admirable tribute to Paul Mellon on his ninetieth birthday and to his lifelong commitment to
Blake. He spent hours in the show, on several visits, carefully examining the many works with which he had
communed privately over the years. His enthusiasm for Blake was unflagging, and at the end of one of our
campaigns he asked, in a capriciously plaintive voice, whatever possessed him to part with such treasures.</p>
        <p>Paul Mellon was a magnificent collector, not only of Blake but of artists of many nationalities and
epochs. He was blessed with a cultivated and incisive taste for objects of both transcendent and private
import; hence the intoxicating appeal of a poet who made an art of the book. He entered the game rather late
yet he garnered many of the finest trophies, and until one has enjoyed these treasures in the serene
atmosphere of Louis Kahn’s building at Yale, it is impossible to grasp the special order of Paul Mellon’s
genius and philanthropy, and the magnitude of our loss.</p>
        <byline><docAuthor>Patrick <name>Noon</name></docAuthor> Minneapolis, March 1999</byline>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
