<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>33.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Linnell, Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.: The Life of John Linnell</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1999</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1999</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">33.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Claire Colebrook</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Perkins</name>
              <name>Joe Riehl</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1999"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_33">
    <body>
      <pb id="p33-21" n="21"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Linnell, <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.: The Life of John
Linnell.</hi> [Lewes] Sussex: The Book Guild Ltd., 1994. 4°, xii, 413 pp., 66 plates (24 in color). ISBN: 0
86332 917 9. £50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>G.E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.</hi> is a very handsome work, full of valuable new
information. It is the product of family enthusiasm—David Linnell is the great-grandson of John
Linnell—making energetic use of the vast archive of papers preserved by his kinswoman Joan Linnell Ivimy, to
whom the work is appropriately dedicated. The absence of indication as to the sources of specific information
makes it exceedingly difficult to follow David Linnell’s footsteps and to evaluate his accuracy, but, as one
who has been through this archive repeatedly myself, I can say confidently that he has displayed an enormous
mass of matter quite unknown before. If Linnell’s press has not been quite so bad during the last half
century as the book’s publicity materials would have us believe,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n60" type="note">1</ref> it is certainly true that the portrait of Linnell presented here is both
judicious and altogether more amiable than was previously easy to see. <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
“For the first time Linnell’s side of the relationship with Blake and Palmer is examined”—the
miniscule “Bibliography” in the book does not indicate that David Linnell has examined very extensively
what has been written about them.</note></p>
          <p>For one thing, there is a consistent vein of humor in Linnell which is not usually remarked in
the context of his serious son-in-law Samuel Palmer. For instance, in 1809 a gentleman offered through an
intermediary to buy a painting by the 21-year-old artist if he would cut off a strip four inches wide on each
side of it, and Linnell replied: “‘pray does the gentleman wish to have the outside pieces or the
inside,’ for I doubted which would be worth most” (16).</p>
          <p>For another, the relationship between Linnell and Palmer shown here is consistently, and rightly,
much more creditable to Linnell than one sees in accounts of the currently much more fashionable Samuel
Palmer. Linnell fostered and supported the work of all his children and their spouses to an extraordinay
extent. The title, <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.</hi>, is of course designed to attract readers
interested chiefly in Blake and Palmer, but the book has a great deal to say not only about Blake and Palmer
(though much of this is already in print) but also about “Linnell and Co.” For 40 years, Linnell was one
of the most successful and prosperous artists in England, frequently being paid £1,000 for a single painting,
the price of a modest house. He used his success systematically to foster the careers of his children—“Of
his nine children James, William, Thomas, Sarah, Polly and Lizzy all exhibited” paintings (281) and others
also painted seriously—and Linnell insisted that customers who came to his house to see his pictures should
consider those by his children and Samuel Palmer as well, and sometimes, at the request of the purchaser, he
touched up his family’s pictures to make them more vendible. He was an exceedingly generous man, as Blake
knew intimately.</p>
          <p>One of the bonds between Linnell and Blake was their deep religious feelings, which may have been
quite similar. David Linnell shows Linnell’s lifelong search for a religious context beyond the priestcraft
of the Established Church. In 1812 he joined the Baptist Church in Keppel Street, whose Treasurer was the
learned Thomas Palmer (his future father-in-law), but he was later excluded from the Church for heterodoxy
(26-27, 122-23). Later he considered joining the Quakers, partly so that he could claim their privilege of
declining to swear on oath in court, but his insistence on “the privilege of judging for myself” alienated
the Quakers as well (124-25). He insisted that both his own marriage and his daughter’s should be merely
civil, not religious (45), and David Linnell claims, without alluding to evidence, that “Linnell himself did
not attend the funeral” of Blake because it was conducted with a Church of England service (110).</p>
          <p>Literary scholars tend to assume that Linnell was a successful artist who is chiefly notable for
his patronage of William Blake; had it not been for Linnell, Blake’s engravings for <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
and his splendid drawings and engravings for Dante would not have existed. We tend to forget that Linnell was
a very fine painter and engraver who taught Blake a good deal. His early successes were chiefly in portrait
painting and engraving, and some admirable examples are reproduced, such as the oil of Blake’s patroness
“Lady Torrens &amp; Her Children.” The portrait sketches too are often remarkably skillful, such as the
one of Mrs. George Stephen (illus. 1), whose husband bought one of the early sets of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
proofs. His later landscapes, for which he was justly famous in his time, are sometimes wonderful, with superb
effects of sky—a formula which eventually became somewhat repetitive. The aureate “Evening—Vicinity of a
Farm” with a herdsman driving cattle towards a thatched cottage evidently shows a scene which Blake may have
seen whenever he visited the Linnells at Hampstead. Blake was in very good, nay, distinguished company
indeed.</p>
          <p>Beyond the fascinating new biographical information, David Linnell also provides valuable lists
of John Linnell’s public art (omitting sketches, etc.), with these appendices:</p>
          <pb id="p33-22" n="22"/>
          <figure n="linnell-mrs-stephen.033.01.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="831">
            <head>1 Oil sketch by John Linnell of Mrs. George Stephen (GEB), presumably in preparation for the
oil portrait on panel 10″ × 8″ which, according to <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.</hi>, 376,
Linnell painted for £15.15 (1821) and exhibited at the Royal Academy (1822).</head>
            <figDesc>Linnell also painted portraits of George Stephen (1827), exhibited at the Royal Academy
(1829), and a miniature (1829) (377, 385). In August 1824 Stephen paid (via Linnell) “to M<hi
rend="s">r</hi> Blake for C. Pilgrims [£]1 1” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> [1988], 122; see
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969], 373, 587), and on 1 July 1833 Linnell went “To M<hi rend="s">r</hi>
Geo Stephens [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] Coleman St to meet Miss Blake @ Administering to her Brothers Effects”
(<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 415).</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p33-23" n="23"/>
          <table rows="8" cols="3">
            <row>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="b">Subject</hi>
              </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="b">Years Covered</hi>
              </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="b">No. of Entries</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Landscapes and other pictures</cell>
              <cell>1807-78</cell>
              <cell>377</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Portraits in oil</cell>
              <cell>1812-50</cell>
              <cell>315</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Portraits in watercolor, chalk, etc.</cell>
              <cell>1814-49</cell>
              <cell>186</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Miniatures</cell>
              <cell>1816-32</cell>
              <cell>78</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Engravings</cell>
              <cell>1813-47</cell>
              <cell>66</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Pictures exhibited at the Royal Academy</cell>
              <cell>1807-81</cell>
              <cell>177</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Pictures exhibited at the British Institution</cell>
              <cell>1808-59</cell>
              <cell>91</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>Notice the extraordinary length of time during which Linnell was exhibiting—75 years—and the
enormous number of finished pictures recorded—over a thousand. This is a prodigious career.</p>
          <p>Readers of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> will be especially interested in new information offered by
David Linnell about William Blake. His prime source of information, the enormous mass of papers in the
possession of the late Joan Linnell Ivimy and the Linnell Trust, has already been mined for <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> (1969) and <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> (1988) (which do not appear in David
Linnell’s half-page bibliography), and most of the Blake references in <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell
and Co.</hi> appeared also in the earlier works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61"
type="note">2</ref> Since some of the documents quoted in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> and its 
<hi rend="i">Supplement</hi> are quoted at greater length in <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.</hi>, it
is plain that the latter derives from the MSS rather than from printed sources. However, some of the entries
are somewhat carelessly transcribed—or at least they appear in forms different from those in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> and its <hi rend="i">Supplement.</hi> For instance, Linnell’s wife is recorded
as having written to him that Edward Chance “has been every day to Lakers” “respecting the Job” (97;
see also 99), but the printer of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> was named “Lahee” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
321; see also 300, 350, 582, 588-89, 591, 594-94, 603). The bill for Blake’s funeral has entries for “Paul
for Lime to make up Coffin” and “Paul Mens allowance for refreshment” (110), though of course in each
case “Paul” should be “Paid” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 343-44). In Blake’s letter to Linnell
of 11 October 1825 (quoted from an unidentified source) beginning “I have had the pleasure to see Mr Linnell
set off safe in a coach, for we both got in” (96), the curious syntax is made clear if after “in a
coach” we restore the omitted phrase “&amp; I may say I accompanied him part of the way on his Journey in
the Coach.” The transcriptions, then, are somewhat erratic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n62" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Contemporary references to Blake from the Ivimy MSS appear on the
following pages of <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.</hi> (the numbers in parentheses representing
the corresponding pages in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>): 53 (253), 53-54 (253-54), 55 (263), 60 (263),
75-76 (263), 85-86 (277), 88 (282), 88 (282), 96 (304), 97 (305-06), 97-98 (320-21), 98 (306), 99 (538, 539),
101 (85 of <hi rend="i">BRS</hi>), 110 (343-44), 120 (290), 135-36 (404-05), 136 (408-09), 137 (405), 137-38
(406-08), 141 (411); references on 100 and 147-48 are not in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> or its 
<hi rend="i">Supplement.</hi></note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Though David Linnell says that “The original spelling has been retained
in quotations from Linnell’s autobiographical notes, journal, and all letters” (vii), he regularly
normalizes quotations and punctuation, changes capitalization <hi rend="i">ad libitum</hi>, expands
abbreviations (“St” becomes “Street,” “&amp;” becomes “and”), moves dates from the ends of
letters to the beginning, and corrects spelling (“beleived” [53], “accomodation” [104]). Some of this
may be simple carelessness, as when “shew” is spelled “show” (135, 136) and “Jno” becomes
“Jns” (105).</note></p>
          <p>Two entries about Blake from the Ivimy MSS are given here for the first time:</p>
          <p>(1) Linnell wrote to his wife Mary on 6 February 1826 asking her to “obtain all the particulars
you can respecting the printing of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>” (100).</p>
          <p>(2) After Catherine Blake’s death, when Tatham was trying to gain possession of Blake’s Dante
drawings (1 March 1833) which Linnell had commissioned and paid for, Linnell’s father-in-law Thomas Palmer,
a coal-and book-merchant, wrote to Linnell on 22 March 1833 about trying to find Catherine Blake’s will:
<q>
My dear Mr Linnell,<lb/>
I spent the greater part of three hours today, at Doctors Commons, searching the Books; and there appears no
account of either Mr or Mrs Blake’s effects having been administered to at all. I was not satisfied by
examining for the Will of the latter in 1831 but I also went through 1832, supposing it possible that, as she
died so late in the year 1831 as the 18th of October the administration might have been neglected, or
deferred, to the full length of the time allowed, which, I believe, is Six Months from the decease of the
party; but there is no trace of any Will or Administration. . . . I am afraid everything is not as it should
be relative to the disposal of the estates of Mr and Mrs Blake; but I suppose that must be left, unless any
further steps should be taken to annoy you. [147-48]
</q></p>
          <p>We had previously known that no will for either William or Catherine Blake was ever proved, but
we had not known that Linnell sought the information. He was a careful businessman who did not take chances
when it came to the management of his property.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.</hi> is useful on Blake and Palmer, though not so
novel as its publisher imagines, and on Linnell and his family it introduces a great deal of new
information—and reproduces some beautiful and too-little-known pictures. We have much to thank David Linnell
for, particularly the reminder of what a very fine artist and generous man his great-grandfather was.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
