<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>33.1.riehl</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Bernard Barton’s Contribution to Cunningham’s “Life of Blake”: A New
Letter</title>
        <author n="Riehl">Joe Riehl</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1999</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1999</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">33.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Claire Colebrook</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Perkins</name>
              <name>Joe Riehl</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1999"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_33">
    <body>
	<pb id="p33-16" n="16"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Bernard Barton’s Contribution to Cunningham’s “Life of Blake”: A New
Letter</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Joe <name>Riehl</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In 1824 James Montgomery solicited Charles Lamb for a contribution to his 
<hi rend="i">Chimney-Sweepers’ Friend and Climbing Boys’ Album</hi> to benefit “The Society for Ameliorating
the Condition of Infant Chimney Sweepers.” Though Lamb submitted nothing of his own, he suggested Blake’s
“The Chimney Sweeper,” and sent Montgomery a copy of the poem, slightly altered. Bernard Barton
(1784-1849), who also contributed to the <hi rend="i">Album</hi>, seems to have been intrigued by Blake’s
poem, and apparently wrote Lamb for more information. Lamb responded in May 1824, describing “The Tiger”
as “glorious, and Blake as “one of the most extraordinary persons of the age” (Lucas 2: 426). Barton,
known primarily as a Quaker poet and as one of Lamb’s correspondents, had begun writing to Lamb in 1822,
complaining that conditions at Messrs. Alexanders’ bank in Woodbridge, where he clerked, did not permit him
to continue his career as a poet. In 1812, Barton had published <hi rend="i">Metrical Effusions</hi>, followed
by <hi rend="i">Poems by an Amateur</hi> (1818), <hi rend="i">Verses on the Death of P. B. Shelley</hi>
(1822), <hi rend="i">Devotional Verses</hi> (1826), <hi rend="i">A Widow’s Tale</hi> (1827), and 
<hi rend="i">A New Year’s Eve</hi> (1828). In addition, he had published poems in <hi rend="i">London
Magazine</hi>, including, in 1823, a “Sonnet to Elia.” Before striking up a correspondence with Lamb, he
had also, since 1812, been in correspondence with Robert Southey.</p>
          <p>Six years after Lamb sent the Blake poem to Montgomery, Allan Cunningham’s brief life of Blake
was published in <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors and Architects</hi>
(London, 1830), sometime before 6 February 1830, when a
<pb id="p33-17" n="17"/>
review of it appeared in the <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 377-78). G. E.
Bentley, Jr., has noted that “The publication of Cunningham’s life of Blake provoked a spate of comments
upon Blake in the spring of 1830,” and he has reprinted generous selections from the reviews 
(<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 377-401).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">1</ref>
Though Barton’s friend and correspondent Robert Southey expressed a very low opinion of Blake 
(<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 398-400), Barton’s enthusiasm for the painter, kindled by Lamb, inspired him to
write a sonnet to Blake’s associate John Linnell<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">2</ref> and to contact Cunningham with information about Lamb’s 1824 remarks on Blake.
Eventually, Barton supplied Cunningham with a full copy of Lamb’s remarks on Blake. However, after
Cunningham’s initial request for Lamb’s remarks, Barton wrote, in the letter here presented, that he would
need to seek Lamb’s permission before forwarding the extract to Cunningham. The interim was only a few
weeks, and Cunningham had Lamb’s letter in time to include it in the second edition of 
<hi rend="i">Lives</hi> (1831). <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">1</hi> “The two biographical accounts by Cunningham
and J. T. Smith are the last of major importance published by Blake’s contemporaries” (<hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi> 22).</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> 394; eventually Linnell gave Barton one of
the prints from Blake’s unfinished Dante series along with an etching of his own (<hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> 400).</note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Bernard Barton to Allan Cunningham</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Woodbridge 2/24/30</p>
            <p>Dear Allan</p>
            <p>I do not see that I can, consistently with the delicacy and good faith due to such a friend and
correspondent as Chas. Lamb, give thee the extract referred to without first having his consent, but I write
him by this night’s post to request him to give it, &amp; I have said all I can to induce him to meet thy
wishes &amp; mine.—For I would not for five guineas, but thou shouldst have it, as I consider it a sort of
miniature off-hand Lamb sketch of Blake, in the very best Elia style—and in my view it implies no slight
compliment to Lamb’s critical taste &amp; penetration to find him writing of Blake in May 1824 in terms now
applied to him by the unanimous voice of Critics &amp; Critical Journals—Probably thou art acquainted with
Lamb whose present address is Chase-side, Enfield, if so perhaps a line or a call from thee may have more
influence with him than aught I could urge—Do pray try and keep the proof sheets of Blake back for a few
days till we can manage this matter—as a further inducement for thee to do this perhaps I can give thee a
clue to fresh channels of information about Blake—</p>
            <p>My friend Major Moor (an intimate &amp;c of Southeys) a Gent. resident near here, says that
Dawson Turner of Yarmouth was acquainted with Blake, corresponded with him he believes &amp; has many or
several of his drawings or plates. Moor tells me too that there is a good deal about Blake in Dr. Malkin’s
Life of his Son B. Heath Malkin,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">3</ref> who
died quite a boy, &amp; that a Portrait or Portraits in that Volume were engraved &amp; designed by Blake. The
Book itself is I suppose easy to be got sight of &amp; I dare say its Author would be very willing to give any
information in his power. I state these trifles as Turner and Malkin are both persons of considerable eminence
whose testimony to the talent, genius, &amp; worth of his subject any Biography might be formed of and such as
are worth procuring if they can be obtained without much delay or trouble—I consider thy Life of Blake as
the very gem of the Volume, good as the others undoubtedly are—In a letter I had this week from Martin (the
celebrated Painter &amp; Engraver) he says—“It gave me the greatest pleasure to find that your opinion of
the Life of Blake is entirely coincided with mine, for I have not been more delighted with any book that I
have read lately than with these Lives of the Painters, especially with that of Blake”—If therefore we can
in any way add to its interest by any such accumulation either of intelligence, or of tributes to Blake’s
honorable fame from persons of just celebrity the delay of a few days would be well compensated—Excuse the
freedom I take in thus offering my opinion unasked for the sake of my desire to raise yet higher one thou hast
so happily rescued from comparative oblivion—I shall be most grateful indeed for any specimen of Blakes nor
will its value be slightly enhanced by my being indebted for it to his Biographer—Directly I hear from Lamb
I will write thee— <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Barton is mistaken here; Malkin’s son is Thomas
William Malkin. The engraving mentioned is, indeed, designed and engraved by Blake, though Cromek’s name
appears on it.</note></p>
            <p>Thine most heartily</p>
            <p>B.B.</p>
            <p>P.S. thy Letter does not specify in its date where Belgrave Place is—I can only direct as
thine is dated—I should be glad if only of a line just to know this comes safe—that if I receive Lamb’s
consent I may transcribe &amp; forward the extract without any misgivings of reaching thee in due course—was
there ever a Plate from Blake’s Drawing of the Ancient of Days?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Not a drawing, as Barton supposes, but a colored etching.</note></p>
            <p>Unpublished MS: W. Hugh Peal Collection, University of Kentucky Library. Postmark: 10 F-NOON Fe
25, 1830. / Woodbridge./ Address: Allan Cunningham. Esq/24 Belgrave Place/ London.</p>
            <p>Among the “fresh channels of information” which Barton suggests that Cunningham check,
Benjamin Heath Malkin’s <hi rend="i">Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi> (1806) was already known to the
author, who made use of it in preparing the first edition of <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> (1830).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">5</ref> Apparently, however, Barton’s suggestions
<pb id="p33-18" n="18"/>
that he should contact Edward Moor, Dawson Turner, and John Martin were new, and no doubt would have revealed
more information about Blake if Cunningham had chosen to follow up.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n47" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 479, where Bentley notes that
Cunningham uses Malkin’s text of “The Tyger.”</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Turner and Moor seem to have been on Barton’s mind at this time. On 28
April 1830, he recommends to his friend William S. Fitch that he also should visit Turner, and mentions asking
Moor how to address a letter to Sir Walter Scott (<hi rend="i">Literary Correspondence of Bernard Barton</hi>
75).</note></p>
            <p>Edward Moor (1771-1848) was known primarily for his work on Hindu mythology, <hi rend="i">The
Hindu Pantheon</hi> (1810), which, according to the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>, “for
more than fifty years remained the only book of authority in English upon its subject.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">7</ref> He had been a cadet in the East India Company
at Madras and Bombay, where he joined the Asiatic Society of Calcutta in 1796, and where he served from 1782
to 1806,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">8</ref> when he returned to England.
In 1833 he was involved in publishing a new edition of Hogarth (<hi rend="i">Literary Correspondence of
Bernard Barton</hi>, 86). At Moor’s death Barton privately published <hi rend="i">A Brief Memorial of Major
Edward Moor</hi> (Woodbridge: Edward Pite, 1848). As Joseph Burke has shown, Blake was undoubtedly familiar
with Moor’s work, deriving his design for “Lucifer” from one of Moor’s images, that of the Hindu
goddess Durga, consort of Siva (Burke 124, plates 98 and 100). Considering the large volume of scholarship
which has been amassed on the sources of Blake’s ideas and myths, it would be intriguing to know how Moor,
an art collector and accomplished student of Indian culture, might have responded, in turn, to Blake. 
<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">7</hi> This judgment is confirmed by Peg DeLameter in “Some Indian Sources in the Art
of Paul Klee” (<hi rend="i">The Art Bulletin</hi> 66 [1984]: 657-73]) who judges that <hi rend="i">Hindu
pantheon</hi> “included all that was then known about the Hindu religion.”</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See also <hi rend="i">Literary Correspondence of Bernard Barton</hi>
67.</note></p>
            <p>Dawson Turner (1775-1858), the son of a wealthy banker, was himself a banker, as well as a
botanist and an antiquary. He published large and impressive books, including <hi rend="i">Botanist’s Guide
through England and Wales</hi> (1805). On 9 June 1818, in answer to Turner’s request for information, Blake
had responded with a list of prices for <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, for six of the minor prophecies, and for a
group of engravings (<hi rend="i">Letters of William Blake</hi> 142), though <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
does not record that he actually purchased any. Barton was reputedly a good friend of Turner, and made several
visits to his home, at one point recommending that a friend pay a call as well (<hi rend="i">Literary
Correspondence of Bernard Barton</hi> 75). In 1844, shortly after a visit with Barton at Ipswich, Henry Crabb
Robinson visited Turner in Yarmouth and was shown his “library treasures.” While Barton reports, in the
letter above, that Turner had “many or several” of Blake’s works, Robinson does not mention any items by
Blake in Turner’s collection, though he remarks on seeing letters of Cowper, Coleridge, Lamb, Wordsworth and
Southey (<hi rend="i">Henry Crabb Robinson</hi> 2: 645-46). Turner sold a large collection of manuscripts to
the British Museum in 1853. His library of more than 8,000 volumes was sold at auction in 1853 and more than
40,000 letters and manuscripts were sold after his death in 1859. In both cases, catalogues were
published.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">9</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s exhaustive scholarship list no works by Blake in
Turner’s collection, though Turner kept the two Blake letters.</note></p>
            <p>John Martin (1789-1854) was known in this period primarily for his monumentally large paintings
of biblical subjects, particularly “Belshazzar’s Feast,” about which Lamb wrote, disapproving of its
excessive realism in “On the Barrenness of the Productions Modern Art” (1833).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">10</ref> Though Martin and Blake were aware of one another, they do
not seem to have been well acquainted, and it is unlikely that there is any direct influence or connection
between Blake’s 1807-08 illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and Martin’s 24 mezzotints on
that subject in 1823.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">11</ref> Martin often
acted as engraver for his own works. Although he was successful, and, according to the DNB, found patronage
under Princess Charlotte,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">12</ref> he was,
like Blake, an avowed critic of the Royal Academy, and something of a radical. Martin was apparently friendly
with Barton, and engraved the frontispiece for Barton’s <hi rend="i">A New Year’s Eve</hi> (1828) (Balston
118). One would like to know more about the opinion of an established painter like Martin, whose affinities
with Blake (as engraver, critic of the Academy, and creator of prophetic visions) might have provided a unique
perspective on Blake’s art.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See “John Martin” in Morton Paley, <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic
Sublime</hi> (Yale UP, 1986: [122-54] for a discussion of Lamb’s criticism of Martin.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See James Treadwell, “Blake, John Martin, and the Illustration of
Paradise Lost” <hi rend="i">Word and Image</hi> 9 (1993): 363-82.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">12</hi> According to his biographer, John Balston, in 1816 Martin was appointed
Historial Landscape Painter by Princess Charlotte and Prince Leopold (95).</note>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">13</hi> In fact, Martin and Blake were linked in one article of the period, which
found resemblances in the extravagant style of the two painters. In 1834 Richard Henry Horne objected to
Martin’s “phantasmagoria,” which resembled those of Blake and Fuseli. “Art. XI- illustrations of the
Bible. By John Martin. Parts I to VI.-4to. “<hi rend="i">Westminster Review</hi> 20 (1834): 452-65, cited in
<hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> 515.</note></p>
            <p>The evidence of the revisions of the second edition of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>
indicates that Cunningham did not follow up on Barton’s suggestions to interview Martin, Dawson or Moor. A
week or two after writing the letter above, Barton sent Cunningham Lamb’s remarks, which Cunningham inserted
into the second edition. As Barton suggests, Lamb’s comments are the earliest expression of admiration of
Blake among the established or well-known writers of Blake’s time, and Cunningham seized on them for that
reason. (Although Wordsworth had previously expressed admiration for Blake’s poetry, he did so only in
conversation with Henry Crabb Robinson [<hi rend="i">Robinson</hi> 1:85].) Cunningham introduces Lamb’s
<pb id="p33-19" n="19"/>
opinion in terms which project Lamb as a nearly infallible critic:
<q>
The impression which the talents and oddities of Blake made on men of taste and genius, is well described by
one whose judgment in whatever is poetical no one will question. Charles Lamb had communicated to James
Montgomery’s book on chimney sweepers the little song by Blake, which I have already quoted; it touched the
feelings of Bernard Barton so deeply, that he made inquiries of his friend about the author, upon which he
received the following letter in explanation, written some six years ago.” [<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
496]
</q></p>
            <p>In the second edition, as Robinson first noted, Cunningham somewhat softened his judgment of
Blake as a “madman,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">14</ref> a change
for which Barton and Lamb seem at least partly responsible. Cunningham reprinted Lamb’s remarks much as they
had appeared in the original manuscript:
<q>
Your recent acquisitions of the Picture and the Letter are greatly to be congratulated. . . . Blake is a real
name, I assure you, and a most extraordinary man, if he be still living. He is the Robert [that is, William]
Blake, whose wild designs accompany a splendid folio edition of the Night Thoughts, which you may have seen,
in one of which he pictures the parting of soul and body by a solid mass of human form floating off God knows
how from a lumpish mass (fac simile to itself) left behin[d] on the dying bed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">15</ref> He paints in water colours marvellous strange pictures,
visions of his brain, which he asserts that he has seen. They have great merit. He has <hi rend="i">seen</hi>
the old Welsh bards on Snowdon—he has seen the Beautifullest, the Strongest, and the Ugliest Man, left alone
from the Massacre of the Britons by the Romans, &amp; has painted them from memory (I have seen his paintings)
and asserts them to be as good as the figures of Raphael &amp; Angelo, but not better, as they had precisely
the same retro-visions &amp; prophetic visions with themself. The painters in Oil (which he will have it that
neither of them practice) he affirms to have been the ruin of art, and affirms that all the while he was
engaged in his Water paintings, Titian was disturbing him, Titian the Ill Genius of Oil Painting. His
Pictures, one in particular, the Canterbury Pilgrims (far above Stothard’s) have great merit, but hard,
dry,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">16</ref> yet with grace. He has written
a Catalogue of them with a most spirited criticism on Chaucer, but mystical and full of Vision. His poems have
been sold hitherto only in Manuscript. I have never read them; but a friend at my desire procured the Sweep
Song. There is one to a Tiger, which I have heard recited, beginning:<lb/>
<lb/>
Tiger Tiger burning bright,<lb/>
Thro’ the desarts of the night—<lb/>
<lb/>
which is glorious, but, alas! I have not the Book; for the man is flown, whither I know not—to Hades or a
Mad House<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">17</ref>—but I must look on him
as one of the most extraordinary persons of the age.<lb/>
<lb/>
[Letter to Bernard Barton, 15 May 1824. MS: Henry E. Huntington Library; by permission of The Huntington
Library; also published in Lucas, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> 2: 424] 
    <note id="n55"><hi rend="s">14</hi> In <hi rend="i">Henry Crabb Robinson on Books and Their Writers</hi>
1: 394; Bentley writes that in the first edition, Cunningham portrayed Blake as “a kind of Jekyll-and-Hyde,
sanely engraving for the booksellers by day and madly writing <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> by night” 
(<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 477).</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">15</hi> There is no plate in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> which
precisely answers to Lamb’s description. Lucas suggests his illustrations to Blair’s <hi rend="i">The
Grave</hi>, perhaps <hi rend="i">The Soul Hovering over the Body Reluctantly Parting with Life</hi> (Lucas 2:
426) (a design which Robert Hunt had described as “absurd”) [<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 196]), though
Lamb may well be confusing his recollection of the Blair engraving with somewhat similar ones in 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, pl. 19 or 40, indicating that Lamb had probably seen both <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> The best treatment of this is in <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi>, where G. E. Bentley, Jr. suggests that the engraving referred to by Lamb in 1816 (in Lucas 2:
185) as “The good man at the hour of death” is a reference to Blake: “. . . Lamb may have combined in
his mind’s eye one of the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> plates above with another from <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> in which Death is clearly shown with a feathered dart—though the dart is not aimed at ‘Good
man at the hour of death’ (Plates XXI, XXVII, XX)” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 284-85n4).</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Lamb’s remark about the “hard, dry” quality of Blake’s pictures
is echoed in Barton’s letter to Linnell: “There is a dryness and hardness in Blake’s manner of engraving
which is very apt to be repulsive to print-collectors in general—to any indeed who have not taste enough to
appreciate the force and originality of his conceptions” (22 April 1830, <hi rend="i">Literary
Correspondence of Bernard Barton</hi> 74). He thanks Linnell for the loan of “copy of Blakes Inventions for
the Book of Job,” with a view toward possible purchase: “Were I a rich man, I would gladly and instantly
purchase it for its curiosity. . .” (73).</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">17</hi> In a letter from Robinson to Edward Quillinan, Robinson says of Blake
that “Lamb used to call him a ‘mad Wordsworth’[.]” Mark Reed, “Blake, Wordsworth, Lamb, Etc.:
Further Information from Henry Crabb Robinson” (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 3 [1970]: 76-84). Reed speculates
that Lamb may have made the remark in defense of Blake, replying “to a conversational report that Wordsworth
regarded Blake as a madman with a remark like ‘So he is—a mad Wordsworth’” (80).</note></q></p>
            <p>Blake of course was neither in a madhouse nor in Hades; he was at living in the narrow rooms of
3 Fountain Court, the Strand, not far from the East India House, where Lamb clerked. And Lamb undoubtedly soon
learned more about Blake’s fate, since several of his friends were to buy some of Blake’s works within the
following three years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">18</ref> The remarks
on Blake, however, exemplify Lamb’s independent-minded taste, as well as his consistency. He had become
acquainted
<pb id="p33-20" n="20"/>
with Blake’s work 14 years previously when Robinson took him, along with his sister, to see the Blake
paintings on display at the Broad Street, Golden Square, exhibition on 11 June 1810 (<hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Writings</hi> 827.) There, Lamb gained possession of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi>, which he had bound with his own “Confessions of a Drunkard” (see <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> 215-19, 225, 226). His references to “the Beautifullest, the Strongest, and the Ugliest Man,”
to Michelangelo and to Titian are paraphrased or recollected from that work. The exhibit seems to have made a
strong impression both on Lamb and on Robinson, who wrote an article on Blake based on the exhibit and on
Malkin’s publication of some of Blake’s poems (<hi rend="i">Robinson</hi> 1: 15). It should not be assumed
that Lamb’s reference to the possibility of Blake’s being in a madhouse is dismissive, though it is
probably influenced by Southey’s and Robert Hunt’s ill opinion of Blake. Lamb himself had once been
confined, and his sister went periodically into the care of “madhouses.” Such an occurrence would not have
lessened his respect or admiration for a writer or an artist. Lamb’s long struggle with his own depression
and with his sister’s bipolar disorder might, in fact, help to explain Lamb’s sympathetic and admiring
attitude toward Blake. <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Among Lamb’s acquaintance, the following owned
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>: Charles Dilke, T. G. Wainewright (purchased in 1827), Henry Crabb Robinson (1825),
and Mrs. Charles Aders (1825) (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Writings</hi> 1: 685). It is possible that George Dyer
bought <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> before 1821 (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Writings</hi> 1:
693), and Robinson and Wainewright purchased it in 1827. Wainewright, in the September 1820 issue of 
<hi rend="i">The London Magazine</hi>, claimed that he had been introduced to “Jerusalem” by a Dr. Tobias
Ruddicombe, M.D. (possibly a pseudonym for the red-haired Blake himself), who proposes to give an account of
it in the next issue (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 265-66). By 1825, Robinson owned <hi rend="i">Visions of
the Daughters of Albion</hi> (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Writings</hi> 1: 696), and he also borrowed 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Writings</hi> 2: 705). On 29 December 1826 Blake’s health
caused him to refuse an invitation from Mrs. Charles Aders to visit and view their collection of old masters.
Blake’s letter to Mrs. Aders alludes to a previous meeting (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Writings</hi> 2: 1663).
After Blake’s death, Robinson bought two prints of the Canterbury pilgrimage from Catherine Blake, meaning
to give one to Lamb (<hi rend="i">Robinson</hi> 1: 353, 356).</note></p>
            <p>Generally, the new letter from Barton to Cunningham printed here provides further confirmation
of J. A. Wittreich’s claim that Barton should be placed among the very few of Blake’s contemporaries who
“registered profound admiration for the bard’s work and [who] unhesitatingly placed him within that
constellation of geniuses which a troubled age produced but ignored” (91). It also indicates that Cunningham
was apparently at work on the second edition of <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> within a few weeks of the publication
of the first edition. However, the main significance of this letter is in what Barton calls “fresh
channels” of information about Blake. He mentions names of several persons to Cunningham, suggesting that
they might provide more information about Blake, including two names of admirers of Blake who may be new to
Blake scholarship.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>Works Cited</title>
              </head>
              <p>Balston, Thomas. <hi rend="i">John Martin 1789-1854: His Life and Works.</hi> London: Gerald
Duckworth, 1947.</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977.</p>
              <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1995.</p>
              <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969.</p>
              <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1988.</p>
              <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1978.</p>
              <p>Burke, Joseph. “The Eidetic and the Borrowed Image: an Interpretation of Blake’s Theory
and Practice of Art.” <hi rend="i">In Honour of Daryl Lindsay: Essays and Studies.</hi> Ed. Franz Phillipp
and June Stewart. Melbourne: Oxford UP, 1964. 110-127.</p>
              <p>DeLameter, Peg. “Some Indian Sources in the Art of Paul Klee. <hi rend="i">The Art
Bulletin</hi> 66 (1984): 657-73.</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Biography.</hi>
              </p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Henry Crabb Robinson on Books and Their Writers.</hi> 3 vols. ed. Edith J.
Morley. London: Dent, 1938.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Letters of Charles and Mary Lamb.</hi> 3 vols. ed. E. V. Lucas. New Haven:
Yale UP, 1935.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake with Related Documents.</hi> ed. Geoffrey Keynes.
Oxford: Clarendon, 1980.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Literary Correspondence of Bernard Barton.</hi> ed. James Barcus.
Philadelphia: U of Pennsylvania P, 1966.</p>
              <p>Reed, Mark. “Blake, Wordsworth, Lamb, Etc.: Further Information from Henry Crabb
Robinson” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 3 (1970): 76-84.</p>
              <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. “William Blake and Bernard Barton: Addendum to 
<hi rend="i">BNB</hi>—Entry No. a852.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 1 (1968): 91-94.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
