<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>33.1.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1999</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1999</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">33.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Claire Colebrook</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Perkins</name>
              <name>Joe Riehl</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1999"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_33">
    <front>
      <pb id="p33-1-2" n="1-2"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.033.01.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="332">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            Nelson Hilton’s “Blake’s Digital Text Project” Explained<lb/>
            VOLUME 33<lb/>
            NUMBER 1<lb/>
            SUMMER 1999</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-1-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="11" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>CONTENTS</title>
        	  </head>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Articles</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="33.1.perkins">Animal Rights and “Auguries of
Innocence”</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by David Perkins</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">4</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="33.1.hilton">www.english.uga.edu/wblake</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by Nelson Hilton</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">11</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particular</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="33.1.riehl">Bernard Barton’s Contribution to Cunningham’s
“Life of Blake”: A New Letter</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by Joe Riehl</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">16</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="33.1.bentley">David Linnell, <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell
and Co.: The Life of John Linnell</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by G.E. Bentley, Jr.</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">21</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="33.1.esterhammer">William Blake. <hi rend="i">Zwischen Feuer und
Feuer. Poetische Werke. Zweisprachige Ausgabe</hi> and William Blake. <hi rend="i">Milton. Ein
Gedicht</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Angela Esterhammer</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">24</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Newsletter</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="33.1.news">Urizen in New York City</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">by Dr. Elizabeth B. Bentley</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">27</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-1-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p33-3" n="3"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-1-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Elizabeth B. Bentley, aka Beth Budd Bentley, has done research on William Blake on five continents.
She has lived with William Blake for 47 years, which is better than Catherine Blake did. But she is not so
proficient with a pencil or a printing press as Catherine was.</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr. is completing <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise</hi>, a biography of
William Blake.</p>
        <p>Claire Colebrook teaches in the Centre for Comparative Literature and Cultural Studies at Monash
University. She is the author of <hi rend="i">New Literary Histories</hi> (1997) and <hi rend="i">Ethics and
Representation</hi> (1999). She is also the co-editor of <hi rend="i">Deleuze and Feminist Theory</hi>
(1999).</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer is Associate Professor of English and Comparative Literature at the University
of Western Ontario. She is the author of <hi rend="i">Creating States: Studies in the Performative Language of
John Milton and William Blake. The Romantic Performative</hi> is forthcoming from Stanford University
Press.</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton’s “Hymns and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>” appears in <hi rend="i">Blake
in the Nineties</hi>, edited by Steve Clark and David Worrall and recently published by St. Martin’s
Press.</p>
        <p>David Perkins is Marquand Professor, Emeritus at Harvard University. He has published books and
articles on romantic poetry, modern poetry, and other topics. He is currently at work on a book on 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Animal Rights.</hi></p>
        <p>Joe Riehl is Professor of English at the University of Southwestern Louisiana. He is at work, with
Edwin Marrs, Jr., completing the remaining three volumes of <hi rend="i">The Letters of Charles and Mary Anne
Lamb.</hi></p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-1-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Patricia Neill, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY
14627</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Patricia Neill<lb/>
TELEPHONE 716/275-3820<lb/>
FAX 716/442-5769<lb/>
PRODUCTION OFFICE EMAIL: pnpj@uhura.cc.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627<lb/>
Email: meav@uhura.cc.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@socrates.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2. The University of Toronto
declines to forward mail.<lb/>
Email: GBentley@chass.utoronto.ca</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@uga.cc.uga.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill, Waldegrave Road, Twickenham TW1 4SX
England<lb/>
Email: worralld@mailnt.smuc.ac.UK</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE / AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester.</p>
        <p>SUBSCRIPTIONS are $55 for institutions, $30 for individuals. All subscriptions are by the volume (1
year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be
applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and Mexico) require a $10 per
volume postal surcharge for surface, and $25 per volume surcharge for air mail delivery. U.S. currency or
international money order necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi>
Address all subscription orders and related communications to Patricia Neill, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>,
Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627.</p>
        <p>BACK ISSUES are available at a reduced price. Address Patricia Neill for a list of issues and
prices.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to forms suggested in 
<hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of
Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA
94720-1030. Electronic submissions are encouraged. You may send a diskette, or you may send your article as an
attachment to an email message. The optimal format is Microsoft Word. Other formats are usually
acceptable.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A
Selective and Critical Bibliography</hi> (ed. David V. Erdman et al.), American Humanities Index, Arts and
Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi>
	<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1999 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
