<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>33.1.news</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Urizen in New York City</title>
        <author n="Bentley">Elizabeth B. Bentley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1999</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1999</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">33.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Claire Colebrook</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Perkins</name>
              <name>Joe Riehl</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1999"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_33">
    <body>
	<pb id="p33-27" n="27"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-1-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">Urizen in New York City</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Dr. Elizabeth B. <name>Bentley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>At the end of January 1999, we heard that Sotheby’s (New York) was going to offer at auction a
copy of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, one of eight known copies of his “most
ambitiously designed work”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">1</ref> up to
1794. <note id="n63"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
Press, 1977) 181, 476.</note></p>
          <p>It did not take long for Jerry, my husband, to identify it as copy E when he discovered that 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> was from the estate of Mrs. John Hay Whitney (Betsy Cushing Whitney). Copy E has been
associated in our minds with the Whitney family for some time. In the mid-1960s we had contacted all the
locatable heirs of Mrs. Harry Payne Whitney (died 1942) to enquire whether any knew of the whereabouts of copy
E of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, which, along with copy N of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi>, had come into Mrs. Harry Payne Whitney’s possession just before or after they were exhibited at
the Grolier Club in 1919-20.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">2</ref> Nothing
came of our enquiries. I understand that Mrs. Harry Payne Whitney was the mother of John Hay Whitney, the
publisher of the New York Herald Tribune and subsidiaries; he was also the United States Ambassador to the
Court of St. James and was notable for his interest in the world of horses. The <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, at
least, seems to have passed from Mrs. Harry Payne Whitney to John Hay Whitney and then to his widow. It is
quite possible that the Blake titles were scarcely noticed when they were inherited as part of the contents of
one of the many Whitney residences. <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">2</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
Books Supplement</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995) 38. <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (N) still has not been
found.</note></p>
          <pb id="p33-28" n="28"/>
          <p>Members of the Whitney family may have looked at Blake’s work in the 79-year interval between
its last public showing in 1920 and its appearance in the 1999 sale. However, when one looks at the 567-page
Whitney catalog<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">3</ref> and sees that 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> was 535th out of 1240 items in a four day sale (22-25 April), one realizes that not every
family member and friend would necessarily be aware of a 24-leaf book in a slim green morocco slip case. The
catalog title page introducing the third sale session pictures a dozen books, and the Blake book is not
noticeable except for being the only green book amongst the 12. <note id="n65"><hi rend="s">3</hi>
Sotheby’s, <hi rend="i">The Estate of Mrs. John Hay Whitney</hi> to be sold 22-25 April 1999 (NY:
Sotheby’s, 1999).</note></p>
          <p>We hadn’t seen the catalog when Jerry went down to see the Whitney copy of 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> and to consider whether this copy with 24 designs was “complete,” although other
copies had up to four more plates. He returned that night to Toronto full of excitement and pleasure over this
copy, even though he had to make extensive corrections to the <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> descriptions of
copy E.</p>
          <p>It did not take much to convince me that it was important for anyone interested in the work of
William Blake to take the opportunity to see this book now. Not only was it an opportunity for which I had
been waiting over 30 years, but also I was well aware that it was quite possible that this last copy in
private hands would disappear into an inaccessible private collection.</p>
          <p>Of course, we knew several likely bidders, and Blakean email lines buzzed with gossip about
potential buyers. When the catalog was issued a few weeks later, the estimated price was $500,000 to $700,000.
I did not even translate this sum into Canadian dollars as I usually do with anything outside Canada which we
covet. It was unimaginably beyond our means, but I still wished to see this Blake work and to be present at
its sale.</p>
          <p>I had been to book and picture auctions at Sotheby’s and Christie’s in London, but not in New
York, so this was going to be a new experience. There was also going to be an interesting exhibition held at
the Morgan Library which we both wished to see.</p>
          <p>We communicated with friends of Blake and arranged to join Robert Newman Essick, a teacher,
scholar, and collector; John Windle, a prominent dealer in antiquarian books with a polished and strong
emphasis on Blake; Morris Eaves, a teacher, scholar, and editor of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, with his partner,
Georgia; and Joseph Viscomi, a teacher and scholar whose studies have led current thinking about how Blake
worked as a printer and artist.</p>
          <p>The sale consisted of selected furnishings from five of Betsy Cushing Whitney’s residences
including the Greentree estate (on Long Island), and houses in Thomasville (Georgia), Saratoga Springs (New
York), St. James (London), and Beekman Place (New York City) where, we were told, Mr. and Mrs. John Hay
Whitney had never slept and where the Blake item turned up.</p>
          <p>We were a cheerful lot as we joined forces on Thursday 22 April for viewing the items being
offered in the six Whitney estate sessions, trying to respect the privacy of Bob Essick yet curious about his
plans. We met other Blakeans, exchanging information about the location of various Blake materials, while
keeping one eye (or both) on the case where <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> was shelved. From time to time Sotheby
staff members would take the book out of its slipcase and display a design or two to a client. Were these all
potential bidders?</p>
          <p>This was the last opportunity to look at any of the 1240 items in the Whitney sale, and I confess
that I hunted out a few items which had caught my fancy in the catalog. I even had attending staff turn over a
small piece of furniture to discover that it was not as old as I had been romancing it; that “chipped” did
indeed mean just that; that the malachite table which Jerry coveted was not only a veneer, but a thin and
cracked veneer at that. Luckily, I remembered three things: (a) we had a dinner engagement that night, (b) we
had not the wherewithal to engage in such folly, and (c) I had not arranged for my credit to be vetted by
Sotheby’s—and the coming afternoon was to be absorbed by William Blake.</p>
          <p>When the Sotheby’s staff closed the exhibition at noon, they put into operation a masterful
transfer of goods. They had been on duty in the showrooms from ten until noon. Now all 141 items for the 6
p.m. sale had to be moved from the exhibition rooms to the building which houses the auction rooms and offices
of Sotheby’s, New York, which is some distance away.</p>
          <p>Those specialists who are in charge of the protection, cataloging, estimating, promotion and
presentation of books and manuscripts did not have their auction until the next afternoon, but they were
meeting with prospective buyers to show particular items, and it had been arranged to show 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> to the seven of us at 1:30, and to another person or persons at 4 p.m. It is quite
possible that others followed later and the next morning.</p>
          <p>From 1:30 to 4 p.m., William Blake was indeed with us. The book was held by a Sotheby staff
member (Kimball Higgs) and the pages turned for us. Some of us had slides from other copies, but even better
were some color prints of what is being entered into the electronic Blake Archive being produced at the
University of Virginia. I could barely breathe, what with the excitement of each page coming to view,
photographic representation showing the kinds of variants which are commonplace in all Blake’s color-printed
works. In the spring 2000 issue of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, a proper bibliographical description will appear.
I can only attempt to describe the fun it was to listen and either challenge or accept other reactions from
persons whose lives are so involved with books, literature and art. It was a grand experience. I was so
<pb id="p33-29" n="29"/>
involved that I did not want to eat dinner or to try to attend a play; I only wanted to be peaceful and to
think about what I had seen.</p>
          <p>The next morning we reconvened at the Morgan Library to see the superb exhibition of some books
from the English Getty collection, including a copy of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</hi> We met other book persons, which added to the pleasures of the week, and we were treated to a
tour of the Morgan, focusing on Mr. Morgan’s office and the early days of the Library. I never did discover
if J. Pierpont Morgan’s own wine and cigars kept in a humidity-controlled storage area were available to
present-day directors, as they were in the 1960s and 70s. I can recommend the garden lunch room at the Morgan,
especially when the food is embellished with lively company and the excitement of the sale.</p>
          <p>The auction began at 2 p.m. with item 410, and, knowing the ways of Sotheby’s and Christie’s
in London, I expected them to reach the last item, <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, lot 535, by 4:30. This means that
the auction runs briskly, with 125 items to be sold in 150 minutes.</p>
          <p>It was fun watching the proceedings. We seven sat in the middle section of the third and fourth
rows. It was clear that John Windle was going to bid for Bob Essick, and they sat just in front of us. Jerry
circulated a tiny note on which we were to write our estimate of the price the Blake would fetch. We had five
entries ranging from $200,000 to $2,100,000. (Two wimps didn’t guess.)</p>
          <p>There were two banks of Sotheby’s staff mostly handling clients who bid on the phone, with a
few sitting on the auctioneer’s left side obviously commissioned to bid on items. The auction room was
slightly over half full. I would expect the room to be fuller for the furniture sessions.</p>
          <p>The auction room attendees seemed to consist of observers; persons bidding for themselves;
dealers bidding for clients or for stock; Sotheby’s agents hired to bid on direction of the client; and
those bidding for telephone clients.</p>
          <p>The auctioneer was a pleasure to watch. We were amused when one of the women offering telephone
bids on behalf of a Sotheby’s client pointed out that she had bid a sum which had been surpassed by another
telephone bid, and now she was proffering the next bid. The auctioneer made a joke of it, but it was clear
that he was not going to allow any more outside recognition of bids. He is a master of his trade and rewarding
to observe.</p>
          <p>How do you bid? If you live in a community which has a Sotheby’s office, you contact that
office about how to establish your credit. Otherwise, you find out from Sotheby’s in New York how to
proceed. Then, shortly before the session at which you wish to bid, just outside the auction room you step up
to the appropriate desk and identify yourself. You are then issued a card with large numerals on it which is
referred to as a paddle. (Dealers are very superstitious about these numbers.) Now, armed with a paddle in
order to bid for yourself, you enter the auction room. If you have someone else in the room ready to bid for
you, you work out whether or not you communicate during the bidding and choose seating accordingly. Or you can
hire a bidder from the auction house.</p>
          <p>For successful bids, the purchaser pays the auction house a buyer’s premium of 15% of the
successful bid price up to $50,000 or 10% for any price beyond $50,000. If someone else did the bidding, the
client pays the bidder a commission of 10% to 15% on the hammer-price. State sales taxes further exalt the
cost.</p>
          <p>The paddle is only to identify you—“sold to number 453.” You may catch the auctioneer’s
attention by any means you wish, by raising your paddle or raising your eyebrow or scratching your ear. But if
scratching your ear is supposed to mean “I’ll raise you $15,000,” you’d better arrange your code with
the auctioneer before the sale. The auctioneer looks chiefly at previous bidders, so if you wish to enter the
auction at a late stage, you may need to do so ostentatiously.</p>
          <p>We watched the sale of those items leading up to the item 535 with increasing palpitations. Some
items did not reach the reserve (often the minimum catalog estimate), such as a drawing by Aubrey Beardsley
which was estimated to sell for $6,000 to $8,000, but reached only $4,250. Often in this sale, however, the
hammer price was about four times that of the top estimate. Lot 533, copy 13 of a limited edition of 101
copies of Ezra Pound’s <hi rend="i">A Draft of the Cantos 17 to 37</hi>, fetched a hammer price of $45,000,
which was 7.5 times the top estimate of $6,000, while lot 531, a 1799 book containing 12 hand-colored
caricature aquatints of horses,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">4</ref>
brought $12,000, 10 times its top estimate. Lot 518, the first edition of a novel by Surtees estimated at
$400-$600, had no response to the auctioneer’s opening gambit of $100, while lot 531, an 1819 book on
Oriental field sports with 40 hand-colored plates, estimated at $2,500-$3,500, opened at $1,000, had one bid
to $1,500, but was “passed” by the auctioneer, which I took to mean that there was a reserve price on it,
a set price below which the auctioneer may not go. <note id="n66"><hi rend="s">4</hi> George Woodward and
Thomas Rowlandson, <hi rend="i">Horse Accomplishments</hi> (London: Ackermann, 1799).</note></p>
          <p>Which way was the Blake going to go? I could feel the excitement rising. I was so agitated that
my catalog copy has no bidding notes for item 534.</p>
          <p>The auctioneer opened the bidding on <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> by William Blake
at $250,000, which I believe was taken up by bidders just in front of me and continued rapidly but decorously
until suddenly the bidding moved from the floor to the telephones and rose to $1,000,000. There was another
bid from the floor after the $1,000,000 figure, but the real action was from three telephones, then two
telephones, and finally stopped at $2,300,000.</p>
          <p>The Two Million, Three Hundred Thousand Dollar hammer price would bring Sotheby’s a buyer’s
premium of
<pb id="p33-30" n="30"/>
$232,500, which means the buyer’s price is $2,532,500. And of course the buyer had to pay his bidder, which
is likely to have added significantly to his cost.</p>
          <p>The buyer, who evidently was bidding from a telephone within the building and who wishes to
remain anonymous, came down to collect his purchase and took it home with him, leaving the building about
5:30, within the hour of making his purchase. <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> has left New York.</p>
          <p>Of course, this is a RECORD PRICE FOR A BLAKE, almost twice what Copy D of <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi> sold for in 1989<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">5</ref> and multiples of what any copy of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> previously sold for. 
<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Copy D of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> has 54 prints
and sold in 1989 for $1,320,000 (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>),
which means that each print could be said to have cost $24,444. In the same sort of calculation, Copy E of 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> could have its 24 prints priced at over $105,500 a print.</note></p>
          <p>During the rather dazed aftermath of the sale, I was told by Sotheby’s staff who had been
dealing with the press that this is the fourth highest auction price recorded for a book. Remembering that
these books included the Gutenberg Bible and a Caxton Chaucer, it is tempting to make comparisons based on
size. Surely per square inch and even for number of pages, the <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> has fetched the
highest price in book auctions yet, over $100,000 per page.</p>
          <p>However, such commercial comparisons are odious. More interestingly, look at the auction records
of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, which reveal that copies of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> have been sold 10 times at
auction.</p>
          <table rows="11" cols="5">
            <head>
              <hi rend="b">Auction Sales of Blake’s Urizen</hi>
              <ref target="n68" type="note">6</ref>
              <note id="n68"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi> 81-82.</note>
            </head>
            <row>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="b">Copy</hi>
              </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="b">Date</hi>
              </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="b">Auction House</hi>
              </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="b">Price</hi>
              </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="b">Present Location</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>G</cell>
              <cell>20 Jan 1852</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>£8.15</cell>
              <cell>Library of Congress</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>B</cell>
              <cell>20 March 1882</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>£59</cell>
              <cell>Morgan</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>F</cell>
              <cell>20 Nov 1883</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>£124</cell>
              <cell>Harvard</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>C</cell>
              <cell>23 April 1890</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>£66</cell>
              <cell>YCBA<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p30u1" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="p30u1">*<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>Yale Center for British Art</note>
	</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>G</cell>
              <cell>30 March 1903</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>£307</cell>
              <cell>Library of Congress</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>B</cell>
              <cell>1 July 1924</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>£580</cell>
              <cell>Morgan</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>B</cell>
              <cell>10 April 1941</cell>
              <cell>Parke-Bernet</cell>
              <cell>$8,250</cell>
              <cell>Morgan</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A</cell>
              <cell>26 Feb 1956</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>£6,800</cell>
              <cell>YCBA</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>C</cell>
              <cell>29 March 1971</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>£24,000</cell>
              <cell>YCBA</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>E</cell>
              <cell>23 April 1999</cell>
              <cell>Sotheby’s</cell>
              <cell>$2,532,000</cell>
              <cell>Anon.</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>Copies D and J have not been sold at auction. Copy C went early to the British Museum Print Room,
and copy J was recently located by Detlef Dörrbecker in the Albertina Museum in Vienna.</p>
          <p>Sotheby’s has clearly been the auction house of choice for sales of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>
for the last 147 years. Note that Parke-Bernet was taken over by Sotheby’s of New York.</p>
          <p>The re-emergence of copy E and its record-breaking purchase price have had several long term
effects. First, the new buyers have the joy of possession. The sellers have the pleasure of having raised a
significant sum for their foundation. We suspect that this will raise Blake items higher in price; that this
is the point at which individual pages of color designs may be priced at $100,000 a sheet, which means that
even fewer scholars can ever hope to own even so much as a page of original Blake work.</p>
          <p>However, there is silver lining to the dark cloud of such monumental prices for Blake works.
Naturally, two and a half million dollars for a 24-page book attracted notice in the media. This in turn has
encouraged folk to hunt out forgotten family treasures to see if great-aunt Nellie’s treasured Blake picture
really is what she thought it was. Before the sale, Sotheby’s had calls about the value of some works
reputed to be by William Blake. I am sure that since the sale and attendant newspaper stories, there have been
further enquiries directed to Sotheby’s, as I know there have been enquiries to Jerry.</p>
          <p>Perhaps this will lead to the knowledge of yet another copy of something produced by Blake. Look
in your cupboards, trunks and boxes, ladies and gentlemen, I am ready to have my April adventures repeated.
Original Work by William Blake is Seriously Sought.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
