<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>33.3.grant</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">On First Encountering Blake’s Good Samaritans</title>
        <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1999/2000</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1999/2000</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">33.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1999/2000"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_33">
    <body>
    <pb id="p33-68" n="68"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-33-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">On First Encountering Blake’s Good Samaritans</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>John E. <name>Grant</name></docAuthor></byline>
		<q>
		The Vision of Christ that thou dost see<lb/>
		Is my Vision’s Greatest Enemy . . .<lb/>
		Thine is the Friend of All Mankind,<lb/>
		Mine speaks in parables to the Blind . . .<lb/>
		Thy Heaven doors are my Hell Gates.<lb/>
		<lb/>
		“The Everlasting Gospel” e<lb/>
		lines 1-2, 5-6, 8 <hi rend="i">N</hi> 34, E 524
		</q>
          <p>Blake’s sixty-eighth watercolor design for Edward Young’s <hi rend="i">The Complaint: or,
Night-Thoughts on Life, Death &amp;
                            Immortality</hi>, which occurs in “Night the Second: Time, Death,
                        Friendship,” is an unusual representation of Jesus’s
                        well-known parable that was spoken in response to a certain lawyer’s
                        series of tricky questions beginning: “What shall I do to inherit
                        eternal life?” (Luke 10:25-37). Of Blake’s two earlier
                        treatments of this subject, the sketch on page 84 of his Notebook was
                        prepared for possible inclusion in <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>:
                        the Man Who Had Fallen Among Thieves lies face down and is being passed by
                        on the other side by two who ought to have tried to rescue him; the
                        identities of these characters is problematic, but it is certain that no
                        Good Samaritan has yet appeared. Blake’s other “Good
                        Samaritan” picture was actually published, as an interlinear design
                        to the right of the third and fourth “Proverbs of Hell” on
                        plate 10 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> Here a
                        personage entering is distressed to discover a naked victim stretched out on
                        the ground and rushes to help while the spread-armed perpetrator is getting
                        away. This scene is also susceptible to interpretation as a variation on the
                        Cain and Abel story, to which Blake often refers and, on the titlepage of
                            <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>, plate 1, included a similar figure
                        of a flying spreadarmed villain in an Expulsion scene and also as a
                        spreadarmed Cain beneath the description of the theatrical
                        “Scene.” Further consideration of the issues in the Good
                        Samaritan designs is continued in the first footnote.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> The Notebook of William Blake: A Photographic and
                                    Typographic Facsimile</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, with the
                                assistance of Donald K. Moore. rev. ed. (New York: Readex, 1977) 84:
                                i.e., N 84. The editor conjectured that they are either “Good
                                Samaritans or highwaymen.” There could not, on the contrary,
                                be even one Good Samaritan in this pair of passers-by, who make no
                                attempt at benefaction. For <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                                    Hell</hi> plate 10 (as well as reproductions and other works of
                                illuminated printing): <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>,
                                annotated by David V. Erdman (Garden City, NY: Anchor
                                Press/Doubleday, 1974) 107. For <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>,
                                plate 1, <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> 381. Another relevant
                                spread-armed figure appears in <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 14, 
<hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> 111. There is no sign that this
                                figure bears any special relationship to the story of Cain. To
                                minimize the burdensome documentation I shall make few references to
                                the generally excellent new Blake Trust/Princeton UP edition of the
                                illuminated books. In footnote 22 I shall be more specific about
                                matters in Morton D. Paley’s 1991 volume, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi><p>The
best inference (pace Erdman) is that the pair of men passing by
                                the flattened victim, in the night scene of <hi rend="i">N</hi> 84,
                                represent the Priest and a highwayman derived from the good
                                Samaritan parable. These are the considerations: one of this pair of
                                passers-by in this night scene wears a robe, the other a sword. It
                                is not that Good Samaritans don’t carry swords. Around
                                Bassano, in the sixteenth century, they seem regularly to have done
                                so. Usually they also had a servant or dogs as part of their
                                equipage. Bad Samaritans (who are in the majority everywhere), we
                                may infer, did the same. Good Samaritans sometimes also wore robes
                                which, to our eyes, makes it hard to distinguish them from Priests.
                                But Good Samaritans, however equipped, never pass by on the other
                                side. It is a premise of the parable that not as much can be said
                                for Priests and Levites, for they were exempted by the Law from
                                performing such deeds of Charity if the victim seemed already dead;
                                see esp. Num. 19:11-22. The passer-by with the sword might indeed be
                                construed as the Levite, but in other representations he never
                                carries a sword or wears action clothing, or is even a fellow
                                traveller of the Priest. Therefore to make a Blakean inference, the
                                unlikely pair, the Priest and the Highwayman, have become
                                fellow-travellers and passers-by, and are bound for the Gates of
                                Hell, a destination not “For Children.”</p>
	<p>The text for “A Vision of the Last Judgment,” which in
                                    <hi rend="i">N</hi> 84 was written on all sides of the Good
                                Samaritan sketch for <hi rend="i">Gates</hi>, can hardly be
                                appreciated in Erdman or in any other printed text, save in the
                                facing transcription. Why did Blake (a book-designer) strive so hard
                                to contain <hi rend="i">these</hi> ideas on <hi rend="i">this</hi>
                                page that he contrived to set them forth in the form of a marginal
                                frame of words—and yet had to conclude with words carried
                                over to the next page, <hi rend="i">N</hi> 85? Those who would
                                equate this design-strategy with Blake’s usually expedient
                                strategy of simply getting his thoughts down on available paper in
                                the Notebook are missing something. Here I must point out that the
                                motto Blake slipped in, on either side at the middle of the Good
                                Samaritan picture, is a proverb of vision and a subtitle for the
                                section on ideas, rather than an exposition of the picture:
                                “A Last Judgment is neces[picture]sary because Fools
                                Flourish.”</p>
	<p>Blake did publish what I take to be a quite different pictorial
                                variation on the Good Samaritan as an interlinear design following
                                the sixth line of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,
                                plate 10. The central figure, who lies on her left side, is the
                                victim of the spread-armed villain with an indistinct companion, who
                                is making a getaway, at the left. At the right a figure rushes in,
                                waving his arms in distress, ready to act as the benefactor. Whether
                                because of the connection between this villain and those on the
                                first page of <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>, this should be
                                thought an allusion to the Good Samaritan story is, however,
                                debatable. This is one of many cruxes to be encountered in this
                                iconographic study where the vagaries of caricature and cartooning
                                must be acknowledged. Blake the artist was free to transform or
                                invert pictorial motifs and thus challenge the viewer to grasp a new
                                point. “And so Dear Christian Friends[,] how do you
                                do?” (E 507).</p>
	<p>Before making a final judgment as to the two encounters on the road,
                                in <hi rend="i">N</hi> 84 and <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 10, one should
                                ask: How would the Devil who, in the latter, is revealed in the
                                colophon picture as engaged in the spurious teaching-work of
                                deconstructing the scroll of holy writ, at the conclusion of the
                                “Proverbs of Hell,” expound these concise pictures?
                                With Proverb of Hell 67? Go thou and do otherwise.</p></note></p>
          <pb id="p33-69" n="69"/>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68:21E (illus. 2) Blake represents the
                        Samaritan as Jesus himself, kneeling in the act of offering the fully
                        conscious wounded victim a serpent-decorated vessel—an ellipsoid
                        lidded chalice or drinking goblet rather than a medicinal bottle or
                        flask—in an emotionally charged moment of eye-to-eye engagement that
                        occurs just <hi rend="i">before</hi> the traditional scene in which the
                        Samaritan treats the victim’s wounds with oil and wine. This
                        unsettling juxta-position of familiar and unexpected images, against a
                        back-drop of two large trees, living and dead, is further complicated by the
                        design’s (at best) oblique relationship to the line of Young’s
                        poem marked for illustration on this page: “Love, and Love only, is
                        the Loan for Love” (II, 571).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Though the 1797 edition bears the
                                extensive title: <hi rend="i">The Complaint, and the Consolation;
                                    or, Night Thoughts</hi>, this claims more than Young had
                                promised his serially-published four “Nights” would
                                deliver: “The Consolation” is Young’s later
                                (1745) title for the long terminal “Night the Ninth.”
                                But perhaps by employing “The Christian Triumph” as
                                the sole title for the fourth and last unit, with no indication of
                                other Nights to follow, and embellished with Blake’s 43
                                illustrations and an “Explanation of the Engravings”
                                publisher R. Edwards indicated that his 95-plus pages represented an
                                essential Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi><p>Except for the
unreliable color films of all the subjects that were
                                issued by EP Microform in the 1980s, the only generally good quality
                                reproductions of (practically) all the subjects are to be seen in
                                what I shall refer to in this essay as the Clarendon edition: i.e.,
                                    <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward
                                    Young’s Night Thoughts: A Complete Edition</hi>, eds.
                                John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, Michael J. Tolley, with co-ordinating
                                editor David V. Erdman (Oxford: Clarendon, 1980) 2 vols.
                                Blake’s 538 watercolors and drawings, which were made
                                recto/verso on the borders of 16 × 12-inch paper with
                                Young’s text set in, are reproduced on large paper and
                                numbered consecutively. Seventy-eight of the watercolors, including
                                the Good Samaritan picture, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68, are reproduced
                                in color, with captions, on unnumbered pages toward the end of
                                Volume II. Following are much-reduced color reproductions of two
                                different copies of the titlepages (only) for the four Nights in the
                                1797 edition, engraved by Blake and perhaps also colored by the
                                Blakes. Only one colored copy of Blake’s set of 43 prints,
                                that in the National Gallery of Victoria, Melbourne, has been (in
                                1988) reproduced in its entirety. Almost certainly, however, Blake
                                had no responsibility for its coloring. Peculiarities in the
                                coloration of the Good Samaritan print, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 43E,
                                indeed are among the strongest evidence that the not-unskillful
                                colorist did not understand Blake’s design. See Martin Butlin
                                and Ted Gott, <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Collection of the
                                    National Gallery of Victoria</hi>, Robert Raynor Publications in
                                Prints and Drawings, Number 3 (Melbourne: National Gallery of
                                Victoria, 1989) 157-78 and pls. 51:i-xliii. In his study of this
                                copy in the 1989 issue of <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin of Victoria</hi>
                                no. 30, 24-25, Michael J. Tolley saw no reason to question
                                Blake’s responsibility for the coloring, as I do here.</p>
	<p>The Clarendon edition also includes a section of engraving proofs for
                                the 1797 edition, among them the proof for the Good Samaritan
                                subject, which was utilized for page 129 in Night the Ninth of the
                                manuscript poem, <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four
                                    Zoas</hi>—though (unlike some other proofs) this print is
                                not significantly different from the published state. The second
                                volume concludes with a reproduction of an entire uncolored copy of
                                the 1797 edition of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, including the
                                (anonymous) two-page “Explanation of the Engravings,”
                                which is bound into most copies. The (reduced) reproduction of the
                                proof page used as p. 129 for <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> and the
                                accompanying commentary are both presented in high-quality facsimile
                                by Cettina Tramontano Magno and David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The
                                    Four Zoas</hi> by William Blake: <hi rend="i">A Photographic
                                    Facsimile of the Manuscript with Commentary on the
                                    Illuminations</hi> (Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 1987) 243; 94-95.
                                The 1963 Clarendon Press edition of <hi rend="i">Vala or the Four
                                    Zoas</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr., presents actual size
                                reproductions of the pages and thus gives a better sense of the
                                scale on which Blake chose to address ideal viewers of his own
                                epic-in-progress.</p>
	<p>Blake’s designs for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> are
                                summarized in catalogue form but only three of the watercolor
                                    designs—<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 117, <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                                196, and <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 510, and some related
                                drawings—are reproduced in Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The
                                    Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven and
                                London: Yale UP, 1981) 1: 178-255. I have chosen not to employ
                                Butlin’s catalogue prefatory number 330 (-334) because the
                                abbreviation <hi rend="i">NT</hi> seems more self-explanatory when
                                moving among the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs, which
                                often need to be distinguished from Blake’s other designs. To
                                Butlin’s citation of the relevant literature on <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68, the
Good Samaritan picture, should be added
                                Margoliouth’s important comments, which are discussed below.
                                Other pictorial works by Blake are identified by Butlin’s
                                catalogue and plate numbers, abbreviated as “cat.” and
                                “pl.”</p>
	<p>The reviews of the Clarendon edition were discussed and debated in
						<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 18.3 (1984-85) by myself and three
						reviewers: J.E. Grant, 155-81; W.J.T. Mitchell, 181-83; Morton D.
						Paley, 183-84; D. W. Dörrbecker, 185-90. The discussions were
						accompanied by good reproductions of these <hi rend="i">Night
						Thoughts</hi> designs (in illustrative sequence): <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 2
						(misidentified as <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1); <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1E (proof, 
						Harvard); <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6; <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 8; 
						<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 20; <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 78; <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 79; 
						<corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264;</corr> 
						<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 345 (often referred to herein); 
						<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 417.</p>
	<p>All quotations, including my epigraph, cite (as is customary)
						Blake’s texts as they appear in <hi rend="i">The Complete
						Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman,
						with commentary by Harold Bloom; newly rev. ed. (Berkeley and Los
						Angeles: U of California P, 1982, 1988); cited as E followed by page
						number: E 524.</p></note></p>
          <p>The most challenging feature of Blake’s portrayal of the Good
                        Samaritan’s appearance in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68 lies in the
                        characterization of the principals: why is the Samaritan represented as
                        Christ, proffering a serpent-decorated vessel, and why is the half-dead
                        victim straining to rise, his mouth open in a gasp or a shout, his right
                        hand bent back at the wrist, palm toward the would-be benefactor with
                        fingers raised in what appears to be a defensive gesture? The most extensive
                        interpreters of this watercolor (illus. 1) and its closely related engraving
                        (illus. 2) have put forward radically different accounts of what is going
                        on.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> 
                        H. M. Margoliouth (1954, 
<pb id="p33-70" n="70"/>
<figure n="BUT330.1.68.WC" rend="file" width="794" height="1000">
	<head>1 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68, II, p. 35. Watercolor. c.
                                1796.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum, Department of Prints and
                                Drawings.</figDesc>
</figure> 
                        1957), the first to call attention to the victim’s
                        rejection of his would-be benefactor’s remedy, acknowledges that the
                        Good Samaritan might be construed as Jesus Christ but unaccountably refrains
                        from affirming this identification. Robert N. Essick and Jenijoy La Belle
                        (1975), perhaps supposing the image of Christ to be self-evident, do not
                        name the benefactor, but they were the first to discuss the serpent-marked
                        vessel as a warning that recalls the legendary test of St. John and to
                        describe the victim as shunning “the offer of an ostensibly poisonous
                        gift.” The 1980 Clarendon edition records, in passing, the
                        Samaritan/Christ identification, and in 1987 Cettina Tramontano Magno and
                        David V. Erdman, linking the design (the proof employed in the manuscript
                        for <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 129) to Young’s observations
                        on friendship, <pb id="p33-71" n="71"/>
<figure n="night-thoughts-21e-ii-p37.033.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="408" height="500">
	<head>2 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 21E, II, p. 37. Uncolored
                                print.</head>
	<figDesc>Undated (c. 1796/97). Special Collections, University of Iowa
                                Libraries.</figDesc>
</figure> describe the victim as “hesitant to receive comfort from a
                        stranger—whose cup bears a serpent and whom Blake depicts as Jesus
                        himself (teller of the parable).” In 1990, as part of a more general
                        exposition of Blake’s depictions of Christ in the designs for Young,
                        I maintained on the basis of the watercolor that the focus of the design is
                        the tension between the donor and the rejector, who fears and distinctly
                        resists his rescuer’s ministrations. Christopher Heppner (1991, 1995,
                        see my n3), while agreeing that the Samaritan is Jesus Christ, emphatically
                        denies that the victim is rejecting the medication and maintains that the
                        serpent, construed as an Aesculapian emblem, can have only positive
                        connotations in this context. A more complex line of argument is needed, I
                        think, to cope with the symbolic density of Blake’s picture in its
                        two somewhat different versions, watercolor and engraving, in relation both
                        to iconographic and exegetical tradition and to Young’s text. The
                        enigma centers on the instant when, <hi rend="i">in the eyes of the
                            victim</hi>, the healing potion appears dangerous and the motives of the
                        rescuer are inferred to be dubious. This inquiry will eventually lead to
                        considerations of how several other key encounters in Blake are to be
                        understood. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Among the many features of the
                            Introduction to Volume I of the 1980 Clarendon edition is a
                            chronological “Checklist of Studies and Reproductions”
                            (72-84) published through 1977. Those of special interest to this study
                            are Margoliouth’s revised reprint of his 1954 essay (no. 34),
                            “Blake’s Drawings for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
                                Thoughts</hi>,” in <hi rend="i">The Divine Vision: Studies in
                                the Poetry and Art of William Blake</hi>, ed. Vivian de Sola Pinto
                            (London: Victor Gollancz, 1957) 191-204, and (no. 83) Robert Essick and
                            Jenijoy La Belle, eds., <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts or, The Complaint
                                and the Consolation: Illustrated by William Blake, Text by Edward
                                Young</hi> (New York: Dover, 1975), a reduced good-quality
                            reproduction of the 1797 edition together with an introduction and a
                            page-by-page commentary. Important discussions of <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                            68:21E published since the 1980 Clarendon edition include John E. Grant,
                            “Jesus and the Powers that Be in Blake’s Designs for
                            Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” in <hi rend="i">Blake and His
Bibles</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (West Cornwall, CT:
                            Locust Hill Press, 1990), esp. 77-79, and Christopher Heppner,
                            “The Good (in Spite of What You May Have Heard)
                            Samaritan,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 25 (1991): 64-69, revised and
                            condensed in chapter 6 of Heppner’s <hi rend="i">Reading
                                Blake’s Designs</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995), esp.
                            161-70. Unluckily neither Heppner nor I refers to Margoliouth’s
                            essay; in consequence, he debates some matters with me that I had taken
                            over from Margoliouth, without citation, as though they were commonly
                            understood and accepted, not requiring documentation.</note></p>
          <pb id="p33-72" n="72"/>
          <p>Because some recent matters of contention have concerned details that are not
                        treated identically in both the watercolor, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68, and the
                        subsequent engraving, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 21E, it should be clarifying, at
                        the outset, to study closely the two side by side (illus. 1 and 2),
                        beginning with the watercolor. In the foreground, at the foot of two huge
                        trees, the principals in the encounter are represented in profile. The
                        wounded, half-naked victim of highwaymen is agitated and attempting to rise,
                        his mouth wide open. He looks into the eyes of the Good Samaritan, who
                        appears to the viewer in the image of Christ, kneeling to offer and uncap a
                        serpent-decorated ellipsoid chalice. The Samaritan-Jesus’s mouth
                        falls open, as if in surprise, distress, or chagrin at the negative
                        reception his beneficence is receiving. In no other image of Christ created
                        by Blake, including the engraving of this subject, does the mouth of Jesus
                        fall open in this way. Also perhaps because Blake’s Christ seldom
                        elsewhere kneels to anyone, commentators have refrained from identifying
                        this Samaritan as Jesus.</p>
          <p>Dead branches from the tree at left point down toward the stone that had
                        supported the victim; by contrast, leafy branches from the bifurcated tree
                        at right luxuriate on the side of the rescuer. The head-down wriggling snake
                        embossed upon the Samaritan’s chalice, which presumably contains the
                        curative wine or oil mentioned in the parable, is turned so as to be fully
                        visible to the viewer though perhaps not to the victim; the snake’s
                        head, with open mouth, twists back toward the donor. In the background, the
                        Samaritan’s outsized horse is tethered to an (improbably) low branch
                        of the tree at right, and is browsing on grass beside the road. Farther on,
                        where the road drops out of sight, two crossed palm trees rise from the
                        declivity. On either side of these trees are travelers who are departing
                        downward, perhaps by different routes, to Jericho, already famous as
                        “the city of palm trees,” which is mentioned by name in the
                        parable. The traveler at left, with a walking stick, is presumably the
                        Levite who had “looked on” the wounded man before he, like the
                        Priest before him, “passed by on the other side”; this man is
                        still looking back toward the encounter that is taking place in the
                        foreground, while the traveler at right, presumably the Priest, pays no
                        attention as he hastens downward. The Levite’s view, now that the
                        Samaritan has arrived, we may infer, is probably blocked by the huge grazing
                        horse. Whether or not the Priest and the Levite may rejoin the same
                        invisible curving road, they do not go as fellow-travelers down to
                        Jericho.</p>
          <p>Blake altered this design in a number of particulars when he made the
                        engraving, 21E, for page 37 of the 1797 edition of <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> (illus. 2), correcting, for example, the impossibly long
                        legs of the victim in the watercolor version by covering the area of the
                        protruding right foot with an extended roll of cloth. Other altered details,
                        such as the more oak-like rendering of the bark of the tree at the right and
                        the addition of varied fruits to the crossed palm trees in the background,
                        perhaps have interpretive significance; the distinctive detail of the dead
                        branch hanging down from the background tree at left is essentially
                        unchanged from the watercolor to the engraving, though now, not clustered
                        with shorter dead branches, but mingled with leaves perhaps issued by the
                        living tree, the dead branch tends to stand out more starkly as a sign of a
                        dead tree. The most significant differences are in the faces of the two
                        principals: the engraving has been altered to remove the indications in the
                        watercolor of their <hi rend="i">mutual</hi> shock of recognition. The Man
                        Fallen Among Thieves still raises his hand to reject the gift, but the
                        suggestion of a second wound, visible above his fingers, on his redrawn
                        torso, has been removed. His face has also been redrawn, with a larger nose
                        in exact profile and with the expressive mouth re-shaped, so that he is
                        speaking to, not shouting at, his would-be rescuer. While still resisting,
                        he now seems to be talking things over. The Samaritan Jesus Christ of the
                        engraving encounters the victim-refuser with composure, lips hardly open, as
                        he looks intently into the face of the man who is in need of help. Here the
                        Samaritan takes the part of a healer, or a therapist, well-composed to deal
                        with resistance from a patient who refuses the medicine that is being given
                        for his own good.</p>
          <p>The dramatic tableau of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68: 21E confronts viewers with a
                        scene for which they must provide a significant part of the context, not
                        least in identifying the principals. The predominantly Anglican audience for
                        Young’s poem and for Blake’s designs is presumed to be quite
                        prepared to recognize not only the parable but a traditional image of Christ
                        in this unexpected context. There is ample foundation for this
                        identification in biblical exegesis: in the fifth century St. Augustine and
                        St. Ambrose, building upon an older exposition of Origen, had developed the
                        idea that it was Christ himself who was, or was figured as, the Good
                        Samaritan. As St. Augustine wrote, “even God himself, our Lord,
                        desired to be called our neighbor. For our Lord Jesus Christ points to
                        Himself under the figure of the man who brought aid to him who was lying
                        half dead on the road, wounded and abandoned by the robbers.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Post-Augustinian interpreters extended
                        the typological allegory to identify the Man Fallen Among Thieves as Adam
                        and the thieves as Satan, etc. It follows that the Priest and Levite, as
                        Jews, represent the Old Law, the wine employed in the cure is the Eucharist,
                        and the inn to which the victim is taken to recuperate is the Church. The
                        main allegorical points of this interpretation of the parable are wholly in
                        accord with the “<hi rend="i">spiritual</hi>” exposition of
                        the story as quoted at length by Thomas Coke, and, as Heppner points out,
                        with the interpretation of Matthew 
<pb id="p33-73" n="73"/>
Henry, two
                        leading evangelical commentators whose works were read in the late
                        eighteenth century.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> On Christian Doctrine</hi>, trans. J. F. Shaw, in 
<hi rend="i">The Works of Aurelius Augustine</hi>, ed. Marcus Dods, 9
                            vols., 3rd ed. (Edinburgh: T. &amp; T. Clark, 1883) 1: 33. See also
                            Origen, <hi rend="i">Homilies on Luke, Fragments on Luke</hi>, trans.
                            <corr type="emend">Joseph T. Lienhard</corr> (Washington: Catholic U. of America, c. 1992), esp.
                            Homily 6, 23-27 and Homily 34, 137-41.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See <hi rend="i">Matthew Henry’s
                                    Commentary on the Whole Bible</hi> (c. 1707) (Peabody, MA:
                                Hendrickson, 1991) 5: 552-55. See also Stephen L. Wailes, 
<hi rend="i">Medieval Allegories of Jesus’ Parables</hi>
                                (Berkeley: U of California P, 1987) 209-14.
                            <p>For a perspicacious modern account of the parable, see the concluding
                                section of Andrew J. McKenna, <hi rend="i">Violence and Difference:
                                    Girard, Derrida, and Deconstruction</hi> (Urbana and Chicago: U
                                of Illinois P, 1992) 211-21: “The Law Before the Good
                                Samaritan.” McKenna liberates the parable from construal as
                                an exhortation to do good deeds by emphasizing the predicament of
                                the lawyer and Jesus’s other hearers as they are made to
                                acknowledge that a non-Jew of an abhorred kindred race has shown
                                himself the superior of high-ranking Jews in keeping the
                            law.</p></note></p>
          <p>But in the visual arts, from the Reformation on, this representation of the
                        parable disappears: Blake was probably the first artist since Heemskerck in
                        1565 to depict the Good Samaritan as Jesus Christ.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Unlike Heemskerck, however, who designed a print
                        that switches the figuration to the exegetes’ allegorical level of
                        interpretation to depict the act of healing as a shower of blood raining
                        down on the victim from Christ upon the cross, Blake depicts Jesus in the
                        guise of an ordinary wayfarer, doubtless viewed by the victim to be a
                        Samaritan, offering aid by the roadside, according with the literal level of
                        the parable. The extreme rarity of the Jesus-Samaritan identification in
                        Protestant art, particularly among pictures that were made in the eighteenth
                        century or that were then prominent in England—most notably, those of
                        Hogarth (illus. 8) and Jacopo Bassano—leads to the inference that
                        Blake had a particular point to make 
<pb id="p33-74" n="74"/>
by returning
                        to this medieval and Renaissance symbolism. Although it is odd that the
                        author of the 1797 “Explanation of the Engravings,” who
                        readily identifies the other obvious images of “Christ” or
                        “the Saviour” in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1:31E, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 121:34E, 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 143:38E, and <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        148:40E, is silent on this point, it is safe to assume that Blake expected
                        his viewers to recognize what the victim himself does not, could not, know:
                        the Samaritan who has come to his aid is the Messiah. 
<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Though I am aware of no full catalogue of Good
                                Samaritan pictures, Christopher Wright’s <hi rend="i">The
                                    World’s Master Paintings: From the Early Renaissance to
                                    the Present</hi> Day (London: Routledge, 1992) lists 43 European
                                paintings on this theme, with a guide to their locations worldwide
                                (see 2: 4, Index of Titles). But in his tally of eighteenth-century
                                Good Samaritans Wright neglects to list Hogarth’s famous wall
                                painting on the staircase of St. Bartholomew’s Hospital and
                                does list several pictures by artists nearly anonymous. Wright,
                                since he begins after the Medieval period, mentions only a few of
                                the 18 pictures listed by Louis Réau, <hi rend="i">Iconographie De L’Art
Chrétien, Tome Second:
                                    Iconographie De La Bible</hi> II <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Nouveau
                                    Testament</hi></corr> (Paris: Presses Universitaires de France, 1957)
                                331-33. Réau also lists a number of Good Samaritans in
                                illuminated manuscripts, including two in France which I have not
                                seen, that feature Christ in the role of the rescuer. So far as the
                                study of Blake is concerned, what matters most are representations
                                of the Good Samaritan by British artists, or by other artists whose
                                works were readily accessible to a Londoner of Blake’s time,
                                or by artists (particularly those Blake felt strongly about) whose
                                works were readily available in prints. Among those of particular
                                interest are the engraving after Marten de Vos by Johannes Sadeler
                                (the First, c. 1550-1600), one of four master engravers named in
                                Blake’s “Public Address” (E 574), which
                                provides good examples of the common elements that had become
                                conventional in pictorial representations of the scene: the
                                Samaritan in a turban or other Middle Eastern headdress, the victim
                                unconscious or nearly so, the horse, the road, the departing Priest
                                and Levite, and the city in the distance. Serial engravings (e.g.,
                                two sets by Heemskerck, one by Aldegrever) commonly feature three or
                                more of the following episodes: the robbery, the passing of the
                                Priest and Levite, the Samaritan’s medical intervention, the
                                loading of the victim onto the beast, the journey to the inn, the
                                arrival at the inn, the Good Samaritan’s negotiation with the
                                innkeeper, either on arrival or at his departure the next day.
                                Heemskerck, whose work Blake placed at the same level as that of
                                Michelangelo, Raphael, Dürer, and Julio Romano (G. E.
                                Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [Oxford: Clarendon,
                                1969] 422, 433, 448) produced two four-print sets on the Good
                                Samaritan theme: the 1549 series depicts the robbers leaving the
                                traveler half dead, the Priest and the Levite passing by while the
                                Samaritan tends the traveler, the Samaritan carrying the victim to
                                the inn, and the Samaritan paying the innkeeper in advance. The 1565
                                series presents almost the same episodes, but all are treated
                                allegorically: the robbers are Cupido, Voluptas, and Error (Desire,
                                Lust, and Error); the Priest and the Levite, as Aaron and Moses,
                                represent Jewish ceremony and law; the healing is performed not by a
                                Samaritan traveler but directly at the allegorical level, as by
                                Christ on the cross raining blood on the victim’s wounds;
                                finally, the risen Christ (carrying his cross) pays not the
                                innkeeper but St. Peter, who holds the keys to the Church, and the
                                payment is in the form of the Gospels and Epistles, reproduced in
                                    <hi rend="i">The Illustrated Bartsch</hi>, and more usefully in
                                Ilja M. Veldman, comp. and Ter Luijten, eds., <hi rend="i">The New
                                    Hollstein: Dutch &amp; Flemish Etchings, Engravings and
                                    Woodcuts / 1459-1700 / Maarten van Heemskerck</hi>, Part I
                                (Roosendaal, the Netherlands: Koninklijke van Poll, 1993) 134-36.
                                Heemskerck also made a fascinating major painting, <hi rend="i">Landscape with
the Good Samaritan</hi>, which was not engraved.
                                Thomas Kerrich in <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of the Prints Which Have
                                    Been Engraved after Martin Heemskerck, or Rather, An Essay
                                    Towards Such a Catalogue</hi> (London, J. Rodwell, 1829) does
                                not usually specify where prints are located but offers clear
                                descriptions of them.
                            <p>Probably the most distinguished Italian Renaissance paintings of the
                                Good Samaritan in England in Blake’s time are two versions of
                                the subject by Jacopo da Ponte, Il Bassano, one at Hampton Court
                                since 1630, the other in Joshua Reynolds’s collection since
                                1772, now in the National Gallery, repr. as figs. 83-86 in Eduardo
                                Arslan, <hi rend="i">I Bassano</hi> (Milan: Ceschina, 1960). But for
                                an English audience in Blake’s time, the picture that comes
                                closest to providing a universally recognized interpretive standard
                                is Hogarth’s huge mural, <hi rend="i">The Good Samaritan</hi>
                                (repr. except for left quarter in Mary Webster, <hi rend="i">Hogarth</hi>
[1978; London: Studio Vista / Danbury, CT: Master
                                Works, 1984] 71-73, 78), a companion to his <hi rend="i">The Pool of
                                    Bethesda</hi>, both of which were painted for the grand
                                staircase of St. Bartholomew’s Hospital, not far from St.
                                Paul’s, and easily accessible to Blake not only in the
                                original but in the 1772 print by Ravenet and Delatre (illus. 8),
                                published in Boydell’s splendid 1790 assemblage of
                                Hogarth’s work, which included Blake’s own print of
                                    <hi rend="i">The Beggar’s Opera.</hi></p>
	<p>For the Bassano brothers see also Erica Pan, ed. <hi rend="i">Jacopo
                                    Bassano l’ incisione</hi> (Bassano del Grappa: Museo
                                Civico, 1992). The posthumous print, no. 60 <hi rend="i">Buon
                                    Samaritano</hi>, is attributed to “I Bassan, p.”
                                i.e., Jacopo dal Ponte as designer (<hi rend="i">not</hi> his
                                brother or son Francesco, as the catalogue declares) and signed by
                                Boel as engraver. The tree beside the head of the victim is
                                bifurcated; the trunk closer to the head of the victim was cut off;
                                the other rises and flourishes. Also no. 120, <hi rend="i">Buon
                                    Samaritano</hi>, an eighteenth-century print of another Jacopo
                                Bassano painting which belonged to Reynolds and is now in the
                                National Gallery, London, catalogued as no. 277; it features the
                                loading of the victim, after treatment, upon the Samaritan’s
                                beast. Two seventeenth-century pictures that variously treat
                                problems of recognition in the Good Samaritan story are a painting
                                by Luca Giordano, in which the Samaritan looks villainous but acts
                                charitably to the unconscious victim, and a print by Rembrandt,
                                dated 1633 (illus. 9); these will be discussed below.</p></note></p>
          <p>Heppner is right to emphasize the importance of the dramatic framework of the
                        story in Luke 10:25ff., which presents the parable as Jesus’s adroit
                        response to a sharp lawyer’s trick question on a vexed point in the
                        Torah. Jesus, recognizing that this “questioner who sits so
                        sly” has no sincere concern for eternal life, about which he had
                        pretended to inquire, responds to the legalistic interrogation with a
                        supra-legal test-case that requires the ostensive scholar of Jewish law,
                        presuming to piety, to judge as if <hi rend="i">he</hi> were the victim
                        whether the heterodox Samaritan were a more faithful observer of the law
                        than either the Priest or the Levite—or at least of that part of the
                        law that commands a person to love his neighbor as himself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Once the questioner has submitted the answer
                        required by the parable, Jesus abruptly switches the perspective from the
                        victim to the rescuer, and instructs the devotee of Jewish law to adopt the
                        despised Samaritan as a model, and extend neighborly love even to strangers
                        and enemies: “Go and do thou likewise.” <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> This law
was spoken by the Lord to Moses in
                            Leviticus 19:18; curiously, Matthew Henry did not mention this
                            cross-reference, though he understood the sense well enough. Similarly,
                            Henry deplored the “cruelty” of the Priest and the Levite
                            in passing by “on the other side” on their way between
                            Jerusalem and Jericho, rather than exercising the
                            “charity” that the “half-dead” victim
                            required. Henry did not attempt to explain the insensitivity of these
                            clerics, though other commentators had done so, and Blake may well have
                            been aware both of the relevant biblical text and of Renaissance prints
                            that show the parts of the passers-by taken by Moses and Aaron. In
                            Numbers 19 the Lord told these two of the curious process of
                            purification that is to be followed in cleansing from sin. Then,
                            19:11-22, the Lord explains at length the pollution that occurs when
                            anyone has contact with any dead person, including, it goes without
                            saying, one who dies in the faith of Moses and Aaron. Since the waylaid
                            victim had been left “half-dead,” it was hardly surprising
                            that the Priest and the Levite would not risk ritual pollution by
                            ministering to him. At a safe distance they could hardly tell his exact
                            condition, and what would be the consequences for their clerical
                            obligations even if he were still alive when sighted but then died while
                            in their care? Prudence would dictate that they have somewhere to get to
                            and accede to their duties.</note></p>
          <p>Reviewing most of the relevant biblical texts about the Jews’ contempt
                        for the Samaritans, Heppner goes some distance toward recovering the force
                        of Jesus’s representation of a hated Samaritan as the beneficent
                        “neighbor” of a Jew. One additional episode involving
                        Samaritans—not cited by Heppner—bears on the case: in
                        Jesus’s encounter with the Woman at the Well, his request for water
                        is such a shocking violation of social taboo that the woman responds
                        suspiciously, “How is it that thou, being a Jew, asketh drink of 
<figure n="night-thoughts-43e-p95.033.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="407" height="500">
	<head>3 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 43E, p. 95. Uncolored
                                print.</head>
	<figDesc>Undated (c. 1797). University of Iowa Libraries.</figDesc>
</figure> me, which am a woman of Samaria, for the Jews have no dealings
                        with the Samaritans” (John 4:9). The cultural tensions built into the
                        parable are heightened and further complicated by Blake’s pictorial
                        identification of the Samaritan as Christ. Ethnically, of course, Jesus of
                        Nazareth was not a Samaritan, but because of his unorthodox behavior he was
                        inferentially identified as one by some of his suspicious compatriots:
                        “‘Say we not well that thou art a Samaritan, and hast a
                        devil?’ Jesus answered, ‘I have not a devil; but I honor my
                        Father, and ye do dishonor me’” (John 8:48-49). In this
                        exchange, as the early commentators noted, Jesus denies only that he has a
                        devil, <hi rend="i">not</hi> that he is a “Samaritan.” This
                        silence in the text is meaningful; if it caught Blake’s attention, it
                        may well have offered scriptural reinforcement for his use of the symbolic
                        Christ/Good Samaritan identification in the Augustinian exegetical tradition
                        engaged in his reworking of the parable.</p>
          <p>Given that this Good Samaritan is enacted by Jesus Christ, what should an
                        eighteenth-century Christian audience make of the serpent-marked chalice in
                        which he proffers oil or wine, and why would the victim resist being
                        helped?</p>
          <p>The snake-decorated lidded cup—more properly, a ciborium—is
                        Blake’s most striking departure from iconographic convention. Artists
                        other than Blake usually depict the Samaritan’s vessel as a flask,
                        not a chalice, and no other artist marks it with a serpent. There are no
                        snakes, decorative or otherwise, in Sadeler’s Good Samaritan print,
                        for example, or in other depictions of the parable by painters or 
<pb id="p33-75" n="75"/>
graphic artists such as Veronese, the Bassani,
                        Heemskerck, Pencz, Aldegrever, van de Velde, met de Bles, Fetti, Merian,
                        Rembrandt and his followers, Ribera, Teniers the Younger, Bourdon, Luca
                        Giordano, or, in the English school, Hogarth, Hayman, Highmore and West; or
                        in emblem books from Ripa to Hertel; or in a sculpture done by Flaxman in
                        1813-15. It is noteworthy that none of the later nineteenth-century artists
                        who address the Good Samaritan theme: Delacroix, Van Gogh, Watts, et al.,
                        treated it at all as Blake had done in 1797.</p>
          <p>Despite Heppner’s numerous examples of the positive attributes of
                        snakes in Greek mythology and the ingenuity of his argument for Aesculapius
                        as a pagan type of Christ, the primary association of serpent, in a
                        Christian context, is with evil, not healing; the <hi rend="i">Harper’s Bible
Dictionary</hi> (1985) provides a convenient
                        summary of support for this self-evident point. Even if it were supposed
                        that the victim is knowledgeable enough to identify the snake as an emblem
                        of the Greek cult of Aesculapius, as maintained by Heppner, the grounds for
                        refusal would remain the same.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref> Whether
                        the proffered cure be understood as Samaritan, or Aesculapian, or
                        Gentile-exotic (something from Ancient Britain, say), or proto-Christian,
                        the alien potion or ointment would be perceived as an abhorrence by an
                        observant Jew. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi>. An able art-historical
                            account of Aesculapius not mentioned by Heppner is J[an] Schoten, <hi rend="i">The
Rod and the Serpent of Askelepios</hi> (Amsterdam,
                            London, New York: Elsevier, 1967). See esp. chapters 6 and 9 for some
                            remarkable Christian permutations of the symbols associated with the
                            Greek god. Lemprière (1788) on “<hi rend="i">Aesculapius</hi>” and James
Hall, <hi rend="i">Dictionary of
                                Subjects and Symbols in Art</hi>, rev. ed. (New York: Harper &amp;
                            Row, 1979), mention little that could be employed to render this Blake
                            serpent redemptive.</note></p>
          <p>It makes no difference to my argument whether the snake were depicted as a
                        mere decorative motif or as a live reptile in the act of striking: Christian
                        tradition, following Jewish tradition, encodes nearly all manifestations of
                        the serpentine form in Christian art as evil. The chief Gospel exception is
                        Jesus’s appropriation of the curative emblem of Moses’s brazen
                        serpent as the antitype and prophecy of his own crucifixion (John 3:14, as
                        noted by Heppner). Disentangling this notion in relation to the watercolor
                        entitled <hi rend="i">Moses Erecting the Brazen Serpent</hi>, based on Num.
                        21: 6-9 (Butlin, cat. 447, pl. 521) is a challenge. But even in the night
                        meeting with “the rich learned Pharisee” (E 518), Nicodemus
                        (which is like the dialogue with the lawyer in that it concludes with
                        promise of “eternal life”), the evil nature of serpent qua
                        serpent is assumed; that is why the miraculous brazen serpent is needed as
                        an antidote. Apart from this one reference to Moses’s miracle and the
                        injunction to be “wise as serpents, and harmless as doves”
                        (Matthew 10:16), whenever Jesus himself uses imagery of
                        snakes—whether denouncing his contemporaries as a “generation
                        of vipers” (e.g., Luke 3:7), asking his hearers whether they would
                        give a serpent to a child who had asked for a fish (Luke 11:12), or
                        promising the faithful that they, too, will have power over serpents (Luke
                        10:17-19)—the negative import of this usage is clear. Since apostolic
                        times (e.g., Romans 16:20), it has been understood that Christ, as the
                        Second Adam, fulfills in his crucifixion the prophecy of Genesis 3:15 by
                        crushing the serpent’s head. This is shown in the penultimate or
                        final designs in the three <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> series (Butlin,
                        cat. 529.<hi rend="i">11</hi>, pl. 642; cat. 536.<hi rend="i">11</hi>, pl.
                        655; cat. 537.<hi rend="i">3</hi>, pl. 659). These scenes forecast 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 76, to be discussed later, in which, however,
                        the serpent does not figure. I believe the preponderance of iconographical
                        and biblical evidence, supported by the Genesis-to-Revelation identification
                        of the serpent with Satan in exegetical tradition, weighs overwhelmingly
                        against Heppner’s positive interpretation of the snake, in
                        Blake’s Good Samaritan scene, as an emblem of Aesculapius.</p>
          <p>There is a troublesome Young text early in Night the Second, which occurs on
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 41, p. 8, unrelated to that Blake design, and on p.
                        20 of the 1797 published edition, which lacks any design, that declares that
                        Aesculapius does not figure in the friendly kind of concern engaged by
                        Young’s poem: 
						<q> For what calls <hi rend="i">thy</hi> Disease 
<hi rend="i">Lorenzo</hi>?! not<lb/>
 For <hi rend="i">Esculapian</hi>,
                            but for <hi rend="i">Moral</hi> Aid.<lb/>
 (II, 50-51) </q></p>
          <p>Heppner (1995, 169) attempts to enlist these lines <hi rend="i">for</hi> his
                        Aesculapian theory about <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 21E:68, but their plain sense
                        works directly <hi rend="i">against</hi> the interpretive line he wishes to
                        maintain for the picture occurring 17 or 27 pages further into Night the
                        Second. Moreover, Young’s exhortations in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>:21E,
                        p. 37, lines 556 and especially 572, which directly follows the asterisked
                        line 
						<q> *Love and love only, is the loan for love, </q>
are again addressed
                        to “Lorenzo.” It follows that, in Blake’s tableau,
                        Lorenzo corresponds to the Man Fallen Among Thieves, who is refusing the
                        proffered cure, while Young the advice-giver who wishes to provide Moral
                        Aid, is playing Christ. Aesculapius could be of no help here.</p>
          <p>The more specific configuration of serpent-and-cup, as noted by Essick and
                        LaBelle, refers in Christian iconography to a central episode in the legend
                        of St. John the Evangelist (or the Divine). As a test of faith by the
                        Emperor Domitian, the saint was made to drink from a poisoned cup that had
                        killed two other men or, in another version of the story, the compelling
                        authority is the high priest of Diana of Ephesus. John, the only apostle to
                        meet the ordeals of martyrdom without losing his life, proves immune to the
                        drink, and the poison, in the form of a serpent, slithers harmlessly
                            away.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> In Jacobus de Voragine, <hi rend="i">The
                                Golden Legend</hi>, trans. Granger Ryan and Helmut Ripperger (New
                            York: Arno, 1969), re 27 December 61-62, the story of the test of St.
                            John by poison is told without employment of the serpent, but there are
                            countless representations of St. John holding a cup containing a
                            serpent, both as a solitary saint and among assemblages of saints, as,
                            for example, in Memling’s 1479 <hi rend="i">The Mystic Marriage
                                of St. Catherine.</hi> This legend of St. John is clearly told in
                            Hall, <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Subjects and Symbols in
                            Art.</hi></note></p>
          <pb id="p33-76" n="76"/>
          <p>It is also notable that Blake departs from convention in representing the
                        Samaritan’s proffered container of liquid as a lidded goblet, thus
                        signifying that this is a drinking vessel rather than the oil vial or wine
                        flagon that would be indicated at the literal level of the story. Other
                        artists portrayed the Samaritan equipped with a narrow-necked vessel,
                        clearly a portable medicine bottle, from which he pours oil or wine directly
                        into the (usually unconscious) victim’s wounds, or applies the balm
                        or antiseptic with his hands. By contrast, Blake’s covered vessel,
                        held up directly in the conscious victim’s line of sight, more
                        forcibly and obviously recalls the exegetical tradition that identifies the
                        Samaritan’s cure with the taking of communion: the ciborium is the
                        receptacle that holds the consecrated wafers of the Eucharist. Offered as a
                        drinking vessel, this representation of the sacrament might seem to take
                        Luther’s side in the Chalice Controversy, which supported the
                        Protestant practice of making the cup as well as the Host available to
                        laymen—though Blake, an unchurched dissenter who was baptized,
                        married, and buried by Anglican clergy, was unlikely to have been concerned
                        with such disputes of the Reformation and Counter-Reformation. The point is
                        that the Samaritan’s presentation of this peculiar vessel, at eye
                        level, indicates that the cure it contains is to be taken by mouth. And as
                        the Samaritan is only just about to open the vessel—its contents are
                        not yet being poured out, as in most representations of this episode by
                        other artists—the conscious victim is able to exercise a right of
                        first refusal to the ministrations of his rescuer.</p>
          <p>Too exclusive attention to the drama of the encounter between the men
                        represented in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21 E may obscure deeper issues that
                        ought to be considered along with the Good Samaritan parable: How should
                        Charity and Faith be related to good deeds? Blake wrote this memorandum in
                        his Notebook: “Jesus . . . makes a Wide Distinction between the Sheep
                        &amp; the Goats[;] consequently he is Not Charitable” (N 72, E
                        695).</p>
          <p>Later he inserted this aphorism, a virtual title, on either side of his
                        sketch for the very Good Samaritan problem that was finally excluded from
                            <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise:</hi> “A Last Judgment is
                        Neces [“Emblem 54”] sary because Fools flourish” (N 84,
                        E 561).</p>
          <p>Why, it should be questioned, if Jesus was “Not Charitable” did
                        he play the Good Samaritan? And what is to become of “Fools”
                        at <hi rend="i">the</hi> “Last Judgment”? Two answers Blake
                        would have thought to be profoundly anti-Christian are raised in
                        Counter-Reformation art that Blake would have been aware of through prints
                        containing similar themes if not through the particular paintings I shall
                        mention. In two recent exhibition catalogues, several pictures are featured
                        that show Christ either as exterminator or as a cosmic reservoir 
<figure n="BUT330.1.380.WC" rend="file" width="787" height="1000">
	<head>4 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 380, VIII, p. 34. Watercolor.
                                c. 1797.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum, Department of Prints and
                                Drawings..</figDesc>
</figure> of blood.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> The most extreme
                        case of the former, by (that “Fool” N 38 E 513) Rubens,
                        exhibits a Christ who brandishes Jupiter’s thunderbolts and is about
                        to terminate the whole world but is just restrained by saints or angels.
                        This image of Christ had been recklessly escalated from a less
                        indiscriminate role (bad enough, Blake would have objected) assigned him by
                        Scarcellino in which Christ is poised to launch his missiles down to wipe
                        out (only) three women, those deplorable Vices: Lust, Avarice, and Pride.
                        The saint-filled titles assigned to such pictures deflect attention from the
                        Messiah as ominous would-be destroyer to those exceptional personages who
                        attempt to restrain him. Thus they abet in the mental processes that make
                        holy war seem acceptable, indeed Christian. Ironically both Scarcellino and
                            <pb id="p33-77" n="77"/>
Rubens enlisted the raised right arm of
                        Michelangelo’s Christ at the Last Judgment and filled his hand with
                        exterminating weaponry. As though to avoid the implication that, at the Last
                        Judgment, his Judge might employ such abominable weaponry, Blake made his
                        Judge even-handed. In the final version (Butlin, cat. 645, pl. 871) his
                        Christ raises his arms equally and horizontally, no higher than when he
                        underwent the Crucifixion. At the End the issue is Bounty, not Vengeance.
                            <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See Allen Duston and <corr type="emend">Arnold
                                Nesselrath,</corr> <hi rend="i">Angels From the Vatican: The Invisible Made
                                    Visible</hi> (Alexandria, VA: Art Services International, 1998)
                                esp. 300-03. Also Hans Vlieghe, <hi rend="i">Saints I</hi> in 
<hi rend="i">Corpus Rubenianum: Ludwig Burchard</hi> (Arcade, 1972)
                                no. 88 (fig. 151) and no. 100 (fig. 173). See also James Clifton,
                                    <hi rend="i">The Body of Christ in the Art of Europe and New
                                    Spain, 1150-1800</hi> (Munich and New York: Prestel, 1997) esp.
                                nos. 52, 55, 57 and 70.
                            <p>Bloody-mindedness easily escalates to visions of “The Scourge
                                of God” and thence to God as scourge, which Blake thought was
                                theologically abominable. In Hertel’s Ripa of 1762, for
                                example, no. 71 features “The Scourge of God,” as
                                Atilla the Hun, who brandishes a whip while displaying, in his other
                                hand, both a fiery brand (like that of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi>) and
a pair of arrow-tipped thunderbolts. Blake, in
                                (what became) the terminal design for the engraved version of Night
                                the Third, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 30E (cf. 108) reveals that Death,
                                the “KING OF TERRORS,” is, according to Young,
                                “the PRINCE of PEACE”; he is stretched out with his
                                mysterious scroll while, at the same time, emitting some 17
                                arrowheads downward, against Mankind. The subordinate Thunder God
                                tries to explain the same idea (i.e., by indicating that he is not
                                the ultimate authority for the bolts that fall) to Young the poet in
                                Night the Fourth: <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 133:36E. As we shall see, it
                                is toward this vision of an abominable God to which Truth points in
                                    <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 43E (illus. 3 of the watercolor), the last
                                of the published engravings.</p>
	<p>How Blake redesigned the hinge-pictures between the end of Night the
                                Third <hi rend="i">NT</hi>:109, and the beginning of Night the
                                Fourth, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 110, for the 1797 edition shows that he
                                aimed to critique the code of Christian violence which Young had
                                endorsed without much reflection. <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1, the
                                frontispiece of Volume I, became 31E, the titlepage “The
                                Christian Triumph,” as the last unit of these <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi> So positioned it becomes more clear that
                                the two angels who are present at the Resurrection of Jesus are
                                (like Swedenborg), wholly absorbed with “the linen clothes
                                folded up” (cf. E 34). In this replacement for <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 110, 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 31E, Young, who had at first
                                appeared as the pilgrim with the book, becomes the angel who is
                                kneeling to the linen clothes that enwrap his arm. His Emanation,
                                the woman who looks up to the New Jerusalem, has lowered her
                                companionate gaze to the empty grave, which the ascending Jesus
                                Christ is leaving behind. Since these spirits were hardly witnesses,
                                neither is yet ready to be a follower.</p>
	<p>For the end of Night the Third the great god Death, who was
                                comparatively mild in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 108, was in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
30E reassigned the terminal position, given a larger
                                armory of arrows and a horrendous Hebrew inscription on his scroll,
                                and cued to Young’s preposterous sentiment. “This KING
                                OF TERRORS is the PRINCE OF PEACE.” At the conclusion of
                                Volume I, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 263, Death is defeated and bows down
                                to the resurrecting Christ. But in the 1797 edition, for all we are
                                shown, the great god Death retains his supremacy above “The
                                Christian Triumph.” The best Truth can do in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 43E is to
show us that, until now the god of this
                                world, Jupiter, is unremoved.</p></note></p>
          <p>The other Counter-Reformation motif, the Fountain of Blood, is hardly less
                        appalling. As “The Fountain of Elijah” or “<hi rend="i">Fons Pietatis</hi>”
Jesus stands on one side in heaven, Mary on
                        the other; he spurts blood, she milk, into a fountain atop which Elijah
                        stands holding a fiery sword and around which the Church Fathers trample
                        upon their adversaries while Carmelite Nuns express their devotions. There
                        were also pictures that focus on Jesus: <hi rend="i">Christ in a
                            Chalice</hi> (no. 57), in which he stands, ready to be drunk, or 
<hi rend="i">Allegory of the Eucharist</hi> (no. 55), in which Christ grows
                        a grape vine from the wound in his chest and squeezes out the juice of a
                        cluster onto an ecclesiastical platter held out by a pope. All this occurs
                        while Christ is backed by the cross and kneels upon the world that swims in
                        a pool of blood and is watched adoringly by an 
<figure n="night-thoughts-380-detail.033.03.100" rend="file" width="570" height="372">
	<head>5 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 380, detail.</head>
</figure> assembly of seven shorn sheep. Closer in symbolism to our point of
                        departure in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E, however, is the later sixteenth
                        century <hi rend="i">Man of Sorrows (Allegory of Redemption)</hi> by
                        Passerotti (no. 52), in which Jesus, holding his cross, stands on a shore
                        and looks up at the Father while making the sign of the span of mortality
                        with his right hand; Blake was to employ the same sign in Night the Second,
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 44:13E, and elsewhere. But most remarkable in
                        Passerotti’s picture is that the stream of blood issuing from the
                        wound of Christ falls into an overflowing chalice where it is being fed upon
                        both by a dove and by a serpent, which is wound four times around the stem
                        of this vessel of charity. These animals are derived from the aforementioned
                        Matthew 10:16.</p>
          <p>Since the blood that spills out of this cup also functions to convey the
                        writing upon the scroll that is wrapped about the base of this chalice,
                        believers are supposed to understand that Christian doctrine derives from
                        the overflow of blood. Lest we surmise that such indulgences had become
                        quite out-of-date among English Protestants, consider Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Olney
Hymn</hi>, Bk. I, 79 of 1779: “Praise for the
                        Fountain Opened.” Those who still indulge in the hymn books imagine
                        that they should bathe in Christ’s blood (rather, indeed, than drink
                        it), but this exercise of faith is hardly distinguishable for those who
                        think about it. If The Man who had Fallen Among Thieves, in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
68:21E, had been informed as to the full extent of the
                        symbolism represented by the snake-decorated ciborium being proffered for
                        his health, he would doubtless have persisted in his rejection of whatever
                        it was that the ostensible Samaritan had put in it. Blake would have agreed
                        that such observances have no place in the Everlasting Gospel: If
                        cannibalism were Christianity. . . .</p>
          <p>The choice of the anticipatory moment is an unusual feature of Blake’s
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E, whether or not it necessarily leads to
                        inferences as to the Christian mythology it would involve. Other artists who
                        had projected images from the parable, whether in single subjects, or
                        representations of numerous episodes within one picture, or renditions of
                        the parable in a succession of four pictures, concentrate on earlier or
                        later 
<pb id="p33-78" n="78"/>
text-based episodes, mainly the assault of
                        the thieves, the passing by of the Priest and the Levite, the Samaritan
                        dressing the victim’s wounds, the loading of the mended victim onto
                        the Samaritan’s equine mount and the journey to the inn, and the
                        arrangements with the innkeeper for his further care. When the victim is
                        dazed or unconscious, he can play at best a passive role. But Blake in
                        effect places the viewer in the psychological situation of an alert and wary
                        victim, whose first impression of a serpent-marked chalice is that it would
                        denote evil and corruption, not healing—even if the bearer of the cup
                        were Jesus and Aesculapius rolled into one. If this primary symbolic
                        identification of the serpent with evil in Christian art were set aside or
                        diminished, the whole force of Blake’s reinterpretation of the Good
                        Samaritan parable in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs would be
                        lost.</p>
          <p>What is the evidence, considering serpents and cups in the <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> designs themselves, for maintaining that the
                        serpent-decorated cup in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E is to be understood (by
                        the viewer) as appearing (to the victim) so menacing as to provoke
                        resistance, despite the fact that Christ himself assumes the role of the
                        Good Samaritan? In Blake’s work in general there are of course many
                        positive images of serpents, but as Essick and La Belle have remarked, none
                        of the serpents in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs that precede
                        the Good Samaritan design exhibit positive characteristics: those in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 25 and 27:7E are no more promising than the worms in
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 29 and 60:19E. And with the exception of one
                        neutral manifestation of the serpent as ouroboros in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        257, all subsequent serpentine forms in both Volume I (<hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        78, 79, 163) and Volume II (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 296, 307, 312, 345, 349,
                        358, 361, 366, 368, 369, 380, 442, 486, and 496) are represented as
                        unmistakably evil. As for cups associated with warnings, the overturned cup
                        of Belshazzar in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 19E: 60, an engraving
                        closely preceding the Good Samaritan design, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 21E: 68,
                        bears no sinister decorative mark. But the snake-inhabited cup of Silenus in
                            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 380: VIII, 34 (illus. 4 and 5), casts
                        retrospective doubt on the cups of Friendship that once were tippled by the
                        late Philander and his drinking companion, Young himself, as shown in the
                        watercolor verso design for the Good Samaritan episode, <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        69. But the huge grape vine, the source of “the generous blood / Of
                        Bacchus” (II, 595-96) formidably over-arching the scene, ought not to
                        be trusted to affect everyone so happily. By Night the Eighth 
<hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> (“Man of the World”) is having a drinking
                        problem and is about to lose “a new Eden . . . by [his] Fall”
                            (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 379, VIII, 568-69). The ultimate source of all
                        dissipation is revealed to be “Mystery,” the Whore of Babylon,
                        who is featured on the titlepage for Night the Eighth (<hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        345), in some distress, displaying her cup that contains the blood of the
                        saints. But the earthly source of the treacherous blood of the grape is
                        featured in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 380: we are shown a huge grape vine that
                        produces a goblet of debauchery that is being held out, to the viewer, in
                        the left hand of the inveigling god Silenus who hides his right fore-arm 
<figure n="BUT330.1.486.WC" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
	<head>6 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 486, IX, p. 68. Watercolor. c.
                                1797.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum, Department of Prints and
                                Drawings.</figDesc>
</figure> behind his back; behind Silenus, on one side, is his trifurcated
                        tree that is wrapped by the huge grape vine and on the other side by a
                        five-hundred-gallon wine barrel. Within his cup, being proffered to the
                        viewer as a toast—“To your health”—occurs a
                        detail obscured in the reproduction in the Clarendon edition (see illus. 5):
                        in the wine swims a writhing open-mouthed snake bearing a tiny nude rider,
                        seen from behind, who is unable to control it. Silenus, the vintner, in the
                        interests of full disclosure, is trying to tell the viewer that anybody who
                        names his poison can manage it. Except, as the reader of Young has been
                        constantly reminded, that ne’er do well, “<hi rend="i">Lorenzo</hi>!” Blake’s
source for the figure is
                        Ribera’s etching of 1628, <hi rend="i">Drunken Silenus</hi>, though
                        that image of the god is too preoccupied with having another himself poured
                        into his curly-handled cup to think of tempting the viewer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> This well-known print is reproduced
                                in Alfonso E. Pérez Sanchez and Nicola Spinosa, eds., <hi rend="i">Jusepe de
Ribera: 1591-1652</hi> (New York:
                                Metropolitan Museum /Abrams, 1992) no. 84, 186-88. One noteworthy
                                feature is that the head of Silenus’s ass obtrudes into the
                                scene, braying derisively at the god and his attendant satyrs.
                            <p>In 1732/33 Hogarth modernized the scene of dissipation in the
                                widely-imitated print <hi rend="i">A Midnight Modern
                                    Conversation</hi> by gathering 11 drunken men (half of whom are
                                also pipe-smokers) about a table that features a large punch bowl.
                                In <hi rend="i">Hogarth Volume II: High Art and Law: 1732-1750</hi>
                                (New Brunswick: Rutgers UP, 1992) esp. 4-7 and fig. 4, Ronald
                                Paulson declares that Hogarth’s claim that no portraits were
                                intended was disingenuous, though he does not offer identifications
                                of any of these midnight men-about-town drunks.</p>
	<p>A pair of drawings in Night the Eighth, “The Man <hi rend="i">of the</hi> World 
<hi rend="i">Answr’d</hi>,”
                                recall a scene in Night the Third: <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 99:29E and
                                act as sequels to the mythological featuring of the god Silenus of
                                    <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 380. In <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                                409 and 410, Blake displays an all-too-human group of four singing
                                drunkards who are stretched out, classical style, around a table
                                that features a punch bowl on the edge of which five spirits are
                                dancing. Four other little people are disporting upon the table. In
                                the clouds above are many more dissolute spirits. As is clear in the
                                large color reproduction, issued by Keynes in 1927, at least 10
                                other spirits at the right cavort around a jolly black devil while
                                at the left five others are getting sloshed. Most imposing to the
                                viewer but invisible to the drunkards is a red-eyed, green-winged
                                menace who peers out above the text panel. The sequel-design, 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 410, appears more clear in the 63rd color plate
                                of the Clarendon edition. The woman reveler of the previous design
                                has disappeared leaving only her three male drinking companions, who
                                are stretched-out unconscious at table. Each of them is adorned with
                                two small, mostly inert, spirits. Three of those who formerly danced
                                about the now-broken bowl can also be seen. In the clouds at left at
                                least seven spirits are in process of passing out while above them a
                                man with a knife pursues a fugitive male. Curiously, the ominous
                                green bat-devil who had been peering out from above the text panel
                                has been replaced by a slighter grey, Disney-like creature with eyes
                                shut, ass-ears, a smile, and pale blue bird-wings. Presumably this
                                is the benign spirit of indulgence, though the knife-man under his
                                charge appears to be more harmful than any spirit in <hi rend="i">NT
                                    409.</hi></p></note></p>
          <p>The audience of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series understands of
                        course that the ultimate motives of the Good Samaritan in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E
and those of Silenus in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 380 are as
                        different as can be. But in retrospect the viewer is again placed in the 
<pb id="p33-79" n="79"/>
position of the Man Fallen: now we are able to see
                        and feel what confronting a serpent-cup that is being thrust at us would
                        feel like. The admonitory sign of the snake on the Samaritan’s
                        chalice and the active snake in the cup of Silenus (like the one in the cup
                        given to St. John) are semiotically identical: they serve as warning labels
                        like the skull and crossbones on a medicine bottle. Both mark a lethal
                        liquor, whether it is sought in debauchery (as shown earlier in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
99:29E, or later in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 409 and 410) or thrust
                        as a cure upon one who (according to Augustinian interpretive tradition) is
                        a type of Adam lost in sin and reluctant to abandon his old faith.</p>
          <p>Moreover, there is nothing in Blake’s use of similar motifs outside
                        the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series to support a positive
                        interpretation of any image uniting a serpent and a cup, particularly an
                        egg-shaped cup. At the top right of Plate IV, the most memorable of the many
                        engravings of exotic serpents and eggs in Bryant’s <hi rend="i">A New
                            System, Or, An Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi> (1774, 1775), a snake
                        makes four coils around an egg, over the inscription: “<hi rend="i">OPHIS et Ovum /
Mundatum.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> This design,
whether or not the attribution to Blake as
                        apprentice engraver is correct, is supposed to be related to Blake’s
                        Mundane Shell symbolism (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 19:21-25; depicted in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 36); the primary allegory would seem to be that the
                        serpent of time controls the finitude of this world. Among Blake’s
                        other pictures there are two problematic depictions of chalices which help
                        to indicate how the Samaritan’s serpentine vessel is supposed to be
                        understood by the viewer. The most decisive is the ellipsoid chalice which
                        appears in conjunction with a serpent in Blake’s fifth design for his
                        second series on Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> (Butlin, cat.
                        528.5, pl. 628). Blake extensively revised this design (dated by Butlin c.
                        1815) from an earlier version (Butlin, cat. 527.<hi rend="i">5</hi>, pl.
                        620) executed as early as 1801. A most noteworthy alteration was to
                        introduce at the left side, just behind the chair in which the Lady sits,
                        immobilized, a meager bald barefooted male attendant, the only human-shaped
                        figure in this version of Comus’s rout. The attendant carries a large
                        ellipsoid chalice which in shape closely resembles that proffered by the
                        Samaritan in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68:21E, except for its small
                        ball on the top (as in Bryant) and the absence of a horizontal line
                        distinguishing the lid from the cup. Clearly this is a chief instrument of
                        Comus, although his command to “Be wise and tast” (line 813)
                        evidently refers to the (unlidded) cup he holds in his own left hand, while
                        almost touching with his magician’s wand the chalice brought in by
                        his attendant. One important detail is not always clear in reproductions: a
                        huge serpent with wide-open mouth and forked tongue springs up from the
                        attendant-borne chalice and undulates along the magician’s wand,
                        ready to fall upon the Lady should she yield to the invitation to partake of
                        Comus’s cup. This cup is immediately seized by the Brothers when, in
                        the next design (Butlin, cat. 528.6, pl. 629), they break up the Banquet,
                        but Comus eludes their grasp and the attendant’s chalice is nowhere
                        to be seen. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> This page is clearly
                            reproduced and catalogued in Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi>, Vol. II (Memphis:
                            American Blake Foundation, 1979) no. XII, pl. 14, and p. 14. Beside the
                            snake-and-egg is a separate picture of an ellipsoid cup that bears a
                            crescent on the top and is attached to a pedestal base by a flattened
                            sphere and inscribed “Heliopo — litanus.” A
                            blending of these elements of cup-and-serpent could easily produce the
                            proffered ciborium that intimidates the victim in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                            68:21E. The combination of such elements would result in a pretty piece
                            of paganism which, if proffered him, would intimidate the Man Fallen in
                            his weakened condition.</note></p>
          <p>Much the same serpentine symbolism is present in the first version of the <hi rend="i">Magic
Banquet</hi> (Butlin, cat. 527.5, pl. 620) where, on the
                        edges of the massive chair in which the enchanted Lady is frozen, are carved
                        three naked female figures wound about by serpents. In neither version is
                        the beleaguered Lady able to see the serpents in the service of Comus, but
                        she must understand well enough that there is something more sinister in his
                        stratagems than is revealed in the inviting cup he displays during his
                        <corr type="emend">carnivalesque</corr> spiel. The viewer, who is being shown more of
Comus’s
                        machinations than she, should have no doubt as to the ominous meaning of the
                        attendant serpent revealed in the later version. When Blake recast this
                        episode for <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, in <hi rend="i">Christ
                            Refusing the Banquet Offered by Satan</hi> (Butlin, cat. <pb id="p33-80" n="80"/>
544.<hi rend="i">6</hi>, pl. 689), the would-be victim, by
                        contrast, is still on his feet and thus able to reject, with both raised
                        hands visible, the proffered temptation: three doxies, one dressed in
                        scales, who take the part of the cups in <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi></p>
          <p>The other indubitably sinister conjunction of serpent and cup in
                        Blake’s work occurs in his 1809 picture of ultimate evil, <hi rend="i">The Whore of
Babylon</hi> (Butlin, cat. 523. pl. 584), in which
                        the cup of abominations held up by this bare-breasted instigator of war was
                        greatly elaborated from the plain version displayed in <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> 345, the titlepage design for Night the Eighth. The 1809
                        vessel containing the wine of the grapes of wrath is elaborately embellished
                        with handles made of two serpents that meet by crossing their tongues above
                        the top of the vessel and thence undulate downward and coil around its stem,
                        where their tails intertwine.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> The side
                        of this chalice exhibits women dancing; eight female spirits with drinks and
                        horns effuse from the top of the cup and zoom over the Whore’s head
                        and down her side to incite and join in the militant revelry on the ground;
                        at the left, a ninth female just by the browsing head of Behemoth exhorts
                        and celebrates this appalling spectacle of carnage. At a finer level of
                        detail, probably too fine to have interpretive significance, the criss-cross
                        pattern of wires that holds together the bracelet and anklet bangles of the
                        Great Whore notably resembles the pattern carefully inscribed on the
                        (visible) lower part of the Samaritan’s proffered chalice (in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
68 and 21E, illus. 1 and 2). Both this picture and the
                            <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> design present encounters in which the deployers
                        of serpent vessels are certainly up to no good and should be resisted by
                        their intended victims. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Blake
                            appropriated this vase with serpent handles from James Gillray’s
                            print of October 1805, entitled <hi rend="i">Matrimonial-Harmonics</hi>,
                            in which similar vases are displayed on the mantlepiece of an unhappy
                            family. See Draper Hill, ed., <hi rend="i">The Satirical Etchings of
                                James Gillray</hi> (New York: Dover, 1976) no. 87 and 133-34. The
                            seven-headed Behemoth that carries the Whore and leads the carnage was
                            adapted by Blake from his own earlier visions of <corr type="emend">Nebuchadnezzar</corr> (e.g.,
                                <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 24, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 299) and of the
                            Beast. Also, I think, from Gillray’s print of 1798, <hi rend="i">New
Morality</hi>, in which Leviathan as the Duke of Bedford is
                            drawn ashore as the most imposing figure among the foolish celebrants of
                            the latest French religion. This two-foot wide print (BMC 9240) is
                            clearly reproduced, though lacking the detailed inscription, in Draper
                            Hill, <hi rend="i">Mr. Gillray: The Caricaturist: A Biography</hi>
                            (London: Phaidon, 1965), pl. 74 and 69-70. More current reproductions by
                            Bindman (1989), Johnston (1998), and Magnusson (1998) likewise present
                            only parts of Gillray’s broad and extremely particularized
                            picture. With the aid of a magnifier the whole of Gillray’s
                            masterpiece is visible in John Miller, ed., <hi rend="i">Religion in The
                                Popular Prints, 1600-1832</hi> (Cambridge: Chadwyck-Healey, 1986)
                            no. 100, 260-61.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s victim in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E has not been enchanted
                        and is thus able to signal that he is just saying no. His right hand (his
                        left arm is almost hidden by his body) is raised, palm out, at a 60°
                        angle, with the fingers almost straight up in relation to the hand. In his
                        half-dead condition, this is the most forceful gesture of rejection he can
                        manage as, alarmed, he rouses himself to support his weight on his right
                        fore-arm. According to Heppner, who bases his remarks on Blake’s
                        engraved version only, “The victim’s response is not to be
                        read as a rejection; he is simply very, very surprised.” In
                        disagreement with Margoliouth, Essick and La Belle, Magno and Erdman, and me
                        in interpreting this gesture, Heppner refers to a compendium of hand signals
                        in Bulwer’s 1644 <hi rend="i">Chirologia</hi>, which I believe to be
                        an inapt model; similar gestures in Blake’s own work, especially in
                            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
                        provide a better basis for comparison. For example, in the design
                        immediately following in the engraved series, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 22E: 71,
                        a virtuous man on the point of death uses a similar gesture as he tries
                        gently or feebly to discourage the vain importunities of his anxious friend.
                        For an escalation of rejection see <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 73, where the Good
                        Old Man tries to fend off intimidating Death, and <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 6,
                        where the agonized victim attempts, in the first version (Butlin, cat.
                            550.<hi rend="i">6</hi>, pl. 702; cf. 550.<hi rend="i">9</hi>, Eliphaz)
                        with one (visible) hand raised and in subsequent versions with both visible
                        (e.g., Butlin, cat. 551.<hi rend="i">6</hi>, pl. 738) to ward off the
                        oppression of Satan, who is smiting him with sore boils from a vial of
                        infections. In all versions of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 11, where the recumbent
                        hero is oppressed by a dream-Vision of Satan impersonating the God of
                        damnation, Job is able to raise his hands to repel this hovering incubus who
                        is the negation of God in <hi rend="i">Elohim Creating Adam</hi> (Butlin,
                        cat. 289, pl. 388). Unwise rejectionism more emphatic than that in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E is, on the contrary, exhibited by the recumbent
                        rationalist in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 42E:153; this Lorenzo twists away while
                        holding out a stiff left arm with raised hand to repel male and female
                        spirits who had offered him their good advice. But the most emphatic
                        rejectionist among the wounded 
<pb id="p33-81" n="81"/>
figures who are
                        lying down in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> appears in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 152, an unengraved recto design that just precedes. In
                        it the male spirit of Young dives down, with proffering cup in each hand,
                        only to have the frantic sick man, stung by the “Venom”
                        (IV.767) of Death, turn away and “push our <hi rend="i">Antidote</hi>
                            aside.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> Later, in Night the
                        Eighth, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 358, a horrified male traveler with his hair
                        standing on end, who encounters a huge rearing serpent poised to strike,
                        raises both of his hands, wrists up, fingers splayed, to fend off the
                        attack. Allowing for the difference in the physical situation of the Man
                        Fallen Among Thieves, the hand gestures of all these male figures are
                        similar, expressing their attempts to repel things unacceptable or menacing.
                            <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> The effort to match the gestures of
                            Blake’s figures with those in a standard handbook is not, of
                            course, invalid, but in life, art, or on stage, gestures must be
                            understood in relation to cultural or individual idioms of expression.
                            Unless the viewer sees the rest of the body language of any figure, as
                            well as other signs, such as words, the viewer is liable to misinterpret
                            what the hands, considered by themselves, are saying. Yet at some
                            junctures hand gestures may be the crucial signs. From the several pages
                            of the <hi rend="i">Chirologia</hi> reproduced in Janet Warner’s
                                <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art</hi> (Kingston and
                            Montreal: McGill-Queens UP, 1984), esp. 50-51, Heppner singles out the
                            gesture “<hi rend="i">Admiror</hi>” (example D on
                            Warner’s page 51), which consists of <hi rend="i">upraised</hi>
                            hands, bent outward at the wrists, indeed, but with the fingers somewhat
                            curved inward toward the palms so that, together, the two hands are
                            gently cupped. The wrist mechanics here are quite different from what
                            can be seen of the stiff-fingered upraised repelling hand in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
68:21E. A closer comparison on the cited page in
                            the <hi rend="i">Chirologia</hi> appears in example X, 
“<hi rend="i">Dimitto</hi>,” in which the arm is horizontal and
                            the hand is raised to an 80° angle at the wrist, although here,
                            as in example D, the fingers are bent; the dismissal is a gentle one.
                            The most apposite of the hand signals from <hi rend="i">Chirologia</hi>
                            represented in Warner’s book appears at the leftmost bottom of
                            the facing page (50, pl. 23) as example W, “[<hi rend="i">Exe</hi>]<hi
rend="i">cratione repellit</hi>” (partially
                            concealed, unfortunately, in the reproduction), in which the relevant
                            gesture of extreme refusal is expressed with both hands to signify the
                            intensity of rejection. The gesture is shown straight on, not in profile
                            as in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E, as it would appear from the
                            perspective of the one being repelled, and the hands, with three of the
                            fingers tense and straight, appear to be raised to a 90° angle
                            from the horizontal forearm, which has no weight to bear.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Heppner’s citation of
                                Blake’s early drawing entitled <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe
                                    Discovers the Footprint in the Sand</hi> does not support his
                                interpretation of the victim’s gesture in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E as
non-resisting. In the text Heppner quotes,
                                Crusoe is not only “exceedingly surpriz’d,” he
                                is “Thunder-struck,” as if he had “seen an
                                Apparition.” Indeed, Heppner himself endorses a comment by
                                Rodney M. Baine which mentions Crusoe’s “isolation and
                                horror,” causing him that night to sleep “not at
                                all” (Heppner 69n18). In looking out across the sea at some
                                unrepresented cause for apprehension appearing to him (but not to
                                the viewer), Crusoe is the precursor of many other Blake figures
                                terrified by some unseen horror offstage: Bromion, for example, in
                                the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                                    Albion.</hi> Three of the seven heads of the Beast in <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 345, the titlepage design for Night
                                the Eighth, entitled “Virtue’s Apology: or ‘The
                                men of the World <hi rend="i">answer’d</hi>. .
                                .,’” also look off at some ominous vision and their
                                passenger, the Whore, raises her hand in distress at something at
                                the right that she can see but we are not shown. The Miser in 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 115 (IV, 6) does the same thing.
                                Those splayed fingers of Blake’s Robinson Crusoe, expressing
                                extreme apprehension or horror, are displayed in a posture
                                resembling that of the younger man being accused and sent into exile
                                in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 160 (v, dedication), on the
                                second titlepage for Night the Fifth, “The Relapse.”
                                This man’s arms, almost exactly like Crusoe’s, are
                                held rigidly down and, though his fingers are not as splayed, his
                                hands are stiffly spread out at right angles. He is horrified: his
                                hair stands on end, his eyes pop out, and he shouts at receiving his
                                sentence from the implacable old man, whose head rather remarkably
                                prefigures that on the so-called <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar
                                    Coin</hi> (Butlin, cat. 704, pl. 919) drawn more than 20 years
                                later. Like this figure, like Robinson Crusoe, and like the woman
                                discovering the dead child in “Holy Thursday,” plate
                                33 of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, the victim in the Good
                                Samaritan scence is expressing horror and, since he is lying down,
                                his gesture also serves to fend off what is about to be thrust upon
                                him.
                            <p>But the victim’s refusal, even at its most extreme, in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
68, is not as conclusive as that of the foolish
                                girl in “The Angel,” plate 41, of <hi rend="i">Songs
                                    of Experience.</hi> Too long ago she rejected the possibility of
                                joy. There may still be hope for the Man Fallen.</p></note></p>
          <p>Thus, at the instant Blake illustrates, in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E
                        (illus. 1 and 2), immediately before the curative liquid is to be dispensed,
                        the wounded man—believing that no Jew can expect any good thing from
                        the hand of a Samaritan—would be reading aright the sign of the
                        serpent according to the codes he has been taught to trust. In choosing to
                        set the parable in this moment, and to embellish the story with other
                        details not mentioned in the parable itself, Blake becomes the first artist
                        in 18 centuries to depict this episode in the parable of the Good Samaritan
                        from the point of view of the Man Fallen Among Thieves, on first
                        encountering his presumably hostile neighbor. Blake employs the sinister
                        image of the serpent to challenge the viewer to imagine afresh the
                        victim’s response to this unexpected and dubious source of help, even
                        though appearing in the form of Jesus himself, within the framework of the
                        parable’s powerful ethnic antagonisms: <hi rend="i">Isn’t it
                            enough that I’ve been mugged and left for dead in this
                            god-forsaken crime-infested alien territory, on a notoriously dangerous
                            stretch of road, where even the clergy I believed I could trust
                            won’t stop to help me? Now on top of all that, here comes this
                            traditional enemy of my people, a Samaritan, offering who-knows-what in
                            a snake-decorated vessel. NO THANKS!</hi> It is no wonder that Blake
                        depicts the victim (especially in the watercolor version) with his eye-brows
                        shooting up, his mouth open, terrified, straining to lift his head and upper
                        body from the boulder behind him, mustering the last ounce of his ebbing
                        strength to raise his hand just off the ground, palm-out at the wrist, to
                        fend off his would-be rescuer and signal his aversion to whatever snake-oil
                        this suspicious-looking Samaritan medico wants to thrust upon him. The
                        alarmed reaction Blake depicts here is even more striking in comparison to
                        the lack of expression in the often-unconscious or barely conscious inert
                        victims depicted by other artists. Indeed, one of the few artists other than
                        Blake to depict the victim (<hi rend="i">later</hi> in this episode) with an
                        animated expression is Hogarth, who, in the mural in St.
                        Bartholomew’s Hospital (illus. 8) represents the injured man,
                        grimacing in pain, his fist clenched, staring dazedly ahead as the Samaritan
                        pours oil into his chest wound. But the victim in Hogarth’s painting
                        is not exhibiting fear; he has already allowed his extended left arm to be
                            bandaged.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> It cannot be supposed that Blake did
                                not trouble to study the great Hogarth <hi rend="i">Good
                                    Samaritan</hi> (of 1736) on the second flight of the staircase
                                at St. Bartholomew’s Hospital, near St. Paul’s. Even
                                more certain is that Blake was aware of the picture as ably engraved
                                in 1773 by Ravenet and Delatre, since it was included in the Hogarth
                                100-print portfolio of 1790 to which Blake contributed his own fine
                                engraving of Hogarth’s <hi rend="i">The Beggar’s
                                    Opera.</hi> It should be understood that one reason that
                                Hogarth’s <hi rend="i">Good Samaritan</hi> is not now better
                                known, or indeed, well discussed, is that it is situated on the wall
                                of a staircase and, except from above, is almost impossible to
                                photograph as a whole. The viewer who lacks the print or cannot move
                                up and down the stairs and lean back on the rail may not take in the
                                figure of the Levite who, with his nose in a text—doubtless
                                biblical—is wandering to the left in the boscage.
                            <p>This can be confirmed in Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">Hogarth</hi>,
                                2: 83-86 and (uncolored) pls. 39 and 41. As Paulson observes, the
                                garments of Hogarth’s Good Samaritan and those of Christ in
                                    <hi rend="i">The Pool of Bethesda</hi>, which is positioned at
                                right angle to the <hi rend="i">Samaritan</hi> picture, are similar,
                                but this should not be taken to signify that these two figures are
                                identical. Hogarth’s point is that the Samaritan is
                                performing an exemplary Christ-like act, but <hi rend="i">not</hi>
                                that what is shown in the two pictures is equivalency, yet another
                                case of Christian typology. Hospital doctors should do well but
                                cannot guarantee to perform miracles.</p>
	<p>One feature of particular interest to Blake’s Good Samaritan
                                picture is that in Hogarth the encounter takes place just in front
                                of and beneath a nearly dead tree which, however, has a few leaves
                                on twigs that extend just above the Samaritan who performs the
                                healing. A parasitic growth of ivy on the lower trunk does not reach
                                high enough to cover the broken-off main trunk, which twists to the
                                left, pointing in the direction of the arrogant Priest and his
                                groveling devotee, who are enacting their forms of worship near the
                                top of the road. On the other side, the Samaritan’s horse is
                                tethered to a (dead) branch of the tree that protrudes from a mass
                                of ivy on the trunk. In such details one can observe motifs that
                                Blake was able to redeploy in his quite different realization of the
                                parable.</p>
	<p>Due to pictures of the Bassani and Rembrandt the dog had become such
                                an established presence in the iconography of the Good Samaritan
                                that Hogarth needed no other prompting to include his own favorite
                                animal in his, the largest, of Good Samaritan pictures, doubtless in
                                part because the “beast” of the parable seemed
                                sufficiently accounted for by a horse or other equine that could
                                carry the victim. One would not wish to argue, however, that Blake
                                    <hi rend="i">meant</hi> something by <hi rend="i">not</hi>
                                including a dog in his Good Samaritan pictures. Some of these
                                matters are discussed by Ronald Paulson in <hi rend="i">Popular and
                                    Polite Art in the Age of Hogarth and Fielding</hi> (Notre Dame,
                                IN: U of Notre Dame P, 1979) in chapters “The English
                                Dog,” 49-63, and “The Good Samaritan,”
                                157-71.</p></note></p>
          <p>Other unusual details of the Blake’s portrayal of the Good Samaritan
                        story take on added significance in relation to Young’s text. As
                        Heppner observes, the parable of the Good Samaritan “does not exactly
                        illustrate” Young’s drift; on the 
<pb id="p33-82" n="82"/>
                        contrary, Blake’s depiction of a completely gratuitous act of
                        kindness, from which no return is expected, constitutes an implicit critique
                        of the line marked for illustration: “Love, and Love only, is the
                        loan for Love.” Heppner cogently notes the aptness of the parable as
                        a correction of Young’s reliance on blatantly commercial imagery: 
						<q>
                            A true neighbor does not simply return love for love, or buy love by
                            lending or giving love, but freely gives love to those most culturally
                            remote when they are in need, even if they have shown nothing but scorn
                            in the past, and are not likely to change in the future, and may have no
                            occasion to return that love. (1995, 169-70) </q></p>
          <p>This point was missed altogether by the anonymous writer of the Explanation
                        of the Engravings in 1797, whose uncritical adoption of Young’s
                        monetary imagery makes it seem that the Good Samaritan’s deed somehow
                        balances the books on love and thus serves to illustrate an unassailable
                        moral principle.</p>
          <p>And the commercial imagery in this part of the poem is even more egregious
                        than Heppner’s summary suggests. The voice of the author has been
                        obsessively addressing one Lorenzo, traditionally identified with
                        Young’s nephew, a character who is not very clearly delineated
                        through thousands of lines but who is almost everywhere (as in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
380, as said; illus. 4 and 5) presumed to be unregenerate.
                        Young’s exhortations seem to prevail occasionally in leading this
                        sinner to repentance, but it is not until halfway through the 
<figure n="BUT330.1.483.WC" rend="file" width="794" height="1000">
	<head>7 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 483, IX, p. 65. Watercolor. c.
                                1797.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum, Department of Prints and
                                Drawings.</figDesc>
</figure> last Night, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486 (IX, 68), as we shall see,
                        that Lorenzo at last gives up, vomits up, what ought to be the root cause of
                        his recalcitrance. And yet he will remain recalcitrant still.</p>
          <p>The subject of friendship, about which Young the narrator has been haranguing
                        the recalcitrant Lorenzo in the latter part of Night the Second, is at first
                        sharply distinguished from anything to do with money—but only in the
                        unconvincingly banal imagery that is typical of much of the poem:
                        “Their Smiles the <hi rend="i">Great</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Coquet</hi> throw out
/ For Others Hearts . . . / Ye Fortune’s
                        Cofferers! Ye Powers of Wealth! . . . Can Gold gain Friendship?” (II,
                        563-34, 566, 569) etc. But then, pivoting on the marked line, “Love,
                        and Love only, is the loan for Love” (II, 571), Young
                        enthusiastically switches the valuations in his discourse, revealing the
                        authorial presence to be, as so often in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,
                        on both sides of the question. Given the monetary context Young has
                        established, it is no wonder that the author of the Explanation of the
                        Engravings, extrapolating from Young’s own words, describes the
                        “Loan” for love, or the interest charges, as an outright
                        “purchase.” On the previous page Young had asked Lorenzo to
                        “pardon what my Love extors, / An honest Love, and not afraid to
                        frown” (II, 556-57), Friendship, for Young, is discussed as a
                        commodity requiring in-kind payment (or emotional extortion), according to
                        what Heppner rightly calls the “impoverished doctrine” that
                        Lorenzo cannot “hope to find / A Friend, but what has found 
<pb id="p33-83" n="83"/>
<figure n="hogarth-good-samaritan-print.033.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="359">
	<head>8 Hogarth, <hi rend="i">The Good Samaritan</hi>, print by Ravenet
                                and Delatre. c. 1772/1790.</head>
	<figDesc>Prints of Hogarth. Albert E. Stone collection, Walker Museum of
                                Art, Bowdoin College.</figDesc>
</figure> a friend in thee.” Faced with strict bankers’ terms
                        in a tight market, “All like the Purchase, Few the price will pay; /
                        And this makes Friends such Miracles below” (II, 574-75).</p>
          <p>In the next paragraph (overleaf, p. 38 in the engraved version), however,
                        Young undermines his own counsel without realizing it. He has been urging
                        Lorenzo to repress his pride and take a chance on friendship. Now, in the
                        next breath, he advises caution: Friendship is such an easily damaged luxury
                        item (“Delicate, as Dear,” II, 577) that “<hi rend="i">Reserve</hi> will wound
it; and <hi rend="i">Distrust</hi>,
                        destroy” (I, 579). Since Lorenzo would be taking on a lifetime
                        commitment, as exemplified by Young’s own 20-year relationship with
                        the now-dead Philander, it is wise to “Pause, ponder, sift”
                        (I, 584). Only after a thorough background check, apparently, can it be
                        affirmed that “A Friend is worth all hazard we can run” (I,
                        589). All these contradictory images and nuggets of advice, and most
                        particularly Young’s high-handed way of attempting to impose them
                        upon an unwilling Lorenzo, enter into Blake’s use of the Good
                        Samaritan parable as a critique of Young’s thinking on
                        “Friendship”—the third announced subject of Night the
                        Second. But in itself the Good Samaritan parable is best understood as
                        conveying a lesson in disinterested charity towards one’s 
<hi rend="i">neighbor</hi>, of whatever persuasion, rather than as an
                        expression of “love” for one’s friend.</p>
          <p>Once it is recognized that Blake’s application of the parable to
                        Young’s text turns on the victim’s resistance, the unusual
                        details of the design fall into place, linking two iconographic features
                        which have no obvious connection with each other: Jesus’s appearance
                        as Good Samaritan and his use of a vessel recalling the serpent-charged
                        chalice of St. John. Given the cultural context, the conscious
                        victim’s acceptance of this object from this man would be
                        foolhardy—or it would require an extraordinary act of faith, a
                        conversion. It is the latter issue that Blake is getting at here. The ethnic
                        and religious antipathies that underlie the standoff depicted in <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 68 are reinforced by the symbolism of the
                        two huge overlapping trees behind the central figures: the one at the left
                        apparently dead, a barren branch drooping over the side of the wounded man;
                        the one at the right abundantly alive, spreading its flourishing leaves over
                        the Good Samaritan and beyond.</p>
          <p>The trunks of these two trees are as realistically represented as any Blake
                        ever made, but how these trees are interrelated is quite beyond arboreal
                        relationships to be found in nature 
<pb id="p33-84" n="84"/>
and thus points
                        to their symbolic import. Beneath the text panel the trunk of the tree at
                        right emerges from the ground <hi rend="i">behind</hi> but touching the
                        trunk of the tree at left. Especially in the engraving, <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        21E (illus. 2), the bark on the trunk of the tree at right is striated,
                        establishing itself as being of a distinctly different species. In nature
                        the two could not possibly have grown together in such proximity to the
                        massive heights indicated. More extraordinarily, the tree at right becomes
                        bifurcated, as it emerges above the text panel <hi rend="i">in front of</hi>
                        the tree at left; the huge trunks must have crossed behind the text
                        panel.</p>
          <p>In their distinctiveness this pair are reminders of the two trees of Eden,
                        associated in Christian tradition with Adam’s fall and
                        Christ’s crucifixion, Law and Gospel, the Old and New Covenants.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> The Man Fallen Among Thieves is thus
                        suspended between faiths. In his ritually unclean state, wounded and left
                        half dead, he has just been rejected by the departing clergy of his native
                        religion, Judaism. But he has not yet accepted a new Savior who appears to
                        him in the detested image of a Samaritan, proffering a cure marked with the
                        horrifying sign of a serpent, the bestial guise in which Satan first walked
                        the earth. To reinforce the point that the cup should be taken as a test of
                        susceptibility to the Christian faith, the serpentine design alludes both to
                        the legendary trial of St. John the Evangelist, who survived the
                        serpent-poisoned drink, and to its Gospel source in Jesus’s promise,
                        after upbraiding his followers for their “unbelief and hardness of
                        heart” in failing to credit his resurrection, that if as believers
                        they “drink any deadly thing, it shall not hurt them” (Mark
                        16:18). In setting the Good Samaritan tableau at the moment of initial
                        encounter, as the healer prepares to offer the cup but before he has
                        prevailed upon the victim to accept his strange new cure, Blake shows how
                        unbelief hinders the victim’s salvation. The victim’s
                        reaction, although understandable in the circumstances—it looks like
                        poison and he has reason to fear the source—perturbs the would-be
                        rescuer, as indicated (in the watercolor version) by his open mouth and
                        troubled brow; the completion of the act of healing depends upon what the
                        skeptical recipient does next. In his role as Samaritan, Jesus’s
                        concern is with spiritual causes, not natural ones, and symbolically his
                        vessel holds balm for the soul, not an Aesculapian therapeutic formula that
                        could cure physical wounds of the chest and abdomen, with or without the
                        patient’s cooperation. <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi>
                                According to Luke 23:31, Jesus left the Daughters of Jerusalem with
                                one last question before the crucifixion: “For if they do
                                these things in a green tree, what shall be done in the dry?”
                                In this prophetic question concerning the disasters to come in times
                                without the presence of Christ on earth, Jesus alludes to Ezekiel
                                17:24: “And all the trees of the field shall know that I the
                                Lord have brought down the high tree, have exalted the low tree,
                                have dried up the green tree, and made the dry tree to flourish . .
                                . .” The consequences of the symbolism of the contrasting
                                trees, taken by Christians to signify Judaism and Christianity, are
                                made abundantly clear in Heinz Schreckenberg, <hi rend="i">The Jews
                                    in Christian Art</hi>, trans. John Bowden (New York: Continuum,
                                1996). One example, reproduced in Schreckenberg, p. 64, will
                                suffice: in “The Living Cross,” a woodcut of 1600
                                after a church fresco, Christ is being crucified between two trees,
                                the one at left supervised by <hi rend="i">Ecclesia</hi>, who
                                gathers Jesus’s blood in a cup, the one at right in the
                                keeping of <hi rend="i">Synagoga</hi>, who is being struck down from
                                above.
                            <p>There are many other variations on the symbolism of the two trees,
                                one dead, one living, or of a single tree, dead on the Old Testament
                                side, living on the New. Both Carpaccio and Holbein the younger
                                employed it in major pictures. I am only slightly acquainted with
                                the vast bibliography appended to Schreckenberg’s 1996 book
                                but wish particularly to call attention, on the art side, to the
                                compendious discussions in Gertrud Schiller’s five volumes
                                    <hi rend="i">Iconographie der christlichen Kunst,
                                1966-1981</hi>, the first two of which were translated in 1972.
                                Volume 4, <hi rend="i">Die Kirche</hi>, contains useful information
                                concerning the symbolism of church and synagogue. For a learned and
                                balanced account of the appalling polarizations of Judaism and
                                Christianity, see Frank E. Manuel, <hi rend="i">The Broken Staff:
                                    Judaism Through Christian Eyes</hi> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP,
                                1992), which must have appeared too late for inclusion by
                                Schreckenberg.</p></note></p>
          <p>For Blake, Jesus’s powers are at least partly contingent upon the
                        faith of the potential beneficiary. As he insisted a year after completing
                        his <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs, in commenting on the
                        controversy about biblical authority between Thomas Paine and Bishop Watson:
						<q> Jesus could not do miracles where unbelief hinderd . . . . The
                            manner of a miracle being performed is in modern times considered as an
                            arbitrary command of the agent upon the patient but this is an
                            impossibility not a miracle[;] neither did Jesus ever do such a miracle
                            . . . . How can Watson ever believe the above sense of a miracle who
                            considers it an arbitrary act of the agent upon an unbelieving
                            patient[,] whereas the Gospel says that Christ could not do a miracle
                            because of Unbelief[?] (E 616-17) </q></p>
          <p>The “modern” idea of a miracle, since it does not require the
                        active, willing, participatory faith of the recipient, can be no more than
                        the arbitrary action of an “agent” upon an “unbelieving
                        patient”—and this is not the kind of miracle Blake’s
                        Jesus would ever perform. Although no scriptural text explicitly states that
                        Jesus <hi rend="i">could not</hi> perform miracles in the face of
                        “Unbelief,” the validity of Blake’s inference is well
                        supported by accounts of at least two occasions on which he <hi rend="i">did
                            not</hi> do so (Matthew 13:58 and Mark 6:5-6). In the latter text it is
                        perhaps also worth noting, with reference to Heppner’s Aesculapian
                        interpretation of the cure, that routine physical “healing” is
                        not counted among Jesus’s “mighty works.” The incident
                        described in Mark 9:24 further bears out this inference: a father who asks
                        that Jesus heal his son declares his faith but also pleads, “Help
                        thou my unbelief.” Blake’s views on the nullifying effects of
                        unbelief are also supported by the many texts in which people who have been
                        healed are told that their faith has made them whole. In the annotations to
                        Watson, Blake also declares that “the man who holds miracles to be
                        ceased puts it out of his own power ever to witness one,” and that
                        “It is man[’]s fault if God is not able to do him good[,] for
                        he gives to the just &amp; to the 
<pb id="p33-85" n="85"/>
<figure n="rembrandt-arrival-at-the-inn-print.033.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="416" height="500">
	<head>9 Rembrandt, “The Arrival at the Inn,” called <hi rend="i">The Good Samaritan.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Print. Later impressions dated 1633. Courtesy of the Boston
                                Museum of Fine Arts.</figDesc>
</figure> unjust[,] but the unjust reject his gift” (E 616). Although
                        in the Good Samaritan story set forth in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E the
                        resistant victim should not be stigmatized as “unjust,” the
                        force of his rejection has the same effect: the Man Fallen Among Thieves,
                        exhibiting a lack of the faith that would contribute to his recovery,
                        rejects Jesus’s gift and stops the healer before he can even begin
                        his work. Like the biblical Jesus grieving over Jerusalem who “would
                        not” respond to his love (Matthew 23:37), Jesus in the watercolor
                        version in this design shows that he feels the pain of being rejected by the
                        person he has come to help.</p>
          <p>There is one other Gospel episode, known as Washing the Disciples’
                        Feet (John 13:4-17), which was often painted by Baroque artists, that can
                        quite closely resemble the encounter in Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        68:21E. As represented by, for example, Baglione, Christ kneels before
                        Peter, who is seated, and is about to wash the Disciple’s feet with a
                        vessel conveniently at hand. The focal moment is signaled by Peter’s
                        raising his hands in a surprised, resistant or “deprecatory
                        gesture” (Hall, <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Subjects and Symbols</hi>,
                        rev. 1979, 240), though the viewer understands that St. Peter will acquiesce
                        forthwith. Indeed, this was the basis of a ceremony in the English church
                        until 1750 and still carried on, it is said, by the Pope and the English
                        monarch. If Blake’s Good Samaritan stand-off in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        68:21E should be understood as entailing the conversion of the Jews, the
                        process will not be completed until the victim and his would-be benefactor
                        are safely ensconced within the as-yet invisible Church, that is, the Inn,
                        which is still to be discovered somewhere in Samaria.</p>
          <p>In stating in my 1990 article that Jesus’s expression of dismay and
                        chagrin in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68 “marks (at this stage) his
                        inability to accomplish his mission” (84), I gave the impression that
                        Blake represents Jesus as undergoing an evolutionary development, though
                        what is really at issue is the <hi rend="i">victim’s</hi> stage of
                        development, which determines whether or not the cure will be accepted. I
                        should have made clearer that Blake, as part of his pictorial critique of
                        Young’s often vaguely imagined or concealed theological positions,
                        sometimes represents 
<pb id="p33-86" n="86"/>
Jesus as acting in ways that
                        Young would have him, rather than as Blake would have him—in this
                        case, seeming on the verge of forcing medicine upon a helpless victim
                        against his will. In Young’s narrative, the “<hi rend="i">Reserve</hi>” and
“<hi rend="i">Distrust</hi>”
                        (line 579) of Lorenzo place him in a relationship to Young analogous to that
                        of the fallen man who rejects the Good Samaritan’s intended
                        benefaction in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68. But unlike Blake’s
                        Jesus-as-Samaritan, who is actively engaged with the person he is trying to
                        help, Young—with his interminable persistence in trying to improve
                        Lorenzo by telling him what to do, think, feel, and believe—rides
                        roughshod over Lorenzo’s resistance. He insists presumptuously and
                        intrusively on imposing his well-intentioned advice upon his protegé,
                        apparently expecting Lorenzo simply to follow doctor’s orders and
                        take his moral medicine as directed. So Blake responds in pictorial terms,
                        “Let us suppose, Reverend Dr. Young, that even the Savior himself had
                        tried to operate according to your scenario, imposing cures on unbelievers
                        as you attempt to impose spiritual instruction on Lorenzo; it
                        wouldn’t have worked.” Blake’s critique remains valid
                        even when occasionally Lorenzo seems to be responding to Young’s
                        improving advice: these temporary responses are usually not signs that
                        Lorenzo has become any the less a reprobate; in most of the poem, they
                        indicate merely that he has made one step forward, with some backward steps
                        quickly to follow.</p>
          <p>The watercolor version of the Good Samaritan picture takes its place in a
                        narrative about Lorenzo’s development and eventual salvation that
                        forms part of a larger Christological scheme that extends all the way from
                            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 1 to 537, as outlined in my 1990 essay.
                        The engraved version, however, is part of a curtailed sequence that breaks
                        off at the end of the fourth Night, when the publisher apparently ran out of
                        money. Although there is no decisive evidence that as Blake worked on the
                        engravings for the first four Nights he became aware that the project would
                        end abruptly, the changes he made in engraving the Good Samaritan picture
                        have the effect of implying that the process of Lorenzo’s potential
                        conversion may sooner occur. Rather than the watercolor’s as yet
                        unresolved impasse between resisting patient and chagrined would-be healer,
                        the engraving presents Jesus, who is making his first appearance, engaged in
                        the confident initiation of an act of healing expected, even momentarily, to
                        overcome the patient’s resistance. As it happens, the engraved
                        four-Night series accords with a plan that may once have been considered by
                        Young himself to conclude the poem in four Nights; hence the subtitle
                        “The Christian Triumph” seems a sufficiently conclusive title
                        for the last section of the poem when, in the engraved edition, the
                        designation “Night the Fourth” has been eliminated. The
                        suggestion of an earlier recovery for Lorenzo, within the truncated engraved
                        series, is reinforced by Blake’s regenerate-soul motif of the
                        chrysalis-and-butterfly, which has been moved from its original position in
                            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 272 (where it had resumed a sequence of
                        metamorphosis imagery initiated in such earlier designs as <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 13 and
15) to a new location in the concluding section of the
                        poem as engraved and is situated atop the text panel of <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        40E (see illus. 10 and 11). The triumphant figure of the resurrecting
                        Christ, having been moved from its position in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1 as the
                        frontispiece to Volume I of the watercolor series to 31E, is adapted to
                        serve as a titlepage for what promises to be a most positive conclusive
                        section. But the penultimate engraving, in response to Young’s
                        rhetorical question to Lorenzo as to whether a Christian could wipe off the
                        cross “As a foul blot, from his dishonour’d brow” (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 42E:153,
IV, 792), has been taken from a pessimistic
                        sequence in the watercolor series (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 152-55): it depicts
                        a reclining man (“a determined infidel,” the Explainer called
                        him) with his right hand to his brow, though perhaps he is shading his
                        searching eyes rather than wiping off the cross as he twists his body and
                        holds out his raised left hand to ward off male and female heavenly beings
                        who had exhorted the sinner but now despair of his salvation. The text
                        culminates in an admonitory crescendo urging Lorenzo to consult his
                        conscience before Truth, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 156 (illus. 5), bursts upon
                        him “in thunder and in flame” (II, 837) in his final hour. But
                        the engraved design sequence does conclude with some possibility of
                        redemption even if Lorenzo should fail again or forever; the Goddess Truth,
                        as depicted in 43E, is speaking or shouting <hi rend="i">not</hi> at
                        Lorenzo, “the sinner,” as the Explainer misconstrues the
                        audience that Truth is addressing, but with her eyes fixed directly on the
                        viewer, rousing the faculties of those who have ears to hear, and with both
                        hands pointing straight up, for those who have eyes to see. Yet what it is
                        that Truth most aims to reveal does not appear at all in the watercolor, 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 156, and only by inference in the conclusive engraving
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi>:43E.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> As David Bindman has shown me, a
                                London dealer 70 years ago advertised a proof of an engraving for
                                Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 158, which features Lot’s
                                Wife as she turns back, appalled, to witness the destruction by
                                death rays from the clouds on high, of the city of Sodom. Such a
                                page, with some other text substituted for the announcement of Night
                                the Fifth, would have confirmed what Truth is trying to tell in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 156 and has evidence to show in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 43E: the powers above are maleficent.
This is not, of
                                course, to deny that the elusive print of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 158
                                may have been a relic of 1796 when the large scale project for
                                publishing the whole of Young’s poem, together with as many
                                as 200 of Blake’s engravings, was still being
                                contemplated.
                            <p>The publisher’s “Advertisement” that functions
                                as a preface in the (fall) 1797 edition does not make a commitment
                                one way or the other either to the shorter or the longer scheme for
                                the edition. It was dated 22 Dec. 1796, well before many of the
                                dated inscriptions on many of Blake’s plates. On p. vi
                                Edwards particularly commends Young for this pair of lines that
                                (without location) occur in Night the Fifth, 10 and 11, lines 72-73:
<q> But solemn counsels, images of awe,<lb/>
 Truths which
                                    eternity lets fall on man </q></p>
	<p>Blake made two watercolors, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 165 and 166, for
                                these pages and the latter, at the top of the p. 11, received the
                                curious check mark that in early Night the Fifth tends to replace
                                the asterisk or cross that (usually) signifies the line of verse
                                that is supposed to be illustrated. The theme of Truth, so
                                forcefully enunciated in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 156:43E, at the end of
                                the fourth Night, is here resumed in Blake’s picture that
                                features a celestial woman who, with pen poised in her left, hands
                                down with her right a bound volume which is being received with
                                gestures of open-handed surprise by a man aroused in bed.</p>
	<p>It will, of course, occur to the viewer that what is shown amounts to
                                a reprise of the issues and perhaps the
                                personnel—“Lorenzo!” is addressed in
                                1.81—who had been indicated by the recalcitrant victim in the
                                tableau of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E. Moreover, the unmarked II.
                                78-79 mention the “Pencil” in the hand of <hi rend="i">Midnight!</hi>,
with which she darkens the “<hi rend="i">Truths</hi> which Eternity lets fall on Man.” Whenever a
                                man in bed is learning a lesson, since <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 2, the
                                figure is normally identifiable as Young himself. <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi>,
by contrast, doesn’t learn anything
                                there. The figure of the traveler, as in subsequent design 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 167, is still more clearly identifiable as
                                Young, rather than <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi>, who
                                characteristically lacks get up and go; in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                                52:17E, for example, <hi rend="i">Lorenzo</hi> is drunk in bed, cup
                                in hand, and staring blear-eyed out of the picture at the viewer. We
                                are to gather that this man in bed, in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 167, is
                                Young himself, who will soon get over his surprise and accept the
                                book of Truths that has been produced by the combined authorship of
                                Eternity and of Midnight, the colorist.</p></note></p>
          <p>In the full-length watercolor sequence on Lorenzo, there are three decisive
                        moments leading to a triumphal conclusion: the first is the rejection of the
                        cure in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E (illus. <pb id="p33-87" n="87"/>
1 and
                        2); the second is an ostensibly successful healing in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        148:40E (illus. 10 and 11); the third, what should be the climactic event of
                        part II of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, is a successful exorcism in
                        Night the Ninth, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486 (illus. 6). Whether or not Blake
                        expected a viewer to keep in mind a sequence spread out over so many pages
                        can only be conjectured. But given the predominance of mood swings and
                        attitudes rather than of plot in Young’s verses, the thin thread of
                        continuity is easily lost, and Blake’s pictures, like a sequence of
                        photographic stills, help to reinforce, clarify, and correct the dimly
                        indicated story-line: one can pick up the poem almost anywhere and still
                        hope for the best. Repeated gestures and motifs serve as reminders of ideas
                        expressed earlier and create connections in ways that the soft-edged poem
                        rarely does. In Blake’s visual sequence highlighting Young’s
                            <hi rend="i">Lorenzo</hi> plot, the figure of Jesus as healer links the
                        first scene (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E) to the second (<hi rend="i">NT</hi>
148:40E), and the posture of the patient links the second scene
                        to the third (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486). The Man Fallen Among Thieves in 
<hi rend="i">NT 68</hi> (illus. 1), the first stand-in for Lorenzo, lacks,
                        at the moment represented, the faith that would contribute to his own
                        recovery, while for Lorenzo’s next stand-in, the man in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148:40E
(illus. 10), “<hi rend="i">That
                        Touch</hi>” of Jesus has the power to “heal the Soul /
                        Diseased” (IV, 39, 689-90). In the engraved version, the cure in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 40E is nearly conclusive; but in the watercolor version
                        Lorenzo has a relapse, as foretold in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 152 and 153:40E.
                        Then after more than 320 designs of ups and downs, what ought to be the
                        decisive cure is set to occur in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486, halfway through
                        the last Night of the poem.</p>
          <p>In order to move beyond the status of “poor, benighted
                        Traveller” (IX, 641), <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 450, and arrive as a
                        pilgrim on the verge of “<hi rend="i">Eternity</hi>,” <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 485
(IX, 1364), Lorenzo must in the last
                        “Night” undergo a two-part rectification: a purgation of the
                        reptilian from his heart, as shown in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486, and an
                        acceptance of the human in its place, as shown in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 487.
                        In the event it is the second phase of this cure “not . . .
                        Esculapian,” called for long ago in Night the Second, that proves
                        impossible, though it seems easy enough in the showing, which illustrates
                        Young’s vision of how <hi rend="i">Lorenzo’s</hi> problem <hi rend="i">ought</hi>
to be solved.</p>
          <p>The resolution of the Lorenzo plot occurs with the casting out of a demon in
                            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 486 (IX, 68; illus. 6), after several
                        Christ-dominated pictures that begins with <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                        482 (IX, 64). In <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486 the nude figure of Lorenzo,
                        curiously balanced, with knees drawn up, on a barren slope, and making
                        contradictory hand gestures, one accepting, the other rejecting, is shown
                        regurgitating a huge flaming salamander, issuing in a seven-pointed
                        pyrotechnic burst, in what is unmistakably a visual representation of
                            exorcism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref> This scene, confirming
                        Lorenzo’s continued illness and revealing its fundamental cause,
                        tends to bear out the implication that the cure proposed in <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 68:321E has been inefficacious: as the chief marked
                        lines (1386 and 1392-93) indicate, “Lorenzo’s
                        Salamander-Heart” has remained (for seven and a half long Nights)
                        largely unresponsive: “Cold, and untouch’d” (1387). The
                        poet therefore invokes “Great JEHOVAH’s Breath” to
                        “assist my Song” and thereby to “exorcize his
                        Heart” (1393). <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> See the picture of
                            the exorcism of a dumb man, based upon Luke 11:44ff., in <hi rend="i">The Bible in
Word and Art</hi>, ed. Melzer (sic) <hi rend="i">with
                                Illustrations by <corr type="emend">Matthäus Merian</corr></hi> (New York: Arch Cape, 1988)
                            211. In this scene the man writhes on the ground and vomits out, in a
                            sheet of fire, a small reptilian devil. A crowd of some 30 witnesses
                            stands around to see Jesus effect the exorcism which, according to Luke,
                            only briefly worked. The contrast between Merian’s crowd scene
                            and Blake’s solitary scene of exorcism is an indication of
                            Blake’s purposes. Merian’s unexceptional Good Samaritan
                            episode occurs just two pages earlier on 209.</note></p>
          <p>In this design, Lorenzo is positioned in what amounts to a combination of the
                        postures of the resistant patient of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68:21E
                        (illus. 1 and 2) and the ideally healed man in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148:40E
                        (illus. 10 and 11). The very tilt of his head to his right echoes that of
                        the regenerate man (to the left) in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148 (reversed in
                        the verso design 40E), but Lorenzo’s gaze in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486
                        is groggily directed outward toward the viewer; compare the eyes of Young in
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 525 and of Adam in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 529. The
                        coverlet of the wounded man in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68, which served only as
                        ground cover in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148, has wholly disappeared from 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486, and in this scene Lorenzo’s knees are drawn
                        up as far as possible beneath him, representing a further retraction of the
                        bent legs of the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68 figure and of the (tensionless)
                        back-bent legs of the receptive figure in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148. Now, in
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486 (IX, 58), Lorenzo reaches out to accept 
<pb id="p33-88" n="88"/>
a beneficence with his left hand (which is
                        practically invisible in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E), while with his right
                        hand raised palmout at the wrist in the rejectionist gesture, he is still
                        trying to ward off what he, as impersonation of the Man Fallen Among
                        Thieves, had not been able to accept from Jesus in the form of the Good
                        Samaritan. Although the Redeemer himself is not in evidence in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
486, he has just appeared in that role in the recto drawing <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 485 (IX, 67) and will
promptly reappear directing the
                        fishers of mankind in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 488 (IX, 70). The prodigious
                        salamander in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486, with its open mouth, forked tongue,
                        and undulating tail, recalls the serpent engraved on the ellipsoid chalice
                        in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E—the vessel which at the initial stage
                        of Lorenzo’s recovery was blocked from effecting the needed cure
                        because the victim was unable to recognize his beneficent neighbor who
                        appeared as a Samaritan. By Night the Ninth it has become all too clear that
                        the Man Fallen Among Thieves had suffered a spiritual wound and that,
                        consequently, the ominous-looking potion proposed by the Good Samaritan was,
                        after all, the best medicine for what has ailed the recalcitrant Lorenzo all
                        along—a homeopathic dose to cure the salamander of satanic Selfhood
                        harbored in his breast.</p>
          <p>There is a cosmic sign that the solitary exorcism in <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> 486 is going to prove incomplete. It reflects back on what
                        might have been accomplished in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E and relates to
                        one of Blake’s most insistent concerns: distinguishing between Divine
                        Mercy and Divine Wrath and the God or Gods who are responsible for each. In
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 486 two stars, one developed, the other unshapen,
                        appear in a break between the white cloud above and the black cloud below,
                        within which Lorenzo appears to be undergoing a self-exorcism. It must be
                        observed, however, that there is a kind of vertical tunnel or vortex that
                        extends down from above and effects the drawing-up of the flaming salamander
                        that had been possessing the man, who is still unfree beneath the dark
                        cloud. To this point the salamander has reached only a position of defiance,
                        mouth wide open, standing on its tail with a single flame-tip extending to
                        the verge of the sky that contains the unshapen star, at left. The motif of
                        a star, personified, who appears in a break in the clouds for the guidance
                        of “thou, poor benighted Traveller” (IX, 32, line 641) had
                        been set forth in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 450 and in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 483
                        (illus. 7); thus is revealed how the Creator originally situated the fiery
                        fixed stars, for better or for worse. In this design Blake adapts
                        Young’s imagery of Christian militancy so as to indicate a First
                        Judgment that is to be confirmed or altered in the Last. Above a chorus of
                        angels, who have been shown earlier in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 437 and 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 474, Christ the Creator performs a two-handed
                        disposition of cosmic fires: with his right hand upraised he upholds tongues
                        of flame that will settle in as a fixed and morning star. To do so Blake
                        adapts the raised right hand gesture of Michelangelo’s judge that had
                        been appropriated by the likes of Scarcellino and Rubens to handle the
                        thunderbolts of vengeance. With this right-handed God Blake makes an
                        improvement.</p>
          <p>With God’s left hand, however, the viewer must recognize a crooked
                        road (E 38) that may never become a star (E 35). In other words, Blake here
                        makes a concession to the cult of vengeance which seems to contradict his
                        own beliefs. Christ’s left hand is emitting flames downward that
                        apparently obliterate two or three of the innumerable angels who had
                        assembled in praise at the verge of the circle of fixed stars. We are to
                        understand that these are the very flames that, alas, continue to fall upon
                        Sodom, as revealed much earlier to Lot’s awestruck wife, in the
                        aforementioned <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 158, the titlepage for Night
                        the Fifth.</p>
          <p>Blake later wrote “The Everlasting Gospel,” including the lines
                        of the epigraph for this essay, in order to liberate the vision of the
                        Christian God from that of his antitype <hi rend="i">Jupiter tonans</hi>,
                        which seems too credible, especially in time of war. Blake’s campaign
                        to reveal God was still going on about 1820 when he was again working
                        through the Christian imagery of another writer to create a true <hi rend="i">Epitome
of James Hervey’s</hi> “<hi rend="i">Meditations among the Tombs</hi>” (Butlin, cat. 770, pl. 967).
                        The God who acts as Judge, in this Judgment upon the Bible, is seated within
                        a circle, book open, and supported by wings that contain eight or more
                        horsemen that are about to issue forth. This is the central upper image of a
                        system that disposes the fires of wrath equally upon the Just and the
                        Unjust. Above the left wing of this Judge appears an inscription that ought
                        to have found a central place within “The Everlasting Gospel”:
                        “God out of Christ is a Consuming Fire” (E 691). Below, as
                        Hervey approaches the communion table, his angels offer help in making a
                        distinction between the goblets of Mercy and Wrath. Much less remote from
                        present humanity is Jesus, who hovers above a cloud strip, between Moses and
                        Elias, over the communion table. We recall that this Jesus had already 
(<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E) offered his own, unprepossessing, beneficence
                        to the Man Fallen after he had been passed by, on the other side, by
                        potential guides who ought to have helped but who believed they had higher
                        obligations and thus continued on down to Jericho. There remains a question
                        as to whether Hervey the communicant, his hands spread at his side in awe,
                        is able to envision the group of Jesus who are hovering above the communion
                        table and also to reject that (left-handed) God of Deuteronomy 4:34 and
                        Hebrews 12:29, who was no better than “a consuming fire.”
                        Considering the position taken up by Hervey in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        72:51 (E 227), at the Southern Gate of Love, he ought to be able to do so.
                        But a gatekeeper might be engaged to exclude himself, as well as other
                        potential entrants. Just at the bottom of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 72 the
                        old serpent covers a sinister warning that is conveyed in reversed writing:
                        “Women the comforters of Men become Tormentors and Punishers.”
                        Should we doubt whether this is another “serpentine
                        dissimulation” (E 614)?</p>
          <p>Despite the exorcism in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 486 (illus. 6), and
                        the salutary exhortation in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 487, <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi>
continues through several other ups and downs: in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 489, it is 
<pb id="p33-89" n="89"/>
	<hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> who is again drawn by flesh and the Devil as he
                        waves off the exhortation of Spirit to rise. But in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 490
                        he seems again, according to directions, to have turned his life around. He
                        has another chance in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 517, a sort of reprise of 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 71:22E, where it is <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> who
                        appears as the bed-side witness at the dying of a good man, who, however,
                        raises his hand in a gentle gesture against such solicitude. The dying,
                        open-eyed Friend is able to see, as <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> is not, the
                        spirits who will effect his transport. In <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 519, a
                        reprise of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 76:23E, <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> is being
                        carried up forcibly by his angelic Friend, but he nevertheless protests,
                        howling against this rapture. In <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 521, <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi>
is back in his bed, bearing a cousin of Fuseli’s
                        incubus that squats upon his head and experiencing a nightmare that features
                        a fair lady pursued by wild hunters with dogs, such as were last seen in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 117:32E. It is again <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> who, in
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 523, is scared and admonished by a ghost in a
                        gothic grove at midnight. One might be tempted to read <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        525 as one final chance for <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> in bed, with an angel
                        at his head waving the wand of sleep and about to administer a beneficent
                        draught, now from an unmarked cup, which nevertheless recalls the goblet
                        proffered by the Good Samaritan in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E. But Young
                        has stopped thinking about <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> on the previous page,
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 524, where he makes his last appearance, damned in
                        a generational conflict. The viewer of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 525 is supposed
                        to recall the situation of the sleepless Young, in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        8:2E, where the angel applies his wand of sleep to the flock, rather than to
                        the insomniac author. There is no sign that <hi rend="i">Lorenzo!</hi> will
                        ever get another chance to be corrigible. At least, that is the conclusive
                        inference.</p>
          <p>One reason the healing motif in the earlier <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                        has not been clearly recognized is that it has become customary to refer to
                            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148:40E (illus. 10 and 11) as a picture of the
                        raising of Lazarus (e.g., Butlin, cat. re 330.148). But comparison with the
                        later watercolor <hi rend="i">The Raising of Lazarus</hi> (Butlin, cat. 487,
                        pl. 564)—as well as with renderings of this subject by other
                        artists—makes this seem an iconographically unjustifiable connection.
                        In the watercolor Jesus effects the resuscitation with an open hand raised
                        to heaven, together with a call to Lazarus in a loud voice; in response
                        Lazarus rises, diagonally, with eyes wide, mouth open, and hands spread in
                        wonder. In <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148:40E, by contrast, the healing is
                        effected in an unspecified location where there are no other witnesses, and
                        with a hands-on technique. If the scene is to be related to any Gospel story
                        it is to the Cleansing of the Leper (Mt. 8:2-4, Mk. 1:40-45; Lk. 5:12-16),
                        which is always represented as a hands-on cure, and for which the raised arm
                        in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148:40E would translate as the solicitation of the
                        leper. That the touch of Jesus is a crucial determinant has been overlooked,
                        in turn, because of another tradition (see Essick and La Belle, xvii) in
                        which this design is related to three pages in the illuminated books. In two
                        of these, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> b<hi rend="s">1</hi> and
“The Divine Image” in <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi> 18, the gesture of the out-stretched arm is clearly that
                        of the creator (and is intended to recall—with a
                        difference—Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Creation of Adam</hi>
                        in the Sistine Ceiling.) In the third, “The Chimney Sweeper,”
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> 12, the “angel” with
                        a long gown bends over and touches the resuscitating sweep, who climbs out
                        of the ground, thus inviting some comparison with <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
                        148:40E. But in “The Chimney Sweeper” the distinguishing motif
                        is of the touching of helping hands, as in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                        144 (IV, 35), where Jesus kneels and draws out of the flames of hell a
                        “him” evidently to be identified with “me,” or
                        the spirit of Young, who would otherwise have been damned to his “<hi rend="i">Fear
of Death.</hi>” This motif, in turn, derives from
                        Dürer’s woodcut <hi rend="i">The Harrowing of Hell</hi>, which
                        likewise does <hi rend="i">not</hi> employ a healing hand gesture, the
                        essential distinguishing gesture in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148:40E.</p>
          <p>The importance and the efficacy of Jesus’s touch are again emphasized
                        in two pictures near the end of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, one an act
                        of creation, the other a gesture of reassurance. Deliberately recalling the
                        rehabilitating touch in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 148:40E (illus. 10 and 11) is a
                        scene in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 529 (IX, 111), responding to the
                        text “Father of IMMORTALITY to Man” (IX, 2295), in which Jesus
                        appears in his originary role as the creator of Adam (fig. 2 in my 1990
                        article). As Jesus looks down into the half-living eyes of Adam, who at this
                        point has only partially emerged from the earth, he breathes visible breath
                        into the open mouth of the new man, while reaching with his right hand for a
                        clod of clay and resting his left hand on the top of the man’s nearly
                        finished head. Two pages later there is yet another kind of touch, a touch
                        of reassurance: in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 531 (IX, 113), Jesus bends down from
                        heaven and lowers his hand to which the recumbent Young, at his book still,
                        responds by raising his head and returning Jesus’s touch—the
                        first contact between the two in the entire series.</p>
          <p>There have been readers who doubt whether the kinds of irony I declare to be
                        operating in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68:21E (illus.
                        1 and 2) could possibly have occurred two centuries ago. In his earlier
                        identities, it has been maintained, the Good Samaritan, especially in his
                        anagogic identity as the Messiah, would have been too venerable for
                        imputation, with regard either to tactics or purposes. That is perhaps why
                        the Explainer in 1797 had nothing to say about such unsettling
                        potentialities and why, even in 1957, Margoliouth saw fit to equivocate as
                        to the Samaritan’s identity as Christ. I shall rest my case as to
                        what was once imagined with the example of a print by Rembrandt which,
                        though made by an artist Blake deeply disapproved of, shows how subversive
                        an illustration of the parable could have been imagined, in
                        seventeenth-century Holland. And likewise misread by commentators who have
                        been variously inhibited from acknowledging what the artist is showing.</p>
          <p>Rembrandt’s so-called “Good Samaritan” (illus. 9) exists
                        in four states, which vary only slightly, and in later impressions 
<pb id="p33-90" n="90"/>
<figure n="BUT330.1.148.WC" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
	<head>10 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 148, IV, p. 39. Watercolor. c.
                                1797.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum, Department of Prints and
                                Drawings.</figDesc>
</figure> are both signed and dated 1633.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref> Rembrandt’s actual subject is the Arrival at the Inn,
                        which is rendered with such complexity amid the bustle that one must look a
                        little to determine which figure is supposed to be the Good Samaritan. Why
                        is he shown from behind? What is he offering to pay the 
<pb id="p33-91" n="91"/>
<figure n="night-thoughts-40e-iv-p90.033.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="410" height="500">
	<head>11 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 40E, IV, p. 90. Uncolored
                                print.</head>
	<figDesc>Undated (c. 1797). University of Iowa Libraries.</figDesc>
</figure> innkeeper? Are “two pence” (here, in advance)
                        adequate for the shabby facilities indicated? What is going on behind the
                        Samaritan’s back while he is trying to carry through with his
                        beneficence? One sees just enough of this Samaritan to be certain, at least,
                        that he bears no resemblance to Jesus Christ. In the foreground, by
                        contrast, a dog appears that pays no attention to any people as he relieves
                        himself. Elsewhere in the inn yard a rooster and hen are interacting in an
                        ordinary way. And farther to the right of the stone porch is a cracked and
                        deteriorated well over which a woman is bending to draw water. Naturally
                        these figures take no notice of the Arrival. Various other structures in the
                        innyard add little of significance to the sense of the setting. 
<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> The so-called <hi rend="i">Good
                                    Samaritan</hi> of 1633 is well presented in Gary Schwartz, ed.,
                                    <hi rend="i">The Complete Etchings of Rembrandt: Reproduced in
                                    Original Size</hi> (New York: Dover, 1994) no. B90. Two other
                                prints to be considered are: <hi rend="i">Christ and the Woman of
                                    Samaria: Among Ruins</hi>, of 1634, no. B71, and a later print,
                                    <hi rend="i">Christ and the Woman of Samaria: An Arched
                                    Print</hi>, of 1658, which is assigned the no. B70. Somewhat
                                more detailed verbal descriptions, though with less satisfactory
                                reproductions, are set forth in Christopher White and Karel J. Boon,
                                eds., <hi rend="i">Rembrandt van Rijn, Holstein’s Dutch and
                                    Flemish Etchings, Engravings and Woodcuts</hi>, Two Vols.,
                                XVIII-XIX (Amsterdam: Vangendt, 1969) 50 and 36-37. Ludwig
                                Münz’s <hi rend="i">A Critical Catalogue of
                                    Rembrandt’s Etchings. . .</hi> Two Vols. (London:
                                Phaidon, 1952) contains excellent reproductions in vol. I but the
                                discussions in vol. II, 93-94, 95, 109, are burdened by suppositions
                                about contributions made by Rembrandt’s school. Münz
                                had earlier considered the “Good Samaritan” matters in
                                    <hi rend="i">Die Kunst Rembrandts und Goethes Sehen</hi>
                                (Leipzig: Heinrich Keller, 1934), esp. 82-88. Hidde Hoekstra, 
<hi rend="i">Rembrandt and the Bible</hi> (Utrecht: Magna, 1990),
                                esp. 324-39, presents good reproductions and notes on many but not
                                all of the “Good Samaritan” pictures in several media.
                                Versions of Jesus and the Woman at the Well appear, under the
                                heading “Living Water,” 300-05. Rembrandt’s
                                drawing of the “Washing of the Feet,” a theme to which
                                I allude, is shown 366-67, and the sketch of <hi rend="i">The Last
                                    Supper</hi>, 368-69, which copies what the artist supposed to be
                                Leonardo’s picture, contains a dog that curiously relates to
                                the dog introduced in Rembrandt’s <hi rend="i">Arrival at the
                                    Inn.</hi> The matter of the dog in Rembrandt (without mention of
                                    <hi rend="i">The Last Supper</hi>) is well surveyed in Susan
                                Donahue Kuretsky, “Rembrandt’s <hi rend="i">Good
                                    Samaritan Etching</hi>: Reflections on a Disreputable
    Dog,” in Cynthia P. <corr type="emend">Schneider,</corr> William W. Robinson, and Alice
                                J. Davies, eds., <hi rend="i">Shop Talk: Studies in Honor of Seymour
                                    Slive</hi> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Art Museums, 1995)
                                150-53 and 351-53. Readers who consult Ernst Van De Wetering,
                                “Rembrandt’s <hi rend="i">Satire on Art
                                Criticism</hi>,” in the same <hi rend="i">Festchrift</hi>,
                                264-70 and 425, will understand that the attitudes of the animals in
                                the (unmentioned) <hi rend="i">Arrival at the Inn</hi> were
                                deliberately presented by Rembrandt.
                            <p>Goethe’s observations on “Rembrandt as a
                                thinker,” of 8 July 1831, are ably set forth by John Gage,
                                ed. and trans., <hi rend="i">Goethe on Art</hi> (Berkeley: U of
                                California P, 1980) 207-09. In Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, <hi rend="i">Essays
on Art and Literature</hi>, ed. John Geary and
                                tr. by Nardroff and Nardroff, <hi rend="i">Goethe’s Collected
                                    Works</hi>, Vol. 3 (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1994) 66-68 and
                                247n, by contrast, many things go wrong. The worst of these is that
                                the reproduction of the print in question is cropped on the left
                                side so that the robber chieftain is entirely eliminated from the
                                picture. The moderately-curious reader of this text would wonder,
                                for a little, what Goethe could possibly have been driving at in his
                                discussion of this print. It must also be pointed out, however, that
                                Goethe, the astute critic, also nodded: he tried to count the humans
                                in the picture and tallied (only) <hi rend="i">six</hi>—the
                                males. There is, indeed, a seventh, the <hi rend="i">woman</hi> at
                                the well! If, as I have suggested, she is to supposed to be
                                recognized as the future Woman of Samaria, Goethe’s mistally
                                seems deplorable. It is a fact, however, duly pointed out by Gage,
                                that Goethe took <hi rend="i">no</hi> notice whatever of the
                                defecating dog that dominates the foreground in Rembrandt’s
                                    <hi rend="i">Arrival at the Inn</hi>, though a number of modern
                                commentators have held forth concerning that unseemly canine. In his
                                unpublished observations, of course, Goethe had no obligation either
                                to acknowledge the dog or to count the woman, though his inattention
                                to them limits the value of what he had to say.</p>
	<p>Strangely, however, at least two art historians of distinction have
                                declared that Goethe’s comments were focused upon the
                                defecating dog: Kenneth Clark, <hi rend="i">Rembrandt and the
                                    Italian Renaissance</hi> (New York: Norton, 1968) 12, and Jean
                                Starobinski, <hi rend="i">Largesse</hi>, tr. Jane Marie Todd (U of
                                Chicago P, 1997) 192. It has not, I think, been remarked that the
                                Samaritan’s horse, which carried the victim to this inn, has
                                its lips curled and indulges in a quiet horse laugh—at what
                                fools these mortals be.</p>
	<p>Those who doubt whether Rembrandt’s horse is grinning should
                                consider the full-fledged horse-laugh of the beast in a quite
                                different handling of the Inn episode by Maarten Heemskerck: the
                                fourth design of the 1549 set, as engraved by Dirck Volkertsz. [sic]
                                Coornhert (<hi rend="i">Illustrated Bartsch</hi> 55:034.3). Here,
                                although neither the Samaritan nor the Innkeeper is good looking,
                                there is no sign that the victim has been brought to a dangerous
                                place; this horse must just feel good about its
                            benefaction.</p></note></p>
          <p>As Goethe was the first to write in 1831, the focus of Rembrandt’s
                        picture is the discovery made by the still-wounded Man Fallen as he is being
                        lifted down by a servant from the Good Samaritan’s horse, of a male
                        face that looks unconcernedly out a window at the inn to which the victim
                        has been brought. That stolid younger man, with a feather in his hat, is,
                        however, recognized with distress by the Man 
<pb id="p33-92" n="92"/>
Fallen
                        as none other than the captain of the thieves who had waylaid him! To such a
                        place of rehabilitation (quite seedy when you look at it) had the Jewish
                        victim been brought by a Samaritan! Blake, who might, hypothetically, have
                        discovered Rembrandt’s main idea 35 years or more before Goethe,
                        would very likely have gone on to infer that the decrepit inn to which the
                        Jewish victim had been brought by the Good Samaritan must be in Samaria.
                        Rembrandt can have had no other purpose in including in this busy scene of
                        the Arrival a woman drawing water at a well. At that juncture she was a
                        woman of no importance, but soon thereafter, in 1634, Rembrandt, in accord
                        with John 4:1-42, recast her as the companion who spoke with Jesus, the
                        Woman at the Well. He somehow knew a lot about her. That Samaritan woman
                        soon recognized him as the Messiah.</p>
          <p>I believe that, though Blake came to detest Rembrandt, he could have
                        penetrated the welter of genre imagery in this <hi rend="i">Arrival at the
                            Inn</hi> to imagine back to what must have been the feelings of the Man
                        who had Fallen Among Thieves, when he first laid eyes on a Samaritan who
                        proffered something in an unprepossessing vessel which supposedly would heal
                        his wounds. What the victim is able to see in the encounter at the inn, as
                        imagined by Rembrandt, or beside the road, as imagined by Blake, could only
                        have confirmed the ethnic apprehensions of the waylaid victim.</p>
          <p>One other artist before Blake who had explored the ethnic antipathies that
                        underlie the parable was, as has been noted, Luca Giordano in his Good
                            Samaritan<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref> of c. 1670 and this only
                        with respect to the viewer, who is shown a sinister-appearing benefactor.
                        But Giordano’s victim is wholly unconscious and thus unable to react
                        to the sinister appearance of this Samaritan. Since Blake could not have
                        know of the Giordano painting and it was not (so far as I know) reproduced
                        as a print, Blake could have seen only Rembrandt’s print, which
                        features amidst the bustle the reactions of the conscious Jewish victim to
                        what he sees in Samaria. Certainly nothing the poet Edward Young had to say,
                        in Night the Second, would have served to prompt the pictorial ideas Blake
                        set forth in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68:21E. 
<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> The Jacopo Bassano <hi rend="i">Good Samaritan</hi>
                            (National Gallery, London, no. 277) and the Luca Giordano <hi rend="i">Good
Samaritan</hi> (Rouen) are both reproduced in color (with
                            details obscured, unfortunately) on 186 and 187 in Bruce Bernard, <hi rend="i">The
Bible and Its Painters</hi>, with an introduction by
                            Lawrence Gowing (New York: Macmillan, 1983). The editor,
                            incontrovertibly, comments on 291: “You can at first mistake the
                            Samaritan for the robber in this picture . . . .”</note></p>
          <p>Blake is not known to have made another Good Samaritan design, after <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E,
nor did he make any design on the
                        closely-related subject of the Samaritan Woman at the Well, though some of
                        his followers took up the theme. However, for the climactic work 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem, the Emanation of the Giant Albion</hi> Blake did
                        make a design that alludes to the Good Samaritan parable and in many
                        respects recalls the distinctively Blakean treatment of the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> encounter. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 33/37, at
                        the top<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
(illus. 12), Blake presents a
                        naked man <hi rend="i">fallen</hi> onto his left knee as he collapses limply
                        backwards into the supporting arms of a haloed kneeling figure who,
                        especially in colored copy E, exhibits the unmistakable features of Jesus
                        Christ. As Wicksteed, Erdman, and Paley have pointed out, this scene of
                        Albion sinking down is taking place “between the Palm Tree &amp; the
                        Oak of Weeping.” (esp. <hi rend="i">J</hi> 23:24, cf. <hi rend="i">J</hi> 59:5-6).
And as Paley adds, when Albion collapses in despair,
                        “the merciful Savior in his arms / Receiv’d him” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 48:1-2)
and placed him upon “the Rock of
                        Ages,” which is then built up as a pillared “Couch of
                        repose” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 48:6). <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i">
Jerusalem</hi> 33/37, the colored copy E, is readily
                                available in Morton D. Paley, ed., William Blake, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem: The
Emanation of the Giant Albion</hi>,
                                Blake’s Illuminated Books Vol. I (William Blake
                                Trust/Princeton UP, 1991). <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>
                                contains a clear reduced reproduction of uncolored copy D. Joseph
                                Wicksteed’s [A Commentary on] <hi rend="i">William
                                    Blake’s Jerusalem</hi> (London: Trianon, 1953) is a
                                companion volume to the Trianon reproduction of uncolored copy C
                                issued by Trianon in 1952 as well as of the 1951 facsimile of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, colored copy E.
                            <p>Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William
                                    Blake’s Jerusalem</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1983)
                                contains important comments on some aspects of this plate and also
                                presents, as illustration 1, a high quality (though reduced)
                                reproduction of the page in the final copy F, which Blake perhaps
                                produced as late as 1827. See David Bindman, assisted by Deirdre
                                Toomey, <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William
                                    Blake</hi> (London: Thames and Hudson, 1978) pl. 512 for copy A.
                                The point of the chin of the benefactor displays what might be taken
                                to signify a tiny pointed beard.</p>
	<p>There is a concise summary of what some of the major symbols on page
                                33/37 have been taken to mean by interpreters in Henry Summerfield,
                                    <hi rend="i">A Guide to the Books of William Blake for Innocent
                                    and Experienced Readers</hi>, with notes on interpretive
                                criticism 1910 to 1984. (Gerrards Cross Bucks: 1998) declared to be
                                dist. in USA by Oxford UP, NY, 779. How the posture of Albion in 
<hi rend="i">J</hi> 33/37 should be understood can be derived from
                                the postures of WILLIAM in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32 and ROBERT in
                                    <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 37. The cast-back heads directed toward
                                the heavens and the bent-back torsos of both brothers, who are about
                                to be hit by falling stars, notably resemble those of the collapsing
                                Albion. But, by contrast, the characters in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                                retain their footings and, presumably, their consciousness, whereas
                                Albion is represented as unable to avoid collapse without the
                                intervention of the Good Savior. This comparison perhaps shows that
                                collective humankind lacks the unaided staying-power proven by
                                witnesses or prophets. Is this “a self-evident thing”
                                (E 613-14; cf. 621)?</p></note></p>
          <p>This episode as described and shown (and linked to other pictorial details on
                            <hi rend="i">J</hi> 33/37, not here considered) pointedly alludes to the
                        Good Samaritan in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68:21E, with such images
                        as the two contrasting trees, one oakish, in the foreground and two crossed
                        (thin) palm trees at the right. In two of the five versions of the design in
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, copies D and E, the benefactor is revealed,
                        chiefly by his beard, to be none other than Jesus Christ himself, much as he
                        had appeared to be in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68:21E. The cause of
                        Albion’s 
<pb id="p33-93" n="93"/>
<figure n="jerusalem-d-33-37.033.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="758" height="1000">
	<head>12 Jerusalem 33/37.</head>
	<figDesc>Copy D, c. 1820. By permission of the Houghton Library, Harvard
                                University.</figDesc>
</figure> collapse is, however, different. It is Albion’s own despair
                        rather than a consequence of an assault of highwaymen, and matters of
                        recognition and rejection are quite differently managed. In all five
                        versions Albion’s head has fallen back so that his attention (if any)
                        is directed skyward and he seems quite unaware of his benefactor, who is
                        sustaining him.</p>
          <p>There are small but suggestive differences among the four uncolored copies
                        and the larger differences between colored copy E and any of the uncolored
                        copies, most of which have not been described, that tend to be more apparent
                        to the viewer who is aware of the permutations of Good Samaritan pictures by
                        other artists. Among the noteworthy variations are the following: in copies
                        A, C, and F the benefactor lacks any distinct beard and, especially in F,
                        the features seem more those of a woman than a man. Add to that the presence
                        of a gowned figure supporting a helpless nude male and the allusion suggest
                        a <hi rend="i">Pietá</hi>, such as that in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
                        52, “To Tirzah,” where two women more or less support the
                        corpse, with his head thrown back, while old Joseph of Arimathea prepares to
                        empty a pitcher upon the victim, in an attempt to revive him.</p>
          <p>The two trees also differ markedly among the five copies. The oak tree at the
                        right, in colored copy E, has a solid heavy trunk (although with mottled
                        shading upon it) and a thick, almost uniform, foliage. All the uncolored oak
                        trees, however, bear black spots or split-marks and the later copies
                        definitely diverge at the top. Only at the left side of the oak do the
                        uncolored copies of this tree emit some four branches, one bearing a large
                        acorn, that stretch out toward the collapsed Albion. At the left of this
                        Good Samaritan pair there is a peculiar thick palm tree with some seven
                        “bark-shields” on its trunk and three to five small coconuts
                        and a large frond hanging down its left side. Also noteworthy is a small
                        plant that grows to the left of its base. In colored copy E, by contrast,
                        there are only four or five of the trunk “shields,” which seem
                        more like tailored stones than bark, and there is no fruit. But palm
                        branches surround this “trunk” on both sides and the large
                        one, at left, sweeps down (as the uncolored counterparts do not) into the
                        lower sky that begins beneath the winged orb.</p>
          <p>After a considerable amount of research into the bewildering varieties of
                        palm trees, I was about to abandon the 
<pb id="p33-94" n="94"/>
idea that
                        this object was supposed to be entirely arboreal. But then I was reminded by
                        Alexander Gourlay of Blake’s watercolor of 1806, <hi rend="i">The
                            Repose of the Holy Family in Egypt</hi> (Butlin, cat. 472, pl. 543) in
                        which a huge thick palm, with some 17 bark “shields,” and two
                        branches of dates, overarches the fugitive family. And near the parents
                        there is a veritable garden of four varied flowers that recall the tuft of
                        grass growing at the base of the palm tree in uncolored copies of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 33/37.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Sturdy palms do, of course, signify
                                Egypt, as in the late watercolor <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the
                                    Ark of the Bulrushes</hi> (Butlin, cat. 774, pl. 968) and in the
                                print evidently related to it, <hi rend="i">The Hiding of
                                    Moses.</hi> See Bindman 1978 pls. 624a and 624b. But the
                                positioning of palms at the exit gate of the Garden of Eden is more
                                explicitly ominous, as in the 1803 <hi rend="i">Angel of the Divine
                                    Presence Clothing Adam and Eve with Coats of Skins</hi> (Butlin,
                                cat. 436, pl. 513). At the end of a colonnade of bunched palm trees,
                                the branches of which overarch a tunnel-gate exit, the giant angel
                                blocks the way back into the garden as he clothes the first people
                                prepatory to dismissing them into the corridor between the flaming
                                sacrificial altars that stand on the very edge of this world. The
                                most prominent oak tree back in Eden is featured in <hi rend="i">Adam Naming
the Beasts</hi> (Butlin, cat. 667, pl. 890) of
                                1810. It frames Adam’s head and features its three large
                                acorns. He points up to one acorn—not to an apple—as
                                his serpent familiar smiles in expectation of what this will lead
                                to. Did the serpent smile, foreseeing how its own image would be
                                engraved on the ciborium to be proffered by Jesus Christ, the Good
                                Samaritan, to the Man Fallen?
                            <p>As for the prototype for Blake’s Spectre in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
33/37, to which I allude in the next paragraph,
                                see “The Vampire of Guiana” (A Smith Sculpt—<hi rend="i">not</hi>
Blake), as published by J. Johnson in 1791,
                                37. John Gabriel Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative of a Five Years
                                    Expedition against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</hi>,
                                Translated for the First Time from the Original 1790 Manuscript,
                                eds. Richard Price and Sally Price (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP,
                                1988) 430.</p>
	<p>Earlier (355), reacting to the conduct of the anti-guerilla troops,
                                Stedman recalled Ovid, <hi rend="i">Tristia</hi>, 2.33-34;
                                translated in the Price edition on 691: “If Jupiter used his
                                thunder Bolts as often as Men deserve He soon would have none to
                                use.” If Classic Virtue was Christianity.... the Good
                                Samaritan would be past hoping for.</p></note></p>
          <p>I must, however, point out that Blake included, in this <hi rend="i">Riposo</hi>, the donkey
which brought the Family to Egypt. It is
                        drinking from a stream, doubtless a tributary of the Nile, while the Infant
                        is feeding at his mother’s breast. Unluckily I did not recall this
                        benign donkey when, in my 1990 essay, I referred to an identical donkey that
                        browses near <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>, in the three versions of the color
                        print (Butlin, cat. 316, pl. 396; cat. 317, pl. 415; cat. 318, pl. 416). As
                        Heppner correctly pointed out, I mistakenly inferred that the resemblance
                        between Hecate’s donkey and the browsing horse of the Samaritan in
                            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68:21E should suggest that there may be
                        something else amiss in Blake’s encounter between the Man Fallen and
                        the Samaritan. I would, however, maintain that the human-headed bat flying
                        above the triple Hecate (when combined with the vampire bat of Surinam) must
                        have produced the horrific pterodactyl that hovers above the recumbent
                        Jerusalem who is laid out at the bottom of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        33/37.</p>
          <p>The Jesus who, in a Good Samaritan maneuver, receives the falling Albion,
                        looks in copy E very like the other main image of Jesus in this copy of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 76, who is tranquilly crucified upon the
                        bifurcated oak but is energetically responded to by the vigorous re-arisen
                        Albion. Many details were, however, altered when this design was colored;
                        one of the most suggestive is that a pool of blue water was added at the
                        base of the tree, just by the right foot of Albion. In the uncolored
                        versions of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 33/37 (except D) by contrast, the
                        face of the Savior looks wholly unlike the dark bearded face of the
                        crucified Jesus in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 76, whose mouth is gathered
                        into an “O” of pain. But Blake intended to contrast the
                        insensate Albion of the earlier plate with the alert and observant
                        “Albion” of the later plate. Recall how much depended on the
                        inability of the Man Fallen, in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 68:21E, to
                        recognize his Savior who appeared to him as a Samaritan.</p>
          <p>We ought to be clear that though in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 33/37 the
                        benefactor is <hi rend="i">behind</hi> the man falling this does not signify
                        a departure from earlier Good Samaritan tableaus. In such presentations of
                        the subject as Hayman’s, the Samaritan administers his medicines from
                        behind the victim. In other cases, as in the aforementioned <hi rend="i">Good
Samaritan</hi> by Jacopo Bassano (Reynolds-National Gallery), the
                        benefactor is situated behind the (already-bandaged) victim, for he strives
                        to raise the wounded man, who is only dimly conscious, onto the back of his
                        horse. These and other resemblances are sufficient to sustain the allusion
                        to the exemplary parable even though the words of the text of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> contain no literal mention of the Great
                        “Samaritan.” Indeed the picture at the top of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 33/37 is
almost the only pictorial feature within
                        chapter 2 that, at least by allusion, can be construed as sustaining the
                        opening address “To the Jews” on plate 27. Because Jesus was
                        the Savior of Albion, the Ancient Man, Israel, should return and participate
                        in the building of Jerusalem.</p>
          <p>What the Good Samaritan can do is to rescue the Man Fallen from misprision or
                        misapprehension. When Jesus appears in <hi rend="i">The Everlasting
                            Gospel</hi> he tells what Humanity must learn to adore, not the God of
                        Death but the Spirit of Life. We are shown that this communication has
                        already taken place on the scroll being passed down from Jesus himself to
                        Adam arisen in the Genesis titlepages (Butlin, cats. 828. <hi rend="i">1</hi> &amp;
<hi rend="i">2</hi>, pls. 974 &amp; 975). Evidently this
                        message is rarely grasped outside of Eden. In <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> 6:1E it was again delivered by a visionary boy but neither
                        the Spinner nor Death nor the commentators paid any attention to it. And
                        when in <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 12 Elihu explains the same matter, without
                        benefit of text, the most distinguished expositors have supposed that he is
                        issuing a “wrathful rebuke” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 95:23, E
                        255).</p>
          <p>It may be that Blake himself had not fully comprehended the project of
                        building Jerusalem in the years 1795-97, when he was working on the designs
                        for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> To read any set of motifs solely in
                        the light of Blake’s use of similar 
<pb id="p33-95" n="95"/>
motifs
                        elsewhere, to put a standardized Blakified spin on each design for Young, is
                        to oversimplify both Blake and Young. The total corpus of Blake’s
                        work abounds with similarities that have no elucidatory power so far as the
                            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series is concerned, even though that
                        fact may be concealed, even from an interpreter, by the persuasive force of
                        his or her critical rhetoric. I have not found a sure way to navigate such
                        dilemmas with confidence of discovering interpretations unerringly
                        consistent with Blake’s own intentions and purposes, insofar as they
                        can be recovered. But I do not consider the sifting of truth from error a
                        utopian goal, even though the work can never be finished. I welcome the
                        discovery of errors in interpretation, my own included, because recognition
                        of false leads helps to close blind alleys and open more productive lines of
                        exploration, clearing a temporary path to the next interpretive
                        crossroads.</p>
          <p>Let me end with these reflections on Blake’s grandest design project,
                        the 538 watercolor drawings for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts.</hi> I suppose that there were days when, faced with a text
                        panel bearing some 22 lines of Young’s discursive verses requiring a
                        pictorial response, Blake’s invention was not up to the challenge of
                        producing something profoundly meaningful. Yet after many decades of
                        pondering the designs and struggling with perplexities arising from them,
                        often in collaboration with greatly gifted scholars, I continue to believe
                        that Blake’s imagination rarely failed him in his mighty endeavor to
                        wrest art, life, energy, and meaning from what Young himself, at his most
                        prophetic, acknowledged as his “parson’d Page” (IV,
                        842).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
