<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>34.1.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Blake Drawing Rediscovered and Redated</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2000</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2000</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">34.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Anne Birien</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Claire Colebrook</name>
              <name>Hans-Ulrich Möhring</name>
              <name>Nicholas M. Williams</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2000"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_34">
    <body>
	  <pb id="p34-22" n="22"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-34-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Blake Drawing Rediscovered and Redated</title>
          </head>
          <byline>BY <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>William Michael Rossetti’s “Annotated Lists of Blake’s Paintings, Drawings and
Engravings,” added as an appendix to Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi>,
1863, and revised for the second edition of 1880, are invaluable in listing Blake’s works when they were
still in the hands of a relatively small number of owners, and in helping identify particular works through
the almost naive specificality of some of his descriptions. However, unless the work is actually dated (and
not even then in every case), Rossetti rarely gives any indication as to the period of a work, nor of its
connection to any specific series of designs or set of illustrations. Remarks such as “A sketch for a design
afterwards executed” is tantalizing to say the least (1863, p. 247, list 2, no. 78, and 1880, p. 266, list
2, no. 103; this drawing, listed as untraced in my catalogue, Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and
Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 1981, pp. 455-56, no. 610, has still not been identified). Hence it is not
altogether unforgivable that the drawing entitled by Rossetti “The Last Trumpet” (illus. 1: see cover) 
should have been listed by me as a possible illustration to [Robert] Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, “c.
<pb id="p34-1" n="1"/>
  <figure n="BUT617.1.1.WD.100" rend="file" width="958" height="929">
	<head>Cover (and illus. 1<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/>): <hi rend="i">The Last Trumpet</hi>, c. 1785.</head>
<figDesc>Pen, black ink and grey wash, 8 1/16 × 8 3/8 in. (20.4 × 21.2 cm). 
Butlin #617 recto.<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/></figDesc>
  </figure>
<pb id="p34-23" n="23"/>
<figure n="verso617.34.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="386">
	<figTranscr>3/</figTranscr>
	<head>2 Sketches for Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, and other works, c. 1802-03.</head>
	<figDesc>Pencil, 8 ⅙ × 8 ⅜ in. (20.4 × 21.2 cm). Newly recorded verso of Butlin #617. Photo courtesy of
Sotheby’s, London.</figDesc>
</figure>
1805 (?)” (Butlin, p. 458, no. 617). Nor, at first sight, W. Graham Robertson in his edition of
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, incorporating Rossetti’s Lists of 1907, now available in a welcome
reprint by Dover Publications, 1998, should identify it with the drawing in the British Museum of 
<hi rend="i">An Angel Awakening the Dead with a Trumpet</hi> (Butlin, p. 456, no. 612, repr. pl. 853A), possibly
done for the “Characteristic Frontispiece” intended for <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi></p>
          <p>However, a comparison between the British Museum drawing and Rossetti’s description had already
demonstrated that Robertson’s identification was incorrect, the most specific part of Rossetti’s
description failing to be matched in the drawing: “An Angel in the upper mid-plane of the design is blowing
the trumpet, <hi rend="i">the tube of which comes forward in a conspicuous way.</hi> Souls, chiefly of women
and children, are rising from the earth, and received by angels” (Rossetti 1863, p. 248, list 2, no. 86, and
1880, p. 266, list 2, no. 112; Robertson 1907, p. 473, list 2, no. 86; emphasis mine). The trumpet in the
British Museum drawing is unmistakably facing more or less directly downwards, but in the drawing here
illustrated it does come forward in a conspicuous way.</p>
          <p>This drawing, for sight and information of which I am indebted to Henry Wemyss of Sotheby’s,
fits Rossetti’s description exactly and is clearly one of that large group of pen and wash drawings to be
dated to the early 1780s; in particular, the heads of the resurrected souls are very close to those of
Joseph’s <corr type="emend">brethren</corr> in the drawing for the watercolor of <hi rend="i">Joseph Making
Himself Known to His <corr type="emend">Brethren</corr></hi> exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785 (see B 159
recto and verso; the finished work, in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, is B 157). The drawing is probably,
therefore, from late in the group, about 1785 and, as if in justification of my misidentification, may be
linked in subject to two illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> not of 1805 but of c. 1780-85, 
<hi rend="i">The Counsellor, King, Warrior, Mother and Child</hi> (not in Rossetti; B 136, pl. 153) and the 
<hi rend="i">Burial Scene</hi> entitled by Rossetti “Young burying Narcissa (?)” and related by him to two
lines from Night 3 (1863, list 2, no. 102, and 1880, list 2, no. 130; B 137 recto, pl. 154). In any case, it
is one of the strongest of this group of early drawings and deserves more than Rossetti’s dismissive “A
moderately good design, having no salient qualities of execution.”</p>
          <p>The drawing is on a sheet of paper 8 1/16 by 8 ⅜ in. (20.4 × 21.2 cm) which has been folded
slightly to the left of center. On the reverse (illus. 2) are a number of drawings, those which can be
identified being probably related to Blake’s illustrations to William Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>
and in particular to the first edition of 1802-03 rather than to that of 1805. The agonized face in profile in
the upper right-hand corner seems to be a sketch for the young man about to be saved from being eaten by a
crocodile by the self sacrifice of his dog, used for the frontispiece to “The Dog” (David Bindman,
<pb id="p34-24" n="24"/>
	<hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake</hi>, 1978, pl. 396). The head of the eagle, center
left, was presumably done in connection with the frontispiece, and less directly the headpiece, to “The
Eagle” (Bindman pls. 390, 391). The lion, for such it seems to be, particularly on account of its large
claws, in the center right is not directly related to the depiction of the lion in “The Lion” (Bindman pl.
393) but could well be a study. In the upper left-hand corner of the drawing there are two distinct studies
for a human right eye which call to mind the child in Blake’s frontispiece to B. J. Malkin’s 
<hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi>, 1806, though it is impossible to make any specific
identification.</p>
          <p>The basic information in my catalogue entry seems to be correct given a misdating of some 20
years, with the addition to the provenance of the drawing of Iolo Aneurin Williams, the well-known collector
of English drawings and watercolors, about which he wrote an important book, <hi rend="i">Early English
Water-Colours, and Some Cognate Drawings by Artists Born Not Later Than 1785</hi>, published by 
<hi rend="i">The Connoisseur</hi> in 1952.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
