<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>34.1.woodring</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Morton D. Paley, Apocalypse and Millennium in English Romantic Poetry</title>
        <author n="Woodring">Carl Woodring</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2000</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2000</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">34.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Anne Birien</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Claire Colebrook</name>
              <name>Hans-Ulrich Möhring</name>
              <name>Nicholas M. Williams</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2000"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_34">
    <body>
	<pb id="p34-24" n="24"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-34-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Apocalypse and Millennium in English Romantic
Poetry.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1999. x +323 pp. $72.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Carl <name>Woodring</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>This book marks still another peak in Morton Paley’s studies of Blake, Coleridge, and other
English poets and painters sublime and romantic. Although Paley knows enough about the subject to produce an
encyclopedia or to qualify as one of James Thurber’s “get ready” men, <hi rend="i">Apocalypse and
Millennium in English Romantic Poetry</hi> is a trim book with a compact argument. Taking apocalypse to be an
uncovering of ultimate truths, with associated imagery of entrenched evil destructively removed; taking 
<hi rend="i">millenarian</hi> to refer specifically to the Second Coming of Christ; and considering the millennium
as—for the Romantics—a less specifically defined final regenerate utopia of social or spiritual peace,
Paley attests that the six major English Romantic poets all readily conceived works on apocalyptic revelation,
but none found an unproblematic way to continue the narrative into utopian millennium.</p>
          <p>An introduction surveys the pertinent biblical materials and such notable influences on the
Romantics as <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and Thomas Burnet’s <hi rend="i">Theory of the Earth.</hi>
Early pages on Blake add the Swedenborgians, the notorious Richard Brothers, the lesser known Ralph Maher, and
the provocation from Burke’s excoriation of Price’s tribute to the “false apocalypse” in France, with
the lesser provocation of Malthus’s rebuttal to Godwin’s belief in progress. Thereafter, the book follows
the main road of significant poems by the six major poets. The method is exegesis, line by line when needed,
with attention to the figurative, thematic, and recurrent, such as plague, serpent, and chains, and to
allusions explainable by historical context. For each work, early reviews are cited when informative.</p>
          <p>Blake and Coleridge occupy the first half of the study, partly because they wrestled longest and
hardest with the relation of Christianity to ultimate human destiny, partly
<pb id="p34-25" n="25"/>
because they offer a full opportunity to relate prophetic and apocalyptic poetry to events in Britain and
France between the fall of the Bastille and the fall of Napoleon. As if for convenience in giving Paley’s
argument a narrative dimension, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> treats apocalypse and
millennium as simultaneous, with only the appendage, <hi rend="i">A Song of Liberty</hi>, containing closure
in a millennial dawn. Paley suggests that Blake, after this beginning in a stasis of contraries, breaks off
<hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> with Book the First because of “the sheer recalcitrance of
history”; proposes that no millennium is realized in <hi rend="i">America</hi> because slavery had not
ended; and shows that in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> Orc remains intensely ambiguous because the cyclic
interferes with linear movement toward the utopian (as if the apocalyptic from America had reached Europe
without the shackles of slavery, but had joined the ancient cyclic dance there). In contrast with the refusal
of political events to fulfill prophecy, which brought to the poetry an increase in war, famine, plague, and
fire instead of a quiet millennium, Blake broke off <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, not so much because
events had remained uncooperative, but because he was blessed with a religious conversion (identified in 1965
by Jean Hagstrum). With so much to explain, and with so many insights into particular lines and particular
tropes, the chapter will close without mention of Fuseli. By concentrating on poetry, on words, Paley provides
in this fine book a counterpart to <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime</hi> of 1986 on paintings.</p>
          <p>Blake was ready in 1804 to apply in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> his new vision. He renewed attention
to Swedenborg, perhaps through Charles Augustus Tulk (who awakened Coleridge both to Swedenborg and to
Blake’s accomplishments), and gained new excitement from the electrical experiments, courage, and compassion
of Thomas Birch. He could at last, to his own satisfaction, continue apocalypse into utopia. Here, Paley
reminds the already anxious reader, Blake “continues to take both Milton and Wesley further than either
would wish to go” (79). But the romantic project of celebrating a collective millennium has at this point
been reduced to the union of Milton with the pre-pubescent Ololon, and simultaneously to domestic repose in
the cottage of William and Catherine Blake. Romantic poetry provides this study with recurrent examples, as in
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, of a thousand years indistinguishable from an infinite moment. One would not like to
think it weariness from editing <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that accounts for the brevity of Paley’s
appraisal, and not until the chapter on Shelley, that “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> devotes only the last
four of its 100 plates of text and design to the millennium” (270-71).</p>
          <p>In the opening pages of chapter 2 on Coleridge, he carefully analyzes the relation of the
preternatural to prophetic apocalypse in “The Destiny of Nations” and other early poetry. If Coleridge
does not in the poems most widely read today concentrate on the Book of Revelation or on Belshazzar or other
apocalyptic topics in the Book of Daniel, he spent a lifetime concerned with such cruxes. Paley explicates the
resultant early poetry. Coleridge, struggling over the relation
of public fact to poetic invention, as in “Religious Musings,” like Blake casts contemporary events “in
Prophetic and apocalyptic terms” (109); and like Blake, he encounters perverse resistance from events. Paley
agrees with Thomas McFarland and others that the young rebel was much given to “the hysterical sublime.”
He notes that Coleridge makes his heroic female figures more active than Blake’s but the poetic figure
himself less active, “a Bardic celebrant, a seer of visions, a roving ambassador of Sensibility” (118). He
notes that the private dell in Coleridge is sometimes millennial, even millenarian, but in other instances
merely private.</p>
          <p>The Napoleonic invasion of Switzerland curbed Coleridge’s apocalyptic excesses into the
moderated strophes of “France: an Ode” and into renunciation of the curses he had “prophesied” in
“Ode on the Departing Year,” but he reveled immediately in what Paley calls the “apocalyptic
grotesque” of “Fire, Famine, and Slaughter,” “The Devil’s Thoughts” (with Southey), and the
extravagantly hostile lampoon on Mackintosh, “The Two Round Spaces on the Tombstone.” In an example of
Paley’s curbing of wit into mere truth, he observes that Coleridge in “Ode on the Departing Year,” with
its rejection of monarchs such as the “insatiate
<pb id="p34-26" n="26"/>
Hag” Catherine the Great, approaches the grotesque: “He may have intended an effect like Dante’s vision
of Philip the Fair embracing the Whore of Babylon, but he sometimes achieved something closer to the
caricatures of Gillray and Isaac Cruikshank” (127). Paley grants to Coleridge’s later marginalia and other
prose jottings evidence of an interest in Revelation that he does not find in such later poems as “Limbo,”
to which he gave attention in a wise book of 1996.</p>
          <p>Acknowledging that the apocalyptic and millennial lend power to Wordsworth’s poems throughout
his long <corr type="emend">career—and</corr> can be uncovered in nearly all his adumbrations of peaceful
rural life—Paley concentrates on how the two states are related in <hi rend="i">The Prelude.</hi> He renders
a sensitive account of the discharged soldier episode; at his very best relates the apocalyptic parable of the
stone and the shell to Burnet, destruction by deluge, and the Last Man narratives; is informed on the
irresolute and ultimately disillusioned treatments of the French Revolution in Books IX-XI; is admirably
subtle on the Simplon Pass, and acute on the allegory of Mt. Snowden, where apocalypse and millennium “exist
in a perpetual interchange with each other” (188). Wordsworth’s internalizations of the apocalyptic in
other poems are often too amorphous for Paley’s focused examination, but will be fodder for some less
scrupulous critic who takes up the subject.</p>
          <p>Byron often refers metaphorically to a giant steed from Revelation, but seldom makes it a central
topic (193). The exception to such quick glances is course “Darkness,” which evokes comparison with other
Last Man narratives (197-209). Paley takes seriously Lucifer’s meditations on Cuvier in Act II of 
<hi rend="i">Cain</hi>, and notes that Cain is more realistic than Shelley in reacting to apocalyptic knowledge;
he dismisses <hi rend="i">Heaven and Earth</hi> from prolonged attention as “merely a disaster scenario”
(209, 219). The chronology that assigns the last chapter to Keats creates an anti-climax. The two questions
chiefly confronted are Keats’s interest in political ideas and events and the relation of the two abandoned
Hyperion poems, the first a vision of progress, the second apocalyptic. To the thematic question—why no
millennium?—Paley answers that a sequel to apocalypse as Keats presents it cannot be imagined. One can
imagine a dedicated Keatsian finding the millennial elsewhere in Keats’s poetry unobstructed at least from
interpretation, somewhat as one can imagine Victorianists becoming voluble if charged, as the Victorian poets
are in the brief epilogue, with neglect of Revelation except in fictional wars of the worlds without the joy
of millennium.</p>
          <p>Before the anticlimax rises Shelley. Paley demonstrates the foreshadowing by Shelley’s
apprentice works of the major poems to come. <hi rend="i">Queen Mab</hi> is “a rarity,” a “long
millennial (not millenarian) poem” of slow growth toward perfection (225). A section on “Apocapolitics”
studies the “rewriting” of Revelation in <hi rend="i">The Mask of Anarchy</hi>, with close attention to
the title, the structure, the graphic images, the reversals of meaning, and the poet’s hesitant pointing
toward a road from apocalypse to millennium. Within a series of perceptive comments, Paley proposes
Mortimer’s <hi rend="i">Death on a Pale Horse</hi> as a better candidate than the possible 
<hi rend="i">Death on the Pale Horse</hi> of Benjamin West as pictorial source for Shelley’s Anarchy, “pale
even to the lips,” on “a white horse, splashed with blood” (239). After the <hi rend="i">Masque, The
Revolt of Islam</hi> serves largely to elucidate the heritage of images such as the serpent of revolution that
links Blake, Coleridge, and <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound.</hi></p>
          <p>To <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi> Paley devotes care just short of the reverential, for it
“provides the most extensive treatment of the millennium to be written during the Romantic period” (253),
“the most ambitious and least unsuccessful Romantic attempt to unite apocalypse and millennium” (275). He
recognizes the simultaneity that allows the dawn of millennium before apocalypse has been fully realized
(261), the amphisbaena’s annulling alternative to the ouroborous, and the cyclic that obstructs any
assurance of sustained utopia. Although he does not go as far as some of us would in attributing to Asia the
predominant power in attaining millennium, he declares Asia unlike Blake’s passive Jerusalem in initiating
descent into the Cave of Demogorgon (261). He points more precisely than previous critics to the difficulties
the “oratorio” of Act IV puts in the way of the more assured ending of Act III. A Shelleyan determined to
explore beyond the reach of this book would give more space to <hi rend="i">Hellas.</hi></p>
          <p>Paley says nothing about the timeliness of his subject, but every student of Blake, Coleridge,
<hi rend="i">The Prelude, Prometheus Unbound</hi>, and the Romantic period in England should avoid delay in
studying this book, even if Clarendon’s price makes it easier to own in fancy than in fact.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
