<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>34.2.gourlay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Jason Whittaker, William Blake and the Myths of Britain</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2000</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2000</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">34.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Hatsuko Niimi</name>
              <name>Kazuya Okada</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2000"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_34">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-34-2-0007">
        <pb id="p34-61" n="61"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Jason Whittaker. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Myths of Britain.</hi> New
York: St. Martin’s Press, 1999. xii + 215 pp. $55.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Alexander <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>This book, an under-revised 1995 dissertation, is not easy to read—or to review. Mr. Whittaker
has intelligently considered the resources available up to about 1993, primary and secondary, on the important
and complex subject of Blake’s use of the poetic and mythic versions of British history and prehistory.
Unfortunately, the result is little more than an index of what is already known, and even as such it will not
be very helpful, either to beginners or those who have studied these materials extensively.</p>
          <p>Part of the problem is that although Whittaker has read other scholars’ work with enough
penetration to know that not all of it is equally useful, he invariably assembles his discussions—they
aren’t arguments, exactly—out of contingent assertions culled from his predecessors, as if the
decontextualized sentences of David Erdman, Kathleen Raine, Edward Larrissy, Robert Gleckner and Don Cameron
Allen were fully compatible bricks in a wall of Blakean science. As a result, bits from here and there mingle
in an arbitrary stew of primary and secondary sources, made all the more bewildering because Whittaker often
refers to writers by surnames only: one can easily determine whether “George” on page 170 is M. Dorothy
George, Diana Hume George, or our poor George III, but by that time the point of the reference is lost. And
because so much of the text is endnoted paraphrase and quotation, the reader must drop everything two or three
times per page to examine notes and bibliography to divine what sort of spirit Whittaker is channeling at any
given moment.</p>
          <p>But the most important problem is that although he has done his homework, apparently understands
the criticism he has read, is good at summarizing the main issues in extra-Blakean materials, and has the
knowable facts straight, Whittaker doesn’t show that he has yet figured out very much about Blake on his
own: Blake’s words and ideas are almost always seen through critics darkly, and when Whittaker directly
addresses a Blake text or, very rarely, a picture, the results are often naïve. This is not a question of a
flawed approach, a theory misapplied, or even critical misprision in service of an argument: Whittaker is
willing (to a fault) to incorporate ideas from almost any source or point of view, and he does so with both
authority and finesse, but never really gets around to creating his own intellectually useful account of
Blake’s historical mythtaking and mythmaking. This leaves a reviewer very little to praise or even argue
with, since there is no explicit or even implicit theoretical position to examine and if there is a novel and
coherent argument to debate it is buried somewhere beneath a drift of secondary sources. The book might be
helpful as a review of the literature to someone who had not yet done any work on these issues (especially
chapter 3, on Druids), but because Whittaker tends to be oblivious to incongruities and uncongenialities in
critical arguments he is not an ideal synthesist or guide.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">William Blake and the Myths of Britain</hi> exemplifies at once why dissertations
are often published, and why they usually shouldn’t be: most are undertaken as speculative exercises in
dutiful plodding, and even if nothing very exciting comes of a given project, the plodder must push on grimly
to the end, then polish the voluminous results to a deceptively high gloss. In this case the plodding is of
the highest quality, the gloss is very high, and the consequence inconsequential.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
