<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>34.2.okada</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Orc under a Veil Revealed: Family Relationships and their Symbols in Europe and
The Book of Urizen</title>
        <author n="Okada">Kazuya Okada</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2000</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2000</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">34.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Hatsuko Niimi</name>
              <name>Kazuya Okada</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2000"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_34">
    <body>
      <pb id="p34-36" n="36"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-34-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Orc under a Veil Revealed: Family Relationships and their Symbols in 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> This essay was originally read at BARS (British Association for Romantic
Studies) 6th International Residential Conference, Keele University, in the summer of 1999. I acknowledge with
gratitude a grant from the English Literary Society of Japan which enabled me to give the presentation at the
conference.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Kazuya <name>Okada</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Introduction</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Attention has often been drawn to the veil of Enitharmon (illus. 1a, 1b), representing her
relationship to her child, Orc; and its symbolic importance to Blakean mythology is generally agreed upon. But
the attendant discussion has produced several, often problematic, arguments. To understand the deeper
significance of the imagery, we have to re-examine Orc’s figure in the light of a reconsideration of the
traditional mythic sources which throw light upon the meanings of family relationships. These relationships,
which provide Blakean mythology with their interlocking dimensions, in effect systematize his idiosyncratic
cosmology. His mythology is activated especially by the interaction of certain names which are identified with
each character: namely, Los as father figure, Enitharmon as mother, and Orc or Oothoon as child. Elucidating
the significance of family relationships thus helps us realize how Blake’s proto-mythological framings are
fundamentally based on certain family relationships, extending from the earlier works—such as 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> or <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>—all through to such later
works as <hi rend="i">Vala, or The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> More important, perhaps,
attention to these relationships can throw light upon transitional works, particularly, 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi> Here in particular, the relationships, when
more deeply analyzed, enable us to take a fresh look at Orc, to recognize Urizen with Jupiter as a greater
father figure, Los with Vulcan as the father, or Enitharmon with Venus as the mother of Orc. I wish to argue
here that this new light reveals the so far hidden position of Orc’s figure as the son between Vulcan and
Jupiter, i.e., Cupid. It is not common to see a Cupid figure implied within the characterization of Orc; but
it is my contention that this construction leads us to discover a more significant profundity which Blake
intends in the figuration of Orc. The discussion will work towards the ultimate aim of encouraging Blake
readers to reinterpret the creation of Orc as a challenge to
                            <figure n="europe.b.p6-7" id="europe.b.illbk.06" work-copy="europe.b" rend="db" width="709" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>4<lb/>
	The shrill winds wake!<lb/>
	Till all the sons of Urizen look out and envy Los;<lb/>
	Sieze all the spirits of life and bind<lb/>
	Their warbling joys to our loud strings<lb/>
	Bind all the nourishing sweets of earth<lb/>
	To give us bliss, that we may drink the sparkling wine of Los<lb/>
	And let us laugh at war,<lb/>
	Despising toil and care.<lb/>
	Because the days and nights of joy. in lucky hours renew.<lb/>
	Arise O Orc from thy deep den,<lb/>
	First born of Enitharmon rise!<lb/>
	And we will crown thy head with garlands of the ruddy vine;<lb/>
	For now thou art bound;<lb/>
	And I may see thee in the hour of bliss, my eldest born.<lb/>
	The horrent Demon rose, surrounded with red stars of fire,<lb/>
	Whirling about in furious circles round the immortal fiend.<lb/>
	Then Enitharmon down descended into his red light,<lb/>
	And thus her voice rose to her children, the distant heavens reply.</figTranscr>
	<head>1a <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> plate 4.</head>
	<figDesc>Glasgow University Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="urizen.B.P23-21" id="urizen.b.illbk.23" work-copy="urizen.b" rend="db" width="638" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>23</figTranscr>
	<head>1b <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>The Pierpont Morgan Library, New York. PML 63139 copy B, plate 19 (Bentley 21).</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p34-37" n="37"/>
<figure n="europe.b.p1" id="europe.b.illbk.01" work-copy="europe.b" rend="db" width="717" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>2 Frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Glasgow University Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
restore Cupid’s original position: a move in which Blake can be seen as discursively aligned with the
contextual revolutionary ethos, which in turn poses the larger question of radicalism in romanticism.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Infant/Infinity Compassed</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>A rough sketch of the <hi rend="i">Ancient of Days</hi> in the Notebook is an original design
of the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (illus. 2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref> The original sketch contains an inscription of five words, quoted within the
following lines cited from the Prophecy:
<q>
. . . <hi rend="i">who shall bind the infinite</hi> with an eternal band,<lb/>
To compass it with swaddling bands? and who shall cherish it<lb/>
With milk and honey?<lb/>
[E 61: italics mine<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>] 
                            </q>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2 </hi><hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi> 96.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Blake texts are quoted from the Erdman edition, cited as E followed by the
page numbers.</note></p>
            <p>The act of “bind[ing] the infinite” or “compass[ing] it” has provoked several
interpretations in the history of Blake studies. One major interpretation derives from the point of view which
sees it as a biblical allusion to the charting out
                            <figure n="bb515.1.13.com" id="bb515.1.comb.13" work-copy="bb515.1" rend="db" width="817" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv. &amp; sc<lb/>
	WB<lb/>
	Pubd. June 27th. 1796 by R. Edwards No. 142 New Bond Street.</figTranscr>
	<head>3 One of Blake’s illustrations to Edward Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></head>
</figure>
of the seven days of creation, i.e., a view which regards it as the depiction of “the Divine
Circumscriber.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Critics on the side
of the latter prefer to depend on the following description of Urizen in chapter VII of <hi rend="i">The Book
of Urizen</hi> as a supplementary citation: “. . .formed golden compasses / And began to explore the
Abyss” (E 81). <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Sutherland, “Blake and Urizen,” 248. See also M.
Tolley’s comment; the act of “[t]he compasses of this ratio form the circular horizon which limits man,
spatially and mentally” (117).</note></p>
            <p>Although the act of encompassing has long been thus understood in conceptual terms, in the
following discussion I want to draw the point of emphasis, at least at first, away from this to the question
of the form of the compasses as an iconic symbol. To collate the various instances of the form, a subject
seemingly oft noticed but little investigated, will illustrate with fresh clarity how a degree of repressive
authoritarianism is elaborated within Blake’s connotative vocabulary.</p>
            <p>To try to understand the elaboration more deeply, let us examine Blake’s illustration to
Edward Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (illus. 3: later used as the plate representing Night the
Fifth of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>). This illustration seems to allude to the holy family. However, we
may explain the parent figures, especially the father figure shown in an encompassing gesture, as Blake’s
ironical protest against the repressive nurture of infants.</p>
            <pb id="p34-38" n="38"/>
            <figure n="but411.1.1.pt" id="but411.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="682">
	<figTranscr/>
              <head>4a <hi rend="i">The Christ Child Asleep on the Cross.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum, London.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="but410.1.1.pt" id="but410.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="637">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
              <head>4b <hi rend="i">The Christ Child Asleep on the Cross.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Private Collection. On loan to the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>As for the image of encompassing the infant, we may well remember that the image of compasses
itself is a well known signifier in the iconography of the Christian tradition; when God as creator is
compared to a carpenter, the image of compasses can represent him in the role of designer or builder of the
world, and the meanings of the icon are in this same tradition, further elaborated to identify Christ as a
carpenter. Interestingly, this development of the Christian connotation of the image can help explicate some
of Blake’s illustrations of the biblical stories, such as, for example, <hi rend="i">The Christ Child Asleep
on the Cross</hi> (illus. 4a). In the illustration, the Christ child is sleeping on a cross beside a
scaffolding of timber, and just next to the cross a set-square is placed which seems to be emphasized by
another pair of compasses leaning against the woodwork. The importance of this compasses icon gains in
emphasis through his additional use of the shape in another illustration on the same theme (illus. 4b). In
this illustration Joseph holds the compasses over the Christ child. We can decode this image conventionally,
i.e., as an implied prefiguring of the Child’s future as the one
<pb id="p34-39" n="39"/>
<figure n="but486.1.1.wc" id="but486.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="958" height="952">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
	<head>5 <hi rend="i">The Woman Taken in Adultery.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</figDesc>
</figure>
who will create the world of love; but, on the other hand, it might also be understood skeptically, for Blake
uses the form of compasses to connote a disapproval of restrictive authority, which can be seen, for example,
in Christ’s resentment against such authority in his future ministry.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Such a skeptical interpretation seems warranted when we look
at another piece of biblical illustration by Blake entitled <hi rend="i">The Woman Taken in Adultery</hi>
(illus. 5), where Christ is shown in a stooping posture, and his hand in a gesture of compassing.
Traditionally Christ is simply writing on the floor, but this gesture may be seen to imply Christ’s ironical
criticism of the fleeing crowd behind him, in that they are only compassing others, as well as themselves,
within a repressive morality. We should emphasize that the shape of the compasses here signifies Christ’s
resentment against Urizenic power. <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> As for this illustration, George Goyder
includes in his explanation: “the compasses of rational thought . . . symbolising the two ideals of love and
truth, united and reconciled in Christ’s sacrifice”; and David Bindman suggests that “the compasses in
this work. . .may also indicate that Christ’s death is to be at the hands of Reason in the form of the Law
of Solomon” (cited in Butlin’s <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> 2:
328).</note></p>
            <p>Curiously, this kind of emphasis on the image of compasses as denoting circumscribing authority
may be deepened and enhanced by considering Blake’s illustrations of the nativity. These offer confirmation
of ironic interpretations of the imagery through the repeated appearance of the shape of compasses in the six
illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity.</hi> One advocate of such a
reading is Michael Tolley, through whose research we are in a better position to appreciate Blake’s ironical
attitude towards the Miltonic understanding of the infant Christ (145). Tolley’s interpretation is as
follows:
<q>
. . . throughout <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> we find Blake looking very closely at Milton’s Hymn[<hi
rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity</hi>] and it is not going too far to say that 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is primarily a reworking of Milton’s poem. (119)
</q></p>
            <p>If, with this explication in mind, we assume that Blake here ironically indicts this type of
Miltonic-Newtonic creator, we can go on to recollect Milton’s account concerning God’s use of “the
golden compasses . . ./. . . to circumscribe / This Universe and all created things.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Once we can register Blake’s resentment
against the Miltonic notion of a rational great-father (creator figure), one to be regarded in the light of a
confining and repressive power, we can be more confident in detecting the irony ingeniously implied by the
compasses-like shape of the roof of the stable depicted in the illustrations of the series (illus. 6a and 6b).
<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Paradise Lost</hi>, VII, 225-27.</note></p>
            <p>A consciousness of this irony enables us now to take a fresh look at the frontispiece of 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (illus. 2), where we might consider the form of the cloud as suggesting a womb from which
a potential infant might just have been given birth and whom Urizen is now compassing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> This possibility may lead us further to identify the infinity,
i.e., the unseen object below the compasses, with Orc as the potential infant. However, an Orc whose symbolic
meanings extend beyond those connoted by the image of Christ leads us to further investigation of, in
particular, the role of Los and Enitharmon as Orc’s parents as well as reproducers of the Urizenic power of
confinement; and this is the topic to which I now turn. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Tolley’s
helpful argument, though my ultimate argument is different from this opinion; “The birth of Christ
represented the crucial challenge to Urizen’s compasses” (119).</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Parents: Los and Enitharmon</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The Greek ουριζειν (“to limit”), from which Kathleen Raine and others prefer to
derive the name of Urizen,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> may
precisely summarize his character, a circumscriber. That Los as a father of Orc cooperates with Urizen so as
to reinforce the confinement initiated by him is discernible, for example, in the last illustration of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (illus. 7), where Los holds compasses-like tongs in his left hand. In fact, we might
better characterize Los by designating him as a sustainer, or a reproducer, of Urizenic domination, since, as
this plate shows, Los seems to be trusted with the charge of confining Orc.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> The hammer in the other hand, for use in
<pb id="p34-40" n="40"/>
binding Orc in chains on the mountain, emphasizes his character as a blacksmith.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See Damon 419.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> This is in contrast to <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, where
“Urizen explored his dens/ Mountain, moor, &amp; wilderness,/ With a globe of fire lighting his journey/ A
fearful journey, annoyed/ By Cruel enormities . . .” (E 81).</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> The serpent temple illustrated in the background suggests by implication
the idea that a blighting (and also blighted) system is sustained by the priestcraft of authoritarian
regimentation. As for the serpent temple, cf. Dörrbecker 273-74; Mee 92-97.</note></p>
            <p>In the same plate appears another supporter of Urizen, Enitharmon, who is a mother figure of
Orc. She is shown unwinding the “aching fibres of Los” (E 247),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n11" type="note">11</ref> who seems bound up in what looks very much like a version of the concealing
veil, whose function is depicted in the illustration of plate 4 of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (illus. 1a), where
it has the purpose of concealing Orc.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">12</ref> As the statement of the nameless shadowy female implies—she is a vague figure of
Oothoon, the other rebellious child of Los and Enitharmon—Enitharmon is another figure of confinement: “Ah
mother Enitharmon! / Stamp not with solid form . . .,” “thou dost stamp them with a signet.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> In addition to the veil, Enitharmon as an
authoritative figure commands the use of a net so as to enforce greater restrictions.
<q>
. . . tell the human race that <hi rend="i">Woman’s Love is Sin</hi>:<lb/>
That an Eternal life awaits the worms of sixty winters<lb/>
In an allegorical abode where existence hath never come:<lb/>
Forbid all Joy, &amp; from her childhood shall the little female<lb/>
Spread <hi rend="i">nets</hi> in every secret path.<lb/>
[E 62, italics mine]
</q>
These nets may be identical with the ones described in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> with which Urizen is endowed
in addition to his compasses, i.e., “the Net of Urizen” (E 83). <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Cf.
Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> 379.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> As for the argument as to whether she is concealing or revealing Orc in
this plate, see Dörrbecker 269-70; Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> 162; and Chayes 218
(“Above him [Orc], kneeling on a cloud, a nude woman who is probably Enitharmon leans forward in a sweeping
gesture and lifts a cloth to reveal him”). Beer reproduces a Raphael Madonna and compares it to the plate,
describing the Christ child under the veil as “[t]he Jesus who has been veiled by the Church” (Beer 374
and plates 53, 54).</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> See also a similar image in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi>: “Stampt with my signet are the swarthy children of the sun” (E 46). The description of her as
a dominant queen figure, “Now comes the night of Enitharmon’s joy” (E 62), may be associated with the
annotation of Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">Divine Love</hi>, “When the fallacies of darkness are in the
circumference <hi rend="i">they cast a bound about the infinite</hi>” [E 604, italics mine]. Cf. Tolley
119.</note></p>
            <p>In this section we have mainly investigated the relationships between the parents of Orc and
Urizen. In retrospect, we can now identify Urizen with Jupiter, and Los with Vulcan as a blacksmith, and in
consequence we may go some way to acknowledging the further identification of Enitharmon with Venus as the
wife of Vulcan. These identifications, reviewed
                            <figure n="but538.1.1.wc" id="but538.1.wc.01" work-copy="but538.1" rend="db" width="772" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake 18</figTranscr>
	<head>6a <hi rend="i">The Descent of Peace</hi>: Milton’s <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s
Nativity.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>The Whitworth Art Gallery, Manchester.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="but538.1.6.wc" id="but538.1.wc.06" work-copy="but538.1" rend="db" width="761" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake 1809</figTranscr>
	<head>6b <hi rend="i">The Night of Peace</hi>: Milton’s <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s
Nativity.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>The Whitworth Art Gallery, Manchester.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p34-41" n="41"/>
<figure n="jerusalem.e.p100" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.100" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="958" height="653">
	<figTranscr>100</figTranscr>
	<head>7 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 100.</head>
	<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
through the various family relationships in the myth, may lead us to infer that “Orc their son is
Cupid.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> It is not usual to see a
Cupid figure implied within the characterization of Orc, but to argue this construction will lead us to
discover the more significant profundity which Blake intends in the figure of Orc as the child of Vulcan-Venus
parents. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Tolley 130; it might be better to have a full citation of it;
“. . . she (Enitharmon) was worshipped principally as Venus (as Los is the blacksmith Vulcan, and Orc their
son is Cupid).”</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Creation of Orc; or the Restoration of Cupid Revealed</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Knowledge of contextual discourse is naturally requisite for any critical argument, but here I
want to focus on one topic among others raised by the figure of Cupid, or the story of <hi rend="i">Cupid</hi>
(or Eros) <hi rend="i">and Psyche.</hi> Although significant meanings for the topic have been adduced by
various critics, such as, Irene Chayes and Erdman,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> I shall argue the assumption that Blake may have intended to restore to Cupid some of his
original meanings when creating the figure of Orc. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> See Erdman’s comment
in Worrall’s “Blake and the Night Sky I”; “. . .the Cupid and Psyche myth, one of the active strings
in Blake’s bow,” 288).</note></p>
            <p>Interestingly, the plate entitled “Aged Ignorance,” one of Blake’s illustrations of 
<hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> (illus. 8), can serve to introduce the theme. In the design, the aged
Urizenlike figure is depicted in an attempt to cut Cupid’s wings. The glasses on his blind eyes seem to
emphasize his “ignorance” in a kind of ironical inversion of the conventional notion of “the blind
Cupid.” Yet, we come to recognize that this illustration ought more properly to be contextualized within the
contemporary discourse of “the selling of Cupid”, or the captivated Cupid (illus. 9a and 9b).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Henry Fuseli’s illustration of the theme
(illus. 9c) exemplifies this discourse, and is important in reference to Blake, for Fuseli inspired and
enlightened Blake as an artist as well as an engraver. Evidence that Blake was in fact conscious of this
discourse can be found in his design for Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, where the
discourse itself seems to be betraying its own implied recognition of an oppressive captivity figured in terms
of the inverted state of Eros being bound (illus. 10), rather than simply showing the poet-engraver’s
rendering of the story. <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> As for this contemporary discourse, cf. Rosenblum
3-9.</note></p>
            <p>This significant image of a child restrained from flying, which is embodied in the discourse of
the captivated Cupid,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> stimulates a
curious reading of the “Preludium” plate
<pb id="p34-42" n="42"/>
<figure n="Gates-Child.AgedIgnorance.YCBA.34.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="383">
	<head>8 <hi rend="i">For Children The Gates of Paradise</hi>, pl. 13: “Aged Ignorance.”</head>
	<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
              to <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> (illus. 11). Although some critics want to see “an
idealized image of the family” in this design,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref> it seems obvious that the mother figure looks quite severe and the child looks worried,
or rather held captive. This mother figure, or an <corr type="emend">Enitharmonian</corr> mother, with her
restricting gesture, might be read to represent parents who educate their children in conventional morality,
or transmit taboos to the young, and can be seen engaged in the economy of another relevant contextual
discourse: that of the idealized marriage, as has been observed by Marilyn Butler.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> The inscription, “Teach these Souls to Fly,” on the
headpiece, produced as a separate plate for <hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi>, should be considered as
an ironical statement of Blake’s resentment of repressive parentage. In a poem in which we can appropriately
identify the birth of Orc, Blake depicts the reluctance of an infant to enter the world from which it
immediately struggles to escape:
<q><hi rend="i">My mother groan’d! my father wept</hi>—,<lb/>
Into the dangerous world I leapt:<lb/>
Helpless, naked, piping loud:<lb/>
Like a fiend hid in a cloud.<lb/>
<lb/>
Struggling in my father’s hands<lb/>
Striving against my swaddling bands,<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Bound and weary, I thought best</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="i">To sulk upon</hi> my mother’s breast.<lb/>
(E 28, italics mine)
</q>
<figure n="vien.34.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="368">
	<head>9a Joseph-Marie Vien, <hi rend="i">La Marchande d’Amours</hi>, 1763.</head>
	<figDesc>Giraudon, Paris.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="sellingcupids.34.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="392">
	<head>9b <hi rend="i">The Selling of Cupids</hi>, engraving by C. Nolli from <hi rend="i">Reale Accademia
Erolanese de Archeologia Le Antichita di Ercolano Expose</hi>, Napoli 1757-92.</head>
	<figDesc>Volume 3. Supplied by the Bodleian Library, Oxford.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="fuseli.34.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="303">
	<head>9c Henry Fuseli, drawing, ca. 1775.</head>
	<figDesc>Blunt Bequest, Courtauld Gallery, Courtauld Institute, London.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p34-43" n="43"/>
<figure n="conjugalcupid.34.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="316" height="400">
	<head>10 “The Conjugal Union of Cupid,” engraving from <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> by George
Cumberland (1796).</head>
	<figDesc>Print Collection, Miriam and Ira D. Wallach Division of Art, Prints and Photographs, The New York
Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations.</figDesc>
</figure>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Certainly, it should not be forgotten that there is another possible
identification of Orc with Prometheus.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> For example, Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> 144 and
Essick 133.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Butler 132-33.</note></p>
            <p>In addition to the apparent similarity on a visual level (see the design of the plate [illus.
12]), we should note that the description of the struggling infant includes the image of a band, i.e., “my
swaddling bands,” an image which has already been examined above; “[w]ho shall bind the infinite with an
eternal band? / To compass it with swaddling bands?”</p>
            <p>It is not Blake’s ultimate aim to allow an infant “[t]o sulk upon [her] breast.” What the
discourse of captivity involves is an implied recognition that the infant, as a representative of fragile and
weak existence, has no choice except to live as an obedient child. Yet, this is what is problematic from the
point of the rebellious child, who is expected to overthrow such an oppressive authority. Being obedient to
the economy of endlessly reproducing the Urizenic family of restriction will only result in repeating the
cycle of domestic repression. Blake’s is a protest, therefore, against this dominant economy of circularity
in which no progress can ever be made.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref> Then the question must be asked; how is the infant to attain to a symbolic power
sufficiently formidable to escape,
                            <figure n="urizen.b.p2" id="urizen.b.illbk.02" work-copy="urizen.b" rend="db" width="633" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>2<lb/>
	PRELUDIUM<lb/>
	TO<lb/>
	THE<lb/>
	FIRST BOOK OF<lb/>
	URIZEN<lb/>
	Of the primeval Priests assum’d power,<lb/>
	When Eternals spurnd back his religion:<lb/>
	And gave him a place in the north,<lb/>
	Obscure. shadowy. void. solitary.<lb/>
	Eternals I hear your call gladly,<lb/>
	Dictate swift winged words. &amp; fear not<lb/>
	To unfold your dark visions of torment.</figTranscr>
	<head>11 <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>The Pierpont Morgan Library, New York. PML 63139 copy B, plate 2 (Bentley 2).</figDesc>
</figure>
or more precisely, to overthrow the system? <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> On this matter we have an
interesting suggestion pointed out by Robert Essick, that “Paine unleashes a metaphor of consumption” in
the discussion of the problem of the relationship between Blake and Paine; “‘natural’ feelings were
contrasted “to the aristocratic perversion of the family into an artificial system of power relationships”
(202). The anguish of the nameless shadowy female, who can be considered as an Oothoon-like figure, i.e.,
another rebellious child of Los and Enitharmon, is significantly related to this economy of
consumption—“Consumed and consuming! / Then why shouldst thou accursed my mother bring me into life?”;
or “O mother Enitharmon, wilt thou bring forth other sons? / To cause my name to vanish, that my place may
not be found” (E 60).</note></p>
            <p>I would like to go back to the icon of compasses positioned over the infant. Among the six
designs for Milton’s “Nativity Ode,” one plate, entitled <hi rend="i">The Flight of Moloch</hi>,
presents us with the child who leaps out of the furnace as if marching through a cathedral window whose upper
portion echoes the compasses shape (illus. 13). In the original text the infant is supposed to die according
to the story of the sacrifice to Moloch (“that no man might make his son or his daughter pass through the
fire to Moloch”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>. Here,
<pb id="p34-44" n="44"/>
<figure n="songsie.L.P39-48" id="songsie.l.illbk.39" work-copy="songsie.l" rend="db" width="632" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>39<lb/>
	INFANT SORROW<lb/>
	My mother groand! my father wept.<lb/>
	Into the dangerous world I leapt:<lb/>
	Helpless, naked, piping loud:<lb/>
	Like a fiend hid in a cloud.<lb/>
	Struggling in my fathers hands:<lb/>
	Striving against my swadling bands:<lb/>
	Bound and weary I thought best<lb/>
	To sulk upon my mothers breast.</figTranscr>
	<head>12 <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, 1789 [c. 1789-94].</head>
	<figDesc>(Copy L) pl. 39 [Bentley 48]: “Infant Sorrow.” Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon
Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
Blake’s invention may be regarded as intending to imply the creation of a new and formidable type of infant.
It might not be going too far to identify this infant with Orc, as Jean Hagstrum does in his discussion of
this plate.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> 2 Kings 23: 10.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake</hi> 123-24.</note></p>
            <p>My assumption is that the characterization of Vulcan as Los is reinforced as a result of
Blake’s aspiration to create a formidable infant, though the image of compasses might have been a more
important factor in enhancing this aspect. For we can well imagine Blake to have been acquainted with the
original significance of Cupid, as the child of Vulcan and Venus, in some versions of ancient mythology. As a
possible engraver of Jacob Bryant’s <hi rend="i">A New System, or An Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi>,
Blake would likely have been in a position to observe a reworking of the mythologies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> This would permit us to suppose that he welcomed the
original version of the God of Love, whose figure seems capable of being revitalized as an appropriately
subversive force, and who is a child of Vulcan the compasses-tong holder. Bryant phrases his rediscovery in
the following way;
<q>
. . . they [the Greek] gave him a material bow, with the addition of a quiver and arrows. Being furnished with
these implements of mischief he was supposed to be the bane of the world. . . . This was different from his
original character. He is styled by Plato . . . a mighty God: it is said . . . <hi rend="i">That Eros was the
cause of the greatest blessings to mankind.</hi> The bows of Apollo and of Diana, were, I believe, formed from
the same original.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> [italics
original] 
                            </q>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Cf. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
Illustrations</hi> 117.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Bryant 2: 345. It should be noticed that the same part is cited by
Erasmus Darwin in the context of the notion that “the ancient God of love was of much higher dignity than
the modern Cupid. He was the first that came out of the great egg of night” in <hi rend="i">The Botanic
Garden: Part I, The Economy of Vegetation</hi>, 3rd ed. (London, 1795) 56.</note></p>
            <p>Orc as a redeemed Cupid has the potentiality to break the conventional forms of oppression. His
subversive aspect, whose most often noted feature is the serpent figure, is now brought to a further level of
profundity as revealed by a reconsideration of family relationships.</p>
            <p>Although these figures of Orc as Cupid are not immediately visible in his poetry—they must
rather be deduced from within contextual discourses—<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">25</ref> once we can conceive the possibility of this interpretation, we will find, at the level
of the poetry’s deep structure, the richest connotations of the Orc figure, which complicate and extend the
original significance of Cupid. For instance, when we realize that the word “Eros” becomes “rose” by
rearranging the letters of the word, the altered significance of the redeemed figure of Cupid / Eros requires
as a consequence a thorough re-reading of Blake’s works. This is because the anagram must prompt readers to
reinvestigate the still-enigmatic image of the sick rose in relation to the sick Cupid who is degraded in the
discourse of the Psyche story, and which may in this way have been intended as a contextual symbol of the
repressed emotion of love. More curiously still, in the Notebook, c. 1791-92, just prior to the sick rose
poem, there occurs another in which “Love” is winged. Of course, winged Love can easily represent Cupid.
The lines are as follows:
<q>
Love . . .<lb/>
Always is to joy inclined,<lb/>
Lawless, winged and unconfined,<lb/>
And breaks all chains from every mind.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">26</ref></q>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> In his illustrations, nevertheless, there are some designs which clearly
includes Cupid figures.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Stevenson 158-59.</note></p>
            <p>Here, intriguingly, “winged” “Love” is described as “lawless,” which can be seen to
have political implications if we agree to trace the Cupid-Orc figure in the figure of “Love.” Orc may
well represent the contextual revolutionary ethos,
<pb id="p34-45" n="45"/>
and Blake may equally well be expressing his radicalism by way of the refiguring of Cupid. My assumption here,
which I recognize needs further demonstration, is that “Unconfined Love” can share the same foundation as
the figure of the unconfined Orc, and that for Blake the emotional emancipation of Love could be equated with
the emancipation of the human spirit from political repression. I hope, however, that this discourse of
liberty, seen in the light I have demonstrated here, will lead to a recognition of the deeper levels of
significance within Blake’s entire mythology, since Orc, hitherto veiled in Blake studies as an original
figure of Cupid, now stands revealed as the subversive figure of Love, a breaker of psychic and, by
implication, social chains.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Beer, John. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Universe.</hi> Manchester: Manchester University
Press, 1969.</p>
            <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “Blake’s Illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Nativity Ode.”
Philological Quarterly</hi> 55 (1976): 65-95.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake.</hi> A Photographic and Typographic
Facsimile. Edited by David V. Erdman with the assistance of Donald K. Moore. Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1973.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman,
commentary by Harold Bloom. New York: Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p>Bryant, Jacob. <hi rend="i">A New System, or An Analysis of Ancient Mythology.</hi> 3 vols.
1775-1776, 2nd ed. Rpt. ed. Burton Feldman. Garland Publishing, Inc., 1979.</p>
            <p>Butler, Marilyn. <hi rend="i">Romantics, Rebels &amp; Reactionaries: English Literature and its
Background 1760-1830.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1981.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New
Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1981.</p>
            <p>Chayes, Irene. “The Presence of Cupid and Psyche.” In <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary
Forms Dramatic.</hi> Eds. David V. Erdman and John E. Grant. Princeton NJ: Princeton University Press, 1970.
214-43.</p>
            <p>Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary.</hi> 1965. Ed. Morris Eaves. London: Thames
and Hudson, 1973.</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker, D. W., ed. <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies.</hi> By William Blake. London:
William Blake Trust, Tate Gallery, 1995.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> New York: Dover Publications,
1974.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. and John Grant, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic.</hi>
Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1970.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. “William Blake, Thomas Paine, and Biblical Revolution.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 30 (1991): 189-212.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations: A Catalogue and Study of the
Plates Engraved by Blake after</hi>
<figure n="but538.1.5.wc" id="but538.1.wc.05" work-copy="but538.1" rend="db" width="775" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake 18</figTranscr>
	<head>13 <hi rend="i">The Flight of Moloch</hi>: Milton’s <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s
Nativity.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>The Whitworth Art Gallery, Manchester.</figDesc>
</figure><hi rend="i">Designs by Other Artists.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991.</p>
            <p>Hagstrum, Jean. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Poet and Painter.</hi> Chicago: University of
Chicago Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>Mee, Jon. <hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm: William Blake and the Culture of Radicalism in the
1790s.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1992.</p>
            <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton
University Press, 1978.</p>
            <p>Rosenblum, Robert. <hi rend="i">Transformations in Late Eighteenth Century Art.</hi> Princeton,
NJ: Princeton University Press, 1967.</p>
            <p>Stevenson, W. H., ed. <hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> 2nd ed. London: Longman,
1989.</p>
            <p>Sutherland, John. “Blake and Urizen.” In <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic.</hi> 244-62.</p>
            <p>Tolley, Michael J. “<hi rend="i">Europe:</hi> ‘to those ychain’d in sleep.’” In 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic.</hi> 115-45.</p>
            <p>Worrall, David. “Blake and the Night Sky I: The ‘Immortal Tent.’” <hi rend="i">Bulletin
of Research in the Humanities</hi> 84 (1981): 273-95.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Urizen Books.</hi> By William Blake. London: William Blake Trust, Tate
Gallery, 1995.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
