<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>34.2.johnson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Clifford Siskin, The Work of Writing: Literature and Social Change in Britain,
1700-1830</title>
        <author n="Johnson">Mary Lynn Johnson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2000</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2000</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">34.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Hatsuko Niimi</name>
              <name>Kazuya Okada</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2000"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_34">
    <body>
	<pb id="p34-54" n="54"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-34-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Clifford Siskin. <hi rend="i">The Work of Writing: Literature and Social Change
in Britain, 1700-1830.</hi> Johns Hopkins University Press, 1998. x + 285 pp. $39.95, paper $16.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Mary Lynn <name>Johnson</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Why is this journal reviewing Clifford Siskin’s <hi rend="i">The Work of Writing: Literature
and Social Change in Britain, 1700-1830</hi>, when “Blake” is not even in the index? It must be because
the title links one of the arts Blake practiced to one of his highest aspirations as an artist, the
transformation of society. But composing prophecies by night under the inspiration of the Poetic Genius after
doing commercial engravings by day to put food on the table is not what Siskin means by “writing”: here
the operative word is “work,” as in “produce observable social results.” For Siskin, following Raymond
Williams in <hi rend="i">Writing in Society</hi> (1983), writing is “shorthand for the entire configuration
of writing, print, and silent reading” (2) that rapidly expanded in the eighteenth and early nineteenth
centuries as “more people had more occasions to write more,” and as readers themselves became writers
(contributors of letters to periodicals, for example). Siskin seeks to recover a history of writing that
reveals “what changed and who paid the price” (3) in this critical period. He holds that gender
inequities, in particular, were exacerbated by the “work of writing,” which organized knowledge into
deeper and narrower channels (from which emerged new university disciplines), instituted sharper divisions and
rankings among occupations by means
<pb id="p34-55" n="55"/>
of written qualifying examinations, and elevated “literature” from the written word in general to a
special category of highly imaginative works produced by gifted individual authors in a tightly restricted
range of genres—all at a time when the newly united British nation was shaping, through writing, a sense of
its collective identity. The densely compressed introduction, “The Argument: Writing as a New Technology”
(best re-read as a coda), forces into conceptual proximity the loosely parallel historical strands of the
book’s four main sections—disciplinarity, professionalism, “novelism” (the subordination of writing to
the newly-recognized literary genre of the novel) and gender—all considered as developing in tandem with,
and partially in response to, the increasing dominance of print culture. By the end of the period, according
to Siskin, “writing” had ceased to be experienced as unruly and threatening and had come to seem familiar,
safe, manageable, and even natural, along lines analogous to our own adjustments to the much faster rate of
change in contemporary communications technologies.</p>
          <p>Siskin does not claim to present “an absolute theory of how writing works” but rather “a
description of some of the work that writing did do” (10) to impose order and manage growth at a time when
its forms, purposes, and participants were multiplying as wildly as Internet interactions are now. Part of
this “work” was a self-reflexive criticism of writing itself that permeated all literary genres. Siskin
cautions that academic literary studies, insofar as they perpetuate such romantic-value-laden distinctions as
the one between critical (inferior) and creative (superior) forms of writing, fail to consider that “what we
take now to be secondary may have functioned, back then, as a primary condition and product of the act of
writing itself, as long as that act was still experienced as new” (25). By repositioning “Literature”
(which he spells with a capital L to call attention to its comparatively recent “higher” meaning) within
“a materialist history of writing” (7), Siskin hopes to “reconceive literary study by mixing different
kinds of data into it” (23), as he had begun to do in his <hi rend="i">The Historicity of Romantic
Discourse</hi> (1988). His “relentlessly combinatory” (15) method breaches received distinctions,
especially that between “creative” and ordinary utilitarian writing, and interweaves critical commentary
on familiar and unfamiliar texts with data and insights from such varied disciplines as sociology, pedagogy,
communication studies, law, and of course history. These ad-hoc mixtures, he says, are neither “haphazard
combinations” nor formulas to be applied to all cases; they are to be judged by how well they “help make
sense of the current proliferation of descriptions of contemporary change” (211) in an age of proliferating
electronic media, declining print culture, and self-chosen aliteracy.</p>
          <p>Criticism of a thesis as complex and far-reaching as this one, developed from hundreds of period
vignettes alternating with contemporaneous media-prompted reflections on American academic and popular
culture, cannot be accomplished within a single field of study, nor can it be conducted intelligibly without
citation of a great many more secondary sources than is customary in a book review. Siskin likens the
“thrill of interdisciplinarity” to bungee jumping: “flying free of certain constraints while staying
solidly tethered to the platform of one’s own discipline” (72), even at the risk of smacking into that
discipline on the rebound. With “culture” as the super-flexible tether, he zooms and boings among his four
principal topics with such velocity that facts, assertions, and speculations whiz by in a blur. Is the
perceived superiority of mental labor, above physical labor, really datable to 1700-1830 (24)? Can silent
reading, which is subsumed under the shorthand term “writing,” be presumed (without discussion) to be a
post-Gutenberg skill (2, 31), despite vigorous challenges over the last 20 years from biblical and classical
scholars as well as the medievalist Paul Henry Saenger, whose 1982 essay has recently been incorporated into
his <hi rend="i">Space Between Words: The Origins of Silent Reading</hi> (1997)? Is it fair to say that by
1830 “courses in English Literature” were being taught “in English universities” and “a section of
school” could be known as the English department (12), if only one university, the newly founded University
College of London, and only one school (in Belfast) are cited? Granted that such eighteenth-century
developments as increased mechanization of the printing process, mass marketing, and enforcement of the
copyright law encouraged the proliferation of writing and associated changes in personal and social behavior,
should “writing” in this period be considered a “new technology” (3, 31)? In six of the nine chapters,
some of the choppy (or perhaps deliberately nonlinear) exposition may result from adaptation of previously
published work in journals and essay collections devoted to romanticism, eighteenth-century studies, the
novel, and Austen and feminism—only a tiny sampling of Siskin’s research interests. The thrill of
following so many heterogeneous juxtapositions and quickie generalizations soon becomes distracting (bungee
jumping is not much of a spectator sport), yet to wish that fewer subjects had been considered in greater
depth would be to reimpose upon the author the very disciplinary limits he seeks to escape.</p>
          <p>Both the provocations and the provocativeness of Siskin’s cross-disciplinary leaps are
intensified by his organizational strategy, which produces forward movement in a multi-stranded, doubling-back
spiral. Because early sections rely on sketchy adumbrations of matters to be developed more fully in later
sections, the reader is always <hi rend="i">in medias res</hi>, constantly struggling with the work of
reading, and grateful for footnotes beginning “My point here is . . . .” As with Mandelbrot’s fractals,
intricate patterns are generated from the breakdown of progressively smaller units into still smaller parts
containing the same structural elements in miniature. For example, in the first and longest section,
“Disciplinarity: The Political Economy of Knowledge,” all three chapters—
<pb id="p34-56" n="56"/>
<corr type="emend">“Writing</corr> Havoc,” “Engendering Disciplinarity” and “Scottish Philosophy and
English Literature”—touch in one way or another upon the book’s four main themes of disciplinarity,
professionalism, literature, and gender. These three chapters, like the six that follow, are in turn
subdivided into at least three smaller parts, making 29 in all (not counting the six sub-units of “The
Argument”), many of which contain microcosmic elements of the parent chapters. This is evident already in
the first chapter, “Writing Havoc,” which consists of “Writing and Madness,” concerning poetry;
“Pens and Periods,” concerning gender; “Productivity and Proper Subjects,” concerning disciplines; and
“Disciplinarity and the Middle Class,” concerning presentday socioeconomic and political
classifications.</p>
          <p>Within the fractal units, as within the book as a whole, disparate materials are linked partly by
analogy, partly by contemporaneity, partly by reference to the controlling thesis. The first unit of
“Writing Havoc,” “Writing and Madness,” sets up Pope’s “Epistle to Arbuthnot” and Wordsworth’s
“Resolution and Independence” as a “chronological framework for focusing on the chapter’s central
issue: writing’s capacity to wreak what Hume called ‘havoc’ on itself and its users” (this explanatory
statement [38] is from the second unit; the discussion of Hume [49-50] appears in the third unit); within this
framework, society’s concern shifts “from the potentially disruptive power of the technology of writing to
the possibly disrupted personalities of the people who wrote” (34). For Pope, hordes of crazed,
overproductive writers are leechlike annoyances and threats to the social order; for Wordsworth, 70 years
later, mental illness is an occupational hazard to be warded off by emulating in his own vocation the
leech-gatherer’s perseverance in his task, thus turning his crisis in poetic development into the subject,
in turn, of yet more writing. With the once out-of-control technology of writing now subjected to
“disciplinary and professional ends” (38), Wordsworth’s commitment to poetry as a professional
discipline has come to define his personal identity and his value to society. The next section, “Pens and
Periods,” undertakes to make up for the incompleteness of the patriarchal Pope-Wordsworth paradigm by
putting forward an alternative pair of period-framing texts: Anne Finch’s mixed-genre preface to the folio
manuscript of her poems (c. 1702) and excerpts from “A Tour to the Glaciers of Savoy” (1796) by someone
who wrote as “Eliza.” Here the similarities are more important than the differences: both poets
“adjust[ed] to the obstacles they faced as women by acquiescing to limits in ways that made those limits
occasions, sooner or later, for more writing” (40). For Siskin’s purposes, it does not matter that Anne,
later Countess of Winchilsea, was recognized as a poet not only by Wordsworth but by some of her most
prominent male contemporaries, or that “Eliza,” in the rollicking anapests of a comic epistolary
travelogue addressed to a male friend, only playfully acknowledges her friend’s artistic prowess. Siskin’s
point is that both of these female-identified writers declare themselves deficient in poetic talent; both
defer to more gifted male poets; both choose to limit themselves to lesser subjects or forms; both make their
self-imposed limits the subject of pieces of writing; and together they exemplify “a gendered pattern
demonstrably common to women writers but certainly not restricted to them (or them to it): proliferation
through limitation” (42).</p>
          <p>The notion of proliferation through limitation forms the bridge to the next section,
“Productivity and Proper Subjects,” which argues that “exertions of control for the sake of growth . . .
helped to effect the large-scale behavior we call disciplinarity” (43). The Wordsworthian turn toward
“internalization” served to generate more (and more disciplined) writing on narrower and deeper subjects,
but it also led to the separation and downgrading of unproductive or useless studies. Here the exemplary text
is from Marx and Engels’s <hi rend="i">The German Ideology</hi> (1846; published 1932)—a bit beyond the
study’s cut-off date and geographical range, but useful as “a means of articulating . . . the work of
writing” because it so memorably presents the “new criterion of productivity—specifically the capacity
to produce progress” (42). In this text Marx and Engels attack idealist philosophy as the intellectual
equivalent of onanism, as opposed to “study of the actual world,” which is analogous to productive sexual
love. Citing Henry Abelove’s “now infamous” 1989 article in <hi rend="i">Genders</hi>, “Some
Speculations on the History of Sexual Intercourse during the Long Eighteenth Century in England,” Siskin
notes that Marx and Engels’s assumed sexual norm “turns out to be a statistical and thus historical
phenomenon” (45); Abelove attributes the increase in fertility to “a remarkable increase in the incidence
of cross-sex genital intercourse” and speculates that “nonreproductive sexual behaviors” (as well as
other “behaviors, customs, usages which are judged to be nonproductive,” such as being idle on weekdays)
must have come under “extraordinary negative pressure.” The result, according to Siskin, was “a sweeping
reorganization and reconstruction of the human according to the criterion of productivity, including—and, in
many ways, transpiring through—the increasingly important behavior of writing” (45), especially in
eighteenth-century discourses on political economy and in such developments in natural history as
Priestley’s “systematic historicizing of experience, discovery, and theory” (48) and establishment of a
research agenda for future investigators in <hi rend="i">The History and Present State of Electricity</hi>
(1767), as noted by Charles Bazerman in <hi rend="i">Shaping Written Knowledge: The Genre and Activity of the
Experimental Article in Science</hi> (1988).</p>
          <p>“Productivity and Proper Subjects” ends with a discussion of the concluding pages of Hume’s
<hi rend="i">Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding</hi> (1748)—sparingly quoted—as a milestone in
establishing limits for disciplined inquiry. Because the final paragraph of this treatise supplies the second
<pb id="p34-57" n="57"/>
word of the chapter title, “Writing Havoc,” and because allusions to “havoc” as a product of
“writing” recur throughout the book, the passage is worthy of detailed attention. In Siskin’s summation,
Hume
<q>
wrought havoc by insisting skeptically on narrowness and limitation—not as caps to, but as the enabling
conditions of, productivity: disciplines made narrow could become deep and thus serve to induce and control
the proliferation of writing and knowledge. Cast in that form, these newly differentiated kinds of knowledge,
as with social classes, could then be made subject to arguments about their relative productive value: the
distinction of kind between a dominant philosophy and its subordinate branches collapsed and was replaced with
a new hierarchy of degrees—degrees of productivity. (52)
</q></p>
          <p>In context, however, it is clear that Hume’s restrictions on inquiry concern philosophical
investigations only, not inquiry in general. Having pointed out the destructive effects of 
“<hi rend="i">excessive</hi> skepticism,” Hume identifies two species of “<hi rend="i">mitigated</hi>
skepticism, which may be of advantage to mankind”: one is to awaken “dogmatical reasoners” to an
awareness of “the strange infirmities of human understanding, even in its most perfect state,” thus
diminishing “their fond opinion of themselves” and encouraging “a degree of doubt, and caution, and
modesty” which “ought forever to accompany a just reasoner”; the other is “the limitation of our
inquiries to such subjects as are best adapted to the narrow capacity of human understanding,” while
“leaving the more sublime topics to the embellishment of poets and orators, or to the arts of priests and
politicians.” Relying as they must on the limited faculty of reason, as opposed to the unfettered powers of
the imagination, philosophers should concentrate on common life, using either “the more perfect species”
of abstract reasoning concerning quantity and number (the only proper “objects of the abstract sciences or
of demonstration”) or the lesser species of experimental reasoning concerning matters of fact and existence,
as tested by experience of cause-effect relationships. This lesser species is “the foundation of moral
reasoning” and of many of what we would now call the natural and social sciences. For philosophers,
borderline studies involving reason are off limits: for example, although theological study has a foundation
in reason, as supported by experience, “its best and most solid foundation is faith and divine
revelation,” while morals and criticism (e.g., judgments of beauty) “are not so properly objects of the
understanding as of taste and sentiment.” Hume, then, freely acknowledges the legitimacy of studies other
than philosophy and the employment of faculties other than reason; his final paragraph proposes principled
skepticism as an acid test for detecting worthless books of philosophy, not worthless books in general:
<q>
When we run over libraries, persuaded of these principles, what havoc must we make? If we take in our hand any
volume; of divinity and school metaphysics, for instance; let us ask, <hi rend="i">Does it contain any
abstract reasoning concerning quantity and number</hi>? No. <hi rend="i">Does it contain any experimental
reasoning concerning matter of fact and existence</hi>? No. Commit it then to the flames: For it can contain
nothing but sophistry and illusion.
</q></p>
          <p>Siskin insists on reading Hume’s finale more broadly as a rejection of “all volumes that do
not concern either ‘quantity or number,’ on the one hand, or experiential reasoning on human
‘existence,’ on the other” (52). By establishing this division, he argues, Hume “helped to institute
our now familiar distinction between the sciences and the humanities” (52). This division forms the link to
the chapter’s final unit, “Disciplinarity and the Middle Class,” which credits Marx and Engels with
making disciplinary change “a prerequisite for larger-scale institutional and social change” and Hume with
contributing, through his writings, to both kinds of change. Siskin suggests that “Humean havoc,” or the
reslicing of the body of knowledge into new disciplinary categories, “is now our institutions” (50), so
that nowadays “if one wants to produce institutional havoc by challenging what is proper—propriety and
property—then, like Marx and Engels, one must struggle with the force of disciplinary difference” (51).
Thus it is not surprising that “today’s havoc” in the academic world, in the face of disciplinary
realignments, middle-class tax revolts, and threats to humanities funding, “is occurring at another moment
of technological change” (53). Commandeered as the governing metaphor for “Writing Havoc,” Hume’s
image of library-wrecking is powerful, even irresistible. So why not just say so? It is not necessary to
distort Hume’s text to appropriate his image for other purposes; a straightforward acknowledgment of the
broader application would only have strengthened this chapter.</p>
          <p>Throughout <hi rend="i">The Work of Writing</hi>, but especially in section two,
“Professionalism: The Poetics of Labor,” Siskin has interesting things to say about the shifting meanings
of “work.” He relates the invention of the “deep, developmental self” (106)—a romantic (or
Wordsworthian) innovation—to a “rewriting” of the concept of work that altered it “from that which a
true gentleman does not have to do, to the primary activity informing adult identity” (107). The myth of
vocation “made work more than necessary: it made work desirable—and necessary for personal happiness”
(107). Siskin notes that the adjective “professional,” along with the differentiating term “amateur,”
entered the language at the end of the eighteenth and the beginning of the nineteenth centuries; before that
time, “profession” meant simply “known employment” and “professional behavior had been idealized as
the behavior of gentlemen” (108); afterward, codes of professional conduct had to be developed as the new
way of writing about work “rearranged the relationships
<pb id="p34-58" n="58"/>
among—and the functions of—character, identity, status, work, money, education, property, and propriety”
(109). One of the surprises of this section is that both of its chapters employ literary genres as explanatory
devices to suggest that the proliferation of writing “not only helped to occasion through limitation the
re-forming of knowledge into disciplines—including Literature as the disciplinary home of writing
itself—it also altered work, enabling and valorizing newly specialized forms of intellectual labor” (104).
“The Georgic at Work” goes so far as to describe “writing in the form of the georgic” as a “crucial
tool in the making of modern professionalism” (120) because in dignifying hard work as “the proper mode
for nation building and the affirmation of personal and civic virtue” (119) and in “naturalizing what it
articulated,” it became “the means by which the work of writing itself came to be seen as a potentially
heroic activity” (120), with the key texts being Dryden’s translation of Virgil, the “prose georgics”
of Adam Smith’s <hi rend="i">The Wealth of Nations</hi>, and Wordworth’s <hi rend="i">The Prelude.</hi>
The balancing chapter, “The Lyricization of Labor,” seeks to connect the historical development of the
lyric to other developments of the same period: the recategorization of work into higher and lower orders on
the basis of age, skill, character, and gender, and the reorganization of knowledge into disciplines “that
fostered narrow but deep subjects such as Literature” (133). Here Siskin is careful to stop well short of a
cause-and-effect claim that lyrics actually produced changes in the form of labor; instead, “the work of
writing, and how writing worked, changed in the same kinds of ways in which other kinds of work changed”
(146). With specialization as the link, Siskin finds broad social significance in the lyric’s movement from
a mixed, experimental form employed early in the century by many different kinds of writers of both sexes to
its glorification later in the period, by the romantics, as the most “literary” form of literature, the
most intensely poetic form of poetry, a form of expression so exalted that it could be attempted only by the
most gifted and sensitive poets (all male): “Without claiming causation, we can find in the lyric—and in
its fate (i.e., in whose hands it ended up)—ways to make sense of contemporaneous regroupings of knowledge
and labor” (146). Regrettably, however, Siskin turns away from poetics to find silly slogans for these
changes: “‘Bring home the bacon’—from by-employments to occupation; ‘Whistle while you
work’—from combinations to trade unions; and ‘Look Ma, no hands!’—the advent of mental labor”
(135).</p>
          <p>Siskin begins the section on “Novelism: Literature in the History of Writing” by pointing out
a striking incongruity: standard accounts of the “rise” of the novel, which peak with Fielding,
Richardson, Smollett, and Sterne, give short shrift to the last two decades of the century, just when the
publication rate of new novels (and other genres as well) shot up to unprecedented heights. Making use of
figures tracking both the general economy and print markets, from sources as varied as Anthony J. Little, 
<hi rend="i">Deceleration in the Eighteenth-Century British Economy</hi> (1976), John Richetti, 
<hi rend="i">Popular Fiction Before Richardson: Narrative Patterns 1700-1739</hi> (1969), James Raven, 
<hi rend="i">Judging New Wealth: Popular Publishing and Responses to Commerce in England 1750-1800</hi> (1992),
Robert Mayo, <hi rend="i">The English Novel in the Magazines 1740-1815</hi> (1962), and Jon Klancher, 
<hi rend="i">The Making of English Reading Audiences, 1790-1832</hi> (1987), Siskin explores how the novel
participated “in the increased proliferation and in the naturalization of writing” (156). Although there
was a mid-century slump in the book business coinciding with a period of “profitless prosperity” (159
[Little’s term]) in the overall British economy, periodicals flourished, bringing fiction to more and more
readers, before becoming concentrated at the end of the century in fewer magazines of wider circulation. The
proliferation of periodicals heightened awareness of the Author (Siskin’s capitalization) in two ways:
“Author-Before-Work,” a term drawn from Eliza Haywood’s statement in <hi rend="i">The Female
Spectator</hi> that she prefers “to get as well acquainted as I can with an Author, <hi rend="i">before</hi>
I run the risque of losing my Time in perusing his <hi rend="i">Work</hi>” (qtd. 162, Siskin’s italics),
spurred critical commentary that created a following for individual writers; “Reader-As-Author,” the
fictionalization of readers as participants in print-conversations with other readers and with magazine
editors (who often wrote letters to the journal from imaginary readers, to encourage real ones to join in),
helped to keep the magazines supplied with free content and aroused in readers the desire to read more novels
and to become writers themselves. Without making clear that William Godwin’s 1797 essay, “Of History and
Romance,” was not published until 1988 (when Maurice Hindle appended it to his Penguin edition of 
<hi rend="i">Caleb Williams</hi>), Siskin cites it as a landmark in freeing the novel from “the gender to which
it was linked throughout the eighteenth century” and making it a respectable vehicle for serious writing, on
a par with histories exhibiting what Godwin called “bold and <hi rend="i">masculine</hi> virtues” (quoted
171; Siskin’s italics, unattributed). In the same way that “poetry was lyricized, prose was novelized”
(178), and as more novels came under critical scrutiny in periodicals, the encoding of certain forms of
fictional characters’ improper behavior as foreign, particularly French, contributed to a sense of British
national identity while at the same time laying the groundwork, in critical commentary, for the soon-to-emerge
discipline of English literature.</p>
          <p>The fourth section, “Gender: The Great Forgetting,” zeroes in on an overriding concern of the
study: how did women participate in the proliferation of writing, how were they affected by it, and why has so
much of their participation been forgotten? The question of why one writer in particular, Jane Austen, has not
only been remembered but has become part of the curriculum in English literature leads Siskin into a sustained
consideration of Austen’s relation to the discipline in which her work is studied. Back in the second
chapter, “Engendering Disciplinarity,” Siskin had argued
<pb id="p34-59" n="59"/>
that modern disciplinarity “was not first constituted and then later altered by gender difference” but
rather has “functioned from its inception to articulate and enact those differences” (55), beginning with
eighteenth-century writings on education. Depth and narrowness, formerly cultivated as the alternative private
sphere of studious women like Mary Astell, guided the selective pruning of writing in the reorganization of
knowledge, work, and printed matter into higher and lower-status disciplines, professions, and literary
genres—all of which worked to the advantage of men. Burke’s <hi rend="i">Philosophical Enquiry into the
Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful</hi> (1757), which identifies men with the sublime and women
with the beautiful, accelerated this reorganization of knowledge through “the celebration of intellectual
labor, the specialization of that labor into increasingly distinct and thus potentially deep fields, and the
construction and accessing of that distinctive depth through specialized uses of words” (70-71). (The weird
notion that Longinus and Burke championed the sublime as a means of combating indolence and “making men
work” is underpinned with drastically out-of-context quotations.) As these specialized divisions of labor
became a “proliferation-through-limitation strategy,” “culture” replaced “the sublime” as “the
inclusive rubric for what had been legitimated” (71), making lines of division between disciplines appear to
be natural while unintentionally perpetuating gender-related hierarchies. Culture became the eventual domain
of the discipline of English literature, as taught and studied by academic professionals. Within this
discipline, Austen has always been an anomaly: an early-canonized woman writer whose achievement in her genre
(as considered in studies of the “rise” of the novel) resists categorization with that of Fielding and
Richardson in one century or with Scott and Dickens in another—and now, when “Literature” has been
knocked off its pedestal and swept into cultural studies, one who defies categorization as a feminist and
challenges the disciplinary identity of all who try to classify her.</p>
          <p>The case of Austen is instructive. Because Siskin gives sustained attention to Austen’s
situation and anchors his exploratory speculations in specifics, the section on Gender is his most persuasive
and illuminating. In <hi rend="i">The Historicity of Romantic Discourse</hi> Siskin had placed Austen, as a
narrator of development, among the romantics; in this book, he investigates how it was that her innovations in
the novel, her way of drawing readers into the interior lives of her characters, set the direction for the
future of the genre, while the stylistic models of Fielding and Richardson became dead ends. Without quoting
F. R. Leavis’s 1948 statement that Austen was “the inaugurator of the great tradition of the English
novel,” Siskin notes that what he calls “The Great Forgetting” of women writers (Austen excepted) became
“The Great Tradition” in departments of English; Austen’s acceptance by male critics of her own time
signals a crucial moment when “some of the fundamental links between women and the novel—links that we are
only now recovering—were first detached, or at least obscured” (197). By placing Austen’s work within
the history of writing, rather than literature, Siskin reveals that the late eighteenth-century “takeoff in
publication rates,” especially in periodicals, made Austen’s career and later reputation possible, both by
“giving new value to the position of Author and by making that position more accessible to more people”
(198). For Siskin’s argument, it is somewhat awkward that Austen preferred to publish anonymously, but his
point is still valid: Scott—for one—recognized her distinctive authorial hand in his (anonymous) 1815
piece in the <hi rend="i">Quarterly Review</hi> and praised her work as “new” and better than that of her
contemporaries. The strangeness of Austen’s publication history—writing prolifically in the 1790s but not
publishing until the second decade of the nineteenth century, despite her desire to see her work in print—is
made even stranger by her decision not to publish in magazines, a readily available outlet in which she could
have maintained her anonymity. Siskin notes that by publishing in book form only, whatever her reasons may
have been, Austen participated in “the historical transformation of the two-tier market [for fiction] into a
hierarchical system of what we now know as high versus low culture,” a development that “ushered in the
disciplinary advent of the new category of Literature” (200). Her novels, in earning praise for what they
did <hi rend="i">not</hi> include—Gothic claptrap that, according to the <hi rend="i">Quarterly Review</hi>,
“should now be left to ladies’ maids and sentimental washerwomen”—played “an unexpected role in the
disciplinary exclusion of women and women’s writing” (200). Siskin suggests that a major reason for
Austen’s early acceptance into the literary canon is that she helped to change writing from a threatening
new technology to a reassuringly “natural,” domesticated, and entertaining medium for portraying British
life. For example, she was so good at putting her readers at ease as they read about the unsettling effects
(on her characters) of too much romance-reading that - to the question raised in <hi rend="i">Northanger
Abbey</hi> as to whether readers (especially young women) become what they read - Austen’s answer, according
to Siskin, is “Yes and no, but don’t worry,” signaling “a change in the status of writing from a
worrisome new technology to a more trusted tool” (204).</p>
          <p>But the development of an “Author-centered, gender-conscious economy of print” (215), as
changes in copyright law and in the textual marketplace closed off opportunities for women writers to publish
and to have their work known and discussed, led to “Authorial professionalism,” which contributed to the
taming of writing and the elevation of certain kinds of writing to the status of high literature; all this
made possible the “remasculinization of British Literature at the turn into the nineteenth century” (216)
and the academic institutionalization of the Great Tradition in the twentieth century. <hi rend="i">The
Edinburgh Review</hi>, founded in 1802, “helped to masculinize the literary” by establishing an oldboys’
<pb id="p34-60" n="60"/>
network of reviewers, interspersing reviews with “newly specialized treatments of traditionally masculine
subjects, particularly economics and politics” (224) and replacing inclusive coverage of new books with
fewer and deeper reviews of selected books. To elucidate the disproportionate impact of these developments on
women writers in “the social life of texts,” Siskin picks up the jarring term “reverse vicariousness”
(217) from David S. Kaufer and Kathleen M. Carley’s <hi rend="i">Communication at a Distance: The Influence
of Print on Sociocultural Organization and Change</hi> (1993). According to Kaufer and Carley, this phenomenon
allows even nonreaders to “positively register at social gatherings that they ‘know of’ the book without
having seen or read it first hand” and keep up with the “vogue information of culture” that establishes
membership in their peer groups. This “keeping up,” Siskin observes, became “a very particular problem
for a particular group at the particular historical moment that Authorial momentum began to turn Britain into
an information culture” (218). Thus the forgetting of women writers “was neither causal nor natural; it
was, rather, the result of what was reproduced, for whom, and how[;] . . . it was a matter of whose texts,
read or <hi rend="i">even unread</hi>, did get talked about and reproduced and whose texts, unread or 
<hi rend="i">even read</hi>, slipped into silence and out of production” (218). How much deeper into silence, he
might have added, risk slipping those texts, read or unread, that were never in the production system in the
first place!</p>
          <p>And so, after all, <hi rend="i">The Work of Writing</hi> will find its uses in Blake studies—at
least as a contrasting backdrop for the kind of work Blake did, and as a lens through which his critical
reception may be viewed. Siskin compellingly characterizes exactly the sorts of “writing” in which Blake,
a dropout from print culture, chose not to participate, except as a professional engraver, and upon which, as
a poet, he made scarcely a dent. Ardently and industriously engaged in his artistic vocation, in near-poverty
and obscurity, Blake managed to slip through the tightening nets of disciplinarity, professionalism, and
genre-divisions of his time. He never benefited, as a writer, from an influential contemporary’s
“Author-before-Reader” hype, buzz, or spin. To the extent that his poems “did get talked about” by
Wordsworth, Coleridge, and other poets, the conversations took place in private or through correspondence,
with the single exception of a brief entry in <hi rend="i">A Biographical Dictionary of the Living Authors of
Great Britain and Ireland</hi> (1816), while more substantial public comments on Blake’s poetry, by a
handful of memoirists and fellow artists, appeared mainly as adjuncts to accounts of his development as an
artist. The proliferation of periodicals had absolutely no effect on Blake’s literary reputation (T.G.
Wainewright’s promise in <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> [September 1820] of a forthcoming article by
“Dr. Tobias Ruddicombe, M.D.” on “Jerusalem the Emanation of the Giant Albion” never materialized).
The only thing Blake himself ever published in a journal was an indignant letter to the editor of the 
<hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> (1 July 1806) in defense of Fuseli’s painting of Dante’s Ugolino. As he
noted in a letter of 1 September 1800 to George Cumberland (into which he copied a letter submitted to the 
<hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> in support of Cumberland’s proposal for a national gallery of art), “I so
little understand the way to get such things into Magazines or News papers that if I have done wrong in Merely
delivering the Letter at the Publishers of the Magazine beg you will inform me” (Robert N. Essick and Morton
D. Paley, “‘Dear Generous Cumberland’: A Newly Discovered Letter and Poem by William Blake,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 32 [1998]: 5). Two and a half years later, in a letter of 30 January 1803, Blake boasted
to his brother James that he had learned from Hayley “&amp; his connexions &amp; his method of managing”
that “The Profits arising from Publications are immense,” but if he really knew how to realize “almost
certain profits” of “500 G.” on a book “got out at the Expense of Ten pounds,” he never put his
scheme into effect. Blake’s entire poetic output, whether produced in letterpress (the privately printed 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, the unpublished and unsold <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>) or in
self-printed, hand-finished limited editions, utterly eschews the “Authorial professionalism” and
“historical connections between Authorship and economic change” (160) that Siskin traces in 
<hi rend="i">The Work of Writing.</hi> A case in point: on 25 April 1803, after three years of writing “from
immediate Dictation twelve or sometimes twenty or thirty lines at a time without Premeditation &amp; even
against my Will,” Blake informed Thomas Butts that “an immense Poem Exists which seems to be the Labour of
a long Life all produced without Labour or Study.” So it was not as a writer that Blake was eulogized in
literary papers (e.g., the <hi rend="i">Literary Gazette</hi> of 18 August 1827, reprinted in the 
<hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> and elsewhere), but as an artist. Until the publication of Gilchrist’s
biography in 1863, as noted in G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), his name was
kept alive mainly in Allen Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors
and Architects</hi> (1830).</p>
          <p>Since 1830, the closing year of Siskin’s book, the work of writing has continued to make short
work of Blake the writer. When he finally gained recognition as a poet, late in the nineteenth century, he was
unusually slow to benefit from the institutionalization of English literature as an academic discipline, and
he has remained a similarly anomalous, out-of-the-mainstream figure in art history. His short-lived canonical
status among the “big six” male English romantic poets, which was not attained until the late 1950s (after
a long probationary period with Burns among the pre-romantics), was quickly challenged, in part on the grounds
of gender, in the many waves of “writing havoc” that have washed over the disciplines of the humanities in
the last 30 years. Now his space in the MLA annual bibliography appears to be shrinking, and it seems that
fewer graduate students aspire to build their professional lives around him.</p>
          <p>For some of these very reasons, however, the work that Blake executed in his experimental
eighteenth-century technology of relief etching has not, even yet, been tamed or
<pb id="p34-61" n="61"/>
naturalized; for all we know, it may prove impervious to the formidable cultural forces Siskin associates with
the enterprise of “writing.” Blake, of all writers, stands to benefit most from the ongoing boom in
post-literary technologies, and Blake studies, as an academic endeavor, may have a good chance of surviving,
even thriving, in the waning years of print culture. In the millennium just ahead, as discussed at the 1998
convention of the Modern Language Association and in <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi> 30 (1999),
web-based electronic marvels like the Blake Archive (and its ever more dazzling reincarnations in technologies
yet to come) will allow unprecedented numbers of the children of the future age to experience the thrills and
threats of Blake’s achievement—already, Internet users anywhere in the world can call up images from a
wider range of illuminated writings in a shorter span of time than anyone, including Blake himself, has ever
seen at one sitting before. For Blake’s future readers and viewers, it is possible that the response to this
exhilarating experience won’t simply be more writing, in the form of yet more work-products. What if some of
these readers should forego, however briefly, “the meer drudgery of business,” as Blake wrote to Butts on
10 January 180[3], and make the difficult choice, with Blake, to “follow the dictates of our Angels” and
carry out “the Tasks set before us”? And what if a few, somewhere, someday, should actually heed Blake’s
call, in the Preface to chapter 4 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, to “expel from among you those who pretend
to despise the labours of Art &amp; Science” and decide to engage “openly &amp; publicly before all the
World in some Mental pursuit for the Building up of Jerusalem”? Where would the work of writing be then?</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
