<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>34.2.niimi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Book of Ahania: A Metatext</title>
        <author n="Niimi">Hatsuko Niimi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2000</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2000</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">34.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Hatsuko Niimi</name>
              <name>Kazuya Okada</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2000"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_34">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-34-2-0006">
        <pb id="p34-46" n="46"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>: A Metatext</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Hatsuko <name>Niimi</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The three books etched by Blake in 1794-95, namely <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen, The Book of
Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> have been considered by many critics to be a sequence of
parodies or satires on the Pentateuch; David W. Lindsay, Leslie Tannenbaum and Stephen C. Behrendt maintain
that they constitute Blake’s Bible of Hell, intended to revise and challenge the received Bible of Heaven,
while Harold Bloom believes they belong in the framework of the Orc myths. Tannenbaum, examining them in the
context of the Bible and its traditions, regards <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">Los</hi> as dealing
with the events in the book of Genesis and <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> as related to the book of Exodus. Finally,
David Worrall, in his edition of the three books, which appeared in 1995 and is the most recent, groups them
together and refers to them as the Urizen Books; he considers the trilogy to be “an expression of Blake’s
scepticism about his age’s politicization of scriptural authority” (153). This corresponds to Jon Mee’s
claim that “Blake is constantly seeking to break down the notion of scripture as monolithic authority”
(14); his primary assumption is that Blake’s “rhetorical practices” (2) in the 1790s can be construed
better and differently, if put in the context of the controversy over the French Revolution. Worrall examines
the extent to which Blake was affected by the political and religious debates in progress in London during
this decade: disputes which intensified and grew more dangerous for those suspected of sedition, when England
declared war against France in 1793, and Thomas Paine’s <hi rend="i">The Age of Reason</hi> was published in
1794-95. Worrall defines the Urizen Books, written in the years of “Pitt’s Terror” (12), as Blake’s
“most politically interventionist works” (19) and gives particular attention to his Muggletonian
sympathies and his connection with one of his contemporaries, the radical anti-clericalist, Thomas
Spence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">1</ref> It may, then, be an
invitation to disagreement to single out one of these books as a work with its own peculiar merit and
significance. But to read <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> closely encourages us, I believe, to see it as
unique in its ability to shed light on Blake’s ideas concerning writing or literacy, as opposed to speaking
or orality, and consequently on his view of the text, or the book, in general. 
<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Worrall’s assertion that the Books were written “against a background of an authoritative
and repressive culture” (15) is cogently illustrated in his discussion of <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>, which he
situates in the contemporary print culture of political caricature (157-59), and in his analysis of its
endpiece design (162-63).</note></p>
          <p>One of the distinctive features of this work, in contrast with <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Los</hi>, is the role <corr type="emend">allotted</corr> to the female character. In 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, Enitharmon is presented by means of description as a figure giving birth to Orc, and
weeping over her son chained to a rock, but at no point does she speak for herself. Similarly, 
<hi rend="i">Los</hi> consists entirely of the recollections of its narrator, Eno, apart from the six lines which
introduce her, but Eno does not tell her own story. Yet Ahania, whose plight is described in the opening
chapter of the book named after her, begins to speak for herself in the fifth and last chapter: her
lamentation for the prelapsarian state of her union with Urizen occupies almost the whole of this chapter, and
is therefore given great prominence. This fact, together with the content of her speech, suggests that the
events connected with Urizen and Fuzon, which are related in the first four chapters, are, like her own
situation, capable of being interpreted in a new way: in the context of linguistic activity, with its various
moral, historical and ideological connotations.</p>
          <p>Jon Mee, who considers the three books to be “Blake’s critique of the Bible” (162), refers,
in his discussion of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, to Blake’s making use of “an antithesis between written and
oral forms” (103), and characterizes the former as oppressive and the latter as liberated. His argument
includes a consideration of the status of Blake’s own writing in his chosen medium of illuminated printing.
Although Mee is only concerned with the opposition between the druid-priest Urizen and bard-prophets like Orc
and Los, I think this sort of opposition exists also in <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>, in the contrast between
Urizen who “wrote / In silence his book of iron” (pl. 4:63-64)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">2</ref> and Ahania, “his parted soul” (pl. 3:32), and in the relationship between
Urizen and Fuzon, whose corpse “Urizen nail’d” on the topmost stem of “the accursed Tree of Mystery”
(pl. 5:6-8). Urizen is depicted as the murderer of his rebellious son and a producer of written books, but he
remains silent throughout the book, except for four lines addressed to his bow. Fuzon, a character who
resembles Orc, denounces Urizen in four lines which occur early in chapter 1, just before he attempts to
assassinate him: in chapter 2 he utters one line of exultation when he thinks he has succeeded: otherwise he
also remains silent. In striking contrast, Ahania shows herself capable of prolonged eloquence in the
concluding chapter, as she speaks of her love for Urizen and her vision of the past, her fervor unaffected by
her sense of the futility of her appeal. <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">2</hi> All quotations from 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> are from <hi rend="i">The Urizen Books</hi> edited by David Worrall (London:
The William Blake Trust/The Tate Gallery, 1995). Subsequent references to the text will be designated by the
plate number, followed by the lines in parentheses, as in (Pl. 3: 1-5).</note></p>
          <p>The purpose of this paper is to interpret <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> as a metatext, concerned with
conflicting and antagonistic linguistic realities, represented by the activities of these three characters.
First, Ahania’s speech will be discussed, with reference to Saussure’s distinction between parole and
langue and Walter J. Ong’s analysis of orality and literacy. My argument is that Ahania is an instance of
parole, which is “active
<pb id="p34-47" n="47"/>
and individual” (Saussure 70a), or a “winged word,” a Homeric phrase, familiar to many of Blake’s
contemporaries through Horne Tooke’s book,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">3</ref> and signifying “evanescence, power, and freedom” (Ong 77). In addition, I hope by
discussing her speech, to connect it with her markedly feminine “ethics of care” (Mellor 3). 
<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The phrase, in Greek, constituted the first two words of the title Horne Tooke
gave to his two-volume study of language and grammar, <hi rend="i">Epea Pteroenta: Or, the Diversions of
Purley</hi> (1786-1805). Tooke (1736-1812) was known primarily as a radical politician, but achieved temporary
fame as an etymologist as a result of this book until genuine philological knowledge began to reach England
from the continent in the nineteenth century.
                            <p>Robert N. Essick, in <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of Adam</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1989), discusses Tooke’s work on language in relation to Blake as well as to Locke in
the linguistic context of the late eighteenth and the early nineteenth century (57-66). He also gives an
explication of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> as Blake’s criticism of contemporary linguistic theories
(140-59). Although Tooke’s book was published by Joseph Johnson, there is no surviving evidence that Blake
met him or knew his book.</p>
	<p>The phrase is used by Blake in the Preludium to <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, where he asks the
“Eternals” to “Dictate swift winged words” (Pl. 2:6). Angela Esterhammer, in her <hi rend="i">Creating
States</hi>, discusses the poem in terms of naming and speech acts and argues that the Preludium “must
already make us suspicious about the extent to which (inspired) words will be instruments of imposition on a
passive audience” (155).</p></note></p>
          <p>Conversely, Urizen, it seems to me, represents an aspect of langue, which is “passive and
resident in the collectivity” (Saussure 70a), and he also possesses, I believe, the characteristics of
writing, which is “a particularly pre-emptive and imperialistic activity” (Ong 12). I shall attempt to
show that Urizen’s casting out of Ahania, who represents his “pathos,” that is, his ability to feel pity
or sadness, and his murder of Fuzon, who is his eros, demonstrate his conception of justice, which consists of
enforcing repressive and self-righteous laws and of the writing of books, which in their inflexibility are
incapable of response to the dynamic procedures of language formation.</p>
          <p>Finally, I would like to discuss the unmistakable affinities between Ahania’s lucid eloquence
and Blake’s creation of illuminated hand-printed texts, and the close resemblance between Urizen’s writing
of “his book of iron” and the standardized printing of texts which have been established with finality.
Blake’s production of his etched texts, analogous to the production of manuscripts, is much more akin to
spoken language than the reproduction by a printing press of written language. Moreover, in <hi rend="i">The
Book of Ahania</hi> there are two designs which depict Ahania; they help to justify my belief that Blake’s
conception of the text/book can be deduced from an analysis of the various contrasts between Urizen and
Ahania. Blake’s books will never be definitive and the same to all readers; they will remain flexible and
fluid, seeking a dialogue with readers every time they are produced, with successive copies always differing
in some respect.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>I</title>
            </head>
            <p>In chapter 1 of <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>, the heroine represents the soul, or emanation of
Urizen, divided from him after Fuzon’s attack on his “cold loins” has caused him to discard her as sin:
she is said to move as “the moon anguishd circles the earth,” for she is under the control of Urizen; as
“a faint shadow” and the “mother of Pestilence,” she is bound to revolve round him, “Unseen,
unbodied, unknown.” She becomes a voiceless figure, associated with disease and death, the victim of
Urizen’s suppression and hatred, as well as an invisible and amorphous being. Except for the first six
lines, which describe her formless presence, chapter 5 consists first of her lamentation over her miserable
separation and alienation from Urizen; secondly, of her unwearied questionings of his rejection, aloofness and
rigidity, and finally, of her frank and impassioned recollections of her glorious past, sharing sexual and
mental joy, beauty and freedom with Urizen.</p>
            <p>Although at the beginning of the work, Ahania is said to be his “parted soul,” in the final
chapter, she can be said to be a representation of either wisdom (Bloom 176, Tannenbaum 242), or pleasure
(Paley 30), or desire (Worrall 185), according to the aspect of her supplication which is seen as predominant.
She is also relational and interpersonal, with “the mutualism of selflessness” (Behrendt 147): she has
care and compassion for others, as well as resistance to the dualism and universalization which characterise
abstract thinking (Cox 160). As regards style, she uses pictorial and concrete images and introduces into the
poem “a new speed and flexibility” (Lindsay 146). Ahania is described as wandering and floating, as well
as weeping and chanting “on the verge / Of Non-entity,” which indicates the extent to which her exiled
condition can vary.</p>
            <p>It is obvious that her role is primarily that of a speaker: a protagonist whose medium is
language. More specifically, she is endowed with the functions of parole and orality, or oral culture. I would
like to demonstrate this by referring first to Saussure’s conception of parole, as expounded in his third
course of lectures on general linguistics (1910-11). He distinguishes two kinds of parole: “The use of
faculties in general for linguistic purposes (phonation, etc.)” and “individual use of the language code
to express individual thought” (70a); this last function of parole, which is the source of all change in a
language, is of crucial importance in linguistic activity. He further indicates the interdependency between
parole and langue:
<q>
There is nothing in the language which has not entered (directly or indirectly) through speech, that is
through the sum total of words perceived, and conversely no speech is possible before the development of this
product called the language, which supplies the individual with the elements for the composition of his
speech. (71a)
</q></p>
            <pb id="p34-48" n="48"/>
            <p>In contrast to langue, which is constructed structure, parole is constructing structure; parole
is regulated by the collective knowledge of langue, which in turn is to be reformed through the individual
activity of parole. David Holdcroft lists six comparable characteristics shared by the two, according to
Saussure’s account: parole is individual, contingent, has an active role, is designed, is not conventional,
and provides a heterogeneous subject matter which is studied by different disciplines, whereas langue is
social, essential, has no active individual role, is not designed, but conventional, and provides a
homogeneous subject matter to be studied as a branch of social psychology (21). By quoting Saussure’s
              <corr type="emend">statement</corr> that “Each change is launched by a certain number of individuals before it is accepted for general
use,” Holdcroft emphasizes that “parole is needed to explain not only how langue is constituted as a
stable system in a community, but also how changes occur in it” (33).</p>
            <p>Ong, who recognizes the primacy of parole (oral speech) in Saussure’s classifications, has
given further consideration to the respective spheres of the oral and the literate. It is relevant to draw on
his argument in order to clarify certain aspects of the function of language in a community. He states:
<q>
. . .oral cultures must conceptualize and verbalize all their knowledge with more or less close reference to
the human lifeworld, assimilating the alien, objective world to the more immediate, familiar interaction of
human beings.(42)
</q></p>
            <p>Orality “situates knowledge within a context of struggle,” engaging “others in verbal and
intellectual combat” (44); “Primary orality fosters personality structures that in certain ways are more
communal and externalized, less introspective than those common among literates. Oral communication unites
people in groups” (69). He also points out that “Oral man is not so likely to think of words as
‘signs,’ quiescent visual phenomena,” but as “constantly moving, but by flight, which is a powerful
form of movement, and one lifting the flier free of the ordinary, gross, heavy, ‘objective’ world” (77).
It is necessary to see these characteristics of oral cultures in contrast with those of writing cultures, and
I would like to discuss this topic later in part 2, in connection with Urizen’s role as a writer. But the
immediate relevance of Ong’s account of the distinctive features of oral cultures to my argument concerning
Ahania, consists in his claim that they spring from direct contacts with the living world, from a strong
interest in differences between the self and others, and from a consequent wish to become involved with
others, by setting up personal relationships. Finally, his suggestion that language is seen as flexible and
mobile by speakers in an oral culture, is particularly relevant to my interpretation of this character.</p>
            <p>In chapter 5 of <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>, we can detect in the descriptions of her state and in
her own utterances various elements which remind us of the aspects of parole and orality to which I have drawn
attention:
<q>
Her voice was heard, but no form<lb/>
Had she: but her tears from clouds<lb/>
Eternal fell round the Tree<lb/>
(pl. 5:49-51)
</q></p>
            <p>It is noticeable that her existence is verbal, yet has no fixed form. It has therefore one
quality essential to orality: so has her unrestricted power to feel sorrow and compassion for the pain and
suffering of others. In addition, her passionate yearning for Urizen and her continuing sense of his merit and
superiority, are repeatedly suggested by her actions and words:
<q>
And the voice cried: Ah Urizen! Love!<lb/>
Flower of morning! I weep on the verge<lb/>
On Non-entity; how wide the Abyss<lb/>
Between Ahania and thee!<lb/>
(pl. 5:52-55)
</q></p>
            <p>The significance of her invisibility as well as the danger that she will become extinct,
separated from Urizen, will be discussed later, but the point to notice here is that, in spite of his hardness
and cruel rejection of her, she never fails to show care and love for him, unable to see his initial
brightness and magnificence as lost, and seeking to reestablish their unity. Memory is also an important
element in orality (Ong 19). Worrall states that Ahania’s solitary lament “is presented as the most
dubious authentification of Urizen” (153) and thinks her “irrevocable loss of Urizen’s presence might
itself be a misremembered recollection of a paradisaical joy which never happened” (155). It is, however,
hard to discover any grounds in her speech for this interpretation. Her plea is earnest and pressing, vividly
recalling his “bright presence” (pl. 5:63). Her intense and continuous plea for change is vain, which
makes her appeal pathetic, but no less authentic.</p>
            <p>Ahania’s most individual and unconventional characteristics are very evident in her vision of
her former blissful intercourse with Urizen, and in her vindication of the passion and fulfilment of their
love as her recollections proceed. She is eager to “awake my king in the morn! / To embrace Ahanias joy / On
the breadth of his open bosom” (pl. 6:10-12) and looks back to the time:
<q>
When he gave my happy soul<lb/>
To the sons of eternal joy:<lb/>
When he took the daughters of life<lb/>
Into my chambers of love:<lb/>
When I found babes of bliss on my beds.<lb/>
And bosoms of milk in my chambers<lb/>
Fill’d with eternal seed<lb/>
O! eternal births sung round Ahania<lb/>
In interchange sweet of their joys.<lb/>
(pl. 6:15-23)
</q></p>
            <pb id="p34-49" n="49"/>
            <p>She dwells with passionate affirmation on the unique world of unrestrained desire, sexual joy
and consequent fertility, which she shared with Urizen: she is referring to “the eternal exchange of the
joys of love freely given and received in a sexual embrace” (Tannenbaum 246). Lindsay, emphasizing the fact
that “the human integrity and creativity of an unfallen mind” are portrayed in this section, indicates
that the “golden age here is remembered as one of free and confident energy, of delight unrestricted by
possessiveness, of abundance and unfettered generosity” (147). Ahania recalls the sense of belonging to a
unified whole, which she experienced when she and Urizen were together and in harmony. She expresses herself
in fluid and prolific images, which contrast strongly with Urizenic categorization and demarcation.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">4</ref> She is not uttering a prophetic vision, but
recreating an experienced world of life and love. She is a daring believer in her own vision of the past,
though she does not know how to reclaim it, and it is the fervor of her belief that gives her speech its
individuality. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Cox discusses Ahania’s attempt to “try to picture the
state of undivided yet <hi rend="i">related</hi> wholeness that existed before Urizen began his revolutionary
career” and suggests that her “pictorializations are vaguely bordered, expandable things that resist both
sharp division and dogmatic universalization” (160).</note></p>
            <p>The generosity of maternal love, the willingness to forgive natural to a liberal mind, and the
urge to recover the unstinted reciprocity of a sexual and personal relationship are all demonstrated in
Ahania’s speech, and all correspond to the characteristics of parole and orality. It will deepen our
understanding of this speech, from a linguistic viewpoint, if we consider the feminine ethics it implies,
which also share some of the qualities of parole and orality. In her study of Michel Foucault and feminism,
Lois McNay examines the feminine critique of rationality, stating that in contrast to an abstract, masculine
ethics of justice, “a feminist ethics is based on a responsiveness to others and a respect for the
particular which leads to moral concerns connected to providing care, preventing harm and maintaining
relationships” (92). In her discussion of Carole Gilligan’s “particular ethics,” which is “based
more on caring and interpersonal relations” (93), she explicates Gilligan’s view of women’s moral
judgments, which are “more contextual and more immersed in the details of relationships and narrative (the
‘particular other’)” (93). This ethics of care is certainly to be found in Ahania’s attitude to Urizen
and in the pity for Fuzon which the opening lines of chapter 5 attribute to her. Her longing for the
restoration of broken relationships is central to her character. As Anne K. Mellor points out, Blake’s
“feminine ethics” is developed fully in later prophetic books, especially in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
in his creation of “Emanations” which “are clearly maternal and valued for their feminine capacities for
sympathy and empathy” (21). But in <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>, the heroine’s speech and her implied
characteristics do not only arise from a moral outlook which anticipates postmodern feminine ethics. They also
reveal her commitment to a far more amorphous and generous love relationship. She places a strong emphasis on
the primacy of physicality, sexually based difference, and the capacity for reform. Being unseen, unbodied and
unknown to fallen Urizen, and asking insistently for change and for a close personal bond, as she gives full
vent to her innermost sorrow and joy, she embodies speech, or Saussurean parole, though this parole is
received or approved by no one, as it reaches out towards a reciprocal relationship which has been lost.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">II</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>If it is appropriate to regard Ahania as representing parole and orality, what are the roles of
Urizen and Fuzon in terms of linguistic activity? And especially what is the meaning of Ahania’s solitary
and rejected situation in the context of language? It is again relevant to examine Saussure’s concept of
parole in contrast to langue, and Ong’s differentiation of orality and literacy as opposing principles; it
will enable us to see that Urizen is possessed of some attributes of langue and the function of writing. In
<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, he is depicted chiefly as the crucifixer of Fuzon and as a writer of
books, seated on the rock enclosed by the Tree of Mystery.</p>
            <p>As we have seen, Ong stresses the primacy of orality and suggests that writing “was a very
late development in human history” (83). Moreover, writing “separates the knower from the known and thus
sets up conditions for ‘objectivity,’ in the sense of personal disengagement or distancing” (46). He
offers a four-point summary of Plato’s view of writing: it is inhuman and thing-like; it destroys memory; it
creates an unresponsive text; it is passive (79). Ong also points out “the deadness of the text, its removal
from the living human lifeworld, its rigid visual fixity,” though this “assures its endurance and its
potential for being resurrected into limitless living contexts by a potentially infinite number of living
readers” (81). In comparison with spoken words, writing entails “the reduction of dynamic sound to
quiescent space, the separation of the word from living present” (82). Moreover, the writer of a text is
alone and writing is “a solipsistic operation” (101), but it “makes possible the great introspective
religious traditions such as Buddhism, Judaism, Christianity, and Islam” and all of which have “sacred
texts” (105). These characteristics of writing illuminate various aspects of Urizen as a writer and his
writings.</p>
            <p>Before he is attacked by Fuzon’s “sounding beam” (pl. 3:27), Urizen had been “shrunk
away / From Eternals”:
<q>
. . . he sat on a rock<lb/>
Barren; a rock which himself<lb/>
From redounding fancies had petrified . . .<lb/>
Soon shot the pained root<lb/>
<pb id="p34-50" n="50"/>
Of Mystery under his heel:<lb/>
It grew a thick tree; he wrote<lb/>
In silence his book of iron:<lb/>
(pl. 4:56-64)
</q></p>
            <p>What is suggestive here is the simultaneity of the growing of the mystery tree with Urizen’s
writing of the book of iron, as well as his association with the rock. Almost all the critics of this work
identify Urizen with Jehovah, and Fuzon with Moses, or Christ; other suggestions have been Satan, St.
Sebastian and Robespierre. His role in <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> certainly has apparent allusions to the last
four books of the Pentateuch, and to the Atonement. But Urizen is absorbed in the production of religious
texts which are essentially concerned with mystery. Moreover, the rapid enlargement of the Tree of Mystery
clearly means that its leaves are multiplying, and there is a possible punning allusion to the multiplying
leaves of Urizen’s book, which suggests that his role as a writer will lead to his becoming a despot,
increasing in power and isolation as the tree increases.</p>
            <p>The tree developing into a forest is seen as symbolizing several things: “the network of
Church-and-State religion” (Paley 32); “the restrictions he placed on intellectual freedom” (Lindsay
145); “the establishment of the priesthood of the Levites” (Tannenbaum 233); “the psychic origin of
Urizen’s repressive institutions” (Webster 171); “Urizenic state religion” (Mee 102). These
interpretations of the Tree of Mystery enable us to see in it one of the attributes of writing which has been
distinguished by Ong: its tendency to encourage the establishment and perpetuation of rigid and fixed
“sacred texts,” through the medium of priestcraft or of institutions like churches of state religion, even
though the original code might have taken shape in the immediacy of care and love.</p>
            <p>In this sense, the book of iron is the Bible of Heaven, and as he writes it, Urizen is
“compassed round / And high roofed over with trees” (pl. 4:69-70); he is incapable of seeing through the
world of appearances, though possessing the power to demand sacrifice and subjection. The rock, the thick tree
and the book of iron, which are associated with the earth and resistant to change, are his instruments for the
enforcement of his written law and for the infliction of cruel punishment, creating “An endless labyrinth of
woe” (pl. 5:4). He represents the established power, the guardian and promoter of “the deadness of the
text”. He can also be said to be an embodiment, after his own fashion, of Saussure’s langue, the
constructed structure of the social code, which is developed and made durable by “the collective
intelligence” (Saussure 71a), so widely different from the individual wills which are responsible for
parole; in Urizen’s case, of course, the difference has become extreme, and the code a tyranny.</p>
            <p>As stated in my introduction, Jon Mee draws our attention to “an antithesis between written
and oral forms” when referring to Urizen, who is “associated with the process of transcription and the
written law”; he also suggests that “One obvious implication of these metal books is the inflexibility of
the political and psychological order Urizen sponsors,” while the “struggle against the iron authority of
Urizen’s written laws is often figured in terms of orality” (103). Mee cites as examples Orc in 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> and Los in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los.</hi>
My argument is that in <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, orality is represented by the heroine, though her
voice occasions no hint of change on the part of Urizen, who embodies the system of langue; her speech fails
to receive its “collective approval.”</p>
            <p>Another common factor shared by interpretations of <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> is the assumption
that Fuzon is the hero of the poem, as a rebellious spirit. His revolt against his father, and consequent
crucifixion, presented in the first two chapters, have obvious biblical associations, recognized, as noted
above, by most critics.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">5</ref> Paley,
however, sees Fuzon rather differently: “Fuzon as the Energy principle, the element of fire, is the force
within man that will redeem him from the bondage of Urizen’s repressing law” (28). Webster and Cox
construe Fuzon as representing impulse or passion. His “beautiful visage, his tresses,/ That gave light to
the morning of heaven” (pl. 4:41-42) are just what Ahania once enjoyed admiring in Urizen. 
<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Tannenbaum, for example, suggests that “Fuzon-Moses represents the passion for
justice, the spirit of righteousness that quickly extends its vitality as it takes the form of doctrines,
laws, and codes of living” (226-27).</note></p>
            <p>When Fuzon attacks Urizen in chapter 1, he already sees his father as “this Demon of
smoke,” spreading the deceiving vapor of a joyless religion, and demanding worship. Fuzon calls him:
<q>
. . . this abstract non-entity<lb/>
This cloudy God seated on waters<lb/>
Now seen, now obscur’d; King of sorrow (?)<lb/>
(pl. 3:11-13)
</q></p>
            <p>Fuzon refuses to worship him, and “in a fiery flame” of wrath throws “The howling
Globe” which lengthens into “a hungry beam” (pl. 3:18-19). His beam of desire is encountered by
Urizen’s disk of abstract geometry, which constitutes the shield of reason. Fuzon’s attempt at parricide
undeniably entails a sexual assault, “The cold loins of Urizen dividing” (pl. 3:29) and this is clear also
from Urizen’s reaction: “Dire shriekd his invisible Lust” (30). The result is that Ahania is divided
from Urizen, who casts her away; as Bloom says, “Urizen rejects his sexuality, and dismisses his female
counterpart as Sin” (177). Webster suggests that “Urizen’s opposing shield, forged in “mills” of
logic, functions, like the curtains in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, to distance dangerous impulses by denying
both hungry sexuality and aggression” (169).</p>
            <pb id="p34-51" n="51"/>
            <p>It is clear, I think, that Fuzon is the projection of Urizen’s sexual and rebellious
impulses. In chapter 2, the parent’s retaliation starts, which is the beginning of the process by which
Urizen endeavors to repress his eros. The detailed procedures by which he prepares his weapon are significant:
his bow is the “Bow of the clouds of secresy” (pl. 4:26) and his arrow is a “poisoned rock” (24); the
son is struck down and killed by the rock. The development of Urizen’s character in chapter 3 reveals that
it is “the rock of the Law,” which serves “as a negation of an arrow of desire” (Bloom 179). Lindsay
also offers an interpretation of this assault, suggesting that “the spirit of rebellion is struck down by
the moral law” (145). It is not difficult to see why Urizen’s nailing of his son’s corpse to the Tree of
Mystery is seen by many critics as an unmistakable parody of the Atonement, but it is more difficult to be
sure, even approximately, of the significance of Fuzon’s declaration in chapter 2 “I am God. said he, the
eldest of things!” (pl. 4:38) To one critic, it suggests that “the rebel has become the tyrant”
(Tannenbaum 226); to another that “By proclaiming his omnipotence, Fuzon breathes new life into the Urizenic
system” (Mee 194).</p>
            <p>It is possible to suggest an explanation, in terms of the linguistic analogy, of Fuzon’s
boastful claim, and I will attempt this after a further brief discussion of the part he plays in 
<hi rend="i">Ahania.</hi> It would be reasonable to expect to find some illumination of his second speech in
chapter 4, but it is the most enigmatic of the five chapters. It could conceivably be a continuation of the
atonement of Fuzon, or a stage in Urizen’s own gradual degradation, or in his ossification of the fluid lava
of life and energy. Lindsay is, as far as I know, the only critic who makes any extensive comment on this
chapter: he says of the “white Lake” (pl. 5:14), “By his withdrawal from eternal liberty into the
futilities of abstract thought, Urizen transmuted his active powers into inertia and chill frustration”
(146); with regard to Fuzon’s body, he comments that it is displayed as “an advertisement for
suffering,” and believes it is meant to suggest that “the first inventing of religion confined humanity
within the physical body, so this consolidation of clerical privilege reduces man to a still more earth-bound
existence and further hardens the bony prison of his brain” (146). The second consequence of Urizenic rule,
which Lindsay mentions here, is of course an allusion to chapter 4, verse 8.</p>
            <p>Lindsay’s explication, though a little schematic, offers an interesting summary of the power
struggle with which the poem is concerned: “the rational intellect is by the destructive violence of its own
offspring wrenched apart from intellectual joy” (144). His exegesis suggests that as Urizen represents
repressive reason and law, Ahania represents intellectual pleasure and Fuzon passion and lust; reason is
destined to negate every emotional, sexual or mental joy and fulfilment. More might be said about Ahania, but
it seems clear that Fuzon does indeed represent a vehement assertion of the claims of unashamed sexual
impulse: his castration of his father is an instinctive attack on passionless and repressed sexual activity:
the “cold loins” of Urizen and his “invisible Lust.” It seems reasonable to conclude that Urizen’s
elimination of his son and his female counterpart and his attempt to perpetuate his logocentric rule signify a
victory of reason over eros and pathos.</p>
            <p>It is clear that a situation of this kind can arise with respect to the need to find an
appropriate language, which may exist in any single human being, or in any community. Writing, speech, and the
nascent language impulses which arise from the need to claim fulfilment for sexual impulse, can become
involved in a three-sided struggle, each urge to self-expression trying to assert its own primacy over the
others, but not in the hope of winning interactive responses. Hostility or rejection may continue, in so far
as difference and the existence of other functions are denied. The lava of meanings, or the signified, latent
in the internal world of sexuality and emotion, and in contacts with the external world, is struggling to
achieve entrance into the solid universe of language, and could bring about an alteration in its system if it
could do so. But a writing culture, too reliant on unchangeable texts, cannot accommodate this direct
assertion of eros, and orality or parole cries in vain for the moments of interaction with the literacy or
langue, and for assimilation into it.</p>
            <p>Fuzon’s ominous second speech is explicable, if he represents both impatient sexual passion,
demanding its right to reject repression and hypocritical control, and nascent language impulse, determined to
challenge tyrannical control by the langue. When he makes his attempt at assassination, he is renouncing his
legitimate means of promotion through the parole, in which he was already beginning to be at home, as his
first speech shows. In attempting to obtain forced entrance to the langue, by violent assault, he deprives
himself of the support of parole, and of the vestigial chance that he might change the langue by right of
kinship and by traditional non-destructive modifications. So it is understandable that as to his attack, his
confidence should contract into hollow swagger, and his command of speech should be equal only to a crude
adolescent assertion of supremacy, which reveals that his rebellion was self-defeating: this was not the way
to deal with Urizen.</p>
            <p>Thus the three characters, Urizen, Ahania and Fuzon could be said to have become isolated in
their separate spheres, unable to influence each other constructively because all normal interaction has been
halted. Emotion welling up to become language has to encounter negation by the accumulated knowledge of the
written. This has repressed the challenge and entreaty of speech, which would ordinarily be the means of
shaping nascent language impulses, and providing their means of gaining access in the language. The following
diagram shows what each of the characters represents.
<pb id="p34-52" n="52"/>
<figure n="AttributesTable.34.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="252"/>
If there is no normal interaction, the three forms of language activity remain closed off from each other, as
in the diagram. My second diagram shows a normal interaction operating without rejection and hostility.
<figure n="NascentSpeech.34.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="113"/><list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1 Nascent speech impulses welling up to become language</p></item>
	<item><p>2 Innovations seeking collective approval</p></item>
	<item><p>3 Acceptance for general use Materials to create speech</p></item>
	<item><p>4 Encouragement to become articulate</p></item>
</list></p>
            <p>The last seven lines of Ahania’s speech effectively convey the stagnant state of language
which ensues, when the reciprocal interchange is arrested:
<q>
Cruel jealousy! selfish fear!<lb/>
Self-destroying: how can delight,<lb/>
Renew in these chains of darkness<lb/>
Where bones of beasts are strown<lb/>
On the bleak and snowy mountains<lb/>
Where bones from the birth are buried<lb/>
Before they see the light.<lb/>
(pl. 6:41-47)
</q></p>
            <p>The “bones of beasts” suggest the refuse or carcasses of words which have failed to become
langue, and the last four lines indicate that language is at an impasse, where sexual energy and love are
denied their right to be born either as langue or parole: this is the work of Urizen, the writer of the iron
books, who is trying to create a universe of death, and to abstract everything from “the all-creative
Imagination” (Tannenbaum 248). Bloom states that in <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> “Few images, even in Blake,
are grimmer than that final <corr type="emend">vision</corr> of infanticide” (180). It is also true to say with Lindsay that “this is
the most negative of Blake’s major poems since <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>” (144), for if its linguistic
implications are accepted, there is little sign of a positive intercourse. But it must be remembered that this
is Ahania’s comment on the situations not necessarily Blake’s last word.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>III</title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake’s designs for <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> do much to clarify the meaning of the text,
especially as regards the linguistic function of Ahania and Urizen, and will next be examined. Then with
reference to Jerome J. McGann’s idea of an indeterminate text, I would like to consider the significance of
Los in this work, and finally to deduce Blake’s view of written texts and printing in relation to oral
culture. My investigation of these questions will be concerned with reading <hi rend="i">The Book of
Ahania</hi> as a metatext, relevant to Blake’s method of book production.</p>
            <p>It is a distinctive visual feature of the three Urizen books that they “mostly mimic the
layout of the Authorized Version, double columns divided into chapter and verse” (Mee 162). But the two
memorable images of Ahania on the frontispiece and on the titlepage respectively reinforce the theme of
language and text. The first shows her in an attitude of protest and supplication, as she is “about to be
“siez’d on his [Urizen’s] mountains of Jealousy” after the castration of Urizen’s “cold loins”
by his son Fuzon” (Worrall 160). This Ahania strongly contrasts with the figure on the titlepage, who is
depicted as “still flying but (the direction of her hair tells us) descending obliquely” (Worrall 161),
with a worried expression on her face. These two contrary states of Ahania, one earthbound and the other free
from the ground, correspond well with those conveyed in the text. The figure on the titlepage illustrates the
role of oral speech or “winged words,” and her pathetic facial expression emphasizes her suffering under
“the iron authority of Urizen’s written laws” (Mee 104), which means either that parole is denied entry
into langue, forced to keep circling around aimlessly, or that liberated speech is repulsed by oppressive
writing (Mee 104). The Ahania of the frontispiece, who is the character in chapter 5 before her final
expulsion, suggests that orality is being deprived of the opportunity to express love and care. It also
illustrates the rigid control exercised by Urizen or the written language, shut up in its own sphere. As for
the design on the last plate, it has been generally agreed that it “depicts severed heads and mangled limbs,
leavings of the guillotine” (Paley 33), but in terms of the linguistic interpretation I am suggesting, it
may depict the body of Fuzon finally murdered, the wreckage of the pre-literal state of eros or energy
demanding to be a component of language, but savagely broken into pieces by the drive towards fixed written
texts which result from exclusive and empirical thinking.</p>
            <p>The coordination between text and designs vindicates my belief that Blake is describing in 
<hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> a language situation in which pre-language chaos and oral speech are forcibly
<pb id="p34-53" n="53"/>
suppressed by the written; if nothing is done, this situation is going to bring about the prohibition of
freedom of expression at a political level, as well as in artistic creation, and the negation of free love and
sex. But Blake seems to imply, while symbolizing this state of linguistic turmoil, that his own composite art
offers a solution, and in order to discuss this possibility it is necessary to consider the concept of an
indeterminate text proposed by McGann and Mee.</p>
            <p>McGann regards <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> as Blake’s indeterminate text, claiming
that Dr. Alexander Geddes’s work showed Blake “not only that many texts of the Bible of Heaven existed,
but also that those texts exhibited lacunae and redundancies within and between themselves” (323). He
believes that Blake’s reading of Geddes encouraged him to rewrite the Bible by interpolating material into
his version which seems incongruous with the surrounding text. But although there are two passages in 
<hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> which unexpectedly introduce Los and could be said to resemble interpolations, there is
no evidence that they are insertions. Los first appears in chapter 1, verse 9, retrieving “the fiery beam of
Fuzon”; he “siezd it and beat it in a mass / With the body of the sun.” In chapter 4, verse 5 he appears
again, in lines which refer to his exertions in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> chapter 4, when this demon was
beginning the process of acquiring a semblance of the human form, and Los was laboring to fetter him into this
shape. We are told, this time, that having “forg’d nets of iron around,” Los “threw them around the
bones.” These fragmentary descriptions of Los’s characteristic task of beating and forging, which
represents Blake’s idea of imaginative creation, are a reminder of what he was trying to do himself. The
passages in question are not really out of place: the first shows Los conserving the passion of anger and
sexual aggression and amalgamating it with the sun, and the second shows him laboring to ensure that Urizen is
confined within an identifiable body: both are imaginative and resourceful actions. If his readers were
reminded of interpolations in the biblical text (as they might have been, in view of the fact, noted above,
that all three of the Urizen books mimic the lay-out of the Authorized Version), they could only have noted
the contrast between the pointless mystification caused by such a practice, in this text venerated by a
writing culture, and the effect of Blake’s own apparent digressions. Blake was repudiating the repetition of
identical words on printed pages and attempting to avoid producing texts which looked determinate and final:
his aim was to create new perspectives by an activity similar to parole.</p>
            <p>To believe that this is the case is to wish to consider Blake’s own illuminated printing. In
his comparative view of writing, manuscript, and print, Ong states “typographic control typically impresses
more by its tidiness and inevitability: the lines perfectly regular, all justified on the right side,
everything coming out even visually,” and that the print is “an insistent world of cold, non-human,
facts” (122); on the other hand, manuscript culture, he argues, preserves “a feeling for a book as a kind
of utterance, an occurrence in the course of conversation, rather than as an object” (125). Moreover print
“encourages a sense of closure, a sense that what is found in a text has been finalized, has reached a state
of completion,” and “encloses thought in thousands of copies of a work of exactly the same visual and
physical consistency” (132). The most important point of difference is that the “printed text is supposed
to represent the words of an author in definitive or ‘final’ form,” while manuscripts “were in
dialogue with the world outside their own borders. They remained closer to the give-and-take of oral
expression” (132).</p>
            <p>The closeness of Blake’s manuscripts to oral expression is pointed out by Mee in a similar
vein:
<q>
Blake operates with a notion of writing as containing both positive and negative potentialities. He seeks a
writing that retains the fluidity of the voice; that seeks the status of “poetic tales” rather than
“forms of worship”....Blake sought to achieve a means of literary production that was fluid and operated
against the notion of the single authoritative Word .... (105-06)
</q></p>
            <p>In other words, Blake is trying to avert the fixation or standardization of his books, and to
keep the fiery vitality, passion and freedom of the living voice, which has its source in the individual will.
Metaphorically speaking, Blake aims to maintain Ahania’s orality as far as possible and to assimilate
Fuzon’s violent impulses. In a sense, Blake’s artistic creation has a recurring nature, which does not
proceed from repeating the same dull round, but from eternally recreating the prime eros and pathos. The fact
that the germ of all change is first found in speaking has already been discussed in this essay, but speech,
through the activity of various individuals, seeks to constitute literate culture, by continually modifying
the established system. The production of his etched plates means that Blake was trying to open up a new
perspective on the world by situating the plates at the point of intersection of orality and literacy, so that
they maintain the fluid reciprocity between parole and langue, which is to lead to a change and renewal of
language.</p>
            <p>Blake’s other attempt to avoid the inflexibility of a written text is his “double printing
method” (Mee 106): his books were etched on copper plates and then printed on paper, which “allowed him to
insert differences at each stage of production. Changes were always available to Blake in transcribing
copy-text to plate and in the process of <corr type="emend">transferring</corr> plate to paper.... His books always went beyond the state
of Urizen’s books of metals, that is, the copper-plate, and each of the final states varied one from the
other so none could claim the status of scriptural authority” (Mee 106). This constant flight from
establishing one single final version of his text helps to establish, as far as possible, an impression of
indeterminacy, as I have said. His creative principle is to
<pb id="p34-54" n="54"/>
attain a mutual infiltration of parole and langue and consequent linguistic activation, thus resisting
political, religious and intellectual oppression, or sterility and obscurantism.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> provides an example of the state of linguistic activity
under the autocratic reign of the written; the voice of change is suppressed. As I suggested at the beginning
of this article, Blake was drawing attention to his own view of printing and the printed text; he was, in
addition, criticizing the contribution made to a dangerous situation by automatic deference to the biblical
text. He believed that the danger could be counteracted: to read Blake’s illuminated books is to be well
aware not only of his unique “printing” method but of his metatextual concept of writing. Behrendt states
that the “reading activity Blake advocates is one of dismantling, of uncovering, of removing the semantic
and intellectual garments and displaying the pristine, naked eternal truth that is everywhere the primary
<corr type="emend">objective</corr> of his art” and the reading “must be a subversive activity whose processes are corrosive to the
authority both of text and of the acts and principles embodied in that text” (127). As Blake’s corrosive
acid removes surfaces and allows the truth to stand out, his texts, with the convergence of the oral and the
written, make us question the validity of the language situation of our own time and our methods of linguistic
expression and communication, so much controlled by institutional customs, rules and prejudices. They
demonstrate a way of achieving freedom from coercion, discrimination and suppression in almost every human
activity and society, by their endless effort to flee from finalization.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. <hi rend="i">Reading William Blake.</hi> London: Macmillan, 1992.</p>
              <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic Argument.</hi> London:
Victor Gollancz, 1963.</p>
              <p>Cox, Stephen. <hi rend="i">Love and Logic: The Evolution of Blake’s Thought.</hi> Ann
Arbor: U of Michigan P, 1992.</p>
              <p>Esterhammer, Angela. <hi rend="i">Creating States: Studies in the Performative Language of
John Milton and William Blake.</hi> Toronto, Buffalo and London: U of Toronto P, 1994.</p>
              <p>Holdcroft, David. <hi rend="i">Saussure: Signs, System, and Arbitrariness.</hi> Cambridge:
Cambridge UP, 1991.</p>
              <p>Komatsu, Eisuke and Roy Harris, ed.and transl. <hi rend="i">Saussure’s Third Course of
Lectures on General Linguistics (1910-1911).</hi> Oxford, New York, Seoul and Tokyo: Pergamon P, 1993.</p>
              <p>Lindsay, David W. “<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>: An Interpretation of the Text.”
<hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> 68 (1976): 144-47.</p>
              <p>McGann, Jerome J. “The Idea of an Indeterminate Text: Blake’s Bible of Hell and Dr.
Alexander Geddes.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 25 (1988): 303-24.</p>
              <p>McNay, Lois. <hi rend="i">Foucault and Feminism.</hi> Cambridge: Polity Press, 1992. Rep.
1994.</p>
              <p>Mee, Jon. <hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm: William Blake and the Culture of Radicalism in
the 1790s.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1992.</p>
              <p>Mellor, Anne K. <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Gender.</hi> New York and London: Routledge,
1993.</p>
              <p>Ong, Walter J. <hi rend="i">Orality and Literacy: The Technologizing of the Word.</hi> New
York and London: Routledge, 1988.</p>
              <p>Paley, Morton D. “Method and Meaning in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of Ahania.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public Library</hi> lxx (1966): 27-33.</p>
              <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies: The Great
Code of Art.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1982.</p>
              <p>Webster, Brenda S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology.</hi> Athens: U of Georgia P,
1969.</p>
              <p>Worrall, David, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Urizen Books.</hi> London: The William
Blake Trust/The Tate Gallery, 1995.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
