<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>34.3.diamond</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">John Diamond, The Healing Power of Blake</title>
        <author n="Neill">Patricia Neill</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2000/01</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2000/01</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">34.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editors</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Agnes Peter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2001"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_34">
    <body>
      <pb id="p34-95" n="95"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-34-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
		<head>
          <title type="main">THE HEALING POWER OF BLAKE: A Distillation, edited and with an introduction by
John Diamond, M.D.</title>
        </head>
        <p>John Diamond. <hi rend="i">The Healing Power of Blake.</hi> Bloomingdale, IL: Creativity
Publishing, 1998. $14.95. The author of this charming little book is a medical doctor. Dr. Diamond, rather
than relying on the current medical model of treating the disease rather than the patient, prefers to
concentrate “on the positive—the sufferer’s innate healing power, his spirit, his life Energy.” In
other words, Diamond posits that poetry has a therapeutic power to actuate a person’s own ability to heal:
“All creativity has the power to raise the Life Energy, the healing power within, the <hi rend="i">vis
medicatrix naturae</hi> of Hippocrates. And poetry is no exception, in fact its ability is second only to that
of music—and when it is sung it is, of course, the equal.” As he says in the Introduction, he finds the
poems of Blake to “have the greatest Healing Power.”</p>
        <p>The book is a compendium of extracts from Blake’s works, the prophetic books for the most part.
And, as such, may not be of much interest to Blake scholars. However, the book might find its way into the
hands of other types of readers, such as those folks interested in alternative forms of medicine.</p>
        <p>I can say that the book did nothing for the raging migraine I had, or for my back, when I pulled
some muscles. But it did have a nice effect during a recent head cold, when I mellowed out with some ginger
tea and <hi rend="i">The Healing Power of Blake.</hi> Also, if I put the book on my head, my posture
straightens up quite nicely. For $14.95, that’s not a bad deal.</p>
        <byline>—<docAuthor>Patricia <name>Neill</name></docAuthor></byline>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
