<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>34.3.ferber</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s “Jerusalem” as a Hymn</title>
        <author n="Ferber">Michael Ferber</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2000/01</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2000/01</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">34.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editors</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Agnes Peter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2001"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_34">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-34-3-0006">
        <pb id="p34-82" n="82"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s “Jerusalem” as a Hymn</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Michael <name>Ferber</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Blake’s poem “And did those feet,” given the title “Jerusalem” since its setting in
1916 by Hubert Parry, is Blake’s best known work, except perhaps for “The Tyger.” The “second national
anthem” of England and Wales, a staple of English hymnals and public schools, the last song of the Last
Night of the Proms, it has been sung with equal fervor by suffragettes, Fabians, high-church Tories,
Presbyterian missionaries, and American leftists. Having heard it and sung it many times myself and come to
love it, I have grown interested in how it came to be written and what groups or causes adopted it—its
“reception history”—as well as how it works as a song. The two standard biographies of Parry give the
main facts about its inception and early performances, though there is more one would like to know.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>I have not found any extended discussion of it
as a setting, and hence an interpretation, of Blake’s text.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Nor have I found much concerning its later history in Britain or America. In
this essay, then, I will present what is generally known about its origins and history and discuss it as a
hymn. Some of what follows will be sketchy, but I hope it will at least provoke others, especially those with
better access to British libraries, to fill in the gaps around this wonderful song. 
<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Charles L. Graves, <hi rend="i">Hubert Parry: His Life and Works</hi>, 2 vols. (London:
Macmillan, 1926); Jeremy Dibble, <hi rend="i">C. Hubert H. Parry: His Life and Music</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon,
1992). I would like to thank Jeremy Brecher, Richard Flacks, David Fuller, Susan Reilly, Judith Sizer, and
Phillip Zaeder for helpful tips.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> A recent article by Samuel J. Rogal, “Blake’s ‘And did those feet’
as Congregational Hymn,” in <hi rend="i">The Hymn: A Journal of Congregational Song</hi> 44:3 (July 1993):
22-25, is disappointing, indeed maddening. It confidently asserts that the “feet” of the first line belong
to the Druids (per Stukeley), it thinks it important to track the chariot back to Gray and Milton, and is
generally at a loss regarding the text. Worse is a peculiar suggestion that Parry’s “hymn tune known today
as <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” existed independently of the text: “Blake’s ‘And did those feet in
ancient time,’ set to the Parry tune <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> . . .”; “Parry’s choral song,
‘Jerusalem,’ accompanying Blake’s ‘And did those feet in ancient time’ . . .,” as if Parry had the
tune lying around in his notebook and then found that it suited Blake’s verses. Rogal may have been misled
by the existence of new lyrics to the Parry setting in certain unforgivable hymnals, such as <hi rend="i">A
New Hymnal for Colleges and Schools</hi>, ed. <corr type="emend">Jeffery Rowthorn</corr> and Russell Schulz-Widmar (New Haven: Yale UP,
1992), where the “music” to hymn 567 is “Jerusalem” by Parry but the words begin: “O day of peace
that dimly shines / through all our hopes and prayers and dreams, / guide us to justice, truth, and love, /
delivered from our selfish schemes.”</note></p>
          <p>“Jerusalem,” of course, is not Blake’s name for it, nor is it part of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem/The Emanation of The Giant Albion.</hi> The four-quatrain poem appears untitled at the end
of the prose “Preface” to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (E 95-96).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Taken out of that immediate context, the poem’s opening is a bit
mysterious—“And did those feet in ancient time, / Walk upon Englands mountains green”—for we can only
infer whose feet “those feet” are when we are given the next two lines—“And was the holy Lamb of God,
/ On Englands pleasant pastures seen!”—and invoke the biblical stylistic principle of parallel members,
whereby two or three successive verses are variants of the same general meaning. In the prose context there is
a clear suggestion, though it is hardly obvious, that those are indeed Jesus’s feet, for the last words
before the poem are “in Jesus our Lord,” while “Christ &amp; his Apostles” have been named a sentence
earlier. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The “Preface” (E pl. 1) is lacking in copies C and D, probably
the last two of the four extant copies of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Though <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is dated
“1804” on the title page, the paper of the two copies with the “Preface” (A and B) is watermarked
1808. See Erdman’s note, E 806.</note></p>
          <p>On hearing the song for the first time, I imagine, many people must have asked “Whose feet?”
as well as “Why <hi rend="i">feet</hi>?” (I remember feeling similarly puzzled over the opening of the
second stanza of “America the Beautiful”—“O beautiful for pilgrim feet”—and wondered “Why
feet?”) Blake took from the Bible and John Bunyan an interest in feet and their symbolism, which has to do
with our pilgrimage through this world, our “walk” or way of life, our stance before life’s dangers and
temptations, and what Bunyan in <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> calls our “conversation” or
conduct.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>A passage from Isaiah may well
lie behind Blake’s lines (and perhaps Katharine Lee Bates’s line in “America the Beautiful”): “How
beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace” (52.7);
the great bringer of good tidings is of course Jesus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref> Feet, moreover, or at least one foot, and sandals, or at least one sandal, are central
symbols at turning points of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, if we may widen the context for a moment.
“Then Los took off his left sandal placing it on his head, / Signal of solemn mourning” 
<hi rend="i">M</hi> 8.11-12); Milton “on my left foot falling on the tarsus, enterd there; / But from my left
foot a black cloud redounding spread over Europe” (15.49-50); “Milton labourd with his journey, &amp; his
feet bled sore / Upon the clay now changed to marble” (19.3-4), but with red clay he builds Urizen,
“Beginning at the feet” (19.12). <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> When Apollyon wounds Christian in head,
hand, and foot, Bunyan adds a note explaining that he means “understanding, faith, and
conversation.”</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> As noted in an article by the editors of <hi rend="i">The Explicator</hi> 1
(March 1943): no. 38. See Nancy M. Goslee, “‘In Englands green &amp; pleasant Land’: The Building of
Vision in Blake’s Stanzas from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,” <hi rend="i">SiR</hi> 13 (1974): 105-25 (108).
The Isaiah passage is quoted by Paul in Romans 10.15.</note></p>
          <p>In the “Preface” Blake argues that Greek and Roman literature was stolen and perverted from
the Bible, and set up against the Bible, which is the “more ancient” and inspired work. He calls on the
“Young Men of the New Age” to combat
<pb id="p34-83" n="83"/>
the “Hirelings in the Camp, the Court &amp; the University,” who have promoted these thefts and
perversions, the worst of which is the reduction of “Mental” war to “Corporeal” war, brought about by
“the silly Greek &amp; Latin slaves of the Sword”—not only Achilles and Aeneas, of course, but also
their inventors Homer and Virgil, who were hirelings of kings and emperors. The young men are to fight back
with their “foreheads,” not corporeal weapons.</p>
          <p>The poem neatly echoes and amplifies these two points. In the first half the ancientness and
priority of the Bible corresponds to the visit of Jesus to England and the building of Jerusalem there,
presumably before the Roman conquest, while the theme of the second half is “Mental Fight,” where the list
of spiritual weapons culminates in the sword of line 14, which replies to the corporeal Greek or Latin sword
that concludes the first paragraph of the prose “Preface.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">6</ref> As Parry rightly shows in making his melody repeat only once, covering two
stanzas each time, the poem divides satisfyingly into two equal parts. The first half is a series of four
two-line questions each beginning with “And” while the second half is the resolute response. The latter
falls into two parts as well, first a command (as if to a squire or valet) to bring the armor and then a vow
to fight until Jerusalem is built, or rebuilt, in England. Each half concludes with the building of Jerusalem,
while their two locales are set in contrast, the “Satanic Mills” of here and now as opposed to the
“green &amp; pleasant Land” of the future. <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For a discussion of the
importance of spiritual warfare throughout Blake’s work, see Michael Ferber, “Blake and the Two Swords,”
in Steve Clark and David Worrall, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake in the Nineties</hi> (London: Macmillan and New
York: St. Martin’s, 1999). Goslee connects the spiritual weapons to “the Petrarchan or Ovidian convention
of love as warfare” (114), but this is to narrow the meaning of “desire” to the erotic. The primary
source is Ephesians 6.11-17.</note></p>
          <p>It is tempting to take the four questions of the first half as “rhetorical,” as Nancy Goslee
does in the only substantial article on the poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> Blake certainly makes extensive use of such questions throughout his work. I think,
however, that these are not rhetorical in the usual sense, as questions implying obvious answers, as here
those answers would be in the negative, and so they would “begin to call into doubt the validity of that
vision,” as Goslee argues, and generate bitter ironies that I believe are not in the poem. It is better to
take them as genuine expressions of amazement at the good tidings—<corr type="emend">“Can</corr> it be
true?” or “Was it really so?”—as exclamations as much as questions. They are what Mastronarde calls
“apistetic” questions, questions expressing disbelief or shock.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">8</ref> Though it is never safe to rely on Blake’s quirky punctuation, it is worth
noting that Blake does not end the first two couplets with a question mark; the second ends in an exclamation
point. These lines are the same exclamations of wonder, and over the same tidings, as those that begin the
dedication to Chapter Two of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: “Jerusalem the Emanation of the Giant Albion! Can
it be? Is it a Truth that the Learned have explored? Was Britain the Primitive Seat of the Patriarchal
Religion?” (E 171). <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Goslee 107, 111. She does not discuss the poem as a
hymn.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Donald J. Mastronarde, <hi rend="i">Contact and Discontinuity: Some
Conventions of Speech and Action on the Greek Tragic Stage</hi> (Berkeley: U of California P, 1979) 12.
Mastronarde distinguishes 10 sorts of “rhetorical questions,” of which “apistetic” is one.</note></p>
          <p>From the first to the second stanza the description of England darkens from “mountains green”
and “pleasant pastures” to “clouded hills” and “dark Satanic Mills.” On Goslee’s reading this
shift deepens the doubts and ironies. But surely its function is to dramatize the amazement of the speaker.
The locale shifts subtly from “Englands mountains green” and “Englands pleasant pastures” to “our
clouded hills” and “here, / Among these dark Satanic Mills,” almost as if we are not now living in
England and will not do so again until we have rebuilt Jerusalem “In Englands green &amp; pleasant Land.”
The speaker seems to leave the England of ancient time and slide, by means of deictic terms (“our,”
“here,” “these”) into the England of the present: How astonishing to think Jerusalem could be here,
and now! At a stretch one could take the last question as strictly rhetorical, for a “No” would be a
logically appropriate answer, there having been no Satanic Mills in that ancient time, yet as an expression of
astonishment it still makes good dramatic and psychological sense. And to end on the Mills, however
illogically, serves also to supply the motive for all the weaponry that follows, as opposed to the hammers and
trowels that would be called for if the only mission were building, for surely the Mills must first be
destroyed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> As Mary Lynn Johnson and John E. Grant point out in a note in their
edition, Nehemiah 4 reports that during the rebuilding of Jerusalem half the people stood guard with weapons
while the other half worked. In 4:17 we are told that each of the builders “with one of his hands wrought in
the work, and with the other hand held a weapon.” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and Designs</hi> (New York:
Norton, 1979) 238. In the end, for Blake, spiritual weapons are constructive tools.
                            <p>As commonly sung today, even by trained choirs, “these dark Satanic Mills”
is altered to “those dark Satanic Mills,” as if the shift to “these” is too visionary or threatening.
It is “those” in the recordings by the Choir of Winchester Cathedral and the Choir of St. George’s
Chapel, listed here at the end; it is “those” in <hi rend="i">Hymns for Church and School</hi>, which is
the fourth edition of <hi rend="i">The Public School Hymn Book</hi> (Henley-on-Thames: Gresham Books, 1964),
but “these” in the <hi rend="i">Church Hymnary</hi> (Church of Scotland and Presbyterian Churches, 1927
and subsequent editions). Paul Robeson; Emerson, Lake &amp; Palmer; and Billy Bragg get it right on their
recordings.</p></note></p>
          <p>Parry’s manuscript and the first published version (by Curwen) indicate “solo” for the
first half and “all available voices” for the second.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> I have never heard it sung that way, but it is not a bad idea. The series of astonished
questions gains poignancy when voiced by one man,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> as if he is alone,
<pb id="p34-84" n="84"/>
cut off from the ancient spiritual community of England that he has just heard tell of. Indeed it is a basic
Blakean tenet that it is the very illusion of being alone, no longer a member of Albion’s body, no longer a
brother in loving contention with brother, that brings about the fall into this dark Satanic world, and that
the first step toward restoring the original community is to act in concert with one’s fellows in waging
spiritual war against all that divides them. With that realization, when the narrator calls for his weapons,
all available voices (300 at the first performance) join in. It is true that they sing “Bring me” rather
than “Bring us,” and one might momentarily note the absurdity of a host of knights all calling on their
squires, but then the words become a vow, a collective vow like the oath on the Rütli (painted by Fuseli) but
where each must swear in his own name and on his own sword. Then the pronoun shifts to “we” at the climax
of the hymn, where Parry wrote “allargando” (slowing down and increasing volume), leading to the highest
note of the hymn (high E) on “built,” over which Parry wrote “ff,” almost superfluously, one would
think, for if the chorus or congregation are following the words as well as the melody they irresistibly sing
these lines with full throat and heart. <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Dibble 484; first page of MS
reproduced, 505.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> It does not have to be a man, of course, but given that it is the
narrator and not a character speaking it, and that the narrator calls for sword, spear, and other normally
male accoutrements, however spiritual or metaphorical, I will use masculine pronouns.<p>In <hi rend="i">Parry
before</hi> Jerusalem (Aldershot: Ashgate, 1997), Bernard Benoliel says that “Parry intended the first
stanza of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to be sung by a solo female voice” (134), but the manuscript does not
specify the sex. No doubt at some women’s rights rallies it was sung that way.</p></note></p>
          <p>Building a city, after all, can only be a collective act. But these stanzas of demands and vows
are also a kind of prophecy: Jerusalem <hi rend="i">will</hi> be built in England, again, as it once was.
Blake, as we know, dismissed prophecy and prophets “in the modern sense of the word” in favor of what we
might call a conditional sense: “Thus / If you go on so / the result is So” (anno. Watson, E 617). So here
he may be saying, If we do not cease from mental fight (as I will not), the result is Jerusalem. It all
depends on us, and I am ready. This prophetic edge to what is literally a demand and an oath is implicit in
the poem alone, I think, but it is brought out by the quotation from Moses that Blake places immediately
following it: “Would to God that all the Lords people were Prophets.”</p>
          <p>The other phrase whose meaning is affected by the context of the poem is the famous “dark
Satanic Mills,” but here the case may be the opposite of that with “those feet.” For almost everyone
assumes it refers to the smoke-producing industrial mills that had begun to darken some of the northern cities
by 1804 though not yet Blake’s London. In fact Blake was not referring to modern factories, at least not
directly, but to (1) flour mills of the traditional sort, driven by water, wind, or animals, where they take
their place beside plow and harrow in the threefold division of agricultural labor in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Satan being the “Miller of Eternity” (3.42); and to (2) “the Starry Mills of
Satan” (4.2), the rotating nighttime heaven that stands for the tyranny of supposedly natural laws dreamed
up by Newton and Locke and imposed on mortals to whom “thy Mills seem everything” (4.12). In the prose
“Preface” we are warned about “the Camp, the Court &amp; the University” but not the factory. By
implication, nonetheless, industrial factories, if not steam factories, can be included under “Satanic
Mills” because they are complicated developments of the flour mills and they enslave workers the way Samson
was bound to the mill in Gaza<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> and
because they are the outcome of the doctrines of Newton and Locke now inculcated in the minds of the youth:
“I turn my eyes to the Schools &amp; Universities of Europe / And there behold the Loom of Locke whose Woof
rages dire / Washd by the Water-wheels of Newton. black the cloth / In heavy wreathes folds over every
Nation” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 15.14-17). The common assumption about the “Satanic Mills,” then, is not so
much mistaken as overly simple, but it gives a satisfying reading, and who is to say Blake would not have
endorsed it in 1916? <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>
(Princeton: Princeton UP, 1947) 290.</note></p>
          <p>Sir Charles Hubert Hastings Parry (1848-1918) was a prolific and much admired composer, held in
his day to rank with Purcell and Elgar. He was knighted in 1895 and appointed Professor of Music at Oxford in
1900. He wrote an immense number of choral settings, hymns, part-songs, unison songs (of which “Jerusalem”
is one), solo songs, canticles, and anthems, as well as five symphonies, a piano concerto, an opera, theatre
music, chamber music, and piano and organ solos.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> He set texts from the whole history of English poetry from Skelton to Robert Bridges,
including <hi rend="i">Scenes from Shelley’s “Prometheus Unbound”</hi> (1880) and his best-known piece
(after “Jerusalem”), <hi rend="i">At a Solemn Music: Blest Pair of Sirens</hi> (1887), a choral setting of
Milton’s poem. Among the romantic poets he set five poems by Shelley, one by Coleridge, four by Scott, two
by Byron, and two by Keats, but nothing else by Blake. Blake must nonetheless have been a part of Parry’s
literary culture, for one of his longtime friends was William Blake Richmond (1842-1921), an artist who was
steeped in Blake; he was the son of George Richmond, who admired Blake in his later years and was present at
his death.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> I am using the categories in Dibble, Appendix 2.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> George Richmond (1809-96) made one of the “Ancients” with his friends
Samuel Palmer, Edward Calvert, and Frederick Tatham; he married Tatham’s sister Julia; William was their
second son.</note></p>
          <p>The impulse to set Blake’s “And did those feet” came from Parry’s friend Robert Bridges,
then the Poet Laureate, whom he had known since their days together at Eton and Oxford. They had collaborated
on at least seven of Bridges’ own poems from 1895 to early 1916, and Parry set another later that year. For
his part Bridges had a deep interest in music, and had worked with Edward Elgar, Gustav Holst, and Charles
Villiers Stanford as well as with Parry. <hi rend="i">Eden</hi>, an oratorio 
                        <pb id="p34-85" n="85"/>
based on <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, was set by Stanford and dedicated to Parry.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> He was particularly devoted to hymns: he was a precentor of
a church choir for nine years, compiled a hymnal, and regularly spent Sunday evenings with his family singing
hymns around the piano. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> I am drawing mainly on Catherine Phillips, 
<hi rend="i">Robert Bridges: A Biography</hi> (Oxford: Oxford UP, 1992).</note></p>
          <p>Bridges knew Blake’s poetry, and some tenuous influences might be detected beneath the much
stronger impact of Milton, Shelley, Keats, and the classics. Albert Guerard plausibly suggests that his sonnet
“Democritus” (1919) echoes Blake’s “Mock on Mock on Voltaire Rousseau.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> One wonders about Bridges’s appreciation for Blake,
however, when one considers his “translation” of Blake’s early sonnet “To the Evening Star” into
four alcaic quatrains. Bridges had a lifelong interest in prosody, particularly classical prosody, and wrote
several essays on it; this translation is one of his many experiments. To expand a sonnet into alcaics demands
some padding, but there is something excessively bookish and fastidious in the circumlocutions that smother
Blake’s simple diction. Blake’s two adjectives for “dew,” for example, are decorative enough
(“silver” and “sacred”), but Bridges seems to regard “dew” itself as too vulgar for alcaics, so we
get “Silently dost thou with delicate shimmer / O’erbloom the frowning front of awful / Night to a glance
of unearthly silver,” whatever that means.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> It is hardly in Blake’s spirit. Still, we can pardon it for the brilliant idea to have
Parry translate “And did those feet” into a unison song, into “suitable, simple music,” as Bridges put
it, “that an audience could take up and join in.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Albert Guerard, <hi rend="i">Robert Bridges: A Study of Traditionalism in
Poetry</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard UP, 1942) 288. “Mock on Mock on” might have made an interesting
unison song had Bridges suggested it to Parry.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Evening: From Wm. Blake,” <hi rend="i">Poetical Works of Robert
Bridges</hi> (London: Oxford UP, 1936) 437. He has another alcaic translation of Blake (“To Morning”) in
his <hi rend="i">Demeter: A Mask</hi> 656-63 (71).</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Letter from Bridges quoted in Graves, 2: 92; Dibble 483. Bridges had long
disliked both the words and the tune of “God Save the King” and hoped Parry’s “Jerusalem” might
replace it, as it very nearly has. In April 1918 Bridges was asked to write new words for the second and third
stanzas of the national anthem; he did so, but they were rejected as “not simple enough” (Phillips
264).</note></p>
          <p>What cause at length moved Bridges to this unexampled deed? Alas, a campaign called “Fight for
Right,” founded by General Sir Francis Younghusband to counteract German propaganda, which he apparently
believed was a threat to the British war effort in 1916.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref> He or his organizers enlisted Bridges, who had been Laureate since 1913, and several
musicians, including Elgar and Parry’s former student Walford Davies, to help with a concert for a rally at
Queen’s Hall on 28 March 1916.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
Parry, a man of liberal political views, was no jingoist, and had doubts about “Fight for Right.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Perhaps he was visited in his dreams by
Blake, who reminded him that in nearly all his work, and in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> in particular, he had set
his forehead against corporeal war, that General Sir Francis was a hireling of the camp, that “Mental
Fight” is the opposite of artillery barrages, barbed wire, machine guns, and gas. Perhaps Blake prophesied
the Easter Rising in Erin’s green and pleasant land less than a month later, and warned against corporeal
retribution. Nonetheless Parry gave the hymn to Davies the day after he wrote it and it was performed at
Queen’s Hall under Davies’s direction with 300 voices from several London choirs. If Blake’s ghost
stalked the Hall that day so did William Morris’s, for Elgar presented a setting of a part of 
<hi rend="i">Sigurd the Volsung.</hi>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Francis Edward Younghusband (1863-1942) had a remarkable career as a
soldier and explorer in India, the Himalayas, Manchuria, and the Gobi Desert before retiring to England 1910.
He was also a devout Christian and a mystic who studied Hinduism and Buddhism. He wrote a dozen books of
travel, mysticism, and memoirs. His biographer gives half a page out of nearly 400 to the “Fight for
Right” society, and nowhere explains why Younghusband felt called upon to organize it. See George Seaver,
<hi rend="i">Francis Younghusband: Explorer and Mystic</hi> (London: Murray, 1952) 292.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Dibble 483. Sir Henry Walford Davies (1869-1941) studied composition with
Parry. After a career as a church organist he became an organizer of concerts for the troops; in 1918 he was
appointed musical director to the Royal Air Force. In 1934 he succeeded Elgar as Master of the King’s
Music.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> See Dibble 470-71 for an account of Parry’s opinion of Germany: he held
it to blame for the war, but confessed to have been a “pro-Teuton” for its music, philosophy, and
literature. Schumann, Wagner, and Brahms were major influences on his work.</note></p>
          <p>Parry’s “Jerusalem” was a rousing success, and Davies got it published right away. It
quickly caught on. The original version was scored for organ or piano accompaniment, but Parry soon
orchestrated it, and it was performed everywhere in Britain at concerts and rallies. (Elgar’s more elaborate
orchestration, first performed at the Leeds Festival of 1922, has displaced Parry’s version in nearly all
performances since then.) “Fight for Right” was happy with it, but Parry soon grew unhappy with “Fight
for Right,” and in May 1917 he wrote to Younghusband withdrawing his support for it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> He was delighted, however, that the women’s suffrage
movement took it up, and on 17 March 1917 he himself conducted it for the Women’s Demonstration meeting. A
year later it was sung at a Suffrage Demonstration concert, after which Millicent Garrett Fawcett, for many
years the president of the National Union of Women’s Suffrage Societies and an old friend of Parry’s,
wrote to thank him for it and propose that it become the Women Voters’ hymn.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Parry 
<pb id="p34-86" n="86"/>
replied, “Thank you for what you say about the “Jerusalem” song. I wish indeed it might become the Women
Voters’ hymn, as you suggest. People seem to enjoy singing it. And having the vote ought to diffuse a good
deal of joy too. So they would combine happily.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">24</ref> It was soon adopted as the national hymn for the Women’s Institutes. 
<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Dibble 485. Seaver, <hi rend="i">Younghusband</hi> 292, says Parry gave “Fight for Right”
the copyright to “Jerusalem.”</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Millicent Garrett Fawcett (1847-1929) was a member of the first women’s
suffrage committee in 1867 and helped found Newnham College, Cambridge. She became the first president of the
National Union in 1897 and remained tirelessly active in that role until she resigned shortly after Parliament
passed a limited women’s suffrage bill in early 1918.
                            <p>Parry’s wife, the former Maude Herbert, was an active campaigner for
women’s rights, and a friend not only of Fawcett but of the more militant Pankhursts. See Benoliel
23.</p></note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Graves 2: 93; Dibble 485.</note></p>
          <p>It is hardly surprising that the women’s movement should want to make the song its own, as
indeed nearly everyone seemed to enjoy singing it, and felt stirred by both its words and melody. The biblical
imagery of spiritual warfare captures echoes of several intense eras and movements in British history from the
seventeenth-century sects to nineteenth-century Anglican reform movements, the “Satanic Mills” and the
building of Jerusalem make it attractive to laborers, and its wondrous claim that Jerusalem can be built or
rebuilt here in England make it seem both patriotic and revolutionary, and even restorationist. In 1916,
however, the imagery of spiritual weaponry culminating in the sword may have struck home, as it were,
particularly in the women’s movement, for that movement, or some branches of it, had made great use of it. A
poem printed in <hi rend="i">Votes for Women</hi> in March 1912, for instance, reads “Woman! Arise! And take
thy fitting place, / Amid the armies of the human race. / Gird on thy sword of justice and of right, / Nor
rest till victory crowns the valiant fight.” <hi rend="i">The Suffragette</hi> of June 1913 carried a
cartoon of a woman walking out of Holloway Prison, still shackled, bearing a flame and a flaming sword labeled
“Spirit.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> For some factions of
the women’s movement the sword was less a metaphor than an archaic synecdoche, for they were using literal
weapons such as explosives in their campaigns. As Millicent Fawcett firmly disagreed with their tactics, her
enthusiasm for Parry’s song may have been due to its subsuming of warrior imagery under strictly “mental
fight.” <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Both examples from Cheryl R. Jorgensen-Earp, “<hi rend="i">The
Transfiguring Sword”: The Just War of the Women’s Social and Political Union</hi> (Tuscaloosa: U of
Alabama P, 1997) 91. This book deals mainly with British women who took up violence for the cause.</note></p>
          <p>Parry died in October 1918, a month before the armistice that put an end to the war that he had
watched with despair. A tablet to his memory is mounted in Gloucester Cathedral, with an inscription by
Bridges. For his part, Bridges celebrated the Allied victory with a truly awful poem called “Britannia
Victrix,” which belongs in a select anthology with Wordsworth’s “Thanksgiving Ode” of 1816.</p>
          <p>Blake’s poem is a four-square structure: four quatrains of iambic tetrameter, with half a dozen
trochaic inversions but consistently octosyllabic (except possibly line 7, if one gives “Jerusalem” four
syllables). In an actual recital of the poem, of course, one will give some syllables interm ediate stresses:
“those” will take more weight than “And” or “in,” for example, while “Shine” might take a
stress almost equal to “forth.” To my ear the poem is metrically interesting throughout, for it escapes
sing-song monotony through just enough inversions and semi-stresses. The final stanza, for instance, is
perfectly regular except for the inversion in the third foot of line 14, putting the stressed “sleep” next
to “sword,” a striking effect that brings out the suggestion that the sword is not only spiritual but
conscious.</p>
          <p>Once Parry decided to couple the stanzas and compose an eight-line melody, he was faced with
certain difficulties, for neither as quatrains nor as octets are they metrically equivalent or “strophic.”
The four “Bring me” lines match only the second line of stanza one. The phrase “pleasant pastures” is
a more substantial phrase than the corresponding “chariot of,” though in metrical schema they are the
same. Some inadequacies in the resulting setting seem to be due to the compromises required to fit the tune to
two somewhat different metrical patterns; thus “chariot of” gets an almost absurd weight. I think too that
Parry planned the melody of the sixth line to fit line 14 of the original, not line 6, for it is perfect for
“Nor shall my sword sleep in my hand” (“sword” and “sleep” each receiving a full beat), but too
portentous for “-on our.” But there are few of these awkward moments. The tune seems right for the text in
so many ways that it is difficult to return to the text alone without hearing it in the mind, and I have had
students who think Blake wrote the music himself.</p>
          <p>Parry’s setting is in D major and three-four time. That it is in triple meter might be
surprising when one thinks of the four beats and eight syllables of the poem, but musical rhythm, of course,
is much less dependent on stress than on time or interval; it is quantitative rather than qualitative, to use
the terms of classical metrics. The analysis will be a little easier if we think of the three quarter notes or
crotchets as six eighth notes or quavers, whereby an eighth note gets one count or beat and there are six
counts per measure. Since the quantitative equivalent of an iamb is three beats—one beat for the “short”
and two for the “long”—it then should not be a surprise after all that Parry gives two measures (12
beats) to each line. On the other hand he seldom distributes two beats to the originally stressed syllables
and one to the unstressed; that would have been unbearable. Instead, after pondering what to do with feet and
time, he gave “feet” three beats and “time” four, while to the other two stressed syllables, “did”
and “an-,” he gave only one beat. The result sounds natural semantically, since “feet” and “time”
are more significant than “did” and “an-” (the latter gaining semantic weight with its second
syllable, to which Parry wrote two sixteenth notes). As he begins each line in mid-measure, “feet” and
“time,” along with “Eng(land),” “green,” “ho(ly),” “God,” and so on, fall on the opening
beat or downbeat of the measure.</p>
          <p>As an experiment I have tried to convey to those who do not read music the rhythmical structure
of the setting by writing numbers above the syllables. This is how one would 
<pb id="p34-87" n="87"/>
count it if each eighth note had one beat, with the symbol “&amp;” representing a half-beat (sixteenth
note).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Text from <hi rend="i">The Church Hymnary</hi>, 3rd ed. (Oxford: Oxford
UP, 1973) (1st ed. 1927).</note></p>
          <figure n="JerusalemHymn.Meter.34.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="296" height="550">
          	<figTranscr>(3 1/2 measures of accompaniment)<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	 4   5   6        123  4   5  6         1234<lb/>
          	And did those     feet in ancient       time<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	5     6           1    2    3 4  5 6    1 2 3<lb/>
          	Walk upon         England’s mountains   green?<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	 4   5   6        123  4   5   6        123<lb/>
          	And was the       ho - ly Lamb of       God<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	 4  5   6          1   2   3 4 5 6       123<lb/>
          	On England’s      pleasant pastures     seen?<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	  4  5   6         123 4  5 6  &amp;     123<lb/>
          	And did the       countenance di-       vine<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	  4     5   6    123  4    5  6         1 2 3<lb/>
          	Shine forth up-   on our clouded        hills?<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	  4  5   6       12 &amp; 34  5 6 &amp;  123<lb/>
          	And was Je-       ru-salem builded      here<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	 4 5    6         1 2 &amp; 34  56       1234<lb/>
          	Among these       dark satan - ic       mills?<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	(2 2/3 measures of accompaniment)<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	  34  5  6        123 4   5   6         1234<lb/>
          	Bring me my       bow of burning        gold<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	   5    6          1  2  34 56          123<lb/>
          	Bring me my       arrows of de-         sire!<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	   4  5  6         1 2   34   5   6      123<lb/>
          	Bring me my       spear! O clouds un-   fold!<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	   4  5  6       12 &amp; 34 56          123<lb/>
          	Bring me my       chari- ot of          fire!<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	4  5    6         1 2 3   4  5 6 &amp;   1 2 3<lb/>
          	I will not        cease from mental     fight,<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	 4    5   6        1 2   3 4  5  6      123<lb/>
          	Nor shall my      sword sleep in my     hand,<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	   4 5   6        1 2 3 4    56  &amp;  123<lb/>
          	Till we have      built Je - ru - sa    lem<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	 4  5   6           1    2   3 4 5 6    123456    12<lb/>
          	In England’s      green and pleasant    la------ -nd.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	(1 2/3 measures of accompaniment)</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <p>Though Bridges insisted that it be “suitable, simple music to Blake’s stanzas—music that an
audience could take up and join in,” the setting is a good deal less simple than that of most congregational
hymns. The organ or piano accompaniment is more elaborate than normal, with a three-and-a-half-measure
prelude, a somewhat shorter interlude (or prelude to the second half), and a postlude of one and a half
measures. There is enough going on in the harmony that even an experienced sight-reader of hymns will need to
practice it carefully. In part to accommodate the different patterns of emphasis of the two halves, it is to
some extent “through-composed” like a Lied or art-song, that is, it is not perfectly strophic like hymns
in a hymnal, where each stanza has the identical music. Parry altered the “left-hand” accompaniment here
and there, and the dynamic markings, but, more important, he varied the melody, or rather the rhythm of the
melody, at three significant points.</p>
          <p>Most of the lines begin, as the “counting” text shows, at the second half of the measure,
that is, on the fourth beat (at six beats per measure); the exception in each half is the second line, which
begins on the fifth beat (“Walk upon” and “Bring me my”), the words that end the preceding lines
(“time” and “gold”) having each taken four beats. So far they are perfectly parallel
strophically—even to the falling of the sixth beat on two syllables (“upon” and “me my”). But the
opening word of the second half (“Bring”) begins one beat earlier in the first measure and lasts for two
beats, the “O” of the third line does the same thing in the second measure, and the “sleep” following
“sword” does the same thing in the second measure of the sixth. In all three cases Parry jumps the gun and
slightly throws off the rhythm as established in the first half, but to good effect: the early arrival of the
first “Bring” expresses its urgency (softened a little by its falling nearly at the bottom of the melodic
range), as if the speaker cannot wait another beat to take up his bow, and so with the “O” on high D, an
octave above the “Bring,” as if he can no longer contain himself. (All the more effective, I think, since
the “O” is unstressed, or only lightly stressed, in the verse scansion.) As for “sleep,” also on high
D, the melody seems made for it, as I suggested, and it gives proper weight to the metrical inversion of
Blake’s original poem.</p>
          <p>Walford Davies was the first to see the setting, the day after Parry wrote it, and they discussed
it at length. A few years later Davies remembered:
<q>
One momentary act of his should perhaps be told here. He ceased to speak, and put his finger on the note D in
the second stanza where the words “O clouds unfold” break his rhythm. I do not think any word passed about
it, yet he made it perfectly clear that this was the one note and one moment of the song which he
treasured.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Letter from Sir Walford Davies to <hi rend="i">The Times</hi>, 27 August
1927, quoted in Dibble 484.</note></q></p>
          <p>As it is often printed in hymnals, in strophic form, the two stanzas lineated one above the other
between the bass and treble clefs, the moment Parry treasured is obliterated, along with the comparable
“Bring” and “sleep.” The second stanza is assimilated to the rhythm of the first, so “Bring,”
“O,” and “sleep” all begin on the fourth beat and last half as long. No doubt the hymn is easier to
sing that way, and it certainly takes up less space in the hymnal, but the result is a diminished thing. Two
recordings, by Emerson, Lake and 
<pb id="p34-88" n="88"/>
Palmer in 1973 and by Billy Bragg in 1990, though they are both effective and interesting renditions (the
former adding many syncopations and fermatas to the rhythm), are weaker than they should be because they
depended on a strophic text.</p>
          <p>The first hymnal to include “Jerusalem” was <hi rend="i">A Students’ Hymnal</hi>, published
by the Student Christian Movement in 1923 (illus. 1 and 2-6). Founded at Cambridge in 1892, the SCM encouraged
students to practice the Christian life and recruited them as missionaries.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> Hence it was exactly the right hymn to conclude the movie
<hi rend="i">Chariots of Fire</hi> (1981), which deals with a Scottish Christian athlete called to be a
missionary after he competes in the 1924 Olympic games. Probably through SCM the <hi rend="i">American Student
Hymnal</hi> carried it in 1928, while the <hi rend="i">Church Hymnary</hi> (Church of Scotland and
Presbyterian Churches) included it in 1927. The Church of England followed suit with the text but not the
music in the 1933 revision of <hi rend="i">The English Hymnal</hi> (orig. 1906). The hymn is now very common
in English public schools and American private schools. <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Rogal
23-24.</note></p>
          <p>Since its first appearance in an American hymnal, unfortunately, it has often been Americanized.
The version in the <hi rend="i">American Student Hymnal</hi>, edited by H. Augustine Smith, begins:
<q>
And did those feet in ancient time<lb/>
Walk upon Zion’s mountains green?<lb/>
And was the holy Lamb of God<lb/>
In Zion’s pleasant pastures seen?
</q></p>
          <p>It would have been all right to substitute “America” for “England” if the meter had
permitted, but to insert “Zion” is to destroy the point of the whole stanza and make the speaker into an
idiot. Of course Jesus walked in Zion! So what?</p>
          <p>There are several other tamperings that drain sense out of the text:
<q>
And could that countenance divine<lb/>
Shine forth upon our clouded hills?<lb/>
And could Jerusalem arise<lb/>
Among these dark satanic mills?
</q></p>
          <p>What is the motive for denying that Jerusalem is built like any other city? The editor might have
substituted “And could they build Jerusalem,” which would have paralleled line 15 and eliminated the weak
“builded here”; instead he gives us the even weaker, almost unsingable, “arise,” with two beats on
“a-.” Apparently he felt uneasy at the illogical slide from ancient time to the present and so substituted
the conditional “could.” But it saps the dramatic tension, the sense of astonishment, while making it only
a little more logical.</p>
          <p>This version ends not with “Zion” again, which would be too absurd even for Mr. Smith, but
with
<figure n="hymnal.34.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="302" height="450">
	<figTranscr>A<lb/>
	STUDENTS’ HYMNAL<lb/>
	FOR USE IN<lb/>
	SCHOOLS &amp; COLLEGES<lb/>
	INCLUDING<lb/>
	200 ENGLISH HYMNS (‘HYMNS OF THE KINGDOM’)<lb/>
	128 WELSH HYMNS<lb/>
	AND A FEW<lb/>
	PSALMS, ANTHEMS, AND CAROLS<lb/>
	<lb/>
	PRIFYSGOL CYMRU<lb/>
	<lb/>
	SCIENTIA INGENIUM ARTES<lb/>
	<lb/>
	EDITED BY SIR WALFORD DAVIES FOR THE NATIONAL<lb/>
	COUNCIL OF MUSIC IN WALES AND THE WELSH<lb/>
	COUNTY SCHOOLS ASSOCIATION<lb/>
	<lb/>
	BEXLEY HALL LIBRARY<lb/>
	14637<lb/>
	<lb/>
	HARMONIZED EDITION<lb/>
	<lb/>
	HUMPHREY MILFORD<lb/>
	<lb/>
	OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS<lb/>
	<lb/>
	LONDON   EDINBURGH   GLASGOW   COPENHAGEN<lb/>
	NEW YORK   TORONTO   MELBOURNE   CAPE TOWN<lb/>
	BOMBAY   CALCUTTA   MADRAS   SHANGHAI<lb/>
	<lb/>
	1923</figTranscr>
	<head>1 Cover of <hi rend="i">A Students’ Hymnal</hi> (1923), the first hymnal to include
“Jerusalem.”</head>
</figure>
<q>
Till we have built Jerusalem,<lb/>
In every green and pleasant land.
</q>
We might have thought that the point was to build Jerusalem (or make it arise) here—in America. He might
have written “In this our green and plesant land.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref> But as it stands it is certainly well adapted for recruiting overseas missionaries. 
<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> A Connecticut friend tells me he often substitutes “New England” for
“England.” In Wales, apparently, “Jerusalem” is sung enthusiastically in Welsh, with “Cymru”
replacing “England.” G. V. Barton, “Blake’s ‘Cymru,’” <hi rend="i">Independent</hi> [London], 23
May 1996, 19.</note></p>
          <p>One would think the labor movement would have adopted the song right away. Several historians of
the period have told me they thought “Jerusalem” was sung by miners and other workers during the great
General Strike of 1926, but I have been unable to confirm it. We do know that when the Strike came to an end
on 12 May in a defeat for the miners, Prime Minister Baldwin made a radio broadcast to the nation, which was
followed by a BBC “valedictory.” It concluded: “In going back to work to-morrow, or the next day, can we
not all go as fellow-craftsmen, resolved in the determination to pick up the broken pieces, repair the gaps,
and build the walls of a more enduring city—the city revealed to the mystical eyes of William Blake when he
wrote:—” and then followed all four stanzas. This is powerful rhetoric, though how much it moved the
workers, who won nothing from the largest strike in British history, is another matter. It is possible that
the song had been widely sung by the workers, in which case the BBC tried to co-opt it, perhaps as 
<pb id="p34-89" n="89"/>
Lyndon Johnson announced “We shall overcome” in 1965, but since for 10 years the song had been circulating
widely among many groups it does not seem likely that the labor movement had made it distinctively its
own.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref> It may have done so in 1945,
however, for it was sung outside Transport House, the Labour Party head quarters, after the Labour electoral
victory.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> In America labor unionists
and leftists have often sung the song or had it performed at rallies. It was Walter Reuther’s favorite
hymn.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> Paul Robeson sang it often and
recorded it. Its manifest Englishness may have limited its appeal, but the American left has been strongly
internationalist and has often sponsored concerts and published books with songs from around the world. At
least the left has not, as far as I know, been guilty of rewriting it. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi>
Alfred Havighurst, <hi rend="i">Twentieth-Century Britain</hi>, 2nd ed. (New York: Harper, 1962) 198-99, seems
to say that Baldwin himself quoted the poem. For the text of the BBC statement, see R. Page Arnot, ed., 
<hi rend="i">The General Strike: May 1926; Its Origin and History</hi> (London: Labour Research Dept., 1926; rpt.
New York: Augustus M. Kelley, 1967) 228-29.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> “Scholars will assert that the famous ‘Jerusalem’ hymn is
crypto-Anglo-Israelitism or what not; but when it was sung in front of Transport House at the Labour victory
of 1945 the singers showed that they understood it far better than such scholars did.” Northrop Frye,
“Blake After Two Centuries,” <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 27 (1957), rpt. in Frye,
<hi rend="i">Fables of Identity</hi> (New York: Harcourt Brace, 1963) 140.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> I owe this fact to Frank Wallick, editor of the United Auto Workers
newsletter, in a personal conversation, June 1981.</note></p>
          <p>Two important motion pictures have drawn heavily on the hymn. It is the theme music to 
<hi rend="i">The Loneliness of the Long-Distance Runner</hi> (1962), directed by Tony Richardson, and based on the
novel by Alan Sillitoe. The film tells of a young man (played by Tom Courtenay) in a reform school whose
talent for long-distance running is exploited by the headmaster (Michael Redgrave) for the glory of the
school. We hear instrumental variations of the melody during the boy’s long runs, and in one painful scene
the boys sing the hymn in assembly while a captured runaway is beaten with a strap in an office. The
bitterness of the irony here relies on the hymn’s revolutionary or reformist provenance. The other, as we
noted, is <hi rend="i">Chariots of Fire</hi> (1981), directed by Hugh Hudson. Though the title is drawn from
the hymn, the hymn itself is not heard until the final scene in a church. Most viewers of the film remember
the music of Vangelis Papathanassiou, but, unless I am imagining things, the evocative main theme of his music
is reminiscent of Parry’s melody. Yet here the associations of the hymn seem the contrary of those in the
earlier film: idealistic, no doubt, but more concerned with missionary work and personal moral courage—the
earliest context for the imagery of spiritual warfare, after all (Ephesians 6.11-17)—than with social
reconstruction.</p>
          <p>It is not surprising, then, that the socialist singer Billy Bragg has run into opposition in his
championing of the song. “My belief that ‘Jerusalem’ is a left-wing anthem has got me into arguments
with public schoolboys at Eton and Trotskyist newspaper sellers in Trafalgar Square. I remain convinced that
the song does not belong alongside ‘Rule Britannia’ and ‘Land of Hope and Glory’ at the last night of
the Proms.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> I agree with Bragg
about “Jerusalem,” but I think we should encourage the patriotic bourgeoisie to come and sing it anyway.
It will do them good. <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> Liner notes to Bragg’s <hi rend="i">The
Internationale.</hi></note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Discography</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The song has been recorded too many times to make a thorough list possible or necessary. Here
are some examples on CD:</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, with the Choir of Winchester Cathedral, the Waynflete Singers, and
the Bournemouth Symphony Orchestra (Argo D102372); orchestral version by Elgar. Includes “Blest pair of
Sirens,” “I was glad,” and two more songs by Parry, as well as several by Stanford and Elgar, among
others.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">I Was Glad: Cathedral Music by Parry</hi>, with the St. George’s Chapel Choir,
Windsor (Hyperion CDA66273); organ accompaniment. Includes “I was glad,” “Evening Service in D,”
“Songs of Farewell,” and “Hear my Words, Ye People.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Allegri: Miserere</hi>, with the Choir of Trinity College, Cambridge (BMG/Conifer
16851). Includes Parry’s “I was glad” and a song by Walford Davies, as well as works by Allegri,
Schubert, Barber, Bach, Mendelssohn, et al.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Last Night of the Proms</hi>, with the BBC Chorus, Choral Society, and
Orchestra, recorded live at the Royal Albert Hall, directed by Sir Colin Davis (Philips 420-085-2); orchestral
version by Elgar. Includes pieces by Elgar, Berlioz, Wagner, Mendelssohn, and Handel, and of course Arne’s
“Rule Britannia.”</p>
            <p>Paul Robeson, <hi rend="i">Ballad for Americans</hi> (Vanguard B000000ECS); and 
<hi rend="i">The Odyssey of Paul Robeson</hi> (Vanguard Classics B00000239N).</p>
            <p>Emerson, Lake and Palmer, <hi rend="i">Brain Salad Surgery</hi> (Rhino R2-72459). This is an
acid-rock “trip-music” version with heavy synthesizer overlay and echoey voice. According to Greg Lake,
however, “The lyrics are very bland except for one line, ‘Bring me my bow of burning gold / Bring me my
arrows of desire.’ The rest of the song was all waffle. But when it came to that line, it was a moment that
you had to sing the song for” (liner notes).</p>
            <p>Billy Bragg, <hi rend="i">The Internationale</hi> (Utility/Wea/Elektra 60960-2); Bragg also has
a CD called <hi rend="i">William Bloke</hi>, but there is nothing by Blake on it.</p>
            <pb id="p34-90" n="90"/>
            <figure n="feetpg1.34.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="305" height="450">
              <figTranscr>11. And did those feet in ancient time<lb/>
              (JERUSALEM. 8 8 8 8. 8 8 8 8)<lb/>
              Doh = D.<lb/>
              Slow, but with animation.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              3<lb/>
              4<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {|   :   :   |   :   :   }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              3<lb/>
              4<lb/>
              <lb/>
              f   mf cres.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              3<lb/>
              4<lb/>
              <lb/>
              SOLO.<lb/>
              mf<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {|   :   :   |   : .d :m .s | l   :- .d :l .s ,f }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              And did those feet in an - cient<lb/>
              <lb/>
              ff   mf<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Copyright, 1916, by Hubert H. Parry.<lb/>
              24</figTranscr>
              <head>“And did those feet in ancient time.” Page 1.</head>
              <figDesc>Music score by Hubert Parry.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p34-91" n="91"/>
            <figure n="feetpg2.34.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="312" height="450">
              <figTranscr>p<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| s   :-   :l .s ,f | s .m :r :d | l :- .d :m .s }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              time   Walk upon England’s moun-tains green? And was the<lb/>
              <lb/>
              p<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| l   :- .d :t .l ,s | l   :- .l :t .m | s .fe :m   :r   }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Ho - ly Lamb of God   On England’s plea-sant pas - tures<lb/>
              <lb/>
              mf   poco cres.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| s   :- .r :r .m | f   :- .l :s .,r | f :- .r :f .s }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              seen?   And did the Count - te-nance Di - vine   Shine forth up-<lb/>
              <lb/>
              mf   poco cres.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              25</figTranscr>
              <head>“And did those feet in ancient time.” Page 2.</head>
              <figDesc>Music score by Hubert Parry.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p34-92" n="92"/>
            <figure n="feetpg3.34.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="307" height="450">
              <figTranscr>f<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| l   :- .d :ta .s | l   :- .f :l .d | r .,d :t :t .,l }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              - on   our cloud-ed hills?   And was Je - ru - sa - lem build - ed<lb/>
              <lb/>
              f<lb/>
              <lb/>
              poco rit.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| s   :- .s :d .l | s .,l :m :r   | d   :-   :   }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              here   A-mong those dark Sa - tan - ic   mills?<lb/>
              <lb/>
              poco rit.   f<lb/>
              <lb/>
              ALL AVAILABLE VOICES.   mf<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {|   :   :   |   :   :   |   :d :m .s }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Bring me my<lb/>
              <lb/>
              ff   mf<lb/>
              <lb/>
              26   8</figTranscr>
              <head>“And did those feet in ancient time.” Page 3.</head>
              <figDesc>Music score by Hubert Parry.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p34-93" n="93"/>
            <figure n="feetpg4.34.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="297" height="450">
              <figTranscr>{| l   :- .d :l .s ,f | s   :-   :l .s ,f | s .m :r :d   }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              bow of burn-ing gold! Bring me my ar-rows of de - <lb/>
              <lb/>
              8<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| l   :- .d :m .s | l   :d   :t  .l ,s | l   :- .l :t .m }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              - sire!   Bring me my spear! O clouds un - fold!   Bring me my<lb/>
              <lb/>
              p<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| s .,fe :m :r   | s   :- .r :r .m | f   :- .l :s .,r }<lb/>
              Cha - ri - ot of Fire!   I will not cease from men - tal<lb/>
              <lb/>
              p<lb/>
              <lb/>
              27</figTranscr>
              <head>“And did those feet in ancient time.” Page 4.</head>
              <figDesc>Music score by Hubert Parry.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p34-94" n="94"/>
            <figure n="feetpg5.34.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="306" height="450">
              <figTranscr>Allargando.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| f   :- .r :f .s | l :d :ta .s | l   :- .f :l .d }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              fight; Nor shall my sword sleep in my hand   Till we have<lb/>
              <lb/>
              ff   rit.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| r   :- .d :t .,l | s   :- .s :d .l | s .l :m :r   }<lb/>
              <lb/>
              built Je - ru - sa - lem   In England’s freen and plea - sant<lb/>
              <lb/>
              ff   rit.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              {| d   :-   :-   | -   :   :   |   :   :   ||<lb/>
              <lb/>
              land.   .   .   .<lb/>
              <lb/>
              ff<lb/>
              <lb/>
              8<lb/>
              <lb/>
              28</figTranscr>
              <head>“And did those feet in ancient time.” Page 5.</head>
              <figDesc>Music score by Hubert Parry.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
