<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>35.1.mazzeo</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Verbal Echoes of Cumberland’s Thoughts on Outline, Sculpture, and the System
that Guided the Ancients (1796) in Jerusalem</title>
        <author n="Mazzeo">Tilar Jenon Mazzeo</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2001</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2001</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">35.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Tilar Jenon Mazzeo</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2001"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_35">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-1-0007">
        <pb id="p35-24" n="24"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Verbal Echoes of Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline, Sculpture,
and the System that Guided the Ancients</hi> (1796) in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Tilar Jenon <name>Mazzeo</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Blake’s references to sculpture develop one of the most persistent metaphors in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and the relationship between the poem and sculptural forms has received considerable
critical attention in recent years. Studies by Vincent De Luca, W.J.T. Mitchell, Morton Paley, Molly
Rothenberg, Jason Whittaker, and Joseph Viscomi have each suggested that Blake’s investment in sculpture is
reflected in the structural and thematic principles of the poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n69" type="note">1</ref> However, Blake’s verbal echoes of George Cumberland’s 
<hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline, Sculpture, and the System that Guided the Ancients in Composing Their Groupes
and Figures</hi> (1796) in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
	<pb id="p35-25" n="25"/>
have not been noted as a source for his interest in the medium, although the parallels between these two texts
offer suggestive conceptual implications. <note id="n69"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Discussions of sculptural forms
within <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> typically focus on three predominant images—the bright sculptures of
Los’ halls in Golgonooza, the “unhewn” Druidical temples at Stonehenge and Avebury, and Blake’s visual
emphasis on the iconic arrangement of words. The most developed discussion of Blake’s sculptural aesthetic
is offered by De Luca’s reading of the hieroglyph (literally “sacred statue”) and the biblical sublime,
in the <hi rend="i">Words of Eternity: Blake and the Poetics of the Sublime</hi> (1991). Other approaches to
this topic are offered in: Viscomi’s <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (1993); Mitchell’s
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> (1978); Paley’s “Wonderful Originals: Blake and Ancient
Sculpture” in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, Eds. Essick and Pearce (1978); Rothenberg’s 
<hi rend="i">Rethinking Blake’s Textuality</hi> (1993), and Whittaker’s <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
Myths of Britain</hi> (1999).</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s familiarity with the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> and his enthusiasm for the
author’s imagery are evident from his letters to George Cumberland, who employed Blake as an engraver on the
project from 1794 to 1796.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">2</ref> During
this period, Blake completed six plates for Cumberland’s book, and his letters emphasize his confidence in
Cumberland’s artistic sensibilities.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">3</ref> Blake writes in 1796, for example, that he sends his plates to Cumberland “to be
transmuted, thou real Alchymist” (Erdman, 700). Again in 1799, upon receipt of the finished volume, he
professes to “study [Cumberland’s] outlines as usual just as if they were antiques” (Erdman, 704). This
particular interest in Cumberland’s outlines was to develop further when Blake came to write 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and his engagement with the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> stemmed, I propose,
from Cumberland’s unusual definition of sculpture as an essentially linear form. 
<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">2</hi> All references are to George Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline, Sculpture, and
the System that Guided the Ancient Artists in Composing their Figures and Groupes: Accompanied with Free
Remarks on the Practice of the Moderns, and Liberal Hints Cordially Intended for their Advantage: to which are
Annexed Twenty-four Designs of Classical Subjects Invented on the Principles Recommended in the Essay by
George Cumberland</hi> (London, 1796). References to Blake’s works refer to David V. Erdman’s 
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> (New York, 1988).</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">3</hi> For further identification and discussion of the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
Outline</hi> plates, see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977)
542-44; and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Engravings</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
Press, 1991) 67-70 and figs. 147-54.</note></p>
          <p>In the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, Cumberland develops a complex and quite original
definition of sculpture, which identifies the bounding line as the defining and potentially transformative
feature of this medium. As a linear form, sculpture is characterized by outline, surface, and circumference
and is reducible to two dimensions without any change in its essential quality. In fact, Cumberland writes
that:
<q>
The Sculptor’s art, by which is not meant merely finishing his compositions in marble, but forming, with
correctness, figures in any material, is a truly rational and liberal employment....The statue is 
<hi rend="i">all</hi> outline; a creation, the bounds of whose surface require inconceivable knowledge, taste, and
study, to circumscribe.
(Cumberland, 8-9)
</q>
Here, Cumberland suggests that sculpture is independent of its traditional media and is a form characterized
instead by its outline, boundary, and surface. The relationship among these elements is more clearly
delineated later in his treatise, when Cumberland explains how these model outlines are produced—as
projections cast from a limited number of antique originals. In his estimation “there are statues in the
world which, if turned around on a pivot before a lamp, would produce, on a wall, some hundreds of fine
outlines” (33). Thus, the bounding line of a sculptural form contains a multiplicity of outlines within it,
and this is its rarest quality. Not only can sculpture transform itself, however, Cumberland also claims that
its production is an act of artistic and intellectual alchemy. He writes:
<q>
form stamps a value on the meanest materials [and] when this nation shall have nursed a race of men, capable
of creating finer forms than others, out of clay, stone, wood, and metals, we shall possess a better thing
than the ideal stone of the philosopher. For that pretends only to the skill of compounding gold from mixed
metals, but these men will transmute, by aid of the mind, and hand, the basest materials into solid bullion.
(12)
</q>
Sculptural activity becomes both a national project and an act of alchemical restoration. And, while Blake
echoes Cumberland’s concept of sculpture throughout <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, it is this last
passage—which proposes the delineation of form as the imaginative renovation of base existence—that
particularly interested the poet.</p>
          <p>Blake’s subsequent interest in Cumberland’s aesthetic principles and in this passage from the
<hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> in particular is suggested by several of his own critical statements. In
the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, for example, Blake indicates his abiding interest in both outline
and sculpture, claiming that his own works have been shaped by an investment in the “bounding line” of
form and in the richness of “Antique Statues” (Erdman, 550; 536). However, Blake’s letters also indicate
his particular interest in this alchemical passage in Cumberland’s treatise. This metaphor of transmutation
appears only once in Cumberland’s text, and it is surely the source of Blake’s invocation of Cumberland as
“thou real Alchymist!” in the letter of 23 December 1796. More importantly, Blake also seems to have had
this passage in mind when composing the final plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and the poem’s
apocalypse incorporates verbal echoes of Cumberland’s treatise on outline and sculpture.</p>
          <p>In the dramatic final lines of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake alludes specifically to the
alchemical passage from <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, narrating an apocalypse that evokes
Cumberland’s imaginative transmutation of “clay, stone, wood, and metals” (12). In the final visionary
conversation, Blake describes “All Human Forms identified even Tree Metal Earth &amp; Stone” (99:1),
repeating precisely Cumberland’s sculptural elements. And, while this instance marks the only 
<hi rend="i">precise</hi> reference to the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, other passages in the final
plates of the poem suggest that Blake may have had Cumberland’s treatise in mind, most notably the
celebration of “the Outline the Circumference &amp; Form” of the human lineaments in Beulah (98:22). In
light of these references,
<pb id="p35-26" n="26"/>
it seems clear that Blake was thinking of Cumberland’s treatise as he composed 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          <p>The significance of Blake’s verbal echoes and allusions, unfortunately, lies beyond the scope
of a short note such as this; however, several conceptual similarities between Cumberland’s essay and
Blake’s poem suggest themselves immediately, and they perhaps merit further consideration. After all, the
thematic parallels with the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> extend beyond the final plates of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Not only does Cumberland’s description of statuary as a linear form offer a new way
to read Blake’s process of relief etching and his aesthetic sensibilities in the visual images of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, but there is also a sense in which the base narrative of the poem—Los’s journey
with “red globe of fire in hand” around the “stonified” body of Albion—can be read as an enactment
of Cumberland’s process of casting outlines. Above all, there is this central similarity: Blake proposes,
like Cumberland, a series of “stupendous originals,” each described by and, in a sense, composed of the
scattered images, outlines, and projections of its own form. While Cumberland’s aesthetic project is to
collect these outlines in a single didactic text, Blake’s objective, though surely more complex and subtle,
may ultimately be much the same.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
