<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>35.1.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2001</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2001</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">35.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Tilar Jenon Mazzeo</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2001"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_35">
    <front>
      <pb id="p35-1-2" n="1-2"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.035.01.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="334">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            Peter Otto on Phallic Religion in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi><lb/>
            VOLUME 35<lb/>
            NUMBER 1<lb/>
            SUMMER 2001</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-1-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="12" cols="2">
          <row>
          	<cell>
        	<head>
              <title>CONTENTS</title>
        	</head>
        	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="35.1.otto">A Pompous High Priest: Urizen’s Ancient Phallic
Religion in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Peter Otto</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">4</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particulars</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="35.1.ferber">Blake for Children</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Michael Ferber</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">22</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="35.1.mazzeo">Verbal Echoes of Cumberland’s 
<hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline, Sculpture, and the System that Guided the Ancients</hi> (1796) in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Tilar Jenon Mazzeo</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">24</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Review</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="35.1.spector">Steve Clark and David Worrall, eds. 
<hi rend="i">Blake in the Nineties</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Sheila A. Spector</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">26</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Corrigenda</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="35.1.phillips"><hi rend="i">William Blake The Creation of
the</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">From Manuscript to Illuminated Printing Corrigenda</hi> and a Note on the
Publication of Gilbert Imlay’s <hi rend="i">A Topographical Description of the Western Territory of North
America</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Michael Phillips</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">30</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Newsletter</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="35.1.editors">Blake’<hi rend="i">s Managing Editors,
1986-</hi></ref>; 
<ref type="article" issue="35.1.news"><hi rend="i">www.rochester.edu/college/eng/blake</hi></ref></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">31</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-1-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p35-3" n="3"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-1-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Michael Ferber is Professor of English and Humanities at the University of New Hampshire. His most
recent book is <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of Literary Symbols.</hi> His daughter can now play “Jerusalem”
on the violin.</p>
        <p>Tilar Jenon Mazzeo teaches at the University of Wisconsin, Oshkosh, where she specializes in travel
literature and Romantic poetry. She has contributed volumes to the series <hi rend="i">Critical Writings of
Mary Shelley</hi> and <hi rend="i">Travels, Explorations, and Empires: Middle East</hi> (Pickering and
Chatto), and published a facsimile edition of Thomas Medwin’s <hi rend="i">Lady Singleton.</hi></p>
        <p>Peter Otto is the author of <hi rend="i">Constructive Vision and Visionary Deconstruction</hi>
(Oxford, 1991) and <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence</hi> (Oxford, 2000). He has recently
co-edited a microfilm collection of Gothic Fictions to be published by Adam Matthew Publications in 2002. He
is currently working on a project that explores the relations between Romanticism, Mesmerism and
Millenarianism.</p>
        <p>Michael Phillips teaches an interdisciplinary MA, William Blake and the Age of Revolution, at the
Centre for Eighteenth Century Studies, University of York. In addition to the recent publication of 
<hi rend="i">The Creation of the</hi> Songs, he was guest curator of the William Blake exhibition at Tate Britain,
London. He is completing a biography of Blake in Lambeth during the anti-Jacobin terror in Britain.</p>
        <p>Sheila A. Spector’s two-part study of Blake as a Kabbalist—<hi rend="i">“Glorious
incomprehensible”: The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Language</hi> and <hi rend="i">“Wonders
Divine”: The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Myth</hi>—has just been published by Bucknell University
Press (2001).</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-1-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones<lb/>
TELEPHONE 716/275-3820 FAX 716/442-5769<lb/>
PRODUCTION OFFICE EMAIL: sjns@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@socrates.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2. The University of Toronto
declines to forward mail.<lb/>
Email: GBentley@chass.utoronto.ca</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens GA 30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@uga.cc.uga.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill, Waldegrave Road, Twickenham TW1 4SX
England<lb/>
Email: worralld@smuc.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses
(except Canada and Mexico) require a $10 per volume postal surcharge for surface, and $25 per volume surcharge
for air mail delivery. Credit card payment available for non-U.S. subscribers. Make checks payable to 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to
Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627. Back
issues are available; address Sarah Jones for a list of issues and prices.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in <hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, to either of the editors:
Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of
English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by
a stamped self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a diskette, or you may send your
article as an attachment to an email message. The optimal format is Microsoft Word. Other formats are usually
acceptable.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A
Selective and Critical Bibliography</hi> (ed. David V. Erdman et al.), American Humanities Index, Arts and
Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover: Details of figures on pages 13, 16, and 21. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2001
Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
