<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>35.1.otto</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">A Pompous High Priest: Urizen’s Ancient Phallic Religion in The Four
Zoas</title>
        <author n="Otto">Peter Otto</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2001</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2001</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">35.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Tilar Jenon Mazzeo</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2001"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_35">
    <body>
      <pb id="p35-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Pompous High Priest: Urizen’s Ancient Phallic Religion in <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Peter <name>Otto</name></docAuthor></byline>
		<q>
It is the Semen of Man in which lieth hid the inmost [Principle] of his Life, and thence the Inchoament or
Beginning of a new Life, and from this Circumstance the Semen is holy; to make this common with the inmost
Principles and Inchoaments of others, as is done in Adulteries, is prophane.<lb/>
                        Swedenborg<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref><lb/>
<lb/>
<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Emanuel Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">A General Explication of the Ten Precepts
of the Decalogue</hi>, Extracted from the “Apocalypsis Explicata” (London: R. Hindmarsh, 1794) 94.
                            <p>A shorter version of this paper was delivered at the Romanticism and the New
conference of NASSR, held in Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada, 12-15 August 1999. The discussions of individual
designs in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> are drawn from my <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence:
Love, Jealousy, and the Sublime in “The Four Zoas”</hi> (Oxford: Oxford UP, 2000).</p></note>
The female organs of generation were revered as symbols of the generative powers of nature or matter, as the
male were of the generative powers of God.<lb/>
Knight<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref><lb/>
<lb/>
<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Richard Payne Knight, <hi rend="i">A Discourse on the Worship of Priapus,
and its Connection with the mystic Theology of the Ancients, to which is added an Essay on the Worship of the
Generative Powers During the Middle Ages of Western Europe</hi> (London: Privately Printed, 1865) 28. This
volume reprints Knight’s <hi rend="i">An Account of the Remains of the Worship of Priapus, Lately existing
at Isernia, in the Kingdom of Naples: in Two Letters; One from Sir William Hamilton, K. B., His Majesty’s
Minister at the Court of Naples, to Sir Joseph Banks, Bart., President of the Royal Society. And the other
from a Person residing at Isernia: To which is Added, A Discourse on the Worship of Priapus, And its Connexion
with the mystic Theology of the Ancients</hi> (London: T. Spilsbury, 1786).</note>
a good number of these flying dreams are dreams of erection; for the remarkable phenomenon of erection, around
which the human imagination has constantly played, cannot fail to be impressive, involving as it does an
apparent suspension of the laws of gravity.
                        <lb/>
Freud<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref><lb/>
<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Sigmund Freud, <hi rend="i">The Interpretation of Dreams</hi>, trans. and
ed. James Strachey, Penguin Freud Library, vol. 4 (London: Penguin, 1991) 518.</note>
	<lb/>
the phallus is . . . the signifier intended to designate as a whole the effects of the signified.<lb/>
Lacan<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Jacques Lacan, “The signification of the phallus” in 
<hi rend="i">Écrits: A Selection</hi>, trans. Alan Sheridan (London: Tavistock, 1977) 281-91: 285.</note></q>
          <p>Despite the ubiquity of the word “phallus” and its cognates in feminist, deconstructive and
psychoanalytic (particularly Lacanian) criticism of the last three decades, Blake critics have shown little
interest in the remarkable array of phalli found in the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Arguably, this neglect
extends to the illustrations as a whole. In 1973 Grant noted that “the publication of G. E. Bentley Jr.’s
monumental Clarendon edition of <hi rend="i">Vala or The Four Zoas</hi> in 1963” had not inaugurated “a
tradition of commentary on the drawings.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> Twenty-seven years later, the situation is not markedly different.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The work of Marsha Keith Schuchard is a notable exception, particularly her
“Why Mrs. Blake Cried: Swedenborg, Blake, and the Sexual Basis of Visionary Art,” <hi rend="i">Esoterica:
The Journal of Esoteric Studies</hi> 2 (2000): 45-93.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> John E. Grant, “Visions in Vala: A Consideration of Some Pictures in the
Manuscript,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on “The Four Zoas,” “Milton,” and
“Jerusalem,”</hi> ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. (Madison, Wisconsin: U of Wisconsin
P, 1973) 141-202: 141. Grant makes a “partial exception” of the drawings on page 26.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Critics often consign discussion of the illuminations to a brief appendix.
See, for example, Donald Ault, <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound: Re-Visioning William Blake’s “The Four
Zoas”</hi> (Barrytown: Station Hill Press, 1987) 469-72; John Beer, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary
Universe</hi> (Manchester: U of Manchester P; New York: Barnes and Noble, 1969) 343-52; Andrew Lincoln, 
<hi rend="i">Spiritual History: A Reading of William Blake’s “Vala” or “The Four Zoas”</hi> (Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1995) 291-92; George Anthony Rosso, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Workshop: A Study
of “The Four Zoas”</hi> (Lewisburg: Bucknell UP; London and Toronto: Associated University Presses, 1993)
164-79. When they are discussed in the body of the text, it is usually only in passing: Kathryn Freeman, 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Nostos: Fragmentation and Nondualism in “The Four Zoas,”</hi> SUNY Series in Western
Esoteric Traditions (New York: State U of New York P, 1997); John B. Pierce, <hi rend="i">Flexible Design:
Revisionary Poetics in Blake’s “Vala” or “The Four Zoas”</hi> (Montreal and Kingston:
McGill-Queen’s UP, 1998); V. A. De Luca, <hi rend="i">Words of Eternity: Blake and the Poetics of the
Sublime</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1991).
                            <p>Grant’s “Visions in Vala” and Cettina Tramontano Magno and David V.
Erdman’s “Commentary on the Illuminations” in <hi rend="i">“The Four Zoas” by William Blake:
Photographic Facsimile of the Manuscript with Commentary on the Illuminations</hi> (Lewisburg: Bucknell UP;
London and Toronto: Associated University Presses, 1987) pp. 25-102, provide the most helpful accounts of the
designs.</p></note></p>
          <p>This neglect is in part due to the manifold difficulties of the poem. As Ault writes, 
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is the most uncanonical, unmanageable, and recalcitrant text Blake ever wrote. The
poem’s internal operations exceed the possibility of mastery by virtue of their heterogeneity and
complexity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> These difficulties are
generated in part by two factors: the assumption that after <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
Swedenborg exerted no significant influence on Blake’s artistic practice or iconography;<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> and the still widespread commitment in Blake
studies to an idealizing, logocentric (rather
<pb id="p35-5" n="5"/>
than prophetic) imagination.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> The
first discounts the most important context for the poem’s illuminations; the second leads viewers to
downplay or ignore the poem’s powerful representations of the tormented, suffering body of humanity. 
<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Ault, <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound</hi> xviii. Pierce, <hi rend="i">Flexible
Design</hi> xv, writes that “the unfinished state of all but the drawings on the first few pages leaves the
reader lost in a field of conjecture with no firm basis for argument.”</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> See, for example, Joseph Viscomi, “The Lessons of Swedenborg; or, The
Origin of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Lessons of
Romanticism: A Critical Companion</hi>, ed. Thomas Pfau and Robert F. Gleckner (Durham and London: Duke UP,
1998). The most useful overview of Blake’s relation to Swedenborg is Morton Paley’s “‘A New Heaven is
Begun’: William Blake and Swedenborgianism,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12: 64-90.
Paley identifies four distinct phases of Blake’s response to Swedenborg. In the first, “From the late
1780s until 1790, Blake’s attitude was studious and respectful; even in disagreeing with Swedenborg during
these years, Blake expresses himself so as to put the most optimistic construction upon Swedenborg’s
doctrines.” In the second stage (1790), “Blake repudiated Swedenborg vehemently in the marginalia to 
<hi rend="i">Divine Providence</hi>, and he wrote at least part of the satire of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi>” (64). The third stage spans the “decade following the beginning of <hi rend="i">The
Marriage.</hi>” During this time, Paley writes, “there is little to indicate Swedenborgian interests in
Blake’s poetry and art. Then from about the turn of the century and well into the nineteenth century, Blake
displays a renewed interest in (though by no means a simple attitude toward) Swedenborg” (78). It is my view
that even in the third of Paley’s four stages Blake was deeply engaged with, although at the same time
strongly critical of, the architecture and thematics of Swedenborg’s thought.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> For a critique of this aspect of Blake studies see my 
<hi rend="i">Constructive Vision and Visionary Deconstruction: Los, Eternity, and the Productions of Time in the
Later Poetry of William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991) 1-33.</note></p>
          <p>With regard to the designs, of course, difficulties also arise from the “unfinished” state of
many of the drawings and from the work of an unknown hand who erased or disguised important elements of the
most “pornographic” designs. Others are the product of Blake’s artistic practice, in particular his
penchant for creating visual fields composed of multiple (at first sight often incommensurate) interacting
elements and “layers.” This third source of difficulty is compounded by Magno and Erdman’s facsimile of
the poem, <hi rend="i">“The Four Zoas” by William Blake</hi>, published in 1987.</p>
          <p>Bentley printed his facsimile from conventional photographic prints of the manuscript. This
photographic technology was unable to reproduce many of the faint lines, partial erasures and other details
visible to the naked eye. When Magno and Erdman prepared their facsimile of the poem, they arranged for
infrared photographs to be taken.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> As
a result, they were able to reproduce many, although not all, of the details lost to Bentley. They indicated
the still significant gap between facsimile and manuscript by making “tracings and sometimes partly
conjectural redrawings of lines, to bring out particulars almost lost to the camera” (ME 17). The most
significant shortcomings of Magno and Erdman’s facsimile, however, arise from their decision to print,
without enlargement, from “the 8 × 10 inch prints . . . obtained for this work” (ME 17). Most of the
pages of Blake’s manuscript are approximately 12 3/4 × 16 1/2 inches. Where Bentley’s facsimile
reproduces these pages in full, the reproductions found in Erdman and Magno’s facsimile are approximately
one third the size of the originals. <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Prints of many of the infrared
photographs obtained by Magno and Erdman can be viewed in the British Library’s Manuscript Reading Room. See
<hi rend="i">Prints from MS Negatives</hi>, vol. 71.</note></p>
          <p>Magno and Erdman were advised that printing from the photographs, without enlargement, would
“retain their sharpness of detail” (ME 17). Unfortunately, this same strategy makes it more likely that
those details will be overlooked or seem insignificant. Moreover, diminishing the size of a visual field tends
to resolve its elements into a unity (much like seeing an engraving close-up and then at a distance).
Consequently, it becomes more likely that viewers will overlook the elements constitutive of that unity, and
the ways in which they might open other “layers” of meaning. For example, on page 90[98] of the 
<hi rend="i">manuscript</hi>, the head of the Prester Serpent can be seen as a unified whole. Equally, it can be
seen as an assemblage of incongruous parts (there is a human head, a serpentine head, and a heart-shaped
mask). In Magno and Erdman’s facsimile, the much reduced size of the Prester Serpent’s head emphasizes the
former and makes the latter much harder to see.</p>
          <p>For these reasons, it is perhaps worth mentioning that my account of the poem’s designs relies
on repeated and lengthy study of the manuscript, housed in the British Library, supplemented by the available
facsimiles (used in part as mnemonic devices). To assist readers without access to the manuscript, I have used
footnotes to describe some of the aspects of the designs not easily visible in the available facsimiles. I
have also used footnotes to draw the reader’s attention to some of the points at which my account of the
designs diverges from the account offered by Magno and Erdman.</p>
          <p>In the argument that follows, I focus on one of the varieties of phallus in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi>, namely the Urizenic or hermaphroditic phallus, as seen in the drawings on pages 24, 26,
32, 88[96], 90[98] and 112[108] of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">12</ref> I argue that the phallus is created by Urizen as a privileged image of the
absolute (God the Father/Heaven), the ultimate source and guarantor of the Law used to discipline the wayward
bodies of the fallen world. As such, it provides an important perspective on: the mechanisms deployed by
Urizen to turn living flesh into a garment appropriate for a rational spirit; the role played by the body in
its own disempowerment; and the ways in which the flesh resists the construction of a (rational) spiritual
body. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> All citations of the poem’s illuminations refer to 
<hi rend="i">“The Four Zoas” by William Blake</hi>, ed. Magno and Erdman. References to Magno and Erdman’s
“Commentary on the Illuminations” will be inserted parenthetically in the text, preceded by “ME” (e.g.
ME 50).</note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Head and the Phallus</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, it was “commonly believed that the brain was
connected to the testes by the nerves, which transmitted ‘the white or spermatic
<pb id="p35-6" n="6"/>
components’” thought to the source of life.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> Charlton, for example, publicizing and developing the views of Glisson, argued in 
<hi rend="i">Natural History of Nutrition, Life and Voluntary Motion</hi> (1659) that the testes “received the
<hi rend="i">succus</hi> [a nutritive juice] through its nerves and thus from the brain.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> In <hi rend="i">Conjugial Love</hi>,
Swedenborg gives these ideas a more spiritual inflexion when he writes of an “influx” from God through the
soul to the reason and then to the body.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> Influx opens the body to the rational/spiritual stuff of life. Consequently “the
ability and vigour called virile accompanies wisdom,” and men whose bodies are open to influx from reason
are blessed with “enduring efficacy” (433). Robert Hindmarsh draws on both medical and religious versions
of these ideas when he writes that
<q>
The characteristic peculiar to male animals is the formation of seed in themselves, which is first conceived
in the understanding, then formed in the will, and afterwards translated to the lower parts of the body, where
it is enveloped with a material covering, and thence conveyed into the wombs, and last of all brought forth
into open day.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref></q>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of
Words</hi> (Berkeley: U of California P, 1983) 92.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Edwin Clarke, “The Doctrine of the Hollow Nerve in the Seventeenth and
Eighteenth Centuries,” in <hi rend="i">Medicine, Science and Culture: Historical Essays in Honor of Owsei
Temkin</hi>, ed. Lloyd G. Stevenson and Robert P. Multhauf (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins P, 1968) 123-41.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Emanuel Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">The Delights of Wisdom concerning
Conjugial Love, after which follows The Pleasures of Insanity concerning Scortatory Love</hi>, trans. Alfred
Acton, 1953 (London: Swedenborg Society, 1970) para. 101.
                                <p>Swedenborg published <hi rend="i">Delitiae Sapientiae de Amore Conjugiali;
post quae sequuntur Voluptates Insaniae de Amore Scortatorio</hi> in Amsterdam in 1768. A first English
translation, possibly the work of H. Servanté, was published in London in 1790. Between January and June
1790, nearly a third of <hi rend="i">Delitiae Sapientiae de Amore Conjugiali</hi>, translated by the Rev. John
Clowes, was published serially in the <hi rend="i">New Jerusalem Magazine</hi> as an appendix. Clowes’s
translation, <hi rend="i">The Delights of Wisdom concerning Conjugial Love, after which follows The Pleasures
of Insanity concerning Scortatory Love</hi> was printed by R. Hindmarsh in London in 1794.</p>
	<p>For details of late eighteenth-century editions of <hi rend="i">Conjugial Love</hi> see Acton’s
“Translator’s Preface” (v-vi) and John Chadwick’s “Preface” (iii) to his new translation of 
<hi rend="i">Delitiae Sapientiae de Amore Conjugiali: The Delights of Wisdom on the subject of Conjugial Love
followed by The Gross Pleasures of Folly on the subject of Scortatory Love</hi> (London: Swedenborg Society,
1996).</p>
	<p>In this article I quote from the translation by Clowes published in 1794. References to this volume will
be inserted parenthetically in the text, citing the relevant paragraph numbers.</p></note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Robert Hindmarsh, <hi rend="i">Letters to Dr Priestly containing proofs
of the sole, supreme, and exclusive Divinity of Jesus Christ, whom the scriptures declare to be The Only God
of Heaven and Earth; and of the Divine Mission of Emanuel Swedenborg. Being a Defence of the New Church
signified by the New Jerusalem in the Apocalypse</hi> (London: R. Hindmarsh, 1792) 344-45.</note></p>
            <p>These views derive ultimately from Greek, Roman and Jewish thought. As Onians notes, “for the
Jews originally, as for the Greeks, Romans, etc., the head contained not only the life-soul . . . but also the
life-fluid, the seed, and was the source.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> In the words of one writer: “the seed is a drop of the brain containing in itself warm
vapour.” Although “we have fragments of knowledge that in the latter half of the fifth century Hippocrates
and Democritus held that the seed was drawn from the whole body,” this view was commonly coupled with the
belief that “it gathers to the spinal marrow and that most of it flows from the head.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> As Onians explains:
<q>
It was natural and logical to think that the “life” . . . issuing from a man must come from the “life”
. . . in him, from his head therefore, and, helping that location, to see in the seed, which carries the new
life and which must have seemed the very stuff of life, a portion of the cerebro-spinal substance in which was
the life of the parent.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref></q>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Richard Broxton Onians, <hi rend="i">The Origins of European Thought</hi>
(New York: Arno Press, 1973) 234 n.6. Onians, 234, notes that “In the Jewish Kabbalah . . . the liquid in
the divine head is the vehicle of life.”</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Onians, <hi rend="i">Origins</hi> 121.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Onians, <hi rend="i">Origins</hi> 109-110.</note></p>
            <p>A more immediate source of Blake’s iconography of the phallus, however, may have been Richard
Payne Knight’s <hi rend="i">A Discourse on the Worship of Priapus, And its Connexion with the mystic
Theology of the Ancients</hi>, published in London in 1786 for the Dilettanti Society.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> The winged phallus depicted on the second plate of
Knight’s book resembles the 
<pb id="p35-7" n="7"/>
winged phalli on pages 26 and 42 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Echoes of the curious, composite figures
(part man, beast and genital) found in the former can also be seen in the latter. More important than these
visual parallels, however, may have been Knight’s account of an ancient phallic religion. 
<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> It is not known whether Blake read Knight’s book. It is, however, likely that he was at
least aware of the controversy surrounding it. Giancarlo Carabelli, <hi rend="i">In the Image of Priapus</hi>
(London: Duckworth, 1996) 72, writes that “It was not until 1794 that [Knight’s] book . . . was publicly
spoken of in London . . . when the critics discovered its existence, the work was summarily dismissed and
furiously attacked as obscene.” Blake began work on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in 1797. For an account
of the public debate over <hi rend="i">A Discourse on the Worship of Priapus</hi> see pages 84-89 of 
<hi rend="i">In the Image of Priapus.</hi> For a brief account of the influence of Knight’s work on Blake see
Jon Mee, <hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm: William Blake and the Culture of Radicalism in the 1790s</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1992) 145-47.
                                <p>There are, of course, other sources for Urizen’s primitive phallic
religion. It was widely known that priapic objects were uncovered at Herculaneum (1713) and <corr type="emend">Pompeii</corr> (1748).
See, for example, Knight, <hi rend="i">A Discourse</hi> 27; Pierre d’Hancarville, <hi rend="i">Recherches
sur l’origine, l’esprit et les progrès des arts de la Grèce; Sur leur connexion avec les arts et la
religion des plus anciens peuples connus; sur les monumens antiques de l’inde, de la perse, du reste de
l’asie, de l’europe et de l’egypte</hi>, 2 vols., (Londres: B Appleyard, 1785); Pierre d’Hancarville,
<hi rend="i">Antiquites Etrusques, Grecques, et Romaines</hi>, Gravées par F.A. David, Graveur de la Chambre
&amp; du Cabinet de Monsieur, Frère du Roi, Membre de l’Acadèmie Royale des beaux Arts de Berlin, &amp;c.
&amp;c. Avec leurs Explications; Par D’Hancarville, 4 volumes (Paris L’Auteur, M. David, 1787).</p>
	<p>The “pansexual naturalistic philosophy” of Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden, in two
parts. Part I. Containing the economy of vegetation. Part II. The loves of the plants. With philosophical
notes</hi> (London: J. Johnson, 1789-91) is another important influence on Blake’s iconology of the phallus.
See Mee, <hi rend="i">Dangerous Enthusiasm</hi>, 145-60.</p></note></p>
            <p>Knight describes the diverse forms of an “ancient polytheism” that, lacking the
“artificial decency” of the modern world, represented the creative power of God “by the organ of
generation in that state of tension and rigidity which is necessary to the due performance of its
functions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Indeed,
<q>
what more just and natural image could they find, by which to express their idea of the beneficent power of
the great Creator, than that organ which endowed them with the power of procreation, and made them partakers,
not only of the felicity of the Deity, but of his great characteristic attribute, that of multiplying his own
image.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Knight, <hi rend="i">A Discourse</hi> 14, 17, 27. For a brief account of
phallic worship, see Paul Chambers, <hi rend="i">Sex and the Paranormal</hi> (London: Blandford, 1999)
57-72.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Knight, <hi rend="i">A Discourse</hi> 17.</note></q>
This iconography identifies men as conduits of divine power and women as the material body (the passive
powers) waiting to receive divine influx.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">23</ref> As Knight notes, “the chaste and pious matrons of antiquity wore round their necks and
arms” images in which
<q>
the organ of generation appears alone, or only accompanied with the wings of incubation in order to show that
the devout wearer devoted herself wholly and solely to procreation, the great end for which she was ordained.
So expressive a symbol, being constantly in her view, must keep her attention fixed on its natural object, and
continually remind her of the gratitude she owed the Creator, for having taken her into his service, made her
a partaker of his most valuable blessings, and employed her as the passive instrument in the exertion of his
most beneficial power.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref></q>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> This is, of course, a fairly common theme. Thomas Laqueur, 
<hi rend="i">Making Sex: Body and Gender from the Greeks to Freud</hi> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP, 1990) 146,
quotes William Harvey’s claim in <hi rend="i">Disputations Touching the Generation of Animals</hi> (1653),
trans. Gweneth Whitteridge (Oxford: Blackwell Scientific Publications, 1981) 165-66, that “The hen’s
acting ‘as one ravished with gentle delight’ . . . is a sign of gratitude toward the male for his godlike
act”:
<q>
She shakes herself for joy, and, as if she had now received the greatest gift, preens her feathers as if
giving thanks for the blessing of issue granted by Jove the creator. The dove . . . expresses her joy in
coitus in wondrous wise; she leaps and spreads her tail and with it sweeps the earth below her, and combs her
feathers with her beak and settles them, as if the gift of fertility did lead to the greatest glory.
</q></note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Knight, <hi rend="i">A Discourse</hi> 27-8.</note></p>
            <p>Knight was not, of course, the first person to imagine events that brought together God, the
phallus (or the male body) and the female body. In Genesis 6:4, the “mighty men which <hi rend="i">were</hi>
of old, men of renown,” are described as the product of intercourse between “the sons of God” and “the
daughters of men.” In Roman mythology, Jupiter takes the form of a swan in order to lie with Leda and a
shower of golden rain to lie with Danaë. Representations of the former, such as Marcantonio Raimondi’s 
<hi rend="i">Leda and the Swan</hi>, often explicitly coordinate the divine, the phallus, and a docile female body.
The swan/phallus becomes a vehicle for the divine seed that shapes human history. In representations of the
latter, such as Titian’s <hi rend="i">Danaë</hi>, the shower of golden rain is treated as a euphemism for
divine semen. Danaë lies passive and receptive, while an old woman holds out her apron to catch the heavenly
seed.</p>
            <p>The practices of certain eighteenth-century sects, such as the Moravian Brethren, also
coordinate the divine, the phallus and the female body in a manner broadly analogous to Knight’s primitive
religion. Zinzendorf announced that Jesus changed Pudendum to Verendum. Consequently,
<q>
what was chastised by Circumcision, in the time of the Law, is restored again to its first Essence and
flourishing State; ’tis made again equal to the most noble and respectable Parts of the Body, yea ’tis, on
Account of its Dignity and Distinction become superior to all the rest.
</q>
Indeed, Zinzendorf continues, “I consider the Parts for distinguishing both Sexes in Christians, as the most
honourable of the whole Body.” In sexual intercourse, the husband “represents for a Time the Husband of
all Souls [Jesus], and the [wife] the whole Congregation of Souls”:
<q>
When an Esther by Grace, and Sister, according to her Make, gets Sight of this Member (which is called here
the Member of the Covenant, [the phallus]) her Senses are shut up, and she holily perceives that God the Son
was a Boy. Ye holy Matrons, who, as Wives, are about your Vice-Christs, you honour that precious Sign by which
they resemble Christ, with the utmost veneration.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Quoted in Henry Rimius, <hi rend="i">A Candid Narrative of the Rise and
Progress of the Herrnhuters, commonly call’d Moravians, or, Unitas Fratrum; with a short Account of their
Doctrines, drawn from their own Writings</hi> (2nd ed; London: 1753) 48.</note></q></p>
            <p>Yet another important context for the Urizenic phalli in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is
Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">Conjugial Love.</hi> This volume describes in detail a far-reaching purgation and
reorientation of desire that concludes with the achievement of a chaste, sexual union, in which the female
body (through the conduit of the male/reason) is opened to influx from the divine. Having turned from the body
and the desires of the self, the masculine (reason and the phallus) becomes a vehicle
<pb id="p35-8" n="8"/>
for the divine fluid now able to flow from heaven to earth:
<q>
There are three (things or principles) whereof every man (<hi rend="i">homo</hi>) consists, and which follow
in an orderly connection, viz. the soul, the mind, and the body . . . Every thing which flows from the Lord
into man, flows into his inmost principle, which is the soul, and descends thence into his middle principle,
which is the mind, and through this into his last principle, which is the body: such is the nature of the
influx of the marriage of good and truth from the Lord with man; it flows immediately into his soul, and
thence proceeds to the principles next succeeding, and through these to the extreme or outermost principles;
and thus conjointly all the principles constitute conjugial love.
</q>
It is evident from the “idea of this influx,” Swedenborg continues, “that two conjugial partners are the
form of conjugial love [the marriage of good and truth] in their inmost principles, and thence in the
principles derived from the inmost” (101): the relation between man and woman repeats that between God and
the masculine mind (soul), and the mind and the body.</p>
            <p>Knight complains that
<q>
Of all the profane rites which belonged to the ancient polytheism, none were more furiously inveighed against
by the zealous propagators of the Christian faith, than the obscene ceremonies performed in the worship of
Priapus; which appeared not only contrary to the gravity and sanctity of religion, but subversive of the first
principles of decency and good order in society.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Knight, <hi rend="i">A Discourse</hi> 14.</note></q>
This repression has led to the disappearance or marginalization of such “natural” rites and the religion
to which they belong, despite Knight’s confidence that education, science and religion
<q>
may turn and embellish the currents; but can neither stop nor enlarge the springs, which, continuing to flow
with a perpetual and equal tide, return to their ancient channels, when the causes that perverted them are
withdrawn.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Knight, <hi rend="i">A Discourse</hi> 13.</note></q></p>
            <p>When writing of the phalli in Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi>, critics often adopt a similar
narrative, assuming that the phallus is a sign of the human form divine rather than of the human remade in the
image of the sempiternal. Like Knight, they hope to uncover the primitive phallus that, before the imposition
of social restraints, could be seen as a “human form” and its “balmy drops [as] the promise of a newborn
child that will ensure Creative Life” (ME 74).</p>
            <p>As I shall argue, although Blake deplored attempts to disguise the sexual ground of culture and
was critical of the cultural institutions that attempt to confine sexuality, the Urizenic phallus is not an
ideal form. Although Knight’s primitive, priapic religion parades what “civilized” religion hides, it
deploys the phallus as a symbol of practices designed to create a body that conforms to the divine. This is
why the “matrons of antiquity” described by Knight are “chaste and pious.” They strive to become
vessels of the divine rather than voluptuaries of the flesh or active in their own right. Similarly, the story
of Jupiter and Danaë is often taken as an anticipation of the annunciation, a sexual encounter in which
mortal man plays no part and the female body again plays the role of passive receptacle for divine seed.</p>
            <p>Even the sexuality praised by Zinzendorf and Swedenborg has been purged of the desires of the
flesh. Swedenborg writes that
<q>
spiritual purification may be compared with the purification of natural spirits, as effected by the chemists,
and called defaecation, rectification, castigation, cohobation, acution, decantation, and sublimation; and
wisdom purified may be compared with alcohol, which is a spirit highly rectified . . . Now whereas spiritual
wisdom in itself is of such a nature, that it grows more and more warm with the love of growing wise, and by
virtue of this love increases to eternity, and inasmuch as this is effected in proportion as it is perfected
by a kind of defaecation, castigation . . . and this by elimation and abstraction of the intellect from the
fallacies of the senses, and of the will from the allurements of the body, it is evident that conjugial love,
whose parent is wisdom, is in like manner rendered successively more and more pure, and thereby chaste (145).
</q>
Zinzendorf is still more extreme: “Our very Nature and the whole Mass of Man is infected with the Poison of
the <hi rend="i">Sinful Matter</hi>, the best remedy against which is its Fermentation in the Grave, that thus
our Saviour may produce something better.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Count Zinzendorf, <hi rend="i">Sixteen Discourses on the Redemption of
Man by the Death of Christ. Preached at Berlin, by the Right Reverend and most illustrious Count Zinzendorf,
Bishop of the Ancient Moravian Church</hi>, trans. from the High Dutch (London: James Hutton, 1740)
11.</note></p>
            <p>In Urizen’s religion the phallus is worshipped because its rise above the body, “involving
as it does an apparent suspension of the laws of gravity,” anticipates the resurrection. In contrast to the
flesh—which is soft, multifaceted, polymorphous in its pleasures—the phallus is unbending, singular,
unequivocal. For Urizen it provides, therefore, an apt symbol of the static, law-abiding order of his heaven
and synecdoche of the disciplined body he labors to construct
<pb id="p35-9" n="9"/>
in this world. The phallus, in other words, is for Urizen the most important (material) image of the mind’s
immaterial essence.</p>
            <p>Hart and Stevenson observe that “When a man or a woman is imagined as aroused but not yet
sexually united with a partner, terms carrying strong ascensional connotations are usual: the man is erect,
the woman’s heart may ‘flame up and burn with love’ . . . Both may look forward to a time when they will
achieve a state of heavenly bliss.” Yet “When the two are sexually joined, it is common for the
upward-tending language and imagery to give way to something predominantly horizontal: <hi rend="i">coire</hi>
means to go or come together; <hi rend="i">congressus</hi> is a mutual walking or proceeding; a 
<hi rend="i">coniunx</hi> is yoked to a partner.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref> The Urizenic phallus resolves this tension between vertical and horizontal movements by
dividing one from the other, separating transcendent from mortal faculties, forms congruent with the eternal
from the supposed chaos of the flesh. In the drawing on page 132 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Urizen
wears his penis on his buttocks.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref>
This pliant, flaccid organ represents everything that he wants to put behind him. In contrast, the organ that
Urizen worships is divided from the body that supports it. In the pages of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> it
is most commonly seen rising above the earth or standing alone. The Urizenic phallus is the paradoxical symbol
and product of Urizen’s disavowal of the flesh: it embodies the desire to be disembodied. 
<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Clive Hart and Kay Gilliland Stevenson, <hi rend="i">Heaven and the Flesh: Imagery of Desire
from the Renaissance to the Roccoco</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995) 3.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Magno and Erdman write that “The standing giant seems to have a coat
with short tails, though just possibly we are meant to see his genitalia from behind” (96). The coat
tails/genitalia, however, are hung too high (almost from the waist) to be confused with a penis and
scrotum/testes glimpsed from behind.</note></p>
            <p>The desire to cast off the flesh and become one with God is a common theme in the literature of
religion. Vaughan asks the “Father of eternal life” to
<q>
Either disperse these mists, which blot and fill<lb/>
My perspective (still) as they pass,<lb/>
Or else remove me hence unto that hill,<lb/>
Where I shall need no glass.
</q>
He longs for “that night! where I in him / Might live invisible and dim.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> Young writes that we are angels whose true nature lies apart
from the material world:
<q>
Angels are Men in lighter Habit clad,<lb/>
High o’er celestial Mountains wing’d in Flight;<lb/>
And Men are Angels, loaded for an Hour,<lb/>
Who wade this miry Vale, and climb with Pain,<lb/>
And slippery Step, the Bottom of the Steep.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">32</ref>
</q>
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> offers a critique of these aspirations, and the concomitant desire to shape
the material body into one that does not betray the soul/reason’s supersensible destiny. Central to this
critique is Blake’s account of the phallus as the product of a profound re-shaping of the body and
re-orientation of its energies. The focalization of sexual desire in the phallus is the product of culture
rather than nature: it is a phenomenon that Urizen must labor to achieve. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi>
Henry Vaughan, “They are all gone into the world of light” and “The Night” in <hi rend="i">The
Complete Poetry of Henry Vaughan</hi>, ed. French Fogle, Stuart Editions (New York: New York UP, 1965) 270-71,
323-25.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Stephen Cornford, ed., <hi rend="i">Edward Young, “Night
Thoughts”</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1989) Night IV, lines 20-25.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Marriage of Love and Wisdom</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The [second] night of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> begins <hi rend="i">in medias res</hi>,
with Albion “Rising upon his Couch of Death.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">33</ref> As the drawing on page 23 makes clear, however, Albion can lift only his head and right
shoulder above the couch;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">34</ref> the rest
of his body, already in an advanced stage of decomposition, is breaking into its constituent parts and appears
to be flowing away from him. For a person in the throes of death, this is as it should be. Albion’s rising
head enacts the first stages of the rational soul’s ascent from the disintegrating body. According to
Swedenborg, after casting off the “dying” body the rational soul enters the spiritual world. As Urizen
rises, however, he beholds “his Sons / Turning his Eyes outward to Self. losing the Divine Vision” (23:
1-2). This is a serious difficulty for, as Swedenborg tells us, love of God and one’s neighbor is the source
of all good, while love of self and nature is the source of all evil, turning us away from God.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> All quotations of Blake’s poetry and prose are taken from the newly
revised edition of <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman,
comm. by Harold Bloom (New York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988), and will be cited parenthetically in the text.
References to the text of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> cite page and line number in that work (e.g. 73:
1-3); references to Blake’s prose give the page number in Erdman, preceded by “E.”</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Grant, “Visions in Vala” 153, suggests that this drawing depicts
Urizen. More accurately, it depicts Urizen as the head, rising above the other Zoas and the whole man.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi> Emanuel Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">A Treatise concerning Heaven and Hell,
and of the Wonderful Things therein, as Heard and Seen</hi>, trans. William Cookworthy and Thomas Hartley, 2nd
ed. (London: R. Hindmarsh, 1784) paras. 342, 484.</note></p>
            <p>Albion responds to this debacle as a conservative Swedenborgian: he blames Luvah (sexual
desire) for his plight and hands his Scepter to Urizen (23: 7,5). According to Swedenborg, “It is well
known, that the Head governs and controuls the Body under it, for in the Head reside the Understanding and the
Will, and from the Understanding and the Will, the Body is acted upon, insomuch that the Body is nothing but
Obedience.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref> By ceding his
authority to Urizen, Albion hopes to bring his body into congruence with the rational-spiritual and so prove
worthy of heaven. Abjuring the influence of the hell beneath him, Urizen must
<pb id="p35-10" n="10"/>
set to work to reshape the world in the image of the divine: he must create a spiritual-natural, a body
passively receptive of divine (rational) influx.</p>
            <p>According to Swedenborg, the divine is composed of both Love and Wisdom, Essence and Existence.
The latter, like the former, are
<q>
distinctly one . . . for Love is Essence, and Wisdom is Existence, inasmuch as Love doth not exist but in
Wisdom, nor Wisdom but from Love; wherefore, when Love is in Wisdom then it existeth.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">37</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> Emanuel Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">The Wisdom of Angels, concerning Divine
Love and Divine Wisdom</hi>, trans. N. Tucker (London: W. Chalklen, 1788) para. 25.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi> Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi> para.
14.</note></q>
As this suggests, the Divine Soul (Love, Essence) cannot be imagined outside of the Divine Body (Wisdom,
Existence). Indeed,
<q>
That a Soul can exist without a Body, and exercise Thought and Wisdom, is an Error proceeding from Fallacies;
for every Soul of Man is in a spiritual Body, after it hath put off it’s (<hi rend="i">sic</hi>) material
Coverings which it carried about with it in the World.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">38</ref>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">38</hi> Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi> para.
14.</note></q>
In attempting to create a spiritual body (a spiritual-natural) distinct from the physical body and entirely
subject to reason, Urizen encounters a number of difficulties. 
                        </p>
            <p>Swedenborg allows no influx from the natural to the spiritual worlds; influx descends from God
to the angels, to reason and then to the natural world, with each level ultimately taking its form from God.
Men and angels are recipients of life rather than themselves being life.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref> In this static, hierarchical universe, order is dependent
upon a curious mixture of insight and blindness. We must allow ourselves to be shaped by God and the good
(heaven), while remaining unmoved by the desires of the self and the body (hell). In the absence of this
influx, faced with a resurgence of the “selfish” energies of the body, Urizen must actively shape
recalcitrant flesh into forms consonant with the divine. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Swedenborg, 
<hi rend="i">Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi> paras. 4-6. Swedenborg’s doctrine of “use” does imply a
limited return circulation from below to above. However, this circulation merely returns to the higher realms
what they have given to the lower. It defines a hierarchy (in which lower realms are for the use of the
higher) and a teleology (in which the lower realm returns to the purported source of its life). The cycle of
use always begins with the higher realms. Moreover, the return of lower to higher realms is itself driven by
God and not by anything within those realms. See <hi rend="i">Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi> paras. 65-68
and 316.
                                <p>In his annotations to <hi rend="i">Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi>
(1788), Blake focuses on passages which suggest, sometimes in contradistinction to the main thread of
Swedenborg’s argument, the equality of spirit and body. Love, Blake notes in an annotation to para. 419,
“does not receive influx thro the understanding” (E 608). And in an annotation to para. 432, he writes
that “Heaven &amp; Hell are born together” (E 609). When Swedenborg writes that “there is a Progression
from first Principles to Ultimates, and from Ultimates to first Principles” (para. 316), Blake ignores the
hierarchical relation between Principles and Ultimates in Swedenborg’s thought and writes instead: “A
going forth &amp; returning” (E 607). Read in context this phrase can be taken to imply, contra Swedenborg,
the possibility and desirability of both natural and spiritual influx. In Blake’s annotations to 
<hi rend="i">Divine Providence</hi> (1790), the attempt either to place the most positive construction on or to
reform Swedenborg’s thought is displaced by vigorous criticism.</p></note></p>
            <p>The most striking of Urizen’s difficulties, however, arise from the fact that, in the
universe of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Love and Wisdom are separate powers (Luvah and Urizen) with
separate emanations (Vala and Ahania). The reduction of love to <hi rend="i">Esse</hi> that is “in” and
realized as “wisdom” therefore involves a fundamental reorganization of the psyche. First, Love (Luvah)
must be divided from his emanation (Vala) and his energy rerouted to serve Urizenic ends. Second, Vala must be
forced to take the shape of Urizen rather than Luvah. This will involve the emergence of her rational,
spiritual form from her fleshly self which will then be cast off. Third, wisdom must be driven by love, but in
a manner that does not disturb the equipoise of reason. The form constructed to meet these criteria can be see
on page 24 (fig. 1).</p>
            <p>Immediately below and to the left of lines five and six — “Luvah &amp; Vala trembling &amp;
shrinking, beheld the great Work master [Urizen]/ And heard his Word!” (24: 5-6)—floats a figure that is
ambiguously a large phallus <hi rend="i">and</hi> an armless and headless woman, whose feet have both been
severed above the ankle.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">40</ref> The top of
the phallus is suggested by the woman’s breasts and its trunk by her torso. Magno and Erdman speculate that
“At the place of her vulva there was something (much erased) resembling a keyhole—perhaps symbolizing the
guilt that forbids sexual intercourse.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">41</ref> This chaste, mutilated, phallic form is Vala as a spiritual-natural body, shaped in
accordance with Urizenic wisdom. At the bottom of the page, the natural Vala, divided from her spiritual form,
constrained by the “ropes and nets” (ME 38) of Urizen, sinks into the abyss. Vala assumes her spiritual
body as her natural, sexual body undergoes confinement and exile. <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">40</hi> In the
manuscript, this figure is not quite as faint as it appears in either of the facsimiles. Viewing the
manuscript, there can be little doubt that the breasts and shoulders of this figure were drawn to resemble the
head (and the torso the upper portion of the trunk) of a large circumcised phallus.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
Blake</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale UP, 1981) 2 vols., 1: 278, writes that “in the left margin there is a
phallic form, perhaps a figure.” Magno and Erdman reverse the emphasis of Butlin’s description: they see
“the torso of a female with legs apart but with neither head nor feet.” The figure does have “a phallic
appearance”; but because “knees, even the right kneecap, can be made out; also the double bulge of
breasts,” they imply that this is likely to be fortuitous (ME 38). Butlin, Magno and Erdman assume that this
curious figure must be <hi rend="i">either</hi> a phallus or the torso of a woman. A deconstructive or
romantic postmodern reader might argue that it is impossible to decide and that, consequently, this drawing
creates a stumbling block for the rational understanding. In this case, however, the oxymoron of a female (or
hermaphroditic) phallus nicely evokes the violence and absurdity of the marriage of Love and Wisdom (as
imagined by Swedenborg).</note></p>
            <pb id="p35-11" n="11"/>
            <figure n="BB209.1.24.MS.enhanced" rend="file" width="785" height="1000">
              <head>1 <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 24. Ms. 39764.</head>
              <figDesc>By permission of The British Library.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>To close one’s body in a rigid form is inevitably to confine the active powers that once
animated it. To construct the Urizenic phallus is, in other words, also to build Urizen’s “Furnaces of
affliction” (25: 40), which he will use to smelt Luvah into malleable form. Urizen sees “Vala 
<hi rend="i">incircle round</hi> the furnaces where Luvah was clos’d” (26: 1; my italics). Vala is both the
inside and outside surface of the Urizenic world that confines Luvah. Like the bodies of the pious, from the
outside she is dominated by Reason/God; from inside, however, she maintains a relation with repressed desire
(Luvah). On the one hand, Luvah’s energy now drives (is consumed by) Vala/Urizen’s body; on the other
hand, the same body compresses Luvah, thereby generating the heat that will reduce him to “molten metal”
(28: 8). Both aspects are suggested by the narrator’s equivocal observation, “Vala fed in cruel delight,
the furnaces with fire” (25: 41). Vala is a “body embalmd in moral laws” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 80:
27).</p>
            <p>In brief, Urizen’s furnaces represent the congruence of three elements: Urizen’s moral
laws, Vala’s body and Luvah’s sexual energy. The first turns the second into rigid, masculine form and the
third into a liquid that can be diverted to Urizenic ends. As this suggests, and the mutilated female on page
24 demonstrates, this convergence is realized as a phallus in which the Swedenborgian conjunction of love and
wisdom is achieved. Vala and Luvah now take the form of patriarchal authority. Blake critics are often quick
to associate the phallus with revolutionary desire, forgetting that in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> it is
described as “a pompous High Priest entering by a Secret Place” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 69: 44). In 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> the Urizenic phallus “believes” it has a supersensible destiny in which the
body to which it is attached does not share.</p>
            <p>Although shaped by Urizen, Vala’s life (the life of the now chaste body) still depends on
Luvah. As he loses form, Vala’s “fires” fade until she falls “a heap of Ashes / Beneath the furnaces .
. . in living death” (28: 5-6).
<pb id="p35-12" n="12"/>
	<q>
Then were the furnaces unseald with spades &amp; pickaxes<lb/>
Roaring let out the fluid, the molten metal ran in channels<lb/>
Cut by the plow of ages held in Urizens strong hand<lb/>
In many a valley, for the Bulls of Luvah dragd the Plow<lb/>
(28: 7-10)
</q>
Love (Luvah and Vala) is now congruent with the form imposed by Urizen (wisdom): Vala has been reduced to
ashes on the surface of Urizen’s world, while Luvah is the sexual fluid contained and shaped by Urizen’s
phallus. This rigid, unbending instrument turns sexual congress into ploughing, a violent (masturbatory)
opening of a female “channel.” Urizen holds “the plow of ages” in his “strong hand” and, dragged
by “the Bulls of Luvah,” cuts “channels” in which the molten Luvah, ejaculated when the furnaces are
opened, will congeal. Luvah and Vala have been harnessed to the production of an inert, material
world/body.</p>
            <p>Although Urizen’s phallic furnaces are efficient engines for the sublimation of Luvah, the
bodies they produce are not as docile as Urizen would like. Once the emanations adopt a determinate, objective
form, they cannot be so easily bent to the ends of the active powers. In Swedenborg’s terms, passive power
(the power to receive impressions, characteristic of emanations) becomes inert:
<q>
Inert power is not a dead power, but it exists whenever a body is deprived of the power of re-acting in the
same proportion as it is acted upon, or when it has lost it’s (<hi rend="i">sic</hi>) elastic virtue; thus
the power impressed on it is absorbed [or swallowed up in it], since it does not return the same degree of
re-action, as it at first received of action.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">42</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">42</hi> Emanuel Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">An Hieroglyphic Key to Natural and
Spiritual Mysteries by way of Representations and Correspondences</hi>, trans. R. Hindmarsh (London: R.
Hindmarsh, 1792) 25.</note></q>
This poses no difficulties for the rational power described by Swedenborg, which he imagines as standing
midway between heaven and hell, God and the selfish desires of the body. Indeed, Swedenborg suggests that the
spiritual-natural forms a barrier that divides us from the hell of the body. In <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, however, Urizen is housed <hi rend="i">within</hi> the body, without access to divine influx.
Consequently, at the moment when the body as a whole assumes rigid, phallic form, Urizen finds that he been
engulfed by the female body he had hoped to escape. The designs on page 26 (fig. 2) explore these difficulties
as a struggle between, on the one hand, rising and penetrating powers (phallus) and, on the other hand,
opening and enclosing powers (vagina). This struggle is driven by the phallus’s attempt to rise above the
(feminine) body that supports it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">43</hi> With regard to the “objective” description of the elements of this
design and the assumption that its figures form a sequence “that can be read from the top of the page to the
bottom,” my account broadly follows that offered in “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” <hi rend="i">by
William Blake.</hi> Magno and Erdman, however, describe the interaction of the design’s elements only in the
most general terms (the “four stages of metamorphoses . . . combine love and hate, humanity and
monstrosity,” etc.) and they assume that the design’s visual narrative constitutes “a prophecy of true
progression” rather than, as I argue, the cycle of phallic sexuality. In order to establish this positive
progression, they ignore the complex interaction between male and female powers, and the involvement of Urizen
(and the desire for transcendence) in these metamorphoses.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Phallic Sexuality</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Towards the top of the left-hand margin of page 26, Blake drew a small figure with frizzy hair,
butterfly wings and small legs, which trail beneath a swollen belly and large pendulous breasts implying that
she is heavy with child. A line drawn down the centre of the belly allows one to construe the same figure as a
large vulva. This flying, breasted, vulva-womb is an apt representation of the sensuous world (Vala) described
by Luvah as “the cold &amp; dark obscure” and by Urizen as “the Abyss” (23: 15).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">44</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">44</hi> For Magno and Erdman, the page’s “prophecy of true progression”
begins here. They identify this figure as “the Earth-worm” “calld forth” by Luvah “from the cold
&amp; dark obscure” (26: 7). As there is nothing that associates this figure with an Earth-worm, they
contend (however improbably) that the figure “depicts a ‘worm’ [an Earth-worm?] in butterfly form.”
Although Luvah does not portray the Earth-worm as an overtly positive figure, Magno and Erdman conclude that
the butterfly-worm is “an emblem of hope and humor: a droll creature with girlish, winking face” (39). It
seems more straightforward, however, to associate this first figure with “the cold &amp; dark obscure,”
the feminine world seen from the point of view of Luvah who, imprisoned within the furnaces of Urizen, is able
to recall the steps that led to his confinement only by “Reasoning from the loins” (28: 2). As Brenda S.
Webster writes, the figure’s “whole body suggests a voracious sexual organ” [<hi rend="i">Blake’s
Prophetic Psychology</hi> (London and Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1983) 213]. This is the sexual, fleshly
“abyss”/ womb above which the phallus wants to rise.</note></p>
            <p>Immediately beneath the vulva-womb woman is a large bat-winged phallus, beneath which hangs a
scrotum and two large testicles (fig. 2a). A woman has wrapped her arms around the trunk of this creature. Her
legs trail beneath the scrotum; her head has been pushed to one side by the phallus. In the text, Vala feeds
the fires of the furnace and is fed by them. The figure clinging to the winged penis plays an analogous role:
her arms encircle the phallus, providing the friction that causes Luvah to boil and the phallus to rise. This
creates the impression that the woman (like Vala) is being fed by Luvah, lifted with the phallus. Her
elevation, however, is short-lived. The narrator reports that when Luvah is “quite melted,” the “fires
of Vala” fade. Similarly, in Luvah’s account of these events, the appearance of the dragon is followed by
the Flood, which submerges the body (26: 12-14). The third figure echoes both of these narratives.</p>
            <p>Here, the upward thrust of the flying phallus appears to have loosened the hold of the clinging
female figure, causing her to fall downwards and establishing a division between
<pb id="p35-13" n="13"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.26.MS.enhanced" rend="file" width="792" height="1000">
	<head>2. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 26. Ms. 39764.</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of The British Library.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="BB209.1.26.MS.detail" rend="file" width="300" height="373">
	<head>2a. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 26 (detail). Ms. 39764.</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of The British Library.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
male and female, “rational” and physical portions of the self<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">45</ref> The upper half of the figure is once again a flying phallus, attached to a
hairy scrotum. Unlike its precursor, it is capped by a bird’s head with a single eye, and its bat-wings have
two rather than four segments. The bird-phallus is able to elevate itself above the female body, but cannot
entirely separate itself. It brings with it a pair of “scaled thighs which grow together to form a
mermaid’s body that trails off into four absurd filaments” (ME 39). Immediately beneath the scrotum, at
the top of the mermaid body, is a darkly drawn vulva, echoed by the giant vulva formed by its “scaled
thighs.” This female body is a creature of the watery, material realm precipitated by the elevation of
Urizen and the sublimation of Luvah. It is the unwanted “shadow” of the bird-phallus. 
<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">45</hi> Magno and Erdman ignore the implied struggle and binary opposition between male and female
portions of this creature. They see only “male and female organs fused into a unity” (39).</note></p>
            <p>Unable to divide himself from his female body, the bird-phallus must reform it, turning the
natural into a spiritual-natural that corresponds to the dictates of (Urizenic) reason. In the third figure,
this process has already begun: the phallic bird’s neck is turned and his beak bent towards the vulva, as if
he were about to enter his own body. The result of this intercourse can be seen in the remarkable drawing of a
female dragon at the bottom of the page, which turns the previous figure inside out.</p>
            <p>The human face of the female dragon is stylized and elegant, with one strand of hair falling
casually in front of her face. This dragon is so domesticated that her arms and legs have atrophied. The
latter trail uselessly behind her; the hands or paws of the former have been replaced by “elegant” fans.
Two, perhaps three, breasts hang from her body. Two large wings hold her aloft, ensuring she remains an
unobtainable object of desire.</p>
            <p>The most surprising feature of this dragon is her masculine interior, implied by her segmented
wings (previously attached to male rather than female bodies) and her long, serpentine neck (which echoes the
neck of the bird-phallus). The neck appears to be an extension of the long, serpentine tail that has thrust
her legs apart and trails behind her. Like the two figures immediately above her (and Enion on page 7), this
dragon is a hermaphrodite; unlike her precursors, however, the winged dragon’s female body is now
<pb id="p35-14" n="14"/>
no more than the exterior to the phallic interior. She is the chaste, domestic woman: yet another version of
the spiritual-natural whose form corresponds to the rational.</p>
            <p>The dragon realizes the ideal phallic female depicted in embryo on page 24: his/her docile
exterior is completely subservient to his/her rational (masculine) interior. Yet the achievement of this state
also brings its demise, taking the sequence we have been tracing back to its beginning. By subduing the female
power, the male power closes himself within “the cold and dark obscure” of the body it has created. Urizen
must once more resume his efforts to rise above the body.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">46</ref>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">46</hi> Magno and Erdman conclude their discussion of the fourth figure by
suggesting that it is only from Luvah’s perspective (from within “the furnaces of affliction”) that the
hermaphroditic dragon appears monstrous. They write that “the movement of the hair and wings, the hands
fanned like all-reaching pinnae, the swollen breasts and the belly and legs assimilated to the phallic serpent
tail: all express the passion of the female—to capture the male organ?—to transform it into a baby to
feed” (ME 39). It is my view that the opposition between withdrawal from and engulfment by the female body
(the phallic attempt to rise above and the subsequent fall into the female body) are complementary parts of
the Urizenic sexual economy represented on page 26.</note></p>
            <p>As I have argued, the text of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> describes determinate bodies as
the product of a bizarre sexuality in which Urizen’s phallus is both the source of seed (the furnaces) and
the instrument for opening female channels to receive that seed (the plough). These phases of Urizenic
sexuality correspond, respectively, to the rising bat-phallus and the delving bird-phallus. At the same time,
the designs emphasize that rigid bodies are not achieved once and for all; they rest on a vigorous, unending
attempt to subdue the female body.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">47</ref>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">47</hi> Grant, “Visions in Vala” 153-60, offers a valuable description of,
and a useful critique of earlier commentary on, this design. However, he misleadingly describes the composite
creatures on page 26 as “female figures . . . driven by desire but . . . unable to satisfy each other in
spite of their ostensible readiness to do so” (160). See also Claire McCarthy, “‘Terrors of the
Uncertain’: Mapping the Feminine in William Blake’s ‘Vala or The Four Zoas’,” thesis (M.A.), U of
Melbourne, 1998, 60-62; Brenda S. Webster, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology</hi> 213-14.</note></p>
            <p>The absurdity of the phallic desire for transcendence is well illustrated by the winged phallus
on page 42 that, having detached itself from the body, rises into the air. Although the phallus has managed to
rise some distance above the earth/body, it is still attached to a string held in the left hand of a naked
woman who raises her right hand as if to swat it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">48</ref> From this perspective, the winged phallus is no more than a plaything of the very powers
it hopes to escape, doomed to a cycle in which each rise is followed by a fall. This cycle does not, of
course, qualify its status as a symbol of the transcendent. The periodic rise of the phallus is, for the
believer, a compelling sign of a power in excess of the flesh: it offers an image of the resurrection that
will one day lift us above the temporal world. On page 88[96], three believers prostrate themselves before a
huge phallus resting on two large testicles (fig. 3). The phallus is worshipped because, like the flying
penis, it rises above both women and the body. It is an emblem of a religion that treats death as the path to
life.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">49</ref>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">48</hi> As the string does not quite reach the winged phallus, it is possible to
argue that the latter is on the verge of escape. At best, however, its chances of escape are slim. This
one-eyed bird-phallus is presumably “blind” and therefore cannot see that the transcendental realm it
desires does not exist. If it is to escape death it must return to the body from which it has been
severed.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">49</hi> Although they note that the design on page 88[96] depicts “The hidden
wonders allegoric . . . Of secret lust” (4-5), Erdman and Magno are unwilling to see either the phallus or
the worshippers as entirely negative. They write: “The appearance here of an eyed penis should perhaps be
taken to signify a contrary view to the pagan penis-worship of pages 39-42, a view of its human form that can
see in its balmy drops the promise of a newborn child that will ensure Creative Life. Cannot the bowing
figures be the Three Wise men?” (ME 74). There is no evidence in the poem to support either
suggestion.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Phallic Institutions</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>As Urizen tightens his grip on the world, life becomes congruent with phallic forms. A key
moment in these developments occurs in Night the Seventh, when Urizen establishes “Trades &amp; Commerce”
and constructs a Temple ([95]: 25; 88[96]: 1), the institutional forms of his religion. The phallus
establishes a rigid order which turns the body into a furnace, melting Luvah (sexual energy) into a liquid
substance which can then be directed to Urizenic ends. Similarly, “Trades &amp; Commerce” establish a
nascent global order at one remove from local cultures. Humanity is sacrificed to the demands of this inhuman,
“non-material” order: “slaves in myriads in ship loads burden the . . . deep”; “children are sold to
trades / Of dire necessity” and forced to labor “day &amp; night till all / Their life extinct they [take]
the spectre form in dark despair” ([95]: 29, 26-8).</p>
            <p>From the outside, the Temple speaks of eternal rather than temporal things. Like the phallus
worshipped on page 88[96], the Temple solidifies the physical organ which is its archetype, enlarges it and
severs it from the body, teaching believers that eternal life depends on the death of the body. At the centre
of the phallus on page 88[96] can be seen the small space that contains the tormented and molten Luvah; the
small congregation who worship this phallus emulate this form, rolling themselves into a ball to hide their
own genitals. Similarly, “in [its] inner part” Urizen creates a “Secret place”
<q>
That whosoever enterd into the temple might not be-hold<lb/>
The hidden wonders allegoric of the Generations<lb/>
Of secret lust when hid in chambers dark the nightly harlot<lb/>
Plays in Disguise in whisperd hymn &amp; mumbling prayer<lb/>
(88[96]: 1, 2, 3-6)
</q>
<pb id="p35-15" n="15"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.96.MS.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="587">
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 88[96] (detail). Ms.
39764.</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of The British Library.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
The walls of the temple, therefore, allow Urizen to hide the fact that his frozen heart and phallus are the
correspondent forms not only of an unmoving heaven but of his perverted sexuality as well. During the day he
wages a public war against the body. During the night he is the prime actor in “secret religion” (88[96]:
18). Rather than being “open, seeking / The vigorous joys of morning light” (<hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 6:
5-6), the phallus, temple, and believer shelter a “secret lust” that plays beneath “hymn” and
“prayer.”</p>
            <p>Urizen’s Commerce, Trades and Temple sketch, on the surface of the world, an ideal,
(apparently) non-material order that, contrary to appearances, rests on a profound sublimation and rerouting
of desire and imagination. Even the sun (emblem of Los and Orc) is dragged into his temple “to give light to
the Abyss / To light the War by day to hide his secret beams by night” (88[96]: 15-16).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Phallic Selves</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake depicts the open-ended, active life of Eternity (as opposed to the sempiternality of
Urizen’s closed heaven) as forged in relations of brotherhood and equality between the Zoas or faculties of
Albion. The transformation of these relations in the macrocosm, wrought by Urizen’s phallic religion, is
repeated in the microcosm. The phallic dynamic constitutive of trades, commerce and religion can also be
identified in the body and psyche of the individual. Perhaps the most striking of Blake’s many analyses of
the psyche fostered by Urizenic religion can be found in the drawing on page 90[98] of the Prester Serpent,
“with human face and cobra hood” (fig.4). As Magno and Erdman note, if we consider the serpent’s head to
be Urizen’s, “we may take the three coils to be the other Zoas, reduced to headless articulations” (ME
75).</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, Milton writes that prior to the Fall the serpent did not
move
<q>
with indented wave,<lb/>
Prone on the ground, as since, but on his rear,<lb/>
Circular base of rising folds, that towered<lb/>
Fold above fold a surging maze, his head<lb/>
Crested aloft, and carbuncle his eyes;<lb/>
With burnished neck of verdant gold, erect<lb/>
Amidst his circling spires, that on the grass<lb/>
Floated redundant<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">50</ref>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">50</hi>John Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, Book XI, lines 496-503, in
<hi rend="i">The Poems of John Milton</hi>, ed. John Carey and Alastair Fowler (London and Harlow: Longmans,
Green, 1968) 886-87.</note></q>
Arguably, the Prester Serpent is the product of an attempt to force the material body into a form
correspondent with this unfallen, elevated creature. As such, it embodies the Urizenic struggle to divide
spirit from body, reason from the flesh. Like the periodically tumescent phallus, the head of the Prester
Serpent finds itself attached to a material body that he can periodically rise above but not leave behind.
Nevertheless, the Prester Serpent claims to be the “Priest of God,”
<pb id="p35-16" n="16"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.98.MS.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="627">
	<head>4. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 90[98] (detail). Ms. 39764.</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of The British Library.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
with divine authority to “Go forth &amp; guide [God’s] battles” (90[98]: 23, 25).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">51</ref> He represents another, parodic version of the
rational body desired by Urizen. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">51</hi> In the context of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, the association of the Prester Serpent with the cobra and the priesthood is apt. A “Prester” is
“A serpent, the bite of which was fabled to cause death by swelling” (<hi rend="i">OED</hi>). Thomas
Pennant notes this effect of the Prester’s venom before comparing it with the <hi rend="i">Torrida
dipsas.</hi> He writes: “both serpents inhabit dry, hot, and rocky places; and they live on insects full of
saline and acrimonious particles, which cannot fail of exalting the <hi rend="i">virus</hi> of the serpents
that make them their food.” See Thomas Pennant, <hi rend="i">The View of Hindoostan</hi>: vol. 1, 
<hi rend="i">Western Hindoostan</hi> (London: Printed by Henry Hughs, 1798) 199.
                                <p>The cobra, like the Prester Serpent depicted on page 90[98], is able to
elevate the front third of its body, making it a good symbol of Urizen’s phallic religion. Pennant writes
that when the Cobra de Capella “is agitated by some passion, such as fear, or rage, it then quits its
creeping attitude, raises the fore part of the body a third of its whole length, spreads its hood, and moves
its head around, darting a fiery glare to every part, often remaining in all other respects immoveable . . .
it is often represented twisted round the deities, under the name of <hi rend="i">Calengam</hi>, in memory of
the victory of one of their gods, over an enormous <hi rend="i">Naja</hi> [serpent]” (<hi rend="i">Western
Hindoostan</hi>, 197-8). The Cobra de Capella, he writes, is a “frequent” attendant on “the brain-sick
deities of the country” (<hi rend="i">The View of Hindoostan</hi>: vol. 2, <hi rend="i">Eastern
Hindoostan</hi>, 277).</p>
	<p>Pennant also describes the Cobra de Morte, a “most fatal reptile” which, he notes, “has on its head
the marks of a scull, and two cross bones, perhaps imaginary.” His description is repeated by Francis
Wrangham in a footnote to his “The Restoration of Learning in the East.” See Francis Wrangham, 
<hi rend="i">The Holy Land; A Poem on the Restoration of Learning in the East; Joseph made known to his Brethren;
A Few Sonnets Attempted from Petrarch; Hendecasyllabi</hi>, intro. by Donald H. Reiman (New York and London:
Garland, 1978) 14, 24n.</p>
	<p>In the art of ancient Egypt, the cobra is depicted “as a rearing serpent, the divine-royal uraeus cobra
. . . Whether she is on the king’s forehead, a part of his titulary, or represented as decorative ornament,
the uraeus, ‘the risen one,’ is consistently associated with Horus, the king.” See Sally B. Johnson, 
<hi rend="i">The Cobra Goddess of Ancient Egypt: Predynastic, Early Dynastic, and Old Kingdom Periods</hi> (London
and New York: Kegan Paul, 1990) 11.</p></note></p>
            <p>Without arms or legs, the bulk of his body serves only to support his head, positioned at the
center of his cowl. At first sight, the cowl is a body that mirrors the serpent’s human head. Both are round
in outline, and the heart-shaped space at the front of the cowl, through which the serpent looks, repeats the
shape of his face. The Prester Serpent, it seems, is a temporal form correspondent with the eternal: he
represents divine love (the heart) perfectly in accord with divine wisdom (the head). Yet this is an
appearance designed to disguise a less palatable reality. The serpent’s heart-shaped face is in fact a mask,
quite distinct from what one assumes is a human head behind it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n52" type="note">52</ref> Moreover, the mask
<pb id="p35-17" n="17"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.98.MS.detail2" rend="file" width="526" height="542">
	<head>4a. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 90[98] (detail).</head>
	<figDesc>Ms. 39764. By permission of The British Library.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
disguises a serpent’s head.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">53</ref> From
the tip of the serpent’s head (just above the human eyes), his forked tongue extends to outline the upper
portion of the “heart” (fig. 4a). <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">52</hi> Erdman and Magno make no mention of
the complex, “layered” structure of the Prester Serpent’s face. In their facsimile, the dramatic
reduction in size of this design tends to resolve the face into a seamless whole. Bentley’s facsimile offers
a more accurate reproduction of this aspect of the manuscript.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">53</hi> This can be difficult to see (particularly in Magno and Erdman’s
facsimile) because, like a Gestalt diagram, viewers must see as the figure what they had first taken to be the
ground (and vice versa). It is also difficult to describe clearly and succinctly. Nevertheless, the following
may be of help: on the right-hand side (from his perspective) of the Prester Serpent’s head, the line
forming his chin/mask meets one of the lines that defines the uppermost part of his trunk. At this point of
intersection, the former divides into three. Two of these “branches” go on to define the right-hand side
of the mask/face and head. A third “branch,” however, joins a continuation of the latter, which passes
across the Prester Serpent’s right cheek (giving the area around his lower nose and mouth a distinctly
“fleshy” appearance) and through the center of his right eye before curving across the center of his
forehead and finally coming to rest in his left eye. On the left-hand side of his face, a similar line (from
the left-hand side of the serpent’s chin to the serpent’s left eye) is suggested by shading, still visible
in the facsimiles. The figure formed between the curve of the Prester Serpent’s chin and the semi-circle
drawn between his eyes, defines the serpentine, as opposed to the human, head of the Prester Serpent. From the
uppermost point of this serpentine head, emerge the twin forks of his tongue.</note></p>
            <p>As I have argued, the Urizenic phallus is the product of an equilibrium between Love (Vala),
Wisdom (Reason) and sexual energy (Luvah), first glimpsed in the hermaphroditic phallus on page 24. The same
elements—Love (the heart), Wisdom (the “human” head) and sexual energy (the serpent)—form the
composite body of the Prester Serpent. From Urizen’s point of view, influx is a celestial fluid, received by
influx from heaven through the brain (wisdom), and issuing forth to create a spiritual body (love). This
drawing, however, suggests that influx has a bodily rather than heavenly origin: it is the sublimated sexual
energy formed by turning the human body into a serpent/phallus. Influx is a “poison,” manufactured in the
(disciplined) body, that enters the brain through the serpent’s mouth. It is this dynamic that the Prester
Serpent’s human mask, like Urizen’s Temple, is designed to hide.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Conjugial Love</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Like the phallus, conjugial love emulates the divine by bringing love (the woman) and wisdom
(the man) into a unitary form. Indeed, according to Swedenborg,
<q>
THE MALE AND FEMALE WERE CREATED TO BE THE ESSENTIAL FORM OF THE MARRIAGE OF GOOD AND TRUTH [love and
wisdom].<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">54</ref> The reason is, because the
male was created to be the understanding of truth, thus truth in form, and the female was created to be the
will of good, thus good in form, and there is implanted in each, from their inmost principles, an inclination
to conjunction into one . . . thus two make one form, which emulates the conjugial form of good and truth
(100).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">55</ref></q>
The “male is born that he may be made understanding, and the female” is born so
<q>
that she may be made will loving the understanding of the male; from which consideration it follows, that
conjugial conjunction is that of the will of the wife with the understanding of the man, and the reciprocal
conjunction of the understanding of the man with the will of the wife (159).
</q>
This conjunction is so far-reaching that, during one of his visits to heaven, a conjugial husband felt it
necessary to inform Swedenborg that contrary to appearances he was “not alone, my wife is with me, and we
are two, yet still not two but one flesh” (56).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">56</ref> Curiously, seen as a whole, this flesh is masculine rather than feminine or androgynous.
When a man and woman are united in a love truly conjugial, they become “an united man, and as it were one
flesh” (178).
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">54</hi> Swedenborg treats “good and truth” as equivalent to “love and
wisdom.”</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">55</hi> See also <hi rend="i">Conjugial Love</hi>, para. 101.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">56</hi> In the 1794 edition of <hi rend="i">Conjugial Love</hi> the numbers have
been accidentally transposed and this paragraph is numbered as 65.</note></p>
            <p>Swedenborg describes this congruence of male and female minds and bodies as the product of a
<hi rend="i">rejection</hi> of sexual desire and an <hi rend="i">embrace</hi> of divine influx. Although
conjugial love “commences by the love of the sex,” it does not, Swedenborg asseverates, “originate in
it.” Instead, “it originates in proportion to advancement in wisdom, and to the dawning of the light
thereof in man, inasmuch as wisdom and that love are inseparable companions” (98). Its source therefore lies
in God. As an African, in his prize-winning
<pb id="p35-18" n="18"/>
oration on “the ORIGIN OF CONJUGIAL LOVE, AND RESPECTING IT’S VIRTUE OR POTENCY” (103), explained to
representatives of nine European nations:
<q>
Ye christians deduce the origin of conjugial love from love itself; but we Africans deduce it from the God of
heaven and earth. Is not conjugial love a chaste, pure, and holy love? Are not the angels of heaven principled
therein? Is not the universal human race, and thence the universal angelic heaven, the seed of that love? And
can such a supereminent principle have existence from any other source than from God himself the creator and
preserver (<hi rend="i">statore</hi>) of the universe? Ye christians deduce conjugial virtue or potency from
various causes rational and natural; but we Africans deduce it from the state of man’s conjunction with the
God of the universe; this state we call a state of religion, but ye call it a state of the church; for when
the love is derived from that state, and is stable and permanent, it must needs operate it’s own virtue,
which is like unto it, and thus also is stable and permanent . . . this potency is described by the angels in
the heavens as the delight of perpetual spring (113).
</q>
Conjugial love is “chaste” only in the sense that it is sustained by influx from God rather than the body.
Indeed, the “delights” of conjugial love purportedly “exceed the delights of all other loves . . . for
it expands the inmost principles of the mind, and at the same time the inmost principles of the body” (68).
Sexual love lacks constancy and eventually loses its potency. In contrast, because the source of the seed that
feeds it is infinite, conjugial love knows “the delight of perpetual spring,” a permanent erection. The
“wisdom of this love opens a vein from it’s fountain in the soul, and thereby invigorates, and also
blesses with lastingness the intellectual life, which is the very essential masculine life.” As Swedenborg
observes, conjugial love makes man (<hi rend="i">homo</hi>) more a man (<hi rend="i">vir</hi>) (433).</p>
            <p>The influx of heavenly semen in turn remakes the body. Having raised conjugial love from the
body to the heavens, and so opened a conduit from heaven to the body, the body is itself transformed:
<q>
conjugial love, from the first beginnings of it’s heat, is to be elevated out of the lowest region into a
superior region, that it may become chaste, and that thereby from a chaste principle it may be let down
through the middle and lowest region into the body; and when this is the case, this lowest region is purified
from it’s unchaste principles by this descending chaste principle; hence the ultimate of that love becomes
also chaste (305).
</q>
The spiritual body formed in this manner is, however, unable finally to divide itself from the desires of the
flesh. Like the phalli on page 26, conjugial love is able to distinguish but not divide itself from the flesh:
<q>
conjugial love altogether chaste or pure hath not place with men (<hi rend="i">homines</hi>), nor with angels,
there is still somewhat not chaste or not pure, which adjoineth or subjoineth itself thereto . . . with the
angels the chaste principle is above, and the principle not chaste is beneath, and there is as it were a door
with an hinge interposed by the Lord, which is opened by determination, and is providently prevented from
standing open, lest one principle should pass into the other, and they should mix together (146).
</q></p>
            <p>As we have seen in our analyses of the phallus, Trades, Commerce, Religion and the Prester
Serpent, Blake understands Swedenborg’s heavenly influx as the product of a <hi rend="i">reorientation</hi>
rather than <hi rend="i">obliteration</hi> of sexual desire. Influx from heaven is sublimated sexual desire,
deployed to discipline the body that is its source. With this “slight” revision of Swedenborg’s ideas,
one could argue that conjugial love introduces phallic organization into relations between the genders. Like
the phallus, its form emulates an unchanging, transcendent God, bringing wisdom and love, men and women, into
an unchanging form (everlasting potency) in which the body (woman) is subservient to the mind (man) and God.
It is therefore not surprising to find in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> that relations between the sexes
take phallic form. This is most evident in the remarkable drawings on page 32 (fig. 5).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Phallic Embraces</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The curious figure on the right-hand side of page 32, described by Magno and Erdman as
“certainly a penis, though it also suggests a standing couple embracing” (ME 43), is an exemplary instance
of conjugial, phallic relations. Husband and wife together form a hermaphroditic phallus (similar to the ones
depicted on pages 24 and 30) that has grown so rigid it seems part of the vegetable world. This couple’s
emulation of the unchanging, undivided order of heaven turns difference into unity, and flexible, human bodies
into inert objects. The other couples on this page are similarly “two, yet still not two but one flesh”:
each forms the outline of a hermaphroditic phallus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">57</ref>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">57</hi> Magno and Erdman observe that all of the figures in this design
“suggest variants on the theme of planting and the theme of love, ‘in various forms,’ unrecognized”
(ME 42). It is not clear, however, in what sense the love depicted here is “unrecognized.”</note></p>
            <p>The outline of the couple immediately to the left of the phallic toadstool parallels its form.
It is as if the couple, previously locked in phallic embrace, have each taken a step backwards to look at each
other. Further to the left, a woman lies face down, draped over the top of a mound of “ripe, lodged wheat,
as if to take the ripe grain as seeds into her body” (ME 42).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">58</ref> In this conjugial relation, the woman is
<pb id="p35-19" n="19"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.32.MS.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="621">
	<head>5. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 32 (detail).</head>
	<figDesc>Ms. 39764. By permission of The British Library.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
the passive recipient of male seed. Her hands and feet are undeveloped, her legs bound together with a rope,
and a heavy object, perhaps a loadstone,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">59</ref> has been strapped to her buttocks, pressing her firmly against the mound.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">60</ref> Love again takes the form of phallic
“wisdom.” <note id="n58"><hi rend="s">58</hi> At the centre of the mound, clearly distinguished from the
stalks of wheat which, like the woman, lie across it, Blake drew what appears to be the closed top of a
(phallic?) tube. At the centre of this tube can be seen a second one, perhaps analogous to the seminal
reservoir contained by the standing phallus on page 88[96]. A third (more serpentine) cylindrical form emerges
from the left-hand side of the larger tube. Its body and curiously serrated head (a head of ripe seed?) point
in the direction of the woman’s loins. Could these rough shapes be intended to represent the active, male
forces within the seed?</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">59</hi> Magno and Erdman write only that “The woman’s rump is swollen as if
it were a pregnant belly” (ME 42).</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">60</hi> In <hi rend="i">Sympathetic Attractions: Magnetic Practices, Beliefs, and
Symbolism in Eighteenth-century England</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1996) 150-51, Patricia Fara
observes that “magnets, sexual attraction, and childbirth” were often linked: “William Harvey had
attributed to semen a powerful magnetic ability enabling it to act at a distance . . . midwifery texts
pictured the womb attracting male seed like magnets attracting iron filings . . . Women strapped loadstones to
their thighs to aid delivery or guard against miscarriage.”
                                <p>Hindmarsh observes that “In the inanimate creation we may also trace
similar representations, as in the heat and light proceeding from the sun, which are both united in one ray;
the two polar virtues of magnetism; and the two powers of electricity, called positive and negative, which are
united in one substance, as in a kind of marriage between male and female” (<hi rend="i">Letters to Dr
Priestly</hi> 344).</p></note></p>
            <p>Immediately above this mutilated woman, an exhausted man lies on the ground, his face turned
towards the reader. His equally languid partner lies across his body, her back resting on top of his
shoulders. The man’s arms cradle his head, as does the woman’s left arm, creating a form suggestive of a
large testicle. Its partner is suggested by the woman’s head, while her outstretched body becomes the
flaccid penis to which the testicles are attached.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61"
type="note">61</ref>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">61</hi> Magno and Erdman ignore the larger form traced by this couple.</note></p>
            <p>These three tableaux—the couple in erect conversation, the woman bound to phallic seed, and
the deflated lovers—are arranged in a triangle mapping the movement from erection to conception and then to
deflation. These are the steps of conjugial rather than physical love: relations between men and women are
contained by the rigid forms prescribed by Urizen, and in each stage of this cycle, women passively take the
form of male desire. Swedenborg’s claim that couples bound together by conjugial love, through conjunction,
“BECOME ONE MAN (<hi rend="i">homo</hi>) MORE AND MORE” (177) is literally true of the couples depicted
here.</p>
            <p>Above and to the left of the exhausted lovers, Blake drew a fifth couple. Despite erasure, one
can see the outline of a naked women standing on the tips of her toes. Her back is arched, head thrown
backwards and chest thrust upwards, as if she were a crescent moon. Beneath her, a man “kneels, with his
face in her long hair” (ME 42) and his right arm bent towards his genitals. Precisely what he is doing is no
longer evident, but one might speculate that this drawing originally depicted “chaste” ejaculation, the
product of masturbation
<pb id="p35-20" n="20"/>
rather than contact between the sexes. Reduced to a passive body that merely registers the actions of the
active power, she takes the form of his emanation: she arches her back and is lifted upwards, becoming a
heavenly body able only to reflect her husband’s light. Like the Urizenic ploughing and release of fluids
discussed earlier, conjugial love is, in the words of the last two lines of page 32, a process of sowing and
planting, digging of channels and the pouring “abroad” of water, in which seed and receptacle are both
formed by the rational power.</p>
            <p>On page 26, the winged dragon marks the subjugation of the female body to Urizenic desire 
<hi rend="i">and</hi> the consequent enclosure of Urizen within a rigid female form. A similar dynamic is evident
on page 32, where the embracing couple on the right, although forming a Urizenic phallus, seem in danger of
becoming a toadstool (ME 43). It is likely that the couple to the left of the phallus are investigating the
first signs of a similar reversal. The man (like Luvah on the preceding page) crosses his legs and holds his
hands behind his back. Not content with these signs of chastity, he has hung his penis behind him, beneath his
buttocks, out of sight of his partner. What the man hides, however, his partner gains. He stares with quiet
consternation at the penis that she grasps in her right hand (it is possible that she holds a second penis in
her left hand).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">62</ref>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">62</hi> The right-hand figure is identified by Magno and Erdman as at first
glance male, at second glance possibly female, and then finally as male (ME 42). The first and third choices,
however, need not entirely rule out the second. This male figure has, following the course of conjugial love,
assumed features that were once the province of his female partner. As Swedenborg notes in 
<hi rend="i">Conjugial Love</hi>: “Now whereas the soul and the mind adjoin themselves closely to the flesh of
the body, in order that they may operate and produce their effects, it follows that the union of soul and mind
with a conjugial partner is made sensible also in the body as one flesh” (178).</note></p>
            <p>By creating a chaste material body sufficiently rigid to serve as an exterior image of his
rational interior, this man inadvertently ensures that he is henceforth confined and so shaped by that body:
the active power is feminized (like Luvah on page 31), and the passive power gains a penis, emblem of her
shaping (rather than receptive) power. The other couples betray signs of the same reversal: the mutilated
woman presses down on and forms the outline of the mound of seed; the languid woman’s arm circumscribes the
head of the exhausted man; and, arguably, the back of the rising woman encloses the kneeling man. Seen from
this point in the oscillation between male and female powers, Urizen’s world is contained by a shapeless
bulb. This turns his world inside out. The material world contains the rational world, rather than forming the
dust on its periphery.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Desublimation</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Throughout <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Urizen focuses his attention on the supersensuous
and insists on a strict division between thought and body, thus relegating Ahania (his emanation) to the
margins of his world. As this suggests, Urizen also takes the form of the phallus: this rigid, solitary figure
imposes laws of chastity and obedience on his body (his emanation) in the hope that he will one day be
released from the flesh and ascend to heaven. Like the winged phallus, however, Urizen finds that he is unable
ultimately to divide himself from the body that supports him. Attempts to do so must ultimately result either
in death or a collapse back into the body. The former is the end described in the penultimate pages of the
third Night, when Urizen attempts to divide himself from Ahania. He falls
<q>
down down rushing ruining thundering shuddering<lb/>
Into the Caverns of the Grave &amp; places of Human Seed<lb/>
Where the impressions of Despair &amp; Hope enroot for ever<lb/>
A world of Darkness.<lb/>
(44: 2-5)
</q>
The latter is Urizen’s fate when, towards the end of Night the Eighth, he makes a last, desperate attempt to
reach the supersensuous. This ignoble fall into the flesh can be seen in the design on page 112[108] (fig.
6).</p>
            <p>This design depicts Ahania reclining on a “regal bed” or legless sofa. As Magno and Erdman
note, the sofa resembles a huge flaccid penis attached to two large testicles. In previous Nights, Urizen has
attempted to make life itself (the body, the individual, conjugial love, social relations) take phallic form.
It is important to note, however, that as a human faculty he remains <hi rend="i">within</hi> the phallic
forms he constructs. In the moment of desublimation, when the body’s energies are exhausted, Urizen is of
course still contained by the body. However, at this point in the cycle of Urizenic sexuality, he is “No
longer . . . Erect” (108[116]: 41). The body is now flaccid and labile. We can therefore say that, rather
than dominating the body, Urizen has become Ahania’s sofa. It is his now softened flesh that receives the
imprint of her outstretched body.</p>
            <p>One more feature of this design deserves comment: curiously, this flaccid penis/sofa has a
toenail, suggesting that it is also a big toe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">63</ref> Ernest Jones observes that “toes [and] feet . . . are in folklore and mythology, as
well as in dreams and psychoneurotic symptoms, frequently recurring phallic symbols.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">64</ref> Thus William Hamilton, in “A Letter from
Sir William
<pb id="p35-21" n="21"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.108.MS.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="563">
	<head>6. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 112[108] (detail).</head>
	<figDesc>Ms. 39764. By permission of The British Library.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
Hamilton, &amp;c. Naples, Dec. 30, 1781,” claims that participants at the “Feast of the modern PRIAPUS,
St. COSMO” described the Saint’s phallus as “the Great Toe.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n65" type="note">65</ref> Equally relevant in this context is the Swedenborgian belief that each part
of the temporal body corresponds with a portion of the Universal Human:
<q>
heavenly things in the Universal Human constitute the head, spiritual things the body, and natural things the
feet. . . . the heavenly things, which are highest, are bounded by the spiritual things, which are
intermediate; and the spiritual things are bounded by the natural things, which are lowest.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">66</ref></q>
This moral geography is no doubt one of the reasons why in the design on page 37 Ahania looks so intently at
the big toe of Urizen’s left foot. She is astonished to find, beneath Urizen’s heavenly garments, a
natural foot, and a toe that could also be part of a cloven hoof.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n67" type="note">67</ref>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">63</hi> What one takes as a significant feature of a design is in part
conditioned by what one believes the design to be about. Although the toe nail is clearly outlined, it is
likely to have been ignored by Magno and Erdman because they had no interpretative context in which this
collocation of sofa, phallus and toe (and reason/head) could make sense.</note>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">64</hi> Quoted in Hilton, <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination</hi> 163-65. See also
Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, Bollingen Series XXXV-11, 2 vols., (Princeton:
Princeton UP for the Bollingen Foundation, 1968), vol. 2, 50-51, and Schuchard, “Why Mrs. Blake Cried”
17.</note>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">65</hi> William Hamilton, “A Letter from Sir William Hamilton, &amp;c. Naples,
Dec. 30, 1781,” in Knight, <hi rend="i">A Discourse</hi> 3-8:5. See also Schuchard, “Why Mrs Blake
Cried” 17-18.</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">66</hi> Emanuel Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">The Universal Human</hi> in 
<hi rend="i">The Universal Human and Soul-Body Interaction</hi>, trans. George F. Dole, The Classics of Western
Spirituality (London: SPCK, 1984) 4938.</note>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">67</hi> The big toe of the left foot, particularly its nail, has still more
disturbing associations. See, for example, Schuchard, “Why Mrs. Blake Cried” 73-74.</note></p>
            <p>Previously Urizen has labored to ensure a relation of correspondence between head and phallus,
in which the latter acts as the material image and representative of the former.</p>
            <p>On page 112[108], however, this relation has been reversed. The head and phallus have sunk to
the lowest part of the body. Urizen has been engulfed by the body and sexual energy that he had previously
repressed.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">A Phallic Labyrinth</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Sitting on Ahania’s buttocks, an aged Cupid, without arrows and wings, is busy unstringing
his bow. Ironically, it is Ahania rather than Urizen who retains sufficient strength to raise the upper
portion of her body from her couch of death. She lifts her right shoulder from the sofa, turning her chest
toward the reader, and folds her right arm around her head. This slight divergence of their otherwise parallel
bodies is sufficient for Ahania to take stock of the Death that engulfs them both. She opens her mouth to cry
out in anguish, and holds her left hand in the same position as Urizen on page 110[106]. No doubt Ahania also
suffers pangs of conscience owing to Urizen’s unexpected collapse into the body. She asks in astonishment,
<q>
Will you seek pleasure from the festering wound or marry for a Wife<lb/>
The ancient Leprosy that the King &amp; Priest may still feast on your decay<lb/>
And the grave mock &amp; laugh at the plowd field saying<lb/>
I am the nourisher thou the destroyer in my bosom is milk &amp; wine<lb/>
(112[108]: 13-16)
</q>
	<pb id="p35-22" n="22"/>
The answer to her questions is “yes.” The Urizenic belief that life can be found only in death has
inspired humanity to “erect a lasting habitation in the mouldering Church yard” (112[108]: 11). As Ahania
laments,
<q>
alas that Man should come to this<lb/>
His strong bones beat with snows &amp; hid within the caves of night<lb/>
Marrowless bloodless falling into dust driven by the winds<lb/>
O how the horrors of Eternal Death take hold on Man<lb/>
(112[108]: 32-5)
</q>
Ahania deplores the hold death has on humanity; yet against such a formidable foe, what can she do? In her
account, humanity is the victim of horrors no human efforts could remove. The lesson to be drawn from her
lamentation is that we can do not more than prepare ourselves for the advent of the Savior, who will take us
from this world to heaven. The “phallic” congruence of passivity, fear, and death that this implies is
nicely evoked by Enion, who replies to Ahania “from the Caverns of the Grave” (113[109]: 13):
<q>
A voice came in the night a midnight cry upon the mountains<lb/>
Awake the bridegroom cometh I awoke to sleep no more<lb/>
But an Eternal Consummation is dark Enion<lb/>
The watry Grave. O thou Corn field O thou Vegetater happy<lb/>
More happy is the dark consumer hope drowns all my torment<lb/>
For I am now surrounded by a shadowy vortex drawing<lb/>
The Spectre quite away from Enion that I die a death<lb/>
Of bitter hope altho I consume in these raging waters<lb/>
(113[109]: 20-7)
</q>
Ahania’s despair and Enion’s hope are responses to the devastating effect on the body of Urizen’s
phallic religion. Their responses, however, remain within the orbit of that religion.</p>
            <p>As I have argued, the phallus rises as Urizen, confronted by death, confines the body within a
form that, he hopes, will be judged worthy of salvation. His efforts, of course, exacerbate Albion’s
suffering and sense of powerlessness. This in turn intensifies humanity’s desire for the advent of a Savior
and so brings the cycle back to its beginning. As this suggests, the phallus stands at the centre of a
labyrinth that includes its own exits within itself:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">68</ref> the desire for transcendence is both the product of and the precondition for the
labyrinth of the fallen world. <note id="n68"><hi rend="s">68</hi> Jacques Derrida, “Différance,” in 
<hi rend="i">Speech and Phenomena: And Other Essays on Husserl’s Theory of Signs</hi>, trans. David B. Allison
(Evanston: Northwestern UP, 1973) 129-60: 104.</note></p>
            <p>With regard to this type of labyrinth, humanity is both lock and key. The possibility of exodus
can be achieved only by recognizing heaven and hell as the contingent products of human actions. In 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake writes as a prophet, patiently mapping the contours of Albion’s prison,
in the hope that the relations that constitute Urizen’s primitive phallic religion can be recognized and
then changed. As Blake writes in his Notebook:
<q>
If it is True What the Prophets write<lb/>
That the heathen Gods are all stocks &amp; stones<lb/>
Shall we for the sake of being Polite<lb/>
Feed them with the juice of our marrow bones[?]<lb/>
(E 501)
</q></p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
