<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>35.3.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">35.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_35">
    <front>
      <pb id="p35-65-66" n="65-66"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.035.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="334">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            Martin Butlin Unearths Unknown Watercolors for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi><lb/>
            Robert Essick and Joseph Viscomi Revisit Blake’s Method of Color Printing<lb/>
            VOLUME 35<lb/>
            NUMBER 3<lb/>
            WINTER 2002</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-3-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="4" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
       		<head>
          	  <title>CONTENTS</title>
        	</head>
        	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Articles</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="35.3.butlin">New Risen from the Grave: Nineteen Unknown
Watercolors by William Blake</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Martin Butlin</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">68</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="35.3.essick">An Inquiry into William Blake’s Method of Color
Printing</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">74</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p35-67" n="67"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Martin Butlin was formerly Keeper of the Historic British Collection at the Tate Gallery, London.
Since retirement, he has continued to work on Blake, J.M.W. Turner, and other British artists.</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick studied printmaking at Pasadena City College in the mid-1970s. Since then, he has
continued to experiment with Blake’s etching processes and to print from facsimile plates. Selections of his
plates and prints have been shown at several exhibitions, including “William Blake and the Art of His
Time,” held at the University of California at Santa Barbara in 1976, “The Mechanised Image,” organized
by the Arts Council of Great Britain in 1978, and “William Blake’s Illuminated Prints,” held at the
Huntington Library in 1994.</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi studied printmaking at Columbia University, and identified and catalogued prints for
the Departments of Prints and Drawings at the Museum of the City of New York and Herbert F. Johnson Museum. He
was the technical consultant on the Manchester Etching Workshop 1983 facsimile of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, for
which he wrote <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated Prints</hi>, has curated numerous print
exhibitions, including “Prints by Blake and His Followers” held at the Johnson Museum, and edited 
<hi rend="i">Process &amp; Problems in Contemporary Printmaking</hi>, the exhibition catalogue of prints by John
Brody. He is the author of “Illuminated Printing” in the forthcoming <hi rend="i">Cambridge Companion to
Blake.</hi></p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr. REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson
Hilton ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey Hall 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones<lb/>
TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX: 585/442-5769<lb/>
PRODUCTION OFFICE EMAIL: sjns@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@socrates.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada. The University of
Toronto declines to forward mail.<lb/>
Email: GBentley@chass.utoronto.ca</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens GA 30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@english.uga.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill, Waldegrave Road, Twickenham TW1 4SX
England<lb/>
Email: worralld@smuc.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Addresses outside the
U.S., Canada, and Mexico require a $10 per volume postal surcharge for surface, and $25 per volume surcharge
for air mail delivery. Credit card payment available for non-U.S. subscribers. Make checks payable to 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to
Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451.
Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for information on issues and prices, or consult the web
site.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in <hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, to either of the editors:
Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of
English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by
a stamped self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a diskette, or you may send your
article as an attachment to an email message. The preferred file format is RTF. Other formats are usually
acceptable.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, American Humanities Index, Arts and
Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover: Detail of “The Gambols of Ghosts according with their affections previous to the final
Judgment.” Pen, ink and watercolor, 27.4 × 21.7 cm., 1805. Courtesy of Dominic Winter Book Auctions. 
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2002 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
    	<pb id="p35-104" n="104"/>
    	<div1>
    		<div2>
    			<div3 type="in-memoriam">David V. Erdman<lb/>
    			1911-2001</div3>
    		</div2>
    	</div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
