<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>35.4.yoder</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Henry Summerfield, A Guide to the Books of William Blake for Innocent and
Experienced Readers</title>
        <author n="Yoder">R. Paul Yoder</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">35.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Bo Ossian Lindberg</name>
              <name>R. Paul Yoder</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_35">
    <body>
	<pb id="p35-130" n="130"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Henry Summerfield. <hi rend="i">A Guide to the Books of William Blake for
Innocent and Experienced Readers.</hi> Gerrards Cross: Colin Smythe, 1998; New York: distributed in North
America by Oxford University Press. Pp. 874. £14.99/$29.95, paperback.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>R. Paul <name>Yoder</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In the preface to <hi rend="i">A Guide to the Books of William Blake for Innocent and Experienced
Readers</hi>, Henry Summerfield describes his “primary purpose” as “provid[ing] for the serious reader
of poetry, for the student, and for the scholar who is not a Blake specialist, a bridge between an initial joy
in poems of exquisite and poignant beauty and a larger engagement, at once aesthetic and intellectual, with
the lifework of a great author and artist” (11). Toward this end Summerfield provides much of the apparatus
for an edition of Blake’s poems, but without the poems themselves. As such, the book is perhaps best
considered as a companion to the two volumes to which it is keyed, David Erdman’s edition of 
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> and Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Illuminated
Blake.</hi> Especially in Part II of his book, Summerfield clearly expects his own reader also to be reading
Erdman at the same time. Indeed, without some edition of Blake’s poetry and illuminations at hand, much of
Summerfield’s book makes little sense.</p>
          <p>Part I of Summerfield’s <hi rend="i">Guide</hi>, “The Books of William Blake: An
Introduction,” is intended for those less initiated “innocent” readers, and it can be read profitably
without necessarily having an edition of Blake’s work at hand. This section is intended to provide the new
reader of Blake with an overview of the poet’s life and the development of his work. Nine of the twelve
chapters summarize Blake’s books, grouping them together in ways intended to suggest the chronological
development in Blake’s career. After the “Biographical Outline” of chapter 1, chapter 2, entitled
“Rationalism Rejected,” covers <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches, All Religions Are One, There Is No Natural
Religion, Tiriel, Songs of Innocence</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi> Chapter 3, “In Praise of
Energy,” covers <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>, followed in chapter 4, “The Lustre Fades,” by discussions of <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion, For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi>
Chapter 5, “The Myth of History,” covers <hi rend="i">America, Europe</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi>, and chapter 6, “The Myth of Creation,” the books of <hi rend="i">Urizen, Ahania</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Los.</hi> After discussions of “Blake’s Conversion,” focusing on Blake’s Felpham period under
the patronage of William Hayley (chapter 7), and “Blake’s System” (chapter 8), Summerfield’s chapter
9, “An Incomplete Structure,” summarizes <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Pickering
Manuscript.</hi> Chapter 10, “Heroic Narrative,” is devoted to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, chapter 11,
“The Forgiveness of Sins,” to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem, For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel.</hi> Chapter 12, “Masterpiece of a New Kind,” discusses 
<hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job.</hi> There is no discussion of the broadsheet <hi rend="i">On
Homers Poetry</hi> [and] <hi rend="i">On Virgil</hi> or <hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi></p>
          <p>The summaries in these chapters, in many cases virtual paraphrases of the poems, are better for
the shorter books than for Blake’s longer epics. For all of the books, he provides useful frames of
reference primarily from the Bible, the classics, and Milton, along with some brief comments on historical and
philosophical contexts, and the summaries proceed more or less plate by plate, sometimes verse paragraph by
verse paragraph. While this approach works fairly well for the shorter books, it is rather less successful for
the longer books, especially in the discussion of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Part of the problem is that
Summerfield is so interested
<pb id="p35-131" n="131"/>
in presenting what appears to be an objective summary that his discussions finally have no guiding
perspective. The closest Summerfield comes in the book to making an argument is in his chapter on “Blake’s
Conversion,” in which he presents the arguments of “those who hold that Blake has fixed beliefs and those
who consider that his philosophy mutates through distinct phases” (155). This is an important distinction,
and Summerfield clearly is of the latter party, as his discussions of the later poems demonstrate, but even
here he is reluctant to assert his own perspective.</p>
          <p>This is not to say that there are no opinions offered. Indeed, Summerfield often makes remarks
quite critical of Blake’s work, but without much discussion of the basis for these remarks. For example,
Summerfield acknowledges the “greatness” of “The Tyger,” but then remarks (without explanation) that
it “has a feeble illustration” that is “aesthetically unsuccessful” (95). In the summary of the fate
of Urizen and Ahania in Night 3 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, he adds parenthetically, “The account of
their fate, marred by poverty of vocabulary and slackness of rhythm, is stylistically the weakest passage in
this Night” (197), but he offers no further explanation or example to support this judgment to the
“innocent” readers to whom this section of the book is addressed. Of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> he tells
these same innocent readers, “Unfortunately Blake, overanxious to elaborate his system, piles on schematic
correspondences in a way that becomes bizarre” (253), and “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> has
significant defects: uneven diction, disconcerting transitions, and formidable obscurity” (264). I am not
trying to claim that <hi rend="i">Zoas</hi>, or <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, or any of Blake’s poems or
illuminations, for that matter, is above criticism. My point is that Summerfield seems to have little
appreciation for the difficulty of Blake’s work, and he does little to encourage new readers of Blake to
engage that difficulty as anything other than a defect. Many readers of Blake’s work find his “formidable
obscurity” less a defect than a challenge to which the reader must rise. We return to Blake again and again
precisely because his schematic correspondences strike us as bizarre and rouse our faculties to act. In
contrast to his negative remarks, Summerfield’s highest praise goes to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations
of the Book of Job</hi>, a book in which Blake’s textual input is minimal, and which Summerfield describes
as “unique among the books of his maturity for its near perfection and easy approachability” (298).</p>
          <p>His <hi rend="i">Guide</hi>’s “secondary purpose,” Summerfield says, is “to constitute a
record of how Blake’s works came to be understood and to show how successive interpretations, while they can
be irritatingly or amusingly contradictory, often complement each other bringing out the richness of the
poetry” (11). Indeed, Summerfield’s long “Part II: Notes on Criticism” is a useful and handy work of
bibliographic compression covering the period 1910-1984. In this sort of compression it resembles somewhat the
essays in Frank Jordan’s <hi rend="i">The English Romantic Poets: A Review of Research and Criticism</hi>
(MLA 1985), which includes Mary Lynn Johnson’s great chapter on Blake, but the format is completely
different. Where Johnson’s chapter on Blake is organized by “General Remarks,” “Aids to Research,”
“Editions, Facsimiles, and Reproductions,” “Bibliographic Resources,” “Criticism” (divided into
“General Studies” and “Studies of Individual Works”), and “Trends and Prospects,” Summerfield
makes almost no comment on the different versions or editions of Blake’s work, and focuses only on
criticism. His discussions follow Blake’s career in roughly chronological order, with a chapter dedicated to
each of Blake’s books discussed in Part I. All chapters follow the same pattern: an overview of critical
comments on important interpretive issues of the book in question, followed by brief discussions of
potentially problematic specific lines or passages in that book, followed by an overview of critical
commentary on the individual illuminations for the book. General studies of Blake’s work, such as Frye’s
<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, are not discussed in and of themselves, but instead are excerpted for
brief remarks on particular issues or lines.</p>
          <p>However, if Summerfield’s goal is to “show how successive interpretations, while they can be
irritatingly or amusingly contradictory, often complement each other bringing
<pb id="p35-132" n="132"/>
out the richness of the poetry,” this section falls short. He does record a host of critical remarks and
interpretations of Blake’s work, but he provides very little in the way of showing how these readings
complement each other in order to bring out the richness of the poetry. The introductory material in these
chapters is generally sound and informative, and the notes on particular lines offer various interpretations
of the passages, usually without taking sides (although he does occasionally describe a given interpretation
as “persuasive”). The introductory remarks on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, for example, focus on the
problems of structure (including a brief paragraph on the two versions of chapter 2) and theme before focusing
on more particular concerns such as the furnaces of Los, fibers of materiality, wheel imagery, number
symbolism, and Albion’s cities and children (including Bath, Jerusalem, and Reuben). The particular notes
draw from Wicksteed, Sloss and Wallis, Frye, Ostriker, Raine, Hilton, Stevenson, and lots of others, but
Summerfield offers only the briefest of comments on the basis or implications of their critical
disagreements.</p>
          <p>In his notes on specific lines and passages, Summerfield clearly assumes that his reader is
actually reading Blake’s poems with Summerfield’s <hi rend="i">Guide</hi> on the side. He provides minimal
context for his notes, sometimes quoting a line, phrase, or word, but more often than not giving only plate
and line numbers before listing the various interpretations. This approach makes the book by itself very
difficult to read, and the same goes for his discussion of the illuminations. In these remarks Summerfield
assumes that his reader is also looking at Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> He provides no
general description of the illuminations, but instead records opinions on the various aspects of the
illumination in question. For example, his remarks on the design of <hi rend="i">America</hi> plate 10 begin,
“Though the turn of Orc’s head and his gesture with his hands are similar to those of Urizen in pl. 8, in
most other respects the two designs are antithetical” (453); this is true enough, but neither in the rest of
these remarks, nor in the remarks on Urizen in pl. 8, does Summerfield describe the turn of the head or the
hand gestures or those “other respects.” (For those of us without <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>
in immediate reach, the design on plate 10 depicts a young, beardless man, presumably Orc, crouching among
flames, his head turned to his right, arms outspread, left foot forward.) Unless the reader has memorized
Blake’s various illuminations, or is also looking at them (along with a text of the poem), Summerfield’s
remarks on them are not really much help.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, if one does happen to be reading Blake’s poetry and following along in 
<hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, Summerfield’s <hi rend="i">Guide</hi> makes some useful connections,
and brings to the reader several critical perspectives to compare to his or her own. Indeed, the 
<hi rend="i">Guide</hi> could be useful as a recommended text for classes devoted to Blake. The biographical
sketch, discussions of Blake’s “conversion” and system, and the more detailed critical notes on the
poems would helpfully supplement the material in Erdman’s edition. Part II of Summerfield’s book is
successful as a quick guide to critical resources for students of Blake (including their teachers and other
scholars) who are deep enough into their research to want to gather various perspectives about particular
lines of poetry, or particular aspects of the illuminations. I am not sure, however, that his summaries of the
books in Part I would do much to encourage readers at any level to read the poems.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
