<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>35.4.lindberg</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Bindman and Simon Baker, William Blake 1757-1827, catalogue of the
exhibition at the Helsinki Art Museum</title>
        <author n="Lindberg">Bo Ossian Lindberg</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">35.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Bo Ossian Lindberg</name>
              <name>R. Paul Yoder</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_35">
    <body>
	<pb id="p35-132" n="132"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-35-4-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Bindman and Simon Baker. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi>
Catalogue of the exhibition at the Helsinki City Art Museum, 11 April-25 June 2000.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Bo Ossian <name>Lindberg</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>One hundred and thirty seven works by William Blake from the collection of the British Museum
were shown at the Helsinki City Art Museum from 11 April to 25 June 2000. From Helsinki the exhibition went to
Prague.</p>
          <p>Some copper plates and wood blocks excepted, the exhibition consisted entirely of works on paper,
engravings, drawings, watercolors, and color prints. It is good that day-light is excluded from the exhibition
rooms, situated in the former Tennis Palace in the heart of the city. The building also contains an
ethnographical collection, fourteen cinema theatres, cafes, snack bars, shops, etc. For people under the age
of 18, access to the museums is free.</p>
          <p>In connection with the exhibition a series of lectures was given, beginning with David
Bindman’s lecture in English on the art of William Blake (12 April). Petri Pietiläinen talked on Blake’s
visions of femininity (19 April), and the artist Timo Aarniala on Blake as a psychedelic prophet with an
influence on present-day popular culture (3 May), both in Finnish. Finally Bo Ossian Lindberg, presented by
museum staff as “Finland’s only Blake scholar,” lectured in Swedish about Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> (16 May). The lectures had to be held in the exhibition’s exit/entrance room, the
microphones did not function properly, and there were several other difficulties which the first lecturer,
Bindman, suffered more than the others. In order to overcome this problem, another lecture room will have to
be found.</p>
          <p>On several occasions the group Oblivia appeared with <hi rend="i">Etcetera</hi>, a performance
consisting of dance, music, song, sound (but no words), and theatre, directed and manuscripted by Annika
Tudeer (choreography) and Katariina Vähäkallio (theatre). William and Robert Blake, the angry Rose, etc.,
appeared in a humorous and acrobatic journey through the
<pb id="p35-133" n="133"/>
exhibition rooms and through Blake’s life. At other occasions ten <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> were
sung, translated into Finnish by Hector (well-known Finnish singer) and set to music by Toni Edelmann. A
couple of times the Finn-Brit Players enacted <hi rend="i">Mr. and Mrs. Blake</hi>, reciting some of Blake’s
poems and showing glimpses of his and his wife’s life. A booklet called <hi rend="i">Tiikeri (The
Tyger)</hi> was distributed free of charge for use at schools. It contains several translations of 
<hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi> into Finnish, and is intended to give a basis for class discussions of problems in
translating poetry.</p>
          <p>The exhibition was well covered by the media. It was seen by 38,458 visitors, a tremendous
success. Many a leading museum in Finland does not have that many visitors in a year. Good marketing and the
many activities connected with the exhibition contributed to this success. While an exhibition of paintings by
Diego Rivera was shown in the upstairs rooms, it is clear that it was Blake rather than Rivera who attracted
the crowds.</p>
          <p>Seeing a large collection of Blake originals on view in Finland was a strange experience. Even
those in charge of the Helsinki City Art Museum never expected to get a Blake exhibition. When then museum
director Tuula Karjalainen and curator Maija Tanninen were in London as guests of the British Council, they
admitted that they were dreaming of a Blake exhibition, but realized that they could not have one. Somebody
knew that Blake works in the British Museum might be available—many of the illuminated books needed
rebinding, and an exhibition of Blakes in Prague was being planned. The British Museum director, Dr. Robert
Anderson, agreed that the collection meant for Prague would go to Helsinki first. Antony Griffiths helped with
the arrangements. Professor David Bindman and Simon Baker had already started choosing the collection that
would be shown at Prague Castle in the autumn of 2000. They had also started writing the 188-page catalogue
called, simply, <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Both cities happened to be cultural capitals of the
year 2000. That Helsinki got the exhibition was a result of lucky timing.</p>
          <p>The British Museum possesses works from Blake’s youth up to the year of his death, and the well
chosen exhibits gave a good survey of his <hi rend="i">œuvre.</hi> The BM has only one of the large color
prints <hi rend="i">(The Lazar House)</hi>, which, of course, was exhibited. It does not own any of Blake’s
so-called tempera paintings, that is size-color paintings on canvas or wood. Both these omissions, one of them
partial, are accounted for in David Bindman’s and Simon Baker’s excellent catalogue.</p>
          <p>Engravings and drawings such as <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea, Robin Hood and Clorinda</hi>
(engraved after J. Meheux), the advertisement for Moore &amp; Co., the <hi rend="i">Head of a Damned Soul</hi>
(after Fuseli), the drawing of a naked youth, <hi rend="i">The Death of Earl Godwin</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Har
Blessing Tiriel</hi> represented Blake’s early period. They were followed by an extremely full presentation
of Blake’s illuminated printing. One book was shown in its entirety, the disbound copy A of <hi rend="i">The
Song of Los</hi>, each plate mounted separately. Copy D of the same book, opened so as to show frontispiece
and title page, made it possible to experience variations between the copies. Selections of plates from other
illuminated books were shown: <hi rend="i">There Is No Natural Religion</hi> (A), <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (B),
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (A, D), <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (O), <hi rend="i">America</hi> (H), 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (A). Over thirty color prints from the <hi rend="i">Small</hi> and <hi rend="i">Large
Books of Designs</hi> included images from other illuminated books <hi rend="i">(Thel, The Marriage,
Urizen).</hi></p>
          <p>Other exhibits were the large engravings of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>,
engravings and watercolors for Young, the Butts portrait miniatures, the broadsheet <hi rend="i">Little Tom
the Sailor</hi>, watercolors of 1803-11 (such as <hi rend="i">Jacob’s Ladder</hi>, an unused design for
Blair, <hi rend="i">Queen Katharine’s Dream, Hamlet and the Ghost of His Father, The Judgment of Paris</hi>
and a couple more), the Chaucer engraving, eight of the Thornton wood engravings, all 22 engravings for the
<hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>, one engraving and four glorious watercolors for Dante, and, finally,
Cumberland’s card of 1827. Exhibits of a mid-nineteenth century electrotype of the lost copper for 
<hi rend="i">The Ecchoing Green</hi>, the copper for <hi rend="i">Job</hi> pl. 15, a woodblock for Thornton’s
<hi rend="i">Virgil</hi> and the uncut woodblock with a drawing of <hi rend="i">Isaiah Foretelling the
Crucifixion</hi> added to the attraction. Works not by William Blake were Schiavonetti’s engraving after
Phillips’s portrait of William Blake, and Robert Blake’s drawing <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom.</hi>
In some cases an intaglio engraving and a color print from the same plate were shown side by side 
<hi rend="i">(Glad Day, The Accusers).</hi></p>
          <p>As the above list should make clear, the exhibition was well chosen, both from the pedagogical
and the aesthetic point of view. It was great seeing it and fun showing it to students and to the general
public. The Finnish public seemed to appreciate it. They walked slowly through the exhibition, examining each
small design at close quarters for a long time. The exhibition was particularly informative on Blake’s
illuminated printing. The only omission I noted was the intaglio-printed illuminated books, a bit surprising
since the BM owns the only known copy of the intaglio-printed <hi rend="i">Book of Los. The Gates of
Paradise</hi> could have made up for the omission, but only one plate of <hi rend="i">Gates</hi> was shown
(“Fear and Hope are—Vision”), mounted together with <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi> from <hi rend="i">The
Large Book of Designs.</hi> The exhibition could not include the only known fragment of an original
illuminated plate, because it is in the Rosenwald collection, National Gallery of Art, Washington. The
inclusion of an electrotype of one of the coppers for the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, made before the originals
were lost, made an interesting substitute.</p>
          <p>Seeing many illuminated prints and color prints exhibited together makes the beholder realize
what had earlier remained only half-known to him. A characteristic of Blake’s relief-etching and
color-printing methods is that they do not allow a complete control of the result. There is always room for
accidents of etching, inking, and printing.</p>
          <pb id="p35-134" n="134"/>
          <p>Since plates were etched within walls of wax, each reliefetched plate became surrounded by an
irregular frame. Blake masked it out in early prints, but later he retained it, and in colored copies he often
developed it, wholly or in part, into wooded landscapes, serpents, flames, clouds, or tendrils (copy E of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>). He put the paints onto the color-printing plates as a thick paste, to make them
“blur well.” Then he developed the chaotic, indistinct marks into “blazing and changing wonder” (D. G.
Rossetti in Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 1863, 1:374) and confirmed the outlines of man
and beast with a pen. Blake describes his method in a famous passage, often quoted and often misunderstood:
<q>
The great and golden rule of art, as well as of life, is this: That the more distinct, sharp, and wirey the
bounding line, the more perfect the work of art; and the less keen and sharp, the greater is the evidence of
weak imitation, plagiarism, and bungling .... Leave out this line, and you leave out life itself; all is chaos
again, and the line of the almighty must be drawn out upon it before <hi rend="i">man or beast</hi> can exist.
(emphasis mine, <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> XV, E 550)
</q></p>
          <p>We do not always understand Blake’s dialectics of chaos and cosmos, and read passages such as
this as a classicist denouncement of everything indistinct and indefinite. Actually, Blake 
<hi rend="i">used</hi> chaos in the creative process, and he wanted chaos to show in the finished work. He let
accidents of inking and printing (both relief and color) create a chaos of blots and blurs. Upon this image
Blake drew out the contours of man and beast—figures are regularly more sharply defined than the rest. Chaos
was left as contrast in the backgrounds, and, often, as chaotic marks on Urizenic codes of law and fallen,
darkened suns. Blake used accident in a way similar to his contemporary Alexander Cozens (<hi rend="i">A New
Method of Assisting Invention in Drawing Original Compositions of Landscape</hi>, 1786), although his purpose
was quite different. He did not use the blot method primarily in order to assist imagination, but rather for
iconographical reasons.</p>
          <p>The Helsinki catalogue has a preface by Tuula Karjalainen and an introduction by David Bindman.
This is followed by detailed entries by Bindman and Simon Baker on each of the exhibits. There is also a
chronological table of Blake and his times. Fifty-seven of the exhibits are reproduced in color illustrations
of good quality. Unfortunately the title page of copy E of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is illustrated without
any statement that this copy is neither included in the exhibition nor possessed by the British Museum.
Instead, there were fifteen plates from the monochrome copy A on show, including the title page. The catalogue
does mention the fully colored copy at the Yale Center for British Art, New Haven, but without a reference to
the illustration, which, like all illustrations in the catalogue, lacks a caption.</p>
          <p>The text has been translated into Finnish and Swedish, the two official languages of Finland. I
am happy that the museum does not adopt the growing practice of leaving out the minority language Swedish. As
of this writing, the English text has not been printed, but I have seen the manuscript.</p>
          <p>The points on which I disagree with the catalogue text are few. Bindman and Baker date the large
engraving of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (cat. no. 14) after 1803 and add that it was possibly engraved as early as
the 1780s. I think that the second state, bearing the date 1793, was printed, after reworking, in the 1820s,
certainly after 1810, because it is printed on India paper, introduced about that time. The date 1793 is a
survivor from the first state, of which a single, damaged print exists, lacking the lower part with imprint
and date. Geoffrey Keynes’s suggestion that it was possibly done in the 1780s is almost certainly
mistaken.</p>
          <p>I would also suggest an alternative interpretation of the old man below the title of 
<hi rend="i">The Song of Los.</hi> I do not think he is either Urizen or Noah and he is not “fading”; he is
emerging out of his grave and opens his blue eye to the morning light, in illustration of the resurrection
scene at the end of the song: “Forth from the dead dust rattling bones to bones / Join. . . .”</p>
          <p>I also have some doubts about the contrast that the catalogue authors see between the sun in the
frontispiece of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> and that in the endpiece. If Blake had any such contrast in
mind, why did he cover both disks with darkness, in the former image black spots on the disk, in the latter
black clouds in front of it, and that in all known copies? I do not have an alternative explanation, but
believe that the good sun is not completely good.</p>
          <p>None of the twelve large color prints bears any date other than 1795, although some are undated.
Yet some watermarks date the production of the paper 1804. Eight of the color prints are mentioned in
debtor-and-creditor accounts between Thomas Butts and Blake on 5 July and 7 September 1805, which is the first
record of any of them. They are further mentioned as “12 Large Prints” in a letter by Blake to Dawson
Turner 1818. The prints are so similar in conception and style that if only one of them can be shown to date
from about 1805, all must be of that date. Why Blake wrote 1795 on works produced one decade later must remain
a matter of speculation. But in their entry on no. 68 the catalogue authors give the date “ca. 1795,”
without any discussion. I think that about 1805 should be accepted as the most likely date for these prints.
The problematic dating should at least be acknowledged.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">A Dream of Tiralatha</hi> is called “the erotic or impotent dream . . . contrasted
with the free and uninhibited figures to the left.” The illustration was originally meant for 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, and part of the suppressed text is known. I believe that the image illustrates the
lines: “As when a dream of Tiralatha flies the midnight hour: / In vain the dreamer grasps the joyful
images, they fly / Seen in obscured traces . . . So / The British Colonies beneath the woful Princes fade.”
Obviously
<pb id="p35-135" n="135"/>
the crouching woman is Tiralatha and the figures on the left are her dream, moving out of the image. Possibly
influenced by the catalogue text, the Swedish translator calls the color print <hi rend="i">En dröm om
Tiralatha</hi> (<hi rend="i">A Dream about Tiralatha</hi>), while it is correctly rendered in Finnish 
<hi rend="i">Tiralathan uni.</hi> See Detlef Dörrbecker, ed., <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Books of William
Blake: Volume 4. The Continental Prophecies</hi> 136-38.</p>
          <p>The catalogue mentions as one of the advantages of Blake’s illuminated printing that it made a
copper press superfluous. This is doubtful, since we know that Blake owned a wooden copper press at his death,
although we cannot be sure how early he possessed it. Judging from the deep impressions that the illuminated
plates have left in the paper, we know that most of them were printed in a copper press, from the 1790s
on.</p>
          <p>The translations into Finnish (by Tomi Snellman) and Swedish (by Camilla Ahlström-Taavitsainen),
though for the most part well done, contain a number of mistakes, for which I feel in part responsible.
According to an agreement between the museum and myself, the translators were to consult me if difficulties
arose. Apparently they never realized when they ran into difficulties, and never contacted me. And I,
unsuspecting, did not have the sense to contact them.</p>
          <p>There is a point of general interest here for anyone involved in translation, as the following
examples will show. The Finnish translation calls exhibit number 131 <hi rend="i">Kuparipürros</hi>, meaning
engraving on copper, which implies a print. Actually, the item is the <hi rend="i">copper</hi> for plate 15 of
<hi rend="i">Job.</hi> The Swedish translation is correct here: <hi rend="i">Kopparplåt.</hi> The English
text calls the exhibit a <hi rend="i">copper plate.</hi> Of course, <hi rend="i">plate</hi> is ambiguous in
English, meaning a metal plate but also an impression of such a plate. The translator has missed the force of
the word <hi rend="i">copper.</hi></p>
          <p>Further, David Bindman and Simon Baker mention whiteline work, describing it as etching or
engraving a plate—or part of a plate—in intaglio, and printing it from the surface of the parts in relief,
like a woodcut. The translations, however, make no sense, as shown by catalogue numbers 36 <hi rend="i">(The
Ancient of Days)</hi>, 97 (pl. 33 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>), and 108 (<hi rend="i">The Man Sweeping the
Interpreter’s Parlour</hi>). There is no attempt to translate the word <hi rend="i">white-line</hi>, and as
a consequence the passages appear pointless.</p>
          <p>Technical terms, even the simplest, are consistently mistranslated. Or is the word 
<hi rend="i">copy</hi> (noun) really so simple? Blake’s illuminated books exist in one or several 
<hi rend="i">copies.</hi> The Finnish translator uses the word <hi rend="i">nide</hi> (<hi rend="i">binding</hi>),
which is wrong. Even copy A of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> is called a <hi rend="i">nide</hi>, although
in the exhibition each plate was hung in a separate mount. <hi rend="i">Kappale</hi> is the best translation,
even <hi rend="i">eksemplaari</hi> would be correct, though awkward. The Swedish translator has chosen 
<hi rend="i">kopia</hi>—indeed the same word as the English <hi rend="i">copy</hi>, but, unfortunately, 
<hi rend="i">kopia</hi> means <hi rend="i">copy</hi> only in the sense of <hi rend="i">imitation.</hi> If you mean
several copies of similar things, the only good translation into Swedish is <hi rend="i">exemplar.</hi>
Sometimes <hi rend="i">utgåva</hi> is used by the Swedish translator, incorrectly, since it means 
<hi rend="i">edition. Plates</hi>, meaning <hi rend="i">prints</hi>, should in Swedish be <hi rend="i">blad</hi>,
not <hi rend="i">planscher.</hi> The Swedish translator confuses terms like <hi rend="i">frontispiece</hi> and
<hi rend="i">title page.</hi> The translations of poetry, Blake’s and Young’s, are not good. They are
“free,” and as a consequence the poet of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> appears, in Swedish only,
“fettered” instead of “self-fettered.” Snellman has been able sometimes to quote existing
translations, such as Risto Ahti’s of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> or Aale Tynni’s of 
<hi rend="i">The Tyger.</hi></p>
          <p>The translators are neither poets nor experts on the graphic arts. But even so, many mistakes
could have been avoided had the translators had a chance to see the exhibits, at least in reproduction.
Everyone involved in translation should observe the following rules:
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1. A translator should avoid translating descriptions of images or other objects which he has not
seen.</p></item>
	<item><p>2. The translator should make a careful examination of the objects of the description under
translation.</p></item>
	<item><p>3. The translator should render the text as literally as possible, especially in poetry.</p></item>
	<item><p>4. The translator should avoid handling texts on subjects of which he lacks experience.</p></item>
	<item><p>5. If a translator has to deal with such texts, a consultant expert should be appointed—and
used.</p></item>
	<item><p>6. The consultant should contact the translator unbidden.</p></item>
</list></p>
          <p>Although I have spoken Finnish since I was a child, I am not qualified to criticize translations
into Finnish; I belong to the minority of Swedish-speaking Finns. Therefore I have consulted two native
Finnish-speaking colleagues, Kari Kotkavaara and Heidi Pfäffli, both working at my department.</p>
          <p>Finally, a suggestion to the authorities of the British Museum: why not show the exhibition also
in London?</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
