<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.1.schiff</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</title>
        <author n="Schiff">Gert Schiff</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Gert Schiff</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <body>
      <pb id="p36-38" n="38"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>Catalogue entry by <docAuthor>Gert <name>Schiff</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>It was Martin Butlin who first brought to our attention the importance of the late Gert
Schiff’s catalogue entry on the color-printed drawing formerly known as <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>, which was
published in Japanese in the catalogue of the exhibition of which Dr. Schiff was Commissioner: 
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> 22 September-25 November 1990 (Tokyo: National Museum of Western Art, 1990) 137-38
(see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> 308-09). Dr. Schiff wrote the majority of
the entries (with about one quarter supplied by Martin Butlin) and, in the second edition only, an
introductory essay. The entry has therefore remained unread by most Anglophone readers, but it deserves to be
widely known in the world of Blake scholarship, as it advances a very interesting hypothesis as to the
significance of the design, and retitles it accordingly. We are therefore grateful to Martin Butlin for
suggesting that we publish it, and to Robert N. Essick for lending us Dr. Schiff’s English text and for
providing several points of information. For permission to print the entry, we wish to thank Chief Curator
Akira Kofuku and the National Museum of Western Art, Tokyo, and, for permission to reproduce 
<hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>, Deborah Hunter, Photographic and Licensing Manager, National Galleries of Scotland. We
are also grateful for the assistance of David Weinglass, Chris Heppner, Richard Bernstein, and Beth
Mandelbaum.—MDP
<q><hi rend="i">‘The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy,’ formerly called ‘Hecate’</hi> c. 1795<lb/>
Color print finished in pen and watercolor, 43 × 57.5 cm. Signed “Fresco WBlake inv” b.l.<lb/>
Probably the second pull after the first one in the Tate Gallery (Butlin 316)<lb/>
Literature: Butlin 317<lb/>
The National Gallery of Scotland, Edinburgh
</q></p>
          <p>Blake left this print untitled, and it has been known to generations of scholars under
Rossetti’s misnomer of “Hecate”—notwithstanding the fact that this classical goddess is invariably
depicted with three conjoined bodies, their faces turned outwards, in the directions of three branching
crossroads. Hagstrum and, following him, Jones, noticed that instead Blake’s group consists of three
separate figures: a mature woman, sitting with raised knees and partly eclipsing the facing bodies of a girl
to her left and a boy to her right. Both authors derived specific interpretations from this observation.
Hagstrum (1970, p. 329): the two figures are separated by the goddess of jealousy; Jones (1972, pp. 125-129):
their innocent love is spoiled by institutional religion. Heppner, who had independently recognized that the
figure does not represent Hecate, linked the composition in an exemplary analysis to witchcraft: the central
figure resembles the Witch of Endor (<hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</hi>, New
York Public Library, Butlin 144); the cave is her habitation; the winged animal, her familiar; the book, her
conjuring book. She is intent upon a ritual which might be “a dedication of the children to an underworld
deity . . . (their) initiation . . . into sexuality viewed as shame and guilt . . . (or) even . . . a
premature marriage ceremony conducted under powerful and unfavorable circumstances.” Heppner rightly
emphasizes that, since we do not know the underlying narrative—whether it was found or created by Blake—we
cannot arrive at his full intention. Yet he concedes that “Hagstrum’s Jealousy and Jones’s institutional
religion, both described as separating lovers, seem pointed in a relevant direction” (1981, pp. 355-365).
Lindsay concurs with these interpretations by defining the “witchcraft depicted . . . as a Vala-like envy
which eclipses vitality by impeding the union of Cupid and Psyche” (1989, p. 29). “Cupid and Psyche” is
a figure of speech. More important is the introduction of Vala, Blake’s evil goddess of Nature, for this
points at the possibility that the missing narrative might include, in addition to witchcraft, elements of
Blake’s own mythology.</p>
          <p>It seems highly significant that in all interpretations the function of the central figure is
defined as <hi rend="i">separating the lovers.</hi> This holds also for the rites proposed by Heppner. For
those barely pubescent children who were initiated into sex through lurid rituals of witchcraft may thereby
well have lost their capacity of loving. That the two youthful figures <hi rend="i">look ashamed</hi> was the
magic word that freed Heppner “from the encrusted texts through which (he) had always looked at the print”
(p. 356). Boy and girl hang their heads as if they hardly dared to look into each other’s eyes. While the
boy (only in the present copy) raises his arm in a half-hearted attempt at a caress, the girl keeps her hand
obediently behind her back. The woman’s demeanor is expressive of the most perfect indifference. Her mind is
neither with the children nor with her menagerie—a sign that both are safely under control. Only in the Tate
Gallery’s copy does her forefinger point at a particular spot in her book; in our and in the Huntington
version, her hand rests aimlessly—yet possessively—on the page. In the Tate copy she stares at nothing in
particular; in the present pull one imagines her sight becoming blurred; in the remaining one, her eyes are
closing with sleep.</p>
          <p>Two observations in the literature point in the direction where, according to my own reading, the
subject might be found. Several writers (Bindman 1977, p. 100; Paley 1978, p. 38; Lindsay p. 29) notice that
the <hi rend="i">book</hi> with its blurred writing is none other than Urizen’s Book of Brass, in which he
codified his repressive law (cp. Butlin, pls. 329, 378, 380, and Erdman, <hi rend="i">TIB</hi>, pp. 183, 187).
Bindman, while still considering the figure as “Hecate,” notes that “the mystery and
<pb id="p36-39" n="39"/>
<figure n="but317.1.1.cpd" id="but317.1.cpd.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="722">
	<head>William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</hi> (also known as 
<hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> or <hi rend="i">Triple Hecate</hi>).</head>
	<figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the National Gallery of Scotland.</figDesc>
</figure>
darkness for which she stands would be an apt parallel to Enitharmon’s ‘1800 year sleep’ in 
<hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>”</p>
          <p>The likeliest explanation of this print is, I think, that it allegorizes Enitharmon’s scheme to
enslave mankind by way of sexual repression:
<q>
Now comes the night of Enitharmons joy!<lb/>
Who shall I call? Who shall I send?<lb/>
That Woman, lovely Woman! may have dominion?<lb/>
Arise O Rintrah thee I call! &amp; Palamabron thee!<lb/>
Go! tell the human race that Womans love is Sin!<lb/>
That an Eternal life awaits the worms of sixty winters<lb/>
In an allegorical abode where existence hath never come:<lb/>
Forbid all Joy, &amp; from her childhood shall the little female<lb/>
Spread nets in every secret path. (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 5:1-9, E 62)
</q>
There could be no better visualization of her resolve to “separate male and female in every civilization”
(Bloom 1963, p. 151) than this group of three. For under this premise it is obvious that the young lovers are
bewitched by Enitharmon’s ban on sex as enforced by her adoption of Urizen’s book. By depicting Enitharmon
as a brooding witch, Blake shows that both her religion of chastity and her promise of an afterlife are
nothing but evil spells. And how well does the figure’s somnolence fit her impending, world-historical
sleep!
<q>
My weary eyelids draw towards the evening, my bliss is yet but new. (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 5:10, E 62)
</q></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G.E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995.</p>
            <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi> Oxford: Phaidon, 1977.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Ed. David V.
Erdman. Rev. ed. New York: Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic Argument.</hi> New York:
Doubleday, 1963.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New
Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1981.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake: William Blake’s Complete Illuminated
Works with a Plate-by-Plate Commentary.</hi> Garden City, New York: Anchor Press, 1974.</p>
            <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. “‘The Wrath of the Lamb’: A Study of William Blake’s Conversions,”
in <hi rend="i">From Sensibility to Romanticism</hi>: Essays Presented to Frederick A. Pottle. London and New
York: Oxford University Press, 1970 [1965] 311-30.</p>
            <p>Heppner, Christopher. “Reading Blake’s Designs: <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Hecate.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 84 (1981): 337-65.</p>
            <p>Jones, Warren. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Large Color-Printed Drawings of 1795.</hi> Ph.D.
dissertation. Evanston, IL: Northwestern University, 1972.</p>
            <p>Lindsay, David W. “The Order of Blake’s Large Color Prints.” <hi rend="i">Huntington
Library Quarterly</hi> 52 (1989): 19-41.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Oxford: Phaidon, 1978.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
