<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.2.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <front>
        <pb id="p36-41-42" n="41-42"/>
        <div1 id="cover">
            <figure n="cover.036.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="335">
                <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
                    AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
                    One Pull or Two?<lb/>
                    Michael Phillips, Martin Butlin, Robert Essick and Joseph Viscomi<lb/>
                    Revisit Blake’s Method of Color Printing<lb/>
                    VOLUME 36<lb/>
                    NUMBER 2<lb/>
                    FALL 2002</figTranscr>
            </figure>
        </div1>
        <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="9" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
				<head>
					<title>CONTENTS</title>
				</head>
			</cell>
		  </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Discussion</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="36.2.phillips">Color-Printing <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> and
                            Blake’s Method of Registration: A Correction</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Michael Phillips</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">44</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="36.2.butlin">“Is This a Private War or Can Anyone Join In?”:
A Plea
                            for a Broader Look at Blake’s Color-Printing Techniques</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Martin Butlin</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">45</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="36.2.essick">Blake’s Method of Color Printing: Some Responses
and Further Observations</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">49</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><supplied type="emend"><hi rend="b">Further Discussion</hi></supplied><lb/>
			<supplied type="emend" rend="plain">Online Features</supplied></cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><supplied type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="bonus.butlin">William Blake, S. W. Hayter
and Color Printing</ref></supplied><lb/>
			<supplied type="emend" rend="plain"><hi rend="i">By Martin Butlin</hi></supplied></cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><supplied type="emend"><ref type="article"
issue="bonus.response">Response</ref></supplied><lb/>
			<supplied type="emend" rend="plain"><hi rend="i">By Robert N. Essick and Joseph
Viscomi</hi></supplied></cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="36.2.bentley">The Blake Exhibition at Tate Britain, 9 November
2000-11 February
                            2001, and at the Metropolitan Museum, 27 March-24 June 2001, and their
Catalogues</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by G.E. Bentley, Jr.</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">64</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="36.2.gourlay">Michael Phillips, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
Creation of the</hi>
                            Songs <hi rend="i">from Manuscript to Illuminated Printing</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Alexander S. Gourlay</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">66</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p36-43" n="43"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>G.E. Bentley, Jr. writes about Blake’s life and his books; his <hi rend="i">The Stranger from
Paradise: A Biography of William Blake</hi> was
                    published by Yale in 2001, and the second edition of his <hi rend="i">Blake
                        Records</hi> (1969), incorporating <hi rend="i">Blake Records
                        Supplement</hi> (1988) and much added matter, is scheduled for publication
                    by Yale in 2002.</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin was formerly Keeper of the Historic British Collection at the Tate
                    Gallery, London. Since retirement, he has continued to work on Blake, J.M.W.
                    Turner, and other British artists.</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick teaches English Literature at the University of California,
                    Riverside. He is not nearly as good a printmaker as Joe Viscomi.</p>
        <p>Alexander Gourlay recently edited <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on
                        William Blake in Honor of John E. Grant</hi> (Locust Hill Press, 2002), a
                    collection of new work on Blake, much of it by regular contributors to 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> He teaches at the Rhode Island
                    School of Design.</p>
        <p>Michael Phillips teaches an interdisciplinary one-year MA course at the Centre
                    for Eighteenth Century Studies, University of York, on William Blake and the Age
                    of Revolution. In addition to publication of <hi rend="i">The Creation of
                        the</hi> Songs, and being guest curator of the recent William Blake
                    exhibition at Tate Britain, he is completing a biography of Blake in Lambeth
                    during the anti-Jacobin terror in Britain. The biography will be anticipated by
                    the Waynflete Lectures he is to deliver as Visiting Fellow at Magdalen College,
                    Oxford, in Spring 2003.</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi is James G. Kenan Distinguished Professor of English Literature at
                    the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Unlike Robert Essick, he does
                    not live ten minutes from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                    copy E and other color-printed works by Blake.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey Hall 410, University of
                    Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sjns@mail.rochester.edu<lb/>
 TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820
                    FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
                    14627-0451<lb/>
 Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA
                    94720-1030<lb/>
 Email: mpaley@socrates.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada. The
                    University of Toronto declines to forward mail.<lb/>
 Email:
                    GBentley@chass.utoronto.ca</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens GA 30602<lb/>
                    Email: nhilton@english.uga.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill, Waldegrave Road,
                    Twickenham TW1 4SX England<lb/>
 Email: worralld@smuc.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the
                    sponsorship of the Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions
                    are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals. All subscriptions are by the
                    volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
                    received after the summer issue will be applied to the 4 issues of the current
                    volume. Addresses outside the U.S., Canada, and Mexico require a $10 per volume
                    postal surcharge for surface, and $25 for airmail delivery. Credit card payment
                    is available. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications
                    to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of
                    Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah
                    Jones for information on issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies,
                    typed and documented according to forms suggested in <hi rend="i">The MLA Style
                        Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to either of the editors: Morris
                    Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451;
                    Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley CA
                    94720-1030. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by a stamped
                    self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a diskette, or
                    you may send your article as an attachment to an email message; please number
                    the pages of electronic submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other
                    formats are usually acceptable.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is indexed in the Modern Language
                    Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
                    Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature,
                    American Humanities Index, Arts and Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents
                    and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover: William Blake, <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, plate 3. Relief
                    etching, 15.0 × 10.2 cm., 1794, color printed with touches of hand
                    tinting with brush and pen and ink c. 1794. Robert N. Essick collection. Detail
                    of the design. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2002 Copyright
                        Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
