<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.2.phillips</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Color-Printing Songs of Experience and Blake’s Method of Registration: A
Correction</title>
        <author n="Phillips">Michael Phillips</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <body>
    <pb id="p36-44" n="44"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">DISCUSSION</title>
        </head>
        <head>
          <title type="section-subtitle"><hi rend="i">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged
                            arrows of thought</hi></title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Color-Printing <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> and
                            Blake’s Method of Registration: A Correction</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Michael <name>Phillips</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>I wish to correct a mistake in <hi rend="i">William Blake The Creation of
                            the</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">From Manuscript to Illuminated Printing</hi>
                        (London: The British Library; Princeton: Princeton UP, 2000), specifically
                        in Chapter V, “Colour-Printing <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Experience.</hi>” This concerns the claim that Blake used a form of
                        pinhole registration in color printing four impressions from Copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi>
of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> in the
                        collection of the National Gallery of Canada.</p>
          <p>In my effort to see every copy of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in researching
                        my book, I visited the National Gallery of Canada in August 1991. While
                        inspecting the examples in the collection my attention was drawn to the four
                        color-printed impressions of the title-page, “Introduction,”
                        “EARTH’S Answer” and “LONDON.” With the
                        help of the Senior Conservator of Prints and Drawings, Geoffrey Morrow,
                        these were taken to the conservation laboratory and viewed under
                        magnification, raking light and ultraviolet light. This clearly revealed
                        that Blake had used a method involving two printing stages, the first to
                        print in monochrome and the second in colors. In some instances, like that
                        of the title-page, Blake had then applied color with a brush over areas of
                        the color-printed pigments. It was clear that the monochrome ink had been
                        largely absorbed into the fabric of the paper, while the viscous color
                        pigments had been printed with less pressure and remained on the surface,
                        often forming minute peaks and shallows when the print had been lifted from
                        the copper plate.</p>
          <p>From the evidence of our study in the laboratory, we were both curious as to
                        how Blake could have printed these impressions in two stages. In May 1992,
                        Geoffrey sent 35mm. color slides of each of the four color-printed
                        impressions from Copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi>, including a number of details.
                        In his covering letter he suggested that perhaps the “small black dot
                        which can be clearly seen in the very corner of the plate is related to a
                        method of registering the plate.” I wrote asking how he thought this
                        could have been done. He replied that Blake may have used a
                        “swivel” technique, “where the single registration
                        point in the top left corner allowed him to somehow swivel the paper
                        sideways for the addition of colour to the plate and then back into
                        registration for a second printing.” Adding, “It is just a
                        thought, I have never seen such a technique used.” From this
                        speculation I deduced that Blake must have used a pin or etching needle to
                        hold the monochrome impression and registration sheet in place while he
                        swiveled the impression out of the way, either to add color to the plate or
                        to remove it to do so. I tried this method in the printmaking studio. By
                        marking off the opposite corner of the impression (from where it was held by
                        the pin) on the registration sheet, the impression could be swiveled and
                        returned into register. As represented in the 35mm. color slide details, the
                        tiny dot visible in the upper left corner of each impression I interpreted
                        to be the indentation or hole that had been left by the pin or needle using
                        this method.</p>
          <p>In September 2000, while correcting proof of my book, I wrote to ask Geoffrey
                        to check my text where it referred to the color-printed impressions from
                        Copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi> in the collection of the National Gallery of
                        Canada, including the passages referring to pinhole registration (on pp. 98,
                        99 and 101 as published). He replied to say that “Everything looks
                        good except for one sentence” that concerned my description of the
                        blackened lead white pigment that was found on the title-page; a description
                        that I duly amended and passed to the printer.</p>
          <p>Geoffrey Morrow has now confirmed that I was mistaken in deducing from his
                        description that the small black dots seen in the 35mm. color slides were in
                        fact pinholes. I am now able to draw attention to this error in my book.
                        Unfortunately, it was not possible to correct the label in the Tate Britain
                        Blake exhibition describing the title-page of Copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi> of
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> as showing pinhole registration.
                        There was no allowance in the exhibition budget for me to revisit the
                        collections from which I had requested exhibits, where I would have had a
                        chance to look again at the title-page. It was also not possible to see the
                        exhibits in London in time to make changes. All of the exhibits arrived
                        during the week before the opening, and immediately they arrived were
                        unpacked and secured in their showcases under the supervision of their
                        couriers.</p>
          <p>Geoffrey Morrow’s reply to my request to check my descriptions in
                        proof gave me no reason to question the presence of pinhole registration on
                        these four impressions. Nevertheless, as I made clear (p. 101): “The
                        four impressions in the collection of the National Gallery of Canada,
                        title-page, ‘Introduction’ ‘EARTH’S
                        Answer’ and ‘LONDON,’ are the only examples that I have
                        found that have been registered by using a pin. All of the remaining
                        colour-printed impressions have no visible sign of registration.”</p>
          <p>It was the overwhelming evidence that Blake had found another, simpler method
                        of registration that led to the experiments that I describe in my book.
                        After printing the impression in monochrome, Blake could have nipped the
                        margin of the registration sheet and impression between the rollers. This
                        allowed the impression to be lifted at the opposite end to daub the plate
                        with color pigment, or to remove the plate to do so (described on pp.
                        101-02). This method is illustrated in my chapter using the
                        eighteenth-century rolling 
<pb id="p36-45" n="45"/>
press in the Science
                        Museum, London (Fig. 34), the same rolling press that was on display in the
                        Tate Britain Blake exhibition and illustrated in the exhibition catalogue
                        (p. 101).</p>
          <p>A more flexible method of registration was also described. Using this method
                        the monochrome impression and registration sheet passed between the rollers,
                        but before the impression was lifted from the plate a weight was placed at
                        one end. This allowed the opposite end of the impression to be lifted and
                        the copper plate to be daubed with color, or for the plate to be removed,
                        cleaned and applied with color before being placed back into register. As I
                        describe, using this second method also made it possible to remove the print
                        and replace it with a second monochrome impression, which could then be
                        color printed using the color pigments remaining on the plate (pp.
                        107-08).</p>
          <p>Relying upon photographic reproduction led to the error published in my book.
                        Such a mistake illustrates how there is no substitute, however
                        sophisticated, for seeing Blake’s illuminated books and prints
                        firsthand, ideally in laboratory conditions where special lighting and
                        magnification are available. Only by studying Blake’s illuminated
                        books and prints in this way are we able to discover the materials that he
                        used and how they were printed. This in turn will bring us closer to an
                        understanding of the time and effort that were involved in their making, and
                        place us in a position to address questions of intention and audience that
                        follow directly from such an understanding.</p>
          <p>I have recently confirmed my description of events with Geoffrey Morrow. He
                        adds: “The main point, that Blake did use a double printing technique
                        on occasion, is one about which we are in full agreement. Only by examining
                        prints like the title-page under the conditions you describe can the
                        technical reality be experienced with full understanding.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
