<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.2.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Blake’s Method of Color Printing: Some Responses and Further
Observations</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
        <author n="Viscomi">Joseph Viscomi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0006">
        <pb id="p36-49" n="49"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Method of Color Printing: Some Responses and Further
                            Observations</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor> and
                            <docAuthor>Joseph <name>Viscomi</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">
            <hi rend="i">Authors’ note: An online version of this article, with
                            illustrations in color, is available on the journal’s web site at
                            http://www.blakequarterly.org. Readers interested in the full pictorial
                            evidence supporting the views expressed here are encouraged to consult
                            the online version.</hi>
          </note>
          <p>“Labour Well the Minute Particulars, attend to the
                            Little-ones”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n10">1. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 55, line
                            51. <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry and Prose</hi>, ed. Erdman, 205.
                            Hereafter cited as “E” followed by page number.</note></p>
          <p>We are pleased that a scholar of Martin Butlin’s eminence would find
                        our long, technical essay on Blake’s color printing of interest. We
                        are also pleased that, in his reply, he does not take exception to any of
                        our basic arguments in favor of one-pull color printing or question their
                        evidentiary basis. Rather, he raises several issues related, if somewhat
                        peripherally, to our topic, continues to favor a two-pull process, and
                        proposes a new method for two-pull printing distinctly different from the
                        methods offered by Michael Phillips in his recent book, <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake: The Creation of the</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">from Manuscript to
                            Illuminated Printing.</hi> We wish to comment on Butlin’s
                        observations seriatim as they arise in his essay.</p>
          <p>Butlin notes that “the concentration” of our article “on
                        technical detail” missed out the “more general considerations
                        of Blake’s overall development in the 1790s” and left
                        “several important questions unanswered.” Our essay indeed
                        concentrated on a single issue raised by Phillips’ book,
                        Blake’s color printing of relief-etched plates. This topic, however,
                        covers more than 600 impressions in ten books and touches on one of the
                        major goals in Blake studies, that of understanding Blake’s practice
                        and thinking as an artist. More general considerations of all the techniques
                        Blake deployed in his illuminated books, and the evolution of those books
                        into the large color prints of 1795 and finally into the tempera paintings
                        of the late 1790s, would take a book-length study. We (and we suspect the
                        editors of this journal and most of our readers) found our article long
                        enough as it is. The fact that most of the large color prints are
                        planographic (i.e., printed from the surface), and that the temperas were
                        painted (not printed) on their supports, does not alter the way Blake color
                        printed his relief etchings. We continue to believe that questions about
                        print technology are best answered by looking closely at the primary
                        evidence (in this instance, color-printed impressions of Blake’s
                        relief etchings), by conducting experiments in the print studio, and by
                        contextualizing one’s findings within the history of color printing
                        in the eighteenth century. Connoisseurship that produces only the most
                        general comments (“looks like two pulls to me and my
                        friends”), or rounding up the opinions of various scholars and taking
                        a vote, are not as helpful. Technological issues are best resolved by
                        considering “technical detail,” even if this tends to bore or
                        annoy some of our readers. But since Butlin has raised questions about the
                        color-printed intaglio plates and color-print drawings that followed the
                        color-printed relief etchings, we feel compelled to answer them, which we do
                        later in this response.</p>
          <p>Butlin’s second paragraph forces us to quibble over the meaning of
                        “prominent.” As we pointed out in our second footnote, several
                        scholars, including Butlin, had indicated a belief in a two-pull process
                        prior to Phillips’ book. These earlier comments are brief and not
                        even “prominent” within the essays and books in which they
                        appear. It seemed to us discourteous to critique those who had only
                        mentioned the two-pull process in passing and had not offered any supporting
                        arguments or evidence. The history of the two-pull theory prior to
                        Viscomi’s 1993 study, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the
                            Book</hi>, appears to be one of those cultural traditions that many
                        assent to but none investigates. Surely Phillips must be credited with the
                        first, prominent attempt to make a case for the two-pull theory.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n11">2. Butlin refers throughout his response to an online version
                            and a “significantly revised” print version of our essay.
                            He is confusing the final online version with an early draft of the
                            essay (15 October 2001) that the authors put online for the purpose of
                            eliciting responses from curators, scholars, print historians, and other
                            invited guests. The published online version (February 2002) and the
                            print version are the same essay, except that the latter has fewer and
                            only black and white illustrations and some of the captions and
                            descriptions of the illustrations are altered to take that into
                            account.</note></p>
          <pb id="p36-41" n="41"/>
			  <figure n="blake-urizen-4-top.36.2.100" rend="file" width="600" height="372">
				<figTranscr>Chap: I<lb/>
				5. But Eternals beheld his vast forests</figTranscr>
				<head>Cover: William Blake, <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, plate 3.</head>
				<figDesc>Relief etching, 15.0 × 10.2 cm., 1794, color printed with touches of hand
tinting with brush and pen and ink c. 1794. Robert N. Essick collection. Detail of the
design.</figDesc>
			  </figure>
          <pb id="p36-50" n="50"/>
          <p>We apologize to Martin Butlin for not including his review of
                        Viscomi’s book in our footnote 2. It was an oversight on our part,
                        not an egregious attempt to slight Butlin’s great contributions to
                        Blake scholarship. As far as we can discover, that review contains
                        Butlin’s fullest statement, prior to his present essay, in support of
                        the two-pull theory—a paragraph of 206 words. There he refers to the
                        “badly registered” impression of “Nurses Song”
                        in the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> section of <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy E and claims that “having
                        made such an error, Blake could easily have succeeded in the not very
                        difficult task of producing a perfect register.” As we have made
                        clear in our article, producing a “perfect” register, one that
                        shows absolutely no signs of the first pull even under magnification, is,
                        impression after impression, an extraordinarily difficult task indeed, even
                        for the eighteenth-century French masters of multiple-plate (and hence
                        multiple-pull) printing and for twentieth-century masters of color printing,
                        such as Stanley Hayter, who says without qualification that it is not
                        possible (see below). Butlin’s reasoning seems to be that an example
                        of poor registration argues for Blake’s easy mastery of perfect
                        registration. The logic here escapes us.</p>
          <p>Butlin also notes in his paragraph that Viscomi’s “argument,
                        based on the white lines left where the paper failed to pick up the color at
                        the base of the sharply etched relief lines [see cover illus.], could apply
                        irrespective of whether there were one or two printings.” This is
                        true but misses the point concerning registration. These fine white lines
                        parallel their relief lines. When they are produced in a second pull,
                        experiments reveal, they will intersect minutely with their relief lines. It
                        is impossible, impression after impression, to so perfectly register the
                        paper to the copperplate that these very narrow white lines remain perfectly
                        parallel. Minute intersecting or touching of white lines and relief inked
                        lines signifies a second pull, but it is a sign consistently absent from
                        Blake’s color prints.</p>
          <p>According to Butlin, our failure to cite his review, or more generally our
                        “approach” in footnote 2, “is symptomatic of the
                        Inquiry as a whole.” He has a point, in that our concern was with an
                        investigation of the primary evidence rather than with recording every word
                        ever published on Blake’s color printing method. Perhaps if we had
                        concentrated more on that publication record rather than on Blake’s
                        own prints we would have remembered and added Butlin’s review to his
                        other works we cite. We trust that we have now made up for our original
                        oversight. However, given the nature of our approach to the subject, our
                        failure to cite his review is irrelevant to our case for one-pull color
                        printing.</p>
          <p>Butlin expresses discomfort over our “restricted definition” of
                        “Illuminated Printing.” We were concerned with establishing
                        what Blake meant by “Illuminated Printing” in his 1793
                        Prospectus and not trying to determine how the term should always be used.
                        We are not arguing against the use of the term to include later works with
                        unetched plates printed planographically (<hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>,
                        1795), or those printed from plates etched in intaglio (<hi rend="i">The
                            Book of Los, The Book of Ahania</hi>, both 1795), although Blake did not
                        apply the term to <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> (an intaglio work
                        of 1793) in the Prospectus (E 693). In our contribution to the festschrift
                        for Morton Paley, which we co-authored with Morris Eaves, we claim only that
                        Blake “christened his works in the medium [of relief etching]
                        ‘Illuminated Books’ in ‘Illuminated
                        Printing’” (220) in the 1793 Prospectus. This does not exclude
                        the possibility of Blake so christening works in other media in some other
                        document, nor does it exclude modern scholars from using the term any way
                        they wish, nor does it restrict the historical and theological resonances of
                        the word “illuminated.” We fail to see how we have perpetuated
                        a “restricted definition.” We can’t understand how the
                        simple statement that Blake called his relief-etched works
                        “Illuminated Books” in the 1793 Prospectus shows how
                        “quickly . . . a theory becomes an assertion of fact”
                        (Butlin).</p>
          <p>We find it odd that Butlin believes that “Nurses Song” in the
                            <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> section of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
                            and of Experience</hi> copy E “is not color-printing at all in
                        the usual sense.” Phillips believes that this impression is
                        color-printed, and so do we. Otherwise, it would not be the center of so
                        much attention. The disagreement we have with Phillips is whether the colors
                        were applied with the ink in one pull (Essick and Viscomi) or separately in
                        a second pull (Phillips). Apparently Butlin agrees with us about which pull
                        produced the color printing—the first one—but misses our
                        point. He quotes our saying that “Yellow ink on top of green color
                        means that the inked text was printed <hi rend="i">after</hi> the color
                        printing in green” (97), and from this he concludes that “in
                        other words, it is not color printing at all in the usual sense.” He
                        appears to have ignored the rest of the passage: 
						<q> . . . <hi rend="i">after</hi> the
color printing in green—the reverse of the
                            sequence Phillips proposes for all two-pull color printing. On even
                            closer examination, one can see why Blake printed the text after he had
                            printed the colors. He was actually <hi rend="i">reprinting</hi> the
                            text. He had printed the plate <hi rend="i">à la
                                poupée</hi> with ink and colors together, in the style of the
                            other color-printed plates. . . .The colors printed well but the text
                            was exceptionally faint and illegible. . . . Blake attempted to re-ink
                            the text and print or stamp it into place . . . . (97-98) </q>
The
                        registration, however, was poor; the newly printed plate was displaced below
                        its first, exceedingly weak, printing. The ink traces of the text’s
                        first printing are clearly visible in illus. 34a and 34b of the print
                        version and 68-70 of the online version of our “Inquiry.” In
                        other words, the plate was initially printed with ink and colors
                        simultaneously, like all the others; had it been printed well, there would
                        not have been a <hi rend="i">reprinting</hi> of text after colors. But
                        perhaps this is not color printing in the “usual sense”
                        because for Butlin the only “usual” method of color printing
                        requires that the colors be applied in a second pull.</p>
          <p>It is true that our “Inquiry fails to take up Phillips’ point
                        (103) that ‘small failures of registration in colour-printing 
<pb id="p36-51" n="51"/>
<figure n="1.mhh.10.detail.100" rend="file" width="501" height="500">
	<head>1. <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, plate
                                10.</head>
	<figDesc>Handmade relief etching based on Blake’s design, 15.3
                                × 10.1 cm., color printed in two pulls in oil-based ink and
                                water-based colors. Detail of devil showing visual effect of very
                                slight misregistration of second pull, with colors and ink slightly
                                misaligned. Printed 24 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> can also be seen in’ other plates in Copy E of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>” (Butlin). This is
the sort of general
                        comment in which the advocates of the two-pull theory specialize. Which
                        plates? Where in each plate? What is the evidence supporting this opinion?
                        Where is the “overwhelming evidence” (mentioned in his
                        “Correction,” printed in this issue) that Phillips states
                        exists but does not describe? We looked through <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy E (and other color-printed books
                        and prints) with considerable care and could find no further examples of
                        misregistration or signs of a second printing. We believe we failed in this
                        search because Blake printed all plates, except for “Nurses
                        Song” in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, in one pull. We dealt at some
                        length in our article with various types of foul inking, found in monochrome
                        impressions as well as color-printed ones, that can be mistaken as evidence
                        of misregistration.</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker’s claim that some of the full-page designs in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
were “coloured-printed from almost
                        unetched plates, occasionally in multiple layers of paint” (319) does
                        not, as Butlin states, necessarily imply “multiple pulls.”
                        Multiple layers of color-printing medium can be painted on a copperplate and
                        printed in one pull (see, for example, the ground beneath the figures in
                        plate 10 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> copy F [illus.
                        7]). The crucial distinction is between colors printed from the plate and
                        those applied to individual impressions. The two can be differentiated on
                        the basis of their very different textures (see illus. 2). This is indeed
                        the case with <hi rend="i">The Song of Los.</hi> We can find nothing in
                        Dörrbecker that supports a two-pull process or is incompatible with a
                        one-pull process, yet a consideration of his comments leads Butlin to assert
                        that “exact registration is therefore hardly a consideration when
                        discussing Blake’s usual form of color-printing. . . .”
                        Further on in his essay he claims that “precise registration is not
                        in question.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">3</ref> We contend that
                        exact registration is precisely the point, and we suspect that Phillips
                        would agree, given his statements that “multiple plate
                        colour-printing demanded exact registration” (96) and that
                        “Blake’s method also required precise registration”
                        (97). If the registration were not exact, then evidence for the second pull
                        would be easily observed throughout Blake’s color printing (illus.
                        1). It is self-contradictory to claim, on the one hand, that precise
                        registration is not the issue and tacitly admit, on the other hand, that
                        with one exception there is no evidence of imprecise registration in
                        Blake’s color-printed relief etchings. The issue is not decided only
                        on the basis of general “muzziness” (Butlin), but on specific
                        evidence provided by offset texts (even if one printing is only a subtle
                        blind embossment of the text), multiple platemarks, the nonparallelism of
                        white escarpment lines, and displacements between the image printed in the
                        first pull and the same image printed in any subsequent pull.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">4</ref> We can find such evidence throughout
                        the vast majority of eighteenth-century, nineteenth-century, and
                        twentieth-century prints that were printed in multiple pulls through the
                        press. With the sole exception of the impression of “Nurses
                        Song” noted above, we can find no such evidence in Blake’s
                        color prints. Hence, we conclude that he did not print his plates more than
                        once to create his color prints. We have verified this conclusion by
                        printing facsimiles and recreations of Blake’s relief etchings,
                        intaglio etchings, and monotypes in the <hi rend="i">à la
                            poupée</hi> method that replicate Blake’s various visual
                        and textural features (see illus. 5a, 6a, 13, 15, and 18, and in the print
                        version of “Inquiry,” see illus. 5a-b, 6, 11, 29, 33, 35a-c,
                        and in the online version, illus. 18-22, 26, 28, 49, 71-73, and 76). <note id="n12">3.
Butlin has apparently changed his mind since 1995, when he
                            alluded to “perfect registration” in his review of
                            Viscomi’s book.</note>
	<note id="n13">4. Butlin apparently believes that if you apply colors only
                            to the illustration and not the text, then only the illustration will
                            print and a slight misregistration (or “muzziness”)
                            won’t be noticeable. But the uncolored text still stands in
                            relief as the plate is reprinted and it subtly embosses the text,
                            flattening out the first printing and/or creating a slight halo effect
                            around the letters (see “Inquiry” illus. 10a in the print
                            version; 26 in the online version).</note></p>
          <p>Butlin next claims that, having “forgotten one of Viscomi’s
                        most important discoveries” about edition printing, we cast the
                        two-pull process “in its worst light by making it as complex as
                        possible.” He accuses us of assuming that Blake would have to wipe
                        the plate clean of ink before adding colors and then wipe colors before
                        adding more ink (“Inquiry” 80). Again, he appears not to have
                        read the “Inquiry”—or 
<pb id="p36-52" n="52"/>
                        Phillips—carefully. We are merely agreeing with Phillips (95, 101)
                        about what would be the necessary stages of production had Blake printed
                        plates twice, and we are explicit about why “Phillips is correct to
                        assume” these labor-intensive stages (82). In his
                        “Correction,” Phillips continues to say that the plate is
                        cleaned of ink and colors per pull. It is the advocates of the two-pull
                        theory who make Blake’s processes unnecessarily complex. They fail to
                        perceive that complexity by considering the two-pull process only as a
                        one-off activity that produces a single impression. It is by remembering
                        “one of Viscomi’s most important discoveries” that we
                        were led to follow out the consequences of the two-pull process as part of
                        edition printing—that is, a procedure in which multiple impressions
                        were printed from each plate before moving on to the next. When we
                        contextualized the two-pull process proposed by Phillips within edition
                        printing, we were ensnared within a labor-intensive, time-consuming, and
                        materials-wasting series of inking, printing, wiping off the ink, coloring,
                        registering, printing, wiping off the colors to ink the plate again,
                        printing . . . and on and on.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n14">5. This was no mere thought experiment on our part. For
                            “Inquiry,” we actually used the two-pull process in the
                            studio, using Phillips as a guide, for about 45 minutes. At that point
                            we got very tired of its complexity. For the present essay, Viscomi
                            spent 22 hours in the print studio at the University of North Carolina
                            (16, 24, and 26 July 2002) and as many hours in his home studio printing
                            and coloring plates he made based on Blake’s designs and
                            conducting tests; at least ten hours were spent printing the plates in
                            the two-pull method. This experience (and previous experience at
                            multiple plate printing in the 1970s and 1980s) reconfirms his opinion
                            that for a work like <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                                Experience</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, the
                            technique is tedious and slow, wastes materials, has a high error rate,
                            and, most importantly, provides no aesthetic gain.</note></p>
          <p>To avoid the complexity of Phillips’ two-pull method, Butlin advances
                        a new procedure. Instead of coloring the plate immediately after the first
                        pull and printing a second time, Butlin suggests printing all the plates in
                        a series in ink, and later printing “the same series of sheets with
                        his [Blake’s] thick color medium.” This would indeed be a
                        simpler process, but it actually makes registration more difficult. Indeed,
                        it would make impossible anything even approaching acceptable registration.
                        Unfortunately, to back up this observation will require us to descend, once
                        again, into a few technical details.</p>
          <p>Neither of the registration methods Phillips continues to advance, in his
                        “Correction,” would allow for the production process Butlin
                        proposes. If the printed sheet were held under the roller of the press after
                        the first pull in ink, then it could not be removed to allow for another
                        sheet to be printed in ink. Removing the sheet would quite obviously destroy
                        the possibility of keeping it firmly in place. If bottom-sheet registration
                        were used, then the registration for any one plate would be ruined when a
                        second plate was placed on the bed of the press for printing in ink. This is
                        because Blake’s plates differ in size and configuration, even within
                        a single illuminated book, and thus each plate would require a new bottom
                        sheet.</p>
          <p>We would like to see Butlin test his hypothesis in practice, for we cannot
                        imagine any method of registration that would be compatible with it, but let
                        us suppose there is one. Printing a series of ink impressions first, and
                        then returning to them to print in colors, implies a substantial amount of
                        time between these two activities, particularly if (as Butlin seems to
                        suggest) the ink is allowed to dry. During that interval, the dampened paper
                        would dry. It was standard practice for all professional plate printers in
                        Blake’s time to dampen the paper. We can be confident that Blake
                        continued this procedure in his printing from relief-etched plates because
                        of the consistent differences in the size of the plate impressions between
                        examples pulled by Blake himself and the posthumous prints pulled by
                        Frederick Tatham.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">6</ref> Lifetime pulls shrunk
                        as they dried. Tatham apparently did not dampen his paper and thus there was
                        no shrinkage. If Blake had allowed his inked impressions to dry before a
                        second pull, the image in those impressions would have been smaller than the
                        image on the copperplate. Registration would have been impossible. Wetting
                        the paper again would have been no help, since one cannot control the extent
                        to which a sheet of paper will shrink or stretch under varying degrees of
                        dampness and printing pressure except under scientifically controlled
                        conditions. <note id="n15">6. These measurable differences were first
                            pointed out in Bentley 67. We are confident that Bentley is right about
                            the origin of these differences: “The reason for this variation
                            may be that Blake and his wife dampened the paper when printing to get
                            the best possible impressions, and it subsequently shrank, while Tatham
                            did not dampen his posthumous pulls.”</note></p>
          <p>We regret that Butlin was confused by our overly abbreviated caption to
                        illus. 16 in the print version of our essay (illus. 36 in the online
                        version). By “printed colors <hi rend="i">painted</hi> over inked
                        relief lines” we were referring to the way in which the printed
                        colors in the impression of plate 1 from <hi rend="i">The First Book of
                            Urizen</hi> copy D were painted on to the copperplate (not on to the
                        impression) in such a way as to spill over both sides of the relief lines on
                        the copperplate. The point here is that Blake approached the coloring of the
                        plate in a painterly and imprecise way rather than in the exacting manner
                        required of precise registration. We hope that we did not mislead too many
                        readers on this point.</p>
          <p>Butlin does not believe that we can determine, in the case of the title plate
                        to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                            Experience</hi> copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi>, that the colors over the date
                        were painted on the impression rather than printed from the copperplate. We
                        think we can, based in part on careful comparison between the reticulated
                        surfaces created by color printing and the much smoother surfaces when the
                        same medium is painted on the impressions (see illus. 19 and 20 in the print
                            <pb id="p36-53" n="53"/>
<figure n="2.exp.date.hand.100" rend="file" width="591" height="500">
	<head>2. <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, title plate.</head>
	<figDesc>Handmade relief etching based on Blake’s design, 12.8
                                × 7.5 cm., color printed in oil-based ink and undiluted burnt
                                sienna watercolor. Detail: the color lower right, below the area
                                where the date appears in Blake’s original (only a faint
                                trace of it is present here), was printed from the plate and
                                reticulated as it transferred from the plate to the paper; the color
                                covering the date (upper right) was brushed on the impression after
                                the ink was dry and has a flat texture and stronger covering power
                                because it did not mix with the wet ink. Printed 26 July and painted
                                27 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> version of our essay; 42 and 46a in the online version).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">7</ref> Faint traces of the date can be seen
                        through the gray color, the texture and covering power of which are not
                        difficult to duplicate. The recreation of the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
                        title plate in illus. 2 was printed in a Van Dyke brown intaglio ink with
                        burnt sienna opaque watercolor and was hand colored in a gray made of
                        Chinese white (zinc white) and Payne’s gray. The printed color (lower
                        right, below the date), though painted on the plate smoothly with a brush,
                        has the reticulated texture characteristic of colors pulling away from one
                        support to another; the color upper right, covering the date, was applied
                        directly to the impression with a similar brush and mixes flat with the
                        texture of the paper. <note id="n16">7. In his note 4, Butlin says that the
                            three-dimensional qualities of the paint over the date of the 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> title page cannot be ascertained in a
                            digital reproduction and that it needs to be examined by the eye. One
                            can, however, see in the enlarged digital reproduction (46a bottom of
                            the online version of “Inquiry”) and in the enlarged print
                            reproduction in the Tate exhibition catalogue (Hamlyn 119) that the
                            texture of the gray pigment is smoother than the colors around
                            it.</note></p>
          <p>But our argument concerning the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> title page in
                        copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi> also rests on the patterns of color printing
                        observable in Blake’s other impressions (in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
                        copies F and G) of the plate pulled in the same printing session. Patterns
                        are repeated in sequentially pulled color prints because the colors, 
<figure n="3.wlines.full.100" rend="file" width="333" height="550">
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, title plate.</head>
	<figDesc>Handmade relief etching based on Blake’s design, 12.8
                                × 7.5 cm., printed in a Van Dyke brown intaglio ink from the
                                surface and shallows simultaneously to show the two levels of the
                                plate and where ink is and is not picked up by the paper. Printed 29
                                July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> after that first impression, remain on the plate; these colors in
                        turn guide the hand coloring of the plate. If they were wiped off between
                        pulls, as Phillips claims, then Blake was not only wasting colors and
                        preventing color build up—which allowed him to add less color in
                        subsequent printings—but was also repainting his plate in imitation
                        of his previously pulled impression. In the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
                        title plate impressions, these patterns are all the same in the areas that
                        were color printed, except that none of the other impressions has the date
                        covered. In all these sequential impressions, Blake has avoided printing
                        colors over the date, hooking them around the beginning of the date instead.
                        It is far more likely that Blake painted out the date directly on the copy
                            T<hi rend="s">1</hi> impression than that he interrupted his printing
                        process to color the area of the date on the copperplate in a new color for
                        a single impression. It is also unlikely that he could print a pigment that
                        ignored the physical laws of surface 
<pb id="p36-54" n="54"/>
<figure n="4a-d.date.100" rend="file" width="650" height="290">
	<head>4a-d. <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, title plate.</head>
	<figDesc>Hand made relief etching based on Blake’s design, 12.8
                                × 7.5 cm., printed in a Van Dyke brown intaglio ink and gray
                                and burnt sienna watercolors. Detail of pillar and date from four
                                impressions all showing white lines around the numbers: a. (far
                                left) date printed over in gray pigment in one pull; b. (second from
                                left) date printed over in gray pigment in a separate, second pull;
                                c. (third from left) date printed over in gray pigment in a
                                separate, second pull using less pressure than used to print the
                                ink; d. (far right) date printed over in gray pigment in a separate,
                                second pull using more pressure than used to print the ink. All four
                                methods of applying colors over the date fail to cover the date the
                                way it is covered in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi>
impression. The same color applied directly to the
                                impression once it is dry, however, can cover the date (see illus.
                                2). Printed 29 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> tension to reticulate less than all the others in the same
                        impression. Further, the gray pigment covering the date in the T<hi rend="s">1</hi>
impression is the same as that used to paint over the white-line
                        escarpments that remain uncovered in the other impressions produced in the
                        same session.</p>
          <p>And finally, and most convincingly, there is the physical character of the
                        plate itself that would make covering the date by printing colors over
                        it—in one or two pulls—extremely difficult and extremely
                        obvious had it been done. Illus. 3 shows the structure of the plate, its
                        surface areas and shallows. Note that ink does not print at the base of the
                        relief lines or spaces between letters and lines, and this includes the
                        lines forming the numbers of the date. The pattern around the date resembles
                        that in the impressions of the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> title plate in
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copies T<hi
rend="s">1</hi>, F, and G (“Inquiry” illus. 20 and 21 in
                        the print version; 46a and 46b in the online version). Had the color hiding
                        the date actually been printed, there would be fine white lines around and
                        between the numbers. Unless Blake had previously built up colors in that
                        area and/or printed with undue pressure or with very thick colors (both of
                        which would cause splotching and filling up of lines), the escarpments
                        around these relief lines would be present whether the plate was color
                        printed in one pull (illus. 4a) or two pulls (illus. 4b), or if the second
                        pull had “been printed with less pressure” (illus. 4c), as
                        Phillips claims (“Correction”), or with more pressure (illus.
                            4d).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">8</ref>
Knowing the structure of his
                        plate and the character of his printing technique, Blake also knew there was
                        no point in blotting out the date as part of his printing procedure when it
                        could be covered up more effectively during hand finishing—as were
                        the escarpments around the lines forming the pillars. <note id="n17">8.
                            Logic alone indicates that the colors over the date could not have been
                            printed separately with <hi rend="i">less</hi> pressure to create a top
                            layer above the ink since the colors were printed from the
                            plate’s shallows and not just its surface areas. Less pressure
                            would not have picked up all the colors from the shallows. Depending on
                            the depth of the plate, colors printed with less pressure would appear
                            thinner, not thicker, and have less rather than more covering
                            power.</note></p>
          <p>Phillips implies that the inked date hidden under opaque color is evidence
                        that the colors were applied separately. Otherwise, he concludes, the ink
                        would lie on top of colors as it presses into the paper. Butlin is explicit
                        about this supposed “sandwich” effect. He states that he is
                        convinced by our argument (his footnote 4) that a denser medium or a darker
                        color will always appear to be lying on top of a thinner medium or a lighter
                        color, as we demonstrated in our discussion of “Nurses Song,”
                        but he continues to believe that “ink lines” would appear to
                        be “lying on top of the denser colored areas” in a one-pull
                        process. Because we do not see this visual effect in Blake’s color
                        prints, he reasons that Blake printed the colors in a second, separate pull
                        through the press. But this is faulty reasoning. We do not see it in
                        one-pull printing because the colors are applied over the ink and are thus
                        mixed wet on wet with it. The result is that the colors often dominate the
                        ink. Intermixing of colors and 
<pb id="p36-55" n="55"/>
<figure n="5a-b.mhh.devil.100" rend="file" width="650" height="419">
	<head>5a-b. <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, plate
                                10.</head>
	<figDesc>Handmade relief etching based on Blake’s design, 15.3
                                × 10.1 cm., printed in oil-based ink and water-based colors.
                                a. (left) Detail of devil’s wing and shoulder, table, and
                                right figure printed in one pull showing printed color intermixing
                                with ink. b. (right) Detail of devil’s wing and shoulder,
                                table, and right figure printed in two pulls showing the black
                                printed ink dominating the color. Printed on 26 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="6a-b.exp.det.100" rend="file" width="457" height="550">
	<head>6a-b. <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, title plate.</head>
	<figDesc>Handmade relief etching based on Blake’s design, 12.8
                                × 7.5 cm., printed in oil-based ink and water-based colors.
                                a. (top) Detail of figures printed in one pull showing printed color
                                intermixing with ink. b. (bottom) Detail of figures printed in two
                                pulls showing the black printed ink dominating the color. Printed on
                                26 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> ink increases for the subsequent impressions, because the dabber
                        reinks over the colors and the colors are then reapplied over that ink. The
                        color-printed relief etching based on <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
                            and Hell</hi> plate 10 (illus. 5) demonstrates this intermixing. The
                        plate was printed in black ink and various water-based colors
                        simultaneously; the colors painted over the ink on the wings and body of the
                        devil intermix with the ink and remain clearly on top (illus. 5a). Printing
                        this plate in two pulls, however, first in ink and then in colors, minimizes
                        intermixing, the result of which is a cleaner looking ink or outline (illus.
                        5b). This is true whether the ink is intaglio or relief, whether printed on
                        a press or by hand. We see the same contrast between relief etchings based
                        on the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> title plate color printed in one and two
                        pulls (illus. 6a and 6b). This intermixing effect is seen throughout
                        Blake’s color prints (illus. 7; see also in the print version of
                        “Inquiry” illus. 9, 12, 16, 36, and in the online version,
                        illus. 25, 29, 36, 74, 75). By painting over some inked lines and leaving
                        others uncolored (painting within the lines, as it were), Blake could
                        continue to vary the tonality and textures of his color prints.</p>
          <p>At issue is the covering power of the colors. They have the most when applied
                        thickly as an opaque film on the impression, as illus. 2 demonstrates. They
                        cover less completely when intermixed with ink, as in one-pull printing
                        (illus. 5a <figure n="7.mhh.f.10.det.100" rend="file" width="572" height="520">
	<head>7. William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                                    Hell</hi>, copy F, plate 10.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief etching, 15.0 × 10.2 cm., 1790, color printed and
                                finished in watercolors and pen and ink, c. 1794. The Pierpont
                                Morgan Library, New York, PML 63935. Detail of devil’s wings,
                                table, figure on left, and plant showing printed yellow ochre and
                                burnt sienna color intermixing with and covering the black ink. The
                                ground below the figures shows layers of colors printed from the
                                plate.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p36-56" n="56"/>
<figure n="8.0pen.lines.100" rend="file" width="650" height="414">
	<head>8. Printed colors and pen and ink washes, detail.</head>
	<figDesc>The blotchy colors were printed from an unetched plate onto
                                damp wove paper; the horizontal gray wash lines were applied with a
                                brush directly on top of the printed colors once they were dry.
                                Printed and colored on 26 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> and 6a). And they cover least when printed separately in a second
                        pull (illus. 5b and 6b). A cleaner or sharper outline is comparable to
                        Butlin’s “ink lines lying on top of the denser colored
                        areas.” In other words, what Butlin says should happen with one-pull
                        printing actually happens with two pulls. The facts that the intermixing of
                        colors and ink is present throughout Blake’s color prints—and
                        that sharper ink lines showing through colors is not—are further
                        evidence for one-pull and against two-pull printing.</p>
          <p>Butlin is also misled by the illusion created by thin washes applied on top
                        of printed colors. Thin, water-based colors are absorbed by unprinted areas
                        of the paper. At the same time, because of their different viscosities,
                        water-based colors tend to run off of oil-based ink or thick color-printing
                        medium. Thus, washes will appear to be <hi rend="i">under</hi> a dense
                        medium printed prior to the application of the washes. This is, pace Butlin,
                        a “provable fact,” and can be demonstrated without resorting
                        to “the miracles of modern technology.” Illus. 8 shows three
                        horizontal gray wash lines of various thickness that appear to lie under
                        thick, reticulated colors (burnt sienna and raw umber) printed from a plate
                        onto damp paper, but all three horizontal lines were applied with a brush
                            <hi rend="i">over</hi> the colors once they were dry. This illusion is
                        probably the reason why Richard Lloyd, “head of the print department
                        at Christie’s London,” observed that “in one place a
                        layer of watercolor has been added over the printing ink but under the
                        color-printed pigments” (Butlin) on an impression of <hi rend="i">The
                            Book of Urizen</hi> plate 3 sold by Christie’s London on 18
                        December 2001. Note the lack of specifics. Which “place” on
                        the print? What color is the wash? Is it thinner than the printed colors? We
                        have carefully inspected the <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> print in question (see
                        cover illus.). The thin grayish washes that outline the arms and legs do
                        indeed appear under the printed colors, but all were applied on top of
                            them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n18">9. The illusion, claimed by Phillips in his
                            “Correction” (see also his book, 103), of multiple layers
                            on the title plate of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                                Experience</hi> copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi>, and which he read as
                            evidence of two pulls, appears to be another instance in which the
                            various viscosities and surface tensions of ink and colors trick the
                            eye. An illusion of various layers can be experienced by viewing a
                            reproduction of the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> title plate (or of any
                            color or colored print) in the Tate exhibition catalogue (Hamlyn 119)
                            with a magnifying glass.</note></p>
          <figure n="9.urizen.forearm.100" rend="file" width="650" height="519">
            <head>9. William Blake, <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, plate
                            3.</head>
            <figDesc>Relief etching, 15.0 × 10.2 cm., 1794, color printed with
                            touches of hand tinting with brush and pen and ink c. 1794. Robert N.
                            Essick collection. Detail of left forearm, with gray wash filling in
                            areas of the arm where the color printing is weak or did not
                            print.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>One need not know how washes and colors interact or resort to facsimile
                        reproduction to realize how absurd the idea is that the watercolor washes on
                        the <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> print were applied <hi rend="i">before</hi> the
                        colors were printed. One need only think through the production process to
                        see how unworkable it is to apply colors by hand prior to finishing all
                        stages of the printing procedure. The text is lightly printed in a light
                        orange-yellow ochre ink. We have searched diligently, but we can find at
                        most only a few very small spots of this ink in the design area. The figure
                        and flames, the relief lines of which guided the coloring on the
                        copperplate, are defined primarily by the colors in which they were printed
                        (burnt sienna, raw umber, red, beige, and yellow-ochre pigments) rather than
                        the ink. Thus, if Blake had added washes to the design area before he color
                        printed it, he would be painting on what was virtually a blank piece of
                        paper. How did he determine where to place the finishing washes before there
                        was any image on the paper to finish? The purple-gray wash surrounding the
                        figure’s left forearm is clearly an attempt to fill in areas of the
                        arm where the color printing is weak or did not print at all (illus. 9). How
                        would Blake know that he needed to improve this area before the color
                        printing had been executed and its incompleteness on the arm made evident?
                        The black ink line, almost certainly added with a pen, that outlines the
                        upper edge of the figure’s right leg carefully follows the edge of
                        the color printing (illus. 10). There is no underlying orange-yellow ochre
                        ink printed in this area. How would Blake know where this fine pen and ink
                        line should be drawn prior to color printing? Adding handwork to a print is
                        always the last step, after all printing has been 
<pb id="p36-57" n="57"/>
<figure n="10.urizen.leg.100" rend="file" width="650" height="683">
	<head>10. William Blake, <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>,
                                plate 3.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief etching, 15.0 × 10.2 cm., 1794, color printed
                                with touches of hand tinting with brush and pen and ink c. 1794.
                                Robert N. Essick collection. Detail of top edge of right leg below
                                the knee, with a black ink line, added to the impression with a pen,
                                outlining the leg where the ink did not print.</figDesc>
</figure> finished. To reverse this procedure and add an intervening layer
                        of handwork between printing operations creates unnecessary problems,
                        particularly when there is little if any image printed on the paper. All
                        such difficulties and complexities are avoided if, as we are convinced,
                        Blake printed the inked text and the color-printed image in one pull through
                        the press and later added the washes and pen and ink outlining. The fact
                        that this was the conventional sequence in Blake’s time does not
                        persuade us that Blake did not follow it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n19">10. Butlin states that “creating precise registration
                            . . . was indeed anything but a mechanical process”—which
                            is to misunderstand the material exigencies of printmaking and printing
                            because he equates “registration” with pen and ink
                            “outline” that is done on the impression after printing.
                            He argues that Blake was “forced to fill in the outlines in ink
                            or with the point of a brush” on many of his color-printed
                            impressions because the outline as printed was imprecise. He is right
                            about the printed line being less sharp and wiry, hence
                            “precise,” than hand-drawn pen and ink lines, which would
                            be true of impressions printed in one pull or two pulls. But he is wrong
                            to imply that we think that one-pull printing was
                            “precise” in this sense of the word and hence not in need
                            of hand finishing. We are very clear in “Inquiry” and in
                            its captions for illustrations that Blake finished his color prints in
                            watercolors and pen and ink. In short, registering a plate precisely to
                            an earlier impression from it is not the same thing as adding fine lines
                            and details in pen and ink on impressions. Butlin also equates a 
<hi rend="i">two-part</hi> or “double process” of printing
                            impressions and then coloring them in watercolors with a 
<hi rend="i">two-pull</hi> printing process. This analogy obscures the issue at
                            hand. Most image-making processes can be divided into multiple
                            activities; the question is where those divisions occur.</note></p>
          <figure n="b-los.a.p2" id="b-los.a.illbk.02" work-copy="b-los.a" rend="db" width="733" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>THE<lb/>
	BOOK of<lb/>
	LOS<lb/>
	LAMBETH<lb/>
	Printed by W Blake 1795</figTranscr>
            <head>11. William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, copy A, title
                            plate.</head>
            <figDesc>Etching, 13.5 × 9.8 cm., 1795, color printed and finished in
                            watercolors and pen and ink, 1795. British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Butlin faults us for not discussing the intaglio illuminated books, the
                        “independent color-prints” (i.e., the intaglio and relief
                        etchings color printed as part of the <hi rend="i">Large Book of
                            Designs</hi>), and the large color prints. He suggests that all these
                        provide strong evidence for two-pull printing of all of Blake’s color
                        prints. We disagree and take the opportunity to examine them now.</p>
          <p>Why Blake switched in 1795 to intaglio printing for the last two illuminated
                        books of the 1790s is a good question, but the idea that “the switch
                        was intended to make it easier to print by the two-pull process”
                        (Butlin) is not the answer. If that was Blake’s intention, why do <hi rend="i">The
Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>
                        exist in one copy each? Why only eight color prints—counting
                        proofs—among the 17 extant impressions 
<pb id="p36-58" n="58"/>
<figure n="12a-c.bevels.100" rend="file" width="632" height="560">
	<head>12a-b. (left and center) William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Book of
                                    Los</hi>, copy A, title plate.</head>
	<figDesc>Etching, 13.5 × 9.8 cm., 1795, color printed and
                                finished in watercolors and pen and ink, 1795. British Museum.
                                Details of the right and left sides of the image showing colors
                                spreading beyond the platemark and over the beveled edges. <hi rend="b">12c.
                                (right) William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Book of Job</hi>,
                                    copperplate for plate 2.</hi> Engraving, 21.3 × 16.5 cm., 1826.
                                British Museum. Detail showing bevel at lower right
                                corner.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="13.b-los.2.e1.100" rend="file" width="373" height="500">
	<head>13. <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, copy A, title plate.</head>
	<figDesc>Handmade intaglio plate based on Blake’s design, 13.8
                                × 10.0 cm., printed simultaneously in ink from the intaglio
                                lines and in colors from the surface of the plate. Impression before
                                finishing. Printed 16 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="14a-b.los.bevels.100" rend="file" width="474" height="600">
	<head>14a (left)-b (right).</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, copy A, title plate.
                                Handmade intaglio plate based on Blake’s design, 13.8
                                × 10.0 cm., printed simultaneously in ink from the intaglio
                                lines and in colors from the surface of the plate. Impressions
                                before finishing. Detail of colors extending past the left and right
                                platemarks and over the bevels in two different impressions. Printed
                                16 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> of the two works? How does this compare to over 600 color-printed
                        relief etchings? From this minority report, Butlin reasons that, if two
                        pulls here, then two pulls in everything leading up to it. Such logic should
                        give one pause, given how experimental Blake was as a painter and
                        printmaker, often engaging in methods that are unique to a single work (as
                        Butlin notes in his comments about <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi> of
                        1793). In this matter, however, Blake was as consistent as Butlin supposes.
                        But this consistency resides in his continued use of one-pull printing.</p>
          <p>We have argued that Blake color printed his relief-etched plates by inking
                        the raised surfaces with a dabber and applying colors locally with brushes
                        and small dabbers to the inked surfaces and uninked shallows in the standard
                            <hi rend="i">à la poupée</hi> manner and then printing
                        raised surfaces and shallows simultaneously. Printing the two levels of an
                        intaglio plate simultaneously is a variation on this technique. Essick once
                        suspected otherwise, because he interpreted the colors extending beyond the
                        platemark in <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> title plate (illus. 11) as
                        signs of a second printing (<hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi> 130). What he now
                        realizes is that these colors were printed from the beveled edges of the
                        copperplate (illus. 12a, b). Because an intaglio plate requires more
                        pressure than surface printing, <pb id="p36-59" n="59"/>
<figure n="16.los.5.det.100" rend="file" width="389" height="366">
	<head>15. <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, copy A, plate 5.</head>
	<figDesc>Handmade intaglio plate based on Blake’s design, 9.0
                                × 9.0 cm., printed simultaneously in ink from the intaglio
                                lines and in colors from the surface of the plate. Detail of bottom
                                right corner showing intaglio text, surface colors, and slight
                                intaglio lines in the illustration. Impression before finishing.
                                Printed 26 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> it was (and still is) common practice to bevel the plate to remove
                        sharp edges and thereby prevent them from possibly tearing the paper. Illus.
                        12c shows the bevel that Blake gave to his <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>
                        plate 2. It is very easy to replicate the visual effect of colors spreading
                        past the platemark in <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>—in fact, if
                        the colors are applied near the edge of the plate, it is very difficult to
                        prevent such spreading. Viscomi printed his replica of <hi rend="i">The Book
                            of Los</hi> title plate simultaneously in intaglio with an oil-based
                        black ink and in relief with water-based colors (illus. 13). It is one of 21
                        impressions he printed on 16 July 2002 in the University of North Carolina
                        print studio in a two-hour period. A detail of the left margin of the
                        impression in illus. 13 and one of the right margin of another impression
                        show the colors extending past the platemark and even past the bevel (illus.
                        14a-b). Viscomi also color printed etched replicas of the bottom corner of
                            <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> plate 5 (illus. 15) and of <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> plate 10 (illus. 16)
                        simultaneously in intaglio and relief. The latter impression, with intaglio
                        text and color-printed vignette, is analogous to <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Los</hi> plate 5 and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> plate 6.
                        Blake’s illustrations in <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> plates 2
                        and 5 appear to have been rudimentarily etched and lightly printed with the
                        colors; <figure n="16.mhh.10.etch.100" rend="file" width="335" height="500">
	<head>16. <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, plate
                                10.</head>
	<figDesc>Handmade intaglio plate based on Blake’s design, 15.3
                                × 10.1 cm., printed simultaneously in oil-based ink from the
                                intaglio lines and in water-based colors from the surface of the
                                plate. Impression before finishing. Printed 16 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> the illustration in the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> replica plate
                        was inked but the ink did not print through the colors. With intaglio
                        plates, printing the inked lines of the illustration is actually unnecessary
                        since the etched lines themselves direct where one applies the colors to the
                        copperplate. Blake appears to have used the etched lines of <hi rend="i">Albion rose,
The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi> only as
guidelines for
                        coloring, since they appear to have no printed outlines in color-printed
                        impressions. Their outlines were added to the impressions with pen and
                        ink.</p>
          <p>We do not expect our images to substitute for a thousand words. Thus, it is
                        worth reviewing the contributions to what we know about color printing made
                        by the twentieth-century printmaker Stanley Hayter and others at Atelier 17
                        in Paris and New York: 
						<q> Experiments combining surface and intaglio
                            methods of printing were made at Atelier 17 as early as 1930. The
                            earliest color prints at Atelier 17 were made by applying color with a
                            roller to the surface of an uninked intaglio plate, from which an
                            impression was made on paper. The plate 
<pb id="p36-60" n="60"/>
was
                            then cleaned and inked for intaglio, and overprinted on the same paper.
                            Because this method presented the problem of registering the two
                            impressions exactly, the two steps were combined in a single printing by
                            first inking for intaglio and then adding a surface color by means of a
                            roller. (Moser 35) </q>
Variations on “this simultaneous relief
                        and intaglio printing technique,” which Hayter referred to as
                        “simultaneous color printing,” included “the direct
                        wiping of certain areas with an ink soaked rag, or poupee,” which
                        “allowed the artist to use a variety of colors on a single
                        plate,” as well as the use of stencils, silk screens, inks of
                        different viscosities, and rollers of varying hardness to control the
                        placement of the relief colors (Moser 35-36; see also Hayter, <hi rend="i">New Ways of
Gravure</hi> 158).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">11</ref>
                        However the colors were applied to the surface of the plate, 
						<q> the
                            application of colours . . . was less important than the big idea of
                            combining all colours on one plate and printing it in one passage
                            through the press. Efficiency was not the only reason for adopting this
                            process; it gave imaginative artists an entirely different notion of
                            working in colour intaglio. New textural possibilities, new aesthetic
                            means of expression lay open. In the past, traditional colour aquatint
                            had appeared sporadically; after Hayter’s breakthrough, . . .
                            intaglio printing in colour began to burgeon and is now common practice.
                            (Black and Moorhead 16) </q>
	<note id="n20">11. A thicker, more viscous ink rolled over a thinner ink is
                            rejected and adheres only to the surface surrounding the first ink. This
                            technique is usually referred to as “color viscosity
                            printing,” but Hayter considered that a misnomer and preferred to
                            call it “simultaneous color printing, making no distinction
                            between this technique and that used for other prints made with stencil,
                            silk screen, or offset colors” (Moser 38). Plates etched to
                            create relief areas and open shallows (called “open
                            etched,” “relief etched,” and “deep
                            etched” plates) could be inked with hard rollers for the surface
                            in an ink of one viscosity and softer rollers for the shallows in inks
                            of different viscosities. For more on Hayter’s experiments in
                            color printing and its origins, see Black and Moorhead’s
                            catalogue raisonné, <hi rend="i">The Prints of Stanley William
                                Hayter</hi> (15-16, and 23ff). The reproduction in this catalogue of
                            the print <hi rend="i">Jeux D’Eau</hi> (#208) from 1953 is of
                            particular interest to the present discussion because it was one of the
                            color prints produced from the same plate registered and printed twice.
                            Along the edges and corners ink slightly overlaps from the two printings
                            to reveal the registration. In other words, even a great printer like
                            Hayter in a first class workshop like Atelier 17 could not completely
                            hide the signs of registration. By the mid 1950s, Hayter
                            “stressed so strongly the advantages of printing color from a
                            single plate that an artist interested in printing from several plates
                            rarely did it at the workshop” (Moser 46).</note></p>
          <p>Simultaneous color printing was born out of the attempt to avoid “all
                        the difficulties of register,” which Hayter knew all too well (<hi rend="i">New
Ways</hi> 159). In <hi rend="i">About Prints</hi>, he
                        describes various methods for registering plates, including pinholes, bottom
                        sheets, and pinching the paper with the press’s roller, and concludes
                        that “it is worthy to note that none of these methods is absolutely
                        precise” (58). Phillips continues to suggest that Blake might have
                        used the roller to hold his paper in place, despite our pointing out that
                        the sheets used in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                        are too short for this method, given the circumference of the roller of his
                        press (“Inquiry” 95), and he suggests a variation on the
                        method in which the paper is held in place by a weight. Of the pinched sheet
                        method (and this would be true of its variant), Hayter states: “If
                        done carefully it is accurate to within 1/32 inch even on large plates, but
                        it is only applicable when printing wet on wet” (<hi rend="i">New
                            Ways</hi> 136). This means that the paper must be printed damp and
                        sequentially, and thus cannot be set aside as Butlin has suggested, and that
                        the best alignment one can hope for might fall below the threshold of vision
                        but will be detected by close scrutiny and 
                        magnification.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">12</ref> 
                        Our facsimile in “Inquiry” is this
                        good, but when examined under a magnifying glass it reveals the
                        characteristic ghosting of a second pull (see illus. 6 and 7a in the print
                        version; 20 and 21 online). Moreover, plates that pass through the press
                        twice look the part: “. . .it must be obvious that the full, sharp
                        relief can only be seen from the last plate printed, that of all other
                        plates having been flattened by subsequent passes through the press.”
                        And, as we noted in “Inquiry,” registering one plate on top of
                        another is “typical of the practice of a skilled artisan rather than
                        a process by which the original thought of the artist becomes visible
                        directly in a print” (Hayter, <hi rend="i">About Prints</hi> 58-59).
                            <note id="n21">12. Phillips was, he realizes now, too quick to accept
                            the notion that Blake produced four perfectly registered color prints
                            without signs of registration using just one pinhole, a technique never
                            before used for good reason. Common sense tells one that it cannot work;
                            at least two pinholes are required (see Hayter, <hi rend="i">About
                                Prints</hi> 57). Yet, not only was he willing to believe in
                            Blake’s use of this technique, but he claims the technique does
                            “work,” because he has tried it
                            (“Correction”). We are curious to know what he means by
                            “work” and to see the results. Are his registrations
                            acceptable or perfect and without any traces of the second
                        pull?</note></p>
          <p>It may come as a surprise to Butlin, as it did to Essick, that Hayter
                        believed that simultaneous printing in intaglio and surface colors 
						<q> to
                            the layman . . . will seem so obvious that he will be surprised to hear
                            that it was not carried out successfully long before, as the advantages
                            of producing a full colour proof in a single operation, rather than
                            having to recommence the whole operation three or four times, are
                            obvious enough. Of course it had been tried before, and what happened to
                            the printer attempting it was probably what happened to us many times
                            during the fourteen years we spent developing this method. (<hi rend="i">About
                            Prints</hi> 59-60) </q>
                        His method as finally or fully
                        developed could be very complicated, involving multiple intaglio techniques
                        on a large plate (e.g., engraving, soft-ground, aquatint) and multiple roll
                        ups in relief inks of different viscosities (see note 11). But Hayter, who
                        was “among the first to admit that the fewest and simplest operations
                        should be used to achieve the 
<pb id="p36-61" n="61"/>
<figure n="17.colortest.los.100" rend="file" width="427" height="500">
	<head>17. Colors test, demonstrating different textures created by
                                different recipes for colors used in printing.</head>
	<figDesc>Printed 16 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> 
						desired effect” (Moser 40), identified the fundamental
                        technical problem as “surface colour shifting under the rolling
                        pressure of the press, [which] once clearly understood, was solved by
                        controlling the surface tension of the [relief] ink” (<hi rend="i">About Prints</hi>
                        61). For Blake, who used water-based colors instead
                        of relief inks, this meant making colors that could be applied thickly or
                        thinly to shallows or surfaces and which transferred to damp paper without
                        prominent splotching or smearing. As illus. 17 demonstrates, modifying the
                        composition of the colors can affect their surface tension and viscosity.
                        Too much or too little pigment, glue, ox gall, honey, whiting, or water in
                        the color makes for different visual qualities in the print, as do the type
                        and texture of the paper, the amount of size in it, and the amount of
                        pressure used in 
                        printing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">13</ref> 
                        Painting quickly and keeping the colors moist works well, but so does painting the
                        plates and letting them dry (which is inevitable for larger works), because
                        when printed onto damp paper under pressure the dried water-based colors are
                        reconstituted and will transfer to the paper. The color-printed replicas
                        reproduced here are of this second kind. 
                        <note id="n22">13. We do not know
                            the exact recipe for Blake’s colors, but we know that the vehicle
                            was glue and/or gum and not oil (pace Frederick Tatham; see Gilchrist
                            1:376 and Tatham’s letter in Rossetti 16). At least one large
                            color-print drawing has gum as the medium in which its colors were
                            suspended (see Essick, <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi> 131, 259-60).
                            Additives like honey and ox gall (replaced today by glycerin and wetting
                            agents) impart moistness, prevent extreme caking and drying, and improve
                            the uniform flow of paints on surfaces, while whiting adds body to the
                            color (Mayer 300). The quality of the pigments and the size of the
                            particles to which they are ground also affect the behavior of the
                            colors. Blake’s pigments in color printing appear not to have
                            been ground very finely.</note></p>
          <p>We agree that the large color-print drawings (1795) and the Books of Designs
                        (1796) “represent a culmination of Blake’s color-printing
                        experiments.” But it is not as Butlin imagines. He sees
                        Blake’s development as moving from simple to complex, from small
                        relief etchings printed in one pull, to etchings and relief etchings printed
                        in two pulls, to large color prints produced in two pulls and elaborately
                        finished in watercolors and pen and 
                        ink.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">14</ref> 
                        The development, however, was towards greater simplicity, from
                        printing a combination of oil-based ink and water-based colors from two
                        levels of one plate to the planographic printing of just water-based colors
                        from the surface of a support. Technically, the color-printed <hi rend="i">Albion
                        rose</hi> is the vignette from <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>
                        title plate writ large: the unprinted intaglio line was used as a guide for
                        painting the surface of the plate in colors that were printed onto damp
                        paper and finished in watercolors and pen and ink. The large color-print
                        drawings are, technically, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> writ large, in that
                        the colors were painted on a flat support. The outline of the design was
                        probably drawn on a gessoed millboard (though copper was used for at least
                        one design) in India ink, which would adhere permanently to the support and
                        not transfer to the 
                        paper.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">15</ref> 
                        The composition was painted in colors using brushes and dabbers and printed onto
                        damp paper and finished in watercolors and pen and ink. The outline and
                        composition, the latter in thin layers of dried colors on the support after
                        printing, could be returned to years later and the process 
                        repeated.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n23">14. Butlin does not explicitly say so, but he implies that
                            the large color prints were printed in two pulls, first in outline and
                            then in colors. In earlier statements, he implies that Blake used both a
                            two-pull and a one-pull procedure: “In some cases, such as <hi rend="i">God
                            Judging Adam</hi>, Blake seems to have printed a
                            monochrome outline of his design before over-printing it in his tacky,
                            tempera-like medium, a process akin to that used in the colour-printed
                            examples of his books. . . . In others only colour-printing can be
                            detected” (<hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings</hi> 1:156). He
                            makes the same point in his “Physicality” essay
                            (4-5).</note>
	<note id="n24">15. The outline may also have been drawn in watercolor and
                            covered over in a thin film of transparent varnish or gum Arabic, which
                            would prevent it from printing and assist in transferring colors from
                            the support. Gum Arabic is used in this manner today in printing
                            monotypes in watercolors. Millboard, the thick kind used in binding
                            books, would have to be sealed with a glue or gesso to prevent the
                            watercolors from being absorbed into the board. The idea that the
                            patterns in the gesso may have contributed to the spongy appearance of
                            the color print or parts of it was suggested to Viscomi by Beth
                            Grabowski, Professor of Art at the University of North Carolina, who
                            teaches printmaking. To test this hypothesis, impressions from the same
                            board color printed in 1795 and c. 1804-1805 would need to be examined
                            minutely. Identical patterns of reticulation in two such examples would
                            suggest that they were produced by the surface structure of the gesso on
                            the board.</note>
	<note id="n25">16. It is interesting to note that Blake provided his chief
                            patron, Thomas Butts, with a set of the large color-print drawings in
                            1805, some printed on paper dated 1804, and a copy of <hi rend="i">Songs
                                of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (copy E) in 1806. In the latter
                            case, he returned to sets of impressions printed 1789, c. 1794, and 1795
                            and finished them in watercolors and pen and ink. With the color prints,
                            he did something very similar. Instead of executing new images, he
                            returned to his series of painted boards executed in 1795 and repainted
                            some of them to produce new impressions, dating them
                            “1795” in pen and ink.</note></p>
          <pb id="p36-62" n="62"/>
          <figure n="18.Albion.rose.1.100" rend="file" width="352" height="500">
            <head>18. <hi rend="i">Albion rose.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Monoprint based on Blake’s design, 28 × 20 cm.,
                            printed in water-based colors in one pull. Impression before finishing.
                            Printed 24 July 2002.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>The color-print drawings are monoprints, in that the impressions pulled from
                        the painted surface are not exactly repeatable. The monoprints reproduced
                        here were executed in the method described above. Illus. 18 is a recreation
                        of <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> before finishing, printed without outlines
                        in one pull in undiluted watercolors from the surface of a sheet of 1/16
                        inch plexiglass in place of an intaglio plate. Illus. 19 is a color print of
                        a still life printed in watercolors from a 3/32 inch gessoed board (illus.
                        20) with India ink outline, which did not print. If dark outlines are wanted
                        with the colors, they need only be applied with them, over the India ink
                        outline, as another monoprint from a different gessoed board demonstrates
                        (illus. 21). Blake appears to have used the method more for its textural
                        possibilities (illus. 21) than its reproductive potential. However, he could
                        print two or three impressions from a well-painted plate or board before
                        having to replenish <figure n="19.color.print1.100" rend="file" width="650" height="427">
	<head>19. Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Circles out of the
                                Basket.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Monoprint, printed in water-based colors in one pull.
                                Impression before finishing. Printed 26 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="20.monoprint.board.100" rend="file" width="650" height="432">
	<head>20. Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Circles out of the
                                Basket.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Painted gessoed board used for monoprint, after one impression
                                was printed from it. Executed 26 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="21.cprint.olines.det.100" rend="file" width="606" height="550">
	<head>21. Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Circles on a Platter.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Monoprint, printed in water-based colors in one pull. Detail of
                                textures and outlines. Impression before finishing. Printed 18 July
                                2002.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p36-63" n="63"/>
<figure n="22.albion.rose.2.100" rend="file" width="353" height="500">
	<head>22. <hi rend="i">Albion rose.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Monoprint based on Blake’s design, 28 × 20 cm.,
                                printed in water-based colors in one pull. Second impression pulled
                                from plate without recoloring. Impression before finishing. Printed
                                24 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> colors. Such subsequent impressions are called maculatures, which
                        are usually lighter and less intense than the first impression (illus. 22
                        and 23). Increasing pressure for the subsequent prints helps to secure a
                        good impression but is not absolutely necessary (it was not done for the
                        maculatures here, but was done for a third still life impression). Many of
                        the color-printed illuminated plates (relief etchings and intaglio etchings)
                        have maculatures (see “Inquiry” illus. 12, 13 in the print
                        version; 29-32 online).</p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, Butlin claims correctly that Blake did
                        not repaint “his plate before taking each impression. In at least
                        some cases Blake seems to have printed two or even three copies of a print
                        without renewing his application of paint to the plate, each impression
                        being therefore weakened in intensity” (83). He does not, however,
                        explain how the second impression is compatible with two-pull printing, nor
                        does he or Phillips appear to realize that maculatures undermine the entire
                        hypothesis of two-pull printing. Neither addresses the issue of maculatures
                        directly and thus they appear to assume that the maculatures of relief and
                        intaglio etchings and, for Butlin, of the large color prints were also
                        printed in two pulls, one for the outline and then for the 
<figure n="23.color.print.2.100" rend="file" width="650" height="425">
	<head>23. Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Circles out of the
                                Basket.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Monoprint, printed in water-based colors in one pull. Second
                                impression printed from board without recoloring. Impression before
                                finishing. Printed 26 July 2002.</figDesc>
</figure> colors. But this could not be, since the colors and outlines of
                        the maculatures are diminished because they come from the plate just
                        printed; they show, in other words, that there was printable color left on
                        the plate or board from the first pull (even if replenished in some areas).
                        Thus, the relief or intaglio etching or board was not cleaned of all colors
                        in order to print the outline only. Rather, it was printed again, without
                        intervening steps, to produce a second impression. This second impression,
                        from the same plate, is necessarily one pull. Why then would Blake go
                        through all the trouble of registration when a good impression could be
                        produced from the plate in one pull? That second impression again
                        demonstrates the efficacy of one-pull printing.</p>
          <p>The core question in this discussion about color printing is not whether
                        relief or intaglio plates <hi rend="i">could</hi> be registered (of course
                        they can—though certainly not with just one pinhole), but whether
                        they could be registered consistently without <hi rend="i">ever</hi> showing
                            <hi rend="i">any traces</hi> of that registration. We have argued that
                        traces of the second pull are always present if one knows how and where to
                        look, and have argued from much practice in the printing of both intaglio
                        and relief-etched plates, from the close examination of Blake’s
                        prints, and from the practice of many other printmakers. We have also argued
                        and demonstrated that both intaglio and relief-etched plates can be printed
                        from both their surfaces and incised lines and shallows simultaneously, and
                        that water-based colors can be used with oil-based inks. Blake pioneered
                        these printing and etching techniques as well as the monoprint and the
                        modern concept of the color print as an aesthetic work equal to painting. A
                        question we asked in “Inquiry” is worth repeating: why do in
                        an intricate and expensive way (two-pull printing) what can be done directly
                        and more simply and less expensively (one-pull printing)? As Hayter and
                        other printmakers knew, there is no aesthetic gain from printing the plates
                        twice. Butlin and Phillips do not claim that Blake could not do what he did
                        in one pull or that two 
<pb id="p36-64" n="64"/>
pulls made for better
                        images. They merely keep asserting, without solid evidence and without
                        refuting our counter-evidence, that Blake consistently used two-pull
                        printing.</p>
          <p>Butlin’s concluding paragraph returns to the theme with which he
                        began. We have indulged in too much technical detail, focused over-much on
                        the primary evidence, and this has blinded us to larger issues. Only general
                        knowledge, painted with a broad brush, is allowed. We find this approach
                        unsatisfactory for the study of printing technology. Surveys of
                        Blake’s artistic development must neither ignore nor contradict
                        material facts. Indeed, one can speculate on the meaning and aesthetic
                        qualities of an art work, but to ascertain its medium, whether the colors
                        are oil or water based, the support paper or canvas, the plate an engraving
                        or a mezzotint, the print pulled once or twice through a press, it is the
                        material facts, discerned by chemical analysis, x-rays, magnification,
                        hands-on experiments, computer enhancement, and other research aids, that
                        will prove most objective and helpful. Avoiding Minute Particulars will not
                        lead to the Palace of Wisdom.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P,
                            1977. Plate numbers and copy designations for Blake’s illuminated
                            books follow Bentley.</p>
            <p>Black, Peter, and Desiree Moorhead. <hi rend="i">The Prints of Stanley
                                William Hayter.</hi> London: Phaidon, 1992.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose.</hi> Newly
                            Revised Edition, ed. David V. Erdman. New York: Doubleday, 1988. Cited
                            as “E” followed by page number.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
                                Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New Haven and London: Yale UP, 1981.</p>
            <p>Butlin. “The Physicality of William Blake: The Large Color Prints
                            of ‘1795’.” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library
                                Quarterly</hi> 52 (1989): 1-17.</p>
            <p>Butlin. Review of Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.
                                Burlington Magazine</hi> 137 no. 1103 (Feb. 1995): 123.</p>
            <p>Butlin. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Tate Gallery
                            Collections vol. 5. London: Tate Gallery, 1990.</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker, D.W. Commentary in William Blake, <hi rend="i">The
                                Continental Prophecies.</hi> Blake’s Illuminated Books vol.
                            4, General Editor David Bindman. London: William Blake Trust/Tate
                            Gallery, 1995.</p>
            <p>Eaves, Morris, and Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi. “The
                            William Blake Archive: The Medium when the Millennium is the
                            Message,” in <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Millenarianism</hi>,
                            ed. Tim Fulford. New York and Basingstoke: Palgrave, 2002. 219-33.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker.</hi> Princeton:
                            Princeton UP, 1980.</p>
            <p>Essick, and Joseph Viscomi. “An Inquiry into William
                            Blake’s Method of Color Printing.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 35 (2002): 74-103. Online version
                            available at http://www.blakequarterly.org</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols.
                            London and Cambridge: Macmillan, 1863.</p>
            <p>Hamlyn, Robin, and Michael Phillips. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi>
                            Exhibition catalogue, Tate Britain, London. London: Tate Publishing,
                            2000; New York: Harry N. Abrams, 2001 (with a supplement on the
                            Metropolitan Museum version of the exhibition).</p>
            <p>Hayter, Stanley William. <hi rend="i">About Prints.</hi> Oxford: Oxford
                            UP, 1962.</p>
            <p>Hayter. <hi rend="i">New Ways of Gravure.</hi> New York: Pantheon Books,
                            1949.</p>
            <p>Mayer, Ralph. <hi rend="i">The Artist’s Handbook of Materials and
                                Techniques.</hi> Third edition. New York: Viking, 1977.</p>
            <p>Moser, Joann. <hi rend="i">Atelier 17: 50<hi rend="s">th</hi> Anniversary
                                Retrospective Exhibition.</hi> Madison, Wisconsin: Elvehjem Art
                            Center, 1977.</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Creation of the</hi>
                            Songs <hi rend="i">from Manuscript to Illuminated Printing.</hi> London:
                            British Library, 2000. Distributed in the US by Princeton UP.</p>
            <p>Rossetti, William Michael. <hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers.</hi> London:
                            Sands &amp; Co., 1903.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi>
                            Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
