<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.2.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">“Is This a Private War or Can Anyone Join In?”: A Plea for a Broader Look
at Blake’s Color-Printing Techniques</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <body>
	<pb id="p36-45" n="45"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Is This a Private War or Can Anyone Join In?”: A Plea
                            for a Broader Look at Blake’s Color-Printing Techniques</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>This article arose as a response to “An Inquiry into William
                        Blake’s Method of Color Printing” by Robert N. Essick and
                        Joseph Viscomi that first appeared on the latter’s web site on 15
                        October 2001. A revised version appeared in <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                            Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 35 (winter 2002): 74-103. This piece, in its
                        concentration on technical detail and its assertion that Blake’s
                        color-printing in his illuminated books was only feasible through an
                        exclusively single-pull technique, seems to me to miss out more general
                        considerations of Blake’s overall development in the 1790s and to
                        leave several important questions unanswered.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n1">
                            1. Publications referred to in abbreviated form in this
                                essay are: Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">William Blake
                                    Printmaker.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1980.
                            <p>David V. Erdman, ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
                                    William Blake.</hi> Garden City, NY: Anchor Books, 1982.</p>
	<p>Joseph Viscomi. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi>
                                Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
	<p>D.W. Dörrbecker. <hi rend="i">William Blake, The Continental
                                    Prophecies.</hi> London: William Blake Trust/Tate Gallery,
                                1995.</p>
	<p>Phillips 2000; see below.</p></note></p>
          <p>First, as they say in the Michelin guides, <hi rend="i">un peu
                            d’histoire.</hi> The opening paragraphs
                        (“Introduction” in the web site version) assert that the
                        “first, prominent appearance” of the two-pull technique was in
                        the catalogue of the Tate Britain Blake exhibition of 2000-01, followed by
                        Michael Phillips’ <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Creation of
                            the</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">from Manuscript to Illuminated
                        Printing</hi>, published by the British Library in 2000. It was only in 2000
                        that “printing techniques rose to the forefront of attention among
                        the small band of scholars interested in how Blake made his books . .
                        .” (74). This assertion is almost immediately contradicted by
                        footnote 2 (significantly revised in the printed version, 74), which shows
                        that the question of Blake’s color-printing techniques has been
                        discussed from at least as early as Graham Robertson’s account in the
                        1907 edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">The Life of
                            William Blake</hi> (404-06). This supports the double-pull theory, but
                        the authors discount this by distinguishing Blake’s technique in the
                        large color prints of “1795,” discussed by Robertson, from the
                        color-printing technique in the books, despite the fact that the former grew
                        directly out of the latter. In fact, the double-pull theory was generally
                        accepted, if only as an assumption rather than on the basis of any deep
                        research, until relatively recently. The footnote also refers to the fact
                        that the one-pull method was described by Essick in <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake Printmaker</hi>, but fails to point out that the description is
                        somewhat qualified: “Blake’s technique unites the design or
                        ‘key’ plate and additional color plates into one relief plate,
                        and requires one, or at most two, printing operations” (125). It was
                        in fact Viscomi, in his epoch-making <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the
                            Book</hi> (119-28, 287-88, etc.), who first wholeheartedly promulgated
                        the idea of the one-pull technique at the expense of any other method; this
                        is again relegated to the footnote. The authors fail to point out that, in
                        this respect, Viscomi’s theory was challenged in an otherwise highly
                        positive review of the book in <hi rend="i">The Burlington Magazine</hi> 137
                        (Feb. 1995): 123. Alas, <hi rend="i">The Burlington Magazine</hi>, the
                        leading art-historical journal in Great Britain, clearly does not make a
                        prominent appearance in American literary circles, despite the fact that the
                        review was listed in G.E. Bentley, Jr.’s listings for that year.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
	<pb id="p36-46" n="46"/>
It may seem petty to niggle about a mere footnote
                        but, sadly, its approach is symptomatic of the Inquiry as a whole. Surely,
                        the article was, specifically, a review of Phillips’ views on
                        color-printing in his book and at the Tate Gallery. <note id="n2">2.
                            “William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and
                            Discoveries in 1995,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 29 (spring 1996): 163.</note></p>
          <p>And now, to go back nearly three hundred years for another piece of history,
                        Blake’s prospectus “To The Public” of 10 October 1793
                        (E 692-93). The authors of the Inquiry go to some pains to define
                        Blake’s term “Illuminated Printing,” later qualified by
                        Blake as to be “Printed in Colours,” as being “created
                        simply by printing from relief-etched plates” (75). This excludes the
                        books of 1795 printed in intaglio. It seems far more likely however that
                        Blake is relating his books to the “illuminated manuscripts”
                        of the Middle Ages in which text and design are combined on the same page;
                        the use of the word “illuminate” in this sense goes back to
                        the beginning of the eighteenth century. Incidentally, the authors’
                        restricted definition of the books in “Illuminated Printing”
                        has now become their accepted usage, as in their essay in the recent
                        festschrift for Morton Paley;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> so quickly
                        does a theory become an assertion of fact. <note id="n3">3. Morris Eaves,
                            Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, “The William Blake Archive:
                            The Medium When the Millennium Is the Message,” <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Millenarianism</hi>, ed. Tim Fulford (New York:
                            Palgrave, 2002) 220.</note></p>
          <p>Lacking the detailed expertise and technical experience of the authors of the
                        Inquiry, I must leave most technical details to the better qualified, though
                        one or two points deserve comment, such as the question of the
                        mis-registration of the “Nurses Song” in Copy E of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
and of Experience.</hi> The Inquiry seems
                        effectively to demonstrate (96-98) that what caused the mis-registration in
                        this case was not color-printing but a reprinting of the outlines of the
                        text in a yellow ink rather than the more painterly pigments of
                        Blake’s color-printing technique; the yellow ink must have been fluid
                        enough to have produced a linear, rather than a more general blotting
                        effect, and indeed the authors refer to the fact that “Yellow ink on
                        top of green color means that the inked text was printed <hi rend="i">after</hi> the
color printing in green” (97). In other words, it
                        is not color-printing at all in the usual sense, and Blake soon realized
                        that it was much easier to reinforce such linear elements with the pen or
                        the point of the brush (96). Incidentally, while disposing of the suggestion
                        that the mis-registration of “Nurses Song” proves a two-pull
                        process, the Inquiry fails to take up Phillips’ point (103) that
                        “small failures of registration in colour-printing can also be seen
                        in” other plates in Copy E of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> In fact
                        the authors repeatedly assert that the “Nurses Song” is the
                        sole example of mis-registration (81, 94, 96, 98, 100). Interestingly, these
                        cases seem to have been confined to the odd pages that Blake salvaged for
                        his special copy of the book that he prepared for Thomas Butts in about
                        1805.</p>
          <p>Blake’s main use of color-printing in his books was to produce a depth
                        of color and a textural effect that was impossible in his previous procedure
                        of coloring by hand in watercolors, and it was used for the illustrations
                        and decorative features rather than for the text itself. Linear quality was
                        the one thing for which this technique was not suited. In the first book
                        that Blake seems to have designed from the beginning to be color-printed,
                            <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, 1794, he was careful to
                        distinguish the pictorial areas, whether they filled a whole page or part of
                        a page, from those occupied by the text. In already existing books, such as
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, he did add color-printing to the
                        decorative details that appear among the body of the text. Here the blobs of
                        color-printed pigment can be seen to be more or less superimposed upon the
                        linear decoration but they do not follow the lines with any exactitude. Nor
                        do the fields occupied by the independent designs follow the areas defined
                        by the passages of text with any precision, tending to spread beyond the
                        borders implied by the width of the text. The same happens in <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi> of 1795 where, presumably to match the preceding
                        “Continental” books, the format is larger and retains
                        decorative features among the text. (Here, to complicate matters still
                        further, Dörrbecker has suggested that the full-page illustrations
                        were “coloured-printed from almost unetched plates, occasionally in
                        multiple layers of paint . . .” (<hi rend="i">Continental
                            Prophecies</hi> 319); this implies multiple pulls.) Exact registration
                        is therefore hardly a consideration when discussing Blake’s usual
                        form of color-printing and, despite the assertions in the Inquiry, it is
                        very difficult to see that any of the color-printing in Blake’s
                        books, as defined in this sense, avoids the muzziness that the authors claim
                        would result from a two-pull process.</p>
          <p>The Inquiry’s description of how Blake might have used a two-pull
                        process (taken but elaborated from Phillips 95) seems to be deliberately
                        designed to put this process in its worst light by making it as complex as
                        possible (80). The authors seem to have forgotten one of Viscomi’s
                        most important discoveries, that Blake, in his illuminated books of 1789 and
                        the early 1790s, tended to print individual pages in series with one inking
                        of the plate, sometimes continued with a renewed printing possibly in a
                        differently colored ink, before assembling the pages into different copies
                        of the book and coloring them by hand (<hi rend="i">Idea</hi> 112-18,
                        260-61). The Inquiry admits that such series printing could occur in the
                        color-printed books, as in the argument over the “Nurses Song”
                        (96), and also that the color-printing medium could be applied more than
                        once (84n15, 87), but insists on assuming that Blake would have had to wipe
                        the plate completely clean of ink before adding colors, and then wipe the
                        color off the plate before adding ink for the second impression (80). If in
                        fact Blake first continued with his existing practice of printing the
                        outlines on a number of sheets in series, and then went back and printed the
                        same series of sheets with his thick color medium (renewing the color as
                        necessary), the problem of registration would not have been nearly so
                        difficult, particularly in view of the fact that, as we 
<pb id="p36-47" n="47"/>
have
already seen, precise registration is not in question.
                        Indeed, Viscomi (<hi rend="i">Idea</hi> 126-28) accepts that “Color
                        printing did not prohibit edition printing,” adding that
                        “Unlike ink, water-soluble colors, even those mixed with a retardant,
                        would have dried on the plate had Blake dawdled.”</p>
          <p>Another assumption made by the authors of the Inquiry is that, in a two-pull
                        process, the color-printing would have to be done whilst the ink was still
                        wet (87). If individual sheets were printed in series, first in ink and then
                        by color-printing, there would have been no necessity for this. However, the
                        authors never examine directly the question of the different drying times of
                        ink and Blake’s color medium, though the implication is that ink took
                        considerably longer to dry, both on the plate and on the paper.</p>
          <p>There is also the problem of what actually happens to the ink in a one-pull
                        process. In my simplistic way I see the processes, whether one-pull or
                        two-pull, as producing a sort of sandwich. In a one-pull process one has the
                        plate at the bottom, then the ink defining the text and the outlines of the
                        designs (the authors suggest that there are exceptions to this when only
                        part of the raised surface of the relief etching is inked) and finally the
                        color-printed medium (again applied selectively); one then adds the paper on
                        top. Removing the paper from the plate reverses the sandwich and one has the
                        final colored page. In a one-pull process one would then expect to find the
                        ink lines lying on top of the denser colored areas. In the case of a
                        two-pull process, the inked text and outlines would be applied to the paper
                        first and subsequently covered, at least in part, by the thick color medium.
                        To the naked eye it would appear that, in so far as one can see the printed
                        outlines, they lie below the color-printed pigment. The authors of the
                        Inquiry use enlargements and enhancements to refute (86-88) Phillips’
                        theory (102-03) that the printed date 1794 in Copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi> was
                        covered by color-printing, saying that this was in fact done by hand. This
                        is, of course, extremely difficult to prove absolutely, and the
                        Inquiry’s approach does not altogether arouse confidence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> The caption to illus. 16 (85) reads
                        “Detail showing printed colors <hi rend="i">painted</hi> [sic] over
                        inked relief lines . . .”; are these details printed or painted and
                        which finish up on top? On page 87 it is admitted that the black color on
                        certain pages of Copy E of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                            Experience</hi> “is easily confused with true color
                        printing.” <note id="n4">4. Any form of reproduction, including
                            digital techniques, involves a sampling process. Hence certain audio
                            perfectionists still prefer LPs to CDs, claiming that analogue
                            reproduction preserves subtleties lost in digital recording. Whereas
                            enlargement in color on the web site of a detail of the “Nurses
                            Song” from copy E of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                                Experience</hi> (section 6, illus. 65 and 66; less effectively
                            reproduced in black and white in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> p. 97, illus.
                            32) does convincingly demonstrate that the yellow ink is on top of the
                            green, the illustration of details involving the printing over or
                            hand-coloring over of the date on the title page of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
in copy T<hi rend="s">1</hi> of <hi rend="i">Songs
                                of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (digital version section 5,
                            illus. 46a, 46b, 47; <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> p. 88, illus. 20, 21, 22)
                            conveys nothing of the texture on which the argument is based. No form
                            of reproduction, and in particular none that involves projection onto a
                            screen, can convey the three-dimensional quality of a painterly medium.
                            Examination by the eye, including scrutiny under magnification, is
                            essential. (Thanks to Robin Hamlyn, Rosie Bass, and Chloe Johnson of
                            Tate Britain for introducing me to the mysteries of the web.)</note></p>
          <p>The recently sold independent plate 3 from <hi rend="i">The First Book of
                            Urizen</hi> (Christie’s London, 18 December 2001, lot 84, illus.
                        in color) seems to show, as well as the lines added after the coloring by
                        pen or the point of a brush, printed lines beneath the color. To add to the
                        complications Richard Lloyd, head of the prints department at
                        Christie’s London, has argued to me, unprompted, that in one place a
                        layer of water-color has been added over the printing in ink but under the
                        color-printed pigments. Despite the miracles of modern technology, one feels
                        that such distinctions will always be a question of opinion rather than
                        provable fact.</p>
          <p>Another general point not fully discussed by the authors is that of the
                        relative pressures needed to print on the one hand the outlines in ink and
                        on the other the designs in Blake’s color medium. We are told that
                        printing in color from the depths of a relief etching requires greater
                        pressure than from the surface of a plate (83; Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Idea</hi> 123,
126) but not how this compares with the pressure needed
                        for printing in ink. It is assumed that color-printing from a relief-etched
                        plate and printing in ink are compatible. However, what does seem to be
                        clear is that printing in intaglio requires a much greater degree of
                        pressure (Viscomi 103, 367). That the color-printing was done
                        planographically from the surface of a more or less smooth plate rather than
                        from a relief-etched plate would still create a two-pull process, nor can
                        one see how, for instance, the design at the foot of page 6 of <hi rend="i">The Book
of Ahania</hi>, let alone that filling the bottom right-hand
                        corner of page 5 of <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, could somehow have
                        been applied at the same time as the areas of text above were being printed
                        under much greater pressure. Here surely a two-pull process was necessary,
                        as is admitted by Essick (<hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi> 130):
<q> The
                            pressure needed to print the intaglio texts in these books was too much
                            for simultaneous color printing from the plate surfaces. That Blake used
                            a separate printing for the designs is confirmed by the title-page of
                                <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> .... Even in a reproduction, the
                            deep platemark caused by intaglio printing is visible. On both the left
                            and right margins, the design extends about 2 mm. beyond the platemark,
                            indicating that the design could not have been printed from the text
                            plate. The design must have been painted directly on the print and
                            blotted, printed from another plate with a very light pressure, or
                            printed from a sheet of paper .... </q>
Again, whatever the precise
                        technique, the process was a multiple one.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5">5. The title page of <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>
                            seems to show Blake experimenting in a different form of color-printing
                            to create textural effects on the otherwise blank paper as well as more
                            typical areas of color around the figure; see David Worrall, <hi rend="i">William
Blake, The Urizenic Books</hi> (London: William
                            Blake Trust/Tate Gallery, 1995) 161, and color illustrations on 169,
                            180, and 181. The effect is very different from, say, the facing
                            frontispiece, Indeed, as Essick says of the two Beinecke Library proofs,
                            “these proofs may record Blake’s progress from single to
                            double printing for his intaglio color printed books . . .”
                            (“New Information on Blake’s Illuminated Books,”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 15 (summer 1981):
                            12)—that is, if Blake was actually moving from a single-pull
                            process.</note></p>
          <pb id="p36-48" n="48"/>
          <p>Moreover, if, as we are assured by the authors of the Inquiry, the one-pull
                        process was “more efficient, direct, immediate, and artistically
                        exciting . . .” (100-01), why should Blake move from this supposedly
                        much easier and more exciting process by switching to intaglio printing? It
                        is much easier to believe that this switch was intended to make it easier to
                        print by the two-pull process. The whole development of the books of 1794
                        and 1795 supports this.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> Firstly, there
                        is the simplification found in <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>
                        whereby the color-printed designs are confined to particular areas. This was
                        accompanied by the increase in the number of full-page illustrations which,
                        in the case of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, may not have required any
                        etching or printing of the outlines as such at all. Finally, in the last two
                        books of the 1790s, <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
                            Book of Ahania</hi>, Blake realized that it was easier to use a two-pull
                        process if he distinguished between linear elements and pictorial elements,
                        and also that it was simpler to print planographically from a basically
                        smooth surface rather than from the pitted surface of a relief-etched plate,
                        hence intaglio printing. Given that, in these two books of 1795, Blake seems
                        to have been obliged to use a two-pull process, and given the way that this
                        seems to have arisen as part of the development shown in the previous books,
                        one can no longer assert that Blake must have confined himself exclusively
                        to a one-pull process. <note id="n6">6. I have been discussing, rather
                            superficially it must be admitted, the development in Blake’s
                            books leading up to the great color prints of “1795” ever
                            since I began a series of reviews of the original Blake Trust’s
                            facsimiles with <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> (<hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi> 101 (July/Aug. 1959): 301-02; see also
                            ibid. 102 (1960): 544-46, and 103 (1961): 368); these reviews are
                            omitted from Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake
                        Records.</hi></note></p>
          <p>One must also remember that, until he started using color-printing, Blake
                        employed a double process, printing the text and design outlines from the
                        relief-etched plate and then coloring the plate by hand in watercolor.
                        Conceptually this is as much a “two-pull” process as if he did
                        it in two different sorts of printing. Moreover, the two-pull process does
                        not necessitate “a man who favored precision over variation”
                        (101). It was indeed anything but a mechanical process creating precise
                        registration; rather, it was the reverse of the precision that, it is
                        claimed, could have been produced by a one-pull process. Blake recognized
                        this, in his more detailed designs, by being forced to fill in the outlines
                        in ink or with the point of a brush. Just the same happened in the large
                        color prints of “1795” which the Inquiry leaves out of the
                        discussion. Surely, whatever the precise dates of these large prints and the
                        separate Books of Designs of 1796, they represent a culmination of
                        Blake’s color-printing experiments in which, recognizing the power of
                        his designs on their own, he was able to discard any written text. These
                        prints in their turn led to the small paintings in tempera of 1799-1800,
                        just as the later pulls of the larger color prints, those on paper
                        watermarked 1804<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> (and still neglected
                        for their implications for the dating of the color-printed books), led to
                        the tempera paintings that formed the basis of Blake’s one-man
                        exhibition of 1809. <note id="n7">7. Martin Butlin, “A Newly
                            Discovered Watermark and a Visionary’s Way with his
                            Dates,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 15 (fall
                            1981): 101-03, and “<hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of
                                William Blake</hi>: Some Minor Additions,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 17 (spring 1984):
                        159.</note></p>
          <p>There are also further related topics to be explored. At the end of this
                        crucial period in Blake’s development there is the question of the
                        independent color prints, where Blake seems to have dispensed totally with a
                        printed outline, leading to such experiments as the repeated printing of his
                        color medium under increasing pressure as the medium thinned out from copy
                        to copy. Bentley has led the way with his fascinating article on the
                        full-page plate 21 of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> from Copy B of
                            <hi rend="i">The Large Book of Designs</hi> in the National Gallery of
                        Victoria, Melbourne.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref> This appears to be
                        a repeat pull without any further coloring of the page in Copy A of the same
                        book, and Blake, to obtain a more effective transfer of color, considerably
                        increased the pressure of his printing, resulting in a heavily embossed
                        platemark and the registration of Blake’s relief-etched lines on the
                        reverse of the paper. <note id="n8">8. G.E. Bentley, Jr., “The Shadow
                            of Los: Embossing in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of Urizen,”
                                Art Bulletin of Victoria</hi> 30 (1989): 18-23, recto illustrated in
                            color, verso in black and white.</note></p>
          <p>In addition, at the beginning of this period, 1793, there is the (to me)
                        strange case of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, of which only four of the known
                        eighteen copies (of which three are posthumous) have been colored, and that
                        in watercolor rather than by color-printing. Stephen Behrendt has stressed
                        the “monochromaticism” of the uncolored copies and the way in
                        which this underscores their “radical departures from the visual form
                        of the conventional typeset book adorned with engraved
                            illustrations,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> and Viscomi
                        has pointed out how the lack of color makes “<hi rend="i">America</hi> the most
printlike of the early illuminated books”
                            (<hi rend="i">Idea</hi> 264). Dörrbecker goes further in claiming
                        that the particularly elaborate etching technique, including white-line
                        modelling, of <hi rend="i">America</hi> demonstrates that, at least in
                        “the first edition of the ‘Prophecy’, Blake must not
                        have intended to add watercolour washes to these prints” (<hi rend="i">Continental
Prophecies</hi> 77). All this suggests that Blake
                        was experimenting in two radically opposed directions in the crucial years
                        1793-94, on the one hand towards the richer effects produced by
                        color-printing and on 
<pb id="p36-49" n="49"/>
the other towards an
                        engraving technique by which he could dispense with color altogether. <note id="n9">9.
Stephen C. Behrendt, <hi rend="i">Reading William Blake</hi>
                            (London: Macmillan, 1992) xiii.</note></p>
          <p>Such questions necessitate a much wider approach to this short but radical
                        period of technical experimentation than one confined to the establishment
                        of whether Blake used an exclusive one-pull process or a two-pull process. I
                        do not claim to have answered all the points raised by the Inquiry, let
                        alone to have proved that Blake used an exclusively two-pull process. What
                        is necessary, however, is that those with the skill and technical expertise
                        to research this question should distance themselves a little from the
                        technical details and approach the subject impartially in the light of
                        Blake’s development as a whole. Research along these directions
                        cannot but be more enlightening for our appreciation of Blake’s
                        achievement.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
