<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.2.gourlay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Michael Phillips, William Blake: The Creation of the Songs from Manuscript to
Illuminated Printing</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander S. Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <body>
	<pb id="p36-66" n="66"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Michael Phillips. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Creation of
                                the</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">from Manuscript to Illuminated
                                Printing.</hi> London: The British Library; Princeton: Princeton UP,
                            2000. [xi] + 180 pp. 37 monochrome and 72 color illus.
                            £16.95/$29.95 paper, £30.00/$55.00 cloth.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Alexander S.
                        <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Michael Phillips’ engaging account of the origins, early history, and
                        production of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                        bristles with startling insights, fresh perspectives, and new discoveries,
                        but important aspects of its most prominent arguments are simply wrong. The
                        idea behind it is outstanding: to review the publishing, political, and
                        aesthetic contexts in which the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> arose, to
                        reconstruct as far as possible the stages in which they were composed, and
                        to detail the physical processes by which Blake actually produced the books,
                        all accompanied by compelling images of relevant documents, tools, and other
                        visual materials, many in color. In many ways the promise of this concept is
                        admirably fulfilled. The writing is clear, bracing and energetic, the
                        typography and layout are attractive and readable, and the illustrations are
                        fresh, plentiful, well chosen and clear. The book includes more than two
                        dozen large full-color images of pages from particular copies of 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, many of which have not been reproduced elsewhere.
                        Given all these positive characteristics, it is unfortunate that it is
                        marred throughout by major and minor errors in interpreting the complex
                        evidence about how Blake created the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                            Experience.</hi></p>
          <pb id="p36-67" n="67"/>
          <p>Phillips begins to establish the formative context and origins of these poems
                        by adducing two interesting books of prints from his personal collection
                        that Blake may have owned and doodled on as an adolescent. These
                        aren’t shown to be especially relevant to the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, either in
themselves or because of Blake’s putative
                        additions to them, but they do effectively suggest the potential range of
                        his early interests, and it is tantalizing to see a few pages from them.
                        Phillips then focuses more narrowly on <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>,
                        reviewing early Blake poems copied (by someone other than Blake) into a copy
                        of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> and also lyrics in the dramatic
                        satire <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, of which Phillips published
                        a sumptuous and scholarly facsimile edition in 1986. Certain of these are
                        versions of poems that later appeared in <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi>, and others explore related themes in ways that
                        illuminate Blake’s developing sense of the topography of both
                        Innocence and Experience. Although some poems probably had versions even
                        earlier than the fairly polished drafts we see recorded in these mss., and
                        any or all could have been adapted to the contexts in which they appear
                        rather than being steps in a straightforward evolutionary process
                        culminating in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Phillips’ account of the
                        poetic process is generally persuasive and consistently illuminating.
                        Knowing what a poem used to be or where it came from should not determine
                        our understanding of what it became, but this chapter makes an excellent
                        case for reading poems in their developmental context.</p>
          <p>Some troublesome issues arise two chapters later as Phillips conducts the
                        reader through the much more complicated documents that underlie the etched
                        texts of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> These are more clearly
                        drafts in development even if some may have been copied into Blake’s
                        Notebook from still earlier unrecorded versions, and most contain
                        discernable (but not easily distinguishable) layers of revision in addition
                        to plentiful false starts, dead ends and other expected signs of poetry
                        caught early in the creative process. When the late David V. Erdman
                        documented these changes in his editions of Blake and of the Notebook, he
                        only described the sequence of marks that overlap, and didn’t specify
                        a chronology of creation and revision or attempt to sort out broad layers of
                        changes made about the same time. Phillips undertakes to do both, but the
                        resulting account of Blake’s process of composition and revision is
                        rife with dubious assertions—the broad outlines of the process
                        Phillips describes are plausible and the narrative as a whole provides a
                        very useful perspective, but much of what he specifies about the mechanics
                        and chronology of composition and revision is unlikely and most is
                        impossible to confirm.</p>
          <p>Part of the problem is that although Phillips’ account is not overtly
                        polemical, it is more tendentious than it first appears to be: throughout
                        the book, the descriptions of Blake’s creative and printing processes
                        are skewed by misconceived reaction to the portrait of Blake as a maker of
                        illuminated books promulgated by Robert N. Essick in <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake, Printmaker</hi> (1980) and <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
                            Language of Adam</hi> (1989) and even more emphatically by Joseph
                        Viscomi in <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (1993). Essick
                        and Viscomi represent Blake as an heroic and ingenious inventor of means by
                        which the poet/artist is freed from the drudgery and mechanization that
                        dominate creativity in conventional book production. In their view,
                        Blake’s methods maximize artistic control, spontaneity, and the ratio
                        of productivity to uncreative labor. When Viscomi described the process of
                        making illuminated plates in 1993, he was especially concerned with
                        debunking critical corollaries to the persistent myth that in making his
                        plates Blake mechanically transferred finished calligraphic texts to the
                        copper after they were actually written on something else. In that context
                        Viscomi noted that when writing on the copper Blake could have recorded
                        spontaneous effusions of verse or created designs directly on the plate,
                        without any drafting or premeditation. But when Viscomi wrote of Blake
                        regularly “composing” text and pictures on the copper he
                        referred not to literary or graphic invention (as Phillips seems to think)
                        but to the arrangement (and adaptation) of pictorial and textual material on
                        the page.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">1</ref>
Some of the shaggiest
                        passages of such later prophecies as <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> could have been invented wholesale as Blake
                        recorded them on copper, but nobody has ever argued that Blake wrote the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> without drafts. The critical point that both Essick
                        and Viscomi were trying to make was that every stage of making a Blake book
                        was a fresh performance by the artist, whereas in conventional bookmaking
                        there is almost always at least one stage that is at best a simulacrum of a
                        performance that has been fixed at an earlier stage and in another medium,
                        as when a commercial engraver copies a design by an artist or a compositor
                        makes a copy in type from fair copy in the poet’s hand.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n34">1. See esp. chapter 3, “Illuminated Printing as
                            Composing Process,” Viscomi 26-31.</note>
	<note id="n35">2. The engraver or compositor in conventional book production
                            may be an artist in his or her own right, and may have considerable
                            control, but nothing like what Essick and Viscomi call Blake’s
                            “autographic” command of processes and content.</note></p>
          <p>In a move that is characteristic of this book, Phillips undertakes to set
                        Essick and Viscomi straight about the means of production by showing how
                        hard Blake appears to have worked on drafting the proto-<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in the
Notebook, as if they were claiming that
                        Blake’s poems, including the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, were all
                        communicated to him by spirits while he worked on the copper. Just as he
                        seems to misunderstand “composition” of texts and designs,
                        Phillips treats the word “autographic,” used by both Essick
                        and Viscomi to describe the way Blake produced the printed texts and designs
                        for his books, as a synonym for “automatic,” as in
                        “automatic writing”: Phillips writes, “The manuscript
                        drafts, both in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> and in the 
<hi rend="i">Manuscript Notebook</hi>, make clear that Blake did not write
                        autographically, unpremeditated or from any form of dictation divine or
                        otherwise” <pb id="p36-68" n="68"/> (111).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n36" type="note">3</ref> The word “autographic” actually means
                        “written in the author’s own hand,” and to the extent
                        that it is related to the issue of volition it means that the author is
                        more, not less, in control of what appears in the published book. <note id="n36">3.
Ominously, Phillips has communicated his confusion to the
                            reviewer Vincent Carretta, who concludes that “the evidence for
                            the evolution of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> . . . renders this notion
                            of ‘Blake’s autographic mode of graphic
                            composition’ no longer tenable” (443).</note></p>
          <p>The misdirection of the argument about composing on copper is complemented by
                        systematic errors in interpreting the manuscript drafts of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
that make it appear that Blake, far from being in control,
                        was both inattentive and irrational. Ironically, because Phillips is so
                        diligent about specifying what he supposes to be the minutiae of the
                        creative process (and so careful to provide the materials that we need to
                        corroborate his narrative), it quickly becomes apparent that he is not
                        entirely reliable as a guide through the editorial thickets of the Notebook
                        drafts. In most of these erroneous reconstructions, Phillips treats
                        tentative moves by Blake that were rejected immediately or overwritten as if
                        they were still part of the context as Blake moved on with an entirely
                        different thought in mind. To take one example, in reconstructing the
                        “first draft” of “I laid me down upon a bank”
                        (36), Phillips has Blake writing “Triven” for
                        “Driven” in the last line. Are we to suppose that
                        Blake’s first inspiration was to invent a nonsense word, then thought
                        better of it after he finished the poem? Isn’t it more likely that he
                        abandoned a word beginning with “T” and wrote
                        “Driven” on top of it, then went on to the rest? This
                        isn’t an important error by itself, but as the instances multiply one
                        realizes that Blake is being treated more like an oblivious telegraph clerk
                        than a poet.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n37">4. To take another example, in reconstructing the
                            “first draft” of the poem “I asked a thief”
                            on page N114 of the Notebook, Phillips offers a neat draft of the whole
                            poem ending with a nonsense phrase, “And twixt earnest &amp;
                            game / He enjoyd the dady.” Later, Phillips reports, as part of a
                            general scheme of revision, Blake revised it to read, “And twixt
                            earnest &amp; joke / Enjoyd the Lady,” correcting
                            “dady” to read “Lady” (38-39). I think
                            Phillips has grievously misinterpreted a harmless over-reading by
                            Erdman, thereby producing editorial hash. In transcribing the poem for
                            his 1965 edition of Blake, Erdman supposed he saw vestiges of a
                            “d” at the beginning of the word “Lady” and
                            guessed, in his impetuous way, that Blake must have first written
                            “dame” to rhyme with “game” (itself a very
                            speculative reading, perhaps suggested by an initial “g”
                            that seems to be underlying the “j” of
                            “joke”) and then later changed it to “Lady.”
                            In his edition of the Notebook and in his 1981 revised edition of Blake,
                            Erdman corrected his account of the revision, recognizing that the
                            letters “me” were never written, but he still reported
                            “da[me],” that is, an abortive “dame”
                            rejected even before the poet finished writing it, with
                            “Lady” written on top of it. I think Erdman’s
                            “da[me]” was a figment of his fertile editorial
                            imagination: more likely, Blake initially wrote “lady” and
                            then, either immediately or sometime later, capitalized it with his
                            usual majuscule “L,” which has a leftward loop in the
                            lower corner, thus producing something that looks like a
                            “d” made up of that loop and the superimposed stems of the
                            “l” and “L.” The hypothetical Blake who
                            inhabited Erdman’s head when he examined manuscripts was
                            creative, logical, and purposive, his mind bursting with synonyms and
                            potential rhymes as he writes. The hypothetical Blake who writes
                            “enjoyd the dady” is as unaware of what he is producing as
                            a numb-fingered recruit from the typing pool. Similar improbabilities
                            are specified as fact in transcribing “Thou hast a lap” on
                            N111 (Phillips 52), where Phillips leaves “can” in line 3
                            of the second stanza, though it is much more likely that the word would
                            have been deleted before he wrote it again in the next line. In line 3
                            of “The Earth’s Answer,” also on N111 (52),
                            Phillips has Blake writing “Her eyes fled dead” in the
                            position of a tri-syllabic line; even if we assume that Blake had not
                            yet determined the metrical structure when he drafted the first stanza,
                            he would at least have settled on “eyes fled” or
                            “orbs dead” (another rejected reading) before writing the
                            rest of the poem, and it makes no sense to offer a
                            “reconstructed” draft of the poem containing meaningless
                            and mis-metrical scraps of both readings at once. Once one starts
                            looking closely at these editorial reconstructions one can quickly find
                            as many more that are down-right impossible, as well as numerous
                            instances in which more plausible alternative reconstructions are
                            neglected. It does not help that there are also several annoying typos
                            in Phillips’ transcriptions that suggest the intervention of an
                            officious electronic automaton rather than flawed editorial methods:
                            e.g. “new moan hay” on pages 39 and 41,
                            “jealously” on both 52 and 53. (In his
                            “Corrigenda” of 2001 Phillips lists other errors in the
                            book—see “Works Cited.”)</note></p>
          <p>In spite of the problems in interpreting manuscript particulars,
                        Phillips’ reconstruction of the broad stages of composition of <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> is usually sharp and suggestive.
                        Examining the reconstructed drafts helped me to understand the poems better
                        even when I was most skeptical about his specific reasoning, and if taken
                        with a grain of salt this part of the book would be a very useful resource
                        for anyone studying the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> at any level. The elaborate
                        foregrounded evidence of pens, ink, and writing sessions is a minor
                        distraction from the more important story Phillips has to tell about the
                        these poems.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">5</ref>
Furthermore, Phillips has
                        a gift for finding and presenting compelling illustrative evidence, and many
                        of the photographs, flyers, and other historical documents that he offers in
                        conjunction with the primary texts are important and illuminating as well as
                        eye-catching. (A different problem arises with one of these—see
                        Appendix.) <note id="n38">5. I agree with Phillips that the Notebook drafts
                            reflect several stages of revision, but his stroke-by-stroke account of
                            multiple pens and inks is more positive in its assertions than my
                            experience with sharply pointed quill pens and period inks would allow
                            me to be. Such pens and such inks can produce writing with highly
                            variable characteristics, even at a sitting, if the pen is set down,
                            held aloft, trimmed, recut, or even shifted in the hand.</note></p>
          <p>Following each of the chapters detailing the development of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in draft
are chapters describing Phillips’ version of
                        the processes by which Blake produced the printed versions of <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> and then <hi rend="i">Experience.</hi> The
                        material here has already generated considerable controversy, so I will not
                        attempt more than a perfunctory review of the problems as I see them.
                        Phillips’ account of the publication process appears at first to be
                        an objective exposition building upon previous scholarship and
                        experimentation, and much of it is exactly that, but once again a misguided,
                        partially covert, polemic against <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the
                            Book</hi> bubbles up at critical points in the discussion. Viscomi
                        emphasized not only the “autographic” aspect of Blake’s
                            <pb id="p36-69" n="69"/>
methods of creating printable text on plates,
                        but also the efficiency of the techniques used to print from those plates,
                        techniques which similarly freed the artist from mechanistic drudgery.
                        Viscomi pointed out evidence of small-scale mass production everywhere in
                        Blake’s illuminated canon, and showed that even though copies of
                        illuminated books are often quite different from each other, Blake’s
                        method permitted him to create individuated copies efficiently without
                        having to become a slave laborer in his own mills of reproduction. Viscomi
                        may have exaggerated the efficiencies achieved by systematic production
                        while downplaying some of the ways in which Blake worked unsystematically
                        and inefficiently, but once again Phillips’ account of the printing
                        process goes far overboard in the other direction, and again he sometimes
                        has Blake acting in ways that don’t make much sense.</p>
          <p>Phillips’ description of how Blake wrote, drew, and etched text and
                        design on the plate basically follows Viscomi and Essick, but whereas they
                        were especially interested in the “composition” stage of the
                        process, Phillips glides by it in a few sentences. All three agree that
                        Blake wrote and drew backwards directly on the plate with a quill or brush
                        loaded with an acid-resistant substance, and then etched or engraved further
                        on some plates after initial etching. Phillips does not dwell on the fact
                        that as Blake worked with the resist he could stop and erase errors or make
                        improvements fairly easily (we don’t yet know exactly how easily,
                        since the recipe for the resist itself is still the subject of speculation),
                        so improvising the layout on the copper and freely creating or modifying
                        text or design as Viscomi described would be practical if not inevitable. As
                        part of the campaign against <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the
                            Book</hi>, Phillips emphasizes the existence of some preliminary
                        drawings of elements used in the etched images, but even these are very
                        sketchy designs copied freely to the plates, and hardly prove that Blake
                        never created major images on the copper. The fact is, we have very few
                        sketches of design elements that appear in any illuminated books, and even
                        fewer combining text and design, and those circumstances suggest strongly
                        that Blake usually composed (in Essick’s and Viscomi’s sense)
                        his pages directly on the copper. In spite of Phillips’ arguments, it
                        is also likely that some primary designs for the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
                        never existed in any material form before Blake drew them in resist upon the
                        plate.</p>
          <p>Although Phillips does not say as much as he could about the process of
                        preparing plates, photographs of beautiful facsimiles of Blake’s
                        relief plates “by Michael Phillips” are sprinkled throughout
                        the book (frontispiece, figs. 33, 34, pls. 30, 31, 32, 35, 65) and were
                        featured prominently in the Tate Britain/Metropolitan Museum Blake shows of
                        2000-2001 (co-curated by Phillips). These are probably accurate replicas,
                        and they are impressive to see, important to show, and inadvertently
                        misleading, because they make it appear that the author has personally
                        mastered Blake’s plate-making techniques. When asked, Phillips freely
                        acknowledges that they were created photographically, using a modern
                        light-sensitive resist to reproduce Blake’s writing and drawing on
                        the plate, then etched in stages, as Blake did. At least two reviewers of
                        this book have supposed that these plates were created using Blakean
                        techniques rather than photographically generated.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n39">6. Carretta was misled (443), as was the astute John Windle
                            in his online review.</note></p>
          <p>When Phillips turns to inking and printing from relief plates, he again
                        pointedly emphasizes how hard and how long Blake must have worked, as if
                        Essick and Viscomi had represented Blake churning out prints effortlessly or
                        carelessly. Phillips makes much of an 1839 account by John Jackson (not the
                        color printer John Baptist Jackson), who says that Blake spent longer wiping
                        the ink off his plates after inking than he did inking them (20). But even
                        if we accept this belated report at face value, the amount of time for the
                        whole inking process would have been brief: if Blake was adept at
                        manipulating the printer’s ball<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">7</ref>
                        that he probably used to ink his plates, basic inking (exclusive of loading
                        the ink on the ball) might have taken at most five to ten seconds per plate,
                        so if he spent twice or three times that much time wiping the border of the
                        plate and removing an occasional spot of ink from the etched areas, the
                        total time spent on inking would still be measured in seconds rather than
                        minutes, and probably didn’t require removing the plate from the bed
                        of the press. Unlike Phillips, I believe that Blake usually <hi rend="i">didn’t</hi>
foul the etched “whites” when inking,
                        or if a plate did get fouled occasionally it would usually happen in the
                        middle of a large open area where wiping would be almost as easy as cleaning
                        the border. We need not assume, as Phillips seems to, that every inking was
                        followed by several minutes of tedious wiping (and perhaps reinking) before
                        Blake could take a clean impression. I am not a skilled printmaker, but I
                        can’t imagine any self-respecting artisan who would work that
                        way—usually, one strives to do things right the first time, operating
                        briskly with care and grace, rather than blundering through and then
                        laboriously cleaning up the mess. When we see an illuminated page printed
                        pristinely, with no residual ink smudges in the white areas, we are probably
                        seeing an impression from a plate that was inked carefully and efficiently
                        in a few seconds, without any fouling at all, and wiped only on the border
                        edge (if the edge was wiped, as it often was not in Blake’s later
                        practice). The entire printing process for ordinary relief printing could
                        have averaged as little as one or at most two minutes per impression. That
                        is more time than it would take a commercial printer to print a simple
                        relief woodcut of the same size, but such a rate hardly
                        “belies” (Phillips’ word) Viscomi’s estimate that
                        Blake and his wife could in theory have done the printing for all the first
                        copies of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (700 pages) in a single week,
                        especially if they printed two separate leaves at a time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n40">7. Or a dabber, used in intaglio printing, as Viscomi
                            proposes.</note>
	<note id="n41">8. See Phillips 21, where Viscomi’s week shrinks to
                            “a few days.” In fact, even printing a single page at a
                            time at the two-minute rate, it would have been possible to complete the
                            whole job in three eight-hour days of continuous work—“a
                            few days” by any standard. Phillips also challenges the idea that
                                <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> was printed in “conjunct
                            pairs,” which as far as I know nobody has proposed, rather than
                            pairs of separate leaves, which Viscomi does mention as a possibility in
                            discussing how efficient the process could have been; there was probably
                            room in Blake’s press to print two separate leaves side by side,
                            and conjunct pairs were certainly used, for instance, in printing 
<hi rend="i">MHH</hi>; see Viscomi 107, 250.</note></p>
          <pb id="p36-70" n="70"/>
          <p>For the first copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, which were
                        printed in color as well as washed with watercolors, Phillips insists upon a
                        printing process that is both cumbersome and extremely improbable. In their
                        earlier writings (and in their recent refutation of the two-pull theory
                        promoted in this book<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">9</ref>) Essick and
                        Viscomi argue that for most color printing, Blake applied a variety of thick
                        color pigments to some areas of the relief plates in addition to his usual
                        printing ink and printed from the etched and unetched surfaces of the
                        shallow plate at once. He could then replenish the ink and/or colors as
                        needed and print again, often without cleaning or even removing the plate
                        from the press. The process would have taken only a little longer than
                        relief printing in monochrome—if that took a minute or two per page,
                        the most careful color printing might take twice or at most three times as
                        long, depending on the amount of color involved. If two or more impressions
                        were taken from each inking and pages were printed in pairs (both probable
                        if not inevitable), the per-page rate would have been much faster than that.
                        I think it is likely that runs from a given plate between cleanings would
                        typically be shorter than in monochrome printing, since the plate would get
                        messy fairly quickly, but he could still take several impressions in
                        succession before stopping to clean accumulated ink and colors from the
                        plate, a tedious process. In contrast, Phillips supposes that Blake must
                        always have color-printed the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> plates in two stages,
                        once in monochrome and once in colors, working one leaf at a time, and 
<hi rend="i">twice</hi> cleaning the plate completely <hi rend="i">for every
                            single impression.</hi> With the exception of the obviously
                        double-printed “Nurses Song” of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
                        Copy E, the isolated, slender and ambiguous evidence that Phillips produces
                        as evidence of universal two-stage color printing—occasional
                        suggestions of overprinting and isolated “registration”
                            Pinholes<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">10</ref>—are much better
                        explained as accidents in one-stage printing or the consequence of
                        subsequent hand-coloring. We would need much more and much clearer evidence
                        before we could conclude that Blake always or often or ever worked in this
                        extremely inefficient way. <note id="n42">9. Essick and Viscomi, “An
                            Inquiry”; I have drastically shortened this review, originally
                            written before I saw their piece, so as not to repeat their
                            arguments.</note>
	<note id="n43">10. These “pinholes” do not exist (as Phillips
                            now acknowledges), and wouldn’t mean very much if they did. See
                            Essick and Viscomi “An Inquiry” 88-90 and
                            “Blake’s Method” and Phillips’ response (and
                            Martin Butlin’s) in this issue. I do not believe that Phillips or
                            Butlin have effectively answered any of Essick’s and
                            Viscomi’s objections to the two-pull theory.</note></p>
          <p>Nevertheless, before we can resolve these disputes decisively, several more
                        rounds of careful experiments with Blakean media are due—someone will
                        have to show that it is possible to make Blake-like plates from scratch
                        (with something like his lettering) and print truly Blake-like impressions
                        in color from them efficiently. Though Viscomi’s experimental plates
                        and the prints from them are very good<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n44" type="note">11</ref>
                        and strongly indicate that he is on the right track, I hope we can
                        eventually get even closer to Blake’s methods. The stakes in the
                        debate about printing are significant, for these technical questions affect
                        virtually every aspect of Blake studies. We can’t, for instance, edit
                        illuminated books authoritatively without understanding how he made them,
                        and we can’t read them well without good texts. We will better
                        understand the books when we know more about their projected audience, and,
                        as Phillips cogently argues, understanding the ergonomics and economics of
                        publishing illuminated books is essential to understanding his concept of
                        audience (and to Blake’s biography, dating and establishing the
                        illuminated canon, restoring and preserving Blake’s art, and much
                        more). <note id="n44">11. See <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the
                                Book</hi> and the illustrations to the Essick/Viscomi article
                            (“Blake’s Method”) in this issue.</note></p>
          <p>Some of the new information about Blake’s methods and media that
                        Phillips has uncovered is both sound and important, especially the dramatic
                        evidence of lead white and its deterioration in some copies of 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> and his reports of other new physical and chemical
                        analyses conducted by several other researchers. The description of
                        Blake’s watercolor palette, with nicely reproduced samples, is likely
                        to be a useful resource for anyone studying Blake works that include
                        watercolor. Also compelling are Phillips’ explanations of the ways in
                        which the technical aspects of Blake’s procedures intricately relate
                        to contemporary historical and political circumstances and the metaphors and
                        images in his poems and designs. All in all, this book represents a
                        significant, albeit significantly flawed, contribution to our understanding
                        of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and the processes that went into
                        them.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Appendix: Phillips’ Annotated Edition of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi></hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In 1995 G. E. Bentley, Jr., accepted Phillips’ copy of the 1732
                            edition of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> edited by Richard Bentley as
                            a probable “Blake Book,” adding it to the carefully tended
                            “Books Owned” section of his <hi rend="i">Blake Books
                                Supplement</hi>; he judged that its two annotations are
                            “persuasively signed ‘W.B.,’ probably by the
                            poet” (322). Aside from its appearances in the Tate
                            Britain/Metropolitan Museum Blake shows, the reproduction of the bottom
                            of two pages in <hi rend="i">The Creation of the</hi> Songs is the first
                            public appearance of this annotated Milton. Only one of the two
                            annotated openings is actually reproduced, and the same pages were
                            displayed in the London and New York exhibitions. The encircled, 
<pb id="p36-71" n="71"/>
slightly botched, monogram “WB”
                            that appears there (Phillips 56-57, fig. 25) does indeed closely
                            resemble the very distinctive one with which Blake sometimes signed his
                            art. But this monogram is easily imitated, and I don’t think
                            Blake ever used it to sign a text—only visual art. Further, the
                            rest of the lengthy annotation is definitely not in Blake’s hand
                            and its sentiments are at odds with his usual opinions, so the monogram
                            must be either a forgery or an improbable coincidence, the work of some
                            other “WB.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n45">12. Probably not the lawyer William Blake, whose hand is
                                quite different. See Bentley, “William Blake and His
                                Circle” 177, and Phillips, “William Blake and the
                                Sophocles Manuscript Notebook” 64.</note></p>
            <p>The annotation’s tone and content are not Blakean. It begins
                            sarcastically: “I cannot enough admire the hardiness of Bentley,
                            who would expunge these two last Lines, as proper and surely as
                            beautiful as any in the whole Poem, and substitute cold expressions
                            foreign to the Author’s [Judgement <hi rend="i">del.</hi>]
                            probable and natural meaning . . .” (56). Blake undoubtedly would
                            have rejected Richard Bentley’s editorial intervention if he were
                            ever aware of it. But I don’t expect to find Blake making an
                            argument in which an appeal to what is “probable and
                            natural” trumps all, and the icy contempt in the
                            annotator’s use of “hardiness” (i.e., audacity) is
                            hardly consistent with Blake’s thoughts about inspiration (or his
                            vocabulary elsewhere).</p>
            <p>But the handwriting in the body of the annotation is the most powerful
                            evidence that the annotator was not Blake. It shares some features with
                            some of Blake’s many hands, as does almost any eighteenth century
                            roundhand. Blake occasionally used a very formal
                            “copperplate” roundhand (as in the original title page of
                                <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>), modulating into a variety of more or less
                            informal hands that incorporate some of its characteristics—if it
                            were Blake’s, this handwriting would be one of the more formal
                            ones. But this hand is much too tight (the bead-like minuscules,
                            particularly), too metronomically rhythmic, and too consistent in its
                            extreme rightward tilt to be like any of Blake’s that I can
                            remember seeing anywhere. Further, a damning cluster of improbabilities
                            quickly becomes evident when one examines particular letterforms and
                            common ligatures or quasi-ligatures. For example, in every one of
                            Blake’s hands from every period, in all but one instance<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">13</ref> of the letters “ld”
                            at the end of a word that I have found featuring a retrograde
                            (uncial-style) “d,” it crosses or is too short to reach
                            the ascender of the “l,” but the annotator’s
                            similar retrograde “d,” occurring twice in the words
                            “would” and “cold,” loops carefully up, over
                            and around the “l” that precedes it. Further, the
                            annotator always used the same retrograde “d” in all
                            positions, whereas Blake almost always used an upright “d”
                            in initial positions, often used it medially (and if medial and
                            retrograde it usually swoops forward again), and he sometimes used it in
                            final position—Blake’s most formal hand in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
features an upright “d” in all
                            three positions, though there are a few retrograde examples in final
                            position. <note id="n46">13. The solitary exception I have ever found is
                                in the word “should” five lines up from the bottom of
                                page f9r of <hi rend="i">An Island</hi>; see Phillips’
                                edition, facing page 60; the same brief passage, however, contains
                                four ligatures in the usual form as well as many examples of the
                                usual up-right initial “d.”</note></p>
            <p>Similarly, Blake rarely used the formal roundhand version of a Roman
                            majuscule “A,” almost always preferring a capital that
                            looks like a large version of the minuscule “a,” and when
                            he did use the Roman-style “A” it invariably has a strong
                            horizontal crossbar; the annotator’s “A” has an
                            elaborate curved crossbar, so obviously practiced that it must have been
                            part of his usual “A.” And so on.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n47" type="note">14</ref> Given all these uncharacteristic features of
                            the annotator’s hand, I see no reason to believe that the poet
                            William Blake had anything to do with this book. <note id="n47">14.
                                Bentley reviews some other features of Blake’s hands in the
                                course of refuting another mistaken Phillips attribution. See
                                “William Blake and the Sophocles Enigma.” The
                                “Sophocles” manuscript features several un-Blakean
                                hands, none of them anything like the one used in the Milton
                                annotation.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement.</hi> Oxford:
                            Clarendon, 1995.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of
                            Publications and Discoveries in 1994.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 28:4 (spring 1995): 142-86.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake and the Sophocles Enigma.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 31:2 (fall 1997):
                            65-71.</p>
            <p>Carretta, Vincent. “Exhibition Review.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 34:3
(spring 2001): 440-45.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
                                William Blake.</hi> New York: Doubleday, 1965; Newly rev. ed.,
                            Berkeley, CA: U of California P, 1981.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed., with Donald K. Moore. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of
                                William Blake.</hi> 1973. Rev. ed. New York: Readex, 1977.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of
                                Adam.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, 1989.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker.</hi> Princeton:
                            Princeton UP, 1980.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. and Joseph Viscomi. “An Inquiry into William
                            Blake’s Method of Color Printing.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 35:3 (winter 2002): 74-103 and online at
                            http://www.blakequarterly.org</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon.</hi>
                            Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1986.</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael. “William Blake and the Sophocles Manuscript
                            Notebook.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 31:2
                            (fall 1997): 44-64.</p>
            <p>—. “<hi rend="i">William Blake: The Creation of the</hi>
                            Songs <hi rend="i">from Manuscript to Illuminated Printing:</hi>
                            Corrigenda and a Note on the Publication of Gilbert Imlay’s <hi rend="i">A
Topographical Description of the Western Territory of
                                North America.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 35:1 (summer 2001): 30-31.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi>
                            Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>Windle, John. [Online review of Phillips].
                            http://www.worldbookdealers.com/articles/br/br0000000283.asp</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
