<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.2.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">The Blake Exhibition at Tate Britain, 9 November 2000-11 February 2001, and at
the Metropolitan Museum, 27 March-24 June 2001, and their Catalogues</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2002</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <body>
	<pb id="p36-64" n="64"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Blake Exhibition at Tate Britain, 9 November 2000-11 February
                            2001, and at the Metropolitan Museum, 27 March-24 June 2001, and their
                            Catalogues.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>G.E. <name>Bentley</name>,
                        Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Blake went with his nineteen-year-old disciple Samuel Palmer to the Royal
                        Academy exhibition of May 1824. Years later Palmer remembered vividly seeing
						<q> the image of Blake in his plain black suit and <hi rend="i">rather</hi>
broad-rimmed, but not quakerish hat,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">1</ref>
standing so quietly among all the dressed-up,
                            rustling, swelling people, and myself thinking “How little you
                            know <hi rend="i">who</hi> is among you!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n26">1. Blake was wearing his hat indoors; the watercolor by
                                Richard Newton of an exhibition of c. 1794 shows men wearing and
                                doffing their hats (p. 143 in the catalogue here); see the apparent
                                self-portrait of Blake in a rather broad-rimmed hat in the
                                Canterbury Pilgrims design (illus. 1).</note>
	<note id="n27">2. <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
                                Press, 1969) 280.</note></q></p>
          <p>At the dinner at Tate Britain opening the exhibition in November 2000 and
                        next day at the Tate reception, there were no broad-brimmed black
                        hats—indeed, there were no hats at all. But if Blake had been there,
                        or Gully Jimson either, what would he have made of it all?—the
                        discrete sponsors leading off the quadrille, the cataracts of champagne, and
                        room after deftly-lighted room exhibiting a plethora of his works such as
                        the quiet artist-engraver had never seen assembled in one place. Indeed,
                        some of these works had never been in the same room together, and a number
                        of them 
<pb id="p36-65" n="65"/>
<figure n="CanterburyDetail.36.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="363">
	<head>1. Detail of William Blake, “Chaucers Canterbury
                                Pilgrims” (1810), reproduced by permission of Robert N.
                                Essick.</head>
	<figDesc>“Blake” is fourth from the left.</figDesc>
</figure> had not been on the same continent together for a century or
                        more.</p>
          <p>Of course he would have been dazzled by the generosity of lenders throughout
                        the English-speaking world—thirty-two in Britain (mostly the British
                        Library [28], the British Museum Print Room [54], the Tate [37], and the
                        Fitzwilliam Museum [25]); eleven in the United States, three in Canada, and
                        one in Australia.</p>
          <p>He might have been as curious as we to compare the coloring of early and late
                        copies of, say, his <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, to see how the
                        Great Color Prints have withstood the ravages of time (often brilliantly),
                        and how the seasons have assailed his beloved temperas (sometimes
                        lamentably).</p>
          <p>But most of all he might have marveled at these bank directors and
                        advertising executives and luminaries of fashion assembled to dine at the
                        table of William Blake. Blake’s own private exhibition in 1809 in his
                        brother’s hosiery shop may not have attracted more than three or four
                        viewers at a time—indeed, we know of no occasion when there were as
                        many as four there at once. William Blake as a culture or cult hero of the
                        Establishment would have bemused or bewildered the man who wrote of the
                        world of Pitt and Paine in 1798—and could have written of the world
                        of Blair and Bush in 2001—“The Beast &amp; the Whore rule
                        without control.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n28">3. Marginalium (1798) to Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology
                                for the Bible</hi> (1797) (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                                Writings</hi> [1978] 1404).</note></p>
          <p>Have Blake’s arts reduced the power of the Whore and the
                        Beast—or have his arts been perverted, so that the
                        “Jerusalem” hymn becomes in 1917 a war song to Englishmen and
                        the state itself fosters in 2000 the arts of the most eloquent anarchist in
                        England?</p>
          <p>Most of those who enjoy Blake’s works have to make do with not-as-good
                        substitutes, from facsimiles to mere “reproductions” to (even
                        though we know better) editions of his works in Illuminated Printing without
                        pictures. The opportunity to see the real thing is rare, for the originals
                        are scattered from Vienna (Austria) to the National Gallery of Victoria
                        (Australia).</p>
          <p>As a consequence, a Blake exhibition such as the enormous one at Tate Britain
                        is a rare treat, though a treat which is becoming less rare. Since Martin
                        Butlin organized the great Blake exhibition at the Tate in 1978, there have
                        been important Blake exhibitions in Toronto and New Haven (1982-83), Tokyo
                        (1990), Barcelona and Madrid (1996), and even Helsinki (2000). Perhaps if
                        you just sit still a major Blake exhibition will come to your own hamlet. Or
                        perhaps not.</p>
          <p>The Tate Blake exhibition of 2000-2001 was certainly a major exhibition,
                        mounted with enormous éclat and puffery. It included almost all
                        Blake’s works in Illuminated Printing, sometimes in several copies
                        and sometimes with each plate separately exhibited (as in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
[E]). They included <hi rend="i">All Religions Are
                            One</hi> (A—the only known copy), <hi rend="i">America</hi> (C,
                        F), <hi rend="i">Book of Los</hi> (A, unique), <hi rend="i">Book of
                            Thel</hi> (A), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (B), <hi rend="i">First Book of
                            Urizen</hi> (D), <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi>
                        (E), “Laocoön” (B), <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven
                            and</hi> Hell (E, L-M), <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (A, E), 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (L), <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (B), <hi rend="i">Songs
                            of Innocence</hi> (F), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
                            Experience</hi> (B, E-F-G, T<hi rend="s">1</hi>), <hi rend="i">There is
                            No Natural Religion</hi> (L), and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
                            of Albion</hi> (a, D). Among Blake’s major manuscripts there were
                        his Notebook, <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and
                            <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, but not the unillustrated Ballads
                        Manuscript.</p>
          <p>The drawings included those for <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (all the nine known
                        surviving watercolors), Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (8),
                        Gray’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (5), Chaucer, Dante (29), <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi> (11 of 12 from the Thomas set), <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>,
the Large
                        Blake-Varley Sketchbook and the Large Book of Designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n29">4. The exhibition and catalogue do not, however, include <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Descriptive
                                Catalogue</hi> (which are not illustrated) or the Bunyan designs,
                            and they have only two of the scores of Visionary Heads.</note></p>
          <p>It is wonderful to be able to see the real thing—but some of these
                        works are not the real thing. Exhibits 111a-d are copperplates made and
                        printed by Michael Phillips, and #103 is a rolling press with arms about
                        9’ high, much higher than the ceiling of the only surviving room in
                        which Blake printed, in his cottage at Felpham.</p>
          <p>The most rewarding of the exhibits were those which cannot be adequately
                        reproduced, either because of their size or because of their medium. Most
                        impressive among the originals of the watercolors are the “Vision of
                        the Last Judgement,” 20” × 15½” (#59,
                        Petworth House), “An Allegory of the Spiritual Condition of
                        Man,” 59 5/8” × 47 ¾” (#60), and
                        Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims tempera, 18 3/8” × 53
                        15/16” (#62). But the most extraordinary effect is made by the
                        complete series of twelve Large Colour Prints (#241-52) which have rarely
                        been seen together—even Butts, his chief 
<pb id="p36-66" n="66"/>
                        patron at the time, did not have a complete set. They are enormous, c.
                        18” × 24”, no method of reproducing their
                        three-dimensional effects is at all satisfactory, and their cumulative
                        effect is well-nigh overwhelming.</p>
          <p>The exhibition was organized chiefly by Robin Hamlyn, and the catalogue is a
                        worthy memorial of the exhibition. The pro forma essays by Peter Ackroyd<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">5</ref> and Marilyn Butler<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">6</ref> are remarkable for little more than good will. 
<note id="n30">5. Ackroyd’s “William Blake: The Man” (pp.
                            11-13) is notable for his knighting of “Sir William
                            Hayley” (p. 13), rectifying an omission by George III.</note>
	<note id="n31">6. Marilyn Butler, “Blake in his Time” (pp.
                            15-25) speaks of Blake’s “death at seventy” (p. 14:
                            he was 69), “his first volume of poems (<hi rend="i">Songs of
                                Innocence</hi>, 1789)” (p. 14: his “first volume of
                            poems” was <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> [1783]),
                            “the busy printing house of the publisher Joseph Johnson”
                            (p. 17: Joseph Johnson had no printing house; he farmed his books to
                            numerous printers), and “Blake’s paganism” (p.
                            19).</note></p>
          <p>The catalogue<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">7</ref> is very
generously
                        illustrated, though the reproductions vary capriciously in size; for
                        instance, the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> designs are reproduced in three
                        radically different sizes, though the originals are all approximately the
                        same size. The reproductions include all those known for <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (9),
29 for Dante, 8 for <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (A), <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (L-M) entire, 9 from 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                        (B), 16 from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (E), and 22 from the Bible. <note id="n32">7.
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: Tate, 2000)
                            4°, 304 pp., 286 plates, ISBN: 1854373145, £29.99; (New
                            York: Harry N. Abrams, 2001) ISBN: 0810957108, $75.00, hardcover. The
                            “Catalogue” (pp. 29-293) is by Christine Riding, David
                            Blayney Brown, Elizabeth Barker, Ian Warrell, Lizzie Carey-Thomas,
                            Martin Postle, Martin Myrone, Michael Phillips, Noa Cahaner McManus, and
                            Robin Hamlyn. The Abrams version adds a “Checklist of Works
                            Exhibited at the Metropolitan Museum of Art” (pp. 299-304), with
                            far fewer works than in the Tate exhibition and some
                        additions.</note></p>
          <p>The catalogue is useful and responsible. However, Richard Edwards was
                        scarcely “the leading London bookseller” (p. 52), though his
                        brother James might be so described, and Boydell’s Shakspeare Gallery
                        was not “abandoned” (p. 52).</p>
          <p>The most original part of the catalogue is Michael Phillips, “The
                        Furnace of Lambeth’s Vale” (pp. 98-171). He claims, as he does
                        in his <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Creation of the</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">From
Manuscript to Illuminated Printing</hi> (London: British
                        Library, 2000), with many of the same reproductions, that the proprietary
                        chapel built in 1793 in Lambeth was “built on the village
                        green” (p. 145), as background for “The Garden of
                        Love,” but he offers no evidence that it was indeed on the village
                        green, as is the plain intent of “The Garden of Love” (1794),
                        and there is no village green on the map of Lambeth which he reproduces (p.
                        145). In the anti-Paine riots in October 1793, “The fires would have
                        been clearly seen from . . . Hercules Buildings” where Blake lived
                        (p. 154), but no evidence is offered. “Clearly, any ambitions that
                        Blake had to engage publicly in the debate provoked by the events in France
                        had been suppressed” in the autumn of 1793 (p. 154), but Blake
                        produced <hi rend="i">America</hi> (1793), <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Experience</hi> (1794), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794), and <hi rend="i">Song of
Los</hi> (1795), in each of which an assiduous informer
                        could easily have found generous evidence for his sympathies with
                        revolutionary France. And Dr. Phillips insists (e.g., p. 107), as he does in
                            <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (2000), that Blake’s color prints
                        passed through the press twice, once with the basic design in monochrome and
                        a second time with the colors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">8</ref> Most
                        Blake scholars doubt his conclusion. <note id="n33">8. The argument is based
                            in significant part on evidence which does not exist; see Robert N.
                            Essick and Joseph Viscomi, “An Inquiry into William
                            Blake’s Method of Color Printing,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 35 (winter 2002): 74-103, and
                            www.blakequarterly.org.</note></p>
          <p>For those who could not see the exhibition at the Tate, a somewhat diminished
                        version of it was exhibited at the Metropolitan Museum in New York on 27
                        March-24 June 2001.</p>
          <p>Both exhibition and catalogues are achievements of extraordinary ambition and
                        accomplishment. All who made it possible deserve our thanks.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
