<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.3.news</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Blake exhibition at the Huntington Library</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2002/2003</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002/2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Minckler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002/2003"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <body>
	  <pb id="p36-91" n="91"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <p>The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens in San Marino, California, will
present a major William Blake exhibition, 19 January 2003 to 25 May 2003. The show, entitled “Vision and
Verse: William Blake at The Huntington,” will be curated by Robert N. Essick. The Huntington has mounted a
number of small Blake exhibitions over the years, but space limitations meant that only a few dozen works
could be displayed at any one time. The recent development of the former carriage house on the Huntington
grounds into the MaryLou and George Boone Gallery will permit a generous selection of the Blake collection to
be shown. All the watercolors, including the three series illustrating John Milton’s poetry, will be
included, along with many plates from Blake’s illuminated books, the Job and Dante engravings, drawings,
manuscripts, separate plates, and commercial book illustrations. The exhibit will honor the institution’s
founder, Henry E. Huntington, for his prescience in collecting outstanding works by Blake at a time when the
artist/poet was still little known. There will be no catalogue, but an illustrated brochure will be available
free of charge to all those who visit the exhibition. Further information about the Huntington and its
exhibition program is available online at www.huntington.org.</p>
        <p>For other newsletter items, see our web site at www.blakequarterly.org.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
