<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>36.3.heppner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Bathsheba Revisited</title>
        <author n="Heppner">Christopher Heppner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2002/2003</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2002/2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">36.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Minckler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2002/2003"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_36">
    <body>
      <pb id="p36-76" n="76"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-36-3-0006">
        <figure n="but390.1.1.pt" id="but390.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="672">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
          <head>1. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Bathsheba at the Bath.</hi></head>
          <figDesc>© Tate, London 2001.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head>
          <title type="main">Bathsheba Revisited</title>
        </head>
        <byline>By <docAuthor>Christopher <name>Heppner</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>The present essay is prompted by two desires, the first to delete and overwrite what I now consider
a mistaken reading offered some years ago of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Bathsheba at the Bath</hi> (Tate, B 390;
illus. 1),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> and the second to revisit
the complex interactions between already existing narratives and Blake’s own thoughts and mythology, in a
further effort to understand the process of invention that created such images. Associated with this latter
aim is the desire to explore again the reasons for the resistance of many of Blake’s designs, including
this, to definitive interpretation. <note id="n1">1. Christopher Heppner, <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s
Designs</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1995) 175-78.</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Bathsheba</hi> has to date drawn little commentary, most of that little focused on
questions of style. Bindman calls it “strikingly Venetian” in spirit, pointing to the “sensuality of the
naked figures” as suggestive of Correggio, and to the “luxuriance of the palm trees by the pond” (has he
mistaken the ornamental wooden pillars for trees?) as prompted by “study of original paintings by Titian and
perhaps Veronese.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Butlin’s
catalogue entry comments that “This particularly sensuous picture suggests the influence of Parmigianino or
Correggio, whose work would have been known to Blake through engravings if not from actual paintings.”
Neither of these writers aims at a detailed reading of the design. <note id="n2">2. David Bindman, 
<hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977) 127.</note></p>
        <p>My first attempt to interpret the design focused on the anomalous presence of the two children; the
Bible records no children born to Bathsheba before David’s abduction, and no such children appear in
previous illustrations of the episode. I proposed that this made it impossible to identify the central figure
as Bathsheba, and that she must represent Maachah, a previous wife of David, with her two children Absalom and
Tamar (1 Chronicles 3:2 and 2 Samuel 13). I identified the seated woman at our left as
<pb id="p36-77" n="77"/>
Bathsheba, despite her visually subordinate position. Though the presence of those children still presents a
major problem, I now find unacceptable both the radical disjunction that reading created between the center of
implied narrative interest and the center of visual attention, and the associated displacement of a slim and
attractive young woman by a heavier, even Rubenesque figure of doubtful seductiveness in Blake’s eyes. I
retract that reading and try again, beginning with a brief sketch of some key moments in the interpretive
history of the scene in order to foreground what is new and different in Blake’s version of the
episode.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n3">3. See Elisabeth Kunoth-Leifels, <hi rend="i">Uber die Darstellungen der “Bathseba im
Bade”: Studien zur Geschichte des Bildthemas 4. bis 17. Jahrhundert</hi> (Essen, 1962), for an overview of
the iconographic history up to the late seventeenth century.</note></p>
        <p>Medieval interpretation read the scene typologically as representing the marriage between David as
Christ and Bathsheba as the Church, the latter washing herself in order to become worthy of her
spouse.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> In late medieval times there
was a shift from typology towards moralizing, Bathsheba often being used as an illustration of the dangerous
seductiveness of female beauty, particularly when nakedly exposed. <note id="n4">4. Louis Réau, 
<hi rend="i">Iconographie De L’Art Chrétien</hi> (Paris: Presses Universitaires de France, 1957) II.i.273. See
also Edgar Wind, <hi rend="i">Pagan Mysteries in the Renaissance</hi> (New York: Norton, 1968) 27, for St.
Gregory’s allegory, that makes David innocent, and Uriah culpable.</note></p>
        <p>The subject was not common in the early Renaissance, but a little later Raphael created a version
for the loggia of the Vatican, reproduced in several engravings, including one by Sisto Badalocchio. Raphael
shows David in the background watching Bathsheba, who sits alone in the foreground on a raised terrace beside
a large basin of water, combing out her hair, and naked apart from draped loins. Along the street separating
Bathsheba from David run a multitude of armed soldiers, two or three of whom look at Bathsheba as they rush
by, though the majority disregard such charming but for the moment irrelevant sights. The design implies that
Bathsheba is being rather ostentatious in appearing in so public a space, but does not clear David from guilt,
as his better disciplined soldiers show.</p>
        <p>Giulio Romano designed (Rinaldo did the actual painting) a series of frescoes on the life of David
for a loggia in the Palazzo del Te in Mantua. The <hi rend="i">Toilet of Bathsheba</hi> shows her tended by
three young maidservants. The sequel, <hi rend="i">David Spying upon Bathsheba</hi>, shows a nude Bathsheba
with her foot in a fountain; an attendant holds a drape up behind her, as if to protect her from the eyes of
David, who looks across from a nearby window, accompanied by another man who points towards Bathsheba. There
are flowers around the balustrade of the fountain, and trees in the background.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Verheyen suggests that the fresco reflects Romano’s desire
to please his patron Federigo Il Gonzago, who hired Romano to build and decorate a splendid palace outside
Mantua. Like David, Gonzago had loved another man’s wife, and had caused the death of her husband; Romano
may have intended to use the parallels to clear both David and Gonzago of serious wrongdoing: “What was
lawful for the gods could not be wrong for Federigo; if he considered himself a second David, why then should
he be ashamed of his love of someone else’s wife?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n5">5. The frescoes are reproduced in Frederick Hartt, <hi rend="i">Giulio Romano</hi> (New Haven:
Yale University Press, 1958) vol. 2, #334, 335. See also Ernst Gombrich et al., <hi rend="i">Giulio
Romano</hi> (Milan: Electa, 1989) 364.</note>
	<note id="n6">6. Egon Verheyen, <hi rend="i">The Palazzo del Te in Mantua: Images of Love and Politics</hi>
(Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1977) 33.</note></p>
        <p>The subject also attracted a few Venetian painters. Paris Bordone produced a version, now in
Cologne, interesting for its Serlio-based perspective architecture and for the lemon bushes behind Bathsheba
and her assistants, which suggest the possibility of a botanical allegory, since lemon trees were often
interpreted as connoting the bittersweet nature of erotic experience.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Veronese also painted a version, now at Lyons, notable for a fully dressed
Bathsheba, who sits below a nude male sculpture and is addressed by a mature, bearded man who looks oddly out
of character as he seems to plead David’s case.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n7">7. See Peter Daly, ed., <hi rend="i">Andreas Alciatus</hi>, 2 vols. (Toronto: University of
Toronto Press, 1985) Emblem 207.</note>
	<note id="n8">8. Both of these are illustrated and discussed by kunoth-Leifels, <hi rend="i">Darstellung</hi>
illus. 30 and 31, pp. 39-42.</note></p>
        <p>The Flemish Hans Memling produced an interesting version in the second half of the fifteenth
century, now in Stuttgart. This indoor scene shows a nude Bathsheba stepping out of an elaborate bath as she
is helped into a white shift by a young servant. On the floor are waiting slippers, an empty plate, a pitcher,
and a small dog. There is an open window through which can be seen the small figure of David watching intently
from a distant balcony. He is very much a peeping-Tom intruder, while Bathsheba’s modest behavior absolves
her of any charge of provocative self-display. The decorously domestic atmosphere suggests that Memling may be
responding to the text’s implication that the washing observed by David may have been the ritual cleansing
after menstruation: “for she was purified from her uncleanness” (2 Samuel 11:4).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n9">9. The painting is reproduced, and very briefly discussed, in Bruce Bernard, <hi rend="i">The
Bible and its Painters</hi> (New York: Macmillan, 1983) 99 and 284.</note></p>
        <p>The northern Protestant tradition, developed in German and Netherlandish prints in the first half
of the sixteenth century, placed Bathsheba among other unchaste or seductive women.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Dürer’s 1521 sketch for the council room at <corr type="emend">Nuremberg</corr>
showing, in separate episodes, Bathsheba in the bath, Samson and Delilah, and Aristotle and Phyllis, is in
<pb id="p36-78" n="78"/>
this tradition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Heinrich Aldegrever,
praised by Blake as one of the “old original Engravers, who were great Masters in Painting and Designing”
(<hi rend="i">First Chaucer Prospectus</hi>, E 567), produced an interesting print in 1532 (illus.
2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> This shows a naked and seated
Bathsheba in full view of David. Her left arm suggests the gesture of the Medici <hi rend="i">Venus
pudica</hi>, though her hand covers her shoulder rather than her breast; perhaps she is showing modesty before
David’s gaze. Another equally naked woman stands to our left; her relationship with Bathsheba is not made
clear, though I see no implication that she is a maidservant. Maarten van Heemskerck produced an influential
composition ca. 1566 made known through an engraving by Herman J. Muller distributed in several editions,
including one signed by Hieronymus Cock. In this design, Bathsheba, tended by several maidservants, reaches
out to receive a letter from David’s messenger; an ointment jar, a jewel box, and a mirror emphasize that
Bathsheba is preening herself, and evoke associations with such allegorical figures as Superbia and Vanity.
The design is in fact the sixth in a series drawn by van Heemskerck to illustrate the Ten Commandments, and
has the words “non moechaberis.exod.xx” (“Thou shalt not commit adultery”) along the lower
edge.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> In many of the northern
versions an old woman appeared, regularly interpreted as a bawd, and often carrying a letter understood to be
from David. In addition to the adulterous implications of this, the juxtaposition of old and young reflected
both vanity and the transience of earthly beauty.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> The moral climate had become distinctly chilly for Bathsheba. <note id="n10">10. Eric Jan
Sluitjer, “Rembrandt’s Bathsheba and the Conventions of a Seductive Theme,” in Ann Jensen Adams, ed.,
<hi rend="i">Rembrandt’s “Bathsheba Reading King David’s Letter”</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University
Press, 1998) 49.</note>
	<note id="n11">11. Kunoth-Leifels, <hi rend="i">Darstellung</hi> illus. 25a and 25b, and p. 33.</note>
	<note id="n12">12. Kunoth-Leifels, <hi rend="i">Darstellung</hi> 44-45.</note>
	<note id="n13">13. Sluitjer, “Rembrandt’s Bathsheba” 50, and Ilja M. Veldman (comp.), Ger Luijten
(ed.), <hi rend="i">The New Hollstein Dutch and Flemish Etchings, Engravings and Woodcuts, 1450-1700: Maarten
van Heemskerck, Part I</hi> (Roosendaal, Netherlands: Koninklijke von Poll, 1993) 66-67.</note>
	<note id="n14">14. Sluitjer, “Rembrandt’s Bathsheba” 52-53.</note></p>
        <figure n="Aldegrever.Bathsheba.36.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="509">
          <head>2. Heinrich Aldegrever, <hi rend="i">Bathsheba at the Bath.</hi></head>
          <figDesc>Courtesy British Museum, Department of Prints and Drawings.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>Rembrandt produced two versions of the story; the first, dated 1643, “portrayed Bathsheba as a
more or less ‘active’ seductress”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> his later (1654) and more famous Louvre version of <hi rend="i">Bathsheba Reading King
David’s Letter</hi> offers a more complex response to the story. It was in London by the early nineteenth
century, but was not reproduced in a print before 1876, and was almost certainly unknown to Blake.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> This shows an older woman tending
Bathsheba’s foot, while the latter holds a letter, already it seems read and now being digested; whether the
older woman was also the bearer of the letter is unclear. Bathsheba is conspicuously bejewelled. The feelings
passing over her face are complex and subtle, but taken together with the jewels suggest some degree of
complicity or acceptance. <note id="n15">15. Sluitjer, “Rembrandt’s Bathsheba” 81.</note>
	<note id="n16">16. Gary Schwartz states that the painting, bought by William Young Ottley some time before
1811, was not mentioned in any published record before that date: “‘Though deficient in beauty’: A
Documentary History and Interpretation of Rembrandt’s 1654 Painting of Bathsheba,” in Adams, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Rembrandt’s “Bathsheba”</hi> 176-80. Blake did not make Ottley’s acquaintance until
1827—see G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969) 341.</note></p>
        <p>The last painting I shall mention is that by Rubens, now at Dresden, painted before Rembrandt’s
second version. Here Bathsheba sits beside a fountain, her breasts and thigh fetchingly exposed to the viewer
though her loins are draped and her nearer arm is lightly veiled. Her hair is being combed by a young female
attendant, while she looks over her shoulder at a black page who proffers a letter, evidently an invitation or
summons from the David visible on the balcony of the palace behind the bathing scene. A pearl string is draped
around her left forearm, and hangs down between her fingers.</p>
        <p>The iconographic history shows that Bathsheba was often seen as a woman of some wealth, proud of
her appearance and grooming, and not averse to making a public display of her beauty. Many images imply that
she shares in
<pb id="p36-79" n="79"/>
David’s guilt by her self-exposure, triggering his desire to possess her. She is frequently shown with
attendants, who are often tainted with the suspicion of acting as bawds to David’s desires, a function
sometimes made explicit by the non-biblical motif of the bearing of a letter of assignation. Such implications
of female complicity or worse in Bathsheba’s fate have aroused such feminist commentary as that embodied in
the collection of essays edited by Ann Jensen Adams and in Mieke Bal’s <hi rend="i">Lethal Love</hi>
(Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1987).</p>
        <p>Blake may have known a few of these versions through prints, but his version has very little in
common with any of them, except in showing David as a small and distant figure, and in possibly following
Aldegrever’s addition of a second standing nude woman, though Blake has as I now think reversed the
positions of the two, making Bathsheba, very unusually, the standing figure. Blake’s tempera surprises also
in the prominence of the flowers that surround the bath, and in the unexampled children accompanying
Bathsheba, whose presence confirms the probability that Blake is pursuing themes rather different from those
proposed by previous versions.</p>
        <p>A search for Blake’s intentions can begin with what the biblical account tells about David and
Bathsheba and their meeting. Bathsheba is one of the female ancestors of Jesus in Matthew’s genealogy:
“And Jesse begat David the king; and David the king begat Solomon of her that had been the wife of Urias”
(Matthew 1:6). Luke traces a different line: <corr type="emend">“Mattatha,</corr> which was the son of Nathan, which was the son of
David, Which was the son of Jesse” (Luke 3: 31-32), cutting out both Bathsheba and Solomon. Nathan was the
prophet who promised David an eternal dynasty, but then rebuked him for adultery with Bathsheba, threatening
him with a divinely sanctioned death, which upon David’s repentance was shifted to the first child born of
the adulterous union.</p>
        <p>In the story in 2 Samuel, Bathsheba is identified by one of David’s servants or friends
(doubtless the other man in Giulio Romano’s version), who comes back with the news or rumor “Is this not
Bathsheba the daughter of Eliam, the wife of Uriah the Hittite?” (2 Samuel 11:3). Eliam was the son of
Ahithophel the Gilonite (2 Samuel 23:34), one of David’s counselors, who joined Absalom’s rebellion and
advised Absalom to allow Ahithophel and twelve thousand men to put to flight David’s men and then kill the
king himself (2 Samuel 17:1-3); his counsel was undermined by Hushai “to the intent that the Lord might
bring evil upon Absalom” (2 Samuel 17:14), and Ahithophel finally hung himself upon seeing “that his
counsel was not followed” (2 Samuel 17:23). This raises the possibility that David’s seizure of Bathsheba
represented an act of revenge against the dead Ahithophel, Bathsheba’s grandfather, but there are no signs
that such an interpretation is at play in any representation of David and Bathsheba known to me.</p>
        <p>David, like Bathsheba, figures in the genealogy of Jesus as father of Solomon. In Christian
interpretation David is not only an ancestor (Matthew 22:42, Mark 12:35, etc.) but also a type of Jesus in his
roles as poet, shepherd and prince (Ezekiel 34:23-24). Though a hero, he committed great errors and even
crimes. Nathan sums up the contradiction in the parable of the rich man and the poor man; the rich man,
visited by a traveller, and wishing to provide a feast, kills not one of his own numerous flock, but the ewe
lamb of the poor man. Nathan, speaking on behalf of God, applies the parable to David:
<q>
I gave thee thy master’s house, and thy master’s wives into thy bosom, and gave thee the house of Israel
and of Judah. . . . Wherefore hast thou despised the commandment of the Lord, to do evil in his sight? thou
hast killed Uriah the Hittite with the sword, and hast taken his wife to be thy wife, and hast slain him with
the sword of the children of Ammon. Now therefore the sword shall never depart from thine house; because thou
hast despised me, and hast taken the wife of Uriah the Hittite to be thy wife. (2 Samuel 12:8-10)
</q>
This is the double face of David: rich in gifts and power, but unable to resist the temptation to abuse both
on occasion, to the detriment of both Israel and himself. Despite founding the kingship of Israel, he was
destined never to fulfill the ambition to build a better house for the ark of God than the “curtains”
within which it dwelled (2 Samuel 7:2); God confirmed to David via Nathan that it would be left to the “seed
. . . which shall proceed out of thy bowels” (i.e. Solomon) to “build an house for my name” (2 Samuel
7:12-13).</p>
        <p>Blake left some evidence for his views of David and Bathsheba. His one textual reference to
Bathsheba<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> again reflects Matthew’s
genealogy rather than Luke’s (though with a large difference):
<q>
I see the Maternal Line, I behold the Seed of Woman!<lb/>
Cainah, &amp; Ada &amp; Zillah &amp; Naamah Wife of Noah.<lb/>
Shuahs daughter &amp; Tamar &amp; Rahab the Canaanites:<lb/>
Ruth the Moabite &amp; Bathsheba of the daughters of Heth<lb/>
Naamah the Ammonite, Zibeah the Philistine, &amp; Mary<lb/>
These are the Daughters of Vala, Mother of the Body<lb/>
of death[.] (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 62, E 213)
</q>
These female ancestors of Jesus were of considerable interest to Blake, and he pictured several of them: Ada
and Zillah in the large color print of <hi rend="i">Lamech and His Two Wives</hi> (B 297), Ruth in the print
of <hi rend="i">Naomi Entreating Ruth and Orpah</hi> (B
<pb id="p36-80" n="80"/>
299—despite the name given to the print, all of Blake’s references to the subject name Ruth rather than
Naomi as the focus), Bathsheba in the present design, and Mary in many designs. <note id="n17">17. There is a
“Visionary Head of Bathsheba with Uriah” (B 699); see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Works of William
Blake in the Huntington Collections</hi> (San Marino: The Huntington Library, 1985) 84. Essick records that
Rossetti described this Bathsheba as “sweet, soft, yielding, witty”; this comment on a drawing done at
least twenty years after the tempera offers no interpretive guidance here.</note></p>
        <p>S. Foster Damon (s.v. “Maternal Line”) comments on the passage cited above:
<q>
the traceable female ancestry of Mary, and hence of Jesus. As the genealogies given by Matthew and Luke both
trace his ancestry (surprisingly) through Joseph, Blake accepted the Roman theory that Mary was Joseph’s
cousin; and as he believed that all she gave her son was this mortal and sinful body, it seemed appropriate to
him that her female ancestry included some of the worst characters in the Old Testament.
</q>
Morton D. Paley repeats the notion that Blake’s “Maternal Line” represents the ancestry of Mary,
crediting Sloss and Wallis as well as Damon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref> However, Damon has misread Sloss and Wallis, who wrote that Blake “sets out to trace
the ancestry of Jesus on the maternal side in such a manner as to stress the element of ‘feminine
delusion’ noticed elsewhere in his use of the term ‘maternal’”; they then annotate the names listed,
showing that all are involved in the descent from Adam to Jesus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n18">18. Morton D. Paley, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Jerusalem (Princeton: William Blake
Trust/Princeton University Press, 1991) 231.</note>
	<note id="n19">19. D.J. Sloss and J.P.R. Wallis, eds., <hi rend="i">The Prophetic Writings of William
Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1926) 1:560.</note></p>
        <p>Blake is listing not the ancestry of Mary, which is nowhere given in the Bible beyond the statement
that she was a cousin of Elizabeth “of the daughters of Aaron” (Luke 1:5), but rather some of the women
who were wives or consorts of the male ancestors of Jesus; I do not know Damon’s evidence for the theory
that Blake used a Roman notion that Mary was Joseph’s cousin. Cainah was presumably invented as the wife
needed to make Cainan an ancestor of Jesus, as he is in Luke 3:36; Ada and Zillah were the wives of Lamech,
the father of Noah, and thus one of them was Noah’s mother; Naamah’s role is clear; Shuah’s daughter is
the wife of Judah, also in Luke’s list (3:30); Tamar is almost certainly the woman with whom Judah lies in
Genesis 38 (cf. Ruth 4:12), begetting the Pharez who appears in both lists (Matthew 1:3, Luke 3:33). Rahab is
problematical, but there is a Rachab upon whom Solomon begat Booz in Matthew 1:5, and the story of Rahab the
harlot ends with her and all her family being integrated into Israel, so that “she dwelleth in Israel even
unto this day” (Joshua 6:25)—Blake may have assumed that her blood entered into the ancestry of Jesus in
some general way, while she added to the strain of outsiders and transgressors among the female ancestors:
“If [Jesus] intended to take on Sin / The Mother should an Harlot been” (E 877). Ruth, a Moabite, and
Bathsheba, “of the daughters of Heth” (i.e. a Hittite) add further outsider blood to the mix. Damon
suggests that Zibeah the Philistine is the Zibiah of Beersheba listed as the mother of Jehoash (or Joash) in 2
Kings 12:1, though since he is not in the lineage given by either evangelist, it remains unclear why Blake has
included Zibeah—perhaps as mother of a king of Israel she can be assumed to have participated in the ongoing
process of incarnating Israel.</p>
        <p>These women are described by Blake both as a “Line,” implying successiveness, and as sisters,
“Daughters of Vala,” implying that they are sibling collaborators in the continuing process of the
creation of the “Body of death.” Blake uses this phrase in several other contexts, as in <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi>, where Enitharmon taunts Los: “Howl thou over the body of death tis thine” (E 323), and in
plate 13 of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: “For then the Body of Death was perfected in hypocrite holiness, /
Around the Lamb, a Female Tabernacle woven in Cathedrons Looms” (E 107). On plate 9 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> we find Los testifying that he saw “disease forming a Body of Death around the Lamb
/ Of God, to destroy Jerusalem, &amp; to devour the body of Albion” (E 152). Robert N. Essick and Joseph
Viscomi suggest that the phrase may refer to the doctrine of the virgin birth or a false notion of the
incarnation;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> more generally, the
phrase covers all those processes through which history incrusts an imagination embodied within time and
space. In Night the Eighth of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> those in Eternity use a related phrase in urging
on the incarnation: “Assume the dark Satanic body in the Virgins womb / O Lamb divin[e]” (E 377). Like
many of Blake’s terms, “Body of death” can be interpreted from both positive and negative perspectives;
the Eternals urge on the incarnation because they understand its creative necessity, but they also lament the
inevitable darkening of the light by its enclosure in a dying body. The end-product of the process of
incarnation can be called “the Body of death,” but is also the path to life; as the Divine Voice comforts
Jerusalem at the prospect of the incarnation, “behold Joseph &amp; Mary / And be comforted O Jerusalem”
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, E 211). <note id="n20">20. Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi, eds., 
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Milton a Poem (Princeton: William Blake Trust/Princeton University Press, 1993)
137.</note></p>
        <p>The “Daughters of Vala” are the mothers not of Mary but of Israel and finally of Jesus. Their
function, however, is only to weave bodies, and Blake’s deep ambivalence about bodies shapes his
interpretation of Vala and probably of her daughter Bathsheba. Doubtless Blake was working with a model of
reproduction that attributed the gift of life to the male seed, and saw the womb as merely the matrix from
which the seed took sustenance as it grew (cf. “Vala produc’d the Bodies. Jerusalem gave the Souls” 
[<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, E 163]). Bathsheba, in Blake’s only textual reference to her, as a “Daughter of
Vala” and metaphorically an elder sister of Mary, has a role in the incarnation of the progressive stages of
the human imagination.</p>
        <pb id="p36-81" n="81"/>
        <p>Blake’s view of David has a sharp cleavage line that reflects Nathan’s critique; David was both
king and “great poet” (<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, E 39), not a conjunction normally
found in Blake, and capable of both heroic action and great wickedness. Blake’s view of David is not made
more transparent by the idiosyncratic punctuation of a key statement: <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 27 tells us
that “when compulsory cruel Sacrifices had brought Humanity into a Feminine Tabernacle, in the loins of
Abraham &amp; David: the Lamb of God, the Saviour became apparent on Earth as the Prophets had foretold” (E
174). Are the “loins of Abraham &amp; David” the space of the “Feminine Tabernacle,” or are they part
of the (pro)creative process that made “apparent on Earth” the Savior? The logic of Blake’s argument
implies that the “Return of Israel” (E 174) is the process begun by Abraham and continued by David:
“Jesus as also Abraham &amp; David considerd God as a Man in the Spiritual or Imaginative Vision”
(annotations to Berkeley’s <hi rend="i">Siris</hi>, E 663). The “Saviour became apparent on Earth” in
(through) the loins of Abraham and David, though all incarnation (becoming apparent) takes place through the
medium of a “Feminine Tabernacle.” The punctuation invites us to take it both ways.</p>
        <p>Both Abraham and David are focal points for Blake’s version of the history of human progress as
recorded in the Bible. Abraham was “called to succeed the Druidical age, which began to turn allegoric and
mental sacrifice into corporeal command, whereby human sacrifice would have depopulated the earth” 
(<hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, E 542-43). David’s role was that of heroic defender of his people,
and carrier of a poetic power that supported the “allegoric and mental” against the “corporeal”; his
playing of the harp, for instance, had power to drive evil spirits away from Saul (1 Samuel 16:23). In another
episode, David thanked Abigail for urging him to spare his enemies: “blessed be thy advice, and blessed be
thou, which hast kept me this day from coming to shed blood, and from avenging myself with mine own hand” (1
Samuel 25:33). In such moments David advanced the cause of the imagination, transforming revenge as Abraham
had transformed sacrifice.</p>
        <p>But Blake also offers David as one “Example of the possibility of Human Beastliness” to be
found in the “Jewish Scriptures” (annotations to <hi rend="i">An Apology for the Bible</hi>, E 614); the
good will “abhor wickedness in David or Abraham” (E 618). In both Abraham and David, wickedness was
intimately mingled with great good; in the case of David, a form of resolution is achieved in his buying the
threshing floor from Araunah and there building an altar to the Lord, who in response stays a plague from
Israel (2 Samuel 24:18-25). Blake describes Araunah “emptying out the vanities of Riches &amp; Worldly
Honours” (<hi rend="i">A Vision of The Last Judgment</hi>, E 557) in an act that symbolically cleanses both
David and kingship. Perhaps Blake envisioned David’s taking Bathsheba for himself as another version of the
fortunate fall, as a movement prompted by the energy of desire, initially destructive but ending in the happy
conception of one who played a role in leading Israel—humanity—towards the freer future embodied in
Jesus.</p>
        <p>Blake portrayed both aspects of David in his art. The heroic young David is the subject of a
drawing in the Visionary Heads notebook (B 698) and of <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi> (B 457); a
maturer David is shown in <hi rend="i">David Pardoning Absalom</hi> (B 459). <hi rend="i">David Delivered out
of Many Waters</hi> (B 462), based as Butlin points out on Psalm 18, shows David entangled with ropes and
looking up at flying angels while, at center top, Jesus descends to save him from drowning. This David has
been dragged down by “the floods of ungodly men,” “the sorrows of hell” and “the snares of
death,” disasters that are the result of his own errors as well as the ill-will of others; he needs
redemption by his descendant.</p>
        <p>As with Bathsheba, Blake shows an interest in David’s role in the genealogy leading to Jesus, and
in the late <hi rend="i">Epitome of James Hervey’s Meditations among the Tombs</hi> (B 770) visualizes some
of the key figures. Adam and Eve with the Serpent are followed by Cain and Abel and then Enoch and Noah,
Abraham and Isaac, Aaron, and, a little lower, David and Solomon. At the bottom is Jesus at the moment of
transfiguration, flanked by Moses and Elias. The painting also shows, between Noah and Abraham, figures
labelled “Mother of Leah &amp; Rachel” and “Mother of Rebecca”; it is a minor oddity of the Genesis
narrative that these mothers are never named. Rebekah was the wife of Isaac and mother of Jacob and Esau; Leah
and Rachel were won as wives by Jacob, and between them produced the tribes of Israel. Blake has given both
visibility and a title (“Mother of . . .”) to these unnamed women who occupy key positions in Matthew’s
lineage. It remains to be seen whether recognition of this incorporation by Blake of the genealogies and
stories of the Bible into his mythologized vision of the history of culture offers any leverage in
interpreting Blake’s tempera.</p>
        <p>Some aspects of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Bathsheba</hi> follow the biblical text or iconographic
tradition. The blue sky streaked with orange, for instance, reflects the biblical narrative’s note that the
sighting of Bathsheba took place “in an evening-tide” (2 Samuel 11:2). David is portrayed, as became usual
in the iconography of the episode, as a small figure in the background. His gesture is easily read in both
conventional and Blakean language; his raised arms as he catches sight of the unexpected beauty before him
echo the reaching arms of “Mans desires” in plate V of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion (a).</hi>
Blake has also followed a common iconographic tradition in showing Bathsheba with another figure or figures at
the bath, though in this case the other figure appears not to be the usual maidservant. There are, however,
major novelties in Blake’s design that demand and challenge interpretation, in particular the prominence of
the flowers and the children.</p>
        <pb id="p36-82" n="82"/>
        <p>I have elsewhere made the argument that Blake, in approaching texts other than his own, often
modified them in the direction of his mythology, or, better, his mode of poetic thinking, though he did not
simply substitute that myth for the text being illustrated.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">21</ref> I offered as underlying model the notion that Blake was practising an art of
invention akin to Le Bossu’s theory of epic invention, the most widespread theory of the time. Here is the
most succinct articulation of that theory:
<q>
The first thing we are to begin with for Composing a Fable, is to chuse the Instruction, and the point of
Morality, which is to serve as its Foundation . . . In the next place this Moral Truth must be reduc’d into
Action, and a general Action must be feign’d in Imitation of the true and singular Actions [that illustrate
the point chosen] . . . then [the Poet] should look for the Names of some Persons (to whom a parallel Action
has either truly or probably happen’d) in History, or some well-known Fables: And lastly, he ought to place
his Action under their Names. Thus it will be really feign’d and invented by the Author, and yet will seem
to be taken out of some very ancient History and Fable.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n21">21. Heppner, <hi rend="i">Reading</hi> 82-86, 120-31.</note>
	<note id="n22">22. Stuart Curran, ed., <hi rend="i">Le Bossu and Voltaire on the Epic</hi> (Gainesville,
Florida: Scholars Facsimiles and Reprints, 1970) 15.</note></q>
The theory allowed for “accommodation” between the originating “Moral Truth” and the “History”
under the names of which it was placed. 
                </p>
        <p>A letter to Butts dated 6 July 1803 records Blake’s own comments on such “accommodation” in
the context of another illustration of the Bible, the <hi rend="i">Riposo</hi>, which
<q>
represents the Holy Family in Egypt Guarded in their Repose from those Fiends the Egyptian Gods. and tho’
not taken directly from a Poem of Miltons . . . yet it is very similar to his Hymn on the Nativity. . . . I
have given in the background a building which may be supposed the ruin of a Part of Nimrods tower which I
conjecture to have spread over many Countries for he ought to be reckoned of the Giant brood. (E 729)
</q>
Blake regards the Bible, like Milton’s work, as a poem, to be treated with respect as “an original
derivation from the Poetic Genius” (E 1), as was Milton’s epic, but subject to reinterpretation by
“Conscience or the Word of God Universal” which empowers “every man [to] converse with God &amp; be a
King &amp; Priest in his own house” (E 615). In this case Blake expands upon the tradition surrounding
Nimrod’s tower, the tower of Babel (Genesis 10: 9-10), adding the “conjecture” that the cursed culture
which he created spread over the whole earth. “[S]upposed” and “conjecture” imply the playfully
imaginative insertion of new meaning into the original text, which however remains almost intact;
“accommodation” rather than superimposition and replacement.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately the picture here described is lost, but there is extant a closely related watercolor,
<hi rend="i">The Repose of the Holy Family in Egypt</hi> (B 472). This shows small and inconspicuous ruins on
the banks of the river that flows between the distant pyramids and the holy family in the foreground. Assuming
that the lost painting described by Blake showed similar architecture, it seems that Blake could assign to
inconspicuous images meanings more explicit than any we should feel safe in assigning ourselves, meanings that
substantially expand those inherent in the subject as given. Simultaneously, we learn that it would be unwise
to ignore objects clearly present in a design, though not taken directly from the original subject, even if we
are initially unsure what they might mean.</p>
        <p>Before attempting to reconstruct the motivation for Blake’s unique transformation of the story of
Bathsheba, using some process of “accommodation” as possible key, there is another question to settle.
Blake’s biblical paintings were commissioned and paid for by Butts, a practising Christian,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> who may have had a hand in choosing the
subjects: “I wish to ask you what subject you choose to be painted on the remaining Canvas” (E 720).
However, Blake also wrote to Butts claiming his “Just Right as an Artist &amp; as a Man. &amp; if any
attempt should be made to refuse me this I am inflexible &amp; will relinquish Any engagement of Designing at
all unless altogether left to my own Judgment. As you My dear Friend have always left me” (E 731). We do not
know whether the subject of <hi rend="i">Bathsheba</hi> was chosen for Blake by Butts, proposed as one
possibility among others, or freely chosen by Blake, but we can assume that Blake shaped the design in accord
with his own interests and desires. <note id="n23">23. The notion that Butts was a Swedenborgian has been
generally dropped for lack of specific evidence, though it remains a possibility. The most responsible
assessment is that of G.E. Bentley, Jr., who notes that Butts quotes the Archbishop of Canterbury, and
summarizes thus: “It is likely that he was an Anglican or a respectable Methodist, but in the absence of
evidence it is safest to say that his religious affiliation is unknown.” “White Collar Maecenas,” 
<hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> 71 (1956): 1053.</note></p>
        <p>We can focus now on those “principal peculiarities and differences from other representations of
the scene” that both “demand explanation” and offer a path into the intentionality of a specific
design.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> Despite Giulio Romano’s
unobtrusive flowers and Bordone’s lemon bushes, nothing like Blake’s pervasive garden imagery had been
offered in previous handlings. Honeysuckle grows around one of the columns on the left of the picture, while
drooping lilies fill the space between the young girl and the column to our right, and roses the space
separating the further column 
<pb id="p36-83" n="83"/>
on the right from the frame. Like the distant buildings in <hi rend="i">The Repose of the Holy Family in
Egypt</hi>, these apparently ornamental flowers may hold at least a partial key to the design’s intent.
<note id="n24">24. I am adopting language used by Michael Baxandall, <hi rend="i">Patterns of Intention</hi>
(New Haven: Yale University Press, 1985) 121.</note></p>
        <p>Here is the core of Rodney Baine’s commentary on the honeysuckle:
<q>
One of the most easily distinguishable of the vines of Innocence is the honeysuckle. . . . Its long tube was
for Erasmus Darwin an emblem of fertility: ‘With artless grace and native ease she charms / And bears the
Horn of Plenty in her arms’ (I. 215-16). In Blake’s symphony of flowers in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> the
honeysuckle is early awakened by the odors of the herbs and flowers as it is ‘sleeping on the Oak’: ‘the
flaunting beauty / Revels along upon the wind’ (31: 54-55). . . . In a number of designs Blake seems to have
depicted the scarlet trumpet honeysuckle . . . long cultivated in English gardens because of its beauty, its
evergreen leaves, and the longevity of its flowers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n25">25. Rodney M. Baine, with the assistance of Mary R. Baine, <hi rend="i">The Scattered
Portions</hi> (Athens, Georgia: Baine, 1986) 157.</note></q>
There is ample evidence for Blake’s knowledge and use of Erasmus Darwin, and his treatment of this flower
suggests that he was aware of its joyous participation in the “vegetable Loves” of all plant life. After
the lines quoted by Baine, Darwin writes “Five rival Swains their tender cares unfold, / And watch with eye
askance the treasured gold”—the female stamen, as his note makes clear: “Honeysuckle. Five males, one
female.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> Blake’s flowers are
reddish in tone, and almost alarmingly fleshy looking; one could without difficulty see both penises and
reaching fingers. Should we read Blake’s portrayal of the “rival Swains” as a vegetable analog to
David’s lusting after another man’s wife, as representing the sexual energy that reaches out to enter
history at this moment? <note id="n26">26. Erasmus Darwin, <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> (London, 1791;
facsimile reprint, Scolar Press, 1973) vol. 2, “The Botanic Garden,” 21-22.</note></p>
        <p>On the right are white lilies and roses, often paired as Baine notes. The lily was “associated
with the bride in The Song of Solomon and praised for its beauty by Christ himself” and had “for centuries
symbolized beauty, purity, and divine grace.” It was assigned to Mary as an attribute, and often appeared in
depictions of the Annunciation. The rose traditionally “suggested love and beauty”; in “the emblem books
and the poets, roses usually suggest mercy, grace, beauty, cheerfulness, pleasure, love and marriage, and
lyric poetry.” The two flowers often appear together in Blake’s work; for instance, there is a lily
entwined with roses behind Mary in <hi rend="i">The Christ Child Asleep on a Cross</hi> (B 410). Baine points
out that in <hi rend="i">Satan Watching the Endearments of Adam and Eve</hi> (B 536:4) Adam holds a lily and
Eve a rose: “Roses and lilies are marital flowers also in <hi rend="i">Job, Jerusalem</hi>, and apparently
also in <hi rend="i">Bathsheba at the Bath</hi> . . . where the honeysuckle of fertility climbing the column
at our left may be intended to remind us of David’s line.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n27" type="note">27</ref> I shall expand on these suggestions in what follows. <note id="n27">27.
Baine, <hi rend="i">Portions</hi> 161-66.</note></p>
        <p>The flowers are consonant with Blake’s one poetic reference to Bathsheba as, like Mary, of the
“Seed of Woman”; they support the hypothesis that Bathsheba is presented as a type of Mary, as the still
unconscious recipient of an Annunciation that will take the form of the regal favor that discovers in her
naked beauty the fruitful womb in which to seed the next leader of his people, and another ancestor of Jesus;
her beauty and innocence are expressed in the lilies and roses, and her impending fruitfulness in the
luxuriant honeysuckle, which also reflects the intrusive but creative sexual energy of David. This offers a
conceptualization of the moment of the painting, and integrates Blake’s one poetic reference to Bathsheba
with the one major design from his hand to show her. We can read Bathsheba as an avatar of Vala without
seriously disrupting the biblical account that underlies the design, the insertion of Blake’s poetic
mythology just giving an extra dimension to a familiar story. Nevertheless, even such a simple connection as
this raises questions; can one, for instance, assume enough chronological consistency within Blake’s
mythology to support interpretation of a tempera painted in 1799-1800 by means of a poetic statement made
considerably later? And can we move between Blake’s poetry and his painting as if the two were a seamless
unity?</p>
        <p>Blake’s mythology grew and changed. We do not know exactly when Vala entered Blake’s myth; the
“nameless shadowy female” of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (E 60) is probably an early version.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> She seems to have grown in focus and
prominence while Blake was illustrating Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, and by around 1797 she had
become the titular figure of <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi> Paley sees her presence in several groups of figures in
the illustrations to Young, tracing her in such roles as Fate, Life, and Fortune in pursuit of the argument
that “Young’s personification becomes Blake’s symbol” as Blake “assimilated [his subject] into the
mythological system that he was creating in his own prophetic works.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref> Margoliouth suggests that we may see the “actual genesis
of the name” in a manuscript fragment in which “Vala” has been substituted for an erased word that he
declines to read, though he disagrees with Sloss and Wallis’s suggested “Mystery”;<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref> Erdman proposes “[?<hi
rend="i">Enion</hi>]” (E 845). It looks as if the central concepts which animate Vala entered Blake’s
imagination some time
<pb id="p36-84" n="84"/>
before his work on the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations and the poem named after her, and grew
into focus during that work, but not without difficulty, as witnessed by such occasional slips as a switch
between the names of Vala and Enitharmon in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> 10:17-18 (E 825).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n28">28. See S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (Providence: Brown University
Press, 1965) 369, and Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1970) 166.</note>
	<note id="n29">29. Morton D. Paley, “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>: Explorations of the Fallen
World,” in Alvin H. Rosenfeld, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi> (Providence:
Brown University Press, 1969) 142-43, 135-36.</note>
	<note id="n30">30. H.M. Margoliouth, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Vala (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1956)
xix.</note>
	<note id="n31">31. See John B. Pierce, <hi rend="i">Flexible Design: Revisionary Poetics in Blake’s</hi>
Vala <hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas (Montreal and Kingston: McGill-Queen’s Press, 1998) 74.</note></p>
        <p>Apart from the tempera itself, there is no evidence to tell us whether by ca. 1800 Blake had
already connected Vala with Bathsheba, since the reference in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to Bathsheba as a
daughter of Vala is considerably later. Such a connection, which puts a particular emphasis on the story of
David and Bathsheba, though one already implicit within it, needs to be supported by an interpretation of the
two children, the most significant departure of the design from both biblical narrative and iconographic
tradition. Whose children are they, and why are they present?</p>
        <p>The Bible narrative shows considerable interest in the children born to David by former wives and
concubines, who are listed in 2 Samuel 12:8; there is further comment in 2 Samuel 5:13-16, 1 Chronicles 3:1-9
and 1 Chronicles 14:3-7. The focus is on children born to David by Bathsheba; 1 Chronicles 3:5 specifies that
four children, including Solomon, were born of this relationship, while 2 Samuel 12:13-18 recounts the death
of the first born, condemned by God in exchange for the commutation of David’s own death sentence when the
latter repents. However, the children in the tempera are obviously not David’s, and the Bible records no
children born to Bathsheba and Uriah.</p>
        <p>That the children are Bathsheba’s is evident from the familiarly affectionate way in which her
arms drape over their shoulders. If Blake has imagined them as born to Bathsheba and Uriah, he may have added
them to intensify the pathos of vulnerable women and children exposed to the powerful desires of a king, who
is breaking up not only a marriage but also an apparently affectionate family. Such an interpretation,
however, does not account for the gesture of the boy, who turns his back on us, and faces in the opposite
direction from his mother; his right arm, though hidden from us by Bathsheba’s body, seems to reach upwards
to caress her hair or neck. There is a puzzling mixture of affection and rejection in his bodily relation to
his mother that invites further reflection.</p>
        <p>If Bathsheba can be understood from the perspective of Blake’s myth, so perhaps can the children,
and such a repositioning might throw light on the boy and his ambiguous gesture. Though a boy and a girl
together are common in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, the key configuration in the early prophecies had been a
man, a woman, and a male child: Los and Enitharmon with Orc, their first born. A new emphasis appeared with
the image of a woman accompanied by a boy and a girl in the large color print formerly known as 
<hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> (B 316);<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> around
this time (nominally 1795) the configuration of a woman with two children, a boy and a girl, became more
central to Blake’s pictorial imagination. In the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors, there are
recurring images of a woman with two such children of varying age; they are babes in arms in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 4, lie dead before her in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 28, representing “Nature’s . . . Joys”
killed “while we clasp”; they become Body and Soul in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 290; they embrace in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 413, and commit adultery in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 467; finally, they are shown at several
stages simultaneously in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 512, in spaces created by the branches of Jesus as the vine on
which humanity grows: “O what a Root! O what a Branch is Here? / O what a Father! What a Family!” In the
course of these illustrations, the young boy/girl couple take on a wide variety of both narrative and
allegorical functions. <note id="n32">32. There has recently been a move to retitle this print 
<hi rend="i">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</hi>, on the basis of a catalogue entry by Gert Schiff written for an
exhibition in Japan; see “The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy,” with comments by Morton D. Paley, in 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 36.1 (Summer 2002): 38-39. Schiff accepts a good deal of my
earlier reading (“Reading Blake’s Designs: <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>,” 
<hi rend="i">BRH</hi> 84 (1981): 337-65), but identifies the central person with Enitharmon in the act of
“Forbid[ding] all Joy” (<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, E 62); the print “allegorizes Enitharmon’s scheme to
enslave mankind by way of sexual repression.” There is much overlap between our views, but in a later
account (<hi rend="i">Reading</hi>, 121-31) I proposed that the print offers a Blakean “accommodation” of
the story of Medea killing her two children, relating an underlying Blakean meaning to an extant narrative.
Schiff’s version of allegory seems to me to offer a rather weak explanation of why Blake has portrayed
Enitharmon as a witch: “By depicting Enitharmon as a brooding witch, Blake shows that both her religion of
chastity and her promise of an afterlife are nothing but evil spells.” I am also uncomfortable with
Schiff’s statement that “The woman’s demeanor is expressive of the most perfect indifference”; this
ignores the significant triple frown lines visible on her brow in all copies of the print, and also the
strongly marked sideways turn of her head. My own second reading, hypothetical though it must remain in the
absence of supporting text or inscription, does at least address these issues.</note></p>
        <p>This new visual emphasis on a young couple (whether implicitly siblings or in a sexual
relationship), without illustrating the mythology directly, may nevertheless reflect a shift in the roles of
some of its key figures; Los and Enitharmon, who had appeared as parents in earlier poems such as 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, now reappear as children of Enion—which shows how difficult it is for
interpretation to pass with conviction from visual image to poetic myth, unless the image is in intimate
connection with that myth.</p>
        <p>Given Blake’s later association of Bathsheba with Vala, should we identify the two children in
the tempera with Los and Enitharmon, the most conspicuous youthful male and female pair in Blake’s
mythology, a pair moreover who had recently been revisualized as children rather than as parents? The idea is
tempting, but brings problems. One is that the origin of, and relationship between, Los and Enitharmon are
both expressed through a wide variety of metaphors: Enitharmon emanates from Los as they both
<pb id="p36-85" n="85"/>
<figure n="jerusalem.e.p32" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.32" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="749" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>32<lb/>
	Leaning against the pillars. &amp; his disease rose from his skirts<lb/>
	Upon the Precipice he stood: ready to fall into Non- Entity.<lb/>
	Los was all astonishment &amp; terror: he trembled sitting on the Stone<lb/>
	Of London: but the interiors of Albions fibres &amp; nerves were hidden<lb/>
	From Los; astonishd he beheld only the petrified surfaces!<lb/>
	And saw his Furnaces in ruins, for Los is the Demon of the Furnaces,<lb/>
	He saw also the Four Points of Albion reversd inwards<lb/>
	He siezd his Hammer &amp; Tongs, his iron Poker &amp; his Bellows,<lb/>
	Upon the valleys of Middlesex, Shouting loud for aid Divine.<lb/>
	In stern defiance came from Albions bosom Hand, Hyle, Koban,<lb/>
	Gwantok, Peachy. Brertun, Slaid. Huttn Skofeld. Kock, Kotope<lb/>
	Bowen, Albions Sons: they bore him a golden couch into the porch<lb/>
	And on the Couch reposd his limbs, trembling from the bloody field.<lb/>
	Rearing their Druid Patriarchal rocky Temples around his limbs.<lb/>
	All thing begin &amp; end. in Albions Ancient Druid Rocky Shore.)</figTranscr>
	<head>3. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 32.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
separate from the Spectre of Urthona (E 333), they are born as brother and sister from Enion (E 359), they are
man and wife, even William and Catherine, as at the end of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> But nowhere are Los and Enitharmon described as born from
Vala, though there is some indication that the reverse is at least metaphorically possible, as in the
“Preludium” to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (E 60) and the later statement that “Vala shall become a Worm in
Enitharmons Womb” (E 326). Enitharmon does sing a “Song of Death” in which she describes herself as
walking “in the visions of Vala” (E 305), but this is remote from the scene depicted in the tempera. 
<note id="n33">33. For a fuller account, see Peter Otto, “The Multiple Births of Los in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas” SEL 1500-1900</hi> 31.4 (1991): 631-53.</note></p>
        <p>A group that appears in plate 32 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the Blake Trust/Princeton
facsimile looks at first as if it might throw some oblique light on the issue (illus. 3). This shows a nude
Jerusalem between two of her daughters,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">34</ref> while a third flies upward with an arm affectionately intertwined with a sister’s.
Jerusalem has her arms extended to caress the children much as Bathsheba caresses hers in the tempera, while
the daughter on our right has an arm affectionately extended to Jerusalem’s neck and shoulder in a fashion
reminiscent of the boy’s arm extended (albeit invisibly to us) behind Bathsheba’s back. But as usual
analogies must be pursued with caution. The daughter who flies upwards in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 32
invites us to read her freedom from gravity as a sign that she is a visual metaphor for a thought or mental
creation;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref> Bathsheba’s children
appear as grounded creatures of flesh and blood, though that does not disbar metaphoric connotations. We
interpret Jerusalem’s nakedness as primarily metaphorical, as part of the definition of “Liberty,”
whereas Bathsheba’s nakedness, whatever further connotations it may possess, is in the first place
naturalistically motivated by the story depicted. The two images belong to different semiotic worlds, and we
cannot transfer more significance from the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> illumination to the tempera than a
feeling of reassurance that the children in the tempera really are Bathsheba’s. <note id="n34">34. The
identification is made on the basis of the associated text by David V. Erdman in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated
Blake</hi> (New York: Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1974) 325.</note>
	<note id="n35">35. See Janet A. Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art</hi> (Kingston and
Montreal: McGill-Queen’s Press, 1984) 127-34.</note></p>
        <p>Two passages in Blake’s poetry might be used to incorporate Los and Enitharmon into the story of
David and Bathsheba. One is from plate 29 of <hi rend="i">Milton:</hi> “Los conducts the Spirits to be
Vegetated, into / Great Golgonooza,” while “Enitharmon and her Daughters take the pleasant charge. / To
give them to their lovely heavens till the Great Judgment Day” (E 128). Los here functions not according to
any of Frye’s mythical associations,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">36</ref> but as a kind of psychopomp, a Hermes leading souls down to be incarnated, while
Enitharmon builds a pleasant environment for them during their stay here. The other passage, from 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, lists “Joseph Benjamin David Solomon” among others as “Sons of Los &amp;
Enitharmon” (E 380). Supported by these passages, we could suggest that Blake re-imagined Bathsheba as one
of the “Daughter[s] of Vala” engaged in the progressive incarnations of the human imagination—the
history of Israel—and added the children to represent versions of Los and Enitharmon acting in their
part-time role as spirits assisting in the incarnation of Solomon, one of their “sons”; if Bathsheba can
be a daughter of Vala, then Solomon may be a son of Los. <note id="n36">36. Northrop Frye, 
<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1947) 277-78.</note></p>
        <p>However, this suggestion too is not problem free. In order to imagine these children as Los and
Enitharmon assisting in the incarnation of Solomon, we have to imaginatively superimpose upon the calm garden
scene a difficult to visualize cosmic environment in which powerful mythical/historical forces embodied within
figures from biblical narrative work to reshape human culture. Mitchell writes that “[Blake’s] usual
approach to . . . texts, in contrast to the general practice of eighteenth-century illustrators, is to provide
not a plausible visualization of a scene described in the text but rather a symbolic recreation of the ideas
embodied in that scence.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">37</ref> That is
true, but interpretation of
<pb id="p36-86" n="86"/>
a scene as a “symbolic recreation” is here rendered difficult by the artist’s inclusion of concrete
detail that resists such translation into symbol. In the illuminated poetry, Blake can and does, as Mitchell
writes, largely obliterate “the visual and objective aspects of the poetic landscape” in favor of “the
phantasmagoric ‘fluxile’ spaces of the prophetic books, in which the ‘look’ of Blake’s scenery
changes with every change in the mind of the perceiver.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n38" type="note">38</ref> But in the present case it takes considerable effort to imagine these two
children, firmly visualized as about to bathe in a pool near David’s palace, as “actually” facilitating
the incarnation of Solomon, who will be conceived some time in the future. <note id="n37">37. W.J.T. Mitchell,
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1978) 18.</note>
	<note id="n38">38. Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> 21.</note></p>
        <p>The possibility of seeing the human energies represented by Los and Enitharmon as present within
Bathsheba’s children as pictured here depends upon our understanding of the nature of Blake’s mythology.
We know this mythology largely through the poetic narratives in which it is articulated. Many of Blake’s own
comments, however, focus not so much on these narratives as on the individual figures of his myth, who are
described as embodying fundamental energies. Blake sometimes identifies these named energies with figures
embedded in preexisting stories; for instance, in <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> Blake writes that
“The giant Albion, was Patriarch of the Atlantic, he is the Atlas of the Greeks, one of those the Greeks
called Titans. The stories of Arthur are the acts of Albion, applied to a Prince of the fifth century” (E
543). This identifies a name from his own mythology first with a figure from Greek myth and then “applies”
that figure to a prince in the legendary history of England. Moving in the reverse direction, from poetic
character to archetype, Blake identifies Chaucer’s Pilgrims with “the physiognomies or lineaments of
universal human life” (E 533), who in turn are identified with the gods of Greece: “The Franklin is one
who keeps open table, who is the genius of eating and drinking, the Bacchus; as the Doctor of Physic is the
Esculapius, the Host is the Silenus, the Squire is the Apollo, the Miller is the Hercules, &amp;c.” (E 536).
Blake does not here give the Blakean names of these “visions of the eternal attributes, or divine names”
(E 536), but we may try to do so if we wish. Blake evidently sees his own figures as representative of
energies capable of acting out situations far removed from the narratives of his own mythological poems. The
pattern follows approximately that outlined by Le Bossu, and we can imagine the same processes at work in
“applying” part of the story of Vala to Bathsheba.</p>
        <p>In another passage, Blake writes of “having been taken in vision into the ancient republics,
monarchies, and patriarchates of Asia,” where he “has seen those wonderful originals called in the Sacred
Scriptures the Cherubim . . . being originals from which the Greeks and Hetrurians copied Hercules, Farnese,
Venus of Medicis, and all the grand works of ancient art” (E 531). These words imply that Blake’s “Giant
forms” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 3, E 145) are also copies of the originals seen in vision:
“Names alter, things never alter” (E 533). However, what we know is always mediated by names, either
Blake’s own, or those given by equally gifted poets like Chaucer, who also had an intuition of these
archetypes; like Jung, Blake seems to have believed that the archetype itself is never the object of direct
experience—though it may be glimpsed in “vision”—and can normally only be known through secondary
embodiments that have been culturally or personally configured. As poet, Blake sometimes maintains the fiction
that his particular names are the unaltering “things” themselves, but he implicitly allows on occasion
that his names are only one way of putting things, that they designate a partial and temporary rendering of an
underlying reality.</p>
        <p>Blake’s figures thus have two complementary and intertwined modes of being; in the one, they act
out roles in narratives in which they are born, split, and undergo a variety of transformations. In the other,
they are described as representing universal and unchanging energies or powers. One perspective that helps to
unify these models is provided by a passage on the “bright Sculptures of / Los’s Halls,” which suggests
that Blake’s mythology is grounded on what might be called the elementary forms of kinship, the building
blocks of social human life, that mediate between constant archetypal energies and the most fundamental forms
of narrative:
<q>
All things acted on Earth are seen in the bright Sculptures of<lb/>
Los’s Halls &amp; every Age renews its powers from these Works<lb/>
With every pathetic story possible to happen from Hate or<lb/>
Wayward Love &amp; every sorrow &amp; distress is carved here<lb/>
Every Affinity of Parents Marriages &amp; Friendships are here<lb/>
In all their various combinations wrought with wondrous Art<lb/>
All that can happen to Man in his pilgrimage of seventy years<lb/>
Such is the Divine Written Law of Horeb &amp; Sinai:<lb/>
And such the Holy Gospel of Mount Olivet &amp; Calvary[.] (E 161)
</q>
These lines describe the “Sculptures” as constituted by single figures who combine into persisting
narratives, Laocoön groups struggling with difficulties rather than solitary and stationary Apollos.
Blake’s way of putting this appears to give ontological priority to his own mythology—the sculptures exist
within the Halls of Los, which were “builded by Los &amp; his mighty children”—but since he lists David
and Solomon among those children, Blake simultaneously implies that his mythology and the writers of the
testaments exist in one and the same world.</p>
        <pb id="p36-87" n="87"/>
        <p>For Blake the figures of his mythology had a potential for life both before and after the poetic
narratives from which most of our knowledge of them derives; they could exist as single archetypes embodying
various energies, and they could enter and transform figures acting out the narratives of already existing
texts, poetic or historical. In the latter state, transfigured and with borrowed names, they can appear in
designs that represent actions nowhere described in his poetry, and significantly changed from the borrowed
preexisting narratives, though we may then find ourselves unable to make confident identifications without
help from Blake himself.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Milton</hi> illustrates the complex relationships that can arise when Blake’s
mythical names are embodied in a context in which they interact with other texts, both poetic and
biographical:
<q>
Then Milton knew that the Three Heavens of Beulah were beheld<lb/>
By him on earth in his bright pilgrimage of sixty years<lb/>
In those three females whom his Wives, &amp; those three whom his Daughters<lb/>
Had represented and containd. (E 110)
</q>
Three levels interact in these lines. The first is represented by the “Heavens of Beulah,” a term that
points to a mode of experience only reachable through interaction with “females”; these “Heavens” are
spaces or states in Blake’s mythology, and appear elsewhere in his poetry. They are “containd” within
the second level, constituted by the “Wives” and “Daughters” who are figures from history, with
ascertainable names and biographies. These in turn “contain” the third level of those “females” who
taken together form Ololon, a complex mythological figure who appears in no other poem. In this passage,
Blake’s mythology is imaged as a deep structure embedded within history; in Swedenborgian language, it is
the “spiritual” sense of “natural” figures grounded in the world. To complicate the picture further,
we are told that Milton discovers that “his Wives &amp; Daughters names were these / Rahab and Tirzah, &amp;
Milcah &amp; Noah &amp; Hoglah,” who sit around him “as the rocks of Horeb round the land / Of
Canaan.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref> These rocks have names:
“Hor &amp; Peor &amp; Bashan &amp; Abarim &amp; Lebanon &amp; Hermon” (E 110). Figures from Milton’s
family history are here identified through analogy with female figures from the Old Testament, which suggests
that family patterns replicate “combinations” that recur throughout history, as is implied in their
identification with mountains, images of the permanent. The mythical and universal is embodied within the
historical particular; the “bright Sculptures” that represent “Every Affinity” exist and act below and
within particular events. <note id="n39">39. The ultimate source for Blake’s imagery may be Paul’s
allegory of Abraham’s wives in Galations 4:21-31, in which “Sinai, which gendereth to bondage,. . .is
Agar”; there is stimulating comment in a number of sources, including Daniel Boyarin, <hi rend="i">A Radical
Jew</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1994) 32ff.</note></p>
        <p>Ololon comes into being by an interaction between Blake’s mythology as it existed prior to the
writing of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (in such forms as “the Three Heavens of Beulah”) and the persons and
events of the life of the historical poet; she mediates between fundamental energies and the moving patterns
of history. In the final plates of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> we see a spectacular demonstration of the analysis
and decomposition of Ololon into several distinguishable figures and concepts; having played out her role in
the poem, she is resolved back into her component parts. As a mediating structure, the mythology is open to
influx from both sides—from the archetypes represented by the “bright Sculptures,” and from the moving
shapes of history. Blake’s language—“represents” and “contains”—implies the less than total
overlap between levels.</p>
        <p>Blake’s image of the “bright Sculptures” that embody fundamental “Affinit[ies] of Parents,
Marriages &amp; Friendships” reflects upon the possible presence of Blake’s mythology within the figures
of <hi rend="i">Bathsheba.</hi> The most substantial “Sculpture” represented in the tempera is that of a
mother with two children, boy and girl to represent the future of all humanity, but without visible father,
and thus open to the winds of change and damage. If this is truly an archetype, it has no obvious name, though
many possible significations. Bathsheba as mother draws our eyes, as she drew those of David, but is not
presented from the point of view of those northern artists who implicitly or explicitly held her self-exposure
partly responsible for David’s acts. This Bathsheba, though frankly naked, bears neither jewelry nor guilt.
She is first and foremost a mother with her children, prompting us to respond protectively; the family
atmosphere, and the presence of the other nude woman already bathing, imply that this is, or should be, a
secluded quasiparadise of baths and flowers in which the gaze of adult males is not welcome, or welcome only
with a clear statement of non-sexual intent. David, in responding sexually to Bathsheba, is invading a
protected space. The vulnerability of such a family group without visible father forms a vital part of the
subject of this painting, and the naked attractiveness of Bathsheba herself associates her with other stories
that focus on the vulnerability of women to the desires of powerful men, like that of Susanna and the
elders.</p>
        <p>The presence of the other woman is related to this image of a protected space rather than to the
iconographic history of the episode or to any explicit event from Blake’s myth. There are very few previous
handlings of the story that show such apparently unrelated women bathing in the nude, Aldegrever’s version
being one of those few. Usually, the only other women shown are either young and clothed attendants or old
bawds bringing David’s letter. The seated woman in Blake’s design is already dressing her own hair, and
looks up at Bathsheba’s arrival without stopping her own toilet; she appears not as a servant, but as simply
spectator
<pb id="p36-88" n="88"/>
of a drama not her own. However, she does show by contrast just how attractive Bathsheba is; it was beauty,
and not merely nakedness, that urged David to grasp for himself a woman whose children mark her as associated
with another man.</p>
        <p>Within the frame of this “Sculpture” of a family group and its significance, we can perhaps
also see in Bathsheba and her children aspects of named figures from Blake’s mythology. As shown above, the
flowers, in conjunction with Blake’s later textual reference, support the notion that Bathsheba enacts some
of the meanings represented by Blake under the name of Vala; she will give birth to Solomon, taking a place in
the line of descent that leads to Jesus; she is, in that sense, a figure in Blake’s “Female line,” a
“Daughter of Vala.” However, her unashamed nakedness makes it difficult to completely erase the memory of
Blake’s visualizations of Jerusalem from our minds, and we can see her as also part of the saving vision
that continues throughout history. In a narrative, Blake could have described her with some of the machinery
used to describe Ololon as a complex creature; in a single tempera Blake can only include multiple
perspectives and coexisting contrary values indirectly through analogy or implication.</p>
        <p>It is also possible that Blake might have called the children Los and Enitharmon in a hypothetical
lost addition to <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, as a form of shorthand; the line cited above
identifying Solomon as a son of Los supports the possibility. Blake could describe all genuine poets as
“Sons of Los,” so that the boy in the tempera could be seen symbolically as the father of both David and
Solomon, poet and architect respectively, despite the absurdity thus produced at the level of the originating
biblical narrative—an almost literal case of “The child is father to the man.”</p>
        <p>The girl is less specific in stance and gesture; she is a bit player, who fills out a pattern, but
needs no elaborate rationale for her presence. The line from Blake’s poetic mythology cited above gives us a
function that can be used to annotate her role here, but with no useful gain in understanding. It seems that
the girl’s chief function here is to fill in a space, to help constitute that basic family group that had
become a feature of Blake’s designs from the late 1790s on.</p>
        <p>However, such an “accommodation” of the children into Blake’s myth does not provide a
complete or even adequate account of what they are doing in the tempera with their mother Bathsheba, and the
roles suggested give rise to fairly violent conflict with the host narrative. We have also yet to account for
the complexity of the boy’s gesture and stance; without an understanding of these, we cannot give a firm
reading of the tempera. The boy’s gestures imply a breaking away from the direction of family bonds towards
his own different path, though the break has not been fully implemented at the moment caught in the design.
The mother’s arm passes in front of his neck to rest on his shoulder; that continued linkage, and his own
raised but hidden right arm, both show that he is still entwined affectionately with his mother. The
interaction suggests the pivotal moment in which a boy moves from the protected condition of childhood towards
the freedom and potential dangers of manhood.</p>
        <p>However, the situation is not totally articulate or persuasive in its <hi rend="i">designo</hi>,
and there remains an unresolved discontinuity in the visual syntagmatic structure; what should be a
quasi-grammatical sequence of meaningfully connected bodies contains implicit internal contradictions that
render a firm reading of their interaction difficult or impossible without assistance from an attached or
associated text. The boy’s back is turned as he not only faces away from us and the other members of his
family, but also appears to move away from them and from us; his right and forward foot is firmly planted
while his left foot is raised, only the toes touching ground, indicating movement. All three members of the
family group are in fact caught in contradictions between stasis and movement; all are drawn as if in motion,
rearward feet raised with only toes touching ground, and yet forward motion for all three is virtually
impossible—Bathsheba and her daughter would step straight into the bath, the boy would choke on his
mother’s arm. We can enjoy the bodies without becoming aware of the internal contradictions, but as soon as
we attempt a full reading of their implied intentionality we confront problems that admit no full solution.
Blake’s desire to create pleasing bodies has here conflicted with the desire to create bodies that
articulate a legible intent, and the resulting forms resist attempts to impose clear and consistent
meaning.</p>
        <p>At play here is the larger question of the readability of Blake’s bodies and faces. Blake’s own
comments are optimistic; he directs us repeatedly towards the bearers of explicit human intentionality in a
picture, and away from the mere furniture: “Rubens thinks Tables Chairs &amp; Stools are Grand / But Rafael
thinks A Head a foot a hand” (E 513), and again “Complicated &amp; Minute Discrimination of Character. .
.is the Whole of Art” (E 653). In practice, however, Blake often either used the well-established but rather
crude and simplified schema of facial emotion published by Le Brun and others, or, as here, offered faces
surprisingly void of explicit emotion.</p>
        <p>There was much discussion during the 18<hi rend="s">th</hi> century about the powers and limits of
facial expressiveness in painting. One of the focal points was the concept of mixed passions, which had been
exploited by Benjamin Ralph in his popular <hi rend="i">The School of Raphael; or, the Student’s Guide to
Expression in Historical Painting</hi>, which included such attempts at subtle analysis of expression as this
account of Raphael’s cartoon of the <hi rend="i">Draught of Fishes</hi>: “In Peter’s countenance, fear,
wonder, and solicitude are blended in a most extraordinary manner,” and this description of the face of the
lame man in the cartoon of <hi rend="i">The Lame Man Healed</hi>: “the expression of joy and gratitude which
appears in it, is finely balanced
<pb id="p36-89" n="89"/>
by a mixture of doubt and astonishment.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">40</ref> Reynolds in his fifth discourse, without mentioning Ralph’s name, questions those
<q>
who praise excellencies that can hardly exist together; and above all things are fond of describing with great
exactness the expression of a mixed passion, which more particularly appears to me out of reach of our art.
Such are many disquisitions which I have read on some of the Cartoons and other pictures of Raffaelle, where
the Criticks have described their own imaginations; or indeed where the excellent master himself may have
attempted this expression of passions above the powers of the art; and has therefore, by an indistinct and
imperfect marking, left room for every imagination, with equal probability to find a passion of his
own.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref>
	<note id="n40">40. Benjamin Ralph, <hi rend="i">The School of Raphael; or, the Student’s Guide to
Expression in Historical Painting</hi> (first published London, 1757; cited from London: John Boydell,
[1800?]) 23, 26.</note>
	<note id="n41">41. Sir Joshua Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Discourses on Art</hi>, ed. Ralph R. Wark (New Haven:
Yale University Press, 1997) 78-79; Wark’s notes refer to Félibien, but Ralph seems closer to the context.
There is a fine example of what Reynolds is talking about in E.H. Gombrich, <hi rend="i">Symbolic Images</hi>
(London: Phaidon, 1972) 224n23, which lists a variety of interpretations of the expression of the central
figure in Botticelli’s <hi rend="i">Primavera</hi> ranging from “melancholy” to
“laughing.”</note></q>
Blake registers his disagreement: “If Reynolds could not see. variety of Character in Rafael Others Can”
(E 653), which at first sight seems to bypass Reynolds’s point, which was about not “variety of
Character” but the possibility of representing a “mixed passion.” But Blake also wrote “expression
cannot exist without character as its stamina” (<hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, E 549); for him
expression was the outering of a permanent, or quasi-permanent, inner state. That puts in question not only
his confidence in an artist’s power to express subtle and fleeting states of mind through modifications of
face and body, but also his belief that such states had real existence. Blake’s defence of “Complicated
&amp; Minute Discrimination of Character” (again “Character” where we might have expected
“Expression”) as “the Whole of Art” (E 653) has some pathos, given his own difficulties in producing
readable expression outside the realm of the powerfully exaggerated and simplified. In the present case, there
is a singular lack of clear expression on the faces of all present; if there is “Minute Discrimination of
Character,” it is too subtle to register. 
                </p>
        <p>Blake also had occasional trouble combining multiple bodies into persuasive and fully articulate
relationship, and in relating bodily movement to the immediate physical context; both these weaknesses are in
evidence in <hi rend="i">Bathsheba</hi>, inhibiting confident reading of the meaning held in “a foot a
hand.” Blake doubtless learned some anatomy as an art student, but was not interested enough on a long-term
basis to consistently create bodies capable of communicating subtle states of energy or thought,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">42</ref> though some of his bodies do indeed express a
direct and powerful intentionality. These recurring weaknesses, areas in which Blake simply did not exert his
powers adequately, put in doubt the wisdom of pushing too far an interpretation of the intentionality encoded
within the gestures and faces of his figures. In the case of <hi rend="i">Bathsheba</hi>, an attached or
inscribed text might have enabled a more confident response, though at the cost of a partial overwriting of
the design itself, as has happened in the case of <hi rend="i">A Vision of The Last Judgment</hi>, where the
accompanying text has drawn more attention than the extant drawings; the case might of course be different if
the tempera had survived. <note id="n42">42. Blake learned enough to make a good drawing of a cast of the
Belvedere Torso (B 115v), but his well-attested dislike of life classes (see Malkin in Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 423) suggests that anatomical accuracy was not a primary concern.</note></p>
        <p>As interpreters of Blake, we are caught between a rock and a hard place. There is a temptation to
assert or adopt a “firm perswasion” to remove the mountain of doubt and make a thing “so” 
(<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, E 38-39). But the results of such firmness can be disastrous, as
Ezekiel goes on to demonstrate—“what greater subjection can be”—and little is won by abandoning one
shaky interpretation only to replace it with another almost equally suspect; Blake’s Milton knew the danger
of becoming the “Tabernacle” of Satan, “A covering for thee to do thy will, till one greater comes / And
smites me as I smote thee &amp; becomes my covering,” for these are the laws of Satan’s “false Heavns”
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, E 139). The history of interpretation of many of Blake’s designs that come
without attached text shows the high level of risk in making firm identifications, the large color prints
offering some particularly good examples.</p>
        <p>In that spirit, and in the absence of any associated text, I shall not make an attempt at a
definitive interpretation of the meaning and identity of the boy in <hi rend="i">Bathsheba</hi>, nor of his
complex but puzzling gesture; Blake has simply left insufficient evidence for us to answer these questions
with confidence. Some incorporation of figures from Blake’s mythology into the story of Bathsheba seems very
likely, and the evidence offered above suggests Los as the most probable candidate for the figure of the boy.
It is also clear that some act is in progress that will change the relationship between him and his mother,
but exactly how we do not know. Such a change would probably fit into what we learn from the illuminated
poetry of the relationship between boys and mothers, but not easily into either the relationship between
Bathsheba and this otherwise unknown son, or the workings of the energy embodied in the figure of Los and
possibly acted out by this boy. The attempt to read the children’s identities, and the boy’s gesture,
through the lens of Blake’s myth reaches a premature end without producing any firm conclusion. The residue
of unintelligibility
<pb id="p36-90" n="90"/>
haunts and teases the viewer, who must handle the uncertainty as best he or she can.</p>
        <p>A partial solution to the problem is to cease beating so hard on the portal of explicit meaning,
though invited to do so by Blake himself, and seek satisfactions elsewhere. Baxandall, after considering
various iconographic readings of the imagery of Piero della Francesca’s <hi rend="i">Baptism of Christ</hi>,
turns to “the authority of the pictorial character, forms and colours,” commenting that “[i]n a verbal
explanation of a picture the authority of such matters, as compared to the significance of something or other
found verbalized in some directory of symbols, is difficult to drive home. But their authority is primary, if
we take the visual medium of pictures with any seriousness at all; they, not symbols, are the painter’s
language.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref> Even Blake, with his
unusually strong emphasis on meaning, had an urge to produce a varied and interesting surface. The children,
and the boy’s interestingly differentiated orientation and gesture, may have been added for visual
complexity and variety as well as for the kinds of meaning explored above. The three interconnected bodies
afford Blake some exercise of his skills in creating gentle <hi rend="i">contrapposto</hi>—the girl and her
mother both turn their faces slightly away from their forward foot, and turn slightly towards each other in an
affirmation of affectionate relation. The bodies are harmonious and pleasingly molded, though without any
particular subtlety of anatomical observation. The body of the seated woman is by contrast lumpy and not
totally convincing; the waistless torso has been compressed vertically in a manner that recalls the flying
figure of <hi rend="i">Elohim Creating Adam</hi> (B 289), and the foreshortened right leg modulates clumsily
into the rounded knee. Blake’s dislike of life classes had a cost. <note id="n43">43. Baxandall, 
<hi rend="i">Patterns</hi> 132-33.</note></p>
        <p>In other areas Blake has successfully put the claims of surface interest and variety into creative
tension with significance. He has, for instance, followed tradition by relegating David to a top corner, but
has picked him out with a kingly crimson robe, incidentally proving the good sense of Richardson’s statement
that “<hi rend="i">sometimes the Painter happens to be Obliged to put a figure in a Place, and with a Degree
of Force which does not sufficiently distinguish it. In that Case, the Attention must be awakened by the
Colour of the Drapery, or a Part of it, or</hi> by the Ground on which ‘tis painted, or some other
Artifice.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">44</ref> The minimization of
David, contrasted with Bathsheba at center front, creates tension between the narrative, in which David
provides the motivating energy, and the surface composition, in which he plays so small a part; his isolation
within the window formed by the columns, the wall, and the frame of the painting joins with the color of his
robe to give his small figure a power out of all proportion to its size on the canvas. The crimson of his robe
echoes the bright red of the honeysuckle on the left hand column and the roses at the bottom right of the
design, reinforcing the symbolic associations of those flowers proposed above. The separation of the spaces in
which David and Bathsheba exist emphasizes the intrusiveness of his act, which is about to break up a virtual
haven of innocence. <note id="n44">44. Jonathan Richardson, <hi rend="i">An Essay on the Theory of
Painting</hi> (1725; reprinted Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1971) 131-32.</note></p>
        <p>The flowers in the foreground and the backdrop of rather lumpy and undifferentiated trees further
the impression of an enclosed and sheltered garden paradise that is about to be broken into by the serpent of
sexual desire prepared to inflict damage and even death in the pursuit of its will—to invoke the imagery of
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Satan Watching Adam and Eve</hi> in the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations
(B 529:5, 531, 536:4), appropriate particularly as the last of these, as Baine noted, shows Eve holding a rose
and Adam a lily. David’s body is constructed on the basis of diagonals and oppositions, showing a strong 
<hi rend="i">contrapposto</hi> in the opposed movements of his right leg and both arms that counter his turned
head. This animation differentiates him from the calmly modulated frontal aspect of Bathsheba and her
daughter. David’s energetic desire is expressed also by the angle presented by the castle wall upon which he
walks to the frontal plane of the bath—a note of harmonic discord in the othewise planar composition. Males
in this composition are sources of disquieting energy, females centers of calm nurture.</p>
        <p>We look at the female figures from a low vantage point, the legs of the figures softly reflected by
the water that forms the lower boundary of the design. Our vantage point is directly in front of Bathsheba,
and the exact center of the surface of the design is in the dark space between Bathsheba and her daughter, at
just the height of her genitals. The columns create a secondary internal frame within which the female figures
are placed, and within that frame Bathsheba’s genitals occupy the exact center, which is also close to the
implied vanishing point of the painting, though, as is usual with Blake, there is little perspectival
information with which to work. The sexual nature of the impending action has been well mapped onto the
surface of the design.</p>
        <p>Overall, the painting is a mixture of successes and relative failures. Blake has visualized the
well-known episode from the Bible in a form unique enough to stimulate a search for its underlying
intentionality, with the unprecedented children as its focus. But he has not provided the
information—pictorial or textual—needed to enable that search to reach a confident conclusion. An
exploration of the relationship of the figures and action of this design to the names and narratives of his
mythological poetry produces interesting suggestions, but these suggestions are complicated by our inability
to fully read the intent of the boy’s gestures, though these are specific enough to assure us that they were
intended to carry specific meaning. One result has been the critical silence surrounding those children, apart
from my own well-meant but ill-judged earlier account. Edgar Wind once wrote that “the presence of unresolved
<pb id="p36-91" n="91"/>
residues of meaning is an obstacle to the enjoyment of art. However great the visual satisfaction
produced by a painting, it cannot reach a perfect state so long as the spectator is plagued by a suspicion
that there is more in the painting than meets the eye.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">45</ref> That statement was made in a book featuring a new reading of Botticelli’s 
<hi rend="i">Primavera</hi> that stressed “the intellectual character of Botticelli,” though it also aimed to
maintain our sense of the painter’s “<hi rend="i">lyrisme exact.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">46</ref> However, even all Wind’s skilfully applied learning has
not put an end to the multiplication of interpretations of Botticelli’s work, which suggests that painting
is inherently an art that resists definitive iconographic interpretation. Wind’s language calls to mind
Blake’s comment about the “wonderful originals called . . . the Cherubim” which he saw “in vision,”
which contained “mythological and recondite meaning, where more is meant than meets the eye” 
(<hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, E 531); we can do our best to reach out for that “more,” but Blake
is even more resistant than Botticelli to the imposition of firm iconographic conclusions. <note id="n45">45.
Wind, <hi rend="i">Pagan Mysteries</hi> 15.</note>
	<note id="n46">46. Wind, <hi rend="i">Pagan Mysteries</hi> 126.</note></p>
        <p>If we turn to plastic values, we experience an analogously mixed state of arousal / frustration,
though there is here no parallel with Botticelli’s fascinating surfaces. The figures of the family group are
attractive and graceful, but lacking in the kind of anatomical and expressive accuracy that might give them a
more deeply satisfying articulateness. The scene contains a good deal of vegetation, split into two very
differently handled realms; in one we have a background of blurred and melded trees, that appear to have been
added simply to provide a contrastive but non-interfering mat against which the bodies of the family group
appear to advantage, and in the other we have the rather repetitive and underindividualized though strongly
registered flowers, that appear to have been added to indicate specific meanings; the two realms do not cohere
into a closely observed and naturally varied garden landscape, though the generalized indications of a
quasi-paradisal garden do support the innocent implications of the frank nudity. The sky too is made up of
streaks of color that indicate evening, but do not fuse into a persuasive sky; the desire to be faithful to a
specific textual reference has won a tug-of-war over the production of a convincing background to the
action.</p>
        <p>In short, the design does not fully satisfy either the intellectual or aesthetic interests that it
arouses, though it offers enough to engage our interest. In defending a painting less problematical than 
<hi rend="i">Bathsheba</hi>, Blake told Trusler that “What is Grand is necessarily obscure to Weak men. That
which can be made Explicit to the Idiot is not worth my care” (E 702). One can retreat before the imputed
slur, and bravely claim that a painting is after all perfectly perspicuous to an adequately prepared viewer,
or one can see the statement as a form of bullying, justified in the face of all that Trusler as author of a
book subtitled <hi rend="i">The Way to be Rich and Respectable</hi> meant to Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">47</ref> but not a statement we should accept as a control over our
own responses. We can enjoy the painting for what it has to offer, without feeling ashamed to admit that Blake
in this and other designs has partially subordinated plastic and pictorial values to the quest for
significance, without giving means to fully satisfy the latter. There is a gentle irony in the fusion within
one person of the poet who wrote “The School Boy” (E 31) and, while receiving no formal education in
letters, wrote some of the greatest poetry in the language, with the artist who underwent a full seven year
apprenticeship as professional engraver, followed by two years’ study at the Royal Academy, and yet often
had trouble producing fully satisfying independent designs. The illuminated poetry remains the area within
which Blake most successfully integrated the two identities, the textual base providing a continuous support
for and interaction with the powerful images that surround and comment upon it. <note id="n47">47. Bentley,
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 60.</note></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
