<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>37.1.storch</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Christopher Z. Hobson, Blake and Homosexuality</title>
        <author n="Storch">Margaret Storch</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2003</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">37.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Duff</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Margaret Storch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2003"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_37">
    <body>
	<pb id="p37-38" n="38"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-1-0008">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Christopher Z. Hobson. <hi rend="i">Blake and Homosexuality.</hi> New York:
Palgrave, 2000. xxii + 249 pp. $59.95/£40.00, hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Margaret <name>Storch</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Christopher Z. Hobson has written a welcome study of an important aspect of Blake that is too
often ignored. People have noted the ideal beauty of Blake’s male figures, his sometimes androgynous female
figures, and the centrality of the theme of brotherhood in his work. Rarely has it been suggested that Blake
had a specific homosexual sympathy.</p>
          <p>Hobson presents the view not that Blake himself was necessarily homosexual or bisexual but that
he came to empathize with male homosexuals and lesbians as he became increasingly aware of the prejudice and
victimization they suffered. The study is well grounded in the social history of the eighteenth and early
nineteenth centuries, when a specific awareness of male homosexual identity together with intolerance, greater
legal repression, and mob antagonism came about. Even the republican tradition of reform which Blake espoused
was inimical to sodomy. Hobson suggests that Blake’s views may have developed in a way similar to those of
Jeremy Bentham, his close contemporary, who over several decades moved to a position of acceptance of
homosexuality as a variant of human nature.</p>
          <p>Hobson considers that Blake’s works before <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> reflect “the
poetics of masculinity,” including the tendency observed by feminists and others to treat desire and
gratification in terms of heterosexual male dominance. The Preludium to <hi rend="i">America</hi> is a notably
aggressive example. The illustrations to the poems may depict possibly homosexual figures, for instance the
women in the opening plates of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, but they are absorbed in
the overall heterosexual male-centered ethos. Hobson also discusses Blake’s views on masturbation as shown
in this period, which like his masculinist perspective are regressive. He suggests that masturbation,
resulting from social repression, is an expression of “deformed desire.” Thus, masturbation expresses and
determines Urizen’s negativity in the creation sequence in <hi rend="i">Ahania.</hi></p>
          <p>It is in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, that vast, many-faceted work that occupied Blake for
more than ten years, that Hobson finds the first clear emergence of homoerotic expression and sympathy. Most
prominently, homosexual acts are depicted as expressions of rebellion against the oppressive father, Urizen.
Hobson suggests that in Blake’s middle and later work depictions of homosexuality frequently accompany
statements in the text of resistance to social oppression. Certain illustrations in the poem are studied
carefully for evidence of homosexual activity or interest. One of Hobson’s key examples is the illustration
to page 78 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, which, as he interprets it, shows a male figure, assumed
<pb id="p37-39" n="39"/>
to be Orc, about to engage in fellatio with another male figure who is leaning over him. The accompanying text
concerns Urizen’s successful subjugation of Orc in Night 7. Hobson reads a sequence such as Orc’s adoption
of a phallic, snake-like form in Night 7a, at Urizen’s injunction, as a criticism of male sexual
possessiveness. In illustrations such as those for page 88 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, where three
figures are depicted worshipping an exaggerated phallic form, Hobson posits censure of masculine erotic
aggression, the dangerous “secret religion” to which the text refers.</p>
          <p>Hobson identifies various female figures in the poem as engaging in lesbian sexual activity, like
male homosexuals, in defiance of the power of Urizen, and he discounts heterosexual interpretations such as
those of Magno and Erdman. A problem in reading these illustrations of female activity as benignly intended by
Blake is that the text of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> contains significant misogynistic allusions, some on
the same pages as the illustrations, as Hobson acknowledges. Thus it seems unnecessary to posit a positive
interpretation of the female figures. Elements from the <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> illustrations may be
transferred with their original impetus to the finished works: the exquisite design for the title page of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 2, holds menace in its surreal female forms and the tripartite motifs
associated with abstraction and denial of sensuality.</p>
          <p>Blake’s responses to Milton are central to Hobson’s case. He discusses extensively both
Blake’s illustrations to Milton’s works and the poem <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Hobson finds a homosexual
character in the depictions of the brothers in the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustrations with their classical
warrior motifs, and also in the designs for <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, in which Blake revises
Milton’s disdain for the body. His interpretation of the historical significance of the Bard’s Song,
departing from Erdman, is that Satan, here and elsewhere, is the English state in Blake’s own time, applying
the strictures of Moral Law to aspects of personal life, including homosexuality. Satan’s expulsion of
Leutha, his female principle, and her guilt at sexuality, are seen as an ironic condemnation of moral
repression.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is essential to any discussion of homosexuality in Blake, and Hobson
persuasively places it in a new historical context. He puts forward the view that the revisions to the poem
after 1811 in the C and D versions, entailing a stronger condemnation of Moral Law, may be related among other
causes to a period of heightened prosecution and persecution of homosexuals during 1810-1811, the most
notorious being associated with activities at the White Swan Inn in Vere Street. Prisoners were reviled by
angry mobs, including many women. Blake does not mention Vere Street, but Hobson suggests that the episodes
may have intensified his sympathy for the victims of homophobia and that “Calvary’s Foot” in plate 4 is
a veiled reference to the mob persecution, rather than specifically to Tyburn, the usual reading.</p>
          <p>In discussing the two “homosexual” plates, 45 and 47, Hobson considers whether the contacts
involve fellatio, and inclines towards the view that 45 depicts Urizen’s fainting at the naked male body,
while 47 may show Blake’s genital kiss of the glorified form of Los. However, a most significant
consideration is surely that in plate 47, as well as in 32, 37 and 45, Blake uses a homosexual image to
express a theme of the utmost artistic importance—the incorporation of creative power. This possibly
indicates not merely empathy with homosexuals on Blake’s part but his own homoerotic, or bisexual,
sensibility.</p>
          <p>Hobson places homosexuality, with an emphasis on lesbianism, among the major themes that Blake
resolves in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> He focuses upon the sequence leading to the death of Albion in which
Albion confronts Jerusalem in the arms of Vala (plates 19-25). This female embrace is depicted in the lily
design, plate 28 of copy D, of which Erdman notes that the figure on the left was originally male and the
embrace less chaste. The sequence has been read by others as lesbian. Convincing as this may be, the emphasis
seems to be not upon eroticism so much as a powerful female partnership that will destroy Albion. Hobson goes
on to show that in this culminating epic emanations are not specifically female, as seen in Shiloh, and states
that hermaphrodites are sexually differentiated, removing threat and bias from gender relations.</p>
          <p>Hobson’s argument for Blake’s sympathetic espousal of lesbians is less convincing than that
for his empathy with male homosexuals. Female homosexuals were not subjected to the same legal and social
persecution as males, and therefore presumably would not have evoked the same response. Hobson reads the
attribution of sexuality and male organs to women as evidence of Blake’s positive feeling. However, the
illustrations of erotic lesbian poses and enlarged clitorises in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> do not
necessarily suggest a sympathy with lesbians: they may imply a prurient fascination pursued more fully in
these private sketches than in the illustrations intended for public view. A phallic woman, as a mother
figure, can be seen as threatening to men; a phallic woman as an object of desire may be reassuring, since she
is already in possession of mastery. Both fantasies spring from anxiety.</p>
          <p>Hobson’s book opens up the important topic of Blake and homosexuality as never before.
Blake’s empathy with male homosexuality and his own sensibility that embraces the homoerotic are fundamental
and revealing elements in his work.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
