<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>37.1.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">K. E. Smith, An Analysis of William Blake’s Early Writings and Designs to 1790,
Including Songs of Innocence</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2003</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">37.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Duff</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Margaret Storch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2003"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_37">
    <body>
	<pb id="p37-36" n="36"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">K. E. Smith. <hi rend="i">An Analysis of William Blake’s Early Writings and
Designs to 1790, Including</hi> Songs of Innocence. Lewiston: Edwin Mellen Press, 1999. Studies in British
Literature, vol. 42. xxi + 273 pp., 11 b&amp;w illus. $119.95/£74.95, hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>As its title suggests, this expensive, workmanlike study sets out to consider the oeuvre and
trajectory of a William Blake who, say, fell into a “consumsion” and died in November 1790, days before
his thirty-third birthday. At one time to have been called <hi rend="i">Blake: The Road to Innocence</hi>
(back cover, 61, 87, 154), the book might more aptly be imagined as <hi rend="i">Innocent Blake.</hi> It
brings together some of the research on these early productions to support the incontrovertible claim that
<q>
[t]he early work has its own authority, demands our attention to its enterprise. One does not have to claim
artistic equality of any kind with the later work to argue that <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> is one of
the most adventurous and energetic poetry books of the 1780s, that <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> is
one of few attempts in its time to take Sterne’s narrative innovations seriously or that Blake’s history
paintings of the early 1780s map an unusually ambitious role for the painting of English historical scences.
(4)
</q>
	<pb id="p37-37" n="37"/>
Its assertion that “to attempt to substantiate and fill out these claims of artistic significance . . . this
study dwells in detail on specific texts and designs” (4) seems more problematic. While the book serves
passably as an introductory discussion or “commentary” (186), it is neither comprehensive in scholarship
nor convincing with regard to the analytical pretensions of the title.</p>
          <p>Consider for instance the following treatment of “Song 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> by a Young
Shepherd,” an early version of “Laughing Song” added (but not in Blake’s hand) to one copy of 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi> For Smith,
<q>
the innocent note is here in the unabashed and buoyant refrain which confirms that already for Blake Mirth is
better than Fun and Happiness than either:<lb/>
Come live &amp; be merry and join with me,<lb/>
To sing the sweet chorus of Ha, Ha, He. (E 11)<lb/>
In the context of the early 1780s, then, we can see proto-Innocence as a pulling away first from the elaborate
literarity [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> and then from the satirical cynicism
of <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon.</hi> Although it is the second movement which will concern us in detail
here, the mention of the first highlights the extent to which the momentum is away not only from satire but
also from the more general knowingness of tone and outlook in which Blake’s early satire is embedded. (87)
</q>
Despite stated awareness of the “mixing of sources . . . central to Blake’s creative process” (22), the
“very direct way in which Blake would take what he wanted” (20), not to mention the blatant literariness
of “come live . . . with me . . . &amp; be . . .,” Smith has no place for the echo of the bawdy chorus
from <hi rend="i">Troilus and Cressida</hi> 3.1: “Yet that which seems to wound to kill / Doth turn oh oh to
ha ha he” and an endemic “knowingness of tone and outlook” which such an allusion would posit in the
holy place [ha, ha, he] of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> (For Smith, “the presence of a vitalistic,
sexual reference [‘unabashed and buoyant’ or not!] suggests a world which, for good or ill, breaks free of
Innocence” [170].) Such commentary has little capacity for dealing with vision. Despite its identification
of “three modes of innocent poem” (102) or, in another mood, “four levels of innocent song”—
<q>
(a) a group of “London-humanitarian” songs, (b) songs of infant joy with strongly
Christian-pastoral-symbolic overtones, (c) songs which use Innocence as startling light into pressing social
problems of the age and (d) songs which affirm in a broad, sweeping context the validity of Innocence as a
world-view. This would then leave us with a residual category of songs, namely those four which Blake
eventually transferred from Innocence to Experience. (161)
</q>
—it can in no sense imagine innocent song functioning at once as a three-part glee much less in a four-fold
manner. Curious also is that “residual category of songs,” when “it is necessary to see 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> as a composed whole, as the first achieved version of Blake’s composite
art” (121) with its own “free-standing significance” (207). Smith can approve of “drawing attention .
. . to the care needed by both editors and their readers in attending to precisely what Blake wrote” (157),
then quote precisely even as he passes unremarked the text of the black boy he sees as “returning good for
evil”: “‘Ill shade him from the heat till he can bear.’” While Smith asserts that “the very notion
of a road towards Innocence is surely made more credible rather than less by acknowledgment of conscious or
unconscious artistic choices taken by Blake along the way” (87), the possibility of the artist’s encoding
of unconscious expression into the “fully-dramatized context of the words” in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> goes
unacknowledged, though when it suits Smith’s purpose of invoking orthodox allusions to the Psalms or the
Anglican prayer book he can note “the slight but marked shift of syntax which alerts us to the new
dimension” (168).</p>
          <p>A pervasive reliance on pathos undercuts logos and ethos throughout with frequent invocations of
“surely,” “indeed,” “of course,” and, in particular, repeated, tiresome assertions of what is
“important” (a word never used by Blake). Saving the most important almost for last, Smith suggests in his
consideration of “The Chimney Sweeper” that
<q>
whatever our various interpretations may be, the most important thing is to have the right starting-point for
them in the simulation of the chimney sweeper’s voice—our intuition of authorial sub-texts and search for
our own framework of evaluation will follow soon enough. (175)
</q>
How, one wonders, does one voice “Ill shade him”? And how is “the simulation of the chimney sweeper’s
voice” not always already an “intuition”? The footnote to this heartfelt insistence relates the
author’s debt to some personal correspondence “for bringing me strongly back to this fundamental—yet
easily-evaded—starting point of understanding ‘The Chimney Sweeper’ of Innocence” (245). The
fundamental starting point is, evidently, the right starting point, not necessarily the same as “precisely
what Blake wrote.” Thus the reader’s relation to the problematic last line of “The Chimney
Sweeper”—“So if all do their duty, they need not fear harm”—depends on “an ability to listen to
exactly what is being said by this child at this moment” (174). Just as, one supposes, Smith’s reader
discerns “exactly what is being said” in the sweeper’s cry “weep weep weep weep” amid the multiple
semantics and inferences of its writing.</p>
          <p>The fundamental problem, for this reviewer at least, is Smith’s unquestioned, uncritical
conception of “voice” that text serves only to transcribe. “Putting it at its simplest,” we read a bit
further on, “the songs need to be heard before they can be analyzed, their energies responded to before
their framework is deconstructed” (177-78). (Or did you hear that?) (And how does one “respond” to
“energies” anyway?) The consideration of these things is the whole duty
<pb id="p37-38" n="38"/>
of any reader, and so the subject of the “Introduction,” that opening road into Innocence (“Innocence
sustains itself as a voice,” writes Smith [181]). Of that plate’s compressed narrative of
individual/cultural progression from sound to words to writing SMith hears only “consonance between the
world of the child on a cloud who sets the agenda of wholesome joy and tears and the piper who provides their
artistic articulation” as he marks for us also the absence of any “felt contradiction between the downward
triumphant narrative of the verse and the upward swing towards heaven of the design’s vegetation” (159).
The reason “Every child may joy to hear,” one supposes, is that with the songs now written down, etched,
and printed, they may be read aloud—perhaps even with real inspiration—by some knowledgeable (i.e.
experienced) reader. But in either event There Is No Natural (or, unmediated) Access—the songs can never be
“heard” before they have been analyzed—not by the reader, who must negotiate the signifiers (“Ill”?
*I’ll?), nor by young listeners, with no voice about whatever reading experience they cannot choose but
overhear. Several innocent references to “deconstruction” (above, and 85, 98, 151) add to the impression
that, some useful if unexceptional contextualization notwithstanding, this effort does not live up to its
claim to offer “An Analysis.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
