<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>37.2.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2003</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">37.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rosamund A. Paice</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2003"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_37">
    <front>
      <pb id="p37-41-42" n="41-42"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.037.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="335">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            Rosamund Paice on the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi><lb/>
            Sheila Spector on Blake’s Graphic Use of Hebrew<lb/>
            VOLUME 37<lb/>
            NUMBER 2<lb/>
            FALL 2003</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-2-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="4" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
				<head>
				  <title>CONTENTS</title>
				</head>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Articles</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="37.2.paice">Encyclopaedic Resistance: Blake, Rees’s 
<hi rend="i">Cyclopædia</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> Separate Plate</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Rosamund A. Paice</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">44</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="37.2.spector">Blake’s Graphic Use of Hebrew</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Sheila A. Spector</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">63</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p37-43" n="43"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Rosamund A. Paice lectures in English at the University of Lancaster. She completed her doctoral
study of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> separate plate in 2002, and is currently working on Blake’s
illustrations to Dante and the Bible, with the aim of producing a book on literary responses in Blake’s
later works. Her particular interest is in the way in which Blake rewrote for his own purposes the history and
meaning of his own and others’ creations.</p>
        <p>Sheila A. Spector, author of <hi rend="i">“Glorious incomprehensible”: The Development of
Blake’s Kabbalistic Language</hi>, and <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”: The Development of Blake’s
Kabbalistic Myth</hi> (both published by Bucknell University Press in 2001), is most recently editor of 
<hi rend="i">British Romanticism and the Jews: History, Culture, Literature</hi> (New York: Palgrave Macmillan,
2002).</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sjns@mail.rochester.edu<lb/>
TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@socrates.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada<lb/>
The University of Toronto declines to forward mail.</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens GA 30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@english.uga.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham NG11
8NS United Kingdom</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Addresses outside the
U.S., Canada, and Mexico require a $15 per volume postal surcharge for surface delivery, and $20 for airmail.
Credit card payment is available. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi>
Address all subscription orders and related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department
of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones
for information on issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in <hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to
either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451;
Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030. No articles will be
returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a
diskette, or send your article as an attachment to an email message; please number the pages of electronic
submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are usually acceptable.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, American Humanities Index, Arts and
Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover: William Blake, <hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi> <corr type="emend">Fitzwilliam Museum.</corr>
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2003 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
    	<pb id="p37-80" n="80"/>
    	<div1>
    		<div2>
    			<div3 type="in-memoriam">Kathleen Raine<lb/>
    			1908-2003</div3>
    		</div2>
    	</div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
