<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>37.2.spector</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Graphic Use of Hebrew</title>
        <author n="Spector">Sheila A. Spector</author>]
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2003</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">37.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rosamund A. Paice</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2003"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_37">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-2-0006">
        <pb id="p37-63" n="63"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Graphic Use of Hebrew</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Sheila A. <name>Spector</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The one certainty that emerges from the controversies surrounding the relationship between
Blake’s verbal and visual art is that neither medium alone was capable of expressing the plenitude of his
Divine Vision.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n0"> I would like to thank John E. Grant for his many insightful comments and suggestions about an
earlier version of this paper.</note> As the articulation of a conception beyond the range of either
conventional painting or poetry, Blake’s visual art, as Christopher Heppner has said, “is in continual
flight from the purely and/or merely visual towards the more explicit modes of meaning available only to
language itself.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">1</ref> Conversely, it
might be added, the poetic is in continual flight from the purely and/or merely literal, the language of the
prophecies being illuminated by the composite art. Basically, Blake lacked a medium of expression through
which to articulate the full range of his imagination, for it exceeded the material limitations of the visual
and the verbal, inevitably leaving a gap between his conception and the means of its execution. Consequently,
much of Blake’s artistic experimentation was dialectical, involving the attempt to develop a vehicle through
which to coordinate the two. Most likely, it was in conjunction with this aim that Blake turned to Hebrew.
Because of its significance as the language of the Old Testament, and hence, as the purported language of
Adam, Hebrew provided Blake with a medium that could be used to expand the magnitude of his poetry.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">2</ref> Beyond its literal implications, however,
Hebrew could also contribute to the graphic dimensions of the art as well, its symbolic and mystical
associations providing a useful tool for extending the range of the visual art. <note id="n52">1. Heppner 233.
Along the same lines, in “Visible Language: Blake’s Wond’rous Art of Writing,” W. J. T. Mitchell notes
that “Blake treats his pictorial art as if it were a kind of writing and summarizes the entire history of
writing from pictogram to hieroglyphic to alphabetic script in the pages of his illuminated books.” At the
same time, “he also pushes alphabetic writing toward the realm of pictorial values, asking us to see his
alphabetic forms with our senses, not just to read through or past them to the signified speech or
‘concept’ behind them, but to pause at the sensuous surface of calligraphic and typographic forms”
(83).</note>
	<note id="n53">2. My earlier study of Blake’s use of Hebrew, “Blake as an Eighteenth-Century Hebraist,”
has been superseded by my monograph, <hi rend="i">“Glorious incomprehensible”: The Development of
Blake’s Kabbalistic Language.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Hebrew was clearly not a major element of Blake’s graphics, there being fewer than a dozen
examples of obvious Hebrew lettering in the entire corpus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n54" type="note">3</ref> Even so, its use clusters into definite chronological periods, each
reflecting a distinctive approach to the alphabet. Specifically, the first period, introduced by graphic
experimentation on the verso of a <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> drawing, spans the decade of the 1790s, 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 30E and 435 using pseudo-Hebrew to imply some sort of indecipherable supernatural
message. After that, we have no evidence that Blake drew any letters again until 30 January 1803, when he
wrote his brother James that he was studying Hebrew. During the decade introduced by that letter, Blake
produced <hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams, Enoch</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> plate 15, each of which
contains what can be considered a text-based use of Hebrew, revolving around explicit passages from the Old
Testament. Finally, Blake returned to Hebrew in his last years when, on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32*(e), the
title page and plate 2 of the Linnell Job engravings, and <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, he again experimented
with hebraic graphics, though this time Blake seems to have replaced the literal sense of the text with
symbolic aspects of the alphabet that expand the verbal and visual components into the dynamic unity of his
last works. Before analyzing how Hebrew contributes to the graphic art, though, it is necessary first to
consider the non-linguistic aspects of the alphabet. <note id="n54">
                            3. Because of their obscurity, the possible Hebrew letters found in 
<hi rend="i">The Sea of Time and Space</hi> (Butlin [hereafter B] 803), as well as <hi rend="i">Christ Nailed to
the Cross: The Third Hour</hi> (B 496) and <hi rend="i">Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch</hi> (B 499) are
beyond the range of consideration in this study; see also Heppner 242 and 292n14.
                            <p>Given the confusion surrounding the order of plates in many of Blake’s books,
for the illuminated books the numbering used in this essay will conform to that found in the William Blake
Trust/Princeton University Press Series, gen. ed. David Bindman; for <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, The Four
Zoas <hi rend="i">by William Blake: A Photographic Facsimile of the Manuscript with Commentary on the
Illuminations</hi>, ed. Cettina Tramontano Magno and David V. Erdman (Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 1987); and for
the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward
Young’s</hi> Night Thoughts, complete edition, ed. John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, Michael J. Tolley, and
David V. Erdman, 2 vols. (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1980).</p></note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Non-Linguistic Aspects of the Hebrew Alphabet</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Because of its special history, Hebrew developed in conjunction with numerical, visual and
mystical modes of thought that extend the use of the alphabet far beyond its conventional function as a
component of a material sign system (illus. 1).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">4</ref> Numerically, Hebrew is used for computational purposes to a far greater extent than the
system developed by the Romans. Mathematically, each of the twenty-seven characters of the alphabet
(twenty-two letters, five of which have different forms for use at the end of a word) has a specific value, so
that letters, or even words, can be used as the equivalent of numbers. For example, the word for “life,”
<rtl>חי</rtl><span> </span><hi rend="i">(hai)</hi>, composed of the eighth and tenth letters—ח 
<hi rend="i">(heth)</hi> and י <hi rend="i">(yod)</hi>—is equivalent to the number 18, with which it is used
interchangeably, <hi rend="i">hai</hi> signifying 18, and conversely, 18 the concept of life. Certain 
                            <pb id="p37-64" n="64"/>
<figure n="TableHebrew.37.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="349">
	<head>1. “Table of Hebrew and Chaldee Letters,” plate i of S. L. MacGregor Mathers, ed. and trans., 
<hi rend="i">The Kabbalah Unveiled</hi> (London, 1887; reprint, New York: Samuel Weiser, 1968).</head>
</figure>
                            groups of letters, especially those containing particular combinations of א 
<hi rend="i">(alef)</hi>, ה <hi rend="i">(he)</hi>, ו <hi rend="i">(vav)</hi> and י <hi rend="i">(yod)</hi>,
that are associated with the name of God, are avoided in arithmetical computations. Thus, instead of 
<hi rend="i">yod-he</hi> or <hi rend="i">yod-vav</hi>, a 10-5 or 10-6 combination, <hi rend="i">teth-vav</hi>,
that is, 9-6, is used to signify 15, and <hi rend="i">teth-zayin</hi>, 9-7, for 16. <note id="n55">4. For a
popular introduction to the Hebrew alphabet, see Munk. More scholarly explanations of the letters can be found
in Ginsburgh.</note></p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Gematria</hi> (from the Greek γεωμετρία), the numerological computations
developed by Kabbalists, extends these practices to the fullest.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n56" type="note">5</ref> Believing that words with identical numerical values are mystically related,
Kabbalists substitute words of equivalent value for each other in the biblical text. In other words, any group
of letters totaling 18 could be used to replace the Hebrew word <hi rend="i">hai</hi>, thereby producing
entirely new meanings for the text. In addition, Kabbalists practice letter substitutions, for example
exchanging all א’s, the first letter, for ת’s, the last letter, ב’s, the second letter, for ש’s,
the next to the last, and so forth. Finally, they extract the first letters of words in particular sentences
to develop acronyms that themselves become the basis for further numerical computations. <note id="n56">5. For
an overview of <hi rend="i">gematria</hi>, see Scholem 337-43.</note></p>
            <p>Beyond their numerological signification, the letters also serve as visual icons, being
associated with the natural objects they resemble. Of those letters found in Blake’s drawings, the most
significant include the א <hi rend="i">(alef)</hi>, named after the ancient word for the head of an ox; ב
<hi rend="i">(beth)</hi>, named for the word “house”; ג <hi rend="i">(gimel)</hi>, a camel; ד 
<hi rend="i">(daleth)</hi>, a door; ה <hi rend="i">(he)</hi>, a word of uncertain derivation, though visually
associated with a window; ו <hi rend="i">(vav)</hi>, a peg or nail; ז <hi rend="i">(zayin)</hi>, weapon or
sword; ח <hi rend="i">(heth)</hi>, of unknown derivation, though symbolizing an enclosure, fence; ט 
<hi rend="i">(teth)</hi>, also of unknown derivation, symbolizing a serpent; י <hi rend="i">(yod)</hi>, from
hand; and ע <hi rend="i">(ayin)</hi>, the eye.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n57">6. The Hebrew etymologies are from Klein.</note></p>
            <p>In addition, the letters are also associated with the gamut of phenomena in both the corporeal
and spiritual worlds. On the physical level, different numbers and letters signify body parts, the senses,
physical activities, emotions, and planets; on the spiritual plane, they represent the angels, their
intelligences, spirits, their significations, aspects of the Supernal Man, names of God, and commandments of
the Law. In this context, the fifth letter, <hi rend="i">he</hi>, signifies sight, and is governed by the
angel Melchidale; <hi rend="i">vav</hi>, hearing, governed by Asmodel; <hi rend="i">yod</hi>, copulation,
governed by Hamaliel; <hi rend="i">ayin</hi>, laughter, and Hamael.</p>
            <p>Most significantly, Kabbalists, identifying language as the material of Creation, believe that
each letter is incarnate, deriving from a Divine hypostasis through which the God-head produced the
cosmos.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">7</ref> Associating each
letter/number with a particular state in the twenty-seven steps of creation,
<pb id="p37-65" n="65"/>
                            they divide the process into three parts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n59" type="note">8</ref> The first ten numbers, comprising the World of Emanations, correspond to the
ten <hi rend="i">Sefirot</hi>, or Divine hypostases, that emanated successively each from its immediate
predecessor. In this context, the first letter, א <hi rend="i">(alef)</hi>, corresponds to the first
emanation, the “Supreme Crown”; the second letter, ב <hi rend="i">(beth)</hi>, to “Divine Wisdom”;
third, ג <hi rend="i">(gimel)</hi>, “Human Intelligence”; and so on to the sixth, ו 
<hi rend="i">(vav)</hi>, “Grace”; and finally culminating in the tenth, י <hi rend="i">(yod)</hi>, the
“Divine Kingdom,” also known as the <hi rend="i">Shekhinah</hi>, or “Divine Presence.” Each of these
emanations has numerous theological, mythical and anatomical associations, the most germane to this paper
being the association Christian Kabbalists developed between the sixth, <hi rend="i">vav</hi>, “Grace,”
and Christ. Located in the symbolic “heart” of the human configuration of the emanations, the 
<hi rend="i">vav</hi> is depicted as the intermediary between the corporeal cosmos inhabited by man, the spiritual
realm of the emanations and, finally, the Godhead Himself. The World of Emanations constitutes the highest
spiritual level of the created cosmos. Beyond that, the next twelve numbers, which correspond to the next
twelve letters of the alphabet, contain the “Starry World,” including the First Mover, the Circle of Fixed
Stars, and the seven planets, followed by the Rational Soul, the Animal Soul, and the Elements of Sense.
Finally, the last five numbers refer to the corporeal cosmos, which contains the four elements, inanimate
matter, vegetation, animals, and finally, number 27, ת <hi rend="i">(toph)</hi>, man himself. 
<note id="n58">7. In their edition of <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake</hi>, Edwin John Ellis and William
Butler Yeats first introduced the subject of Kabbalism into the critical dialogue generated around
interpretations of Blake’s illuminated books. In order to clarify the confusion caused by differing
attitudes towards Kabbalism, I published “Kabbalistic Sources: Blake’s and His Critics’,” in which I
distinguished between the printed sources of Kabbalism available to Blake and those used by later critics. In
my <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”: The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Myth</hi>, I establish the
historical context for the kind of Kabbalism to which Blake would have had access, and then trace his gradual
incorporation of the kabbalistic myth into his illuminated books.</note>
	<note id="n59">8. The twenty-seven steps of creation are comparable to Blake’s twenty-seven heavens, both
systems tracing the cycle of existence from Creation through Apocalypse. Because my purpose here is to analyze
Blake’s use of the alphabet, I have somewhat simplified the discussion of Kabbalism, whose multifaceted
complexity actually comprises a four-part structure that conforms to the Tetragrammaton. This particular
delineation derives from Stehelin 156-66.</note></p>
            <p>The most important letter is א <hi rend="i">(alef).</hi> Symbolizing unity and the
undifferentiated reality of the One, it is considered the most spiritual of the letters, having been emãnated
directly from the Godhead Himself, and itself serving as the source for subsequent emanations. As summarized
by Jacques Basnage in his popular <hi rend="i">History of the Jews</hi> (translated into English in 1708):
<q>
    The א or <hi rend="i">A</hi> is the Doctrine. This Letter denotes the inaccessible light of the Deity;
that <hi rend="i">infinitum</hi>, call’d <hi rend="i">Ensoph</hi>, and relates to the first of the 
<hi rend="i">Sephiroths</hi>, which is the Crown: But this is not all; for this Letter is compounded of a 
<hi rend="i">Vau</hi> [ו] and two <hi rend="i">Jod</hi>’s [י], which has still some great Mysteries
compriz’d in it; for the <hi rend="i">Vau</hi> that makes the middle Branch, signifies the 
<hi rend="i">Tipheret.</hi> The two <hi rend="i">Jods</hi> are two Arms, which open to embrace the 
<hi rend="i">Malchut</hi> or the Kingdom. The <hi rend="i">Jod</hi> on the right indicates Wisdom, which always
carries her views upwards; and sheds her influences upon the other splendors beneath her. The 
<hi rend="i">Vau</hi> is the intelligence, which Wisdom has conceived, and the <hi rend="i">Jod</hi> above
bespeaks the Knowledge which the Intelligence has produced. Another inverts the Letters which compose the word
<hi rend="i">Alef</hi>, which making <hi rend="i">Pala</hi>, and signifying to conceal, he here discovers
another way the first of the <hi rend="i">Splendors</hi>; that Crown which is actually conceal’d; for Eye
has not seen it, nor has it enter’d into the Heart of Man. (189)
</q>
                            In his account, Basnage alludes to most of the non-linguistic aspects of the
letter. In addition to the concept of incarnation, and the associations with numerical values, planets,
angels, intelligences, spirits, Divine names, bodily organs, physical senses and emotions, Basnage also
personifies language, endowing the letters with gender and will. Not only are the two <hi rend="i">yod</hi>s
described in terms of arms reaching up to embrace <hi rend="i">Malkhut</hi>, but, as he will explain in his
discussion of the letter ב <hi rend="i">(beth)</hi>, at least one Kabbalist believes “that this Letter is a
Woman, and that the two Lines ב are two Arms, betwixt which she receives and embraces her Husband 
<hi rend="i">Tipheret.</hi>” This would be especially significant to Christian Kabbalists, who believe that 
<hi rend="i">Tiferet</hi>, the sixth <hi rend="i">Sefirah</hi>, signifies Christ. For this reason, Basnage reminds
his reader, “<hi rend="i">Jesus Christ</hi> says that one <hi rend="i">Jod</hi>, or rather least point of
the Law shall not pass away” (190), each containing its own kind of mystery.</p>
            <p>These mysteries are visual as well as literal. As Basnage notes, the graphic א 
<hi rend="i">(alef)</hi> can be broken down into two יs <hi rend="i">(yods)</hi>, the one descending on the left,
and the other ascending on the right, connected by the diagonal ו <hi rend="i">(vav)</hi>, like two hands
pegged onto an intervening nail. Numerically, when broken down in this way, the quantitative value of the 
<hi rend="i">alef</hi> is increased to 26, the value of the two <hi rend="i">yod</hi>s, at 10 each, and the 6 of
the intervening <hi rend="i">vav</hi>; and 26 is the number of the Tetragrammaton—<rtl>יהוה</rtl>—the
ineffable name of God, rendered as Jehovah in English. Consequently, the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> contains the
totality of the macrocosm, from 1, the “Supreme Crown,” down through the corporeal cosmos. Visually,
therefore, the outline of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, the symbol of the “Supreme Crown,” can be
interpreted cosmically, the expanses at the top and bottom corresponding, respectively, to the spiritual and
corporeal realms, above which is the Godhead, and beneath which is man. The intervening <hi rend="i">vav</hi>
provides the horizon, the starry realm intended to mediate between the spiritual and material worlds. In the
kabbalistic myth—as well as Blake’s version—the initial fault occurred on this median plane, when the
Rational Soul/Urizen, looking down, lost sight of the upper spiritual realms, and mistaking himself for the
height of existence, became an impediment, preventing man, in the lower space, from perceiving higher
things.</p>
            <pb id="p37-66" n="66"/>
            <figure n="BUT199.1.1v.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="722">
              <head>2. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Study of Hebrew Characters in Human Form.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>By permission of the Whitworth Art Gallery, University of Manchester.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Graphic Experimentation</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>From the beginning, Blake seems to have been attracted to the graphic potential of the Hebrew
alphabet. In what might be the earliest surviving example of his Hebrew lettering, found on the verso of a
sketch for the drawing, <hi rend="i">Tiriel Denouncing His Sons and Daughters</hi>, executed around 1789,
Blake outlined a random <hi rend="i">Study of Hebrew Characters in Human Form</hi> (B 199v), in an apparent
attempt to personify the first ten letters of the Hebrew alphabet (illus. 2). Blake seems to have begun with
the א drawn in the center of the page, and from there, randomly filled in the rest of the letters. Reading
from right to left, the top row apparently contains a ה (<hi rend="i">he</hi>, the fifth letter), ו 
(<hi rend="i">vav</hi>, sixth letter), and ז (<hi rend="i">zayin</hi>, seventh letter). Right in the middle of the
page is a giant א, apparently followed by a ד (<hi rend="i">daleth</hi>, fourth letter) and a י 
(<hi rend="i">yod</hi>, tenth letter). Then, the bottom seems to contain a ב (<hi rend="i">beth</hi>, second
letter), followed by a ח (<hi rend="i">heth</hi>, eighth letter), a ג (<hi rend="i">gimel</hi>, third
letter), and a ט (<hi rend="i">teth</hi>, ninth letter). The human heads and torsos on the letters suggest an
attempt to personify in a manner comparable to that alluded to by Basnage in his discussion of the Hebrew
letters. As Heppner notes, “The little fantasy drawing of small human forms on their way to becoming letters
of the Hebrew alphabet, [is] a representation in the form of a miniature allegory of a powerful tendency
within Blake’s art” (233).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n60">9. Although Butlin tentatively dates the letters 1803 (1:82), circumstantial evidence suggests
the possibility of an earlier provenance. The <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> drawing, whose verso is used for the
lettering, was executed in the late 1780s, and David V. Erdman dates comparable experimentation with the Roman
alphabet in the early 1790s (see <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi>, ed. Erdman,
N74-75).</note></p>
            <p>The next examples are numbers 30E and 435 from the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
illustrations, both of which contain pseudo-Hebrew messages. Collectively, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
108 and 30E, along with page 43 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, call into question the conventional
assumption that the lettering must contain a literal message somehow related to the visual text. In what is
likely its earliest extant version, the rough sketch on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 108 contains the
figure of a bearded old man, usually identified as Death. The figure holds in his hands a
<pb id="p37-67" n="67"/>
partially unfurled scroll that, in this early state, contains a few illegible scrawls, usually interpreted as
indicating how it is possible that “<hi rend="i">Life</hi> lives beyond the Grave.” When finally engraved,
the picture is used to illuminate the next page of text, in which the line, “This KING OF TERRORS is the
PRINCE OF PEACE,” is highlighted. In the engraved version, the figure looks away from, rather than towards,
the viewer, and in this case, the scroll contains what can best be described as pseudo-hebraic letters that
are virtually impossible to decipher. Some are in mirror writing, others are symmetrically ambiguous, while
the rest, though generally approximating Hebrew, actually are not. The effect of the lettering is
non-verbal.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">10</ref> Functioning like runes,
which some of the characters actually resemble, the writing appears to contain the secrets of immortality
possessed by Death, though impenetrable to us in our mortal state. Of course, the opposite inference is also
plausible: what appears from a distance to be the secret of life might also be revealed, upon closer
examination, to be nonsense (“This KING OF TERRORS is the PRINCE OF PEACE”?). The fact that both
interpretations are equally feasible suggests the larger significance of the graphics, that we will have to
use our imaginations, rather than our rational faculties, if we wish to penetrate the essential truth beyond
the range of Young’s meanderings. <note id="n61">10. In their commentary about page 63, Robert Essick and
Jenijoy La Belle summarize early attempts to read the letters (<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts or The Complaint
and The Consolation</hi> xiv-xv). See also John E. Grant, “Visions in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>” 162. The
fact that these readings generally conform to preconceptions about the message might be attributed to
Hebraists’ projections of their own expectations onto what remain inherently ambiguous figures that, with a
bit of imagination, can be made to resemble any number of possible Hebrew letters.</note></p>
            <p>The same hermeneutic can be applied to page 43 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> where, in
Night the Third, Blake uses the same illustration, this time apparently to underscore Urizen’s hubris in
identifying himself as God (Magno and Erdman 49). By using the same illustration for both Young’s
conventional interpretation of Death and the Urizenic imposture, it is possible that Blake is implying an
equivalence between the two false doctrines, both to be abrogated in part by the regeneration of Urizen
himself, at the climax of Blake’s epic. In both cases, the pseudo-Hebrew lettering might be seen to reflect
back on the inadequacy of a literal reading of Scripture, the kind of interpretation upon which both
Urizen’s and Young’s vacuous theologies are predicated.</p>
            <p>The same kind of reasoning applies to <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 435. Although the
letters are clearly recognizable, they do not spell any words in conventional Hebrew. Rather, it would appear,
they are used to evoke the secrets of eternity, especially those contained in a book held by the
personification of Eternity, the subject of the text on the plate.</p>
            <p>The most significant aspect of the Hebrew in these drawings is its unintelligibility. Clearly,
Blake had no interest in conveying a literal message; yet, he painstakingly executed the lettering, in the one
obfuscating the characters, in the other clarifying them though signifying nothing comprehensible, in both
cases apparently to imply a message that extends beyond the bounds of either the visual or the verbal medium.
In contrast, when he did wish to convey a decipherable message, Blake reverted to the Roman alphabet, as in
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 60/<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 51. Exploiting Young’s allusion to
Belshazzar, Blake’s illustration depicts, according to Essick and La Belle (xiv), the figure of a prophet
interrupting Belshazzar during his feast—he drops his glass and the wine spills out—to see the writing on
the wall. Here, the Roman letters spell out the first word and a half of the warning in Daniel (5:24-28),
“MENE” and “TEK.” As explained by Daniel: “MENE, God has numbered the days of your kingdom and
brought it to an end; TEKEL, you have been weighed in the balances and found wanting.” Missing from
Blake’s picture is the third word, “PERES, your kingdom is divided and given to the Medes and Persians.”
Blake’s choice of Roman rather than Hebrew letters seems to indicate that in this instance, he considered
the content of the message to be more significant than its medium.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n62" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n62">11. In personal correspondence, Grant associates these illustrations with a series of messages
found throughout Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, including <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 53, 108, 109, 298,
302, 303, 330, 388, 434, 435, 436, 18:4E, 20:5E, 52:17E, 60:19E, 30E.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Biblical Commentaries</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The next extant example of Hebrew graphics is found in the letter to James Blake of 30 January
1803, in which Blake boasts
<q>
    am now learning my Hebrew. <rtl>אבג</rtl> I read Greek as fluently as an Oxford scholar &amp; the
Testament is my chief master. astonishing indeed is the English Translation it is almost word for word &amp;
if the Hebrew Bible is as well translated which I do not doubt it is we need not doubt of its having been
translated as well as written by the Holy Ghost (E 727)
</q>
The passage is problematic for several reasons. Most obviously, as indicated by the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations, not to mention the verbal art, Blake had clearly been
interested in Hebrew long before this letter to his brother, and presumably, some time in the previous decade
and a half, Blake would have mentioned it to James. Moreover, by the nineteenth century, the problems with
Hebrew linguistics and Bible translation were fairly well known, as Blake certainly would have discovered from
his experimentation with hebraic etymologies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">12</ref> Finally, the
<pb id="p37-68" n="68"/>
<figure n="but550.1.11.wc" id="but550.1.wc.11" work-copy="but550.1" rend="db" width="958" height="787">
	<figTranscr>אלהיך נתנ<lb/>
	<lb/>
	שםיה        לא תרצח<lb/>
	<lb/>
	לא תנאף<lb/>
	<lb/>
	תגנב<lb/>
	<lb/>
	inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
	<head>3. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams</hi>, no. 11 of the Butts Job illustrations.</head>
	<figDesc>Morgan Library and Museum.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p37-69" n="69"/>
inclusion of Hebrew lettering was obviously gratuitous, just to show off to James how well William could draw
the first three letters of the alphabet—which we have no reason to assume that James would have recognized.
Yet, despite all this, the letter does indicate that, meaning aside, in the next decade Blake would use the
Hebrew allusively, to refer to a specific context. Here, in the letter to James, he includes the first three
characters to create a hebraic equivalent to learning one’s ABCs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n64" type="note">13</ref> Similarly, during this period, while Blake worked on the series of Bible and
Milton illustrations, as well as his own prophecy <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, he included Hebrew lettering in
three pictures—<hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams</hi> of the Butts series, <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, copy C, plate 15—in each case manipulating a biblical text to comment on the larger
theme of the visual art. <note id="n63">12. On the impact of biblical High Criticism, see McGann
152-72.</note>
	<note id="n64">13. In contrast to the English expression, the common Hebrew equivalent is to cite only the
first two letters, that is, to say that one is learning the <hi rend="i">alef-beth.</hi> The fact that Blake
transliterates the English version rather than using the Hebrew seems to be further evidence that he did not
study the language with a Jewish teacher.</note></p>
            <p>Begun soon after the letter to James, the watercolor <hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams</hi> (c.
1804-07) contains the first example of what appears to be an attempt to combine the symbolic implications of
literal Hebrew with graphic art (illus. 3). Depicting a dream state, the drawing portrays Job resisting being
pulled down. At the bottom of the picture are the flames of hell, out of which rise three demonic beings that
attempt to restrain the prone figure of Job, who apparently otherwise might rise beyond their grasp. The
figure on the left holds Job’s ankles, the one in the middle his loins, and the demon on the right lifts a
chain towards Job’s head, presumably intending to lock up Job’s mind. Stretched out above Job, in a parody
of the <hi rend="i">Elohim Creating Adam</hi> (1795), is Satan, identifiable by his cloven hoof and the
serpent entwined around his body.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">14</ref>
Not breathing life into Job, whose head is turned away, Satan gazes down, at a point beyond his extended left
arm that, itself cradled by the serpent’s head, in turn cradles Job’s head. Above Satan’s body is the
lightning that pierces the two tablets, to which Satan points with his right hand. The movement of the picture
is downward, as the lightning, Satan and the demons all combine to manipulate Job to the lower reaches. In
contrast, Job, lying flat on his back, pushes upward, thus keeping as much distance as possible between
himself and the serpentine Satan, who otherwise would be pulled by gravity down onto Job. <note id="n65">14.
See John E. Grant, “Blake’s Designs for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>” 80-82.</note></p>
            <p>Unlike the later engraving for the Linnell series, in this early version of the drawing, Blake
includes Hebrew lettering to underscore the threat implied by Satan. His choice of text, consistent with
Jewish iconography, contains the tablets of the Law, frequently illuminated by abbreviations of the ten
commandments. Blake’s text comes from Exodus 20. Read from right to left, the first tablet contains the
single Hebrew word <rtl>שמים</rtl>, “heaven,” which occurs twice in the Commandments: in verse 4,
“Thou shalt not make unto thee a graven image, nor any manner of likeness, of any thing that is in heaven
above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth”; and verse 11, “for in
six days the Lord made heaven and earth, the sea, and all that in them is, and rested on the seventh day;
wherefore the Lord blessed the sabbath day, and hallowed it.” The second tablet contains commandments from
verses 12 and 13:
<q><rtl>אלהיךָ נתן</rtl> (from Exodus 20:12: Honor thy father and thy mother, that thy days may be
long upon the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.)<lb/>
<rtl>לא תרצח</rtl> (Exodus 20:13: Thou shalt not murder.)<lb/>
<rtl>לא תנאף</rtl> (Exodus 20:13: Thou shalt not commit adultery.)<lb/>
<rtl>לא תגנב</rtl> (Exodus 20:13: Thou shalt not steal.)<lb/>
</q>
Of the ten, Blake cites those most concerned with material existence. While the commandment to honor one’s
parents is itself idealistic, the justification is corporeal, for long life. Similarly, by omitting the fourth
commandment from verse 13—“Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour,” the text in the
illustration concentrates on crimes of property violation. In selecting these commandments, Blake seems to be
implying that the evil dream imposed by Satan consists of corporeal values, at the expense of the spiritual
ideals relegated to the other tablet.</p>
            <p>Consistent with the choice of commandments, it can be argued that Blake selectively introduces
errors to underscore the erroneous law being imposed by Satan. Leaving the correctly spelled “heaven” to
speak for itself on its own tablet, Blake crowds the second stone with linguistic anomalies that apparently
emphasize the theme of the picture as a whole. Most noteworthy in the context of English Hebraism is the
pointed ךָ at the end of the first word. Here, Blake correctly includes the final <hi rend="i">khaph</hi>,
ך, at the end of the word signifying “your God.” Even more noteworthy, though, is the inclusion of the
vowel ָ  in the letter, both because vowels were eschewed by many Christian Hebraists of the day (including
John Parkhurst, whose lexicon Blake likely used<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">15</ref>), and because that particular form is extremely rare. This suggests that Blake had a
Jewish text in front of him as he completed the drawing. In contrast, the second word, “gave,” contains an
error, Blake’s version omitting the final <hi rend="i">nun</hi> at the end of the word. That is, Blake has
<rtl>נתנ</rtl> instead of <rtl>נתן</rtl>.
<pb id="p37-70" n="70"/>
The assumption that the error was committed out of ignorance seems belied by the technical accuracy of the
previous word. It is at least conceivable that the anomaly was deliberate, reflecting a corruption of the
concept of giving, a possibility in the context of this particular version of the Godhead, especially since
Satan’s finger points directly at the word <hi rend="i">elohecha</hi>, the genitive form of 
<hi rend="i">Elohim.</hi>
	<note id="n66">15. In “The Reasons for ‘Urizen,’” I argue that Parkhurst’s <hi rend="i">Hebrew and
English Lexicon, without Points</hi> was probably Blake’s main source of Hebrew. For more complete
discussions of Parkhurst’s influence on Blake, see my “Blake as an Eighteenth-Century Hebraist” and
“<hi rend="i">Glorious incomprehensible</hi>” 47-49.</note></p>
            <p>Significantly, the next commandment, <hi rend="i">lo tirzah</hi>, “Thou shalt not kill,” is
executed flawlessly, Blake apparently having no quarrels with its sentiment. Interestingly, the word 
<hi rend="i">tirzah</hi> provides the basis for both the plate, “To Tirzah,” a late addition to the 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, as well as the mythological figure who, in the major
prophecies, seems to symbolize the material concept of time, mortality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n67">16. On the name Tirzah, see my “Sources and Etymologies of Blake’s ‘Tirzah.’” On her
linguistic and mythic significance in the major prophecies, see my two monographs, “<hi rend="i">Glorious
incomprehensible</hi>” 134-36 and “<hi rend="i">Wonders Divine</hi>” 126 and 135.</note></p>
            <p>In the next commandment, Blake again introduces an anomaly, this time reversing the first א,
from the word <hi rend="i">lo</hi>, “thou shalt not,” of the injunction against adultery. Considering the
fact that there is a correctly executed א directly above this reversed one, as well as one for the third
letter of the next word, it seems likely that Blake deliberately corrupted the letter of this particular
negation, possibly to indicate ambivalence about the commandment.</p>
            <p>Collectively, the Hebrew in this picture seems to associate the literal interpretation of the
Bible with the false image of God, now specifically identified as Satan. In this context, the tablets
containing the law are products of the Satanic imposture, as symbolized by the broken Hebrew engraved on their
surface. Yet, the fault lies with Job’s own limited mode of perception. According to kabbalistic belief, the
material manifestation of the Bible, as perceived by man in his fallen state, is incomplete, reflecting the
inability to apprehend the One. Similarly, the damaged text on this picture is a projection of Job himself,
his perceptual limitations being personified by the figure of Satan. The challenge, as suggested by the
letters, is to see through the distorted literal level into the Divine truths of Scripture.</p>
            <p>This theme also dominates the two samples of Hebrew lettering contained in the lithograph of
<hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> (1807; illus. 4). Erroneously identified as <hi rend="i">Job in Prosperity</hi>, the
subject of the picture was not identified until 1936, when Laurence Binyon and Geoffrey Keynes credited Joseph
Wicksteed with the discovery that the Hebrew lettering on the book in the picture spells out the name
Enoch.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">17</ref> As interpreted allegorically
by Essick, Enoch represents the Divinely inspired instructor of the arts, especially writing, as represented
by the other figures surrounding the father figure in the center of the picture. <note id="n68">17. Binyon and
Keynes 8. In <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake</hi>, Essick provides a comprehensive history
of the lithograph (55-59).</note></p>
            <p>The inclusion of the Hebrew, though, seems to suggest that as with the biblical character
himself, the situation is far more complex. Historically, the ambiguous phrase in Genesis, that “Enoch
walked with God; and he was not, for God took him” (Gen. 5:24), has generated a great deal of speculation,
the most mystical being that he was the first man to ascend to heaven without having to undergo the pains of
death. As such, Enoch became the subject of mystical discourse, especially in the apocalyptic literature of
the intertestamental period. In the most significant account, 1 Enoch, or the Ethiopic Book of Enoch, Enoch
provides the basis for the earliest form of Kabbalism, <hi rend="i">Merkavah</hi>, or Chariot Mysticism.
Consequently, beyond the spare biblical account can be found a fairly extensive body of myth, most revolving
around the mystery of his death.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n69">18. The First Book of Enoch was not translated into English until 1821, long after Blake had
finished this lithograph. However, John Beer argues that Blake’s picture might have been influenced by an
unsigned article, “Concerning the Writings and Readings of Jude,” itself clearly influenced by the Book of
Enoch, that was published in <hi rend="i">The Monthly Magazine</hi> for 1 February 1801. For an analysis of
the influence of the Book of Enoch on Blake’s later work, see Bentley.</note></p>
            <p>Consistent with the legends, the figure in the picture is the illuminated center, looking
straight ahead, half-seated half-kneeling, holding on his lap an open book on which his name is written.
Enoch’s stillness is emphasized by the activities of the surrounding figures, placed like spokes in a wheel
whose center, the source of light, is located beyond the margins of the picture. As noted by Essick, those
closest to Enoch are the three artists, the painter, musician and poet, all deeply engrossed in their own
creativity. Beyond them are two groups of figures, each reading some sort of scroll, the one to the right
containing legibly written Hebrew. Probably the most striking aspect of the picture as a whole is that with
the exception of Enoch, no one seems the least bit affected by the light, all looking down towards the
material forms of their productions, as opposed to the spiritual source of their inspiration. Only Enoch looks
“through the eye.” Not requiring the text for his vision, he gazes out rather than down towards the book,
which would be pulled down were he not holding it.</p>
            <p>This apparent disparity between the letter and the spirit of the Law seems underscored by the
use of Hebrew on the plate. Written on the book held by the central figure is <rtl>חנוך</rtl>, the Hebrew
for Enoch. While the lettering is lexigraphically correct, the text is located on the wrong half of the page.
Because Hebrew is read from right to left, the name should either be in the center, as the title, or at the
right margin. Here, however, it seems to be justified to the left margin. While, obviously, the left hand of
the central figure blocks our view of the appropriate location of the name, Blake could either have moved the
hand over or he could have visually turned the book in the other direction, placing the lettering on the side
secured by the left hand of
<pb id="p37-71" n="71"/>
<figure n="ESXV.1.1A.SP" rend="file" width="958" height="679">
	<head>4. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Enoch.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>By permission of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
the figure. It seems possible that Blake deliberately chose to place the name in an odd position, thus
emphasizing the need to look beneath the surface appearance of the text. For his part, Enoch seems oblivious
to the book, which almost falls from his lap. Bathed in the Divine light, he has already transcended the
limitations of the material volume.</p>
            <p>In contrast, the two figures at the right holding the scroll, though facing the light, look
down at the writing, the one at the right pointing, with his left hand, to the final word of the phrase, 
<hi rend="i">elohim</hi>:
<q><rtl>וא[י]ננו כי לקח אתו אלהים</rtl></q>
                            In their anxiety about the material manifestation of the Word, they apparently
overlooked the omission in their text of the י <hi rend="i">(yod</hi>, symbol of the Divinity), which is the
third letter (Trinity) of the first word (God) in the biblical text. (The middle three words of the
sentence—“because [he] took him”—are correct, containing no anomalies.)</p>
            <p>Worked on around the same time as the Job and Enoch illustrations,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">19</ref><hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, copy C, plate 15 combines the
biblical text of <hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams</hi> with the symbolic import of <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> to
provide a mythic representation of the Urizenic imposture. In dramatizing the motivation of the hero, Blake
places Milton with his back to us, as he apparently climbs up into the Urizenic world in order, as punctuated
by his right foot, “to Annihilate the Self—hood of Deceit &amp; False Forgiveness.” Although the two
figures constitute the focal point of the picture, they are flanked by the two tablets of the Law, this time
held by a sorrowful Urizen. By replacing the Satan of <hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams</hi> with Urizen, Blake
redefines the concept of morality, substituting for the conventional duality of good and evil the delusions
produced by an erroneous interpretation of the text. In contrast to the Satanic prototype, Urizen is not as
old, not assisted by acolytes but alone, not powerful but sorrowful, almost as though he realized the
necessity of reforming his mode of thought. <note id="n70">19. According to Viscomi, the full production and
evolution of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> span the period from 1804 to 1818, though it was probably first printed
in 1811. For a detailed discussion, see “The Production and Evolution of <hi rend="i">Milton:</hi>
1804-1818,” chapter 32 (315-29) of his <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi></note></p>
            <p>Consistent with the transformation, this time the Hebrew on the tablets is virtually
indecipherable. While it is possible that the tablet in Urizen’s right hand might contain on the first line
the word <rtl>תחו</rtl>, <hi rend="i">tohu</hi>, “chaos,” and on the third, <rtl>לא</rtl>, 
<hi rend="i">lo</hi>, “not,” there is no way to be certain what the
<pb id="p37-72" n="72"/>
letters signify.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">20</ref> Rather, the point
seems to be the corruption of the text. Because the visual tablets provide the obvious allusion to the Ten
Commandments, Blake has no real need to etch particular letters to convey a literal reading of the Law. All he
need do is sketch in a few Hebrew-like characters to imply the irrationality of Urizenic thinking, that which
Milton will revise throughout the rest of the epic. In contrast to the illegible lettering found on the scroll
in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 30E/<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 43, though, here the graphics are text
specific, the allusion to the Ten Commandments being obvious, even without legible lettering. 
<note id="n71">20. Essick and Viscomi provide a “conjectural” transcription in their Blake Trust edition of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, 143, with commentary on 24-25.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Verbal Illumination</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>During the period when Blake completed <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, his last illuminated
prophecy, he also experimented with alternate ways of combining pictures and poetry in his composite art, in
some cases actually reversing the orientation between the two media. That is, while in the earlier books, the
verbal message was illustrated by the visual ornamentation, in some of his last works, the visual message was
complemented by surrounding graphics whose ornamentation is verbal.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n72" type="note">21</ref> Consistent with this reorientation, the Hebrew lettering used in the last
years of his life tends to be more symbolic than verbal. That is, generally unconstrained by a specific text,
as the Hebrew of the middle phase had been, here the Hebrew seems to be used more for its mystical and graphic
associations than for the literal meanings signified by any particular group of letters. <note id="n72">21.
Burwick notes that in the Job series, Blake “gives us in sequence a visual narrative mediated through a
frame containing the verbal text,” and that the “abundantly annotated <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> . . .
mediates the visual image through a welter of polemical graffiti . . . Indeed, Blake uses the Laocoön, much
as Lessing used it . . . to argue the nature and limits of verbal and visual signs” (128).</note></p>
            <p>As a transition to this new approach, the Hebrew in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32*(e), a late
addition to the prophecy, printed after 1821,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73"
type="note">22</ref> provides a graphic ornamentation for a verbal text. Apparently intending to exploit a
macaronic pun, Blake includes the Hebrew word/phrase, <rtl>כ‪/י‬רבים</rtl>, to correspond with the
English “as Multitudes” and the Latin “Vox Populi” in the margins of the plate.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">23</ref> The correct Hebrew for “as multitudes” is
a single word without the first <hi rend="i">yod</hi>—<rtl>כרבים</rtl>—a spelling that could also
signify the Hebrew for cherubs, the order of angels surrounding the Holy Ark (this is a complex word to which
the Hebraist John Parkhurst devotes almost twenty pages [339-57]). The Cherubim were especially significant to
Blake, who associated them with the original forms of “all the grand works of ancient art,” which were
later copied by the classical artists (<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, E 531). <note id="n73">22.
According to Viscomi, plate 32*(e) is a late addition to copy C of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, being printed on
paper Blake did not begin using until c. 1821. For a full discussion, see <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of
the Book</hi> 327-28.</note>
	<note id="n74">23. See Essick and Viscomi’s edition of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> for possible
interpretations of the Hebrew (188-89).</note></p>
            <p>Beyond any literal associations it might have, the Hebrew also has symbolic and graphic
significance. Symbolically, the inclusion of the extra <hi rend="i">yod</hi> could indicate the presence of
the “hand of God,” the word <hi rend="i">yod</hi> meaning “hand,” while its number, ten, signifies
God. Thus, it is possible that to illuminate a verbal passage explaining the difference between individuals
and states, Blake includes a verbal ornament whose implications graphically illuminate the refrain repeated
periodically in the Bard’s Song: “Mark well my words. they are of your eternal salvation!” Visually, the
verbal phrase is interwoven with the tendrils decorating the side of the page, becoming part of the
ornamentation as well.</p>
            <p>In the Linnell Job, Blake completely inverts his approach to the media. In the earlier book
illustrations, like those for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, the verbal text was spatially
central, its literal contents providing the focal point for the surrounding pictures. In the engraved Job,
however, the biblical text is reduced to the level of ornament, the central “text” being Blake’s visual
rendition of “<hi rend="i"><rtl>ספר איוב</rtl> / Illustrations of / The Book of Job</hi> / Invented
&amp; Engraved / by William Blake / 1825.” To be distinguished from the biblical text, this is Blake’s
composite reproduction of the “original,” of which, by implication, the later versions and interpretations
are merely derivative. In this reconstruction, the verbal line found in the biblical text is reduced to the
level of visual ornamentation, and within this context, the two examples of Hebrew lettering, as with that of
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32*(e), seem to be graphic rather than literal, both revolving around the full
symbolism of א <hi rend="i">(alef)</hi>, the first letter of the alphabet.</p>
            <p>When considered as an example of Blake’s Hebrew, the most significant aspect of the lettering
on the title page is the absence of errors. The two words, literally meaning “the book of Job,” are both
appropriate and correct, visually comprising the top part of the circle formed by the line of angels
surrounding the English title of the book. That the Gothic letters of the English title are decorated by
angels suggests a limited form of sanction, the implication being that the English, i.e., verbal, text can
convey only so much about the true import of <hi rend="i">sefer ‘iyob</hi>, a book whose Hebrew title
stands, as Burwick notes, “aloft upon a cloud of material reason (the statement of legal conformance, given
here within the cloud, is excluded from the frame in all twenty-one subsequent plates)” (136).
Significantly, the Hebrew contains a perfectly engraved <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, almost identical to the one
found in the early doodling, though without the stylistic grace of the two on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
435. The symbolic implication, as will be clarified on the next plate, is a starkly outlined letter that omits
the Divine spirit.</p>
            <p>These inferences are underscored by the illumination of plate 1. In this picture of 
<hi rend="i">Job and His Family</hi>, Blake depicts
<pb id="p37-73" n="73"/>
the initial fault of Job in terms of a literal, as opposed to imaginative, reading of the Bible. In what might
be viewed as a parody of the title page of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Blake portrays Job and
his wife seated beneath a tree whose fruits, in contrast to those of the earlier drawing, are musical
instruments. Surrounded by kneeling children, Job and his wife are seated, with their knees bent in Urizen’s
characteristic pose, to form two tablets, and both have open books on their laps. Severely boxed in by the
borders of the picture, the illustration is contained within a border depicting the outline of a Gothic
church, at the bottom of which is an altar whose flames appear to generate the entire picture. The message
beneath the altar is from 2 Corinthians 3:6 and 1 Corinthians 2:14: “The Letter Killeth / The Spirit giveth
Life / It is Spiritually Discerned.” Beyond the outline of the church is a ring of clouds containing the
opening of the Lord’s Prayer.</p>
            <p>Both literally and figuratively illuminating the engraving, the verbal lines help to
recontextualize the visual message. By expanding the perspective beyond the border of the picture itself, the
circumscribing ornamentation indicates that Job’s own perspective is foreshortened, the physical presence of
the unused instruments, which themselves are enclosed within the lines of the church, obscuring the spiritual
message above and its explanation below. Not an evil man, Job “feared God &amp; eschewed Evil,” as the
illuminating text explains. But he lacked vision, and as a result, he projected a moralistic interpretation
onto the Bible, creating God in his own literalistic image. The function of his experience, then, will be to
expand his own imaginative faculties so that he might elevate himself spiritually, rather than
literalistically debasing the concept of God.</p>
            <p>Mystically, the narrative can be said to revolve around the loss of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi>,
symbol of the unified vision of God, as manifested by the first Divine hypostasis, the “Supreme Crown.”
Hence the use of Hebrew on plate 2, <hi rend="i">Satan Before the Throne of God</hi> (illus. 5). Visually, the
picture introduces God, drawn in the image of Job from plate 1,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n75" type="note">24</ref> the only difference being that God, whose hair is spiked to resemble a
king’s crown, looks down, while Job had looked up. Between God and Job is presumably a figure of Satan,
though without the cloven hoof or encircling serpent, it is hard to tell (Burwick notes the resemblance
between Satan and Job’s eldest son). At the bottom of the picture, Job and his family all have reading
materials in their hands, though with the exception of his wife, whose gaze is ambiguous, all look away from
the texts. Although not as foreshortened as plate 1, plate 2 is also confined by the religious institution,
this time a Gothic trellis working its way up the side of the page, its spire projected beyond the border of
the engraving. Even though it is not physically present, its imaginative lines confine the verbal illumination
in the clouds above the picture. <note id="n75">24. See S. Foster Damon’s commentary on the plate, in 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Job, 14.</note></p>
            <p>Viewed from center to circumference, the text focuses in on the Hebrew phrase, <rtl>מלך
יהוה</rtl>, <hi rend="i">melekh</hi> “<hi rend="i">Jehovah</hi>,” above which is “The Angel of the
Divine Presence.” Beyond that is “Hast thou considered my Servant Job,” and finally, “I beheld the
Ancient of Days.” Although the Hebrew phrase can be literally translated as “the king Jehovah,” its use
could convey both ironic and mystical dimensions beyond what can be conveyed by a simple English translation.
First of all, the Hebrew can be read as a corrupted form of the English “The Angel of the Divine
Presence,” that would be <rtl>מל[א]ך יהוה</rtl> with the inclusion of an <hi rend="i">alef.</hi>
Second, for the name of God, Blake chooses the Tetragrammaton, the ineffable Name whose numerical value, 26,
is the same as the total of the components of the omitted <hi rend="i">alef.</hi> Thus, by substituting the
corrupted spelling, Blake may be visually implying Job’s debased concept of God, who has been transformed
into a royal image of man. At the same time, the Hebrew could suggest a corresponding degeneration of the
concept of angel, from which the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> of the One has been eliminated.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">25</ref> Thus, the version of the “Angel of the
Divine Presence” found in Job’s conventional mode of thought is incomplete, for it lacks the visionary
component provided by the spirit of the letter, the 1 and 26 of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, whose total, 27,
symbolizes man. Symbolically, the loss of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> can be attributed to the intervening
line, “Hast thou considered my Servant Job,” the challenge that caused the literalistic debasement of the
concept of God into the pseudo-One who abdicated his responsibilities to Satan. Above the challenge, though,
is the phrase “I beheld the / Ancient of Days.” Taken from Daniel 7:9, the term “Ancient of Days” was
used by Kabbalists to designate the highest physiognomy of the Supernal Man, corresponding to 
<hi rend="i">alef</hi>, “the Supreme Crown.” Thus, even though the challenge may have obscured Job’s vision,
thereby degrading the “angel” into a corporeal “king,” the Divinity is still ever present. 
            <note id="n76">25. According to Burwick, “’The Angel of the Divine Presence’ is manifest as
satanic contradiction, and the Hebrew words, ‘Jehovah is King,’ pronounce the surrender to his tyranny”
(144)</note></p>
            <p>This Divine Presence might be graphically indicated by the formal properties of the picture
itself. In the center, it is possible that Satan is depicted in the form of an <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, his
raised arms, like those described by Basnage, reaching up, as if ironically to embrace God, while his legs
extend outward to encompass Job and his family. From a broader perspective, Satan himself could be viewed as
part of a larger <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, formed by the whirlwind rising on either side of God, and the figures
extending down towards either corner. Kabbalistically, the diagonal corresponds to the mediating 
<hi rend="i">vav</hi>, the symbol of Christ whose function is to unite the lower material world with the spiritual
realm. Thus, from the cosmic perspective, Satan’s challenge could be performing
              <pb id="p37-74" n="74"/>
<figure n="bb421.1.4-3.ps" id="bb421.1.spb.04" work-copy="bb421.1" rend="db" width="793" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>2<lb/>
	I beheld the Ancient of Days<lb/>
	Hast thou considered my Servant Job<lb/>
	I shall see God<lb/>
	Thou art our Father<lb/>
	We shall<lb/>
	awake up<lb/>
	The Angel of the Divine Presence<lb/>
	מלך יהוה<lb/>
	in thy<lb/>
	Likeness<lb/>
	WBlake inv &amp; sc<lb/>
	When the Almighty was yet with me, When my Children<lb/>
	were about me<lb/>
	There was a day when the Sons of God came to present themselves before the Lord &amp; Satan came also among them<lb/>
	to present himself before the Lord<lb/>
	London Published as the Act directs March 8; 1825. by Willm Blake N3 Fountain Court Strand<lb/>
	Proof</figTranscr>
	<head>5. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Satan before the Throne of God</hi>, from <hi rend="i">Illustrations of
the Book of Job</hi>, plate 3.</head>
	<figDesc>Collection of Robert N. Essick.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p37-75" n="75"/>
the christological function of helping to expand Job’s visionary faculties so that he might perceive the
Ancient of Days. Hence the absence of cloven hooves or serpents. Just as the depiction of God is a projection
of Job, so, too, is that of Satan.</p>
            <p>Blake does not include any more Hebrew lettering in the series, its absence in this version of
<hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams</hi> (plate 12) possibly indicating a graphic economy. By now, the bare
outline of the tablets has become enough to convey his criticism of the Commandments. Instead, he engraves
Job’s prayer at the bottom of the page: “Oh that my words were printed in a Book that they were graven
with an iron pen &amp; lead in the rock for ever.” Blake’s illuminations graphically literalize the
verse.</p>
            <p>Although there are no other Hebrew words in the Job series, it is possible that Blake exploited
the symbolic values of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> as an underlying form through which to criticize Job’s
vision of God. As Munk points out in his first chapter in <hi rend="i">The Wisdom of the Hebrew Alphabet</hi>,
the mystical value of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, as symbol of God’s unity and omnipotence, is visually
conveyed through its graphic form (43-44). As such, the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> is the symbol that unifies God
and man, <hi rend="i">alef</hi> also being the first letter of the name Adam. Consequently,
<q>
    The א is seen as a ladder placed on the ground reaching heavenward. . . . Thus the א conveys to man
that—in order to free himself from earthly bondage—he must infuse his physical existence with spirituality
so that he can ascend to the summit: the Divine. . . . In summary:—א is the channel by which the Infinite
Spiritual is brought to the finite physical. . . . (54)
</q>
While there is no way to be certain whether or not the formal resemblance of some pictures to the letter 
<hi rend="i">alef</hi> is intentional, still, there are enough similarities to warrant their exploration.</p>
            <p>It is quite possible that as early as <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, Blake was interested in the
structuring potential of the <hi rend="i">alef.</hi> On copy E, plate 13 (plate 12[14] of the Blake
Trust/Princeton facsimile, ed. Dörrbecker, 4:239), the two angels, extending their wings up the sides of the
plate, and connected in the middle by an intervening cloud, create the symmetrically distorted impression of
the kind of <hi rend="i">alef</hi> Urizen might use to support himself and his book of brass (illus. 6).
Unlike the true <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, in this one the intervening <hi rend="i">vav</hi>, which should
symbolize the christological function, has been flattened out into the horizontal plane on which sits the
erroneous image of a god who lacks the dynamics of a true diagonal reaching up to the heavens. This kind of
outline can also be found on several of the Job plates. As seen on plate 2, a horizontal swath occupies the
middle third of the picture, with God resting on its top, and Job and his family pressed down by the bottom.
Yet, as noted, the extended figure of Satan seems to generate the energy of the true diagonal, his challenge
                            <figure n="europe.e.p13-14" id="europe.e.illbk.13" work-copy="europe.e" rend="db" width="719" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>13.<lb/>
	Albions Angel rose upon the Stone of Night,<lb/>
	He saw Urizen on the Atlantic;<lb/>
	And his brazen Book,<lb/>
	That Kings &amp; Priests had copied on Earth<lb/>
	Expanded from North to South.</figTranscr>
	<head>6. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi>, 1794, copy E, plate 13.</head>
	<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Rare Book and Special Collections Division, Library of
Congress.</figDesc>
</figure>
providing the means by which to correct the <hi rend="i">alef.</hi> In contrast, on plate 16, <hi rend="i">The
Fall of Satan</hi>, the lines produced by the flanking angels, whose extended wings resemble those framing
Urizen in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 13, here clearly comprise an intervening diagonal, as Satan is
summarily—with a true vertical—exiled to hell.</p>
            <p>It is also possible that the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> contributed to Blake’s development of
human figures as well, especially as culminating in the <hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi> In 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, plate 17(18) (Blake Trust/Princeton 4:249), Blake could conceivably be indicating the
future role of Los as Christ figure by positioning him like a dynamic <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, his torso and
extended left leg suggesting the diagonal of the <hi rend="i">vav</hi>, and his left arm 
(<hi rend="i">yod</hi>) lowered in the attempt to raise the figure he attempts to bring along with him. Similarly,
the central statue of the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> might also be viewed as a symbolic 
<hi rend="i">alef</hi>, which in its totality signifies the dynamic unity of God, while its components—the two
<hi rend="i">yods</hi> and the median <hi rend="i">vav</hi>—total 26, the number of the Tetragrammaton
(illus. 7). In addition, the two <hi rend="i">yods</hi>, each signifying 10, reach up to embrace heaven, while
the diagonal <hi rend="i">vav</hi>, numerically 6, symbolizes Christ, who mediates between the upper and lower
worlds. In Blake’s version, while his right arm reaches up to the level of God,
<pb id="p37-76" n="76"/>
being situated next to the Hebrew Tetragrammaton, his left arm is lowered to restrain the intertwined
serpent, located just above the Hebrew for Lilith, the she-demon, thus emphasizing the mediating function of
the <hi rend="i">vav</hi>, through which the viewer will be able to apprehend the occluded Divinity of the
figure. In this way, the engraved <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> might be seen as revolving around the dynamics of
an <hi rend="i">alef</hi> in the process of completing itself, thereby providing the means by which the
reader/viewer could discern the true form of the Divinity occluded by the overlay of Greek art.</p>
            <p>This is not to imply that the engraving was original to Blake. To the contrary, Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> was likely based on the reconstructed cast of a marble statue that was carved around 25
B.C., and rediscovered in the Palace of Titus in Rome in January 1506. When found, the statue lacked, among
other things, the right arm on the central figure. In his version, Blake tilted the head more to the left,
contracted the stomach muscles and moved the right knee more to the left.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">26</ref> Essick suggests that Blake might have been influenced by
Johann Winkelmann’s description of Laocoön’s body, in <hi rend="i">Reflections on the Painting and
Sculpture of the Greeks.</hi> Still, the figure’s form is also quite close to that of the male in 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 17(18). Even though Laocoön looks up while the other looks back at the person he is
bringing along with him, their heads are in the same position. A Kabbalist might infer that Blake had
attempted to bring out the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> he had envisioned incarnate within the Greek statue. Not
insignificantly, although he had first begun working on the concept of the Laocoön around 1814-15, in a
commission for Abraham Rees’s <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia; or, Universal Dictionary of Arts, Sciences, and
Literature</hi>, published 1816-19, Blake returned to the concept at the end of his life, the 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, completed c. 1826-27, being his last illuminated work. <note id="n77">26. For detailed
discussions of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, see Essick’s <hi rend="i">Separate Plates of William
Blake</hi>, 98-101, and Essick and Viscomi’s edition of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, 229-33. Essick and Viscomi
note that some of Blake’s changes may have been influenced by Marco Dente’s engraving of the statue before
its restoration.</note></p>
            <p>Sporadically interspersed in the verbal component of the visual line are four Hebrew messages.
Directly in the center of the picture, between the figure of Laocoön and one of his sons, is the only
grammatically correct Hebrew on the entire plate, the name of Lilith: <rtl>לילית</rtl>.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">27</ref> Probably derived from Babylonian demonology,
Lilith was the first wife of Adam. Because, like him, she was also formed from dust, Lilith demanded sexual
equality, and when her husband refused, she ran away, to be transformed into a she-demon who killed new-born
infants and seduced men. In kabbalistic myth, Lilith is Samael’s female counterpart, queen of the “other
side,” becoming the demonic counterpart of the <hi rend="i">Shekhinah</hi>, the Divine Presence (Jerusalem
in Blake’s myth). Not an isolated name, Lilith is visually enclosed in a space circumscribed by Laocoön and
the son on his left, bisected by Laocoön’s arm that restraints the serpent. Visually, the Hebrew is the
lower part of a duality opposed by the English word “Good,” coordinated by the serpent. Within the context
of the picture as a whole, the verbal duality of good and evil/Lilith is, on the one hand, a product of the
intervening serpent, and on the other, enclosed within the lowered <hi rend="i">yod</hi> of Laocoön’s left
arm. Consequently, while the duality occupies the central area of the picture as a whole, it is spatially
reduced to an aberration that, presumably, will be eliminated when Laocoön raises his arm to complete the
form of the <hi rend="i">alef.</hi> In the meantime, the mediating <hi rend="i">vav</hi>, whose width is
visually expanded by the touching arms and legs of Laocoön and his son, extends the christological function
which will ultimately facilitate the completion of the <hi rend="i">alef.</hi> Within this visual context, the
grammaticality of Lilith’s name reflects the facile appeal of the letter, ultimately to be superceded by the
spirit of the <hi rend="i">alef.</hi>
	<note id="n78">27. On the Lilith myth, see Graves and Patai 65-66; on the mystical implications, see Scholem
356-60.</note></p>
            <p>Although the Hebrew Lilith is in the middle of the picture, the most prominent example of
Hebrew is the heading at the top: <rtl>מל[א]ך יהוה</rtl>. Revolving around the same concept as that
used for plate 2 of the Job engravings, here the Hebrew rendering of “The Angel of the Divine Presence”
contains the <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, though reversed. In addition, the context is far different. In the Job
drawing, the Hebrew was used to describe the devolution of transcendence, from the Ancient of Days (the
kabbalistic <hi rend="i">alef</hi> of the Supernal Man, to Christian mystics the symbolic Christ) down to the
mediating angel, manifested in our world by the symbol of material power, the king. Now, assuming that the
inclusion of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> was deliberate, Blake reverses the perspective, portraying the 
<hi rend="i">alef</hi> in terms of the concept of incarnation, the internal Christ, the means by which man can
apprehend the One.</p>
            <p>Located spatially where Blake frequently (as in <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi>, for example) places
the source of light, the Hebrew is part of a triangle whose point is apparently the head of Laocoön, which
describes the materialization of art:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79"
type="note">28</ref><q>
Where any view of Money exists Art cannot be carried on, but War<lb/>
only Read Matthew C.X. &amp; 10 v.<lb/>
by pretences to the Two Impossibilities Chastity &amp; Abstinence Gods of the Heathen<lb/>
He repented that he had made Adam<lb/>
(of the Female, the Adamah)<lb/>
[<hi rend="i">scratched out</hi>] &amp; it grieved him at his heart<lb/>
The Angel of the Divine Presence<lb/>
<rtl>מל[א]ך יהוה</rtl></q>
	<note id="n79">28. According to Morton D. Paley, the aphorisms surrounding the statue transform the 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> “into <hi rend="i"><rtl>יה</rtl> &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam</hi> by
surrounding it with texts denouncing money, war, and empire and affirming the ultimate value of art”
(235).</note></p>
            <pb id="p37-77" n="77"/>
            <figure n="laocoon.A.P1" rend="file" width="846" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>If Morality was Christianity Socrates was the Saviour<lb/>
 יה &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam as they were copied from the Cherubim<lb/>
		of Solomons Temple by three Rhodians &amp; applied to Natural Fact. or History of Ilium<lb/>
		              Art Degraded Imagination Denied War Governed the Nations<lb/>
		Evil<lb/>
		                  Good &amp; Evil are<lb/>
		Riches &amp; Poverty a Tree of<lb/>
		                                        Misery<lb/>
		                  propagating<lb/>
		                  Generation &amp; Death<lb/>
		The Gods of Priam are the Cherubim of Moses &amp; Solomon: The Hosts<lb/>
		                                                                                             of Heaven<lb/>
		    Without Unceasing Practise nothing can be done Practise is Art<lb/>
		     If you leave off you are Lost<lb/>
		The Angel of the Divine Presence<lb/>
		                                             מלאך       יהוה<lb/>
		ΟΦΙουΧος<lb/>
		                                              Hebrew Art is<lb/>
		                                       called Sin by the Deist Science<lb/>
		                            All that we See is Vision<lb/>
		from Generated Organs gone as soon as come<lb/>
		                     Permanent in The Imagination; Considerd<lb/>
		                                 as Nothing by the<lb/>
		                                       Natural Man<lb/>
		What can be Created<lb/>
		Can be Destroyed<lb/>
		    Adam is only<lb/>
		The Natural Man<lb/>
		&amp; not the Soul<lb/>
		or Imagination<lb/>
		Good<lb/>
		                                       לילית<lb/>
		Satans Wife The Goddess Nature is War &amp; Misery &amp; Heroism a Miser<lb/>
		    Spiritual War<lb/>
		Israel deliverd from Egypt<lb/>
		    is Art deliverd from<lb/>
		       Nature &amp; Imitation<lb/>
		         A Poet a Painter a Musician an Architect : the Man<lb/>
		         Or Woman who is not one of these is not a Christian<lb/>
		You must leave Fathers &amp; Mothers &amp; Houses &amp; Lands if they stand in the way of Art<lb/>
		The Eternal Body of Man is The Imagination, that is God himself<lb/>
		                                   The Divine Body }    ישע     Jesus   we are his<lb/>
		                                                                                             Members<lb/>
		                     It manifests itself in his Works of Art (In Eternity All is Vision)<lb/>
		The True Christian Charity not dependent on Money (the lifes blood of Poor Families)<lb/>
		         that is on Caesar or Empire or Natural Religion<lb/>
		Money, which is The Great Satan or Reason<lb/>
		              the Root of Good &amp; Evil<lb/>
		                  In The Accusation of Sin<lb/>
		Prayer is the Study of Art<lb/>                            
		Praise is the Practise of Art<lb/>                            
		Fasting &amp;c. all relate to Art<lb/>
		The outward Ceremony is Antichrist<lb/>
		       Where any view of Money exists Art cannot be carried on, but War only Read Matthew C X. 9 &amp; 10v<lb/>
		by pretences to the Two Impossibilities Chastity &amp; Abstinence Gods of the Heathen<lb/>
		He repented that he had made Adam<lb/>
		            (of the Female, the Adamah)<lb/>
		                                       &amp; it grieved him at his heart<lb/>
		Art can never exist without<lb/>
		         Naked Beauty displayed<lb/>
		The Gods of Greece &amp; Egypt were Mathematical<lb/>
		                                                        Diagrams<lb/>
		                                                            See Plato’s<lb/>
		                                                                   Works<lb/>
		       Divine Union<lb/>
		    Deriding<lb/>
		And Denying Immediate<lb/>
		Communion with God<lb/>
		The Spoilers say<lb/>
		Where are his Works<lb/>
		That he did in the Wilderness<lb/>
		           Lo what are these<lb/>
		Whence came they<lb/>
		These are not the Works<lb/>
		Of Egypt nor Babylon<lb/>
		Whose Gods are the Powers<lb/>
		Of this World. Goddess, Nature.<lb/>
		Who first spoil &amp; then destroy<lb/>
		Imaginative Art<lb/>
		For their Glory is<lb/>
		War and Dominion<lb/>
		Empire against Art          See Virgils Eneid.<lb/>
		                                               Lib. VI.v 848<lb/>
		For every<lb/>
		Pleasure<lb/>
		Money<lb/>
		Is Useless<lb/>
		     There are States<lb/>
		         in which. all<lb/>
		     Visionary Men<lb/>
		     are accounted<lb/>
		           Mad Men<lb/>
		         such are<lb/>
		     Greece &amp; Rome<lb/>
		     Such is<lb/>
		     Empire<lb/>
		     or Tax<lb/>
		See Luke Ch 2 v 1<lb/>
		Jesus &amp; his Apostles &amp; Disciples were all Artists Their Works were destroyd by the Seven Angels of the Seven Churches in Asia    Antichrist      Science<lb/>
		                            The unproductive Man is not a Christian much less the Destroyer<lb/>
		The Old &amp; New Testaments are<lb/>
		    the Great Code of Art       Art is the<lb/>
		                                                   Tree<lb/>
		                                               of Life<lb/>
		                                                   GOD<lb/>
		                                               is Jesus<lb/>
		                                               Science is the<lb/>
		                                               Tree of Death<lb/>
		The Whole Business of Man Is<lb/>
		The Arts &amp; All Things     Common<lb/>
		                         No Secresy in Art<lb/>
		What we call Antique Gems<lb/>                 
		                are the Gems of Aarons Breast Plate<lb/>
		                Christianity is Art<lb/>
		                &amp; not Money<lb/>
		                Money is its Curse<lb/>
		       Is not every Vice possible to Man<lb/>
		                described in the Bible openly<lb/>
		       All is not Sin that Satan calls so<lb/>
		                  all the Loves &amp; Graces of Eternity.<lb/>
		Drawn &amp; Engraved by William Blake.</figTranscr>
              <head>7. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Fitzwilliam Museum.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p37-78" n="78"/>
            <p>In this area of the picture, the messages of the verbal and visual art coalesce, as the
horizontal lines cross, and thereby block, any potential source of light beyond the picture. The reason, as
the verbal lines explain, is materialism, and the result is an inverted concept of God. While it is always
possible that Blake simply erred in executing the <hi rend="i">alef</hi>, we should not discount the
likelihood that as a careful artist, Blake deliberately reversed the letter, perhaps in order to shift the
burden of interpretation to the readers/viewers who must for themselves reverse the perspective on the
Divinity, and thereby recognize the fallacy of the “good versus Lilith” duality, so that Laocoön might be
freed to raise his left arm towards the heavens and thus complete the potential <hi rend="i">alef</hi> on
which the picture’s form might be predicated.</p>
            <p>Until then, only half of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> will be possible, as indicated by the
inscription beneath the plinth: “<rtl>יה</rtl> &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam as they were copied
from the Cherubim of Solomons Temple by three Rhodians &amp; applied to Natural Fact, or History of
Ilium.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">29</ref> Reflecting the
degeneration from the original inspiration of “the Cherubim of Solomons Temple,” the Greek rendition of
Laocoön, while good art, lacks the full inspiration of “the Cherubim.” Consequently, it can only be
identified by <hi rend="i">ya</hi>, the first two letters of the Tetragrammaton <hi rend="i">(yod</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">he)</hi>, lacking the final ו <hi rend="i">(vav)</hi>, Christ, and ה <hi rend="i">(he)</hi> of the
full name of God, in English rendered “Jehovah.” <note id="n80">29. It should be emphasized that at this
point, I am referring to the mystical plenitude of the Tetragrammaton, as opposed to a signifier signifying
the concept of God. While both <hi rend="i">yod</hi> alone and the <hi rend="i">yod-he</hi> combination are
names of God, the full Tetragrammaton—<hi rend="i">yod, he, vav, he</hi>—is a mystical concept, the
ineffable Name which is never pronounced (when the Tetragrammaton is encountered in the text, the signifier
“ha-shem,” i.e., “the Name,” is usually substituted). Therefore, while <hi rend="i">yod-he</hi> does
signify God, it still comprises only half of the Tetragrammaton.</note></p>
            <p>The final instance, barely visible in the upper left corner of the picture, involves Christ as
“The Eternal Body of Man,” that is, “the Imagination, that is God himself / The Divine Body.” The
English is followed by a corrupted version of the Hebrew name Jesus: <rtl>יש[וע]</rtl>, in which the 
<hi rend="i">ayin</hi> is reversed, and the mediating <hi rend="i">vav</hi> is omitted. <hi rend="i">Ayin</hi>,
the name of the letter, is also the Hebrew word for “eye”; and, as already noted, the 
<hi rend="i">vav</hi> is the kabbalistic symbol of Christ. Again, assuming that the variations were deliberate,
the reversed <hi rend="i">ayin</hi> and omitted <hi rend="i">vav</hi> could suggest that the conventional
interpretation of Jesus is a corruption that ignores the true christological vision. By implication, the
audience will be able to reconstruct the true Christ by symbolically reversing the <hi rend="i">ayin</hi> and
adding the <hi rend="i">vav</hi>, that is, by retrieving the true art occluded by the transformations of later
versions.</p>
            <p>This brief excursion into Blake’s graphic use of Hebrew suggests that we may have been asking
the wrong question: it is less a matter of <hi rend="i">what</hi> the words mean than <hi rend="i">how</hi>
the letters signify within the total context of a particular picture or plate. In <hi rend="i">“Glorious
incomprehensible”: The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Language</hi>, I argue that Blake was never
interested in Hebrew as a conventional sign system. Rather, believing in the Adamic theory of language, Blake
incorporated Hebraisms into his verbal art, ultimately as the vehicle for expanding consciousness in order to
apprehend the One, through whose speech the act of Creation had been accomplished. I also argue that at some
point during the composition of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake redefined the name Albion
(etymologically a Latin reference to the white cliffs of Dover), in terms of spurious hebraic roots—<hi
rend="i">al</hi>, meaning “God,” and <hi rend="i">ben</hi>, for “son”—to justify his belief that the
English were the true chosen people, and English the Divine language, containing within its material shell
(“rough basement”) the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> incarnate. Blake’s graphic use of Hebrew lettering seems
to complement the belief that English derived from Hebrew, the language of God.</p>
            <p>In the first instances—the lettering on the verso to the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> drawing,
and the pseudo-Hebrew words in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts/Four Zoas</hi> illustrations—Blake seems to
be seeking ways to penetrate the mystical essence contained within the material form of the letter. By the
second phase, the text-based use of Hebrew probably completed after he had redefined Albion as the “son of
God,” Blake exploits the symbolic values of the letters, reforming the Word, as found in the biblical text,
to comment prophetically on contemporary England as the promised land. At the end of his life, when he again
returns to the Hebrew alphabet, his use is purely mystical. Consolidating the disparate approaches to Hebrew,
Blake seems to have unified all of his earlier experimentation around the concept of the 
<hi rend="i">alef.</hi> As the first letter of the alphabet, the <hi rend="i">alef</hi> is the first of the Divine
emanations, the unknowable Supreme Crown from which all successive potencies were emanated. Yet, the visual
correspondence between the letter and the human form suggests the existence of an incarnate relationship
between God and man, who was created in His image. Consequently, even though the Job engravings were based on
a series of drawings initiated approximately twenty years earlier, and even though the 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> design was not original to Blake, in both cases he seems to have revealed the incarnate
<hi rend="i">alef</hi> that he might have intuited as early as the mid-1790s, when he worked on 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, as the means by which he—and we—might apprehend the One.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Basnage, Jacques. <hi rend="i">History of the Jews, from Jesus Christ to the Present Time:
Containing their Antiquities, their Religion, their Rites, the Dispersion of the Ten Tribes in the East,
and</hi>
	<pb id="p37-79" n="79"/>
	<hi rend="i">the Persecutions this Nation has Suffer’d in the West. Being a Supplement and Continuation of
the History of Josephus.</hi> Trans. Tho. Taylor. London, 1708.</p>
            <p>Beer, John. “Blake’s Changing View of History: The Impact of the Book of Enoch.” 
<hi rend="i">Historicizing Blake.</hi> Ed. Steve Clark and David Worrall. NY: St. Martin’s P, 1994. 159-78.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “A Jewel in an Ethiop’s Ear.” <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time.</hi>
Ed. Robert N. Essick and Donald Pearce. Bloomington: Indiana UP, 1978. 213-40.</p>
            <p>Binyon, Laurence and Geoffrey Keynes. <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job by William
Blake.</hi> NY: Pierpont Morgan Library, 1936.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Job: <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi>
Illustrations of the Book of Job. Ed. S. Foster Damon. Hanover and London: UP of New England for Brown UP,
1966.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman. Commentary by Harold
Bloom. Newly rev. ed. Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1988. [abbreviated “E”]</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Continental Prophecies</hi>: America: A Prophecy; Europe: A Prophecy; The
Song of Los. Ed. D. W. Dörrbecker. Blake’s Illuminated Books, gen. ed. David Bindman, vol. 4. Princeton:
William Blake Trust/Princeton UP, 1995.</p>
            <p>—. The Four Zoas <hi rend="i">by William Blake: A Photographic Facsimile of the Manuscript
with Commentary on the Illuminations.</hi> Ed. Cettina Tramontano Magno and David V. Erdman. Lewisburg:
Bucknell UP, 1987.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem.</hi> Ed. Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi. Blake’s
Illuminated Books, gen. ed. David Bindman, vol. 5. Princeton: William Blake Trust/Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake: A Photographic and Typographic Facsimile.</hi>
Ed. David V. Erdman, with Donald K. Moore. Rev. ed. NY: Readex Books, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s</hi> Night Thoughts. 
<hi rend="i">A Complete Edition.</hi> Ed. John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, Michael J. Tolley, and David V. Erdman. 2
vols. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1980.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake: Poetic, Symbolic, and Critical.</hi> Ed. Edwin
John Ellis and William Butler Yeats. 3 vols. London: Quaritch, 1893.</p>
            <p>Burwick, Frederick. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> and <hi rend="i">Job</hi>: or, On
the Boundaries of Painting and Poetry.” <hi rend="i">The Romantic Imagination: Literature and Art in England
and Germany.</hi> Ed. Burwick and Jürgen Klein. Studies in Comparative Literature 6. Series ed. C. C. Barfoot
and Theo D’haen. Amsterdam: Rodopi, 1996. 125-55.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New
Haven: Yale UP, 1981. [abbreviated “B”]</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi>
Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. and Jenijoy La Belle, eds. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts or The Complaint and
The Consolation.</hi> Illustrated by William Blake. Text by Edward Young. NY: Dover, 1975.</p>
            <p>Ginsburgh, Yitzchak. <hi rend="i">The Alef-Beit: Jewish Thought Revealed through the Hebrew
Letters.</hi> Northvale, NJ: Jason Aronson, 1994.</p>
            <p>Grant, John E. “Blake’s Designs for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Blake and His Bibles.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman. West Cornwall, CT: Locust Hill P, 1990. 71-115.</p>
            <p>—. “Visions in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>: A Consideration of Some Pictures in the
Manuscript.” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on</hi> The Four Zoas, Milton, Jerusalem. Ed.
Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1973. 141-202.</p>
            <p>Graves, Robert and Raphael Patai. <hi rend="i">Hebrew Myths: The Book of Genesis.</hi> NY:
McGraw-Hill, 1963.</p>
            <p>Heppner, Christopher. <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s Designs.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge UP,
1995.</p>
            <p>Klein, Ernest. <hi rend="i">A Comprehensive Etymological Dictionary of the Hebrew Language for
Readers of English.</hi> NY: Macmillan, 1987.</p>
            <p>Mathers, S. L. MacGregor. <hi rend="i">The Kabbalah Unveiled. Containing the following Books of
the Zohar:</hi> The Book of Concealed Mystery, The Greater Holy Assembly, The Lesser Holy Assembly. Translated
into English from the Latin version of Knorr von Rosenroth, and collated with the original Chaldee and Hebrew
text. 1887. New ed. London: Routledge &amp; K. Paul, 1926, 1954. Rpt. NY: Weiser, 1968.</p>
            <p>McGann, Jerome J. “The Idea of an Indeterminate Text: Blake and Dr. Alexander Geddes.”
1986. Rpt. in his <hi rend="i">Social Values and Poetic Acts: The Historical Judgment of Literary Work.</hi>
Cambridge: Harvard UP, 1988. 152-72.</p>
            <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. “Visible Language: Blake’s Wond’rous Art of Writing.” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer. Ithaca: Cornell
UP, 1986. 46-95.</p>
            <p>Munk, Michael L. <hi rend="i">The Wisdom in the Hebrew Alphabet: The Sacred Letters as a Guide
to Jewish Deed and Thought.</hi> Brooklyn: Mesorah Publications, 1983.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. “<rtl>יה</rtl> &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 41 (summer 2002): 201-35.</p>
            <p>Parkhurst, John. <hi rend="i">Hebrew and English Lexicon, without Points.</hi> 1762; 3rd. ed.
London, 1792.</p>
            <p>Scholem, Gershom. <hi rend="i">Kabbalah.</hi> NY: Quadrangle, 1974.</p>
            <p>Spector, Sheila A. “Blake as an Eighteenth-Century Hebraist.” <hi rend="i">Blake and His
Bibles.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman. West Cornwall, CT: Locust Hill P, 1990. 179-229.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">“Glorious incomprehensible”: The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic
Language.</hi> Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 2001.</p>
            <p>—. “Kabbalistic Sources: Blake’s and His Critics.’” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 17 (winter 1983-84): 84-101.</p>
            <p>—. “The Reasons for ‘Urizen.’” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
(spring 1988): 147-49.</p>
            <p>—. “Sources and Etymologies of Blake’s ‘Tirzah.’” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 23 (spring 1990): 176-83.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”: The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Myth.</hi>
Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 2001.</p>
            <p>Stehelin, John Peter. <hi rend="i">The Traditions of the Jews, or the Doctrines and Expositions
contained in the Talmud and Other Rabbinical Writings. Translated from the High-Dutch. To which is Added, A
Preliminary Preface: or, An Enquiry into the Origin, Progress, Authority, and Usefulness of Those Traditions,
wherein the Mystical Sense of the Allegories in the Talmud and Other Writings of the Rabbins is
Explained.</hi> 2 vols. London, 1732-34; 2nd ed. 1742-43.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP,
1993.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
