<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>37.3.wellens</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Dutch Bibliophile Edition of The Marriage of Heaven and Hell (1928)</title>
        <author n="Wellens">Oskar Wellens</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2003/2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2003-04</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">37.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Rosamund A. Paice</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Oskar Wellens</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2003/2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_37">
    <body>
	<pb id="p37-104" n="104"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Dutch Bibliophile Edition of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> (1928)</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Oskar <name>Wellens</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>After the publication of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> in 1863,
“Blake was,” in the words of G. E. Bentley, Jr., “immediately elevated from obscurity to fame and
notoriety.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">1</ref> It is no matter for
surprise that henceforth numerous editions of his works started rolling off the presses, not only in England
and America, but also on the Continent. <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, By William Blake</hi>,
appeared in Maastricht, the Netherlands, in 1928, an edition that deserves some special attention, for it was
brought out in a limited run designed for bibliophiles only. This note is meant to throw some light on the
genesis of this remarkable publication.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n19">1. G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Critical Heritage</hi> (London:
Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1975) 11 (Introduction).</note>
	<note id="n20">2. Listed in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books: Annotated Catalogues of William
Blake’s Writings</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977) 303, and in George Watson, ed., <hi rend="i">The New
Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature</hi>, vol. II (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1971) 624.</note></p>
          <p>First a word on its publisher Alexandre Alphonse Marius Stols (illus. 1) is in place here, for he
was a monument in the annals of notable publications of Dutch as well as of foreign belletristic
works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">3</ref> Born in Maastricht in 1900 as
the son of a printer and publisher, Stols was from an early age steeped in the world of book production which
exerted a strong fascination over him. However, his father never wanted his son to succeed in the business,
but instead sent him to the University of Amsterdam in 1919 to acquire a degree in law. In that lively city
Stols was caught up in the maelstrom of intellectual and cultural life, commencing his lifelong acquaintance
with writers, sculptors, painters, and actors. He also attended lectures on art history, paleography,
philosophy, and Dutch and French literature. In 1923 he changed to the University of Leiden, where he
graduated with a B.A. in law. Meanwhile, he had started printing and publishing his own works, which over the
years included an extraordinary range of prominent Dutch and Flemish poets and novelists, many of them rising
to prominence. Stols seems to have been endowed with an unusual flair for spotting genuine literary talent.
From the very beginning of his publishing career Stols also catered for an international market, printing
works by Paul Valéry, Shakespeare, Paul Claudel, Rainer Maria Rilke, André Gide, etc. His correspondence
with writers and artists all over the world—more than 10,000 letters have been pre
<pb id="p37-105" n="105"/>
<figure n="stols.37.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="523">
	<head>1. Portrait of A. A. M. Stols by Edmond Bellefroid (1938).</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of Stadsbibliotheek Antwerpen.</figDesc>
</figure>
served—constitutes a rich mine of information on the changing climate of opinion in the former half of the
past century. When he died in 1973, Stols had brought out more than 1,000 literary works of outstanding value.
His biographer C. van Dijk describes him as “a man of not one outspoken talent or competence” but as a
“mixture of intelligence, artistic-typographical capacity, linguistic knowledge, social adaptability,
decency, conceitedness, unbusinesslikeness, feeling for quality, and the capacity of growing with his
time.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n21">3. Among the many articles and books on Stols, see especially C. van Dijk, 
<hi rend="i">Alexandre A. M. Stols, 1900-1973, Uitgever en Typograaf: Een Documentatie</hi> (Zutphen: Walburg,
1992).</note>
	<note id="n22">4. van Dijk, <hi rend="i">Stols</hi> 437. This and the subsequent translations from the Dutch
are my own.</note></p>
          <p>In 1927 Stols launched a prestigious series called “The Halcyon Press,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">5</ref> which, according to the <hi rend="i">First
Prospectus of The Halcyon Press</hi> (1927),
<q>
proposed to publish in Dutch, English, French, German and Italian books whose exceptional importance demands
an adequate typographical execution. . . . It is hoped ere long to carry out the work with private materials
entirely, but for the time being either Mr. J. van Krimpen’s new and particularly fine ‘Lutetia’ type
will be used . . . or the old types of which the matrices belong to the world-famous typographical collection
of Messrs. Joh. Enschedé en Zonen of Haarlem. Advantage will be taken, too, of copies of old types such as
modern art has learnt to produce so well. Similarly, it is intended that the Halcyon publications shall ere
long be printed on specially made paper bearing the watermark of the Press. Until this can be done use will
generally be made of the various makes of antique paper handmade after old Dutch methods. Title-designs and
initials shall give to text and page their full measure of beauty.
</q>
Jan van Krimpen (1892-1951) was probably the most distinguished typographer and calligrapher of the twentieth
century in the Netherlands, who was also much in demand internationally, especially in Britain, France, and
America.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">6</ref> He had created and cast the
Lutetia Roman letter, called after the old name for Paris, for the catalogue of L’Art Hollandais à
l’Exposition Internationale des Arts Décoratifs et Industriels Moderns, an exhibition held in Paris in
1925. This new letter, for which he was awarded the Grand Prix by the French organizers of the exhibition,
caused quite a stir among contemporary typographers. An anonymous contributor to <hi rend="i">The Fleuron: A
Journal of Typography</hi> wrote that the Lutetia “created something of a sensation, not only for its
singular beauty and clarity of form, but because the face was in no recognizable way purloined from ancient
times but instead rose freshly from the reasoned canons of type design.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">7</ref> Bruce Rogers described the Lutetia as having “strength with
delicacy, grace with dignity”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">8</ref> A.
van der Boom styled it “a letter of noble pomp and full of distinguished grace”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">9</ref> and Stols himself wrote that the new letter was “the result
of labor and of a study of the good old-national Italian and French letters . . . it has a fresh, original
cachet . . . it can be used for every good work.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">10</ref> The house Enschedé and Sons of Haarlem, for which van Krimpen worked, was founded at the
beginning of the eighteenth century and soon emerged as one of the most famous Dutch printing businesses and
especially typefounders the Netherlands has ever witnessed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n23">5. A. A. M. Stols, “A Short History of The Halcyon Press,” <hi rend="i">The Private
Library</hi> 5 (1972): 69-82.</note>
	<note id="n24">6. On van Krimpen, see John Dreyfus, <hi rend="i">The Work of Jan van Krimpen: An Illustrated
Record</hi> (Haarlem: Joh. Enschedé en Zonen, 1952).</note>
	<note id="n25">7. <hi rend="i">The Fleuron: A Journal of Typography</hi> 6 (1928): 215.</note>
	<note id="n26">8. Quoted by Dreyfus, <hi rend="i">van Krimpen</hi> 23.</note>
	<note id="n27">9. “De Letter ‘Lutetia’, Ontworpen door J. van Krimpen voor de Firma Joh. Enschedé en
Zonen te Haarlem,” <hi rend="i">Elsevier’s Geïllustreerd Maandschrift</hi>, vol. 35 (1925) 152.</note>
	<note id="n28">10. “De Letter ‘Lutetia’ van J. van Krimpen.” <hi rend="i">De Witte Mier</hi> 3
(1926): 84.</note>
	<note id="n29">11. See Jan van Krimpen, <hi rend="i">Het Huis Enschedé: 1703-1953</hi> (Haarlem: Joh.
Enschedé en Zonen, 1953).</note></p>
          <pb id="p37-106" n="106"/>
          <figure n="textmmh.37.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="452">
			<figTranscr>A MEMORABLE FANCY<lb/>
			<lb/>
			I Was in a Printing house in Hell &amp; saw the method<lb/>
			in which knowledge is transmitted from generation<lb/>
			to generation.<lb/>
			In the first chamber was a Dragon-Man, clearing<lb/>
			away the rubbish from a cave’s mouth; within, a number<lb/>
			of Dragons were hollowing the cave.<lb/>
			In the second chamber was a Viper folding round<lb/>
			the rock &amp; the cave, and others adorning it with gold<lb/>
			silver and precious stones.<lb/>
			In the third chamber was an Eagle with wings and<lb/>
			feathers of air: he caused the inside of the cave to be<lb/>
			infinite: around were numbers of Eagle-like men, who<lb/>
			built palaces in the immense cliffs.<lb/>
			In the fourth chamber were Lions of flaming fire,<lb/>
			raging around &amp; melting the metals into living fluids.<lb/>
			In the fifth chamber were Unnam’d forms, which cast<lb/>
			the metals into the expanse.<lb/>
			There they were receiv’d by Men who occupied the<lb/>
			sixth chamber, and took the forms of books &amp; were<lb/>
			arranged in libraries.<lb/>
			<lb/>
			20<lb/>
			<lb/>
			THE Giants who formed this world into<lb/>
			its sensual existence and now seem to live<lb/>
			in it in chains, are in truth the causes of its life<lb/>
			&amp; the sources of all activity; but the chains<lb/>
			are the cunning of weak and tame minds which<lb/>
			have power to resist energy: according to the<lb/>
			proverb, the weak in courage is strong in<lb/>
			cunning.<lb/>
			Thus one portion of being is the Prolific, the<lb/>
			other the Devouring: to the devourer it seems<lb/>
			as if the producer was in his chains; but it is<lb/>
			not so, he only takes portions of existence and<lb/>
			fancies that the whole.<lb/>
			But the Prolific would cease to be Prolific unless<lb/>
			the Devourer as a sea received the excess<lb/>
			of his delights.<lb/>
			Some will say: ‘Is not God alone the Prolific?’<lb/>
			I answer, ‘God only Acts and Is, in existing<lb/>
			beings or Men.’<lb/>
			These two classes of men are always upon<lb/>
			earth, &amp; they should be enemies: whoever tries<lb/>
			to reconcile them seeks to destroy existence.<lb/>
			Religion is an endeavour to reconcile the two.<lb/>
			Note. Jesus Christ did not wish to unite, but<lb/>
			to separate them, as in the Parable of sheep<lb/>
			and goats! &amp; he says: ‘I came not to send Peace<lb/>
			but a Sword.’<lb/>
			<lb/>
			21</figTranscr>
		  </figure>
          <figure n="Halcyon_Marriage.37.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="519">
			<figTranscr>THE MARRIAGE<lb/>
			OF<lb/>
			HEAVEN AND HELL<lb/>
			by<lb/>
			WILLIAM BLAKE<lb/>
			<lb/>
			The Halcyon Press<lb/>
			1928</figTranscr>
            <head>2-3. Text (above) and title page (below) of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell by
William Blake</hi> (Maastricht: Halycon Press, 1928).</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of Koninklijke <corr type="emend">Bibliotheek,</corr> The Hague.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>The Halcyon Press was to publish limited editions only, chiefly aimed at an international market,
for fanciers of exclusive works were exceptional in Holland at the time. In the year of the foundation of this
distinguished, if expensive, bibliophile series Stols published his first English work, <hi rend="i">Odes by
John Keats</hi>, in a dual language edition of 125 copies featuring Keats’s six famous odes. The following
year, 1928, the Halcyon Press brought out <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, by William Blake</hi>
(illus. 2-3) in a run of 325 copies on Pannekoek Antique paper, printed by Joh. Enschedé en Zonen, using van
Krimpen’s Lutetia Roman and Italic with caps in red for the initials. They were bound in limp parchment with
the title on the spine and the printer’s mark on the upper cover in gold, or in quarter buckram. The
editorship was entrusted to P. N. van Eyck (1887-1954), a prominent Dutch poet and journalist, who later
became professor of Dutch literature at the University of Leiden. Although Stols had hinted that he had drawn
van Eyck’s attention to André Gide’s French translation of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>, published first in the 1922 issue of the <hi rend="i">Nouvelle Revue Française</hi> and separately
reprinted in 1923 by Claude Aveline, Stols’s French agent in Paris, it was probably van Eyck himself who had
spurred Stols to publish Blake’s work. In a letter to Stols, dated 12 September 1927, van Eyck, residing in
London as a foreign correspondent, focused on Max Lowman’s facsimile edition of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, published in 1927 by J. M. Dent, and from the many books on Blake
in van Eyck’s library we know that ever since 1925 he had been engrossed in the English poet.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n30">12. See S. A. J. van Faassen, “Een Weldoordacht Uitgaafje,” <hi rend="i">Optima</hi> 6
(1988-89): 310. I am much indebted to this article for information concerning the relationship between Stols,
van Eyck, and van Krimpen.</note></p>
          <p>Apparently the preparatory work for the text and typography of Stols’s <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> entailed some serious difficulties. Stols spoke of “a vehement quarrel”
between van Eyck and van Krimpen because
<pb id="p37-107" n="107"/>
	<q>
The publisher had left the typography entirely in Van Eyck’s hands—considering him deservedly as an
experienced private printer—but had not reckoned with Van Krimpen’s touchiness. It appeared that the
latter did not suffer interference with typographic design in ‘his’ department . . . . It became a
question of ‘give and take.’<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n31">13. “Chronological List of the English Publications of The Halcyon Press, 1927-1934,” 
<hi rend="i">The Private Library</hi> 5 (1972): 76.</note></q></p>
          <p>Whatever the differences of opinion between van Eyck and van Krimpen concerning the typography,
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> was printed as a brilliant example of their superior
craftsmanship and therefore must be seen as a fine tribute to Blake’s genius. Regrettably, I have been
unable to trace any critical English and Dutch response to this splendid publication. But that Stols scored a
success with his Halcyon Press’s publications in English appears from the fact that he continued to bring
out such exclusive English works, including Dante Gabriel Rossetti’s <hi rend="i">Hand and Soul</hi> (1928),
Milton’s <hi rend="i">The Sonnets, Both English and Italian</hi> (1929), Keats’s <hi rend="i">The
Collected Sonnets</hi> (1930), Lord Byron’s <hi rend="i">Lyrical Poems</hi> (1933), etc.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
