<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>37.4.anderson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Subir Dhar, Burning Bright: William Blake and the Poetry of Imagination</title>
        <author n="Anderson">Daniel Gustav Anderson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">37.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Robert W. Rix</name>
              <name>Nancy Moore Goslee</name>
              <name>Daniel Gustav Anderson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_37">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-4-0007">
        <pb id="p37-149" n="149"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Subir Dhar. <hi rend="i">Burning Bright: William Blake and the Poetry of
Imagination.</hi> Kolkata [Calcutta]: G. J. Book Society, 2001. 240 pp., hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Daniel Gustav <name>Anderson</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In his monograph <hi rend="i">Burning Bright</hi>, Subir Dhar touches on virtually every text in
the Blake canon, explicating many at length, and often leaning heavily on the now-classic scholarship of
Northrop Frye, David Erdman, and S. Foster Damon. Dhar argues with vigor that
<q>
reason and imagination were facultative concepts that remained in Blake’s attention throughout his long and
active life as a litterateur, that the engagement (counteraction and confluence) between reason and
imagination resulted in the creation of Blake’s texts, and finally that there are three different and
distinct stages in Blake’s intellectual apprehension and literary reflection of the meanings of reason and
imagination—an initial stage of unbridled enthusiasm for the imagination (seen as a transcendental faculty)
. . . ; a darker, pessimistic interregnum during which the imagination was regarded as fallen; and a final
stage of a realization of both reason and imagination as redemptive potentia. (15)
</q>
He returns to the reason/imagination dichotomy with vehemence, often in every paragraph. Methodologically,
Dhar divides his time between narrating the history of Blake’s intellectual development largely by
explicating his writings, and identifying Blake’s place in intellectual history. While he puts forward a
critical argument, then, he also tries at the same time to provide a kind of introduction to the mechanics of
Blake’s poems and preoccupations.</p>
          <p>Explicating and contextualizing Blake’s corpus in 203 pages plus notes, as Dhar attempts to do,
necessitates foregrounding some material while backgrounding the rest. He emphasizes Blake’s early texts
such as <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon, Tiriel</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, since
(according to Dhar) Morton Paley had not devoted enough attention to them in his 1970 study 
<hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi> (14), a text which, incidentally, argues a point very similar to
Dhar’s. Dhar asserts that in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, “Blake was not so much interested in
mocking individual members of a certain social circle as in satirizing the ratiocinative intellectual
orientation of an entire society and age”; he then identifies by name the specific individuals in a certain
social circle he thinks Blake had targeted allegorically (43). Dhar reads wordplay in this text with much
care, including the instance of Blake’s punning on John Locke’s name: “The word ‘Lock’ with its
range of eighteenth century meanings, including shutting up . . . of fixing in position or regimentation, is
the perfect exponential indicator of the limitations of the intellectual model” Blake most detested,
“Urizen’s ‘Philosophy of the Five Senses’” (50). He points out Blake’s frustration with the limits
of empiricism in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> as well, “to which cause he attributed the increase in political
repression, and the decay in religion and the arts that he saw round him” (74). Dhar also foregrounds texts
seemingly most likely to be anthologized or familiar to an audience of non-specialists, particularly Blake’s
lyrics. He handles some, such as “The Tyger,” at length, with a closer eye for useful detail than might be
expected of such a brief study. Unfortunately, he gives only a limited treatment of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and almost no accounting of scholarship since the
1970’s.</p>
          <p>To contextualize his discussion of imagination in “the tradition of thought that was
available” to Blake, Dhar includes a summary of imagination as a concept in the West beginning with Plato,
“since no comprehensive philosophic or psychological analysis of the concept of imagination seems to have
been attempted before Plato’s time” (17). He assumes semantic continuity across historical time, assuring
his reader that “As modern scholars have shown, the ideas of the Middle Ages were carried forth into the
Renaissance” (25). Unfortunately, the breakneck pace in this chapter prevents him from treating contested
positions—that in “the era of modern philosophy,” beginning with Descartes, “the ghosts of alchemy,
scholasticism, and metaphysical speculation were finally laid to rest” (32), for example—with any more
rigor than the accepted ones: “Bacon and Shakespeare were men who straddled the sixteenth and the
seventeenth centuries” (31). The reader is forced to consider Dhar’s unargued conviction that ideas
arising from an etheric “temper” of a given age condition the shape and movement of material history
(rather than the more typical deterministic assumption of the opposite), instead of Blake’s place in a
narrative of history.</p>
          <p>Dhar is at his most interesting and most relevant when he gives himself a breather from
programmatically reasserting his thesis on reason and imagination. He contributes to the ongoing discussion of
Blake’s use of Indian sources (unfortunately citing twentieth-century translations rather than materials
Blake may have himself read), and of useful comparisons between Blake’s mythic vision and that of classical
Sanskrit literature by comparing the fourfold vision of the later epics to the four states of being elaborated
in terms of yogic consciousness in the <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Mandukya Upanishad</hi></corr> (186, 229n41). Dhar’s attempts
at thinking radically at times lead to moments of real insight:
<q>
Blake . . . was a man whose vision was always societal in the sense of being concerned, not with society
viewed as an organism, but with the fates of the discrete individuals who constitute society in their
congeneric identity. Blake believed that the condition of a state could be changed as the condition of an
individual could be ameliorated—by way of imagination. (189)
</q>
It follows from this that the potential to change one’s mind is a threat to the social structure brought
about (according to 
<pb id="p37-150" n="150"/>
Dhar’s Blake) by empiricism and rationalism. Dhar implies that Blake identifies rationalism as a means of
oppression, but does not develop this idea. He misses some opportunities to elaborate his idea of Blake as a
social critic; he cites Blake’s criticism of those who abandon pity for the poor and hungry not as a
critique of inhuman social conditions and their causes (including Urizenic thinking) as such, but only as a
furthering of his project of proving rationalism to be a limited, self-interested abstraction Blake detested
(95). Following Dhar, a scholar could take the logical step of connecting Blake’s frustration with
eighteenth-century social practice and his contempt for English discourse of abstraction as a Urizenic means
of manipulating relationships of power.</p>
          <p>Finally, Dhar’s explications are remarkably subtle and precise; he is genuinely interested in
showing how aspects of these poems work, particularly diction, and the tense and aspect of verbs, showing how
in “Night” Blake’s “shifts of tense merge into one another so that the total effect of the lyric is
that of a vibrating present” (91). That he does not take the opportunity to discuss subordinate and
ancillary aspects of his argument and its implications in closer detail or in a more rigorous sociomaterial
context is disappointing.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
