<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>37.4.rix</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake, Bacon and “The Devils Arse”</title>
        <author n="Rix">Robert W. Rix</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">37.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Robert W. Rix</name>
              <name>Nancy Moore Goslee</name>
              <name>Daniel Gustav Anderson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_37">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-4-0006">
        <pb id="p37-137" n="137"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake, Bacon and “The Devils Arse”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert W. <name>Rix</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Blake owned a copy of Francis Bacon’s <hi rend="i">Essays Moral, Economical, and Political</hi>
(London: J. Edwards and T. Payne, 1798), which he annotated extensively. The book was first described by
Alexander Gilchrist, who writes that “the artist’s copy of the <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> . . . is roughly
annotated in pencil, in a very characteristic, if very unreasonable, fashion.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">1</ref> The annotations were made in various pencils. The thickness of
the line and the pressure applied to the paper vary considerably, which may indicate that the comments were
not all made at one time. This copy, which is bound in green cloth with a few of the first pages loose, is now
held at Cambridge University Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n3">1. Gilchrist 1:315.</note>
	<note id="n4">2. The book has shelfmark: Keynes U.4.20.</note></p>
          <p>On the title page Blake writes: “Good Advice for Satan’s Kingdom” (E 620) (illus.
1).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">3</ref> G. E. Bentley, Jr., notes that the
frequent comparison of Bacon’s advice to that of Christ suggests a date for the annotations not long after
this edition was published (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 682). This was not the first time Blake attacked Bacon in a
series of annotations. We know that Blake also owned and annotated a copy of Bacon’s <hi rend="i">The Tvvo
Bookes of Francis Bacon</hi> (London, 1605), for he writes in his annotations to <hi rend="i">The Works of Sir
Joshua Reynolds</hi> (1798): “when very Young . . . I read . . . Bacon’s Advance of Learning on Every one
of these Books I wrote my Opinions” (E 660), and, in a letter of 23 August 1799, he quotes Bacon’s
“Advancem<hi rend="s">t</hi> of Learning, Part 2, P 47 of the first Edition” (E 702-03). Blake’s copy of
this book has never been traced. <note id="n5">3. Unless otherwise indicated, all citations from Blake are
from <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry and Prose</hi>, ed. Erdman, and will be marked as E in the text.</note></p>
          <p>In 1833 Samuel Palmer acquired Blake’s annotated copy of Bacon’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> and
inscribed this year and his name on the first endpaper. (Several of Blake’s books came into Palmer’s
possession after Catherine Blake’s death.) Blake’s editor, Sir Geoffrey Keynes, who later acquired the
book, surmised that it was passed on to Samuel Palmer’s son, A. H. Palmer, who probably kept it until his
death.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">4</ref> Keynes was told by A. G. B.
Russell that it was then held by “Mr. Lionel Isaacs of the Haymarket about 1900.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">5</ref> In his autobiography, <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory</hi>,
Keynes describes how in 1947 he approached the Boston bookseller George T. Goodspeed and asked if he had sold
any books relating to Blake. Goodspeed could recall that eighteen years previously, in 1929, he had sold a
book containing some annotations of Blake’s to the pharmaceutical millionaire of Indianapolis, Joshua K.
Lilly, Jr., the founder of the Lilly Library<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">6</ref>
		  <figure n="Bacon.Essays.37.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="297" height="500">
			<figTranscr>ESSAYS<lb/>
			MORAL, ECONOMICAL,<lb/>
			AND<lb/>
			POLITICAL.<lb/>
			Good Advice for Satans Kingdom<lb/>
			BY FRANCIS BACON,<lb/>
			BARON OF VERULAM,<lb/>
			AND<lb/>
			VISCOUNT ST. ALBANS.<lb/>
			LONDON:<lb/>
			Printed by T. Bensley,<lb/>
			FOR J. EDWARDS, PALL MALL, AND T. PAYNE,<lb/>
			MEWS GATE.<lb/>
			1798.</figTranscr>
			<head>1. Francis Bacon, <hi rend="i">Essays Moral, Economical, and Political</hi> (1798).</head>
			<figDesc>Title page of copy owned by Blake, with his annotation. Reproduced by permission of the Syndics of
Cambridge University Library.</figDesc>
		  </figure>
Lilly wrote a letter dated 30 October 1947 (now enclosed with the volume) which shows Keynes had requested
that the annotations be photographed for the purpose of editing and publication. In the letter Lilly rejects
this request on the grounds that the photographing of Blake’s many scattered annotations would be too
costly. Furthermore, he adds that some of Blake’s annotations in pencil are “very difficult to read except
with a magnifying glass, and I am just sure that several of the entries would thus not reproduce well at
all.” The letter, however, also contains Lilly’s agreement to sell the annotated <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>
at the generous price of $1000, which was $500 less than he had originally paid, because, as he writes, he 
<pb id="p37-138" n="138"/>
is “not particularly a Blake collector.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">7</ref> Another letter of 3 August 1948 (also enclosed with the volume) shows that Keynes
subsequently acquired the volume through the agent John Lacy McLean. After Keynes’ death in 1982, his huge
collection of books, including his Blakeana, went to Cambridge University Library and the Fitzwilliam Museum.
<note id="n6">4. Keynes (1957) 152. Also reprinted in Keynes (1971) 90-97.</note>
	<note id="n7">5. Keynes (1921) 51.</note>
	<note id="n8">6. Keynes (1981) 301-02.</note>
	<note id="n9">7. In this letter, Lilly gives the year of his acquisition of the volume as 1939.</note></p>
          <p>On page 55, among the written marginalia, Blake drew a sketch—or rather a diagram for a sketch.
This sketch has never been reproduced and has so far been available to the Blake reader only through the
eyewitness accounts of Blake’s editors, who have rendered the contents of the illustration in
words.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">8</ref> In his edition of 
<hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Writings</hi>, Keynes describes it in the following way: “<hi rend="i">A
representation of hinder parts, labelled</hi>: The devil’s arse, <hi rend="i">and depending from it a chain
of excrement ending in</hi>: A King.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">9</ref> In <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, David Erdman writes:
“[A drawing of] The devils arse [with chain of excrement ending in] A King” (E 624). The drawing in
question relates to the section of Bacon that follows on pages 56-60, which is entitled “Of a King.” Bacon
opens his discussion on kingship with the statement “A king is a mortal god on earth, unto whom the living
God hath lent his own name as a great honour” (56). Though he goes on to qualify this statement considerably
in the following paragraph, this must have seemed like an affirmation of the Divine Right of Kings to Blake,
who responded with the charge: “O Contemptible &amp; Abject Slave” (E 626). <note id="n10">8.
Unfortunately, no holograph facsimile is available of these annotations as there is of Blake’s marginalia to
Bishop Richard Watson; see <hi rend="i">Annotations</hi>, ed. James.</note>
	<note id="n11">9. <hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>, ed. Keynes (1979) 400.</note></p>
          <p>When I recently consulted Blake’s original copy in Cambridge University Library, I was
surprised to learn that the sketch on page 55 no longer fits the description Blake’s editors have given of
it. The upper part of the page has been erased, leaving only a part of the lumps of excrement and the
inscription “A King.” Unfortunately, page 55 was annotated in a soft pencil, which has left no significant
impression in the paper. With the help of the staff in the Rare Books Reading Room, I have thoroughly examined
the page: even with the help of UV light, the erased impression cannot be lifted.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">10</ref> In the top margin of the page, only a faint “T” and some
of a “D” can with the utmost difficulty be made out when the page is viewed in the right light and at the
right angle: this does not show on a microfilm copy (illus. 2). What is striking is that Erdman, whose mark of
distinction is an otherwise rigorous particularity in recording practically every deletion or insertion in
Blake’s annotations or manuscripts, apparently finds no reason to make any note of the fact that a
considerable part of the drawing is not visible. Only G. E. Bentley, Jr., in his 1978 edition of 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> rates this important enough to mention it upfront, informing us that
page 55 is “[<hi rend="i">An erased sketch of buttocks (?), with an erased identification:</hi>] The Devils
arse[(?). <hi rend="i">From these depend a chain, at the bottom of which is:</hi>] A King.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">11</ref> In Keynes’ edition of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>, a note on the vandalized state of the drawing is found in the appendix of
editorial comments. Keynes attaches relatively little importance to the erasure, for as he confidently notes,
“the upper part of the diagram has been rubbed out, but the impress of the pencillings is clearly
visible.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">12</ref> This is similar to the
description he gave it when first publicizing his acquisition of the volume in the <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> on 8
March 1957. Keynes here singles out the sketch for particular attention, making Palmer responsible for
“partially, though ineffectually, erasing the drawing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">13</ref> Apparently, at the time Keynes bought the book, the upper part of the
drawing stood out with unequivocal clearness; examining it today yields no such positive result. 
<note id="n12">10. I owe thanks to library officer (Dept. of Rare Books) Annemarie Robinson for her help and
assistance with examining the volume.</note>
	<note id="n13">11. <hi rend="i">Writings</hi>, ed. Bentley (1978) 1:1430.</note>
	<note id="n14">12. <hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>, ed. Keynes (1979) 905.</note>
	<note id="n15">13. Keynes (1957) 152.</note></p>
          <p>After correspondence with Professor Bentley, I learned that when Keynes put Bacon’s 
<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> on deposit for him in 1964, the image was so faint that he could make nothing of it. Yet,
in all revisions of <hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Writings</hi> (1957, 1969, 1970, 1972, 1974, 1979), i.e.
<hi rend="i">after</hi> Bentley examined the drawing and found the upper part had vanished beyond legibility,
Keynes makes no comment on any changes in the imprint on this page. How the upper part of the drawing could
have faded from Keynes’ confident “clearly visible” of 1957 to a state of invisibility when Bentley
examined it in 1964 still demands explanation. The condition of the book today does not appear to vary from
the description given of it by Keynes in 1957. That the page should have been exposed to sunlight or other
such external factors that might have caused its deterioration seems unlikely, as the bottom part of the
drawing stands out as clearly as many other annotations in the volume. Furthermore, it is an axiom in
holograph forensics that whereas some inks may fade, this is not normally the case with pencil.</p>
          <p>Fortunately, we are not completely without a visual record of what the original and complete
drawing looked like. Quite unexpectedly, another copy of Bacon’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> turned up during
my research in the library. This was an identical edition, which Keynes had purchased and into which he, with
rigorous precision, copied out Blake’s annotations page for page in the exact place they appeared in the
original.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">14</ref> This hitherto unrecorded
copy, transcribed in what now appears as a reddish-brown ink, was probably made in 1949, the year Keynes
writes on the front paste-down endpaper. This indicates that this transcript copy was written up shortly after
Keynes acquired the book, perhaps for his own easy reference or in preparation for editing the annotations. On
page 55 the drawing is shown as it appeared before the obliteration. A comparison
<pb id="p37Bac139" n="139"/>
<figure n="Bacon.p55.37.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="287" height="500">
	<figTranscr>55<lb/>
	in season, and are ever on the loading part;<lb/>
	not so good as the dogs that licked Lazarus’<lb/>
	sores, but like flies that are still buzzing upon<lb/>
	any thing that is raw; misanthropi, that make<lb/>
	it their practice to bring men to the bough,<lb/>
	and yet have never a tree for the purpose in<lb/>
	their gardens, as Timon had: such dispositions<lb/>
	are the very errors of human nature, and yet<lb/>
	they are the fittest timber to make great politics<lb/>
	of; like to knee timber that is good for<lb/>
	ships that are ordained to be tossed, but not<lb/>
	for building houses that shall stand firm. The<lb/>
	parts and signs of goodness are many. If a<lb/>
	man be gracious and courteous to strangers,<lb/>
	it shews he is a citizen of the world, and that<lb/>
	his heart is no island cut off from other lands,<lb/>
	but a continent that joins to them: if he be<lb/>
	compassionate towards the afflictions of others,<lb/>
	it shews that his heart is like the noble tree<lb/>
	that is wounded itself when it gives the balm:<lb/>
	if he easily pardons and remits offences, it<lb/>
	shews that his mind is planted above injuries,<lb/>
	so that he cannot be shot: if he be thankful<lb/>
	for small benefits, it shews that he weighs<lb/>
	men’s minds, and not their trash: but, above<lb/>
	all, if he have St. Paul’s perfection, that he<lb/>
	<lb/>
	A King</figTranscr>
</figure>
<figure n="Bacon.p55.Keynes.37.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="276" height="500">
	<figTranscr>The devils arse<lb/>
	<lb/>
	55<lb/>
	in season, and are ever on the loading part;<lb/>
	not so good as the dogs that licked Lazarus’<lb/>
	sores, but like flies that are still buzzing upon<lb/>
	any thing that is raw; misanthropi, that make<lb/>
	it their practice to bring men to the bough,<lb/>
	and yet have never a tree for the purpose in<lb/>
	their gardens, as Timon had: such dispositions<lb/>
	are the very errors of human nature, and yet<lb/>
	they are the fittest timber to make great politics<lb/>
	of; like to knee timber that is good for<lb/>
	ships that are ordained to be tossed, but not<lb/>
	for building houses that shall stand firm. The<lb/>
	parts and signs of goodness are many. If a<lb/>
	man be gracious and courteous to strangers,<lb/>
	it shews he is a citizen of the world, and that<lb/>
	his heart is no island cut off from other lands,<lb/>
	but a continent that joins to them: if he be<lb/>
	compassionate towards the afflictions of others,<lb/>
	it shews that his heart is like the noble tree<lb/>
	that is wounded itself when it gives the balm:<lb/>
	if he easily pardons and remits offences, it<lb/>
	shews that his mind is planted above injuries,<lb/>
	so that he cannot be shot: if he be thankful<lb/>
	for small benefits, it shews that he weighs<lb/>
	men’s minds, and not their trash: but, above<lb/>
	all, if he have St. Paul’s perfection, that he<lb/>
	<lb/>
	A King</figTranscr>
	<head>2-3. Francis Bacon, <hi rend="i">Essays Moral, Economical, and Political</hi> (1798), page 55.</head>
	<figDesc>Comparison of Blake’s original (above) and Keynes’ transcript copy (below). Reproduced by
permission of the Syndics of Cambridge University Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p37-140" n="140"/>
of Keynes’ transcript copy and Blake’s original shows that what has been erased is an outline of a pair of
buttocks with the inscription “the devils arse” and the top part of the excremental chain (illus. 3).
<note id="n16">14. Keynes’ copy has shelfmark: Keynes E.2.2.24.</note></p>
          <p>Despite the mystery of the erasure, there is no reason to believe that Keynes “invented” this
reading. Though he at times made mistakes in deciphering Blake’s hand (as later editors have pointed out),
there are no records of Keynes ever making things up, and his integrity as a scholar speaks against any such
suggestion.</p>
          <p>Keynes’ conjecture that the erasure was the work of Samuel Palmer is plausible.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">15</ref> It may be significant that it is only the
part that refers to the satanic that he sought to remove. A similar attempt can be found in Blake’s
annotations to Bishop Watson’s <hi rend="i">An Apology for the Bible</hi> (1797). This book was also
acquired by Palmer, who inscribed his name on the title page. On the verso of the title page, Blake prefaced
the annotations with the statement: “The Beast &amp; the Whore rule without control” (E 611). Erdman
comments that the sentence is cancelled by “a ruled double line, in pencil” and judges this to be
“uncharacteristic of Blake” (E 884-85).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n17">15. There are other examples of erasures in Blake’s work. For example, in the ms. to 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, several erotic portions are partly obliterated. Whether this was by done by Blake
himself or by others later is unclear. For a detailed discussion of these drawings, see Grant 192-94 and
Lincoln 58.</note>
	<note id="n18">16. Erdman’s findings have been corroborated by G. Ingli James on grounds that the strokes
of the deletion “lack Blake’s characteristic strength and decisiveness: they are faint, undulating and
broken”; see “Notes to Transcript,” in <hi rend="i">Annotations</hi>, ed. James, n2.</note></p>
          <p>It is possible that Palmer misconstrued the statement as literal and affirmative, where we may
assume Blake wrote allegorically and critically. Varying with the time, place and persuasion of the
interpreter, the figures of the “Beast” and the “Whore” from the Book of Revelation have been called
in to identify the Jews, the Ottomans, France, Charles I, Cromwell, the aristocracy, capitalism, the American
slaveholders or whatever forces in society the interpreter wanted to oppose. There is a long tradition in
Protestant propaganda of allegorizing the Pope and Catholicism by these New Testament figures for the
Antichrist, but in Blake they clearly signify a more immediate and contemporary religious and political state
of affairs. Offering a translation of the allegory in very general terms, Jacob Bronowski explains that “The
Beast is the State, and the Whore is its Church.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">17</ref> Though he does not rely on any contextualizing evidence, Bronowski’s interpretation may
however still be historically correct, In a footnote to “Religious Musings,” Coleridge, for instance, can
be found commenting: “I am convinced that the Babylon of the Apocalypse does not apply to Rome exclusively;
but to the union of Religion with Power and Wealth, wherever it is found.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">18</ref> However, it is possible that Blake’s reference may more
specifically refer to Prime Minister Pitt and Queen Charlotte. In <hi rend="i">Prophet Against Empire</hi>,
Erdman draws attention to the fact that the Queen’s influence increased as a consequence of George III’s
madness in 1788. She was believed to rule the Empire through Pitt. The Prime Minister’s peace in 1790 had
popularly been attributed to the Queen’s influence. On this theme Gillray drew a caricature allegorizing
Milton’s Sin and Death as the Queen and Pitt.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">19</ref> Whatever reference Blake may have meant to give this allegory, it seems unavoidably
political; the phrase serves as a prefatory maxim summing up Blake’s defense of Thomas Paine’s 
<hi rend="i">Age of Reason.</hi> If the deletion was made by Palmer out of his inability to decode Blake’s
political allegory (misreading it as a religious heresy that he saw fit to remove), it is likely that the same
could have been the case with “The Devils Arse.” <note id="n19">17. Bronowski 82.</note>
	<note id="n20">18. <hi rend="i">Complete Poetical Works</hi>, ed. E. H. Coleridge 1:121n1.</note>
	<note id="n21">19. Erdman (1977) 221. The cartoon is <hi rend="i">Sin, Death, and the Devil</hi> (1792); see
George no. 8105.</note></p>
          <p>When Gilchrist compared Blake’s annotations to Bacon with those to Reynolds, he finds them
lacking the “leaven of real sense and acumen which tempers the violence of those on Reynolds” and only
quotes out of the “interests of faithful biography.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">20</ref> The annotations are admittedly written in the mode of literary satire rather than as a
considered philosophical argument. <note id="n22">20. Gilchrist 1:315.</note></p>
          <p>Many of Blake’s annotations are really clearly spontaneous. He employs shock tactics and satire
as an immediate response rather than attempting to establish a coherent counter-argument. The form of hostile
dialogue we find in the annotations to Bacon and other of Blake’s “Spiritual Enemies” whose books Blake
owned can also be seen in published satire. In <hi rend="i">Pig’s Meat</hi>, Thomas Spence prints Sir John
Sinclair’s <hi rend="i">An Antidote Against Revolutions</hi>, a piece of loyalist propaganda showing the
anarchy that will erupt if monarchy is overturned. Spence prints this with “remarks by a Spenconian on the
same,” providing the reader with a series of interjectory comments, so it is now turned into a dialogue. The
hostile annotation is supplied with a citation from St. Mark: “Out of thy own mouth will I judge thee thou
wicked servant.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n23">21. <hi rend="i">Pig’s Meat</hi> 3 (1796): 186-92.</note></p>
          <p>In Blake’s annotations to Bacon, he makes numerous references to his opponent as someone
speaking for the “Devil” or “Satan.” In positing Bacon as someone who provides “Good Advice for the
Devil” (E 625), it has gone unnoticed how Blake shares a vocabulary with the biblical critic and man of
letters, Alexander Geddes, whose satire <hi rend="i">L’Avocat du diable: the Devil’s Advocate; or, Satan
versus Pictor</hi> was published in 1792. This work is a political satire on the privileges enjoyed by the
aristocracy in legal matters; it is written in the voice of a lawyer, who represents the Devil in a court of
law. For all the abuse he has been made to suffer he is seen as a “libelled Peer.” In the annotations,
Blake uses a similar satirical strategy, casting
<pb id="p37-141" n="141"/>
<figure n="BillyBugaboo.37.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="358" height="500">
	<figTranscr>London Pub by R Newton at his Original Print Shop<lb/>
	Bridges St Covent Garden August 13 1797<lb/>
	<lb/>
	What a stinking<lb/>
	breath he has got<lb/>
	Sherry.<lb/>
	<lb/>
	THE TREASURY<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Rd NEWTON desin et fecit 1797<lb/>
	Sheridan Fox Pitt Dundas<lb/>
	1797<lb/>
	<lb/>
	THE BIRTH OF BILLY BUGABOO!<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Newton.</figTranscr>
	<head>4. Richard Newton, <hi rend="i">The Birth of Billy Bugaboo</hi> (1797).</head>
	<figDesc>© Copyright British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
Bacon in the role of the Devil’s advocate, understanding “the kingdom of Satan” in political terms. For
instance, on page 14 Blake writes: “The Prince of darkness is a Gentleman &amp; not a man he is a Lord
Chancellor” (E 622). Blake seems also to address the political implications of Bacon’s thinking when, in
his annotations to <hi rend="i">The Works of Sir Joshua Reynolds</hi>, he writes that “Bacons Philosophy has
Ruind England” (E 645). Understanding the sketch within its context of political satire is important as it
relates to a topos of revolutionary satire in the 1790s. It is to this context I shall now turn.</p>
          <p>Blake’s satirical drawing is clearly motivated by Bacon’s claim that a king is divinely
ordained. The king has therefore traditionally been given the title “heaven-born.” According to the OED,
this term had in analogy also been used to describe governors of the state, who were seen as endowed with
divine skill and abilities of governance. But, as the OED also records, from the time of the French Revolution
the epithet is generally used ironically. The irony is clear in the satirist Charles Pigott’s 
<hi rend="i">Political Dictionary.</hi> In the entry on “heaven-born” we are laconically informed that it
means “the most infamous of mankind” (55). It is similarly wholly ironic when Pigott refers to “Mr.
Pitt, and his heaven-born family, Mr Rose, Henry Dundas, and others” (104). The term is also played upon in
the cartoonist Richard Newton’s political drawing <hi rend="i">The General Sentiment</hi> (1797).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">22</ref> Here Pitt is depicted in the gallows, hanging
by the neck, beneath which two characters of obvious plebeian origin make the ironic wish: “May our heaven
born minister be SUPPORTED from ABOVE.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n24">22. George no. 8999.</note>
	<note id="n25">23. Though Pitt was the favorite victim of this irony, at times Edmund Burke was satirized in
similar terms. In a piece that appeared in <hi rend="i">The Courier</hi>, 28 November 1794, Burke is
represented as a “puppet-master,” who controls a parliament reduced to “AUTOMATA, OR MOVING PUPPETS,”
a function which gives him the title of “HEAVEN-BORN CONIURER.” For the origin of the term, see Barrell
11.</note></p>
          <p>The disruption of the semantic content of the phrase could also manifest itself as a satirical
inversion. In a placard dated “Norwich, 16 October 1795, a call to form popular Societies and demand redress
of grievances,” Pitt is also satirized. The text here concludes, “You may as well look for chastity and
mercy in the Empress of Russia, honour and consistency from the King of Prussia, wisdom and plain dealing from
the Emperor of Germany, as a single speck of virtue from our <hi rend="b">Hellborn Minister.</hi>”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">24</ref> This inflammatory piece of satire, inverting
“heaven-born” to its infernal opposite, was widely circulated and attained great popularity. It inspired
Richard Newton to a couple of satirical prints, in which he renders the inversion of the phrase in pictorial
puns. In <hi rend="i">The Devils Darling</hi> (1797), the Devil is dandling Prime Minster Pitt (one of
Newton’s favorite victims) on his knee. Underneath the design is written, “Never a man beloved worse / For
sure the Devil was his nurse.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">25</ref> In
<hi rend="i">The Birth of Billy Bugaboo</hi> (1797), Pitt’s policies of taxation are criticized. The Devil
is shown standing on the edge of a cliff “giving birth” to Pitt by excreting him out of his backside into
the arms of Henry Dundas, who pokes his head out of a building inscribed “The Treasury.” Beneath the cliff
are also Fox and Sheridan holding their noses to the smell. Fox remarks to Sheridan, “What a stinking breath
he has got Sherry” (see illus. 4).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">26</ref>
Some years ago Marcus Wood brought this cartoon to our attention in a “Minute Particular,” suggesting that
it supplied the major compositional elements for Blake’s engraving <hi rend="i">The Dog</hi>, which was
engraved for William Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">27</ref> According to Wood, Blake apparently liked the visual composition enough to
borrow the material of a satirical sketch and use it in a non-satirical context. If Blake annotated his copy
of Bacon’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> shortly after the volume was published in 1797, Newton’s cartoon of
the same year would still have been fresh in his mind. <note id="n26">24. Cited in Rose 284.</note>
	<note id="n27">25. George no. 9011. This print is reproduced in Alexander 49.</note>
	<note id="n28">26. George no. 9029.</note>
	<note id="n29">27. See Wood. The image is featured on the front cover of that issue of <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly.</hi></note></p>
          <p>There is a long tradition of scatological reference in caricature. Heaping abuse and libel on
authorities by such 
<pb id="p37-142" n="142"/>
<figure n="Ursprungen.37.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="371">
	<figTranscr>Jo[annes] vid[e].<lb/>
	Vos ex patre diabolo<lb/>
	estis: et desideria patris<lb/>
	vestri perficietis.<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Non vocabitur in eternu[m]<lb/>
	seme[n] pessimoru[m]. Esa[ias] vid[e].</figTranscr>
	<head>5. <hi rend="i">Von der München Ursprungen</hi> (1523).</head>
</figure>
                        uncouth imagery dates back to the Reformation polemic and the Lutheran supporters’
use of the so-called <hi rend="i">Schandbilder.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">28</ref> The association of defecation and demons is, for example, used to great effect in a
flyleaf showing <hi rend="i">The Origins of Monks</hi> (<hi rend="i">Von der München Ursprungen</hi>, 1523),
where we see the Devil relieving himself by excreting a pile of monks (illus. 5). In the 1790s scatological
reference became a stock weapon in the rhetoric of the Revolution. In his discussion of James Gillray’s and
Jacques-Louis David’s anti-aristocratic illustrations, the art historian Albert Boime shows how the
excremental was habitually associated with the <hi rend="i">ancien régime.</hi> This was a way of breaking
“a privileged code of <hi rend="i">politesse</hi> and decorum,” establishing a “discourse for the crowd
. . . encoding a new environment with an inclusive, nonprivileged space.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">29</ref> An example of this in French caricature is the anonymous
print <hi rend="i">The Two Infuriated Devils</hi> (<hi rend="i">Les deux Diables en fureur</hi>, 1790), which
shows the two notorious clergymen Abbé Maury and Jean-Jacques d’Eprémesnil excreted from the bottoms of
two red-winged devils. The lines underneath the illustration translate: “On 13 April 1790 two flying devils
/ Made a bet/ Who would shit most foul / On human nature / One shat the Abbé M. . .y / The other paled / And
dropped D’E. . .y/And his entire clique” (illus. 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">30</ref> Newton would have been familiar with such revolutionary propaganda through his employer,
the radical print publisher William Holland, who made French prints available to the English public, a trade
that also went the other way.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n30">28. See Scribner, esp. 84-87; also Hyman.</note>
	<note id="n31">29. Boime 75.</note>
	<note id="n32">30. The ministers Maury and d’Epremesnil were two of the most outspoken critics of the
National Assembly’s hostility against maintaining Catholicism as a state religion, as this would put an end
to the privileges formerly enjoyed by the clergy. The design is reprinted in <hi rend="i">French
Caricature</hi> (1988).</note>
	<note id="n33">31. In the early 1790s, Holland advertised on his prints that “In Holland’s Caricature
Exhibition Rooms may be seen the largest Collection in Europe of Political and other Humorous prints with
those published in Paris on the French Revolution.” For Holland’s business and his affiliation with
Newton, Gillray, Cruikshank and others, see Alexander 26.</note></p>
          <p>It is worth noting that the connection between political libel and the demonic was current in the
1790s. We find, for instance, the people’s prophet Richard Brothers addressing
<pb id="p37-143" n="143"/>
<figure n="diables.37.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="336" height="500">
	<figTranscr>Les deux Diables en fureur.<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Le 13 Avril 1790 deux Diables Volant.<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Le 13 Avril 1790 deux Diables en Volant<lb/>
	Firent une Gageure<lb/>
	A qui Chierait le plus puant<lb/>
	Sur l’humaine nature<lb/>
	l’Un nous Chia l’Abbé M....y<lb/>
	l’autre en devint tout pale<lb/>
	Et nous Lacha d’Ep....y<lb/>
	Et toute sa Cabale.</figTranscr>
	<head>6. Anon., <hi rend="i">Les deux Diables en fureur</hi> (1790).</head>
	<figDesc>Cliché Bibliothèque nationale de France, Paris.</figDesc>
</figure>
his reader as an oppressed subject of George III: “thou didst . . . submit thyself to the laws that were
imposed on thee by a monster spewed out of HELL.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">32</ref> In the political debates of the 1790s, the exposition of the origin of tyranny and
oppressive institutions was a key line of attack used by the opposition, perhaps most notably in the writings
of Thomas Paine. This was also worked into satire, as for instance in Eaton’s <hi rend="i">Politics for the
People</hi> and its investigation into “The Origins of Nobility.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n35" type="note">33</ref> The same publication later featured “The Genealogy of a modern
Aristocrate,” which is a list of how one evil has begot another, starting at the time when “The Devil
begat Sin” and ending with how “Time-Serving Sycophants begat Modern Aristocracy on the Body of the Whore
of Babylon.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">34</ref>
	<note id="n34">32. “Letter received from Richard Brothers,” printed in Wright 29. On Brothers’
prophetic politics, see Garrett 177-220.</note>
	<note id="n35">33. <hi rend="i">Politics for the People</hi> 3 (1793): 26-31.</note>
	<note id="n36">34. <hi rend="i">Politics for the People 7</hi> (1794): 6.</note></p>
          <p>The image of “hell-born” would have come naturally to Blake, as Bacon, on page 56, after his
statement that “God hath lent his own name as a great honour” to kings on earth, qualifies this by stating
that a king should not be so “proud” as to think himself immortal as a god and “flatter himself that God
hath with his name imparted unto him his nature also.” This apparently spurred Blake on to show that a
king’s office is not imparted from Heaven but from Hell: the king being <hi rend="i">born</hi> out of the
“Devils Arse.” It is Blake’s visual rendering of this satirical attack that has now sadly been partially
lost.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Alexander, David. <hi rend="i">Richard Newton and English Caricature in the 1790s.</hi>
Manchester: Whitworth Art Gallery, University of Manchester in association with Manchester UP, 1998.</p>
            <p>Bacon, Francis. <hi rend="i">Essays Moral, Economical, and Political.</hi> London: J. Edwards
and T. Payne, 1798.</p>
            <p>Barrell, John, ed. <hi rend="i">“Exhibition Extraordinary!!”: Radical Broadsides of the Mid
1790s.</hi> Nottingham: Trent Editions, 2001.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> 2 vols. Oxford:
Clarendon P, 1978.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Annotations to Richard Watson—An Apology for the Bible in a
Series of Letters Addressed to Thomas Paine.</hi> 8<hi rend="s">th</hi> ed., 1797. Ed. G. Ingli James.
Cardiff: University College Cardiff P, 1984.</p>
            <p>Boime, Albert. “Jacques-Louis David, Scatological Discourse in the French Revolution, and the
Art of Caricature.” <hi rend="i">French Caricature and the French Revolution, 1789-1799.</hi> Los Angeles:
Grunwald Center for the Graphic Arts, Wight Art Gallery, University of California, Los Angeles; Chicago:
Distributed by the U of Chicago P, 1988. 67-82.</p>
            <p>Bronowski, Jacob. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Age of Revolution.</hi> New York: Harper
Colophon, 1969.</p>
            <p>Coleridge, Ernest Hartley, ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetical Works of Samuel Taylor
Coleridge.</hi> 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1912.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Prophet Against Empire: A Poet’s Interpretation of the History
of His Own Times.</hi> Rev ed. Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1977.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Rev.
ed. New York: Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">French Caricature and the French Revolution, 1789-1799.</hi> Los Angeles: Grunwald
Center for the Graphic Arts, Wight Art Gallery, University of California, Los Angeles; Chicago: Distributed by
the U of Chicago P, 1988.</p>
            <p>Garrett, Clarke. <hi rend="i">Respectable Folly: Millenarians &amp; the French Revolution in
France &amp; England.</hi> Baltimore and London: Johns Hopkins UP, 1975.</p>
            <p>George, Mary Dorothy, ed. <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Political and Personal Satires Preserved in
the Department of Prints and Drawings in the British Museum (1771-1832).</hi> 7 vols. London: British Museum,
1935-54.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> Rev. ed. 2 vols. London:
Macmillan, 1880.</p>
            <p>Grant, John E. “Visions in Vala: A Consideration of Some Pictures in the Manuscript.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory.</hi> Ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. Madison:
University of Wisconsin P, 1973. 141-202.</p>
            <p>Hyman, Timothy. “A Carnival Sense of the World.” <hi rend="i">Carnivalesque.</hi> Ed. T.
Hyman and R. Malbert. London: Hayward Gallery Publishing, 2000. 8-73.</p>
            <pb id="p37-144" n="144"/>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William Blake.</hi> New York: Grolier Club,
1921.</p>
            <p>Keynes. “William Blake and Sir Francis Bacon.” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> 2871 (8 March 1957):
152.</p>
            <p>Keynes. <hi rend="i">Blake Studies: Essays on His Life and Work.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P,
1971.</p>
            <p>Keynes, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Writings with Variant Readings.</hi> Rev. ed.
Oxford: Oxford UP, 1979.</p>
            <p>Keynes. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1981.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew. <hi rend="i">Spiritual History: A Reading of William Blake’s</hi> Vala 
<hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1995.</p>
            <p>Pigott, Charles. <hi rend="i">A Political Dictionary Explaining the True Meaning of Words.</hi>
London: Daniel Isaac Eaton, 1795.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Pig’s Meat; or Lesson for the Swinish Multitude.</hi> London: T. Spence,
1793-96.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Politics for the People; or, a Salmagundy for Swine.</hi> London: D. Eaton,
1793-95.</p>
            <p>Rose, J. Holland. <hi rend="i">William Pitt and the Great War.</hi> London: G. Bell and Sons,
1911.</p>
            <p>Scribner, R. W. <hi rend="i">For the Sake of Simple Folk: Popular Propaganda for the German
Reformation.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1994.</p>
            <p>Wood, Marcus. “A Caricature Source for One of Blake’s Illustrations to Hayley’s 
<hi rend="i">Ballads.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 24.1 (summer 1990): 247-48
[31-32].</p>
            <p>Wright, John. <hi rend="i">A Revealed Knowledge of Some Things That Will Speedily be Fulfilled
in the World.</hi> London: n.p., 1794.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
