<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>37.4.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake in the Marketplace, 2003</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">37.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Robert W. Rix</name>
              <name>Nancy Moore Goslee</name>
              <name>Daniel Gustav Anderson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_37">
    <body>
      <pb id="p37-116" n="116"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-37-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake in the Marketplace, 2003</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>For the second year in a row, I begin with the saga of Blake’s 19 water colors illustrating
Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> They were recorded in an 1836 Edinburgh auction catalogue and
not rediscovered until 2001; they have already received considerable attention in this journal.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Based on various reports in the British press,
plus a few private sources. I can now fill in several gaps in the history of the designs.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> The artist John Stannard (1794-1882) acquired
the illustrations at or shortly after the 1836 auction. At his death they passed to his son Henry John
Stannard (1840-1920), then to his son, Henry John Sylvester Stannard (1870-1951), and grandson, and finally to
a Stannard nephew living in Glasgow. In 2000, this last owner sold them to, or placed them on consignment
with, a Glasgow shop, Caledonia Books. In the next year, they were purchased for about £1000 by the book
dealer Paul Williams of Fine Books, Ilkley, Yorkshire. In partnership with, or at least with the assistance
of, another dealer, Jeffrey Bates of Bates &amp; Hindmarch in Leeds, Williams took the water colors to the
auction house of Dominic Winter, located in Swindon, who contacted Martin Butlin and Robin Hamlyn. These two
Blake scholars authenticated the designs. In February 2002, Tate Britain offered £4.2 million for the set.
All parties agreed to the sale, the water colors were placed on deposit at the Tate, and the gallery was given
5 months to raise the necessary funds (£4.9 million when the value-added tax is included). <note id="n1">1.
Martin Butlin, “New Risen from the Grave: Nineteen Unknown Watercolors by William Blake,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 35.3 (winter 2001-02): 68-73; G. E. Bentley, Jr., “William Blake and His Circle: A
Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 2001,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.1 (summer 2002): 13-16;
Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2002,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 116;
Alexander S. Gourlay, “‘Friendship,’ Love, and Sympathy in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
Illustrations,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3 (winter 2003-04): 100-04.</note>
	<note id="n2">2. Much of the information given here, including the provenance of the designs from 1836 to
2001, is taken from Martin Bailey, “From £1,000 to £10 Million in Two Years,” <hi rend="i">The Art
Newspaper</hi> no. 136 (May 2003): 42. This article includes the first reproduction known to me of the water
color apparently illustrating the following passage: “Methinks I see thee with thy head low laid; / Whilst,
surfeited upon the damask cheek, / The high-fed worm, in lazy volumes roll’d, / Riots unscar’d . . .”
(p. 11 in the 1808 ed. with Blake’s illustrations).</note></p>
          <p>Only weeks after the agreement with the Tate had been signed, Caledonia Books learned, apparently
through press reports, about the true value of the designs. A dispute over ownership and sales rights began,
culminating in a court writ issued on behalf of Caledonia Books barring any sale. The matter was settled
between Caledonia and the two Yorkshire dealers in November 2002 and the Tate arranged for a meeting on 18
December to continue with the sales agreement. Only 5 days before the meeting, the Tate was notified that, the
5 months’ fund-raising period having expired, the designs had been sold to another party.</p>
          <p>The story becomes murky at this point, but apparently the joint owners of the designs, now
including at least the Glasgow and Yorkshire dealers, sold them to the London art dealer Libby Howie. She
promptly offered the designs to the American wife and husband who have, over the last 20 years, assembled a
remarkable collection of Blake’s illuminated books. They expressed no interest at the asking price of $20
million. Press reports indicate that Howie sold the drawings to some other collector, probably an American;
but John Windle, the San Francisco book dealer who specializes in Blake, tells me that a rumor in the London
book trade has it that the designs are still with Howie, who plans to keep them for some time as an
investment. The supposed private purchaser may be someone providing Howie with the requisite financial
resources. Let us hope that the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> water colors do not again disappear for another 165
years.</p>
          <p>Blake’s tempera painting of <hi rend="i">The Virgin Hushing the Young Baptist, Who Approaches
the Sleeping Infant Jesus</hi> came to the market late in 2002 (illus. 2). One of just six temperas by Blake
remaining in private hands, it is the only one in acceptable condition and free of obvious over-painting by a
restorer. The work had a number of localized condition problems when acquired in 1975 by the San Francisco
book dealer Warren Howell, but it was expertly repaired before its sale in 1977 to a man who in turn gave it
to his wife, Elaine Klemen of Chicago, as a birthday present. Klemen placed <hi rend="i">The Virgin
Hushing</hi> on joint consignment with John Windle and Artemis Fine Arts of New York in the summer of 2002.
The first public announcement that the painting was for sale appeared in Windle’s mid-December 2002
catalogue. A color reproduction of the painting also appears in the fifth in Windle’s series of catalogues
devoted to Blake and Blakeana, issued as cat. 36 in Sept. 2003. All materials from cat. 36 regularly covered
by my sales reviews are included in the lists below. Although most of the 397 lots are modern works of
scholarship and criticism, Windle’s latest effort is one of the more impressive Blake catalogues published
by a book dealer.</p>
          <p>Late in 2002, Ursus Books of New York contacted Windle, asking questions about Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783). Ursus claimed that a copy in a late nineteenth-century binding was
part of a collection they were evaluating for insurance or estate purposes. Only copy E (see Bentley) is still
recorded as being in private hands; it was sold by the London book dealer Pickering &amp; Chatto to an
American collector in 1991. Ursus told Windle that the copy in question is not copy E. Perhaps untraced copy
M, last recorded in the Buxton Forman sale in 1920, was the volume brought to Ursus. Although copy M was bound
in blue morocco by Roger de Coverly in the twentieth century, the binding might appear to be earlier. Neither
<pb id="p37-117" n="117"/>
Windle nor I have seen the book, and it is possible that Ursus was fooled by the very convincing William
Griggs facsimile of 1890. I have not been able to learn anything further about the volume other than a rumor
that a copy of the book—perhaps the Ursus copy—had been acquired by a collector in Washington, D.C.</p>
          <p>In recent years, Swann Galleries, the New York auction firm, has offered some exceedingly dubious
materials as works by Blake. There could be no question, however, about the authenticity of the drawing
offered by Swann on 23 January 2003. This slight pencil sketch, dated by Butlin to the 1790s, had been
untraced since 1968. It is always satisfying to rediscover any portion of Blake’s oeuvre, however minor.
Further information is given in the caption to illus. 1.</p>
          <p>A previously unrecorded “Visionary Head” appeared on the market in 2003. It shows a menacing
fellow, probably a warrior, wearing a tall hat decorated with a griffin (illus. 3). The first announcement of
this discovery known to me is the catalogue of the 130<hi rend="s">th</hi> annual exhibition of water colors
and drawings issued in March 2003 by the venerable London art dealer Agnew’s. I have not seen the original,
but the attribution to Blake in this catalogue seems convincing.</p>
          <p>By far the finest work by one of Blake’s contemporaries or followers to come to market in 2003
was Samuel Palmer’s <hi rend="i">The Golden Valley</hi> (illus. 5), one of only a handful of Shoreham-period
water colors remaining in private collections. In spite of extensive advertising and elaborate cataloguing,
the drawing fetched only a little above the low estimate at Christie’s London on 11 June.</p>
          <p>Readers will find a great many entries for eBay online auctions (now abbreviated as “EB”) and
for dealers’ names followed by “online cat.” Most of the latter are not individual online catalogues
maintained by a dealer; rather, they are listings under a dealer’s name on search sites for antiquarian
books, such as BookFinder (http://www.bookfinder.com) or Biblion (http://www.biblion.com). I have not repeated
online listings previously recorded in my 2002 sales review.</p>
          <p>The year of all sales and catalogues in the following lists is 2003 unless indicated otherwise.
The auction houses add their purchaser’s surcharge to the hammer price in their price lists. These net
amounts are given here, following the official price lists. The value-added tax levied against the buyer’s
surcharge in Britain is not included. Late 2003 sales will be covered in the 2004 review. I am grateful for
help in compiling this review to Shelley Bennett, G. E. Bentley, Jr., David Bindman, Morris Eaves, Tim
Linnell, Dennis Read, Steven Tabor, Joseph Viscomi, and John Windle. My special thanks go to Alexander Gourlay
for his generosity in keeping me abreast of internet auctions. Once again, Sarah Jones’ editorial expertise
and John Sullivan’s electronic imaging have been invaluable.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <table rows="18" cols="2">
              <row>
                <cell>BBA</cell>
                <cell>Bloomsbury Book Auctions, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Bentley</cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977). Plate
numbers and copy designations for Blake’s illuminated books follow Bentley.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>BH</cell>
                <cell>Bonhams auctions, London unless otherwise specified</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Butlin</cell>
                <cell>Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 2 vols.
(New Haven: Yale UP, 1981)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>cat.</cell>
                <cell>catalogue or sales list issued by a dealer (usually followed by a number or letter
designation)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CE</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s East, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CL</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CNY</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CSK</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, South Kensington</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>EB</cell>
                <cell>eBay online auctions</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Essick</cell>
                <cell>Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi>
(Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>illus.</cell>
                <cell>the item or part thereof is reproduced in the catalogue</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>pl(s).</cell>
                <cell>plate(s)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>SL</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>SNY</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>st(s).</cell>
                <cell>state(s) of an engraving, etching, or lithograph</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Swann</cell>
                <cell>Swann Galleries, auctioneers, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>#</cell>
                <cell>auction lot or catalogue item number</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Illuminated Books</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, copy P. Since 1978 in the collection of
Sir Paul Getty, who died on 17 April 2003. According to <hi rend="i">The Art Newspaper</hi> online service
(accessed 9 June), Sir Paul’s entire library will go to the Wormsley Foundation, a dormant trust founded in
1992 and, I suspect, soon to spring to life through a generous bequest. The name of the foundation suggests
that the collection will stay in its present location in Wormsley, Buckinghamshire.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Drawings and Paintings</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Death of Ezekiel’s Wife.</hi> Pen and washes over pencil, approx. 33 × 47
cm. Butlin #165, dated to c. 1785. The owner for many years, George C. Homans of Boston, died in 2002. The
drawing is currently in his estate, with its final disposition uncertain.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Fate.</hi> Pencil sketch, 12.4 × 19.6 cm. on a sheet of wove paper 14.9 × 22.4
cm. Butlin #210, dated to <hi rend="i">c.</hi> 1793. Inscribed “Fate” lower right, possibly by William
Michael Rossetti. Swann, 23 Jan., #395, illus. ($16,100 on an estimate of $6000-9000 to J. Windle acting for
R. Essick). See illus. 1.</p>
            <pb id="p37-118" n="118"/>
            <figure n="BUT210.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="640">
			  <figTranscr>Fate</figTranscr>
              <head>1. <hi rend="i">Fate.</hi> Pencil, 12.4 × 19.6 cm. on a sheet of wove paper without
watermark, 14.9 × 22.4 cm. Butlin #210, listed as untraced since 1968 and dated to c. 1793. Sold at Swann
Galleries, New York, 23 Jan. 2003, #395.</head>
              <figDesc>Essick collection. The title inscription, lower right, is not by Blake, but may have
been added by William Michael Rossetti, who lists the work under that title in his catalogue of Blake’s
drawings and paintings in Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (London: Macmillan,
1863) 2:252, #147. The identification of the figure as “Fate” is supported by its similarity to Blake’s
personifications of Destiny and Fate noted below. The figure, backed with what appear to be clouds, sits with
eyes closed (suggesting “blind” fate?), or at least lowered with heavy lids, in a posture oddly suggestive
of the lotus position in yoga meditation. The ovoid forms below and to the outer sides of each hand may be the
links of large chains that further emphasize a conception of the natural body, its senses, and fallen time as
profoundly limited and limiting—central themes in Blake’s writings by the mid-1790s. In Night the Fourth
of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake refers to “The Links of fate link after link an endless chain of
sorrows” (David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, Newly
Revised Ed. [New York: Doubleday, 1988] 336). The loose sketching and deployment of multiple lines to define
outlines distinguish the drawing from Blake’s more controlled and rigid style of the 1780s and help support
Butlin’s dating.<lb/>
<lb/>
As Butlin points out, the design is related to Blake’s emblem sketch on p. 85 of his Notebook, drawn above
the following inscribed lines from John Donne’s “The Progresse of the Soule,” stanza 4: “Whose
changeless brow / Neer smiles nor frowns.” The figure so described is “Great Destiny,” as indicated by
the first line in Donne’s stanza. W. M. Rossetti’s brother, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, owned Blake’s
Notebook from 1847 to 1882. Perhaps W. M., having noticed the similarities between the Notebook sketch and the
one reproduced here, was prompted by the quotation from Donne to add the “Fate” title inscription. The
Notebook figure is also curly-haired, bearded, seated with legs folded, and may have his eyes closed or at
least lowered sharply; but his wrists are together (and probably bound) in front of him and the belt around
his chest may be binding him to the background mountain. This configuration hints at a Promethean figure more
forcefully than the present sketch. David V. Erdman suggests that the Notebook drawing recalls lines 43-45
from Blake’s <hi rend="i">French Revolution</hi> describing the “strong man” who sits “in the den
nam’d Destiny” in the Bastille, “His feet and hands cut off, and his eyes blinded; round his middle a
chain and a band / Fasten’d into the wall . . .” (<hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi>, ed.
Erdman, Revised Ed. [New York: Readex Books, 1977] N85). The personification of Fate on p. 55 of Night 9 in
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> water colors (Butlin #330.473) also resembles the rediscovered
drawing. He is bearded and blind (or at least has his eyes closed), but his legs are drawn up toward his chest
in Blake’s typical Urizenic posture. He holds a chain in his left hand but does not seem to be bound by
it.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p37-119" n="119"/>
            <figure n="but406.1.1.pt" id="but406.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="685">
			  <figTranscr>WB 1799</figTranscr>
              <head>2. <hi rend="i">The Virgin Hushing the Young Baptist, Who Approaches the Sleeping Infant
Jesus.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Tempera, 27 × 38.2 cm., inscribed “WB inv [in monogram] 1799.” Butlin #406.
Reproduced by permission of John Windle.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Judgement of Solomon</hi>, a copy (with variations) of the Vatican fresco of
the same subject designed by Raphael. Pen and black ink, water color with body color, 13.5 × 17.5 cm.
Attributed to Blake; not in Butlin. SL, 27 Nov., #235, sold “The Property of a Lady” who acquired the work
“circa 1960,” illus. color (£15,600). Previously sold SL, 28 Nov. 2002, #235, illus. color (£26,290). If
actually sold in 2002, rather than bought-in, the water color was apparently returned to the vendor. For
discussion and illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 116-19.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Profile of a Man, Perhaps Voltaire</hi>, p. 106 from the Smaller Blake-Varley
Sketchbook. Pencil on leaf 20.3 × 15.6 cm., datable to c. 1819. Butlin #692.106. Acquired Oct. by Adam Fuss,
New York.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Resurrection</hi> (recto), with studies of eyes, the head of an eagle, a human
face, and a lion (verso). Some of the verso sketches are related to Blake’s 1802 <hi rend="i">Designs to a
Series of Ballads</hi> by William Hayley. Pen and gray ink, gray wash over pencil (recto), pencil (verso),
recto image and sheet 20.5 × 21 cm., recto datable to the mid-1780s. Butlin #610 (listed as untraced since
1863). Agnew’s, <hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition of Watercolours &amp; Drawings</hi>,
5-28 March, #17, recto illus. color (£260,000—a record asking price for a monochrome wash drawing by
Blake). Previously sold SL, 5 July 2002, #183, recto and details of the verso illus. color (£144,150 on an
estimate of £20,000-30,000 to Agnew’s). For illus. and discussion of the auction, see 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 116, 121, illus. 5.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Virgin Hushing the Young Baptist, Who Approaches the Sleeping Infant
Jesus.</hi> Tempera, 27 × 38.2 cm., inscribed “WB inv [in monogram] 1799.” Butlin #406. John Windle, Dec.
2002 cat., no entry #, illus. color on the cover (“full details upon request”); Sept. cat. 36, #1, illus.
color (“price on application”). Artemis Fine Arts, Jan. “Review 2002,” pp. 31-33, no entry #, with an
essay on the painting by David Bindman, illus. color (not priced). According to Martin Bailey, “From £1,000
to £10 Million in Two Years,” <hi rend="i">The Art Newspaper</hi> no. 136 (May 2003): 42, the asking price
is $3.8 million. See illus. 2.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Visionary Head: A Man Wearing a Tall Hat</hi> (provisional title). Pencil
strengthened in part with black chalk, 36 × 27.7 cm.
<pb id="p37-120" n="120"/>
Datable to c. 1819-25. Not in Butlin. Agnew’s, <hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition of
Watercolours &amp; Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March, #18, illus. color (£15,000). See illus. 3.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Manuscripts</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Letter of 18 Jan. 1808 to Ozias Humphry, 4 pp. describing Blake’s <hi rend="i">Last
Judgment</hi> design. Roy Davids, March 2000 cat. for “The Artist as a Portrait” exhibition and sale (3-14
April) at the Fine Art Society, London, #10, first and last pp. illus. (£40,000). Previously sold SNY, 14
Dec. 1988, #58 ($26,400 to the dealer John Wilson for stock); SL, 14 Dec. 1992, #16, p. 1 illus. (£19,800 to
a private collector or possibly a consortium of dealers). By late 2002 sold by Davids to an anonymous private
collector.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Separate Plates and Plates in Series</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>“Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims.” John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #12, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
a Colnaghi printing on laid India, illus. ($18,750). Swann, 6 Nov., #310, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., a
Colnaghi printing on laid India, illus. (not sold; estimate $7000-10,000).</p>
            <p>“Christ Trampling on Satan,” Butts after Blake. EB, Oct., Essick impression 1J, from the
stock of the New York print dealer Donald Heald, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of
$2000).</p>
            <p>Dante engravings. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #18-24, complete set sold individually,
1968 printing, all illus. (each priced at either £1500 or £1200). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #15, 5 pls.
only, sold individually, all on laid India, printing date uncertain but probably 1892: pl. 1, illus.
($16,500); pl. 2 ($10,000); pl. 4 ($12,500); pls. 5 and 6 ($7500 each). EB, Oct., pl. 2 only, probably the
1892 printing, from the stock of the New York print dealer Donald Heald, illus. color ($2400).</p>
            <p>“The Fall of Rosamond,” Blake after Stothard. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #17, st.
not identifiable, printed in pink and brown, blue-green hand coloring, cut close (only signatures remaining
from the inscriptions), with a similar (companion?) print, not by Blake and not further identified, both pls.
illus. (£2500).</p>
            <p>“George Cumberland’s Card.” John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #14, printed in black on wove
paper, sheet 11 × 6 cm., illus. ($12,500; sold to Alan Parker, London).</p>
            <p>Job engravings. Larkhall Fine Art, complete set, 1874 printing on laid India, light foxing,
some pls. damp stained in upper margin, loose, illus. (£17,500). BH, 31 March, #23, pl. numbered 11 only,
apparently the 1826 printing on wove paper, some staining, illus. (£480). R. E. Lewis &amp; Daughter, May
cat. of “recent acquisitions,” #13, pl. numbered 13 only, “Proof”
<figure n="VisionaryHead.37.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="480">
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">Visionary Head: A Man Wearing a Tall Hat</hi> (provisional title).</head>
	<figDesc>Pencil strengthened in part with black chalk, 36 × 27.7 cm. Datable to c. 1819-25. Not in Butlin.
First published and attributed to Blake in Agnew’s <hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition of
Watercolours &amp; Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March, #18, illus. color. The sheet of paper appears to have been
trimmed, given the way the image is cut into on the right and left. But even at its present dimensions, this
may be the largest single Visionary Head, comparable in size to the double portrait of <hi rend="i">Pindar and
Lais the Courtesan</hi> on a sheet 26.7 × 41.9 cm. (Butlin #711). The presence of black chalk is unusual, but
there are a few other Visionary Heads in which Blake (or possibly John Linnell or John Varley) used it to
strengthen pencil lines (e.g., the head of an Archbishop on leaf 30 verso, and the head of Charlemagne on leaf
45 verso, of the Larger Blake-Varley Sketchbook). I have not been able to find any clear precedents, classical
or medieval, for the extraordinary headgear. The cheek guard looks Roman. Reproduced courtesy of Agnew’s,
London.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p37-121" n="121"/>
impression of 1826 on laid India, illus. ($3500). Peter Nahum, May cat. “Medieval to Modern,” #6, complete
set, 1874 printing on laid India, “loose in original folder,” all 22 pls. illus. color, much reduced
(£17,000). Sims Reed, July cat., #22, complete set, 1874 printing on laid India, loose, pl. numbered 2 illus.
color (£14,000); #23, 1826 printing on Whatman paper after the removal of the “Proof” inscription, slight
marginal foxing, tissue guards, original cloth-backed boards, cover label (£40,000); same copy of the
printing on Whatman paper, Ursus Books, Nov. cat. 242, #11, illus. ($85,000). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #2,
complete set, 1826 printing on Whatman paper after the removal of the “Proof” inscription, no information
on condition, “original cloth-backed paper wrappers,” pl. numbered 7 illus. ($68,750); #3, pl. numbered 7
only, 1826 printing on Whatman paper after the removal of the “Proof” inscription ($3500). Swann, 6 Nov.,
#311, pl. numbered 3 only, 1826 printing on Whatman paper after the removal of the “Proof” inscription,
illus. ($2200); #312, pl. numbered 13 only, same printing and paper ($1100). CL, 2 Dec., #6, complete set,
1826 printing on Whatman paper after the removal of the “Proof” inscription, wide margins, a few tears,
half morocco worn, covers detached, pl. numbered 16 illus. color (£16,730). SNY, 10 Dec., #46, complete set,
1826 printing on Whatman paper after the removal of the “Proof” inscription, original boards worn, cover
label, illus. color ($40,800).</p>
            <p>“The Man Sweeping the Interpreter’s Parlour,” 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. John Windle,
Sept. cat. 36, #11, Essick impression 2L, illus. (“price on application”). Windle has had this impression
since Feb. 1999, 1 of only 6 remaining in private hands.</p>
            <p>“Rev. John Caspar Lavater.” EB, Oct., 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st., possibly Essick impression
3I, from the stock of the New York print dealer Donald Heald, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid
of $1200).</p>
            <p>“Venus dissuades Adonis from Hunting,” Blake after Cosway. A 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st.
impression was acquired in fall 2003 by Louis Girling of San Francisco from the British print dealer Nicholas
Lott. Although it seems probable that all uncolored impressions printed in black ink are 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
st., this is the only such impression known to me complete with the 1787 imprint.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, Including Prints Extracted
from Such Books</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Allen, <hi rend="i">Roman History</hi>, 1798. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #16, pl. 2
only, illus. (£225).</p>
            <p>Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando Furioso.</hi> EB, Dec. 2002, 1791 ed., 2 vols., Blake’s pl.
foxed, modern boards, illus. color ($120). Andovers Books, April online cat., 1783 ed., 5 vols., slight foxing
on some pls., contemporary calf ($850). Jeffrey Thomas Books, April online cat., 1783 ed., 5 vols.,
contemporary calf ($750).</p>
            <p>Hava Books, April online cat., 1783 ed., 5 vols., Blake’s pl. loose, contemporary calf worn
($532). Book Net, Inc., April online cat., 1785 ed., 5 vols., some foxing, early calf worn, 1 cover loose
($600). Maggs, April cat. 1341, #5, 1799 ed., 5 vols., contemporary calf worn (£300). EB, Nov., 1783 ed., 5
vols., contemporary quarter calf worn, illus. color ($303). Farnworth Books, Dec. online cat., 1799 ed., 5
vols., later half morocco (£150).</p>
            <p>Bible, <hi rend="i">The Royal Universal Family Bible</hi>, 1780-81. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36,
#4, pls. 1-3, 5 only ($875).</p>
            <p>Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> EB, Dec. 2002, pl. 3 only, “1911” (probably an error
for 1926) printing, illus. (no bids on a required minimum bid of $175). EB, Jan., pls. 1, 2, 4-12 only,
offered individually, 1926 printings, illus. (no bids on required minimum bids ranging between $150 and $275).
EB, Jan., apparently the 1813 ed., but in a cloth binding (backstrip repaired with tape) similar to the
publisher’s binding of 1870, possibly an 1870 issue of 1813 letterpress sheets, sts. of the pls. not
determined, illus. color ($611). EB, Feb., pl. 7 only, apparently the 1926 printing, illus. color (no bids on
a required minimum bid of $140). EB, Feb., pl. 9 only, 1926 printing, illus. color ($162.50). EB, Feb., 1813
quarto, considerable foxing, quarter morocco, illus. color ($495). EB, Feb., 12 pls., 1926 printing, offered
individually, illus. (only 1 sold, $165). EB, Feb., pl. 3 only, 1926 printing, illus. color (no bids); offered
again, April ($227.50). EB, Feb., pl. 7 only, apparently 1926 printing, illus. color ($99). EB, March, pls. 1
and 12 only, offered individually, 1926 printings, illus. color (no bids on required minimum bids of $130 and
$150 respectively). EB, April, pl. 4 only, 1926 printing, illus. color ($152.50). EB, July, pl. 10 only,
imprint and printing date not indicated, illus. color ($275). Sims Reed, July cat., #21, 1813 quarto, later
half morocco, illus. color (£500). EB, Aug., pl. 12 only, 1813 imprint, illus. color (no bids on a required
minimum bid of $235). EB, Sept., pl. 3 only, 1813 imprint, illus. color ($181.48); pl. 5 only, 1813 imprint,
illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $175). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #5, 1808 quarto, pl. 1
cropped, some soiling and browning, later full morocco, illus. ($2750); #6, 1813 quarto, half morocco ($2250);
#7, [1870] folio, original cloth ($1250); #8, [1870] folio, full morocco ($1250); #9, [1870] folio, half calf
($1000); #10, [1870] cloth portfolio of the pls. only, as issued ($950). Peter Harrington, Dec. online cat.,
“1813 folio” (probably either the 1813 quarto or the [1870] folio), half calf worn (£350). Book Alley,
Dec. online cat., [1870] folio, original cloth ($800). Old Tampa Book Co., Dec. online cat., 1808 (quarto?),
foxed, quarter calf worn ($2000). Phillip Pirages, Dec. online cat., 1808 quarto, half morocco ($2800).</p>
            <p>Note: Several of the unsold individual pls. listed above were reoffered at least once on EB. I
have not recorded these unsuccessful second attempts.</p>
            <pb id="p37-122" n="122"/>
            <p>Bonnycastle, <hi rend="i">Introduction to Mensuration.</hi> Cameron House Books, April online
cat., 1787 ed., contemporary calf rubbed (£160). SessaBks, Dec. online cat., 1794 ed., Blake’s pl. stained,
contemporary sheep worn ($125). All eds. of Bonnycastle containing the unsigned title-page vignette by Blake
after Stothard are rare.</p>
            <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Graphic Illustrations . . . of Shakspeare</hi>, 1803. The Lark, April
online cat., margins foxed, some damp staining, early calf rebacked ($2200). EB, May, 54 pls. only, but
including Blake’s, later quarter calf, illus. color ($510). BBA, 27 Nov., #34, marginal foxing, full morocco
worn, illus. (not sold; estimate £750-1000). Eveleigh Books, Dec. online cat., foxing and damp staining, calf
rebacked ($3157.89).</p>
            <p>Bryant, <hi rend="i">New System . . . of Ancient Mythology.</hi> BBA, 3 April, #147, apparently
2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1775-76, 3 vols., contemporary calf rubbed (£350). Chequamegon Books, April online
cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., 1774, vols. 1-2 only, modern cloth ($250). Xerxes Books, April online cat.,
2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1775-76, vols. 2-3 only, full calf very worn, hinges repaired with tape ($500).
Todd Leif Pratum, April online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1775-76, 3 vols., contemporary calf rebacked
($950). Librairie Ancienne Minet Frères, April online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1775-76, 3 vols.,
contemporary calf repaired ($816). Everyman’s Bookshop, April online cat., apparently 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi>
ed., 1775-76, 3 vols., full calf ($1000). Kitazawa Bookstore, April online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed.,
1775-76, pls. from an 1807 ed. added, “early” cloth ($1670). N &amp; A Smiles, April online cat., 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> ed., 1774-76, 3 vols., uncut in recent half calf, 1 leaf in vol. 1 loose ($1800). Richard
Smith, Dec. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., 1774-76, 3 vols., foxed, recent half calf (£600).
Hoffman’s Bookshop, Dec. online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1775-76, 3 vols., modern cloth ($650).
Weiser Antiquarian Books, Dec. online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1775-76, 3 vols., later calf
($1315.80).</p>
            <p>Catullus, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1795. Ximenes Rare Books, Sept. cat. M11, #33, 2 vols. in 1,
lacking the half-titles, pl. 1 foxed, contemporary calf rebacked (£750).</p>
            <p>Chaucer, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, vol. 13, from <hi rend="i">Bell’s Edition of the
Poets of Great Britain</hi>, 1782. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #13, contemporary calf ($975).</p>
            <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Attempt to Describe Hafod</hi>, 1796. Ken Spelman, Oct. cat. 49, #188,
“a very good copy in original[?] marbled wrappers,” but with the leaves trimmed to 17.3 × 11.2 cm.
(£480). Uncut copies of the small-paper issue measure 19.5 × 12.1 cm.</p>
            <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden.</hi> Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #15, 1791 ed., pl.
1 only, water stain in top margin, slight foxing, illus. (£375). SessaBks, April online cat., “1791”
(apparently Part 1 so dated; Part 2 not dated), lacking frontispiece (not by Blake) and 2 of Blake’s pls. of
the Portland Vase, stained, modern buckram worn ($650). A. Asher &amp; Co., April online cat., 3<hi
rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1795), Part 2 dated 1794, contemporary half calf worn ($490). Kenneth Hince
Books, April online cat., 1799 ed., 2 vols., slight water staining, contemporary half calf ($491). Woodburn
Books, April online cat., 1799 ed., 2 vols., morocco worn ($400). EB, July, pl. 1 only ($265.99).
Blackwell’s Rare Books, July cat. B141, #120, 1791 ed., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1, 3<hi
rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, contemporary calf (£850). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #16, 1799 ed., 2 vols.,
half calf ($1250). Robert Frew, Oct. cat. 2003, #191, 1791 and 1789, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> eds. of both parts,
lacking the title page to Part 1, slight foxing, recent half calf (£750). James Cummins, Dec. online cat.,
3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1795), 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. of Part 2 (1795), some spotting and
tears, contemporary calf ($1500). ASP Art &amp; Science Projects, Dec. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed.
of Part 1 (1791), 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. of Part 2 (1790), 2 vols., uncut in recent half calf (£970).
Hollett &amp; Son, Dec. online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791), 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> ed. of
Part 2 (1794), 2 vols., foxed and damp stained, contemporary calf (£1200). Hordern House, Dec. online cat.,
“1791” (no further information on eds.), contemporary calf ($4810). Acadia Art &amp; Rare Books, Dec.
online cat., 1799 ed., 2 vols., “boards partially detached” ($500).</p>
            <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, 1806. Kitazawa Bookstore, April online cat., 3 vols., few
leaves torn, modern half calf ($1252.50). EB, June, 3 vols., contemporary calf worn, illus. color (no bids on
a required minimum bid of $599); same copy, Aug. (no bids on a required minimum bid of $449).</p>
            <p>Enfield, <hi rend="i">The Speaker</hi>, 1797. Barry McKay Books, April online cat., modern
cloth (£40). Barter Books, Dec. online cat., foxed, calf very worn (£35).</p>
            <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Classical Compositions</hi>, 1870. Heritage Book Shop, Dec. online cat.,
contemporary morocco ($1500).</p>
            <p>Flaxman, Hesiod designs, 1817. Tamerlane Books, March online cat., half morocco, 2 pls.
repaired with tape ($950). Sims Reed, July cat., #92, fold-marks down the centers of the pls., later
cloth-backed boards with the cover label relaid (£450); #93, bound with Flaxman’s designs for the 
<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> (1805), <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> (1805), and <hi rend="i">Tragedies of Aeschylus</hi>
(1795), some foxing, later full morocco, illus. (£1200). EB, Oct., bound with Flaxman’s Aeschylus designs
(1831), scattered foxing, later quarter roan, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £600). For
one of Flaxman’s preliminary sketches for pl. 7 of the Hesiod designs, see <hi rend="i">Study for Pandora
Brought to Epimetheus</hi> under Flaxman in “Blake’s Circle and Followers,” below.</p>
            <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs, 1805. BH, 31 March, #39, with the 
<hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs, 1805, 2 vols., foxed and stained, illus. (not sold; estimate £200-300). Barter
Books, Oct. online cat., foxed, original(?) boards worn, cloth spine partly detached (£229). Swann, 20 Nov.,
#117, foxed, with Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>
	<pb id="p37-123" n="123"/>
designs, 1805, foxed, 2 vols., half morocco ($275). Kingswood Books, Dec. online cat., “1806” (very
probably an error for 1805), foxed, boards (£500).</p>
            <p>Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables.</hi> EB, March, pls. 3 and 11 only, sold individually, illus. color
(no bids on a ridiculous required opening bid of $799.99 [pl. 3]; top bid of $91 failed to meet the hidden
reserve price [pl. 11]); both offered again (no bids). EB, April, pl. 7 only in an elaborate frame, illus.
color (reserve not met even though the bidding went to $700). Golden Legend, April online cat., 1793 ed., 2
vols., full morocco ($2000). Henry Sotheran, April online cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols. in 1, contemporary morocco
(£1250). A Book By Its Cover, April online cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols. in 1, some foxing, calf rebacked ($1200).
EB, April, pl. 8 only in an elaborate frame, illus. color (reserve not met; highest bid $255). EB, April, pls.
3 and 11 only, sold separately, illus. color (pl. 3 not sold on a required minimum bid of $250; pl. 11 sold
for an astonishing $513). EB, May-June, pls. 2, 3, 5, 7-10, 12 only, offered individually, most with slight
foxing, elaborately framed, illus. color (no bids on ridiculous required minimum bids). EB, June, pls. 2-5
only, offered individually, illus. color ($249 each for pls. 2 and 5, no bids on pl. 3, top bid of $204 on pl.
4 did not meet the reserve). EB, July, pl. 6 only, illus. color (reserve not met; top bid $108.50); same
impression, Aug., illus. color ($199.99). Ursus Rare Books, Sept. cat. 241, #36, 1793 ed., 2 vols., light
foxing, contemporary calf worn, 1 spine damaged ($1250). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #17, 1811 ed., 2 vols.,
modern full calf ($575). Appelfeld Gallery, Dec. cat. 68, #31, 1793 ed., 2 vols., some spotting, later full
calf ($1200). Hermitage Book Shop, Dec. online cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols., calf rebacked ($1250). Phillip
Pirages, Dec. online cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols., contemporary calf ($1500).</p>
            <p>Note: Most of the unsold individual pls. listed above were reoffered at least once on EB. I
have not recorded these unsuccessful second attempts.</p>
            <p>Gough, <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments</hi>, 1786-96. Kitazawa Bookstore, April online cat.,
5 vols., lacking 3 title pages, half calf ($7097.50).</p>
            <p>Hartley, <hi rend="i">Observations on Man</hi>, 1791. Rachel Lee Rare Books, Dec. online cat.,
quarto issue (Bentley 464A), contemporary half calf rebacked (£750).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, 1805. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #19, lacking 1 pl. (not
identified), signature of Sophia Dibdin, wife of the bibliophile Thomas Frognall Dibdin, half calf rebacked
($875). Chapter and Verse Booksellers, Oct. online cat., later full calf, “superb condition” (£2500). EB,
Nov.-Dec., apparently 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. of pl. 2 (and probably of all pls.), later full calf, illus.
color (undisclosed reserve price not met; top bid $821.77).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, 1800. Quaritch, June cat. 1308, #37, pls. foxed,
contemporary half calf rebacked (£475). Brand Bookshop, Dec. online cat., boards worn ($350).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>, 1803-04. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #18, 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 3 vols., calf rebacked ($375).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi>, 1809. Heritage Book Shop, April online cat.,
contemporary Russia worn ($600); another copy, Dec. online cat., fancy binding ($1350). “Private Collector
via Abebooks,” April online cat., some foxing, three-quarter calf worn ($450). James Fenning, May cat. 199,
#252, slight foxing, half morocco (£650). Swann, 16 Oct., #21, contemporary calf rebacked, worn ($161).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 1803. Kitazawa Bookstore, April online cat.,
small-paper issue, contemporary morocco ($1628.25). Strand Book Store, April online cat., apparently
small-paper issue, calf rebacked, worn ($450). Ursus Rare Books, Oct. cat. 243, #31, small-paper issue, recent
half calf ($750). Jarndyce, Oct. cat. 155, #18, apparently small-paper issue, later calf (£750). Appelfeld
Gallery, Dec. addenda to cat. 68, #1, large-paper issue, contemporary calf slightly worn ($600).</p>
            <p>Henry, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Albert De Haller</hi>, 1783. John Gach Books, Dec. online cat.,
pl. water stained, later leather-backed marbled boards very worn, lacking spine ($150).</p>
            <p>Hoare, <hi rend="i">Inquiry</hi>, 1806. Sims Reed, Nov. cat. of “Books on Art before 1900,”
#137, half cloth over boards worn (£285).</p>
            <p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">The Beggar’s Opera by Hogarth and Blake</hi>, 1965. John Windle, Sept.
cat. 36, #21, original folding cloth box worn ($975).</p>
            <p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #20, Blake’s pl. only, 4<hi
rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. ($1500). BBA, 25 Sept., #150, apparently an undated Baldwin and Cradock issue
with the pls. “restored” by Heath, some staining and soiling, few tears, some leaves loose, contemporary
half morocco very worn, covers detached (Alfred Boeddinghaus, £1293).</p>
            <p>Hunter, <hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi>, 1793. Hordern House, April online cat., octavo
issue, contemporary calf ($1751). Messrs. Berkelouw, April online cat., quarto issue, some foxing, calf-backed
boards ($2703); quarto issue, large paper, 2 copies, full calf and original(?) boards ($6082 each); Dec.
online cat., octavo issue, modern half calf ($2595.95). St. Mary’s Books, April online cat., octavo issue,
some soiling, contemporary calf worn ($3496). Peter Harrington, April online cat., quarto issue, recent calf
(£4750). Time Booksellers, April online cat., quarto issue, later calf ($4792). Randall House, April online
cat., octavo issue, lacking the frontispiece, contemporary calf worn, covers detached ($250). Michael Treloar,
April online cat., octavo issue, later half calf ($768). J and SL Bonham, April online cat., quarto issue,
some foxing, contemporary calf rebacked (£3500). Jane &amp; Richard Adelson, April online cat., quarto issue,
slight water stains to a few leaves, half calf 
<pb id="p37-124" n="124"/>
<figure n="LadyDress.37.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="605">
	<figTranscr>[T.] S. d<lb/>
	W. B, sc<lb/>
	1781<lb/>
	A Lady in the full Dress, &amp; another in the<lb/>
	most fashionable Undress now worn.</figTranscr>
	<head>4. “A Lady in the full Dress, &amp; another in the most fashionable Undress now worn.”</head>
	<figDesc>The left image from a single copperplate bearing 2 designs, engraved by Blake after Stothard, for
<hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi>, published by J. Johnson in 1782 (for the
year 1783). 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> (only published?) st., trimmed to 11 × 6.2 cm., thereby eliminating a bit
of the image at the top and about 2 mm. of the image (including the first letter of the signature “T. S.
d”) on the left margin. Signed “W. B, sc” below the design on the right. A long, poorly-repaired tear
extends upward from the left margin. Inscribed “1781” in pen and ink between the image and the title
inscription. Essick collection. No copy of this issue of the annual has ever been located, in spite of a
worldwide search by Dr. Elizabeth B. Bentley. A copy of the issue for 1780 (published 1779) is in the
Huntington Library. Only the 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> recorded impression of this image. Pasted into an album of
186 fashion pls., c. 1755-1845, some probably from other issues of the same annual. One such unsigned pl.,
titled “Two Ladies in the most fashionable Dejeuner dresses,” is lightly inscribed in etched or drypoint
letters, “Engraved for the Ladies New Memorandum Book for 1786.” Several other unsigned pls., particularly
one inscribed “Fashionable Dresses for the Year 1787,” exhibit a graphic style remarkably similar to
Blake’s own. We should, however, resist the temptation to make attributions on that basis alone since
several other engravers who executed pls. after Stothard for publications such as <hi rend="i">The
Novelist’s Magazine</hi> employed much the same engraving and etching style in the 1780s. For further
information about this publication, see E. B. Bentley, “Blake’s Elusive Ladies,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
26.1 (summer 1992): 30-33; and G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
P, 1995) 232-34.</figDesc>
</figure>
($3185). Quaritch, Dec. online cat., octavo issue, some staining, uncut in original boards worn (£350). James
Cummins, Dec. online cat., quarto issue, contemporary calf rebacked ($4250). Evergreen Books, Dec. online
cat., apparently quarto issue, “rebound” ($2500).</p>
            <p>Kimpton, <hi rend="i">History of the Holy Bible</hi>, c. 1781. Andersens Antikvariat, April
online cat., 57 pls. only (of 61), full calf ($264). EB, Nov., some foxing, stains, and torn edges, quarter
calf over very worn boards, illus. color (£62).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi>, 1782 (for 1783). Left image
only from Blake’s pl., “A Lady in the full Dress, &amp; another in the most fashionable Undress now
worn,” 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., pasted into an album of 186 fashion pls., some probably from other issues
of the same annual. Complete album acquired summer 2003 by David Bindman at an Edinburgh bookshop; sold Aug.
by Bindman to R. Essick. See illus. 4.</p>
            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man.</hi> John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #28, 1789 ed., pl. in
1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st., half calf worn ($595). Adam Mills, Oct. online “Blake List,” #12, 1794 ed., st.
of pl. not recorded, contemporary calf slightly worn (£250).</p>
            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy.</hi> Alexandre Antique Prints, April online cat.,
1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, some foxing, contemporary calf rebacked ($2500). Thomas Goldwasser, April online
cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, uncut in three-quarter morocco worn, some covers detached ($1250).
Antiquariat Nikolaus Weissert, April online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, early calf restored ($3263).
www.zubal.com, April online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, no description of binding or condition ($2000).
John Gach Books, April online cat., 1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, modern leather spines over contemporary boards
($2500). Messrs. Berkelouw, April online cat., 1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, full calf worn ($1845). Austwick Hall
Books, April online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, full calf rebacked (£1600). BBA, 
<pb id="p37-125" n="125"/>
8 May, “1789-92” ed. (hence, a mixed set?), 3 vols. in 5, foxed, later calf rebacked, worn (£320). John
Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #22, 1789-92 (hence, a mixed set?), 3 vols. in 5, contemporary morocco ($6750); #23,
1789, 1792, 1810 (hence, a very mixed set?), “uncut,” number of vols. not given, three-quarter morocco
very worn, spines defective and covers detached ($1750); #24, pl. 1 only ($125); #25, pl. 3 only ($125); #26,
pl. 4 only ($200). A. Asher &amp; Co., Dec. online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, calf rebacked ($2444.20).
Erasmushaus, Dec. online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, full morocco ($5145.40).</p>
            <p>Malkin, <hi rend="i">Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi>, 1806. Johnnycake Books, April online
cat., with 2 impressions of the frontispiece, signed by Malkin, some spotting, uncut in original boards very
worn ($1750). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #29, “large-paper copy,” original boards ($1675); #30,
contemporary morocco worn ($1275). Jarndyce, Oct. cat. 155, #2, slight foxing, uncut in original boards worn,
bookplate of Pamela and Raymond Lister, illus (£1200).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine.</hi> EB, May, vol. 9 only, 1782, contemporary calf, illus.
color ($308). EB, May, vol. 8 only, 1782, half calf, illus. color ($104.50). Adam Mills, Oct. online “Blake
List,” #11, vol. 8 only, 1784, lacking pl. numbered 13 (not by Blake) and pp. 361-64, contemporary calf
slightly worn (£165).</p>
            <p>Olivier, <hi rend="i">Fencing Familiarized</hi>, 1780. Abracadabra Bookshop, April online cat.,
later half calf ($950).</p>
            <p>Rees, <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi>, 1820. EB, Feb., pl. 7 only, stained, illus. color (no bids
on a required minimum bid of $49.95); same impression and result, EB, March; same impression, EB, April
($24.95). FineArt, April online cat., number of vols. not indicated, 263 pls., full calf lacking spines,
covers detached (£878). Henry Sotheran, April online cat., complete in 45 vols., recent quarter calf ($5592).
Sims Reed, April online cat., complete in 45 vols., contemporary calf (£3500).</p>
            <p>Ritson, <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi>, 1783. Argosy Books, April online
cat., 3 vols., contemporary calf rebacked ($750). Kenneth Karmiole, April online cat., 3 vols., contemporary
calf worn ($1250). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #31, 3 vols., half morocco ($1150); #32, pls. 1, 4, 6-8 only
($300).</p>
            <p>Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality.</hi> Quaritch, handlist for the April New York
Book Fair, #158, 1791 ed., 3 vols., modern calf, from the collection of Raymond and Pamela Lister with the
latter’s bookplate ($6400). Jarndyce, April online cat., 1791 ed., 3 vols., minor tears and staining,
contemporary calf, hinges repaired (£3500). Heritage Book Shop, April online cat., 1792 ed., 3 vols., pl. 34
partly hand colored, minor marginal staining, modern quarter calf ($6500). Robert Frew, Oct. cat. 2003, #349,
1791 ed., 3 vols., some browning and staining, minor tears, contemporary calf, hinges repaired, illus.
(£3500).</p>
            <p>A. Parker’s Books, Dec. online cat., 48 pls. only loose in a cloth portfolio, many foxed or
stained ($3000).</p>
            <p>Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, 1782. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #33, pls. 1 and 3
only ($175).</p>
            <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi>, 1802. CSK, 3 June, #195, 9 vols., some spotting,
contemporary calf very worn, 3 covers detached (£881).</p>
            <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, 1805. EOS Buchantiquariat Benz, April online cat., 9 vol.
issue, contemporary calf ($1313). Grant’s Bookshop, April online cat., 10 vol. issue, some foxing,
contemporary calf ($2280). EB, July, pl. 1 only, illus. ($150). Blackwell’s, Dec. cat. B143, #350, 10 vol.
issue, contemporary Russia (£2250).</p>
            <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, 1796, colored copies. Sims Reed, April online cat., 2
vols., contemporary Russia, spines “renewed” (£9500). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #34, 2 vols.,
contemporary Russia rebacked, pl. 16 illus. color ($19,750).</p>
            <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, uncolored copies. Peter L. Stern, April online cat., 1796
ed., 2 vols., foxed, modern quarter morocco ($2000). D &amp; E Lake, April online cat., 1796 ed., 2 vols.,
foxed, some pls. browned, contemporary calf worn ($4000). J. N. Bartfield, April online cat., 1806 ed., 2
vols., contemporary calf rebacked ($3000). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #35, 5 unidentified pls. from the 1813
ed., “details on request” ($250). Librería de Antaño, Dec. online cat., 1813 ed., 2 vols. in 1,
three-quarter calf ($2500). Krul Antiquarian, Dec. online cat., 1806 ed., 2 vols., pls. browned, full calf
($5344). 19<hi rend="s">th</hi> Century Shop, Dec. online cat., 1796 ed., 2 vols., half calf ($7000). Bolerium
Books, Dec. online cat., 1796 ed., 2 vols., foxed and stained, some tears, modern buckram ($2750).</p>
            <p>Stuart and Revett, <hi rend="i">Antiquities of Athens.</hi> Paralos Ltd., April online cat., 5
vols., 1762-1830, some spotting, contemporary Russia rebacked (£19,000). CSK, 8 May, #272, 3 vols., 1762-94,
some tears, contemporary calf worn (£5640).</p>
            <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">Pastorals</hi>, 1821. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #36, 2 vols., full calf,
illus. ($22,500).</p>
            <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">The Wood Engravings of William Blake for Thornton’s Virgil</hi>, 1977.
Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #25, original folding box, 6 cuts illus. (£2600). John Windle, Sept. cat.
36, #160, original folding box ($6500).</p>
            <p>Whitaker, <hi rend="i">The Seraph.</hi> John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #37, “c. 1824” but
apparently Bentley’s issue “A” dated by him to c. 1818-28, vol. 2 only (containing the pl. after Blake),
calf-backed boards ($325); #38, pl. only from Bentley’s issue “C” of c. 1825-28 ($125).</p>
            <pb id="p37-126" n="126"/>
            <p><hi rend="i">Wit’s Magazine</hi>, 1784. Fireside Books, April online cat., pls. torn, some
parts missing, binding shot ($200); same copy, Dec. online cat. ($150). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #39-41,
pls. 4-6 only ($400 each).</p>
            <p>Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real Life</hi>, 1791. Phillip Pirages, cat.
for the Feb. San Francisco Book Fair, #69, sts. of the pls. not described, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century calf
rebacked ($5500). Burkony Books, April online cat., lacking 2 pls., later full calf (£800). John Windle,
Sept. cat. 36, #42, incorrectly described as having “all the plates in the final state,” 2 pls. “lightly
stained,” later full morocco ($3750); same copy and price, Oct. cat. 37, #278, pl. 1 (clearly in the 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> st.) illus. Jarndyce, Oct. cat. 155, #17, sts. of the pls. not described, later morocco
(£3200). Dailey Rare Books, Dec. online cat., stained and soiled, modern boards ($2500). Heritage Book Shop,
Dec. online cat., contemporary sheep rebacked ($5500).</p>
            <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, 1797, uncolored copies. EB/Butterfields auction, live
and online, 12 Jan., pp. 79-80, 87-88 (including pls. 36, 38, 39) only, illus. ($120). BH, 11 March, #7,
apparently lacking the “Explanation” leaf, no description of the binding, illus. (£3500). Heritage Book
Shop, March cat. for the April New York Book Fair, #25, with the “Explanation” leaf, slight staining in
some margins, later half morocco ($10,000); same copy and price, Dec. cat. 212, #28, illus. color. Brillig
Books, April online cat., “fair copy,” foxed, pls. trimmed, 3 leaves torn, apparently lacking the
“Explanation” leaf, contemporary calf very worn, covers detached and spine missing (£2850). Sims Reed,
April online cat., no mention of the “Explanation” leaf (and thus missing?), recent half calf (£5000).
Scialom Jean-Pierre, April online cat., “Explanation” leaf supplied in photocopies, half calf ($10,941).
Sims Reed, July cat., #24, no mention of the “Explanation” leaf (and thus missing?), contemporary morocco,
illus. color (£9000). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #43, with the “Explanation” leaf, “well-margined
copy,” full morocco worn, illus. ($9750); #44, lacking the “Explanation” leaf, some pls. trimmed, full
morocco ($8250).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Interesting Blakeana</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>J. Boehme, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, the so-called “Law edition,” 1764-81. Heritage Book
Shop, Aug. cat. of “Recent Acquisitions,” #21, 4 vols., full calf ($12,500). SL, 20 Nov., #40, 4 vols.,
some spotting and damp staining, modern morocco, illus. color (£4080). The ed. of Boehme known to Blake and
perhaps owned by him—see his comment to Henry Crabb Robinson on the beauty of the “figures” (i.e., the
illus.) in “Law’s transl<hi rend="s">n</hi>.” (G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
[Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969] 313).</p>
            <p>Dante, <hi rend="i">A Translation of the Inferno</hi> by H. Boyd, 2 vols., 1785. EB, July, vol.
1 only, water damaged, no description of the binding, illus. color (reserve not met; highest bid £26).
Blake’s annotated copy also consists of vol. 1 only; see Bentley #721.</p>
            <p>C. H. Tatham, <hi rend="i">Etchings, Representing the Best Examples of Ancient Ornamental
Architecture</hi>, 1799. Ursus Rare Books, June cat. 240, #95, contemporary Russia, illus. ($5500). “Mr.
William Blake” appears in the list of subscribers; see Bentley #744.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Monthly Magazine.</hi> Philadelphia Rare Books, Dec. online cat., vol. 12,
1801, boards very worn ($150). The April 1801 issue, p. 246, notes that Blake received £80 from Thomas
Macklin for engraving Stothard’s “The Fall of Rosamond,” published in 1783.</p>
            <p>T. Butts, Jr., “Man on a Drinking Horse,” etching/engraving signed “T Butts: sc” and
dated “22 Jany 1806.” EB, March, mounted in original folder with printed caption, illus. color ($25,
acquired by G. E. Bentley, Jr.). For illus. and comments on this recent discovery, see Alexander S. Gourlay,
“‘Man on a Drinking Horse’: A Print by Thomas Butts, Jr.,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.1 (summer 2003):
35-36.</p>
            <p>W. P. Carey, <hi rend="i">Critical Description of the Procession of Chaucer’s Pilgrims to
Canterbury, Painted by Thomas Stothard</hi>, 1808. Quaritch, Feb./March cat., #5, contemporary calf rebacked
(£850). Contains a passing reference to Cromek’s commission for Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
designs.</p>
            <p>P. Wakefield, <hi rend="i">Perambulations in London, and Its Environs</hi>, 1809. Londinium
Books, Dec. 2002 online cat., contemporary calf worn (£60). Contains Blake’s “Holy Thursday” from 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, pp. 181-82. The second letterpress printing of the poem; the first appears
in Malkin, <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi> (1806) xxix-xxx.</p>
            <p>L. Schiavonetti, letter of 30 January 1810 to Messrs. Cadell and Davies discussing an engraving
commission and with a passing reference to “Blake’s Portrait for Mr. Cromek” (i.e., the portrait of
Blake published as the frontispiece in Cromek’s 1808 ed. of Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>). Nick
Lott, May private offer (£300).</p>
            <p>J. Montgomery, ed., <hi rend="i">The Chimney-Sweeper’s Friend</hi>, 1824. BBA, 27 Feb., #313,
some foxing, contemporary boards rebacked, worn (J. Hart, £223). James Burmester, Sept. cat. 55, #58, some
foxing, newer boards (£500). Contains Blake’s “The Chimney Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence.</hi></p>
            <p>W. Hayley, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, 1823. Adam Mills, Oct. online “Blake List,” #5, 2
vols., half calf, with the bookplate of Raymond Lister (£300). Kitazawa Bookstore, Dec. online cat., 2 vols.,
modern calf spine over old boards ($381.92). Contains important contemporary references to Blake.</p>
            <pb id="p37-127" n="127"/>
            <p>J. T. Smith, <hi rend="i">Nollekens and His Times.</hi> EB, June, 1829 ed., 2 vols., heavily
foxed, quarter calf worn and chipped, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $39.99). Simon Finch,
Norfolk, Nov. cat. 59, #34, 1828 ed., 2 vols., some spotting, contemporary half calf (£200). Contains an
important early biography of Blake; see Bentley #2723.</p>
            <p>[J. B. Nichols, ed.], <hi rend="i">Anecdotes of William Hogarth . . . to Which is Added A
Catalogue of His Prints; Account of Their Variations, and Principal Copies</hi>, 1833. Choosebooks, Dec.
online cat., later half calf ($150). The entry on “Beggar’s Opera” (p. 323) is I believe the first
published description of the sts. of an engraving by Blake. There is also a reference to the pl., “Engraved
by Blake,” on p. 174.</p>
            <p>S. Maunder, <hi rend="i">The Biographical Treasury</hi>, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> ed., 1845. Adam
Mills, Oct. online “Blake List,” #15, some foxing, modern cloth, with the bookplate of Raymond Lister
(£110). Contains a brief entry on Blake. Bentley #2194 lists only the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of 1838.</p>
            <p>B. D’Israeli, autograph letter signed to Mrs. Gilchrist, 4 pp., 5 Nov. 1862. Roy Davids,
Sept. online cat. (£400). According to Davids’ website, the letter informs Mrs. Gilchrist “that there are
some drawings, possible [sic] a considerable number, by Blake in the collection at Hughenden, though he
[D’Israeli] has not seen them for years, and his impression is that they are ‘rather his own startings,
colored by himself, than strictly speaking, drawings,’ offering to allow Mr [William Michael] Rossetti the
opportunity of seeing the drawings, and stating that his father [Isaac D’Israeli] was not acquainted with
Blake nor is there is [sic] a single book in the library at Hughenden ‘enriched by his drawings.’” Isaac
D’Israeli owned a number of Blake’s illuminated books, but is not known to have owned any drawings (see
Isaac D’Israeli’s letter of 24 July 1835 to T. H. Dibdin in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> [Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969] 243-44). Benjamin D’Israeli may simply have been confused about the
matter. For more on Isaac D’Israeli’s Blake collection, see Joseph Viscomi, “The Myth of Commissioned
Illuminated Books: George Romney, Isaac D’Israeli, and ‘One Hundred and Sixty designs . . . of
Blake’s,’” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23.2 (fall 1989): 48-74.</p>
            <p>A. Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, extra-illus. copies only. EB, Nov., 2
vols. with 72 added pls., mostly portraits but including 26 by Blake, contemporary calf rebacked,
publisher’s front covers bound in (no bids on a required minimum bid of $2900). The Blake pls. are stated to
be Lavater, <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>, pl. 2; Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi>, pl. 1; Hunter, 
<hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi>, only pl.; <hi rend="i">Wit’s Magazine</hi>, pl. 6; Allen, 
<hi rend="i">History of England</hi>, all 4 pls.; Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 4 of 6 pls.; and
Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>, 14 of 44 pls.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Camden Hotten facsimile, 1868.
John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #84, light foxing, boards ($1000); #85, foxing “as usual,” original
leather-backed boards ($800).</p>
            <p>S. Palmer and G. Richmond, letters concerning Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of Pitt
Guiding Behemoth</hi> (Butlin #651). Palmer’s letter of 7 July 1870, 1 p., to Sir William Boxall, Director
of the National Gallery (London), offering the painting for £300, accompanied by 4 letters by Richmond, also
of the 1870s, total of 9 pp., proposing and supporting the acquisition by the National Gallery. Nick Lott, May
private offer (£1600). The Palmer letter is not in <hi rend="i">The Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>, ed.
Raymond Lister, 2 vols. (1974). The tempera was acquired by the National Gallery in 1882 after it failed to
sell at auction at CL, 20 March 1882, #108.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, the Pearson “facsimiles” (to use the term loosely),
1876. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #167, original quarter roan worn ($1250).</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Pearson facsimile, 1877. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36,
#64, full morocco, original wrappers bound in ($1975).</p>
            <p>J. Giles (Samuel Palmer’s cousin) and G. Richmond, Christie’s auction cats. of their
collections. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #344, 4 cats., as follows: Giles, 2 Feb. 1881 (including the original
copperplate of Blake’s “Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims,” sold to Colnaghi for £35); Richmond, 29 April
1897, including a “Head of William Blake” by Richmond and 2 water colors by Blake; Richmond, 1 May 1897,
including 2 oil paintings by Palmer; Richmond, 6 July 1897, including sets of Blake’s Job and Dante
engravings ($375 the lot).</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, Pickering facsimile, 1886. John
Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #156, “large-paper copy,” full morocco, original wrappers bound in ($1500).</p>
            <p>W. Muir facsimiles of Blake’s illuminated books. John Windle, Dec. 2002 cat., #57, 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, 1887, 1 of c. 12 colored copies, no copy number by Muir, modern boards, original
wrappers retained ($7500—probably a record asking price for a Muir facsimile); #59, 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, 1887, Muir’s copy #50, hand colored, original wrappers, modern cloth folder ($4500);
#61, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, 1885, Muir’s copy #45, hand colored, original
wrappers, bookplate of T. E. Lawrence ($2950); #62, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, 2 vols. in 1, 1884-85, Muir’s copy #47 of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, no
inscribed copy # for <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, contemporary vellum ($5500). Simon Finch, May cat. 56, #30,
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, 1884, Muir’s copy #49, original wrappers, “The Little Boy lost”
illus. color (£2000). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #48, 54, 86, 145, same titles, copies, and prices as in his
Dec. 2002 cat. listed above, with the title page to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> illus. color; #87, 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, 1885, Muir’s copy #40, original wrappers ($2000); #91, 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, 1886, Muir’s copy #25, contemporary vellum ($2500); #92, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,
1886, no copy number by Muir, modern cloth, original wrappers bound in ($2250); #134, <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi>,
<pb id="p37-128" n="128"/>
1927, Muir’s copy #25, original wrappers ($1500); #150, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, 1885, Muir’s
copy #38, full morocco, original wrappers bound in ($2500); #151, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, 1920, 2
copies, Muir’s copies #16 and 21, original wrappers ($2250 each); #157, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural
Religion</hi>, 1886, “numbered and signed by Muir” but the number not recorded in Windle’s cat.,
original wrappers ($1675); #164, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 1885, 1 of 7 copies on
“Antique notepaper” (according to an inserted note by Muir), no copy number but inscribed “Academy”
(probably meaning a review copy for the journal of that name) on the front cover, original wrappers
($2500).</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, ed. Ellis and Yeats, 1893. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #168,
3 vols., large-paper issue, some foxing, original half morocco worn ($2750); #169, 3 vols., small-paper issue,
original cloth ($3750). Apparently the handsome giltstamped cloth and better condition of the small-paper copy
justify a higher valuation than the large-paper copy.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, ed. Yeats, 1893. Locus Solus Rare Books, July cat., #991,
large-paper issue, original parchment over cloth, spine rubbed ($2500). Certainly a record price for this
“Muses’ Library” ed.</p>
            <p>J. Grego, <hi rend="i">Mrs. Q— and “Windsor Castle,”</hi> 1906. Jarndyce, Oct. cat. 155,
#16, endpapers heavily foxed, slight foxing elsewhere, original vellum spine and blue boards stained (a
bargain at £60). Contains a lithographic facsimile of Blake’s 1820 separate plate, “M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>
Q” after Villiers, which is often mistaken for an original impression (see Bentley #462 and Essick 191-200).
Although printed in an ed. of 500 copies, this is the only copy I have seen on the market in over 35 years of
Blake collecting.</p>
            <p>Postage stamp bearing a portrait of Blake, issued by the Soviet Union in 1958. EB, June, block
of four, cancelled, illus. color (£2.20). For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 35.4 (spring 2002)
cover.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">A Letter from William Blake</hi>, illus. by Leonard Baskin, Gehenna
Press, 1964. Swann, 20 Nov., #123, 1 of 25 with an extra suite of the illus., publisher’s full morocco
($1200 on an estimate of $500-750).</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Poems from William Blake’s Songs of Innocence</hi>, illus. Maurice
Sendak, 1967. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #141, original wrappers ($6500). This small pamphlet is now well
established as the 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> most valuable (or at least most expensive) letterpress ed. of
Blake’s poetry. Positions 1 through 3 are held by the following: Blake, <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>,
1783 (reportedly sold in recent years for over $100,000); Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, an
“Artist Book” by Joel-Peter Witkin weighing “over 14 pounds,” Platinum Series vol. 2, 2002 (listed on
the internet at $19,550); Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, also Witkin, Platinum Series vol. 3,
2003 ($15,000).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, Manchester Etching Workshop facsimile
of copy B, 1983. 3 complete sets of the 16 plates only, hand colored on order by Jacqueline Marshall, one of
the original facsimilists (£2500 each set). Flyer from Marshall, Cheshire, England, included in a late Feb.
mailing by the Blake Society at St. James’s, London. Also on offer are individual impressions of 15 plates,
hand colored on order and ranging in price between £75 and £300.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, “The Ancient of Days” (the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>), feline
version. EB, Sept., a color print (photo-lithograph?) of “The Ancient of Days” with a white domestic cat,
left paw extended and holding the dividers, substituted for the human figure, size not given, illus. color (no
bids).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Blake’s Circle and Followers</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Works are listed under artists’ names in the following order: paintings and drawings sold in
groups, single paintings and drawings, letters and manuscripts, separate plates, books by (or with plates by
or after) the artist.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">BARRY, JAMES</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>“The Angelic Guards,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #11, 1808 printing,
illus. (£395).</p>
              <p>“Detail of the Diagoredes Victors,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #10, 1808
printing, illus. (£375).</p>
              <p>“Divine Justice,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #12, 1808 printing, illus.
(£220).</p>
              <p>“Elysium and Tartarus,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #9, 1808 printing,
illus. (£395).</p>
              <p>“The Glorious Sextumvirate,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #13, 1808
printing, illus. (£275).</p>
              <p>“A Grecian Harvest Home,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #14, 1808 printing,
illus. (£280).</p>
              <p>Barry, <hi rend="i">Series of Etchings</hi>, 1808. BBA, 10 April, #234, some margins stained
and with tears into the images, line engraving of Barry’s “Pandora” by Schiavonetti inserted, upper
cover detached and lower cover missing, “Lear and Cordelia” illus. (£600).</p>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p37-129" n="129"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">CALVERT, EDWARD</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Landscape with Man Driving Cattle.</hi> Tempera on vellum, 10 × 16.5 cm. SL, 2
July, #296, illus. color (not sold; estimate £300-400).</p>
              <p>Calvert, <hi rend="i">The Early Engravings</hi>, published by Carfax &amp; Co. (the so-called
“Carfax Portfolio” of original impressions of Calvert’s engravings and lithographs), 1904. SL, 6 Oct.,
#56, slight foxing, with an additional impression of “The Sheep of His Pasture” in brown ink, “The
Bacchante,” Sherman after Calvert, illus. color, original wrappers (£10,200 on a ridiculously low estimate
of £1000-1500).</p>
              <p>“The Flood,” lithograph. Garton &amp; Co., April cat. 88, #1, India paper, “printed
circa 1829-30,” illus. color (£2750).</p>
              <p>“The Lady with the Rooks,” wood engraving. BH, 31 March, #31, probably from the 
<hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, slight staining, illus. (£300).</p>
              <p>“The Sheep of His Pasture,” engraving. BH, 31 March, #32, probably from the 
<hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, illus. (£250).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">FLAXMAN, JOHN</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Head and Shoulders of a Boy, Arms Raised.</hi> Pencil, 15.2 × 20.3 cm. Abbott
and Holder, Nov. online cat. 357, #37 (£850).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study for Pandora Brought to Epimetheus</hi>, pl. 7 in Flaxman’s Hesiod
designs, engraved by Blake. Pencil, 29.5 × 40 cm. CL, 5 June, #10, illus. color (£1553); Abbott and Holder,
Aug. online cat., #39, titled <hi rend="i">Pandora Presented by Mercury to Prometheus</hi> (£3000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of a Lady Wearing an Elaborate Hat.</hi> Pencil, gray ink, gray wash, 14.7
× 13.9 cm., signed and dated 1798. CL, 5 June, #2, illus. color (not sold; estimate £3000-5000).</p>
              <p>Autograph letter signed, 2 pp., to William Hayley, 28 Aug. 1786. Quaritch, June cat. 1308,
#26, in part about Flaxman’s bust of John Howard (£750).</p>
              <p>Autograph letter signed, 2 pp., addressee not indicated, 11 May 1803. Erasmushaus, May cat.
916, #58, in part about the monument to Mr. and Mrs. Marsh, illus. (1400 euros—about $1700).</p>
              <p>Autograph letter signed, 2 pp., to Dawson Turner, 1819. Roy Davids, Sept. online cat.,
“praising, with a proper degree of self-denegration, an etching of Ozias Humphry’s portrait of himself
executed by Turner’s wife” (£400).</p>
              <p>Aeschylus designs, 1831. Barter Books, Oct. online cat., foxed, original(?) boards worn,
cloth spine detached (£229).</p>
              <p>Dante designs. EB, March, apparently the 1802 ed. with inscriptions in Italian, bound into a
copy of Dante, <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi>, trans. Boyd (1802), 3 vols., some foxing, contemporary
morocco, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $750). BBA, 12 June, #259, 1807 ed., some foxing,
original cloth rebacked, worn (£40). J &amp; S Wilbraham, Aug. online cat. 41, #228, 1807 ed., light foxing,
early cloth, rebacked, with cover label (£125).</p>
              <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Anatomical Studies</hi>, 1833. EB, May, many pls. stained, original
cloth, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $120). Sims Reed, July cat., #94, original cloth
boards rebacked (£400). The Bookcellar, Dec. online cat., original cloth ($249.95).</p>
              <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Sculpture.</hi> Krown &amp; Spellman, April online cat.,
1829 ed., heavily foxed, contemporary calf “artlessly rebacked in cloth,” worn ($250). J. Palmer, Dec.
online cat., 1838 ed., calf rebacked ($125). Pageant Books and Prints, Dec. online cat., 1838 ed., pls. foxed,
“rebound” ($175).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Latin and Italian Poems</hi>, trans. Cowper, 1808. G. W. Stuart, March
cat. 106, #1063, light foxing, uncut in later quarter morocco ($595); #1064, contemporary morocco rebacked
($750). John Windle, Dec. online cat., large-paper issue, inscribed by Hayley (the ed.) to Lord Sheffield,
modern half calf ($675).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs, 1805. www.zubal.com, April online cat., some damp
staining, modern cloth ($900).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">FUSELI, HENRY</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Empress Agrippina</hi>, a fragment from <hi rend="i">Caractacus at the
Tribunal of Claudius at Rome.</hi> Oil, 40.6 × 33 cm., datable to c. 1786. CL, 25 Nov., #39, illus. color
(not sold; estimate £2500-3500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Marta Hess, for an Idealised Portrait in Lavater’s</hi>
Physiognomy. Pencil, 11.7 × 8.5 cm. CL, 20 Nov., #2, illus. color (not sold on an estimate of
£4000-6000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Sin and Death Bridging Chaos Meet Satan on His Return from Earth.</hi> Gray
washes, 30.8 × 38.2 cm., c. 1821. SL, 12 June, #120, illus. color (£18,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Vision of the Deluge.</hi> Oil, 254 × 210 cm., datable to 1799. CL, 20
Feb., #216, illus. color (£100,150).</p>
              <pb id="p37-130" n="130"/>
              <p>“Evening Thou Bringest All,” lithograph. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #2, 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> st., on the original backing sheet with aquatint border, illus. (£5000).</p>
              <p>Portrait of Fuseli, engraved by Bromley, from Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on
Physiognomy</hi>, 1789-98. John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #27 ($200).</p>
              <p>Portrait of Fuseli, engraved by Rogers after Harlowe, 1834. R. G. Watkins, Aug. cat. of
“Engraved Portraits,” #55 (£10).</p>
              <p>Bible, published by Macklin, 1800. BBA, 13 Feb., #44, 6 vols. in 7, some water staining,
contemporary Russia worn, pl. after Fuseli illus. color (£800). CSK, 25 March, #17, 7 vols., contemporary
morocco, binding illus. color (£4700).</p>
              <p>Boothby, <hi rend="i">Sorrows Sacred to the Memory of Penelope</hi>, 1796. J &amp; S
Wilbraham, Aug. online cat. 41, #14, some foxing, original boards backed with cloth, cover label (£150).</p>
              <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Collection of Prints . . . Illustrating . . . Shakspeare</hi>, 1803.
CSK, 25 March, #19, vol. 2 only, some tears and folds, contemporary morocco worn (£750). SL, 10 July, #90, 2
vols. complete, “some plates proofs before letters,” some foxing, contemporary morocco worn, binding and 1
pl. illus. color (£5760). SL, 11 Dec., #98, 2 vols. complete, “including proof duplicates,” later
morocco, binding illus. color (£9600); #99, 2 vols. complete, contemporary Russia rebacked and repaired, 1
pl. after Fuseli illus. color (£2880).</p>
              <p>Cowper, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1811. EB, Feb., 2 vols., contemporary calf, illus. color
($129.50).</p>
              <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi>, 1791. EB, June, frontispiece to vol. 1 only,
“Flora Attired by the Elements,” Smith after Fuseli, framed, illus. color (£58).</p>
              <p>Homer, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, trans. Pope, 1805-06. EB, July,
large-paper issue, 12 vols. in 6, pls. foxed, later quarter calf, illus. color ($412.99).</p>
              <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms.</hi> J &amp; S Wilbraham, March online cat., Dublin 1790
ed., frontispiece by Maguire after Fuseli, stains in margins, contemporary calf worn (£63). Michael Brown,
April online cat., Dublin 1790 ed., foxed, 2 signatures bound out of order, contemporary calf worn ($75).
Minnesota Bookman, April online cat., Boston 1790 ed., contemporary calf worn, front cover detached ($150).
Cobnar Books, April online cat., New York 1790 ed., contemporary sheep worn (£145). James Fenning, April
online cat., Dublin 1790 ed., contemporary calf worn (£145). David Lesser, April online cat., Boston 1790
ed., calf rebacked ($275). Hoffman’s Bookshop, Dec. online cat., Worcester 1787 ed., foxed, “binding
shot” ($200).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> G. W. Stuart, March cat. 106, #1101, 1802 Du Roveray
ed., 2 vols., apparently the small-paper issue, contemporary calf worn ($950); #1103, 1808 ed., contemporary
calf very worn ($385). EB, Dec., 1802 Du Roveray ed., 2 vols., large-paper issue, some foxing, contemporary
calf, illus. color (£205).</p>
              <p>Park, ed., <hi rend="i">Works of the British Poets</hi>, 1805-09. EB, Dec. 2002, an
incomplete set of 39 vols. but including both Milton vols. with the 2 pls. after Fuseli and other vols. with
at least 3 of the pls. after Stothard, contemporary calf very worn, several spines missing, illus. color
($183.30).</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">The Plays</hi>, published by Stockdale, 1807. EB, Dec. 2002, 
<hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>, full-page pl. only, Heath after Fuseli, full margins, illus. ($19.95).</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Seventeen Engravings to Illustrate Shakspeare</hi>, published by
Woodmason, 1817. EB, Dec. 2002, <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi> only, Bromley after Fuseli, full margins, slight
staining, illus. ($52).</p>
              <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Celebrated Collection of Pictures of . . .
Angerstein</hi>, 1823. Sotheran’s, Nov. cat. 47, #88, large-paper issue, half morocco (£225).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">LINNELL, JOHN</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">An Apple Tree.</hi> Water color, 14.6 × 10.2 cm., signed with initials and
dated 1811. Acquired 2002 by The British Museum, Dept. of Prints and Drawings, either at, or shortly after,
the sale of this early work at CL, 6 June 2002, #54, illus. color (£21,510).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Children of Gen. John Smith with a Pony.</hi> Oil, 39 × 48.5 cm., signed
and dated 1829. Derek Johns Limited, June cat., not numbered, illus. color (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">At Cullercoats, Northumberland.</hi> Oil sketch, 19.1 × 24.8 cm., datable to
1817. CL, 5 June, #72, illus. color (not sold; estimate £4000-6000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Dolwyddelan Valley, North Wales.</hi> Water color, 19.1 × 24.8 cm., signed and
dated 1813. CL, 5 June, #76, illus. color (£2868).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Extensive Landscape in North Wales.</hi> Water color, 24.7 × 37.4 cm., signed
and dated 1813. CL, 5 June, #75, illus. color (£6572).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Forest.</hi> Oil, 29 × 48 cm. SL, 29 Jan., #28, illus. color (not sold;
estimate £4000-6000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Hillside.</hi> Black chalk and wash, 38 × 51 cm. SL, 2 July, #225, illus.
color (£744).</p>
              <pb id="p37-131" n="131"/>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portraits of Robert and Jane Ogle, Aged Five and Three.</hi> Oils, each 21.5 ×
16 cm., both signed, one dated 1822. SL, 12 June, #81, both illus. color (£9600).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Resting Woodcutters, Bray Wood, Windsor.</hi> Water color, 16.5 × 27 cm.,
signed and dated 1827. CL, 5 June, #78, illus. color (£10,755). Previously sold SL, 8 April 1998, #55
(£14,950 to the dealer Spink-Leger, which offered the work in its Oct. 1998 cat. of “British Watercolours
and Drawings” for £30,000). For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 32.4 (spring 1999): 110.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Return of Ulysses.</hi> Oil, 124.5 × 185.5 cm., signed and dated 1848. CL,
19 Feb., #4, illus. color (£171,650). Possibly an auction record for a work by Linnell.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Rooks Hill, Kent.</hi> Water color, 29.2 × 34.9 cm., signed and dated 1828. CL,
5 June, #92, illus. color (£13,145 on an estimate of £4000-6000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Shepherd’s Amusement.</hi> Oil, 67.9 × 90.2 cm., signed and dated 1816,
retouched by Linnell in 1836. CL, 25 Nov., #144, illus. color (not sold; estimate £8000-12,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Sunset.</hi> Oil, 71.2 × 102.8 cm., signed and dated 1860. CL, 25 Nov., #124,
illus. color (not sold; estimate £15,000-20,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Twilight.</hi> Oil, 36.8 × 29.2 cm., datable to c. 1819. Capes Dunn auction,
Manchester, 29 July, #20, illus. color (a bargain at £2800).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Woodcutters, Bray Wood, Windsor.</hi> Pencil heightened with white on blue
paper, 14.6 × 18.4 cm., signed with initials. CL, 5 June, #79, illus. color (£1195).</p>
              <p>3 autograph letters signed, each 1 p., 1 to Richard Redgrave and 2 to unnamed correspondents,
1834, 1858, 1865. Roy Davids, Sept. online cat. (£150, £85, £150).</p>
              <p>“Herne’s Oak, Windsor Forest,” etching, Prior after Linnell, c. 1850s? EB, Oct., illus.
(no bids on a required minimum bid of £9.99).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">MORTIMER, JOHN HAMILTON</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Falstaff.</hi> Pen and ink, oval, 34.5 × 28.4 cm. Campbell Fine Art, March cat.
10, #3, apparently the direct preliminary (and not a copy by another hand) for the etching, illus.
(£5400).</p>
              <p>“Banditti Gambling,” engraving, Hall after Mortimer. Justin <corr type="emend">Skrebowski</corr> Prints, March
online cat., illus. (£220).</p>
              <p>“Banditti Regaling,” etching, Ireland after Mortimer. EB, March, printed in brown ink,
illus. color ($49.95).</p>
              <p>“Banditti: Three Heads,” etching, Haynes after Mortimer. Campbell Fine Art, March cat.
10, #7, illus. (£165).</p>
              <p>“Boat in a Storm,” etching, Blyth after Mortimer. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #6,
illus. (£220).</p>
              <p>“A Captain of Banditti and His Family,” etching, Ireland after Mortimer. BBA, 25 Sept.,
#89, with 3 pls. by Blyth after Mortimer (Michael Finney, £48).</p>
              <p>“Captive Family,” etching, Blyth after Mortimer. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #5,
illus. (£240).</p>
              <p>“Cassandra,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #4, 1812 printing, illus.
(£220).</p>
              <p>“Gerard Lairesse,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #8, early impression,
illus. (£420).</p>
              <p>“King John Ratifying the Magna Carta,” etching, Ryland after Mortimer, 1799. Michael
Finney, May online cat., color printed, marginal foxing (£500).</p>
              <p>“Richard II,” etching. BBA, 25 Sept., #90, illus. (not sold).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Bell’s British Theatre</hi>, 1777. EB, March, 2 pls. only, “Tragedies” and
“Operas,” offered individually, both Hall after Mortimer, margins stained, illus. color (no bids on
either).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">PALMER, SAMUEL</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Broken Bridge.</hi> Water color, 39.7 × 49.8 cm., datable to the second
half of the 1840s. CL, 20 Nov., #59, illus. color (£31,070).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Evening: A Cottager Returning Home Greeted by His Children.</hi> Water color, 19
× 41 cm., c. 1848. SL, 12 June, #147, illus. color (£24,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Golden Valley.</hi> Water color with body color, pen and black ink, gold,
and scratching out, 13 × 16.2 cm., datable to c. 1833-34. CL, 11 June, #5, illus. color, accompanied by
essays by Andrew Wilton and Colin Harrison and a list of the 17 “Shoreham Period Works on Paper in Private
Collections” (£587,650 on an estimate of £500,000-800,000 to the New York collector Leon Black). See
illus. 5.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Head of Christ</hi>, traditionally attributed to Palmer as in part a
self-portrait. Oil, 34.8 × 23.5 cm. CL, 20 Feb., #219, illus. color (not sold; estimate £20,000-30,000).
Perhaps the painting failed to sell because of uncertainties about its attribution to Palmer.</p>
              <pb id="p37-132" n="132"/>
              <figure n="Palmer.GoldenValley.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="398">
                <head>5. Samuel Palmer, <hi rend="i">The Golden Valley.</hi></head>
                <figDesc>Water color with body color, pen and black ink, gold, and scratching out, 13 × 16.2
cm., datable to c. 1833-34. Collection of Leon Black, New York. Arguably the finest Shoreham-period water
color still in private hands, <hi rend="i">The Golden Valley</hi> can be grouped with 2 other fine works of
about the same date, <hi rend="i">The Weald of Kent</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Timber Waggon</hi>, both in the
Yale Center for British Art, New Haven, Connecticut. Photo courtesy of Christie’s London.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <p><hi rend="i">Landscape with Windmill.</hi> Water color, 12 × 16.5 cm., datable to c. 1851.
Lowell Libson, London, Nov.-Dec. exhibition of water colors and drawings (price on request). Previously sold
CL, 21 Nov. 2002, #31, under the title <hi rend="i">A Windmill near Pulborough, West Sussex</hi>, illus. color
(£6572).</p>
              <p>28 autograph letters signed, none published, Feb. 1857 to Aug. 1880, to members of the
Redgrave family. Roy Davids, Nov. online cat. (£24,000). Apparently there are no references to Blake in these
or any of the other Palmer letters listed below.</p>
              <p>4 autograph letters signed, 2-4 pp. each, to Mrs. George, an unnamed correspondent, Leonard
Valpy, and Ernest Gambart, 1872, undated (possibly c. 1865), 1866, and undated (possibly c. 1854). Roy Davids,
Sept. online cat. (£1650, £750, £2000, £450).</p>
              <p>Autograph letter signed, 4 pp., to George Richmond, 8 Jan. 1881. Quaritch, June cat. 1308,
#66, on the death of Richmond’s wife (£600).</p>
              <p>Letter by Palmer. See S. Palmer and G. Richmond under “Interesting Blakeana,” above.</p>
              <p>“Bellman,” etching. Garton &amp; Co., April cat. 88, #2, 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., 1879
printing, illus. color (£8500). EB, July, st. not indicated, illus. (no bids on a required minimum bid of
$249.99).</p>
              <p>“Cypress Grove,” etching. CSK, 30 Oct., #25, with “The Sepulchre,” both 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> st. (£352).</p>
              <p>“Early Ploughman,” etching. EB, Jan., 8<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.?, illus. color ($449.99).
SL, 25 March, #57, 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., pencil signature, slight
<pb id="p37-133" n="133"/>
foxing, illus. color (£1200). Swann, 18 Sept., #472, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. ($518). CSK, 30 Oct.,
#24, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., pencil signature (£2585).</p>
              <p>“Herdsman’s Cottage,” etching. SL, 25 March, #59, with “The Vine” and “The
Sleeping Shepherd,” all final sts., slight foxing, “Herdsman’s Cottage” illus. color (£2040).
Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #28, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., illus. (£750).</p>
              <p>“Lonely Tower,” etching. SL, 25 March, #55, 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., some damage in
margins, illus. color (not sold; estimate £1000-1200); #58, 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., pencil signature,
upper corners replaced, illus. color (£3840). EB, July, st. not indicated, pencil signature, evenly stained
brown, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $5000).</p>
              <p>“Moeris and Galatea,” etching. CSK, 30 Oct., #26, with “Homeward Star,” both 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> st. (£352).</p>
              <p>“Morning of Life,” etching. EB, July-Aug., st. not indicated, illus. color (no bids on a
required minimum bid of $249.99). Abbott and Holder, Oct. online cat. 356, #286, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.
(£950).</p>
              <p>“Opening the Fold,” etching. BH, Chester, 15 April, #816, 10<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
1926 printing (£240).</p>
              <p>“Portrait of Samuel Palmer,” etching by C. W. Cope, 1884. Campbell Fine Art, March cat.
10, #32, illus. (£1500).</p>
              <p>“Rising Moon,” etching. SL, 25 March, #53, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., with “The Weary
Ploughman” and “The Morning of Life,” both final sts., slight foxing, “Rising Moon” illus. color
(£1200). Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #33, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. (£1250).</p>
              <p>“Skylark,” etching. SL, 25 March, #60, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., slight foxing, illus.
color (£3000). Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #26, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. (£1450). EB, July,
st. not indicated, illus. (no bids on a required minimum bid of $99.99).</p>
              <p>“Sleeping Shepherd,” etching. Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #34, 4<hi
rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. (£2000).</p>
              <p>“Weary Ploughman,” etching. SL, 25 March, #54, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., pencil
signature, slight foxing, illus. color (£960).</p>
              <p>Dickens, <hi rend="i">Pictures from Italy</hi>, 1846. EB, Dec. 2002, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
ed., original cloth, illus. color ($482.87—probably an auction record). Adam Mills, March online cat., 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> ed., original cloth (£450); 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., original cloth (£400). EB, June,
2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., later calf, illus. color (£42). Joseph Falcone, Nov. cat. 91, #168, 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> ed., original cloth slightly worn, full calf solander case ($1000).</p>
              <p>Hamerton, <hi rend="i">Etching &amp; Etchers.</hi> Swann, 6 Nov., #401, 1868 ed. with
Palmer’s “Early Ploughman” etching, quarter morocco, illus. ($1500); #402, 1880 ed. with Palmer’s
“Herdsman’s Cottage” etching, half calf ($1100).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Shorter Poems</hi>, 1889. Adam Mills, March online cat., small-paper
issue, original cloth slightly worn (£200). EB, June, large-paper issue, foxed, original vellum stained,
illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $295). John Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #393, large-paper issue,
original vellum slightly soiled ($1750).</p>
              <p>A. H. Palmer, <hi rend="i">Life and Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>, 1892. Adam Mills, March
online cat., with Palmer’s etching of “The Willow,” large-paper issue, original cloth (£450). John
Windle, Sept. cat. 36, #391, large-paper issue, original cloth ($975); #392, small-paper issue, original cloth
($550).</p>
              <p>S. Palmer, <hi rend="i">English Version of the Eclogues of Virgil</hi>, 1883. SL, 25 March,
#56, pls. only, minor stains in margins, “Opening the Fold” illus. color (not sold; estimate £1800-2200).
Sims Reed, July cat., #193, large-paper copy, original vellum slightly worn, illus. color (£1250); #194,
small-paper copy, original cloth slightly worn (£950).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Songs and Ballads of Shakespeare Illustrated by the Etching Club</hi>,
“1843” (actually 1853). BBA, 12 Dec. 2002, #256, full morocco, including Palmer’s “The Vine or Plumpy
Bacchus,” 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. (£240). Campbell Fine Art, March cat. 10, #31, large-paper
issue, no description of the binding, “The Vine or Plumpy Bacchus” illus. (£1200).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">RICHMOND, GEORGE</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Figures in a Landscape, perhaps Susanna and the Elders.</hi> Pen and brown ink
over pencil, 22.7 × 17.5 cm. Agnew’s, <hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition of
Watercolours &amp; Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March, #62, illus. color (£12,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Post Mortem Likeness of Our Beloved Mother.</hi> Pencil, 20.3 × 28 cm., dated
1836. Abbott and Holder, Jan. cat. 351, #75 (£425).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Shepherd Waking.</hi> Medium not described, but apparently pencil, 14.3 ×
20.5 cm. Agnew’s, <hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition of Watercolours &amp;
Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March, #63, illus. color (£3500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of a Figure in Contemplation.</hi> Brown ink, 23.5 × 15.2 cm. CL, 5 June,
#24, illus. color (not sold; estimate £1500-2000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of Figures in Classical Robes.</hi> Brown ink, 18.5 × 23.5 cm. CL, 20
Nov., #32, illus. color (not sold on an estimate of £800-1200).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of Trees.</hi> Black and white chalk on brown paper, 55.3 × 32.4 cm. CL,
5 June, #77, illus. color (not sold; estimate £2000-3000).</p>
              <pb id="p37-134" n="134"/>
              <p>16 autograph letters, all but 1 signed, c. 37 pp. in all, c. 1859-88. Roy Davids, Sept.
online cat. (£450).</p>
              <p>Autograph letter signed, 1 p., to Samuel Palmer, not dated. Roy Davids, Sept. online cat., an
invitation to visit (£150).</p>
              <p>Autograph letter signed, 3 pp., to William Boxall, not dated. Roy Davids, Sept. online cat.
(£145).</p>
              <p>Letters by Richmond. See S. Palmer and G. Richmond under “Interesting Blakeana,”
above.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">ROMNEY, GEORGE</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Fall of the Rebel Angels.</hi> Pencil, 13.5 × 16.5 cm. SL, 19 March, #127,
illus. color (not sold; estimate £2500-3500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Mother Holding Her Child.</hi> Pencil, pen, brown wash, 24.7 × 16.5 cm. CL,
22 Jan., #11, illus. color (£26,290).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Serena Reading</hi> (based on Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of
Temper</hi>). Pencil, 33.7 × 26 cm., slight figure studies on verso. Agnew’s, <hi rend="i">130<hi
rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition of Watercolours &amp; Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March, #16, illus. color
(£15,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Studies of a Woman Dancing.</hi> Pen and brown ink, 19 × 15.5 cm. SL, 12 June,
#118, illus. color (£2160).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study for Howard Visiting the Prisons.</hi> Pencil, 16 × 19.5 cm. Swann, 23
Jan., #393, illus. ($920).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of Lady Macbeth.</hi> Pencil, 15.3 × 11.1 cm. Agnew’s, 
<hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition of Watercolours &amp; Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March, #15,
illus. color (£2250).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of a Lady Sewing.</hi> Pencil, 17.2 × 11.5 cm. Agnew’s, 
<hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition of Watercolours &amp; Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March, #14,
illus. color (£2250).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of a Standing Woman.</hi> Pen, brown washes, pencil, 30.5 × 26 cm. SL, 27
Nov., #233, illus. color (not sold; estimate £4000-6000).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, Boydell ed., 1795-97. EB, Feb., “Milton and His Two
Daughters” only, stipple and aquatint by B. Smith after Romney, illus. color ($51).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">STOTHARD, THOMAS</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Designs for the Outer Compartments of the Wellington Shield: Ten Drawings.</hi>
3 in pen and brown ink and oils on paper, varnished; 7 in brush and brown ink and brown wash over pencil. Each
approx. 16.5 × 25.5 cm. EB/Sotheby’s live auction, 21 Oct., illus. color ($95,000 on an estimate of
$30,000-40,000). I suspect that the high price had more to do with Wellington than Stothard.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Mother with Her Sleeping Baby.</hi> Water color, 12.7 × 12.7 cm. Abbott and
Holder, Aug. online cat., #95 (£450).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Sylvia and the Outlaws: A Scene from Shakespeare’s</hi> Two Gentlemen of
Verona. Oil, 69.9 × 52.4 cm., with indistinct signature. CL, 20 Feb., #68, illus. color (£10,755).</p>
              <p>“Catherine of France Presented to Henry V,” engraved by Cardon after Stothard, 1799.
Michael Finney, May online cat., color printed (£480).</p>
              <p>“Pilgrimage to Canterbury,” engraved by Schiavonetti and Heath after Stothard, 1817. EB,
March, framed, perhaps stained, illus. color (reserve not met; highest bid £387).</p>
              <p>Portrait of Stothard, engraved by Meyer after Jackson, 1815. EB, Jan., illus. (£1.50). K
Books, May online cat. (£60). R. G. Watkins, Aug. cat. of “Engraved Portraits,” #146, marginal foxing
(£15).</p>
              <p>Aesop, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, 1793. Tavistock Books, 31 May-1 June Pasadena Book Fair, 2
vols., original boards uncut, new spine labels ($850). The finest copy I have ever seen.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Bijou</hi>, 1829. J &amp; S Wilbraham, Aug. online cat. 41, #249, contemporary
cloth (£20).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Book of Common Prayer</hi>, n.d. (c. 1811?). EB, June, with the 1794 pls. after
Stothard (inserted?), some pls. foxed, contemporary calf very worn, illus. color (£16).</p>
              <p>Bray, <hi rend="i">Life of Stothard</hi>, 1851, extra-illus. copies only. EB, June, 88 pls.
added, not further identified, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco, illus. color (no bids on a required
minimum bid of $275).</p>
              <p>Bunyan, <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> portfolio of large pls., English/French ed.
EB, June, “The Affright” only, Zancon after Stothard, stain lower right margin, illus. color (no bids on a
required minimum bid of $25).</p>
              <p>Burns, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, 1817. EB, May, contemporary calf, illus. color
($72.50). With a title-page vignette after Stothard, not previously recorded.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Catullus, Tibullus et Propertius</hi>, Pickering ed., 1824. Grant &amp; Shaw,
Feb. cat. 58, #34, contemporary half calf rebacked (£50).</p>
              <pb id="p37-135" n="135"/>
              <p>Chaucer, <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi>, Pickering ed., 1822. BBA, 11 Sept., #281, 5
vols., browning and spotting, contemporary half calf very worn (Piers Rodgers, £188). This ed. contains
Worthington’s small engraving of Stothard’s “Canterbury Pilgrimage.”</p>
              <p>Cromek, ed., <hi rend="i">Remains of Nithsdale and Galloway Song</hi>, 1810. Blackwell’s,
Dec. cat. B143, #78, foxed, modern half calf (£150).</p>
              <p>Defoe, <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe.</hi> Chapter and Verse Booksellers, May online cat.,
1790 ed., 2 vols., some foxing and marginal tears, half calf (£275); 1820 ed., 2 vols., full morocco (£975).
Harrington Rare Books, May online cat., 1820 ed., 2 vols., “plates in two states,” slight foxing, full
morocco rubbed (£950). Stella and Rose’s Books, May online cat., 1790 ed., 2 vols., calf worn (£450). EB,
Sept., 1790 ed., 2 vols., contemporary calf rebacked, illus. color ($695). Marlborough Rare Books, Sept. cat.
197, #147, 1820 ed., the 22 pls. only, Heath after Stothard, proofs before titles on laid India, slight
foxing, contemporary half morocco (£450). EB, Sept., 1804 ed., 2 vols., later quarter morocco, illus. color
($600). BBA, 27 Nov., #65, 1820 ed., 2 vols., contemporary morocco worn, covers detached (not sold; estimate
£80-120).</p>
              <p>Fenelon, <hi rend="i">Telemachus</hi>, 1795. EB, Dec., calf rebacked, illus. color (not
sold).</p>
              <p>Franklin, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, 1809. EB, Feb., some staining, half morocco over very worn
boards, illus. color ($50). EB, Feb.-March, contemporary calf worn, illus. color ($66).</p>
              <p>Gessner, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, 1802. John Price, Jan. cat., #108, 3 vols., modern half
calf (£125). EB, April, 3 vols., contemporary morocco, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of
$180).</p>
              <p>Goldsmith, <hi rend="i">Vicar of Wakefield.</hi> EB, April, 1801 ed., bound with 2 unrelated
works, quarter calf, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $95). EB, Oct., 1819 ed. published by
Bumpus, “engraved title and frontispiece by Stothard,” foxed, contemporary boards very worn, part of spine
missing, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £4.99). The title-page vignette in this 1819 ed.,
Heath after Stothard, was first published by Suttaby, in his “Miniature Library,” in 1808. The
frontispiece, however, is a completely different design. I could not tell from the EB illus. if the signature
on the frontispiece is indeed Stothard’s.</p>
              <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 1788. Sam Gatteno Books, April online cat.,
contemporary calf worn ($125).</p>
              <p>Homer, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, trans. Pope, 1805-06. See under
Fuseli, above.</p>
              <p>Josephus, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, c. 1785-86? EB, July, 1 pl. only, “Pharaoh and His Host
of Egyptians Drowned in the Red Sea,” Morris after Stothard, illus. color ($12).</p>
              <p>Metastasio, <hi rend="i">Dramas and Other Poems</hi>, 1800. EB, Feb., 3 vols., contemporary
quarter calf very worn, 2 spines missing, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $100).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, 1799. EB, Dec. 2002, contemporary calf very worn, illus.
color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £30).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, suite of pls. engraved by Bartolozzi, c. 1792-95.
EB, Jan., “Adam and Eve in Paradise” only, illus. color ($52).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine.</hi> Glover’s Bookery, April online cat., vols. 1-4
only, 1780, no mention of pls., calf worn ($203 each). Kitrenwick Books, April online cat., vol. 2 only, 1787,
disbound (£30). Books Junk Etc., April online cat., vol. 2 only, 1780, heavily foxed, calf very worn ($80).
Goldsworth Books, April online cat., vol. 17 only, 1785, no mention of pls., calf worn (£70). Sanctuary
Bookshop, April online cat., vol. 4 only, no mention of pls., binding very worn, some gatherings loose (£10).
J &amp; S Wilbraham, Aug. online cat. 41, vols. as follows, all in contemporary quarter calf: #49, vol. 4,
1781 (£28); #50, vol. 2, 1780 (£35); #51, vol. 1, 1781 (£30); #52, vol. 7, 1782 (£35). EB, Nov., vol. 4
only, 1781, quarter calf, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $499.95). EB, Dec., Fielding’s
<hi rend="i">Jonathan Wild</hi> only, 1788, modern boards, illus. color (not sold). See also under
“Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake,” above.</p>
              <p>Park, ed., <hi rend="i">Works of the British Poets</hi>, 1805-09. See under Fuseli,
above.</p>
              <p>Robertson, <hi rend="i">History of the Reign of the Emperor Charles V</hi>, 1798 (pls. dated
1799). David Mason Books, July online cat., 4 vols., contemporary calf ($250). Apparently A. C. Coxhead saw
only the pls., and thus dates the work to 1799 (<hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard, R. A.</hi> [London: Bullen,
1906] 195; same dating in Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard</hi> [Columbia: U of Missouri P,
1988] 75). Coxhead titles each of the 12 pls. according to the inscriptions beneath the designs—with one
exception: “A group of armed men.” He may have seen only an impression with the inscriptions trimmed off.
This pl. is very probably “The Elector of Saxony a Prisoner before Charles V at the Battle of Mulhausen”
(vol. 3, facing p. 365), not otherwise listed by Coxhead.</p>
              <p>Rogers, <hi rend="i">Pleasures of Memory.</hi> EB, Jan., 1793 ed., with 2 pls. after
Stothard, quarter calf, illus. color ($13.50). EB, April,
<pb id="p37-136" n="136"/>
1794 ed., contemporary morocco, illus. color ($89). EB, May, 1794 ed., contemporary morocco, illus. color (no
bids on a required minimum bid of $49). EB, Nov., 1806 ed., contemporary calf, illus. color ($28).</p>
              <p>Rogers, <hi rend="i">Poems.</hi> EB, Feb., 1851 ed., no description of the binding, illus.
color ($16). EB, Feb., 1854 ed., some foxing, full morocco worn, illus. color (£4.25). BBA, 11 Sept., #291,
with Rogers, <hi rend="i">Italy</hi>, both 1838 large-paper issues, some spotting, contemporary morocco worn
(Piers Rodgers, £129). Swann, 16 Oct., #201, 1830 ed., with Rogers, <hi rend="i">Italy</hi>, 1834, 2 vols. in
later full morocco (not sold; estimate $250-350); #234A, same 2 eds., later full morocco (not sold; estimate
$400-600).</p>
              <p>Scott, <hi rend="i">Rokeby</hi>, 1813. Londonline Books, May online cat., “1815”
(actually 1813?), foxed, calf very worn, spine missing and covers loose (£35). EB, Aug., foxed and browned,
contemporary calf worn, illus. color (£14.99).</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">The Plays</hi>, published by Stockdale, 1807. EB, Dec. 2002, the
following pls., Heath after Stothard, full margins, illus. color, offered individually: <hi rend="i">Comedy of
Errors</hi>, title pl. ($19.95); <hi rend="i">Comedy of Errors</hi>, full-page pl.; <hi rend="i">King
John</hi>, fullpage pl. (no bids on these last 2 on a required minimum bid of $19.95 each).</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">The Plays</hi>, published by Pickering, 1825. EB, May-June, 8 vols.
only (lacking vol. 4), full calf, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $500).</p>
              <p>Somerville, <hi rend="i">The Chase</hi>, 1800. Claude Cox, March cat. 154, #40, uncut in
cloth-backed boards (£45).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Spectator</hi>, in <hi rend="i">The British Classics</hi>, pub. Sharpe, 1803.
EB, Dec., vol. 1 of <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi> (vol. 5 of <hi rend="i">British Classics</hi>) only, scattered
foxing, contemporary calf, illus. color ($24.99).</p>
              <p>Thomson, <hi rend="i">The Seasons.</hi> EB, March, 1794 ed., 2 vols., later quarter calf
worn, illus. color ($26). EB, May, 1793 ed., contemporary calf worn, illus. color (no bids on a required
minimum bid of $275). Claude Cox, May cat. 155, #228, 1793 ed., contemporary calf slightly worn (£110).</p>
              <p>Thomson, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, 1802. EB, Feb.-March, with at least 1 pl. after Stothard, 3
vols., some foxing, contemporary calf worn, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $89.50). This
ed. not previously recorded as having pls. after Stothard.</p>
              <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, 1824. EB, Feb., badly stained and spotted,
contemporary calf very worn, illus. color ($9.99).</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Appendix: New Information on Blake’s Engravings</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Listed below are substantive additions or corrections to Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick,
<hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi>, vol. 1, Plates Designed and Engraved by Blake (1972);
Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (1983); and Essick, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (1991). Abbreviations and citation styles follow
the respective volumes, with the addition of “Butlin” according to the List of Abbreviations at the
beginning of this sales review. Newly discovered impressions of previously recorded published states of
Blake’s engravings are listed for only the rarer separate plates.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>“Venus dissuades Adonis from Hunting,” Blake after Cosway, p. 145. For the only 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> st. impression known to me complete with the 1787 imprint, see under “Separate Plates and
Plates in Series,” above.</p>
            <p>“James Upton,” Blake and John Linnell after Linnell, pp. 186-88. An impression in the 3<hi
rend="s">rd</hi> state is reproduced in Seymour J. Price, <hi rend="i">Upton: The Story of One Hundred and
Fifty Years</hi> (London: Carey P, 1935) facing p. 28. The inscriptions are not reproduced and no mention is
made of Linnell, Blake, or the owner of this rare print.</p>
            <p>“The Morning Amusements of her Royal Highness [and] A Lady in the full Dress,” pp. 239-41.
A previously unrecorded impression of the left image only, “A Lady in the full Dress, &amp; another in the
most fashionable Undress now worn,” 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., is now in the Essick collection—see 
<hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi> under “Letterpress Books with Engravings by
and after Blake,” above, and illus 4.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
