<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
2003</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
		<author n="Sato">Hikari Sato</author>
		<author n="Chang">Ching-erh Chang</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Marsha Keith Schuchard</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <body>
    <pb id="p38-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
2003</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor><lb/>
		  With the Assistance of <docAuthor>Hikari <name>Sato</name></docAuthor> for Publications in Japan and of
<docAuthor>Ching-erh <name>Chang</name></docAuthor> for Publications in Taiwan</byline>
          <div3>
            <p>The annual checklist of scholarship and discoveries concerning William Blake and his circle
records publications and discoveries for the year (say, 2003) and those for previous years which are not
recorded in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995), and
“William Blake and His Circle” (1994-2003). The organization of Division I of the checklist is as in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977):</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <table rows="6" cols="2">
                <row>
                  <cell>Part I:</cell>
                  <cell>Editions, Translations, and Facsimiles of Blake’s Writings<lb/>
Section A: Original Editions, Facsimiles, Reprints, and Translations<lb/>
Section B: Collections and Selections</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part II:</cell>
                  <cell>Reproductions of his Art<lb/>
Section A: Illustrations of Individual Authors<lb/>
Section B: Collections and Selections</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part III:</cell>
                  <cell>Commercial Book Engravings</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part IV:</cell>
                  <cell>Catalogues and Bibliographies</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part V:</cell>
                  <cell>Books Owned by William Blake of London (1757-1827)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part VI:</cell>
                  <cell>Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies<lb/>
Note: Collections of essays on Blake and issues of periodicals devoted entirely to him are listed in one
place; their authors may be recovered from the index.</cell>
                </row>
              </table>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
                  <ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
                  <note id="n1">1. There is nothing in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995) corresponding to Division II: Blake’s Circle.</note>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Division II is organized by individual (say, William Hayley or John Flaxman), with works by
and about Blake’s friends and patrons, living individuals with whom he had significant direct and
demonstrable contact. It includes Thomas Butts and his family, Robert Hartley Cromek, George Cumberland, John
Flaxman and his family, Henry Fuseli, Thomas and William Hayley, John Linnell and his family, Samuel Palmer,
James Parker, George Richmond, Henry Crabb Robinson, Thomas Stothard, John Varley, and Thomas Griffiths
Wainewright. It does <hi rend="i">not</hi> include important contemporaries with whom Blake’s contact was
negligible or non-existent, such as John Constable and William Wordsworth and Edmund Burke. Such major figures
are dealt with more comprehensively elsewhere, and the light they throw upon Blake is very dim.</p>
              <p>Reviews, listed here under the book reviewed, are only for works which are substantially
about Blake, not for those with only, say, a chapter on Blake. The authors of the reviews may be recovered
from the index.</p>
              <p>I take <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>
(1995), faute de mieux, to be the standard bibliographical books on Blake<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> and have noted significant differences from them. 
<note id="n2">2. Except for the states of the plates for Blake’s commercial book engravings, where the standard
authority is Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi>
(1991).</note></p>
              <p>I have made no systematic attempt to record manuscripts and typescripts, audio books and
magazines, broadcasts on radio or television, calendars, CD-ROMs, chinaware,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> comic books, computer printouts, exhibitions without
catalogues, festivals and lecture series, furniture with inscriptions, lipstick,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> microforms, music, pillows, poems, postage stamps, posters,
published scores, recorded readings and singings, rubber stamps, T-shirts, tattoos, video recordings, or
e-mail related to Blake. <note id="n3">3. E.g., the decorated ceramic bowl by Bernard Leach with verses from
Blake round the rim (reproduced in the Kyoto Blake exhibition catalogue [2003] fig. 14).</note>
	<note id="n4">4. See Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2002,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4
(spring 2003): 129.</note></p>
              <p>The status of electronic “publications” becomes increasingly vexing. Some such works seem
to be merely electronic versions of physically stable works, and some suggest no more knowledge than how to
operate a computer, such as reviews invited for the listings of the book sale firm of Amazon.com, which are
divided into those by (1) the author, (2) the publisher, and (3) other, perhaps disinterested, remarkers. In
my experience, they rarely provide more than fool’s gold. For instance, on 3 March 2004 “Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Stranger from Paradise</hi>” (without quotation marks in the search) had 772 Google entries, which
included catalogues (e.g., Tuscaloosa Public Library), academic course prospectuses, curricula vitae, Town
&amp; Country Toy Dog Club of Greater Andover, Karaoke WOW!, and endless offers for sale, while 
“<hi rend="i">Stranger from Paradise</hi>” had 2920 entries. I have not searched for electronic publications, and
I report here only those I have happened upon which appear to bear some authority.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5">5. See for instance entries for 2002 Northwestern exhibition (review); Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Stranger from Paradise</hi> (review); Butlin; Connolly; Essick and Viscomi; Friedlander; Goldberg;
Howie; Kraemer; Lussier; Prickett; Rix.</note></p>
              <pb id="p38-5" n="5"/>
              <p>The chief indices used in compiling this 2003 checklist were <hi rend="i">Art Index</hi>,
Nov. 2000 to Oct. 2001 (2002); <hi rend="i">Bibliografía Española Monografías</hi> 2002 (2003); 
<hi rend="i">Book Review Digest</hi> 98-99 (2003); <hi rend="i">Book Review Index:</hi> A Master Cumulation
1998-2002 (2003); <hi rend="i">Books in Print 2003-2004</hi> ([Sept.] 2003) (under Authors, 45 Blakes, all
cross-references; under Titles, 42 for “Blake, William,” plus others for “William Blake” and Subject);
<hi rend="i">Books in Print Supplement 2002-2003</hi> ([May 2003]) (39); <hi rend="i">British Humanities
Index</hi> for 2002-2003 (only 2); <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> (2003); 
<hi rend="i">Forthcoming Books</hi>: A List of Recently Published Books and Books to Come—October 2003 through
September 2004 (New Providence, New Jersey: R. R. Bowker [Oct.] 2003); <hi rend="i">Modern Language
Association Bibliography</hi> for 2002 (2003) (#4398-4518); <hi rend="i">Whitaker’s Books in Print 2003</hi>
([March 2003]) (107); <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 79 (Covering works published in
1998) (2001), 80 (for 1999) (2001), 81 (for 2000) (2002); and <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in Modern
Language Studies</hi> 60 (for 1998) (1999), 61 (for 1999) (2000), 62 (for 2000) (2001), 63 (for 2001)
(2003).</p>
              <p>I am indebted for help of many kinds to Bel Atreides, Dr. E. B. Bentley, Mr. Martin Butlin,
Professor Ching-erh Chang, the Davies Group Publishers, Dr. D. W. Dörrbecker, Professor Robert N. Essick,
Professor Jean Freed, Professor David Fuller, Ms. Yumiko Goto, Professor Alexander Gourlay, Dr. Francisco
Gimeno Suances, Mr. Ron Heisler, International Specialized Book Services, Ms. Sarah Jones at 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Professor Suzanne Matheson, Mr. Jeff Mertz (our man at the Library of Congress) for
xeroxes, Mr. Paul Miner, Professor Morton D. Paley, the Plough Publishing House, Professor Dennis Read,
Professor Hikari Sato, Mr. James Shaffner, Professor Sheila Spector (for Hebrew works), Professor Warren
Stevenson, and Professor Masashi Suzuki.</p>
              <p>I should be most grateful to anyone who can help me to better information about the unseen
(§) items reported here, and I undertake to thank them prettily in person and in print.</p>
              <p>Research for “William Blake and His Circle, 2003” was carried out in the Bibliotheca La
Solana, Huntington Library, University of Miami Library, University of Toronto Library, and the Toronto Public
Library.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Symbols</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>* Works prefixed by an asterisk include one or more illustrations by Blake or depicting him.
If there are more than 19 illustrations, the number is specified. If the illustrations include all those for a
series by Blake, say for <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> or his illustrations to <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>, the
work is identified.</p>
              <p>§ Works preceded by a section mark are reported on second-hand authority.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <table rows="5" cols="2">
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                  </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell><hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2)</cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Second Edition) (2004)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Butlin</cell>
                  <cell>Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>
(1981)</cell>
                </row>
              </table>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake Publications and Discoveries in 2003</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Blake studies are alive and well in 2003. This checklist records 50 books, 205 essays, and 47
reviews, and certainly there are some which have been overlooked, particularly reviews. The books include 17
editions of Blake’s writings and art, 8 exhibition catalogues of 1919, 2001, 2002, and 2003, and 5
dissertations, from Florida, Hungary, Iowa, Southampton, and Texas.</p>
              <p>The works recorded here come from around the world, not only from English-speaking countries
such as Australia, Britain, Canada, India, and the United States, but from xenophonic countries as well. There
are works in Chinese (15), French (3), German (2), Hebrew (4), Hungarian (2), Italian (3), Japanese (34),
Korean (4), Russian (1), and Spanish (8). The works in Hungarian are supplemented by an English essay in a
Hungarian journal and a book in English which was a Hungarian doctoral dissertation, and there are English
essays in journals in Japan and Taiwan (6).</p>
              <p>The most striking innovation here is in the number of works about Blake from Taiwan. When my
wife and I went to Taiwan in 1970<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> to
work in the National Library for a week, we found, as I recall, no Chinese work by or about Blake, though my
wife, playing hooky, found one work by my mother and several by my father—more, to her disrespectful
delight, than by me. Consequently we spent a wonderful week at the National Palace Museum. <note id="n6">6.
Because of Senator McCarthy and his ilk, it was not convenient to go to China in 1970.</note></p>
              <p>Thirty-four years later, Professor Ching-erh Chang of the National Taiwan University compiled
“William Blake in Taiwan: A Bibliography,” of which he very generously sent me a copy. This includes a
poem by Blake translated in 1960 (omitted below), a translation of Blake in 1966, and 20 publications about
Blake in Taiwan—plus 6 M.A. theses dealing with Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n7">7. Pei-chün Chen, “Blake shire zhong shehui piping zhi yenjiou ji qi yu Yingyu jiaoxue shang
zhi yingyung [A Study of Social Criticism in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> and Its Application to English Teaching],” National Chang-hua Normal University [Taiwan]
(1997), 121 pp., in Chinese (Chapters 1-3 deal with “The Little Black Boy,” “London,” “The Chimney
Sweeper,” “Holy Thursday,” and “The Garden of Love,”; Chapter 4 is how to apply “London” to
English teaching). Beatrice H. C. Hsü, “William Blake Revisited: A Kabalistic Reading,” National
Chung-shan University [Taiwan] (1993), 99 pp. Yün-shan Leu, “Goodness and Evil: Human Nature in Blake’s
and Wordsworth’s Poetry through the Relationship of Innocence and Experience,” National Chung-shan
University [Taiwan] (1992), 95 pp. (it examines how Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and Wordsworth’s 
<hi rend="i">Prelude</hi> and other important works express their views on society and human nature by means of
the contraries of innocence and experience). Ching-hsüan Li, “Innocence and Experience in Blake’s
Poetry,” Chinese Culture University [Taiwan] (1973). Jerry Chia-je Weng, “Re-visioning Milton: William
Blake and the Poetics of Appropriation,” National Taiwan University (2003), 121 pp. Jin-li Xie, “Chastity
and the Feminine in William Blake’s Poetry,” Providence University [Taiwan] (1994), 145 pp. (the context
of mysticism exonerates the feminine in Blake’s archetypes).</note></p>
              <pb id="p38-6" n="6"/>
              <p>A problem arises with the transliterations of works from Taiwan. Recently the Pinyin system
of transliteration, adopted in China in 1949, was introduced in Taiwan. However, it is still customary to give
proper names of Taiwanese authors in the older Wade-Giles system. The same Chinese character for a proper name
may therefore be transliterated differently in Taiwan, in China, and in Japan. This is particularly trying
with family names, which may appear in different places in an alphabetical list according to the system of
transliteration used.</p>
              <p>Other evidence of Blake’s international and polyglottal appeal is the record of Mr. Taro
Nagasaki’s Blake collection, now partly in Kyoto City University of Arts. The collection, formed early in
the twentieth century, consists of 52 books, including a number with Blake’s commercial book illustrations.
At the time it was formed, it was probably the largest collection of Blake’s commercial book illustrations
in Japan—and perhaps it remains so today.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Writings</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>There are relatively few significant discoveries or publications concerning Blake’s
writings.</p>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Original Works</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Newly uncovered sketches for <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> are reported by Robert N. Essick and Rosamund Paice, and a few more details of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> contemporary facsimile (Beta) are recorded by courtesy of
its Toronto owner.</p>
                <p>A couple of well-known works have changed hands. Blake’s letter of 18 January 1808 (A)
has been sold to yet another anonymous collector for a huge price (£40,000), and, on the death of Sir Paul
Getty in 2003, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (P) passed, perhaps permanently, to the
Wormsley Foundation.</p>
                <p>A previously unrecorded copy of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> pl.
2 has surfaced in the collection of Professor Harold Bloom.</p>
                <p>Most excitingly and tantalizingly, Robert N. Essick reports rumors of an unknown copy of
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi> What other treasures remain to be discovered? The copy of 
<hi rend="i">Outhoun</hi> offered for sale about 1828 by Catherine Blake found in a cottage in County Durham? The
huge “Ancient Britons,” lost since 1809, in a loft in rural Wales?</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Reprints and Translations</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>There is a new edition of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, tr. Giora
Leshem (1997) in Hebrew.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Collections and Selections</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>The new editions of Blake’s selected works offer little in the way of solid new knowledge
to Blake students. A few are doubtless useful as introductions to Blake in areas where English is not the
first language, such as <hi rend="i">Blake no kotoba</hi> [<hi rend="i">Aphoristic Words from Blake</hi>], ed.
Soetsu Yanagi (1921) in Japan, a new edition of <hi rend="i">Ol mi-shire blak ve-kits</hi> [<hi rend="i">More
from the Poetry of Blake and Keats</hi>], tr. Joshua Kochav (1980), <hi rend="i">Tenison, robert herik, edgar
alan po, vilyam blak, vilyam ernst henli, heinrikh heine</hi>, tr. Samuel Friedman (1986) in Israel, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: Versek és Próféciák</hi> [<hi rend="i">Poems and Prophecies</hi>], ed. Miklós
Szenczi (1959) in Hungary, and <hi rend="i">Poesía completa:</hi> Versión, prólogo y presentación Francesc
LL. Cardona (1999) in Spain. And it is perhaps worth drawing attention to a work in Catalan which is excluded
from the list below because it is a multi-author anthology: <hi rend="i">William Blake, William Wordsworth,
Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Percy Bysshe Shelley, John Keats: Poesia, veritat i vida</hi>, Presentació i
traducció de Joan Solé (Barcelona: Columna Edicions, Dec. 2001) Clàssics i Moderns Columna, 8°, 248 pp.;
ISBN: 8466401873; its “Notas biogràfiques” includes “William Blake (1757-1827)” (19-28); the Blake
texts from Ostriker consist of <hi rend="i">All Religions are One, There is No Natural Religion</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (61-88), all of course in prose.</p>
                <p>The William Blake Archive (www.blakearchive.org) continues to expand its resources, with
reproductions of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (B), the engraved designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>,
Blake’s watercolors for “On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity” and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>,
a biography, a glossary, and a chronology.</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Art</hi>
                  <ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
                  <note id="n8">8. “Blake’s Art” here includes only unengraved series of illustrations
of the works of others, such as Milton or Gray. For his drawings for his own works in illuminated printing,
see Part I: “Blake’s Writings”; for his drawings for commercial book illustrations, see Part III.</note>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>A handsome new edition of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> with Blake’s drawings is an
agreeable work to handle and own but offers nothing new to the scholar.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Commercial Engravings</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>A textless and one might almost say pointless new edition of the engravings for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1808) appeared.</p>
              <p>Trifling Blake sketches for Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> (1791) and Hayley’s
<hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi> (1802) have been newly uncovered.</p>
              <p>A new copy of Blake’s elusive print for <hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket
Memorandum-Book</hi> (1782) was discovered by David Bindman in an album of fashion plates and has now
<pb id="p38-7" n="7"/>
passed, like so many other fascinating Blake <hi rend="i">disjecta membra</hi>, into the collection of Robert
N. Essick at the Bibliotheca La Solana. No copy of the book itself has yet been discovered.</p>
              <p>The history of Blake’s nineteen watercolors (1805) for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
(1808) rediscovered in 2001 becomes yet more bizarre. From about 1836 to 2001 they were in the collection of
the Stannard family, whose latest heirs in Glasgow lost sight of their significance. They went for a risible
sum as part of a small family library to a Glasgow general second-hand bookstore called Caledonia Books, where
they were apparently taken to be colored engravings—though no engraving for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> colored by Blake is known.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> From Caledonia Books they were acquired, perhaps on approval, for £1,000 by a Yorkshire
bookseller named Paul Williams. All this was discovered by a brilliant journalist named Martin Bailey who
succeeded where all the warranted Blake scholars who had seen the watercolors<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> and tried to trace their history had failed. 
<note id="n9">9. A copy of the quarto Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1808) in the Huntington is skillfully hand
colored, but not by Blake.</note>
	<note id="n10">10. Dr. E. B. Bentley, G. E. Bentley, Jr., Professor David Bindman, Mr. Martin Butlin,
Professor Robert N. Essick, Dr. Robin Hamlyn, Dr. Rosamund Paice, Professor Morton D. Paley.</note></p>
              <p>But the drama does not end there. The Tate, doubtless the most appropriate home for the Blair
watercolors, was given an option to buy the drawings at £2,000,000 (or about £100,000 each), later raised to
£4,200,000 plus £700,000 tax, and started scampering about to raise such a huge sum. At this point, the sale
hung fire while a legal sideshow determined who really owned the designs and on what terms they had or should
have changed hands. When this issue was resolved, the Tate heaved an institutional sigh of relief and
doubtless prepared publicity about acquiring the most sensational Blake find for a century—when they
discovered that the Blair watercolors had been abruptly acquired at a yet larger price by the London dealer
Libby Howie, ostensibly for an unnamed American collector. The latest information is that they are languishing
in a London bank vault, perhaps waiting for a better offer or for permission to export them, a permission
which is unlikely to be granted them without a struggle. In sum, the Blair watercolors have returned almost to
the status quo ante; the existence of the drawings is known, their authenticity (unlike their price) is
unquestioned, and a few have been reproduced, but they are as inaccessible as ever. At least one Blake
scholar’s request to see them has been politely put off sine die.</p>
              <p>It seems that the more expensive Blake’s works become, the less visible they are likely to
be to serious Blake scholars. Fortunately there are many exceptions to this gloomy rule. Long life to the
generous!</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake Catalogues and Exhibitions</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The Huntington held an exhibition of its Blake holdings, with some of its gaps filled in from
the extraordinary collection of Robert N. Essick, who also prepared the exhibition, though—alas!—there was
no catalogue worthy of the institution or the curator.</p>
              <p>The exhibition in Kyoto was short on original works by William Blake, even books with his
commercial engravings, but the catalogue and exhibition were very rich in the history of Blake enthusiasm in
Japan. In this area the catalogue is a major contribution to scholarship, going far beyond <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies in Japan</hi> (1995) and all other works on the subject known to me.</p>
              <p>John Windle produced a catalogue of Blakes with something for every taste and pocketbook,
from obscure reprints to the finest tempera still in private hands, from $3.95 to a price so high it would be
embarrassing to print it (“Price on Request”).</p>
              <p>In 2002 Northwestern University Library held a modest exhibition of books with Blake’s
commercial engravings.</p>
              <p>The Albright-Knox Gallery in Buffalo held a little exhibition of Blake, chiefly 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> and Dante prints, but there was no catalogue.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Books Owned by William Blake the Poet</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The name of William Blake Esq. appears as a subscriber not only in Joseph Thomas’s 
<hi rend="i">Religious Emblems</hi> (1809), but also in a newly discovered prospectus for the work, indicating
that William Blake Esq. had been among the first to subscribe to the book, probably as a result of a private
solicitation among the author’s friends—the poet was certainly a protégé of Joseph Thomas. And the fact
that Thomas’s designer J. Thurston is also dignified by the otherwise unwarranted “Esq.” suggests that
it is the poet-artist William Blake who subscribed to Thomas’s book and not one of the legions of other
William Blakes who lived in London at the time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n11">11. See “My Name is Legion: for we are many’: ‘William Blake’ in London 1740-1830,”
Appendix VI (829-46) of <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2).</note></p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Scholarship and Criticism</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Books</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>No book recorded here compares in novelty or lasting significance to Joseph Viscomi’s 
<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> or E. P. Thompson’s <hi rend="i">Witness against the
Beast</hi>, both of 1993—but then, these are monuments of Blake scholarship, and one should not expect their
ilk annually.</p>
                <p>Of several of the books here I can give no opinion because I have not seen them. Joyce
Townsend, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work</hi> (2003) promises well, for her previous
highly technical work on Blake’s paint media is wonderfully accomplished and original. Shoichi Matsushima,
<hi rend="i">Blake no Shiso to Kindai Nihon: Blake wo Yomu</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Idea of Blake and Modern
Japan: A Reading of Blake</hi>] (2003) and Fumi Nakayama, <hi rend="i">William Blake: 200 Nen go no
Seikimatsu</hi> [<hi rend="i">William Blake: Blake in 2000</hi>] (2001) are inaccessible to me because of my
scandalous ignorance of Japanese.</p>
                <pb id="p38-8" n="8"/>
                <p>Derek Pearsall, <hi rend="i">William Langland, William Blake, and the Poetry of Hope</hi>
(2003), though separately published, is merely the text of a lecture, perhaps chiefly valuable to students of
the Poetry of Hope.</p>
                <p>Dóra Janzer Csikós, <hi rend="i">“Four Mighty Ones Are in Every Man”: The Development
of the Fourfold in Blake</hi> (2003) is a Hungarian doctoral dissertation concerned with “personality
typology” based on physiognomy in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> which may seem exotic to those unfamiliar
with the Szondi test or “system of drives.”</p>
                <p>Saree Makdisi, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Impossible History of the 1790s</hi>
(2003) carefully uses the “varieties of radical ideology” among Blake’s contemporaries (26) to
illuminate with admirable sensitivity Blake’s works of the 1790s, especially <hi rend="i">America.</hi></p>
                <p>John Pierce, <hi rend="i">The Wond’rous Art: William Blake and Writing</hi> (2003) is
concerned with “the way in which the graphic and the oral are used as conceptual fields in Blake’s
works” (27). It is not significantly related to calligraphy or handwriting.</p>
                <p>Nick Rawlinson, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Comic Vision</hi> (2003) makes a
surprisingly strong case that “Blake was a subtle, profound and skilled comic writer” whose “work seems
to pulse with comic energy.” His definition of “comic” focuses upon joy, which gives him surprisingly
wide scope.</p>
                <p>Cristóbal Serra, <hi rend="i">Pequeño diccionario de William Blake</hi> (Caracteres
simbólicos) (§1992), [Second Edition] (2000), is an alphabetical account of hard names in Blake, in
Spanish.</p>
                <p>Frederick Sontag, <hi rend="i">Truth and Imagination: The Universes Within</hi> (1998) is a
“quest for the new vision in which Blake specializes,” especially in Chapter 1, “Exploring the Worlds
within the Mind.”</p>
                <p>Janet Warner, <hi rend="i">Other Sorrows, Other Joys: The Marriage of Catherine Sophia
Boucher and William Blake</hi> (2003) is a cheerful “tapestry of fact and fiction” in which the facts are
carefully reported from the poet’s life and writings and the fiction imports graphic sex, genteel or at
least artistic crime, secret societies, and drugs, with a plausible stress upon banality in Catherine. An
example (264-65) derives from Blake’s letter to Thomas Butts of 2 October 1800:
<q>
William was sitting on the Sea Shore yesterday and had a wonderful Vision. He said that the Light was
reflecting off the Sands, and each particle of light was a Man, and every stone and herb and tree that he saw
was in Human Form, and that finally all Human Forms became One, and he was part of it, and so was I and [his
sister] Cathy, and Mr. Hayley, and Mr. and Mrs. Butts also.<lb/>
I am now baking bread.
</q></p>
                <p>David Weir, <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West: William Blake and the Oriental
Renaissance</hi> (2003) is an earnest and intelligent study of Hinduism as its theological and political
contexts were perceived in London (not in England or “the West”) particularly in the pages of the 
<hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> in the 1790s. The most sensational event in London then was the long drawn-out
trial of Warren Hastings for, among other things, abuse of his power while Governor General of India, and Weir
points out that the trial was, and was widely seen to be, a political issue including attacks on or defense of
colonialism. Some readers of the book may wonder at his confidence or his evidence “that Blake read
[Volney’s] <hi rend="i">The Ruins</hi>” (51) or “that he would have read” “the Gita” (99), but the
political and theological context of Hinduism in the 1790s in London is usefully established.</p>
                <p>There are also new editions (not just reprints) of Ackroyd’s <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1995) in Japanese (2002), of Altizer’s <hi rend="i">New Apocalypse</hi> (1967) with a new appendix on what
he’d do differently this time (2000), and of Muggeridge’s <hi rend="i">Third Testament</hi> (1976) in
2002.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Essays</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>There are in this checklist many reprints in Bloom’s anthology of fragments of Blake
criticism (2003—40 excerpts) and detailed proposals for lectures at the Kyoto Blake Conference
(2003—37)—though the full essays were (or doubtless will be) meritorious. There are collections of essays
in <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves and M. D. Paley (2003—19), 
<hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves (2003—16), and 
<hi rend="i">Taiyoka</hi> (1927—11), plus contemporary directories referring to Blake (43) and records of his
father and brother voting (6) which, oddly, have never appeared in a Blake bibliography before.</p>
                <p>Significant but—alas!—unseen essays on Blake include John Beer, <hi rend="i">Romantic
Consciousness: Blake to Mary Shelley</hi> (2003), which has a section on Blake. And Shoichi Matsushima, Hisao
Ishizuka, Masashi Suzuki, Yoko Ima-Izumi, and Yuko Takahashi, <hi rend="i">Ekkyo suru Geijutsuka—Ima Blake
wo Yomu: William Blake: A Border-Crossing Artist—Reading his Works Now</hi> (2002) seems to be a collection
of Japanese essays on reading Blake.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">The Tools of Scholarship</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Among the most obvious tools of scholarship is finding lists of what is known about the
subject. These include G. E. Bentley, Jr., with the assistance of Dr. Hikari Sato for Japanese publications,
“William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 2002,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.1 (summer 2003): 4-31, which covers all newly discovered publications with Blake in the
title or works about him of more than five consecutive pages, together with all briefer references to Blake
published before 1863, especially those before 1831. These lists are extensive but hardly comprehensive; for
instance, in the present one for 2003, there are works published in 2002 (29), in 1863-2001 (101), in 1831-63
(2), and even the most heavily mined field before 1831 (30), indicating embarrassingly how much had previously
been overlooked.</p>
                <p>A similar but much more comprehensive undertaking is in Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the
Marketplace, 2002,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 116-37. His essay records in wonderful
detail not only original works by Blake and his close friends such as George Cumberland and John Linnell, with
mini-essays in the captions of works reproduced, but also curiosities and rumors of troop movements on the
borders of buying and selling. He seems to know everyone worth knowing in the worlds of Blake and book-,
print-, and picture-selling and to persuade them to give up their dearest secrets. And when his
<pb id="p38-9" n="9"/>
report does not identify a shy vendor or buyer, he probably knows who it is but is too discreet to tell
us.</p>
                <p>Francisco Gimeno Suances, “Notas sobre la difusión, influencia y recepción crítica de
la obra de William Blake en España durante las décadas de 1920 y 1930,” <hi rend="i">Los Papeles Mojados
de río seco</hi> Año 5, no. 6 (2003): 38-45, considerably expands our information about works concerning
Blake in Spain as long ago as the 1920s. The number of Spanish works previously unknown to Blake
bibliographers indicates how difficult it is for the virtual monoglots among us such as myself to read
everything in their field about Blake; even impressively multilingual bibliographers such as D. W. Dörrbecker
seem to have overlooked some of these Spanish publications.</p>
                <p>There are also recorded here surprisingly extensive lists of directories and elections in
which are given the addresses and votes of Blake’s father and brothers, though he himself rarely appears in
the directories, and apparently he never voted, though eligible to do so.</p>
                <p>There are several essays of importance about Blake drawings. Robert N. Essick and Rosamund
A. Paice, “Newly Uncovered Blake Drawings in the British Museum,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3 (winter
2003-04): 84-100, report on nine previously unknown sketches by Blake on the versos of other drawings
discovered when they were dismounted for photography, and Martin Bailey, “From £1,000 to £10 Million in
Two Years for Newly Discovered Blake watercolours,” <hi rend="i">Art Newspaper</hi> online, finds crucial
details of the history of Blake’s nineteen watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> which had
eluded all the Blake scholars panting hard on the trail. Troy Patenaude, “‘The glory of a Nation’:
Recovering William Blake’s 1809 Exhibition,” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 4.1 (2003): 52-63,
discovers crucial details of the arrangement and dimensions of the rooms of Blake’s family home at 28 Broad
Street and from them deduces plausibly the hanging sequence of the pictures exhibited there in Blake’s
private exhibition of 1809-10 and the dimensions of Blake’s long-lost and huge “Ancient Britons.”</p>
                <p>Joseph Viscomi provides a masterful, brief account of Blake’s “Illuminated Printing”
in <hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves (2003), 37-62. And G. E.
Bentley, Jr., “Blake and God in the Garden: The Life of a Myth,” <hi rend="i">Descant</hi> 34.4 (winter
2003): 112-23, musters detailed evidence once again to persuade the credulous of the mythical (i.e., untrue)
character of the story of Blake and Catherine naked in their garden reading <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi>—or climbing trees or dancing.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Critical Essays: The Plums in the Pudding</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>The connection between Blake and Hebrew is surprisingly extensive. Not only are there newly
recorded editions of Blake in Hebrew (1968, 1986, 1997), but there is a new doctoral dissertation on the
subject.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> More accessibly, Sheila A.
Spector, “Blake’s Graphic Use of Hebrew,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.2 (fall 2003): 63-79, discusses how
Blake used the forms of the Hebrew alphabet, particularly aleph. And Ted Holt, “Blake’s ‘Elohim’ and
the Hutchinsonian Fire: Anti-Utopianism and Christian Hebraism in the Work of William Blake,” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism</hi> 9 (2003): 20-36, provides fascinating evidence that “Blake’s reading of the
Pentateuch was undoubtedly coloured by Hutchinsonian interpretations of it.” Investigation of the distant
but tantalizing connection between Hutchinsonians, Thomas Butts, and Epsom might lead the investigation yet
closer to Blake. <note id="n12">12. Rachel Leah Wagner, “‘Words of eternity in human forms’: William
Blake’s Transformation of Styles, Forms, and Genres of the Hebrew Bible in ‘Jerusalem,’” 
<hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 64 (2003): 1294-95A.</note></p>
                <p>Similarly, Ian Balfour, “The Mediated Vision: Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and the
Lines of Prophetic Tradition,” Chapter 6 of his <hi rend="i">The Rhetoric of Romantic Prophecy</hi> (2002),
argues learnedly and persuasively that “Blake engages the Hebraic, Christian, and English prophetic
traditions in a spectacular and highly self-conscious way.” And Robert Ryan, “Blake and Religion,” 
<hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves (2003), 150-68, provides a useful
account of what we know of Blake’s religion based on the distressingly meager evidence.</p>
                <p>In the same collection, David Bindman’s essay on “Blake as a Painter,” 85-109,
provides a confident and comprehensive synopsis which is just what such a <hi rend="i">Companion</hi> calls
for, and Jon Mee, “Blake’s Politics in History,” 133-49, argues once again that “Blake was always a
deeply political writer.”</p>
                <p>Rosamund A. Paice, “Encyclopaedic Resistance: Blake, Rees’s 
<hi rend="i">Cyclopœdia</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> Separate Plate,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.2
(fall 2003): 44-62, suggests “that the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> plate was begun as a commercial plate,”
an hypothesis with fascinating implications.</p>
                <p>In the exceedingly unlikely vehicle of an online undergraduate B.A. thesis (1973, revised
1986), Edward Robert Friedlander, M.D., “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Meaning and Madness,”
argues with distressing or at least surprising plausibility that “Blake’s poetry and paintings present
classic illustrations of the schizophrenic experience. . . . We can look to the schizophrenic experience to
understand Blake’s works.” Dr. Friedlander’s evidence, and his training as a student of literature and
of medicine, make his conclusion worth consideration.</p>
                <p>Blake in the service of somewhat rabid anti-capitalism has been found by Ron
Heisler<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> from the 
<hi rend="i">Christian Socialist</hi> of 1884-85. These consist of: quotation from “Auguries of Innocence” ll.
75-76, 51-52, 81-84, 79-80, 113-18 following but not visibly attached to E. L. Garbett, “Interest” (an
attack on it), <hi rend="i">Christian Socialist</hi> (March 1884): 157; “Holy Thursday” from 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> following but not visibly attached to an excerpt from <hi rend="i">Darkness and
Dawn</hi> in <hi rend="i">Christian Socialist</hi> (July 1884): 27; “Mammon” (i.e., “I rose up at the
dawn of day” [Notebook, p. 89] ll. 1-12, 21-22, 13-18, 25-28), <hi rend="i">Christian Socialist</hi> (Aug.
1884): 37, which may well have been the stimulus for the skillful anonymous poem called “Oh, Mammon, Hear
Us!” (March 1885: 155) parodying a popular hymn; Anon., “In Answer to a Prayer for Light,” 
<hi rend="i">Christian Socialist</hi> (March 1885):
<pb id="p38-10" n="10"/>
254-55, on “the principles of Anarchism” reprinted from <hi rend="i">Liberty</hi> (“Boston, U.S.”),
concluding with a “message . . . sung to us by William Blake”: “I give you the end of a golden thread
[i.e., ‘string’]” [<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl. 77]. Perhaps they appeared on the initiative of the
journal’s founding co-editor J. L. Joynes. <note id="n13">13. In a letter to me. These Blake entries do not
appear in the checklist below because I do not report there incidental excerpts from Blake.</note></p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Roads Not Taken: The Nuts in the Fruitcake</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>A tiresomely perennial issue in Blake studies is the allegation of his Cockneyism. For
instance, a recent critic writes of “the Cockney in which he [Blake] wrote and, no doubt, spoke,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> and the allegation is likely to recur. Is it
relevant to the author of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience?</hi>
	<note id="n14">14. David Punter, “Blake and Gwendolen: Territory, Periphery and the Proper Name,” in 
<hi rend="i">English Romanticism and the Celtic World</hi>, ed. Gerard Carruthers and Alan Rawes (2003)
68.</note></p>
                <p>The answer may depend on which of the changing meanings of “Cockney” is being used. The
term has been variously applied. Over the last half-millennium or so “Cockney” has been used to mean: an
egg; a mother’s darling, a milksop; a wanton townsman; a person born in London within the sound of Bow
bells; a class term of vilification, as in Blackwood’s dismissal of Keats and Leigh Hunt as members of
“The Cockney School of Poetry”; one who loves London inordinately;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">15</ref> and a Humpty Dumpty definition of what I want it to mean. <note id="n15">15.
Definitions 1-5 derive from the <hi rend="i">OED</hi>; 6 is a modern usage, to be found in, for instance,
Ackroyd’s <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi></note></p>
                <p>I hope we may agree that Blake is not “an egg.” Besides, “‘It’s very
provoking,’ Humpty Dumpty said after a long silence, ‘to be called an egg—<hi rend="i">very</hi>!’”
Blake’s contemporaries would not have called him a “milksop,” particularly those who had encountered him
in anger. Nor is “a wanton townsman” more relevant. Blake was certainly not “born within the sound of
Bow bells,” and indeed the place of his birth near Golden Square had not long before 1757 been an area of
some fashion—aristocrats and future prime ministers had been christened as he was at St. James, Piccadilly.
Blake is no more a member of the Cockney School of Leigh Hunt and John Keats than he is of the Lake School of
Wordsworth and Coleridge. In a more common pejorative context, he does not share the “Cockney”
characteristics of gross ignorance of high-culture sophistication, he is not aspirately-challenged, omitting
the “h” sound in “hope” and “how” and wantonly adding it as in “honor” and “hour”—and,
besides, these cultural and linguistic characteristics of “Cockney” are largely anachronistic when applied
to Blake, their widespread use being popularized by Dickens subsequent to Blake’s death.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Blake’s attitude toward London is
devastatingly demonstrated in his “London” with its universal “marks of woe,” in “the terrible
desart of London” and “the manacles of Londons dungeons dark.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">17</ref> And one may speculate on the aptness of “Cockney” as applied to that
great London-lover Dr. Johnson. But I am a sufficient democrat to agree with Humpty Dumpty: “‘When 
<hi rend="i">I</hi> use a word,’ Humpty Dumpty said in a rather scornful tone, ‘it means just what I choose it
to mean, neither more nor less.’” “‘The question is,’ said Humpty Dumpty, ‘which is to be
master—that’s all.’” <note id="n16">16. For a summary of the scholarship here, see <hi rend="i">The
Stranger from Paradise</hi> (2001) 4fn.</note>
	<note id="n17">17. Blake’s letters of 14 and 1 September 1800.</note></p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part I: Blake’s Writings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section A: Original Editions, Facsimiles,</hi>
                        <ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
                        <hi rend="b">Reprints, and Translations</hi>
                        <note id="n18">18. In this checklist, “facsimile” is taken to mean “an exact
copy” attempting very close reproduction of an original named copy including size of image, color of
printing (and of tinting if relevant), and size, color, and quality of paper, with no deliberate alteration as
in page order or numbering or obscuring of paper defects, or centering the image on the page.</note>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Watermarks: A Cumulative Table</p>
                    <p>Addendum</p>
                    <p>fleur-de-lis</p>
                    <p>“The Approach of Doom” (BMPR)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> (1789)</p>
                    <p>Plate 6</p>
                    <p>A new sketch on the verso of the previously known one was reported and reproduced by
Robert N. Essick and Rosamund A. Paice, “Newly Uncovered Blake Drawings in the British Museum,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3 (winter 2003-04): 84-100.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794)</p>
                    <p>Copy a</p>
                    <p>Previously unknown sketches on the versos of pls. 1 and 18 were reported and reproduced
by Robert N. Essick and Rosamund A. Paice, “Newly Uncovered Blake Drawings in the British Museum,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3 (winter 2003-04): 84-100.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> (1794)</p>
                    <p>Copy B</p>
                    <p>History: Reproduced in the William Blake Archive (2003).</p>
                    <p>Edition</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">El Libro de Urizen</hi> (<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>). Ed. and
tr. José Luis Palomares. Edición Facsímil y Bilingüe. (Madrid: Ediciones Hiperión, 2002) 8°, 189 pp.;
ISBN: 8475177379. In Spanish. &lt;§<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                    <p>“Estudio Preliminar: <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>: La creación como catastrofe”
(7-56), color reproduction of copy G, the plates printed back to back (59-86), English transcription and
Spanish translation on facing pages (87-137), “Notas y comentarios” (139-84), “Bibliografía: [3]
Ediciones existentes de <hi rend="i">El Libro de Urizen</hi> en Castallano” (185).</p>
                    <pb id="p38-11" n="11"/>
                    <p><hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> (?1826)</p>
                    <p>Newly Recorded Copy</p>
                    <p>Plate 2</p>
                    <p>History: Sold, with George Richmond’s sketch of Blake on his death bed, by a London
dealer in 1942 to William Inglis Morse, the son of Samuel F. B. Morse the painter and inventor, from whom they
passed to Morse’s son-in-law Professor Frederick Hilles, who gave them about 1955 to Professor Harold Bloom
(from whose letter to me of 22 July 2003 all this information derives).</p>
                    <p>Letters (1791-1829)</p>
                    <p>18 January 1808 to Ozias Humphry (A)</p>
                    <p>History: Offered in Roy Davids’ catalogue (March 2000) of his exhibition at the Fine
Art Society (London) called “<hi rend="i">The Artist as a Portrait</hi>,” #10 (first and last pages
reproduced, £40,000), and sold to an anonymous private collector, according to Robert N. Essick, “Blake in
the Marketplace, 2003,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.4 (spring 2004): 120.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> ([1790])</p>
                    <p>Editions</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> (Maastricht, Holland, 1928) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> # 106/&gt;</p>
                    <p>It was edited by P.N. van Eyck, printed by Joh. Enschedé with Jan van Krimpen’s
Lutetia type, and published by Alexandre Alphonse Marius Stols at his Halcyon Press in 325 copies, “a
brilliant example of their superior craftsmanship,” according to Oskar Wellens, “A Dutch Bibliophile
Edition of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (1928),” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3 (winter
2003-04): 104-07.</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Nisu’e ha-’eden veha-she’ol.</hi> Tr. Giora Leshem. (Tel Aviv:
Eked, 1967/68). In Hebrew. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 100&gt; B. §(Tel Aviv: G. Leshem, 1997).</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">El Matrimonio del Cielo y del Infierno.</hi> Traducción de Soledad
Capurro y prólogo de Luis Cernuda. (Madrid: Visor, 1977). In Spanish. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2002)&gt;</p>
                    <p>The prólogo is reprinted from Luis Cernuda, “William Blake,” 
<hi rend="i">Pensamiento poético en la lírica inglesa (Siglo XIX)</hi> (Mexico [City]: Imprenta Universitaria,
1958).</p>
                    <p>The work was apparently reprinted in <hi rend="i">El Matrimonio del Cielo y del
Infierno y Cantos de Inocencia y de Experiencia</hi>, tr. Soledad Capurro (Madrid, 1979). &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 158&gt;</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783)</p>
                    <p>Newly Recorded Copy</p>
                    <p>Copy Q?</p>
                    <p>History: A previously unknown copy, not corresponding to the only ones in private
hands,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> was evaluated by Ursus Books
(New York), according to Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2003,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.4
(spring 2004): 116-17. <note id="n19">19. Copy E, sold from Pickering &amp; Chatto catalogue 686 [1991], lot
164, to a private American collector, and copy M, the Buxton Forman copy, not traced since it was sold at
Anderson Galleries, 15 May 1920, lot 35.</note></p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> Photographs by Joel-Peter Witkin. Poems by
William Blake. Essay by John Wood. (No place: [Leo &amp; Wolfe Photography, Inc., 2002]) Platinum Series.</p>
                    <p>“Edition of 65 copies,” “Opened at $7500—SOLD OUT—Closed at $15,000,”
“18″ × 15″ and weighs over 14 pounds,” according to <hi rend="i">The Journal of Contemporary
Photography 21st</hi> online.</p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> Photographs by Joel-Peter Witkin. Poems by
William Blake. (No place: Leo &amp; Wolfe Photography, Inc., [2002]) Platinum Series.</p>
                    <p>“65 numbered copies and 5 lettered copies, 10 initialed, bound platinum prints” on
“basswood clamshell box 18″ × 15″ . . . currently $12,000,” “Text by John Wood,” [sic] according
to <hi rend="i">The Journal of Contemporary Photography 21st</hi> online.</p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Copy P</p>
                    <p>History: On the death of Sir Paul Getty on 17 April 2003, the Wormsley Estate and
Library passed to the Wormsley Foundation, perhaps permanently.</p>
                    <p>Contemporary Facsimile</p>
                    <p>Copy Beta</p>
                    <p>By the courtesy of its owner, a new examination was made of the watercolored thin paper
guest leaves (mounted on thick paper host leaves watermarked J Whatman | 1821). A flashlight shining through
the host and guest leaves, the latter extensively colored, revealed the following watermarks on the guest
leaves:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n20">20. Pace <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 132, which says that there is no watermark on the colored
guest leaves.</note></p>
                    <p>EEN | 0 (both “E”s and the “0” uncertain, the “0” under the first
hypothetical “E”) on Pl. 22, first page of “Spring”</p>
                    <p>Pine on Pl. 54, “The Voice of the Ancient Bard”</p>
                    <p>Ruse &amp; on Pl. 15, “Laughing Song”</p>
                    <p>[T]HOMAS on Pl. 12, “The Chimney Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (but
bound in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>)</p>
                    <p>[Tu]rner on Pl. 53, “The School Boy”</p>
                    <p>Blake used paper from the same papermakers for his own works,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> though the paper he used was thick and heavy, unlike the
thin leaves bearing the watercolors for <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> facsimile Beta. <note id="n21">21. According
to the cumulative table of watermarks in paper used by Blake in his writings, drawings, and printing, 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 31.4 (spring 1998): 171-73.</note></p>
                    <pb id="p38-12" n="12"/>
                    <p>Works by Blake using paper with the same watermarks:</p>
                    <p>EDMEADS &amp; PINE in the 1813 printing of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi></p>
                    <p>EEN | 9 in “Three Tabernacles” (1820-25) (Butlin #792) as in J GREEN 1819 in three
Visionary Heads (Butlin #709, 736, 763)</p>
                    <p>Ruse &amp; Turner | 1810 [and 1812 and 1815]</p>
                    <p>THOMAS is not found elsewhere in Blake</p>
                    <p>J WHATMAN | 1821</p>
                  </div7>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section B: Collections and Selections</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Blake no kotoba [Aphoristic Words from Blake].</hi> Ed. Soetsu Yanagi.
                      (Tokyo: <corr type="emend">Sobunkaku,</corr> 1921) 36 reproductions. In Japanese.</p>
                    <p>Selections from Blake’s letters and marginalia, plus a translation by Yanagi [from
English?] of Crabb Robinson’s “William Blake, Kunstler, Dichter und religiöser Schwärmer,” 
<hi rend="i">Vaterländisches Museum</hi> 2 (1811): 107-31.</p>
                    <p>Presumably the book incorporates his “Blake no kotoba,” <hi rend="i">Shirakaba</hi>
[<hi rend="i">White Birch</hi>] 5.7 (July 1914), reprinted (Rinsen Shoten, 1969-72).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Blake shi Xuan [Selections of Blake’s Poems</hi>]. Tr. Wenbin Zhou.
(Taipei: Wuzhou chupan she, 1966). In Chinese.</p>
                    <p>It includes poems from <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (14), <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> (17), <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (15), and others (17).</p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="i">how do we know but ev’ry bird that cuts the airy way, / Is an immense
world of delight clos’d to your senses five? From ‘the marriage of heaven and hell.</hi>’” (London:
Spoon Print Press, 2002).</p>
                    <p>A folded leaf in the shape of a bird with designs by Linda Anne Landers.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">In England’s Green and Pleasant Land.</hi> Illustrated by Julie Haigh.
([No Place:] Bradford and Ilkley Community College, 1986) 4°, 14 loose leaves printed on one side only, in a
portfolio; no ISBN.</p>
                    <p>The “Jerusalem” lyric from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> with “A collection of
illustrations suggested by William Blakes [sic] <hi rend="i">From Milton</hi> [sic] comparing his satirical
comments of the Eighteenth Century dawn of industrialization to the Political climate of England in the
1980’s,” “limited edition of 20” copies.</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">El Matrimonio del Cielo y del Infierno y Cantos de Inocencia y de
Experiencia.</hi> Tr. Soledad Capurro. (Madrid, 1979) Colección Visor de Poesía Vol. 87. B. (Madrid, 1983)
210 pp. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 158&gt;</p>
                    <p>Luis Cernuda, “William Blake” is reprinted from <hi rend="i">Pensamiento poético
en la lírica inglesa (Siglo XIX)</hi> (Mexico [City]: Imprenta Universitaria, 1958).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">El Matrimonio</hi> appeared by itself in 1977. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2002)&gt;</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Mi-shire</hi> [<hi rend="i">From the Poetry of</hi>] <hi rend="i">vilyam
blak.</hi> Tr. Joshua Kochav. (Tel Aviv: Ofir, 1968). In Hebrew.</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Ol mi-shire blak ve-kits</hi> [Duplicate title page: <hi rend="i">More
from the Poetry of Blake and Keats</hi>]. Tr. Joshua Kochav. (Tel Aviv: Ofir, 1980). In Hebrew. &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 159&gt;</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Poesía completa.</hi> Versión, prólogo y presentación Francesc LL.
Cardona. (Barcelona: Edicomunicación, 1999) Colección Cultura, 8°, 286 pp.; ISBN: 847672893X. In
Spanish.</p>
                    <p>“William Blake, Vida y obra” (5-8), “Poesía completa” (9-278) consisting only
of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches, Island in the Moon</hi> (poems only), <hi rend="i">Thel, Tiriel,
Songs</hi>, Rossetti ms. poems, <hi rend="i">French Revolution</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and
Hell.</hi></p>
                    <p>The work seems to be a very slightly altered version of <hi rend="i">Poesía
Completa</hi>, tr. Pablo Mañé Garzón (1984) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt; with the same strange
list of titles (though lacking <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion).</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> (London: Arthur L. Humphreys, 1911) square 12°,
with paper covers (as on the title page) folded over pasteboard. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #155, mistakenly
listed under <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>&gt;</p>
                    <p>Despite the title, the text includes poems from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
and Blake’s Notebook. There are seven charming pasted-on sepia vignettes on india paper, apparently from
18th-century engravings, the initial letter to each poem is printed in red, “A Poison Tree” in 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> (56-57) is entitled “Christian Forbearance” (as in Notebook p. 114), and “A
Cradle Song” (from Notebook p. 114) is inserted in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> without Blake’s
authorization.</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Tenison, robert herik, edgar alan po, vilyam blak, vilyam ernst henli,
heinrikh heine</hi> [Duplicate title page: <hi rend="i">Alfred Tennyson, Robert Herrick, Edgar Allan Poe,
William Blake, William E. Henley, Heinrich Heine.</hi> New Translations into Hebrew]. Tr. Samuel Friedman.
(Tel Aviv: S. Friedman, 1986).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">These Metres Meet: Six Poems by William Blake.</hi> (San Francisco: Pentad
Press, 1975) 4°, 10 pp.</p>
                    <p>The poems are all from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi></p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Videniia strashnogo suda</hi> [<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last
Judgement</hi>]. Tr. V. Chukhno. (Moskva: Eksmo Press, 2002) 8°, 384 pp., 64 reproductions (including 16 from
<hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> and all of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>); ISBN: 5040096712. In Russian.</p>
                    <p>An anthology derived from <hi rend="i">The Portable Blake</hi>, ed. Alfred Kazin
(1946), <hi rend="i">Poems of William Blake</hi>, ed. W. B. Yeats (1978), and <hi rend="i">Poems and
Prophesies</hi> [sic] [ed. Max Plowman] (Everyman, 1927).</p>
                    <p>Preface (7-15), chronology (367-82).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">William Blake: Complete Illuminated Books.</hi> Ed. David Bindman. (2000).
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2001)&gt;</p>
                    <p>Review</p>
                    <p>§G. Ingli James, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 143 (2001): 171.</p>
                    <pb id="p38-13" n="13"/>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Selected by Peter Butter. (Penguin, 1996). B.
(London: Phoenix Poetry, 2003) 8°, [vi], 144 pp.; ISBN: 0753816555.</p>
                    <p>In 2003 there is no preface, notes, index, reproduction, or acknowledgements, though
there is a “Chronology of Blake’s Life and Times” ([150-53]).</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">William Blake: Versek és Próféciák</hi> [<hi rend="i">Poems and
Prophecies</hi>]. Ed. [and tr.?] Miklós Szenczi. (Budapest: Európa, 1959). In Hungarian.</p>
                    <p>William Blake Archive (www.blakearchive.org)</p>
                    <p>They announce the additions of a biography of Blake by Denise Vultee and the editors,
with 109 reproductions; Alexander S. Gourlay, glossary of Blake terms,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n22" type="note">22</ref> chronology of Blake’s life and works; <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (B); the
engravings for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1808) and Blake’s own engraving of “Death’s Door”;
Blake’s designs to Milton’s “On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity” (Thomas set in the Whitworth
Gallery, Manchester); and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained.</hi>
	<note id="n22">22. See also Alexander Gourlay, “A Glossary of Terms, Names, and Concepts in Blake,”
272-87 of <hi rend="i">Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves (2003).</note></p>
                  </div7>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part II: Reproductions of Drawings and Paintings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section A: Illustrations of Individual Authors</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>John Milton, “On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity” The drawings were reproduced
in the William Blake Archive.</p>
                    <p>John Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>: A Poem in Twelve Books with a Preface by Peter
Ackroyd, an Introduction by John Wain and Illustrations by William Blake. (London: The Folio Society, 2003)
4°, no ISBN.</p>
                    <p>Ackroyd’s “Preface” (ix-x) is about Milton and Blake, Wain’s introduction about
Milton. The reproductions are from the larger, Butts set (Butlin #536).</p>
                    <p>John Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi></p>
                    <p>The drawings were reproduced in 2003 in the William Blake Archive.</p>
                  </div7>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section B: Selections and Collections</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Yuzhou, zaichuangzaozhe: Blake</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Re-Creator of the
Universe: Blake</hi>]. Ed. Yüngfen Hu. (Taipei: Kelin guoji tushu gongsi [Greenland International Books Co.
Ltd], 2001) Yishu tashi shiji hualang [Century Art Gallery of Great Masters] 49. In Chinese.</p>
                    <p>It consists of a brief biography and 32 reproductions in color, apparently translated
from Japanese (original © 2000 by DeAgostini UK Ltd., Japanese/Chinese translation © 2000 by Greenland
International).</p>
                    <p>Yishu tashi shiji hualang is a series (100 volumes) with one volume per
“Master.”</p>
                  </div7>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part III: Commercial Book Engravings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808 . . .)</p>
                  <p>Blair, Robert. THE | Grave, | <hi rend="i">A Poem</hi> | <hi rend="i">Illustrated by
twelve Etchings</hi> | Executed | <hi rend="i">BY</hi> | Louis Schiavonetti | <hi rend="i">from the
Original</hi> | Inventions | <hi rend="i">OF</hi> | <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> | 1808. D. [Ackermann
imprint 1813 (i.e., Camden Hotten, 1870)].</p>
                  <p>New Locations: A or B (1808) University Art Museum (Kyoto City University of Arts); D
(1870) G. E. Bentley, Jr. (portfolio of engravings only, no text, in a cover blind-stamped with designs
identical to those on the GEB copy of the Hotten 1870 facsimile, the prints with the same variants of
lettering [replacing the Spanish of 1826] as in 1870, e.g., “Tis” [lacking the apostrophe] in the
quotation for pl. 7, “The descent of Man”).</p>
                  <p>The Blair engravings (1808) and the separate print of “Death’s Door” engraved by
Blake were added to the William Blake Archive in 2003.</p>
                  <p>Drawings</p>
                  <p>History: Blake made “a set of 40 drawings from Blair’s poem of the Grave 20 of which
he [Cromek] proposes [to] have engraved by the Designer and to publish them” (according to Flaxman’s
letter of 18 October 1805); Cromek bought twenty drawings for £21 (according to his letter to Blake of May
1807), commissioned Louis Schiavonetti to engrave them, and published them in 1808; after Cromek’s death in
1812 the drawings, copperplates, and copyright passed to his widow Elizabeth Hartley Cromek, who promptly sold
the copperplates and copyright for £120<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">23</ref> to Ackermann (who published the prints in 1813 and 1826); she vainly offered the
watercolors on 3 February 1813 to William Roscoe “with other curious Drawings of his, valued at thirty
Pounds and likely to sell for a great deal more if ever the man should die”; the Blair watercolors were sold
at C. B. Tait’s auction in Edinburgh with the property of Thomas Sivright of Meggetland, 10 February 1836,
Lot 1835 (“Volume of Drawing, by Blake Illustrative of Blair’s Grave, entitled ‘Black Spirits and White,
Blue Spirits and Grey’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref>), for
£1.5.0; acquired by John Stannard (1794-1882), watercolor artist of Bedford, from whom it passed to his son
Henry John Stannard (1840-1920), watercolor artist, thence to his grandson Henry John Sylvester Stannard
(1870-1951), and from him to John’s great-grandson, “and then a
<pb id="p38-14" n="14"/>
nephew in Glasgow”,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> “The
portfolio was finally sold [as colored prints] in 2000, as part of a small family library, to Caledonia Books,
a general second-hand bookshop in Glasgow . . . run by Maureen Smillie” who offered them at £1,000; in
April 2001 the portfolio was acquired by Dr. Paul Williams of Fine Books, Ilkley, Yorkshire, who associated
Jeffrey Bates of the Leeds bookshop of Bates &amp; Hindmarch with the purchase; the portfolio was offered for
£2,000,000 (later raised to £4,200,000 plus £700,000 tax) to the Tate, but the sale was held up by a
lawsuit initiated by Caledonia Books (claiming that the portfolio had not been purchased but simply taken on
approval); the suit was resolved when Messrs. Williams and Bates agreed to share the profits with Caledonia
Books, and the portfolio was abruptly sold through Libby Howie to an unidentified buyer in the United States,
though in November 2003 the drawings remain in a bank vault in London. <note id="n23">23. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>
(2) 315.</note>
	<note id="n24">24. This title was not with the designs when they were rediscovered in 2001.</note>
	<note id="n25">
                                            25. Martin Bailey, “From £1,000 to £10 Million in Two Years
for Newly Discovered Blake Watercolours,” <hi rend="i">Art Newspaper</hi>, which I have seen only online at
&lt;http://www.theartnewspaper.com/news/article.asp?idart=11037&gt;; this is the source for all the Stannard
provenance and some details of the sales in 2001-03.
                                            <p>See also entries for Karin Goodwin; Anon., “Lost Blake
Paintings Fetch £5m . . .”; Anon., “Blake Paintings May Leave UK . . .,”; Will Bennett; and Anon.,
“Collector Buys Lost Blake Paintings for £5 Million . . . .”</p></note></p>
                  <p>Edition</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Grave: A Poem Illustrated by Twelve Etchings</hi> (1808). [picture of
pierced heart] William Blake: Louis Schiavonetti. ([no place:] Kessinger Publishing’s Rare Mystical Reprints
[?2003]) 4°, plus 42 blank leaves.</p>
                  <p>There is no title page or text of Blair, but it includes reproductions of the engravings,
“To the Queen” and “Of the Designs.”</p>
                  <p>Jacob Bryant, <hi rend="i">A New System, or An Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi>
(1774-75)</p>
                  <p>Edition</p>
                  <p>§(New York: Garland, 1979)</p>
                  <p>George Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> (1796) New Location:
Bibliothèque nationale.</p>
                  <p>Erasmus Darwin, <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> (1791) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#450&gt; Plate 1, “The Fertilization of Egypt”: A new sketch (of the sistrum only) on the verso of the
previously known one was reported and reproduced by Robert N. Essick and Rosamund A. Paice, “Newly Uncovered
Blake Drawings in the British Museum,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3 (winter 2003-04): 84-100.</p>
                  <p>William Hayley, <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi> (1802)</p>
                  <p>The drawing of “The Resurrection” with sketches on the verso related to the 
<hi rend="i">Designs</hi> (1802) was offered in Agnew’s <hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition
of Watercolours &amp; Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March 2003, lot 17, for £260,000, according to Robert N. Essick,
“Blake in the Marketplace, 2003,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.4 (spring 2004): 119.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi>, For the Year of our
Lord 1783 ([1782])</p>
                  <p>&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #479, <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 232-34&gt;</p>
                  <p>A copy of Blake’s engraving of <hi rend="i">“A Lady in the full Dress, &amp; another
in the most fashionable Undress now worn,”</hi> [T]S del, W.B. sc, is in an oblong octavo nonce collection
of 18th and early 19th-century fashion plates pasted in chronological order on both sides of stiff,
unwatermarked paper acquired in 2003 by Robert N. Essick.</p>
                  <p>Edward Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Bibliothèque nationale; University Art Museum (Kyoto City University of
Arts).</p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part IV: Catalogues and Bibliographies</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>1919</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">“Shirakaba bijutsukan” setsuritsu no tame ni: William Blake fukusei
hanga tenrankai mokuroku</hi> [<hi rend="i">An Annotated Catalogue of an Exhibition of Reproductions from the
Works of William Blake: For the Establishment of Shirakaba Art Museum</hi>]. (1919). In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>§Oro Akabane, [Brief essay on the Japanese Blake exhibition. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#611&gt;] <hi rend="i">Chijo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Earth</hi>] Year 1, no. 3 (Dec. 1919). In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>1983</p>
                  <p>Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi>
(1983). &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 301&gt;</p>
                  <p>For new information on Blake’s separate plates, see Essick, “Blake in the
Marketplace, 2002,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 137 (appendix).</p>
                  <p>9 November 2000-11 February 2001; 27 March-24 June 2001</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> (London: Tate Publishing, 2000).</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>§*A. MacAdam, “William Blake: Metropolitan Museum of Art,” <hi rend="i">Art
Newspaper</hi> 100 (June 2001): 128.</p>
                  <p>§Carter Ratcliff, <hi rend="i">Art in America</hi> 89 (2001): 116-23.</p>
                  <p>§Barthélemy Jobert, <hi rend="i">Revue de l’art</hi> 132 (2001): 87 (with Michael
Phillips, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Songs). In French.</p>
                  <p>§Jadviga M. da Costa Nunes, “Visionaries, Realists, and Reformers: Exploring the
Creative Impulse in Nineteenth-Century Art,” <hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century Studies</hi> 16 (2002):
157-79.</p>
                  <p>15 October 2001-14 January 2002</p>
                  <p>§Régis Michel. <hi rend="i">La peinture comme crime</hi>: ou, la part maudite de la
modernité. Musée du Louvre, Hall Napoléon. (Paris: Éditions de la Réunion des musées nationaux, 2001)
ISBN: 2711843084. In French.</p>
                  <p>There are sections on Blake (“Blake ou le mal(e) absolu”), Fuseli, Goya, and Romney,
inter alia.</p>
                  <pb id="p38-15" n="15"/>
                  <p>March-May 2002</p>
                  <p>*Scott Krafft. <hi rend="i">The Commercial Mr. Blake</hi>: William Blake as Book
Illustrator and Copy Engraver: An Exhibition at the Charles Deering McCormick Library of Special Collections,
Northwestern University Library March-May 2002. ([Evanston, Illinois: Northwestern University Library, 2002])
A leaf 35.4 × 21.5 cm. folded in three.</p>
                  <p>A flier contrasting Blake’s “remarkably unmarketable dreamworlds of his prophetic
illuminated books” with the “‘commercial’ works . . . after his own designs” exhibited here,
including Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805), Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797), <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, and Blake’s
separate portrait of Lavater.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Wendy Leopold, “Presenting the Commercial Mr. Blake,” <hi rend="i">Northwestern
University Observer online</hi> 18.5, 24 Oct. 2002
&lt;http://www.northwestern.edu/univ-relations/observer/stories/10_24_02/ blake.html&gt; (says the exhibition
was October-21 December 2002).</p>
                  <p>19 January-25 May 2003</p>
                  <p>*[Robert N. Essick.] <hi rend="i">Vision and Verse: William Blake at The Huntington.</hi>
Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Mary Lou and George Boone Gallery, January 19-May
25, 2003.</p>
                  <p>A sampling of captions from the 198 entries [33 from the collection of Robert Essick];
there was no separate catalogue.</p>
                  <p>Notices, Reviews, etc.</p>
                  <p>*Robert N. Essick, “Showcasing Blake’s Vision and Verse: Major Exhibit Captures
Essence of Renowned Artist/Poet,” <hi rend="i">Calendar</hi> [of] The Huntington Library, Art Collections,
and Botanical Gardens, January-February 2003: 2-3.</p>
                  <p>Anon., “Around Pasadena: Blake Works Exhibit to Open at Huntington Library,” 
<hi rend="i">Pasadena Star-News</hi> 2 Jan. 2003.</p>
                  <p>*Leah Ollman, “He Set Imagination Free: William Blake’s complex metaphysics inspired
ridicule in his lifetime. But for artists today, he simply inspires,” <hi rend="i">Los Angeles Times</hi> 19
Jan. 2003: E56.</p>
                  <p>There are separate sections with comments about Blake by the artists DeLoss McGraw
(Blake’s “best work is embarrassing,” therefore good), Tom Knechtel (“Blake is how I think”), Nancy
Jackson “He . . . went into the darkness, the unknown . . . and he sent back messages that we can all learn
from”), and Sharon Ellis “It’s this clarity of vision . . . that continues to startle”).</p>
                  <p>Anon., “William Blake at The Huntington,” <hi rend="i">Sierra Madre Weekly</hi> 30
Jan. 2003 (entirely paraphrased from the captions).</p>
                  <p>*Martin S. Gonzalez, “Experience ‘Vision and Verse,’” <hi rend="i">Pasadena
Star-News</hi> 13 Feb. 2003: 31-32 (198 works were on display, including 33 from the Essick collection).</p>
                  <p>Matt Bamberg, “One-Tank Trip: A Taste of Europe at the Elegant Huntington,” 
<hi rend="i">Palm Springs Desert Sun</hi> 16 Feb. 2003.</p>
                  <p>15 March 2003-25 January 2004</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">A Private Passion: 19th-Century Paintings and Drawings from the Grenville
L. Winthrop Collection, Harvard University.</hi> [An exhibition at the Musée des Beaux-Arts, Lyon, March
15-May 26, 2003; National Gallery, London, June 25-September 14, 2003; and Metropolitan Museum of Art, New
York, October 23, 2003-January 25, 2004.] Ed. Stephan Wolohojian with the assistance of Anna Tahinci. ([New
Haven:] Yale University Press; [New York:] Metropolitan Museum of Art, 2003) 4°, ISBN: 1588390764.</p>
                  <p>David Bindman, “William Blake” (338); the Blakes are #144-54, and #171-74 are Flaxman
drawings for Dante, <hi rend="i">The Odyssey</hi>, and Aeschylus.</p>
                  <p>27 November-27 December 2003</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">The Glad Days in the Reception of Blake in Japan</hi>: The International
Blake Conference “Blake in the Orient”: A Concurrent Exhibition [27 November-27 December 2003 at Kyoto
University Museum]. Organized by Masashi Suzuki and Steve Clark. (Kyoto: Blake Conference Committee, 2003)
4°, ii, 93pp., no ISBN. In English (1-53, 93) and Japanese (54-92).</p>
                  <p>Masashi Suzuki and Steve Clark, “Preface.” 1-2, 54.</p>
                  <p>Sori Yanagi, “Message.” 3, 55. About his father.</p>
                  <p>*Anon. “The Glad Days in the Reception of Blake in Japan.” 5-6, 56. “Our Exhibition
aims to show how Blake was received in the early period of his introduction into Japan, mainly through
documents.”</p>
                  <p>Kozo Shioe, “On the ‘[Taro] Nagasaki Collection.’” 7-9, 57-59.</p>
                  <p>His 52 Blakes went mostly to Kyoto City University of Arts.</p>
                  <p>The catalogue entries, first in English and then in Japanese, are by Kozo Shioe and
Yumiko Goto. Each section begins with a short essay.</p>
                  <p>Part I consists of “Japan’s Encounter with Blake,” subdivided into “Master
Writers of the Meiji Period and Blake” (11-14, 65), “The Introduction of Blake’s Art by Soetsu Yanagi
and the Shirakaba Group” (15-20, 66-68), “Blake Exhibitions Organized by <hi rend="i">Shirakaba</hi>”
(21-25, 69-70), and “The Development of Blake Reception and the 100<hi rend="s">th</hi> Anniversary of the
Death of Blake” (26-37, 71-77).</p>
                  <p>Part II, “Japanese Blakeans,” consists of “Ryusei Kishida and the Artists of the
<hi rend="i">Shirakaba</hi> Group” (38-45, 78-81), “Kagaku Murakami and <hi rend="i">Kokuga Sosaku
Kyokai</hi>” (46-50, 81-82), and “Blake Collector: Taro Nagasaki” (51-53, 83-84).</p>
                  <p>See also entry below for <hi rend="i">The International Blake Conference</hi> (2003).</p>
                  <p>2003</p>
                  <p>Jarndyce Catalogue 155: <hi rend="i">The Romantics</hi>: Part One: Byron, Blake, Bowles,
Campbell, Clare, &amp; Other Authors A-C. (London, [autumn 2003]) 8°, 818 lots.</p>
                  <p>The Blakes are #1-24.</p>
                  <p>2003</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">John Windle Catalogue Thirty-Six.</hi> (San Francisco: John Windle,
[October] 2003) 4°, iv, 88 pp.; no ISBN.</p>
                  <p>403 Blake entries at $3.95 to $68,750 and “Price on application,” including his
tempera of “The Virgin Hushing the Young John the Baptist” (1799), <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1808, 1813, 1870) (6 copies), and Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Surinam</hi> (1796) with
contemporary coloring.</p>
                </div6>
                <pb id="p38-16" n="16"/>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part V: Books Owned by William Blake of London (1757-1827)</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Joseph Thomas, <hi rend="i">Religious Emblems</hi> (1809) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#746&gt;</p>
                  <p>“William Blake, Esq.” also appears in the prospectus for the book:
<q>
§<hi rend="i">Proposals for Publishing by Subscription a Series of Engravings on Wood, from Scriptural
Subjects in the Manner of Quarles’s Emblems . . . after the design[s] of J. Thurston Esq. and Executed by
the most eminent engravers on wood</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n26">26. A copy is in <hi rend="i">Religious Emblems</hi> in Glasgow University Library: SM
1853.</note></q>
Notice that the designer is identified as “<hi rend="i">J. Thurston Esq.</hi>,” making it seem more likely
that “William Blake, Esq.” is the poet and designer, despite the unusual honorific.</p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part VI: Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>*Ackroyd, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 1996)&gt;
B-C. (1996, 1997) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 1998)&gt; D. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Dichter, Maler,
Visionär.</hi> Tr. Thomas Eichhorn. (2001). In German. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt; E. *<hi
rend="i">Blake den</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Life of Blake</hi>]. Tr. Masayuki Ikeda, Hachisu Izumi, Shigeru Ito,
and Masayuki Takakura. (Tokyo: Misuzu Shobo, 2002) 468 pp., 105 plates; ISBN: 462047187. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>§Alfred Nemeczek, <hi rend="i">Art: Das Kunstmagazin</hi> (Jan. 2001): 114 (review of
the German edition, in German).</p>
                  <p>Altizer, Thomas J. J. *<hi rend="i">The New Apocalypse: The Radical Christian Vision of
William Blake.</hi> ([Lansing:] Michigan State University Press, 1967) 8°, xxi, 226 pp. &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #807&gt; B. (Aurora, Colorado: Davies Group Publishers, 2000) Philosophical and Cultural
Studies in Religion, 8°, ix, 221 pp; ISBN: 1088570563.</p>
                  <p>According to Altizer’s new “Afterword” (201-09 of the 2000 edition), the chief
changes needed in the book are taking into account the “proliferating” Blake scholarship and criticism;
the integral relationship of “Blake’s vision and the Christian epic tradition”; and the
“extraordinarily complex” nature of “Blake’s relationship to Gnosticism” (201, 204).</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Blake Paintings May Leave UK: The future of a set of watercolours by William
Blake remains uncertain as the foreign buyer decides whether to take them abroad.” <hi rend="i">BBC
News</hi> 13 May 2003 and &lt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/arts/3024811.stm&gt;.</p>
                  <p>About the Blair watercolors.</p>
                  <p>§Anon. “Collector Buys Lost Blake Paintings for £5 Million.” <hi rend="i">Sunday
Telegraph</hi> 27 April 2003.</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Illustrious Corner in Soho: The House Where Blake Was Born 200 Years Ago.” 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> 14 Nov. 1957: 3.</p>
                  <p>A sign-writer is on the ground floor and a “waistcoat tailor” is on the next floor up
a “very narrow stairway.”</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Lost Blake Paintings Fetch £5m: A clutch of William Blake watercolours which
were found in a second-hand bookshop have sold for £5m.” <hi rend="i">BBC News</hi> 19 Feb. 2003 and
&lt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/arts/2781267.stm&gt;.</p>
                  <p>About the sale of the Blair watercolors to an overseas buyer.</p>
                  <p>*Anon. (Gongghuo shibao bianjibu [Editorial Section].) “William Blake hua Shangdi
Chuangzao tiandi [William Blake Illustrating God’s Creation of the World].” <hi rend="i">Zhongguo
shibao</hi> [<hi rend="i">China Times</hi>, Taipei] 20 March 2001: 73 (Literary Supplement). In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>A reproduction of “The Ancient of Days” provided by Dapeng Kao with an essay: “She
de zhuan [Biography of the Snake].”</p>
                  <p>§Ansari, A. A. “Double Perspective of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Aligarh Critical Miscellany</hi> 10.2 (1997): 55-85.</p>
                  <p>On time and eternity.</p>
                  <p>§Ansari, A. A. <hi rend="i">“The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.” Aligarh Critical
Miscellany</hi> 11.1 (1998): 30-44.</p>
                  <p>Ansari, A. A. “Obituary.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Critical Miscellany</hi> 12.2 (2000
[Autumn 2003]): i-ix.</p>
                  <p>On Kathleen Raine (d. 6 July 2003), dealing largely with her work on Blake and quoting
letters from her to Ansari about Blake.</p>
                  <p>§Aquien, Pascal. “Blake et la question du sujet: L’Exemple d’‘Introduction,’
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi>” 251-63 of <hi rend="i">Modernité et Romantisme.</hi> Ed. Isabelle
Bour, Eric Dayre, and Patrick Née. (Paris: Champion, 2001) Colloques, Congrès et Conférences sur la
Littérature Comparée, 7. In French.</p>
                  <p>*Bailey, Martin. “From £1,000 to £10 Million in Two Years for Newly Discovered Blake
Watercolours: A set of 19 watercolours by William Blake was sold to a Glasgow bookshop for a pittance in 2000.
It was then recognized and sold to an overseas collector. An export licence deferral is now expected and Tate
would like to acquire it.” <hi rend="i">Art Newspaper</hi> online 2003
&lt;http://www.theartnewspaper.com/news/article.asp?idart=11037&gt;.</p>
                  <p>An account full of original matter about the ownership and sale of Blake’s watercolors
for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Balfour, Ian. “The Mediated Vision: Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and the Lines of
Prophetic Tradition.” Chapter 6 (127-72, 307-17) of his <hi rend="i">The Rhetoric of Romantic Prophecy.</hi>
(Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2002) &lt;§<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <pb id="p38-17" n="17"/>
                  <p>An impressive and learned essay arguing that “Blake engages the Hebraic, Christian, and
English prophetic traditions in a spectacular and highly self-conscious way” (128).</p>
                  <p>§Beer, John B. “Blake’s Fear of Non-Entity.” 12-20 of his <hi rend="i">Romantic
Consciousness: Blake to Mary Shelley.</hi> (New York and London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2003).</p>
                  <p>*Bennett, Will (art sales correspondent). “Collector Buys Lost Blake Paintings for
£5m.” <hi rend="i">Telegraph</hi> 19 February 2003 &lt;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=%2Fne
ws%2F2003%2F02%2F19%2Fnblake19.xml&gt;.</p>
                  <p>About the Blair watercolors.</p>
                  <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Blake and God in the Garden: The Life of a Myth.” 
<hi rend="i">Descant</hi> 34.4 (winter 2003): 112-23.</p>
                  <p>Evidence that “the story of Blake and his wife naked in the garden is not true”
(118).</p>
                  <p>*Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William
Blake.</hi> (New Haven and London: Published for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art by Yale
University Press, [April 2001]) 8°, xxvii, 532 pp., 182 illustrations; ISBN: 0300089392. B. (2003) ISBN:
0300100302 (paperback).</p>
                  <p>The paperback is a reprint with only trifling changes, chiefly the omission of the
gorgeous endpapers and the addition of information about the newly discovered Blair drawings (483).</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Paul Miner, <hi rend="i">Albion</hi> 34.4 (winter 2002): 661-63. (A “superlative
work” with a “tight focus,” “lucid, highly interesting, and sometimes touching”; “No other
biography on Blake stands this tall” [662, 662, 661].)</p>
                  <p>Andrew Elfenbein, “Recent Studies in the Nineteenth Century,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
English Literature 1500-1900</hi> 42.4 (2002): 837-903. “While Bentley’s book is definitive in the amount
and accuracy of the information it presents, it is not easy to get from it a sense of Blake’s inner life and
development”; with “136 plates of high quality,” it gives “an excellent visual summary of Blake’s
art” [846].)</p>
                  <p>Dóra Janzer Csikós, <hi rend="i">Anachronist</hi> (2002) online
&lt;http://www.insitegrafx.hu/theanachronist/html/2002/csikos.html&gt;. “A masterfully documented
biography,” “affectionately written” and “beautifully illustrated.”)</p>
                  <p>§Alexander Gourlay, <hi rend="i">BARS Bulletin and Review</hi> no. 23 (March 2003):
25-27.</p>
                  <p>Anon., <hi rend="i">Independent on Sunday</hi> 13 April 2003. (A “perceptive and
forceful study” which recognizes that “Blake’s genius was above all pictorial.”)</p>
                  <p>Shernaz Cana, <hi rend="i">Aligarh Critical Miscellany</hi> 12.2 (2000 [Autumn 2003]):
201-08. “William Blake has been brought alive before us in such an inspired way that it almost seems that
the biographer too has been included in Blake’s great visionary company.”)</p>
                  <p>Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3 (winter 2003-04): 107-11. (The book is “the
most useful and reliable guide to Blake’s life,” “an epitome of scholarship” exhibiting remarkable
“sensitivity to tone and content,” “a glorious capstone to his [Bentley’s] labors” [108].)</p>
                  <p>Judith Mueller, “Blake in the New Millennium,” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi> 36.2 (2003): 294-99, esp. 295, 298-99 (with Christopher Z. Hobson, <hi rend="i">Blake and
Homosexuality</hi>, Sheila A. Spector, <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”</hi> and “<hi rend="i">Glorious
incomprehensible</hi>,” and Nicholas M. Williams, <hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William
Blake</hi>). “This monumental work” is “simply beautiful”; it “performs an alchemical transformation
of cold facts into flesh and blood” [299, 298].)</p>
                  <p>§Bindman, David. Essay on “The Virgin Hushing the Young Baptist.” Artemis Fine Arts
“Review 2002” 31-33.</p>
                  <p>§Bindman, David. “Blake and Ossian.” 3-7 of <hi rend="i">Songs of Ossian:
Festschrift in Honour of Professor Bo Ossian Lindberg.</hi> (Helsinki, 2003) Taidehistoriallisia
tutkimuksia/Konsthistoriska studier, 27.</p>
                  <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Volume 36, no. 4 (Spring [April] 2003)</p>
                  <p>*Robert N. Essick. “Blake in the Marketplace, 2002.” 116-37. (A customarily
magisterial survey, with an appendix [137] on new information for his catalogue of <hi rend="i">The Separate
Plates of William Blake</hi> [1983].)</p>
                  <p>W. H. Stevenson. “The Sound of ‘Holy Thursday.’” 137-40. (About the music played
at the ceremony in St Paul’s.)</p>
                  <p>Wayne C. Ripley. “Erdman’s Pagination of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” 140-43.
(The renumbering of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> pp. 19-21, 87-90, 105-16 in the Erdman-Magno reproduction [1987] is
followed “inconsistently” in the text and ignored “completely” in the notes to Erdman’s edition of
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose</hi> [1988], so Ripley provides four tables of corrections to the
<hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Jason Snart. Review of Kathleen Lundeen, <hi rend="i">Knight of the Living Dead: William
Blake and the Problem of Ontology</hi> (2000). 144-48. (The book is “most valuable” for its “analysis of
Blake’s use of metaphor and rhetorical devices” [146].)</p>
                  <p>Eugenie R. Freed. Review of Barbara Lachman, <hi rend="i">Voices for Catherine Blake</hi>
(2000). 149-51. (This “fictionalized autobiography” in a “diversity of narrative voices” is “only
intermittently successful”; Lachman “should at least get the historical parameters right.”)</p>
                  <p>Newsletter</p>
                  <p>Anon. 151. (Mostly an invitation to “visit the newsletter section of our web site at
www.blakequarterly.org.”)</p>
                  <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Volume 37, no. 1 (Summer [July] 2003)</p>
                  <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., with the assistance of Dr. Hikari Sato for Japanese publications.
“William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 2002.” 4-31. “Blake
<pb id="p38-18" n="18"/>
studies are impressively and increasingly international and polyglot” [5].)</p>
                  <p>*David Duff. “Muir’s Facsimiles and the Missing <hi rend="i">Visions.</hi>” 32-34.
(He reproduces an “Extra plate in the Aberdeen copy, showing Muir’s [watercolored ms.] rendition of a
detail from ‘The Ancient of Days.’”)</p>
                  <p>Alexander S. Gourlay. “‘Man on a Drinking Horse’: A Print by Thomas Butts, Jr.”
35-36. (A newly discovered work by Blake’s student, printed c. 1942.)</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Nelson Hilton. Review of K. E. Smith, <hi rend="i">An Analysis of William Blake’s Early
Writings and Designs to 1790</hi> (1999). 36-38. “Some useful contextualization notwithstanding, this effort
does not live up to its claim to offer ‘An Analysis’” [38].)</p>
                  <p>Margaret Storch. Review of Christopher Z. Hobson, <hi rend="i">Blake and
Homosexuality</hi> (2000). 38-39. “Hobson’s book opens up the important topic of Blake and homosexuality
as never before [showing] Blake’s empathy with male homosexuality” [39].)</p>
                  <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Volume 37, no. 2 (Fall [October] 2003)</p>
                  <p>*Rosamund A. Paice. “Encyclopaedic Resistance: Blake, Rees’s 
<hi rend="i">Cyclopœdia</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> Separate Plate.” 44-62. (She suggests “that
the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> plate was begun as a commercial plate, and that it may have been more than just
a by-product of the Rees commission” [60].)</p>
                  <p>*Sheila A. Spector. “Blake’s Graphic Use of Hebrew.” 63-79. “Believing in the
Adamic theory of language, Blake incorporated Hebraisms into his verbal art . . . Blake seems to have unified
all of his earlier experimentation around the concept of the <hi rend="i">alef</hi>” [78]. According to
Anon., “Corrigenda,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3 (winter 2003-04): 111, the reproductions of
“Laocoön” and “Job’s Evil Dream” are from the Fitzwilliam Museum and the Pierpont Morgan Library,
not the Library of Congress.)</p>
                  <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Volume 37, no. 3 (Winter 2003-04)</p>
                  <p>*Robert N. Essick and Rosamund A. Paice. “Newly Uncovered Blake Drawings in the British
Museum.” 84-100. (The nine slight pencil drawings [all reproduced] were discovered on the versos of Blake
drawings and prints when they were dismounted; they include designs for <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> pl. 6 on the
verso of a design for the same subject, the sistrum in Fuseli’s “The Fertilization of Egypt” engraved by
Blake for Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> (1791) on the verso of Fuseli’s sketch for the whole
design, and unrelated designs on the versos of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (a) pls. 1 and 18, one for Blake’s
colorprint of “God Judging Adam.”)</p>
                  <p>*Alexander S. Gourlay. “‘Friendship,’ Love, and Sympathy in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> Illustrations.” 100-04. (Gourlay proposes that, among the newly discovered watercolors
for Blair, the one of eight floating female figures should be called “Friendship” and the one of two men
in hats walking along a road, inscribed “Friendship,” should be called “There’s no bye-road | To
bliss”; both are reproduced.)</p>
                  <p>Oskar Wellens. “A Dutch Bibliophile Edition of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> (1928).” 104-07. (<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#106&gt; was edited by P. N. van Eyck, printed by Joh. Enschedé with Jan van Krimpen’s Lutetia type, and
published by Alexandre Alphonse Marius Stols at his Halcyon Press in 325 copies, “a brilliant example of
their superior craftsmanship.”)</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>*Nelson Hilton. Review of G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Stranger from
Paradise</hi> (2001). 107-11. (The book is “the most useful and reliable guide to Blake’s life,” “an
epitome of scholarship” exhibiting remarkable “sensitivity to tone and content,” “a glorious capstone
to his [Bentley’s] labors” [108].)</p>
                  <p>Newsletter</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Corrigenda.” 111. (In Sheila A. Spector, “Blake’s Graphic Use of
Hebrew,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.2 [fall 2003], the reproductions of “Laocoön” and “Job’s Evil
Dream” are from the Fitzwilliam Museum and the Pierpont Morgan Library, not the Library of Congress,
according to Robert N. Essick.)</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Color-Printing Debate.” 111. (Martin Butlin, “William Blake, S. W. Hayter
and Color Printing,” and the response of Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi “are now available
exclusively on the journal’s web site at www.blakequarterly.org.”)</p>
                  <p>*Bloom, Harold, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Comprehensive Research and Study
Guide. (Broomall, Pennsylvania: Chelsea House, 2003) Bloom’s Major Poets, 4°, 143 pp.; ISBN:
0791068129.</p>
                  <p>“Introduction.” 10-11.</p>
                  <p>“Biography of William Blake.” 12-16.</p>
                  <p>“Critical Analysis of ‘The Tyger.’” 17-19</p>
                  <p>“Critical Views on ‘The Tyger’”</p>
                  <p>“Hazard Adams on Blake’s System.” 20-22. (From “Reading Blake’s Lyrics: ‘The
Tyger,’” <hi rend="i">Discussions of William Blake</hi>, ed. John E. Grant [1961] 53-54. &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1724&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“John E. Grant’s Questions for the Reader and Writer.” 22-26. (From “The Art and
Argument of ‘The Tyger,’” <hi rend="i">Discussions of William Blake</hi>, ed. John E. Grant [1961]
66-68. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1723-24&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Harold Pagliaro on the Changing View of ‘The Tyger.’” 26-28. (From his 
<hi rend="i">Selfhood and Redemption in Blake’s</hi> Songs [1987] 86-88. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p.
598&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Martin K. Nurmi on ‘The Tyger’: Revisions Mirroring Changes in Society.” 29-32.
(From “Blake’s Revisions of ‘The Tyger,’” <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Tyger</hi>, ed. Winston
Weathers [1969] 104-06. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2937&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Stewart Crehan on ‘The Tyger’ as a Sign of Revolutionary Times.” 32-33. (From
his <hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> [1984] 104-106. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 444&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Morton D. Paley on Differing Viewpoints on ‘The Tyger.’” 34-38. (From “Tyger
of Wrath,” <hi rend="i">Discussions of William Blake</hi>, ed. John E. Grant [1961] 70-74. &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1724&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Martin Price on Terror and Symmetry in ‘The Tyger.’” 38-40. (From “The Vision
of Innocence,” <hi rend="i">Critics on Blake</hi>, ed. Judith O’Neill [1970] 106-107. &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #2327&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Critical Analysis of ‘London.’” 41-43.</p>
                  <pb id="p38-19" n="19"/>
                  <p>“Critical Views on ‘London’”</p>
                  <p>“David V. Erdman on People in Blake’s ‘London.’” 44-47. (From “Infinite
London: The Songs of Experience in Their Historical Setting,” <hi rend="i">Critics on Blake</hi>, ed. Judith
O’Neill [1970] 65-68. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2327&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Kenneth Johnston on the Vocabulary of Blake’s ‘London.’” 47-49. (From
“Blake’s Cities: Romantic Forms of Urban Renewal,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>,
ed. D. V. Erdman and John E. Grant [1970] 417-19. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1580&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“E. P. Thompson on the Ways in Which Words Change in ‘London.’” 49-51. (From
“London,” <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake</hi>, ed. Michael Phillips [1978] 5-8. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
pp. 603-04&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“John Beer on ‘London’ as Open to Interpretation.” 51-53. (From “Influence and
Independence in Blake,” <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake</hi>, ed. Michael Phillips [1978] 220-22. &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 603-04&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Stewart Crehan on the Social System of ‘London.’” 54-57. (From his 
<hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> [1984] 73-79. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 444&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Gavin Edwards on Repetition in ‘London.’” 57-61. (From “Repeating the Same
Dull Round,” <hi rend="i">New Casebooks: William Blake</hi>, ed. David Punter [1996]. &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Harold Bloom on Wandering Through ‘London.’” 61-62. (From “Blake and
Revisionism” in his <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [1987] 55-58.
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 416&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Critical Analysis of ‘The Mental Traveller.’” 63-65.</p>
                  <p>“Critical Views on ‘The Mental Traveller’”</p>
                  <p>“Northrop Frye on ‘The Mental Traveller’ as a Life Journey.” 66-68. (From “The
Keys to the Gates,” <hi rend="i">Modern Critical Views: William Blake</hi>, ed. Harold Bloom [1985] 56-57.
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 415&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“John H. Sutherland on Irony and Oppression.” 68-72. (From “Blake’s Mental
Traveller,” <hi rend="i">Critics on Blake</hi>, ed. Judith O’Neill [1970] 74-77. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2327&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“David Wagenknecht on Blake’s History.” 72-74. (From his <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Night</hi> [1973] 169-71. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #A2908&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Harold Bloom on ‘The Mental Traveller’ as Standing Alone.” 74-77. (From his 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi> [1963] 289-92. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1227&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Alicia Ostriker on Sound and Structure.” 77-78. (From her <hi rend="i">Vision and
Verse in William Blake</hi> [1965] 94-99. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2335&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Victor Paananen on Nature.” 79-81. (From his <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> An
Updated Edition [1996] 120-23. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Nicholas Williams on the Unconditional Non-Traditional Blake.” 82-85. (From his 
<hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William Blake</hi> [1998] 1-5. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1999)&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Critical Analysis of ‘The Crystal Cabinet.’” 86-88.</p>
                  <p>“Critical Views on ‘The Crystal Cabinet’”</p>
                  <p>“Irene Chayes on the Influence of Myth.” 89-92. (From “The Presence of Cupid and
Psyche,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. D. V. Erdman and John E. Grant [1970]
214-17. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1580&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Robert E. Simmons on Blake’s Balance.” 92-93. (From “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>:
The Symmetry of Fear,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. D. V. Erdman and John E.
Grant [1970] 167-69. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1580&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Hazard Adams on Innocence and Images.” 94-97. (From “‘The Crystal Cabinet’ and
‘The Golden Net,’” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, ed. Northrop Frye [1965] 80-83. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1643&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“<corr type="emend">Victor Paananen</corr> on Sexual Expression.” 97-99. (From his <hi rend="i">William
Blake</hi> An Updated Edition [1996] 123-24. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Kathleen Raine on Alchemy in ‘The Crystal Cabinet.’” 99-102. (From her 
<hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> [1968] 274-76. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2478&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Critical Analysis of ‘The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.’” 103-06.</p>
                  <p>“Critical Views on ‘The Marriage of Heaven and Hell’”</p>
                  <p>“Joseph Anthony Wittreich Jr on Parody of Religious Writers.” 107-09. (From
“Opening the Seals: Blake’s Epics and the Milton Tradition,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime
Allegory</hi>, ed. Stuart Curran and J. A. Wittreich, Jr. [1973] 29-32. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#A1437&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Max Plowman on Hope and Fear.” 110-12. (From his <hi rend="i">An Introduction to the
Study of Blake</hi> [1967] 116-19. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2421&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“David V. Erdman on Spirituality Versus Society.” 112-16. (From his 
<hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet against Empire</hi> [1969] 178-82. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1561A-B, 
<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 463&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Harold Bloom on the Contraries in ‘The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.’” 116-20.
(From his <hi rend="i">The Ringers in the Tower</hi> [1971] 56-60. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1229C&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“W. J. T. Mitchell on the Marriage of Images and Words.” 120-24 (From “Blake’s
Composite Art,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. D. V. Erdman and John E. Grant
[1970] 63-66. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1580&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Algernon Charles Swinburne on Music and Meaning.” 124-25. (From “Critics on Blake:
1803-1941,” <hi rend="i">Critics on Blake</hi>, ed. Judith O’Neill [1970] 21-22. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2327&gt;)</p>
                  <p>“Mark Bracher on How ‘The Marriage of Heaven and Hell’ Changes the Reader.”
125-28. (From “Rouzing the Faculties: Lacanian Psychoanalysis and the Marriage of Heaven and Hell in the
Reader,” <hi rend="i">Critical Paths: Blake and the Argument of Method</hi>, ed. Dan Clinton Miller, Mark
Bracher, and Donald Ault [1987] 168. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 573-74&gt;)</p>
                  <p>Boyce, Michele Dellafield. “Blake and the Emanation.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 64
(2003): 532C. Southampton Ph.D., 2001.</p>
                  <p>Comparison of Blake with Jung “and his modern interpreter, James Hillman” in the
context of Rousseau.</p>
                  <p>Burt, Daniel S. “William Blake 1757-1827.” Chapter 28 (104-07) of his 
<hi rend="i">The Literary 100: A Ranking of the Most Influential Novelists, Playwrights, and Poets of All
Time.</hi> (New York: Checkmark Books, 2001).</p>
                  <p>Butlin, Martin. “William Blake, S. W. Hayter, and Color Printing.” Online  
(<corr type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="bonus.butlin"><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> bonus content</ref> 2003).</corr></p>
                  <p>See Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi, “Response.”</p>
                  <p>Carey, William Paulet. <hi rend="i">Critical Description of the Procession of Chaucers
Pilgrims to Canterbury, Painted by Thomas Stothard, Esq. R.A.</hi> (1808). Second Edition (1818). &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1338&gt;</p>
                  <p>The second edition, ed. Maria McGarrity, is reprinted in Appendix 2 (379-422) of 
<hi rend="i">Chaucer Illustrated: Five Hundred Years of The Canterbury Tales in Pictures</hi>, ed. William K.
Finley
<pb id="p38-20" n="20"/>
and Joseph Rosenblum (New Castle [Delaware]: Oak Knoll Press, and London: The British Library, 2003).</p>
                  <p>Cernuda, Luis. §“William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Pensamiento poético en la lírica
inglesa (Siglo XIX).</hi> (Mexico [City]: Imprenta Universitaria, 1958). B. §<hi rend="i">Pensamiento
poético en la lírica inglesa del siglo XIX.</hi> (Madrid: Tecnos, 1986) Colección Metrópolis. C. (Madrid:
Tecnos-Alianza Editorial, 2002) Colección Neometrópolis. In Spanish.</p>
                  <p>The essay was also printed in <hi rend="i">El Matrimonio del Cielo y del Infierno</hi>,
tr. Soledad Capurro y prólogo de Luis Cernuda (Madrid: Visor, 1977) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;
and §<hi rend="i">El Matrimonio del Cielo y del Infierno y Cantos de Inocencia y de Experiencia</hi>, tr.
Soledad Capurro (Madrid, 1979) Colección Visor de Poesía Vol. 87. B. (Madrid, 1983) 210 pp. &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 158&gt;</p>
                  <p>Chang, Han-liang. “Blake de shi zhung hua yu hua zhung shi [Blake’s Painting in
Poetry and Poetry in Painting].” <hi rend="i">Zhongguo shibao</hi> [<hi rend="i">China Times</hi>, Taipei] 9
April 1981: 8 (Literary Supplement). B. 205-210 of his <hi rend="i">Bijao wenxue lilun yu shijian</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Theory and Practice of Comparative Literature</hi>]. (Taipei: Dongda tushu gongsi, 1986). In
Chinese.</p>
                  <p>Description of Blake’s life, his engravings, paintings, writings, from a comparative
point of view.</p>
                  <p>Chen, Peng-hsiang. “Social Satire and Humanitarianism in William Blake’s Poetry.”
<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature &amp; Linguistics</hi> 2 (Taipei, April 1977): 23-24.</p>
                  <p>Discussion of the two “Chimney Sweeper”s, the two “Holy Thursday”s, “The Little
Black Boy,” and “London.”</p>
                  <p>Chen, Zhifan. “Shi kong zhi hai—chenggong hu bian sanji zhi san [The Sea of Time and
Space—Third Essay Written on the Side of Chenggong Lake].” <hi rend="i">Lianhe bao</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">United Daily News</hi>, Taipei] 8 Jan. 1994: 37 (Literary Supplement). In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>An account of his experience visiting exhibits of Blake’s poetry and painting. For a
response, see Mu Yang.</p>
                  <p>Child, Mrs. D. L. [Lydia Maria Francis]. “Good Wives. No. I.—Mrs. Blake, wife of
William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Ladies Pocket Magazine</hi> Part 2 (1833): 1-5. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1383A&gt; B. “Mrs. Blake, Wife of William Blake.” 128-33 of her <hi rend="i">Good Wives</hi> (Boston,
1833) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1383B&gt; C-G. <hi rend="i">Biographies of Good Wives.</hi> (1846-55) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1383C-G&gt; H. “Blake, Mrs, Wife of William Blake.” 124-28 of <hi rend="i">Biographies
of Good Wives.</hi> Eighth Edition, Revised. (New York: C. S. Francis &amp; Co., 1859). I. 
<hi rend="i">Married Women</hi>: Biographies of Good Wives. (New York, 1871) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1383H&gt;</p>
                  <p>§Chong, Cue-huan. “[Blake’s Poetry in the Judeo-Christian Line of Prophecy.]” 
<hi rend="i">Milton Studies: The Journal of Milton Studies in Korea</hi> 11 (2001): 171-201. In Korean, with a
summary in English.</p>
                  <p>Chou, Man-wen. “A Study of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> Reflecting the Two Contrary States of the Human Soul.” 
<hi rend="i">Taipei shangyie zuanke xuebao</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of National Taipei College of Business</hi>]
3 (Jan. 1974): 223-53.</p>
                  <p>Detailed analyses of “The Lamb,” “Infant Joy,” and “The Divine Image” from
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, of “The Tyger” and “The Human Abstract” from 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, and of “Holy Thursday,” “The Chimney Sweeper,” and “Nurse’s Song” from
both <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Experience.</hi></p>
                  <p>Clark, Steve. “Blake.” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 80
(Covering work published in 1999) (2001): 455-65.</p>
                  <p>§Corti, Claudia. “Blake, Goethe e le arti sorelle.” 191-202 of <hi rend="i">Il
primato dell’occhio.</hi> Ed. Emilio Bonfatti and Maria Fancelli. (Roma: Artemide Edizioni, 1997) Collana
Proteo, 41. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>*Csikós, Dóra Janzer. <hi rend="i">“Four Mighty Ones Are in Every Man”: The
Development of the Fourfold in Blake.</hi> (Budapest: Akadémiai Kiadó; Distributed by International
Specialized Book Services, Portland, Oregon, 2003) Philosophiae Doctores [no. 15], 137 pp.; ISBN:
9630579367.</p>
                  <p>An “essentially psychological” argument focusing on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
based on “Lipót Szondi’s theory of mental functioning, more precisely the personality typology based on
the Szondi test” or “system of drives” which “revives the age-old theory of physiognomy by assuming
that one can determine character by facial appearance” (14, 45).</p>
                  <p>Csikós, Dóra. “‘Urizen Who Was Faith &amp; Certainty Is Changed to Doubt.’ The
Changing Portrayal of Urizen.” <hi rend="i">Hungarian Journal of English and American Studies</hi> 3.2
([Debrecen, Hungary] 1997): 131-59. &lt;§<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Using as her “main framework” “Lipót Szondi’s theory of . . . personality
typology,” she concludes that “Urizen has an intrinsically progressive role in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>” (132, 150).</p>
                  <p>§Curnutte, Richard A. “Mad Poets: William Blake, Jim Jarmusch and <hi rend="i">Dead
Man.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Film Journal</hi> 1 (2002)
&lt;http://www.thefilmjournal.com/issue1/curnuttedeadman.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>*Dickinson, Patric. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Three Talks: 22 September The Man
and his Background; 29 September Engraver and Painter; 6 October The Poet. 3-11. ([?London,?1962]).</p>
                  <p>Directories<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n27">27. All but those for <hi rend="i">The Post-Office Directory</hi> (1809), (the wrong?) James
Blake, William Staden Blake, Butts, and Rev. Mr. Mathew are recorded in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
(second edition [2004]) 735-36.</note></p>
                  <p>[W.] <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory</hi> [Corrected to the end of April] 
<hi rend="i">1799</hi> (London, [1799]) for “Blake William <hi rend="i">Engraver</hi> Lambeth Green” and
“Blake, James <hi rend="i">Hosier</hi>, 28, Broad-street, Carnaby-market”</p>
                  <p>[W.] <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory for 1802, 1803, 1804</hi> (London, 1802)
for “Blake and Son, <hi rend="i">hosiers and haberdashers</hi>, 28, Broad st. Soho”</p>
                  <pb id="p38-21" n="21"/>
                  <p>[W.] <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory for 1805, 1806, 1807</hi>, Second Volume
(London, 1805) for “Blake James, <hi rend="i">Hosier</hi> 28, Broad street, Golden sq.”</p>
                  <p>[W.] <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory</hi> Fourth Edition, Including the Year
1808 (London, 1808) for “Blake, James, <hi rend="i">Hosier</hi>, 28, Broad street, Golden sq.”</p>
                  <p>[W.] <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory for 1809, 1810, 1811</hi> (1809) for
“Blake, James, <hi rend="i">Hosier</hi>, 28 Broad Street, Golden Square”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1793</hi> (London, 1793) for “Blake &amp;
Son, Hosiers &amp; Haberdashers, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-mar.”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1794</hi> (London, 1794) for “Blake &amp;
Son, Hosiers &amp; Haberdashers, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-mar.” and “Blake, James, Hosier, 28, Broad-street,
Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1795</hi> (London, 1795) for “Blake &amp;
Son, Hosiers &amp; Haberdashers, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-mar.” and “Blake, James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street,
Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1796</hi> (London, 1796) for “Blake &amp;
Son, Hosiers &amp; Haberdashers, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-mar.” and “Blake, James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street,
Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1797</hi> (London, 1797) for “Blake &amp;
Son, Hosiers &amp; Haberdashers, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-mar.” and “Blake, James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street,
Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1798</hi> (London, 1798) for “Blake &amp;
Son, Hosiers &amp; Haberdashers, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-mar.” and “Blake, James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street,
Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1799</hi> (London, 1799) for “Blake &amp;
Son, Hosiers &amp; Haberdashers, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-mar.” and “Blake, James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street,
Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1800</hi> (London, 1800) for “Blake &amp;
Son, Hosiers &amp; Haberdashers, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-mar.” and “Blake, James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street,
Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1801</hi> (London, 1801) for “Blake,
James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1802</hi> (London, 1802) for “Blake,
James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1804</hi> (London, 1804) for “Blake,
James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1805</hi> (London, 1805) for “Blake,
James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1806</hi> (London, 1806) for “Blake,
James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1807</hi> (London, 1807) for “Blake,
James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1808</hi> (London, 1808) for “Blake,
James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory for the Year 1810</hi> (London, 1810) for “Blake,
James, Hosier, 28 Broad-street, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Literary Pocket Book</hi>, Or, Companion to the Lover of Nature and Art
1819 [compiled by Leigh Hunt] (London: Printed for C. and J. Ollier . . ., 1818) under “Eminent Living
Artists” is “Blake, W. Poetry” (Vol. I, p. 167); . . . 1820 (1819) “Blake, W. Poetical subjects”
(Vol. II, p. 169); . . . 1822 (1821) “Blake, W. Visions” (Vol. IV, p. 156) and, under Line Engravers,
“Blake, W.”; . . . 1823 (1822) “Blake, W. Visions” (Vol. V, p. 148)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n28">28. There is no Blake entry in the issue for 1821, and the journal ceased publication after
1822; see “Leigh Hunt’s ‘Literary Pocket-Book’ 1818-22: A Romantic Source Book,” 
<hi rend="i">Victorian Periodicals Newsletter</hi> 3.4 (Dec. 1975): 125-28.</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The London Directory For the Year 1783</hi> (London, 1783) for “Blake,
Stephen, Haberdasher, 28 Broad-str Carnaby-Market”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Lowndes’s London Directory For the Year 1784</hi> (London, 1784) for
Stephen Blake at 28 Broad Street</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1800</hi> (London, 1800) for “Blake
and Son, Hosiers and Haberdashers, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1801</hi> (London, 1801) for “Blake
and Son, Hosiers and Haberdashers, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1803</hi> (London, 1803) for “Blake
and Son, Hosiers and Haberdashers, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1806</hi> (London, 1806) for “Blake,
James, Hosier and Haberdasher, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1807</hi>, Eighth Edition (London,
1807) for “Blake, James, Hosier and Haberdasher, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1808</hi> (London, 1808) for “Blake,
James, Hosier and Haberdasher, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1809</hi> (London, 1809) for “Blake,
James, Hosier and Haberdasher, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1810</hi> (London, 1810) for “Blake,
James, Hosier and Haberdasher, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1811</hi> (London, 1811) for “Blake,
James, Hosier and Haberdasher, 28, Broad-st, Soho”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1812</hi> (London, 1812) for Blake,
James, Hosier at 28 Broad Street</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The New Annual Directory For the Year 1813</hi> (London, 1813) for Blake,
James, Hosier at 28 Broad Street</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">New Complete Guide To all Persons who have any Trade or Concern with the
City of London, and Parts adjacent.</hi> The Sixteenth Edition (London, 1783) for Stephen Blake Haberdasher at
28 Broad Street</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">The Post-Office Annual Directory</hi> (1809) for “Blake, James, Hosier
&amp; Haberdasher, 28 Broad-street, Soho” (p. 32)</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Post-Office Annual Directory</hi> (1812) for “Blake, James, 
<hi rend="i">Hosier</hi>, 28, Broad-street, Soho” (p. 34)</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Universal British Directory of Trade and Commerce</hi>, comprehending
Lists of the Inhabitants of London, Westminster, and Borough of Southwark; And of all the Cities, Towns, and
principal Villages, in England and Wales; with the Mails, and other Coaches, Stage-Waggons, Hoys, Packets, and
Trading Vessels. . . . Together with an Historical and Particular Detail of the Trade, Polity, and
Manufactures of each City, Town and Village. [5 vols.] I (London, 1790) for James Blake, 
<hi rend="i">Hosier</hi>, at Broad Street, Golden Square</p>
                  <p>Also for James Blake<lb/>
(but probably not Blake’s brother the hosier):</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory For the Year 1825</hi> (1825) linen draper at 9, Grafton
Street, Soho</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">New Annual Directory For the Year 1814</hi> (1814), 
<hi rend="i">Hosier</hi>, 7, Buckingham-street Fitzroy-square; (1823, 1824, 1825, 1826, 1827) J. Blake,
Haberdasher and Furrier, 134, St Martin’s-lane; (1829) James Blake, Haberdasher, 218 Oxford street</p>
                  <p>For William Staden (or W.S.) Blake, engraver:</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Universal British Directory</hi>, I (1797), at 16 Exchange Alley</p>
                  <pb id="p38-22" n="22"/>
                  <p>[P.] <hi rend="i">Boyle’s City &amp; Commercial Companion to the Court Guide for the
Year 1803</hi> (London, 1803) at Change alley, Lombard St</p>
                  <p>[W.] <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory</hi> (1799); . . . <hi rend="i">for
1802, 1803, 1804</hi> (1802); . . . <hi rend="i">for 1805, 1806, 1807</hi> (1805); . . . <hi rend="i">for
1817, 1818, 1819</hi> (1817); . . . <hi rend="i">for 1822, 1823, 1824</hi> (1822) at 16, ’Change Alley,
Cornhill</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory For the Year 1808</hi> (1808); . . . (1810); . . .
(1815); . . . (1816) at 16, ’Change Alley, Cornhill</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">New Annual Directory For the Year 1801</hi> (1801); . . . (1803); . . .
(1806); . . . (1807); . . . (1808); . . . (1809); . . . (1810); . . .(1811); . . . (1812); . . . (1813); . . .
(1814); . . . (1815) “Engraver &amp; Printer, 16, Change alley”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Post-Office Annual Directory</hi> (1812), Engraver and Printer, 16,
Change-alley (p. 34)</p>
                  <p>For Butts:</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Universal British Directory</hi>, V (1797): “Mrs Butts” in Great
Marlborough Street</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">New Annual Directory For the Year 1806</hi> (London, 1806), . . . 
<hi rend="i">1807</hi> (London, 1807), . . . <hi rend="i">1808</hi> (London, 1808), . . . <hi rend="i">1809</hi>
(London, 1809), . . . <hi rend="i">1810</hi> (London, 1810), . . . <hi rend="i">1811</hi> (London, 1811), . .
. <hi rend="i">1812</hi> (London, 1812), . . . <hi rend="i">1813</hi> (London, 1813), . . . 
<hi rend="i">1814</hi> (London, 1814), . . . <hi rend="i">1815</hi> (London, 1815): “Butts, Thos. Commissary of
Musters, office, Whitehall”; (1817) at 53, Parliament-street; (1819) at Duke-str. Westminster</p>
                  <p>For Rev. Mr. Mathew, 27 Rathbone Place</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Directory to the Nobility, Gentry, and Families of Distinction, in London,
Westminster, &amp;c</hi> (London [1796])</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Universal British Directory</hi>, V (1797)</p>
                  <p>Most of these directories are in the British Library, a few in Bodley. See Charles W. F.
Goss, <hi rend="i">The London Directories 1677-1855: A Bibliography</hi> (London, 1932), and Gareth Shaw and
Allison Tipper, <hi rend="i">British Directories</hi> (Leicester: Leicester University Press, 1988).</p>
                  <p>§Doi, Kochi. “William Blake no shochoshugi [Symbolism of William Blake].” 
<hi rend="i">Kaizo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reconstruction</hi>] 9.4 (1922): 148-60. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Dortort, Fred. <hi rend="i">The Dialectic of Vision.</hi> (1998) &lt;Blake (1999)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>R. Paul Yoder, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 42 (2003): 405-12 (“We should
be grateful . . . but we might also wish that he had interrogated his own argument with the same rigor he
attempts to bring to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” [412]).</p>
                  <p>*Eaves, Morris, ed. <hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake.</hi>
(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003) Tall 8°, xix, 303 pp., 36 plates; ISBN: 0521781477 (hardback)
and 0521786770 (paperback).</p>
                  <p>The chief contents are:</p>
                  <p>Morris Eaves. “Introduction: To Paradise the Hard Way.” 1-16. (“His poetry risks
every kind of excess to achieve revelation” [1].)</p>
                  <p>[Part] I: Perspectives</p>
                  <p>Aileen Ward. “William Blake and His Circle.” 19-36.</p>
                  <p>*Joseph Viscomi. “Illuminated Printing.” 37-62. (A concise, masterful account.)</p>
                  <p>Susan J. Wolfson. “Blake’s Language in Poetic Form.” 63-84. (“His poetry is
unprescribed, . . . delivered by inspiration alone,” characterized by “intensely performative
antiformalism” [63, 65].)</p>
                  <p>David Bindman. “Blake as a Painter.” 85-109. (An admirably comprehensive
account.)</p>
                  <p>Saree Makdisi. “The Political Aesthetic of Blake’s Images.” 110-32. (“The
‘meaning’ of Blake’s text emerges from the process of reading itself” [112]. Material from it
reappears in his <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Impossible History of the 1790s</hi> [2003] Chapter 4:
“Weary of Time: Images and Commodity in Blake” [155-203].)</p>
                  <p>Jon Mee. “Blake’s Politics in History.” 133-49. (A sophisticated argument that
“Blake was always a deeply political writer” [133].)</p>
                  <p>Robert Ryan. “Blake and Religion.” 150-68. (An intelligent and perceptive
account.)</p>
                  <p>David Simpson. “Blake and Romanticism.” 169-87. (About definitions of Romanticism,
sometimes related to Blake.)</p>
                  <p>[Part] II: Blake’s Works</p>
                  <p>*Nelson Hilton. “Blake’s Early Works.” 191-209. (A responsible outline.)</p>
                  <p>*Andrew Lincoln. “From <hi rend="i">America</hi> to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”
210-30. (A useful summary.)</p>
                  <p>Mary Lynn Johnson. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and Its Contexts.” 231-50.</p>
                  <p>*Robert N. Essick. “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and Blake’s Final Works.” 251-71.
(“Is <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> unreadable? . . . Blake questions the very grounds of understanding”
[251, 252].)</p>
                  <p>Alexander Gourlay. “A Glossary of Terms, Names, and Concepts in Blake.”
272-87.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n29">29. See also Alexander S. Gourlay, glossary of Blake terms (2003) in the William Blake
Archive.</note></p>
                  <p>Alexander Gourlay. “Guide to Further Reading.” 288-93.</p>
                  <p>Alexander Gourlay. “Seeing Blake’s Art in Person.” 294-95. (About where Blake’s
originals are and why one should see them.)</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>T. Hoagwood, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 12 (2003): 337 (“Highly recommended”).</p>
                  <p>§Engelstein, Stefani. “The Regenerative Geography of the Text in William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Studies</hi> 30 (2000): 61-86.</p>
                  <p>About birth.</p>
                  <p>*Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet against Empire.</hi> (1954) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1561A&gt; B. (1969) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1561B&gt; C-D. (1977, 1991) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 463&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">International Blake Conference “Blake in the Orient”: Programme</hi>
(2003) for Eric K. W. Yu, “Blake as a Prophet against Empire: Erdman’s Interpretive Legacy
Reexamined.”</p>
                  <pb id="p38-23" n="23"/>
                  <p>Essick, Robert N., and Joseph Viscomi. “Response.” Online 
(<corr type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="bonus.response"><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> bonus content</ref> 2003)</corr> 
to Martin Butlin, “William Blake, S. W. Hayter, and Color Printing.”</p>
                  <p>*Fairer, David. “Experience Reading Innocence: Contextualizing Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Holy Thursday.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 35.4 (2002): 535-62.</p>
                  <p>The political contexts of the ceremony at St. Paul’s “can illuminate our responses to
Blake’s poem” (540).</p>
                  <p>Frank, Peter. “British Invasion: They’re coming: Exhibitions of U.K. artists William
Blake and Lucian Freud plus Anglo’d Americans John Singer Sargent and R. B. Kitaj march into L.A.” 
<hi rend="i">Angeleno</hi> (May 2003): 142-43.</p>
                  <p>*Fresch, Cheryl H. “Milton and Blake: Visualizing the Expulsion.” 156-73 of 
<hi rend="i">“All in All”: Unity, Diversity, and the Miltonic Perspective.</hi> Ed. Charles W. Durham and
Kristin A. Pruitt. (Selinsgrove: Susquehanna University Press; London: Associated University Presses,
1999).</p>
                  <p>An attempt to “recover the pictorialist conventions that shape both Milton’s and
Blake’s expulsion scenes” (157).</p>
                  <p>Friedlander, Edward Robert, M.D. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Meaning
and Madness.” Brown B.A. honors thesis (1973). Revised 1986.
&lt;http://www.pathguy.com/blake/blakemil.txt&gt; &lt;§<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>“As a medical doctor” in 1986, he concludes that “Blake’s poetry and paintings
present classic illustrations of the schizophrenic experience. So far as I know, these are the best, most
beautiful, and most meaningful ones ever created. They are great value by themselves. . . . We can look to the
schizophrenic experience to understand Blake’s works.”</p>
                  <p>Gimeno Suances, Francisco. “Notas sobre la difusión, influencia y recepción crítica
de la obra de William Blake en España durante las décadas de 1920 y 1930.” <hi rend="i">Los Papeles
Mojados de río seco</hi> Año 5, no. 6 (2003): 38-45. In Spanish.</p>
                  <p>Impressively detailed and original.</p>
                  <p>Goldberg, Brian. “Byron, Blake, and Heaven.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi>
27 (Aug. 2002) &lt;http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/2002/v/n27/006561ar.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>About the views of the afterlife of Byron and Blake.</p>
                  <p>Goodwin, Karin. “Blake’s ‘Lost’ Art Earns Glasgow Sellers £3m . . . but It Will
Stay Hidden.” <hi rend="i">Sunday Herald</hi> 2 Feb. 2003 and
&lt;http://www.sundayherald.com/print31098&gt;.</p>
                  <p>On the sale by Libby Howie of the Blair watercolors.</p>
                  <p>*Gourlay, Alexander S., ed. <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William Blake in
Honor of John E. Grant.</hi> (West Cornwall, CT: Locust Hill Press, 2002) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>§Alice G. den Otter, <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 14 (Dec. 2003):
490-93.</p>
                  <p>Haraguchi, Masao. “On ‘becoming lost and being found’ in Blake’s Poetry
(I[-III]).” <hi rend="i">Kyushu Sangyo Daigaku Kokusaibunka Gakubu Kiyo</hi>: <hi rend="i">Journal of the
Faculty of International Studies of Culture, Kyushu Sangyo University</hi> No. 16 (2000): 45-68; No. 18
(2001): 17-28 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;; No. 24 (2003): 49-56.</p>
                  <p>Harrison, John R. “‘Empire is no More’: William Blake, Tom Paine and the American
Revolution.” <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 3S, 7.1 (1998): 16-32. &lt;§<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1999)&gt;</p>
                  <p>An interesting but not persuasive argument that “Blake withdrew <hi rend="i">The French
Revolution</hi> [1791] himself . . . because he had decided to publish a much more seditious work,” i.e.,
<hi rend="i">America</hi> (1793) “primarily through the influence of, and his support for, Paine”
(17).</p>
                  <p>§Havely, Nicholas, ed. <hi rend="i">Dante’s Modern Afterlife: Reception and Response
from Blake to Heaney.</hi> (Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1998).</p>
                  <p>Hearn, Lafcadio. “Blake—The First English Mystic.” (1916) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1819A&gt; B. (1927) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1819B&gt; C. §<hi rend="i">Koizumi Yakumo zenshu dai 14
kan</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Complete Works of Yakumo Koizumi (Lafcadio Hearn) Volume 14</hi>]. (Tokyo: Daiichi
Shobo, 1927). In Japanese. D. (1965) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1819C&gt;</p>
                  <p>Hearn, Lafcadio. *“William Blake.” (1927) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1820A&gt; B.
§<hi rend="i">Koizumi Yakumo zenshu dai 14 kan</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Complete Works of Yakumo Koizumi
(Lafcadio Hearn) Volume 14</hi>]. (Tokyo: Daiichi Shobo, 1927). In Japanese. C. (1965) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1820B&gt;</p>
                  <p>Hobson, Christopher Z. <hi rend="i">Blake and Homosexuality.</hi> (2000) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Margaret Storch, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.1 (summer 2003): 38-39. (“Hobson’s book
opens up the important topic of Blake and homosexuality as never before [showing] Blake’s empathy with male
homosexuality.”)</p>
                  <p>Judith Mueller, “Blake in the New Millennium,” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi> 36.2 (2003): 294-99, esp. 296-97 (with G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Stranger from
Paradise</hi>, Sheila A. Spector, “<hi rend="i">Wonders Divine</hi>” and “<hi rend="i">Glorious
incomprehensible</hi>,” and Nicholas M. Williams, <hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William
Blake</hi>).</p>
                  <p>Hogarth, William. ANECDOTES | OF | WILLIAM HOGARTH, | WRITTEN BY HIMSELF: | WITH | ESSAYS
ON HIS LIFE AND GENIUS, AND CRITICISMS ON HIS WORKS, | SELECTED FROM | WALPOLE, GILPIN, J. IRELAND, LAMB,
PHILLIPS, AND OTHERS. | TO WHICH ARE ADDED | A CATALOGUE OF HIS PRINTS; ACCOUNT OF THEIR VARIATIONS, AND
PRINCIPAL COPIES; LISTS OF
<pb id="p38-24" n="24"/>
PAINTINGS, DRAWINGS, &amp;c. | - | [Motto from Juvenal] | [dragon vignette] | = | LONDON: | J.B. NICHOLS AND
SON, 25, PARLIAMENT STREET. | - | 1833. Small 4°.</p>
                  <p>For Blake’s <hi rend="i">Beggars’ Opera</hi> plate (174-75) it records the etched
state, 29 Oct. 1788 (174) and the four states: etching, finished proof, “open letters,” and letters filled
up (323), apparently the first such record.</p>
                  <p>Holt, Ted. “Blake’s ‘Elohim’ and the Hutchinsonian Fire: Anti-Utopianism and
Christian Hebraism in the Work of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism</hi> 9 (2003): 20-36.</p>
                  <p>Very interesting parallels between Blake and John Hutchinson (1674-1737), whose
“project was to attribute a trinitarian, Christian meaning to one of the Hebrew names for God,
‘Elohim’” (note “Triple Elohim,” of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> pl. 11, l. 22); “Blake’s reading of
the Pentateuch was undoubtedly coloured by Hutchinsonian interpretations of it” (21).</p>
                  <p>Höltgen, Karl Josef. “<hi rend="i">Religious Emblems</hi> (1809) by John Thurston and
Joseph Thomas, and its Links with Francis Quarles and William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Emblematica</hi> 10 (1996
[1999]): 107-43.</p>
                  <p>“Blake and the Emblem” (132-39); the subject of “Blake and the emblem is
fascinating but elusive” (132).</p>
                  <p>§Hoshino, Eriko. “<hi rend="i">Vala, moshikuwa Four Zoas</hi> Dai Ichiya ni okeru
Tharmas to Enion no Kankei no Hokai—Gnosis teki Kenchi kara [The Disruption of Relations between Tharmas and
Enion in Night the First in <hi rend="i">Vala or The Four Zoas</hi>—from a Viewpoint of Gnosis].” 
<hi rend="i">Saitama Junshin Joshi Tanki Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Saitama Junshin Women’s
Junior College</hi>] 19 (2003): 89-95. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Howie, Michael. “Blake’s Treasure as Artwork ‘Found.’” <hi rend="i">Evening
News</hi> [Edinburgh] 17 Sept. 2002 &lt;http://news.scotsman.com/archive.cfm?id=1034352002&gt;.</p>
                  <p>A “painting” of a uniformed man chiselling a tombstone with his horse by his side is
identified on the verso as by “Flaxman” and entitled “The Iliad,” but Ken Matthews thinks it is by
Blake.</p>
                  <p>Hsia, C. T. “Jinü, shibing, qiuong xiaohai—Blake ming shi xinshang [Harlots,
Soldiers, Poor Children—Appreciation and Analysis of a Famous Poem by Blake].” <hi rend="i">Zhonghua
ribao</hi> [<hi rend="i">China Daily News</hi>, Taipei] 15-16 Feb. 1993: 11 (Literary Supplement). In
Chinese.</p>
                  <p>Appreciation and analysis of “London.”</p>
                  <p>§Ikuta, Kotaro. “Blake no yobuki no soga [Blake’s Illustrations to <hi rend="i">The
Book of Job</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Atorie</hi> [<hi rend="i">Atelier</hi>] 3, no. 2 (1926): 40-45. In
Japanese.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The International Blake Conference “Blake in the Orient”: Programme</hi>
[29-30 November 2003]. Organized by Masashi Suzuki and Steve Clark. (Kyoto: The Blake Conference Committee,
2003) 4°, 46 pp., no ISBN.</p>
                  <p>Masashi Suzuki and Steve Clark. “Preface.” 1. “The broad aim of the International
Blake Conference is to bring attention to both the longevity and complexity of Blake’s reception in Japan
and elsewhere in the East.”</p>
                  <p>The contents are proposals<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">30</ref> for papers, all save the “plenary” papers of Worrall and Shaffer being 20 minutes
long: David Worrall. “<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> and The Swedenborg Project for an African Colony
[Thel in Africa: Swedenborgians and the Idea of the Orient].” 8. “<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> is
Blake’s pondering on the possibility, particularly in its inclusion of women in a passive role, for the
success of such a colony.” <note id="n30">30. In the separate one-leaf program of the conference, some
titles are different; they are identified below within square brackets. A few (not recorded below) omit
subtitles; no title is given for Connolly, Phillips, Tambling, Taylor, and Turner; and Georgia Dimitrakopoulou
appears on the shorter list but not on the longer one.</note></p>
                  <p>Elinor Shaffer. “The Reception of the British [English] Romantics over the Waters.”
9. Only marginally related to Blake. Ching-erh Chang. “Blake in Taiwan.” 12. “William Blake has . . .
attracted sufficient attention” in Taiwan.</p>
                  <p>Tristanne Connolly. “Blake and Wilkins’ Translation of the 
<hi rend="i">Bhagavad-Gita.</hi>” 13.</p>
                  <p>Keri Davies. “Rebekah Bliss: Collector of William Blake and Oriental Books.” 14. If
Blake knew her collection, “this would open up possibilities for a reconsideration of Oriental influences on
Blake’s work.”</p>
                  <p>Sibylle Erle. “William Blake and the Representation of Race in Late Eighteenth-Century
England [Popular Culture].” 15. “I will discuss character representations with special reference to
concurrent body theories about soul-body relationships” concentrating “on the popular reception of
Lavater’s ideas on national physiognomies.”</p>
                  <p>David Fuller. “Madness as ‘Other’: Blake and the Sanity of Dissidence [Madness as
‘Other’].” 16.</p>
                  <p>Yumiko Goto. “The <hi rend="i">Shirakaba</hi> Group and the Early Reception of
Blake’s Art Works in Japan.” 17. An examination of how their exhibitions (1915, 1919) “came to be staged
and their influence on the art worlds of Tokyo and Kyoto” as well as “the image of Blake which the 
<hi rend="i">Shirakaba</hi> group . . . built up from their writings.”</p>
                  <p>Thomas Grundy. “Ontological Difference and the Liberation of Representation in
Blake’s <hi rend="i">America.</hi>” 18. “<hi rend="i">America</hi> is as much about the liberation of
America from King George’s tyranny as it is about the liberation of mythology from the tyranny of the
Priesthood.”</p>
                  <p>Yoko Ima-Izumi. “The Female Voice in Blake Studies in Japan, 1910s-1930s.” 19. Will
focus on Muneyoshi Yanagi, Bunsho Jugaku, and Jugaku’s wife Shizu.</p>
                  <p>Christa Knellwolf. “The Cultural Politics of William Blake’s Exoticism.” 20. Blake
“took recourse to exotic imagery and mythical language in order to uncover the full scope of human emotions
and states of mind.”</p>
                  <p>Kaoru Kobayashi. “Interpretation of Blake’s Philosophy in Japan through the Changes
of Translation of the Poem ‘The
<pb id="p38-25" n="25"/>
Fly.’” 21. “This paper would like to argue for the view of Blake as an early forerunner of existential
philosophical thought.” Keiko Kobayashi. “Blake and Oe Kenzaburo.” 22. She is concerned with “the
overwhelming evocative power of Blake’s polysemous fragments to inspire him” and Oe’s understanding of
“Blake and his poetry and painting as a whole.”</p>
                  <p>Edward Larrissy. “Blake and Orientalism.” 23. “<hi rend="i">His</hi> composite art
is conceived of as oriental.”</p>
                  <p>Susan Matthews. “Black/Blake: Africa and Utopia in the 1790s.” 24. She is concerned
with “Blake’s references to Africa in the 1790s in the light of contemporary writing about the continent .
. . particularly on the meanings of blackness and the sun in writing by George Cumberland . . . in 
<hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Senaar</hi> [sic].”</p>
                  <p>Hiroko Nakamura. “Blake’s Influence on Muneyoshi Yanagi and his Pilgrimage to
Buddhism.” 25. Concerned with “three aspects of Blake’s influence on Yanagi: intuition, individuality
and dualism.”</p>
                  <p>Ashton Nichols. “An Empire of Exotic Nature: Blake’s Botanic and Zoomorphic
Imagery.” 26.</p>
                  <p>Hatsuko Niimi. “Self-Annihilation in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” 27. Proposes to
“analyze Part [i.e., Book] II of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>” with reference to Yanagi’s concern for
“‘self-annihilation’” there.</p>
                  <p>Kazuyoshi Oishi. “A Curious Symmetry of William Blake and Muneyoshi Yanagi.” 28.
Addresses “the cross-cultural problems arising from Yanagi’s (mis)reading of Blake’s work, especially
from a politico-religious perspective.”</p>
                  <p>Kazuya Okada. “Blake and Egypt as the Orient.” 29. “Blake’s knowledge of a wide
variety of Egyptian backgrounds fundamentally motivated him in the formulation of his own mythology. . . . I
will highlight the issue of Egypt-Freemasonry.”</p>
                  <p>Peter Otto. “Nebuchadnezzar’s Sublime Torment: William Blake, Arthur Boyd, and the
East.” 30. About the more than seventy Nebuchadnezzar designs of Arthur Boyd (1920-1999), a prominent
Australian painter.</p>
                  <p>John William Phillips. “Blake’s Question (from the Orient).” 31. Concerned with
“three main kinds of question to be found in Blake’s writings . . . questions answered; . . . questions
without answer; and . . . questions unstated but to which answers are . . . given.”</p>
                  <p>Lalitha [Lalitah] Ramamurthi. “The Nature of Evil and Mysticism in Blake in the
Framework of Hinduism.” 32.</p>
                  <p>Kozo Shioe. “Blake and Young Painters of the Kyoto School.” 33. The young painters
here are Bakusen Tsuchida (1887-1936), Kagaku Murakami (1888-1939), and Hako Irie (1887-1948).</p>
                  <p>Mei-Ying Sung. “Blake and the ‘Chinamen’ [The Printing Techniques of Blake and
Chinese Genre Prints and Book Illustrations].” 34. The “Chinamen” make pottery, but “Blake’s designs
were never used by any ceramic makers.”</p>
                  <p>Ruriko Suzuki. “A Spiritual Twin of Blake in Japan: Miyazawa Kenji.” 35. “Kenji
Miyazawa (1896-1937) . . . also believed in the validity of active universe and personalized religious
myth.”</p>
                  <p>Jeremy Tambling. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” 36. He “argues that
there is not so much fascination with daybreak in Blake’s poetry, as the impossibility of the day breaking,
even if ‘night is worn.’”</p>
                  <p>Minne Tanaka. “Colour Printing, East and West: William Blake’s Large Colour Prints
(1795/1804) and <corr type="emend">Ukiyo-e.”</corr> 37. Proposes “to examine and reveal the process, technique and modifications of
his colour printing, as well as giving an interpretation of the designs.”</p>
                  <p>Takao Tanaka. “Blake’s Zen in the <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of
Job.</hi>” 38. “The state of innocence, which may be seen as the most important thing in Blake’s life,
is almost the same as the mind of Zen.”</p>
                  <p>David Taylor. “‘The First English Mystic’: Lafcadio Hearn, Blake and Late Romantic
Perception of Japan.” 39.</p>
                  <p>Shunsuke Tsurumi. “Yanagi and Jugaku in the Fifteen Years War (1931-45).” 40. “I
felt what Yanagi wrote on Blake served as a bridge from Christianity to Buddhism.”</p>
                  <p>Barnard Turner. “An Anglophonic View of Blake through his Reception in Sato and Oe.”
41. Concerned primarily with Sato Haruo’s <hi rend="i">Gloom in the Country</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Sick
Rose</hi>] and episodes in Oe’s works.</p>
                  <p>Chitta R. Unni. “The Lamb and the Tiger in the Land of Sakura: Blake and the
Revitalization of Japanese Subjectivity.” 42. After some “preliminary discussion” of Blake and other
matters, “My paper . . . will engage the Japanese intellectual and artistic effort to articulate a
distinctly Japanese subjectivity.”</p>
                  <p>Ayako Wada. “Blake’s Oriental Heterodoxy: Yanagi’s Perception of Blake.” 43.</p>
                  <p>Jason Whittaker. “‘Walking thro’ Eternity’: Blake’s Psychogeography and Other
Pedestrian Practices.” 44. Iain Sinclair, <hi rend="i">Lights Out for the Territory</hi>, “described Blake
as ‘the father of psychogeography,’ and the purpose of this paper is to consider some of the ways in which
Blake’s use of symbolic (de)territorialisations has been employed by writers such as Sinclair.”</p>
                  <p>Eric K. W. Yu. “Blake as a Prophet against Empire: Erdman’s Interpretive Legacy
Reexamined.” 45.</p>
                  <p>For the conference exhibition, see 27 November-27 December 2003.</p>
                  <p>§Janssens, V. “Blake, Pope and Voltaire, or the Art of Imitation.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Voltaire and the Eighteenth Century</hi> 10 (2001): 171-86.</p>
                  <p>In his portraits of Pope and Voltaire, Blake alludes to Pope’s “Elegy to the Memory
of an Unfortunate Lady” and Voltaire’s “Vers sur la mort de Mlle Lecouvreur, fameuse actrice” based on
Pope’s poem (147).</p>
                  <p>*Johnson, Mary Lynn. “Human Consciousness and the Divine Image in Blake’s Watercolor
Designs for the Bible: Genesis Through Psalms.” Chapter 2 (20-43) of <hi rend="i">The Cast of Consciousness:
Concepts of the Mind in British and American Romanticism.</hi> Ed. Beverly Taylor and Robert Bain. Afterword
by M. H. Abrams. (New York, Westport [Connecticut], and London: Greenwood Press, 1987) Contributions to the
Study of World Literature, Number 24.</p>
                  <pb id="p38-26" n="26"/>
                  <p>Blake’s Bible designs “form a lively critical commentary on the scriptures”
(37).</p>
                  <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn. “Recent Reconstructions of Blake’s Milton and 
<hi rend="i">Milton: A Poem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Milton and the Romantics</hi> 2 (1976): 1-10.</p>
                  <p>Mostly on Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi> (1975) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #A2993&gt; and Susan Fox, <hi rend="i">Poetic Form in Blake’s Milton</hi> (1976) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 474&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Jose, Chiramel P. “Blake’s Published ‘Theory of Art’ and His Praxis.” 
<hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 17 (1995): 29-47. &lt;§<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Because “Blake wanted to communicate through the media of all the arts in a composite
manner . . . [he] may not be and probably cannot be hedged by the <hi rend="i">ut pictura poesis</hi>
tradition or the <hi rend="i">ut musica poesis</hi> tradition or any other tradition” (45).</p>
                  <p>§Jugaku, Bunsho. “[Blake’s Theory of Painting.]” <hi rend="i">Bi</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Beauty</hi>] 23.3: Blake Issue (1929): 55-84. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Kao, Tien-en. “Blake yu [and] Wordsworth.” 303-27 of <hi rend="i">Xiyang wenxue da
jiaoshi</hi>—<hi rend="i">jingdu jingdian</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reading the Canon: Essays on Western
Literature</hi>]. Ed. Ching-hsi Peng. (Taipei: Jiuke chuban she, 1999). In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>On Blake’s creative activity as “the possibility of human salvation” and the
quality of his works as “visionary and imaginative.”</p>
                  <p>Kao, Tien-en. “Yingguo langmanzhuyi shiren ji qi zhongji guanhuai—Blake de lingxiang
yuzhou [English Romantic Poets and Their Ultimate Concerns—Blake’s Visionary Universe].” 
<hi rend="i">Lianhe wenxue</hi> [<hi rend="i">Unitas: A Literary Monthly</hi>] 6.3 (Jan. 1990): 148-54. In
Chinese.</p>
                  <p>On Blake’s world view.</p>
                  <p>§Kaplan, Nancy. “Blake’s Problem and Ours: Some Reflections on the Image and the
Word.” <hi rend="i">Readerly Writerly Texts</hi> 3.2 (summer 1996): 115-33. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1999)&gt; B. *“Blake’s Problem and Ours: Some Reflections on the Image and the Work.” 25-43 of 
<hi rend="i">The Emerging Cyberculture: Literacy, Paradigm, and Paradox.</hi> Ed. Stephanie B. Gibson and Ollie O.
Oviedo. (Cresskill [New Jersey]: Hampton, 2000) Hampton Press Communication Series. &lt;§<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>“By restructuring the conventional relationship between image and word, Blake mounts a
radical critique of the tradition of the sister arts” (B, 31). The 2000 publication does not seem to refer
to that of 1996.</p>
                  <p>§Kashiwabara, Ikuku. “William Blake, <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> ni okeru
Kaiga Gengo Geijutsu Kozo Bunseki [An Analysis of Visual and Verbal Art Structure in William Blake, 
<hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Osaka Denki Tsushin Daigaku Ningen Kagaku Kenkyu</hi>
[<hi rend="i">Osaka Electro-Communication University, Research in the Humanities</hi>] 5 (2003): 71-91. In
Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Kawasaki, Noriko. “Satan no Chokoku—Blake no Milton ni tsuite (12) [Transcending
Satan-Self in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Gifu Shiritsu Joshi Tanki Daigaku Kenkyu
Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Gifu City Women’s Junior College</hi>] No. 50 (2000): 21-27. In
Japanese. Nos. 1-11, 13 are in Nos. 39-49, 51 (1989-99, 2001).</p>
                  <p>§Kelleway, Kelly. “The Strange Attraction of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">ReconstructionE: A Culture Studies eJournal</hi> 2 (2002): 32 paragraphs
&lt;http://www.reconstruction.ws/021/Urizen.htm&gt;.</p>
                  <p>On image-text relations.</p>
                  <p>§Kim, Heesun. “[The Rebirth of the Poet-as-Prophet and the Poetics of Imagination in
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>]” <hi rend="i">Milton Studies: The Journal of Milton Studies in
Korea</hi> 9 (1999): 105-34. In Korean, with a summary in English.</p>
                  <p>§Kim, Young-shik. “Blake as an Anti-nomian Saint.” <hi rend="i">Journal of English
Language and Literature: Yongo Yongmumhok</hi> 47 (2001): 959-78. Summary in Korean.</p>
                  <p>§Kim, Young-shik. “[Blake’s Perception of the Limitations in Milton’s Prophetic
Vision.]” <hi rend="i">Milton Studies: The Journal of Milton Studies in Korea</hi> 11 (2001): 149-69. In
Korean, with a summary in English.</p>
                  <p>§Kimura, Shohachi. “Blake ni tsuite [On Blake].” <hi rend="i">Gendai no yoga</hi>
[<hi rend="i">Contemporary Western Paintings</hi>] No. 28 (July 1914): 1-7. B. §Journal reprinted (Tokyo:
Rinsen Shoten, 1989). In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Kozlowski, Lisa. “Resonating Resins: ‘Listning to the voices of the ground’ in
William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of Urizen.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 64
(2001): 411-27.</p>
                  <p>“I propose yet another reading of Urizen’s name . . . Urezin” or “Rezin” (411)
with an analysis of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> in terms of resin, “Urizen as stop-out varnish”
(422).</p>
                  <p>Kraemer, Christine Hoff. “‘Mind-Forg’d Manacles’: Self-Imprisonment and
Self-Liberation in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>” (2002)
&lt;http://www.inhumandecency.org/christine/blake.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Lachman, Barbara. <hi rend="i">Voices for Catherine Blake: A Gathering.</hi> (2000)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2001)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Eugenie R. Freed, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 149-151 (this
“fictionalized autobiography” in a “diversity of narrative voices” is “only intermittently
successful”; Lachman “should at least get the historical parameters right”).</p>
                  <p>Liang, Shih-ch’iu. “William Blake.” 1104-25 of his <hi rend="i">Yingguo wenxue
xuan</hi> [<hi rend="i">Selections from English Literature</hi>]. 2 vols. (Taipei: Xiezhi gongyie congshu
chuban gongsi, 1985). In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>A short life of Blake with brief descriptions of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches, Songs,
Thel, Marriage, Visions, Europe, Song of Los</hi>,
<pb id="p38-27" n="27"/>
“Auguries of Innocence,” <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, with
translations of some poems (e.g., “To Autumn”).</p>
                  <p>Liao, Pingwei. “Shi yu hua zhi bianzheng: shi yi Wang Meng yu William Blake wei li [The
Dialectics of Poetry and Painting: Using Wang Meng and William Blake as Examples].” <hi rend="i">Chung-Wai
Literary Monthly</hi> 16.12 ([Taipei] May 1988): 68-86. In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>A comparison of the Chinese poet-painter Wang Meng (c. 1308-85) and Blake.</p>
                  <p>§*Lindop, Grevel. “William Blake (1757-1827).” 33-47 of <hi rend="i">British
                    Writers: Retrospective Supplement.</hi> Ed. Jay Parini. (New York: 
<corr type="emend">Scribner’s,</corr> 2002).</p>
                  <p>Liu, Hwangcheng. “Blake: Divine Vision.” <hi rend="i">Journal of Chinese Military
Academy</hi> 26 (Dec. 1993): 177-214.</p>
                  <p>A critical study of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
                  <p>Lu, Yujia. “<hi rend="i">Lai dao William Blake lüguan</hi>: Gei tianzhen yu shigu
lüke de shi [<hi rend="i">A Visit to William Blake’s Inn</hi>: Poems for Innocent and Experienced
Travellers].” <hi rend="i">Lianhe bao</hi> [<hi rend="i">United Daily News</hi>, Taipei] 24 March 2002: 22
(Dushuren). In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>An introduction to Nancy Willard’s book (1981) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p.
679&gt;.</p>
                  <p>§Lukacher, Brian. “Visionary History Painting: Blake and His Contemporaries.” 103
etc. in <hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century Art: A Critical History.</hi> Ed. Stephen F. Eisenman. (London,
1994).</p>
                  <p>Lundeen, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Knight of the Living Dead: William Blake and the Problem
of Ontology.</hi> (2000) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2001)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Jason Snart, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 144-48 (the book is “most
valuable” for its “analysis of Blake’s use of metaphor and rhetorical devices” [146]).</p>
                  <p>Lussier, Mark. “‘Rest before Labour’: The Pre-Text/s of Blake’s <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi> 27 (Aug. 2002)
&lt;http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/2002/v/n27/006563ar.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>About ambiguities in the aphorism on the title page of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi></p>
                  <p>*Makdisi, Saree. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Impossible History of the 1790s.</hi>
(Chicago and London: University of Chicago Press, 2003) 8°, xviii, 394 pp., 28 reproductions; ISBN:
0226502597 (cloth) and 0226502600 (paper).</p>
                  <p>A politically sensitive study, particularly of <hi rend="i">America</hi>; “In
considering the 1790s, then, we need to keep sight of distinctions among varieties of radical ideology”
(26).</p>
                  <p>Material from “The Political Aesthetic of Blake’s Images,” Chapter 6 (110-32), 
<hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves (2003) appears here in Chapter 4:
“Weary of Time: Image and Commodity in Blake” (155-203), and material from his essay in <hi rend="i">The
Cambridge History of Romanticism</hi> reappears in Chapter 5: “Blake and Romantic Imperialism”
(204-59).</p>
                  <p>§Matsushima, Shoichi. <hi rend="i">Blake no Shiso to Kindai Nihon: Blake wo Yomu</hi>
[<hi rend="i">The Idea of Blake and Modern Japan: A Reading of Blake</hi>]. (Tokyo: Hokuseido, 2003) 308 pp.;
ISBN: 4590011425. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Matsushima, Shoichi, Hisao Ishizuka, Masashi Suzuki, Yoko Ima-Izumi, and Yuko
Takahashi. <hi rend="i">Ekkyo suru Geijutsuka—Ima Blake wo Yomu</hi>: <hi rend="i">William Blake: A
Border-Crossing Artist—Reading his Works Now.</hi> (Tokyo: Eihosha, 2002) 196 pp.; ISBN: 4269720034. In
Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Toru Endo, <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu</hi>: <hi rend="i">Essays in English
Romanticism</hi> 27 (2003): 101-04.</p>
                  <p>Mee, Jon. “William Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and</hi> [of] 
<hi rend="i">Experience.</hi>” Chapter 43 (402-07) of <hi rend="i">A Companion to Literature from Milton to
Blake.</hi> Ed. David Womersley. (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers Ltd., 2000) Blackwell Companions to Literature
and Culture.</p>
                  <p>A reading. Michael F. Suarez, “The Business of Literature: The Book Trade in England
from Milton to Blake” (Chapter 8, 131-48) is not about Blake.</p>
                  <p>*Muggeridge, Malcolm. “William Blake 1757 to 1827.” 84-117 of his <hi rend="i">A
Third Testament.</hi> (London, Glasgow, Sydney, Auckland, Toronto, Johannesburg, 1976) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 580&gt; B. “William Blake 1757-1827.” 45-60 of <hi rend="i">A Third Testament: A
Modern Pilgrim Explores the Spiritual Wanderings of Augustine, Blake, Pascal, Tolstoy, Bonhoeffer, Kierkegaard
and Dostoevsky.</hi> (Farmington [Pennsylvania]: Plough Publishing House, 2002) ISBN: 0874869218.</p>
                  <p>Scripts of a television series on St. Augustine, Pascal, Blake, Kierkegaard, Tolstoy, and
Dietrich Bonhoeffer: “I came to see them as God’s spies” (14 [1976]).</p>
                  <p>Nakayama, Fumi. <hi rend="i">William Blake: 200 Nen go no Seikimatsu</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">William Blake: Blake in 2000</hi>]. (Osaka: Osaka Kyoiku Tosho, 2001) 180 pp.; ISBN: 4271116890. In
Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Niimi, Hatsuko. “Blake no Kakugen teki Hyoghen to Fuyu suru Text [Blake’s Proverbial
Expression and the Floating Text].” 166-75 of <hi rend="i">Sozoryoku no Hisho</hi> [<hi rend="i">Soaring
Imagination</hi>]. Ed. Ririko Tezuka and Kyosuke Tezuka. (Tokyo: Hokuseido, 2003) ISBN: 459001145X. In
Japanese.</p>
                  <p>A study of proverbs in Blake and Pope. The volume contains 42 essays about English and U.
S. literature.</p>
                  <p>*Otto, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence: Love, Jealousy, and the
Sublime in</hi> The Four Zoas. (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <pb id="p38-28" n="28"/>
                  <p>§Alan Nicholson, <hi rend="i">Literature and Theology</hi> 16 (2002): 223-26.</p>
                  <p>§Wayne C. Ripley, <hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi> 27 (Aug. 2002)
&lt;http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/2002/v/n27/006567ar.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Paley, Morton D. “Blake.” 327-40 of <hi rend="i">The Columbia History of British
Poetry.</hi> Ed. Carl Woodring. (New York: Columbia University Press, 1994) &lt;§<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2003), citing a 1996 printing&gt;</p>
                  <p>A summary of the poetry.</p>
                  <p>*Patenaude, Troy R. C. “‘The glory of a Nation’: Recovering William Blake’s 1809
Exhibition.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 4.1 (2003): 52-63.</p>
                  <p>A densely factual and original reconstruction with diagrams of the rooms in which
Blake’s exhibition was held and of the order and exact placement of the pictures one flight above his
brother’s shop at 28 Broad Street. Doubtless more of the facts supporting his hypotheses are given in his
York M.A. thesis called “Window to the World: A Study of William Blake’s 1809 One-Man Exhibition”
(2001).</p>
                  <p>Pearsall, Derek. <hi rend="i">William Langland, William Blake, and the Poetry of
Hope.</hi> (Kalamazoo [Michigan]: Medieval Institute Publications, 2003) The Morton W. Bloomfield Lectures on
Medieval English Literature, 8°, ii, 22 pp.; ISBN 1580440436.</p>
                  <p>Phillips, Michael. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Creation of the</hi> Songs. (2001)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>§Barthélemy Jobert, <hi rend="i">Revue de l’art</hi> 132 (2001): 87 (with the Tate
exhibition [2001]). In French.</p>
                  <p>*Pierce, John B. <hi rend="i">The Wond’rous Art: William Blake and Writing.</hi>
(Madison, Teaneck [New Jersey]: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press; London: Associated University Presses,
2003) 8°, 188 pp.; ISBN: 0838639380.</p>
                  <p>“This book is a study of the representation of writing in the works of William
Blake,” about “the way in which the graphic and the oral are used as conceptual fields in Blake’s
works” (9, 27).</p>
                  <p>Chapter 5, “Rewriting Milton” (130-51, 173-76) appeared in altered form as
“Rewriting Milton: Orality and Writing in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 39.3 (2000): 449-70. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2001)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Prickett, Stephen. “Swedenborg, Blake, Joachim, and the Idea of a New Era.” 
<hi rend="i">Studia Swedenborgiana</hi> 7.4 (June 1992) &lt;http://www.baysidechurch.org&gt;. &lt;§<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;</p>
                  <p>“There can be no doubt at all, I think, that what most appealed to Blake in
Swedenborg’s doctrines was the notion of a new era? and [sic] that he valued it not because it was a
startlingly original teaching but precisely because it was in keeping with a much older tradition of mystical
prophecy.”</p>
                  <p>Punter, David. “Blake and Gwendolen: Territory, Periphery and the Proper Name.”
Chapter 4 (54-68, 220-21) of <hi rend="i">English Romanticism and the Celtic World.</hi> Ed. Gerard Carruthers
and Alan Rawes. (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003).</p>
                  <p>It is an attempt “to think through Blake’s ‘Celtism,’” to examine “a set of
Celtic allusions in Blake’s work—almost entirely in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” (56).</p>
                  <p>*Punter, David. “William Blake.” Chapter 6 (79-90) of <hi rend="i">Literature in
Context.</hi> Ed. Rick Rylance and Judy Simons. (Basingstoke and New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2001).</p>
                  <p>An examination of the “complex” contexts of the “Chimney Sweeper” poems in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi></p>
                  <p>§Raffel, Burton. “Excerpt, ‘Translation: Processes and Attitudes.’” 
<hi rend="i">Literary Review</hi> 45 (2002): 632-34.</p>
                  <p>*Raine, Kathleen. “Blake’s Debt to Antiquity.” (1963) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2482&gt; B. <hi rend="i">Blake and Antiquity</hi>: a shorter version of <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>
(1977) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 613&gt; C. Tr. Masakazu Yoshimura into Japanese as <hi rend="i">Blake to
Kodai</hi> (1988) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 613&gt; D. §<hi rend="i">Blake and Antiquity.</hi> Second
Edition. (London and New York: Routledge, 2002) Classics Series, 192 pp.; ISBN: 0415285828 and 041528581.</p>
                  <p>Rawlinson, Nick. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Comic Vision.</hi> (Basingstoke: Palgrave
Macmillan, 2003) 8°, xiii, 292 pp.; ISBN: 0333745655 (outside North America) and 0312220642 (in North
America).</p>
                  <p>Especially about joy in Blake; “Blake was a subtle, profound and skilled comic
writer” whose “work seems to pulse with comic energy” (2, 1).</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>T. Hoagwood, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 41 (2003): 152 “Recommended”).</p>
                  <p>§Reif-Hülser, Monika. “‘Exuberance is beauty’: William Blake—der Revolutionär
als Sammler.” 227-50 of <hi rend="i">Sammler-Bibliophile-Exzentriker.</hi> Ed. Aleida Assman, Monika
Gomille, et al. (Tübingen: Gunter Narr, 1998) Literatur und Anthropologie, 1. In German.</p>
                  <p>§Risden, E. L. “William Blake and the Personal Epic Fantastic.” <hi rend="i">Journal
of the Fantastic in the Arts</hi> 12 (2002): 417-24.</p>
                  <p>On epiphany.</p>
                  <p>Rix, Robert W. “Blake’s A SONG OF LIBERTY.” <hi rend="i">Explicator</hi> 60 (2002):
131-34.</p>
                  <p>The “Brethren” who are “accepted” and “free” are Freemasons.</p>
                  <p>Rix, Robert. “Healing the Spirit: William Blake and Magnetic Religion.” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi> 25 (Feb. 2002): 37 paragraphs
&lt;http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/2002/v/n25/006011ar.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Robinson, Henry Crabb. “William Blake, Kunstler, Dichter und religiöser Schwärmer.”
<hi rend="i">Vaterländisches Museum</hi> 2 (1811): 107-31. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2538&gt;</p>
                  <pb id="p38-29" n="29"/>
                  <p>The essay is translated in <hi rend="i">Blake no kotoba</hi> [<hi rend="i">Aphoristic
Words from Blake</hi>], ed. Soetsu Yanagi (1921) (in Japanese).</p>
                  <p>Rowland, Christopher. “The Common People and the Bible: Winstanley, Blake and
Liberation Theology.” 149-60 (abstract on 164-65) of <hi rend="i">Winstanley and the Diggers,
1649-1999.</hi> Ed. Andrew Bradstock. (London and Portland [Oregon]: Frank Cass, 2000).</p>
                  <p>Winstanley and Blake belong “to a long line of Christian radicals who . . . [stress]
the ability of all people to understand the ways of God” (149).</p>
                  <p>§Sáenz Obregón, Javier. “Inocencia, experiencia, e imaginación: La obra poética de
William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Revista Universidad de Antioquia</hi> 260 (2000): 18-34. In Spanish.</p>
                  <p>*Saklofske, Jon. “A Fly in the Ointment: Exploring the Creative Relationship between
William Blake and Thomas Gray.” <hi rend="i">Word &amp; Image</hi> 19 (2003): 166-79.</p>
                  <p>About Blake’s watercolors for Gray.</p>
                  <p>§Salvadori, Francesca. “L’Inferno redento: William Blake interprete di Dante.” 
<hi rend="i">Lettere Italiane</hi> 51 (1999): 567-92. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>§Sangu, Makoto. “Shochogaka William Blake [A Symbolic Painter William Blake].” 
<hi rend="i">Mizue</hi> [<hi rend="i">Watercolor</hi>] No. 116 (Oct. 1914): 6-9. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Sato, Hikari. “‘It is not in Terms that Reynolds &amp; I disagree’: William Blake
to [and] Sir Joshua Reynolds.” <hi rend="i">Kobe-Daigaku Bungakubu Kiyo: Bulletin of the Faculty of Letters,
Kobe University</hi> No. 30 (2003): 19-49. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Sato, Hikari. “‘Mite Shri so, Shiri te na Miso’: Yanagi Muneyoshi to William Blake:
‘The Eye sees more than the Heart knows’: William Blake and YANAGI Muneyoshi.” 
<hi rend="i">Tohoku-Gakuin Daigaku Eigo Eibungaku Kenkyujo Kiyo: Journal of Institute for Research in English
Language and Literature, Tohoku-Gakuin University</hi> No. 28 (1999): 1-23. In Japanese, with English
abstract.</p>
                  <p>About “the relationship between his [Yanagi’s] study of William Blake and his folk
craft movement.”</p>
                  <p>Sato, Hikari. “‘Rintrah roars &amp; shakes his fires in the burdend air’: 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> to Ikareru Yogensha: ‘Rintrah roars &amp; shakes his fires in
the burdend air’: The <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and an Angry Prophet.” 
<hi rend="i">Kobe Daigaku Bungakubu Kiyo: Bulletin of the Faculty of Letters, Kobe University</hi> No. 29 (2002):
1-26. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Schock, Peter A. “Blake, the Son of Fire, and the God of this World.” Chapter 2
(41-77, 170-75) of his <hi rend="i">Romantic Satanism: Myth and the Historical Moment in Blake, Shelley, and
Byron.</hi> (Basingstoke and New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2003).</p>
                  <p>§Serra, Cristóbal. <hi rend="i">Pequeño diccionario de William Blake</hi> (Caracteres
simbólicos). (Palma de Mallorca: J. J. de Olañeta, 1992) 86 pp., 30 plates. In Spanish. &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2001)&gt; B. [Second Edition] (Barcelona: Alejandría, 2000) 4°, 86 pp.; ISBN:
8476510861. In Spanish.</p>
                  <p>“A manera de prólogo” (5-6 [2000]). Alphabetical accounts of hard names.</p>
                  <p>Shaw, John. “Unknown Blakes Sell for £5m.” <hi rend="i">Times</hi> 19 Feb. 2003:
5.</p>
                  <p>The drawings for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> were “found by chance [by two book
dealers] in a second-hand [Glasgow] bookshop”; “The Tate Gallery had been prepared to pay £4.9 million
for them, but a dealer [Libby Howie] acting for an anonymous client” bought them for a trifle more.</p>
                  <p>Shioe, Kozo. “Blake to [and] Gothic.” 37-46 of <hi rend="i">Bi to Geijutsu no
Shunposhion</hi> [<hi rend="i">Symposium of Beauty and Art</hi>]. Ed. Osaka Daigaku Bigaku Kenkyukai [Society
of Aesthetic Studies of Osaka University]. (Tokyo: Keiso Shobo, 2002) ISBN: 4326851775. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Smith, K. E. <hi rend="i">An Analysis of William Blake’s Early Writings and Designs to
1790, Including SONGS OF INNOCENCE.</hi> (1999) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (§2000, 2001)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.1 (summer 2003): 36-38 (“Some useful
contextualization notwithstanding, this effort does not live up to its claim to offer ‘An Analysis’”
[38]).</p>
                  <p>§Snart, J. “‘Orison’: A Possible Source for William Blake’s ‘Urizen.’” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 49.1 (2002): 14-15.</p>
                  <p>*Snart, Jason. “Recentering Blake’s Marginalia.” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library
Quarterly</hi> 66 (2003): 134-53.</p>
                  <p>Especially about the authorship and handwriting in the marginalia to Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>: “What I have tried to show here is the degree to which textual and material issues
pervade the marginalia” (153).</p>
                  <p>§Snart, Jason Allen. “The Torn Book: Fixity, Fluidity, Disorder and Energy in William
Blake’s Marginalia.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 63 (2002): 2257A. Florida Ph.D.</p>
                  <p>Sontag, Frederick. <hi rend="i">Truth and Imagination: The Universes Within.</hi> (Lanham
[Maryland], New York, Oxford: University Presses of America, 1998) 8°, xvi, 92 pp.; ISBN: 076180921X.</p>
                  <p>“PREFACE: Blake on the Origin of Creativity and Understanding” (ix-xiii). The book is
a “quest for the new vision in which Blake specializes” (1), especially in Chapter 1: “Exploring the
Worlds within the Mind” (1-45).</p>
                  <p>Spector, Sheila A. <hi rend="i">“Glorious incomprehensible”: The Development of
Blake’s Kabbalistic Language.</hi> (2001); <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”:</hi>
	<pb id="p38-30" n="30"/>
	<hi rend="i">The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Myth.</hi> (2001) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Judith Mueller, “Blake in the New Millennium,” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi> 36.2 (2003): 294-99, esp. 297-98 (with G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Stranger from
Paradise</hi>, Christopher Z. Hobson, <hi rend="i">Blake and Homosexuality</hi>, and Nicholas M. Williams, 
<hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William Blake</hi>).</p>
                  <p>Jeremy Tambling, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 98 (2003): 573-74 (he is
“unconvinced”).</p>
                  <p>Spooner, J. [i.e., Shearjashub]. <hi rend="i">Anecdotes of Painters, Engravers,
Sculptors, and Architects, and Curiosities of Art.</hi> In Three Volumes. (New York: J. W. Booton, 1865).</p>
                  <p>“Extract from Text and Plate of the American Edition of Boydell’s Illustrations of
Shakspeare” (I, 1-10), about the “melancholy” life of William Blake in Cunningham (3).</p>
                  <p>§Stevenson, Mary Malinda. “Martin Heidegger and William Blake: Toward an Ontological
Aesthetics.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 62 (2001): 1007A. Texas (Arlington) Ph.D., 2001.</p>
                  <p>*Stevenson, Warren. “Interpreting Blake’s <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 13 (1977): 115-26. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 439&gt; B. Revised
and updated as *“From Canterbury to Jerusalem: Interpreting Blake’s <hi rend="i">Canterbury
Pilgrims.</hi>” 191-209 of <hi rend="i">Chaucer Illustrated: Five Hundred Years of The Canterbury Tales in
Pictures.</hi> Ed. William K. Finley and Joseph Rosenblum. (New Castle [Delaware]: Oak Knoll Press, and
London: British Library, 2003).</p>
                  <p>A figure-by-figure summary. Appendix 1 in 2003 (369-78) gives the section on Chaucer from
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue.</hi></p>
                  <p>§Streufert, Steven M. “The Anti-Teleological Dialogism of the Imagination: A Study of
the <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>” (2003)
&lt;http://streufert.www4.50megs.com/blaketext.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>This is presumably his M.A. thesis with the same title at Humboldt State University
(Arcata, California).</p>
                  <p>§Szenczi, Miklós. “Blake tanitása képzeletrõl [Blake on Imagination].” 333-47 of
his <hi rend="i">Tanulmányok</hi> [<hi rend="i">Essays</hi>]. (Budapest: Akadémiai, 1989). In Hungarian.</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Taiyoka</hi> [<hi rend="i">Sunflower</hi>] No. 10: Blake Centenary Issue
(Sept. 1927). In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Contributions by Saneatsu Mushanokoji, “[On Blake]” 4-5; Motomaro Senge, “[On
Blake]” 5; Ryusei Kishida, “[Blake]” 6; Kotaro Takamura, “[Blake’s Imagination]” 7; Michisei Kono,
“[On Blake]” 8-9; Kenji Otsuki, “[Blake, a Mystic]” 9-10; Shichiro Nagai, “[On Blake]” 11; Sokichi
Hirose, “[My Recollection of Blake]” 12; Tatsuo Moriwaki, “[Blake’s Eyes]” 13; Kohei Ara, “[Blake
and Myth]” 14; Takeo Sumida, “[On Blake]” 15-16.</p>
                  <p>§Tanaka, Takao. “William Blake no Keiken no Uta [<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
of William Blake].” <hi rend="i">Shikoku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Shikoku
University</hi>] 19 (2003): 27-41. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie. “‘What are Those Golden Builders Doing’: Mendelssohn, Blake,
and the (Un)Building of Jerusalem.” Chapter 4 (79-90) of <hi rend="i">British Romanticism and the Jews:
History, Culture, Literature.</hi> Ed. Sheila A. Spector. (New York and Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan,
2002).</p>
                  <p>Comparisons between the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> of Blake (1804[-20]) and of Moses
Mendelssohn (1783).</p>
                  <p>§Townsend, Joyce H., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work.</hi> (London:
Tate Publishing, 2003).</p>
                  <p>Tsai, Yüan-huang. “Romanticism.” <hi rend="i">Youth wenyi</hi> [<hi rend="i">Youth
Literary Arts</hi>] 64.5 (Nov. 1986): 52-59. In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>A study in general of English Romanticism and in particular of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Marriage, Innocence</hi>, etc.</p>
                  <p>§Tsuchiya, Shigeko. “‘Keiken no uta’ saiko.” <hi rend="i">Eigoseinen: Rising
Generation</hi> 145 (1999): 32-34. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Tung, Tsung-hsüan. “Blake’s Dialectical Vision.” <hi rend="i">Wenshi xuebao</hi>
[<hi rend="i">Journal of the College of Liberal Arts</hi> (National Chung-Hsing University, Taiwan)] 27 (June
1997): 193-211.</p>
                  <p>“Blake’s ever-changing binary opposition . . . has so mastered him that in his works
all concepts involving the numbers three or four can be reduced to two basal dialectical concepts.”</p>
                  <p>Veseley, Suzanne Araas. “The Daughters of Eighteenth-Century Science: A Rationalist and
Materialist Context for William Blake’s Female Figures.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 34
(1998): 5-24.</p>
                  <p>“Blake’s female antivisionaries in his later poems . . . are grounded in the
realities of the age” (8).</p>
                  <p>Voting</p>
                  <p>1749: Peter Leigh, Esq; High-Bailiff. <hi rend="i">A Copy of the Poll for a Citizen for
the City and Liberty of Westminster</hi>; Begun to be Taken at Covent-Garden, Upon Wednesday the Twenty-second
Day of November; and Ending on Friday the Eighth Day of December 1749. Candidates, The Right Hon. Granville
Levison Gower, Esq; commonly called Lord Trentham: and Sir George Vandeput, Bart. (London: Printed for J.
Osborn, at the Golden Ball in Paternoster Row; And Sold by the Book-sellers of London and Westminster
M.DCC.XLIX [1749]) On 25 November 1749 the poet’s father “James Blake <hi rend="i">Glasshouse-str.</hi>
[St James] Hosier” voted for Vandeput [a Tory (d. 1784)] and not for Gower [(1721-1803), son of Earl Gower,
Whig Lord of the Admiralty, brother-in-law of the Duke of Bedford]; Leveson-Gower won by 170 votes.</p>
                  <p>1774: Poll Book. On 12 October 1774 the poet’s father “James Blake Broad S<hi
rend="s">t</hi>. Carnaby Mark<hi rend="s">t</hi>. Hosier &amp; Haberdasher” voted for Earl Percy [Col. Hugh
Percy (1742-1818), son of the Duke of Northumberland, friend of the King’s party] and
<pb id="p38-31" n="31"/>
Lord Clinton (not for Lord Montmorency, Lord Mahon, or Humph Coles). Percy won.</p>
                  <p>1780: Thomas Corbett, Esq. High Bailiff. <hi rend="i">Copy of the Poll for the Election
of Two Citizens to serve in the Present Parliament for the City and Liberty of Westminster</hi>: Begun on
Thursday the 7th, and ended On Saturday the 23d September 1780. Candidates, The Hon. Charles James Fox, Sir
George Brydges Rodney, Bart. The Right Hon. Thomas Pelham Clinton (commonly called Earl of Lincoln). . . .
(London: Printed and Sold by W. Richardson, opposite Salisbury Street, in the Strand, 1780). The poet’s
father “James Blake Broad Street Hosier” voted for Fox and wasted his second vote. Fox, famous as an
opponent of Royal privilege, and Admiral Rodney, hero of the battle of Cape St. Vincent (Jan. 1780), won by a
large majority.</p>
                  <p>1784 April 1-May 17: The poet’s father and brother
<q>Jas Blake Broad Street Hosier<lb/>
John Blake Marshall Street Baker
</q>
voted for Fox and wasted their second vote, which could have been given for Sir Cecil Wray, Bart. (1734-1805)
supported by the Tories, or Admiral Samuel Lord Hood (1724-1816). The result was Hood 6,694, Fox 6,233, and
Wray 5,998.</p>
                  <p>1788: The poet’s brother John Blake, of Marshall Street, Baker, and his sometime
print-shop partner “James Parker N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 27 Broad Street Engraver” voted for Fox’s
candidate Lord John Townsend (not Hood, the Government candidate).</p>
                  <p>1790: Blake’s sometime partner James Parker, 27 Broad Street, Engraver, voted for Fox
(who won) and wasted his second vote which could have been for Hood or John Horne Tooke (1736-1812) who had
opposed Fox.</p>
                  <p>Though the poet as a rate-payer was eligible to vote, apparently he never did
so.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n31">31. These voting records are recorded in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, second edition
(2004) 736-37 (1774, 1780, 1784, 1788), 741n (1788, 1790), 742 (1784, 1788), 840 (1749, 1774), 841 (1774,
1784, 1788, 1790), and 842 (1784, 1788). The manuscript records are in Middlesex County Record Office and the
printed poll books in Westminster Public Library.</note></p>
                  <p>Wagner, Rachel Leah. “‘Words of eternity in human forms’: William Blake’s
Transformation of Styles, Forms, and Genres of the Hebrew Bible in ‘Jerusalem.’” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi>
64 (2003): 1294-95A. Iowa Ph.D., 2003.</p>
                  <p>“Blake was aware of biblical structures long before the insights of formal criticism
became commonplace in the twentieth century.”</p>
                  <p>Wang, Chung-lin. “A Special Frame of Mind to Approach William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature &amp; Linguistics</hi> 11 ([Taipei] May 1985): 1-5.</p>
                  <p>Comment on the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and a list of books Blake read.</p>
                  <p>*Warner, Janet. <hi rend="i">Other Sorrows, Other Joys: The Marriage of Catherine Sophia
Boucher and William Blake.</hi> (New York: St. Martin’s Press, 2003) Small 4°, xi, 371 pp., 24
illustrations; ISBN: 031231440X.</p>
                  <p>It is “a tapestry of fact and fiction” in which the carefully reported facts come
from the poet’s life and writings and the fiction is Kate’s notebook, poems (some of the lines in 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> are hers), visions, her forgeries of Flaxman and Fuseli, her French lover Paul-Marc
Philipon (369, 370), Blake’s affair with the actress and singer Elizabeth Billington, his indulgence in
opium and other drugs, and a good deal of sexual detail. There are “Biographical Notes” on real people
(365-68) and “Author’s Note” (369-71). The fiction is often persuasive: “There are no Evil Spirits,
Kate. There are only Human Spirits” (8).</p>
                  <p>In 2001, an extract about Catherine’s stillborn child called “Blake’s Wife”
appeared on the <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> web site. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>*Weir, David. <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West: William Blake and the Oriental
Renaissance.</hi> (Albany: State University of New York Press, 2003) 8°, xiii, 170 pp., ISBN: 0791458172 and
0791458510.</p>
                  <p>About Blake’s “relationship to Indic culture in three . . . contexts: the political
[Chapter 1], the mythographic [Chapter 2], and the theological [Chapter 3]” largely “as conveyed to Blake
through the medium of the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi>” (16, 36).</p>
                  <p>Appendix A is “Mythographic Material from Joseph Priestley’s <hi rend="i">Comparison
of the Institutions of Moses with those of the Hindoos</hi>” (129-31) (mostly lists of names and books).
Appendix B is “Synopsis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” (133-42).</p>
                  <p>Weng, T.S. “Notes and Observations on William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, Showing the Two Contrary States of the Human
Soul.” <hi rend="i">Guoli bianyi guan guankan</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of National Institute for
Compilation and Translation</hi>] 8.1 ([Taipei] June 1979): 1-95.</p>
                  <p>A life of Blake plus notes and comments on the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
                  <p>Whittaker, Jason. “Blake.” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 81
(Covering work published in 2000) (2002): 634-41.</p>
                  <p>*Williams, Nicholas M. <hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William
Blake.</hi> (Cambridge: University Press, 1998) Cambridge Studies in Romanticism, 28. &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1999)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Judith Mueller, “Blake in the New Millennium,” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi> 36.2 (2003): 294-99, esp. 295-96 (with G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Stranger from
Paradise</hi>, Christopher Z. Hobson, <hi rend="i">Blake and Homosexuality</hi>, Sheila A. Spector, 
“<hi rend="i">Wonders Divine</hi>” and “<hi rend="i">Glorious incomprehensible</hi>”).</p>
                  <p>Worrall, David. “Blake.” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 79
(Covering work published in 1998) (2001): 478-85.</p>
                  <p>Thorough and reliable.</p>
                  <p>§Yamazaki, Yusuke. “Blake’s Novelistic Idea—The Fundamental Idea of the
Contrary.” <hi rend="i">Nagasaki Wesleyan Daigaku Chiiki Sogo Kenkyujo Kenkyu Kiyo</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Research Institute of Regional Area Study, Nagasaki Wesleyan University</hi>] 1.1
(2003): 33-46. In Japanese.</p>
                  <pb id="p38-32" n="32"/>
                  <p>Yanagi, Soetsu (Muneyoshi). <hi rend="i">William Blake: kare no shogai to seisaku oyobi
sono shiso</hi> [<hi rend="i">William Blake: His Life, Works, and Thought</hi>]. (Tokyo: Rakuyo Do, 1914) 756
pp. In Japanese. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #3029&gt;</p>
                  <p>The book incorporates his essays in <hi rend="i">Shirakaba</hi> (1914) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #3027, 3030&gt; and an unpublished essay on “Blake as a Man of Thought.”</p>
                  <p>Yang, Mu. “Wei Blake chen [A Petition for Blake].” <hi rend="i">Lianhe bao</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">United Daily News</hi>, Taipei] 21 Nov. 1993: 37 (Literary Supplement). In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>Pace Zhifan Chen, “Shi kong zhi hai—chenggong hu bian sanji zhi san [The Sea of Time
and Space—Third Essay Written on the Side of Chenggong Lake],” <hi rend="i">Lianhe bao</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">United Daily News</hi>, Taipei] 8 Jan. 1994: 37, Blake is not “a painter” or “a mystic poet”
but “an engraving artist,” and the first two lines of “Auguries of Innocence” (“To see a World in a
grain of Sand | And a heaven in a wild flower”) are not “frequently cited.”</p>
                  <p>§Yano, Atsushi. “Bakemono: Henkaku ki no Motarsu vision to Sono Otoshigo tachi William
Blake: A Study of Images in Art and Literature with Special Reference to the Decline and Fall of Order:
Monstrous and Imaginary Beings in Blake, Gruenewald, and Japanese Literature.” <hi rend="i">Nishinippon
Kogyo Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Nishinippon Institute of Technology</hi>] No. 17 (2001):
11-17. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Yeats, William Butler. “William Blake and his Illustrations to the Divine Comedy.”
(1896) B. Reprinted as 176-225 of his <hi rend="i">Ideas of Good and Evil.</hi> (London, 1903) C. (New York,
1903) D. Second Edition (London, 1903) E. Third Edition (London and Dublin, 1907) F. Reprinted as 138-175 of
<hi rend="i">Ideas of Good and Evil</hi>, which in turn is Vol. VI of <hi rend="i">The Collected Works in
Verse &amp; Prose of William Butler Yeats.</hi> (1908) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 3051 #A-F&gt; G. §<hi
rend="i">Zen-aku no Kannen</hi> [<hi rend="i">Ideas of Good and Evil</hi>]. Tr. Makoto Sangu into Japanese.
(Tokyo: To-undo Shoten, 1915) H. Reprinted in 116-45 of Yeats’s <hi rend="i">Essays and Introductions.</hi>
(1961) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #3051G&gt;</p>
                  <p>The Sangu translation has a preface by Yonejiro Noguchi.</p>
                  <p>Yen, Aizhu, and Chunrong Zhang, ed. <hi rend="i">Ying Mei ming shi shanxi</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Appreciations and Analyses of Famous English-American Poems</hi>]. (Taipei: Wenhe chuban guongsi
[Crane Publishing Company], 1996). In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>Interpretations of “London,” “A Poison Tree,” “Song [I love the jocund
dance],” and “Why Was Cupid a Boy?” (114-21).</p>
                  <p>*Youngquist, Paul. “In the Face of Beauty: Camper, Bell, Reynolds, Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Word &amp; Image</hi> 16 (2000): 319-34. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt; B. Revised as
“Possessing Beauty,” 58-69 of his <hi rend="i">Monstrosities: Bodies and British Romanticism.</hi>
(Minneapolis and London: University of Minnesota Press, 2003).</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Za myuzu</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Muse</hi>] 5.1: Blake Centenary issue
(Oct. 1927). In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>It includes Blake essays by Bunjiro Shima, “Blake ni tsuite [On Blake],” 2-3 &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #2699 (recording the name as Fujiro Shima)&gt;; Masatoshi Kuroda, “Blake’s Illustrations
to the <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi>,” 5-13 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2089&gt;; and Bunsho Jugaku, “Art
of William Blake,” 14-17 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1969&gt;.</p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Allan Cunningham (1784-1842)</p>
                <p>Biographer</p>
                <p>Greene, Richard. “Allan Cunningham (1784-1842).” 46-52 of 
<hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century British Literary Biographers.</hi> Ed. Steven Serafin. (Detroit, Washington
[D.C.], London: Gale Research, 1994) Dictionary of Literary Biography, 154.</p>
                <p>John Flaxman (1756-1826)</p>
                <p>Sculptor, intimate friend of Blake</p>
                <p>24 April-14 June 2003</p>
                <p>§<hi rend="i">John Flaxman, 1755-1826: Master of the Purest Line.</hi> [An exhibition 24
April-14 June 2003 at Sir John Soane’s Museum and University College, London.] Ed. David Bindman. (London:
Sir John Soane’s Museum and University College, London, 2003) 64 pp.</p>
                <p>It includes:</p>
                <p>Deanne Petherbridge, “Constructing the Trajectory of the Line.”</p>
                <p>Anna Schultz, “From Student to Professor of Sculpture: John Flaxman and the Royal
Academy.”</p>
                <p>Alison Wright, “‘In the Spirit’: Flaxman and Swedenborg.”</p>
                <p>Bethan Stevens, “Putting to Rights Some of the Wrecks: Nancy Flaxman’s Contributions to
the Italian Journey.”</p>
                <p>Helen Dorey, “Flaxman and Soane.”</p>
                <p>Eckart Marchand, “The Flaxman Gallery at University College London and its
History.”</p>
                <p>§Bell, Daniel. <hi rend="i">A Pious Bacchanal: Affinities Between the Lives and Works of
John Flaxman and Aubrey Beardsley.</hi> (Frankfurt-am-Main and New York: Peter Lang, 2000) Studies in
Interdisciplinarity, 10.</p>
                <p>§Bilbey, Diane, with the assistance of Marjorie Trusted. <hi rend="i">British Sculpture
1470 to 2000: A Concise Catalogue of the Collection at the Victoria &amp; Albert Museum.</hi> (London: V&amp;A
Publications, 2002).</p>
                <p>Valuable for the section on Flaxman.</p>
                <p>Henry Fuseli (1741-1825)</p>
                <p>Painter, intimate friend of Blake</p>
                <p>7 September-7 December 1997</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Füssli pittore di Shakespeare: pittura e teatro, 1775-1825.</hi> [An
exhibition 7 September-7 December 1997 at Fondazione Magnani Rocca, Mamiano di Traversetolo (Parma).] Ed. Fred
Licht, Simona Tosini Pizzetti, David H. Weinglass. (Milano: Electa, 1997) 239 pp.</p>
                <pb id="p38-33" n="33"/>
                <p>Simona Tosini Pizzetti, “Biografia.”</p>
                <p>Anna Ottani Cavina, “Fuga delle tenebre.”</p>
                <p>Florens Deuchler, “Johann Heinrich Füssli, ‘Tempesta e uragano.’”</p>
                <p>Fred Licht, “Füssli, luci e fosforescenze.”</p>
                <p>Concetto Nicosia, “Lo spazio, il corpo, l’espressione.”</p>
                <p>David H. Weinglass, “Le gallerie pittoresque a Londra tra il 1780 e il 1800.”</p>
                <p>15 October 2001-14 January 2002</p>
                <p>§Régis Michel. <hi rend="i">La peinture comme crime: ou, la part maudite de la
modernité.</hi> Musée du Louvre, Hall Napoléon. (Paris: Éditions de la Réunion des musées nationaux,
2001) ISBN: 2711843084. In French.</p>
                <p>There are sections on Blake, Fuseli, Goya, and Romney, inter alia.</p>
                <p>Junod, Karen. “Henry Fuseli’s Pragmatic Use of Aesthetics: His Epic Illustrations of
<hi rend="i">Macbeth.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Word &amp; Image</hi> 19 (2003): 138-50.</p>
                <p>§Myrone, Martin. <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli.</hi> (London: Tate Gallery Publishing, 2001)
British Artists. 80 pp.; ISBN: 1854373579.</p>
                <p>§Rossi Pinelli, Orietta. <hi rend="i">Füssli.</hi> (Florence: Giunti, 1997) Arte e
dossier: Dossier 126; ISBN: 8809762339. In Italian.</p>
                <p>§Timbs, John (1801-75). <hi rend="i">Anecdote Lives of William Hogarth, Sir Joshua
Reynolds, Thomas Gainsborough, Henry Fuseli, Sir Thomas Lawrence, and J. M. W. Turner.</hi> (1872) B.
§(Portsmouth: Bardon Enterprises, 1997) 912 pp.</p>
                <p>§Zeri, Federico. <hi rend="i">Fuseli: Titania and Bottom with the Head of an Ass.</hi> Tr.
Susan Scott. (Richmond Hill, Ontario: NDE Publishing, 2001) ISBN: 1553210247.</p>
                <p>The Italian edition was published in Milan: RCS Libri, 1998.</p>
                <p>John Linnell (1792-1882)</p>
                <p>Painter and patron of Blake</p>
                <p>1994</p>
                <p>§<hi rend="i">Lifting Veil from Nature, John Linnell, 1792-1882</hi>: An Exhibition to
Mark the Publication of the Book <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell &amp; Co</hi> by David Linnell. (London:
Martyn Gregory, 1994).</p>
                <p>Samuel Palmer (1805-81)</p>
                <p>Painter and disciple</p>
                <p>Christie’s, Important British &amp; Irish Art, 11 June 2003</p>
                <p>Samuel Palmer, “The Golden Valley,” estimate £500,000-£800,000 (made £587,650).</p>
                <p>Essays by Andrew Wilton, “The Golden Valley” (37) and Colin Harrison, of the Ashmolean,
“Palmer the Visionary” (38-46). The two essays are reprinted in the separate Christie publication 
<hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi>, “<hi rend="i">The Golden Valley</hi>,” 11 June 2003, 19 and 20-29, and
Harrison’s essay also appears as “Palmer’s Earthly Paradise,” <hi rend="i">Christie’s Magazine</hi>
(May-June 2003): 62-65.</p>
                <p>Thomas Stothard (1755-1834)</p>
                <p>Artist and friend of Blake</p>
                <p>Read, Dennis M. “Thomas Stothard’s <hi rend="i">The Pilgrimage to Canterbury</hi>
(1806): A Study in Promotion and Popular Taste.” Chapter 6 (211-31) of <hi rend="i">Chaucer Illustrated:
Five Hundred Years of The Canterbury Tales in Pictures.</hi> Ed. William K. Finley and Joseph Rosenblum. (New
Castle [Delaware]: Oak Knoll Press, and London: British Library, 2003).</p>
                <p>The contemporary popularity of the picture is probably due chiefly to “the orchestrations
of publicity, endorsements, and huckstering by its proprietor, Robert Hartley Cromek” (211).</p>
                <p>Part IV (221-23) deals somewhat summarily with Blake’s claim that Stothard stole his idea
for a painting of the procession of the Canterbury Pilgrims: “There is no way to verify this claim, although
Cromek certainly was capable of such theft. Cromek’s claim of the painting’s origin, as elaborated in the
‘Biographical Sketch of Robert Hartley Cromek’ in the 1813 <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> is, to say the least,
fanciful,” for, among other things, it dates Cromek’s conception of “the idea of embodying the whole
procession in a picture” to a time “some ten months after Cromek began exhibiting the painting in his
home” (222).</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Index</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Ackroyd, Peter 8, 10n, 13, 16</p>
              <p>Adams, Hazard 18, 19</p>
              <p>Akabane, Oro 14</p>
              <p>Altizer, Thomas 8, 16</p>
              <p>Ansari, A. A. 16</p>
              <p>Aquien, Pascal 16</p>
              <p>Ara, Kohei 30</p>
              <p>Bailey, Martin 7, 9, 14n, 16</p>
              <p>Balfour, Ian 9, 16</p>
              <p>Bamberg, Matt 15</p>
              <p>Beer, John 8, 17, 19</p>
              <p>Bell, Daniel 32</p>
              <p>Bennett, Will 17</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 8, 9, 13, 17, 18</p>
              <p>Bilbey, Diane 32</p>
              <p>Bindman, David 6, 9, 12, 15, 17, 22, 32</p>
              <p>Blake, Catherine 8, 17, 26, 31</p>
              <p>Blake, James 20, 21, 30, 31</p>
              <p>Blake, John 31</p>
              <p>Blake, William:<lb/>
<hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> 6, 26; <hi rend="i">America</hi> 8, 22, 23, 24, 27; “Crystal
Cabinet” 19; <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 6, 10, 18; <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: Gates of Paradise</hi> 6, 11;
<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 8, 17, 20, 22, 24, 27, 31; <hi rend="i">French Revolution</hi> 23; 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 22, 28, 30, 31; <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 7, 15, 24, 25; Letters 6, 10n, 11; 
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 6, 11, 12, 16, 18, 19, 26, 29, 30; “Mental Traveller” 19; 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 9, 12, 16, 22, 23, 25, 26; Notebook 12; <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> 6, 11; 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 5n, 6, 9, 11, 12, 16, 18, 19, 20, 23, 24, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32; <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>
6, 10, 18, 24; <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> 6; <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 6, 10, 13, 26; 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 18<lb/>
Illustrations/engravings of/for:<lb/>
Blair (<hi rend="i">Grave</hi>) 6, 7, 9, 13-14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 23, 29; Bryant 14; Cumberland 14; Dante 7;
Darwin 6, 14, 18; Gray 29; Hayley 6, 14, 15; <hi rend="i">Ladies New and Polite Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi>
6-7, 14; Milton 6, 13; Young 14, 15</p>
              <p>Bloom, Harold 6, 11, 18, 19</p>
              <p>Boyce, Michele Dellafield 19</p>
              <p>Bracher, Mark 19</p>
              <p>Burt, Daniel S. 19</p>
              <p>Butlin, Martin 18, 19</p>
              <p>Butter, Peter 13</p>
              <p>Butts, Thomas 22</p>
              <p>Butts, Thomas, Jr. 18</p>
              <pb id="p38-34" n="34"/>
              <p>Cana, Shernaz 17</p>
              <p>Capurro, Soledad 11, 12, 20</p>
              <p>Cardona, Francesc LL. 6, 12</p>
              <p>Carey, William Paulet 19</p>
              <p>Cernuda, Luis 11, 12, 20</p>
              <p>Chang, Ching-erh 5, 24</p>
              <p>Chang, Han-liang 20</p>
              <p>Chayes, Irene 19</p>
              <p>Chen, Pei-chün 5n</p>
              <p>Chen, Peng-hsiang 20</p>
              <p>Chen, Zhifan 20</p>
              <p>Child, Mrs. D. L. 20</p>
              <p>Chong, Cue-huan 20</p>
              <p>Chou, Man-wen 20</p>
              <p>Chukhno, V. 12</p>
              <p>Clark, Steve 15, 20, 24</p>
              <p>Connolly, Tristanne 24</p>
              <p>Corti, Claudia 20</p>
              <p>Crehan, Stewart 18, 19</p>
              <p>Csikós, Dóra 8, 17, 20</p>
              <p>Cunningham, Allan 30, 32</p>
              <p>Curnutte, Richard A. 20</p>
              <p>da Costa Nunes, Jadviga M. 14</p>
              <p>Davies, Keri 24</p>
              <p>den Otter, Alice G. 23</p>
              <p>Deuchler, Florens 33</p>
              <p>Dickinson, Patric 20</p>
              <p>Directories 20-22</p>
              <p>Doi, Kochi 22</p>
              <p>Dorey, Helen 32</p>
              <p>Dortort, Fred 22</p>
              <p>Duff, David 18</p>
              <p>Eaves, Morris 22</p>
              <p>Edwards, Gavin 19</p>
              <p>Elfenbein, Andrew 17</p>
              <p>Endo, Toru 27</p>
              <p>Engelstein, Stefani 22</p>
              <p>Erdman, David V. 17, 19, 22</p>
              <p>Erle, Sibylle 24</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert N. 4n, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 14, 15, 17, 18, 22, 23</p>
              <p>Exhibitions:<lb/>
Buffalo 7; Huntington 7, 15; Kyoto 4n, 7, 15; Northwestern U. 7, 15; Tate 14</p>
              <p>Fairer, David 23</p>
              <p>Flaxman, John 32</p>
              <p>Frank, Peter 23</p>
              <p>Freed, Eugenie 17, 26</p>
              <p>Fresch, Cheryl H. 23</p>
              <p>Friedlander, Edward Robert 9, 23</p>
              <p>Friedman, Samuel 6, 12</p>
              <p>Frye, Northrop 19</p>
              <p>Fuller, David 24</p>
              <p>Fuseli, Henry 32-33</p>
              <p>Garzón, Pablo Mañé 12</p>
              <p>Gimeno Suances, Francisco 9, 23</p>
              <p>Goldberg, Brian 23</p>
              <p>Gonzalez, Martin S. 15</p>
              <p>Goodwin, Karin 23</p>
              <p>Goto, Yumiko 15, 24</p>
              <p>Gourlay, Alexander S. 13, 17, 18, 22, 23</p>
              <p>Grant, John E. 18</p>
              <p>Greene, Richard 32</p>
              <p>Grundy, Thomas 24</p>
              <p>Haigh, Julie 12</p>
              <p>Haraguchi, Masao 23</p>
              <p>Harrison, Colin 33</p>
              <p>Harrison, John R. 23</p>
              <p>Havely, Nicholas 23</p>
              <p>Hearn, Lafcadio 23</p>
              <p>Heisler, Ron 9</p>
              <p>Hilton, Nelson 17, 18, 22, 29</p>
              <p>Hirose, Sokichi 30</p>
              <p>Hoagwood, T. 22, 28</p>
              <p>Hobson, Christopher 18, 23</p>
              <p>Hogarth, William 23</p>
              <p>Holt, Ted 9, 24</p>
              <p>Höltgen, Karl Josef 24</p>
              <p>Hoshino, Eriko 24</p>
              <p>Howie, Michael 24</p>
              <p>Hsia, C. T. 24</p>
              <p>Hsü, Beatrice H. C. 5n</p>
              <p>Hu, Yüngfen 13</p>
              <p>Ikuta, Kotaro 24</p>
              <p>Ima-Izumi, Yoko 8, 24, 27</p>
              <p>Ishizuka, Hisao 8, 27</p>
              <p>James, G. Ingli 12</p>
              <p>Janssens, V. 25</p>
              <p>Jobert, Barthélemy 14, 28</p>
              <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn 22, 25, 26</p>
              <p>Johnston, Kenneth 19</p>
              <p>Jose, Chiramel P. 26</p>
              <p>Jugaku, Bunsho 26, 32</p>
              <p>Junod, Karen 33</p>
              <p>Kao, Tien-en 26</p>
              <p>Kaplan, Nancy 26</p>
              <p>Kashiwabara, Ikuku 26</p>
              <p>Kawasaki, Noriko 26</p>
              <p>Kelleway, Kelly 26</p>
              <p>Kim, Heesun 26</p>
              <p>Kim, Young-shik 26</p>
              <p>Kimura, Shohachi 26</p>
              <p>Kishida, Ryusei 30</p>
              <p>Knellwolf, Christa 24</p>
              <p>Kobayashi, Kaoru 24</p>
              <p>Kobayashi, Keiko 25</p>
              <p>Kochav, Joshua 6, 12</p>
              <p>Kono, Michisei 30</p>
              <p>Kozlowski, Lisa 26</p>
              <p>Kraemer, Christine Hoff 26</p>
              <p>Krafft, Scott 15</p>
              <p>Kuroda, Masatoshi 32</p>
              <p>Lachman, Barbara 17, 26</p>
              <p>Landers, Linda Anne 12</p>
              <p>Larrissy, Edward 25</p>
              <p>Leach, Bernard 4n</p>
              <p>Leopold, Wendy 15</p>
              <p>Leshem, Giora 6, 11</p>
              <p>Leu, Yün-shan 5n</p>
              <p>Li, Ching-hsüan, 6n</p>
              <p>Liang, Shih-ch’iu 26</p>
              <p>Liao, Pingwei 27</p>
              <p>Licht, Fred 32, 33</p>
              <p>Lincoln, Andrew 22</p>
              <p>Lindop, Grevel 27</p>
              <p>Linnell, John 33</p>
              <p>Liu, Hwangcheng 27</p>
              <p>Lu, Yujia 27</p>
              <p>Lukacher, Brian 27</p>
              <p>Lundeen, Kathleen 17, 27</p>
              <p>Lussier, Mark 27</p>
              <p>MacAdam, A. 14</p>
              <p>Makdisi, Saree 8, 22, 27</p>
              <p>Marchand, Eckart 32</p>
              <p>Matsushima, Shoichi 7, 8, 27</p>
              <p>Matthews, Susan 25</p>
              <p>Mee, Jon 9, 22, 27</p>
              <p>Michel, Régis 14, 33</p>
              <p>Miner, Paul 17</p>
              <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. 19</p>
              <p>Moriwaki, Tatsuo 30</p>
              <p>Mueller, Judith 17, 23, 30, 31</p>
              <p>Muggeridge, Malcolm 8, 27</p>
              <p>Mushanokoji, Saneatsu 30</p>
              <p>Myrone, Martin 33</p>
              <pb id="p38-35" n="35"/>
              <p>Nagai, Shichiro 30</p>
              <p>Nakamura, Hiroko 25</p>
              <p>Nakayama, Fumi 7, 27</p>
              <p>Nagasaki, Taro 6, 15</p>
              <p>Nemeczek, Alfred 16</p>
              <p>Nichols, Ashton 25</p>
              <p>Nicholson, Alan 28</p>
              <p>Nicosia, Concetto 33</p>
              <p>Niimi, Hatsuko 25, 27</p>
              <p>Nurmi, Martin K. 18</p>
              <p>Oishi, Kazuyoshi 25</p>
              <p>Okada, Kazuya 25</p>
              <p>Ollman, Leah 15</p>
              <p>Ostriker, Alicia 19</p>
              <p>Otsuki, Kenji 30</p>
              <p>Ottani Cavina, Anna 33</p>
              <p>Otto, Peter 25, 27</p>
              <p>Paananen, Victor 19</p>
              <p>Pagliaro, Harold 18</p>
              <p>Paice, Rosamund A. 6, 9, 10, 14, 18</p>
              <p>Paley, Morton D. 18, 28</p>
              <p>Palmer, Samuel 33</p>
              <p>Palomares, José Luis 10</p>
              <p>Parker, James 31</p>
              <p>Patenaude, Troy R. C. 9, 28</p>
              <p>Pearsall, Derek 8, 28</p>
              <p>Petherbridge, Deanne 32</p>
              <p>Phillips, John William 25</p>
              <p>Phillips, Michael 28</p>
              <p>Pierce, John B. 8, 28</p>
              <p>Plowman, Max 19</p>
              <p>Price, Martin 18</p>
              <p>Prickett, Stephen 28</p>
              <p>Punter, David 10n, 28</p>
              <p>Raffel, Burton 28</p>
              <p>Raine, Kathleen 16, 19, 28</p>
              <p>Ramamurthi, Lalitha 25</p>
              <p>Ratcliff, Carter 14</p>
              <p>Rawlinson, Nick 8, 28</p>
              <p>Read, Dennis M. 33</p>
              <p>Reif-Hülser, Monika 28</p>
              <p>Ripley, Wayne C. 17, 28</p>
              <p>Risden, E. L. 28</p>
              <p>Rix, Robert W. 28</p>
              <p>Robinson, Henry Crabb 12, 28</p>
              <p>Rossi Pinelli, Orietta 33</p>
              <p>Rowland, Christopher 29</p>
              <p>Ryan, Robert 9, 22</p>
              <p>Sáenz Obregón, Javier 29</p>
              <p>Saklofske, Jon 29</p>
              <p>Salvadori, Francesca 29</p>
              <p>Sangu, Makoto 29</p>
              <p>Sato, Hikari 29</p>
              <p>Schock, Peter A. 29</p>
              <p>Schultz, Anna 32</p>
              <p>Senge, Motomaro 30</p>
              <p>Serra, Cristóbal 8, 29</p>
              <p>Shaffer, Elinor 24</p>
              <p>Shaw, John 29</p>
              <p>Shima, Bunjiro 32</p>
              <p>Shioe, Kozo 15, 25, 29</p>
              <p>Simmons, Robert E. 19</p>
              <p>Simpson, David 22</p>
              <p>Smith, K. E. 18, 29</p>
              <p>Snart, Jason 17, 27, 29</p>
              <p>Solé, Joan 6</p>
              <p>Sontag, Frederick 8, 29</p>
              <p>Spector, Sheila A. 9, 18, 29</p>
              <p>Spooner, J. 30</p>
              <p>Stevens, Bethan 32</p>
              <p>Stevenson, Mary Malinda 30</p>
              <p>Stevenson, Warren 30</p>
              <p>Stevenson, W. H. 17</p>
              <p>Storch, Margaret 18, 23</p>
              <p>Stothard, Thomas 33</p>
              <p>Streufert, Steven M. 30</p>
              <p>Sumida, Takeo 30</p>
              <p>Sung, Mei-Ying 25</p>
              <p>Sutherland, John H. 19</p>
              <p>Suzuki, Masashi 8, 15, 24, 27</p>
              <p>Suzuki, Ruriko 25</p>
              <p>Swinburne, Algernon Charles 19</p>
              <p>Szenczi, Miklós 6, 13, 30</p>
              <p>Takahashi, Yuko 8, 27</p>
              <p>Takamura, Kotaro 30</p>
              <p>Tambling, Jeremy 25, 30</p>
              <p>Tanaka, Minne 25</p>
              <p>Tanaka, Takao 25, 30</p>
              <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie 30</p>
              <p>Taylor, David 25</p>
              <p>Thomas, Joseph 7, 16, 24</p>
              <p>Thompson, E. P. 19</p>
              <p>Thurston, J. 7, 16, 24</p>
              <p>Timbs, John 33</p>
              <p>Tosini Pizzetti, Simona 32, 33</p>
              <p>Townsend, Joyce H. 7, 30</p>
              <p>Tsai, Yüan-huang 30</p>
              <p>Tsuchiya, Shigeko 30</p>
              <p>Tsurumi, Shunsuke 25</p>
              <p>Tung, Tsung-hsüan 30</p>
              <p>Turner, Barnard 25</p>
              <p>Unni, Chitta R. 25</p>
              <p>Veseley, Suzanne Araas 30</p>
              <p>Viscomi, Joseph 9, 18, 22, 23</p>
              <p>Voting 30-31</p>
              <p>Vultee, Denise 13</p>
              <p>Wada, Ayako 25</p>
              <p>Wagenknecht, David 19</p>
              <p>Wagner, Rachel Leah 9n, 31</p>
              <p>Wang, Chung-lin 31</p>
              <p>Ward, Aileen 22</p>
              <p>Warner, Janet 8, 31</p>
              <p>Watermarks 10, 11-12</p>
              <p>Weinglass, David H. 32, 33</p>
              <p>Weir, David 8, 31</p>
              <p>Wellens, Oskar 11, 18</p>
              <p>Weng, Jerry Chia-je 6n</p>
              <p>Weng, T. S. 31</p>
              <p>Whittaker, Jason 25, 31</p>
              <p>Willard, Nancy 27</p>
              <p>William Blake Archive 6, 10, 13</p>
              <p>Williams, Nicholas 19, 31</p>
              <p>Wilton, Andrew 33</p>
              <p>Windle, John 7, 15</p>
              <p>Witkin, Joel-Peter 11</p>
              <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. 19</p>
              <p>Wolfson, Susan J. 22</p>
              <p>Worrall, David 24, 31</p>
              <p>Wright, Alison 32</p>
              <p>Xie, Jin-li 6n</p>
              <p>Yamazaki, Yusuke 31</p>
              <p>Yanagi, Soetsu 6, 12, 29, 32</p>
              <p>Yanagi, Sori 15</p>
              <p>Yang, Mu 32</p>
              <p>Yano, Atsushi 32</p>
              <p>Yeats, William 32</p>
              <p>Yen, Aizhu 32</p>
              <p>Yoder, R. Paul 22</p>
              <p>Youngquist, Paul 32</p>
              <p>Yu, Eric K. W. 22, 25</p>
              <p>Zeri, Federico 33</p>
              <p>Zhang, Chunrong 32</p>
              <p>Zhou, Wenbin 12</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
