<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.2.lundeen</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Nick Rawlinson, William Blake’s Comic Vision</title>
        <author n="Lundeen">Kathleen Lundeen</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Kathleen Lundeen</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <body>
	<pb id="p38-85" n="85"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Nick Rawlinson. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Comic
                                Vision.</hi> Basingstoke and New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2003.
                            xiii + 292 pp. $65.00/£42.50 cloth.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Kathleen
                        <name>Lundeen</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Nick Rawlinson reveals the impetus for <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                            Comic Vision</hi> to be “a simple hunch” that he and other
                        readers enjoy Blake, in part, because he is a comic writer (vii).
                        Notwithstanding E. D. Hirsh’s long-ago observation that Blake is the
                        most humorous of the romantics, classifying the man behind the searing eyes
                        of the familiar portraits as a comic writer may seem a bit of a stretch.
                        Rawlinson challenges any incredulity by showing the abundance of comedy in
                        Blake and the significance of its function, and in so doing he allows us to
                        hear Blake in a different key. His book proves to be more than an inventory
                        of the comic elements in Blake, <pb id="p38-86" n="86"/>
however. It is an
                        intriguing argument that comedy is Blake’s vehicle for vision.</p>
          <p>Initially, Rawlinson situates Blake in the comic tradition by way of a
                        particular definition of comedy. At the outset of his argument, he
                        stipulates: “Comedy deflates pretensions, disrupts patterns, and
                        lurks behind the façade of reality to prove that reality to be false.
                        But it goes beyond deconstruction because it insists on a meaning even in
                        meaninglessness—and ‘always meaning’ leads to
                        God” (3). Fundamental to comedy is its role of unmasking imposters,
                        as Rawlinson contends, but the reality it reveals is typically more literal
                        and far less sublime than the one created by pretense. Comic elements often
                        lead to mayhem rather than meaning, and to Godot instead of God.
                        Nevertheless, as Rawlinson argues in this book, comedy in Blake’s
                        early poems has a serious function.</p>
          <p>Rawlinson’s study calls out of the shadows poems of Blake that are
                        often bypassed for the “essential” Blake, the long, obscure
                        prophetic works. Blake’s early poems, ranging from the <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                            Experience</hi>, are well served by viewing them through a comic lens.
                        Rawlinson deftly shows in these poems how Blake introduces comic elements to
                        challenge everything from social structure to empiricism. He argues, for
                        example, that “<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> is not just a generalized
                        attack on tyranny but Blake’s next attempt to offer a comic
                        alternative to materialist aesthetics” (90); and of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, he
writes, “Characterized by a recurrent contrast
                        between sentimental pastoral and satirical urban viewpoints and with a
                        wealth of social voices, they display both wise-foolish and knavish readings
                        of contemporary society” (172).</p>
          <p>By foregrounding the comic and carnivalesque motifs in Blake, Rawlinson
                        checks a tendency to read him as an austere mystic. One of the pleasures
                        this study offers the reader is the opportunity to engage Blake’s
                        early poems in what seems to be their natural element. Within a comic
                        context they appear unusually vibrant and substantial, so much so that some
                        of the poems seem ekphrastic, as if Blake has breathed life into Hogarthian
                        illustrations. Their affinity with eighteenth-century illustrations,
                        according to this book, is not accidental. In a short history of comedy in
                        England, Rawlinson shows how rich and various that tradition is in both its
                        literary and graphic manifestations, documenting how Blake draws generously
                        on the comic tradition: “By participating in the contemporary use of
                        satiric imagery and style, Blake was able to de-mystify political, religious
                        and social authority” (215). But he also shows how Blake exploits the
                        tradition for nontraditional purposes: “Blake’s use of
                        carnival imagery is a challenge to the increasing inwardness and separation
                        implicit in the work of Bacon, Newton, Locke, Hume, Hobbes and Descartes. It
                        leads us, jokingly, back to the Divine Humanity” (216). Though most
                        of the poems Rawlinson examines do not have a prophetic function, he
                        contends that their teleology is vision, which he defines in Blakean fashion
                        as “a matter of seeing beyond material existence to eternal
                        truths” (13). He elaborates on this point, arguing that comedy, to
                        Blake, was “a poetics of reading that was both an artistic and social
                        practice.” He then explains: “By using puns, wordplay and
                        absurd humour he tried to disrupt the sense that language conveys a material
                        reality (in the sense of a set of rules and laws external to the self) and
                        to reinforce the importance of the reader in creating meaning”
                        (215).</p>
          <p>Earlier in the book Rawlinson elaborates on his call for “a new
                        poetics of reading,” arguing that it is necessary if we are to read
                        the comic elements of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                        “in a spiritual, positive way” (171). In his commentary on the
                            <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, he proposes a specific way for reading those
                        comic elements: “It is significant that carnival echoes appear at
                        those moments in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> that critics have concentrated
                        on as showing the positive elements of play and imagination. Carnival is
                        also notably absent from some of the songs where the speaker’s
                        viewpoint seems hopelessly limited” (180-81). Though the simplicity
                        of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> creates the illusion that they conform to
                        symbolic and iconographic codes, two centuries of Blake criticism testify to
                        their elusiveness. Rawlinson’s binary sounds reasonable, but in
                        practice it does not address the complexities of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> In
“Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi>, for example, Blake creates a carnivalesque scene of a
                        piper and airborne child, but their imaginative play, arguably, leads away
                        from vision. As the multi-talented piper/singer/writer “stain[s] the
                        water clear,” the poem itself gradually moves from the free-floating
                        participles in the opening lines to rote, monolithic syntax. In his analysis
                        of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Rawlinson further argues that
                        “Wherever it appears, humour in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> is
                        usually aimed at provoking an alternative reading” (181). Since humor
                        in literature almost always provokes an alternative reading, one may
                        conclude from Rawlinson’s observation that Blake uses humor in the
                            <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in a mundane way—a conclusion that is
                        counterintuitive to any reader of Blake. The sheer pervasiveness of the
                        comic and carnivalesque in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, which Rawlinson
                        aptly notes, tantalizes one to inspect those features more carefully to see
                        how they participate in those sly poetic epigrams.</p>
          <p>Though most of Rawlinson’s study addresses Blake’s literary
                        art, he devotes one chapter to his graphic art. In a move parallel to his
                        analysis of Blake’s poetry, he argues that Blake introduces comic
                        elements into his visual art to serve both conventional and unconventional
                        purposes. He points out that Blake, like many comic illustrators of his day,
                        creates visual puns, caricatures, and carnivalesque motifs to satirize
                        social and political institutions; but he further proposes that Blake
                        incorporates comic elements to advance a larger vision. Sometimes these two
                        objectives coalesce, as he demonstrates in his analysis of Blake’s
                        1795 color printed drawing of Nebuchadnezzar. In the illustrations of other
                        artists, the biblical king is presented as an epitome of all political
                        leaders who are humbled by their own hubris. Blake’s portrait carries
                        that political dimension, but, Rawlinson contends, through
                        Nebuchadnezzar’s crouched posture and beastly claws Blake correlates
                        his humiliating predicament to the doctrine of the 
<pb id="p38-87" n="87"/>
                         fearful sublime. “At a stroke,” Rawlinson states,
                        “Blake has linked visionary and aesthetic failings with the dominion
                        of oppressive kingship” (198).</p>
          <p>Rawlinson’s most extensive analysis is saved for <hi rend="i">An
                            Island in the Moon.</hi> His enthusiasm for the unpublished satire is
                        almost evangelical: “[I]nside this apparently random concoction of
                        prose, song and slapstick, with its eccentric mix of real and imaginary
                        characters that read like the cast list of an absurd farce, lies an
                        extraordinary, almost dazzling examination of the relationship between our
                        habits of reading and the society they produce” (99). He further
                        extols the work by declaring it “a masterclass in the development of
                        the satirical style” (99) and “nothing less than a degree
                        course in comic Vision” (100). “<hi rend="i">An
                        Island</hi>,” he writes, “is Blake’s attempt to produce
                        a theatrical experience, a comic education in how to read. This marvellous
                        text is so dense that perhaps the best way to approach it is to treat it as
                        if it were a carnival procession; first having a look at the cast and then
                        discussing each episode sequentially, before summarising the action as a
                        whole” (104). And elsewhere he describes <hi rend="i">An Island</hi>
                        as “an important and valuable work, an extensive comic education that
                        explores the inter-relationship of language, society and God” and
                        calls it “Blake’s first attempt to produce a new form of
                        literary expression, part playscript, part performance, part experimental
                        novel” (161). Few critics have given <hi rend="i">An Island</hi> such
                        a prominent place in Blake’s body of work, but Rawlinson’s
                        argument is convincing (or his exuberance is contagious). <hi rend="i">An
                            Island</hi> does, indeed, seem to be a culmination of Blake’s
                        comic efforts, and, as Rawlinson’s rhetoric urges, it deserves to
                        frequent more undergraduate syllabi.</p>
          <p>Rawlinson’s readings of Blake are by and large rewarding. His thesis
                        is nevertheless problematic in one respect. Whether or not Blake is a comic
                        writer and artist depends, naturally, on how one defines
                        “comedy.” In Rawlinson’s study, “comedy”
                        is a rather flexible term. As noted earlier, it is sometimes defined broadly
                        as anything ironic or festive, while at other times it assumes a very
                        particular definition, requiring a moral teleology. Running into problems of
                        genre may be unavoidable since (in the words of a former professor of mine)
                        Blake “displaces too much water” to fit comfortably into any
                        literary tradition. Yet Rawlinson’s observation that Blake creates
                        “a new form of literary expression” invites us to approach the
                        problem in another way. Blake, in his contrary manner, produces prophecies
                        that are carnivalesque and burlesque poems that have philosophical weight,
                        each type of poetry gravitating toward the other. In effect, he deconstructs
                        the prophetic/profane binary, opting for a hybrid genre in which that
                        oppositional friendship might flourish.</p>
          <p>Toward the end of his study Rawlinson invites other critics to examine the
                        comic and carnivalesque characteristics in Blake’s prophetic poetry.
                        If we extrapolate from the argument Rawlinson presents in this study, we
                        might suspect that Blake introduces comedy into his prophecies also in the
                        service of vision, perhaps giving it the specific function of critiquing the
                        institutionalized ways of reading prophecy, which militate against visionary
                        reception. Then, again, Blake is not above self-mockery, which suggests
                        alternatively that he introduces comedy into the prophecies capriciously to
                        check any essentializing tendencies. To discover whether Blake charges the
                        carnivalesque characters in his later work with a prophetic function or
                        simply enlists them to snicker on the sidelines would require us to take
                        another critical journey—one that exceeds the itinerary of this
                        study, but one for which Rawlinson has provided a topographical map of
                        Blake’s comic terrain.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
