<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.2.taylor</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Sheila A. Spector, “Wonders Divine”: The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic
Myth</title>
        <author n="Taylor">Dena Bain Taylor</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Kathleen Lundeen</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <body>
	<pb id="p38-79" n="79"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Sheila A. Spector. <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”: The
                                Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Myth.</hi> Lewisburg:
                            Bucknell University Press, 2001. 213 pp. $59.50/£41.95
                            cloth.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Dena Bain
                        <name>Taylor</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In two companion volumes—<hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”:
                            The Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Myth</hi> and <hi rend="i">“Glorious
incomprehensible”: The Development of
                            Blake’s Kabbalistic Language</hi>—Sheila A. Spector traces
                        Blake’s use of kabbalistic myth and language from his early prose
                        tracts to his late prophecies. She argues that he gradually appropriated
                        kabbalistic mythemes and linguistic manipulation, and that this is what
                        enabled him to effect the transition from a conventional to a mystical mode
                        of thought. Though the two books are structured in much the same way and
                        advance the same overall argument, <pb id="p38-80" n="80"/>
I intend to
                        review them separately, for what is likely the same reason that Spector
                        chose to divide them—the material is simply too complex to deal with
                        all in one go.</p>
          <p>Spector applies the principles of historical scholarship first developed by
                        Gershom Scholem and others to her analysis of the kabbalistic texts and
                        mythos. She has been doing solid work in this area for decades. Indeed, I
                        wish her magisterial <hi rend="i">Jewish Mysticism: An Annotated
                            Bibliography on the Kabbalah in English</hi> (New York: Garland Press,
                        1984) had been available when I wrote my dissertation on Blake and Kabbalah
                        in the early ’80s, and I have followed her subsequent publications
                        with interest.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”</hi> pursues three goals: to
                        explore the role of kabbalistic myth in Blake’s work as the obverse
                        of the Calvinist myth of Milton; to frame the discussion within a definition
                        of myth as the precursor of intentionality; and to establish the kabbalistic
                        context within which Blake worked. My feeling is that with respect to the
                        first two goals, the book is beautifully argued and of major interest to
                        Blake scholars. Its limits lie in the kabbalistic context it
                        establishes.</p>
          <p>In an early article in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n70" type="note">1</ref> Spector pointed out that “we cannot apply Jewish
                        scholarship to Blake’s Kabbalah” (90); and that “Blake
                        . . . had no access to anything other than the distorted interpretations of
                        the Latin kabbalists; so it is to them, or English renditions of their
                        works, that we must turn if we wish to determine the extent of kabbalistic
                        influence on Blake” (96). I kept wishing she had followed her own
                        advice more closely. The context of Kabbalah she establishes is primarily a
                        Jewish one, whereas Blake’s context is that of a dissenting Christian
                        whose Christian sources mediated between him and the original texts. <note id="n70">1.
Sheila A. Spector, “Kabbalistic Sources:
                            Blake’s and His Critics,”’ <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17.3 (winter 1983-84): 84-101.</note></p>
          <p>For the Christian Kabbalah, Spector relies on Mercurius van Helmont’s
                            <hi rend="i">Adumbratio Kabbalæ Christianæ.</hi> I
                        questioned why she would emphasize van Helmont, a Latin text scarcely
                        available to Blake, when statements by Crabb Robinson and Tatham<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">2</ref> suggest that he owned Law’s
                        translation of Boehme, with its glorious alchemical/kabbalistic designs
                        after Freher. Certainly Blake knew it well and was influenced by it.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">3</ref> I also felt Spector should have placed
                        more emphasis on the connection between the Kabbalah and the Druid revival,
                        and more generally on what she calls the “English Esoterica”
                        (25). <note id="n71">2. Henry Crabb Robinson reports a conversation with
                            Blake in his <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi> (1852) in which “<hi rend="i">Jacob
Bohmen</hi> was placed among the divinely inspired
                            men.—He praised also the designs to <hi rend="i">Laws</hi>
                            translation of Bohmen” (G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Records</hi> [Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969] 541), and Frederick
                            Tatham claimed in a letter to Francis Harvey, the book dealer, that
                            Blake owned a “large collection of the works of the mystical
                            writers” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 41).</note>
	<note id="n72">3. For Boehme’s influence on Blake, see Bryan Aubrey,
                                <hi rend="i">Watchmen of Eternity: Blake’s Debt to Jacob
                                Boehme</hi> (Lanham, MD: University Press of America,
                        1986).</note></p>
          <p>Following Scholem, Spector defines Kabbalism, in the most basic sense,
                        “as a unique combination of three distinct elements: esotericism,
                        mysticism, and theosophy ....[t]hematically associated with occult
                        interpretations of Creation and Ezekiel’s chariot vision”
                        (11). In fact, Spector’s primary focus is on the Creation myth rather
                        than the Chariot visions. She begins by describing the role of kabbalistic
                        esotericism within the Jewish context, as a study restricted by the Talmud
                        to an intellectual elite of “those specially trained to delve into
                        what were considered to be its perilous secrets” (11). She
                        distinguishes Jewish Kabbalah from the “globalized form of
                        esoterica” (11) in which earlier writers on Blake as a kabbalist,
                        like Ellis and Yeats, placed it. It seems to me, though, that there are good
                        reasons why Yeats and the other Golden Dawn writers responded so strongly to
                        Blake—they recognized him as belonging to the same esoteric tradition
                        they did, and correctly placed him within it.</p>
          <p>Spector defines myth as “the structuring principle of
                        intentionality” (19): “More than just a simplistic duality of
                        right and wrong, myth is the vehicle through which the mind can organize the
                        external world, a necessary prerequisite for any kind of thought or
                        action” (56). She develops this definition deftly through the text,
                        demonstrating how Blake, like the kabbalistic mystics, engaged in a
                        “quest for a non-dual mode of existence [that] is structured by
                        theosophical speculations about the secret life of the Godhead”
                        (12).</p>
          <p>The kabbalistic mythos is exceedingly complex, and it is greatly to
                        Spector’s credit that she explains its themes so clearly. She takes
                        them from the writings of Isaac Luria, the sixteenth-century Jewish mystic.
                        Luria consolidated the kabbalistic myth of Creation into a form that reached
                        the Christian world through a compendious, two-volume Latin translation by
                        Christian Knorr von Rosenroth (1636-89) entitled <hi rend="i">Kabbala
                            Denudata.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73"
type="note">4</ref> Knorr’s work,
                        which contains van Helmont’s <hi rend="i">Adumbratio Kabbalæ
                            Christianæ</hi>, has served as the principal source for all
                        non-Jewish literature on the Kabbalah until the present day. Spector
                        describes the central elements of the Lurianic Creation myth in her second
                        chapter (40-44), explains van Helmont’s adaptation of them (44-46),
                        and amplifies and applies them throughout the text: <list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1. <hi rend="i">The Work of Creation</hi>: In contrast to the
                                    Miltonic myth of Creation, Fall, and Redemption, the Lurianic
                                    myth revolves around the three basic concepts of contraction
                                    (Creation), the breaking of the vessels (the Fall), and
                                    restoration (Redemption). The Godhead, <hi rend="i">Ein
                                        Soph</hi>, existed in the form of limitless light, in a
                                    passive state of unrealized potential. Because the <hi rend="i">Ein
Soph</hi> is without limit, when the volition to create
                                    grew within Him, He had to contract His Being in order to
                                    produce a space in which to effect Creation. Into the resulting
                                    vacuum 
<pb id="p38-81" n="81"/>
He emanated the ten 
<hi rend="i">Sefirot</hi>, divine lights or emanations, which He then
                                    used to create the external cosmos. Unlike the emanations of the
                                    Gnostic and Neo-Platonic systems, the <hi rend="i">Sefirot</hi>
                                    are not regarded as separate spheres interposing between God and
                                    the created universe. They are a dynamic part of the divine
                                    life, a process which takes place <hi rend="i">in</hi> God. To
                                    counter the natural tendency of the <hi rend="i">Sefirot</hi> to
                                    reunite with the Godhead, He placed them in vessels of dross.
                                    Unfortunately, the act of contraction created an imbalance
                                    between the sefirotic forces of judgment and love, causing the
                                    vessels to break and the shards to mix with the lights of
                                    purity. Restoration can occur only as a result of the actions of
                                        <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi> and <hi rend="i">Adam
                                        Rishon.</hi></p></item>
	<item><p>2. <hi rend="i">The Cosmic Man:</hi> As they were emanated, the
                                        <hi rend="i">Sefirot</hi> organized into several different
                                    configurations, the first of which was <hi rend="i">Adam
                                        Kadmon</hi> (primordial man). He was originally intended to
                                    serve as an intermediary between the Godhead and <hi rend="i">Adam
Rishon</hi> (created man). But in the fallen universe,
                                        <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi> must “separate the
                                    shards” of the vessels so that the lights of purity can
                                    rise again back to the Godhead. <hi rend="i">Adam Rishon</hi>
                                    must, by performing the 613 commandments of the Hebrew Bible and
                                    by sexual love, purify the souls of the fallen world and end the
                                    exile of the <hi rend="i">Shekhinah.</hi></p></item>
	<item><p>3. <hi rend="i">The Shekhinah:</hi> Like Blake’s
                                    Jerusalem, the <hi rend="i">Shekhinah</hi> is personified as the
                                    female manifestation of the Divine Presence. She is a part of
                                    the Godhead, but was separated from Him as a result of the Fall.
                                    At the final restoration, she will return from exile and the two
                                    will reunite.</p></item>
	<item><p>4. <hi rend="i">The Origin of Evil:</hi> Where the exoteric
                                    Christian myth locates the source of the Fall in man’s
                                    disobedience of God’s law, the Kabbalists locate it
                                    within the Godhead Himself. Evil originated within the Godhead
                                    as the dark, wrathful principle of stern judgment which was
                                    tempered by the contrasting principle of love. Because of the
                                    Godhead’s initial act of self-limitation, this dark
                                    principle broke away from its contrary and finally from God
                                    altogether. Adam’s sin is believed to have extended
                                    history; that is, had he not eaten the forbidden fruit, the
                                    cosmos would have been restored immediately, without the
                                    necessity for a 6000-year cycle of material existence.
                                    Man’s efforts are necessary, not only for individual
                                    salvation, but for cosmic restoration as well.</p></item>
	<item><p>5. <hi rend="i">The Four Worlds:</hi> Kabbalistic cosmogony
                                    conceives of four distinct levels, or worlds: Emanation
                                    (Blake’s Eden), Creation (Beulah), Formation
                                    (Generation), and Fact (Ulro). With the breaking of the vessels,
                                    the entire tenor of the four worlds was altered, and our world
                                    became corporeal.</p></item>
	<item><p>6. <hi rend="i">The Tree of Life:</hi> After the Fall, the
                                    fragmented <hi rend="i">Sefirot</hi> were reconfigured into a
                                    dialectical format consisting of ten spheres arranged in three
                                    “columns.” The masculine right side is
                                    characterized by the divine attributes of mercy or pity, and the
                                    feminine left side by the attributes of rigor or wrath. The
                                    central column provides the means by which the two extremes can
                                    achieve balance.</p></item>
</list>
	<note id="n73">4. Christian Knorr von Rosenroth, <hi rend="i">Kabbala
                                Denudata Seu Doctrina Hebraeorum Transcendentalis Et Metaphysica
                                Atque Theologica Opus Antiquissimae Philosophiae Barbaricae variis
                                speciminibus refertissimum. In Quo Ante ipsam Translationem Libri
                                difficillimi atq; in Literatura Hebraica Summi, Commentarii nempe in
                                Pentateuchum, &amp; quasi totam Scripturam V.T. Cabbalistici, cui
                                nomen SOHAR</hi> . . . [In 5 parts] (Frankfurt: Abraham
                            Lichtenthaler, 1677-84).</note></p>
          <p>Spector’s central argument is that Blake was able to liberate himself
                        from the restrictions imposed by the exoteric myth of Christianity only by
                        adopting these kabbalistic modes of thought. She identifies his pattern of
                        development in this way: 
						<q> [I]n the early prophecies, Blake introduced
                            kabbalistic archetypes to recontextualize particular aspects of
                            Christianity. But then, as his intellect evolved, in the minor
                            prophecies, he structured whole narratives around kabbalistic concepts,
                            until by the major prophecies, he had completely marginalized the
                            Christian myth, reducing what had once been the primary structuring
                            principle of his thought to but a small phase in the larger cycle of
                            existence. (36) </q></p>
          <p>Spector first discusses the appearance of kabbalistic elements in
                        Blake’s early works, which she labels “pre-mythic”: <hi rend="i">All Religions
are One, There is No Natural Religion [a]</hi>
                        and <hi rend="i">[b], The Book of Thel, Tiriel</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion.</hi> These, she says, are examples
                        of Blake’s early syncretism, and “overtly manifest influences
                        as varied as the Greek classics and Ossian, the Bible and Neoplatonism, each
                        of the texts reflecting a serious interest in the subject of myth”
                        (47). His approach in the prose works is to argue “in favor of an
                        ur-myth from which all extant myths purportedly derived” and, in the
                        three poems, to create “mythic narratives that undermine the basic
                        doctrines of Milton’s theology as adumbrated in <hi rend="i">Paradise
                            Lost</hi>” (47). Identifying Milton’s Calvinist doctrines
                        as Original Sin, Ransom, and Eternal Damnation, she shows how <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel</hi> subverts the doctrine of Original Sin; <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, the Ransom Theory; and 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the
                            Daughters of Albion</hi>, Eternal Damnation (48-58). She concludes that
                        the real lesson Blake learns from this sequence is that myth controls
                        thought (59).</p>
          <p>The second group Spector discusses consists of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                            Heaven and Hell, Songs of Innocence and of Experience, America</hi>, and
                            <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> Here, Blake “directly confronts the
                        structural principle upon which the [Miltonic] myth had been predicated,
                        attempting through his doctrine of contraries to transform Milton’s
                        debilitating duality into an energizing dialectic” (59). She argues
                        that the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> is the most successful attempt to
                        substitute contraries for the negations of Milton’s system. It serves
                        as the vehicle for articulating the theoretical base, where the other three
                        works represent decreasingly successful attempts to apply the theory. Thus,
                        in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Blake uses the contraries as a means to supplant
                        Milton’s Original Sin with an esoteric “fortunate fall”
                        into intellect. <hi rend="i">America</hi> introduces Orc, the “human
                        form divine” supposed to convert the Miltonic Ransom Theory into a
                        “liberation theology.” But in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, the
                        Christ-figure Orc is unable to replace the Calvinist concept of Eternal
                        Damnation with Eternal Life, and Blake is forced to create Los to begin the
                        search for a resolution to the problems with myth.</p>
          <p>In her discussion of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, Spector quickly
                        dismisses Swedenborg’s role in Blake’s satire, claiming that
                        it functions only on the literal level (60), and she doesn’t consider
                        Boehme at all. I’d argue, however, that Blake engages with the
                        Swedenborgian myth at more than superficial levels, and clearly 
<pb id="p38-82" n="82"/>
plays Boehme off against both Milton and
                        Swedenborg, not, as Spector suggests, Luria against Milton.</p>
          <p>Lurianic Kabbalah was enjoying widespread study among Christians in the
                        religious and intellectual freedom encouraged in Germany and Bohemia during
                        most of Boehme’s lifetime, by world-shapers such as Rudolf II,
                        Elizabeth of Bohemia, and Christian of Anhalt. Jews were able to study in
                        relative peace, and to share their knowledge, most notably the Kabbalah of
                        Isaac Luria and Moses Cordovero, with interested Christians. Boehme couched
                        his theosophy in alchemical and kabbalistic symbolism derived from
                        Paracelsus and a group of Paracelsist friends that included Balthasar
                        Walther, personal physician to Christian of Anhalt. The link between alchemy
                        and Kabbalah is a distinguishing feature of the <hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi>
                        Boehme’s alchemical vision touched Blake, the engraver working with
                        his own corroding fires, and it was Boehme’s kabbalistic contraries
                        that gave Blake his energizing dialectic.</p>
          <p>The relationship in the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> among Blake, Boehme, and
                        Swedenborg is a complex one. Désirée Hirst amusingly described
                        Swedenborg as being “like some strange spiritual red herring”
                        for Blake and others.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74"
type="note">5</ref> In
                        Swedenborg’s heaven and hell, the societies, numbers and quarters
                        correspond exactly. God’s purpose in this is to have the spirits of
                        hell and the spirits of heaven keep man in equilibrium by acting on either
                        side of him. As long as the two sides are exactly matched in number, weight
                        and measure, man has the freedom to choose between them, even though he is
                        predestined to evil. Blake shatters this structure of negation, arguing
                        instead for the Behmian quality of eternal unresolution that Blake
                        associates with freedom. <note id="n74">5. Désirée Hirst, <hi rend="i">Hidden
Riches: Traditional Symbolism from the Renaissance
                                to Blake</hi> (London: Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode, 1964)
                        226.</note></p>
          <p>Though I wished Spector had focused more on Boehme and Swedenborg, I was
                        impressed by her argument that the contraries would prove inadequate for
                        Blake as a structural principle. As she points out, 
						<q> in the absence of a
                            fully conceived dialectic, Blake has only been able to reverse the
                            polarity, now identifying the erstwhile good angels as oppositional
                            forces, and the presumptively evil Satan as the means of attaining the
                            highest good, vision. His own thought processes still seem controlled by
                            a duality of good and evil. (65) </q></p>
          <p>Spector says that <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> fails to construct a new mythic
                        structure that “rejects the anti-intellectualism of innocence in
                        favor of the active intelligence required for survival in the world of
                        experience” (65). I’m not convinced here that Blake
                        doesn’t in fact establish a kabbalistic understanding of the
                        necessity for both states, an attitude which, for me, has always made
                        “The Tyger” the most representative of the poems in
                        Blake’s developing mythic structure. Spector offers the conventional
                        interpretation of this poem, that “one should recognize in the tiger
                        the power of a Creator capable of creating both him and the lamb”
                        (72). Yet I’ve always read Blake’s tiger as representing the
                        essence of God—not as a creation separate from the Godhead but as a
                        sefirotic power manifesting His dark nature. As Boehme said in the Law
                        edition known to Blake, “The Darkness is the greatest <hi rend="i">Enmity</hi> of
Light, and yet it is the Cause that the Light is
                        manifest: For if there was no <hi rend="i">Black</hi>, then <hi rend="i">White</hi>
could not be manifest to itself; and if there was no Sorrow,
                        then Joy also would not be manifest to itself.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">6</ref> Boehme defines evil as the dark and negative
                        principle of wrath in God, infinitely bound with the qualities of mercy and
                        love. The tiger is a reminder that the contraries form a sacred whole as
                        long as each maintains its proper relationship to the others—in other
                        words, as long as the tiger kills individual lambs but doesn’t try to
                        exterminate all of them. <note id="n75">6. Jacob Boehme, <hi rend="i">The
                                Mysterium Magnum; Or an Explanation of the first Book of Moses,
                                called GENESIS</hi>, in <hi rend="i">The Works of Jacob Behmen, the
                                Teutonic Theosopher</hi>, [tr. J. Sparrow, J. Ellistone and H.
                            Blunden, with minor alterations; ed. G. Ward and T. Langcake], <hi rend="i">With
Figures, illustrating his Principles</hi> [by D. A.
                            Freher] <hi rend="i">left by the Reverend William Law, M.A., III</hi>
                            (London: G. Robinson, 1772) 22.</note></p>
          <p>Spector’s discussion of <hi rend="i">America</hi> begins from the idea
                        that Blake had yet to develop a means of applying the theory of contraries
                        developed in the <hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi> She links Urizen with the
                        sefirotic archetype of judgment that has become occluded by the belief that
                        it is supreme, but she feels that Orc fails to counteract the excesses of
                        rigorous judgment: “Orc performs the negative function of eliminating
                        the opposition . . . but he does not postulate a positive outcome for the
                        conflagration” (77). As a result, in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> Blake
                        seems to recognize that the exoteric Christian myth must be abandoned and
                        begins to explore “obversive explanations for the relationship
                        between reason and vision in the corporeal world” (78) based on the
                        kabbalistic myth and, in particular, on the kabbalistic <hi rend="i">Adam
                            Kadmon.</hi></p>
          <p>Spector shows how the next group of prophecies, <hi rend="i">The Song of Los,
                            The Book of Urizen, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book
                            of Los</hi>, revolve around the relationships between the prophet and
                        the fallen world. They question why the rational faculty has superseded the
                        visionary, and how the visionary faculty can regain its proper level of
                        importance. However, because Blake is using the kabbalistic archetypes to
                        distinguish between the incarnate visionary faculty and the external savior,
                        and to explore the full dimensions of the christological faculty, there is a
                        profusion of Christ figures. The confusion that results, Spector suggests,
                        was quite possibly a significant factor in the shift from <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> to
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and was not to be
                        resolved until <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          <p>Without doubt, Spector’s discussion of the major prophecies is the
                        most rewarding section of the book. Here, she shows that 
						<q> the various
                            kabbalistic motifs Blake had been experimenting with evolve into a
                            complex, multi-faceted myth whose archetypal structure provides the
                            means of reconciling the two dilemmas he had been grappling with . . .:
                            the function 
<pb id="p38-83" n="83"/>
of Christ and the role of the
                            prophet in the fallen world .... Blake finally generates a myth in which
                            the two poles of duality share an obversive relationship with each other
                            [and which is] used as the connecting link between an anagogical realm
                            and the completely different everyday reality of South Molton Street.
                            Through the myth, these two planes—along with ancient biblical
                            and British history, as well as contemporary social and political
                            events—merge into a universal vision of becoming. (107) </q></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Vala/The Four Zoas</hi>, Spector shows, Original Sin is
                        <corr type="emend">transformed</corr> into the Fortunate Fall; in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Ransom
                        becomes self-annihilation; and in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Eternal Death
                        is the passage towards Eternal Life (110).</p>
          <p>Though Spector mentions the “quantum leap” (107) Blake makes
                        into the realm of epic prophecy, and in the evolution of his kabbalistic
                        system, she loses the opportunity to bring in the context that made the leap
                        possible—his three-year sojourn in Felpham and access to the library
                        of William Hayley, which contained a number of volumes of occult and
                        kabbalistic interest. Hayley owned Dr. John Everard’s <hi rend="i">The Divine
Pymander of Hermes Trismegistus</hi> (1650), the <hi rend="i">Fourth Book of Occult Philosophy</hi> (1665),
which is
                        attributed to Agrippa, and Albertus Magnus’s <hi rend="i">De Secretis
                            Mulierum</hi> (1669). He owned Drayton’s <hi rend="i">Poly-Olbion</hi> (1622)
and Evans’s <hi rend="i">Specimens of
                            the Poetry of the Antient Welsh Bards</hi> (1764), both of which speak
                        of a Druidical Kabbalah. He owned two major kabbalistic source works,
                        Guillaume Postel’s <hi rend="i">Alphabetum Variarum Linguarum:
                            Postellus de origine Hebraicae Linguae</hi> (1598) and Gaffarel’s
                            <hi rend="i">Unheard-of Curiosities</hi>, 2 vols. (1650). He owned
                        Josephus’s <hi rend="i">Works</hi> in two editions (1683, 1720);
                        Lowth’s <hi rend="i">De Sacra Poesi Hebraeorum</hi> (Oxford, 1763);
                        his <hi rend="i">Translation of Isaiah</hi> (1778); and Parkhurst’s
                            <hi rend="i">Hebrew-English Lexicon</hi> (1799), which Blake certainly
                        used to learn his Hebrew. Finally, Hayley owned Enfield’s <hi rend="i">History of
Philosophy</hi> (London: J. Johnson, 1791) and
                        Maurice’s seven volume <hi rend="i">Indian Antiquities</hi>
                            (1793-1800),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">7</ref> both of which contain
                        discourses on the Kabbalah, as well as the <hi rend="i">History of Count
                            Gabalis</hi> (1714) by Montfauçon, a classic work on elementals
                        and on the Kabbalah.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">8</ref> Also around this
                        time, Francis Barrett, a leading figure in the London occult community,
                        published <hi rend="i">The Magus, or Celestial Intelligencer</hi> (1801),
                        which made easily available in English texts of occult and kabbalistic lore
                        that either had never been translated into English or had been issued in the
                        seventeenth century and were now rare.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n78" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n76">7. Maurice wrote <hi rend="i">Indian Antiquities</hi> in
                            response to Wilkins’s translation of the <hi rend="i">Bhagavad-Gita</hi> in
1785. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive
                                Catalogue</hi> describes a drawing of “The Brahmins,”
                            of which the subject is “Mr. Wilkin, translating the
                            Geeta” (<hi rend="i">DC</hi> X [E 548]).</note>
	<note id="n77">8. A. N. L. Munby, ed., <hi rend="i">Sale Catalogues of
                                Libraries of Eminent Persons</hi>, Vol. II: Poets and Men of Letters
                            (London: Mansell/Sotheby Parke-Bernet Publications/Scolar Press, 1971)
                            90, 113, 119, 120, 127, 129, 132, 136, 145, 153, 160. The sale catalogue
                            necessarily lists the library’s contents after Hayley’s
                            death; we do not know which books might have been added to it after
                            Blake left Felpham.</note>
	<note id="n78">9. Francis Barrett, <hi rend="i">The Magus, or Celestial
                                Intelligencer:</hi> Being a Complete System of Occult Philosophy. In
                            Three Books (London: Lackington, Allen, and Co., 1801). The most
                            interesting influence from Barrett, though, is his remarkable series of
                            handcolored plates showing heads of daemons. The head of the evil demon
                            Asmodeus, one of the Vessels of Wrath, is remarkably like Blake’s
                                <hi rend="i">Ghost of a Flea</hi> (1819), done for the occultist
                            Varley.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s heightened understanding, Spector shows, begins to bear fruit
                        in <hi rend="i">Vala/The Four Zoas</hi>, in which he transforms Edward
                        Young’s rambling series of meditations on religious orthodoxies into
                        a kabbalistic ascent through the nine <hi rend="i">Nights</hi> and the nine
                        corresponding <hi rend="i">Sefirot</hi> (111-28). Spector explains how
                        kabbalistic mystics elevate their consciousness through meditation on the
                            <hi rend="i">Sefirotic</hi> Tree, beginning with the <hi rend="i">Sefirah</hi> of
existence in the corporeal world and ascending
                        sequentially until the soul/consciousness awakens to eternal life in the
                        highest sphere (110). In the earlier versions of the poem, she argues, the
                        emphasis on the four zoas doesn’t allow Blake to resolve the
                        conflicting archetypal patterns within the Christianized version of Lurianic
                        Kabbalah; that is, the linear progress from Creation through Apocalypse
                        conflicts with the kabbalistic cycle of exile and return focused on the
                        individual’s recognition of a past error. The introduction of Albion
                        as the Christ-like symbol of humanity allows Blake to consolidate the zoas
                        into a single figure, subordinating them to “the overall interaction
                        between Los and Albion, <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi> and <hi rend="i">Adam
                            Rishon</hi>, macrocosm and microcosm” (131), and enabling the
                        final breakthroughs of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Blake consolidates the roles of
                        “upper” and “lower” man: interlaced with
                        Los’s actions as <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi> are Milton’s as
                            <hi rend="i">Adam Rishon.</hi> Further, on the Lurianic base (the fall
                        into division of <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi>/Albion and the eventual
                        reunification with the <hi rend="i">Shekhinah</hi>/Ololon and Jerusalem)<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">10</ref> he superimposes <hi rend="i">Merkavah</hi>
mysticism (i.e., the descent of Ololon, Milton’s
                        emanation, that enables the poet’s final ascent). <pb id="p38-84" n="84"/>
Spector
offers an interesting discussion of the illustration
                        usually identified as “Milton’s Track,” in which a line
                        represents the poet’s descent through the vortices. She provides a
                        context for Blake’s design in van Helmont, with a mention of similar
                        illustrations in Boehme and Thomas Burnet’s [<hi rend="i">Sacred</hi>] 
<hi rend="i">Theory of the Earth</hi>, though I would argue
                        that other sources, such as Basnage and Enfield, should also have been
                            included.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n79">10. Boehme’s adaptation of the Lurianic base would
                            have been worth Spector’s attention in relation to Blake’s
                            development of <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi>/Albion. Volume 3 of
                            Law’s edition includes a set of engravings of human figures,
                            which occur infrequently elsewhere in the books. These figures have a
                            Michelangelesque quality of graceful muscularity; likely Blake had them
                            in mind when he said of the figures to the Law edition that Michelangelo
                            could not have done better. Like all of the figures in the 
<hi rend="i">Works</hi>, they were engraved by an unknown but accomplished
                            engraver after J. C. Leuchter. Leuchter in turn had adapted them from
                            diagrams by the German Behmenist Dionysius Andreas Freher, who lived in
                            England the last thirty years of his life. The <hi rend="i">Three
                                Tables</hi> use the human body as an expression of the original
                            androgynous state of the primordial Adam and man’s return to this
                            state at the Redemption. Each of the Tables has a series of flaps or
                            “Vails” that lift to unfold the development of
                            man’s spirit. The First Table begins with the World and the
                            “First <hi rend="i">Adam’s</hi> State of
                            Integrity,” by which Boehme means the androgynous union of the
                            primordial man and the Virgin Sophia, his name for the 
<hi rend="i">Shekhinah.</hi> The Vails lift to show the Unfallen Man and finally
                            the Creator, the <hi rend="i">Mysterium Magnum</hi> or kabbalistic <hi rend="i">En
Soph.</hi> The Second Table reveals man in his Fallen
                            state, in spiritual darkness, and the Third charts man’s struggle
                            to Redemption, revealing his gradual transformation into the Virgin
                            Sophia and unity of body and spirit. On Freher and his designs to
                            Boehme, see C. A. Muses, <hi rend="i">Illumination on Jacob Boehme: The
                                Work of Dionysius Andreas Freher</hi> (New York: Columbia University
                            Press/King’s Crown Press, 1951).</note>
	<note id="n80">
                            11. Jacques Basnage’s <hi rend="i">History of the
                                    Jews, From Jesus Christ To The Present Time</hi>, translated by
                                Thomas Taylor the Cambridge Platonist (London: J. Beaver and B.
                                Linton; R. Knapstock; J. Sprint; A. Bell, R. Smith, and J. Round,
                                1708), was the most complete and accurate eighteenth-century history
                                and commentary on the Kabbalah. In describing <hi rend="i">Merkavah</hi>
mysticism, Basnage gives an account of the
                                descent of Souls through the Vortex of the four worlds: 
<q> All the
                                    Souls, without excepting the <hi rend="i">Messiah’s</hi>,
                                    were created at the beginning of the World. The World in its
                                    original state was <hi rend="i">Diaphanous</hi>, and separated
                                    into many Vortices. . . . The World, or this great 
<hi rend="i">Vortex</hi>, was divided into unequal parts; whereof one is
                                    call’d <hi rend="i">Aziluthical</hi>, another 
<hi rend="i">Briathical</hi>, the third is the <hi rend="i">Jesirathical</hi> World, and the least of all is the
<hi rend="i">Asiathical.</hi> All the Souls were at first
                                    included in the superior <hi rend="i">Aziluthick</hi> World, but
                                    they were clad with some kind of Body. These Souls were subject
                                    to various Revolutions, and were to pass into the four 
<hi rend="i">Vortices</hi>, or Worlds before mentioned.
                                    (187.2-188.1) </q>
In addition, William Enfield’s <hi rend="i">The
History of Philosophy, from the Earliest Periods:
                                    Drawn up from Brucker’s Historia Critica
                                    Philosophiae</hi> (London: J. Johnson, 1791), which is based on
                                Basnage and which Blake would have seen in Hayley’s library,
                                provides an illustration similar to the one in van Helmont that
                                Spector emphasizes. In Enfield, a line representing <hi rend="i">Adam
Kadmon</hi> cuts through the ten sefirotic
                            circles.
                        </note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is, as Spector says, a perfect poem from the
                        kabbalistic perspective. Its focal point is Jerusalem, the 
<hi rend="i">Shekhinah</hi>, symbolizing Divine immanence, whose position is usurped
                        by Vala as the representation of spirituality in the fallen world (140).
                        Vala prevents Albion from perceiving the Divine Vision, while Los, the
                        active manifestation of <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi>, labors at his
                        furnace, metaphorically separating the shards “to prepare a context
                        in which Albion will be able to rise again” (141). The third male
                        figure, the visionary <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, not only frames the action
                        but provides its locus: “the entire narrative [comprises] his
                        fourfold vision of existence, combining biblical history and current events,
                        along with kabbalistic and British myth” (142). Structurally, the
                        poem adapts the four-part kabbalistic cosmogony into “a narrative
                        form in which Los and Albion actualize the kabbalistic cycle of
                        existence.” Finally, Spector interprets <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s four
chapters (143-68) according to van
                        Helmont’s four stages of the cosmic cycle (the Primordial
                        Institution, the State of Destitution, the Modern Constitution, and the
                        Supreme Restitution on the spiritual plane).</p>
          <p>Spector ends her discussion with <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> In her summary
                        of the book’s argument, however, she concludes with the insightful
                        observation that Blake seems to have strongly identified the pattern of his
                        own life with that of Job. Like Job, Blake retained his faith in the face of
                        trials and losses, and, having survived his Satanic test, he comes to praise
                        God and all his works. She comments briefly on the last plate (plate 21) of
                        the Linnell series of <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>
                        (1825) as a reflection of the balance restored to the cosmos, in which
                        Job’s happily restored family stands between the two extremes of
                        judgment and mercy. Spector could have gone further with this, and looked at
                        the ways in which Blake’s mature visual art unself-consciously
                        incorporates both Tree of Life and Chariot themes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n81">12. In the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> series, for example, the
                            more restful balance represented in the final plate is the obverse of
                            the dynamic representation of the Tree of Life in plate 2. In that
                            plate, two contrary pillars of cloud and fire frame the central scene,
                            in which a pillar of figures spiraling upwards is flanked by two pillars
                            of rising figures. God occupies the highest position in the middle
                            pillar, with Satan in the center, and Job at the bottom. An open book of
                            Laws lies on God’s knees, and his right hand points downward to
                            Job, who also holds a book of Laws. Satan’s limbs extend at the
                            diagonal, a spiral dynamic that links and vitalizes the upper and lower
                            spheres.</note></p>
          <p>The section on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> provides the book’s best
                        discussion of Chariot mysticism as a theme in Blake’s work. Other
                        uses of Chariot mysticism that Spector could have focused on include the
                        Dante drawings and his very late drawings for the Book of Genesis and <hi rend="i">The
Book of Enoch.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n82">13. <hi rend="i">The Book of Enoch</hi> was one of the most
                            important of the early, apocalyptic Merkavah texts. Very little of the
                            voluminous output of the Merkavah mystics was translated from the Hebrew
                            or Aramaic and made available to Christian Europe, but in 1821 the first
                            English translation of <hi rend="i">The Book of Enoch</hi> was
                            published. The resurrection by Richard Laurence of what had been one of
                            the most influential prophecies of the early Christian period created
                            surprisingly little stir. Blake, however, responded to it with a series
                            of vigorous preliminary pencil drawings, of which we have six. Even in
                            their rough state, they show the enthusiasm he felt. The history of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Enoch</hi> and the circumstances of its
                            publication in 1821 are given in G. E. Bentley, Jr., “A Jewel in
                            an Ethiop’s Ear,” <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed.
                            Robert N. Essick and Donald Pearce (London and Bloomington: Indiana
                            University Press, 1978) 213-40; and Allan R. Brown,
                            “Blake’s Drawings for the <hi rend="i">Book of
                            Enoch</hi>,” <hi rend="i">The Burlington Magazine</hi> 77
                            (September 1940): 80-85; rpt. in <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand: Essays
                                for the Study of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics</hi>, ed.
                            Robert N. Essick (Los Angeles: Hennessey &amp; Ingalls, 1973) 105-16.
                            For details of the meager response to Laurence’s translation, see
                            Bentley, “Jewel in an Ethiop’s Ear”
                        216-17.</note></p>
          <p>Spector also misses the chance to show us the poet in fruitfully kabbalistic
                        exchange with the dissenting and Druid groups of his own acquaintance, those
                        who formed what Spector calls the “English Esoterica” (25). In
                        the seventeenth century, the Kabbalah had been an integral part of the
                        occult/political Rosicrucian movement. In Blake’s time, the old
                        “sciences” in new guises were still attractive, and important
                        in several circles with which Blake was connected: the English Behmenists
                        and Swedenborgians;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83"
type="note">14</ref> occultists in
                        secret societies 
<pb id="p38-85" n="85"/>
like the Masons;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">15</ref> dissenting Christians who mingled the occult with
                        religious and political radicalism;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n85" type="note">16</ref>
                        and Druids.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n83">14. In addition to his direct involvement with the
                            Swedenborgian Church, Blake likely had associations through his friend
                            William Sharp with a considerable variety of Behmenists and
                            Swedenborgians. The Reverend Richard Clarke (1719-1802), for example,
                            was a Hebraist and a student of the Kabbalah, and in addition had some
                            serious acquaintance with alchemy. Clarke engaged in public controversy
                            with Joseph Priestley and Thomas Paine. He was a very colorful
                            character, and his concern for social justice made him a well-known
                            figure in London among people interested, like Blake, in Boehme, Law,
                            and Swedenborg. See Hirst 246-63, 271-76; E. P. Thompson, <hi rend="i">Witness
Against the Beast: William Blake and the Moral Law</hi>
                            (New York: The New Press, 1993) 47-48.</note>
	<note id="n84">15. Though the areligious sociability and middle-class
                            sensibilities of English Freemasonry would hardly have appealed to
                            Blake, the remarkable surge in mystical Masonry of the late eighteenth
                            century surely would. These groups sought a spiritual regeneration for
                            the world through “true science and true reason,” by which
                            they meant alchemy, Kabbalah, mesmerism, Swedenborgian spiritualism, and
                            the Bible. See Clarke Garrett, <hi rend="i">Respectable Folly:
                                Millenarians and the French Revolution in France and England</hi>
                            (Baltimore and London: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1975) 99. For
                            example, the Avignon Society, an offshoot of mystical Masonry, supported
                            Richard Brothers and believed in the regeneration of the world through
                            revolution. They derived this belief from a system of kabbalistic
                            numerology they called “the Holy Word” (Leslie Tannenbaum,
                                <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies:
                                The Great Code of Art</hi> [Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                            1982] 17). William Bryan, who published testimonies of his belief in
                            Richard Brothers, was a leader of the Avignon Society and at one time or
                            another was interested in practically every aspect of late
                            eighteenth-century occult, mystical and pseudoscientific enquiry. He was
                            close friends with William Sharp, through whom Blake could have met him,
                            and with their mutual friend Thomas Duché, a talented painter and
                            son of the Rev. Jacob Duché (Garrett 176), whose sermons were
                            influenced by both Boehme and Swedenborg, and whose <hi rend="i">Discourses on
Various Subjects</hi> (1779) Blake owned (G. E.
                            Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of
                                William Blake</hi> [New Haven and London: Yale University Press,
                            2001] 126). Even if Blake did not come in contact with the Avignon
                            Society through the tirelessly sociable Sharp, he could have read a
                            denunciation of them in the Swedenborgian Church’s <hi rend="i">New Jerusalem
Magazine</hi> for April 1790, where they are decried
                            as “the <hi rend="i">Antipodes</hi> of the New Church, erected on
                            the very borders of Babylon.”</note>
	<note id="n85">16. Many groups of Dissenters mixed the same fervor for
                            spiritual regeneration and belief in the esoteric with political
                            radicalism, and Blake had definite affinities with antinomian
                            millenialist groups. The Ancient Deists of Hoxton, for example, were
                            actively involved with occult and mystical traditions, and spoke of
                            conversations with angels and departed spirits (see William Hamilton
                            Reid, <hi rend="i">The Rise and Dissolution of the Infidel Societies in
                                This Metropolis:</hi> Including The Origin of Modern Deism and
                            Atheism; The Genius and Conduct of Those Associations; Their
                            Lecture-Rooms, Field-Meetings, and Deputations; From the Publication of
                            PAINE’S AGE OF REASON till the present Period [London: J.
                            Hatchard, 1800]). Like Blake, too, many of these new converts to the
                            dissenting sects were London craftsmen, whose training in the sects,
                            with their egalitarian and revivalist, Messianic rituals, led them to
                            embrace Jacobin and radical political ideas at the outbreak of the
                            French Revolution. See E. P. Thompson, <hi rend="i">The Making of the
                                English Working Class</hi> (1963; rpt. New York: Vintage-Random
                            House, 1966) 51-53; and George Rudé, <hi rend="i">History of
                                London: Hanoverian London, 1714-1808</hi> (London: Secker &amp;
                            Warburg, 1971) 114. On Blake’s affinities with these groups, see
                            M. H. Abrams, <hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism: Tradition and
                                Revolution in Romantic Literature</hi> (New York: W. W. Norton
                            &amp; Co., 1971) 51-55; Garrett 147; Christopher Hill, <hi rend="i">Milton and the
English Revolution</hi> (New York: Viking, 1978)
                            467-69; A. L. Morton, <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel: A Study in
                                the Sources of William Blake</hi> (London: Lawrence &amp; Wishart,
                            1958) <hi rend="i">passim</hi>; Thompson, <hi rend="i">The Making of the
                                English Working Class</hi> 41, 50-52; Thompson, <hi rend="i">Witness
                                Against the Beast passim.</hi></note>
	<note id="n86">17. Writers like Thomas Maurice or any of the writers on the
                            Druids found a primordial Christian Kabbalah at the heart of all the
                            religious mysteries of the world. Numerous antiquaries held that the
                            deepest Druidic mysteries were really the secret Kabbalah given to Adam
                            by God. The Reverend Evan Evans, for example, spoke about a
                            “Druidical Cabbala,” in his <hi rend="i">Some Specimens of
                                the Poetry of the Antient Welsh Bards</hi> (London, 1764) 18, and
                            there was a copy of Evans’s work in Hayley’s library
                            (Munby 119).
                           <p>There were several other
                                antiquarian writers whose works on the Druids Blake would have known:
                                Henry Rowlands, William Stukeley, Rowland Jones, Edward Williams,
                                William Owen (Pughe), and Peter Roberts. Like Blake, they believed that
                                the Druids and the Patriarchs shared a common kabbalistic religion and
                                language.</p>
	<p>From very similar designs in
                                Rowlands (1723, 1766) and Stukeley (1740), Blake derived the visual
                                context for his “Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of
                                Albion,” in which Blake made his Joseph into a Druid (see Dena
                                Bain Taylor, “The Visual Context of ‘Joseph of Arimathea
                                among the Rocks of Albion,’” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                    Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20.2 [fall 1986]: 47-48).</p>
	<p>Edward Williams (Iolo Morganwg,
                                1747-1826), the indefatigable Welsh poet, lexicographer, and
                                enthusiastic forger of both poetry and historical evidence, claimed to
                                have documentary evidence of the original “<corr type="emend">Patriarchal</corr> Religion
                                of ANCIENT BRITAIN.” See Edward Williams, <hi rend="i">Poems,
                                    Lyric and Pastoral</hi> (London, 1794) II: 194; quoted in A. L.
                                Owen, <hi rend="i">The Famous Druids</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
                                1962) 73. Williams was a close friend of Blake’s friend William
                                Owen (Pughe), and Blake may have attended Druid rituals on Primrose Hill
                                with them both. (See Dena Taylor, “A Note on William Blake and
                                the Druids of Primrose Hill,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                    Quarterly</hi> 17.3 [winter 1983-84]: 104.)</p></note></p>
          <p>In sum, <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”</hi> offers a brilliant
                        explication of the kabbalistic pattern of Blake’s development: from
                        his early use of Kabbalah to liberate himself from the restrictions imposed
                        by the exoteric myth of Christianity to his full retelling, in the major
                        prophecies, of <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi>/Albion’s fall into
                        division and eventual reunification with the exiled 
<hi rend="i">Shekhinah</hi>/Jerusalem. More, the book firmly establishes the
                        Kabbalah as the structuring principle of Blake’s cosmogony and
                        theosophy, in which the Christian myth is transformed into only part of a
                        larger cycle of existence. I believe, though, that the next step is to link
                        Blake’s Kabbalah more firmly with the Christian esoteric tradition.
                    </p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
