<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.2.johnson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Engravings for Lavater’s Physiognomy: Overdue Credit to Chodowiecki,
Schellenberg, and Lips</title>
        <author n="Johnson">Mary Lynn Johnson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Kathleen Lundeen</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <body>
      <pb id="p38-52" n="52"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Engravings for Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>: Overdue
Credit to Chodowiecki, Schellenberg, and
                                Lips<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n1">1. For one-month fellowships in 1993, I am grateful to the
                                Newberry Library in Chicago (American Society for Eighteenth-Century
                                Studies fellowship) and the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript
                                Library of Yale University (John D. and Rose H. Jackson fellowship).
                                I owe much to the expert librarians of these institutions and to
                                those in the University of Iowa Libraries (Special Collections,
                                Interlibrary Loan, John Martin Rare Book Room of the Hardin Library
                                for Health Sciences), Houghton Library, Harvard University, the Yale
                                Center for British Art, the University of Illinois Rare Book Room,
                                the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer Collection, Rare Book
                                department, and Berg Collection), the Harry Ransom Humanities
                                Research Center of the University of Texas, the Pierpont Morgan
                                Library, and the British Library. For generous help via photocopies
                                and e-mail, I thank Marlis Stähli, deputy director of the
                                Manuscript Collection of the Zentralbibliothek Zürich, and
                                Virginia Murray, administrator of the John Murray Archive in London.
                                For further help, I thank Christa Sammons, Sibylle Erle, Ingrid
                                Goritschnig, David H. Weinglass, Joan K. Stemmler, Robert N. Essick,
                                Detlef Dörrbecker, G. E. Bentley, Jr., Ross Woodrow, Andrew
                                W. Greg, Joel Haefner, Ruedi Kuenzli, Kenneth M. Grant, and Sarah
                                Jones. For encouragement of scholarly activity during my
                                “other life” as special assistant in the
                                President’s Office of the University of Iowa (1983-2000), I
                                thank James O. Freedman, now president emeritus of Dartmouth
                                College; Hunter R. Rawlings III, now professor of Classics and
                                former president of Cornell University; and Mary Sue Coleman, now
                                president of the University of Michigan. Finally, for much-needed
                                morale boosts and for innumerable critical readings of my drafts, I
                                thank my husband Jack (John E. Grant).</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Mary Lynn <name>Johnson</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>From the 1770s on, the Swiss pastor and early body-theorist Johann Caspar
                        Lavater (1741-1801)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> sought control over
                        visual as well as verbal components of his physiognomical opus, in ways that
                        sometimes put him in conflict with artists and publishers who had creative
                        and commercial claims of their own. Lavater’s proprietary interests
                        had a ripple effect on all versions of his work, including the deluxe
                        three-volume edition of <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> (1789-98)
                        translated by Henry Hunter,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> to which
                        Blake contributed four engravings. In what follows, I omit consideration of
                        one of the four engravings by Blake, a full-plate portrait of Democritus,
                        because its designer, Rubens, is duly credited in the inscription. My
                        purpose here is to recover the original contextual significance of the three
                        images signed only by Blake by tracing them to their long-forgotten sources.
                        As a larger framework for Blake’s engagement with Hunter’s
                        translation, I also touch upon the <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>’s
                        extraordinary publishing history from inception to English translation,
                        focusing on Lavater’s complex dealings with his first English
                            publishers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n2">2. For informative surveys in English of Lavater’s life
                            and times, see Tytler 3-81 (in my “Selected Sources”), and
                            Karl Julius Fink, “Johann Kaspar Lavater,” <hi rend="i">German Writers from
the Enlightenment to Sturm und Drang,
                                1720-1764</hi>, ed. James Harden and Christoph E. Schweitzer, 
<hi rend="i">Dictionary of Literary Biography</hi> 97 (Detroit, New
                            York, London: Gale Research, 1990) 163-74. On the circumstances of
                            writers in Lavater’s era, see also Martha Woodmansee, “The
                            Genius and the Copyright: Economic and Legal Conditions of the Emergence
                            of the ‘Author,’” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
                                Studies</hi> 17.4 (1984): 425-48. German scholars tend to normalize
                            the spelling of Lavater’s middle name with “K,” a
                            variant used by Lavater himself for a time in the 1790s. Though many
                            English-speaking scholars have adopted the French pronunciation of
                            Lavater’s name, in 1830 Fuseli’s pupil Margaret Patrickson
                            recalled that Fuseli (like German speakers today) “always
                            pronounced Lavater with the accent on the first syllable”
                            (Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Letters of Henry Fuseli</hi> 522).</note>
	<note id="n3">3. See item 481 under “Engravings” in Bentley,
                                <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 593-95, and in his <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books Supplement</hi> 235-36; see also item 84 (with title page
                            photos) in Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Fuseli: Catalogue
                                Raisonné</hi> 96. Further, see Bentley’s astonishing
                            account of back-dated 1817 reprints, “The Physiognomy of
                            Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>,” to be supplemented by
                            Andrew Greg’s not-yet-published bibliographical essay and
                            checklist. The whereabouts of newly reported copies of the Hunter
                            translation (1789-98, “1792,” and 1810) are regularly
                            recorded in the annual listings in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> of Robert N.
                            Essick’s “Blake in the Marketplace” and
                            Bentley’s “Checklist of Publications and
                            Discoveries.” Scholars interested in the Hunter translation
                            should be aware that articles in German often cite the spurious
                            “1792” edition.</note>
	<note id="n4">4. My terse account for Blakeocentric purposes draws mainly on
                            published sources, but I hope to present the whole juicy history, with
                            archival documentation, in an appropriate journal.</note></p>
          <p>A preliminary caveat: a vain search for parallels between Hunter’s
                        translation and the more accessible near-contemporary translation by Thomas
                        Holcroft, which follows a different order entirely, sucked me into the black
                        hole of Lavater studies. In pursuit of Lavater’s original words, I
                        came to realize that neither his unillustrated preliminary work <hi rend="i">Von der
Physiognomik</hi> [On Physiognomics] of 1772<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref> nor his fully illustrated large-quarto four-volume
                            <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> [Physiognomical Fragments]
                        of 1775-78<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> has
ever been translated into
                        English. Indeed, as Michael Shortland has noted, there is no “single
                        Lavaterian text” from which all others descend.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Instead, a loose and shifting corpus of
                        chronologically overlapping Lavater-authorized material made its way from
                        Switzerland and Germany (with a side trip to the Netherlands) through
                        France, leaking intellectual property rights and potential profits at every
                        turn, to become 
<pb id="p38-53" n="53"/>
						<figure n="Lavater.Physiognomies.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="495">
							<figTranscr>Von der Physiognomik, 1772 (scientific emphasis)<lb/>
							First published Hannoverischen Magazin, 3, 7, 10 Feb. 1772 (unauthorized), ed. J. G. Zimmermann<lb/>
							From Lavater’s unrevised lecture notes, Zurich scientific society, late 1771 or early 1772<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Aussichten in Ewigkeit (“Views into Eternity”), 3 vol. 1768-72 (theological emphasis)<lb/>
							25 letters to Zimmermann: 16th letter, vol. 3: “Language in Heaven,” 30 April 1772<lb/>
							on instantaneous, unmediated “physiognomical” communication among risen bodies<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Physiognomische Fragmente, 1775-76-77-78<lb/>
							4 vol. quarto (never translated into English)<lb/>
							“And God created humanity in his own image” (theological theme)<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Over die Physiognomie, 1781-84<lb/>
							4 vol. octavo, from abridged ms. by Lavater<lb/>
							Dutch trans. Johann Wilhelm van Haar;<lb/>
							published Johannes Allert<lb/>
							1st vol. reissued at Lavater’s insistence, 1784<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Essai sur la physiognomonie, [1781]-83-86[87]<lb/>
							3 vol. quarto + posthumous vol. 4, 1803<lb/>
							trans. [La Fite et. al.] from Lavater’s reworked and enlarged ms.<lb/>
							Vol. 4 (6 Fragmente sections + “100 Physiog. Rules”) not trans.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Physiognomische Fragmente (abridged), 1783-84-87; vol. 4 1830<lb/>
							3 vol. octavo; reorganized redaction by J. M. Armbruster<lb/>
							(ed. and condensed from Fragmente and Essai)<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Hunter trans., Essays on Physiognomy, 1789-92-98<lb/>
							from Essai, vol. 1-3 (4th vol. never trans.)<lb/>
							3 vol. in 5; quarto<lb/>
							(prospectus 1787; fascicles, 1788-99)<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Vermischte physiognomische Regeln (pvt. circ. 1789)<lb/>
							(unauthorized, unillustrated publications: 1793, 1802)<lb/>
							Rev. (illus.) as Hundert physiognomische Regeln<lb/>
							in Gessner, ed., Nachgelassene Schriften, vol. 5 (1802)<lb/>
							Used to fill in vol. 4 of Essai (1803)<lb/>
							and incorp. in Holcroft (2nd ed.) 1804<lb/>
							<lb/>
							C. Moore (almost total) piracy<lb/>
							Essays on Physiognomy Calculated to Extend ...<lb/>
							3 vol. closely following Hunter<lb/>
							[1793-94]; 1797<lb/>
							First published Astrologer’s/Conjuror’s Magazine, 1791-94<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Holcroft trans., Essays on Physiognomy, 1789<lb/>
							from Armbruster<lb/>
							3 vol. octavo; 1-vol. abr. 1792<lb/>
							2nd ed., 1804<lb/>
							(incl. excerpts from Gessner biog. and “100 Physiog. Rules”)<lb/>
							<lb/>
							George Grenville reprint<lb/>
							The Whole Works of Lavater on Physiognomy<lb/>
							4 vol. octavo (old vol. 2 split into vols. 2-3)<lb/>
							minor typographical changes from Moore<lb/>
							[1797]<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Samuel Shaw piracy<lb/>
							Physiognomy; Or the Corresponding Analogy...<lb/>
							1 vol. abr. from Holcroft<lb/>
							[1792]<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Chart by Mary Lynn Johnson</figTranscr>
							<head><hi rend="b">1. Lavater’s Many Physiognomies</hi></head>
						</figure>
						<pb id="p38-54" n="54"/>
the work we know in English as <hi rend="i">Essays
                            in Physiognomy</hi> (illus. 1). Still more confusingly, the five
                        (putative) English translations published in Lavater’s lifetime stem
                        from two different intermediate sources. One group derives from the first
                        three volumes (only) of the large-quarto <hi rend="i">Essai sur la
                            physiognomonie</hi> ([1781]-83-86[i.e., 87]),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> not translated from “the German
                        Edition” but from “a Manuscript in which the Author has new
                        moulded many passages of the Text, disposed his Materials in a different
                        order, and added some new articles” (Hunter, <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>
                        I: [Cv]). The other set stems from a three-volume octavo abridged
                        (“verkürzt”) redaction prepared at Lavater’s
                        behest by his amanuensis J. M. Armbruster (1783-84-87).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> The five English editions—here identified
                        only by their translators’ names, their earliest publication dates,
                        and their sources—are (1) Henry Hunter, D.D. (first volume 1789;
                        first fascicle January 1788), translated from <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>; (2)
                        the Rev. C. Moore, LL.D., F.R.S. (first volume 1793, reprinted 1797; first
                        number in serial publication 1791), supposedly translated from <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>
but actually dependent to the point of piracy on
                        Hunter’s translation; (3) George Grenville, Esq. (1797), largely a
                        reprint of Moore; (4) Thomas Holcroft (1789), translated from
                        Armbruster’s German abridgment; and (5) Samuel Shaw ([1792]), a
                        one-volume condensed piracy of Holcroft.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">10</ref> In addition, the bookseller Joseph Johnson engaged Mary
                        Wollstonecraft to prepare an abridged translation from the French in
                        1787—a project abandoned not because it was preempted by
                        Holcroft’s 1789 translation from the German (as commonly thought) but
                        because, as we shall see, Johnson joined forces with publishers of the
                        Hunter translation. <note id="n5">5. For a modern text of the first part
                            only, linked with Lavater’s post-humously published
                            “Hundred Physiognomical Rules” and illustrations culled
                            from other physiognomical publications, see Lavater, <hi rend="i">Von
                                der Physiognomik</hi>, ed. Riha and Zelle, 9-62. For the text and an
                            image of the title page, see
                            &lt;http://gutenberg.spiegel.de/lavater/physiogn/physiogn.htm&gt;.</note>
	<note id="n6">6. For further information see Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Fuseli:
                                Catalogue Raisonné</hi> 34. A faithfully executed facsimile
                            edition of the same title, with an afterword by Walter Brednow (Zurich:
                            Orell Füssli, 1968-69), has the added interest of annotations
                            transcribed by an early owner from Lavater’s own copy. 
<hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente . . . Eine Auswahl mit 101
                                Abbildungen</hi>, ed. Christoph Siegrist (Stuttgart: Phillipp Reclam
                            Jun., 1999) is an excerpted pocket edition in modern typeface.</note>
	<note id="n7">7. Shortland, esp. 305. See also notes 11 and 12 below.</note>
	<note id="n8">8. The third volume, dated 1786 on its title page, was
                            actually delayed until 1787; the fourth volume, planned for 1788, was
                            brought out posthumously (with <hi rend="i">Physiognomonie</hi> changed
                            to <hi rend="i">Physiognomie</hi>) by Lavater’s son Johann
                            Heinrich Lavater in 1803, and never translated into English.</note>
	<note id="n9">9. <hi rend="i">J. C. Lavaters Physiognomische Fragmente zur
                                Beförderung von Menschenkenntniss und Menschenliebe</hi>, ed.
                            Armbruster, incorporates some new material from <hi rend="i">Essai.</hi>
                            Each volume ends with Lavater’s dated endorsement, and the third
                            volume notes the need for a fourth. According to the new standard
                            Lavater bibliography, <hi rend="i">Bibliographie der Werke
                            Lavaters</hi>, a fourth volume was published in 1787, but in all copies
                            known to me this final volume is dated 1830, as reported also in
                            Brigitte Thanner’s meticulous catalogue of Schellenberg’s
                            work, <hi rend="i">Schweizerische Buchillustration.</hi></note>
	<note id="n10">10. Moore’s three-volume <hi rend="i">Essays on
                                Physiognomy: Calculated to Extend the Knowledge and Love of Mankind
                                . . . Translated from the last Paris edition</hi> effaces the French
                            edition’s true place of publication, The Hague, and masks its
                            almost wholesale dependence on Hunter by strategic rephrasings
                            throughout, especially at the beginnings of chapters. Most of this
                            1793-94-94 edition, including title pages, appeared serially, with
                            directions for binding, in W[illiam] Locke’s <hi rend="i">The
                                Conjuror’s Magazine</hi> (August 1791-June 1793), continued
                            as <hi rend="i">The Astrologer’s Magazine</hi> (July 1793-January
                            1794); in 1797, H[enry] D[elahoy] Symonds (also publisher of the 1792
                            Shaw and the 1804 2nd ed. of Holcroft) reissued the Moore translation in
                            four volumes, formed by splitting the second volume into two physical
                            volumes. At times, when Hunter’s fascicles fell behind
                            Moore’s publishing schedule, Moore made his own translation
                            directly from <hi rend="i">Essai.</hi> Grenville’s <hi rend="i">The Whole Works
of Lavater on Physiognomy</hi> (published by W.
                            Butters and sold by W. Simmonds, 1797), also proclaiming the nonexistent
                            “last Paris edition” as its source, is actually a new
                            printing of Moore, under yet another non-Lavaterian title. Shaw’s
                                <hi rend="i">Physiognomy: Or the Corresponding Analogy between the
                                Conformation of the Features and the Ruling Passions of the
                                Mind</hi> (London: H. D. Symonds, [1792]), is a one-volume
                            collection of extracts pirated from Holcroft (“with a pair of
                            scissars” [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>], according to Holcroft’s
                            corrected abridgment of the same year, published by Robinson). In the
                            mid-nineteenth century the remainder publisher William Tegg reprinted
                            both the Holcroft translation and Shaw’s abridgment (the latter
                            under the oxymoronic tertiary subtitle <hi rend="i">Complete
                                Epitome</hi>). Moore’s publisher Locke went bankrupt in 1793,
                            the same year that Shaw’s publisher Symonds began serving what
                            became a total of four years in prison for publishing Paine and others
                            (see public records summarized in lan Maxted, <hi rend="i">The London
                                Book Trades, 1775-1800: A Preliminary Checklist of Members</hi>
                            [Folkestone: Dawson, 1977], continued in Maxted’s online project,
                            “Exeter Working Papers in British Book Trade History,”
                            &lt;http://www.devon.gov.uk/library/locstudy/bookhist/&gt;).</note></p>
          <p>In these murky bibliographical waters, where sources and analogues of
                        Blake’s images may bob up without warning, there is no substitute for
                        page-by-page, side-by-side comparisons among the books themselves. John
                        Graham’s indispensable (though preliminary) 1961 checklist of
                        Lavater’s physiognomical publications in various languages,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> a mainstay of Anglophone scholars, is
                        based only “in part” on personal inspection; it sometimes
                        lumps abridged and unabridged versions and even entirely separate editions
                        under the same entry, and the incomplete accounts of title page wording,
                        numbers of pages and plates, and physical dimensions cannot be properly
                        correlated with bibliographical data in the National Union Catalogue, the
                        Research Libraries Information Network (RLIN), the Online Computer Library
                        Center (OCLC), the Eighteenth-Century Short Title Catalogue, or national
                        libraries abroad. Since this article was accepted in 2001, a new
                        historical-critical edition of Lavater’s collected work has begun
                        appearing. In the edition’s <hi rend="i">Bibliographie</hi> volume,
                        compiled and supervised by Horst Weigelt and edited by Niklaus Landolt, the
                        section on <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> and its translations
                        during Lavater’s lifetime (items 274 and 275), based on the holdings
                        of Swiss and German libraries, largely supersedes Graham’s work but
                        stops short of mapping relationships among the various preliminary,
                        original, revised, reorganized, augmented, and/or condensed editions of the
                            <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> in German, Dutch, French, and English,
                        published under Lavater’s direct or indirect supervision.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n11">11. With an introduction “adapted with
                            corrections” from “Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> in England,”
<hi rend="i">JHI</hi> 22
                            (1961): 561-72, Graham republished his “Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Physiognomy:</hi> A Checklist” virtually without
                            change in his <hi rend="i">Lavater’s Essays on Physiognomy.</hi>
                            Shortland silently corrects some of Graham’s listings “by
                            reference to the British Museum catalogues and by personal
                            inspection” (406n38), but many oversights and erroneous
                            speculations remain.</note>
	<note id="n12">12. For a lively sense of the early publication and reception
                            history of Lavater’s work, see Frey. For corrections of
                            persistent misconceptions surrounding the first German editions, see
                            Ohage.</note></p>
          <pb id="p38-55" n="55"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Sources of Blake’s Engravings</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Let me quickly dispense with the thankless responsibility of throwing
                            cold water on attractive hypotheses advanced in passing by two eminent
                            scholars, G. E. Bentley, Jr., and Robert N. Essick. In 1972, in
                            announcing the discovery of a previously unreported minuscule signature
                            by Blake, Bentley proposed that Blake might have designed as well as
                            engraved a vignette of gowned, long-bearded old men in <hi rend="i">Essays on
Physiognomy</hi> (I: 127; cover illus.).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> And in 1980 Essick speculated that Blake
                            “could easily have modified” the profile of a man
                            identified as Spalding (<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I: 225; illus. 2)
                            “to look as much as possible like himself,” thereby
                            creating “a witty prophecy” of his future appearance in
                            middle age.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> Alas, the truth is
                            otherwise: both engravings simply replicate designs by the popular
                            Berlin-based Polish-French illustrator Daniel Nikolaus Chodowiecki
                            (1726-1801). The vignette of the “Blakean” old gardeners,
                            which Blake copied from an engraving in <hi rend="i">Essai sur la
                                physiognomonie</hi> (I: 127), was originally designed and engraved
                            by Chodowiecki for a different publication altogether, and the Blakelike
                            profile of Spalding is copied from an engraving in <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> (I:
232), which in turn is copied from an engraving
                            designed by Chodowiecki for <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi>
                            (III: opp. 342). The third among Blake’s three plates that do not
                            credit a designer—a vignette of a hand holding a torch in <hi rend="i">Essays on
Physiognomy</hi> (I: 206; illus.
                            3)—derives from an unsigned plate in <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> (I:
                            213), which is itself a re-engraving of an unsigned plate in 
<hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> (IV: opp. 3). <note id="n13">13. Bentley,
                                “A ‘New’ Blake Engraving.”</note>
	<note id="n14">14. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi>
                                61.</note></p>
            <p>In view of Blake’s intense involvement with Lavater-related
                            projects in 1788-89, it is understandable that the possible thematic
                            significance of his engravings has diverted attention from their merely
                            replicative function. All four engravings for the <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>,
as recorded by Bentley, appeared in fascicles
                            published between May 1788 and February 1789, the period of
                            Blake’s closest association with Lavater’s boyhood friend
                            Johann Heinrich Füssli, or Henry Fuseli.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">15</ref> At this very time, 
							<figure n="BB481.1.4.COM" rend="file" width="822" height="1000">
								<figTranscr>Blake sculp</figTranscr>
								<head>2. “DITTO.</head>
								<figDesc>[Spalding] PROFILE, FINISHED,” engr. Blake; fasc.
                                    VIII, February 1789; “Spalding. Ditto [vignette],”
                                        <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, trans. Hunter, I
                                    (1789) 225; 13.3 × 10.5 cm.; image 8.9 × 5.9 cm.
                                    Collection of Robert N. Essick.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
							</figure>
							<figure n="BB481.1.3.COM" rend="file" width="513" height="1000">
								<figTranscr>Blake s</figTranscr>
								<head>3. “A HAND WITH A TORCH,
                                    FINISHED,” engr.</head>
								<figDesc>Blake; fasc. VIII, February 1789; “Female Hand and
                                    Arm holding a Torch, emblematical of Science dissipating
                                    Ignorance. Vignette,” <hi rend="i">Essays on
                                        Physiognomy</hi>, trans. Hunter, I (1789) 206; 14.3 ×
                                    7.0 cm.; image 13.3 × 3.6 cm. Collection of Robert N. Essick.<gap
type="emend"/></figDesc>
							</figure>
							<pb id="p38-56" n="56"/>
Blake had just finished a large profile
                            portrait of Lavater for Joseph Johnson (proofed in December 1787)<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> and was also working on a
                            frontispiece after Fuseli for Lavater’s first publication in
                            English, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi> (published by Johnson in May
                                1788).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> In the course of this
                            latter commission, Blake not only recorded his responses to
                            Lavater’s sayings in the margin but also expressed his general
                            approval by signing his own name after the author’s on the title
                            page and enclosing the two names in a heart. Little wonder that
                            Blake’s readers feel justified in scrutinizing his engravings for
                            an original graphic response to Lavater’s physiognomical text.
                                <note id="n15">15. For discussions of Lavater-Fuseli and
                                Fuseli-Blake relationships, see Mason 96-103, 41-57; Allentuck;
                                Leonard M. Trawick, “William Blake’s German
                                Connection,” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 13
                                (1977): 229-45; Carol Louise Hall, <hi rend="i">Blake and Fuseli: A
                                    Study in the Transmission of Ideas</hi> (New York and London:
                                Garland, 1985).</note>
	<note id="n16">16. As first noted by Stemmler, the original designer was
                                Johann Heinrich Lips. I must leave for another occasion a discussion
                                of Lips’s primary design, which antedates the secondary Lips
                                drawing in the Veste-Coburg cited by Stemmler and the derivative
                                copy (unsigned) that served as Blake’s model. Lips’s
                                design, probably in the version copied by Blake, also underlies
                                engravings by William Bromley (1789), J. Chapman (1813), and William
                                Holl (pre-1838), and J. W. Cook (1842), all noted in Robert N.
                                Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake</hi>
                                (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983).</note>
	<note id="n17">17. See Schroyer.</note></p>
            <p>Disciplinary and national boundaries also tend to obscure, for
                            English-speaking scholars, the Continental origins of the designs Blake
                            engraved. Art historians specializing in the German and Swiss artists
                            whose work Blake copied do not routinely cover English editions in
                            recording secondary and tertiary engravings. And in the Blake community,
                            where the commercial engravings are of interest mainly in relation to
                            Blake’s development as an independent artist, scholars focus on
                            his distinctive style as an engraver—the basis for attributing to
                            Blake his unsigned plates (after Chodowiecki) for Mary
                            Wollstonecraft’s translation of C. G. Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of
Morality</hi> (1791)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> and the
horrific “The Execution of
                            Breaking on the Rack” for John Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative of a Five
Years’ Expedition Against the Revolted
                                Negroes of Surinam</hi> (1796).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref> Even for such a pedestrian project as the crafting of
                            replacements for worn-out plates for a new edition of Gay’s 
<hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793), as Geoffrey Keynes has shown, Blake
                            re-envisioned the images assigned to him and made them his own.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> And so as enthusiasts of Blake we
                            have drifted into a communal presumption of originality that extends
                            even to commercial engravings, without sufficient attention to the
                            constrictive working conditions emphasized by Essick: 
<q> [R]eproductive
                                engraving was dependent upon a rigorous division of labour and the
                                subordination of individual expression to uniformity and
                                repeatability. All illustrations in a book had to conform to its
                                format, and this mechanical unity was extended to graphic style. If
                                more than one engraver was employed, all had to practise compatible
                                techniques. In spite of an engraver’s prerogative to
                                “sign” his plates, the truly autographic tended to be
                                submerged beneath the anonymity of a corporate and systematic
                                    enterprise.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref></q>
	<note id="n18">18. See Essick, “Blake’s Engravings in
                                Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of
                                Morality.</hi>”</note>
	<note id="n19">19. David V. Erdman, “Blake’s Visions of
                                Slavery,” <hi rend="i">JWCI</hi> 15 (1952): 242-52; Essick,
                                    <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi> 52-53.</note>
	<note id="n20">20. Geoffrey Keynes, “Blake’s Engravings
                                for Gay’s <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Book
                                Collector</hi> 21 (1972): 59-64.</note>
	<note id="n21">21. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Commercial Book
                                Illustrations</hi> 5.</note></p>
            <p>In the Lavaterian enterprise, the “truly autographic” was
                            very deeply submerged indeed. Lavater, with only limited facility in
                            drawing but supreme confidence in his visual acuity and innate sense of
                            design, was reluctant to grant the artists on whom he depended an
                            appropriate degree of professional autonomy. Unlike other authors, who
                            might express general preferences about illustrations or decorations but
                            usually delegated day-to-day decisions to the publisher or to a master
                            designer, Lavater personally commissioned all graphic work, bombarded
                            his illustrators with detailed verbal descriptions of the images he
                            wanted, ordered corrections at every stage, and in general demanded
                            “subordination of individual expression” not only from
                            engravers but also from designers. Not surprisingly, his efforts to
                            micromanage his artist-collaborators met stiff resistance, especially
                            from his old friend Fuseli, then studying in Rome. Although Fuseli often
                            pestered Lavater for money, he could not abide taking orders in return,
                            and in May 1771, in response to a request for a head of Christ and other
                            religious images for physiognomical study, he fired back a stinging
                            rebuff: 
<q> The biggest mistake that you make in all the subjects you
                                have laid out before me is that you’re always minting things
                                for me in advance. Understand that invention is the soul of the
                                painter and without it a painter is in the shoemakers’ guild.
                                Your imagination and mine may be the same, but if I am to execute
                                your images they must flame up in my head, not yours.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n22">22. <hi rend="i">Heinrich Füsslis Briefe</hi>,
                                    ed. Muscg, 166. All translations, unless otherwise noted, are my
                                    own (original texts omitted for lack of space). Here the
                                    second-person-familiar verb
                                    “vormunzest”—which I take to stem from
                                    “vor” [before] + “münzen”
                                    (misspelled without the umlaut) meaning “to coin”
                                    or “to mint” (secondary older meaning: “to
                                    form”)—is apparently peculiar to Fuseli; in the
                                    next letter he makes a similar comparison between his original
                                    conceptions and paying “in meiner eigen
                                    Münze” [in my own coin]. Mason (138), apparently
                                    considering the root to be “munden,” meaning
                                    “taste good,” translates the verb as “to
                                    masticate in advance.” Alternatively, it may be intended
                                    to recall the noun “der Vormund,” meaning
                                    “guardian”; if so, Fuseli’s complaint is
                                    that Lavater is always acting as his guardian.</note></q>
On 4 November
1773—after Lavater had given up persuading
                            Fuseli to help with <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> and had
                            enlisted Chodowiecki in his stead—Fuseli reiterated his rejection
                            of Lavater’s demands and mocked his friend’s choice of the
                            comparatively tame Chodowiecki as his master designer: 
<q> I find myself
                                neither able nor in the mood (and I’m telling the truth) to
                                draw physiognomies that fit nine on a quarter-sheet. I can’t
                                draw the Iliad in a nutshell or paint Elijah’s chariot and
                                horses on a gnat’s wing; I’ll leave that to the
                                “most soulful” draftsman in Europe [i.e. Chodowiecki,
                                    <pb id="p38-57" n="57"/>
known as “painter of
                                souls”]. I need space, height, depth, length. Let whoever
                                wants to raise a storm in a wineglass or weep over a rose; I
                                can’t do it. (Muscg 167) </q>
Fuseli goes on to complain that
                            Lavater’s demands will reduce him to beggary, “but I still
                            might pay something, if possible in my own coin.” He boasts that
                            if Lavater can show him an inexpensive way to ship a roll of drawings on
                            parchment, “I’ll send you things that perhaps
                            haven’t yet entered the head of Europe’s ‘most
                            soulful’ draftsman” (Muscg 167). Nine months later, in
                            August 1774, Lavater made a special concession to Fuseli: “Always
                            draw me whatever you want to . . . I was a fool . . . I consider you the
                            greatest painter in the world.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Somewhat mollified, Fuseli brought himself to contribute
                            one design to the fourth volume of <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
                                Fragmente</hi> (1778); after that, he was a prolific contributor to
                            the second volume of <hi rend="i">Essai sur la physiognomonie</hi>
                            (1783). But he was so appalled by the resulting engravings that he made
                            it his business to agitate for proper representation in an improved
                            English edition. <note id="n23">23. Fragmentary ms. letter in the
                                Zentralbibliothek Zürich; quoted (including ellipses)
                                Allentuck 96.</note></p>
            <p>In all publications that Lavater himself controlled, it was not the
                            author’s practice to prepare a finished text and arrange for
                            illustrations afterward. Instead, Lavater ordered drawings, at great
                            cost, to his precise specifications; made a selection from the finished
                            drawings of the images to be engraved; chose from the finished
                            engravings the ones that interested him most (thereby losing his
                            investment in the rejected work); wrote a running commentary on the
                            prints in front of him; and only then sent his manuscript and the
                            engraved plates to the publisher.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n24" type="note">24</ref>
                            But no matter how detailed his verbal instructions, Lavater was usually
                            disappointed with the graphic results. Especially frustrating were his
                            quests for an ideal image of Christ (a subject for another occasion) and
                            physiognomically accurate likenesses of his friends, famous
                            contemporaries, important historical figures, and various ethnic and
                            personality types: 
<q> I have procured a great number of drawings
                                relating to my plan. I have examined and compared a variety of human
                                figures of every class; and I have had recourse to my friends for
                                assistance. The endless blunders committed by those whom I employed
                                to draw and engrave, have become a plentiful source of enquiry and
                                instruction for me. (trans. Hunter, <hi rend="i">Essays in
                                    Physiognomy</hi> I: 11) </q>
In engaging Chodowiecki as his
                            chief designer, Lavater hitched his physiognomical wagon to a proven
                            star—a self-made, self-taught “small master” whose
                            charming portrayals of ordinary people in familiar domestic and
                            workplace settings were a major selling point for the books he
                            illustrated. As Graeme Tytler observes, “but for Chodowiecki,
                            Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> might not have enjoyed
                            quite the popularity that they did” (60). Unlike Fuseli, the
                            workmanlike Chodowiecki stoically accepted the necessity of catering to
                            difficult clients and attuning his output to the requirements of the
                            publishing industry. <note id="n24">24. For the early volumes of 
<hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi>, Lavater sent texts and
                                engravings in installments to Goethe for further amplification and
                                revision, and Goethe forwarded the revised manuscript to the
                                publisher.</note></p>
            <p>Chodowiecki and his brother Gottfried, sons of a Polish father and
                            Swiss-born French Huguenot mother, had been sent as teenagers from their
                            native Danzig (Gdansk) to the Huguenot community in Berlin, three years
                            after their father’s death, to work in their maternal
                            uncle’s hardware and import business. Chodowiecki, who soon
                            excelled in decorating such things as tobacco tins, learned enamel
                            painting at 23 and taught himself etching at the late age of 33. In
                            1766, at the age of 40, he made his debut as a history painter with 
<hi rend="i">Adieux of [Jean] Calas</hi>, a touching portrayal of an
                            unjustly accused Huguenot father’s last moments with his family
                            before his execution. His large and small engravings of this subject
                            sold well, but private commissions for oils on other subjects did not
                            follow. “I want to be a painter,” he wrote his mother in
                            1770; “the public wants me to be an engraver.” He resigned
                            himself to nineteen-hour days of “working like a galley
                            slave” as an illustrator to support his immediate and extended
                            family in the French community of Berlin, a group of dependents that
                            expanded over the next decade to include two unmarried sisters, a
                            mentally disabled brother, and his widowed sister-in-law and her
                            children. When he discovered that his proofs and early states were being
                            snapped up by collectors, he hiked up their value by introducing
                            deliberate graphic variants. By the time Lavater approached Chodowiecki
                            for help with the <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>, he was, at 47, the most
                            famous, most prolific, and best-paid illustrator in Europe. With a
                            strong sense of proprietorship and justifiable pride in his name and his
                            reputation, he insisted that his designs be properly credited,
                            appropriately compensated, and competently executed. And as a protection
                            against piracy, he scrupulously maintained a complete and
                            well-documented file of his originals and proofs, and of engravings made
                            by others after his designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n25">25. Information in this paragraph is synthesized from <hi rend="i">Bryan’s Dictionary of
Painters and
                                    Engravers</hi>, ed. George C. Wonson (London: G. Bell &amp;
                                Sons, 1930) 1: 291; <hi rend="i">Allgemeines Lexikon der bildenden
                                    Künstler von der Antike bis zur Gegenwart; unter
                                    Mitwirkung von 300 Fachgelehrten des In- und Auslandes</hi>, ed.
                                Ulrich Thieme and Felix Becker (Leipzig: E. A. Seemann, [1907]-1950)
                                6: 519-21; Susanne Netzer, “Daniel Nikolaus
                                Chodowiecki,” trans. David Britt, <hi rend="i">Daniel N.
                                    Chodowiecki 1726-1801</hi> (London: Goethe-Institute and Coburg:
                                Kunstsammlungen der Veste Coburg, 1989) 7-15; Willi Geismaier, 
<hi rend="i">Daniel Chodowiecki</hi> (Leipzig: E. A. Seemann, 1993)
                                7-17, 135-38, 226, 227-33; Pamela E. Selwyn, “Daniel
                                Chodowiecki: Der Künstler als Kaufman” (The Artist as
                                Businessman) 11-21, and Maria Bogucka, “Daniel Chodowiecki,
                                seine Familie und Danzig” 23-42, both in <hi rend="i">Daniel
                                    Chodowiecki (1726-1801) Kupferstecher[,] Illustrator[,]
                                    Kaufmann</hi>, ed. Ernst Hinrichs and Klaus Zernack
                                (Tübingen: Max Niemeyer, 1997); and Steinbrucker’s
                                introduction cited in note 26 below.</note></p>
            <pb id="p38-58" n="58"/>
            <p>Lavater’s very first letter to Chodowiecki (10 July 1773) begins
                            with a two-page set of instructions—something like directions to
                            a police artist—for drawing a perfect head of Christ.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> The profile is to be of correct
                            proportions for someone six feet tall; the light should fall from the
                            upper left over loose hazelnut-brown hair, neither straight nor curly;
                            the face should be neither thin nor fat, neither flat nor sloped; the
                            breadth or length of the eyes the same as the breadth or length of the
                            mouth in profile, with the upper eyelid a fourth of the length of the
                            profile of the eyes; eyebrows neither bushy nor sparse; the ear three
                            times the breadth of the nose from the point to the end of the earlobes;
                            the nose straight; the upper lip slightly more protruding than the
                            lower, neither laughing nor serious; the chin set back a little, and so
                            forth. In this same letter Lavater also asks for a title page vignette
                            and two other kinds of drawings: octavo-sized portraits of certain
                            distinguished Berliners in profile or half-profile and whole figures of
                            ideal character types. All sitters (with Chodowiecki himself and
                            Spalding heading the list) are to be invited to pose in Lavater’s
                            name, but “without your revealing my particular intention
                            beforehand”; if possible, they are to be depicted
                            “bald-headed—or at least without wigs or caps.”
                            Lavater closes by apologizing for his bluntness and offering the
                            assurance that “Everything I want on this job will be paid for in
                            cash” (Steinbrucker 61). <note id="n26">26. <hi rend="i">Daniel
                                    Chodowiecki</hi>, ed. Steinbrucker, 58-61, No. 73.
                                Steinbrucker’s “Vorwort,” 1-21, provides an
                                invaluable context for the letters in relation to
                                Chodowiecki’s life, his work, and his times.</note></p>
            <p>Despite a backlog of other commitments and pressing deadlines, the
                            good-natured and devoutly religious Chodowiecki did his best to
                            accommodate Lavater’s order, beginning with a promise to
                            undertake both the head of Christ and the title page vignette, with the
                            mild caution that “what you have so beautifully described in
                            words may not be possible to draw with a pencil. For I can think of an
                            image of the divine, but my imagination shows me only what I can express
                            in a human face.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">27</ref> He even
                            agreed to engrave the head of Christ and other key designs himself (he
                            preferred not to engrave after other artists). But in December 1773, as
                            Lavater’s order continued to grow apace, Chodowiecki broke the
                            news that the rest of the work would have to wait until the following
                            Easter (the deadline for publishing books to be exhibited at the
                            semiannual Leipzig book fair). Meanwhile, Chodowiecki offered to look
                            through his work for existing materials that might lend themselves to
                            Lavater’s uses (Steinbrucker 64-65, 69). Over the next year and a
                            half, frustrations mounted on both sides as Lavater sent the master
                            designer’s finished work back for retouching, rejected engravers
                            of Chodowiecki’s choosing in Berlin and Leipzig in favor of
                            lower-paid Swiss engravers who would work under Lavater’s direct
                            supervision, and usurped Chodowiecki’s prerogative of exercising
                            financial and aesthetic control over engravings after his drawings. As
                            Chodowiecki wrote in March 1774: 
<q> You complain about the engravings!
                                Who has more reason to complain than I! When I get the prints I can
                                hardly recognize my own <hi rend="i">invention</hi> any more. But
                                this will remain an incurable evil as long as these gentlemen
                                aren’t willing to learn how to draw. It’s no good
                                without much, much drawing after nature. Please recommend this to
                                our friend Schellenberg; tell him he has an incomparable manner with
                                his <hi rend="i">insects</hi>, and I believe could do the same with
                                human beings if he studied them as thoroughly[.] (Steinbrucker 83) </q>
	<note id="n27">27. Chodowiecki sent the drawing of Christ’s
                                profile sometime in September 1773 (Steinbrucker 62) and the
                                engraving of this subject on 27 September 1774 (Steinbrucker 99);
                                Lavater received the title page vignette on 8 April 1774
                                (Steinbrucker 88).</note></p>
            <p>Chodowiecki’s target is one of Lavater’s favorite
                            engravers, Johann Rudolf Schellenberg (1740-1806) of Winterthur, who had
                            learned drawing and etching from his father, Johann Ulrich Schellenberg
                            (1709-1795). The elder Schellenberg had been trained as a painter and
                            engraver by his future father-in-law Johann Rudolf Huber (1668-1748), a
                            successful portraitist in Basel. The younger Schellenberg, after
                            executing his first commission as illustrator of a major work on
                            insects, took up insect painting as a specialty and even collected
                            insects himself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">28</ref> By the time he
                            undertook the physiognomical work in 1774, at the age of 33,
                            Schellenberg must have felt that he could handle any subject. But it was
                            all Lavater could do, in settling accounts with the high-priced
                            Chodowiecki, to make sure Schellenberg received even the little that he
                            was able to charge: “We will certainly understand each other
                            about the price—You are more than reasonable—as Mr.
                            Schellenberg is to you. We will always squabble about whether he is too
                            reasonable” (Steinbrucker 87). In late January 1775, Chodowiecki
                            renewed his complaints: 
<q> Oh! how much this printing has humiliated
                                me, to see how few of my drawings sufficed for the engraver
                                [Schellenberg] even to make something passable out of them. I
                                don’t know whether you [Lavater] are satisfied with them, but
                                in all events I’ve tried to correct them. I don’t know
                                anything more to do, though, than to give them roughly the effect
                                they should have [by pencil, marked over the proofs]. Whether the
                                engraver is able to rework his plates this way, I very much doubt. .
                                . . [H]e is not competent enough to work in black. It has to be
                                worked up more extensively, because the narrow strokes rub out after
                                several hundred impressions, and produce only gray flecks.
                                (Steinbrucker 116) </q>
Chodowiecki, ever mindful of his
                            international reputation, also complains in a postscript that “in
                            the things our Schellenberg has etched after me, and where he has set my
                            name under them, I have seen that in Switzerland I am to be continually
                                <pb id="p38-59" n="59"/>
deprived of the last <hi rend="i">C</hi> in
                            my name <hi rend="i">Chodowiecki</hi> . . . you [Lavater] also do the
                            same thing . . .” (Steinbrucker, 118).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">29</ref> Schellenberg’s engraving of
                            Chodowiecki’s profile in <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> (I: 254;
                            illus. 4; not in Lavater’s index) bears a still more egregious
                            misspelling, incorporated into the design itself:
                            “Codowieki.” <note id="n28">28. Information in this
                                paragraph comes from Thanner, “Johann Rudolf
                                Schellenberg.” Almost twenty years later, Chodowiecki wrote
                                to Schellenberg’s friend, the artist Anton Graff, “The
                                man is so little known and so little esteemed; I think it’s
                                because he works so cheaply” (quoted Thanner, “Johann
                                Rudolf Schellenberg” 72).</note>
	<note id="n29">29. As one of Chodowiecki’s admirers explained to
                                another poor speller, “the c can’t be omitted; in
                                Polish it . . . is pronounced as a z” (Steinbrucker 13n1).
                                According to Paul Dehnert, <hi rend="i">Daniel Chodowiecki</hi>
                                (Berlin: Rembrandt, 1977), the “‘Ch’ . . . is
                                pronounced like the ‘ch’ in . . .
                                ‘Sache,’ and . . . wiecki is pronounced like
                                wjetzki” (6); the English equivalent would be something like
                                Khod-o-VYETZ-ki. On 24 February 1775, Lavater informed Chodowiecki
                                that the plates had already been printed, without retouching, before
                                the letter of corrections arrived (Steinbrucker 122).</note></p>
            <p>The vignette of two old men gardening, designed by Chodowiecki and
                            engraved by Schellenberg for <hi rend="i">Essai sur la
                                physiognomonie</hi> (I: 127; illus. 5), belongs to the category of
                            images that Chodowiecki had first prepared for his own purposes and then
                            made available for recycling in the <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>—though, in
this case, the image was not used
                            until 1781. The original design, engraved by Chodowiecki himself and
                            signed by him alone as <hi rend="i">f[ecit]</hi> (“he made
                                it”),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">30</ref> first appeared as
                            a vignette for the dedication page of Gellert’s <hi rend="i">Leçons de
morale</hi> [Lessons on Moral Philosophy] (1772;
                            illus. 6), inscribed “aux élèves du seminaire
                            françois de theologie à Berlin,” “to
                            students of 
							<figure n="Codowicki.Schellenburg.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="336" height="500">
								<figTranscr>Daniel<lb/>
								Codowieki.<lb/>
								Verfertigen durch seinen Freund &amp; Diener<lb/>
								J. R. Schellenberg</figTranscr>
								<head>4. “Codowieki” [Daniel Nikolaus
                                    Chodowiecki], engr.</head>
								<figDesc>Rudolf Schellenberg, incorporating a self-portrait by
                                    Chodowiecki. <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> I
                                    (1775) 254; image 12.7 × 8.4 cm. Orell Füssli
                                    facsimile (1968-69). Author’s collection.</figDesc>
							</figure>
							<figure n="Gardening.Schellenberg.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="380">
								<figTranscr>Schellenberg sc
								D Chodowiecki</figTranscr>
								<head>5. [Old men gardening], engr.</head>
								<figDesc>Schellenberg after a design by Chodowiecki. <hi rend="i">Essai sur la physiognomonie</hi> I
([1781]) 127; reused in
                                    Armbruster’s abridged <hi rend="i">J. C. Lavaters
                                        Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> I (1783) 33. 6.2 × 7.5
                                    cm.; image 5.2 × 7.2 cm. Beinecke Rare Book and
                                    Manuscript Library, Yale University.</figDesc>
							</figure>
							<pb id="p38-60" n="60"/>
							<figure n="DieuDonne.Chodowiecki.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="351">
								<figTranscr>DIEU DONNE L’ACROISSEMENT<lb/>
								D. Chodowiecki s.</figTranscr>
								<head>6. “DIEU DONNE L’ACROISSEMENT,”
                                    engr.</head>
								<figDesc>Chodowiecki after his own design. Dedication page,
                                    Gellert’s <hi rend="i">Leçons de morale</hi>
                                    (1772). 6.0 × 8.9 cm.; image 5.2 × 8.0 cm. Special
                                    Collections Library, University of Michigan.</figDesc>
							</figure> the French [Huguenot] theological seminary in
                                Berlin.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">31</ref> The vignette
                            is entitled “DIEU DONNE L’ACROISSEMENT,” or
                            “God gives the increase,” an allusion (not previously
                            identified) to Paul’s rebuke to competing factions in the church
                            at Corinth: “I have planted, Apollos watered; but God gave the
                            increase. So then neither is he that planteth any thing, neither he that
                            watereth; but God that giveth the increase” (1 Cor. 3: 6-7). In
                            the same year (1772), at the request of the founding director of the
                            seminary (established in 1770), Chodowiecki engraved a variation of this
                            design in upright format as a bookplate for the seminary’s
                            library, omitting the background of buildings and water, and placing the
                            word “Dieu” on a separate line at the center of a beaming
                            sun (Engelmann 64, No. 87; Bauer 37, No. 149). In adapting Paul’s
                            text for the seminary, Chodowiecki represents the “rising”
                            students as trees and the teachers as gardeners who provide different
                            but complementary services of cultivation and nourishment, while
                            entrusting the seminarians’ full development to God.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> In the bookplate version
                            Chodowiecki again signed his engraving as maker (both designer and
                            engraver), and he donated both his labor and the printing of 3,000
                            bookplates as a gift to the seminary.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n33" type="note">33</ref>
	<note id="n30">30. No. 86 in Engelmann 63-64, now largely superseded by
                                the illustrated but less bibliographically detailed catalogue by
                                Bauer, where this plate appears as No. 148, p. 37; see also
                                Bauer’s companion volume, the plate-by-plate (unillustrated)
                                commentary of Elisabeth Wormsbächer, <hi rend="i">Daniel
                                    Nikolaus Chodowiecki: Erklärungen und
                                    Erläuterungen zu seinen Radierungen: Ein
                                    Ergänzungsband zum Werkverzeichnis der Druckgraphik
                                    herausgegeben von Jens-Heiner Bauer</hi> (Hannover:
                                Kunstbuchverlag Galerie J. H. Bauer, 1988).</note>
	<note id="n31">31. I have supplied the accent marks for
                                “élèves,” omitted on the title page of
                                Christian Fürchtegott Gellert, <hi rend="i">Leçons de
                                    morale ou Lectures academiques</hi> . . . (Utrecht: J. van
                                Schoonhoven, 1772), 2 vols.; originally published in German as 
<hi rend="i">Moralische Vorlesungen</hi> (Leipzig: Wiedmanns Erben
                                und Reich, 1770), 2 vols. in 1.</note>
	<note id="n32">32. According to Andreas van Randow, “Chodowiecki
                                und die Hugenottengemeinde in Berlin,” <hi rend="i">Chodowiecki und die
Kunst der Aufklärung in Polen und
                                    Preuβen</hi>, ed. Hans Rothe and Andrzej Ryszkiewicz
                                (Cologne and Vienna: Böhlau, 1986), the sun represents God in
                                imagery also associated with the Enlightenment; the clouds on the
                                left (in the bookplate version of the design) show that God’s
                                view is not always direct and that the realms of heaven and earth
                                are distinctly separated. Without reference to 1 Cor. 3, van Randow
                                suggests that the sage with the watering can “may be
                                recognized without difficulty as Socrates”; the tree-planting
                                sage “is probably the apostle Paul, who has a central role
                                for evangelical believers as author of the most important biblical
                                texts” (61-62). (The bookplate van Randow reproduces as fig.
                                4, p. 59, lacks the lines indicating sun and clouds which are
                                clearly visible in Bauer 37, No. 149.) Chodowiecki later reused the
                                bearded tree-planter, flanked by a female waterer on the left and a
                                bare-chested young male digger on the right, as a title vignette for
                                F. S. G. Sack’s <hi rend="i">Predigten</hi>, or Sermons
                                (1781; Engelmann No. 404, Bauer No. 866). A preliminary drawing with
                                the same motto, showing only one old man without gardening equipment
                                in an orchard, hands clasped, looking toward the sun as it peeks
                                behind a mountain in the background, is reproduced in Müller
                                172, No. 119; commentary on 100.</note>
	<note id="n33">33. In about 1780 Schellenberg appropriated
                                Chodowiecki’s design—signed only
                                “Schellenberg” in reverse lettering—for a
                                bookplate for the city library of Winterthur; reproduced as a
                                frontispiece for Thanner et al., <hi rend="i">Johann Rudolf
                                    Schellenberg.</hi></note></p>
            <p>For the first volume of <hi rend="i">Essai sur la physiognomonie</hi>,
                            published in 1781, Lavater chose Chodowiecki’s image of the old
                            men gardening as a tailpiece for a one-paragraph
                            “Addition”—that is, a newly composed passage not
                            present in <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi>—to his
                            fragment on the physiognomist. The paragraph concludes with a
                            reiteration of Lavater’s often-repeated insistence on the
                            incompleteness of both the emerging discipline and its leading
                            practitioner: “. . . I am very far from being a Physionomist 
[<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]. I am but the Fragment of one; just as the Work I
                            present to the Public, contains not a complete Treatise, but merely
                            Fragments of Physiognomy” (trans. Hunter, <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I:
127).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">34</ref> The
                            image in its new location, rather than allegorizing the development 
<pb id="p38-61" n="61"/>
of seminarians, is pressed into service to
                            represent Lavater’s history (and future expectation) of the
                            ongoing development of both physiognomy and the physiognomist. So
                            Bentley’s speculation, endorsed by Essick, that the image of the
                            old gardeners has something to do with the idea that incomplete or
                            fragmentary books, like young trees, must be nourished, is not far from
                            the mark (Bentley, “A ‘New’ Blake Engraving”
                            49; Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Commercial Book
                                Illustrations</hi> 42). <note id="n34">34. Schellenberg’s
                                engraving for <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> I ([1781]) 127 (Thanner, 
<hi rend="i">Schweizerische Buchillustration</hi> I: 437, cat. 1082)
                                was reused, without noticeable changes, in Armbruster’s
                                abridged edition of <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> I
                                (1783) 33, as the tailpiece for a chapter on the
                                “truth” of physiognomy, a chapter that ends with a
                                reaffirmation by Lavater himself, dated January 1783, of his opinion
                                of “six or eight years ago.” In Holcroft’s
                                translation of Armbruster the tailpiece is omitted.</note></p>
            <p>Schellenberg slightly alters the dimensions of Chodowiecki’s
                            original engraving (from about 6.0 × 8.9 cm.—height is
                            presented before width in this and all measurements—to 6.2
                            × 7.5 cm.) and reverses the design left to right.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref> Such reversals, which of course
                            saved engravers the extra step of reorienting the image to appear the
                            right way around when printed, are by no means uncommon. Much less
                            common, though, is Schellenberg’s treatment of the inscription;
                            instead of reversing it on the plate, in the normal way of engravers, he
                            inscribed it directly, so that in the impression the two signatures
                            “D. Chodowiecki” and “Schellenberg fec.”
                            appear backwards, right to left. Among the 179 signed engravings (in
                            addition to many unsigned ones) that Schellenberg contributed to eleven
                            volumes of Lavater’s physiognomical publications in German,
                            Dutch, and French, at least 81 are signed in this
                            “Spiegelschrift,” or mirror writing (each instance, but
                            not the total, is noted in Thanner’s plate-by-plate descriptions
                            in her complete Schellenberg catalogue, which does not record duplicate
                            imprints appearing in more than one edition).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref> Thanner does not comment on the unusually high
                            proportion of reversed inscriptions—more than 45
                            percent—in either her catalogue or her biographical essay, but
                            perhaps there is a neurological explanation: in adolescence Schellenberg
                            suffered a head injury that put him in a coma for a month, left him with
                            a palpable crease in his skull, and forced him to relearn eating,
                            walking, reading, writing, and everything except drawing “as if
                            he were a baby” (Thanner, “Johann Rudolf
                            Schellenberg” 21-22). <note id="n35">35. The imprint of
                                Chodowiecki’s engraving for Gellert’s <hi rend="i">Leçons</hi> in my own
collection—a half page with
                                only the vignette—measures 6.0 × 8.9 cm. (distinct
                                platemark, with rounded corners); the image area is about 5.1
                                × 8.0 cm.; Engelmann, No. 86, uses “Zoll und Linie des
                                alt-französischen Maasses,” or the old French <hi rend="i">pouce</hi> (=
2.706 cm.), divided into 12 <hi rend="i">ligne</hi>, for a measurement of 2″3‴ ×
                                3″3½‴ (= 6.088 × 8.905 cm.). In the copy
                                of Gellert’s <hi rend="i">Leçons</hi> reproduced here
                                (illus. 6), the faint platemark, which appears no more than 5.9
                                × 8.4 cm., goes slightly into the gutter, but the image area
                                is 5.2 × 8.0 cm. (cf. Bauer’s measurements, No. 148,
                                presumably for the image area: 5.5 × 8.0 cm.). For
                                Schellenberg’s engraving after Chodowiecki for <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>,
reused in Armbruster, Engelmann’s dimensions
                                (platemark) are 2″3‴ ×
                                2″9½‴ (= 6.088 × 7.549 cm.); my own
                                measurements, based on five copies, are 6.2 × 7.5 cm., while
                                Thanner, <hi rend="i">Schweizerische Buchillustration</hi>, reports
                                an absent platemark and an image area of 5.2 × 7.2 cm. (5.4
                                × 6.8 cm. in my own measurements). Not only do cataloguers
                                differ in providing plate vs. image dimensions, but measurements may
                                also vary because of differences in depth of platemarks, paper
                                shrinkage after printing, and lengths of parallel sides (top and
                                bottom, right and left). Engelmann measures bottom and left sides;
                                my own practice has been inconsistent. Image areas reported in
                                Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Commercial Book
                                    Illustrations</hi>, are measured across the largest dimensions,
                                thus sometimes diagonally; mine record the greatest distances along
                                horizontal and vertical planes parallel to the platemarks.</note>
	<note id="n36">36. In the plate-by-plate descriptions of
                                Schellenberg’s engravings in Thanner, <hi rend="i">Schweizerische
Buchillustration</hi> I: 698-897, I count 26
                                reversed signatures in <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi>,
                                26 in the Dutch edition, 23 in the French edition, and 6 in
                                Armbruster’s abridged German edition; the total number of
                                engravings actually signed by Schellenberg (in various capacities)
                                can be derived from Thanner’s figures on 708 and the chart on
                                720.</note></p>
            <p>When Blake copied Schellenberg’s engraving for <hi rend="i">Essays
                                in Physiognomy</hi> I: 127 (cover illus.), he re-reversed the
                            design, fortuitously bringing it back to the orientation of
                            Chodowiecki’s engraving. Although there is no reason to speculate
                            that Blake had access to Chodowiecki’s original, his engraving
                            (6.1 × 8.4 cm.; image 5.2 × 7.2 cm.) improves upon
                            Schellenberg’s in clarity and sharpness of details. In
                            Chodowiecki’s engraving, one tree at the center is obviously
                            dead; both Schellenberg and Blake soften this detail by adding more
                            leaves (especially luxuriant in Blake’s version) to the nearby
                            tree. Blake also levels off the shoreline, makes the land-water
                            distinction more obvious, strengthens the very faint indication of
                            reflections on the water of the buildings on the distant shore, adds a
                            bright rim to the top of the clouds, darkens certain clouds with almost
                            mechanical-looking ruled lines, squares off the smaller tower on the
                            round building across the water, simplifies the marshy estuary area, and
                            makes a rounder hole for the tree-planter. On the tree-planter’s
                            side of the vignette, Blake reduces Schellenberg’s six major
                            projections of land to four, and on the other side he reduces
                            Schellenberg’s eight projections of land to seven. Blake adds
                            bolder stipple effects to the bald gardener’s head, the water
                            pouring out of the can, and the lighter parts of the grass, and he makes
                            the holes of the spout visible. Blake’s tree-waterer has a longer
                            beard than his counterparts in Chodowiecki and Schellenberg; his eyes
                            focus on the trees rather than the can, and his toes are longer, more in
                            the Mannerist style.</p>
            <p>We turn now to the background for Blake’s profile of Spalding
                            (illus. 2). Lavater had known the Shaftesbury-influenced rationalist
                            Lutheran theologian Johann Joachim Spalding (1714-1804) since 1763, when
                            Lavater, Fuseli, and their friend Felix Hess spent eight life-changing
                            months in Spalding’s home in Barth, Swedish (or Nether)
                            Pomerania, on the Baltic coast. The three young seminary graduates,
                            newly ordained as Zwinglian ministers, were on a hastily arranged study
                            tour in the aftermath of the “Grebel affair,” the furor
                            surrounding an anonymous public indictment (later acknowledged by
                            Lavater and Fuseli) of a corrupt but well-connected city official. The
                            opportunity to study with Spalding (and, for Fuseli, the freedom to
                            sketch and paint)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">37</ref> was the most
                            significant and memorable part of a Wanderjahr that included meetings
                            with 
<pb id="p38-62" n="62"/>
such notables as Moses Mendelssohn,
                            Friedrich Klopstock, C. F. Gellert, and J. W. L. Gleim. Lavater kept a
                            detailed diary of his and Hess’s conversations with
                            Spalding—for example, a two-hour discussion of Spalding’s
                            hypothesis on the workings of the Holy Spirit on 13 August
                            1763—and even thirty years later, on a journey to Copenhagen, he
                            fondly recalled those “nine blessed months” with Spalding.
                            The idyll ended in early 1764 as Fuseli, now certain that he had no
                            religious vocation, struck out alone to make a new life in England,
                            while Lavater and Hess, en route to their homeland, accompanied Spalding
                            to Berlin to begin an important ecclesiastical appointment. For the rest
                            of his life, Lavater kept in touch with his mentor by correspondence,
                            sometimes through their mutual friend the Swiss-born aesthetician Johann
                            Georg Sulzer (1720-99) of Berlin, who himself was later the subject of a
                            portrait ordered from Chodowiecki by Lavater.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">38</ref>
	<note id="n37">37. The pleasures of this protracted visit are captured
                                in Fuseli’s now-lost drawing (known only through an 1810
                                engraving) of Spalding, then a recent widower, and his children
                                entertaining his friend Arnim von Suckow, Hess (standing up) and
                                Lavater in the summerhouse, with Fuseli himself peeking from behind
                                with his sketchbook; reproduced, <hi rend="i">inter alia</hi>, in
                                Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Fuseli: Catalogue Raisonné</hi> 333,
                                No. 289, and Jaton 20-21; Tytler 23 offers a different
                                identification of the main figures.</note>
	<note id="n38">38. Lavater informed Chodowiecki that, within a 100-mile
                                radius of Berlin, he and Spalding were the only recipients of
                                Lavater’s private monthly paper, <hi rend="i">Miscellaneous
                                    Thoughts, Manuscript for Friends</hi> (2 April 1774;
                                Steinbrucker 87, No. 109). For further information on Spalding, see
                                    <hi rend="i">Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie</hi> (1893; rpt.
                                Berlin: Durcher and Humbolt, 1971) 35: 30-31; for Fuseli’s
                                perspective on the study tour, his wrenching break from Lavater, and
                                his envy of Lavater’s intimacy with Hess, see Mason 16,
                                88-89, 96-101.</note></p>
            <p>It was not until 6 May 1774, ten months after Lavater’s original
                            request for portraits on 10 July 1773, that Chodowiecki finally
                            mentioned Spalding among the learned gentlemen in Berlin who were to be
                            depicted in medallion format (Steinbrucker 88). But he did not actually
                            approach Spalding until 3 December 1774, via an introductory letter from
                            Lavater, to request permission to draw the theologian along with his
                            elder son Carl (Steinbrucker 110-11). When at the end of January 1775
                            Chodowiecki wrote that he had shown Lavater’s portrait to
                            Spalding and his son (Steinbrucker 118), Lavater apparently assumed that
                            Chodowiecki had also finished his drawings of that family and replied
                            excitedly on 25 February 1775, “I am expecting Spalding’s
                            portrait!” (Steinbrucker 122). At that time he also ordered a
                            portrait of the younger son (Georg Ludwig) in the same size as the
                            others (Steinbrucker 122).</p>
            <p>Four months later, on 24 June 1775, and almost two years after his
                            original order, Lavater was still waiting for a picture of Spalding, as
                            he noted when acknowledging the self-portrait he had just received from
                            Chodowiecki: 
<q> Finally, finally, finally at last a life-drawing of
                                you! I didn’t know at all what to make of your long silence.
                                Every post-day I wanted to write you and every post-day I thought I
                                would receive a letter. Now finally the 23 of <hi rend="i">June</hi>
                                the Kreuzer [a coin, apparently referring to the medallion style of
                                Chodowiecki’s profile], with which in most respects I am very
                                pleased. . .. But where are the rest of the things on order that
                                have been so long in preparation? Where’s the Spalding? etc.,
                                etc., etc. (Steinbrucker 131-32) </q>
On 1 July 1775 Lavater sent
                            Chodowiecki a drawing of a female friend that he wanted him to copy and
                            improve in fifteen 
							<figure n="SSSS.Lips.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="491">
								<figTranscr>SSSS.</figTranscr>
								<head>7. “SSSS,” engr.</head>
								<figDesc>Lips after Chodowiecki. <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
                                        Fragmente</hi> III (1777) opp. 342; 24.2 × 21.3 cm.;
                                    Spalding oval 8.8 × 5.8 cm. Orell Füssli facsimile
                                    (1968-69). Author’s collection.</figDesc>
							</figure> specific ways, listed <hi rend="i">a</hi> through <hi rend="i">o</hi>, and turned up the
pressure for his most-wanted drawing:
                            “With the next post I expect whatever among your drawings you
                            have ready, Spalding, etc.” (Steinbrucker 132-33).</p>
            <p>On 14 July 1775 Chodowiecki at last enclosed nine of the previously
                            ordered portraits, led by 1., “A lovable, gentle physiognomy, Mr.
                            Provost Spalding,” 2., “an alert boy . . . his oldest
                            son,” and 3., “a somewhat quieter one, the second. This
                            one must have his nose a bit stopped up, he always holds his mouth
                            open.” Presumably Chodowiecki’s original black chalk and
                            pen drawing of Spalding’s profile within a larger rounded oval
                            (15.1 × 11.0 cm.), now in the Berlin Print Cabinet, was the one
                            sent to Lavater and later returned after engraving.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref> For these nine profiles, “<hi rend="i">Spalding
etc.</hi>,” Chodowiecki charged the shocking (to
                            Lavater) price of 45 Thaler, or 5 Thaler per portrait (Steinbrucker
                            135). Chodowiecki was proud of the fidelity of the likenesses: on 2
                            September 1775, he named the portraits of Spalding and his sons among
                            the most faithfully rendered of the group, and he passed along a
                            compliment from Spalding himself: “[He] told me too that he found
                            that of all portraits that have been made of him, this appeared to him
                            to be the truest” (Steinbrucker 139-40). In <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
Fragmente</hi>, 
							<pb id="p38-63" n="63"/>
							<figure n="Lips.After.Schmoll.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="501">
								<figTranscr>J. H. Lips.</figTranscr>
								<head>8. “Johann Heinrich Lips,” engr.</head>
								<figDesc>Lips after Schmoll. <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
                                        Fragmente</hi> II (1776) opp. 222; 18.6 × 16.0 cm.
                                    Orell Füssli facsimile (1968-69). Author’s
                                    collection.</figDesc>
							</figure> all three Spaldings, along with Sulzer, appear on one plate
                            (III: opp. 342; illus. 7), labeled “SSSS,” for Sulzer,
                            Spalding, Sohn [Son], and Sohn (or Sulzer, Spalding, Spalding, and
                            Spalding). Apparently only the adults were asked to pose sans wigs.
                                <note id="n39">39. No. 116 in Müller, reproduced on 169, with
                                commentary on 98. If this was an ur-drawing that remained in Berlin,
                                perhaps what Chodowiecki sent Lavater was a set of the nine profiles
                                copied in uniform format for the guidance of the
                            engravers.</note></p>
            <p>For this full-page plate of four portraits, the engraver was
                            Lavater’s youthful protégé Johann Heinrich Lips
                            (1758-1817) of Kloten, near Zurich. Lips, the son of a barber-surgeon,
                            exhibited so much talent while being tutored in Latin by his local
                            pastor, in preparation for taking up his father’s occupation,
                            that the son of the pastor encouraged him to copy old engravings, from
                            which he soon progressed to life drawing. When Lavater saw the
                            14-year-old’s work in late 1772, he immediately took him under
                            his wing, sent him home with art supplies and a set of written
                            instructions on etching, arranged for the minister in Kloten to give him
                            a two-day-a-week crash course in art history, religion, and classical
                            mythology, and hired the boy to help him the rest of the week with
                            physiognomical drawings. Although Lips’s parents would not pay
                            for a two-year apprenticeship under Schellenberg in 1774, Lips managed
                            to study etching with him for six weeks in 1775—the full extent
                            of his formal training. In 1776, when Lips was only “in his
                            seventeenth year,” Lavater elevated the youth to his gallery of
                            celebrities and otherwise physiognomically interesting subjects by
                            including an analysis of the boy’s engraved portrait in 
<hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> (II: 222-24; illus. 8). In
                            Lips’s facial structure, Lavater discerns indications of a
                            natural artist with a good heart and a sharp eye who, without
                            instruction, is growing in strength and genius every day, to the point
                            that with further travel and acquaintance with other artists he may
                            become “one of the greatest, if not the greatest engraver in the
                            world,” in possession of physiognomical insights and creative
                            powers that would make him, “in a few years, a second
                            Chodowiecki” (II: 224).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">40</ref>
	<note id="n40">40. Lavater based his glowing physiognomical account of
                                young Lips on a portrait by G. F. Schmoll, Lavater’s
                                brother-in-law, and awarded the engraving assignment to Lips
                                himself. The facts of Lips’s early life are derived from the
                                “Biographie” timeline in Kruse 21-27, and from
                                Goritschnig. Highlights of Lips’s mature life are
                                depressingly few: in 1778-79, when Fuseli visited his homeland on
                                his way back from Italy to England, Lips became enamored of his
                                style and forever after reproached himself for his inability to
                                break free to a bold and original style of his own. In the 1780s, he
                                made study trips to Germany and Italy; in 1789-94 he worked in
                                Weimar under the patronage of Goethe but returned to Zurich, where
                                he remained under the influence of Lavater or the memory of Lavater
                                for the rest of his life. For a succinct account in English, see
                                Vaughan (a review of Kruse’s catalogue).</note></p>
            <p>In engraving Chodowiecki’s portrait of the distinguished
                            theologian Spalding (III: opp. 342), Lips carefully replicates the
                            features depicted in the black chalk drawing, which both Chodowiecki and
                            Spalding had considered an excellent likeness, scaled down to 8.8
                            × 5.8 cm., to fit within an 11.3 × 10.2 cm. rounded oval,
                            one of four within the same 24.2 × 21.3 cm. outer frame. But
                            Lavater’s commentary on Spalding’s character, while
                            generally approving, mentions neither the accuracy of the likeness nor
                            the engraver’s fidelity to the original. Instead, Lavater
                            complains that, except for the eyes, the portraitist (unnamed) has
                            failed to capture the physiognomically striking features of his beloved
                            former mentor: 
<q> Much more recognizable [i.e., than Sulzer’s
                                face, which Lavater calls a “caricature”], and yet at
                                best an adapted mask of truth. A face sound, noble, bright; in every
                                opinion, not easily self-deceived. The outline of the forehead not
                                pure, not bold enough. . . . Depth of insight is apparent in the
                                transition from the forehead to the nose—and in the
                                marvelous, almost unmistakable eyes. The eye in itself is eternally
                                a firmer indication of sure and accurate understanding. The eyebrow
                                is not strong enough. The nose honest and sound. The mouth extremely
                                reflective and tasteful. It’s too bad that the lower part
                                covers the upper part and is much too rounded off. The shape of the
                                head in back is more sensitive than [Sulzer’s]. In the
                                remaining shading I miss coherence and truth—Now isn’t
                                this a cold, ice-cold way to write about the face of a man who is
                                among those I love most? To whom I owe more thanks than to any other
                                mortal? Whom I believe I know through and through; whose writings
                                have the purest character of truth-loving and independent strength
                                and elegance—and who is himself far more excellent than his
                                excellent writings? (<hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> III: 342) </q>
This
                            commentary, like many others by Lavater, says more about the writer than
                            about his subject. Clearly, no matter how skillfully Chodowiecki may
                            have rendered Spalding’s face from life, nor how accurately Lips
                            copied the face in his engraving, it would have been beyond the power of
                            any artist to capture the idealized mental image that Lavater cherished
                            of 
<pb id="p38-64" n="64"/>
<figure n="Spalding.Lips.AfterChodowiecki.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="457">
	<head>9. [Spalding], engr.?</head>
	<figDesc>Lips (unsigned) after Chodowiecki, <hi rend="i">Essai sur
                                        la physiognomonie</hi> I ([1781]) 232; 13.1 × 10.7
                                    cm.; image 8.7 × 5.6 cm; re-engr. for Armbruster’s
                                        <hi rend="i">J. C. Lavaters Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> I
                                    (1783) following 62; 10.9 × 8.6 cm.; image 8.6 ×
                                    5.5 cm. Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale
                                    University.</figDesc>
</figure> his teacher as he had appeared in 1763, still fresh in memory
                            after twelve years of separation.</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="i">Essai sur la physiognomonie</hi> I: 231, Lavater revised
                            his commentary on Spalding, severely pruning his remarks on
                            Chodowiecki’s portrait to accommodate a new (bewigged) version of
                            the head by Anton Graff, from a three-quarter perspective, in an outline
                            engraving. Lavater places the two images of Spalding in sequence,
                            greatly to Chodowiecki’s disadvantage. His revised text indicates
                            that he has discovered a new flaw in Chodowiecki’s Spalding,
                            whose nose had been described in <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> as
                            “honest and sound.” In <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> I: 231,
                            “the drawing of the nostril is defective: it is too small, and
                            the trait which forms it is indifferently marked” (trans. Hunter,
                                <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I: 225). Whether this is supposed to be
                            Chodowiecki’s fault or the engraver’s we are not told.
                            More than satisfactory, however, is the nose of Spalding in a silhouette
                            (the technique for recording physiognomical features that Lavater
                            considered most reliable because, if traced from a well-cast shadow, it
                            requires only minimal involvement by the artist): “Thinks
                            clearly: his mind furnishes him with ideas just and pleasing; his
                            actions are like his ideas; he introduces much elegance into his
                            conversation and compositions; he adopts not easily new opinions. The 
							<figure n="Spalding.engr.Heath.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="459">
								<figTranscr>V.</figTranscr>
								<head>10. [Spalding], engr.</head>
								<figDesc>Heath. <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>, trans. Holcroft, I (1789)
                                    following 66: fig. V; 17.5 × 11.2 cm., oval 8.8 ×
                                    7.3 cm., head 7.1 × 4.9 cm.; from 2nd ed. (1804).
                                    Author’s collection.</figDesc>
							</figure> drawing of the forehead is not sufficiently characteristic,
                            but the nose expresses the most exquisite taste”; further down
                            the page, Spalding’s mouth is said to be the “most
                            ingenious” of the four silhouettes under review (<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> II:
187).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref>
	<note id="n41">41. This silhouette, unsigned, and inscribed
                                “Spalding, Probst zu Berlin,” appears as item 1 in <hi rend="i">Von
Chodowiecki bis Liebermann: Katalog der
                                    Zeichnungen, Aquarelle, Pastelle und Gouachen des 18. Und 19.
                                    Jahrhunderts</hi>, comp. Dominik Bartmann and Gert-Dieter
                                Ulferts (Berlin: Berlin Museum, 1990) 41.</note></p>
            <p>Blake’s immediate source, the unsigned engraving of
                            Chodowiecki’s Spalding in <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> I: 232,
                            probably also by Lips (illus. 9), differs from the engraving in 
<hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> mainly in representing the theologian alone,
                            without Sulzer or his sons. In <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>, the head is 8.7
                            × 5.6 cm., virtually the same size as in <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi>, on a plate
measuring 13.1 × 10.7 cm. Because
                            of the optical illusion created by the greater image-to-page ratio in
                            the English <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>, Blake’s copy (illus. 2),
                            transposed from a predominantly stipple to a linear style, appears
                            larger than its actual dimensions of 8.9 × 5.9 cm. on a 13.3
                            × 10.5 cm. plate; the image area, on the diagonal, is 9.5
                            × 6.3 cm. (Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Commercial Book
                                Illustrations</hi>; see note 35). James Heath’s 
								<pb id="p38-65" n="65"/>
								<figure n="Spalding.Profile.Barlow.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="493">
									<figTranscr>Barlow sculp.<lb/>
									Spalding, Profile.<lb/>
									From Lavater.</figTranscr>
									<head>11. “Spalding. Profile,” engr.</head>
									<figDesc>Barlow. <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>, trans. Moore, I (1793)
                                    opp. 198; oval 12.6 × 8.8 cm.; head 9.6 × 6.2 cm.
                                    Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale
                                    University.</figDesc>
								</figure> softer-lined engraving of Spalding’s profile (7.1
                            × 4.9 cm., in an oval of 8.8 × 7.3 cm.) for the Holcroft
                            edition (I: following 66, illustrating text on I: 62; illus. 10)
                            faithfully copies an unsigned engraving, probably also by Lips, in
                            Armbruster (I: following 62; 8.6 × 5.5 cm. on 10.9 × 8.6
                            cm. plate, no oval); although the images in <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>
                            (illus. 9) and Armbruster are virtually the same size, they are not
                            identical and are not from the same plate. The resemblance between
                            Blake’s and Heath’s engraved portraits of Spalding,
                            despite their different styles and their use of different but equally
                            skilled intermediary engravings as models, attests both to the strength
                            and clarity of Chodowiecki’s underlying design, the black chalk
                            drawing in Berlin, and to the accuracy and consistency of the Swiss
                            copywork. John Barlow, engraver for the Moore translation, copied almost
                            all his images from Hunter’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> rather than
                            directly from <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>; his head of Spalding (9.6
                            × 6.2 cm., in an oval of 12.6 × 8.8 cm.) is rendered with
                            a drastic coarsening of the linear net (first published <hi rend="i">Conjuror’s
Magazine</hi>, Feb. 1793; bound in I [1793] opp.
                            198; illus. 11); this same plate, somewhat worn, is reused in
                            Grenville’s edition. Furthermore, both Barlow and Heath, who
                            subscribed as well as contributed to the Hunter edition, had ready
                            access to Blake’s engraving of Spalding.</p>
            <p>The third engraving that bears only Blake’s signature as engraver,
                            an emblem of a hand holding a torch with insects nearby (illus. 3), is
                            unsigned in both <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> and <hi rend="i">Fragmente.</hi>
Presumably, like most of the unsigned engravings in
                            these editions, it is the work of either Lips or Schellenberg, the two
                            biggest contributors to both projects, although neither the engraving
                            nor its underlying design is claimed by Joachim Kruse, Lips’s
                            cataloguer, or by Brigitte Thanner, Schellenberg’s cataloguer.
                            (Thanner ascribes many other unsigned engravings to Schellenberg on the
                            basis of documentary evidence.) The designer may never be known, but the
                            occasion for the vignette’s creation has long been hidden in
                            plain sight. The image first appeared at the beginning of the fourth and
                            final volume of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
                                Fragmente</hi> (1778) and then migrated to volume one in the French
                                <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> ([1781]), where it served as Blake’s
                            model. Thus separated from the (never-translated) German text that it
                            was designed to accompany, it became a puzzlement to Essick as he
                            searched for a connection with something in the English text, possibly
                            “the ability to see things clearly” (Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Commercial
Book Illustrations</hi> 42, XIX.3).
                            Focusing on the image of “flies hovering around a flame,”
                            without reference to the hand and arm, Essick speculates that the design
                            may “take its cue from the ‘female butterfly and the
                            winged ant’” (<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I: 202) and
                            “persons who ‘have eyes and the faculty of seeing when
                            they open them to the light’” (<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I:
                            203), possibly continuing the thread of an earlier “reference to
                            a time ‘when the bright shining of a candle doth give thee
                            light,’” (<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I: 117). Thus the torch
                            would represent “the truths of physiognomy to which all should be
                            attracted.” Essick cautions, however, that “A traditional
                            emblematic meaning of these motifs—it is unwise to be attracted
                            to that which can destroy you—seems inappropriate, or at least
                            oddly contrary to the thrust of the text, in this context”
                            (Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi>
                            42).</p>
            <p>In its original physical and historical setting in the front matter of
                                <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> IV, the image of the
                            hand bearing the insect-surrounded torch aloft is an emblem of
                            Lavater’s resolve in the face of his detractors. By the time this
                            final volume of the <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> came out in 1778,
                            Lavater’s physiognomical theories had come under severe attack,
                            even ridicule—most notably by G. C. Lichtenberg—for their
                            utter lack of scientific content.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n42" type="note">42</ref>
                            In a foreword “written 20 December 
<pb id="p38-66" n="66"/>
<figure n="Torch.Physiognomische.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="481">
	<head>12. [Torch upheld by hand under attack from insects:
                                    the Physiognomist upholding the light of Truth despite the
                                    ridicule of his enemies], unsigned.</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> IV (1778) opp.
                                    3; 12.2 × 6.0 cm. Orell Füssli facsimile
                                    (1968-69). Author’s collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="Torch.Essai.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="481">
	<head>13. [Torch upheld by hand under attack from insects],
                                    unsigned.</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">Essai sur la physiognomonie</hi> I ([1781])
                                    213; 14.1 × 10.0 cm.; image 10.9 × 6.0 cm.
                                    Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale
                                    University.</figDesc>
</figure> 1777” but prepared for press in spring 1778, Lavater
                            proclaims with an air of quiet dignity his undaunted commitment to
                            uphold the “truth” of physiognomy in the face of his
                            critics’ disbelief and scorn. “What is, is,” he
                            writes, and despite personal attacks he refuses to allow physiognomy to
                            become the “butt of jokes.” According to Lavater’s
                            son-in-law and biographer Georg Gessner, “His principle was as
                            stated . . . in a vignette where a hand holds a light firmly, in which
                            several mosquitoes singe themselves in the flame, and one wasp stings
                            his hand, as expressed in a little rhyme.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref> That rhyme appears, several pages before the
                            engraving, at the end of Lavater’s introductory remarks: 
<q> And
                                even though the mosquito singes its wing,<lb/>
 Bursts its skull and
                                all its little brains,<lb/>
 Light is still light,<lb/>
 And even
                                though the most severe wasp stings me;<lb/>
 I still won’t let
                                go. (<hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> IV: viii) </q>
The
                            associated vignette appears at the end of the table of contents (IV:
                            opp. 3; illus. 12), facing the first “Fragment” (or
                            chapter) in the volume: a detailed response to Lichtenberg’s
                            attack in his <hi rend="i">Göttinger Taschen-Calender</hi> for
                            1778, published at the end of 1777. As indicated in the poem, the torch
                            represents the brilliant truth of physiognomy consuming its weaker
                            antagonists while Lavater the torchbearer, the indefatigable
                            truth-teller, stoically endures the torments of his harshest critic. The
                            stinging wasp, though unnamed, is understood to represent Lichtenberg.
                                <note id="n42">42. For more on the controversy, which culminated in
                                Lichtenberg’s devastatingly hilarious parody <hi rend="i">Fragment von
Schwänzen</hi> [Fragment on Tails] (1783),
                                see Frey 88-103; Ellis Shookman, “Pseudo-Science, Social Fad,
                                Literary Wonder: Johann Caspar Lavater and the Art of
                                Physiognomy,” <hi rend="i">The Faces of Physiognomy</hi>, ed.
                                Shookman, 1-24, esp. 10-12; Carl Brinitzer, <hi rend="i">A
                                    Reasonable Rebel: Georg Christoph Lichtenberg</hi>, trans.
                                Bernard Smith (New York: Macmillan, 1960) 111-16; E. H. Gombrich,
                                “On Physiognomic Perception,” <hi rend="i">Meditations
                                    on a Hobby Horse</hi> (London and New York: Phaidon, [1963]; 3rd
                                ed. 1978) 45-55; Hannelore Schlaffer, “Physiognomik: Lavater
                                und Lichtenberg,” <hi rend="i">Klassik und Romantik
                                    1770-1830</hi> (Stuttgart: Alfred Kröner, 1986) 13-25.
                                Lavater’s poem is a preemptive response to
                                Lichtenberg’s <hi rend="i">Über Physiognomik; wider
                                    die Physiognomen</hi> [On Physiognomics, against the
                                Physiognomists] (1778), an expanded version of his hastily written
                                article for his popular pocket almanac, <hi rend="i">Göttinger
Taschen-Calender</hi>, to which Lavater
                                replied both in <hi rend="i">Deutsches Museum</hi> in April 1778 and
                                in the long “First Fragment” of <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
Fragmente</hi> IV: 3-38.</note>
	<note id="n43">43. <hi rend="i">Johann Kaspar Lavaters
                                    Lebensbeschriebung</hi> II: 148. In Gessner’s text, the
                                variant spelling “Gehirngen,” is normalized to
                                “Gehirnchen,” or “little brains.”
                                Gessner’s recollection that the poem and emblem appear in
                                volume one is in error.</note></p>
            <p>This is the only plate with which Blake—unaware of the
                            image’s original meaning—allowed himself mild liberties in
                            re-design (illus. 3), while remaining well within the constraints of
                            replicative engraving. In <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> IV, the designer
                            has made Lavater’s lower forearm clearly masculine, sturdy,
                            almost beefy, <pb id="p38-67" n="67"/>
emerging from a loose sleeve. The
                            clenched fist firmly clasps the torch; the stinging wasp is seen from
                            the side as it lights on the fleshy pad under the thumb, while two
                            flying insects (the noun is “Mücke,” meaning fly,
                            mosquito, gnat, or midge, but not moth) approach the flame. For the new
                            location in <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> (I: 213; illus. 13), the engraver,
                            probably the same one responsible for this subject in <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi>,
has kept virtually the same design, reversed so
                            that the torch is held in the left hand. With this design for 
<hi rend="i">Essai</hi> as a model, Blake feminizes and slenderizes the
                            arm (still a left arm, now shown from the back, bare to the elbow),
                            improves the articulation of the wrist, and breaks up the clenched fist
                            by extending the forefinger along the torch. He also adds an extra
                            insect, gives more variety to the four insects’ shapes, and
                            rearranges them so that one lights on the torchbearer’s third
                            finger (without stinging) as another prepares to land on the
                            forefinger.</p>
            <p>In the French and English editions, the section for which this emblem
                            serves as a tailpiece, “XIX Fragment. General Reflections on the
                            Objections against Physiognomy,” touches on some of the same
                            concerns Lavater had expressed in his 1778 introduction to 
<hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> IV: the difficulties of the physiognomist’s
                            disinterested regard for truth, as he advances a discipline still in its
                            infancy, beset by self-contradictory and misguided counter-arguments and
                            outright mockery. There being no explanation of the meaning of the
                            design or the difference between the two kinds of stinging insects,
                            however, the vignette is identified in English simply as “A Hand
                            with a Torch, Finished” in the list of plates for the eighth
                            fascicle, published in February 1789 (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books</hi> 594). In the comprehensive table of contents to 
<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I, which replaced the separate contents sheets
                            of the fascicles, a more detailed title specifies the sex of the
                            torchbearer and attempts to relate the image to its new context:
                            “Female Hand and Arm holding a Torch, emblematical of Science
                            dissipating Ignorance. Vignette” (<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I:
                            iii).</p>
            <p>How and why did Lavater’s physiognomical work undergo such
                            extensive changes in English as to alter the meaning of some images and
                            render the Continental designers invisible? Only the most cursory
                            answers can be provided here.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Proliferation of Lavater’s Physiognomical
                                    Texts and the Making of the “English Lavater”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The sheer number of editions and translations of Lavater’s
                            physiognomical writings, as reported by Graham, has given rise to the
                            mistaken belief that the work enjoyed phenomenal success in the
                            marketplace. In fact, editions that Lavater himself saw through the
                            press tended to be commercial disasters—partly because of
                            Lavater’s personality and bad business judgment, partly because
                            the project got off on the wrong foot from the start. In 1771, when
                            Lavater suddenly realized that it was his turn to present a paper to the
                            Naturforschende Gesellschaft, the natural philosophy society of
                            Zurich—“and I didn’t know what on”—he
                            recalled having been complimented on his knack for face-reading, a
                            talent he cultivated as a pastor as an aid to recognizing God’s
                            image in humanity. Having no other ideas for a topic of interest to
                            devotees of science, he seized upon “physiognomics” for an
                            exploratory lecture, written “God knows with what
                                haste.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">44</ref> The true
                            instigator of the work was Lavater’s friend Dr. Johann Georg
                            Zimmermann (1728-95), who—after moving in 1768 from Brugg,
                            Switzerland, to accept an appointment as court physician to the Elector
                            of Hanover, George III of Britain—continued to pester Lavater to
                            develop his physiognomical findings into something publishable.
                            Lavater’s 1771 lecture gave Zimmermann his chance. As Lavater
                            reports in the opening section of <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
                                Fragmente</hi>, “Mr. Klockenbring of Hanover [Friedrich
                            Arnold Klockenbring, editor of <hi rend="i">Hannoverischen
                                Magazin</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">45</ref>] asked me for the
                            lecture for Zimmermann” (I: 10), and “I gave him in all
                            their incompleteness the unedited papers,” never suspecting that
                            Zimmermann would quickly edit the material and publish it without the
                            author’s knowledge or permission (as the work of an anonymous
                            “youth”) in Klockenbring’s journal. Horrified to
                            find himself thrust before the world as a “defender of
                            physiognomics” (<hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> I: 10; trans. Frey
                            72), Lavater made his own arrangements with his own publisher, Weidmanns
                            Erben and Reich, to publish the lecture under his own name (eliminating
                            Zimmermann’s annotations), along with a second section outlining
                            possible future topics. But Zimmermann’s introduction to the work
                            in book form (20 March 1772) expresses satisfaction with his magazine
                            publishing coup of 3, 7, and 10 February 1772, and accurately predicts
                            that this new publication, <hi rend="i">Von der Physiognomik</hi>, will
                            launch a “Physiognomanie” [craze for physiognomy]. In a
                            panicky response to popular demand for a follow-up, a full-scale
                            illustrated study, Lavater beseeched Zimmermann, Herder, Goethe, and
                            many others to send him ideas, images, citations of authorities,
                            character interpretations, and recommendations for illustrators. 
<note id="n44">44. Most translations relating to the early history of <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi>, as acknowledged
parenthetically
                                hereafter, are quoted verbatim from Frey—a superb rendering
                                of the distinctive voices of Lavater and his collaborators into
                                English. This episode, originally recounted in <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> I:
10-12, is rendered somewhat less vividly by
                                Hunter in <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> I: 9-12.</note>
	<note id="n45">45. Ohage 116n12 provides the first name and position of
                                Lavater’s “Herr Klockenbring.” Lavater’s
                                    <hi rend="i">Aussichten in Ewigkeit</hi> (1768-72), a series of
                                letters to Zimmermann on eternity, describes unmediated
                                physiognomical communication among risen bodies (16th letter, 30
                                April 1772, written after the Feb. 1772 publication of <hi rend="i">Von der
Physiognomik</hi>).</note></p>
            <p>From then on the project became a perpetual work in progress, chronically
                            over budget and over length, always open to change. <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
Fragmente</hi>, printed in a press run of 750
                                copies<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">46</ref> and sold by
                            subscription, set the pattern: it turned out to be the most expensive
                            book ever published by the Leipzig house of Weidmanns Erben and Reich
                            (co-published by the newly formed Swiss firm Heinrich Steiner in
                            Winterthur), and sales did not cover costs. In his original proposal (1
                            February 1773) for simultaneous publication of “my physiognomical
                            work” in French and German, Lavater had undertaken to commission
                            all engravings at his own risk 
<pb id="p38-68" n="68"/>
for a minimum of
                            24 full-page plates and at least 16 sheets of text (128 pages), in
                            return for 600 ducats and 25 free copies, 20 in German, 5 in French
                            (Zentralbibliothek Zürich, Lavater Family Archive, Ms. 578.25;
                            quoted Thanner, <hi rend="i">Schweizerische Buchillustration</hi> 731).
                            Between the first and second volumes, the selling price went up from 18
                            2/3 to 38 Reichthaler, and at the end of the third volume the publishers
                            noted that all volumes thus far contained at least 47 more sheets, 104
                            more full-plate engravings, and 127 more vignettes than planned, but
                            they committed themselves to absorbing the loss to avoid reneging on the
                            announced price. Again, at the end of the even larger final volume, they
                            observed that although the price should be higher, they had decided
                            “out of friendship to Mr. Lavater” to honor “a
                            promise once made,” once again sacrificing their expected profits
                            and raising the price only for new purchasers of the last two
                                volumes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">47</ref> There must have been
                            few takers: the number of subscribers began dropping as soon as the
                            first volume appeared (Vollert 39n46; Ohage 118-19n12), as if in
                            response to Lavater’s money-back guarantee (<hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> I: a3v).
<note id="n46">46. According to
                                Goldfriedrich 631n8, and Vollert 49; Thanner, <hi rend="i">Schweizerische
Buchillustration</hi> (730) gives the print-run
                                number as 700.</note>
	<note id="n47">47. For particulars of the per-sheet cost and selling
                                price of the first two volumes, expressed in Thaler and Groschen, in
                                relation to Lavater’s steep honorarium (from which he paid
                                for the engravings) and his “Douceur,” or sweetener,
                                see Goldfriedrich 631n8. For monetary equivalencies, see Franz Pick
                                and René Sédillot, <hi rend="i">All the Monies of the
                                    World: A Chronicle of Currency Values</hi> (New York: Pick,
                                1971), and for other equivalencies and for comparative data on
                                wellknown authors’ honoraria, book prices, and common wages,
                                see Walter Krieg, <hi rend="i">Materialien zu einer
                                    Entwicklungsgeschichte der Bücher-Preise und des
                                    Autoren-Honorars vom 15. bis zum 20. Jahrhundert</hi> (Vienna:
                                Herbert Stubenrauch, 1953) 27-32.</note></p>
            <p>And so it continued. For Lavater personally, the greatest financial loss
                            resulted from the French edition, an ill-conceived venture in
                            self-publishing. Intending to save money—but without considering
                            transportation costs and delays—Lavater had his reworked and
                            expanded German manuscript translated and printed by members of the
                            Huguenot community in The Hague, with Heinrich Steiner of Winterthur
                            serving as distributor, and new engravings executed under his own eye in
                            Zurich, partly to provide “work and with it, food” for the
                            artists in his retinue whose fortunes “weighed on his
                            soul” (Gessner II: 284n43). But as Gessner laments (II: 282-86),
                            fewer subscriptions were sold than expected; the price of the book, at
                            nine louis d’or for subscribers and twelve for new purchasers,
                            was both too low to cover costs and too high for any but the largest
                            libraries; a very considerable shipment to England sank in transit; and
                            the fourth volume, just on the point of publication, was stalled by
                            revolutions in both France and Holland. At the end of the third volume
                            Steiner appended a public announcement (bound into some extant copies)
                            dated 1 August 1787: instead of being complete in three volumes, as
                            promised in the 1 October 1781 prospectus, six sections that had
                            appeared in <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> will have to be carried over
                            (gratis to subscribers) to a fourth volume, which (at a price) will be
                            filled out by additional materials from Lavater (<hi rend="i">Essai</hi>
                            III, unnumbered endsheet). The Dutch edition, Lavater’s
                            four-volume octavo abridgment <hi rend="i">Over die Physiognomie</hi>,
                            translated by Johann Wilhelm van Haar (Amsterdam: Johannes Allert,
                            1781-84), had unforeseen expenses of a different sort: at
                            Lavater’s request, the publisher reissued volume one on better
                            paper, at his own expense, to do justice to the engravings. Finally, the
                            abridged three-volume octavo redaction by Armbruster (drawing from both
                                <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> and <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>, which was
                            coming out at the same time) ends by noting the need for a fourth volume
                            (not issued until 1830; see note 9) that would, among other things,
                            include more female faces. According to Gessner’s biography,
                            “a considerably large quantity of copies of this work,”
                            remained available for purchase in 1802 (II: 334n44).</p>
            <p>On to Britain. As early as 1773, Lavater had included in his initial
                            contract a provision for an English translation, at the discretion of
                            his co-publishers Reich and Steiner (Thanner, <hi rend="i">Schweizerische
Buchillustration</hi> 761). But when his plan for
                            simultaneous publication of <hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> in French and
                            German fell through and he took over as self-publisher of the French
                            edition, he soon realized that he should try to broaden its market to
                            England. On 6 February 1782, as the first volume of <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>
reached Switzerland, Lavater asked the help of his
                            friend Johann Gottlieb Burckhardt (1756-1800), minister of the
                            Marienkirche in the Savoy area of London, in checking for errors, in
                            collaboration with Lavater’s (recently widowed) friend and
                            translator Madame La Fite (1737?-94), who now had a position reading
                            aloud to Queen Charlotte of England. He also enclosed a letter for
                            Fuseli, presumably on the same subject, In reply (13 March 1782),
                            Burckhardt assured Lavater that La Fite had found no conspicuous errors
                            and would promote the book at court, but he advised against
                            Lavater’s plan to handle sales himself to avoid paying
                            commissions. By the spring of 1784, the first two volumes of 
<hi rend="i">Essai</hi> had attracted attention in <hi rend="i">Critical
                                Review</hi>, Burckhardt was preparing to show them to Benjamin West,
                            and the book importer Peter Elmsley, as Lavater’s agent, had sold
                            37 copies of each volume. Only Fuseli, appalled by the quality of
                            engravings after his work in <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>, continued to
                            insist on a new and corrected edition in English (5 April 1784; 4 May
                            1784), and in the end he had his way.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n48" type="note">48</ref> By the time the third volume of <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>
                            (dated 1786 but delayed until 1787) came out, two English translations
                            were in prospect: an abridged one by Wollstonecraft (from Johnson, with
                            Fuseli as intermediary), and an expansive one by Hunter (from Murray,
                            also with Fuseli’s help). <note id="n48">48. Before I had access
                                to the microfiche archive of Lavater’s unpublished
                                correspondence in the Zentralbibliothek Zürich (see note 58),
                                I worked from abstracts and quotations generously e-mailed to me by
                                Ingrid Goritschnig from her own research notes.</note></p>
            <p>John Murray (the first), who took on the risk of producing the
                            large-quarto lavishly illustrated edition, ran into financial
                            complications so intricately convoluted that his first biographer,
                            Samuel Smiles, and his second, William Zachs, writing more than a
                            century later, reached opposite 
                            conclusions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">49</ref> Either 
<pb id="p38-69" n="69"/> 
							“The Publication of ‘Lavater on Physiognomy’ in parts, a costly
                            work, largely illustrated, resulted in a heavy loss” (Smiles 26)
                            or it was “his most profitable publication” (Zachs 69).
                            According to the 1789 title page, the book’s “upwards of
                            800 engravings” (actually fewer than 600)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">50</ref> were “executed by, or under the
                            inspection of Thomas Holloway,” the master engraver who receives
                            top billing on the page; the text was “translated from the French
                            by Henry Hunter, D.D.,” and the work was “printed for John
                            Murray . . .; H. Hunter . . .; and T. Holloway.” In June 1787, a
                            prospectus promised the first of an expected 40 fascicles on January 1,
                                1788<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">51</ref>
(delayed in a later
                            prospectus to January 21<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">52</ref>); the
                            set, when completed, was to have made up “four magnificent
                            Volumes in Quarto.” But when publication ceased with the third
                            volume in 1799, the work had spilled over into 41 fascicles and bulked
                            so large that the three volumes had to be bound in five physical
                            volumes. The announced price was 12 shillings per fascicle to
                            subscribers, 15 to non-subscribers; one-guinea deposits were
                            acknowledged by a receipt from the “Proprietors,” who
                            would appear to be the three gentlemen leading the list of those taking
                            in subscriptions: Murray, Hunter, and Holloway. <note id="n49">49.
                                Smiles 26-28; Zachs 69-70, 83, 239, 358-59. Zachs mentions
                                Smiles’s biography of the second John Murray (1) but not the
                                fact that the first chapter deals with the first Murray.</note>
	<note id="n50">50. The 800 figure is retracted in “Errata”
                                at the end of “Directions to the Binder,” which was
                                issued with the final fascicle, No. 41, in March 1799.</note>
	<note id="n51">51. For the full text, see Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Fuseli: Catalogue Raisonné</hi>
97-98.</note>
	<note id="n52">52. For the full text, see J[ohn] P. Feather, <hi rend="i">Book Prospectuses Before 1801 in
the John Johnson
                                    Collection: A Catalogue with Microfiches</hi> (Oxford: Oxford
                                Microform Publications for the Bodleian Library, 1976) 14-E09; among
                                other changes, the author’s middle name becomes
                                “Caspar,” not “Gaspard,” and “new
                                dress” becomes “English dress.” The added claim
                                that “British characters make a distinguished
                                appearance” among illustrious personages of Europe is
                                repeated in a prospectus known only from a review in <hi rend="i">Monthly
Magazine</hi> 7 (Dec. 1799): 903; excerpted in
                                Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Fuseli: Catalogue Raisonné</hi>
                                98.</note></p>
            <p>But there were more participants than meet the eye, and their respective
                            contributions and contractual obligations add to the difficulty of
                            arriving at a bottom line. According to the anonymous memoirist who
                            prefixed a “Biographical Sketch” to a posthumous
                            collection of Hunter’s sermons published by the Murray firm in
                            1804, it was Hunter who 
<q> endeavoured in all companies to make
                                converts to translate the work into English; and having communicated
                                his ideas and his enthusiasm to Mr. Thomas Holloway, an eminent
                                engraver of his acquaintance, that gentleman readily undertook to
                                provide the necessary plates. Mr. John Murray, bookseller, had the
                                care of the printing, and the work thus allotted, was begun by all
                                parties with great ardour.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n53" type="note">53</ref>
	<note id="n53">53. [“Biographical Sketch”] in <hi rend="i">SERMONS, and other MISCELLANEOUS PIECES. .
./To
                                        which are prefixed, A BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH OF HIS LIFE, and/A
                                        Critical Account of his Writings</hi> (London: J. Murray et
                                    al., 1804) I: xix.</note></q>
But according to a memoir of Holloway
published anonymously in 1827
                            “by one of his Executors,” the graphic artist took the
                            lead: after “a great lover of the arts” suggested the
                            project as a showcase for engravings, Holloway “in consequence
                            engaged the Rev. Dr. Hunter in the translation; and forming a connexion
                            with two publishers, had the courage to embark in a work containing
                            seven hundred plates, and extending to five volumes imperial
                                quarto.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">54</ref> (The reference
                            to “two” publishers will shortly become clear.) In the
                            end, writes Holloway’s executor, “[S]o balanced was the
                            public favour between the translator and the artist, that some called
                            the work Hunter’s, and some Holloway’s Lavater, which is
                            the case to the present day” (20). Or perhaps, as claimed by
                            Fuseli’s biographer John Knowles, the real driving force was the
                            “great lover of the arts” who put the bug in
                            Holloway’s ear: “Fuseli wrote the preface, or, as he
                            modestly called it, the ‘advertisement;’ corrected the
                            translation by Hunter; made several drawings to illustrate the work; and
                            superintended the execution of the engravings.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">55</ref>
	<note id="n54">54. <hi rend="i">Memoir of the Late Mr. Thomas
                                    Holloway</hi> 17-18.</note>
	<note id="n55">55. <hi rend="i">Life and Writings of Henry Fuseli</hi>
                                I: 79.</note></p>
            <p>Meanwhile, Fuseli’s friend Joseph Johnson was planning an edition
                            of his own, a modest octavo aimed at less affluent readers, to be
                            translated by Mary Wollstonecraft. According to William Godwin’s
                            1798 memoir of his wife, Wollstonecraft “improved herself in her
                            French” in 1787, and in 1788 she “made an abridgment of
                            Lavater’s Physiognomy, from the French, which has never been
                            published.” A memorandum by Johnson confirms that her
                            translation, made after “she entered upon her house in George
                            Street at Michaelmas [late September] 1787,” was “from the
                                French.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">56</ref> But about this
                            time, Johnson’s and Murray’s projects became entangled. As
                            Bentley has reported, Johnson’s recently discovered office
                            letter-book reveals that Johnson eventually became a silent backer of
                            Murray’s edition,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">57</ref> and
                            William Zachs’s biography of Murray provides further details.
                            From my own examination of the unpublished documents in the Murray
                            Archive on which Zachs relies (correcting some of his transcriptions,
                            especially on 246n52, and taking into account other documents Zachs does
                            not cite), and from my interweaving of these materials with key letters
                            from the still-unpublished bulk of Lavater’s vast correspondence
                            in the Zentralbibliothek Zürich,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">58</ref> I have pieced together a loosely 
<pb id="p38-70" n="70"/>
                            sequential narrative of Murray’s and Johnson’s dealings
                            with Lavater from June 1787 to May 1788. <note id="n56">56. <hi rend="i">Memoirs
of Mary Wollstonecraft</hi>, with a supplement by W.
                                Clark Durant (1927; rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1969) 45,
                                202.</note>
	<note id="n57">57. G. E. Bentley, Jr., “William Blake and His
                                Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 1995,”
                                    <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 29.4 (1996): 143n51, 144-45. Claire
                                Tomalin, “Publisher in Prison: Joseph Johnson and the Book
                                Trade,” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> 2 Dec. 1994: 15-16, revealed
                                the existence of this letter-book, now in the Carl H. Pforzheimer
                                Collection of Shelley and His Circle, New York Public Library,
                                Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; see Bentley’s checklist
                                for 1994, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 28.4 (1995): 144.</note>
	<note id="n58">
                                58. More than 21,000 letters in the Zentralbibliothek
                                    Zürich (9,000 letters from Lavater and 12,000 to him)
                                    have recently become available on 1,843 microfiche in <hi rend="i">Lavater
Correspondence</hi>, ed. Eggenberger and
                                    Stähli; see &lt;http://www.idc.nl&gt;. According
                                    to Eggenberger’s online note, 
<q> [A]n actual complete
                                        edition of Lavater’s correspondence is not
                                        anticipated in the foreseeable future, if ever. Academic
                                        efforts are currently focused on the edition which is being
                                        supervised by the Johann Caspar Lavater Research Institute
                                        and the NZZ Publishing House in Zurich, “Johann
                                        Caspar Lavater, Selected Works in a Historico-Critical
                                        Edition” (<hi rend="i">“Johann Caspar Lavater,
                                            Ausgewählte Werke in historisch-kritischer
                                            Ausgabe”</hi>). The publishers make use of the
                                        correspondence and refer to it; however, even they do not
                                        know about all of the letters. </q></note></p>
            <p>According to the Hunter-Holloway-Murray prospectus of June 1787,
                            “The Translator and the Artist have already made considerable
                            Progress in the Work,” as confirmed by Hunter’s memoirist:
<q> Having translated sufficient to occupy the Printer and the
                                Engraver for some time, Dr. Hunter determined upon paying a visit to
                                Lavater at Zurich. . . . In August, 1787, he accordingly repaired to
                                Zurich; but it does not appear that Lavater received his visit with
                                that frankness and cordiality with which it was made. . . .
                                [Lavater] considered this English translation as likely to injure
                                the sale of the French edition in which he was concerned, and
                                scarcely knew how to act. ([“Biographical Sketch”]
                                xx-xxi [see note 53]) </q>
The memoirist reiterates that Hunter, who
                            had made the visit solely to “prevent mistakes” and
                            “to render the English translation as complete as
                            possible,” was shocked to find that “the pressure of
                            indigence” had reduced “poor Lavater” to hear
                            “with chagrin of an undertaking which might possibly diminish his
                            profits from the sale of the French edition” (lxxiii-lxxiv). As
                            previously noted, August 1787 was also the month in which
                            Lavater’s distributor Heinrich Steiner announced that <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>
would not, after all, be complete in three
                            volumes; to accommodate the six remaining sections from 
<hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi>, a fourth volume would be necessary. On 8 October
                            1787—that is, shortly after Michaelmas 1787, when
                            Johnson’s memorandum states that Wollstonecraft moved into the
                            home where she prepared her abridged translation—Murray urged
                            Johnson, with whom he had a long history of co-publication and
                            collaboration (Zachs 82-84), to join him in order to head off
                            competition between their contemporaneous but dissimilar projects. After
                            informing Johnson that Mrs. Hunter anticipated her husband’s
                            return (from abroad?) very soon, Murray urged a meeting: 
<q> It is
                                therefore submitted whether in this stage you should take the steps
                                you threaten. If you have patience, a meeting shall take place
                                immediately upon the Doctor’s Arrival. A coalition is what I
                                have cordially wished for, if it can be accomplished upon principles
                                of reciprocity. For it is no matter whose scheme here is the best; a
                                public competition will infallibly hurt both. Obstinacy therefore
                                should be avoided on both sides, &amp; all of us should keep
                                steadily in our Eye, what will tend most to the general interest.
                                (Murray Archive, Box M 10) </q></p>
            <p>The “steps” Johnson threatened might have included a public
                            announcement that it was his project, not Murray’s, that had
                            Lavater’s approval. But Murray’s letter, probably followed
                            by the proposed meeting with Hunter, appears to have nipped
                            Johnson’s plan in the bud, probably by the end of 1787. On 15
                            January 1788, only days before the first fascicle appeared, Johnson
                            entered into an agreement with Murray, Hunter, and Holloway to produce
                            “a Translation and Embellishments of Lavaters Essays of
                            Physiognomy” for “equal Shares and Proportions both for
                            Profit and Loss”—a one-quarter stake for each partner. The
                            roles of Hunter as translator, Holloway as graphics director
                            (compensated separately for the costs of the engravings), and Murray as
                            publisher are spelled out in the Articles of Agreement; Johnson’s
                            quarter share of responsibilities (unspecified) must have included his
                            services as point person (with Fuseli’s help) in correspondence
                            with Lavater and the provision of additional capital. The partners were
                            to meet quarterly to estimate the value of the work and their quarter
                            shares; if one partner should die before completion of the project, the
                            surviving partners were to buy out the deceased partner after settling
                            accounts up until the time of that partner’s death, and the
                            property was to be divided equally among the surviving partners. In case
                            of a dispute with representatives of the deceased partner, the outcome
                            was to be settled by arbitrators chosen by each party, who in turn would
                            name a third arbitrator.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">59</ref>
	<note id="n59">59. Although the agreement itself is not present in the
                                Murray Archive, its date and terms are reiterated in the
                                arbitrators’ ruling of 11 January 1802 that settled John
                                Murray’s estate.</note></p>
            <p>Unfortunately, Lavater did not date his copy of his own proposal to
                            Johnson, which begins: “My esteemed Mr. Johnson, I have the honor
                            to offer the English nation, through you, a work upon which I am willing
                            to expend all my mental powers, and toward which I have already in stock
                            a wealth of materials, before which I am often horrified”
                            (Lavater Family Archive, Ms. 567.130; see notes 48 and 58).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">60</ref> This sounds like yet another
                            version of his text, with additional illustrations. Referring to
                            previous communications through Fuseli, Lavater goes on to ask Johnson
                            “once again” if the large folio format might not be
                            “more excellent” than quarto—a sign, probably, that
                            Johnson has abandoned the octavo idea and is now committed to the quarto
                            edition. According to Knowles, Fuseli engaged in an “animated
                            correspondence” opposing Lavater’s desire for a folio
                            edition and explaining “that the quarto size best pleased the
                            British public.” After Lavater reluctantly agreed, expecting his
                            images to be “rather traced than imitated by the
                            engraver,” he insisted on “mak[ing] his drawings anew to
                            suit the quarto size” (79). His price, according to the undated
                            letter to Johnson, would be three guineas per sheet of text (each making
                            eight pages in quarto format), one and a half guineas for each large
                            outline drawing, one-half guinea for each small outline drawing, one
                            guinea for each “shaded drawing” (not a silhouette but a
                            more fully rendered portrait), and two and a half guineas for each
                            full-page shaded drawing. The grand total—not counting “20
                            or 28 free copies,” would be 1,060 (a mistranscription of 1,050)
                            guineas for 800 pages of text, 400 outlines (200 large, 200 small), and
                            200 shaded 
<pb id="p38-71" n="71"/>
drawings (100 large, 100 small),
                            with all originals to remain in Lavater’s possession. It appears
                            that Lavater never quite understood that Johnson had teamed up with
                            Murray and that a folio edition was out of the question. Even after the
                            first few fascicles (in quarto) had rolled off the press,
                            Lavater’s Alsatian friend Gottfried Heisch, then living in
                            London, wrote on 16 May 1788: 
<q> Between you, Fuessli and Johnson there
                                are the most dreadful misunderstandings. God knows how they
                                arose—I won’t and can’t investigate. You think
                                Johnson will use English money and expend English generosity for
                                your Physiognomy? [I]t doesn’t seem so to me. From the first
                                word, which has been continuously repeated up till now, this is what
                                I heard: Lavater runs up a quantity of expenses, outlays, which we
                                don’t know anything about. We don’t want anything
                                except two sections of outline images and his text. What’s
                                the purpose of all the rest of this, all these drawings, etc.? [W]ho
                                has ordered them? By the way, every day he changes his opinion,
                                starts new projects that we simply can’t accommodate, and if
                                we write to him about it, he doesn’t answer, never stays on
                                the point that we want to hold him to, and always gives answers that
                                we don’t want to know. </q>
Here Lavater notes in the bottom
                            margin, “This, by God, is not true.” Heisch continues: 
<q>
                                I must make two remarks to you from my heart. First: Don’t
                                make any more contracts by yourself . . . . You are not at all able
                                to manage making a contract. You don’t know the world,
                                because you judge and believe that everybody is like you and will do
                                what is promised. What’s the result? You’re left
                                sitting in excrement. . . . Second: Be on your guard, even more than
                                against Satan himself, from any thought that you might possibly
                                publish the book yourself! You have been burned enough to fear the
                                fire! You let something of these thoughts be glimpsed in your last
                                letter to Johnson, and it made me very uneasy on your account.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">61</ref></q>
Lavater continued at least until August
1788 to allude to his
                            initial offer, and as late as 29 November 1788 he wrote to a Mr. Tighe
                            that he still hoped Johnson would produce a “larger work,”
                            for which purpose he was enclosing each month additional images for
                                engraving.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">62</ref> Johnson had already
                            invested in Wollstonecraft’s translation and owned both a large
                            drawing of Lavater in profile and the engraving of it by Blake, first
                            dated 26 December 1787 (possibly ordered with the Hunter translation in
                            mind, but before Johnson quite realized that Holloway alone was in
                            charge of all engravings and engravers). Whatever the timing may have
                            been, after Johnson was actively allied with the other
                            “Proprietors of the English Lavater” as a co-publisher of
                            Hunter’s translation of <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>, the only new
                            material that he would have accepted from Lavater for possible inclusion
                            in the English edition would have been whatever text and outlines may
                            have already been under contract before he gave up his plan for an
                            edition under his own imprint. <note id="n60">60. This document must
                                have been sent before 27 July 1787, when Lavater’s friend
                                Luder Hoffham, a merchant in London, informed Lavater about
                                Hunter’s translation and his desire to visit Zurich, with the
                                warning that “this will certainly do harm to Johnson”
                                when he publishes the physiognomical work (Lavater Family Archive,
                                Ms. 513.287).</note>
	<note id="n61">61. Quoted by Finsler. The full nine-page text is of
                                great interest, and I hope, in collaboration with Sibylle Erle,
                                to publish a transcription, translation, and annotation as a
                                separate piece or as an appendix to a larger study (see note 4),
                                The “outline images” may have led to
                                Lavater’s 1797 annotations (in French) of faces in
                                outline, published as <hi rend="i">Physiognomical Sketches</hi>,
                                engr. J. Luffman (London: R. H. Westley, J. Luffman, Murray
                                &amp; Highley, n.d. [50 plates, each dated 1802]).</note>
	<note id="n62">62. Letter in French, in the handwriting of one of
                                Lavater’s secretaries, Misc. Swiss, Dept. of Literary and
                                Historical Manuscripts, Pierpont Morgan Library. An “S.
                                Tighe” ordered a book from Cadell on 4 July 1786
                                (Beinecke).</note></p>
            <p>Despite all the misunderstandings, Fuseli continued to labor on
                            Lavater’s (and his own) behalf by writing a scathing two-part
                            review of Holcroft’s translation for Joseph Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Analytical
Review</hi> (5 [Dec. 1789]: 454-62; 6 [Apr.
                            1790]: 426-31). Dismissing Holcroft’s reply (6 [Jan. 1790]:
                            110-12), Fuseli mercilessly exposed Holcroft’s copy-text as
                            Armbruster’s abridged redaction, ridiculed his laments about the
                            difficulties of the German language and Lavater’s new coinages,
                            and displayed Holcroft’s most egregious blunders side by side
                            with “our own” expert translations. Readers of this
                            anonymous review of course had no way of knowing that it was the work of
                            a native Swiss, a lifelong friend of the author, and a sponsor of a
                            rival edition. Nor could they have known that the publisher of this
                            hostile critique also had a financial stake in the project.</p>
            <p>As it happened, Murray died on 6 November 1793, with three fascicles
                            (39-41) still to be published and accounts among partners still up in
                            the air, except for the 1788-93 quarterly share-value estimates based on
                            each period’s cash expenditures and sales. Of the 1000 copies
                            printed (Zachs 359), the published list of subscribers (<hi rend="i">Essays</hi>
I, front matter) accounts for 809 copies under 795
                                names,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">63</ref> but not all subscribers
                            completed their orders. And Holloway’s out-of-pocket engraving
                            expenses had to be subtracted before accrued profits and losses could be
                            calculated. On 12 June 1795 Samuel Highley, the elder Murray’s
                            shopman and the younger Murray’s partner, requested
                            Holloway’s account for engravings for fascicles 25-37, as well as
                            a complete accounting for all numbers to date, along with the remaining
                            prints needed to make up 1000 copies of fascicles 35-37 (Murray Archive,
                            Box M 10), but Holloway did not present his comprehensive
                            account—for the staggering sum of £2331-12-0—until
                            sometime in 1800. By way of justification, Holloway noted that in
                            addition to the time and expense necessary to do such things as oversee
                            the work of in-house engravers (Holloway’s students and
                            assistants) and outside professionals, buy supplies, board visiting
                            artists, make shipments, and arrange for printing and hot-pressing, he
                            had more hands-on work than expected: 
<q> In spite of all his care
                                &amp; even expostulations with most of the Artists—the work
                                they brought home was distressingly inaccurate—many plates
                                were destroyd totally—and those which were the best executed
                                were frequently so erroneous both in outline &amp; expression that
                                many parts were oblig’d to be hammerd 
								<pb id="p38-72" n="72"/>
								<figure n="Lavater.Expenses.38.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="498">
									<figTranscr>Expences Attending the Engravings of Lavater as well<lb/>
									as Sundry other Engravings herein specified A during the<lb/>
									years 1787 to 1799—Inclusive<lb/>
									Paid to Artists out of Doors<lb/>
									Mistr Auderick 97.9.-<lb/>
									Brumby 111.8[.-]<lb/>
									Blake 39.19.6<lb/>
									Barlow 12.1.6<lb/>
									Beuge 10.10.-<lb/>
									Corner 71.18.6<lb/>
									Corbould 5.15.6<lb/>
									Cauldwell 21.-[.-]<lb/>
									Grignion 77.14.-<lb/>
									Gillray 6.6.-<lb/>
									Hall 183.15.-<lb/>
									How 55.9.6<lb/>
									Heath 26.5.-<lb/>
									Hogg 25.4[.-]<lb/>
									Neagle 80.11.6<lb/>
									Noble 14.13.6<lb/>
									Rhodes 99.2.-<lb/>
									Sharp 79.16[.-]<lb/>
									Smith 96.12[.-]<lb/>
									Ham 13.19.8<lb/>
									Sundries Kells &amp;c 51.7.8<lb/>
									Tagg 16.16.-<lb/>
									Thornthwaite 108.14.8<lb/>
									Taylor 65.2.-<lb/>
									Turner &amp; Gillray 244.17.6<lb/>
									Vivaro 54.1.6<lb/>
									1659.12.6<lb/>
									Paid to Artists in Doors<lb/>
									Mistr Toohey 280.3.6<lb/>
									Malpas 116.9.6<lb/>
									Meagle 39.7.6<lb/>
									Warren 98.15.6<lb/>
									Thompson &amp; Bn 309.15.6<lb/>
									Board 106<lb/>
									899.4.6<lb/>
									9558..17</figTranscr>
									<head>14. “Expences [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] Attending the
                                        Engravings of Lavater . . . Paid to Artists out of
                                        Doors” (c. 1800), prepared by Holloway for settlement
                                        of Murray’s estate.</head>
									<figDesc>Published by permission of John Murray (Publishers), 50
                                        Albermarle Street, London WIX 4BD.</figDesc>
								</figure>
								<pb id="p38-73" n="73"/>
out &amp; reproduced—a piece of
                                work this the most painful &amp; the most mortifying imaginable to
                                    TH.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">64</ref>
	<note id="n63">63. By my tally; Zachs (359) counts 758 copies under 748
                                    names.</note>
	<note id="n64">
                                   64. From an undated four-page document,
                                        “Observations submitted to the Consideration of Doct.
                                        Hunter[,] Mr. Johnson—two of the proprietors of
                                        Lavater—and the Execs of the late Mr Murray.”
                                        Holloway also notes that 
<q><hi rend="i">Copying</hi> is the most
arduous as well as
                                            the most tedious of Engraving—but <hi rend="i">Copying</hi> from
indifferent
                                            Engravings—incorrect in outline as well as in
                                            execution[—]requires double the time to execute .
                                            . . Also <hi rend="i">Considerable</hi> time was taken
                                            up in consulting the text &amp; comparing the French
                                            &amp; German Editions to see which Engravings were the
                                            most accurate &amp; in making the necessary
                                            alterations. (Murray Archive, Box M 10) </q>
It has not
                                        been known, until now, that Holloway worked from 
<hi rend="i">Fragmente</hi> as well as <hi rend="i">Essai.</hi> For a sampling of Holloway’s
                                        drawings for the <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>, see the
                                        Wellcome Library’s online photo archive at
                                        &lt;http://medphoto.wellcome.ac.uk&gt;.
                                </note></q>
Johnson reiterated in a letter to Highley of 19 December 1800 that
                            Holloway “could not get a facsimile from any one of them, he told
                            us he was obliged to work himself on every plate to make it what it
                            should be . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">65</ref>
	<note id="n65">65. Letter-book; quoted in G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s
                                checklist, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 29.4 (1996): 145. (Johnson
                                spelled Highley’s name without an <hi rend="i">e.</hi>)</note></p>
            <p>Murray’s executors objected to Holloway’s bill, especially
                            to the interest added to outright expenses from the time of
                            Murray’s death, and the case went to arbitration on 24 April
                            1800. On 12 August 1800, the arbitrators agreed that Murray’s
                            estate was entitled to £150 for his “fourth share” of
                            the copper plates remaining “and all subsequent Interest.”
                            A comprehensive decision, which the arbitrator chosen by the executors
                            refused to sign, was reached on 11 January 1802. The award was for
                            £3571-8-5 to the surviving partners, with £943-8-5 to Hunter,
                            £958-15-9 to Holloway, and the remaining £1669-4-8 to Johnson,
                            plus “the further and additional” sum of £460 to
                            Johnson for principal and interest on cash “advanced to John
                            Murray in his lifetime” for production expenses. As none of these
                            figures matches those in Holloway’s request, and the three
                            surviving partners were entitled to equal one-third shares, I cannot
                            explain why Hunter and Holloway received different amounts. But the
                            payment to Johnson, not counting the reimbursement of his cash advances,
                            indicates that he was the main financial backer.</p>
            <p>Here, in this truncated account, we must leave matters. But one last
                            factual tidbit offers insight into Blake’s relative professional
                            standing in 1788-89. For all four of his engravings for <hi rend="i">Essays in
Physiognomy</hi>, Blake received £39-19-6 from
                            Holloway (illus. 14).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">66</ref> It seems
                            unlikely that Blake could have commanded a higher per-vignette price
                            than Gillray, who was paid 6 guineas (6 pounds and 6 shillings) for his
                            fine vignette after Fuseli (II: 291; reproduced Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Fuseli:
Catalogue Raisonné</hi> 108). At this rate, Blake
                            would have received 18 guineas, or £18-18-0 for his three
                            vignettes, leaving the odd figure of £21-1-6. Perhaps for the full
                            plate of Democritus, highly finished, Blake was able to charge as much
                            as 20 guineas, or £21. But I still have no idea how he earned that
                            last one-and-six! <note id="n66">66. Thomas Holloway, “Expences
                                Attending the Engravings of Lavater as well as Sundry other
                                Engravings herein specified <hi rend="b"><hi rend="u">A</hi></hi>
                                during the years 1787 to 1799—Inclusive”; half-sheet
                                as page 1 of “Case of Mr T. Holloway” (written
                                sideways at bottom of folded large sheet; four pages in all).
                                Holloway’s section A refers to a deduction for (nonspecified)
                                engravings for other purposes during the period. There is also a
                                section B, referring to Holloway’s payments for
                                “Numbers” and subscription deposits. Many other
                                calculations and occasional errors in carryover to different pages
                                make the reckoning extremely hard to follow (Murray Archive, Box M
                                10).</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Selected Sources</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Primary texts</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>[Chodowiecki, Daniel Nikolaus]. <hi rend="i">Daniel Chodowiecki.
                                    Briefwechsel zwischen ihm und seinen Zeitgenossen</hi>
                                [Correspondence between Him and His Contemporaries]. Ed. Charlotte
                                Steinbrucker. Volume 1, 1726-86 [no vol. 2]. Berlin: Carol Duncker,
                                1919.</p>
              <p>[Fuseli, J. H.] <hi rend="i">Heinrich Füsslis Briefe</hi>
                                [Letters]. Ed. Walter Muscg. Basel: Benno Schwabe &amp; Co.,
                                1942.</p>
              <p>Gessner, Georg. <hi rend="i">Johann Kaspar Lavaters
                                    Lebensbeschriebung</hi> [Biography]. 3 vols. Winterthur:
                                Steiner, 1802-03.</p>
              <p>Hunter, Henry. <hi rend="i">Sermons, and other Miscellaneous Pieces .
                                    . . / To which are prefixed, A Biographical Sketch of his Life,
                                    and / A Critical Account of his Writings.</hi> London: J. Murray
                                et al., 1804.</p>
              <p>Knowles, John. <hi rend="i">The Life and Writings of Henry Fuseli,
                                    Esq. M.A., R.A.</hi> 3 vols. London: Henry Colburn and Richard
                                Bentley, 1831.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Lavater Correspondence</hi> [microfiche]. Ed. Christoph
                                Eggenberger and Marlis Stähli. Leiden: IDC Publishers,
                                2002.</p>
              <p>Lavater, Jean Gaspard. <hi rend="i">Essai sur la Physiognomonie:
                                    Destiné à faire connoître l’homme
                                    &amp; à le faire aimer</hi> [Intended to Promote the
                                Knowledge and the Love of Mankind]. [Trans. Henri Renfner, Marie
                                Elisabeth Boué de La Fite, Jean Daniel de La Fite, and
                                {Antoine Bernard?} Caillard.] 4 vols. La Haye [The Hague]: I. Van
                                Cleef [and Winterthur: Heinrich Steiner &amp; Co.],
                                [1781]-83-86[87]-1803.</p>
              <p>Lavater, Johann Caspar. <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy:
                                    Calculated to Extend the Knowledge and Love of Mankind . . .
                                    Translated from the last Paris edition.</hi> Trans. [from 
<hi rend="i">Essai</hi>, via Hunter’s trans.] C. Moore. 3
                                vols. London: W[illiam] Locke, 1793-94-94. Rpt. London, H[enry]
                                D[elahoy] Symonds, 1797. From serial publication in <hi rend="i">The
                                    Conjuror’s Magazine</hi> (Aug. 1791-June 1793), continued
                                as <hi rend="i">The Astrologer’s Magazine</hi> (July
                                1793-Jan. 1794).</p>
              <p>Lavater, Johann Caspar. <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy: Designed
                                    to Promote the Knowledge and the Love of Mankind.</hi> Trans.
                                [from <hi rend="i">Essai</hi>] Henry Hunter. 3 vols. in 5. London:
                                John Murray, 1789-92-98. First published in fascicles, Jan.
                                1788-March 1799.</p>
              <p>Lavater, Johann Caspar. <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy: For the
                                    Promotion of the Knowledge and the Love of Mankind.</hi> Trans.
                                [from Armbruster’s abridgment] Thomas Holcroft. 3 vols.
                                London: G[eorge], G[eorge], J[ohn] and J[ames] Robinson, 1789. 2nd
                                ed. [with “One Hundred Physiognomical Rules” and
                                “Memoirs of the Life of the Author”]. 4 vols. London:
                                H. D. Symonds [and others], 1804.</p>
              <p>[Lavater, Johann Caspar]. <hi rend="i">J. C. Lavaters Physiognomische
                                    Fragmente zur Beförderung von Menschenkenntniss und
                                    Menschenliebe</hi> [J. C. Lavater’s Physiognomical
                                Fragments for Promotion of the Knowledge and Love of Humankind].
                                Verkürzt herausgegeben [abridged edition]. Ed. Johann Michael
                                Armbruster. 3 vols. Winterthur: Heinrich Steiner, 1783-84-87; vol.
                                4, 1830.</p>
              <p>Lavater, Johann Caspar. <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente: Zur
                                    Beförderung der Menschenkenntnis und Menschenliebe.</hi>
                                4 vols. Leipzig: <pb id="p38-74" n="74"/>
Weidmanns Erben und Reich;
                                Winterthur: Heinrich Steiner und Compagnie, 1775-78. Facsimile of
                                the same title, Nachwort von Walter Brednow, Zurich: Orell
                                Füssli, 1968-69.</p>
              <p>Lavater, Johann Caspar. <hi rend="i">Physiognomy: Or the
                                    Corresponding Analogy between the Conformation of the Features
                                    and the Ruling Passions of the Mind.</hi> Trans. Samuel Shaw.
                                London: H. D. Symonds, [1792].</p>
              <p>Lavater, J. C. <hi rend="i">Von der Physiognomik</hi> [On
                                Physiognomics]. Leipzig: Weidmanns Erben und Reich, 1772. Modern
                                text of Part I: 9-62 of <hi rend="i">Von der Physiognomik</hi>,
                                [replacing Part II (Lavater’s lists of topics for future
                                development) with] <hi rend="i">Hundert physiognomische Regeln.</hi>
                                Ed. Karl Riha and Carsten Zelle. Frankfurt am Main and Leipzig:
                                Insel Verlag, 1991.</p>
              <p>[Lavater, Johann Caspar]. <hi rend="i">The Whole Works of Lavater on
                                    Physiognomy.</hi> Trans. George Grenville [rpt. of Moore].
                                London: Butters, 1797.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Memoir of the Late Mr. Thomas Holloway; by one of his
                                    Executors.</hi> London: Printed for the Author, sold by Samuel
                                Bagster, 1827.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Other key citations</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Allentuck, Marcia. “Fuseli and Lavater: Physiognomical Theory
                                and the Enlightenment.” <hi rend="i">Studies on Voltaire and
                                    the Eighteenth Century</hi> 55 (1967): 89-112.</p>
              <p>Bauer, Jens-Heiner. <hi rend="i">Daniel Nikolaus Chodowiecki: Das
                                    druckgraphische Werke.</hi> Hannover: Verlag Galerie J. H.
                                Bauer, 1982. [Supplement to Engelmann.]</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon
                                P, 1977.</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement.</hi> Oxford:
                                Clarendon P, 1995.</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “A ‘New’ Blake Engraving in
                                Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi> 6 (1972): 48-49.</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Physiognomy of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays:</hi> False
Imprints ‘1792’ and
                                ‘1798.’” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                    Quarterly</hi> 29.1 (1995): 16-23.</p>
              <p>Engelmann, Wilhelm. <hi rend="i">Daniel Chodowiecki’s</hi>
                                    [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] <hi rend="i">Sämmtliche
                                    Kupferstiche</hi> [Complete Engravings]. Leipzig: Wilhelm
                                Engelmann, 1857; rev. Robert Hirsch, Leipzig: Wilhelm Engelmann,
                                1906.</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert N. “The Figure in the Carpet: Blake’s
                                Engravings in Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of
                                    Morality.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                    Quarterly</hi> 12.1 (1978): 10-14.</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
                                    Illustrations: A Catalogue and Study of the Plates Engraved by
                                    Blake after Designs by Other Artists.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P,
                                1991.</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker.</hi>
                                Princeton: Princeton UP, 1980.</p>
              <p>Finsler, Georg. “Lavater in Amt und Privatleben [Lavater in
                                Professional and Private Life].” <hi rend="i">Johann Caspar
                                    Lavater 1741-1801: Denkschrift zur hundertsten Wiederkehr seines
                                    Todestages</hi> [Memorial Volume for the Centennial of His
                                Death]. Zurich: Stiftung von Schnyder von Wartensee, 1902, 1-56.</p>
              <p>Frey, Siegfried. “Lavater, Lichtenberg, and the Suggestive
                                Power of the Human Face.” Shookman 64-103.</p>
              <p>Goldfriedrich, Johann. <hi rend="i">Beginn der Klassischen
                                    Litteraturperiode bis zum Beginn der Fremdherrschaft
                                    1740-1804</hi> [From the Beginning of the Classical Period to
                                the Beginning of the Period of Foreign Domination, 1740-1804]. Vol.
                                3 of <hi rend="i">Geschichte des Deutschen Buchhandels</hi> [History
                                of the German Book Trade]. Leipzig: Verlag des Börsenvereins
                                der Deutschen Buchhandler, 1909.</p>
              <p>Goritschnig, Ingrid. “Lavaters auserwählter
                                Künstlerkreis [Lavater’s Chosen Circle of
                                Artists].” <hi rend="i">Das Kunstkabinett des Johann Caspar
                                    Lavater.</hi> Ed. Gerda Mraz and Uwe Schögl. Vienna:
                                Austria National Library, 1999. 96-109.</p>
              <p>Graham, John. “Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy:</hi>
                                A Checklist.” <hi rend="i">Papers of the Bibliographical
                                    Society of America</hi> 55 (1961): 297-308. Republished in John
                                Graham, <hi rend="i">Lavater’s Essays on Physiognomy: A Study
                                    in the History of Ideas.</hi> Berne, Frankfurt am Main, Las
                                Vegas: Peter Lang, 1979.</p>
              <p>Jaton, Anne-Marie. <hi rend="i">Jean Gaspard Lavater.</hi> Lucerne
                                and Lausanne: Editions René Coeckelberghs, 1994.</p>
              <p>Kruse, Joachim. <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Lips 1758-1817: Ein
                                    Züricher zwischen Lavater und Goethe.</hi> Coberg:
                                Kunstsammlungen der Veste Coburg, 1989.</p>
              <p>Mason, Eudo C. <hi rend="i">The Mind of Henry Fuseli.</hi> London:
                                Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1951.</p>
              <p>Müller, Rebecca. “<hi rend="i">Die Natur ist meine
                                    einzige Lehrerin, meine Wohltäterin</hi>”: <hi rend="i">Zeichnungen von
Daniel Nikolaus Chodowiecki (1726-1801)
                                    im Berliner Kupferstichkabinett.</hi> Berlin: Gebr. Mann,
                                2000.</p>
              <p>Ohage, August. “Zimmermanns Anteil [Share] an Lavaters <hi rend="i">Physiognomischen
Fragmenten.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Johann Georg Zimmermann: königlich grossbritannischer
                                    Leibarzt (1728-1795).</hi> Ed. Hans-Peter Schramm. Weisbaden:
                                Harrassowitz Verlag, 1998. 109-22.</p>
              <p>Schroyer, Richard J., ed. <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man (1788) by
                                    Johann Caspar Lavater. A Facsimile Reproduction of William
                                    Blake’s Copy of the First English Edition.</hi> Delmar,
                                NY: Scholar’s Facsimiles, 1980.</p>
              <p>Shookman, Ellis, ed. <hi rend="i">The Faces of Physiognomy:
                                    Interdisciplinary Approaches to Johann Caspar Lavater.</hi>
                                Columbia, SC: Camden House, 1993.</p>
              <p>Shortland, Michael. “The Power of a Thousand Eyes: Johann
                                Caspar Lavater’s Science of Physiognomical
                                Perception.” <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 28 (1986):
                                379-408.</p>
              <p>Smiles, Samuel. <hi rend="i">Memoir and Correspondence of the late
                                    John Murray with an account of the origin and progress of the
                                    house, 1768-1843.</hi> London: John Murray, 1891.</p>
              <p>Stemmler, Joan K. “The Physiognomical Portraits of Johann
                                Caspar Lavater.” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 65.1 (March
                                1993): 151-68.</p>
              <p>Thanner, Brigitte. “Johann Rudolf Schellenberg und die
                                schweizerische Buchillustration im Zeitalter der Aufklärung
                                [Swiss Book Illustration in the Period of the
                                Enlightenment].” Brigitte Thanner, Hans-Konrad Schmutz, and
                                Armin Geus. <hi rend="i">Johann Rudolf Schellenberg: Der
                                    Künstler und die naturwissenschaftliche Illustration im
                                    18. Jahrhundert</hi> [The Artist and Natural Science
                                Illustration in the Eighteenth Century]. Winterthur: Stadtbibliothek
                                Winterthur, 1987. 7-181.</p>
              <p>Thanner, Brigitte. <hi rend="i">Schweizerische Buchillustration im
                                    Zeitalter der Aufklärung am Beispiel</hi> [Example] <hi rend="i">von
Johann Rudolf Schellenberg: Inaugural-Dissertation
                                    . . . Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität zu
                                    München.</hi> 2 vols. Winterthur: Stadtbibliothek
                                Winterthur, 1987.</p>
              <p>Tytler, Graeme. <hi rend="i">Physiognomy in the European Novel: Faces
                                    and Fortunes.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1982.</p>
              <p>Vaughan, William. “Lips.” <hi rend="i">Print
                                    Quarterly</hi> 9.1 (1992): 92-94.</p>
              <p>Vollert, Ernst. <hi rend="i">Die Weidmannsche Buchhandlung in Berlin
                                    1680 bis 1930.</hi> Berlin: Weidmannsche Buchhandlung, 1930.</p>
              <p>Weigelt, Horst and Niklaus Landolt, eds. <hi rend="i">Bibliographie
                                    der Werke Lavaters.</hi> Ergänzungsband: Lavater, Johann
                                Caspar. <hi rend="i">Ausgewählte Werke in
                                    historisch-kritischer Ausgabe.</hi> Zurich: NZZ Verlag,
                                2001.</p>
              <p>Weinglass, David H., ed. <hi rend="i">The Collected English Letters
                                    of Henry Fuseli.</hi> Millwood, NY: Kraus International,
                                1982.</p>
              <p>Weinglass, D. H. <hi rend="i">Prints and Engraved Illustrations By
                                    and After Henry Fuseli: A Catalogue Raisonné.</hi>
                                Aldershot, England and Brookfield, VT: Scolar P, 1994.</p>
              <p>Zachs, William. <hi rend="i">The First John Murray and the Late
                                    Eighteenth-Century London Book Trade.</hi> Oxford: Oxford UP for
                                the British Academy, 1998.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
