<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.2.mcclenahan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert N. Essick, ed., William Blake, Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title>
        <author n="McClenahan">Catherine L. McClenahan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Kathleen Lundeen</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <body>
	<pb id="p38-77" n="77"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake. <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>
                            Ed. Robert N. Essick. San Marino, CA: Huntington Library and Art
                            Gallery, 2002. [11] + 78 pp. 11 color and 10 monochrome illus.
                            $21.95/£18.99 cloth.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Catherine L.
                        <name>McClenahan</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>With this affordable edition of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion</hi>, Robert Essick and the Huntington Library have made
                        Blake’s illuminated text and related visual material available in
                        hard copy to a wide audience of Blake students, scholars and fans, and given
                        easy access to one more copy to compare with those available on the
                        electronic Blake Archive (copies a, A, C, J, F, G, and P). Based on the
                        Huntington’s copy (designated as copy E), this edition provides
                        full-size color reproductions of all 11 plates, a printed version of this
                        copy, bibliographic and textual notes, about 50 pages of detailed commentary
                        that includes monochrome reproductions of pencil drawings from
                        Blake’s Notebook, and a bibliography of critical studies.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Visions</hi> could scarcely ask for a more experienced and
                        informed editor. As <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> readers know, Essick is one of
                        the world’s experts on Blake’s printing methods and visual
                        designs and a noted scholar of Blake’s writing. One of the editors of
                        the Blake Archive, he has also edited or co-edited other illuminated books
                        for the Blake Trust/Tate/Princeton series (<hi rend="i">The Early
                            Illuminated Books</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>), catalogues of
                        Blake’s separate prints and commercial illustrations, catalogues of
                        the Blake holdings in the Huntington collection, and collections of essays
                        on the relation of Blake’s images and texts. Despite the relatively
                        affordable price, there is nothing cut-rate about the look or feel of this
                        volume: both are equally attractive, right down to the little motifs from
                        the visual designs that are placed on the verso sides of pages that begin or
                        end sections, the crisp, readable typeface of the printed sections, and the
                        pleasurable feel of good paper stock.</p>
          <pb id="p38-78" n="78"/>
          <p>Copy E compares interestingly with the copies available in the online Blake
                        Archive, which vary significantly in color and color intensity from each
                        other, even the four (a, A, C and J) published in the same year, 1793. The
                        colors of this copy seem to include more blue and purple shades and
                        sometimes more color shadings, as on plate 4, the first page of the poem
                        proper. This edition makes it possible to see variations in Blake’s
                        script and ambiguities of punctuation marks, while the textual notes point
                        out changes Blake made on the copperplate that would be hard to see in a
                        reproduction. The printing is as clear as the low-contrast colors of ochre
                        ink on buff pages can be, but since some of the lighter lines are hard to
                        read, the inclusion of the printed text is helpful for less
                        experienced—or just older—eyes.</p>
          <p>Essick’s inclusion of the related Notebook drawings in itself makes
                        this edition worthwhile, not just for Blake students or scholars but to
                        anyone interested in tracing the evolution of a visual artist’s
                        ideas. Modern technology has made it possible to digitize photographs from
                        the British Library and then manipulate these to retrieve pencil drawings
                        that were written or drawn over in ink years later and to erase words that
                        covered parts of these pencil drawings, as we can see in Erdman and
                        Moore’s facsimile of Blake’s Notebook. But this edition saves
                        readers an extra research step by including illustrations such as figure 2,
                        which not only shows a drawing of a ring of dancers related to those on
                        plate 2 of <hi rend="i">VDA</hi>, but also the caption underneath, a
                        quotation from Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, that was written
                        over in the Notebook but which sets up a thematic link between the two
                        works.</p>
          <p>The commentary begins with a short, lucid discussion of Blake’s
                        background as a printmaker: how he invented his unique methods of
                        illuminated printing, how these contrasted with conventional methods, and
                        the advantages and disadvantages of Blake’s methods for an
                        independent artisan. Essick also surveys the works of illuminated printing
                        published before <hi rend="i">VDA</hi>, setting up thematic issues and links
                        between this work and its predecessors. This leads to an overview of
                        Blake’s common rhetorical strategies and thus to Essick’s own
                        rhetorical position. Noting the focus in much recent criticism of 
<hi rend="i">VDA</hi> on “precursor texts,” Essick points to
                        the consequent danger of being “led away from the texture of
                        Blake’s poetry, 
                        <hi rend="i">as</hi> poetry ....” In contrast, Essick proposes
                        “a rather old-fashioned solution”: to work through this text
                        (i.e., the Huntington’s) “from start to finish, line by line
                        when necessary” (26). His commentary will take “brief
                        excursions” into historical issues or earlier texts that Blake echoes
                        “when they assist understanding” (26-27). Aside from a
                        somewhat curmudgeonly swipe at “modern interpreters” who
                        overlook Oothoon’s speech in 5:23-6:20, Essick’s emphasis is
                        fair, relevant, and especially helpful to newer readers of Blake’s
                        unique composite art or simply of poetry. Stuart Curran complained 30 years
                        ago about the tendency of some Blake criticism to “play for the big
                        stakes and not fret about the pennies,” imposing structures
                        “on a generally resistant poem” (Curran 330), and while the
                        critical paths we’ve followed in the meantime have been valuable, the
                        complaint still has relevance. Essick’s approach in this book
                        enhances both aesthetic experience and intellectual analysis.</p>
          <p>Readers who want more detailed historical, political and feminist approaches
                        to <hi rend="i">VDA</hi> will find the bibliography a good place to start.
                        Meanwhile, Essick’s close attention to details can be as fruitful for
                        experienced Blake readers as it is excellent training for newer ones. If one
                        follows the commentary, flipping back and forth among its readings, the
                        pencil drawings from the Notebook, and one or more plates of Blake’s
                        text, even a reader familiar with this work is likely to notice something
                        new or reconsider an earlier idea. This process can spur new observations
                        even when Essick isn’t pointing to them. For instance, when I turned
                        back from the commentary to look at plate 7 again (instead of following the
                        syntax of the sentence that runs from plates 6-7 in a printed text), the
                        first four words of plate 7 and their punning relevance to the design just
                        above really stood out. “Wave shadows of discontent” lies just
                        beneath the picture of Oothoon, curving in a wave form above a huddled
                        figure refusing to look up. Read aloud, the words sound like another voice
                        encouraging her complaints against Bromion, Theotormon and the various
                        oppressive systems they embody, a positive note in an otherwise gloomy
                        situation. Other design details reinforce the slight note of hope. The
                        huddled figure who chooses to be deaf and blind to her efforts (so probably
                        Theotormon) is a closed, rigid rectangle except for the curve of the bowed
                        head. <pb id="p38-79" n="79"/>
Although Oothoon arcs over him, apparently
                        imprisoned in one of his “black jealous” waves (5:4), the
                        shape of her body is a half circle that never closes, and the wave itself
                        tapers to the beginning of a dynamic S-curve at its tip. So Oothoon’s
                        persistence in her “discontent” and continued struggles to
                        articulate it to herself and others lead her to new insights. As Essick
                        notes earlier, Oothoon is changing. Her language reaches “a new level
                        of critical consciousness” and is “moving toward . . . a
                        philosophy of mind” in the “They told me . . .” speech
                        that begins at 5:30 (48, 49); Oothoon learns from her own efforts, as the
                        other characters apparently do not.</p>
          <p>Readers may also find themselves taking the lines of Essick’s argument
                        beyond the commentary. He calls our attention to the way facing pages
                        (Blake’s arrangement) interact visually, for example, and deftly sets
                        up the suggestions of “lesbian sexuality” and other
                        “transgressive” elements in the text and design of plate 3,
                        “The Argument.” Noting a page later that the two prostrate
                        figures at the bottom of plate 4 are hard to identify with certainty, Essick
                        observes the way these two figures echo the woman in <hi rend="i">The
                            Nightmare</hi> and Bottom in <hi rend="i">The Awakening of Titania</hi>,
                        two famous paintings by Fuseli. If Essick’s observations on plate 3
                        are still in mind, however, a reader might also see the paired figures on
                        both plates as female. Each design contains one small and one large human
                        figure (arranged large, small, small, large). The sex of the larger figure
                        in plate 4 is not definite in this copy, and its position is a near mirror
                        image of the woman on plate 6 whose flesh is being rent by an eagle
                        (Oothoon, presumably).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">1</ref> Interestingly,
                        the smaller female figure on plate 4 is attached to a vine-like curve that
                        echoes the curve of the vine on plate 3 from which rise
                        “Leutha’s flower” and the nymph that Oothoon
                        alternately sees (4:6). <note id="n69">1. There is ambiguity about the sex
                            of both the larger figure on plate 4 and the figure on plate 6. The size
                            of the body in the former plate and perhaps the muscle definition
                            suggest masculinity, but the pectoral muscles are not unlike breasts.
                            The figure on plate 6 obviously connects with Oothoon’s call for
                            Theotormon’s eagles to rend her flesh in the text (5:13), but the
                            allusion to Prometheus seems inescapable. This blurring of gender
                            markers seems characteristic of Blake to me (McClenahan 301-04, 312-14
                            and <hi rend="i">passim</hi>).</note></p>
          <p>So while any user of this edition might multiply disagreements with
                        Essick’s readings in the commentary, the point is that he is not
                        performing the kind of close reading that simply substitutes a
                        critic’s text for the author’s or for a
                        reader/viewer’s. This edition assembles so much for its audience to
                        use, and the commentary leads them to hold so many things in consciousness
                        at once, that multiple interpretations and ambiguities should inevitably
                        arise, whether the commentary points them out or not. Whatever
                        readers’ critical assumptions are, Essick’s
                        “old-fashioned” method can be productive and even
                        exhilarating, since it really aims to stimulate and support their
                        independent observations and interpretations. Individuals can use all the
                        parts of this edition to help them experience this beautiful and provocative
                        illuminated book in new ways that would be difficult or impossible without
                        it. The Blake Archive is an invaluable resource for us now. At the same
                        time, interacting with a work that can be held in the hands differs from
                        interactions with a work online, whether sensually, aesthetically or
                        intellectually. So given the relatively affordable price for one of
                        Blake’s works in illuminated printing, teachers may want to give
                        their students this experience in a Blake course or one on British
                        literature, Romanticism or poetry. If an instructor had to select just one
                        work of illuminated printing to order, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
                            of Albion</hi> could provide a valuable introduction to Blake’s
                        work, especially in the 1790s, but also to issues and problems of the
                        revolutionary and counter-revolutionary period in England and Europe, or to
                        trends and experiments in literature and the visual arts in the late
                        eighteenth century. Others will want this edition for personal pleasure and
                        use. Either way, it deserves a wide audience.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Curran, Stuart. “The Structures of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Sublime
                                Allegory.</hi> Ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.
                            Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1973. 329-46.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. and Donald Moore, eds. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of
                                William Blake: A Photographic and Typographic Facsimile.</hi>
                            Barrytown, NY: Station Hill Press, 1977.</p>
            <p>McClenahan, Catherine L. “Albion and the Sexual Machine.”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake, Politics, and History.</hi> Ed. Jackie DiSalvo,
                            G. A. Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson. New York and London: Garland
                            Press, 1998. 301-24.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
