<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.2.michael</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Kevin Hutchings, Imagining Nature: Blake’s Environmental Poetics</title>
        <author n="Michael">Jennifer Davis Michael</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Kathleen Lundeen</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <body>
      <pb id="p38-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Kevin Hutchings. <hi rend="i">Imagining Nature: Blake’s
                                Environmental Poetics.</hi> Montreal and Kingston:
                            McGill-Queen’s University Press, 2002. xiv + 256 pp.
                            $75.00/£57.00 cloth; $22.95/£17.50 paper (2003).</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Jennifer Davis
                        <name>Michael</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The past ten years have witnessed a wave of “green” criticism
                        among Romanticists, reacting against both the Yale critics such as Harold
                        Bloom and Geoffrey Hartman, with their emphasis on the imaginative sublime,
                        and the new historicists and Marxists, some of whom, like Alan Liu, deny the
                        existence of “nature” apart from human property and power
                        relations (Liu 104). A primary function of ecocritical readings is to show
                        that the Romantic poets, rather than escaping from history into an
                        imaginatively constructed “nature,” are demonstrating
                        “how human culture can only function through links and reciprocal
                        relations with nature”: i.e., a nature that has an existence apart
                        from that culture (Bate 103-04).</p>
          <p>Blake’s denunciations of “vegetated” nature and his
                        wellknown proverb that “Where man is not nature is barren”
                        have made him an inconvenience, if not a stumbling block, for the
                        ecocritical movement. While James McKusick makes a convincing case for
                        Golgonooza as an “Ecotopia” of “humanscale
                        technology” and offers an interesting reading of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plates
18 and 19 as a warning against pollution
                        (McKusick 102-05), he generally overlooks Blake’s negative depictions
                        of nature in order to claim Blake for the ecological cause. The other
                        leaders of eco-Romanticism, Jonathan Bate and Karl Kroeber, largely avoid
                            Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n67">1. Mark Lussier’s important article,
                            “Blake’s Deep Ecology,” is a significant exception
                            to this avoidance.</note></p>
          <p>Kevin Hutchings’ impressive book challenges and dissects the
                        longstanding orthodoxy of Blake’s hostility toward nature. <hi rend="i">Imagining
Nature</hi> is at once a powerful rereading of Blake
                        and an intervention into what Hutchings sees as the
                        “dichotomy” in which ecocriticism sets itself above and apart
                        from all other (i.e., social and political) ways of reading. On the
                        contrary, Hutchings argues, environmental initiatives have always been
                        shaped by social, political, and economic forces (he cites E. P.
                        Thompson’s account of the Forest Laws), and to pretend otherwise is
                        both naïve and dangerous. Hutchings hopes “to delineate an
                        alternative, distinctively Blakean view of the relationship between humanity
                        and nature” (3). The key to this view is a “doubleness”
                        he finds in Blake’s representation of nature and its objects. On one
                        level they are ideal and infinite, the “world in a grain of
                        sand.” At the same time, they operate “discursively,”
                        meaning they are constructed through human perspectives and power
                        systems.</p>
          <p>Hutchings’ argument, clearly aimed at specialists, has profound
                        implications for the ways in which we read Blake’s statements about
                        “nature,” and hence for our interpretation of Blake’s
                        overall vision. He suggests that Blake’s suspicion of
                        “nature” is directed not toward its material reality but
                        rather toward the ways in which human beings have constructed, named, and
                        exploited “nature.” In other words, when Blake represents
                        nature negatively, through a figure such as Vala or the Polypus, he is
                        criticizing a discourse of nature, a construction of the human mind and
                        society. This means that many of Blake’s anti-natural statements are
                        aimed at discourses of nature, not nature itself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n68">2. Claire Colebrook made a similar argument in these pages
                            recently about Blake’s anti-feminist rhetoric.</note></p>
          <p>In order to substantiate his claim, Hutchings must first establish that there
                        is a “nature itself” for Blake. In his first chapter, he
                        challenges a series of factors that have contributed to Blake’s
                        reputation as “nature’s Romantic adversary,” beginning
                        with Northrop Frye’s <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, which
                        immediately overshadowed Mark Schorer’s book, <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake: The Politics of Vision</hi>, published the previous year. Whereas
                        Schorer emphasized the contradictions in Blake’s attitude toward
                        nature, Frye not only insisted on the unity of Blake’s philosophy 
<pb id="p38-76" n="76"/>
but fixed it in firm opposition to nature.
                        Subsequent generations of Blake scholars have accepted without question
                        Blake’s contempt for the natural world, swayed not only by
                        Frye’s argument but also by the well-known marginalia in which Blake
                        denounces “natural objects” in favor of imagination. Hutchings
                        suggests that these off-the-cuff comments should not outweigh the
                        affirmations of nature that appear throughout Blake’s work. Neither
                        Blake’s self-proclaimed rejection of deism nor his apparent embrace
                        of antinomianism, according to Hutchings, provides consistent evidence of
                        his opposition to nature. Blake’s biographical association with the
                        city is also, he points out unnecessarily, insufficient evidence that he
                        rejects the country.</p>
          <p>Chapter two, “Nature’s Economy and <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Thel</hi>,” begins with a provocative discussion of
                        anthropomorphism and the tendency for Blake’s critics to read the
                        Eagle and the Mole, for example, as “anything and everything but
                        eagles and moles” (76). Hutchings makes a moral case for
                        “attempting at least to imagine the needs of the non-human
                        world” (77), in part by refusing to appropriate animals and plants
                        for symbolic ends. While Blake’s insistent emphasis on “the
                        human form divine” makes his attitude toward such anthropomorphism
                        less than clear, Hutchings cites “The Fly” as evidence that
                        Blake could and did imagine a fly and a human being on equal
                        terms—even having the man call himself “a Fly” at the
                        end of the poem (83). In his reading of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>,
                        Hutchings echoes Helen Bruder’s argument that the utilitarian
                        philosophy articulated by the figures in Har is sharply delineated by
                        gender, so that the Cloud’s masculine “self-assertion”
                        is set against the self-effacement of the Lily and Clod. (One wonders if the
                        female figures would be similarly condemned if they were to assert
                        themselves.) Where Hutchings usefully expands this argument is in his
                        contrast of Blake’s poem with Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Economy of
Vegetation.</hi> Whereas Darwin uses figurative language to
                        naturalize “the gendered economy of human relations,”
                        Blake’s allegory demonstrates and questions the ways in which our
                        anthropomorphic discourse “can ‘naturalize’ the
                        ideological interests of the <hi rend="i">status quo</hi>” (99).
                        While I find this idea persuasive, as it helps to account for the fact that
                        the poem seems to support entirely contradictory readings, I’m
                        puzzled by Hutchings’ assumption that the word “Har,”
                        “followed on two occasions by a grammatically unnecessary
                        period” (not uncommon in Blake), must therefore be an abbreviation
                        for some other word, a word he arbitrarily decides is
                        “Harmony.” (Why not “harvest,”
                        “harp,” “heart,” or “hard”?) A
                        footnote acknowledges and dismisses the reference to Har as a character in
                            <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, contending that the unpublished poem would not
                        be relevant to “Blake’s small contemporary reading
                        public” (224n10). Hutchings’ argument over the next few pages
                        that Blake is making an ironic comment on natural “harmony” is
                        rather hindered than helped by what he acknowledges is a conjectural
                        association. Nonetheless, his conclusion that “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> both
celebrates and abhors” a holistic,
                        interdependent model of life on earth offers new light on the ambiguity of
                        the poem in the context not of Innocence and Experience (as it is usually
                        read), but of nature and the constructions we put upon it.</p>
          <p>Hutchings remains uneasy, however, about Blake’s use of
                        anthropomorphism. In his third chapter, “<hi rend="i">Milton’s</hi> Environmental
Poetics,” he considers
                        instances, both verbal and graphic, in which Blake seems to humanize the
                        things of nature. For Blake, he says, “our encounters with non-human
                        entities are always in some sense anthropomorphic encounters with
                        ourselves,” and yet those entities appear to resist our
                        “disfiguring” gaze (117). This intractability of nature is
                        crucial to Hutchings’ reassessment of Blake’s antipathy to
                        Newton. Both Blake and Newton, he suggests, affirm the
                        “otherness” of nature, but for Newton that reality is knowable
                        through the laws and language of science, whereas for Blake the imagination
                        yields a prophetic “common ground upon which all beings, human and
                        otherwise, might meet in visionary interchange” (120).</p>
          <p>Hutchings goes on in this chapter to complicate Newton’s reputation
                        among Blakeans as the epitome of “single vision,” arguing that
                        Newton in fact brought a previously abstract natural philosophy down to
                        earth, so to speak, making science a “materially engaged
                        praxis” (123). In this he was not entirely at odds with Blake, who
                        abhorred the mystification of a priesthood keeping the secrets of the
                        universe. Blake’s attack on Newton thus has more to do with
                        Newton’s contemporary reputation and the uses to which his theories
                        were put, as well as his emphasis on the laws of nature. Hutchings makes a
                        generally convincing connection between natural and moral legalism, although
                        the evidence he draws from Blake’s color print “Newton”
                        seems loose at best (Newton is sitting on rock; the Decalogue was carved in
                        stone). He reads <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as an “antinomian rejection
                        of legalism in both its physical and moral manifestations” (129). The
                        interdependence of time and eternity in this poem directly challenges
                        Newton’s absolute definitions of time and space.</p>
          <p>“<hi rend="i">Jerusalem’s</hi> Human Ecology” is the
                        most compelling chapter of the book, arguing that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is not
the anti-natural poem that most scholars have
                        assumed it to be. Its complexity, Hutchings argues, involves both
                        essentialist and discursive or deconstructive modes of critique, aimed at
                        challenging the discourse of “natural” religious and legal
                        authority. His best example of Blake’s strategy comes not from 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> but from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, when Los
                        states that “this mournful day / Must be a blank in Nature” (E
                        102). As Hutchings puts it, “Los erases the totality of
                        nature’s cultural inscriptions,” leaving a <hi rend="i">tabula
                            rasa</hi>, but that primitivist ideal appears only as a blank, an
                        absence (155). The point seems to be not that nature has no objective
                        reality, but that that reality cannot be known. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        then becomes not a critique of nature per se, but a critique of its
                        constructions.</p>
          <p>The argument in this chapter focuses especially on the figures of Vala and
                        the Polypus, both of which become destructive because they are products of
                        “institutionalized discourses” (175). Hutchings makes the
                        provocative suggestion that Vala’s role is to some extent
                        predetermined by the necessities of the epic form, and that “Blake
                        condemns nature <hi rend="i">in advance</hi>
	<pb id="p38-77" n="77"/>
by making Vala occupy the structural space
                        attributed to Satan or Hell in influential epics like <hi rend="i">The
                            Divine Comedy</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi>” At the
                        same time, however, since Blake has deconstructed the Heaven/Hell dualism in
                            <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, he “inadvertently encourages his
                        readers to question the structurally similar Eternity/Nature dualism that
                        haunts his own epics” (174-75). Hutchings goes on to point out that
                        Vala’s naming by others is an important part of her presentation,
                        especially since the grossly unreliable Sons of Albion, as well as the
                        self-absorbed Albion himself, are the ones who identify her as
                        “Babylon” and “our Mother! Nature!” (E 163).</p>
          <p>At the same time, Hutchings reads the Polypus as Blake’s critique of
                        “deep ecology.” Just as the Polypus threatens to absorb all
                        things and beings into itself, “too much identification with the
                        external world can, in Blake’s thought, lead to a harmful
                        annihilation of the identifying self” (197). The Polypus becomes
                        “a figure for the indissociate human” (199); paradoxically, by
                        identifying too much with our environment, we lose ourselves and thus our
                        ability to see that environment. Albion deteriorates when he
                        anthropomorphically projects himself onto his natural surroundings: this
                        denial of otherness makes relationship impossible. But so does the loss of
                        self in the absorption of the Polypus, which again is not a natural product
                        but a dark construction of the human will.</p>
          <p>In the “Coda: Blake’s Apocalypse, Druidism, and the
                        Humanization of Nature,” Hutchings resolves much of the lingering
                        ambiguity over anthropomorphism and whether “humanizing”
                        nature is a positive or negative process in Blake. Certainly, as he
                        acknowledges, self-interested and instrumental readings and discourses of
                        nature are ultimately destructive both for human beings and for the rest of
                        the environment. On the other hand, the mutuality that characterizes the end
                        of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> depends on recognizing the independent value
                        of all things, that they are worthy of “conversing” (though he
                        does not draw on that particular term). Hutchings concludes with the
                        suggestion that when “Lion, Tyger, Horse, Elephant, Eagle Dove, Fly,
                        Worm, / And the all wondrous Serpent . . . Humanize” on plate 98 (E
                        258), they not only become human (as most readers have concluded) but make
                        others humane in a “profound ‘ministry of
                        reconciliation’” (217).</p>
          <p>In conclusion, <hi rend="i">Imagining Nature</hi> does more than fill a gap
                        in Blake studies; it re-imagines nature in the context not only of
                        Blake’s work but implicitly of all human imagining. While a few
                        points in the readings, as I have noted, seem stretched or loosely
                        supported, the real value of the book rests not in such details but in its
                        ability to see, as Blake would say, at once the Thistle and the Old Man.
                        This book will change forever the way we read Blake’s reading of
                        nature.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bate, Jonathan. <hi rend="i">The Song of the Earth.</hi> London: Picador,
                            2000.</p>
            <p>Colebrook, Claire. “Blake and Feminism: Romanticism and the
                            Question of the Other.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 34 (2000): 4-13.</p>
            <p>Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study of William
                                Blake.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1947.</p>
            <p>Kroeber, Karl. <hi rend="i">Ecological Literary Criticism: Romantic
                                Imagining and the Biology of Mind.</hi> New York: Columbia UP,
                            1994.</p>
            <p>Liu, Alan. <hi rend="i">Wordsworth: The Sense of History.</hi> Stanford:
                            Stanford UP, 1989.</p>
            <p>Lussier, Mark. “Blake’s Deep Ecology.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 35
(1996): 393-409.</p>
            <p>McKusick, James. <hi rend="i">Green Writing: Romanticism and
                                Ecology.</hi> New York: St. Martin’s, 2000.</p>
            <p>Schorer, Mark. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Politics of Vision.</hi>
                            New York: Holt, 1946.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
