<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.2.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2004</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Kathleen Lundeen</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <front>
      <pb id="p38-49-50" n="49-50"/>
        <div1 id="cover">
            <figure n="cover.038.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="331">
                <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
                    AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
                    Mary Lynn Johnson Delves into Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi><lb/>
                    VOLUME 38<lb/>
                    NUMBER 2<lb/>
                    FALL 2004</figTranscr>
            </figure>
        </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="8" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
				<head>
				  <title>CONTENTS</title>
				</head>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.2.johnson">Blake’s Engravings for Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>: Overdue Credit to Chodowiecki, Schellenberg, and Lips</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Mary Lynn Johnson</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">52</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.2.michael">Kevin Hutchings, <hi rend="i">Imagining Nature:
Blake’s
                                Environmental Poetics</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Jennifer Davis Michael</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">75</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.2.mcclenahan">Robert N. Essick, ed., William Blake, 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the
                                Daughters of Albion</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Catherine L. McClenahan</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">77</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.2.taylor">Sheila A. Spector, <hi rend="i">“Wonders
Divine”: The
                                Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Myth</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Dena Bain Taylor</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">79</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.2.lundeen">Nick Rawlinson, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Comic Vision</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Kathleen Lundeen</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">85</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p38-51" n="51"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mary Lynn Johnson</hi>, special assistant (emerita), President’s Office,
                    University of Iowa, has taught at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
                    and Georgia State University. Her publications include <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> ‘Four
Zoas’: <hi rend="i">The Design of a
                        Dream</hi> (1978; with Brian Wilkie), <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and
                        Designs</hi> (1979, with John E. Grant; 2nd ed. underway), a chapter in 
<hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi> (ed. Eaves, 2003),
                    and “Lavater Contemplating a Bust of Chatham: A Conundrum in National and
                    Personal Physiognomy,” in <hi rend="i">Physiognomy in Profile</hi> (ed.
                    Melissa Percival, expected in 2005).</p>
        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Kathleen Lundeen</hi> teaches and writes on Blake, Romanticism, intermedial studies,
                    and prophetic literature. Her publications include <hi rend="i">Knight of the
                        Living Dead: William Blake and the Problem of Ontology</hi> (Susquehanna,
                    2000). She is a professor of English at Western Washington University.</p>
        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Catherine McClenahan</hi> teaches in the English department and the Robert E. Cook
                    Honors College at Indiana University of Pennsylvania; she has published several
                    articles on gender and politics in Blake.</p>
        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Jennifer Davis Michael</hi> teaches English at the University of the South in Sewanee,
                    Tennessee, and writes on Blake and other convergences of visual and verbal art
                    in the Romantic period. She contributed to <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character:
                        Essays on William Blake in Honor of John E. Grant</hi>, and is currently
                    revising a book manuscript on Blake and the city.</p>
        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dena Bain Taylor</hi> is senior lecturer and director of the Health Sciences Writing
                    Centre at the University of Toronto. Her doctoral dissertation (Toronto, 1983)
                    was <hi rend="i">Emanations of the Divine: William Blake and the
                    Kabbalah.</hi></p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester,
                    Rochester NY 14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sjns@mail.rochester.edu<lb/>
 TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820
                    FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
                    14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA
                    94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@socrates.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens GA
                    30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@english.uga.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton
                    Lane, Nottingham NG11 8NS U.K.<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the
                    sponsorship of the Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions
                    are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals. All subscriptions are by the
                    volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
                    received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses
                    outside the U.S., Canada, and Mexico require a $15 per volume postal surcharge
                    for surface delivery, or $20 for airmail. Credit card payment is available. Make
                    checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all
                    subscription orders and related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>,
Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
                    14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for information on
                    issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies,
                    typed and documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style
                        Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to either of the editors: Morris
                    Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451;
                    Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley CA
                    94720-1030. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by a stamped
                    self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a diskette, or
                    send your article as an attachment to an email message; please number the pages
                    of electronic submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are
                    usually acceptable.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is indexed in the Modern Language
                    Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
                    Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature,
                    American Humanities Index, Arts and Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents
                    and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover: “AGED FIGURES, GARDENING,” engr. Blake; fasc. V, July 1788;
                    “Two old Men gardening,” <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>,
                    trans. Hunter, I (1789) 127; 6.1 × 8.4 cm.; image 5.2 × 7.2 cm.
                    Collection of Mary Lynn Johnson. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2004
Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
