<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.3.komisaruk</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Introducing The Blake Model</title>
		<author n="Komisaruk">Adam Komisaruk</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2004/2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004-05</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adam Komisaruk</name>
              <name>Thomas Frosch</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Antoine Capet</name>
              <name>David Shaddock</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004/2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <body>
    <pb id="p38-92" n="92"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Introducing The Blake Model</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Adam <name>Komisaruk</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The present project arises from my effort, over the years, to hone a concise explanation of
Blake’s mythology to myself, my colleagues and my students.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">*</ref> As a diagram junkie, I have several schemata at my disposal,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">**</ref> including Alicia Ostriker’s chart of the
zoas and their attributes from the Penguin <hi rend="i">Complete Poems</hi> (illus. 1); Northrop Frye’s
earlier and more extensive version from <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> (illus. 2); S. Foster Damon’s map
of Golgonooza, the city of art, from <hi rend="i">The Blake Dictionary</hi> (illus. 3); or my own family tree
of Blake’s cast of characters (illus. 4).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref> Where each of these schemata falls short, however, is in its inability to represent fully
the spatial extent of Blake’s vision. Damon himself says in a footnote to his diagram, “Golgonooza, being
four-dimensional, cannot be reduced to a chart of two dimensions. Each of the four gates not only opens into
each of the other gates but does so ‘each within other toward the Four points’ 
(<hi rend="i">J[erusalem</hi>] 12:48)” (163). Thus about four years ago the idea occurred to me of developing a
physical model that could visualize Blake’s
                        <figure n="ZoasChart.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="349">
							<figTranscr>Name<lb/>
							URIZEN<lb/>
							LUVAH<lb/>
							THARMAS<lb/>
							URTHONA<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(Emanation)<lb/>
							(AHANIA)<lb/>
							(VALA)<lb/>
							(ENION)<lb/>
							(ENITHARMON)<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Title<lb/>
							‘Prince of light’<lb/>
							‘Prince of love’<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Faculty<lb/>
							Reason<lb/>
							Passion<lb/>
							Sensation<lb/>
							Instinct<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Eternal Role<lb/>
							Ploughman<lb/>
							Vintner<lb/>
							Shepherd<lb/>
							Blacksmith<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Eternal Virtue<lb/>
							Faith, certainty<lb/>
							Love<lb/>
							Coherence, receptivity<lb/>
							Creativity<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Fallen Form<lb/>
							‘God, Priest, King’<lb/>
							ORC (SHADOWY FEMALE) ‘Demon Red’<lb/>
							‘Parent Power’<lb/>
							LOS (ENITHARMON) ‘Eternal Prophet’<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Fallen Character<lb/>
							Doubt, Tyranny<lb/>
							Rebellion, Revolution<lb/>
							Flood, Chaos<lb/>
							Poetry, Prophecy<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Element<lb/>
							Air (light)<lb/>
							Fire (heat)<lb/>
							Water<lb/>
							Earth<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Region<lb/>
							S. (zenith)<lb/>
							E. (centre)<lb/>
							W. (circumference)<lb/>
							N. (nadir)<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Note: Los and Enitharmon are born from Tharmas and Enion and in turn become the parents of Orc and the
Shadowy Female.</figTranscr>
							<head>1. Chart of the zoas and their properties.</head>
							<figDesc><hi rend="i">William Blake, The Complete Poems</hi>, ed. Alicia Ostriker (1977; New York:
Penguin, 1988) 1048 (reprinted by permission of Penguin).</figDesc>
						</figure>
						<figure n="ZoasChart2.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="439">
							<figTranscr>1. Eternal Name Luvah Urizen Tharmas Urthona<lb/>
							2. Time Name Orc Satan C. Cherub Los<lb/>
							3. Emanation Vala Ahania Enion (Enitharmon)<lb/>
							4. Quality Love Wisdom Power Fancy<lb/>
							5. Zoa (Bible) Bull Lion Eagle Man<lb/>
							6. Sense Nose Eye Tongue Ear<lb/>
							7. Body Part Loins Head Heart Legs<lb/>
							8. Metal (Bible) Brass Gold Silver Iron<lb/>
							9. Position Centre Zenith Circumference Nadir<lb/>
							10. Nature (Sky) Stars Sun Moon Mountains<lb/>
							11. Element Fire Air Water Earth<lb/>
							12. E. Spirits Genii Fairies Nymphs Gnomes<lb/>
							13. State “Generation” Eden Beulah “Ulro”<lb/>
							14. Place Soil City Garden Underground<lb/>
							15. Activity Weaver Plowman Shepherd Blacksmith<lb/>
							16. Art Painting Architecture Poetry Music<lb/>
							17. Planet Mars Mercury Venus Earth<lb/>
							18. Point East South West North<lb/>
							19. Season Spring Summer Autumn Winter<lb/>
							20. Time of Day Morning Noon Evening Night<lb/>
							21. Age Youth Maturity Age “Death” (sleep)<lb/>
							22. Son of Los Palamabron Rintrah Theotormon Bromion<lb/>
							23. Emanation Elynittria Ocalythron Oothoon (none)<lb/>
							24. City London Verulam York Edinburgh<lb/>
							25. Evangelist Luke Mark John Matthew<lb/>
							26. Color (Fallen) Red White Green Blue<lb/>
							27. Virtue Love Faith Hope Vision<lb/>
							28. Vice Hatred Doubt Despair Dullness<lb/>
							29. Eden River Pison Hiddekel Gihon Euphrates</figTranscr>
							<head>2. Chart of the zoas and their properties.</head>
							<figDesc>Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study of William Blake</hi> (1947; Princeton:
Princeton UP, 1990) 277-78 (reprinted by permission of Princeton UP, ©1947, 1969 revised edition. 1975
renewed).</figDesc>
						</figure>
						<figure n="GolgonoozaMap.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="560">
							<figTranscr>GOLGONOOZA<lb/>
							Jerusalem 12:45-13:29<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							W<lb/>
							Generation<lb/>
							Four Bulls<lb/>
							of<lb/>
							Iron<lb/>
							<lb/>
							S<lb/>
							Ulro<lb/>
							Four Bulls<lb/>
							of Enamel’d<lb/>
							Clay<lb/>
							<lb/>
							E<lb/>
							Beulah<lb/>
							Four Bulls<lb/>
							of the<lb/>
							Four Metals<lb/>
							<lb/>
							N<lb/>
							Eden<lb/>
							Four Bulls<lb/>
							of the<lb/>
							Four Metals<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							N<lb/>
							Gnomes<lb/>
							Nadir<lb/>
							Eden<lb/>
							Ear<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							W<lb/>
							A Cherub<lb/>
							of<lb/>
							Iron<lb/>
							<lb/>
							E<lb/>
							A Cherub<lb/>
							of<lb/>
							Stone<lb/>
							<lb/>
							S<lb/>
							A Cherub<lb/>
							of<lb/>
							Clay<lb/>
							<lb/>
							N<lb/>
							A Cherub<lb/>
							of<lb/>
							Metals<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							W<lb/>
							Nymphs<lb/>
							Circumference<lb/>
							Generation<lb/>
							Tongue<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							MOAT OF FIRE<lb/>
							CATHEDRON<lb/>
							GATE OF LUBAN<lb/>
							LOS’S FORGE<lb/>
							LOS’S PALACE<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							W<lb/>
							Seven<lb/>
							Generative<lb/>
							Forms<lb/>
							<lb/>
							S<lb/>
							Seven<lb/>
							Forms<lb/>
							of War<lb/>
							<lb/>
							E<lb/>
							Stone<lb/>
							Seven<lb/>
							Diseases<lb/>
							<lb/>
							N<lb/>
							Ice<lb/>
							Sevenfold<lb/>
							Forms<lb/>
							of Death<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							E<lb/>
							Genii<lb/>
							Center<lb/>
							Beulah<lb/>
							Nostrils<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Eyes<lb/>
							Ulro<lb/>
							Zenith<lb/>
							Fairies<lb/>
							S<lb/>
							<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Four<lb/>
							Living<lb/>
							Lions<lb/>
							E<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Four<lb/>
							Iron<lb/>
							Lions<lb/>
							W<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Four<lb/>
							Clay<lb/>
							Lions<lb/>
							S<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Four<lb/>
							Lions of<lb/>
							Four Metals<lb/>
							N</figTranscr>
							<head>3. Map of Golgonooza.</head>
							<figDesc>S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi>,
rev. ed. (Hanover and London: Brown UP/UP of New England, 1988) 163 (reprinted by permission of UP of New
England).</figDesc>
						</figure>
						<note id="n29">For their feedback and assistance with this project I am indebted to Sandy Baldwin,
Joshua David Gonsalves, Stephen Harris, Adam Horne, Jeremy Jarrell, Wayne Ripley, Frances Van Scoy and Susan
Warshauer.</note>
						<note id="n30">For further reflections on the project described herein, see Adam Komisaruk, Steve Guynup
and Fred Yee, “Blake and Virtuality: An Exchange,” <hi rend="i">Digital Designs on Blake</hi>, ed. Ron
Broglio, Romantic Circles Praxis Series, forthcoming &lt;http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/&gt;.</note>
						<pb id="p38-93" n="93"/>
						<figure n="AlbionsFamilyTree.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="550" height="403">
							<figTranscr>Child<lb/>
							Emanation of<lb/>
							Aspect<lb/>
							Fallen form of<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Albion<lb/>
							Jerusalem<lb/>
							Urizen Luvah Tharmas Urthona<lb/>
							Ahania Vala Enion Enitharmon<lb/>
							Los<lb/>
							Enitharmon<lb/>
							Satan Orc Rintrah Palamabron Theotormon Bromion Sotha<lb/>
							Shadowy Female Ocalythron Elynittria Oothoon Leutha Thiralatha/Diralada<lb/>
							Hand Hyle Bowen Gwantok Coban<lb/>
							Cambel Gwendolen Conwenna Cordella Ignoge<lb/>
							Rahab<lb/>
							Scofield [Adam] Hutton Slade Kox [Noah] Kotope Peachey Brereton<lb/>
							Gwiniverra Gwinefred Gonorill Estrild Sabrina Mehetabel Ragan<lb/>
							Tirzah<lb/>
							Adam Enoch Shem Han Japeth</figTranscr>
							<head>4. Albion’s family tree.</head>
							<figDesc>By the author.</figDesc>
						</figure>
mythology as he himself appears to have visualized it—a system of spatial relationships extending through
three and, if we include its manipulations through time, four dimensions. My original intent was to create a
sort of kinetic statue or mobile, showing the zoas suspended in space and capable of being rotated along any
axis. It eventually became clear, however, that by using the virtual-reality technology now available, I could
create an even more suitable model: an immersive digital environment through which users might navigate to
encounter Blake’s characters, places and objects in the configuration his works describe. The Blake Model is
a work-in-progress that I hope eventually to make available for researchers, teachers and students of Blake.
This essay will serve as a prospectus to the project, an announcement of its status to date, an invitation for
feedback and a discussion of some theoretical problems the project raises. <note id="n1">1. All my Blake
quotations are from <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman,
newly revised ed. (New York: Anchor, 1988), hereafter “E.”</note></p>
          <p>Supported by internal grants from West Virginia University, in collaboration with the Virtual
Environments Laboratory there, and with an eye to future funding by the National Science Foundation’s
Information Technology program, I am breaking the project into the following phases: (1) the creation of the
overall landscape or Blakean universe; (2) the creation of a human figure corresponding to Blake’s Albion,
who is the chief occupant of this landscape; (3) the decision as to what in the landscape goes where; (4) the
animation of this environment to make it traversable by users and to show its transformations through time;
(5) the creation of a user-friendly interface; (6) the preparation of textual annotations for the objects,
locations and characters in the environment.</p>
          <p>Blake’s landscape, at its most basic, consists of the four levels of existence with which
readers are already familiar—Eden, the redeemed realm of pure spirit; Beulah, the sensual paradise;
Generation, or vegetative life without consciousness; and Ulro, or dead matter. I will be representing these
realms as four concentric spheres, since for Blake the Fall involves a contraction toward a center, not just a
longitudinal descent. Between Ulro and Eden extends the “Mundane Shell,” a large egg-shaped object that
encloses the material world. Ulro, the lowest or inner-most realm, is where the majority of human history
transpires and is therefore wrought by Blake in the most detail. Using the digital modeling program Bryce 3D
(Corel), I made a preliminary attempt (illus. 5) to represent the rocky expanse of Ulro, 
<pb id="p38-94" n="94"/>
including the forest of Entuthon-Benython and, within it, the lake of Udan-Adan and the great city of
Golgonooza. Inside Golgonooza stands Bowlahoola, workshop of the artist-black-smith Los, and the hall of
Cathedron. Bryce 3D is a relatively user-friendly but inflexible program; subsequent modeling will be done in
industry-standard programs such as Maya (Alias) or 3D Studio Max (Discreet). I am fortunate to be assisted in
the landscaping phase of the project by the talented New York artist Fred Yee, who has prepared a wonderful
storyboard that he will soon be realizing digitally. Yee worked without the benefit of Blake’s images, only
his texts, yet the two artists’ visions have some striking parallels. Take, for example, Blake’s sketch of
Cathedron in the margin of the <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> manuscript, Night the Third (illus. 6); the crown
on her head and gothic altar for her genitalia suggest Blake’s association between female sexuality and the
established church. Yee’s realization
                        <figure n="LandscapeInUlro.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="377">
	<head>5. Landscape in Ulro with Golgonooza.</head>
	<figDesc>Created in Bryce 3D by the author.</figDesc>
</figure>
						<figure n="BB209.1.44.MS.detail" rend="file" width="269" height="1000">
							<figTranscr>BRITISH<lb/>
							M[USEU]M</figTranscr>
							<head>6. Cathedron.</head>
							<figDesc>William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 44, Night the Third. By permission of the
British Library, ADD.39764 f44.</figDesc>
						</figure>
(illus. 7) places Cathedron in a yoga goddess pose, her head tipped back in a manner whose significance I will
discuss later. A Mesopotamian ziggurat replaces the cathedral between her splayed legs, but the logic remains
the same. Yee envisions some of the tortured inhabitants of Ulro (illus. 8) as a giant cupped hand that
suggests “false shelter” [a]; a crouching figure bearing a boulder on his back [b]; and a “naked ashamed
tree” [c] that suggests at once a classical discus-thrower, Ovid’s Daphne metamorphosed to escape
Apollo’s clutches and Rodin’s Adam writhing in agony before the gates of Hell. This lattermost figure
further calls to mind not only Blake’s foe outstretched beneath the poison tree, but his cave-dweller
“struggl[ing] into life” from <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> (illus. 9). That Yee independently
visualizes Blake’s symbols in a manner so resonant with Blake himself merely reaffirms a principle
well-known to Blakeans: the continuity of mythic 
                        <figure n="Cathedron.Yee.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="375">
	<head>7. Cathedron.</head>
	<figDesc>By Fred Yee.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p38-95" n="95"/>
thinking even among cultures that could not possibly have had direct knowledge of one another. We only begin
to understand Blake’s archetypal man of genius when we become convinced that Blake himself must have read
Marx, Freud, Jung and Joseph Campbell.</p>
          <p>I would like to step back from this level of detail, which resides rather far off in The Blake
Model’s future, and return to the bigger picture. As I said, the first task is to create the four concentric
spheres that represent Blake’s levels of existence, and the Mundane Egg that stretches between them.
Primitive shapes of this kind may be digitally generated with relative efficiency. The second task is to
create the principal character who will inhabit this environment—Albion, the eternal man whose body serves
as the microcosmic map of Blake’s macrocosmic universe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> Unlike the denizens of Ulro, Albion must be
                        <figure n="InhabitantsOfUlro.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="350">
							<figTranscr>a b c</figTranscr>
							<head>8. Inhabitants of Ulro: (a) false shelter; (b) figure carrying a burden; (c) naked ashamed
tree.</head>
							<figDesc>By Fred Yee.</figDesc>
						</figure>
						<figure n="gates-sexes.d.p5" id="gates-sexes.d.illbk.05" work-copy="gates-sexes.d" rend="db" width="898" height="1000">
							<figTranscr>3 Earth<lb/>
							He struggles into Life<lb/>
							Publishd by WBlake 17 May 1793</figTranscr>
							<head>9. Earth: “He struggles into Life.”</head>
							<figDesc>Blake, <hi rend="i">For The Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, copy D, plate 5. By permission
of the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York, PML 63936 plate 5.</figDesc>
						</figure>
wrought with especial care, for he will function not as static scenery but as a mobile creature whom we will
follow in his fall from Eden and resurrection back again. As my frame of reference for Blake’s “human form
divine,” I have chosen the famous image from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> of man in an idealized state (illus.
10)—at once God, Christ, England and, with characteristic immodesty, Blake himself. The crucifixion posture
suggests spiritual salvation, but the muscular, active body identifies this salvation with life rather than
death. The head tipped heavenward is significant for an additional reason to which I will return later. In
order to render Blake’s two-dimensional figure in three dimensions, I experimented with two techniques. My
research assistant Allen Vandegrift approximated the <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> attitude using the software
application Poser (Curious Labs), which supplies preprogrammed human figures that may be positioned rather
like an artist’s manikin. Since the results seemed rather stiff, however, I resorted to a live model, Brian
Corey of the WVU Theater and Dance Department, who imitated the pose in the Blake watercolor and was then
scanned with a full-body optical scanner at the Morgantown NIOSH (National Institute for Occupational Safety
and
                        <figure n="milton.c.p31-29" id="milton.c.illbk.31" work-copy="milton.c" rend="db" width="718" height="1000">
							<figTranscr>29<lb/>
							WILLIAM</figTranscr>
							<head>10. Self-portrait.</head>
							<figDesc>Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, copy C, plate 31. By permission of the Rare Books
Division, New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations.</figDesc>
						</figure>
						<figure n="3DBodyScan.Milton.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="348">
	<head>11. Three-dimensional body scan recreating Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, plate 31</head>
	<figDesc>Brian Corey, model.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p38-96" n="96"/>
Health) campus (illus. 11). The file is saved as a list of three-dimensional coordinates which, using the
program Geomagic (Raindrop Geomagic), may be interpreted as a point cloud, a wire mesh or a polygon assembly.
Research assistants at the WV Virtual Environments Lab are in the process of cleaning up the noise and
compressing the file into a manageable size. The final step will be for a graphic artist to texture-map the
figure with a detailed “skin” so as to approximate Blake’s original. The program DeepPaint 3D (Right
Hemisphere) is designed for “drawing” directly onto the surface of digital models such as this. 
<note id="n2">2. Technically, Albion himself is both microcosm and macrocosm: the universe is mapped out on his
body, but his body is also positioned within this universe, which in turn is mapped out on his body, etc. To
create this <hi rend="i">mise-en-abyme</hi> effect, The Blake Model will be programmed with a simple loop, so
that zooming in on Albion eventually returns the user to a bird’s-eye view of Albion. Stephen Guynup
captures something of this idea in his virtual rendition of Blake’s “The Crystal Cabinet,” which
envisions “Another England” within England; with Ron Broglio and Thomas Tulis, “William Blake’s
‘Crystal Cabinet,’” January 2003 &lt;http://www.pd.org/~thatguy/crystal/index.html&gt;.</note></p>
          <p>The third task, that which requires the most literary research, is to position this human figure
within the landscape according to Blake’s complicated but precise spatial instructions. We recall that each
of the four “compass points” is the seat of a different faculty: Urizen, reason, resides in the south;
Luvah, love, in the east; Tharmas, sensation, in the west; and Urthona, instinct, in the north. At times
Blake’s directionals are fairly straightforward, as in the famous diagram of the zoas from 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (illus. 12), or the following lines from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: “And the Four
Points are thus beheld in great Eternity / West, the Circumference: South, the Zenith: North, / The Nadir:
East, the Center, unapproachable for ever. / These are the four Faces towards the Four Worlds of Humanity / In
every Man. Ezekiel saw them by Chebar’s flood” (12:54-58; E 156). At other times, however, Blake is
considerably less intuitive. It is especially difficult to work out how the four compass points of the
universe correspond to the four compass points on the body of Albion, which is a microcosm of the universe,
and in turn to the four compass points on the face of Albion, which is a microcosm of
                        <figure n="milton.c.p34-32.detail" id="milton.c.illbk.34" work-copy="milton.c" rend="file" width="958" height="889">
							<figTranscr>N<lb/>
							Urthona<lb/>
							Adam<lb/>
							W Tharmas  Luvah E<lb/>
							Satan<lb/>
							Miltons Track<lb/>
							Urizen</figTranscr>
							<head>12. The four zoas in their spheres.</head>
							<figDesc>Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, copy C, plate 34 (detail). By permission of the Rare
Books Division, New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations.</figDesc>
						</figure>
the body. Blake goes on to say in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that “the Eyes are the South, and the Nostrils
are the East. / And the Tongue is the West, and the Ear is the North. / . . . And the North is Breadth, the
South is Heighth &amp; Depth: / The East is Inwards: &amp; the West is Outwards every way” (12:59-60,
14:29-30; E 156, 158). These directions clearly make no sense if we map them literally onto the face (illus.
13); the south, for instance, falls in the middle of the north. I maintain that in order for them to make
sense, we must return to Blake’s famous self-portrait from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as our frame of
reference. We tip the head back and regard the four compass points not as points but as vectors. Thus vision
reaches up and down; hearing reaches across; the nostrils draw breath in; the tongue issues speech outward.
Then, viewed in profile like the <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> drawing, the vectors assume their proper right-angle
configuration (illus. 14). This manipulation thus demonstrates the
                        <figure n="Jerusalem.FaceMap.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="325">
							<figTranscr>N S S N<lb/>
							E E<lb/>
							W</figTranscr>
							<head>13. Literal, and incorrect, representation of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 12:54-60,
14:29-30, associating points of the compass with points on the human face.</head>
							<figDesc>Created in Bryce 3D by the author.</figDesc>
						</figure>
						<figure n="Jerusalem.FaceMap2.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="282">
							<figTranscr>S<lb/>
							E W<lb/>
							N</figTranscr>
							<head>14. Revised representation of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 12:54-60, 14:29-30,
associating points of the compass with sensory trajectories.</head>
							<figDesc>Created in Bryce 3D by the author.</figDesc>
						</figure>
						<pb id="p38-97" n="97"/>
necessity of three-dimensional space to represent Blake’s system accurately. It also demonstrates that
three-dimensionality itself is only a transitory mode through which we must pass to arrive at an authentic
two-dimensionality. We extend the sensory vectors into virtual space only so that we may collapse the depth of
field again and get the flat composition familiar to us from Blake and from our own cartographic sense. We
recall that in “The Mental Traveller” and elsewhere, Blake uses a three-dimensional ball to represent
contracted consciousness; his symbol for infinity is the two-dimensional plane.</p>
          <p>The goal of phases four and five of the project is to create smooth-scrolling graphics responsive
to user intervention. “First-person shooter” video games will provide the visual metaphor; indeed, The
Blake Model will probably use one of the open-source animation engines written for those games, such as Unreal
(Epic Games), Quake (Id Software) or VRML. I would also like to have preprogrammed animation sequences that
will reenact major events in Blake’s mythology, such as the fall of Albion from Eden to Ulro, the 90-degree
rotation of the zoas during the fall, and Milton’s track across the cosmos. The interface will include
separate viewports for the landscape and for the object annotations, which I will discuss later, as well as
navigational buttons to rotate, zoom and pan. I will probably accomplish these tasks with the cooperation of
WVU’s Geographic Information Systems (GIS), using the program WorldToolKit (Sense8).</p>
          <figure n="Storyboard.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="255">
			<figTranscr>a b c<lb/>
			d e f g<lb/>
			h i j k</figTranscr>
            <head>15. Storyboard for animated routine: Milton’s passage through the vortex.</head>
            <figDesc>By the author and Fred Yee.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>To illustrate how such an animated sequence might work, and help to gloss a particularly cryptic
Blake passage, I refer to the “vortex” metaphor from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>:
<q>
The nature of infinity is this: That every thing has its<lb/>
Own Vortex; and when once a traveller thro Eternity.<lb/>
Has passd that Vortex, he percieves it roll backward behind<lb/>
His path, into a globe itself infolding; like a sun:<lb/>
Or like a moon, or like a universe of starry majesty,<lb/>
While he keeps onwards in his wondrous journey on the earth<lb/>
Or like a human form, a friend with whom he livd benevolent.<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
First Milton saw Albion upon the Rock of Ages,<lb/>
Deadly pale outstretchd and snowy cold, storm coverd;<lb/>
A Giant form of perfect beauty outstretchd on the rock<lb/>
In solemn death: the Sea of Time &amp; Space thunderd aloud<lb/>
Against the rock, which was inwrapped with the weeds of death<lb/>
Hovering over the cold bosom, in its vortex Milton bent down<lb/>
To the bosom of death, what was underneath soon seemd above (15:21-27, 36-43; E 109-10)
</q>
In the “vortex” routine (illus. 15), the user begins with a Milton’s-eye view, hovering in Eden [a].
Because Blake’s four realms of existence are represented as concentric spheres, the globe below describes
the boundary between the purely spiritual Eden and the beginning of matter in Beulah. The outstretched hand, a
familiar icon in first-person-shooter games,
<pb id="p38-98" n="98"/>
corresponds to Milton; it is transparent at this point because Milton’s spiritual body has not yet assumed
its physical cloak. As Milton descends [b], Albion appears in a holographic projection of his eternal state.
Being fallen, Albion is not actually present in Eden, as becomes apparent when Milton tries to move closer
[c]; the landscape scrolls past and the ground approaches, but Albion remains a few steps beyond Milton’s
reach. When Milton touches down in Beulah, another figure appears [d]—it is the bodily form of Milton, which
Milton must assume (by passing through it) so that he may receive admittance to the lower realms. Milton’s
incarnation is signified when the second figure disappears, leaving only the Albion-holograph; the transparent
arm at bottom becomes opaque [e]. Milton continues his descent from Beulah to Generation, then Ulro, whose
unregenerate nature is indicated by a rocky landscape. As he approaches this source of the holographic
projection, Milton begins to see the fallen rather than the ideal state of Albion: Albion’s posture
gradually changes from erect to supine, and his body acquires the same fleshed-out tones as Milton’s arm
[f]. Before long, however, Milton must shed his physical cloak once more in preparation to greet Albion as a
redeemer; the arm becomes transparent again and, off to one side, Milton’s body reappears [g]. By now,
Milton can actually catch up with Albion, and so bends “down / To the bosom of death,” passing directly
through the couchant Albion’s heart and out the other side [h]. Milton has now crossed Albion’s
“vortex.” Continuing to move in the same direction while swiveling around to look behind, “what was
underneath soon seemd above”; Milton sees the fetal-like Albion receding into the distance [i].</p>
          <p>The user’s perspective now switches from Milton’s-eye view to an exterior view, where
Albion’s existential range is represented as a gigantic cone [j]. The cone opens up toward Albion’s
infinite state, to which he will eventually return; its tip corresponds to his present, most narrowly
contracted state; the speck below the tip is Milton. The cone swings around so that it opens away from the
viewer, who looks straight down the tip; the foreshortened cone appears as a globe [k]. The user thus, it is
to be hoped, apprehends Blake’s image: every
                        <figure n="Flowchart.Hypertext.38.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="271">
							<figTranscr>Cathedron<lb/>
							A great hall that stands of the island of Luban within the city of Golgonooza. The name is a synthesis
of “cathedral” and Blake’s wife Catherine. It suggests the dual power of organized religion and feminine
sexuality to entrap the enlightened man.<lb/>
							William Blake, Jerusalem<lb/>
							William Blake, The Four Zoas [image]<lb/>
							Northrop Frye, Fearful Symmetry<lb/>
							<lb/>
							A wondrous golden Building immense with ornaments sublime<lb/>
							Is bright Cathedrons golden Hall, its Courts Towers &amp; Pinnacles<lb/>
							Jerusalem 59.25<lb/>
							<lb/>
							www.blakearchive.org</figTranscr>
							<head>16. Sample flowchart for hypertextual annotation.</head>
							<figDesc>By the author. Inset by permission of the British Library (see caption for illus.
6).</figDesc>
						</figure>
determinate physical form is the tip of a proverbial iceberg (or cone), the tightest possible contraction of a
spiritual immensity. One must not only become a “traveller thro Eternity” but also pass through the very
nadir of reality in order to know this immensity. Redemption, moreover, must be an act of compassion: Milton
recreates the path of Albion’s initial fall, passes through his heart, and must pass through his heart again
in order to return to eternity, presumably taking Albion with him. At the end of the sequence, a “further
reading” link appears to commentaries by Nelson Hilton or by Robert Essick and Joseph Viscomi, now
visualized.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n3">3. See Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of Words</hi>
(Berkeley: U of California P, 1983) 205-30; William Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem and the Final
Illuminated Works</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi, vol. 5 of <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illuminated
Books</hi>, ed. David Bindman (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993) 142.</note></p>
          <p>The sixth and final phase of the project is to annotate the model with embedded hyperlinks to
selected Blake texts, images and critical glosses. For example, clicking on the Cathedron object in the
landscape might spawn a pop-up window with a short definition and links to related terms (illus. 16). One may
also read a relevant passage from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, look at the original drawing from 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> or sample classic commentary from Frye or others. I hope to link the poetry
excerpts to existing internet resources such as the William Blake Archive at the University of Virginia, where
users could avail themselves of additional tools such as search forms and a Blake concordance; or the Blake
Digital Text Project at the University of Georgia, which, like the Archive, offers the entirety of David
Erdman’s standard edition online.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4">4. Blake Digital Text Project, ed. Nelson Hilton
&lt;http://www.english.uga.edu/wblake/home1.html&gt;; William Blake Archive, ed. Morris Eaves, Robert N.
Essick and Joseph Viscomi &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;.</note></p>
          <p>After The Blake Model is complete, it should fit onto a single CD-ROM and be viewable by anyone
with a suitably appointed personal computer, with or without an optional immersion device such as the CAVE or
ImmersaDesk. Once
<pb id="p38-99" n="99"/>
debugged and revised according to a detailed user questionnaire, it will be made available as an open-source
download from the WVU English Department website. As for the future directions of the project, I foresee a
series of Literary Models that extend the 3D-imaging concept to several other writers who think
“spatially” or “geographically” and who, not coincidentally, stand in the chain of influence alongside
Blake. A Dante Model would take the user on a visual tour of the circles of Hell, the mountain of Purgatory
and the reaches of Paradise as described in the <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy.</hi> A <hi rend="i">Faerie
Queene</hi> Model could help keep straight the complex narrative and immense cast of characters in Spenser’s
romance. With a John Milton Model, the user would re-enact Satan’s travels in <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi>, from his fall from Heaven to his entrance into the Garden of Eden. A James Joyce Model could
present a “virtual Dublin” in which the user navigates through the locations and events described in 
<hi rend="i">Ulysses.</hi></p>
          <p>In the remainder of this essay I would like to address some of the conceptual problems that I see
arising from The Blake Model, not so much the project’s technical challenges as its implications for the
study of Blake. The first is the somewhat hoary question about the appropriateness of teaching with
technology, especially given Blake’s own suspicion of alienated labor. My technophilic streak vies with my
Luddite anxiety that I may be hastening my own obsolescence, propelling the dark Satanic mills of the wired
classroom. Cyberspace is a real space, an advertising space that the private sector leases in a diabolical
bargain with a cash-starved public education system; ironically it is here that The Blake Model makes a space
for itself. Electronic transposition does not confer immortality on the text or insulate it from the elements
of production, as Mary Lynn Johnson found in her short-lived Iowa Blake Videodisc Project: “we did not take
an active enough hand in the care and feeding of our newly weaned prodigy.... even files in storage require
eternal vigilance.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> The status of
technological labor in the academy also remains controversial, an issue addressed by the authors of the
DVD-ROM project <hi rend="i">Red Planet: Scientific and Cultural Encounters with Mars.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n5">5. Mary Lynn Johnson, “The Iowa Blake Videodisc Project: A Cautionary History,” 
<hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi> 30.3 (1999): 132-33.</note>
	<note id="n6">6. Helen Burgess, Jeanne Hamming and Robert Markley, “The Dialogics of New Media: Video,
Visualization, and Narrative in <hi rend="i">Red Planet: Scientific and Cultural Encounters with Mars,”
Eloquent Images: Word and Image in the Age of New Media</hi>, ed. Mary E. Hocks and Michelle R. Kendrick
(Cambridge, MA: MIT, 2003) 61-88.</note></p>
          <p>While I cannot fully explore here the political ramifications of my medium, I would suggest that
such questions were not unknown to Blake himself. The editors of the William Blake Archive, responding to
allegations that the project imposes a Urizenic monologism on Blake’s texts, remind us of the assumption
“that Blake somehow exempted himself from the unpleasant realities of labor and commerce. But in fact he
sold his works for real cash money that he accepted.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> Viscomi, in his study of Blake’s technique, argues that efforts to place Blake beyond
the reach of finance are ahistorical, misinformed by a book-publishing rather than print-publishing paradigm:
<q>
Instead of perceiving illuminated printing as a <hi rend="i">reaction against</hi>—or an effort to 
<hi rend="i">reject</hi>—“conventional taste” or the “commercial bourgeoisie,” we need to see in it
Blake’s desire to tap into a market created by the status quo’s demand for drawings, a market actively
supplied by commercial and original printmakers. . . . Like etchings and facsimiles of sketches, they
[Blake’s illuminated prints] move toward the simple and spontaneous, toward drawing, and away from the
overtly skillful performance characteristic of reproductive engraving. But this move away from the
reproductive ideal does not make them “subversive,” except to purists . . .; to collectors of the day,
illuminated prints may have represented Blake at his most fashionable.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n7">7. Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, Joseph Viscomi and Matthew Kirschenbaum, “Standards,
Methods and Objectives in the William Blake Archive,” <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi> 30.3 (1999):
142. The essay is a response to Andrew Cooper and Michael Simpson, “The High-Tech Luddite of Lambeth:
Blake’s Eternal Hacking,” <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi> 30.3 (1999): 125-31. Cooper and Simpson
respond to this response in “Looks Good in Practice, but Does It Work in Theory? Rebooting the Blake
Archive,” <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi> 31.1 (2000): 63-68.</note>
	<note id="n8">8. Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP,
1993) 172.</note></q>
How many copies of his illuminated books Blake produced at any given session “appears to have been
determined by such practical concerns as how much paper the Blakes could afford for each book, as well as by
such material concerns as how many books could be produced per quire of paper” (156). Viscomi also disputes
certain notions of Blake as a technical innovator who sidestepped the trap of alienated labor:
<q>
First, Blake’s control over production was not as complete as imagined, given Mrs. Blake’s assistance in
printing and coloring impressions. Second, even if it were, it would not necessarily be politically
significant or signify a desire to escape the division of labor characteristic of commercial graphics or
letterpress printing. This is because an artist (as opposed to a writer) accustomed to controlling all stages
of labor in the production of original prints . . . is not really varying his practice or controlling more of
his labor by using a new technique or by producing prints with words. (173)
</q>
In short, Blake likely harbored few illusions about either the fallen status of commerce or the impossibility
of escaping it. His focus may rather have been on working within this system to do some good. Accordingly, the
limitations of a Blake-studies technology is not reason to dismiss out of hand its potential for widening and
democratizing Blake’s audience. The editors of the William Blake Archive caution against the presumption
“that purity of principle on intellectual grounds
<pb id="p38-100" n="100"/>
is preferable to accessibility for the general user” (Eaves et al. 141); Karl Kroeber celebrates the Archive
for presenting Blake’s calligraphy in its “<hi rend="i">examinable</hi> detail” and for thereby
facilitating an “intimate, even necessary, interconnection between intensely specialized research and
socially useful teaching at elementary levels.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> I would similarly point to ways in which my department has used technology to improve
access education among underserved communities in rural West Virginia.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n9">9. Karl Kroeber, “The Blake Archive and the Future of Literary Studies,” <hi rend="i">The
Wordsworth Circle</hi> 30.3 (1999): 123, 125.</note>
	<note id="n10">10. See, for example, initiatives of the Center for Writing Excellence, such as the Scott’s
Run Writing Heritage Project, 2002 &lt;http://www.as.wvu.edu/~srsh/&gt;; the Distance Learning Program, 2002
&lt;http://www.as.wvu.edu/english/cwe/distance.html&gt;.</note></p>
          <p>My second concern is the inevitable amount of guesswork involved in fleshing out The Blake
Model’s features. It is one matter to implement Blake’s instructions for, say, the 64,000 each of fairies,
gnomes, genii and nymphs guarding the gates of Golgonooza; the challenge here is one of scale and not
interpretation. It is another thing entirely to extrapolate, say, the body language of Albion, on which the
integrity of The Blake Model depends. I am mindful that my quest for authenticity, to present Blake as he
“really” is, leads me into deeper and deeper layers of conjecture. This is the phenomenon that Jay David
Bolter and Richard Grusin observe in many new media, which
<q>
[l]ike other media since the Renaissance .... oscillate between immediacy and hypermediacy, between
transparency and opacity.... Although each medium promises to reform its predecessors by offering a more
immediate or authentic experience, the promise of reform inevitably leads us to become aware of the new medium
as a medium. Thus, immediacy leads to hypermediacy.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n11">11. Jay David Bolter and Richard Grusin, <hi rend="i">Remediation: Understanding New
Media</hi> (Cambridge, MA: MIT, 2000) 19.</note></q>
This paradox, say Bolter and Grusin, explains the lengths to which high-tech media go to simulate low-tech.
Thus, the graphical user interface (GUI) “remediates” the office desktop; the web page, the tabloid
newspaper; digital graphics, perspectival painting and photography; and virtual reality, film and television
(23,69,115,161). Moreover, “just as there is nothing prior to the act of mediation, there is also a sense in
which all mediation remediates the real” (59).</p>
          <p>Blake himself was an adept remediator. Viscomi points out that Blake’s “facsimile is of the
drawing <hi rend="i">process</hi> and not of an actual drawing or model” (26).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Blake could further immerse himself in the factitiousness of
his process, as when giving directions for executing a “woodcut-on-pewter” or a
“woodcut-on-copper.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Morris
Eaves suggests that such deferral of the “original” may be a therapeutic act:
<q>
blurring may be to sight what distance is to immediate impressions—a way of attaining, paradoxically,
greater clarity and unity. As Gilpin indicated, reproductive engraving may be a beneficial extension of the
process: an additional medium, like another language, affords a new opportunity to generalize and thus improve
the original. An engraving may, as many spokespeople for the trade maintained, have its own special dignity
not as a copy but as a translation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref></q>
Yet bound up with this optimistic view is Eaves’ rather different assertion of Blake’s distrust of
mediation: Blake’s technique, as against the English-school ideas of “Gradual, systemic improvement,” is
“technologically so regressive . . . that it comes close to opposing tools and materials per se.... [it]
seeks to lessen the distortions of time and space by finding the most immediate communication between artist
and viewer and the shortest path between mind and matter” (184). If I may try to unite these two strands in
Eaves, I would argue that while Blake knows something is always lost in the translation from the prototype
that exists in only in his mind, he knows equally that the situation cannot be otherwise. <note id="n12">12.
“By rejecting [Ruthven] Todd’s theory of transferred texts,” Viscomi himself recognizes that he is
remediating “the nineteenth-century theory [of Blake’s technique], in which a ‘preliminary drawing’ of
a plate, or ‘illustrated song,’ is reproduced in ‘facsimile’ by being redrawn directly on the plate
with the same tools used to execute the originals” (26).</note>
	<note id="n13">13. See Robert N. Essick,  <hi rend="i">William Blake: Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton
UP, 1980) 160-61; also Viscomi 68-69.</note>
	<note id="n14">14. Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">The Counter Arts Conspiracy: Art and Industry in the Age of
Blake</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1992) 248.</note></p>
          <p>Indeed, this sense of loss is integral to Blake’s art. Appropriately, his alter ego in the myth
is Los (loss), whose oft-quoted dictum, “I must create a system or be enslav’d by another man’s,”
savors of Urizenic drudgery. Los may not wish to give up his enormous labors, but neither can he transcend the
futility of trafficking in fallen forms within the very bowels of the fiery furnace. He builds the golden city
of art, Golgonooza, in the hope that it may reach back to the Eden from which he himself will be forever
barred; his most redemptive act is a self-immolation in imitation of Christ that has nothing to do with his
art. As if to remind us that visualization is always a concession, Blake frequently frustrates the eye. When
we look to the margins of his page for illustrations of the text, we rarely find what we’re looking for, and
usually we don’t know precisely what we’re looking at. Depictions of the major characters in the myth,
especially in their eternal state, are strikingly difficult to come by. Blake will show us how the zoas
manifest themselves in the fallen language of everyday life but not always show us the zoas themselves.
Corrupted Urizen appears with regularity, redeemed Urizen less often; we see Urthona after he turns into Los,
but seldom before; and does anyone know quite what Luvah or Tharmas looks like? My nagging suspicion that I am
doing violence to Blake’s vision by attempting to represent the unrepresentable—do I lead my students to
believe a lie when I see not through the eye, but too much with the fleshly eye, reducing what is clearly a
symbolical
<pb id="p38-101" n="101"/>
language to Newtonian geometry? does my search for a comprehensive model smack of Sir Joshua Reynolds and his
gang of cunning hired knaves?—this suspicion recapitulates a concern that pervades Blake’s works 
<hi rend="i">qua</hi> works. I am not vain enough to compare myself to Blake or Los, nor an ambitious enough
revisionist to experience an anxiety of influence under their wings. I would suggest, however, that the
oxymoron of a “Blake model” may serve as a very Blakean reminder of the provisional, the transitional
nature of all representation. Accordingly, The Blake Model will seek to remind its user of its difference from
the “original” at every juncture: its visual idiom should evoke Blake’s watercolors wherever possible,
but its overall effect should be schematic rather than Hollywood-verisimilar. The Blake Model is not to be
Blake, any more than the high-resolution scans at the William Blake Archive are Blake, or any more than Fred
Yee’s sketches are Blake as they quickly take on a life of their own, or any more than Blake is identical to
himself, as his texts’ indeterminacy from copy to copy sedulously defies mass production.</p>
          <p>The lattermost point is contested. Viscomi warns that Blakeans who fetishize difference may
overinterpret the variations in the plates and, again, ignore the material realities of the print trade.
<q>
[W]hile designs as initially drawn on plates do differ from the designs as printed, and prints do differ one
from the other, such variations do not signify a rejection of uniformity and all it supposedly represents, nor
do they determine the print’s meaning. The first kind of difference was inherent to a mode of production in
which finishing was conceived as part of the inventive process, and the second kind—for example, the varying
width of a river in a particular image—requires comparisons that Blake could not have expected or intended
his readers to make. (175)
</q>
—since Blake produced his illuminated books not one by one but in small editions or sessions sometimes years
apart. One may still posit an “ideal copy,” if only within each edition or run of an illuminated book
(179). Unfashionable as Viscomi’s unitary vision might appear at first, surely some faith in authorial
intention underlies all Blakeans worth their salt—even so committed a postmodernist as Ron Broglio anchors
his “digging” expeditions in the “minute particulars” of Blake’s imagery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Conversely, Viscomi reminds us, this intentionality, this
theory of identity, requires an historical context and awareness of medium that admits of more difference than
the apostles of difference often allow: variations in the plates, for instance, being “technically
inevitable,” may be “thought of as deliberately allowed to occur,” but do not “signify 
<hi rend="i">deliberate</hi> revision” (175). The historical-material page is a temporal one, subject to
accident, decay, even deformation in spite of its creator’s best efforts. I would like The Blake Model—as
a tool, a supplement rather than a supplantation—to convey some of this temporality not only by virtue of
its inevitable not-being-Blake but by a design that I hope is reminiscent of Blake. To illustrate what I mean,
I will close by showing how The Blake Model would treat one paradox-strewn detail of the myth: the birth of
Los. <note id="n15">15. See Ron Broglio, “Becoming-zoa,” <hi rend="i">Visible Language</hi> 33.2 (1999):
128-49; also, with Marcel O’Gorman and F. William Ruegg, “Digging Transformation in Blake: What the Mole
Knows about the New Millennium,” <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi> 30.3 (1999): 144-54.</note></p>
          <p>Blake gives several different accounts of this event. <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>
introduces Los <hi rend="i">ex nihilo</hi> as the binder of Urizen; in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> he is
the child of Tharmas and Enion; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> identifies him decisively as the fallen form of
Urthona. Yet Tharmas and Urthona are fellow zoas: how can one being descend from another being with whom it is
supposedly co-eternal?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> The answer is
that this relationship makes sense only in the context of just such a descent—the genealogy of the fallen
zoas (which reproduce through, and into, time) and of the successive compositions in which Blake’s myth
evolved (from the atemporal birth of Los in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> to the temporal in the mature
prophecies). I feel it is necessary to convey some of this differential process by building temporality into
the space of The Blake Model. It would be no great matter, for instance, to construct a sphere or object for
each of the zoas/emanations; to program an animation sequence that shows Los/Enitharmon emerging from
Tharmas/Enion, perhaps connected by umbilical cords to show parentage; and to give Los an aspect suggesting
corrupted Urthona, perhaps even have an animation transforming Urthona into Los himself. Once this change is
complete, however, it merely becomes another static tableau, which I feel is inappropriate until the
resurrection of the zoas occurs and time is truly finished. <note id="n16">16. This paradox reappears in Orc,
who is at once the child of Los and Enitharmon and the fallen form of Luvah.</note></p>
          <p>I therefore propose to have Los “flicker” among his different modalities. The effect should
be that of a faulty hotel sign, or of the “insert shots” of sinister images that lace such films as
William Friedkin’s <hi rend="i">The Exorcist</hi> and Stanley Kubrick’s <hi rend="i">The Shining.</hi> As
determined by a random-number generator, Los will sometimes appear tethered to Tharmas/Enion (corresponding to
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>) and sometimes not (corresponding to <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>); sometimes with
Urthona’s beatific visage and sometimes with his own more fearsome one. Three permutations are thus
possible: Urthona as Los tethered to Tharmas/Enion, Urthona as Los untethered to Tharmas/Enion, and Urthona as
himself untethered to Tharmas/Enion (Urthona does not appear as himself tethered to Tharmas/Enion because the
relation between these two forms of the zoas is not genealogical). These “flickers” suggest a Los who
stands both inside and outside the dull rounds of generation; who remains anchored in this world but whose
intimations of the eternal never cease; who encapsulates whatever ways Blake may have changed his mind about
how to structure his myth. By depicting these alternatives not simultaneously but sequentially, the
“flicker”
<pb id="p38-102" n="102"/>
acknowledges the temporal interval across which all representations, whether they be Los’, Blake’s or
mine, fall away from their inspiration, yet it also embraces the restorative possibilities that such an
acknowledgment may open up.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> Indeed,
it is my hope that the temporal condition of The Blake Model may allow for its infinite correctibility within
the community of Blakeans, into whose hands I commend it. <note id="n17">17. In this respect, the flicker may
be thought of in terms of Martin Heidegger’s <hi rend="i">Augenblick</hi>, the twinkling of an eye, the
“moment of vision” in which “nothing can occur; but . . . permits us <hi rend="i">to encounter for the
first time</hi> what can be ‘in a time’ as ready-to-hand or present-at hand” (H338); <hi rend="i">Being
and Time</hi>, trans. John Macquarrie and Edward Robinson (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1962) 388.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
