<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.3.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2004/2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2004-05</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adam Komisaruk</name>
              <name>Thomas Frosch</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>Yoko Ima-Izumi</name>
              <name>Antoine Capet</name>
              <name>David Shaddock</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2004/2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <front>
      <pb id="p38-89-90" n="89-90"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.038.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="333">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
			S<lb/>
			E W<lb/>
			N<lb/>
            Adam Komisaruk Models Blake<lb/>
            VOLUME 38<lb/>
            NUMBER 3<lb/>
            WINTER 2004-05</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-3-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="13" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
				<head>
				  <title>CONTENTS</title>
				</head>
            </cell>
			<cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.3.komisaruk">Introducing The Blake Model</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Adam Komisaruk</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">92</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.3.frosch">Tristanne J. Connolly, <hi rend="i">William Blake
and the Body</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Thomas Frosch</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">102</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.3.wittreich">Alexander S. Gourlay, ed., <hi rend="i">Prophetic
Character: Essays on William Blake in Honor of John E. Grant</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Joseph Wittreich</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">107</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.3.imaizumi">The Program of the International Blake Conference
<hi rend="i">Blake in the Orient</hi> and the Catalogue of a Concurrent Exhibition <hi rend="i">The Reception
of Blake in Japan</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Yoko Ima-Izumi</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">109</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.3.capet">Blake at Work Exhibition, Tate Britain,
London</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Antoine Capet</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">115</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><hi rend="b">Newsletter</hi><lb/>
			Online Features</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="i">119</hi></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><corr type="emend"><ref type="html-issue" issue="bonus.bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Blake
and the Xenoglots”</ref></corr></cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><corr type="emend"><ref type="html-issue" issue="bonus.sklar">A report by Susanne Sklar on a
recent reading of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></ref></corr></cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Poem</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.3.shaddock">Nobodaddy Wakes from His Slumber (After Blake
12)</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By David Shaddock</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">119</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p38-91" n="91"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Adam Komisaruk is assistant professor of English at West Virginia University. He is author of
articles on “Monk” Lewis, Mary Shelley, Thomas Rowlandson, Mary Wollstonecraft, and Lord Byron. His works
in progress include a book-length study of sexuality and the growth of the middle class in British
Romanticism.</p>
        <p>Thomas Frosch is professor of English at Queens College of the City University of New York and
author of <hi rend="i">The Awakening of Albion: The Renovation of the Body in the Poetry of William
Blake</hi>, as well as articles on Wordsworth, Shelley, and Keats.</p>
        <p>Joseph Wittreich is distinguished professor of English at the Graduate Center of the City
University of New York and, most recently, the author of <hi rend="i">Shifting Contexts: Reinterpreting</hi>
Samson Agonistes and co-editor of <hi rend="i">Altering Eyes: New Perspectives on</hi> Samson Agonistes.</p>
        <p>Yoko Ima-Izumi, professor of English and film studies at the University of Tsukuba in Japan, has
been publishing books and essays on William Blake, Romantic literature, and Japanese film. Her recent
publications (in Japanese) include <hi rend="i">Close-Ups of the Woman: Reframing Japanese Cinema</hi> (1997),
<hi rend="i">Representations of the Female Body in English Literature and Film</hi> (1999), 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Revision of the Female</hi> (2001), and <hi rend="i">Film Syntax: Shot Analysis of Japanese
Film</hi> (2004).</p>
        <p>Professor Antoine Capet is head of British studies at the University of Rouen.</p>
        <p>David Shaddock is a poet and psychotherapist. His <hi rend="i">After Blake</hi> won the 
<hi rend="i">Ruah</hi> Power of Poetry prize for a chapbook of spiritual poems.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sjns@mail.rochester.edu<lb/>
TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 Macpherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens GA 30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@english.uga.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham
NG11 8NS U.K.<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the U.S., Canada, and
Mexico require a $15 per volume postal surcharge for surface delivery, or $20 for airmail. Credit card payment
is available. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all
subscription orders and related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English,
University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for
information on issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to
either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451;
Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030. No articles will be
returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a
diskette, or send your article as an attachment to an email message; please number the pages of electronic
submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are usually acceptable.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, American Humanities Index, Arts and
Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover: (clockwise, from top left) Landscape in Ulro with Golgonooza (created in Bryce 3D by Adam
Komisaruk); Cathedron (by Fred Yee); Representation of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 12:54-60, 14:29-30,
associating points of the compass with sensory trajectories (created in Bryce 3D by Adam Komisaruk);
Three-dimensional body scan recreating Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, plate 31 (Brian Corey, model).
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2005 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
	<body>
		<pb id="p38-119" n="119" rend="hidden"/>
	</body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
