<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.4.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jason Whittaker</name>
              <name>Sibylle Erle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <front>
      <pb id="p38-121-122" n="121-122"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.038.04.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="333">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            Robert Essick on Blake in the Marketplace, 2004<lb/>
            VOLUME 38<lb/>
            NUMBER 4<lb/>
            SPRING 2005</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-4-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="7" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
				<head>
				  <title>CONTENTS</title>
				</head>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.4.essick">Blake in the Marketplace, 2004</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Robert N. Essick</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">124</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.4.kroeber">Morris Eaves, ed., <hi rend="i">The Cambridge
Companion to William Blake</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Karl Kroeber</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">151</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.4.whittaker">John B. Pierce, <hi rend="i">The Wond’rous Art:
William Blake and Writing</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Jason Whittaker</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">155</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="38.4.erle">David Weir, <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West: William
Blake and the Oriental Renaissance</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Sibylle Erle</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">157</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-4-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p38-123" n="123"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-4-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Robert N. Essick is professor emeritus at the University of California, Riverside. He currently
holds a three-year appointment as a research scholar at the Huntington Library in San Marino, California.</p>
        <p>Karl Kroeber, Mellon Professor in the Humanities at Columbia University, has just completed a book
on make-believe in film and fiction, and begun a study of children’s literature and environmentalism.</p>
        <p>Jason Whittaker is lecturer in English with media studies at University College Falmouth. He is the
author of <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Myths of Britain</hi> and coauthor of <hi rend="i">Radical Blake:
Influence and Afterlife from 1827</hi>, as well as several books on new media and technologies.</p>
        <p>Sibylle Erle completed her PhD on William Blake in 2004. She is now teaching part time and working
on her first book on Blake and European concepts of physiognomy, with special emphasis on Johann Caspar
Lavater.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-4-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sjns@mail.rochester.edu<lb/>
TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 Macpherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens GA 30602<lb/>
Email: nhilton@english.uga.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham
NG11 8NS U.K.<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-4-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the U.S., Canada, and
Mexico require a $15 per volume postal surcharge for surface delivery, or $20 for airmail. Credit card payment
is available. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all
subscription orders and related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English,
University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for
information on issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to
either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451;
Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030. No articles will be
returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a
diskette, or send your article as an attachment to an email message; please number the pages of electronic
submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are usually acceptable.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, American Humanities Index, Arts and
Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover: “Hinc Terræ Tremor, hinc Motus,” detail. Etching/engraving by Blake’s master, James
Basire. Photo courtesy of Max Reed. See pages 134-35. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2005
Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
