<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>38.4.erle</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Weir, Brahma in the West: William Blake and the Oriental
Renaissance</title>
        <author n="Erle">Sibylle Erle</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">38.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jason Whittaker</name>
              <name>Sibylle Erle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_38">
    <body>
	<pb id="p38-157" n="157"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-38-4-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Weir. <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West: William Blake and the Oriental
Renaissance.</hi> Albany, NY: State University of New York Press, 2003. xiii + 170 PP.; 11 b&amp;w illus.
$21.95/£13.75, paperback.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Sibylle <name>Erle</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Blake has for some time ceased to be the “solitary visionary” with no “definite contacts
with Hindus texts” depicted in Raymond Schwab’s <hi rend="i">Le Renaissance oriental</hi> (1950, English
trans. 1984).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">1</ref> Thanks now to David
Weir, the source texts and also those who possibly mediated Hindu myths to Blake have been further identified.
More importantly, <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West</hi> puts Blake’s references to Hinduism, long since
brought to our attention through the scholarly intuition of S. Foster Damon, Northrop Frye, and Kathleen
Raine, into their contemporary discourses (45ff). Weir’s book is a fresh attempt at interpreting the dynamic
of Blake’s Zoa and Emanation constellations. <note id="n11">1. Raymond Schwab, <hi rend="i">The Oriental
Renaissance: Europe’s Rediscovery of India and the East, 1680-1880</hi>, trans. Gene Patterson-Black and
<corr type="emend">Victor Reinking</corr> (New York: Columbia UP, 1984) 97.</note></p>
          <pb id="p38-158" n="158"/>
          <p>While delineating the scholarly ambitions and different agendas of those who wrote on Hinduism in
the late eighteenth century, Weir argues that Blake was not only highly sensitive but also very receptive to
the political implications of the Oriental Renaissance. <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West</hi> is essentially an
attempt to historicize Blake’s engagement with the knowledge of Hinduism potentially available to him at the
time. Although the links between Blake and some of the protagonists of the Oriental Renaissance are tentative,
information about India was easy to come by. While Blake refers to Charles Wilkins as late as 1809, Weir
documents that the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> discussed the translation of Hindu myths as early as
1790 (91). He stresses further that the comparative studies of Eastern religion “found a ready audience
among members of London’s dissenting community” (87). Casting Blake as a fervent reader of the radical
press and firmly establishing him within the radical and dissenting circle of Joseph Johnson, Weir points out
that Blake’s perception of Hinduism was biased towards radicalism from the very beginning. It was through
Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> that Blake was encouraged to equate political content with
mythological form. This approach makes Weir a stimulating read.</p>
          <p>In Britain, Indian politics were perceived as part of the expansion of the Empire. With the India
Act of 1784—an attempt to assume responsibility and regulate the administration of India and its
inhabitants—the Pitt government made clear its intention to curb the economic power of the East India
Company. Though in <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West</hi> we learn little about global war, British imperialism,
colonial rule, or even the role of the Asiatic Society of Bengal, Weir’s discussion of the complex and
complicated situation of Indian politics and the British constructs of the Orient is often broad and general,
and his referencing of Blake’s potentially India-inspired metaphors is meticulous. When it comes to
Blake’s poem “The Tyger,” Weir takes an imaginative leap to India: encouraged by the power vacuum left
by the French Revolution, the Muslim leader Tipu Sultan—self-declared “Citizen Tipu”—began to attack
the British. Even though he was overwhelmed by General Munro in
1792, a different kind of defeat was noted by the British public when it became known that the general’s son
had been killed by an Indian tiger-in the same year. Weir’s neat conclusion is that “The Tyger” was not
only written in response to young Munro’s death, but that its tiger was also partly Indian (20).</p>
          <p>Within Britain the arguments about empire and revolution centered around Edmund Burke, who
condemned the French Revolution and criticized the former Governor General of Bengal, Warren Hastings
(1732-1818). Whereas Burke’s polemic campaign against Hastings resulted in a conservative policy success,
the English Jacobins began to see both the Governor General and India as victims of the Pitt government (25).
The possible connection between Blake and Hastings is Charles Wilkins’s 1785 translation of the 
<hi rend="i">Bhagavad Gita.</hi> Hastings not only supported this translation, but also wrote its preface and
claimed that Hindu faith was a variation on Christian doctrine. Weir writes: “there are parts of
Hastings’s account of the <hi rend="i">Gita</hi> that relate in general terms to theological elements in
Blake’s evolving mythology”(94).</p>
          <p>By the late eighteenth century works on Hinduism, written by the linguist and first president of
the Asiatic Society of Bengal Sir William Jones (1746-94), were widely available. According to Weir, Jones’s
“On the Gods of Greece, Italy, and India,” reviewed by Henry Fuseli for the <hi rend="i">Analytical
Review</hi> in 1790, may in particular have encouraged Blake to insist on the antiquity of the Eastern faith
when challenging the authority of the Western church in his <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
(often dated 1790-93). Indeed, most of the mythographic studies of the 1790s were either published by Johnson
or reviewed and discussed in the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> (46). The arguments of these
works—often inherently theological and sometimes anti-French—are often closely intertwined, which leads
Weir to conclude that Blake was attracted to India via Jones and his followers rather than through Joseph
Bryant’s <hi rend="i">A New System, or, An Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi> (1774-76)—an edition for
which Blake had made engravings during his apprenticeship to James Basire. Kathleen Raine in 
<hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> (1969) concedes that Blake may have been familiar with Jones and Wilkins,
and
<pb id="p38-159" n="159"/>
then emphasizes what she had identified as the “link between Blake’s philosophical studies of Berkeley and
the mythology of the veiled goddess.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n12">2. Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, 2 vols. (London: Routledge &amp;
Kegan Paul, 1969) II: 177.</note></p>
          <p>Weir analyzes “the Mundane Egg” and the “Veil of Vala” in relation to Thomas Maurice’s
<hi rend="i">The History of Hindustan</hi> (1796-98) and William Jones’s “A Hymn to Narayena” (1785).
Blake’s use of the spider in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is referenced to Joseph Priestley’s 
<hi rend="i">A Comparison of the Institutions of Moses with Those of the Hindoos and other Ancient Nations</hi>
(1799), and the attack on priestcraft is glossed with William Julius Mickle’s “Enquiry into the Religious
Tenets and Philosophy of the Brahmins” (1798). Weir also identifies key visual quotations in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and traces them back to Edward Moor’s <hi rend="i">The Hindu Pantheon</hi> (1810),
pointing out that Moor’s engraver, Moses Haughton, lived with Fuseli (75).</p>
          <p>It is interesting to see how Weir positions himself with respect to the research undertaken into
Blake’s theology—beginning with J. G. Davies’s <hi rend="i">The Theology of William Blake</hi> (1948),
extensively revised by Jon Mee and E. P. Thompson in the early 1990s, and more recently amended in an attempt
to identify Blake’s theology with a specific religious alignment of 1790’s dissent. Weir makes references
to E. P. Thompson’s discussion of Muggletonianism and A. D. Nuttall’s of Gnosticism, but seems strangely
unaware of Keri Davies’s work, which gives compelling evidence that Thompson was wrong in linking Blake to
the Muggletonians.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">3</ref> Indeed, how can
Weir assume that Thompson as a Marxist historian would discuss religion on its own terms? Ideally, Weir ought
to have drawn on a wider range of authorities on eighteenth-century dissent and antinomianism before plunging
himself—and trying to pull his readers after him—into a deep discussion of Blake’s theology. One example
of Weir’s rushed shortcuts is his suggestion that the Behmenists constitute a sect (127). <note id="n13">3.
Keri Davies, “William Blake’s Mother: A New Identification,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 33.2 (fall 1999): 36-50.</note></p>
          <p>Weir’s neoplatonist argument is important. He essentially reintroduces Blake as a neoplatonist
while presenting him as a combination of radial writer and mystic poet. Blake’s link to neoplatonism in the
wake of its “revival” (104) is usually based on his acquaintance with the Plato translator Thomas Taylor.
In <hi rend="i">Witness against the Beast</hi> (1993), E. P Thompson argued that this connection was not very
helpful. Interestingly, while Thompson in his revision of G. M. Harper’s <hi rend="i">The Neoplatonism of
William Blake</hi> (1961) tries to separate interpretation from biographical fact, Weir seems to be doing the
reverse. He argues that next to the antinomian under-current with which Hindu myths were offered to their late
eighteenth-century audience, there also existed a tendency to make Hinduism neoplatonist: “the antinomian
points of Wilkin’s <hi rend="i">Gita</hi> have a kind of theological complement in William Jones’s
Neoplatonic explanations of the Hindu system” (104). The link to Blake is obviously the 
<hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi>, which disseminated the combination of antinomian mythography with
neoplatonist belief made explicit in Jones’s “On the Gods of Greece, Italy and India.” Weir stresses
that neoplatonism was an integral part of dissenting theology. Consequently, Blake “set antinomianism and
Neoplatonism in a reciprocal theological relationship and made them reinforce one another” (105).
Neoplatonism in Blake has most notably been discussed by both Kathleen Raine and E. P. Thompson. While Raine
insisted on Blake’s gradual and selective absorption of hermetic thought, Thompson rejected this stance to
differentiate between an early exposure to radical-dissenting interpretations of the Bible—in particular,
those proposed by Behmenists and Philadelphians—and a later, mature engagement with the sources themselves.
In the end it is not entirely clear how Weir resolves the contradictions between Raine and Thompson.
Regrettable also is that Weir does not acknowledge the pioneering work of Piloo Nanavutty. She identified a
number of available publications on India as well as of Indian texts and started looking for traces of Hindu
thought in Blake long before Raine.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n14">4. Piloo Nanavutty, “William Blake and the Hindu Creation Myths,” <hi rend="i">The Divine
Vision: Studies in the Poetry and Art of William Blake</hi>, ed. Vivian de Sola Pinto (London: Victor Gollancz
P, 1957) 163-82.</note></p>
          <p>In relation to the scholarly interest taken in Blake’s theology and politics in the 1790s, this
study of Blake not only revises—or rather reopens—the discussion on Blake’s awareness of Eastern
religion, but also argues convincingly for Blake’s participation in the Oriental Renaissance. 
<hi rend="i">Brahma in the West</hi> fits in well with the recent developments in Blake studies. It highlights the
possible interpenetration of Blake’s creative mythography and the late eighteenth-century Westernized
version of Hinduism and thus gives a highly useful description of the interaction between religion, society
and cultural change.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
