<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.1.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">William Blake’s A Pastoral Figure: Some Newly Revealed Verso Sketches</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Dr. David Groves</name>
              <name>Howard Jacobson</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-1-0007">
        <pb id="p39-44" n="44"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake’s <hi rend="i">A Pastoral Figure</hi>: Some Newly Revealed
Verso Sketches</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In December 1993 I acquired a leaf of pencil sketches by Blake titled <hi rend="i">A Pastoral
Figure and Other Sketches</hi> (illus. 1).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">1</ref> The drawing was for many years in the collection of W. Graham Robertson and appeared as
lot 74 (with 2 other works) in the legendary auction of his Blake collection at Christie’s in London, 22
July 1949. After passing through the hands of at least two dealers, the sheet of studies was acquired by the
American librarian and bibliographer Edwin Wolf 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi>. After his death in 1991, the drawing
was inherited by one of his sons, who placed it for sale with the dealer Nicholas W. Lott, from whom I
purchased the leaf. Lott told me that he had removed the badly stained drawing from its old, acidic mat and
found more pencil sketches on the verso. Several of these were almost invisible before I cleaned the leaf. The
purpose of this brief essay is to reproduce the heretofore unpublished verso sketches (illus. 2), describe
them, and suggest some ways they can be situated within Blake’s career as an artist and poet. 
<note id="n69">1. Number 81, recto only, in Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1981), hereafter cited as “Butlin” followed by entry number. Butlin
describes the paper as “grey,” but cleaning the sheet revealed it to be a typical off-white
eighteenth-century paper.</note></p>
          <p>The recto drawings, to which the verso sketches are related, are dominated by a young male seated
under a tree. A wavy line below his feet might be the bank of a stream; behind the man and to the right is a
distant mountain. He appears to be nude except for a cloak visible below and to the left of his right elbow, a
line at his left wrist that suggests a cuff, and the gently curving lines defining his left upper-arm that
hint at a cloth sleeve. The diagonal line across his chest may be a string holding the cloak. His posture,
with his left hand raised to his face, vaguely hints at one of the traditional <hi rend="i">pathos
formulae</hi> for melancholy. However, a loop about 1 cm. above this hand, and the shape of the hand itself,
suggest that there may be something—possibly a staff with a knob at its upper termination—held in his left
hand. All but the top of the staff is either left unexecuted or hidden behind the man. The most significant
object, however, is the light outline of a lyre held by the figure’s right hand and extending between his
legs. He is not only a “pastoral figure,” as the title indicates, but a musician/poet. Five versions of
this figure, one of whom is clearly holding a staff, appear on the verso of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job, His
Wife and His Friends: The Complaint of Job</hi>, since 1940 in the Tate Collection (Butlin #162 verso, dated
to c. 1785). Four of these figures, like the main figure on the recto of <hi rend="i">A Pastoral Figure and
Other Sketches</hi>, appear to be nude or only partly clothed. The largest figure, however, bears an arc below
his neck that indicates a shirt or gown. Blake was clearly interested in developing the representation of a
pastoral lyricist in the mid-1780s.</p>
          <p>The remaining figures on the recto include two versions of a recumbent male, perhaps wearing a
brimless hat, sideways along the right margin; a third version of this same figure, sideways near the left
margin; and two standing figures (the lower barely indicated), sideways above the bottom margin. The most
interesting of the smaller sketches is once again a seated figure, upside down just above the bottom margin.
He holds a large, triangular harp of the sort associated with the bard, not the lyric poet.</p>
          <p>Several of the previously unpublished verso sketches (illus. 2) continue themes and types known
from the recto. All the verso drawings were probably executed at about the same time as the recto images, in
the early- to mid-1780s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">2</ref> Of the three
largest figures, the one on the left would appear to be a side view of the pastoral figure dominating the
recto. He sits under a tree and may be holding a lyre on his lap. The lightly sketched lines inhibit a clear
identification of other features. The next, more darkly drawn figure to the right is gowned. The wide strap
extending diagonally across his chest and left hip recalls the slenderer string over the chest of the major
figure on the recto. He holds two objects, possibly the upper reaches of a triangular harp in the right hand
and a staff in the left. The rightmost major figure is a further development of the central standing figure.
He is similarly gowned, wears a cape that extends below the back of his legs, and now holds the large harp in
both hands. He is probably playing the instrument. Some lightly drawn vertical lines right of his left
shoulder may be the trunks of trees or the columns of a portico; a wavy line below his feet and three
verticals right of his left leg also hint at a landscape. <note id="n70">2. I suspect that Butlin’s dating
of the recto to c. 1785 represents the upper end of the date range.</note></p>
          <p>The smaller verso designs include a standing figure drawn sideways upper right, perhaps a female
wearing a wimple or hood and possibly holding, and looking down toward, a child in her right arm; a standing
figure among trees lower right, with an outline frame drawn around the composition; and three very sketchy
figures drawn sideways lower left. The hooded figure may be a further development of the fullfrontal standing
figure drawn sideways in the lower half of the recto.</p>
          <p>Motifs evocative of the lyric/pastoral on the one hand, and the bardic/epic on the other, are the
most significant images on both recto and verso. The former recalls the classical inheritance of
eighteenth-century poetry. The latter might suggest the Homeric epic, but the decidedly non-Greek shape of the
harp implies a nativist British tradition harkening back to the Welsh bards and Ossian.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">3</ref> These two genres and their
            <pb id="p39-45" n="45"/>
			<figure n="BUT81.1.1r.PD" rend="file" width="592" height="1000">
				<figTranscr>William Blake<lb/>
				vouched by Frederick Tatham</figTranscr>
				<head>1. <hi rend="i">A Pastoral Figure and Other Sketches</hi>, recto.</head>
				<figDesc>Pencil on sheet 31.0 × 18.4 cm. Inscribed in now-faded brown ink, lower left, “William Blake /
vouched by Frederick Tatham.” Laid paper with a crown and “GR” watermark. Butlin #81, dated to c. 1785.
Collection of Robert N. Essick.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<pb id="p39-46" n="46"/>
			<figure n="BUT81.1.1v.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="536">
				<head>2. <hi rend="i">A Pastoral Figure and Other Sketches</hi>, verso drawings in pencil.</head>
				<figDesc>See illus. 1 for details. Not previously published.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<pb id="p39-47" n="47"/>
attendant cultural associations also resonate through Blake’s earliest poems, published as 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> in 1783. He laments the attenuated state of both traditions. “The shepherd
leaves his mellow pipe” in “Gwin, King of Norway,” while “the languid strings do scarcely move” for
the “bards of old” in “To the Muses.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">4</ref> Here and elsewhere in Blake’s poems and designs, the shepherd’s pipe is a more common
motif than the lyre, but carries much the same meaning. The specifically British associations of the harp are
indicated in “A War Song to Englishmen,” in which King “Alfred shall smile, and make his harp rejoice”
(E 440). <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, etched and first printed in 1789, also indicates the
complementary differences between pastoral musician and bard. The “Introduction” to the anthology (E 7),
coupled with the frontispiece directly illustrating that poem, announces a revivified lyricism, while “The
Voice of the Ancient Bard” (E 31-32) reaches toward an epic vision that encompasses experience as well as
innocence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">5</ref> In the design above the
text, the bard strums a triangular harp even larger than the one played by his younger counterpart in the
verso sketch (illus. 2). Poised chronologically between <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, the drawings reproduced here show Blake experimenting with visual
representations of the two poetical modes, and the states of consciousness they embody, in which he worked
throughout most of his career. <note id="n71">3. John Flaxman’s first outline design to the 
<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> pictures the Greek harp, or <hi rend="i">cithara</hi>, traditionally associated with
classical epic. See <hi rend="i">The Iliad of Homer Engraved by Thomas Piroli from the Compositions of John
Flaxman Sculptor</hi> (Rome: [Piroli], 1793). For some of Blake’s major pictures of the large triangular
Celtic or Welsh harp, see his illustrations to Thomas Gray’s “The Bard” (Butlin #335.53) and “The
Triumphs of Owen” (Butlin #335.89), and the tempera painting and recto/verso drawings of <hi rend="i">The
Bard, from Gray</hi> (Butlin #655-56). Homer holds a large lyre in Blake’s first design to Gray’s “The
Progress of Poesy” (Butlin #335.41). In Ireland, Scotland, and Wales, the Celtic harp became a symbol of
national independence in the late eighteenth century; see Katie Trumpener, <hi rend="i">Bardic
Nationalism</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1997) 3-34. For Blake’s possible allusions to the Irish harp and
its attendant politics in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, see Catherine L. McClenahan, “Blake’s Erin, the
United Irish, and ‘Sexual Machines,’” in <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William Blake in
Honor of John E. Grant</hi>, ed. Alexander Gourlay (West Cornwall, CT: Locust Hill P, 2002) 165-67.</note>
	<note id="n72">4. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman,
newly revised edition (New York: Doubleday, 1988) 417-18, hereafter cited as “E” followed by page number.
According to the prefatory “Advertisement” to <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (E 846), the poems were
composed well before 1783, roughly 1770-78.</note>
	<note id="n73">5. “The Voice of the Ancient Bard” was composed and etched no later than 1789 and was
included in most separate copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> In later copies of the combined 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, printed 1818-27, Blake moved “The Voice of the Ancient
Bard” to the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> section, which the poem anticipates. The “Bard,” who
“Present, Past, &amp; Future sees,” is invoked in the “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
(E 18). For printing dates, see the chart in Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>
(Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993) 376-81.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
