<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
2004</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
		<author n="Sato">Hikari Sato</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Dr. David Groves</name>
              <name>Howard Jacobson</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
    <pb id="p39-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
2004</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor><lb/>
		  With the Assistance of <docAuthor>Hikari <name>Sato</name></docAuthor> for Japanese publications</byline>
          <div3>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake Publications and Discoveries in 2004</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The most massive and impressive scholarly publishing event of 2004 was the appearance of the
revised <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>, entitled the <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of
National Biography</hi>, in Association with the British Academy, from the Earliest Times to the Year 2000,
ed. H. C. G. Matthew and Brian Harrison (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004), hard copy and online, in 61
volumes all published simultaneously on 23 September 2004. Most of the hundred-some biographies I looked at
were newly written, not merely revisions of those in the <hi rend="i">DNB.</hi></p>
              <p>I have stalked individuals who, though often very minor, played a significant role in the
life of William Blake as they appear first in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, Second Edition (2004) and then
in the <hi rend="i">ODNB.</hi></p>
              <p>Most of those in the <hi rend="i">ODNB</hi> earned their place because they made a mark in
the great world—generals, politicians, bankers, and the like. It is telling that there is a standard section
for wealth at death. Of those connected with Blake, a disproportionate number are men of power and influence,
his patrons, rather than mere friends or fellow artists and engravers.</p>
              <p>The <hi rend="i">ODNB</hi> is especially good on archives.</p>
              <p>The <hi rend="i">ODNB</hi> omits separate entries on Elizabeth Aders (b. 1785), patroness of
Blake, and her husband Charles; Thomas Armitage (1722-51), haberdasher, and his wife Catherine who remarried
after his death and became the poet’s mother; Robert Balmanno (1780-1860), collector; James Blake, the
poet’s grandfather; James Blake, the poet’s father; James Blake, the poet’s brother; Robert Blake, the
poet’s brother; Stephen Blake, haberdasher with the Blake firm in 1783-84 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] xxxi,
735 and fn.); Rebekah Bliss, collector (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 65-66, 444 and fn., 844); Boucher, natal
family of Blake’s wife; William Brereton, JP at Blake’s 1803 trial (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 167); Thomas
Butts (1757-1845), clerk, Blake’s patron; Edward John and James H. Chance, Linnell’s nephews and
assistants (see, e.g., <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 433 and fn.); Private John Cock, dragoon, perjured supporter
of the allegation of sedition against Blake in August 1803; Richard Dally, Blake’s Chichester solicitor 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 175, 185fn.); Maria Denman, sister-in-law of John Flaxman, friend of Blake; Sir Edward
Denny, patron of Blake; Mrs. Enoch, Blake’s neighbor in South Molton Street (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 750);
James Ferguson (1791-1871), artist, patron of Blake’s widow (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 481fn., 496 and fn.,
497); John Giles, Samuel Palmer’s cousin, disciple of Blake (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 404); Samuel
Greatheed, patron of Blake; Dr. William Guy, Hayley’s physician (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 126, 183); Joseph
Hogarth (fl. 1860-78), print dealer; Major George Hulton, dragoon, who preferred charges of sedition against
Blake in 1803 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 164-67); Elizabeth Iremonger, collector (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 298
and fn., 299, 601fn.); Joan Linnell Ivimy, custodian of the Linnell family papers; Richard Charles Jackson
(1851-1923), wishful collector of Blake (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 320fn., 745fn., 747fn., 877); James Lahee,
copperplate printer of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1826); James Linnell, framemaker, father of John;
Herschel M. Margoliouth, scholar; Edward Garrard Marsh (1783-1862), poet, friend of Blake; Rev. Anthony
Stephen Mathew (1733-1824), patron of Blake, and his wife Harriet and son Henry; John Peachey (1752-1830), JP
at Blake’s trials in 1803 and 1804 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 167, 179); R. Pontifex, printseller 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 345fn., 823); Henrietta Poole (d. 1827), friend of Hayley and Blake; John Quantock
(1740-1820), JP at Blake’s trials in 1803 and 1804; William Saunders, picture dealer (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
[2] 178 and fn., 188, 194); Private John Scholfield (Scolfield), perjured accuser of Blake of sedition; Joseph
Seagrave, Chichester printer, defender of Blake; Thomas Siv[e]wright, of Meggetland, Blake collector 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 344fn., 864); John Clark Strange (b. 1826), corn chandler, biographer of Blake 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 707-32); Arthur Tatham (1809-74), brother of Frederick; Frederick Tatham (1805-78),
artist, biographer of Blake (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 661-91); Rev. Joseph Thomas, rector of Epsom, Blake’s
patron; and James Vine, patron of Blake.</p>
              <p>Most of these omitted individuals are pretty minor, but then some pretty minor characters are
included in the <hi rend="i">ODNB</hi>, such as Thomas Hayley (1780-1800), who was merely the natural son of
Thomas Hayley and who did not even outlive his apprenticeship, and Catherine Blake (1762-1831), who is
important to no one but William Blake and his admirers. She is doubtless included to fulfill the mandate of
including more women than in the <hi rend="i">DNB.</hi> The entries which I found containing new information
include: Blake’s biographer Allan Cunningham, manuscript “lives of painters and related corresp.”
including his life of Blake (1830) in the National Library of Scotland (see the entry in Part VI); Blake’s
friend and patron Ozias Humphry, catalogue of his art collection (which once included 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> [H], <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> [O], Large Book of Designs [A], <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> [H], and Small Book of Designs [A]) in the British Library, Add. MS 49682;<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Blake’s reluctant patron Charles Henry
Bellenden Ker, who was baptized 18 February 1787 (not 1785? as in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 302-03); Blake’s
printshop
<pb id="p39-5" n="5"/>
partner James Parker, who was born in 1757, not in 1750 as in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) and 
<hi rend="i">DNB</hi>; and Blake’s lawyer Samuel Rose, whose correspondence is in Glasgow University Library.
<note id="n1">1. However, I am told by Susanne Sklar that the document is a kind of commonplace book by
Humphry’s natural son William Upcott, with some notes on his collection but no reference to
Blake.</note></p>
              <p>The <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi> is an immense and immensely
valuable resource.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Writings</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Only a few score letters by Blake are known, and for a few letters no more is yet known than
the date or the recipient. The last new Blake letter discovered was that of 1 September 1800 acquired by
Robert N. Essick &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)&gt;.</p>
              <p>Consequently the appearance of a new Blake letter, entirely without fanfare, not to say
ballyhoo and hullabaloo, is rare and welcome. A previously unknown letter entered the archives of the
bookseller John Murray at an unknown date in the nineteenth century, alone and palely loitering, and was
exhibited quietly at the exhibition of illustrations of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> at Dove Cottage in
2004—so quietly that even distinguished Blake scholars did not register that the letter was previously
unknown.</p>
              <p>This letter, with its postmark of 25 November 1825, indicates the makeshift conditions of
Blake’s printing, at least in his last years, setting up his press in the kitchen of his landlord and
neighbor Henry Banes. The work to be printed may be his great series for the Book of Job, the earliest
professional proofs of which were pulled on 4-5 March 1825, first by Dixon and then by Lahee. The printer
referred to in the text may well be James Lahee; see the appendix here.</p>
              <p>The letter also contains the only known reference in Blake’s writings to his brother-in-law
Henry Banes, the husband of his wife’s sister Sarah. The relationship of Henry Banes and William Blake was
clearly a friendly one, if Banes was willing to give up his kitchen, perhaps for an indefinite time, for
Blake’s printing.</p>
              <p>How many more such Blake treasures remain to be discovered in long-neglected archives and
attics? And how grateful we should be when they do finally reach a wider public.</p>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">No News Is Bad News</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>In the last year or so, several important works by Blake peered shyly from the boskage, and
then, when a hue and cry arose, disappeared without leaving a forwarding address. A previously unrecorded copy
of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (Q?), <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (N), and
nineteen watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> appeared only long enough to be identified and then
withdrew, like the Cheshire Cat. Of these, the Blair designs disappeared for 165 years (1836-2001) and
surfaced briefly in 2001, only to disappear in 2004 into a bank vault where they are invisible to enquirers
who are not heavy in the purse. <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> was assessed by a bookseller and then
disappeared once more. And <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (N), never seen and described
by a Blake scholar and not confidently traced since 1921, did not appear when its mate <hi rend="i">The First
Book of Urizen</hi> (E) in the Whitney collection was sold in 1999 for a world record price for a book. Then
in the summer of 2004 <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> was brought off the street to Swann Galleries in New York and
was to be offered for auction, until the Whitney family got wind of the affair and tied the book up with legal
proceedings. As a consequence, <hi rend="i">none</hi> of these works is visible to Blake scholars or lovers,
and indeed even their ownership is unknown or obscure.</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Art</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Information about Blake’s art was not greatly enriched in 2004, aside from the sale of his
great color print of “The Good and Evil Angels Struggling for Possession of a Child” for $3,928,000, the
highest price ever paid for a print by Blake—or by anyone else. More characteristic of the year were the
records of <hi rend="i">Coloured Prints by William Blake: 15 Pictorial Cards</hi> (British Museum, 1927) and
<hi rend="i">Blake: 16 Art Stickers</hi> (Dover, 2003).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Commercial Engravings</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Genuine and Complete Works of Flavius Josephus</hi>, for which Blake
engraved some plates, was issued with an extraordinary variety of undated title pages (?1785-?1800), though
the text and prints do not vary significantly. Nine versions of the title page are known, and more seem to
appear almost yearly. No satisfactory explanation has yet been devised to account for this variety. But at
least we can now firmly date Kimpton’s <hi rend="i">History of the Holy Bible</hi>, in which the Josephus
plates first appeared, on the basis of a newly discovered prospectus which announced the first of the 60
numbers for 7 April 1781.</p>
              <p>Drawings and proofs for Allen, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi> (1798), Flaxman, 
<hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> (1817), and [Gough], <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments</hi> (1786) are newly recorded
here. And the earliest repetition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) has
been discovered in the tiny <hi rend="i">English Version of the Polyglott Bible</hi> [ed. Thomas Chevalier]
(Buffalo [New York], 1836) found, acquired, and reported by Robert N. Essick.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake Catalogues</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>An exhibition of the Tate’s Blakes arranged by Robin Hamlyn and Joyce Townsend in May 2004
had no separate catalogue, but the captions, from their book on Blake as an artistic craftsman, were
remarkably original and illuminating.</p>
              <p>An exhibition more difficult of access but more assiduously publicized was of the
illustrators of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> held by the Wordsworth Trust at Dove Cottage, Grasmere. The
most memorable pictures, always commented on in the many puffs and reviews, were Blake’s watercolors from
the Huntington, but the most important significance of the exhibition for Blake students was its quiet
inclusion of a previously unknown Blake letter to John Linnell (see appendix here).</p>
              <p>A tiny exhibition without catalogue with a few plates from <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1826) was
held at the St. Louis Art Museum.</p>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p39-6" n="6"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Books Owned by Blake the Poet</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>A small volume containing Dryden’s <hi rend="i">Annus Mirabilis</hi> (1668), [Jean Claude],
<hi rend="i">An Account of the Persecutions and Oppressions of the French Protestants</hi> (1686), and Anon.,
<hi rend="i">The Life &amp; Death of that Pious . . . Minister of the Gospel, Mr. Richard Baxter</hi> (1692)
is inscribed “William Blake” in a hand like the poet’s, and his admiration for Dryden and the probable
Huguenot connections of his wife Catherine Boucher and his master James Basire mean that the texts would have
been of obvious interest to him. It was sold at auction in 2004 to a private collector.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Scholarship and Criticism</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Books</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>This summary of discoveries and publications on Blake in 2004 covers 40 books on Blake (9
of them editions, 6 catalogues), 139 essays, 6 dissertations, and 79 reviews. Most of course are in English,
but 36 are in other languages, including Dutch (2), French (3), German (2), Italian (3, plus 
<hi rend="i">Italian Studies</hi>), Japanese (15, including 2 editions and an essay in English in a Japanese
publication), Korean (6), Spanish (4, including 3 editions), and Swedish (1, plus a book in English published
in Sweden). In comparison, last year’s checklist documented 50 books (8 of them catalogues, 17 editions),
205 essays, and 47 reviews.</p>
                <p>The most important Blake discovery published in 2004 was the fact that Blake’s mother
Catherine and her first husband Thomas Armitage joined the Moravian Church in 1750. This in turn led to facts
about her birthplace in Walkeringham, Nottinghamshire, about her family, and about a previously unknown son of
the Armitages named Thomas who died at the age of one in 1751. The Armitages were members of the Moravian
Church only briefly, in 1750-51, for both Thomas Armitages, father and son, died in 1751, and when Catherine
Armitage “Became a Widow . . . [she] left the Congregation.” She may have left the congregation because
she had married outside the Moravian community, and there is no evidence that James Blake was a Moravian. All
this gives a firm context to Crabb Robinson’s statement that “Blake does not belong by birth to the
established church, but to a dissenting community” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 599), though it is still
unclear what influence the Moravians had upon the poet or indeed whether his mother ever talked about them. It
would be agreeable to think that she sang to her children the Moravian hymm which she quoted in her
application to join the church:
<q>
Here let me drink for ever drink<lb/>
nor never once depart<lb/>
for what I tast makes me to cry<lb/>
fix at this Spring My heart<lb/>
Dear Savour thou hast seen how oft<lb/>
I’ve turnd away from thee<lb/>
O let thy work renewd to day<lb/>
Remain eternally
</q></p>
                <p>The documentary evidence that Catherine Armitage and her husband joined the Moravian Church
was discovered by Marsha Keith Schuchard and displayed by her and Keri Davies in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.1
(2004): 36-43, and at greater length in Keri Davies’ Surrey doctoral dissertation (2003). This is one of the
most remarkable and illuminating dissertations on Blake which has appeared since Bo Lindberg’s 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi> (1973), and Davies now has a fellowship to
continue his researches on the Nottinghamshire and Moravian contexts of Catherine Blake, which promises great
things for the future.</p>
                <p>Two of the most sensational aspects of Moravian worship were the loving emphasis upon
Christ’s “warm hot jowcy wounds” and the connection between religious communion and sexual intercourse,
which was called fellowship. The enthusiasm with which the twenty-first century press greeted this last
feature may be imagined.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n2">2. See the entry for Martin Wainwright in Part VI.</note></p>
                <p>Three of the books reported here will throw long shadows on the world of Blake
scholarship.</p>
                <p>The first is Morton Paley’s <hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening: The Last Works of
William Blake</hi> (2003), which is a fitting culmination both for the works of William Blake and for the
critical career of Morton Paley. His criticism now covers all Blake’s creations, with <hi rend="i">Energy
and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (1970) and <hi rend="i">The
Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem (1983), and <hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening</hi>
is perhaps the best of them—comprehensive, novel, and illuminating on every page. For instance, Paley points
out that in <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> Eve faints by Abel’s grave, but there is no grave or burial
of Abel in Genesis or in Byron’s <hi rend="i">Cain.</hi> However, both appear in Gessner’s 
<hi rend="i">Death of Abel.</hi> He demonstrates, with measurements, that when Blake’s woodcuts for Virgil were
cut down the designs lost up to 40% of their area, and he shows conclusively that the cryptic and fascinating
engraving always called “Laocoön” (a term not used for it by Blake) should really be identified as
“<rtl>יה</rtl> &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n3">3. The important essay on “<rtl>יה</rtl> &amp; his two Sons” first appeared in 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> (2002).</note></p>
                <p>The second epochal book recorded here is the collection of remarkably fine and original
essays edited by Joyce H. Townsend called <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work</hi> (2003), dealing
with the physical materials of Blake’s visual art. It is full of fascinating matter. How many of us could
have said that there is no surviving original frame for any of Blake’s pictures? Robin Hamlyn records, with
diagrams, Blake’s painting rooms; Joyce Townsend herself reproduces almost all the watercolor pigments
commercially available in Blake’s time; Peter Bower adds enormously to the information available about the
paper Blake used;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> and elsewhere there
is evidence of the specific colorman whose products Blake used—R. Davy of 16 Wardour Street (131, 145)—and
a palette in the Victoria and Albert Museum which Blake may have owned about 1820
<pb id="p39-7" n="7"/>
(181). The photographs reproduced are wonderfully novel and illuminating. This is an extraordinarily original
and valuable book. <note id="n4">4. For instance, “there are some forty different papers, several of which
were used by Blake, watermarked 1794 / J WHATMAN” (55), though in records of Blake’s watermarks these
forty different watermarks are not distinguished from one another (e.g., <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
71-73).</note></p>
                <p>The third of the books which is likely to have long influence is G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> Second Edition: Documents (1714-1841) Concerning the Life of William Blake
(1757-1827) and His Family, Incorporating <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), <hi rend="i">Blake Records
Supplement</hi> (1988), and Extensive Discoveries since 1988 (2004). In comparison with the works it
incorporates:
<table rows="4" cols="4"><row>
	<cell/>
	<cell>Preliminaries</cell>
	<cell>Text</cell>
	<cell>Reproductions</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969)</cell>
	<cell>xxviii</cell>
	<cell>678</cell>
	<cell>71</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> (1988)</cell>
	<cell>xlviii</cell>
	<cell>152</cell>
	<cell>5</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> Second Edition (2004)</cell>
	<cell>xxxviii</cell>
	<cell>943</cell>
	<cell>96</cell>
</row></table></p>
                <p>New information beyond <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Records
Supplement</hi> is incorporated throughout the second edition; the most significant addition is “John Clark
Strange MS Journal (1859-61)” (707-32), which provides the notes Strange made for the biography of Blake
which he proposed to write—but never did. The most important omission from <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) is
information about the membership of Blake’s mother (before his birth) in the Moravian congregation in Fetter
Lane, London, information which did not become available until after <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) was in print.
The second edition of <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> is likely to prove as useful as its first two parts have
been.</p>
                <p>A new and one hopes definitive edition of Northrop Frye’s immensely influential 
<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, ed. Nicholas Halmi (2004), includes not only the prefaces to the editions of
1962 and 1969 but also the Italian preface to the edition in Italian of 1976, and identifications—sometimes
with corrections—of Frye’s sources. This is the edition which careful critics will use in future.</p>
                <p>Julia M. Wright’s <hi rend="i">Blake, Nationalism, and the Politics of Alienation</hi>
(2004) “follows Blake from his subversion of the linearity that enables neoclassical nationalist narratives,
to his critique of the replicated text, to his own replicating imperialist vision” (xxxiii).</p>
                <p>The discovery by Angus Whitehead of four new directories of 1795-1799<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> indicates that the poet-engraver and his
brother were not so obscure as has often been thought, though in one of them the poet masquerades under the
name “William Blocke” at 13, Hercules Buildings. <note id="n5">5. See the entries under <hi rend="i">Blake
Journal</hi> and Directories in Part VI.</note></p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Essays</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>In the 2004 list, 18 of the essays and 16 of the reviews come from <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Blake Journal.</hi></p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">The Tools of Scholarship</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Among the most important tools of scholarship are the invaluable annual records of sales of
works by and related to Blake and the records of publications and discoveries about Blake which appear in
Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2003” and in G. E. Bentley, Jr., Hikari Sato, and Ching-erh
Chang, “William Blake and His Circle” in <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 37.4 (2004):
116-36, and 38.1 (2004): 4-35. Very few scholars read through these records, but all responsible Blake
scholars will consult them.</p>
                <p>Several other essays of major importance appeared in <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> in 2004. Keri Davies and Marsha Keith Schuchard, “Recovering the Lost Moravian History of
William Blake’s Family,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.1 (2004): 36-43, is the first factual published
account of Blake and the Moravians,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
though it was also included in Davies’ unpublished dissertation of 2003. <note id="n6">6. Somewhat oddly,
they say that for Blake’s dissenting context there is “next to no evidence” (36n3), though in 1810 Crabb
Robinson wrote quite plainly, though in German, that “Blake does not belong by birth to the established
church, but to a dissenting community” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 599).</note></p>
                <p>Mary Lynn Johnson, “Blake’s Engravings for Lavater’s Physiognomy,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.2 (2004): 52-74, provides fascinating verbal and graphic detail for the history of the
images in Lavater’s famous and enormously influential book. It had been published in German and French, but
one of the images Blake engraved was not originally an illustration of Lavater at all, though Blake would not
have known this.
<q>
A loose and shifting corpus of chronologically overlapping Lavater-authorized material made its way from
Switzerland and Germany (with a side trip to the Netherlands) through France, leaking intellectual property
rights and potential profits at every turn .... (52)
</q>
In their migrations, the images unwittingly altered in iconography and significance. For instance, the
feminine arm holding a torch surrounded by moths engraved by Blake in 1789 had been, in Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> (1778), a masculine arm being stung by wasps, where it is “an emblem
of Lavater’s resolve in the face of his detractors” (65).</p>
                <p>Michael Phillips, “The Printing of Blake’s <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi>,” 
<hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi> 21 (2004): 18-38, presents extensive evidence from Phillips’ own printing
experiments in support of the conclusion that Blake’s “progress in printing was necessarily slow” by
John Jackson, <hi rend="i">A Treatise on Wood Engraving</hi> (1839). Jackson’s conclusion was perhaps based
upon his firsthand experience with Blake. Phillips made metal facsimiles of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> plates and tried to print them as Blake did. It took him 34-35 minutes to ink each plate
satisfactorily because of the need to wipe the ink out of the hollows in the copper (31). At this rate, Blake
would have needed a week to make ten sets of <hi rend="i">America.</hi></p>
                <p>The length of time seems surprising, for, according to Joseph Collyer, <hi rend="i">The
Parent’s and Guardian’s Directory, and the Youth’s Guide in the Choice of a Profession or Trade</hi>
(London: R. Griffiths, 1761) 118, the whole process of printing from copperplates “is done with such
expedition, that a large plate of a whole sheet is blacked, cleaned, and worked off, in less than a minute.”
And this is for an intaglio plate; a relief plate should be far quicker.</p>
                <pb id="p39-8" n="8"/>
                <p>Phillips presents invaluable and previously unrecorded evidence as to the thickness of
Blake’s copperplates and the depth to which he etched them.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Roads Not Taken: The Nuts in the Fruitcake</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Occasionally one encounters a critic bold enough to say, some “Blake studies cannot be
underestimated,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> and sometimes I
wish I’d had the courage to say that. <note id="n7">7. Magnus Ankarsjö, <hi rend="i">Bring Me My Arrows of
Desire: Gender Utopia in Blake’s</hi> The Four Zoas (2004) 3, written in apparent admiration of the work of
Fox and Ostriker.</note></p>
                <p>A review more remarkable for its artistic ingenuity than for the information it conveys
consists of a design of a blossom with petals bearing the names of authors and titles of the work reviewed and
an underprinted question: “IS THIS TO BE DIVINE IN DIGITAL”? The review is entitled “Which is the Way
The Right or the Left.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> The answers
to the questions are “No” and “Neither.” <note id="n8">8. Tim Heath, review of <hi rend="i">The
Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves, in <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> no. 8 (2004):
92.</note></p>
                <p>The annual checklist of scholarship and discoveries concerning William Blake and his circle
records publications and discoveries for the current year (say, 2004) and those for previous years which are
not recorded in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995), and
“William Blake and His Circle” (1994-2004). “William Blake and His Circle” (1994 ff.) are
continuations of <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>, with similar
principles and conventions.</p>
                <p>I take <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>, faute de
mieux, to be the standard bibliographical books on Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> and have noted significant differences from them. <note id="n9">9. Except for the states
of the plates for Blake’s commercial book engravings, where the standard authority is Robert N. Essick, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (1991). Significant further details, especially
about collations, are given in Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake Book
Illustrator</hi>: A Bibliography and Catalogue of the Commercial Engravings, Volume 1: Plates Designed and
Engraved by Blake (Normal, Illinois: American Blake Foundation, 1972), Volume 2: Plates Designed or Engraved
by Blake 1774-1796 (Memphis, Tennessee: American Blake Foundation, 1979); Volume 3 never appeared.</note></p>
                <p>The organization of Division I of the checklist is as in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>:</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <table rows="6" cols="2">
                <row>
                  <cell>Part I:</cell>
                  <cell>Editions, Translations, and Facsimiles of Blake’s Writings<lb/>
Section A: Original Editions, Facsimiles, Reprints, and Translations<lb/>
Section B: Collections and Selections</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part II:</cell>
                  <cell>Reproductions of His Drawings and Paintings<lb/>
Section A: Illustrations of Individual Authors<lb/>
Section B: Collections and Selections</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part III:</cell>
                  <cell>Commercial Book Engravings</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part IV:</cell>
                  <cell>Catalogues and Bibliographies</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part V:</cell>
                  <cell>Books Owned by William Blake the Poet</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part VI:</cell>
                  <cell>Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies<lb/>
Note: Collections of essays on Blake and issues of periodicals devoted entirely to him are listed under the
titles; their authors may be recovered from the index.</cell>
                </row>
              </table>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
                  <ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
                  <note id="n10">10. There is nothing in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995) corresponding to Division II: Blake’s Circle.</note>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>This division is organized by individual (say, William Hayley or John Flaxman), with works by
and about Blake’s friends and patrons, living individuals with whom he had significant direct and
demonstrable contact. It includes Thomas Butts and his family, Robert Hartley Cromek, George Cumberland, John
Flaxman and his family, Henry Fuseli, Thomas and William Hayley, John Linnell and his family, Samuel Palmer,
James Parker, George Richmond, Henry Crabb Robinson, Thomas Stothard, John Varley, and Thomas Griffiths
Wainewright. It does <hi rend="i">not</hi> include important contemporaries with whom Blake’s contact was
negligible or non-existent, such as John Constable and William Wordsworth and Edmund Burke. Such major figures
are dealt with more comprehensively elsewhere, and the light they throw upon Blake is very dim.</p>
              <p>Reviews, listed here under the book reviewed, are only for works which are substantially
about Blake, not for those with only, say, a chapter on Blake. The authors of the reviews may be recovered
from the index.</p>
              <p>I have made no systematic attempt to record manuscripts and typescripts, audio books and
magazines, CDs,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> chinaware, comic
books, computer printouts, radio<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> and
<corr type="emend">television</corr> broadcasts, calendars, exhibitions without catalogues, festivals and
lecture series, furniture with inscriptions, lipstick, microforms, mosaic pavements,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> music, pillows, poems,
<pb id="p39-9" n="9"/>
postage stamps, postcards,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> posters,
published scores, recorded readings and singings, rubber stamps, stained-glass windows,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> stickers,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> T-shirts, tattoos, tiles,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> video recordings, or e-mail related to Blake. 
<note id="n11">11. See the entry for Nachmanovitch in Part VI; *William Bolcom, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
of Experience</hi>: Soloists, Choirs, University of Michigan School of Music Symphony Orchestra, University
Musical Society, Leonard Slatkin. ([Ann Arbor: Live Concert produced . . . April 8th 2004]) Naxos American
Classics (The liner notes include William Bolcom [b. 1938], “Songs of Innocence and of Experience: A Musical
Illumination of the Poems of William Blake,” 1984 [5-6] [when “I was seventeen, . . . the reading of
William Blake . . . (made) a profound difference in my life”] and “Recollections on the Twentieth
Anniversary of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>,” 2004 [7]). See the review by John
Rockwell.</note>
	<note id="n12">12. “Masao Hataya . . . was devoted to ‘popularizing’ Blake, and from 6 pm on August 12
[1927], the time of the artist’s death, he broadcasted a 30-minute radio program [in Japanese] called ‘100
Years since Blake’s Death’” (Yoko Ima-Izumi, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.3 [2004-05] 113).</note>
	<note id="n13">13. For instance, the mosaic pavement by Boris Anrep (1923) on the main floor of Tate gallery
2 illustrating proverbs from <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (<hi rend="i">William Blake:
The Painter at Work</hi>, ed. Joyce H. Townsend [2003] fig. 139 and 170-71).</note>
	<note id="n14">14. E.g., <hi rend="i">Coloured Prints by William Blake: 15 Pictorial Cards Printed in
Colours</hi> ([London: British Museum, 1927]) British Museum Set C13, a portfolio (or rather envelope) with a
note by Campbell Dodgson: “A Series of Postcards: Coloured Prints by William Blake (1757-1827),” 2
pp.</note>
	<note id="n15">15. In 1976, stained-glass windows with designs by John Hayward after Blake’s portrait of
Catherine and Catherine’s portrait of Blake were installed in St. Mary’s Church, Battersea, where
Catherine Boucher and her siblings were christened.</note>
	<note id="n16">16. See the entry for <hi rend="i">Blake: 16 Art Stickers</hi> in Part II, Section B.</note>
	<note id="n17">17. “Satan Watching the Endearments of Adam and Eve” (from the Thomas set of watercolors
for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> in the Huntington), reproduced in color on 30 “tumbled Italian Botticino
marble” tiles (?2003) each c. 10.2 cm. square, is recorded in Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace,
2004,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (2005): 139.</note></p>
              <p>The status of electronic “publications” becomes increasingly vexing. Some such works seem
to be merely electronic versions of physically stable works, and some suggest no more knowledge than how to
operate a computer, such as reviews invited for the listings of the book sale firm of Amazon.com, which are
divided into those by (1) the author, (2) the publisher, and (3) other, perhaps disinterested, remarkers. I
have not searched for electronic publications, and I report here only those I have happened upon which appear
to bear some authority. Many periodicals (including newspapers), books, and authors (e.g., Joseph
Viscomi—see entry in Part VI) now have electronic shadows online; this duplication is recorded here only
when my evidence comes from the electronic version, or when the electronic version differs significantly from
the three-dimensional copy.</p>
              <p>In transliterations from Chinese and Japanese, foreign proper names are given as they are
represented in our script (e.g., “William” and “Blake”) rather than as they would be pronounced in
Chinese and Japanese (“Iriamu” and “Bureiku”).</p>
              <p>The chief indices used in compiling this 2004 checklist were <hi rend="i">Books in Print
2004-2005</hi> ([Sept.] 2004) subjects (104 books); <hi rend="i">Books in Print Supplement 2003-2004</hi>
([May] 2004) titles (21); <hi rend="i">Book Review Index 2003</hi> (2003) and <hi rend="i">2004</hi> (2004);
Modern Language Association International Bibliography online (viewed Nov. 2004).</p>
              <p>I am indebted for help of many kinds to Acta Universitatis Gothoburgensis, Dr. E. B. Bentley,
Mr. Robert Brandeis (librarian of Victoria College, University of Toronto), Dr. Iain G. Brown (principal
keeper of manuscripts, National Library of Scotland), Mr. Martin Butlin, Mrs. Margaret Carlson, Mrs. Edna
Cooper, Dr. Ava Weinberger Cross, Dr. D. W. Dörrbecker, Professor Robert N. Essick (especially for a
typescript copy of his “Blake in the Marketplace, 2004” for <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [2005]), Senor
Francisco Gimenes (for Spanish publications), the Rev. Derek Hollis (for information about Walkeringham), Mrs.
Heather Howell, Ms. Sarah Jones of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Mr. Allan King (press officer of the Wordsworth
Trust), <corr type="emend">Mrs. Birgitta Kurtén,</corr> Folke Lofgren, Mr. Jeffrey Mertz (our man at the Library of Congress, for
reproductions), Professor Karen Mulhallen, Virginia Murray (archivist, John Murray Archive), Professor Morton
Paley, Professor Hikari Sato, Ms. Susanne Sklar, Mr. David Weston (Special Collections, Glasgow University
Library), Mr. Angus Whitehead (for information about directories and William Bolcom and inconsistencies in 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]), and Mr. Dominic Winter.</p>
              <p>I should be most grateful to anyone who can help me to better information about the unseen
(§) items reported here, and I undertake to thank them prettily in person and in print.</p>
              <p>Research for “William Blake and his Circle, 2004” was carried out in the Bodleian
Library, the British Library, University of Toronto Library, and the Toronto Public Library.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Symbols</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>* Works prefixed by an asterisk include one or more illustrations by Blake or depicting him.
If there are more than 19 illustrations, the number is specified. If the illustrations include all those for a
work by Blake, say <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> or his illustrations to <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>, the work is
identified.</p>
              <p>§ Works preceded by a section mark are reported on second-hand authority.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <table rows="5" cols="2">
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                  </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell><hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2)</cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, Second Edition (2004)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Butlin</cell>
                  <cell>Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>
(1981)</cell>
                </row>
              </table>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part I: Blake’s Writings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section A: Original Editions, Facsimiles,</hi>
                        <ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
                        <hi rend="b">Reprints, and Translations</hi>
                        <note id="n18">18. In this checklist, “facsimile” is taken to mean “an exact
copy” attempting very close reproduction of an original named copy including size of image, color of
printing (and of tinting if relevant), and size, color, and quality of paper, with no deliberate alteration as
in page order or numbering or obscuring of paper defects, or centering the image on the page.</note>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <table rows="1" cols="2">
                      <head>Table of Collections</head>
                      <row>
                        <cell>MURRAY (JOHN) ARCHIVE<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n19">19. Virginia Murray, Archivist, John Murray Archive, tells me that there is no other Blake
material in the Murray Archive.</note>
	</cell>
                        <cell>ALS: 25? Nov. 1825</cell>
                      </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Watermarks in Paper Used by Blake &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998)&gt;</p>
                    <p>This table provides only very crude evidence. Paper watermarked W ELGAR | 1796 is of
course different from paper watermarked 1794 | J WHATMAN. However, some paper watermarked
<pb id="p39-10" n="10"/>
1794 | J WHATMAN may be quite distinct from other paper watermarked 1794 | J WHATMAN, for “there are some
forty different papers, several of which were used by Blake, watermarked 1794 / J WHATMAN,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> differing in size, paper materials,
thickness, etc. <note id="n20">20. Peter Bower, “The Vivid Surface: Blake’s Use of Paper and Board” 55
in <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work</hi>, ed. Joyce H. Townsend (2003).</note></p>
                    <p>For information on the makers and mills of paper used by Blake, see the table of
“Blake’s Papermakers: Watermarks Found in Papers Used by William Blake (1757-1827)” (72-73) in Peter
Bower, “The Evolution and Development of ‘Drawing Papers’ and the Effect of This Development on
Watercolour Artists, 1750-1850,” 61-74 of <hi rend="i">The Oxford Papers: Proceedings of the British
Association of Paper Historians Fourth Annual Conference, Held at St. Edmund Hall, Oxford, 17-19 September
1993</hi>, ed. Peter Bower (London: British Association of Paper Historians, 1996) Studies in British Paper
History, Vol. 1.</p>
                    <p>Three curved lines enclosing a rampant lion or dragon Letter (25 Nov. 1825)<lb/>
BASTED MILL | 1820<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n21">21. BASTED MILL is the watermark used by John Pine and William Thomas at their Basted Mill,
Hertfordshire.</note></p>
                    <p>Butlin #714 (1820)<lb/>
W D[ICKI]E<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> | 1803 <note id="n22">22.
The watermark, misread, or rather misreported, in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> p. 71 as “W DA[CI]E” was
commissioned by William Dickie, Bookbinder, Paper Maker, and Stationer of the Strand; he did not have his own
mill.</note></p>
                    <p>Letter (25 Mar. 1805)<lb/>
W DI[CKI]E &amp; CO | 1804</p>
                    <p>Letter (4 Dec. 1804)</p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">America</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Pl. a</p>
                    <p>The surviving fragment is 8.2 cm. wide by 5.8 cm. high by 0.141 cm. thick and etched
(in two bites, 0.005, then 0.007) to a depth of 0.012 cm.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n23">23. Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton
University Press, 1980) 92.</note></p>
                    <p>Copy M</p>
                    <p>History: Reproductions of it were added to the William Blake Archive in 2004.</p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Copy H</p>
                    <p>History: Reproductions of it were added to the William Blake Archive in 2004.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> (1826)</p>
                    <p>Pl. 1 (<hi rend="i">not</hi> pl. 2 as in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [2004])</p>
                    <p>History: It is to go with Harold Bloom’s archives and “personal library” of
25,000 books to St. Michael’s College, Colchester, Vermont.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n24" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n24">24. Dinitia Smith, “Critic’s Books Go to Small College,” <hi rend="i">New York
Times</hi> 12 April 2003: D7.</note></p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Pl. 96</p>
                    <p>There are irregularities on pl. 96, such as the white-line striations as of shading at
the bottom left of the design and a strong—and graphically irrelevant—horizontal line across the knee of
the man, which suggest that Blake’s relief etching is over an intaglio engraving. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> p.
225 says merely that “Something else seems to have been originally engraved under the present etching,”
and none of the facsimiles I have now [2004] looked at—C (1955), D (1877), E (1955, 1991, William Blake
Archive), and H (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> [1978])—enables me to be more precise.</p>
                    <p>However, David V. Erdman, “The Suppressed and Altered Passages in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem,” Studies in Bibliography</hi> 17 (1964): 36-38, says that he sees in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 96,
<q>
a good deal of submerged cross-hatching in the area below the center of the picture and along its left side
near the text, the only distinguishable form being a perspective drawing of what looks like a small Grecian
temple. From the top to the center of the picture some 7 irregularly spaced lines of cursive italic writing
are fragmentarily visible, as white loops across the thick outlines of Blake’s drawing. In the Rosenbloom
copy [of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (J) pl. 96] the first words are decipherable as “The Greatest” . . .
the first words, in the same cursive engraver’s lettering, of a commercial manifesto . . . for “Moore
&amp; Co’s Manufactory &amp; Warehouse of Carpets”
</q>
which Blake engraved in 1797 or 1798.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">25</ref> He identifies the readings of “the visible seven lines” from Blake’s “Moore &amp;
Co” advertisement, though he does not actually say that they are legible. And he concludes that 
“<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 96 is etched on a piece of copper cut from the lower left quarter (roughly speaking)
of the [Moore &amp; Co] plate.” <note id="n25">25. Reproduced in Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Engravings: The Separate Plates</hi> (1956) pl. 10, and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate
Plates of William Blake</hi> (1983) pl. 23.</note></p>
                    <p>After careful study with a magnifying glass, I can see the features of pl. 96 which
suggest that the plate was previously used for something else, but can neither read any of these words nor
even find precisely where they appear on the plate, nor can Susanne Sklar, who looked at copy J pl. 96 on my
behalf.</p>
                    <p>Letters<lb/>
<table rows="3" cols="5">
	<head>Table</head><row>
	<cell>Date</cell>
	<cell>Postmark</cell>
	<cell>Watermark</cell>
	<cell>Collection</cell>
	<cell>Size</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1825 Nov. [25?]*
                                                    </cell>
	<cell>TP StrandCO</cell>
	<cell>Three curved lines enclosing a rampant lion or dragon</cell>
	<cell>John Murray Archive</cell>
	<cell>16.5 × 20.3 cm.</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell/>
	<cell>8 · MORN · 8 25 · NO 1825<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n26">26. The postmarks are like those in the letters of 11 Oct., 10 Nov. 1825, 31 Jan., 19 May, 2,
16, 29 July, 1 Aug. 1826; only the letter of 10 Nov. 1825 has a watermark with a design. The upper postmark
has “2” scrawled across it.</note>
	</cell>
	<cell/><cell/><cell/>
</row></table></p>
                    <p>* A <hi rend="i">wafer</hi> sealed the letter.</p>
                    <pb id="p39-1" n="1"/>
                    <figure n="lt25nov1825.1.2.LT.cc" rend="file" width="813" height="1000">
					  <figTranscr>Crazy Artist<lb/>
						Dear Sir<lb/>
						Mr Banes says his Kitchen is at our Service <lb/>
						to do as we please. I should like to know from <lb/>
						the Printer whether our own Kitchen would not be <lb/>
						equally or even more convenient as the Press being <lb/>
						already there would Save a good deal of time &amp; trouble <lb/>
						in taking down &amp; putting up which is no slight job. Also <lb/>
						the light is better in <lb/>
						our Kitchen if <lb/>
						there is but room enough.<lb/>
						I am yours Sincerely<lb/>
						Will Blake</figTranscr>
                      <head>Cover: Recto of Blake’s newly discovered letter to John Linnell of 25 
November 1825<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/></head>
                      <figDesc>(reproduced by permission of the John Murray Archive). 
The reference to Blake printing in his kitchen is fascinating, and the reference to his brother-in-law 
Mr. Banes is unique in his writings.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p39-11" n="11"/>
                    <figure n="lt25nov1825.1.1.LT.cc" rend="file" width="950" height="776">
						<figTranscr>John Linnell Esqre<lb/>
							Cirencester Place<lb/>
							Fitzroy Square<lb/>
							<lb/>
							TP<lb/>
							StrandCO<lb/>
							<lb/>
							2<lb/>
							<lb/>
							8 · MORN[ING] · 8 
							25 · NO[VEMBER]<lb/>
							1825</figTranscr>
                      <head>1. Verso of Blake’s newly discovered letter to John Linnell of 25
November 1825</head>
                      <figDesc>(reproduced by permission of the John Murray Archive). 
The recto is the cover illustration here.</figDesc>
					</figure>
                    <p>Previously Unrecorded</p>
                    <p>[25?] November 1825</p>
                    <p>History: Acquired presumably by John Murray (1778-1843), bookseller, or his son and
successor John Murray (1808-92), both of them keen collectors,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n27" type="note">27</ref> and inscribed “Crazy Artist”; it was lent from the John Murray Archive
to the Wordsworth Trust exhibition of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>: The Poem and Its Illustrators (6
July-31 October 2004), in whose catalogue, item 54, it was partially transcribed and reproduced 
(see cover illus. and illus. 1). <note id="n27">27. According to Virginia Murray, Archivist, John Murray
Archive.</note></p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Copy A</p>
                    <p>History: In 2004 reproductions of it were added to the William Blake Archive.</p>
                    <p>Copy D</p>
                    <p>History: In 2004 reproductions of it were added to the William Blake Archive.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (1794)</p>
                    <p>Edition</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Cantos de la Experiencia.</hi> Translation and notes by Roberto Díaz.
(Barcelona: Editorial Astri, S.A., 2000) 91 pp.; ISBN: 8446908123. English and Spanish on facing pages.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1794)</p>
                    <p>Edition</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and Experience</hi> [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>].
Photographs by Joel-Peter Witkin. Ed. and with an introduction by John Wood. (Brewster, Massachusetts: “An
Art Publication of Leo and Wolfe Photography, Inc.,” according to the colophon, but “Published by Steven
Albahari” according to the title page, 2004); ISBN: 1892733110 (trade edition, 915 copies plus 200
<pb id="p39-12" n="12"/>
copies “hors commerce”), 1892733129 (deluxe edition, 85 copies with “an original, signed platinum
print”).</p>
                    <p>According to Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2004,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (2005): 139, “The black and white photo illus. feature dismembered body parts,
laceration, amputees, deformed infants and fetuses, decapitation, torture, cruelty to animals, hermaphrodism,
and child pornography. And that’s just in the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> section.”</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1793)</p>
                    <p>Copy N</p>
                    <p>History: After the death of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney (1877-1942), daughter of
Cornelius Vanderbilt and widow of Harry Payne Whitney (1872-1930), <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (N)<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> was separated from her copy of 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (E); <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (N) was acquired as part of a private collection not
related to the Whitney family by an antiques dealer<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref> (not a bookseller), who sold it to an anonymous buyer who brought it in 2004 to Swann
Galleries (New York) where it was to be sold in April 2005, until it became embroiled in a dispute over
ownership.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref>
	<note id="n28">28. <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (E) passed at the death of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney to Helen
Hay Whitney, thence to Harry Payne Whitney’s nephew John Hay Whitney, thence to John’s widow Betsy Cushing
Whitney (d. 1998), and sold with her estate at Sotheby’s (New York), 23 April 1999.</note>
	<note id="n29">29. According to letters to me from Edwin Wolf 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> and R. B. Adams of Sept.
and 15 Oct. 1965, <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (E) and <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (N) were seen in a desk drawer in
Gertrude Whitney’s house after her death by Arthur Swann, then of Parke Bernet, and by Hyatt Mayor. Can 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (N) have been in the desk when it was sold as an antique?</note>
	<note id="n30">30. All the post-1942 provenance here derives from Robert N. Essick’s account in “Blake in
the Marketplace, 2004,” generously shown me in draft.</note></p>
                    <p>Editions</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Visiones de las Hijas de Albión</hi> (<hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi>). Tr. Pablo Neruda. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                    <p>The first printing in 1934 has a prefatory note in Spanish by “C.K.
CHESTERTON.”</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> Ed. Robert N. Essick. (2002)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                    <p>Reviews</p>
                    <p>Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> N.S. 54 (2003): 691-93
(“The quality of paper and printing are impressive” and “readers can be grateful to Essick” for his
commentary).</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Reference and Research Book News</hi> 18 (2003): 227+.</p>
                    <p>Catherine L. McClenahan, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.2 (2004): 77-79 
(“<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> could scarcely ask for a more experienced and informed editor,” who has provided a
“lucid” commentary).</p>
                  </div7>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section B: Collections and Selections</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Blake Shishu</hi>: Taiyaku [<hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry</hi>: A
translation printed side by side with the English text]. Ed. Shoichi Matsushima. (Tokyo: Iwanami Shoten, 2004)
345 pp., 16 plates; ISBN: 40022217729. In Japanese and English.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience, The Book of Thel</hi>, portions of
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, portions of 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, extracts from the Pickering Manuscript, with a short biography of Blake. A
handy, pocket-size collection for a beginner.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman.
(1988) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 162&gt;</p>
                    <p>It is available online both at
&lt;http://www.english.uga.edu/nhilton/Blake/blaketxt1/&gt; and at
&lt;http://www.blakearchive.org/cgi-bin/nph-1965/blake/erdman/erd&gt;.</p>
                    <p>“The Edition of the Works of Wm. Blake” by “The Blake Press at Edmonton”
[England] of William Muir (1884-90). &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #249&gt;</p>
                    <p>“Volume 1”</p>
                    <p>h. <hi rend="i">On Homer’s Poetry</hi> [&amp;] <hi rend="i">On Virgil</hi> [?C].
(Edmonton, 1886).</p>
                    <p>According to Keri Davies’ thesis “William Blake in Contexts” (2003) 268,
“Muir’s facsimile and that printed with Herbert R. [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] Horne, ‘Blake’s Sibylline
Leaf on Homer and Virgil’, <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi>, 2 (1887), 115-16, differ in many
respects and are unlikely to derive from the same lithographic plate,” though <hi rend="i">BB</hi> pp. 488,
836 imply they are the same.</p>
                    <p>Reviews</p>
                    <p>§Anon., <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> no. 2964 (16 Aug. 1884): 216 (“The reproduction
of the outlines is simply perfect”).</p>
                    <p>§Anon., <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> no. 3203 (16 Mar. 1889): 351-52 (“Their
verisimilitude is absolute”).</p>
                    <p>*“El Viajero Mental (The Mental Traveller).” Tr. Pablo Neruda. <hi rend="i">Cruz y
Raya: Revista de Afirmación y Negación</hi> 20 ([Madrid] Nov. 1934): 103-09. In Spanish.</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake.</hi> ([N.p. (England), 2002 or 2003]) Faerie
Queene Library, 7 unnumbered leaves; no ISBN.</p>
                    <p>A miniature edition, 2.7 × 2.0 cm., consisting of “The Tyger” plus 2 pp. about
Blake.</p>
                    <p>William Blake Archive &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;</p>
                    <p>In 2004 the archive added <hi rend="i">America</hi> (M), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (H),
<hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (A, D), <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (a, A), and 23
reproductions of the 12 large color prints.</p>
                    <p>*Joseph Viscomi, “Illuminated Printing,” 37-62 of <hi rend="i">The Cambridge
Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves (2003), was incorporated in the archive in 2004 with almost
90 additional reproductions.</p>
                  </div7>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part II: Reproductions of Drawings and Paintings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section A: Illustrations of Individual Authors</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>John Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi></p>
                    <p>Thomas Set (Huntington Library and Art Gallery)</p>
                    <p>Reproduced in the 6 July-31 October 2004 Wordsworth Trust exhibition catalogue of 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>: The Poem and Its Illustrators.</p>
                    <pb id="p39-13" n="13"/>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Thirteen Watercolor Drawings by William Blake Illustrating Paradise Lost
by John Milton.</hi> The first facsimiles printed at full scale in full color from the original works in the
collection of The Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California with descriptions and
commentaries by Robert N. Essick &amp; John T. Shawcross to accompany the edition of <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi> published in 2002 by The Arion Press text edited by John T. Shawcross and with an introduction by
Helen Vendler. (San Francisco: Arion Press, 2004) folio (43.0 × 55.6 cm.), 30 unnumbered leaves loose in a
portfolio, limited to 426 copies; no ISBN.</p>
                    <p>Reproductions of the Thomas set of illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
plus the Huntington’s large “Satan, Sin and Death.” Essick’s commentary is essentially the same as
that in his <hi rend="i">William Blake at the Huntington</hi> (1994) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1995)&gt;.</p>
                    <p>The portfolio is a companion to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost: a Poem in Twelve Books The
Author John Milton.</hi> Ed. John T. Shawcross, introduction by Helen Vendler. (san Francisco: Printed by
Andrew Hoyem at the Arion Press, MMII [2002]) xxxiv, 396 pp.; no ISBN.</p>
                  </div7>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section B: Collections and Selections</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Blake: 16 Art Stickers.</hi> (Mineola [New York]: Dover Publications,
2003) 12° (4 1/16″ × 5 ¾″), 6 pp. and covers; ISBN: 0486430685.</p>
                    <p>Anon., “Note” (inside front cover) (“a new work”). The stickers derive from 
<hi rend="i">Urizen, Songs, Milton, Jerusalem</hi>, and “Glad Day.”</p>
                  </div7>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part III: Commercial Book Engravings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Charles Allen, <hi rend="i">A New and Improved History of England</hi>, Second Edition
(1798)</p>
                  <p>Pl. 2 “King John Absolved by Pandulph”: The true-size drawing for it, acquired by
Robert N. Essick, “bears all the hallmarks of a work by Fuseli, including the characteristic left-hand
hatching strokes.” This is perhaps the clearest evidence to support the long-held belief that the designs to
Allen’s books are by Fuseli. The drawing was calked and counterproofed, presumably by Blake, onto the
copperplate for engraving.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n31">31. See Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2004,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4
(2005): 125, 140, and illus. 9-11.</note></p>
                  <p>Bible (1836)—<hi rend="i">Job</hi></p>
                  <p>THE | ENGLISH VERSION | OF THE | POLYGLOTT BIBLE: | CONTAINING THE | <hi rend="i">Old and
New Testaments</hi>, | TOGETHER WITH | A COPIOUS AND ORIGINAL SELECTION OF REFERENCES, | TO PARALLEL AND
ILLUSTRATIVE PASSAGES. | EXHIBITED IN A MANNER HITHERTO UNATTEMPTED. | - | NORTHAMPTON [Massachusetts]—J.H.
BUTLER. | BUFFALO [New York]—T. AND M. BUTLER. | 1836. [Within a double frame of rules.] &lt;Essick
Collection&gt;</p>
                  <p>An engraving labelled “Job and His Family” (“Blake”—Anon.), image c. 5.8 × 9.0
cm., derives from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> pl. “1” (16.5 × 21.3 cm.). In it the foreground sheep
are omitted, two are moved to the flocks at the left and right, and a band of foliage is added. This is
apparently the earliest repetition of Blake’s Job designs.</p>
                  <p>This tiny Bible (6.8 × 11.0 cm.), of a “convenient size for the Pocket,” with a
preface signed “T.C.” as “the Editor,” may be rare; at any rate it, the Butlers, Northampton, and
Buffalo do not appear in <hi rend="i">Historical Catalogue of Printed Editions of The English Bible
1525-1961</hi> Revised and Expanded from the Edition of T. H. Darlow and H. F. Moule 1903 by A. S. Herbert
(London: British and Foreign Bible Society; New York: American Bible Society, 1968) (abbreviated D&amp;M).</p>
                  <p>The <hi rend="i">Polyglott</hi> in the title is justified only in the work from which the
Butler edition was indirectly pirated: <hi rend="i">The English Version of the Polyglott</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] <hi rend="i">Bible</hi> . . . With a . . . selection of references to parallel and
illustrative passages (London: Samuel Bagster, [1815,] 1816), with a preface signed “T.C.” for Thomas
Chevalier; this <hi rend="i">English Version</hi> appeared with separately issued versions of the Bible in
Hebrew, Greek, Latin, French, German, Italian, and Spanish (D&amp;M #1628). Bagster’s <hi rend="i">English
Version</hi> was reprinted in 1819, 1825, 1826, 1828, 1831, 1833, 1834, 1838 [1840?], [1844] (3 varieties)
(D&amp;M #1628) and in U.S. editions of 1825 [Philadelphia: Thomas Wardle, D&amp;M #1748], 1831 [Philadelphia:
Key &amp; Meikle, D&amp;M #1785], 1837, 1841, 1842, and 1844—a total of “well over a hundred [U.S.
versions of Bagster’s <hi rend="i">Polyglott</hi>] reprinted within fifty years” (D&amp;M #1628, 1785).
Plainly the English text of Bagster’s <hi rend="i">Polyglott</hi> was freely pirated and frequently
reprinted; apparently the only remarkable feature of the 1836 edition is in the illustrations.</p>
                  <p>Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808, 1813, . . .)</p>
                  <p>1813 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>Gottfried Augustus Bürger, <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi> (1796)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>John Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> (1817)</p>
                  <p>Pl. 21 (“Theogony” fly-title): A proof before all letters on paper watermarked 1812
is “now [2004] in a private British collection.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n32">32. According to Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2004,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (2005): 130.</note></p>
                  <p>John Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793, [1811])</p>
                  <p>1793 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>[Richard Gough,] <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments, in Great Britain</hi> Vol. 1, Part 1
(1786)</p>
                  <p>Pl. 9: A proof before letters of Blake’s plate<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n33" type="note">33</ref> of the third state of Queen Philippa on a leaf 38.5 × 49.5 cm., formerly in
the collection of Raymond Lister and subsequently in a “private collection, London,” was offered in March
2004 by Christopher Edwards
<pb id="p39-14" n="14"/>
                                        (for £2,750 [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]) and acquired by Robert N.
Essick. The proof is especially interesting because of the inscriptions, in the same hand Gough used on other
proofs now in the Bodleian, giving directions to the writing engraver: <hi rend="i">above the image but within
the platemark</hi>: “pl. xlix p. 125”; <hi rend="i">below the image but within the platemark</hi>:
“Portrait of <hi rend="sub">^</hi>Queen<hi rend="sub">^</hi> Phillippa [Queen of Edward III] from her
monument | Basire In &amp; sc”; <hi rend="i">at the bottom of the page</hi>: “[Put under d portrait of Q
Eleanor Pl xxiii*].” The print as published is inscribed: “<hi rend="i">Pl. XLVIII, p. 123.</hi>” 
“<hi rend="i">Monument of Philippa Queen of Edward III. 1369</hi>” and “<hi rend="i">Basire del &amp;
sc</hi>”. <note id="n33">33. Blake’s responsibility for the drawing is plausibly asserted by Malkin 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 563), and his responsibility for the engraving is a generally accepted
hypothesis.</note></p>
                  <p>Gough wrote in pencil on the proof: “Mr Ashley your people have made a mistake which
appears very extraordinary as it is very clearly wrote with only one 1—Philippa.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">34</ref> Presumably “Mr Ashley” is the writing engraver, but
there is no Ashley in <hi rend="i">Stationers’ Company Apprentices 1701-1800</hi>, ed. D. F. McKenzie
(1978), or William B. Todd, <hi rend="i">Directory of Printers and Others in Allied Trades London and Vicinity
1800-1840</hi> (1972), and the only Ashley in Ian Maxted, <hi rend="i">The London Book Trades 1775-1800: A
Preliminary Checklist of Members</hi> (1977) 6, is John, a music publisher. <note id="n34">34. The inscription
is reported by Christopher Edwards but is invisible to me from his reproduction. This inscription is not given
in Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (1991) 119, which cites
this proof and reproduces the final state with printed inscriptions (pl. 291).</note></p>
                  <p>Josephus, <hi rend="i">Works</hi> ([?1785-?1800])</p>
                  <p>A cumulation of <hi rend="i">BB, BBS, Blake</hi> (1994 ff.), Roger R. Easson and Robert
N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake Book Illustrator</hi>: A Bibliography and Catalogue of the Commercial
Engravings, Volume 2: Plates Designed or Engraved by Blake 1774-1796 (Memphis, Tennessee: American Blake
Foundation, 1979) 21-26,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref> and Essick,
“Blake in the Marketplace, 2004,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (2005). <note id="n35">35. Easson and
Essick describe A as First Issue, B as Second Issue, C as Third Issue, Ca as Fourth Issue, D as Fifth Issue,
and E as Sixth Issue.</note></p>
                  <p>A <hi rend="i">The Genuine and Complete Works</hi>, ed. George Henry Maynard (London: J.
Cooke [?1785-86]) Locations: British Library, British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings, Houston
Public, National Library of Canada (imperfect), Newberry, Union Theological Seminary (New York),
Southampton</p>
                  <p>Ab <hi rend="i">The Genuine and Complete Works</hi>, ed. George Henry Maynard and Edward
Kimpton (London: J. Cooke [?1786-87]) Location: GEB &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Ac <hi rend="i">The Genuine and Complete Works</hi> (London: J. Cooke [?1787-88])
“Useful” substituted for “Copious,” omits “Together with Time of the Author,” adds “Illustrated
with MARGINAL REFERENCES . . . to the HOLY BIBLE” Location: GEB &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Ad <hi rend="i">The Whole Genuine and Complete Works</hi> (London: J. Cooke [?1788-89])
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;</p>
                  <p>B <hi rend="i">The Whole Genuine and Complete Works</hi> (London: J. Cooke [?1789-90])
substitutes “Useful” for “Copious,” ends “And sold by all other Booksellers in <hi rend="i">Great
Britain</hi>” Locations: British Library (2, both imperfect), Cambridge, Durham Cathedral, Leeds, National
Library of Scotland (2), Nottingham, Princeton, Princeton Theological Seminary</p>
                  <p>Ba <hi rend="i">The Whole Genuine and Complete Works</hi> (London: J. Cooke [?1789-90])
Location: Dörrbecker &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Bb Between B and C &lt;Essick (2005)&gt;</p>
                  <p>C By the King’s Royal License and Authority <hi rend="i">The Whole Genuine and Complete
Works</hi> (London: J. Cooke [?1795]) Locations: GEB; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> adds under B-C Durham Cathedral,
Harvard, Lancaster Theological Seminary (Lancaster, Pennsylvania), New York Public Library, Virginia, Yale</p>
                  <p>Ca By the King’s Royal License and Authority <hi rend="i">The Whole Genuine and
Complete Works</hi> (London: J. Cooke [?1790-91]) “is now <hi rend="i">first</hi> added” substituted for
“will now be <hi rend="i">first</hi> added”; ends “And sold by all other Booksellers in 
<hi rend="i">Great Britain</hi>” Location: Cambridge &lt;Easson and Essick&gt;</p>
                  <p>D By the King’s Royal License and Authority <hi rend="i">The Whole Genuine and Complete
Works</hi> (London: C. Cooke [?1799]) Locations: Arizona State (Tempe), GEB, British Library, Boston Public,
Bristol (Wesley College [imperfect]), Dalhousie, Delaware, Library of Congress, Newberry, New York Public
Library, North Carolina State</p>
                  <p>E <hi rend="i">The Whole Genuine and Complete Works</hi> (London: C. Cooke, etc. [?1800])
Locations: GEB, Bodleian, Boston Public, British Library, British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings,
Tate, Ushaw College (Durham)</p>
                  <p>John Caspar Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> (1788; 1789)</p>
                  <p>1788 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>1789 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>John Caspar Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> (1789-98; 1810; “1792”
[i.e., c. 1817])</p>
                  <p>&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 481; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 235-36; <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1994-98, 2000-04)&gt;</p>
                  <p>1789-98 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>1810 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>The sources of the plates signed merely “<hi rend="i">Blake Sc</hi>” or 
“<hi rend="i">Blake sculp</hi>” are brilliantly identified by Mary Lynn Johnson, “Blake’s Engravings for
Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>: Overdue Credit to Chodowiecki, Schellenberg, and Lips,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.2 (2004): 52-74:</p>
                  <p>1 A vignette of two old men planting trees (Vol. I, p. 127) originally appeared in
Gellert’s <hi rend="i">Leçons de Morale</hi> (1772) engraved by Daniel Nikolaus Chodowiecki, and
Chodowiecki engraved another version (1772) for the Huguenot Seminaire françois de theologie à Berlin, where
it indicates the fostering of young theology students. It was engraved, reversed, by Rudolf Schellenberg for
Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essai sur la physiognomonie</hi> I ([1781]) 127. Blake re-reversed the design and
made minor alterations.</p>
                  <p>3 A female arm and hand delicately holding up a candle with moths nearby (Vol. I, p. 206)
derives from an engraving (Anon.-Anon.) of a sturdy male arm and hand gripping a candle and being stung by a
wasp in <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> I: 213, where its significance is not explained. It derives from a plate
(Anon.-Anon.)
<pb id="p39-15" n="15"/>
in Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente</hi> IV (1778) (Vol. IV was never translated) where it
represents Lavater’s determination to uphold the light of Truth in the face of the stings of public
mockery.</p>
                  <p>4 A profile head of the Lutheran theologian Johann Joachim Spalding, a dear friend of
both Lavater and Fuseli (Vol. I, p. 225), was first printed in Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomische
Fragmente</hi> III (1777), 4 portraits on one plate after Chodowiecki engraved by Johann Heinrich Lips, and
repeated, alone [?by Lips] in <hi rend="i">Essai</hi> I: 232.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi> Vol. X-XI (1783, 1785, 1793)</p>
                  <p>1783 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>C. G. Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi> (1791, 1792, 1799, 1805, 1815)</p>
                  <p>1791 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>John Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> (1782)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>John Gabriel Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi> (1796,1813)</p>
                  <p>1796 New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>John Varley, <hi rend="i">Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi> (1828)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Physiology Sherrington Library (Oxford).</p>
                  <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">The Pastorals</hi>, ed. R. J. Thornton (1821)</p>
                  <p>According to Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1863) 275, Blake’s
wood “blocks . . . proved . . . too wide for the page and were . . . summarily cut down to the requisite
size by the publishers.” Proofs from eight blocks (2-5, 6-9) before they were cut down are in the British
Museum Department of Prints and Drawings and reproduced, inter alia, in <hi rend="i">The Illustrations of
William Blake for Thornton’s Virgil</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (1937) 42-43. The differences before and after
this surgery were:
<table rows="9" cols="4"><row>
	<cell>Design</cell>
	<cell>Before trimming</cell>
	<cell>After trimming</cell>
	<cell>Trimmed chiefly on</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>(2)</cell>
	<cell>3.9 × 8.8</cell>
	<cell>3.9 × 7.4</cell>
	<cell>Left, right, top, bottom, plus chip at top left</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>(3)</cell>
	<cell>3.4 × 8.5</cell>
	<cell>3.3 × 7.4</cell>
	<cell>Left, right, top</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>(4)</cell>
	<cell>4.5 × 8.6</cell>
	<cell>3.2 × 7.3</cell>
	<cell>Left, right, top</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>(5)</cell>
	<cell>4 × 8.7</cell>
	<cell>3.7 × 7.4</cell>
	<cell>Left, right, top, bottom, plus chips at top left and top right</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>(6)</cell>
	<cell>4 × 8.4</cell>
	<cell>3.4 × 7.3</cell>
	<cell>Left, right, bottom, top</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>(7)</cell>
	<cell>3.6 × 8.6</cell>
	<cell>3.6 × 7.4</cell>
	<cell>Right</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>(8)</cell>
	<cell>3.3 × 8.7</cell>
	<cell>3.3 × 7.3</cell>
	<cell>Right, top</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>(9)</cell>
	<cell>3.9 × 8.7</cell>
	<cell>3.4 × 7.3</cell>
	<cell>Right, top<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref>
	<note id="n36">36. The dimensions in centimeters given here are reported by Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">The
Traveller in the Evening</hi> (2003) 31, from proofs of the blocks before trimming in the British Museum
Department of Prints and Drawings and from the woodblocks themselves after trimming in the British Museum
Department of Prints and Drawings. The differences were summarized in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #504 as “about
0.5 to 1.0 cm.” The dimensions there are given as design size rather than block size and the cut down
designs as “c. 7.6 × 3.2 cm.”</note>
	</cell>
</row></table></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Wit’s Magazine</hi> (1784)</p>
                  <p>Pl. 1: (“The Temple of Mirth”) the first of two separate engravings of the same
design: A print of the second state is in the collection of Robert N. Essick.</p>
                  <p>Edward Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Liverpool Public.</p>
                  <p>Colored Copies</p>
                  <p>Addenda</p>
                  <p>Copy E</p>
                  <p>History: John Alexander Fuller-Maitland (1856-1936) remembered seeing before 1872 at the
house of his uncle William Fuller-Maitland (1813-76) “a wonderful old chest” in which he was “allowed to
forage, containing books by Blake that would now fetch their weight in gold. There was the unique copy of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [E, plus <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (a)]. . . . There were two copies of Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, and when I referred to the fact in talking about the books to my uncle, he
stoutly maintained that he possessed only one. I assured him that one was coloured [E] and the other plain,
but he was so sure that I was wrong that he said he would give me the second [plain one] if it was there. It
was ....”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">37</ref>
	<note id="n37">37. J. A. Fuller-Maitland, <hi rend="i">A Door-Keeper of Music</hi> (London: Murray, 1929)
38.</note></p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part IV: Catalogues and Bibliographies</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>1812</p>
                  <p>A | CATALOGUE | OF THE | FIFTH ANNUAL | EXHIBITION | BY THE | <hi rend="i">ASSOCIATED
PAINTERS</hi> | IN | <hi rend="i">Water Colours</hi> | - | AT THE SOCIETY’S ROOMS, | No. 16, OLD BOND
STREET. | - | ADMITTANCE, ONE SHILLING. | <hi rend="i">CATALOGUES, SIXPENCE.</hi> | - | LONDON: | PRINTED BY
J. MOYES, GREVILLE STREET, HATTON GARDEN. | - | 1812. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #531&gt;</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Strathclyde (Scotland), Victoria &amp; Albert Museum; a very rare complete
set of the society’s catalogues (1808-12) was offered in Ken Spelman, catalogue 52 (2004), item 18, and is
now in the Essick Collection.</p>
                  <p>“The landlord seized the contents of the gallery in distraint of rent,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">38</ref> including Blake’s Chaucer’s Pilgrims
(item 254), “The Spiritual Form of Pitt” (279), “The Spiritual Form of Nelson” (280), and “Detached
Specimens of . . . <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
type="note">39</ref> (324). Thomas Butts, who apparently owned “Nelson” and
<pb id="p39-16" n="16"/>
Chaucer,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">40</ref> may have bought them—or
bought them back—from the distraining landlord. <note id="n38">38. J. L. Rogers, <hi rend="i">History of the
Old Water Colour Society</hi> (1891) 1: 271, noted in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> under <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
but not under the 1812 catalogue, nor in Butlin, nos. 649, 651, 653 and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) (mea
culpa).</note>
	<note id="n39">39. Probably <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 25, 32, 46 (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> pp.
262-63).</note>
	<note id="n40">40. They were sold by his son in 1853. The history of “Pitt” is not known before 1882,
when Samuel Palmer’s son offered it for sale at auction—Samuel Palmer was seven years old in
1812.</note></p>
                  <p>1922</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">Reproductions from the Works of William Blake.</hi> (Seoul, Korea,
1922).</p>
                  <p>9 November 2000 - 11 February 2001; 27 March-24 June 2001</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> (London: Tate Publishing, 2000). Tate exhibition.
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Comprehensive online information on the exhibition is still (in 2004) at
&lt;http://www.tate.org.uk/britain/exhibitions/blake.htm&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>*Kausalya Santhanam, “Celebrating Blake,” <hi rend="i">The Hindu</hi> 4 Mar. 2001
&lt;http://www.hinduonnet.com/thehindu/2001/03/04/stories/1304007u.htm&gt; (“Richly sourced and
imaginatively conceived, it was a splendid show”).</p>
                  <p>27 November-27 December 2003</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">The Glad Days in the Reception of Blake in Japan: The International Blake
Conference “Blake in the Orient”: A Concurrent Exhibition.</hi> &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Yoko Ima-Izumi, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.3 (2004-05): 109-15 (“The catalogue of the
exhibition will long stand as one of the most solid and reliable accounts of Blake’s legacy in Japan”
[115]).</p>
                  <p>24 February 2004</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Printed Books and Maps</hi> [to be sold] Tuesday 24 February 2004 [by]
Bonhams 101 New Bond Street, London W15 1SR. ([London: Bonhams, 2004]).</p>
                  <p>It included 47 Blake lots, with 18 letterpress books with Blake plates.</p>
                  <p>5 May 2004</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Good and Evil Angels</hi>: Property of the Green-tree
Foundation from the Collection of Mr. and Mrs. John Hay Whitney, New York May 5, 2004. This lot will be
offered as Lot 5, [Sotheby] Sale 7989, Impressionist and Modern Art. (New York: Sotheby, 2004) 4°, 19 pp.
(one a fold-out page); no ISBN.</p>
                  <p>Anon. “The Greentree Foundation: Mrs. John Hay Whitney.” 6.</p>
                  <p>*David Bindman. Untitled, about the color print. 8-19.</p>
                  <p>Estimate $1,000,000-1,500,000. It was sold for a record price of $3,928,000 (including
buyer’s commission) to a collector in Europe not previously associated with Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref>
	<note id="n41">41. For details of the sale, see Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2004,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (2005): 124, 127.</note></p>
                  <p>22 June-19 September 2004</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Heaven in a Wild Flower: William Blake’s</hi> Book of Job. Curated by
Phillip Prodger. St. Louis Art Museum, 22 June-19 September 2004.</p>
                  <p>A flyer for the exhibition of “selections from the Saint Louis Art Museum’s rare
proof edition of the <hi rend="i">Book of Job.</hi>”</p>
                  <p>July 6-October 31 2004</p>
                  <p>*Robert Woof, Howard J. M. Hanley, Stephen Hebron. Paradise Lost: <hi rend="i">The Poem
and Its Illustrators.</hi> [An exhibition 6 July-31 October 2004.] (Grasmere: Wordsworth Trust, 2004) 4°,
viii, 227 pp., 55 Blake reproductions (including all 12 from the Thomas [Huntington] set of 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>); ISBN: 1870787943.</p>
                  <p>An admirable work with splendid reproductions. The work consists of:</p>
                  <p>Allan Guest. “Sponsor’s Preface.” vi.</p>
                  <p>Robert Woof. “Foreword.” vii-viii.</p>
                  <p>*Howard J. M. Hanley. “‘Thou hadst a voice whose sound was like the sea’: Seeing
Milton’s Voice.” 1-53, including “William Blake,” 23-24.</p>
                  <p>*Robert Woof. “The Romantics and Milton.” 55-76.</p>
                  <p>“Catalogue.” 83 entries (77-221) including (47) <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> ([H]),
(48) <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> ([A]), (49) <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> drawings from the Thomas
(Huntington) set, (50-53) <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> drawings from the Butts set, and (54) a previously
unrecorded undated letter from Blake to John Linnell.</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Appendix: The Reverend Joseph Thomas.” 227.</p>
                  <p>Notices, Reviews, etc.</p>
                  <p>*Adrian Mullen, “Paradise Lost: The Poem and Its Illustrators,” 
<hi rend="i">Westmorland Gazette</hi> 2 July 2004: 3.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Rare Drawings on Show,” <hi rend="i">Keswick Reminder</hi> 2 July 2004.</p>
                  <p>*Kate Rees, “Rare Visions of Heaven and Hell,” <hi rend="i">Cumberland News</hi> 2
July 2004.</p>
                  <p>Anon., “Paradise Lost,” <hi rend="i">Carlisle News &amp; Star</hi> 3 July 2004.</p>
                  <p>*Dalya Alberge, “Returned: Blake’s pictures of Paradise Lost,” 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> 5 July 2004.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Poet’s Drawings Go On Display,” <hi rend="i">Carlisle News &amp; Star</hi>
5 July 2004.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Blake Watercolours Return to UK for Exhibition,” <hi rend="i">Scotsman</hi>
5 July 2004.</p>
                  <p>*John Ezard, “Paradise Regained: Blake’s vision on show,” 
<hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> 6 July 2004: 6 (“Arguably, the legacy of Blake’s ideas is now as great as the
influence of Wordsworth’s nature poems”).</p>
                  <p>*Ian Herbert, “Paradise Found: Blake works back in UK,” <hi rend="i">Independent</hi>
[London] 6 July 2004 (“The bicentenary of [Blake’s] <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is being celebrated”).</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Blake Watercolours Back in Britain for the First Time in Nearly a Century,”
<hi rend="i">Irish News</hi> [Belfast] 6 July 2004.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “In Pictures: Paradise Lost Exhibition,” <hi rend="i">BBC News</hi> 6 July
2004 &lt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_pictures/3870363.stm&gt;.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Blake Paintings for Grasmere,” <hi rend="i">North West Evening Mail</hi>
[Barrow-in-Furness edition] 6 July 2004.</p>
                  <p>Anon., “Blake Works at Exhibition,” <hi rend="i">Birmingham Express &amp; Star</hi> 6
July 2004.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Paradise Found at Grasmere,” <hi rend="i">North West Evening Mail</hi>
[Barrow-in-Furness edition] 8 July 2004.</p>
                  <pb id="p39-17" n="17"/>
                  <p>Anon., “Reading in Paradise,” <hi rend="i">East Cumbrian Gazette</hi> 8 July
2004.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Top Author Inspires Pupils,” <hi rend="i">Westmoreland Gazette</hi> 9 July
2004 (about Philip Pullman’s opening the exhibition).</p>
                  <p>*Anon., untitled, <hi rend="i">Church Times</hi> 9 July 2004 (merely a reproduction with
caption).</p>
                  <p>Kate Rees, “Plenty of Dark Material at Paradise Lost Exhibition,” 
<hi rend="i">Cumberland News</hi> 16 July 2004 (On the opening of the exhibition by Philip Pullman, author of 
<hi rend="i">His Dark Materials</hi>).</p>
                  <p>*Tom Paulin, “This Way to Paradise: Milton’s great poem—an English republican
allegory—has inspired generations of writers and illustrators. Now their work has been gathered together at
Wordsworth’s cottage. Tom Paulin drops in for a visit,” <hi rend="i">Guardian Review</hi> 17 July 2004:
14-15 (“Twelve illustrations by Blake . . . from the Huntington . . . dominate the exhibition”).</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Paradise Regained,” <hi rend="i">Week</hi> 20 July 2004.</p>
                  <p>*Matthew Sturgis, “Poetic Works: Matthew Sturgis hopes a new show will reinstate Milton
in the national consciousness,” <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 23 Aug. 2004: 29-30.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “If you’re only going to see one thing this week . . . Art: Milton: Paradise
Lost, the Poem and Its Illustrators,” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> 23 Aug. 2004: 15.</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Wordsworth Trust: A dozen rare Blake drawings in UK for the first time in
nearly a century,” <hi rend="i">Lancashire Today</hi> Aug. 2004.</p>
                  <p>*Clive Wilmer, “Prophet of Life and Liberty: The Romantics’ Sympathy for the Devil,
and John Milton,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 17 Sept. 2004: 18-19 (with Pamela Woof, 
<hi rend="i">Reading “Paradise Lost”</hi>).</p>
                  <p>*Anon., “Paradise Regained,” <hi rend="i">Heritage</hi> [Milton Keynes] Sept.
2004.</p>
                  <p>2004</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Blake at Work.</hi> Exhibition at Tate without printed catalogue.
&lt;http://www.tate.org.uk/servlet/CollectionDisplays?roomid=2780&gt;.</p>
                  <p>An admirable, ground-breaking exhibition.</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Antoine Capet, “Blake at Work Exhibition: Tate Britain, London,” online at H-Museum,
the H-Net Network for Museums and Museum Studies &lt;http://www.h-museum.net&gt; 13 August 2004. Reprinted in
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.3 (2004-05): 115-19 (“a magnificent introduction to ‘art appreciation’ from
the point of view of the media used” [115]).</p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part V: Books Owned by William Blake of London (1757-1827)</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>§John Dryden. <hi rend="i">Annus Mirabilis: The Year of Wonders</hi>, M.DC.LXVI [1666].
An Historical Poem: containing The Progress and various Successes of our Naval War with Holland, under the
Conduct of his Highness Prince Rupert, and His Grace The Duke of Albemarl. And describing The Fire of London.
([London]: Printed for Henry Herringman, 1668) Small 8°.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Bound with</hi><lb/>
[Jean Claude.] <hi rend="i">An Account of the Persecutions and Oppressions of the French Protestants</hi>, to
which is added, the Edict of the French King, prohibiting all Public Exercise of the Pretended Reformed
Religion in his Kingdom . . . with the Form of Abjuration the Revolting Protestants are to Subscribe and Swear
to. ([London]: Printed by G. M., 1686) Small 8°.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Bound with</hi><lb/>
[Anon.] <hi rend="i">The Life &amp; Death of that Pious, Reverend, Learned, and Laborious Minister of the
Gospel, Mr. Richard Baxter, who departed this life Decemb. 8, 1691, and of his age 77.</hi> ([London]: Printed
for Randal Taylor, 1692) 12°.</p>
                  <p>Bound in contemporary full vellum; on the front endpaper are signatures of “William
Blake” and, in modern ballpoint pen, another owner dated 1955. The Blake signature is in a hand of c. 1800
which is significantly like the poet’s.</p>
                  <p>Offered in the auction catalogue of Dominic Winter, <hi rend="i">Printed Books &amp;
Maps</hi> . . . 23 June 2004 (Swindon, Wiltshire), lot 559 (estimate £200-£300); acquired by an anonymous
collector.</p>
                  <p>Joseph Thomas. PROPOSALS | FOR PUBLISHING BY SUBSCRIPTION, | <hi rend="i">A Series of
Engravings on Wood</hi>, | FROM | SCRIPTURAL SUBJECTS, | IN THE MANNER OF | <hi rend="i">QUARLES’S
EMBLEMS</hi>, | AFTER THE | DESIGNS OF J. THURSTON, ESQ. | AND EXECUTED BY | THE MOST EMINENT ENGRAVERS ON
WOOD. | THE SUBJECTS WILL BE SELECTED, AND THE DESCRIPTIONS WRITTEN, BY | <hi rend="i">THE REV. J. THOMAS,
A.M.</hi> | Desirous that my Friend Mr. Thurston’s Talents, with which the World have long been | partially
acquainted, should be more fully known, I thought <hi rend="i">Divine Emblems</hi> particularly suited | to
his Genius, the Subjects for which might be selected from Quotations of Scripture, as in | Quarles’s
celebrated Work on the same Subject: taking care to choose such only as were | best adapted to the Wants and
Comforts of Man in his present State, and most likely to suggest | and enforce the due Preparation for a happy
Immortality.</p>
                  <p>The Art of Engraving on Wood being yet in its Infancy, and presuming, with many respec- |
table and distinguished Artists, that it is capable of producing Effects infinitely superior to what | has
hitherto been seen, the Object of this Work is to present to the Public the most perfect Spe- | cimen that has
ever yet been executed.</p>
                  <p>J. THOMAS.</p>
                  <p>CONDITIONS.</p>
                  <p>1. The Work will consist of Twenty Engravings, with a Head and Tail-piece, and will be
printed in Royal | Quarto, on India Paper, by T. Bensley, in his best Style.</p>
                  <p>2. The Price to Subscribers will be Two Guineas . . . | . . . The Price will be
considerably advanced to Non-Subscribers.</p>
                  <p>3. The Work is intended to be published with all due Dispatch. | Subscriptions are
received by Robinson and Son, Paternoster Row; Miller, Albemarle Street; Williams, | Strand; Colnaghi,
Cockspur Street; Deighton, Cambridge; and Cooke, Oxford; Parish, Circulating | Library, Epsom; Mr. Thurston,
Twickenham Common; and the Rev. Joseph Thomas, Abele Grove, | near Epsom. | - | [<hi rend="i">Printed by
Thomas Bensley</hi>] Bolt Court Printing Office, Fleet Street [<hi rend="i">?1809</hi>]. &lt;Glasgow
University Library&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>The “List of Subscribers” in the prospectus and in the published work (Ackermann,
1809) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #746&gt;) includes “William Blake, Esq.” who may well be the poet despite
the elevating “Esq.” Almost all the males in the lists who have no other 
<pb id="p39-18" n="18"/>
title (Rev., Captain, Earl, Doctor) and who are not blatantly commercial (like the booksellers) are endowed
with “Esq.”—even the Yorkshire engraver “R.H. Cromeck, Esq. 2 Copies”—just as tailors in Oxford
used to do for undergraduates, even when they were benighted colonials. Note that the designer’s style is
“J. THURSTON, ESQ.” but as a subscription collector he is “Mr. Thurston.”</p>
                  <p>The 138 subscribers include Blake’s friends and patrons W. S. Poyntz, Esq., John
Flaxman, R.A., Richard Cosway, R.A., and Henry Fuseli, R.A., for 198 copies. The subscription list in the work
as published has 178 subscribers for 249 copies, so this proposal apparently elicited 40 new subscribers
(including Mr. Charles Heath, perhaps the engraver [1785-1848]) for 51 new copies.</p>
                  <p>R. H. [Robert Hunt] says in the <hi rend="i">Examiner</hi> (July 1808): 494, “We have
lately seen some specimens” of it (there is no specimen with the prospectus) in which “Nothing . . . can
exceed these specimens in richness, sweetness, and delicacy of tint,” and <hi rend="i">The Repository of
Arts</hi> 2 (Sept. 1809): 183, 252, announced that the book would be published in September and reviewed it in
October.</p>
                  <p>The subscription price of £2.2.0 is substantial for an engraver like Blake, the sum he
might have expected for a week’s engraving work, but perhaps he had a special price or a gift because of his
special relationship with the author who, according to Nancy Flaxman (Sept. 1805) “wishes to collect all
B— has done.” Thomas commissioned from Blake his 6 watercolors for Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, 6
for his Shakespeare first folio (1806-09), 12 for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (1807), 6 for “On the
Morning of Christ’s Nativity” (1809), and also bought Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> with Blake’s
designs (1808) and <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (Q, 1810).</p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part VI: Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Ackroyd, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1996)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Penelope Fitzgerald, “Innocence and Experience,” <hi rend="i">New York Times Book
Review</hi> 14 April 1996: 5 (Ackroyd is “a brilliant guide and interpreter”).</p>
                  <p>Agha, Marisa. “UCR Professor [Robert N. Essick], Colleagues Break New Ground: William
Blake: Their web site devoted to the poet is the first electronic effort to win a key honor.” 
<hi rend="i">Press-Enterprise</hi> [Riverside, California] 1 Jan. 2004: B10.</p>
                  <p>§Ando, Kiyoshi. <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha to Furansu Kakumei—Blake, Wordsworth,
Coleridge to 1790 nendai no kakumei ronso</hi> [<hi rend="i">English Romanticism and the French
Revolution—Blake, Wordsworth, Coleridge and the Revolutionary Arguments in the 1790s</hi>]. (Tokyo: Kirihara
Shoten, 2003); ISBN: 4342627019. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Michiko Kanetake, <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu: Essays in English Romanticism</hi>
28 (2004): 102-06. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Ankarsjö, Magnus. <hi rend="i">Bring Me My Arrows of Desire: Gender Utopia in
Blake’s</hi> The Four Zoas. (Göteborg, Sweden: Acta Universitatis Gothoburgensis, 2004) Gothenburg Studies
in English 87, 4°, xi, 206 pp.; ISBN: 9173465054.</p>
                  <p>A dissertation arguing that in “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake emerges as an advocate of a utopian existence with complete gender equality”
(1).</p>
                  <p>*Anon. “And Did Blake’s Feet, in Ancient Time, Walk upon County’s Fields?” 
<hi rend="i">Gainsborough</hi> [Lincolnshire] <hi rend="i">Target</hi> 5 Mar. 2004.</p>
                  <p>David Worrall is alleged to believe that Blake “may have been inspired by fields by the
River Trent near Gainsborough” to write his “Jerusalem” hymn in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> when he
“visited the area to see his mother.”</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Blake, William.” <hi rend="i">Columbia Encyclopedia.</hi> 6th ed. (2001).
Licensed to various sites online.</p>
                  <p>Anon. “An Evening of Blake.” 10 Mar. 2004 &lt;http://www.bookbuffet.com&gt;.</p>
                  <p>On the occasion of the book launch 17 February for Janet Warner’s book, Amir Hussain
(Department of Religious Studies, California State University, Northridge) was interviewed about Blake.</p>
                  <p>*Anon. “Jerusalem, Nottinghamshire?” <hi rend="i">Misterton and West Stockwith</hi>
[Nottinghamshire] <hi rend="i">Parish News</hi> May 2004.</p>
                  <p>About the connection of Blake’s mother with Walkeringham “<hi rend="i">Courtesy
of</hi> [Anon., “And Did Blake’s Feet . . .”] <hi rend="i">Gainsborough Target</hi>,” with additional,
and this time accurate information about Blake himself.</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Midlands Stakes a Claim to William Blake Heritage.” Nottingham Trent
University electronic press release. 1 Mar. 2004.</p>
                  <p>David Worrall has won a grant of £110,000 for research on the birthplace (Walkeringham,
Nottinghamshire) and religion (Moravianism) of Blake’s mother.</p>
                  <p>*Anon. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Wikipedia</hi>: The Free Encyclopedia. Viewed
2004 &lt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Blake&gt;. Also in <hi rend="i">TutorGig Encyclopedia.</hi>
Viewed 2004 &lt;http://www.tutorgig.com/ed/William_Blake&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Ansari, A. A. “Double Perspective of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Aligarh Critical Miscellany</hi> 10 (1997): 55-85. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>A poem-by-poem analysis; the “insistent and continuous eagerness to be acclimatised to
the lost region of Eternity as an anticipatory gesture is very much in evidence in the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>” (84).</p>
                  <p>Ansari, A. A. “The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Critical
Miscellany</hi> 11 (1998): 30-44. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <pb id="p39-19" n="19"/>
                  <p>“<hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> appears in all essentials to be a shrewd, sensuous,
spirited and powerful advocacy for the tendency to stabilize and not reconcile the Contraries” (44).</p>
                  <p>Ansari, A. A. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Minor Prophecies.</hi> (2001) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Shernaz Cama, <hi rend="i">Aligarh Critical Miscellany</hi> 14.1 (2001 [Spring 2004]):
99-104 (This “particularly useful” book comes “to the conclusion that from the very beginning Blake’s
genius was individual” [99, 104]).</p>
                  <p>§Beer, F. B. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Poets: American and British.</hi> 3 vols.
(New York: Scribner’s, 1998); ISBN: 0684806053.</p>
                  <p>Apparently derived from the Scribner Writers series.</p>
                  <p>*Beer, John. “Blake’s Fear of Non-Entity.” Chapter 2 (12-20, 184-85) of his 
<hi rend="i">Romantic Consciousness: Blake to Mary Shelley.</hi> (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2003) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>“Throughout the Prophetic Books, the prospect of falling into ‘Non-Entity’ . . . is
the ultimate nightmare” (19).</p>
                  <p>§Behrendt, Stephen C. “‘The Soul of Sweet Delight’: Blake and the Sensual Soul.”
<hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 15 (2004): 409-23.</p>
                  <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Blake and the Xenoglots: Strange-Speaking Critics and Scholars of
Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> 2005 &lt;http://www.blakequarterly.org/bentleyxenoglots.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Blake scholarship and criticism 1811-2004 is in 37 non-English languages (2,490 essays in
all), including French (267), German (254), Italian (155) and Spanish and Catalan (221), but 48% are in
Japanese (1,196); “let us admit that we are all more extensively ignorant than we had thought.”</p>
                  <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> Second Edition: Documents (1714-1841)
Concerning the Life of William Blake (1757-1827) and His Family, Incorporating <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
(1969), <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> (1988), and Extensive Discoveries since 1988. (New Haven
and London: Published for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art by Yale University Press, 2004)
8°, xxxviii, 943 pp., 103 reproductions; ISBN: 0300096852.</p>
                  <p>It adds to <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi>
“New References to Blake” (xxiii-xxiv), “Seven Red Herrings” (xxv-xxix, 847-48), “Genealogies of
Blake, Armitage, Boucher-Butcher” (xxx-xxxiv, 848), Appendix I G: “John Clark Strange MS Journal
(1859-61)” (707-32), Appendix V: “Blake’s Poems Reprinted, 1806-1849” (825-28, 878-79), and Appendix
VI: “‘My Name is Legion: for we are many’: ‘William Blake’ in London 1740-1830” (829-46, 879). It
omits the introduction: “Blake the Man: The Public and the Buried Life” and Appendix II: “Blake’s
Library” from <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> (1988) xxii-xli, 124-29.</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>*Seamus Perry, “The Wise Man’s Table: In William Blake’s world, nothing is what it
first seems,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 Oct. 2004: 3-4 (with Morton D. Paley, 
<hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening</hi> [2003]) (a “magnificent,” “exhaustive,” “wholly
absorbing” “masterpiece . . . that reads like an augmented epistolary novel”).</p>
                  <p>Anon., “The Pick of the Year: Looking for the perfect book to give someone this
Christmas? Read on for our reviewers’ recommendations,” <hi rend="i">Evening Standard</hi> [London] 29
Nov. 2004. Anon., “Chapter and Verse on 2004: Critics select their favourite books of the last 12 months,”
<hi rend="i">Yorkshire Post Magazine</hi> 11 Dec. 2004: 26-27 (John Mullan calls it “a biography
unobstructed by the self-regard of a biographer, an achievement of passionate scholarship”).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">42</ref>
	<note id="n42">42. There is no apparent difference between the two Anon. reviews (aside from the title and
the omission in the <hi rend="i">Yorkshire Post Magazine</hi> of the few photos in the <hi rend="i">Evening
Standard</hi>) and no apparent acknowledgement in the <hi rend="i">Yorkshire Post Magazine</hi> that its essay
is merely a reprint.</note></p>
                  <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Blake’s Visionary Heads: Lost Drawings and a Lost Book.”
Chapter 12 (183-205) of <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Millenarianism.</hi> Ed. Tim Fulford. (2002) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.1 (2004): 43-47 (a summary).</p>
                  <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise.</hi> (2001) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Kathryn Freeman, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 44 (2002): 297-301 (“meticulously”
researched, “deftly” written, the book gives “the most nuanced and intimate portrait yet of Blake at
each phase of . . . life” [297]).</p>
                  <p>Alexander Gourlay, <hi rend="i">BARS Bulletin &amp; Review</hi> no. 23 (Mar. 2003): 25-27
(here “hard evidence drives out all the fuzzy kinds,” and there is little speculation about the poet’s
“inner” life, but “its enduring value as a readable summary of the latest and hardest biographical
evidence is secure” [26, 27]) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2003)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Paul Youngquist, <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Literature</hi> 57 (2002): 414-18 (“a
new standard for biographical writing on Blake,” “monumental” and “beautiful,” characterized by
“indomitable learning”).</p>
                  <p>*Jöran Mjöberg, “Flöjtspelaren som såg himmel och helvete: Som sexåring såg
William Blake ett träd fullt av änglar framför sig. Liknande visioner präglade hans liv sålväl som hans
måleri och poesi, där hans politiska patos förenades med ett säreget system av myter och symboler. Nu
föreligger en biografi av den framstående Blake-kännaren G E Bentley Jr.,” <hi rend="i">Svenska
Dagbladet</hi> 4 Apr. 2004: 9, in Swedish (“Bentley är en nästan perfektionistisk litteraturvetare, som
belyser Blakes liv, familj, tidsbakgrund, arbetssituation och även gravyrteknik samt redovisar [Bentley is an
almost perfectionist literary
<pb id="p39-20" n="20"/>
scholar who throws light on Blake’s life, family as well as on the times in which he lived, his work
situation and even his technique of engraving]”).</p>
                  <p>§Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">La Questione Romantica</hi> (Sept. 2004).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 37, no. 4 (Spring [14 April]
2004)</p>
                  <p>*Robert N. Essick. “Blake in the Marketplace, 2003.” 116-36. (Masterful.)</p>
                  <p>*Robert W. Rix. “Blake, Bacon and ‘The Devils Arse.’” 137-44.</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Nancy Moore Goslee. Review of Dee Drake, <hi rend="i">Searing Apparent Surfaces: Infernal
Females in Four Early Works of William Blake</hi> (2000). 144-48.</p>
                  <p>Daniel Gustav Anderson. Review of Subir Dhar, <hi rend="i">Burning Bright: William Blake
and the Poetry of Imagination</hi> (2001). 149-50.</p>
                  <p>Corrigenda &amp; Addenda</p>
                  <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr. “<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, Second Edition.” 151.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 38, no. 1 (Summer [12 July]
2004)</p>
                  <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., with the assistance of Hikari Sato for publications in Japan and of
Ching-erh Chang for publications in Taiwan. “William Blake and His Circle.” 4-35. (“Blake studies are
alive and well. . . . This checklist records 50 books, 205 essays, and 47 reviews” in English, Chinese,
French, German, Hebrew, Hungarian, Italian, Japanese, Korean, Russian, and Spanish [5].)</p>
                  <p>Keri Davies and Marsha Keith Schuchard. “Recovering the Lost Moravian History of
William Blake’s Family.” 36-43. (A major discovery which will echo through Blake studies.)</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Andrew Lincoln. Review of Tim Fulford, ed., <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Millenarianism</hi> (2002). 43-47. (A summary of each essay.)</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 38, no. 2 (Fall [28 October]
2004)</p>
                  <p>*Mary Lynn Johnson. “Blake’s Engravings for Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>: Overdue Credit to Chodowiecki, Schellenberg, and Lips.” 52-74. (A brilliant
analysis of the graphic and bibliographical intricacies of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>,
identifying for the first time the sources of three of Blake’s engravings.)</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Jennifer Davis Michael. Review of Kevin Hutchings, <hi rend="i">Imagining Nature:
Blake’s Environmental Poetics</hi> (2002). 75-77. (A “powerful,” “impressive book”; “This book
will change forever the way we read Blake’s reading of nature.”)</p>
                  <p>Catherine L. McClenahan. Review of Robert N. Essick, ed., <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi> (2002). 77-79. (“<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> could scarcely ask for a more
experienced and informed editor,” who has provided a “lucid” commentary.)</p>
                  <p>Dena Bain Taylor. Review of Sheila A. Spector, <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”: The
Development of Blake’s Kabbalistic Myth</hi> (2001). 79-85. (“‘<hi rend="i">Wonders Divine</hi>’
offers a brilliant explication of the kabbalistic pattern of Blake’s development .... the next step is to
link Blake’s Kabbalah more firmly with the Christian esoteric tradition” [85].)</p>
                  <p>Kathleen Lundeen. Review of Nick Rawlinson, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Comic
Vision</hi> (2003). 85-87. (Rawlinson “allows us to hear Blake in a different key.”)</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 38, no. 3 (Winter [24 January]
2004-05)</p>
                  <p>*Adam Komisaruk. “Introducing The Blake Model.” 92-102. (A “prospectus” to “an
immersive digital environment through which users might navigate to encounter Blake’s characters, places and
objects” “Using the digital modeling program Bryce 3D (Corel)” [93].)</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>*Thomas Frosch. Review of Tristanne J. Connolly, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
Body</hi> (2002). 102-07. (The book is “more notable for its highlighting of issues, questions, and
complexities than for persuasive or vivid formulations” [106].)</p>
                  <p>Joseph Wittreich. Review of Alexander S. Gourlay, ed., <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character:
Essays on William Blake in Honor of John E. Grant</hi> (2002). 107-09. (“In the eloquent testimony of all
these essays, . . . Grant is a mental prince” who has produced “nearly half a century of dazzling
scholarship” [109].)</p>
                  <p>Yoko Ima-Izumi. Review of “The Program of the International Blake Conference 
<hi rend="i">Blake in the Orient</hi> and the Catalogue of a Concurrent Exhibition <hi rend="i">The Reception of
Blake in Japan</hi>” (2003). 109-15. (“The catalogue of the exhibition will long stand as one of the most
solid and reliable accounts of Blake’s legacy in Japan” [115].)</p>
                  <p>Antoine Capet. Review of “Blake at Work Exhibition, Tate Britain, London.” 115-19.
(“A magnificent introduction to ‘art appreciation’ from the point of view of the media used” [115].)
“This review . . . first appeared online at H-Museum, the H-Net Network for Museums and Museum Studies
&lt;http://www.h-museum.net&gt;, on 13 August 2004.”</p>
                  <p>David Shaddock. “Nobodaddy Wakes from His Slumber (After Blake 12).” 119. (A
poem.)</p>
                  <p>Newsletter</p>
                  <p>“Go to &lt;http://www.blakequarterly.org&gt; for . . . G. E. Bentley, Jr., ‘Blake and
the Xenoglots’ [and] ‘A report by Susanne Sklar on a recent reading of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>’”
119.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> No. 8 ([June] 2004)</p>
                  <p>Chad E. Rackowitz. “‘Auguries of Innocence’: Blake’s Fractal Poem.” 4-27.
(“Fractals . . . exhibit detailed structure at all scales”; in “Auguries of Innocence,” the 128 lines
[2<hi rend="s">7</hi>] [omitting the introductory quatrain] are here observed “on a number of different
scales to see its pattern of self-similar scaling” [5, 7].)</p>
                  <pb id="p39-21" n="21"/>
                  <p>Shirley Mungapen. “Catherine Blake’s Fireside.” 28-29. (A poem.)</p>
                  <p>Angus Whitehead. “William Blocke’: New References to Blake in <hi rend="i">Boyle’s
City Guide</hi> (1797) and <hi rend="i">Boyle’s City Companion</hi> (1798).” 30-46.</p>
                  <p>Shirley Mungapen. “Little Girl Lost.” 47, 49. (A poem about Blake.)</p>
                  <p>*Jason Whittaker. “‘The poetical vigour of history’: Blake’s Use of Milton’s
<hi rend="i">History of Britain.</hi>” 50-63. (“<hi rend="i">The History</hi> is, as I believe, the most
important text for Blake’s notions of the antiquity of Britain” [55].)</p>
                  <p>Jim McCord. “17 South Molton Street.” 64-65. (A poem.)</p>
                  <p>*Susanne Sklar. “Jerusalem’s Embrace.” 66-73. (“In [<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>]
plate 99, the poem climaxes as Albion embraces his emanation in petals of name [flame?], fountains of living
water” [73].)</p>
                  <p>Shirley Mungapen. “Dennis Severs’ Silk-Weaver’s House, Spitalfields.” 75-78,
80.</p>
                  <p>“Kathleen Raine, 1908-2003”</p>
                  <p>Andrew Vernède. “The Transcendental Cheek (Memories of Kathleen Raine).” 82-84.</p>
                  <p>Mary Gifford Brown. “Tea-Time Memories.” 85-86. (“Kathleen was a splendid
cake-maker.”)</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Will Easton. Review of K. E. Smith, <hi rend="i">William Cowper: A Reappraisal</hi>
([Olney]: Cowper and Newton Museum, 2003). 87-89. Andrew Solomon. Review of “Lucien Posman, ‘Some Blake
Works’ (Cyprès CYP 4616) Performed by the Goeyvaerts Consort directed by Marc Michael De Smet, with Els
Crommen (soprano), Marc Legros (flute), and Bart Meynckens (piano).” 89-91. (The CD is “an interesting
addition to the repertoire of Blake settings.”)</p>
                  <p>*Tim Heath. “Which is the Way The Right or the Left.” Review of <hi rend="i">The
Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves. 92. (The “review” consists of a design of a
blossom with Blake’s head at the center and petals bearing the names of authors and titles of essays,
underprinted with “IS THIS TO BE DIVINE IN DIGITAL.”)</p>
                  <p>Peter Cadogan. Review of “‘A Man without a Mask’ performed by Ruth Rosen at the New
End Theatre, part of the Sixth Hampstead &amp; Highgate Festival, May 11th, 2003 at 8 p.m. and May 12th at
3:30 p.m. and 8 p.m.” 93. (“It worked by virtue of its very simplicity, a delightful disguise for
sophistication and hard work.”)</p>
                  <p>Bower, Peter. “The Evolution and Development of ‘Drawing Papers’ and the Effect of
This Development on Watercolour Artists, 1750-1850.” 61-74 of <hi rend="i">The Oxford Papers: Proceedings of
the British Association of Paper Historians Fourth Annual Conference, Held at St. Edmund Hall, Oxford, 17-19
September 1993.</hi> Ed. Peter Bower. (London: British Association of Paper Historians, 1996) Studies in
British Paper History, Vol. 1.</p>
                  <p>“Blake’s Papermakers: Watermarks Found in Papers Used by William Blake (1757-1827)”
(72-73) in “Appendix: Watermarks Found in Papers Used by William Blake (1757-1827), John Constable
(1776-1837) and John Sell Cotman (1782-1842)” (72-74) gives the name and mill of each papermaker identified
by a watermark.</p>
                  <p>Brooke, Stopford A. “William Blake.” 1-54 of his <hi rend="i">Studies in Poetry.</hi>
(London, 1907) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1291&gt; B. §<hi rend="i">Great English Poets and Their Works.</hi>
(Delhi: Shubhi, 2002).</p>
                  <p>Butlin, Martin. “Word as Image in William Blake.” Chapter 13 (207-17) of 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Millenarianism.</hi> Ed. Tim Fulford. (2002) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.1 (2004): 43-47 (a summary).</p>
                  <p>§Chauvin, Danièle. “Londres dans l’oeuvre poétique de William Blake: La mémoire,
le mythe et l’art.” 19-30 in <hi rend="i">La Mémoire des villes: L’inscription de l’histoire dans
l’espace urbain, du romantisme à nos jours.</hi> Ed. Yves Clavaron and Bernard Dieterle. (St.-Etienne:
Presses Universitaires de Saint-Etienne, 2003); ISBN: 2862722758. In French.</p>
                  <p>Compares London and Jerusalem.</p>
                  <p>Chen, Zhifan. “Wen dao yu mang [Seeking Advice from an Ignorant Person].” 
<hi rend="i">Lianhe bao</hi> [<hi rend="i">United Daily News</hi>, Taipei] 1 Nov. 1993: 37 (Literary Supplement).
In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>For a reply, see Mu Yang.</p>
                  <p>§Chong, Cue-huan. “[Blake’s Poetics of Self-Liberation and Holistic Imagination].”
<hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and Literature: Yongo Yongmunhak</hi> 44 (1998): 275-98. In Korean,
with an English summary.</p>
                  <p>§Chong, Cue-huan. “[The Muse and the Femininity of the Other: Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs].” <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Literature in English</hi> 4 (1998): 119-49.
In Korean, with an English summary.</p>
                  <p>*Clark, Madeline. “The Theosophy of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Sunrise
Magazine.</hi> (Dec. 2000-Jan. 2001) &lt;http://www.theosociety.org/pasadena/sunrise/50-00-1/ar-mclk6.htm&gt;.
B. “De theosofie van William Blake.”
&lt;http://www.theosofie.net/sunrise/sunrise2001/meijuni2001/blake.html&gt;. In Dutch.</p>
                  <p>Connolly, Tristanne J. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Body.</hi> (2002) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>*Thomas Frosch, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.3 (2004-05): 102-07 (The book is “more
notable for its highlighting of issues, questions, and complexities than for persuasive or vivid
formulations” [106]).</p>
                  <p>[Cooper, Joe and Edna.] “Did You Know that the Mother of William Blake (1757-1827) Was
a Moravian[?]” <hi rend="i">Moravian</hi>
	<pb id="p39-22" n="22"/>
	<hi rend="i">History Magazine</hi> no. 20 (18th and 19th Century Personalities) (Sept. 2001): 31.</p>
                  <p>§Corbett, William. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">World Poets.</hi> Ed. Ron Padgett.
3 vols. (New York: Scribner’s, 2000) Scribner Writers series; ISBN: 068480591X.</p>
                  <p>Corti, Claudia. “Blake, Goethe e le arti sorelle.” 191-202 of <hi rend="i">Il primato
dell’occhio: Poesia e pittura nell’età di Goethe.</hi> Ed. Emilio Bonfatti and Maria Fancelli. (Roma:
Artemide Edizioni, 1997) “Proteo” 41. In Italian. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Concerned with “Arti sorelle o arte composita?” (198).</p>
                  <p>§Corti, Claudia. <hi rend="i">Stupende fantasie: Saggi su William Blake.</hi> (Pisa:
Pacini, 2002) Studi di Letterature Moderne e Comparate 6, 254 pp.; ISBN: 887781442X. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>Cunningham, Allan. “William Blake.” 2: 140-79 of his <hi rend="i">The Lives of the
Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi> . . . (1829-98) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1433&gt;</p>
                  <p>A set of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> in the National Library of Scotland (MS.
827) with ms. notes on the life of Blake from the second edition (1830) by Allan’s son Francis<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref> carries information from Malkin (1806)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #482&gt;, Robert Hunt in the <hi rend="i">Examiner</hi> (1808) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1912&gt; and (1809) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1911&gt;, Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Cabinet
Gallery of Pictures</hi> (1833) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1431&gt;, Gilchrist (1863) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1680&gt;, and Swinburne (1868) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2795&gt;—but, oddly, not Cromek’s letter to
Blake of May 1807 which Cunningham’s son Peter (1816-69) lent for publication in the 
<hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> (1852) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> p. 280&gt;. The notes were apparently
used by Mrs. Charles Heaton in her edition of Cunningham’s life (1880). The only previously unrecorded
information seems to be that on MS. f. 92: “I saw in Harvey’s shop (1867) an exquisite little drawing of
Angeli non Angli.” Butlin (#55) records that the drawing was sold in 1862 to Palser and that Francis Harvey
sold it in 1869 to the Victoria &amp; Albert Museum. Clearly Harvey had it by 1867. <note id="n43">43. The
hand is that of the note among them signed “F.C.” (MS 831, f. 172) and of Francis Cunningham’s letter to
Thomas Carlyle in 1869 (MS 1769, f. 119), according to Iain G. Brown, Principal Curator, Manuscripts Division,
National Library of Scotland.</note></p>
                  <p>This is <hi rend="i">not the manuscript of Cunningham’s Lives</hi>, as claimed in the
<hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography.</hi></p>
                  <p>Curnutte, Rick, “Mad Poets: William Blake, Jim Jarmusch and <hi rend="i">Dead
Man.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Film Journal</hi> 1 (2002).
&lt;http://www.thefilmjournal.com/issuel/curnuttedeadman.html&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>The American Indian idea that “life [is] a journey that continues even after death . .
. is at the core of the relationship between William Blake and <hi rend="i">Dead Man.</hi>”</p>
                  <p>Davies, Alan Philip Keri. “William Blake in Contexts: Family, Friendships, and Some
Intellectual Microcultures of Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-Century England.” Surrey Ph.D., 2003; 375 pp., 27
reproductions.</p>
                  <p>An extraordinarily original and mature dissertation, with valuable new information in
chapters</p>
                  <p>I. “Catherine Armitage: the family context” (34-58): Blake’s mother was baptized on
25 November 1725 in Walkeringham, Nottinghamshire. Davies’ essay “William Blake’s Mother: A New
Identification,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 33.2 (1999): 36-50 “forms the basis of . . . Chapter I”
(3).</p>
                  <p>II. “Rebekah Bliss: a book-collecting context” (59-91): Her extraordinary library,
including <hi rend="i">For Children</hi> (A) and <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (P), is “a possible vector of
influence on Blake’s art” (63). The chapter “began” in his “Mrs Bliss: A Blake Collector of 1794,”
212-30 of <hi rend="i">Blake in the Nineties</hi>, ed. Steve Clark and David Worrall (1999).</p>
                  <p>III. “Richard Twiss: the context of a circle of connoisseurs” (92-133).</p>
                  <p>IV. “Alexander Tilloch: the context of printing technology” (134-86): Tilly Lally
(Lally is a diminutive of “Alexander”) in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> may be Alexander
Tilloch, scientist, alchemist, Rosicrucian, book collector, journalist, stereotype inventor, and
Dissenter.</p>
                  <p>V. “Isaac Newton: the context of a private library” (187-224): Books in Tilloch’s
remarkable library included scientific, alchemical, and astrological works which could have influenced
Blake.</p>
                  <p>VI. “Samuel Varley: the context of (al)chemical science” (225-50): “Inflammable
Gass, the Wind Finder” in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> is “most likely Samuel Varley” (232),
uncle of Blake’s friend John Varley.</p>
                  <p>VII. “William Muir: a context for the <hi rend="i">Blake Press</hi> facsimiles”
(251-78): “A first version” of Chapter VII was published in his “William Muir and the Blake Press at
Edmonton with Muir’s Letters to Kerrison Preston,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 27.1 (1993): 14-25 (4).</p>
                  <p>VIII. “Catherine Wright: the religious context” (279-307): Blake’s mother and her
first husband were members of the Moravian Church in Fetter Lane in 1750?-52, and their (previously unknown)
baby was buried there in 1751.</p>
                  <p>There are also genealogical tables of:
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p>[1] “Descendants of Richard Armitage (father of Thomas)” (Blake’s stepfather) (364)</p></item>
	<item><p>[2] “Descendants of Thomas Gorham (including Rebekah Bliss and William Fuller Maitland)”
(365-67)</p></item>
	<item><p>[3] “Descendants of William Muir of Kilmarnock” (368)</p></item>
	<item><p>[4] “Descendants of John Tilloch (including Alexander Tilloch and William Muir)”
(369-70)</p></item>
	<item><p>[5] “Descendants of — Twiss (grandfather of Richard)” (371-72)</p></item>
	<item><p>[6] “Descendants of John Varley (father of Samuel, grandfather of John)” (373-74)</p></item>
	<item><p>[7] “Descendants of Gervase Wright (grandfather of William Blake)” (375)</p></item>
</list></p>
                  <pb id="p39-23" n="23"/>
                  <p>Dhar, Subir. <hi rend="i">Burning Bright: William Blake and the Poetry of
Imagination.</hi> (2001) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Daniel Gustav Anderson, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.4 (2004): 149-50.</p>
                  <p>*Dimock, Wai Chee. “Nonbiological Clock: Literary History against Newtonian
Mechanics.” <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Quarterly</hi> 102 (2003): 153-77.</p>
                  <p>Especially about Blake, Newton, and Dante; “If physics has anything to tell us, it is
that Blake’s arguments are worth revisiting” (154).</p>
                  <p>Directories<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">44</ref>
	<note id="n44">44. Information about Boyle’s directories and the <hi rend="i">Universal British
Directory</hi> (1799) derives from Angus Whitehead (see the entry under <hi rend="i">Blake
Journal</hi>).</note></p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Boyle’s City Companion to the Court Guide for the Year 1798</hi> (1798) is
merely a reprint of <hi rend="i">Boyle’s New London Guide</hi> (1797).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Boyle’s New London Guide</hi> (London: P. Boyle, 1795) 26 for “Blake
&amp; Sons, hosiers and haberdash. 28, Broad-st. Carnaby-mar.”</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Boyle’s New London Guide for the Year 1797</hi> (London: P. Boyle, 1797)
34 for “Blocke, William,—13 Hercules [Buildings, Lambeth]” and, under 13, Hercules Buildings, Lambeth
“William Blocke,” at the address of the poet.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Universal British Directory</hi> (London, 1797) 77 for James Blake.</p>
                  <p>Drake, Dee. <hi rend="i">Searing Apparent Surfaces: Infernal Females in Four Early Works
of William Blake.</hi> (2000) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2001), (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Nancy Moore Goslee, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.4 (2004): 144-48.</p>
                  <p>§Drechsler, Maximiliane. “Geister und Dämonen aus dem Jenseits: William Blakes
‘Pitt’ und ‘Nelson.’” 103-07 of her <hi rend="i">Zwischen Kunst und Kommerz: Zur Geschichte des
Ausstellungswesens zwischen 1775 und 1905.</hi> (München: Deutscher Kunstverlag, 1996) Kunstwissenschaftliche
Studien 63. In German.</p>
                  <p>Part of a dissertation turned into a book on Blake’s exhibition (1809-10). Other
sections are on Barry’s exhibition strategies.</p>
                  <p>*Eaves, Morris, ed. <hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake.</hi> (2003)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>§Detlef W. Dörrbecker, <hi rend="i">BARS Bulletin &amp; Review</hi> no. 25 (Mar. 2004):
30-31.</p>
                  <p>*Tim Heath, “Which is the Way The Right or the Left,” <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi>
no. 8 (2004): 92 (The “review” consists of a design of a blossom with Blake’s head at the center and
petals bearing the names of authors and titles of essays, underprinted with “IS THIS TO BE DIVINE IN
DIGITAL”).</p>
                  <p>Eaves, Morris, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi. “The William Blake Archive: The
Medium, When the Millennium is the Message.” Chapter 14 (219-33) of <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Millenarianism.</hi> Ed. Tim Fulford. (2002) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.1 (2004): 43-47 (a summary).</p>
                  <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake [<hi rend="i">née</hi> Boucher], Catherine Sophia
(1762-1831), wife and assistant to William Blake ....” 6: 94 of the <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of
National Biography.</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004).</p>
                  <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake William (1757-1827), engraver, artist, and poet ....” 6:
119-130 of the <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography.</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press,
2004).</p>
                  <p>It replaces the account by Anne Gilchrist in 5: 180-84 of the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of
National Biography</hi> (1886) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1682&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Fischer, Kevin. <hi rend="i">Converse in the Spirit: William Blake, Jacob Boehme, and the
Creative Spirit.</hi> (Madison: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 2004) 4°, 258 pp.; ISBN:
0838640060.</p>
                  <p>“The difficulty of reading each visionary is considerably lessened if each is read in
the light of each other. To an extent, Blake and Boehme may, through ‘the Holy Ghost . . . the 
<hi rend="i">only</hi> Key,’ be seen as a key to each other” (67).</p>
                  <p>*Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study of William Blake.</hi> (1947 ff.)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1646&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 478&gt; I. <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye’s
Fearful Symmetry: A Study of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Nicholas Halmi. (Toronto: University of Toronto Press,
2004) Collected Works of Northrop Frye Volume 14, 4°, l, 516 pp.; ISBN: 0802089836.</p>
                  <p>In the collected edition are “Editor’s Preface” (ix-xiii), “Note on the Citation
of Blake’s Writings” (xv-xvii), “Abbreviations and Short Titles” (xix-xxi), Ian Singer,
“Introduction” (xxiii-1), “Preface to the 1969 Edition” (5-7), text (9-418), “Appendix A: Preface to
the Beacon Press Edition 1962” (419-20), “Appendix B: Preface to the Italian Translation of 
<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> 1976” (421-22), “Appendix C: Frye’s Shorter Writings on Blake”
(423-24), “Notes” (425-78), “Emendations” (479-81), “Index” (483-516).</p>
                  <p>§*Galvin, Rachel. “William Blake: Visions and Verses.” <hi rend="i">Humanities: The
Magazine of the National Endowment for the Humanities</hi> 25.3 (May-June 2004): 16-20.</p>
                  <p>A general essay on Blake prompted by the NEH support for the online William Blake
Archive. GEB is told that “All the statements attributed to ‘Eaves’ were actually uttered by Essick over
the telephone.”</p>
                  <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Richard Holmes.
(Harper Perennial, 2004 [rescheduled for 2005]) Flamingo Classic Biographies.</p>
                  <p>Notices, Reviews, etc.</p>
                  <p>*Richard Holmes, “Saving Blake: When he died in 1827, William Blake was widely regarded
as ‘mad’. His reputation was
<pb id="p39-24" n="24"/>
restored by an extraordinary biography, begun by a young lawyer and finished by his wife. Richard Holmes
celebrates the work of Alexander and Anne Gilchrist,” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> 29 May 2004: Review 34-35
(an extract from Holmes’ introduction, with information on ordering).</p>
                  <p>*Matt Shinn, “On a Classic Biography that Rescued the Visionary Poet from Obscurity,”
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> 28 July 2004 (Gilchrist’s biography, to be “reprinted next week,” is “a great
read”).</p>
                  <p>Gilchrist, Anne. <hi rend="i">Anne Gilchrist: Her Life and Writings.</hi> (London: T.
Fisher Unwin, 1887) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1681&gt; B. Second Edition. (London: T. Fisher Unwin, 1887).</p>
                  <p>The “Second Edition” is either a reissue of the same sheets or a reprint from
standing type, in either case with the title page slightly emended.</p>
                  <p>*Gilpin, George H. “William Blake and the World’s Body of Science.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 43 (2004): 35-56.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> may have been “intended as an anti-elegy”
countering the lavish mortuary praise for Dr. John Hunter on his death in 1793, and Urizen is “a more
sophisticated, cosmological version of the gruesome ‘Jack Tearguts’” (40, 42).</p>
                  <p>Gimeno, Francisco. “William Blake, vidente de este cielo.” <hi rend="i">Caracteres
literarios: Ensayos sobre la ética de la literatura</hi> Año 6, no. 7 (2003): 43-80. In Spanish.</p>
                  <p>Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">The Piper and The Bard: A Study of William Blake.</hi>
(1959) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1702&gt; B. §(2003)</p>
                  <p>§Goslee, Nancy Moore. “‘Soul-shudd’ring Vacuum’: Space for Subjects in Later
Blake.” <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 15 (2004): 391-407.</p>
                  <p>Gourlay, Alexander S., ed. <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William Blake in
Honor of John E. Grant.</hi> (2002) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Joseph Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.3 (2004-05): 107-09 (“In the eloquent
testimony of all these essays, . . . Grant is a mental prince” who has produced “nearly half a century of
dazzling scholarship” [109]).</p>
                  <p>Hamilton, William L. “House Proud: Dürers Near the Kitchen, William Blake in the
Bedroom.” <hi rend="i">New York Times</hi> 14 Oct. 2004.</p>
                  <p>On the collection of Charles Ryskamp in Princeton.</p>
                  <p>Hayes, Elliott. <hi rend="i">Blake: Innocence and Experience: A Play.</hi> (1983) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 503&gt;</p>
                  <p>A two-act monologue consisting mostly of quotations from Blake.</p>
                  <p>Elliott Hayes. <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>: A Staged Reading. Directed by Richard Monette,
Music by Lawrence Stevenson (Toronto: Recorded in front of an audience, CBC Broadcast Centre, April 1995);
ISBN: 0660179717. One cassette, with liner notes by Barbara Worthy.</p>
                  <p>*Hayes, Tom. “William Blake’s Androgynous Ego-Ideal.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 71
(2004): 141-65.</p>
                  <p>Blake’s Visionary Head of “the Man Who Instructed Blake in His Dreams” “is
Blake’s ego-ideal . . . how Blake would like to have looked if he had been able to avoid conforming to the
code of heterosexual masculinity”; it is “a metonym of socalled queer desire” (143, 144).</p>
                  <p>Hazlitt, William. <hi rend="i">Lectures on the English Poets.</hi> (London, 1818).</p>
                  <p>The date is 1818 (as in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969] 254fn3, 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 865 endnote 93), not 1819 (as in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1816), as Robert N. Essick,
“Blake in the Marketplace, 2004,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (2005): 136 points out gently.</p>
                  <p>§Heringman, Noah. “Blake, Geology, and Primordial Substance.” Chapter 3 (94-137) in
his <hi rend="i">Romantic Rocks: Aesthetic Geology.</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2004).</p>
                  <p>[Hollis, Derek, Vicar of Walkeringham.] “Did you see the article in ‘The Guardian’
on Wednesday March 3d which revealed a connection between the artist and poet William Blake (1757-1827) and
the village of Walkeringham?” <hi rend="i">Walkeringham and Beckingham Newsletter</hi> Apr. 2004: 6.</p>
                  <p>[Hollis, Derek.] “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Walkeringham and Beckingham
Newsletter</hi> Aug. 2004: 5.</p>
                  <p>“Can anyone help with research into William Blake’s connection with Walkeringham
[for] Professor G. E. Bentley, Jr. of Toronto?”</p>
                  <p>Horne, Herbert P. “Blake’s Sibylline Leaf on Homer and Virgil.” 
<hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> 2 (1887): 115-16. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1885&gt;</p>
                  <p>According to Keri Davies’ thesis “William Blake in Contexts” (2003) 268,
“Muir’s facsimile and that printed with Herbert R. [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] Horne, ‘Blake’s Sibylline
Leaf on Homer and Virgil’, <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi>, 2 (1887), 115-16, differ in many
respects and are unlikely to derive from the same lithographic plate,” though <hi rend="i">BB</hi> pp. 488,
836 imply they are the same.</p>
                  <p>Hutchings, Kevin. <hi rend="i">Imagining Nature: Blake’s Environmental Poetics.</hi>
(2002) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Jennifer Davis Michael, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.2 (2004): 75-77 (A “powerful,”
“impressive book” which “will change forever the way we read Blake’s reading of nature”).</p>
                  <p>*Hutchings, Kevin D. “William Blake and ‘The Nature of Infinity’: 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>’s Environmental Poetics.” <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Contexts</hi> 25 (2003):
55-77.</p>
                  <pb id="p39-25" n="25"/>
                  <p>“Blake’s alternative vision of nature, ‘the nature of infinity,’” involved
“an expansive, open, complexly interrelated system of temporal cycles, the multifaceted temporal
structure” (71).</p>
                  <p>§Iwasaki, Toyotaro. <hi rend="i">Roman Shugi no shi to kaiga</hi> [<hi rend="i">The
Poetry and Paintings of Romanticism</hi>]—<hi rend="i">Blake, Wordsworth, Turner and Constable.</hi> (Tokyo:
Eichosha, 2002) 224 pp.; ISBN: 4268003657. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Mamiko Katayama, <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu: Essays in English Romanticism</hi>
27 (2003): 104-08. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Jackson, M. W. “Blake’s Appropriation of the Newtonian ‘Moment.’” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 249 (N.S. 51) (2004): 134-36.</p>
                  <p>“Blake dismantles the mechanical stasis of the Newtonian cosmology by focusing on
Newton’s mathematical definition of the ‘moment’ as measurable time” (135).</p>
                  <p>§John, Donald. “‘They became what they beheld’: Theodicy and Regeneration in
Milton, Law, and Blake.” In <hi rend="i">Radicalism in British Literary Culture 1650-1830.</hi> Ed. Timothy
Morton and Nigel Smith. (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002).</p>
                  <p>§Kang, Ok-Sun. “[A Reading of Blake’s Prophetic Poems from the Point of View of
Feminism].” <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Literature in English</hi> 5 (2001): 5-25. In Korean, with a
summary in English.</p>
                  <p>§Kang, Ok-Sun. “[A Study of the Image of the Father in William Blake’s
Poems—Focusing on <hi rend="i">The Songs of Experience</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>].” 
<hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and Literature: Yongo Yongmunhak</hi> 45 (1999): 117-36. In Korean, with
an English summary.</p>
                  <p>§Kang, Ok-Sun. “[William Blake’s Prophetic Poems and His Social Consciousness:
Focusing on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Journal of
English Language and Literature</hi>: <hi rend="i">Yongo Yongmunhak</hi> 47 (2001): 755-73. In Korean, with an
English summary.</p>
                  <p>§Kashiwabara, Ikuko. “William Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> Spring ni
okeru shi teki geijutsu shi teki gengo [Poetic Art and Language in ‘Spring’ in William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Osaka Denki Tsushin Daigaku Ningen Kagaku Kenkyu</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Osaka Electro-Communication University, Research in the Humanities</hi>] 6 (2004): 9-13. In
Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Kawasaki, Noriko. “Richi no kako, ‘kage no josei’ no baai—Blake no 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> da 18 [20] yo ni tsuite [An Error of Reason, the Case of ‘the Shadowy Female’ about
the 18th (20th) Plate of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Gifu Shiritsu Joshi Tanki
Daigaku Kenkyu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Gifu City Junior College</hi>] 53 (2003): 325-40. In
Japanese.</p>
                  <p>*Kelleway, Kelly. “The Strange Attraction of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Reconstruction: A Culture Studies eJournal</hi> 2 (2002): 32 paragraphs
&lt;http://www.reconstruction.ws/021/Urizen.htm&gt;. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>“<hi rend="i">U</hi>sing the technologies afforded by information theory and
chaotics”—“Message transmission, noisy channels, the Lorenz attractor, information looping and looping
serpents” —according to the editor, the essay “decidedly complexifies . . . 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>.”</p>
                  <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. “‘To the Nightingale’: Perhaps an Unrecognised Poem by William
Blake.” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 30 (1981): 335-45. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 534-35&gt; B.
144-52 of <hi rend="i">The Pleasures of Bibliophily: Fifty Years of</hi> The Book Collector: <hi rend="i">An
Anthology.</hi> Ed. Nicolas Barker. (London: British Library; New Castle, Delaware: Oak Knoll Press,
2003).</p>
                  <p>§Lee, Hyungsoo. “[Vision of Liberty in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Literature in English</hi> 7 (2003): 31-54. In Korean,
with an English summary.</p>
                  <p>*Leigh, Peter. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> (London: Hodder &amp; Stoughton, 2000)
Livewire Real Lives, 27 pp.; ISBN: 0340776153.</p>
                  <p>*Linebaugh, Peter, and Marcus Rediker. “Blake’s African Orc.” 344-51 of
“Conclusion: Tyger! Tyger!” (327-54, 438-41) of their <hi rend="i">The Many-Headed Hydra: Sailors, Slaves,
Commoners, and the Hidden History of the Revolutionary Atlantic.</hi> (Boston: Beacon Press, 2000).</p>
                  <p>In <hi rend="i">America</hi> (1793) pl. 3, Orc is bound down like the slave Neptune in
“The Execution of Breaking on the Rack” in Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Surinam</hi> (1796), and Stedman’s
accounts of “Red Tiger” inspired Blake’s “The Tyger” (1794) (348).</p>
                  <p>*Livergood, Norman D. “William Blake As Mystic.” <hi rend="i">The New
Enlightenment.</hi> (2004) &lt;http://www.hermes-press.com/Perennial_Tradition/blake.htm&gt;.</p>
                  <p>*Lukacher, Brian. “Visionary History Painting: Blake and His Contemporaries.” Chapter
4 (98-114) of <hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century Art: A Critical History</hi>, with 369 illustrations, 51 in
color. Ed. Stephen F. Eisenman. (London: Thames &amp; Hudson, 1994) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
§(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Mostly about Blake.</p>
                  <p>§MacPhee, Chantelle. “Liberté, Egalité, Fraternité: Shakespeare and Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Upstart Crow</hi> 22 (2002): 51-62.</p>
                  <p>On Blake’s sources in Shakespeare.</p>
                  <p>Makdisi, Saree. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Impossible History of the 1790s.</hi>
(2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>David Wagenknecht, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 43 (2004): 297-303 (deplores
“the book’s dogmatism and annoying self
<pb id="p39-26" n="26"/>
promotion”; “The pioneer spirit here is a bit overdone” [303, 299]).</p>
                  <p>§Matsushima, Shoichi. <hi rend="i">Blake no Shiso to Kindai Nihon: Blake wo Yomu</hi>
[<hi rend="i">The Idea of Blake and Modern Japan: A Reading of Blake</hi>]. (2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
§(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Hiroko Nakamura, <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha Kenkyu: Essays in English Romanticism</hi>
28 (2004): 74-78. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>McQuade, Molly. “The Lives of Blake.” <hi rend="i">Booklist</hi> 99 (1-15 June 2003):
1737.</p>
                  <p>An interview with Aileen Ward about her biography of Blake, in progress since about 1969
(“I’m behind schedule”), though she has a contract with Farrar, Straus and Giroux.</p>
                  <p>Mellor, Anne K. “Blake, the Apocalypse and Romantic Women Writers.” Chapter 9
(139-52) of <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Millenarianism.</hi> Ed. Tim Fulford. (2002) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.1 (2004): 43-47 (a summary).</p>
                  <p>*Minton, David. “William Blake: A Vision of the Last Judgment from the Note-book.”
<hi rend="i">Kanto Gakuin Daigaku Bungakubu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Kanto Gakuin University
Society of Humanities</hi>] no. 100 (2003): 163-200.</p>
                  <p>*Minton, David. “William Blake’s Good &amp; Evil Angels.” <hi rend="i">Kanto Gakuin
Daigaku Bungakubu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Kanto Gakuin University Society of Humanities</hi>] no.
98 (2003): 75-121.</p>
                  <p>§Moore, Michael. “Wounds and Roses in Yalom, Blake, Kafka, and Heller.” 
<hi rend="i">Notes on Contemporary Literature</hi> 34 (2004): 5-7.</p>
                  <p>Mounsey, Chris. “Christopher Smart and William Blake: A Distinctive Mode.” Chapter 9
(166-81) of <hi rend="i">Early Romantics: Perspectives in British Poetry from Pope to Wordsworth.</hi> Ed.
Thomas Woodman. (Basingstoke: Macmillan Press; New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1998).</p>
                  <p>“Smart’s and Blake’s theories of language are similar” (178).</p>
                  <p>*Nachmanovitch, Stephen. <hi rend="i">Job Returns: A Meditation on William Blake’s</hi>
Illustrations of the Book of Job. Music &amp; multimedia by Stephen Nachmanovitch. 11 minutes.
([Charlottesville, Virginia: Stephen Nachmanovitch, 2002]).</p>
                  <p>A flyer for the CD-ROM created for the exhibition of <hi rend="i">William Blake: Portions
of the Eternal World</hi> at the University of Virginia Art Museum 26 January-31 March 2002 &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>The work is a descendant of Stephen Nachmanovitch Miller, “Job’s Return: William
Blake’s Map of Everything,” University of California (Santa Cruz) Ph.D., 1975 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p.
575&gt;.</p>
                  <p>§Nagashima, Kazuhiko. “Blake no ‘Vision’—sozoryoku to eien no jitsuzai
[Blake’s ‘Vision’—The Realism of Imagination and Eternity].” <hi rend="i">Kawamura Gakuen Joshi
Daigaku Kenkyu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of Kawamura Gakuen Women’s University</hi>] 15 (2004): 45-59.
In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Nair, Rajeev Kesavan. “Mapping Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>: An Exercise in Textual Cartography.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 63 (2002): 956A. Arizona State Ph.D.,
2002.</p>
                  <p>*Nakagawa, Kazuo. “Blake no ‘seimei no kawa’—nagareru ‘mizu’, yodomu
‘mizu’ sono ni [Blake’s River of Life—Flowing Water and Standing Water, the Second Part].” 
<hi rend="i">Gifu Daigaku Chiiki Kagakubu Kenkyu Hokoku</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Faculty of Regional
Studies, Gifu University</hi>] 12 (2003): 189-200. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Newman, Marcia. “‘Milton’s Track’ Revisited: Visual Analogues to Blake’s
Vortex in the ‘Law Edition’ of Boehme.” <hi rend="i">Interdisciplinary Literary Studies</hi> 5 (2004):
73-93.</p>
                  <p>§Nudelman, Bryan C. “Spaces of Transformation: Liminality and William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America: A Prophecy.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Lamar Journal of the Humanities</hi> 28 (2003): 33-46.</p>
                  <p>Ormsby, Bronwyn Ann. “The Materials and Techniques of William Blake’s Tempera
Paintings.” 2 vols. <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 64 (2003): 786. University of Northumbria at Newcastle Ph.D.,
2003.</p>
                  <p>§Østermark-Johansen, Lene. “Victorian Angles on Blake: Reading the Artist’s Head in
the Late Nineteenth Century.” 141-64 of <hi rend="i">Angles on the English-Speaking World</hi> Volume 3: 
<hi rend="i">Text, Authority and Posterity in British Romanticism.</hi> Ed. Lene Østermark-Johansen. (Copenhagen:
Museum Tusculanum Press, 2003).</p>
                  <p>On phrenology or physiognomy.</p>
                  <p>*Otto, Peter. “Blake, William 1757-1827.” 1: 94-96 of <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia of
the Romantic Era, 1760-1850.</hi> Ed. Christopher John Murray. 2 vols. (New York: Fitzroy Dearborn, 2004).</p>
                  <p>*Otto, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence: Love, Jealousy, and the
Sublime in</hi> The Four Zoas. (2000) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Wayne C. Ripley, <hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi> 27 (Aug. 2002)
&lt;http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/2002/v/n27/006567ar.html&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;
(“For all these difficulties, the book is at its best in its extensive reading of the poem”).</p>
                  <p>Otto, Peter. “The Marriage of Heaven and Hell 1790: Illuminated Book by William
Blake.” 2: 713-14 of <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia of the Romantic Era, 1760-1850.</hi> Ed. Christopher John
Murray. 2 vols. (New York: Fitzroy Dearborn, 2004).</p>
                  <p>§Otto, Peter. “A Sublime Allegory: Blake, Blake Studies, and the Sublime.” 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 43 (2002): 61-84.</p>
                  <pb id="p39-27" n="27"/>
                  <p>*Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening: The Last Works of William
Blake.</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2003) 8°, xiv, 332 pp., 52 reproductions; ISBN: 0199255628.</p>
                  <p>Chapters on (1) Blake’s Virgil woodcuts, (2) “<rtl>יה</rtl> &amp; his Two Sons
Satan &amp; Adam” (“Laocoön”), (3) his Dante drawings and engravings, and (4) “The Everlasting
Gospel,” <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel, Job</hi>, the Genesis mss., the Enoch drawings, and the notes to
Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Lord’s Prayer</hi>, plus a supplementary note on the Visionary Heads.</p>
                  <p>Part of chapter 4 first appeared in his “William Blake and Dr. Thornton’s ‘Tory
Translation’ of the Lord’s Prayer,” 263-86 of <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William Blake
in Honor of John E. Grant</hi>, ed. Alexander S. Gourlay (2002), and chapter 2 is reprinted with minor
corrections from his “<rtl>יה</rtl> &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 41 (2002): 201-35.</p>
                  <p>It is a comprehensively scholarly work, illuminating on every page, deft with Blake’s
designs, a worthy continuation of a lifetime of criticism covering all Blake’s literary works, with 
<hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (1970) and 
<hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem (1983).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">45</ref>
	<note id="n45">45. Not to mention editing (e.g., <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [1991], <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi> [1967-77], <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> [1977 ff.], <hi rend="i">Studies
in Romanticism</hi>), important collaborations (e.g., with Michael Phillips [1973] and Robert N. Essick
[1982]), and scores of essays and reviews.</note></p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>*Seamus Perry, “The Wise Man’s Table: In William Blake’s world, nothing is what it
first seems,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 Oct. 2004: 3-4 (with G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> Second Edition [2004]) (“superbly lucid and learned”).</p>
                  <p>§Paulson, Ronald. “Blake: The Harlot and the Lamb.” In his <hi rend="i">Hogarth’s
Harlot: Sacred Parody in Enlightenment England.</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2003).</p>
                  <p>§Pawlowski, G. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">La Grande encyclopédie</hi> (1885-92).
Apparently digested in “William Blake. Biographie en résumé Poète et peintre anglais.” 
<hi rend="i">L’Encyclopédie de L’Agora.</hi> Viewed 2004
&lt;http://agora.qc.ca/mot.nsf/Dossiers/William_Blake&gt;. In French.</p>
                  <p>§Pellis, Valeria. “Goethe e Blake: I molteplici volti dell’io nell’eterna lotta
tra materia e spirito.” 197-222 of <hi rend="i">L’Io del poeta: Figure e metamorfosi della
soggettività.</hi> Ed. Ingrid Hennemann Barale and Patrizio Collini. (Pisa: Pacini, 2002) Studi di
Letterature Moderne e Comparate 7; ISBN: 8877815043. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>P[éricaud, Val.] “Blake (Guillaume).” 1:405-06 of <hi rend="i">Biographie
Universelle (Michaud) Ancienne et Moderne</hi> . . . Nouvelle Édition, Publiée sous la Direction de M.
Michaud .... (Paris: chez Madame C. Desplaces, . . . 1854). &lt;Bodleian&gt;</p>
                  <p>Blake wrote <hi rend="i">America, Descriptive Catalogue, Europe, The Gates of
Paradise</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, and made illustrations to Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805), Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>,
Chaucer, and Job. “Il ne sortit jamais d’une position voisine de la misère, mais . . . il était
heureux.”</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2380 for the 1843 version.</p>
                  <p>Phillips, Michael. “No. 13 Hercules Buildings, Lambeth: William Blake’s Printmaking
Workshop and Etching-Painting Studio Recovered.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 5.1 (2004):
15-21.</p>
                  <p>Detailed reconstructions, with minutely precise measurements (e.g., 12′ 9″ × 12′
1½″ for the printing room), of Blake’s house, apparently based largely upon the rudimentary sketch of
1853 (reproduced in Robin Hamlyn’s essay in <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work</hi>, ed. Joyce
Townsend [2003]), which lacks almost all these details.</p>
                  <p>*Phillips, Michael. “The Printing of Blake’s <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy.”
Print Quarterly</hi> 21 (2004): 18-38.</p>
                  <p>Minutely detailed evidence supports the conclusion of John Jackson, <hi rend="i">A
Treatise on Wood Engraving</hi> (1839) (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 45-46) that Blake’s “progress in printing
was necessarily slow.”</p>
                  <p>§Plotnitsky, Arkady. “Chaosmic Orders, Nonclassical Physics, Allegory, and the
Epistemology of Blake’s Minute Particulars.” 52 paragraphs. <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Complexity.</hi>
Ed. Hugh Roberts. (College Park, Maryland: University of Maryland Press, 2001), Romantic Circles Praxis
Series. &lt;http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/complexity/plotnitsky/plotnitsky.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>*Punter, David. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience: Notes.</hi> (1998);
ISBN: 5823293292 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1999)&gt; B. §*<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</hi> Notes by David Punter. (London: York Press, 2003) York Notes Advanced, 112 pp.; ISBN
0582784336.</p>
                  <p>2003 is a “new and fully revised edition.”</p>
                  <p>Raffel, Burton. “Excerpt, ‘Translation: Processes and Attitudes.’” 
<hi rend="i">Literary Review</hi> 45 (2002): 632-34. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>About the difficulties of his current translation of “The Tyger”; “This excerpt is
part of a longer essay that will be published in <hi rend="i">Creativity Research Journal.</hi>”</p>
                  <p>*Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition.</hi> (1968) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2478&gt; B. §*(London: Routledge, 2002); ISBN: 0415283981; 0415290872 [Vol. 1]; 0415290880 [Vol. 2].</p>
                  <p>The 2002 edition is a facsimile of that of 1968.</p>
                  <p>Rawlinson, Nick. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Comic Vision.</hi> (2003) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Kathleen Lundeen, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.2 (2004): 85-87 (Rawlinson “allows us to
hear Blake in a different key”).</p>
                  <p>§Reinhart, Charles. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Concise Dictionary of British
Literary Biography</hi> Vol. 3: <hi rend="i">Writers of the Romantic Period, 1789-1832.</hi> (Detroit: Gale
Research, 1992).</p>
                  <pb id="p39-28" n="28"/>
                  <p>§Rix, Robert W. “William Blake and the Prophetic Marketplace.” 47-61 of 
<hi rend="i">Angles on the English-Speaking World</hi> Volume 3: <hi rend="i">Text, Authority and Posterity in
British Romanticism.</hi> Ed. Lene Østermark-Johansen. (Copenhagen: Museum Tusculanum Press, 2003).</p>
                  <p>Rockwell, John. “No Rap but Just About Everything Else for Blake Cycle.” 
<hi rend="i">New York Times</hi> 12 April 2004.</p>
                  <p>Music review of William Bolcom’s poetic cycle <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">46</ref> performed by
“nearly 500 musicians” at the University of Michigan 8 April 2004; it is “musically . . . pretty
awesome” and “dazzlingly” “diverse.” <note id="n46">46. See <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 352, 402, 422,
608, and <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996,1997).</note></p>
                  <p>*Roe, Albert S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine Comedy.</hi> (1953,
1967) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2543&gt; C. §(2003).</p>
                  <p>§Rowland, Christopher. “‘Rouzing the Faculties to Act’: William Blake, Merkabah
Mysticism, the Theology of Liberation and the Exegetical Importance of Experience.” <hi rend="i">Biblical
Interpretation</hi> 11 (2003): 543-54.</p>
                  <p>*Rudd, Margaret. <hi rend="i">Organized Innocence: The Story of Blake’s Prophetic
Books.</hi> (1956, 1973) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2586&gt; C. §(2003).</p>
                  <p>§Samoyault, Tiphaine. “L’Oeuvre visible illisible: A propos de 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> de William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Lecture Littéraire: Revue de Recherche sur la
Lecture des Textes Littéraires</hi> 5-6 (2002): 31-43. In French.</p>
                  <p>Sato, Hikari. “‘I saw a Devil in a flame of fire’: Tengoku to jigoku no kekkon ni
okeru ‘hi’ no yakuwari [The Function of Fire in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>].”
23-35 of <hi rend="i">Romanha Bungaku no Sugata II</hi> [<hi rend="i">Aspects of Romantic Literature II</hi>].
Ed. Naoki Ishihata. (Tokyo: Eihosha, 2004); ISBN: 4269711086.</p>
                  <p>Scott, Peter Dale. “Alone on Ararat: Scott, Blake, Yeats, and Apocalyptic.” 
<hi rend="i">Essays on Canadian Writing</hi> no. 55 (1995): 288-302.</p>
                  <p>On F. R. Scott’s poem “Lakeshore.”</p>
                  <p>§Sklar, Susanne. “The <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Marathon.”
&lt;http://www.blakequarterly.org&gt;; see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.3 (2004-05): 119.</p>
                  <p>“A report . . . on a recent reading [aloud] of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”</p>
                  <p>Smith, Cyril. “Marx and the Fourfold Vision of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">New
Interventions: A Journal of Socialist Discussion and Opinion</hi> 11.3 (spring 2004): 23-28.</p>
                  <p>“Whatever their huge differences, each of these men saw the entire world . . . as
centred on the activity of the human social individual” (23).</p>
                  <p>Snart, J. “‘Orison’: A Possible Source for William Blake’s ‘Urizen.’” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 247 [N.S. 49] (2002): 14-15. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>The source “suggests . . . Blake’s ability to satirize prayer and speech through
Urizen.”</p>
                  <p>§So, Tat-Sang. “Eternal Death in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 63 (2002): 957-58A. Dallas Ph.D., 2002.</p>
                  <p>Spector, Sheila A. <hi rend="i">“Glorious incomprehensible”: The Development of
Blake’s Kabbalistic Language</hi> (2001); <hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”: The Development of Blake’s
Kabbalistic Myth</hi> (2001). &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Sibylle Erle and Mei-Ying Sung, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 42 (2003):
579-84 (“notwithstanding Spector’s superbly illustrated volumes, Blake’s kabbalism must still remain an
enigma” [584]). Dena Bain Taylor, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.2 (2004): 79-85 (review of 
<hi rend="i">“Wonders Divine”</hi> only; <hi rend="i">“‘Wonders Divine’</hi> offers a brilliant
explication of the kabbalistic pattern of Blake’s development .... the next step is to link Blake’s
Kabbalah more firmly with the Christian esoteric tradition” [85]).</p>
                  <p>Stanger, James Aaron, reviser. “William Blake.” 1: 211-22 of <hi rend="i">Cyclopedia
of World Authors.</hi> Revised third ed. (Pasadena, California: Salem Press, 1997) &lt;There were earlier
editions in 1958, 1974, 1989&gt;.</p>
                  <p>*Stavis, Henriette B. “Songs of Innocence and of Experience: Collection of Poetry by
William Blake, 1794.” 2: 1071-72 of <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia of the Romantic Era, 1760-1850.</hi> Ed.
Christopher John Murray. 2 vols. (New York: Fitzroy Dearborn, 2004).</p>
                  <p>Strange, John Clark, Ms. Journal (1859-61)</p>
                  <p>At his death in 2003, Ray Watkinson bequeathed Strange’s journal, with the rest of his
collection, to the library of the University of Brighton.</p>
                  <p>§Suzuki, Masayoki. “William Blake, ‘A Poison Tree’: Hanshinwa no monogatari.”
<hi rend="i">Eigo Seinen: The Rising Generation</hi> 148 (2003): 702-03. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Tambling, Jeremy. “Dante and Blake: Allegorising the Event.” Chapter 2 (33-48) of 
<hi rend="i">Dante’s Modern Afterlife: Reception and Response from Blake to Heaney.</hi> Ed. Nicholas Havely.
(Basingstoke: Macmillan; New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1998). &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>About representations of Count Ugolino.</p>
                  <p>*Townsend, Joyce H., ed., consultant ed. Robin Hamlyn. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
Painter at Work.</hi> (London: Tate Publishing, 2003) 4°, 192 pp., 158 reproductions; ISBN: 1854374680
(U.K.); 0691119104 (U.S.). &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> §(2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>A remarkably fine and original book dealing particularly with the constitution, use, and
deterioration of Blake’s pigments, the materials of the supports, and the framing of his pictures (no frame
survives from Blake’s time), with telling reproductions. An exhibition at Tate in 2004 used captions from
this work. The book consists of:</p>
                  <pb id="p39-29" n="29"/>
                  <p>Joyce Townsend. “Preface.” 7-8.</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Acknowledgements.” 8-9.</p>
                  <p>Part One: Introduction</p>
                  <p>*Robin Hamlyn. “William Blake at Work: ‘Every thing which is in Harmony.’” 12-39,
175-77. (Deals particularly with the rooms in which Blake painted, including previously unreproduced diagrams
of the Blakes’ rooms at 17, South Molton Street [18, “drawn by Robin Hamlyn 2003”] and of their house at
13, Hercules Buildings [29, “Done Feb<hi rend="s">y</hi> 1853”].)</p>
                  <p>Bronwyn Ormsby and Joyce H. Townsend with Brian Singer and John Dean. “The State of
Knowledge on William Blake the Painter.” 40-44, 177-78. (Heretofore “Blake’s paint medium for temperas
and colour prints has not been investigated with great success” [44].)</p>
                  <p>*Joyce H. Townsend. “Analytical Methods.” 45-51, 178. (She reproduces “Almost the
complete range of watercolour pigments available within Blake’s lifetime” [47].)</p>
                  <p>Part Two: Watercolours</p>
                  <p>*Peter Bower. “The Vivid Surface: Blake’s Use of Paper and Board.” 54-60, 178. (A
learned and persuasive demonstration that “Understanding the nature and type of papers that Blake used is
fundamental to an accurate understanding of his working practices” [56].)</p>
                  <p>*Noa Cahaner McManus and Joyce H. Townsend. “Watercolour Methods, and Materials Use in
Context.” 61-79, 178-79. (They deal with Blake’s “pigments . . . with a focus on their appearance in
Blake’s works, their properties, permanence and the likelihood of their use in his time” [68].)</p>
                  <p>Part Three: Large Colour Prints</p>
                  <p>*Noa Cahaner McManus and Joyce H. Townsend. “The Large Colour Prints: Methods and
Materials.” 82-99, 179. (In “God Judging Adam,” the only “relief etched copper plate” among the
large colour prints, “the colour printing was done in more than one pull,” but in “Naomi Entreating . .
.,” “the colour printing was done in one pull” [84, 92].)</p>
                  <p>*Piers Townshend and Joyce H. Townsend. “The Conservation of a Large Colour Print:
Satan Exulting over Eve.” 100-07, 179.</p>
                  <p>Part Four: Temperas</p>
                  <p>*Bronwyn Ormsby with Brian Singer and John Dean. “The Painting of the Temperas.”
110-33, 179-80. (“The structure of temperas such as <hi rend="i">Camoens</hi> and <hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi>
[from the “Heads of the Poets”] has been made more complex by the presence of what is possibly an
abandoned image underneath the final design” [122].)</p>
                  <p>*Bronwyn Ormsby with Joyce H. Townsend, Brian Singer and John Dean. “Blake’s Use of
Tempera in Context.” 134-49, 180-81. (“Contrary to the historical accounts . . . that Blake rejected gum
as a binder . . . the analysis of Blake’s tempera paints also revealed the consistent presence of a mixture
of gums Arabic (or karaya) and tragacanth with the additions of sugar or honey, and occasionally cherry gum”
[138].)</p>
                  <p>*Bronwyn Ormsby with Brian Singer and John Dean. “The Appearance of the Temperas
Today.” 150-59, 181. (“Thirty per cent of Blake’s temperas have been lost through neglect and poor
condition,” including the “almost complete repainting prior to 1885 of each of the eighteen ‘Heads of
Poets,’” but “There appears to be little evidence of the wholesale fading of pigments on Blake’s
temperas, and no remaining evidence of the blackening of the lead-based pigments reported by D.G. Rossetti
[Gilchrist (1863)]” [157, 159].)</p>
                  <p>Part Five: Epilogue</p>
                  <p>*Joyce H. Townsend, Robin Hamlyn and John Anderson. “The Presentation of Blake’s
Paintings.” 162-74, 181-82. (An account of the framing and display of Blake’s pictures in the past and the
present, particularly at Tate.)</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Appendix 1: Watercolours Discussed in the Text.” 183. (Includes a column on
“Colour Change.”)</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Appendix 2: Watercolours—Analytical Results.” 184. (In particular, “Lead
White” was not used in the pictures examined.)</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Appendix 3: Large Colour Prints Discussed in the Text.” 185. (Includes a
useful column on “Signature” on pictures.)</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Appendix 4: Large Colour Prints—Analytical Results.” 186. (It indicates
that, inter alia, “Indigo in Green” was never used here.)</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Appendix 5: Temperas Discussed in the Text.” 187.</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Appendix 6: Temperas—Analytical Results.” 188.</p>
                  <p>§Traeger, Jörg. “Luzifers Revolte um 1800: Blake, Runge, Goya.” 57-62 of 
<hi rend="i">Kopfüber: Kunst am Ende des 20. Jahrhunderts.</hi> (Munich: C. H. Beck, 2004); ISBN: 340651538X. In
German.</p>
                  <p>Viscomi, Joseph. “Blake after Blake: A Nation Discovers Genius.” 8 March 2003
&lt;http://sites.unc.edu/viscomi/blakeafterblake.html&gt;.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n47" type="note">47</ref>
	<note id="n47">47. See &lt;http://sites.unc.edu/viscomi/frontend_page.html&gt; for his §“Collected Essays
on William Blake and His Times” (but not his great book).</note></p>
                  <p>On Linton and Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life.</hi></p>
                  <p>*Wainwright, Martin. “Blake District: Connection revealed between erotic writers and
artists.” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> 3 Mar. 2004: 90.</p>
                  <p>The writers and artists are William Blake and D. H. Lawrence; the “Blake district” is
in Nottinghamshire (Blake’s mother in Walkeringham and Lawrence in Eastwood nearby), and the connection is
the discovery that Blake’s mother was born in Walkeringham (pop. 419 in 1801) and composed [i.e.,
transcribed] a hymn, still extant, when applying to join the Moravian Church.</p>
                  <p>§Wardi, Eynel. “Space, the Body, and the Text in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
and Hell.” Orbis Litterarum</hi> 58 (2003): 253-70.</p>
                  <p>Warner, Janet. <hi rend="i">Other Sorrows, Other Joys: The Marriage of Catherine Sophia
Boucher and William Blake.</hi> (2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>*Gerry Hopson, “Love among the Angels,” <hi rend="i">Globe and Mail</hi> [Toronto] 7
Feb. 2004: D12 (“a serious though homely book, in its quirky way honest, direct and ambitious”).</p>
                  <pb id="p39-30" n="30"/>
                  <p>§Westerweel, Bart. “Some Reflections on William Blake and the Emblem.” 11-25 of 
<hi rend="i">Configuring Romanticism: Essays Offered to C. C. Barfoot.</hi> Ed. Theo D’haen, Peter Liebregts,
Wim Tigges, Colin Ewen. (Amsterdam: Rodopi, 2003) Costerus: Essays in English and American Language and
Literature, 147.</p>
                  <p>§Whissell, Cynthia. “The Emotionality of William Blake’s Poems: A Quantitative
Comparison of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> with <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.” Perceptual and
Motor Skills</hi> 92 (2001): 459-67.</p>
                  <p>§Whitman, Vincent Miller. “‘Clos’d by Your Senses Five’: William Blake’s Early
Illuminated Prophecies and Berkeleian Epistemology.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 63 (2003): 3567A. Connecticut
Ph.D., 2002.</p>
                  <p>*Williamson, Richard. “Visions of Greatness: Poet, artist and radical thinker William
Blake spent a number of years of his artistic career in Felpham. His experiences there were set to inspire the
great poem and song Jerusalem. Richard Williamson looks at Blake, telling the story of the life behind the
blue plaque which commemorates the poet’s time in West Sussex.” <hi rend="i">The Magazine</hi> (supplement
to the <hi rend="i">Bognor Regis Observer</hi>) 13 Feb. 2003: 14-15.</p>
                  <p>Wittreich, Joseph. “‘The Illustrious Dead’: Milton’s Legacy and Romantic
Prophecy.” <hi rend="i">Milton and the Romantics</hi> 4 (1980): 17-32 &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp.
682-83&gt; B.§313-28 in <hi rend="i">John Milton: Twentieth Century Perspectives</hi>, Volume 1: The Man and
the Author. Ed. J. Martin Evans. (New York: Routledge, 2003).</p>
                  <p>“Together, Blake and Wordsworth may epitomize the possibilities of prophecy in the
Romantic Age” (20 [1980]).</p>
                  <p>*Wright, Julia M. <hi rend="i">Blake, Nationalism, and the Politics of Alienation.</hi>
(Athens: Ohio University Press, 2004) 8°, xxxiii, 230 pp.; ISBN: 0821415190.</p>
                  <p>She “follows Blake from his subversion of the linearity that enables neoclassical
nationalist narratives, to his critique of the replicated text, to his own replicating imperialist vision”
(xxxiii).</p>
                  <p>Chapter 1, “The Line of Progress: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> and Classicist
Theories of Art,” appeared in a shorter version as “The Medium, the Message, and the Line in William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi> 33 (2000): 101-24, and chapter 4 was printed
with the same title in <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 7 (1996): 61-84.</p>
                  <p>Yang, Mu [pen name of Jingxian Wang]. “Wei Blake chenqing [A Petition for Blake].”
<hi rend="i">Lianhe bao</hi> [<hi rend="i">United Daily News</hi>, Taipei] 21 Nov. 1993: 37 (Literary
Supplement). In Chinese.</p>
                  <p>Pace Zhifan Chen, “Wen dao yu mang [Seeking Advice from an Ignorant Person],” 
<hi rend="i">Lianhe bao</hi> [<hi rend="i">United Daily News</hi>, Taipei] 1 Nov. 1993: 37, Blake is not “a
painter” or “a mystic poet” but “an engraving artist,” and the first two lines of “Auguries of
Innocence” (“To see a World in a grain of Sand / And a heaven in a wild flower”) are not “frequently
cited.”</p>
                  <p>§Yeshima, Kenkichi. “Whitman to [and] Blake.” <hi rend="i">Eigo Seinen: The Rising
Generation</hi> 150 (2004): 95. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>On Whitman and Blake’s “Infant Joy.”</p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Entries for members of Blake’s circle in the <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National
Biography</hi> (2004) are listed in Table 1.</p>
                <p>Richard Cosway (1742-1821)</p>
                <p>Miniaturist, friend of Blake</p>
                <p>“Richard Cosway.” 72-75 of <hi rend="i">British Paintings at the Huntington.</hi>
Catalogue researched and written by Robyn Asleson: Shelley M. Bennett, general editor; with technical notes by
Rosamond Westmoreland and Shelley Svoboda; and additional contributions by Melinda McCurdy and Elizabeth
Pergam. ([San Marino:] Published by the Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens in
association with Yale University Press, New Haven, 2001).</p>
                <p>Lloyd, Stephen. “The Cosway Inventory of 1820 Listing Unpaid Commissions and the Contents
of 20 Stratford Place, Oxford Street, London.” <hi rend="i">Walpole Society</hi> 66 (2004): 163-217, and pl.
61-130.</p>
                <p>The inventory is at Fondazione Cosway at Lodi (Italy).</p>
                <p>John Flaxman (1755-1826)</p>
                <p>Sculptor, intimate friend of Blake</p>
                <p>Baines, Paul. “Flaxman, John 1755-1826.” 1: 358-60 of <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia of the
Romantic Era, 1760-1850.</hi> Ed. Christopher John Murray. 2 vols. (New York: Fitzroy Dearborn, 2004).</p>
                <p>Hendriks, Ella. “The First Patron of John Flaxman.” <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 618, 620-22, 625.</p>
                <p>Chiefly extracts from the notebooks (1759-92) of Edward Knight (1734-1812) in Kidderminster
Public Library.</p>
                <p>King, James. “Flaxman, Kemble, and Talma: A New Anecdote.” <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi> 219 (N.S. 21) (1974): 175.</p>
                <p>The anecdote of 1817 is from the commonplace book of W. G. Meredith.</p>
                <p>Miller, Charlotte. “John Flaxman’s Working Copy of Dante’s <hi rend="i">Divina
Commedia.” Italian Studies</hi> 58 (2003): 75-87.</p>
                <p>“Flaxman” is written by Nancy Flaxman on the title pages of <hi rend="i">Divina
Commedia</hi>, ed. Andrea Rubbi, 3 vols. (Venezia: Antonio Zatta &amp; Figli, 1784), which is Vol. III-V of
<hi rend="i">Parnaso Italiano</hi> in the Harold Acton Library in the British Institute of Florence.</p>
                <p>Stoker, Mark. “John Flaxman 1755-1826.” 1: 565-67 of <hi rend="i">The Encyclopedia of
Sculpture.</hi> Ed. Antonia Boström. (New York: Fitzroy Dearborn, 2004).</p>
                <pb id="p39-31" n="31"/>
                <p>John Henry Fuseli (1741-1825)</p>
                <p>Swiss painter, intimate friend of Blake</p>
                <p>§Bätschmann, Marie Therese. “Neuentdeckte Zeichnungen des jungen Johann Heinrich
Füssli (1741-1825).” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Schweizerische Archäologie und Kunstgeschichte</hi> 56
(1999): 137-48. In German.</p>
                <p>Four drawings at Berne were made by Fuseli as an adolescent.</p>
                <p>§Deuchler, Florens. “‘Windsturm und Ungewitter’: Zu einem Bild von Johann Heinrich
Füssli in der Fondazione Magnani Rocca.” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Schweizerische Archäologie und
Kunstgeschichte</hi> 56 (1999): 129-36. In German.</p>
                <p>The picture demonstrates Fuseli’s close reading of Johann Georg Sulzer’s 
<hi rend="i">Allgemeine Theorie der schönen Kunste.</hi></p>
                <p>Haycock, David. “Fuseli, Henry 1741-1825.” 1: 392-93 of <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia of
the Romantic Era, 1760-1850.</hi> Ed. Christopher John Murray. 2 vols. (New York: Fitzroy Dearborn, 2004).</p>
                <p>Thomas Johnes (1748-1816)</p>
                <p>Patron of Hafod, North Wales</p>
                <p>Macve, Jennifer. <hi rend="i">The Hafod Landscape: An Illustrated History and Guide.</hi>
(Ymddiriedolaeth yr Hafod, The Hafod Trust, 2004) 4°, 52 pp.; ISBN: 095279411X.</p>
                <p>An account of the famous grounds (not the house, which “was demolished with explosives”
in 1958). Malkin’s biography of Blake (1806) is dedicated to Johnes, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
(P) was given by Malkin to Johnes, and George Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Attempt to Describe Hafod</hi>
(1796) has a map of Hafod which, it has been argued, was engraved by Blake.</p>
                <p>John Linnell (1792-1882)</p>
                <p>Painter, patron of Blake</p>
                <p>“John Linnell.” 256-63 of <hi rend="i">British Paintings at the Huntington.</hi>
Catalogue researched and written by Robyn Asleson; Shelley M. Bennett, general editor; with technical notes by
Rosamond Westmoreland and Shelley Svoboda; and additional contributions by Melinda McCurdy and Elizabeth
Pergam. ([San Marino:] Published by the Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens in
association with Yale University Press, New Haven, 2001).</p>
                <p>John Marsh (1752-1828)</p>
                <p>Lawyer, musical composer, friend of Blake</p>
                <p>Marsh’s important journal with its references to Blake is in the Huntington Library (see
Robert N. Essick, “William Blake and John Marsh,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 25.2 [1991]: 70-74 &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 408&gt; and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] passim), and a microfilm of it is in the West Sussex
County Record Office.</p>
                <p><hi rend="i">Marsh of Chichester (1752-1828): Gentleman, Musician, Composer, Writer.</hi>
Ed. Paul Foster. (Chichester: University College, 9 October 2004) Otter Memorial Papers Number Nineteen, 8°,
158 pp.; ISBN: 0948765348.</p>
                <p>A collection of essays:</p>
                <p>[Paul Foster.] “Introduction.” 11-13. (The focus is “on his music and on the record
of his own activity in Chichester and elsewhere” [11].)</p>
                <p>Alison McCann. “John Marsh and the Intellectual Life of Chichester.” 15-35.</p>
                <p>Ian Graham-Jones. “Marsh and Music: John Marsh—the Composer.” 36-48.</p>
                <p>Martin Renshaw. “John Marsh and the Organ.” 48-53.</p>
                <p>Alan Thurlow. “John Marsh and Chichester Cathedral: Reflections by a Twentyfirst-Century
Organist of the Cathedral.” 55-61.</p>
                <p>Nicholas Plumley. “John Marsh and Domestic Music-Making in Eighteenth and Early
Nineteenth Century England.” 62-71.</p>
                <p>Brian Robins. “John Marsh and the Chichester Volunteers.” 72-83.</p>
                <p>Timothy J. McCann. “Marsh at Goodwood.” 89-112. (On the Duke of Richmond.)</p>
                <p>Ron Iden and Emlyn Thomas. “Marsh at the Seaside.” 113-21.</p>
                <p>Patrick Moore. “John Marsh—Astronomer.” 122-24.</p>
                <p>Barry Fletcher. “Much Pleased with Life.” 125-43. (On Marsh’s character and
life.)</p>
                <p>Appendix. 144-55. It consists of:</p>
                <p>Barry Fletcher. “A Note on <hi rend="i">Peregrine Project.</hi>” 146-49. (There is no
reference to “John Marsh and Peregrine Project: <hi rend="i">A Tour through Some of the Southern Counties of
England</hi> (1804),” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 49 [1997]: 80-81.)</p>
                <p>“Will of John Marsh—Dated 1828.” 150-55.</p>
                <p>Samuel Palmer (1805-81)</p>
                <p>Artist, disciple of Blake</p>
                <p>Christie’s (South Kensington) vainly offered 104 Palmer letters to Richard Redgrave and
family (1859-80) and 47 letters to the Wright family (1866-81) 8 June 2004, lots 158-59, and 17 November 2004,
lots 32-33; <hi rend="i">The Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>, ed. Raymond Lister, 2 vols. (1974) contains some
letters to the Redgraves and Wrights, but not nearly so many as were offered in 2004.</p>
                <p>Wootton, Sarah. “Palmer, Samuel 1805-1881.” 2: 846-47 of <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia of
the Romantic Era, 1760-1850.</hi> Ed. Christopher John Murray. 2 vols. (New York: Fitzroy Dearborn, 2004).</p>
                <p>George Richmond (1809-96)</p>
                <p>Painter, disciple of Blake</p>
                <p>George Richmond’s unrecorded drawing of Blake on his deathbed will be given by Harold
Bloom to St. Michael’s College, Colchester, Vermont.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">48</ref>
	<note id="n48">48. See note 24.</note></p>
                <pb id="p39-32" n="32"/>
                <p>Thomas Stothard (1755-1834)</p>
                <p>Book illustrator, early friend of Blake</p>
                <p>An apparently unrecorded engraved design (1818) by Stothard, reported by Alexander Gourlay,
is in</p>
                <p>§The SELECTOR | CONTAINING THE POETICAL | <hi rend="i">Works of</hi> | Gray Falconer |
Goldsmith Somerville | [<hi rend="i">vignette</hi>] | London | Publish’d by Suttaby, Evance &amp; Fox,
Stationers Court | and Baldwin, Cradock and Joy, Paternoster Row. | 1815[-1818]. | -</p>
                <p>Each of the four sections has its own title page (1816, 1818, 1817, 1817) and pagination.
There is a Stothard frontispiece (1818) to</p>
                <p>§THE | POETICAL WORKS | OF | Oliver Goldsmith, M.B. | - | WITH AN ACCOUNT OF | 
<hi rend="i">THE LIFE AND WRITINGS</hi> | OF | THE AUTHOR | = | LONDON: | PUBLISHED BY SUTTABY, EVANCE AND | FOX
STATIONER’S COURT; | AND BALDWIN, CRADOCK, AND JOY. | 1818. | - | Ellerton and Henderson, Printers.</p>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Appendix: Corrigenda and Addenda to <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, Second
Edition (2004)</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>For previous corrigenda and addenda, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.4 (2004): 151.</p>
                  <p>Owners and Repositories of Unique Materials</p>
                  <p>Moravian Church Archives (London)</p>
                  <p>Murray (John) Archive (London)</p>
                  <p>Nottinghamshire County Archives (Walkeringham Church Register)</p>
                  <p>Universitätsarchiv (Herrnhut, Germany)</p>
                  <p>P. 2</p>
                  <p>Information about Blake’s mother Catherine’s birth in Nottinghamshire, her family,
and her connection to the Moravian Church during her first marriage to Thomas Armitage can be found in Keri
Davies, “William Blake in Contexts: Family, Friendships, and Some Intellectual Microcultures of Eighteenth-
and Nineteenth-Century England,” Surrey Ph.D., 2003 (unpublished; see “William Blake and His Circle,”
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.1 [2005]: 22), and Keri Davies and Marsha Keith Schuchard, “Recovering the Lost
Moravian History of William Blake’s Family,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.1 (2004): 36-43.</p>
                  <p>P. 15</p>
                  <p>“<hi rend="i">James Parker</hi> (1750-1805)” should be “(1757-1805).”</p>
                  <p>Pp. 33 and footnote, 34</p>
                  <p>Omit the references to James Parker’s wife.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n49" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n49">1. G. E. Bentley, Jr., “The Journeyman and the Genius: James Parker and His Partner William
Blake . . .,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 49 (1996): 210 says that on 17 Aug. 1782 James
Parker (aged 25 and up [the engraver was 25 then]), Stationer of the Parish of St. Dunstan in the West,
contracted to marry Ann Serjeantson in the County of York. As Keri Davies points out to me, this is probably
not James Parker, engraver, of the Stationers’ Company, but the James Parker, stationer, of 36, Chancery
Lane in 1782-97 (see Ian Maxted, <hi rend="i">The London Book Trades 1775-1800</hi> [Folkestone: William
Dawson &amp; Sons Ltd, 1977] 170).</note></p>
                  <p>P. 281, 1809</p>
                  <p>“William Blake, Esq.” appears as a subscriber in the prospectus for Joseph Thomas’
<hi rend="i">Religious Emblems</hi> (1809). See “William Blake and His Circle,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
38.1 (2004): 7, 16, and 39.1 (2005): 17.</p>
                  <p>Pp. 302-03</p>
                  <p>In an undated letter to George Cumberland, Charles Henry Bellenden Ker wrote that his
commission to Blake for two drawings, for which Ker did not wish to pay, was given “2 years ago” when he
“was not of age.” As Ker was christened on 18 February 1787 (according to the entry in the 
<hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi> [Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004] 31: 379), the
commission was presumably given in late 1807 or very early 1808 when he came of age, and the present letter
may be of 1809 or 1810.</p>
                  <p>P. 314, the Associated Painters in Water Colours exhibition</p>
                  <p>For the landlord’s seizing the contents of the gallery, see “William Blake and His
Circle,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.1 (2005): 15.</p>
                  <p>P. 363, footnote to “Blake-Varley Sketchbook”</p>
                  <p>This cumulation of Blake’s Visionary Heads also appeared in G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
“Blake’s Visionary Heads: Lost Drawings and a Lost Book,” <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Millenarianism</hi>, ed. Tim Fulford (New York: Palgrave, 2002) 183-205.</p>
                  <p>P. 418</p>
                  <p>On 25 November 1825 (the postmark date), Blake wrote to John Linnell (see 
cover illus. for <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.1 [2005]):
<q>
Dear Sir<lb/>
M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Banes says his Kitchen is at our Service to do as we please. I should like to know from
the Printer whether our own Kitchen would not be equally or even more convenient as the Press being already
there would Save a good deal of time &amp; trouble in taking down &amp; putting up which is no slight job.
Also the light is better in our Kitchen if there is but room enough.<lb/>
I am yours Sincerely<lb/>
Will Blake
</q></p>
                  <p>Henry Banes, the husband of Catherine Blake’s sister Sarah, was the owner of 3,
Fountain Court, where Blake lived in 1821-27, and Banes may well have lived in the same building.</p>
                  <p>Probably the work referred to is Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>; the first commerical
proofs were pulled on 4-5 March 1825, and on 10
<pb id="p39-33" n="33"/>
February 1826 Mary Ann Linnell wrote to her husband about “the Job . . . from all I can learn the printing
is going on well [at Lahee’s shop] by a man of the name of Freeman.” The work was published in March
1826.</p>
                  <p>P. 495</p>
                  <p>The date of Frederick Tatham’s letter offering Blake’s works for sale is 11 April
1829, as in <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> (1988) 90, not 1 April.</p>
                  <p>P. 622, J. T. Smith</p>
                  <p>“Blake preferred mixing his colours with carpenter’s glue, to gum”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n50">2. The phrase is echoed by Tatham (671), but the scientific “analysis of Blake’s tempera
paints . . . revealed the consistent presence of a mixture of gums Arabic (or karaya) and tragacanth with the
additions of sugar or honey, and occasionally cherry gum” (Bronwyn Ormsby, Joyce H. Townsend, Brian Singer,
and John Dean, “Blake’s Use of Tempera in Context,” <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at
Work</hi>, ed. Joyce H. Townsend [2003] 138).</note></p>
                  <p>P. 676, footnote † to Tatham’s story of theft from Blake 1796-1800</p>
                  <p>Add: The “Plate to the Value of 60 Pounds” can scarcely be silver or gold, for the
modest Blakes could not afford or wish such things; it was probably copper, Blake’s stock in trade. The
copper cannot be his own works in illuminated printing, for these would have cost only about £21 (calculating
the price of copper as 1<hi rend="i">d</hi> for a cubic cm., the price of his plates for Flaxman’s 
<hi rend="i">Naval Pillar</hi> [1799]—see p. 759—and the thickness of the copper as 0.141 cm., as in his
fragmentary surviving copperplate from <hi rend="i">America</hi> pl. a), and besides many of them were printed
after his death. But the cost of Blake’s 43 large copperplates for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> (1797) would have been sixty guineas (assuming the plates were 0.183 cm. thick, as in Blake’s
Dante plates of the same size). Probably the thieves took the 207 pounds of copperplates for Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
                  <p>P. 734, Appendix II: Blake Residences</p>
                  <p>Add Walkeringham, Nottinghamshire, 1725.</p>
                  <p>P. 736, Residences</p>
                  <p>After “from 1794 to 1800” add: “Blake &amp; Sons, hosiers &amp; haberdash. 28,
Broad-st. Carnaby-mar” appear in <hi rend="i">Boyle’s New London Guide</hi> (London: P. Boyle, 1795).</p>
                  <p>P. 736, Residences</p>
                  <p>After “James Blake continues by himself in,” add “<hi rend="i">Universal British
Directory</hi> (1797) 77.”</p>
                  <p>P. 741, Residences, fn ‡</p>
                  <p>For “Townshend” read “Townsend.”</p>
                  <p>P. 742, Residences</p>
                  <p>For John Blake “voted in 1784 and 1788 for Fox and Hood” read “voted in 1784 for
Fox and Hood and in 1788 for Townsend.”</p>
                  <p>P. 745, Residences</p>
                  <p>13, Hercules Buildings, “a long narrow garden”: A plan “Done Feb<hi rend="s">y</hi>
1853” shows the width of the lot as 18′ (nearby lots vary from 13′ 11″ to 22′) and the depth as
110′ 3″ (Robin Hamlyn in <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work</hi>, ed. Joyce H. Townsend
[2003] 29).</p>
                  <p>P. 746, Residences</p>
                  <p>13, Hercules Buildings: For “One of the few . . . Carnaby-market” read: Blake’s
name rarely appeared in directories, but in 1797 he was transmogrified or renominated “Blocke, William,—13
Hercules [Buildings, Lambeth]” and “William Blocke” under Lambeth, 13, Hercules Buildings (the poet’s
address) in Patrick <hi rend="i">Boyle’s New London Guide for the Year 1797</hi> (London: P. Boyle, 1797)
34, and the entries were repeated without change in <hi rend="i">Boyle’s City Companion to the Court Guide
for the Year 1798</hi> (1798). And in the spring of 1799 the following striking constellation appeared in [W.]
<hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory</hi> [Corrected to the end of April] 1799, 63:
<table rows="4" cols="3"><row>
	<cell>Blake W.S.</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Engraver and Printer</hi></cell>
	<cell>16, ‘Change-alley, Cornhill</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Blake William</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Engraver</hi></cell>
	<cell>Lambeth Green<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n51">3. “Lambeth Green” (omitted from <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969] 561 and 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 746) is apparently the previous name of Carlisle Lane, which in Horwood’s map (1792-99)
is two streets west of Hercules Buildings.</note>
	</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>. . .</cell>
	<cell/><cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Blake James</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Hosier</hi></cell>
	<cell>28, Broad-street, Carnaby-market</cell>
</row></table></p>
                  <p>Pp. 829-46, Appendix VI</p>
                  <p>According to the Biography Database 1680-1830 (currently 3 CDs), there were printed
accounts of non-poetical men named William Blake and of others in the poet’s circle which supplement the
information in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> Second Edition (2004), particularly in Appendix VI: “‘My
Name is Legion: for we are many’: ‘William Blake’ in London 1740-1830.”</p>
                  <p>William Blake:</p>
                  <p>Aldersgate Street (1765-1800); Mercer (1767-70); Stationer’s Company Apprentice (1772);
Grocer (1784); Tin Plate Worker and Watch Case Maker, of 75, Whitechapel Road (1784-90); Auctioneer
(1784-1823); Inn Keeper, Bull and Gate, Holborn (1785); Wimbledon (1790); Glue-Maker (1790, 1805); Grosvenor
Square (d. 4 March 1795); Tortoise-shell Case-maker (1799)</p>
                  <p>William Staden Blake, Engraver (1748-c. 1817)</p>
                  <p>Mathew, Mrs [Harriet], wife of A. S. Mathew</p>
                  <pb id="p39-34" n="34"/>
                  <table rows="52" cols="4">
                    <head>
                      <hi rend="b">Table 1: Blake’s Circle in the <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National
Biography</hi> (2004)</hi>
                    </head>
                    <row>
                      <cell>Name</cell>
                      <cell>Profession/connection to Blake</cell>
                      <cell><hi rend="i">ODNB</hi> entry</cell>
                      <cell><hi rend="i">ODNB</hi> entry author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>BARTON, Bernard (1784-1845)</cell>
                      <cell>Quaker poet</cell>
                      <cell>4: 191-92</cell>
                      <cell>A. H. Bullen, rev. James Edgar Barcus, Jr.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>BASIRE, James (1730-1802)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n52">1. Included in the entry for “Basire, Isaac (1704-1768).”</note>
	</cell>
                      <cell>Engraver, Blake’s master</cell>
                      <cell>4: 234-37</cell>
                      <cell>Lucy Peltz</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>CALVERT, Edward (1799-1883)</cell>
                      <cell>Artist, disciple of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>9: 579-81</cell>
                      <cell>Raymond Lister</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>COSWAY, Richard (1742-1821)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n53">2. See also Stephen Lloyd, “Baroness Maria Louisa Catherine Cecilia (<hi rend="i">née</hi>
Hadfield),” 13: 554-57.</note>
	</cell>
                      <cell>Miniaturist, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>13: 557-63</cell>
                      <cell>Stephen Lloyd</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>CROMEK, Robert Hartley (1770-1812)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n54" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n54">3. See also Michael Warrington, life of the entrepreneur’s son “Cromek, Thomas Hartley
(1809-1873), painter . . .,” 14: 294-95, who went to the Moravian school at Fulneck in 1820.</note>
	</cell>
                      <cell>Engraver and entrepreneur</cell>
                      <cell>14: 293-94</cell>
                      <cell>Dennis M. Read</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>CUMBERLAND, George (1754-1848)</cell>
                      <cell>Dilettante, lifelong friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>14: 614-15</cell>
                      <cell>Francis Greenacre</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>CUNNINGHAM, Allan (1784-1842)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n55">4. It says that manuscript “lives of painters and related corresp.” including his life of
Blake (1830) are in the National Library of Scotland. [The National Library of Scotland does 
<hi rend="i">not</hi> have the ms. of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>, though it does have (MS 827) a mixed
set of the printed version (1830-39) annotated by Cunningham or (in the case of Blake) by his son (used in
Heaton’s edition of Cunningham [1879-80]), plus correspondence connected with the 
<hi rend="i">Lives.</hi>]</note>
	</cell>
                      <cell>Biographer of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>14: 669-70</cell>
                      <cell>Leslie Stephen, rev. Hamish Whyte</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>ENSOM, William (1796-1832)</cell>
                      <cell>Engraver</cell>
                      <cell>18: 464</cell>
                      <cell>B. Hunnisett</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>FINCH, Francis Oliver (1802-62)</cell>
                      <cell>Artist, disciple of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>19: 559-60</cell>
                      <cell>Raymond Lister</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>FLAXMAN, John (1755-1826)</cell>
                      <cell>Sculptor, intimate friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>21: 4-10</cell>
                      <cell>Sarah Symmons</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>FUSELI, John Henry (1741-1825)</cell>
                      <cell>Swiss painter, intimate friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>21: 207-15</cell>
                      <cell>D. H. Weinglass</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>GIBSON, John (1790-1866)</cell>
                      <cell>Sculptor</cell>
                      <cell>22: 82-87</cell>
                      <cell>Martin Greenwood</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>GILCHRIST, Alexander (1828-61)</cell>
                      <cell>Biographer of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>22: 215</cell>
                      <cell>H. H. Gilchrist, rev. Michael Thorn</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>GILCHRIST, Anne (1828-85)</cell>
                      <cell>Wife of Alexander Gilchrist</cell>
                      <cell>22: 215-17</cell>
                      <cell>Michael Thorn</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>HAWKINS, John (1761-1841)</cell>
                      <cell>Patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>25: 929-30</cell>
                      <cell>H. S. Torrens</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>HAYLEY, Thomas Alphonso (1780-1800)</cell>
                      <cell>Natural son of William Hayley</cell>
                      <cell>26: 46</cell>
                      <cell>L. H. Cust, rev. Jason Edwards</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>HAYLEY, William (1745-1820)</cell>
                      <cell>Poet and biographer, Blake’s patron</cell>
                      <cell>26: 46-49</cell>
                      <cell>Vivienne W. Painting</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>HESKETH, Harriet, Lady (1733-1807)</cell>
                      <cell>Cousin of William Cowper, reluctant patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>26: 876-77</cell>
                      <cell>James William Kelly</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>HUMPHRY, Ozias (1742-1810)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n56">5. See p. 4 here, footnote 1.</note>
	</cell>
                      <cell>Miniaturist, patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>27: 812-14</cell>
                      <cell>V. Remington</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>JOHNSON, Dr. John (1769-1833)</cell>
                      <cell>Cowper relative, friend of Hayley and Blake</cell>
                      <cell>30: 279</cell>
                      <cell>Thompson Cooper and Rebecca Mills</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>JOHNSON, Joseph (1738-1809)</cell>
                      <cell>Bookseller, patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>30: 282-84</cell>
                      <cell>Carol Hall</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>KER, Charles Henry Bellenden (ca. 1785-1871)</cell>
                      <cell>Dilettante, disgruntled patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>31: 378-79</cell>
                      <cell>W. R. Cornish and David J. A. Cairns</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>KIRKUP, Seymour Stocker (1788-1880)</cell>
                      <cell>Artist, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>31: 816-17</cell>
                      <cell>L. H. Cust, rev. David Robertson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>LAMB, Caroline, Lady (1785-1828)</cell>
                      <cell>Byron’s bête noire, entertainer of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>32: 257-59</cell>
                      <cell>Caroline Franklin</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>LEIGH, James Mathews (1808-60)</cell>
                      <cell>Art teacher and painter</cell>
                      <cell>33: 237-38</cell>
                      <cell>Martin Postle</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>LINNELL, John (1792-1882)</cell>
                      <cell>Painter, patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>33: 934-37</cell>
                      <cell>Christiana Payne</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>LIZARS, William Home (1788-1859)</cell>
                      <cell>Painter and engraver</cell>
                      <cell>34: 90-91</cell>
                      <cell>Jennifer Melville</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>MALKIN, Benjamin Heath (1769-1842)</cell>
                      <cell>Biographer of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>36: 323-24</cell>
                      <cell>G. Martin Murphy</cell>
                    </row>
                  </table>
                    <pb id="p39-35" n="35"/>
                  <table>
                    <row>
                      <cell>MARSH, John (1752-1828)</cell>
                      <cell>Lawyer, musical composer, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>36: 801-02</cell>
                      <cell>Brian Robins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>MARTIN, John (1741-1820)</cell>
                      <cell>Baptist minister</cell>
                      <cell>36: 947-48</cell>
                      <cell>J. H. Y. Briggs</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>MONTGOMERY, James (1771-1854)</cell>
                      <cell>Poet</cell>
                      <cell>37: 856-58</cell>
                      <cell>G. Tolley</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>PALMER, Samuel (1805-81)</cell>
                      <cell>Artist, disciple of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>42: 530-35</cell>
                      <cell>Raymond Lister</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>PARKER, James (1757-1805)</cell>
                      <cell>Engraver, Blake’s printshop partner</cell>
                      <cell>42: 689</cell>
                      <cell>Vivienne W. Painting</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>PARS, Henry (1734-1806)</cell>
                      <cell>Drawing school master</cell>
                      <cell>42: 904</cell>
                      <cell>W. C. Monkhouse, rev. Mark Pottle</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>PUGHE, William Owen (1759-1835)</cell>
                      <cell>Cambrian enthusiast, patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>45: 515-17</cell>
                      <cell>J. E. Lloyd, rev. Glenda Carr</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>RICHMOND, George (1809-96)</cell>
                      <cell>Painter, disciple of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>46: 872-74</cell>
                      <cell>Raymond Lister</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>ROBINSON, Henry Crabb (1775-1867)</cell>
                      <cell>Diarist, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>47: 343-45</cell>
                      <cell>Vincent Newey</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>ROSE, Samuel (1767-1804)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n57">6. The Rose mss. in Glasgow University Library consist chiefly of 91 letters of 1783-1800,
mostly <hi rend="i">to</hi> Rose.</note>
	</cell>
                      <cell>Blake’s lawyer</cell>
                      <cell>47: 768-69</cell>
                      <cell>W. P. Courtney, rev. S. C. Bushell</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>RYLAND, William Wynne (1733-83)</cell>
                      <cell>Engraver and forger</cell>
                      <cell>48: 473-75</cell>
                      <cell>Timothy Clayton</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>SCHIAVONETTI, Louis (1765-1810)</cell>
                      <cell>Engraver of Blake’s designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi></cell>
                      <cell>49: 217-18</cell>
                      <cell>Vivienne W. Painting</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>SHARP, William (1749-1824)</cell>
                      <cell>Engraver, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>50: 39-40</cell>
                      <cell>Richard Sharp</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>SMITH, John Thomas (1766-1833)</cell>
                      <cell>Biographer of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>51: 229-31</cell>
                      <cell>Lucy Peltz</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>STEDMAN, Captain John Gabriel (1744-97)</cell>
                      <cell>Soldier of fortune, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>52: 344-45</cell>
                      <cell>Richard Price</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>STOTHARD, Thomas (1755-1834)</cell>
                      <cell>Book illustrator, early friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>52: 964-66</cell>
                      <cell>M. G. Sullivan</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>TATHAM, Charles Heathcote (1772-1842)</cell>
                      <cell>Architect, father of Frederick, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>53: 818-22</cell>
                      <cell>Richard Riddell</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>THORNTON, Dr. Robert John (1768-1837)</cell>
                      <cell>Physician, patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>54: 640-41</cell>
                      <cell>Martin Kemp</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>TILLOCH, Alexander (1759-1825)</cell>
                      <cell>Inventor, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>54: 790-91</cell>
                      <cell>John Burnett</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>TRUSLER, Rev. Dr. John (1735-1820)</cell>
                      <cell>Almost patron of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>55: 470-71</cell>
                      <cell>Emma Major</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>TULK, Charles Augustus (1786-1849)</cell>
                      <cell>Swedenborgian, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>55: 538</cell>
                      <cell>Alexander Gordon, rev. Timothy C. F. Stunt</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>UPCOTT, William (1779-1845)</cell>
                      <cell>Autograph collector</cell>
                      <cell>55: 921-23</cell>
                      <cell>Janet Ing Freeman</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>VARLEY, John (1778-1842)</cell>
                      <cell>Painter, astrologer, friend of Blake</cell>
                      <cell>56: 146-49</cell>
                      <cell>C. M. Kauffmann</cell>
                    </row>
                  </table>
                </div6>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p39-36" n="36"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Index</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Ackroyd, Peter 18</p>
              <p>Agha, Marisa 18</p>
              <p>Anderson, Daniel Gustav 20, 23</p>
              <p>Anderson, John 29</p>
              <p>Ando, Kiyoshi 18</p>
              <p>Ankarsjö, Magnus 8n, 18</p>
              <p>Ansari, A. A. 18, 19</p>
              <p>Asleson, Robyn 30, 31</p>
              <p>Baines, Paul 30</p>
              <p>Banes, Henry 5, 32</p>
              <p>Bätschmann, Marie Therese 31</p>
              <p>Beer, F. B. 19</p>
              <p>Beer, John 19</p>
              <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. 19</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 7, 19, 20, 32</p>
              <p>Bindman, David 16</p>
              <p>Blake (née Boucher), Catherine 9n, 23, 29</p>
              <p>Blake (née Wright), Catherine 6, 7, 18, 21, 22, 24, 29, 32</p>
              <p>Blake, William:<lb/>
<hi rend="i">America</hi> 7, 10, 12, 25, 26, 27; “Auguries of Innocence” 20; <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 10,
12; <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> 10; <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 18, 25, 26, 28; 
<hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi> 22; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 10, 13, 15, 18, 20, 21, 25, 28; 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> 5, 13, 16, 26, 32; Letters 5, 9, 10, 11, 16, 32, cover illus.; “Mental Traveller” 12;
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 8n, 12, 16, 18, 26, 28, 29; <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 13, 16, 18,
24, 25; <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> 5, 12; <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> 11, 12; <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> 11, 18, 25, 30; <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> 25, 30, 31; <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi> 11, 13, 27, 28; <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 12, 15; <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 5,
12, 13, 24, 25; <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 5, 12, 20<lb/>
Illustrations/engravings of/for:<lb/>
Allen 13; Blair 5, 13; Bürger 13; Dante 27, 28; Flaxman 13; Gay 13; Gough 13; Josephus 5, 14; Lavater 7, 14,
20; Milton 5, 9n, 12, 13, 16; <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi> 15; Salzmann 15; Scott 15; Stedman 15;
Varley 15; Virgil 15, 27; <hi rend="i">Wit’s Magazine</hi> 15; Young 15, 33</p>
              <p>Bloom, Harold 10, 31</p>
              <p>Bolcom, William 8n, 28</p>
              <p>Bower, Peter 6, 10, 21, 29</p>
              <p>Brooke, Stopford A. 21</p>
              <p>Brown, Mary Gifford 21</p>
              <p>Butlin, Martin 21</p>
              <p>Butts, Thomas 15</p>
              <p>Cadogan, Peter 21</p>
              <p>Cama, Shernaz 19</p>
              <p>Capet, Antoine 17, 20</p>
              <p>Chauvin, Danièle 21</p>
              <p>Chen, Zhifan 21, 30</p>
              <p>Chong, Cue-huan 21</p>
              <p>Clark, Madeline 21</p>
              <p>Connolly, Tristanne J. 20, 21</p>
              <p>Cooper, Joe and Edna 21</p>
              <p>Corbett, William 22</p>
              <p>Corti, Claudia 22</p>
              <p>Cosway, Richard 30</p>
              <p>Cunningham, Allan 22</p>
              <p>Curnutte, Rick 22</p>
              <p>Davies, Keri 6, 7, 12, 20, 22, 24, 32</p>
              <p>Dean, John 29</p>
              <p>Deuchler, Florens 31</p>
              <p>Dhar, Subir 20, 23</p>
              <p>Diaz, Roberto 11</p>
              <p>Dimock, Wai Chee 23</p>
              <p>Directories 7, 23, 33</p>
              <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. 23</p>
              <p>Drake, Dee 20, 23</p>
              <p>Drechsler, Maximiliane 23</p>
              <p>Easton, Will 21</p>
              <p>Eaves, Morris 21, 23</p>
              <p>Erdman, David V. 10, 12</p>
              <p>Erle, Sibylle 28</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert N. 5, 7, 9n, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16n, 18, 20, 23, 24, 31</p>
              <p>Exhibitions: Associated Painters 15, 32; Kyoto 16, 20; St. Louis 5, 16; Tate (2000-01) 16;
Tate (2004) 5, 17, 20; Wordsworth Trust 5, 11, 12, 16</p>
              <p>Fischer, Kevin 23</p>
              <p>Fitzgerald, Penelope 18</p>
              <p>Flaxman, John 30</p>
              <p>Foster, Paul 31</p>
              <p>Freeman, Kathryn 19</p>
              <p>Frosch, Thomas 20, 21</p>
              <p>Frye, Northrop 7, 23</p>
              <p>Fuseli, John Henry 13, 31</p>
              <p>Galvin, Rachel 23</p>
              <p>Gilchrist, Alexander 23</p>
              <p>Gilchrist, Anne 23, 24</p>
              <p>Gilpin, George H. 24</p>
              <p>Gimeno, Francisco 24</p>
              <p>Gleckner, Robert F. 24</p>
              <p>Goslee, Nancy Moore 20, 23, 24</p>
              <p>Gourlay, Alexander S. 19, 24, 32</p>
              <p>Hamilton, William L. 24</p>
              <p>Hamlyn, Robin 6, 29</p>
              <p>Hanley, Howard J. M. 16</p>
              <p>Haycock, David 31</p>
              <p>Hayes, Elliott 24</p>
              <p>Hayes, Tom 24</p>
              <p>Hazlitt, William 24</p>
              <p>Heath, Tim 8n, 21, 23</p>
              <p>Hebron, Stephen 16</p>
              <p>Hendriks, Ella 30</p>
              <p>Heringman, Noah 24</p>
              <p>Hollis, Derek 24</p>
              <p>Holmes, Richard 23</p>
              <p>Hopson, Gerry 29</p>
              <p>Horne, Herbert P. 24</p>
              <p>Hutchings, Kevin 20, 24</p>
              <p>Ima-Izumi, Yoko 8n, 16, 20</p>
              <p>Iwasaki, Toyotaro 25</p>
              <p>Jackson, M. W. 25</p>
              <p>John, Donald 25</p>
              <p>Johnes, Thomas 31</p>
              <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn 7, 14, 20</p>
              <p>Kanetake, Michiko 18</p>
              <p>Kang, Ok-Sun 25</p>
              <p>Kashiwabara, Ikuko 25</p>
              <p>Katayama, Mamiko 25</p>
              <p>Kawasaki, Noriko 25</p>
              <p>Kelleway, Kelly 25</p>
              <p>Ker, Charles Henry Bellenden 32</p>
              <pb id="p39-37" n="37"/>
              <p>Keynes, Geoffrey 25</p>
              <p>King, James 30</p>
              <p>Komisaruk, Adam 20</p>
              <p>Lee, Hyungsoo 25</p>
              <p>Leigh, Peter 25</p>
              <p>Lincoln, Andrew 12, 19, 20, 21, 23, 26</p>
              <p>Linebaugh, Peter 25</p>
              <p>Linnell, John 31</p>
              <p>Livergood, Norman D. 25</p>
              <p>Lloyd, Stephen 30</p>
              <p>Lukacher, Brian 25</p>
              <p>Lundeen, Kathleen 20, 27</p>
              <p>MacPhee, Chantelle 25</p>
              <p>Macve, Jennifer 31</p>
              <p>Makdisi, Saree 25</p>
              <p>Marsh, John 31</p>
              <p>Matsushima, Shoichi 12, 26</p>
              <p>McClenahan, Catherine L. 12, 20</p>
              <p>McCord, Jim 21</p>
              <p>McManus, Noa Cahaner 29</p>
              <p>McQuade, Molly 26</p>
              <p>Mellor, Anne K. 26</p>
              <p>Michael, Jennifer Davis 20, 24</p>
              <p>Miller, Charlotte 30</p>
              <p>Minton, David 26</p>
              <p>Mjöberg, Jöran 19</p>
              <p>Moore, Michael 26</p>
              <p>Mounsey, Chris 26</p>
              <p>Mungapen, Shirley 21</p>
              <p>Nachmanovitch, Stephen 8n, 26</p>
              <p>Nagashima, Kazuhiko 26</p>
              <p>Nair, Rajeev Kesavan 26</p>
              <p>Nakagawa, Kazuo 26</p>
              <p>Nakamura, Hiroko 26</p>
              <p>Neruda, Pablo 12</p>
              <p>Newman, Marcia 26</p>
              <p>Nudelman, Bryan C. 26</p>
              <p>Ormsby, Bronwyn 26, 29</p>
              <p>Østermark-Johansen, Lene 26</p>
              <p>Otto, Peter 26</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi> (2004) 4-5, 22, 23, 34-35</p>
              <p>Paley, Morton D. 6, 15n, 20, 27</p>
              <p>Palmer, Samuel 31</p>
              <p>Parker, James 32</p>
              <p>Paulson, Ronald 27</p>
              <p>Pawlowski, G. 27</p>
              <p>Pellis, Valeria 27</p>
              <p>P[éricaud, Val] 27</p>
              <p>Perry, Seamus 19, 27</p>
              <p>Phillips, Michael 7, 10n, 27</p>
              <p>Plotnitsky, Arkady 27</p>
              <p>Posman, Lucien 21</p>
              <p>Punter, David 27</p>
              <p>Rackowitz, Chad E. 20</p>
              <p>Raffel, Burton 27</p>
              <p>Raine, Kathleen 21, 27</p>
              <p>Rawlinson, Nick 20, 27</p>
              <p>Rediker, Marcus 25</p>
              <p>Reinhart, Charles 27</p>
              <p>Richmond, George 31</p>
              <p>Ripley, Wayne C. 26</p>
              <p>Rix, Robert W. 20, 28</p>
              <p>Rockwell, John 28</p>
              <p>Roe, Albert S. 28</p>
              <p>Rowland, Christopher 28</p>
              <p>Rudd, Margaret 28</p>
              <p>Samoyault, Tiphaine 28</p>
              <p>Santhanam, Kausalya 16</p>
              <p>Sato, Hikari 28</p>
              <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith 6, 7, 20, 32</p>
              <p>Scott, Peter Dale 28</p>
              <p>Shaddock, David 20</p>
              <p>Shawcross, John T. 13</p>
              <p>Shinn, Matt 24</p>
              <p>Singer, Brian 29</p>
              <p>Sklar, Susanne 4n, 10, 20, 21, 28</p>
              <p>Smith, Cyril 28</p>
              <p>Smith, K. E. 21</p>
              <p>Snart, J. 28</p>
              <p>So, Tat-Sang 28</p>
              <p>Solomon, Andrew 21</p>
              <p>Spector, Sheila A. 20, 28</p>
              <p>Stanger, James Aaron 28</p>
              <p>Stavis, Henriette B. 28</p>
              <p>Stoker, Mark 30</p>
              <p>Stothard, Thomas 32</p>
              <p>Strange, John Clark 28</p>
              <p>Sung, Mei-Ying 28</p>
              <p>Suzuki, Masayoki 28</p>
              <p>Tambling, Jeremy 28</p>
              <p>Tatham, Frederick 33</p>
              <p>Taylor, Dena Bain 20, 28</p>
              <p>Townsend, Joyce H. 6, 8n, 28</p>
              <p>Townshend, Piers 29</p>
              <p>Traeger, Jörg 29</p>
              <p>Vernède, Andrew 21</p>
              <p>Viscomi, Joseph 12, 23, 29</p>
              <p>Wagenknecht, David 25</p>
              <p>Wainwright, Martin 29</p>
              <p>Ward, Aileen 26</p>
              <p>Wardi, Eynel 29</p>
              <p>Warner, Janet 18, 29</p>
              <p>Westerweel, Bart 30</p>
              <p>Whissell, Cynthia 30</p>
              <p>Whitehead, Angus 7, 21, 23n</p>
              <p>Whitman, Vincent Miller 30</p>
              <p>Whittaker, Jason 21</p>
              <p>William Blake Archive 10, 11, 12, 18, 23</p>
              <p>Williamson, Richard 30</p>
              <p>Wittreich, Joseph 20, 24, 30</p>
              <p>Woof, Robert 16</p>
              <p>Wootton, Sarah 31</p>
              <p>Worrall, David 18</p>
              <p>Wright, Julia M. 7, 30</p>
              <p>Yang, Mu [Jingxian Wang] 30</p>
              <p>Yeshima, Kenkichi 30</p>
              <p>Youngquist, Paul 19</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
