<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.1.groves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Great and Singular Genius”: Further References to Blake (and Cromek) in the
Scots Magazine</title>
        <author n="Groves">David Groves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Dr. David Groves</name>
              <name>Howard Jacobson</name>
              <name>Alexander Gourlay</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
	<pb id="p39-47" n="47"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-1-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Great and Singular Genius”: Further References to Blake (and Cromek) in
the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>David <name>Groves</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The generous review of “<hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Illustrations of 
<hi rend="i">Blair’s</hi> Grave” in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> of November 1808 has been known for
some time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">1</ref> No critic, however, has
yet noted the existence of two short anonymous notices, earlier in the same magazine, which paved the way for
the volume’s reception in Edinburgh. The first, in July 1807, appeared as the first of three paragraphs in
the “Scottish Literary Intelligence” column. It announces the forthcoming Blake-Blair volume and describes
an exhibition, organized by the book’s publisher Robert Cromek, in St. James’s Square in Edinburgh. The
exhibition featured Blake’s original paintings for Robert Blair’s poem <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, as
well as a painting to illustrate <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Tales</hi>:
<q>
A Splendid Edition of Blair’s Grave is about to be published, illustrated with paintings by Mr Blake, an
artist and poet of great and singular genius. These paintings are now exhibiting in James’s Square No. 9. by
Mr Cromek, a very ingenious young artist, who proposes to engrave them for the abovementioned work, for which
he is now taking in subscriptions. A beautiful painting of the procession of Chaucer’s pilgrims is exhibited
at the same time, and Mr Cromek is also taking in subscriptions for an engraving which is to be made from
it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n74">1. The review is reprinted in my note “Blake, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and Edinburgh
Literary Society,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 24.1 (summer 1990): 35-36.</note>
	<note id="n75">2. Anon., “Scottish Literary Intelligence,” <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine, and Edinburgh
Literary Miscellany</hi> 69 (1807): 522.</note></q>
The “paintings” by Blake here were presumably the set of nineteen watercolors which have recently come to
light, in what has been described as “the most exciting Blake discovery” in many decades, “and arguably
the most important since Blake began to be appreciated in the second half of the nineteenth
century.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">3</ref> Evidently at this time in
1807, Cromek was planning to engrave Blake’s designs himself. It is unclear whether the painting of
“Chaucer’s pilgrims” is the well-known one by Thomas Stothard, commissioned by Cromek and finished in
<pb id="p39-48" n="48"/>
1807, or the watercolor which Blake completed at about the same time, and which was also commissioned by
Cromek.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n76">3. Martin Butlin, “New Risen from the Grave: Nineteen Unknown Watercolors by William
Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 35.3 (winter 2002-03): 68-73 (68). The paintings apparently remained in
Edinburgh after the exhibition, and were sold to a Scottish collector in 1836. See also G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
“Thomas Sivright and the Lost Designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19.3
(winter 1985-86): 103-06.</note>
	<note id="n77">4. For Stothard’s and Blake’s rival illustrations to Chaucer, see Peter Ackroyd, 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (London: Sinclair-Stevenson, 1995) 271-72, and G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969) 209, 216-17. Blake exhibited his own painting for Chaucer’s 
<hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi> in London in May 1809.</note></p>
          <p>Meanwhile, Cromek’s reputation in Edinburgh continued to grow as a result of his lucrative
researches into Scottish poetry. The December <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> announced that “An
interesting literary discovery of unpublished works of the late Robert Burns, has been made by Mr Cromer
[sic], in a late tour through Scotland.” Many Scots readers would have been stirred by this glowing account
of newfound poems and letters by Burns being “rescued from oblivion” by Cromek.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">5</ref> Coming so soon before the Blake-Blair volume, this advance
publicity for Cromek’s edition of <hi rend="i">Reliques of Burns</hi> probably contributed to the success of
<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, with Blake’s designs, in Edinburgh. <note id="n78">5. Anon., “Scottish
Literary Intelligence,” <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> 69 (1807): 925.</note></p>
          <p>No mention of Blake appeared in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> between July 1807 and
September 1808. But in that month, the magazine noted the actual publication of Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> and its engravings by Luigi Schiavonetti based on Blake’s paintings. This briefer notice
gives the size of the volume and its price of two pounds, twelve shillings and sixpence: “Illustrations of
Blair’s Grave, in 12 Etchings, executed by Louis Schiavonetti, from the Original Inventions of William
Blake, 4to. 2<hi rend="i">l.</hi> 12s. 6d.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79"
type="note">6</ref> The long review of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, praising Blake for his “genius” and
“beautiful” though “eccentric” designs, followed quickly in November.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n79">6. Anon., <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> 70 (1808): 683. The notice is the second of three
paragraphs in the “New Works Published in Edinburgh” section for September 1808.</note>
	<note id="n80">7. <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> 70 (1808): 839-40.</note></p>
          <p>There appear to be no further citations of Blake in the <hi rend="i">Scots
Magazine.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">8</ref> But in December 1808,
its readers were told that Cromek’s long-awaited work on Burns was now in print: “Reliques of Robert
Burns: consisting chiefly of original Letters, Poems, and Critical Observations on Scottish Songs. Collected
and published by R.H. Cromek. 8vo. 10s. 6d.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82"
type="note">9</ref> Long extracts from the <hi rend="i">Reliques of Burns</hi> followed in January 1809, and a
laudatory review in March.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">10</ref> Then, in
August 1809, the same journal announced that “Mr Cromek is receiving subscriptions for an Historical
Portrait of Mr Walter Scott, from the admired Picture by [Henry] Raeburn, which appeared at the last Exibition
[sic] of Scottish paintings.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n81">8. The <hi rend="i">Scots</hi> continued publishing until the end of 1826. One article of some
interest (as it mentions a few of Blake’s fellow engravers) is the anonymous “Account of a Society Formed
for the Encouragement of the Art of Engraving” (72 [August 1810]: 590-92).</note>
	<note id="n82">9. Anon., “New Works Published in Edinburgh,” <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> 70 (1808):
923. The identical notice (with a few changes in capitalization) appeared in the same column for January 1809
(71: 46).</note>
	<note id="n83">
                            10. Anon., “<hi rend="i">Cromek’s</hi> Reliques of <hi rend="i">Burns</hi>,”
<hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> 71 (1809): 30-33 and 198-203 (the title is taken from the table of contents
for March). The appearance of these articles, coming so soon after the same journal’s review of 
<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, would have given Cromek quite a high profile among Scottish readers.
                            <p>No critic has noted that Cromek was probably of Scots descent (though born in
England). Each of his five volumes was Scottish in some way, and his unusual surname is remarkably close to
the Scottish Gaelic words “crom,” “cromack,” or “cromag,” which mean “anything twisted or bent,
particularly fingers” (Blake would have enjoyed that!). “Cromack” is also a variant spelling of the
Gaelic word “crummock,” meaning “a cow with twisted horns” (see the <hi rend="i">Scottish National
Dictionary</hi>, 1952 edition, III: 251-52 and 267).</p></note>
	<note id="n84">11. Anon., “Scottish Literary Intelligence,” <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine, and Edinburgh
Literary Miscellany</hi> 71 (1809): 605.</note></p>
          <p>Around 1810, Cromek’s reputation in Scottish circles began to wane. Perhaps this was due in
part to Walter Scott’s influence, for Scott told one publisher that “Cromek is a perfect Brain-sucker
living upon the labours of others.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85"
type="note">12</ref> Cromek’s two-volume <hi rend="i">Select Scotish Songs</hi>, published in 1810, received
neither review nor notice of any kind in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine.</hi> When his final book, 
<hi rend="i">Remains of Nithsdale and Galloway Song</hi>, came out in 1811, a polite but lukewarm review commended
Cromek’s “copious” notes and “good deal of valuable information” on the subjects of “witchcraft”
and “fairies.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">13</ref> Cromek’s death
in 1812 passed unnoticed in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine.</hi>
	<note id="n85">12. Letter to John Murray, 3 Dec. 1810, <hi rend="i">The Letters of Sir Walter Scott</hi>, ed.
H. J. C. Grierson, 12 vols. (London: Constable, 1932-37) II: 409-10 (409).</note>
	<note id="n86">13. Anon., “<hi rend="i">Remains of Nithsdale and Galloway Song</hi> . . . by R.W. [sic]
Cromek, F.A.S. Ed., Editor of the Reliques of Robert Burns,” <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> 73 (June
1811): 441-47 (444, 445). “F.A.S. Ed.” identifies Cromek as a fellow of Edinburgh’s Antiquarian Society.
The <hi rend="i">Nithsdale</hi> volume has some relevance to Blake, because many of its supposed folk songs
were in fact by Allan Cunningham, who later wrote the well-known chapter on Blake in his <hi rend="i">Lives of
the Most Eminent British Painters.</hi> The imposture was detected by James Hogg, but Hogg was unable to find
a publisher for his review on the subject; Hogg’s review, alas, has never been traced, although he says he
kept the manuscript until at least 1832 (see his <hi rend="i">“Memoir of the Author’s Life” and
“Familiar Anecdotes of Sir Walter Scott,”</hi> ed. Douglas Mack [Edinburgh: Scottish Academic P, 1972]
73).</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
