<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.2.whitehead</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">“I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel”: The Will of Henry
Banes, Landlord of 3 Fountain Court, Strand, the Last Residence of William and Catherine Blake</title>
        <author n="Whitehead">Angus Whitehead</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
              <name>Joyce H. Townsend</name>
              <name>Bronwyn Ormsby</name>
              <name>Julia Jönsson</name>
              <name>Mark Evans</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-2-0006">
        <pb id="p39-78" n="78"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“<hi rend="i">I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing
                                apparel</hi>”<lb/>
                                The Will of Henry Banes, Landlord of 3 Fountain
                            	Court, Strand, the Last Residence of William and Catherine Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Angus <name>Whitehead</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Henry Banes was the brother-in-law of William and Catherine Blake as well as
                        their landlord at 3 Fountain Court, Strand, from 1821 until 1827.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n170" type="note">*</ref> This paper
                        will focus primarily upon the contents of Henry Banes’ will, a
                        document hitherto unknown to Blake scholarship.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">1</ref> As well as explicitly referring to, and providing new
                        information about, William and Catherine Blake, Banes’ will throws
                        new light on the Blakes’ relationship with their relative and
                        landlord. The will also contains information pertinent to a clearer
                        understanding of Catherine Blake’s financial affairs and how and
                        where she was living in the spring of 1829, approximately eighteen months
                        after the death of her husband. In addition, the document provides the dates
                        of the decease of Henry Banes and his wife, Catherine Blake’s sister,
                        Sarah Banes, and evidence of Sarah’s residence at 3 Fountain Court
                        from 1803 until March 1824. Sarah’s established presence at this
                        address may partially explain William and Catherine Blake’s choice of
                        residence on removal from their apartment at 17 South Molton Street in 1821.
                        <note id="n170">* The first two sections of this
                            paper derive largely from chapter 3 of my MA dissertation
                            “‘My Present Precincts’: A Recreation of the
                            Last Living and Working Space of William Blake: 3 Fountain Court,
                            Strand 1821-7,” MA in Blake and the Age of Revolution,
                            University of York, October 2002, directed by Michael Phillips. I am
                            grateful to G. E. Bentley, Jr., for generously sharing his own
                            findings concerning Henry Banes. I also wish to thank Michael
                            Phillips and Keri Davies for reading and commenting so helpfully on
                            earlier drafts of this paper. Finally thanks to John Barrell, Robert
                            Essick, Sarah Jones, David Linnell, Angela Roche and David Worrall
                            for advice on minute particulars.</note>
	<note id="n28">1. Although the original will written by Henry Banes has
                            not been traced, the Prerogative Court of Canterbury probate copy has
                            (see below).</note></p>
          <p>It has been previously assumed that, apart from Blake’s younger
                        sister, Catherine Elizabeth Blake, William and Catherine Blake had no
                        surviving family relations. I will argue that the circumstances surrounding
                        Banes’ choice of “sole Executrix” of his will suggest
                        that Henry and Sarah Banes may have had a daughter and therefore that
                        William and Catherine Blake may have been survived by a niece, named Louisa
                        (or Louiza) Best, née Banes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">2</ref>
                        Finally, the sole witness of Henry Banes’ will, the artist John
                        Barrow, will be conclusively identified as the publisher of Blake’s
                        commercial engraving “Mrs Q” (1820). <note id="n29">2.
                            “Louisa” is the spelling used in the 1841 census return
                            for 3 Fountain Court, Strand (Public Record Office HO 107/731/3 15).
                            “Louiza” is the spelling used in the PCC copy of the will
                            of Henry Banes, proved 14 February 1829 (PRO PROB 11/1751 [Liverpool
                            Quire 51-100, folio 79]).</note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Henry Banes, William and Catherine Blake’s
                                    Relation and Landlord</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In about 1860, Blake’s biographer, the 32-year-old Alexander
                            Gilchrist, visited Fountain Court, on the south side of the Strand, in
                            order to research William and Catherine Blake’s last residence.
                            At 3 Fountain Court Gilchrist encountered a “dirty
                            stuccoed” building that had “suffered a decline of
                                fortune”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">3</ref> (illus. 1). The
                            front room on the first floor, the Blakes’ former reception room,
                            showroom and printing studio, was vacant and “in the market at
                            four and sixpence a week, as an assiduous enquirer found.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">4</ref> The rest of the house was
                            “let out . . . in single rooms to the labouring poor.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">5</ref> During his visit, Gilchrist could
                            have encountered a number of the 36 inhabitants recorded in the 1861
                            census return for 3 Fountain Court. Amidst the “excessive noise
                            of children,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">6</ref> he may have
                            called on and conversed with William Jones, wine porter, George Caudle,
                            vellum binder, Mary Huntley, laundress, James Stone, onion dealer,
                            William Wilby, police constable, William Jones, carman, James Haywood,
                            fishmonger, and Thomas Curtis, water gilder, and their respective
                                families.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">7</ref> However, it seems
                            unlikely that anyone then living either at this residence or elsewhere
                            in Fountain Court had been a fellow lodger or neighbor of William and
                            Catherine Blake over 30 years earlier. <note id="n30">3. Gilchrist
                                282.</note>
	<note id="n31">4. Gilchrist 282.</note>
	<note id="n32">5. Gilchrist 282.</note>
	<note id="n33">6. Gilchrist 308.</note>
	<note id="n34">7. 1861 census [7 April 1861] return for 3 Fountain
                                Court, Strand, PRO RG 9/179/68.</note></p>
            <p>Few details concerning, or indeed derived from, those “humble but
                                respectable”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">8</ref> former
                            neighbors of the Blakes were included in Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of
William Blake</hi>, published posthumously in 1863.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">9</ref> Had such figures been traced, their
                            accounts might have complemented those of the less materially humble
                            figures that Gilchrist did interview or correspond with concerning
                            Blake’s last years, including John Linnell, Samuel Palmer and
                            Frederick Tatham. Indeed, few of the 20 or so biographies of William
                            Blake published between 1893 and 2001 have enhanced our knowledge and
                            understanding of what the Blakes did and whom they associated with 
                            <pb id="p39-79" n="79"/>
							<figure n="FrederickWilliamFairholt.3FountainCourt.bqscan" rend="file" width="367" height="500">
								<head>1. Frederick William Fairholt, <hi rend="i">3 Fountain Court</hi> woodcut, illustration to
Frederick William Fairholt, “Tombs of the English Artists.</head>
								<figDesc>No. 7.—William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi> 4 (1858): 236. City of Westminster
Archives Centre.</figDesc>
							</figure>
							in Fountain Court during the significant intervals between
                            playing host to or visiting friends, fellow artists and patrons.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">10</ref> Even the second edition of G. E.
                            Bentley, Jr.’s <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (2004) provides
                            little new information concerning those who lived and worked alongside
                            William and Catherine Blake during their six year residence in the
                            court. According to Gilchrist, “for two years together”
                            Blake did not venture outside Fountain Court.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">11</ref> Surviving records for the period 1821-27
                            suggest that Blake spent months rather than years without leaving the
                            precincts of the court.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
type="note">12</ref> However,
                            the likelihood that Blake did spend such relatively long and
                            uninterrupted periods within its environs means that any new information
                            concerning William and Catherine Blake’s last residence and
                            neighborhood is of no small importance to Blake scholarship. <note id="n35">8.
Gilchrist 308.</note>
	<note id="n36">9. Gilchrist does refer to a “humble female
                                neighbour, [Catherine Blake’s] only other companion”
                                present at Blake’s death who “said afterwards:
                                ‘I have been at the death, not of a man, but of a blessed
                                angel’” (Gilchrist 353). The neighbor’s
                                description of Blake’s death resembles a line in Sydney
                                Cumberland’s letter to his father George Cumberland c.
                                November 1827 in which he reports that Catherine Blake told his
                                brother George that Blake “died like an angel” (BL
                                Add. MSS. 36512, ff. 52-53, n.d., cited Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                                    Records</hi> [hereafter referred to as <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2)]
                                475).</note>
	<note id="n37">10. See Bentley, “Appendix 1: Principal
                                Biographies of Blake,” <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi>
                                447-51.</note>
	<note id="n38">11. See Gilchrist 259-60.</note>
	<note id="n39">12. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 375-459.</note></p>
            <p>One fellow resident well placed to throw light on the Blakes’ life
                            and work during this period is Henry Banes, William and Catherine
                            Blake’s brother-in-law and landlord at 3 Fountain Court. However,
                            few biographers of William Blake have succeeded in tracing more than
                            Banes’ name. In a letter to the Quaker poet Bernard Barton of 3
                            April 1830, John Linnell, Blake’s friend and patron during the
                            1820s, describes William and Catherine Blake’s last shared
                            residence as “a private House Kept by M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Banes
                            whose wife was sister to M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Blake.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">13</ref> Linnell’s only other
                            recorded reference to Henry Banes is found in the final line of a
                            “Note by J[ohn]. L[innell]. sen[ior]. on strip of paper”
                            “1855?”, transcribed by Linnell’s son John Linnell,
                            Jr. Bentley describes this note as “clearly the heads of what
                            Linnell meant to tell Gilchrist of Blake’s life.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">14</ref> The line reads “[Blake]
                            died at his Brother in Laws first floor 3 F[ountain]
                                Court[.]”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">15</ref> Beyond this
                            “head” Linnell does not appear to have provided Gilchrist
                            with any further information concerning Blake’s last landlord.
                            Gilchrist’s allusion to Banes in a description of Blake’s
                            final residence as “a house kept by a brother-in-law named Baines
                                [sic]”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">16</ref> merely
                            reiterates Linnell’s two statements cited above. <note id="n40">13. Cited 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 526-27. Frederick Tatham in his
                                ms. “Life of Blake” (c. 1832) refers to Henry Banes as
                                Blake’s “Wifes brother” (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 680). As Ruthven
Todd observes: “presumably
                                this is an error for brother-<hi rend="i">in-law</hi>”
                                (Gilchrist 389).</note>
	<note id="n41">14. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 430fn.</note>
	<note id="n42">15. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 430fn.</note>
	<note id="n43">16. Gilchrist 282. Gilchrist almost certainly received
                                this information from John Linnell. Between 1803 and 1822 the Poor
                                Rate collectors responsible for Fountain Court consistently recorded
                                Henry Banes’ surname as “Baines” in their rate
                                books (see illus. 2). However, Banes’ marriage record (illus.
                                7), the only traced document to feature his signature, entries in
                                contemporary trade directories (illus. 4) and poll books (illus. 3),
                                as well as Banes’ own will (illus. 5) all suggest that
                                “Banes” is the correct spelling.</note></p>
            <p>Since Gilchrist, few further details concerning Henry Banes have been
                            traced. Almost a century after the publication of Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life</hi>, Paul Miner consulted the Poor Rate books for the
                            parish of St. Clement Danes and discovered that “‘Henry
                            Baines’ or ‘Banes’ . . . is listed [as ratepayer]
                            for the house [i.e., 3 Fountain Court] during the period of
                            Blake’s occupancy.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">17</ref>
                            In his recent biography of Blake, <hi rend="i">The Stranger from
                                Paradise</hi> (2001), Bentley offers a little more information
                            concerning Henry Banes. The biography features a reconstruction of the
                            Boucher family tree in which Sarah Boucher is first identified as the
                            sister of Catherine Blake who married Henry Banes. The location and date
                            of the marriage are given as St. Bride’s Church, Fleet Street, 10
                            November 1788.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">18</ref> Bentley also
                            records the location (but not the date) of Henry Banes’ baptism,
                            also in the parish of St. Bride.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n46" type="note">19</ref>
                            In addition, Henry Banes’ place of 
<pb id="p39-80" n="80"/>
                            burial is given as “St Andrews, Holborn” and the year of
                            his death as 1837.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">20</ref> In the second
                            edition of <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, Bentley gives the (correct)
                            date of Henry Banes and Sarah Boucher’s marriage as 16 December
                            1788, as well as details concerning the banns, the curate who performed
                            the marriage and the identity of one of the three witnesses.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">21</ref> Bentley also expands upon
                            Miner’s findings concerning the identity of the ratepayers for
                            the property: “The Rate Books confirm that the rate-payers were
                            Henry and Mary Baines (or Banes) from 1820 to 1829.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">22</ref> In an attempt to reconcile the
                            discrepancy between the first names given to Banes’ wife in the
                            marriage certificate of 1788 and the rate book entries almost forty
                            years later, Bentley suggests that “Perhaps Catherine’s
                            sister Sarah Boucher . . . was also called ‘Mary’ after
                            her mother, Mary Davis Boucher.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n44">17. Paul Miner, “William Blake’s London
                                Residences,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public
                                    Library</hi> 62.11 (November 1958): 544.</note>
	<note id="n45">18. Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> xx.</note>
	<note id="n46">19. Presumably Bentley assumed that St. Bride’s,
                                Fleet Street, the parish in which Banes married, was also the parish
                                of his baptism. However, <hi rend="i">FamilySearch</hi>, the records
                                of the <hi rend="i">International Genealogical Index</hi> available
                                online &lt;http://www.familysearch.org&gt;, contains no
                                record of a Henry Banes baptized at St. Bride’s, Fleet
                                Street. Bentley’s assertions concerning the date and location
                                of Banes’ burial are, as will be demonstrated below,
                                mistaken.</note>
	<note id="n47">20. See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> xx. Bentley
                                cites the second edition of <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> as the
                                source of this information (<hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> xix). In 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, Bentley states that “Henry
                                Bain (not Baines) was buried in St Andrew’s Church, Holborn,
                                in 1837, according to Boyd’s Burial Index in
                                Guildhall” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 50fn). As I demonstrate
                                below, Henry Bain (actually buried at Bunhill Fields) cannot have
                                been Blake’s landlord at Fountain Court. <hi rend="i">Boyd’s Burial
Index</hi> is an unpublished index of
                                London and Middlesex burials in parish register transcripts,
                                compiled by Percival Boyd (1866-1955). Boyd only indexed burial
                                registers which had been transcribed and were easily accessible.
                                With the help of the College of Arms, Boyd copied about a quarter of
                                a million burials between 1538 and 1852, including a large part of
                                the registers of Bunhill Fields nonconformist burial ground. See
                                Anthony Camp, “Our Greatest Indexer—Percival
                                Boyd,” <hi rend="i">Practical Family History</hi> no. 72
                                (December 2003): 22-24. In the introduction to his <hi rend="i">Burial
Index</hi> Boyd remarks, “Those who use this
                                index are warned that it must be treated as a ‘lucky
                                dip,’ if you find what you want, well &amp; good; if you
                                dont [sic], you have <hi rend="u">searched</hi> nothing.” I
                                am indebted to Valerie Hart, Reference Librarian, Guildhall, for
                                this information. The only other reference to Henry and Sarah Banes
                                in <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise</hi> occurs on 392, where
                                Bentley cites the passage from Linnell’s letter of 3 April
                                1830, discussed above.</note>
	<note id="n48">21. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 751fn. See also <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 49-50. However, the
mistake is replicated in the
                                Boucher-Butcher genealogy, <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) xxxiv.</note>
	<note id="n49">22. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 751. Bentley explains in a
                                footnote that the rate books for St. Clement Danes, Savoy Ward,
                                recorded: “Henry Ba[i]nes for 1820-22, 1826-28; Mary Banes
                                for 1823; and both for 1824 and 1825” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                [2] 751fn). Bentley goes on to state that in the Poor Rate books 3
                                Fountain Court “is specifically called a
                                ‘House’ to distinguish it from the warehouses in the
                                area . . .” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 751fn). This does not
                                appear to have been the case and would not have been necessary, as
                                the 16 residences in Fountain Court were separated from the
                                warehouses of Beaufort Wharfs by a flight of stairs. See Whitehead
                                illus. 1 and 8.</note>
	<note id="n50">23. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 751fn.</note></p>
            <p>A letter from Blake to John Linnell recently discovered by Michael
                            Phillips provides the sole recorded reference to Henry Banes by
                                Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">24</ref> The letter, postmarked
                            “25 · NO 1825”, begins:
<q>
                                M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Banes says his Kitchen is at our service to do
                                as we please. Still I should like to know from the Printer whether
                                our own Kitchen would not be equally or even more convenient as the
                                Press being already there would save a good deal of time &amp;
                                trouble in taking down &amp; putting up which is no slight job
                                [cited Phillips 140]. </q>
Phillips demonstrates that the new letter
                            refers to preparations for a specially organized printing session of the
                                <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> using
                            Blake’s rolling press at 3 Fountain Court. The printing session
                            was to be conducted by a fine art plate-printer, an employee of the
                            copperplate printer James Lahee, and overseen by Blake and perhaps
                            Linnell. It must have taken place in late November-early December 1825,
                            immediately after the engraving and final proofing of the plates and
                            immediately before the printing of the 315 sets of the <hi rend="i">Illustrations
of the Book of Job</hi> at Lahee’s premises at
                            No. 30 Castle Street East, Oxford Market. As Phillips observes: 
<q> It
                                was now the moment to confer with Lahee’s plate-printer to
                                supervise with him the printing of master impressions for each of
                                the 22 plates. The plate-printer would then be able to return to the
                                Castle Street works and left to get on with it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">25</ref></q>
This printing session, lasting no longer than a few
days, would
                            normally have been conducted at Lahee’s Castle Street works.
                            However, as Blake was evidently incapacitated by illness at this time
                            and therefore unable to travel so far, 3 Fountain Court was proposed as
                            an alternative location. Banes’ “Kitchen” in the
                            basement of 3 Fountain Court, as opposed to Blake’s printing
                            studio in the front room on the first floor, appears to have been
                            proposed by Linnell as the most suitable area of the house in which to
                            conduct the printing session. As Blake’s letter indicates, Banes
                            readily agreed to this proposal. However, due to the considerable
                            technical difficulties involved in dismantling Blake’s printing
                            press, moving it from the Blakes’ front room to Banes’
                            basement and reassembling it there (which Blake describes as “no
                            slight job”), the press almost certainly remained where it was.
                            Therefore, in the event, it seems that Banes’ basement was never
                            utilized as a temporary printing studio (see Phillips). Nevertheless, as
                            Bentley suggests, the fact that Banes was willing to give up his kitchen
                            to accommodate his brother-in-law’s printing shows that
                            “The relationship of Henry Banes and William Blake was clearly a
                            friendly one.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n51">24. For discussion of the letter, see Phillips, Whitehead
                                27-28, Bentley, “William Blake and His Circle” 5,
                                10-11, 32.</note>
	<note id="n52">25. Phillips 153.</note>
	<note id="n53">26. Bentley, “William Blake and His Circle”
                                5.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">New Information Concerning Henry Banes</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The entries for 3 Fountain Court, Strand, contained in the Poor Rate
                            books for the parish of St. Clement Danes, Savoy Ward, reveal that Henry
                            Banes was the sole recorded ratepayer for the property from May 1803,
                            when his name replaced that of “Mary Wood” (see illus.
                                2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">27</ref>
With the exception of the
                                <pb id="p39-81" n="81"/>
								<figure n="1803ratebook.COWAC.B224.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="327">
									<figTranscr>20<lb/>
									<lb/>
														3 . 3  4<lb/>
									20 John Morgan	13.4	. . 16.8 .	16:8	_16:8<lb/>
									<lb/>
														2 . 17 . 0<lb/>
									18 Elizth. Crump	12 _	. . 15.. . .	15:	_15_<lb/>
									<lb/>
									Henry Baines				3  19  2<lb/>
									25 Mary Wood	16.8	1.  . .  10.	1:0:10	1:_:10<lb/>
									<lb/>
														3  3  4<lb/>
									20 John Luntin	13:4	. .  16..  8.	16:8	_16:8<lb/>
									<lb/>
									Lohr					3  3  4<lb/>
									20 Jas. Carstairs	13:4	. .  16..  8.	16:8	_16:8<lb/>
									<lb/>
														3  3  4<lb/>
									20 Ann Hepworth	13:4	. . .  16..  8.	16:8	_16:8</figTranscr>
									<head>2. 1803 rate book, Savoy Ward, Parish of St.</head>
									<figDesc>Clement Danes entry for Henry Banes, 3 Fountain Court,
                                    Strand; COWAC, B224. City of Westminster Archives
                                    Centre.</figDesc>
								</figure>
								<figure n="PollbookentryHenryBanes.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="188">
									<figTranscr>WESTMINSTER POLL.     135<lb/>
									and St. Mary le Strand.<lb/>
									<lb/>
									Burdett<lb/>
									Kinnaird<lb/>
									Romilly<lb/>
									Maxwell<lb/>
									Cartwright<lb/>
									Hunt<lb/>
									<lb/>
									Names.             Residence.                 Occupation.<lb/>
									Brown, Thomas      11, Water street           Carpenter<lb/>
									Bartlett, John     10, Milford lane           Whitesmith<lb/>
									Baker, Edward      13, Wych street            Plumber<lb/>
									Burbidge, Robert   Plough, Beaufort’s build.  Victualler<lb/>
									Banes, Henry       3, Fountain court          Wine cooper<lb/>
									Baker, James       14, Newcastle court        Gentleman<lb/>
									Bingley, Wm.       13, New Inn                Gentleman<lb/>
									Bolton, Robert     59, Stanhope street        Staymaker</figTranscr>
									<head>3. Poll book entry for Henry Banes, 3 Fountain Court, wine
                                    cooper, <hi rend="i">The Poll Book for Electing Two
                                        Representatives in Parliament for the City and Liberty of
                                        Westminster, June 18, to July 4, 1818</hi> (London: J. J.
                                    Stockdale, 1818) 135.</head>
									<figDesc>Institute of Historical Research Library, University of
                                    London, with kind permission.</figDesc>
								</figure>
								<pb id="p39-82" n="82"/>
								period 1823-25,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">28</ref> Banes
remained sole ratepayer until early 1829, when
                            “Richard Best” replaced him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n56" type="note">29</ref> Banes gave the location of his residence as “3,
                            Fountain court” when his vote was recorded in the Westminster
                            Poll Books for 1818, 1819 and 1820 (see illus. 3.).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">30</ref> These three surviving poll books also reveal
                            Henry Banes’ trade. For the period 1818-20, he is recorded as a
                            “wine cooper” or “vintner.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">31</ref> The 1821 <hi rend="i">Book of Trades</hi>
                            defines a wine cooper as: 
<q> a person employed in drawing off,
                                bottling, and packing wine, spirits or malt liquor. In London, many
                                persons follow this business only; it is common for persons of the
                                first consequence to employ the wine-cooper to take charge of their
                                    wines.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">32</ref></q>
Banes’ professional connection with the wine trade suggests
                            that he may have occasionally provided wine for his brother- and
                                sister-in-law.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">33</ref> Gilchrist
                            records that Blake was an unorthodox and sporadic wine drinker who: 
							<figure n="HoldensTriennialDirectory.1805-6-7.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="83">
								<figTranscr>Bancroft Mrs. 20, Southampton-row<lb/>
								Banes Mr. Hen. 3, Fountain-ct. Strand<lb/>
								Banes Wm. Esq. 21, Newington-pl. Kenni[ngton]</figTranscr>
								<head>4. <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory,
                                    1805-6-7</hi> (London: W. Holden, 1805), entry for Henry
                                    Banes, 3 Fountain Court, Strand.</head>
								<figDesc>Cambridge University Library; by permission of the Syndics
                                of Cambridge University Library.</figDesc>
							</figure>
									<q> professed a liking to drink off good draughts from a tumbler, and
                                thought the wine glass system absurd: a very heretical opinion in
                                the eyes of your true wine drinkers. Frugal and abstemious on
                                principle, and for pecuniary reasons, he was sometimes rather
                                imprudent, and would take anything that came his way.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">34</ref></q>
	<note id="n54">27. Poor Rate book for St. Clement Danes Parish, Savoy
                                Ward, 1803, City of Westminster Archives Centre (hereafter referred
                                to as COWAC), microfilm B224. 1803 is of course the year William and
                                Catherine Blake returned from Felpham to London, and then to their
                                lodgings on the first or second floor of 17 South Molton Street.
                                Perhaps Blake visited Henry and Sarah Banes at their new residence
                                in 1803-04 while passing through the Strand. See Blake’s
                                letters to Hayley, 26 October 1803 (Erdman [hereafter cited as
                                “E” followed by page number] 738), 29 September 1804
                                (E 755).</note>
	<note id="n55">28. See note 22.</note>
	<note id="n56">29. For example, see St. Clement Danes, Savoy Ward, Poor
                                Rate books, COWAC, B224 (Poor Rate, 13 May 1803) and B126-27 (Poor
                                Rate, 1 January, 20 April 1829). As discussed above, during the
                                period 1823-25 “Mary Banes” is recorded as either co-
                                or sole ratepayer (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 751fn).</note>
	<note id="n57">30. Information kindly extrapolated and printed out from
                                the <hi rend="i">Westminster Historical Database: Voters, Social
                                    Structure and Electroal Behaviour</hi>, ed. Charles Harvey,
                                Edmund M. Green and Penelope J. Caulfield (Bristol: Bristol Academic
                                P, 1998) by Amanda Norman at COWAC. In the general election of July
                                1818, Henry Banes voted for the law reformer Sir Samuel Romilly and
                                Sir Francis Burdett, the campaigner for free speech and prison
                                reform, as Member of Parliament for Westminster. Romilly won the
                                Westminster seat. However, in November 1818, days after the death of
                                his wife, Romilly committed suicide. Consequently, another election
                                for the Westminster seat was held in February 1819. At this
                                election, Banes voted for the Whig candidate George Lamb. The death
                                of George III on 29 January 1820 brought parliament to an end and a
                                general election was held the following month. In this election,
                                Banes voted for George Lamb’s opponents Burdett and the
                                moderate radical (and friend of Byron) John Cam Hobhouse. Burdett
                                and Hobhouse won and continued to serve as Members of Parliament for
                                Westminster well into the 1830s.</note>
	<note id="n58">31. As Henry Banes was married in 1788, it is likely that
                                he was at least 50 when he entered his name, trade and address in
                                the Westminster Poll Book for 1818.</note>
	<note id="n59">32. Anon., <hi rend="i">The Book of Trades and
                                Library of Useful Arts</hi> (London: Printed for Sir Richard
                                Phillips, 1821) 117. I have found no entry for Henry Banes, wine
                                cooper or vintner, in any trade directory for the period. It is
                                therefore possible that he was employed at a nearby public house
                                such as the Coal Hole in Fountain Court or the Plough at the
                                intersection of Herbert’s Passage and Beaufort Buildings.
                                A more likely employer may have been Banes’ neighbor
                                Samuel Edwards at 8 Fountain Court, at the end of the court and
                                therefore nearest the warehouses of Beaufort Wharfs. Edwards was
                                a wine merchant operating from nearby 8 Beaufort Buildings
                                (1779-1814) and 5 Robert Street, Adelphi (1815-26) (see <hi rend="i">Kent’s
Directory</hi> [London: Henry Kent
                                Causton, 1779-1826]). In the rate books Edwards’ property
                                is distinct from the other 15 properties in the court in being
                                designated a “cellar” (see, for example, COWAC,
                                B236).</note>
	<note id="n60">33. It seems most likely that Banes, as landlord of the
                                property, occupied the ground and basement floors of the house (see
                                Dan Cruickshank and Neil Barton, <hi rend="i">Life in the Georgian
                                City</hi> [London: Viking, 1991] 53-62).</note>
	<note id="n61">34. Gilchrist 312-13. Gilchrist’s source may
                                have been Samuel Palmer, who told John Clark Strange a similar
                                account (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 727). John Linnell, a
                                regular visitor to Blake’s rooms at Fountain Court, may
                                also have taken an interest in Blake’s landlord’s
                                profession. Alfred T. Story, in his <hi rend="i">Life of
                                    Linnell</hi>, recounts how Linnell “was very careful
                                in choosing his wine. He would go down to the docks himself and
                                make his selection and when he had obtained the order for it, he
                                would fetch the cask himself and never lose sight of it until it
                                was safely deposited in his cellar” (Story 2:40-41). When
                                visiting 3 Fountain Court, Linnell may have joined Mr. Banes and
                                Mr. Blake in a glass (or indeed a tumbler) of wine.</note></p>
            <p>Two London directories of the period provide further evidence of Banes as
                            resident, rather than merely ratepayer, at 3 Fountain Court.
                            “Banes Mr. Hen. 3, Fountain-ct. Strand” is listed in the
                            residential section of <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial
                                Directory</hi> for 1805-06-07 and 1808-09-10 (see illus. 4).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">35</ref> Such appearances in the
                            residential rather than the commercial section of Holden’s
                            directory suggest that Banes, at least during the early years of his
                            residence at Fountain Court, may have been a man of some substance who
                            did not need to advertise his trade. <note id="n62">35. <hi rend="i">Holden’s
Triennial Directory, 1805-6-7</hi> (London: W.
                                Holden, 1805) n. pag., and <hi rend="i">1808-9-10</hi> (London: W.
                                Holden, 1808) n. pag. The 1808 edition appears to be a reprint of
                                the 1805 edition.</note></p>
            <p>William and Catherine Blake, arriving 18 years after their brother-in-law
                            became ratepayer for 3 Fountain Court, were almost certainly not Henry
                            and Sarah Banes’ first lodgers. Burial records for St. Clement
                            Danes, the local parish church of the inhabitants of Fountain Court,
                            Strand, reveal evidence which suggests that at least one other family
                            was lodging with Henry and Sarah Banes before the Blakes’
                            arrival. According to these records, a Martha Walker, recorded as
                            resident at 3 Fountain Court, was buried aged three weeks in the
                            churchyard of St. Clement Danes, Strand, on 8 January 1816.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">36</ref> Although I have discovered no
                            information concerning Martha’s parents, it seems likely that
                            they were lodgers at Henry and Sarah Banes’ house in early 1816.
                                <note id="n63">36. Burial register of St. Clement Danes, Strand,
                                COWAC, SCD 16, burial no. 1042.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p39-83" n="83"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Henry Banes’ Will</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>A transcription of Henry Banes’ will has recently come to light
                            (see illus. 5 and 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">37</ref> It is clear
                            from the contents of this document that Banes rewrote his will on 9
                            December 1826, over two years after the death in March 1824 of his wife,
                            Sarah Banes, who had been the “sole Executrix” of his
                            previous will.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">38</ref> Jane Cox observes
                            that, during the early nineteenth century, “wills were witnessed
                            by whoever happened to be in the house.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n66" type="note">39</ref> An artist named John Barrow witnessed Henry
                            Banes’ will. The will reads as follows: 
<q><hi rend="b">I, Henry Banes</hi> of
No. 3 ffountain Court Strand in
                                the parish of St. Clement Danes in the county of Middx being in good
                                health and sound mind and memory do make this my last Will and
                                Testament in manner following after my just debts &amp; funeral
                                expenses are paid I give &amp; bequeath to Catherine Blake half my
                                household goods consisting of Bedsteads Beds &amp; pillows Bolsters
                                &amp; sheets &amp; pillow Cases Tables Chairs &amp; crockery
                                &amp; £20 in lawful money of Great Britain <hi rend="i">I also
                                    beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">40</ref>—I also give &amp;
                                bequeath to Louiza Best the remaining part of my household goods as
                                aforesaid with the Clock &amp; my Watch &amp; silver plate.
                                (&amp; pictures <hi rend="u">what is worth her acceptance</hi>)<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">41</ref> and all the remainder of my
                                property in money &amp; outstanding debts of whatever nature or
                                description for her whole and sole use or disposal I also constitute
                                and appoint the said Louiza Best my sole Executrix of this my last
                                Will and Testament—H. Banes Dec<hi rend="s">r</hi> 9<hi rend="s">th</hi>
1826 witness John Barrow. 
                            </q>
Henry Banes died on 20 January 1829. Just over a fortnight later,
                            on 6 February 1829, Louisa Best and her son Thomas gave their
                            testimonies under oath as to the authenticity of the will at the
                            Prerogative Court of Canterbury at Doctor’s Commons, near St.
                            Paul’s. A week later, on 13 February, Thomas Best returned to
                            Doctor’s Commons, accompanied by the Bests’ lodger and
                            sole witness to Henry Banes’ will, John Barrow, who gave his
                            testimony. The will was proved the following day. 
<q><hi rend="b">Appeared
Personally </hi><hi rend="i">Louiza Best</hi> wife of Richard Best of ffountain
                                Court Strand in the County of Middlesex watch ffinisher <hi rend="i">Thomas
Best</hi> of the same place print colorer and <hi rend="i">John Barrow</hi> of the same place artist and being
                                sworn on the Holy Evangelists made oath as follows and first the
                                said Louiza Best for herself saith that she is the sole Executrix
                                named in the last Will and Testament hereunto annexed of Henry Banes
                                late of ffountain Court in the Strand aforesaid deceased who died in
                                the mourning of the twentieth day of January last past and she
                                further saith that in the evening of the same day deponent and her
                                son the said Thomas Best proceeded to search for the last Will and
                                Testament of the said deceased and the said will now hereunto
                                annexed was found by him the said Thomas Best folded up but not
                                contained in any Envelope in a Drawer (which was kept locked) in the
                                Kitchen of the deceased’s house and in which drawer the
                                deceased kept many private papers and both these deponents jointly
                                say that after the said Will was so found as aforesaid they perused
                                &amp; examined the same and then observed the former Will of the
                                said deceased written at the back of the said last will to be
                                crossed thro with a pen in manner as the same now appears with the
                                word “Will” written at the foot therof and the
                                deponent the said Louiza Best for herself lastly saith that Sarah
                                Banes the deceaseds wife and the sole Executrix and Legatee named in
                                the said former Will of the deceased died in the Month of March in
                                the year one thousand eight hundred and twenty four and the
                                deponents the said Thomas Best and John Barrow for themselves
                                jointly say that they knew and were well acquainted with the said
                                Henry Banes deceased for several years before and down to the time
                                of his death and also with his manner and character of handwriting
                                and subscription having often seen him write and subscribe his name
                                and having now carefully viewed and perused the said last Will and
                                Testament of the said deceased the same beginning thus “I
                                Henry Banes of No 3 ffountain Court Strand in the parish of Saint
                                Clement Danes in the county of Middlx” ending thus “I
                                also constitute the said Louiza Best my sole Executrix of this my
                                last Will &amp; Testament” and thus subscribed “H
                                Banes” and dated Dec<hi rend="s">r</hi> 9<hi rend="s">th</hi>
                                1820 [sic] and having also particularly noticed the interlineation
                                of the words “I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing
                                apparel” between the 10<hi rend="s">th</hi> and 11<hi rend="s">th</hi> lines
and the words “&amp; silver
                                plate” between the 13<hi rend="s">th</hi> and 14<hi rend="s">th</hi> lines
of the said will they the deponents lastly saith
                                that they do verify and in their consciences believe the whole body
                                [illeg.] and contents of the said will and the said writen[?]
                                interlineations respectively as well as the said subscription to the
                                said will to be all of the proper handwriting and subscription of
                                the said Henry Banes deceased—<hi rend="i">Louiza
                                    Best—Thomas Best.</hi> on the sixth day of ffebruary 1829
                                the said Louiza Best (wife of Richard Best) and Thomas Best were
                                duly sworn to the truth of this affidavit before me <hi rend="i">John
Danberry</hi> Surr. Prest.[?] <hi rend="i">John Box</hi>
                                not. pub. On the 13<hi rend="s">th</hi> day of ffebruary 1829 the
                                said Thomas Best was 
								<pb id="p39-84" n="84"/>
								<figure n="WillofHenryBanes.firstpage.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="397">
									<figTranscr>pursuant [to] the other Executors and two of the residuary legatees in trust having first
renounced the probate and execution of the said will and also the Letters of adm[inistrati]on (with the said
will annexed) of the goods of the said deceased. /-<lb/>
									<lb/>
									Henry<lb/>
									Banes<lb/>
									9<lb/>
									<lb/>
									I, Henry Banes of No. 3 ffountain Court Strand in the parish of St. Clement Danes in the county of
Middx being in good health and sound mind and memory do make this my last Will and Testament in manner
following after my just debts &amp; funeral expenses are paid I give &amp; bequeath to Catherine Blake half my
household goods consisting<lb/>
									<lb/>
									orgl 20<lb/>
									<lb/>
									of Bedsteads Beds &amp; pillows Bolsters &amp; sheets &amp; pillow Cases Tables Chairs &amp; crockery
&amp; £20 in lawful money of Great Britain I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel—I also
give &amp; bequeath to Louiza Best the remaining part of my household goods as aforesaid with the<lb/>
									<lb/>
									origl 00<lb/>
									<lb/>
									Clock &amp; my Watch &amp; silver plate. (&amp; pictures {what is worth her acceptance}) and all the
remainder of my property in money &amp; outstanding debts of whatever nature or description for her whole and
sole use or disposal I also constitute and appoint the said Louiza Best my sole Executrix of this my last Will
and Testament—H. Banes Decr 9th 1826 witness John Barrow.<lb/>
									<lb/>
									Appeared Personally Louiza Best wife of Richard Best of ffountain Court Strand in the County of
Middlesex watch ffinisher Thomas Best of the same place print colorer and John Barrow of the same place artist
and being sworn on the Holy Evangelists made oath as follows and first the said Louiza Best for herself saith
that she is the sole Executrix named in the last Will and Testament hereunto annexed of Henry Banes late of
ffountain Court in the Strand aforesaid deceased who died in the mourning of the twentieth day of January last
past and she further saith that in the evening of the same day deponent and her son the said Thomas Best
proceeded to search for the last Will and Testament of the said deceased and the said will now hereunto
annexed was found by him the said Thomas Best folded up but not contained in any Envelope in a Drawer (which
was kept locked) in the Kitchen of the deceased’s house and in which drawer the deceased kept many private
papers and both these deponents jointly say that after the said Will was so found as aforesaid they perused
&amp; examined the same and then observed the former Will of the said deceased written at the ...</figTranscr>
								</figure>
								<pb id="p39-85" n="85"/>
								<figure n="WillofHenryBanes.secondpage.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="410">
									<figTranscr>back of the said last will to be crossed thro with a pen in manner as the same now
appears with the word “Will” written at the foot therof and the deponent the said Louiza Best for herself
lastly saith that Sarah Banes the deceaseds wife and the sole Executrix and Legatee named in the said former
Will of the deceased died in the Month of March in the year one thousand eight hundred and twenty four and the
deponents the said Thomas Best and John Barrow for themselves jointly say that they knew and were well
acquainted with the said Henry Banes deceased for several years before and down to the time of his death and
also with his manner and character of handwriting and subscription having often seen him write and subscribe
his name and having now carefully viewed and perused the said last Will and Testament of the said deceased the
same beginning thus “I Henry Banes of No 3 ffountain Court Strand in the parish of Saint Clement Danes in
the county of Middlx” ending thus “I also constitute the said Louiza Best my sole Executrix of this my
last Will &amp; Testament” and thus subscribed “H Banes” and dated Decr 9th 1820 and having also
particularly noticed the interlineation of the words “I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing
apparel” between the 10th and 11th lines and the words “&amp; silver plate” between the 13th and 14th
lines of the said will they the deponents lastly saith that they do verify and in their consciences believe
the whole body screed and contents of the said will and the said writen interlineations respectively as well
as the said subscription to the said will to be all of the proper handwriting and subscription of the said
Henry Banes deceased—Louiza Best—Thomas Best. on the sixth day of ffebruary 1829 the said Louiza Best
(wife of Richard Best) and Thomas Best were duly sworn to the truth of this affidavit before me John Danberry
Surr. Prest. John Box not. pub. On the 13th day of ffebruary 1829 the said Thomas Best was resworn and the
said John Barrow duly sworn to the truth of this affidavit the several alterations appearing therein having
been first made Before me John Danberry Surr. Prest., John S. Glennie not. pub.<lb/>
									<lb/>
									PROVED at London 14th ffebruary 1829 before the worshipful John Danberry Doctor of Laws and Surrogate
by the oath of Louiza Best (wife of Richard Best) the sole Executrix to whom adm[inistrati]on was granted
having been first sworn duly to administer<lb/>
									<lb/>
									x</figTranscr>
									<head>5 and 6. First and second pages of the Prerogative Court
                                        of Canterbury copy of the will of Henry Banes, proved 14
                                        February 1829 (PRO PROB 11/1751 [Liverpool Quire 51-100,
                                        folio 79]).</head>
									<figDesc>National Archives, Kew.</figDesc>
								</figure>
								<pb id="p39-86" n="86"/>
resworn and the said John Barrow duly sworn
                                to the truth of this affidavit the several alterations appearing
                                therein having been first made Before me <hi rend="i">John
                                    Danberry</hi> Surr. Prest.[?], <hi rend="i">John S. Glennie</hi>
                                not. pub.<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="b">PROVED</hi> at London 14<hi rend="s">th</hi> ffebruary
                                1829 before the worshipful John Danberry Doctor of Laws and
                                Surrogate by the oath of Louiza Best (wife of Richard Best) the sole
                                Executrix to whom admon was granted having been first sworn duly to
                                administer </q>
	<note id="n64">37. The document, made by a clerk at the Prerogative
                                Court of Canterbury, Doctor’s Commons, for the court’s
                                registers (PRO PROB 11/1751, Records of the Prerogative Court of
                                Canterbury, Prerogative Court of Canterbury and related probate
                                jurisdictions: will registers, Liverpool Quire Numbers 51-100), was
                                consulted at the National Archives, Kew. The fact that Banes left a
                                will that was proved by the Prerogative Court of Canterbury suggests
                                that he was a comparatively prosperous individual at the time of his
                                death. However, according to the Probate Act book for [February]
                                1829, Banes’ estate was valued at just £100.
                                “Henry Banes—On the fourteenth day the will of Henry
                                Banes late of Fountain Court, Strand in the Parish of Saint Clement
                                Danes in the Parish of Middlesex deceased was proved by the Oath of
                                Louiza Best (wife of Richard Best) the sole Executrix to whom
                                Administration was granted having been first sworn duly to
                                administer. £100 Resworn at the Stamp Office 14<hi rend="s">th</hi> June 1830
Under £200” (PRO PROB 8/222 [14
                                February 1829]).</note>
	<note id="n65">38. It is possible that Henry Crabb Robinson’s
                                visit to 3 Fountain Court two days earlier, during which Robinson
                                informed Blake of the death of his friend, the sculptor John Flaxman
                                (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 452-53), may have prompted Banes to
                                rewrite his will.</note>
	<note id="n66">39. Cox 24.</note>
	<note id="n67">40.
                                Italics indicate that this sentence is an insertion by
                                Banes.</note>
	<note id="n68">41. I have underlined this section to indicate a
                                deletion (crossing out) by Banes.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Death of Sarah Banes, <hi rend="i">née
                                        Boucher</hi>, and the Identity of “Mary
                                    Banes”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>As observed above, Henry Banes married Catherine Blake’s sister,
                            Sarah Boucher, at St. Bride’s Church, Fleet Street, in late
                                1788.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">42</ref> The marriage register
                            for the parish of St. Bride confirms that Henry Banes, bachelor, married
                            Sarah Boucher, spinster, in this parish on 16 December 1788 (see illus.
                                7).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">43</ref>
With Sarah Banes,
                            née Boucher, conclusively identified as Banes’ wife, it is
                            puzzling that a “Mary Banes” rather than a “Sarah
                            Banes” is recorded as sole ratepayer, and therefore the
                            Blakes’ landlady, at 3 Fountain Court for 1823 and co-ratepayer
                            with Henry Banes for 1824-25.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">44</ref>
                            Bentley has suggested that “Mary” may have been a name
                            Sarah Banes was familiarly known by.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n72" type="note">45</ref> However, at the proving of Banes’ will, his legatee
                            and “sole Executrix” Louisa Best testified that Sarah
                            Banes died in March 1824, a year before “Mary Banes” is
                            last recorded as ratepayer for the residence. Such evidence initially
                            suggests that Sarah and “Mary Banes” are unlikely to have
                            been one and the same person. However, the appearance of “Mary
                            Banes” in the Poor Rate book in 1825, a year after Sarah
                            Banes’ death, may have been due to a failure by the Poor Rate
                            collector to amend his entry for 3 Fountain Court, Strand, in the ledger
                            for that year. After 1825, “Mary Banes” does not reappear
                            in the Poor Rate book entries for 3 Fountain Court. Nor is
                            “Mary” named as a beneficiary or executrix in Henry
                            Banes’ will, written in 1826. Therefore, “Mary” may
                            indeed have been the name Sarah Banes was familiarly known by.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">46</ref>
	<note id="n69">42. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 49.</note>
	<note id="n70">43. Guildhall Library Ms 6542/2, 1386. As Bentley
                                observes, the curate of St. Bride’s, John Pridden, officiated
                                at the ceremony (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 49). Pridden’s
                                father was a bookseller in Fleet Street. As well as performing his
                                clerical duties, Pridden was also an antiquary, amateur artist and
                                architect (see <hi rend="i">Alumni Cantabrigiensis</hi> Part 2,
                                1752-1900, vol. 5 [Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1953] 197). The banns
                                for the marriage of Henry and Sarah Banes were read on the three
                                preceding Sundays: 30 November, 7 December and 14 December 1788
                                (Guildhall Library Ms 6544/4). The witnesses were William Shepherd,
                                W. Finch and E. Boucher. As Bentley suggests, E. Boucher is almost
                                certainly Sarah’s sister, Elizabeth Boucher (1747-91) (see
                                Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 63fn, <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
                                50). The signatures of William Shepherd and W. Finch as witnesses at
                                other weddings at St. Bride’s suggest that they were parish
                                or church officials rather than friends or relatives of the couple.
                                See, for example, the marriage record for William Meredith and
                                Hannah Price, 1 December 1788 (Guildhall Library Ms 6542/2, 1383).
                                Indeed, in the record of the baptism of William Shepherd and his
                                wife Elizabeth’s son, Joseph Gardner Shepherd, St.
                                Bride’s, 20 December 1789, William’s occupation is
                                recorded as “parish clerk” (see St. Bride’s
                                baptismal register, Guildhall Library Ms 6541/2).</note>
	<note id="n71">44. COWAC, B246-48.</note>
	<note id="n72">45. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 751fn.</note>
	<note id="n73">46. Conversely, perhaps a relation of Henry Banes named
                                Mary Banes may have lived at 3 Fountain Court and have left or died
                                between her last appearance in the Poor Rate book on 6 October 1825
                                and Henry Banes’ composition of his new will on 9 December
                                1826.</note></p>
            <p>The discovery that Catherine Blake’s sister, Sarah Banes, was a
                            fellow resident with William and Catherine at 3 Fountain Court from 1821
                            until her death in March 1824 suggests that Sarah’s presence may
                            have been a consideration in the Blakes’ choice of residence on
                            leaving 17 South Molton Street. Perhaps Sarah, then in her mid-60s, was
                            ill and therefore welcomed her younger sister Catherine’s company
                            and care. Three years later, Sarah’s death may very well have
                            altered living arrangements at 3 Fountain Court. It is possible that
                            after March 1824, William and Catherine Blake and Henry Banes, widower,
                            spent more time in each other’s company. As the new letter
                            reveals, the Banes’ and the Blakes’ use of their
                            respective living spaces at 3 Fountain Court may have been considerably
                            more fluid than previously realized.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n74" type="note">47</ref> The wording of his will suggests that Banes had few, if
                            any, other living relatives. His significant bequest to Catherine, and
                            the wording of his legacy to Blake at the time of the writing of his
                            will in late 1826, “I beg Mr Blakes acceptance . . .,”
                            suggest a cordial relationship between Henry Banes and his brother-and
                            sister-in-law. It is also likely that, from the spring of 1824 onwards,
                            Banes, as a widower, required less personal living space and could
                            therefore have invited other households to lodge at his house.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">48</ref>
	<note id="n74">47. See Whitehead 27-28; Phillips 138-42.</note>
	<note id="n75">48. See Samuel Calvert’s anecdote concerning his
                                father, the “Ancient” Edward Calvert, which suggests
                                that another lodger occupied the floor above William and Catherine
                                Blake at 3 Fountain Court (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 438-39).
                                Calvert’s anecdote refers to an incident that must almost
                                certainly have occurred after Sarah Banes’ death, as his
                                father is unlikely to have met Blake before late 1824 (see Lister
                                10). Bentley suggests that the incident may have occurred during
                                “the winter of [i.e., between February and March]
                                1826” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 438).</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Death of Henry Banes and His Bequest to Catherine
                                    Blake</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise</hi>, Bentley claims that
                            Henry Banes died in 1837.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">49</ref> However,
                            Banes’ will now makes clear that he died almost a decade earlier,
                            on the morning of Tuesday 20 January 1829.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n77" type="note">50</ref> Both Catherine and William Blake, 
							<pb id="p39-87" n="87"/>
							<figure n="Parishregister.Dec1788.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="153">
								<figTranscr>No 1386 } Henry Banes of this Parish Batchelor and<lb/>
								Sarah Boucher Spinster were <lb/>
								Married in this Church by Banns<lb/>
								this Sixteenth Day of December in the Year One Thousand Seven Hundred<lb/>
								and Eighty Eight By me John Pridden, B:A:<lb/>
								Curate<lb/>
								This Marriage was solemnized between Us {<lb/>
								Henry Banes<lb/>
								Sarah Boucher<lb/>
								In the Presence of {<lb/>
								Wm. Shepherd<lb/>
								W. Finch E. Boucher</figTranscr>
								<head>7. St. Bride’s, Fleet Street, parish register for
                                    December 1788, showing marriage of Sarah Boucher and Henry Banes
                                    (Guildhall Library Ms 6542/2).</head>
								<figDesc>By permission of Guildhall Library, Corporation of
                                    London.</figDesc>
							</figure> prominent among Banes’ few surviving relatives, and
                            lodgers at his house for a period of approximately seven years, are
                            recorded as legatees in his will. The discovery of a new contemporary
                            reference to William Blake is a relatively rare event and clearly of
                            interest to Blake scholars. However, the legacy Henry Banes intended to
                            leave to William Blake appears comparatively slight. In Banes’
                            will, other names take precedence. Of these, Catherine Blake has
                            received some, if minor, attention in biographical studies of her
                            husband. Richard and Louisa Best and their family and the artist John
                            Barrow are relatively unknown.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n78" type="note">51</ref> Due
                            to their apparent proximity to Blake in his final years, these names
                            merit further consideration. <note id="n76">49. Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> xx. See also <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) xxxiv,
                                50fn, 884.</note>
	<note id="n77">50. Although we now know the date and location of
                                Banes’ death, both the date and location of his burial remain
                                elusive. There is no record of the burial of a Henry Banes during
                                late January to early February 1829 in the burial registers of
                                Bunhill Fields or the parishes of St. Bride, Fleet Street (where
                                Banes was married), St. Andrew, Holborn (the burial place claimed by
                                Bentley), St. Clement Danes (the parish church for Fountain Court,
                                Strand), St. George, Hanover Square, St. Anne, St.
                                Martin-in-the-Fields, St. Mary-le-Strand, St. James, Piccadilly, St.
                                Paul, Covent Garden or St. Margaret, Westminster.</note>
	<note id="n78">51. Richard Best is referred to by Bentley as the
                                ratepayer who replaced Henry Banes in 1829 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
                                751fn). The identity of John or J. Barrow has been briefly discussed
                                by Robert Essick and David Worrall (see Essick 199; Worrall 169,
                                180n1).</note></p>
            <p>In his will, Henry Banes wrote: “I give &amp; bequeath to
                            Catherine Blake half my household goods consisting of Bedsteads Beds
                            &amp; pillows Bolsters &amp; sheets &amp; pillow cases Tables Chairs
                            &amp; crockery &amp; £20 in lawful money of Great
                            Britain.” During the four years of her widowhood, Catherine
                            enjoyed the material support of several of her late husband’s
                            friends. She also derived some income from the sale of items from her
                            remaining stock of her husband’s works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n79" type="note">52</ref> Nevertheless, Banes’ bequest to
                            Catherine is materially significant. In the spring of 1829, such a
                            legacy would have been welcome to a widow whose financial situation at
                            that time would almost certainly have been modest, perhaps even
                                precarious.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">53</ref> However, did
                            Catherine Blake receive Banes’ bequest? No record of
                            Catherine’s inheriting a portion of her brother-in-law’s
                            estate has been traced. This is not altogether surprising. Most
                            surviving records relating to Catherine Blake’s financial
                            circumstances in the period from her husband’s death in August
                            1827 to her own death in October 1831 derive from the account books of
                            John Linnell. After Blake’s death, Linnell both bought, and
                            helped Catherine to sell, a number of those of her husband’s
                            works still in her possession.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n81" type="note">54</ref>
	<note id="n79">52. In addition, Blake’s painting and printing
                                materials were almost certainly still in Catherine’s
                                possession. Catherine may also have retained Blake’s domestic
                                copperplate rolling press. According to Linnell’s journal,
                                the press arrived at his residence at 6 Cirencester Place on 30
                                August 1827. Catherine followed on 11 September (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
468, 471). It is unclear whether the press
                                accompanied Catherine when she moved to Frederick Tatham’s
                                residence in the late spring of 1828. Much of her furniture appears
                                to have been sold at this time (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 791).
                                This may have been because Tatham did not have as much space
                                available for Catherine and her possessions as Linnell had had at
                                his residence. If Catherine’s press was also sold by Linnell
                                in 1828, Tatham, in his printing of posthumous copies of
                                Blake’s illuminated books such as <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                                copies H, I and J (c. 1832), may have used another press such as,
                                perhaps, that of fellow “Ancient” Edward Calvert. See
                                Lister 24.</note>
	<note id="n80">53. In terms of his bequest, Henry Banes appears to have
                                been comparatively generous towards his sister-in-law. However, one
                                wonders why Catherine left 3 Fountain Court, Banes’ house and
                                her home for approximately six and a half years, on 11 September
                                1827, only a month after her husband’s decease (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
471). Perhaps Banes could not afford to
                                have Catherine occupy the best floor of the house rent-free.</note>
	<note id="n81">54. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 474-88, 504,
                                790-93.</note></p>
            <p>In September 1827, a month after Blake’s death, Linnell also
                            provided a home and employment (as housekeeper) for Catherine.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">55</ref> This arrangement came to an end in
                            the late spring of 1828, when Linnell sold his town residence and studio
                            at 6 Cirencester Place, Fitzroy Square, and moved with his 
<pb id="p39-88" n="88"/>
family to 26 Porchester Terrace, Bayswater.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83"
type="note">56</ref> Before vacating Cirencester Place,
                            Linnell appears to have found Catherine a new home (and employment) with
                            Frederick Tatham, the son of the Blakes’ old friend, the
                            architect Charles Heathcote Tatham, and a member of the circle of young
                            artists known as the “Ancients.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n84" type="note">57</ref> With Catherine no longer his fellow resident,
                            employee or immediate responsibility, Linnell appears to have played a
                            less active role in her life.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85"
type="note">58</ref> He
                            therefore may not have been aware of Henry Banes’ legacy to
                            Catherine and is certainly unlikely to have recorded details of it in
                            his account books or his journal. Any papers of Frederick
                            Tatham’s relating to the period of Catherine Blake’s
                            residence with him, which may have referred to Banes’ legacy,
                            have not been traced. It seems highly probable then that Catherine did
                            receive her brother-in-law’s bequest. <note id="n82">55. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>
(2) 754.</note>
	<note id="n83">56. Story 1:248; David Linnell 116.</note>
	<note id="n84">57. David Linnell 116. David Linnell does not cite a
                                source for this information. However, in response to my query, he
                                replied “The meeting between F. Tatham and Linnell is
                                recorded in Linnell’s journal. 29th March 1828 . . .
                                ‘Mr. F. Tatham dined at Hampstead’. Mrs Blake’s
                                move is not mentioned . . . But as Linnell was getting rid of
                                Cirencester Place and needed Mrs Blake to move out it is reasonable
                                to assume that this was discussed over dinner—especially as
                                she moved to live with Tatham” (email, 15 March 2005). David
                                Linnell has also suggested that if Catherine had moved into
                                independent lodgings on leaving Cirencester Place, Linnell would
                                almost certainly have helped with her rent (email 17 March 2005). No
                                such payments are recorded in Linnell’s account book entries
                                for the period 1828-30 (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 791-93).</note>
	<note id="n85">58. In his journal, Linnell records a visit to Catherine
                                Blake on 19 September 1828, almost six months after she had left
                                Cirencester Place (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 488). His next
                                recorded visit took place on 27 January 1829, when Catherine told
                                him “that M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Blake told her he thought I
                                    sh<hi rend="s">d</hi> pay 3 gs. a piece for the Plates of
                                Dante—” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 493). On 3 March
                                1830, Linnell accompanied Haviland Burke to Catherine’s
                                residence in order to purchase “two Drawings 8 gs. two Prints
                                of Job &amp; Ezekiel 2 gs &amp; the color<hi rend="s">d</hi> Copy
                                of the Songs of Innocence &amp; Experience making 20 gs” for
                                John Jebb, Bishop of Limerick (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 509).
                                According to Bentley, Linnell also called on Catherine on 3 August
                                and 3 September 1830 (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 534). However, on
                                checking the relevant volume of Linnell’s journal (collection
                                of the Manuscripts Department of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge,
                                MS 8-2000), Nicholas Robinson, Curator of Manuscripts at the
                                Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, could find no entry referring to
                                Linnell’s visiting Catherine on 3 August 1830 (email 5 April
                                2005). By early 1831, as Bentley observes, “Catherine had
                                become suspicious and mistrustful of Linnell’s
                                motives” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 537). There is no record
                                of John Linnell and Catherine Blake’s meeting again before
                                her death on 18 October 1831. However, Linnell records payments to
                                Catherine in April, 6 July (via Tatham), 16 September 1828 (via
                                Tatham); 26 January (for drawings by Blake and Fuseli), 15 May 1829
                                (via Tatham for “Homer’s Illiad &amp; Oddessey Trans
                                by Chapman”); 25 August 1831 (for copies of Blake’s
                                    <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> and <hi rend="i">Descriptive
                                    Catalogue</hi>) (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
                                    791-93).</note>
	<note id="n86">59.
                                Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 444.</note>
	<note id="n87">60. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 495-96, 498.
                                Tatham’s letter is transcribed by Thomas Hartley Cromek, son
                                of Blake’s former employer Robert Cromek, in his ms.
                                “Recollections of Conversations with Mr John Pye”
                                (1865) 56-58 (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 871n37). Dennis Read has
                                identified Tatham’s correspondent as an acquaintance of
                                William and Catherine Blake, the engraver John Pye (see Dennis Read,
                                “‘An eminent but neglected genius’: An Early
                                Frederick Tatham Letter about William Blake,” <hi rend="i">English Language
Notes</hi> 19 [September 1981]: 30). If Pye
                                was Tatham’s correspondent, it is difficult to reconcile
                                Pye’s sending a letter for Catherine to Fountain Court in
                                early 1829 when he had called on her at Cirencester Place a year
                                earlier (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 482). Is it possible that
                                Catherine returned to live at Fountain Court for a brief period
                                between the spring of 1828 and the spring of 1829? Conversely, Pye,
                                aware of Catherine’s leaving Cirencester Place, but unsure of
                                her address in early 1829, and unaware of Banes’ recent
                                death, may have sent his letter to Catherine’s previous
                                residence, 3 Fountain Court, assuming her brother-in-law would
                                ensure she received it.</note></p>
            <p>In <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise</hi>, Bentley asserts that
                            Catherine remained at Frederick Tatham’s residence and did not
                            move to her own lodgings until “early 1831.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">59</ref> However, a transcription of a
                            letter from Tatham to an unnamed correspondent, and two letters from
                            Catherine herself to Sir George O’Brien Wyndham, third Earl of
                            Egremont, suggest that Catherine had moved to lodgings two years
                                earlier.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87"
type="note">60</ref> In his letter, dated
                            11 April 1829, Tatham writes: 
<q> But to answer your enquiry, which
                                would have been done before, but that in consequence of M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>
Blake’s removal from Fountain Court to
                                    N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 17. Upper Charlotte S<hi rend="u">t</hi>
                                Fitzroy Square, a wrong address was put on the letter at Fountain
                                Court and it was only received by her the day before yesterday.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">61</ref>
	<note id="n88">61. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 495. Tatham, possibly
                                    for the sake of brevity, omits any reference to Catherine
                                    Blake’s having formerly resided either with John Linnell
                                    or himself. However, see note 60.</note></q>
In the light of this
evidence, Bentley has revised his theory as to
                            where Catherine resided after leaving Linnell’s town house. In
                                <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> he suggests that:
<q> Catherine
                                Blake moved in the spring of 1828 from Linnell’s house in
                                Cirencester Place to lodge with a baker at 17 Upper Charlotte
                                Street, south-east of Fitzroy Square.<lb/>
 Shortly thereafter she
                                moved in with the Tathams in Lisson Grove to look after them. . . .
                                According to Tatham, “She then returned to the lodging in
                                which she had lived previously”. She had returned to Upper
                                Charlotte Street by the spring of 1829, for on 11 April Frederick
                                Tatham wrote “of M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Blake’s removal
                                . . . to N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 17. Upper Charlotte S<hi
rend="s">t</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">62</ref>
	<note id="n89">62. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 754-55. However, Bentley
                                    also suggests that Catherine moved from the Tathams’ to
                                    private lodgings in “early 1830” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
755).</note></q>
As I hope to demonstrate in a paper currently in preparation,
                            several details in this passage require further revision. However, Henry
                            Banes’ will does appear to confirm Bentley’s suggestion
                            that Catherine Blake moved from Tatham’s residence to her own
                            lodgings before 11 April 1829. Catherine Blake was almost certainly
                            living at Frederick Tatham’s residence in late January-early
                            February 1829, when she learned of the death of her brother-in-law Henry
                            Banes. As Louisa Best was granted probate as executrix just over three
                            weeks after Banes’ death, Catherine could have received her
                            portion of the estate as early as late February or early March 1829.
                            Although it is likely that Catherine knew of Banes’ bequest to
                            her before his death, I contend that either news of, or her acceptance
                            of, her legacy 
<pb id="p39-89" n="89"/>
in the spring of 1829 influenced
                            Catherine’s decision to move from Tatham’s residence to
                            her own lodgings. Bentley suggests that Catherine was “kept . . .
                            out of want for the rest of her life” in July 1829 when Lord
                            Egremont generously paid her £84 for her late husband’s
                            watercolor <hi rend="i">The Characters in Spenser’s
                                “Faerie Queene.”</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
type="note">63</ref> However, if approximately three months earlier Catherine
                            had received her legacy of £20 together with “Bedsteads Beds
                            &amp; pillows Bolsters &amp; sheets &amp; pillow cases Tables Chairs
                            &amp; crockery,” then Banes’ bequest, rather than
                            Egremont’s purchase, initially may have put Catherine out of need
                            by facilitating her move to her own lodgings. 
                            <note id="n90">63. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 499.</note></p>
            <p>In his “Life of Blake,” Tatham wrote: 
			<q> [Catherine Blake]
                                resided for some time with the Author of this whose domestic
                                arrangements were entirely undertaken by her; until such changes
                                took place that rendered it impossible for her strength to continue
                                in this voluntary office of sincere affection &amp; regard.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">64</ref>
	<note id="n91">64. Frederick Tatham, “Life of Blake”
                                    ms. (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 690).</note></q>
It is unclear what
Tatham is referring to when he writes of
                            “such changes.” Bentley appears to interpret this passage
                            as meaning that Catherine’s move to her own lodgings was due to
                                infirmity.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92"
type="note">65</ref> However, both the
                            new evidence of Henry Banes’ legacy to Catherine and the
                            likelihood of her removal from Tatham’s residence at a
                            considerably earlier date than has previously been recognized suggest
                            that other factors may have influenced Catherine’s decision to
                            move out of Tatham’s chambers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n93" type="note">66</ref> Indeed, Banes’ legacy coupled with Lord
                            Egremont’s purchase may have been the reason for
                            Catherine’s withdrawal of her application to the Artists’
                            General Benevolent Institution around January 1830 and for her return of
                            Princess Sophia’s gift of £100, its being something
                            “she could dispense with.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n94" type="note">67</ref>
	<note id="n92">65. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 755; Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 444.</note>
	<note id="n93">66. Perhaps, as had been the case a year earlier when
                                Catherine left Linnell’s residence, the decision to move was
                                not entirely of her own making. Despite Tatham’s close
                                friendship with Catherine between 1827 and 1831, the relationship
                                appears to have shown signs of occasional strain. Joseph Hogarth
                                records a heated disagreement between Catherine and Tatham which
                                appears to have occurred at some point after Catherine’s
                                departure from Tatham’s residence during spring 1829 (see 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 493-94). However, this does not appear to
                                have been a factor in Catherine’s move. I suspect that by
                                “such changes” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 690) Tatham
                                may be referring to the domestic changes which are likely to have
                                accompanied his marriage, which must have taken place some time
                                before Catherine’s death in the autumn of 1831. Gilchrist,
                                who interviewed and corresponded with Tatham, states that Catherine
                                Blake “died in Mrs Tatham’s arms” (Gilchrist
                                357).</note>
	<note id="n94">67. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 502; A. C. Swinburne, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (1868),
cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                (2) 462-63.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">A New Reference to William Blake</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Following the passage in his will outlining his legacy to Catherine
                            Blake, Henry Banes inserted: “I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of
                            my wearing apparel.” In the early nineteenth century, the bequest
                            of clothes in wills was a common practice. As Jane Cox has observed,
                            “Clothes were much more expensive and prized. . . . Coats . . .
                            and even shirts and underwear might be left to relatives and
                                friends.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95"
type="note">68</ref> Nevertheless,
                            when writing his will in December 1826, it must have been particularly
                            evident to Henry Banes that both Blake as the wearer and Catherine as
                            the likely repairer of her husband’s coats, trousers, shirts, and
                            other costly “wearing apparel” could make effective use of
                            such a bequest.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96"
type="note">69</ref>
	<note id="n95">68. Cox 28.</note>
	<note id="n96">69. Similarly, Sarah Banes’ garments may have been
                                given to Catherine after Sarah’s death in March
                            1824.</note></p>
            <p>A year earlier, on his first visit to the Blakes’ two rooms in
                            Fountain Court, Henry Crabb Robinson recorded of William Blake that:
                            “Nothing could exceed the squalid air both of the apartment
                            &amp; his dress.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97"
type="note">70</ref> Robinson
                            also intimates that both Blake and his wife’s dress were of an
                            “offensive character,” despite the couple’s
                            “air of natural gentility.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n98" type="note">71</ref> Around 1832, Tatham posed the question “Had poor
                            half starved Blake ever a suit of clothes beyond the tatters on his
                                Back?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99"
type="note">72</ref> However,
                            Gilchrist, perhaps citing the recollections of Linnell, George Richmond
                            or Samuel Palmer, observed that: 
<q> In [Blake’s] dress there was
                                similar triumph of the man over his poverty to that which struck one
                                in his rooms. Indoors he was careful, for economy’s sake, but
                                not slovenly: his clothes were threadbare, and his grey trousers had
                                worn black and shiny in front, like a mechanic’s. Out of
                                doors he was more particular, so that his dress did not, in the
                                streets of London, challenge attention either way. He wore black
                                knee breeches and buckles black worsted stockings, shoes which tied,
                                and a broad-brimmed hat. It was something like an old-fashioned
                                tradesman’s dress. But the general impression he made on you
                                was that of a gentleman, in a way of his own.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100" type="note">73</ref></q>
	<pb id="p39-90" n="90"/>
Henry Banes, having married in the 1780s, is
                            likely to have been of a similar age, and evidently not of a dissimilar
                            build, to Blake. Although a tradesman, Banes was wealthy enough to pay
                            the rates, appear in the residential section of <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial
Directory</hi> and leave a provable will.
                            As a consequence, one can imagine that Banes, in bequeathing his wearing
                            apparel to Blake, had intended to leave his brother-in-law a number of
                            presentable garments to replace those Gilchrist described as “the
                            common, dirty dress, poverty, and perhaps age, had rendered
                                habitual.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n101"
type="note">74</ref>
	<note id="n97">70. H. C. Robinson, <hi rend="i">Diary</hi> 17 December
                                1825, cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 426. In the revised diary entry
                                written a quarter of a century later for his
                                “Reminiscences” (1852), Robinson states that
                                Blake’s “linen was clean” (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 698).</note>
	<note id="n98">71. Robinson, <hi rend="i">Diary</hi> 17 December 1825,
                                cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 426. This statement seems reminiscent
                                of George Cumberland’s note on visiting Blake at 17 South
                                Molton Street on 3 June 1813: “Called Blake—still poor
                                still Dirty” (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 316). On 21
                                April 1815, George Cumberland, Jr., reported to his father
                                “found [Blake] &amp; his wife drinking Tea, durtyer than
                                ever . . .” (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 320).</note>
	<note id="n99">72. Cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 676-77.</note>
	<note id="n100">73. Gilchrist 313. This description may partially
                                derive from a passage in a letter from Samuel Palmer to
                                Gilchrist, cited in Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi>,
                                which describes a visit Palmer and Blake made to the Royal
                                Academy c. 1825. “Blake in his plain black suit and <hi rend="i">rather</hi>
broad-brimmed, but not quakerish hat .
                                . .” (Gilchrist 283). In a letter to Dante Gabriel
                                Rossetti, dated 6 December 1860, Thomas Woolner records an
                                anecdote a woman who met Blake as a child had told him. In that
                                anecdote, which Bentley suggests occurred in late 1821, Blake is
                                described as “a poor old man, dressed in such shabby
                                clothes . . .” (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 382).
                                However, this had not always been the case. According to
                                Frederick Tatham, 30 years earlier the Blakes had owned
                                “clothes to the [valued] amount of [£]40 . .
                                .” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 676).</note>
	<note id="n101">74. Gilchrist 316.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Louisa Best: William and Catherine Blake’s
                                    Niece?</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Henry Banes left the remainder, and clearly the majority, of his estate
                            to his appointed “sole Executrix” Louisa Best, wife of
                            Richard Best, watch escapement maker.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n102" type="note">75</ref> Banes left Louisa:
<q> the remaining part of my household
                                goods as aforesaid with the clock &amp; my watch &amp; silver
                                plate (&amp; pictures <hi rend="u">what is worth her
                                    acceptance</hi>) and all the remainder of my property in money
                                &amp; outstanding debts of whatever nature or description for her
                                whole and sole use or disposal. </q>
The precise identity of Louisa
                            Best, Henry Banes’ “sole Executrix,” is unclear. An
                            examination of Banes’ will provides little explicit evidence that
                            at the time of writing his will in December 1826 he expected to be
                            survived by any children. It is possible that Louisa Best was Henry
                            Banes’ niece. Conversely, she may have been an acquaintance or
                            lodger whom Banes had grown fond of and wished to acknowledge in his
                            will. But, as we have seen, Banes did not merely leave Louisa Best a
                            bequest; he made her, rather than his sister-in-law Catherine Blake,
                            sole executrix. A possible explanation for Banes’ choice of
                            Louisa as executrix could be that he deemed the position and its
                            responsibilities too onerous for Catherine (who would have been 64 in
                            late 1826). However, this does not satisfactorily explain why Louisa
                            inherited the majority of Banes’ estate. <note id="n102">75.
                                Richard and Louisa Best had five children: Charles Best, born 1
                                April 1805, baptized Old Church, St. Pancras (St. Pancras parish
                                church, Euston Road) 1 May 1805; Charlotte Louisa Best, born 16
                                August 1807, baptized Old Church, St. Pancras 14 August 1808;
                                Elizabeth Best, born 19 December 1809, baptized 18 July 1817, Old
                                Church, St. Pancras; Thomas Best, born 4 December 1813, baptized 18
                                July 1817, Old Church, St. Pancras; Richard John Best, born 20 March
                                1815, baptized 18 July 1817, Old Church, St. Pancras (see 
<hi rend="i">IGI</hi>; London Metropolitan Archives X030/004;
                                X100/34). No reference to the marriage of a Louisa and Richard Best
                                prior to 1805 has been traced. In the PCC copy of Banes’
                                will, Louisa and her son Thomas Best are recorded as resident at 3
                                Fountain Court “on the sixth day of ffebruary 1829”
                                (PRO PROB 11/1751), just over a fortnight after the death of Henry
                                Banes. This evidence suggests that the Bests were resident at
                                Banes’ house before his death. In editions of <hi rend="i">Robson’s London
Directory</hi> 1833-38, Richard Best is
                                described as a “watch escapement maker” conducting
                                business from 3 Fountain Court, Strand (see, for example, 
<hi rend="i">Robson’s London Directory</hi> [London: William
                                Robson, 1835] 348). It is curious that Richard Best is not listed as
                                watch escapement maker in directories before this date. However, if
                                Banes also left his house to Louisa Best, such a bequest could have
                                enabled Louisa’s husband to launch his own business. In 1839
                                Louisa Best replaced Richard Best as ratepayer for 3 Fountain Court
                                (COWAC, B272). Richard Best is not listed in the 1841 census entry
                                for the property. Therefore it seems likely that he died around
                                1839. However, the firm of “Richard Best, Watchmaker,”
                                appears to have remained at 3 Fountain Court, along with Louisa Best
                                and several of her children, until 1844 (see <hi rend="i">Post
                                    Office London Directory</hi> [London: Kelly &amp; Co, 1844]
                                233). By 1845 William Walker replaced Louisa Best as ratepayer (see
                                COWAC, B306).</note></p>
            <p>A more straightforward explanation may lie in the possibility that Louisa
                            Best was a more intimate relation of Henry Banes than Catherine Blake. I
                            suggest that whereas Catherine was Banes’ sister-in-law, Louisa
                            could have been his daughter.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n103" type="note">76</ref> At
                            my request, Philippa Hoskin of the Borthwick Institute of Historical
                            Research, University of York, the respository of the records of the
                            Prerogative Court of York, examined a transcript of Henry Banes’
                            will. Hoskin observed that the absence of the word
                            “daughter” in the will in no way precludes the possibility
                            that Louisa Best was the daughter of Henry Banes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104" type="note">77</ref> She added that the context of the will suggests
                            that its writer was a widower leaving the majority of his estate to his
                            daughter. Although Louisa Best is not explicitly named as the daughter
                            of Henry Banes, neither are the other legatees (William and Catherine
                            Blake) named as Banes’ brother- and sister-in-law.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105" type="note">78</ref> Indeed, the fact that in her
                            testimony at the proving of Banes’ will Louisa was not obliged to
                            testify to the intimacy or longevity of her relationship with Henry
                            Banes, as her son Thomas and her lodger John Barrow were, again suggests
                            that Louisa was Banes’ daughter. In addition, <pb id="p39-91" n="91"/>
in his
will Banes makes no bequest to Louisa’s
                            husband Richard Best. Instead he stipulates that his legacy to Louisa is
                            “for her whole and sole use or disposal.” Banes does not
                            use this phrase in his bequest to Catherine Blake. It seems likely that
                            by including this phrase, Banes intended to ensure that his only
                            daughter maintained control over her legacy despite her marriage to
                            Richard Best. Banes’ choice of Louisa as “sole
                            Executrix” would have ensured that, as a married woman, her
                            entitlement to and share of the estate was protected. It is also
                            interesting to note that in the record of the proving of the will cited
                            above, Louisa is the authority for the fairly precise (to the month)
                            dating of the death of Sarah Banes almost five years earlier. This might
                            be deemed a detail that a daughter of Henry and Sarah Banes could be
                            relied upon to remember. <note id="n103">76. John Linnell describes 3
                                Fountain Court as “a private House Kept by M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Banes”
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 526-27). As
                                suggested above, Banes’ legacy to Louisa Best may therefore
                                have included the leasehold to 3 Fountain Court. This is suggested
                                by the fact that Louisa remained resident at this address after
                                Banes’ death and after the death of her husband c. 1839. In
                                the 1841 census entry for 3 Fountain Court, Louisa Best describes
                                herself as “ind[ependent]” (PRO HO 107/731/3 15). If
                                Banes was the owner or leaseholder of 3 Fountain Court, the
                                property, as real estate, would have passed automatically to the
                                next of kin without explicit reference in Banes’ will.</note>
	<note id="n104">77. Banes’ will is comparatively brief and makes
                                no provision for the eventuality of a legatee’s predeceasing
                                him, as occurred with William Blake.</note>
	<note id="n105">78. In reply to my query, Stephen Freeth, Keeper of
                                Manuscripts at the Guildhall Library, London, wrote: “I have
                                searched the baptism register of the parish of St Bride, Fleet
                                Street (Guildhall Library Ms. 6541/1) but unfortunately no entry for
                                Louisa or Louiza Banes was found. The years 1789 to 1792 were
                                searched. I also checked the International Genealogical Index (both
                                the microfiche version and the web site) but no reference to Louisa
                                Banes of the parish of St Brides, Fleet Street was found”
                                (email, 2 October 2003). The <hi rend="i">International Genealogical
                                    Index</hi> contains no other baptismal record for a Louisa (or
                                Louiza) Banes, daughter of Henry and Sarah Banes. However, nor does
                                the <hi rend="i">IGI</hi> include a record of the marriage of a
                                Richard and Louisa Best. If Henry and Sarah Banes and Richard and
                                Louisa Best were living in London, records of the baptism of Louisa
                                Banes and the marriage of Richard and Louisa Best may survive in the
                                registers of the 10-20% of London parishes not currently covered by
                                the <hi rend="i">IGI.</hi> See Keri Davies, “William
                                Blake’s Mother: A New Identification,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 33.2 (fall 1999):
                                38n14.</note></p>
            <p>According to the marriage register for St. Bride’s Church, Fleet
                            Street, Henry and Sarah Banes were married on 16 December 1788. The 1841
                            census return for 3 Fountain Court, Strand, records that Louisa Best was
                            50 years old in the summer of that year.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n106" type="note">79</ref> It is therefore likely that she was born between 1790 and
                            1791. That Louisa Best was born a year or two after the marriage of
                            Henry and Sarah Banes also supports the theory that Louisa was Henry and
                            Sarah’s daughter. Sarah Banes’ relatively mature age at
                            the time of her marriage (approximately 31) in 1788 suggests that Louisa
                            may have been Henry and Sarah Banes’ only surviving child.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107" type="note">80</ref> In <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Records</hi>, Bentley observes that: “Blake and his wife had
                            twenty brothers and sisters, but none of them is known to have had
                            children . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108"
type="note">81</ref> If
                            Louisa Best is the daughter of Henry Banes, then she is the only niece
                            of William and Catherine Blake traced to date.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n109" type="note">82</ref>
	<note id="n106">79. PRO HO 107/731/3 14-17 [6 June 1841].</note>
	<note id="n107">80. See Boucher-Butcher family tree, Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> xx.</note>
	<note id="n108">81. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) xxxvi.</note>
	<note id="n109">
                                82. None of Blake’s surviving writings
                                    contains a reference to a “Louisa” or
                                    “Louisa Best.” However, in the table of contents
                                    of the volume of William Wordsworth’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (London:
Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, &amp;
                                    Brown, 1815), which Henry Crabb Robinson loaned to Blake in late
                                    1825, “I Met Louisa” [“To Louisa”]
                                    is one of the 32 titles marked “X” (E 665). But,
                                    as David Erdman observes, Robinson “may have put the
                                    X’s in the list of contents before he lent it to
                                    Blake” (E 887).
                                <p>If Louisa Best’s age was recorded slightly inaccurately in
                                    the 1841 census return for 3 Fountain Court, as that of her son
                                    Thomas Best appears to have been, then she may have been born as
                                    early as the summer of 1789. <hi rend="i">IGI</hi> records give
                                    the date of Thomas Best’s birth as 4 December 1813.
                                    However, the 1841 census return for 3 Fountain Court records
                                    Best’s age as 25 on 6 June 1841, suggesting that he was
                                    born in 1815 or 1816. Could the infant Louisa Best, possibly the
                                    daughter of Catherine’s sister, Sarah, and the only
                                    traced offspring of William and Catherine Blake’s
                                    siblings, have been born at the time of the composition, relief
                                    etching, printing and coloring of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> (1789)? See images of mothers and
                                    babies on both plates of <hi rend="i">The Ecchoing Green, A
                                        Cradle Song, Spring, Infant Joy</hi>; also the texts of the
                                    three latter poems. See also <hi rend="i">Infant Sorrow</hi> and
                                    the image of mother and child on the plate of <hi rend="i">The
                                        Fly</hi> in <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                Experience.</hi></p></note></p>
            <p>We cannot be sure when Louisa Best and her family moved to 3 Fountain
                            Court, Strand. However, it seems significant that during the proving of
                            Banes’ will on 6 February 1829, barely a fortnight after Henry
                            Banes’ death, Louisa, her son Thomas and her husband were
                            described as resident at this address. This detail, coupled with Louisa
                            and her son Thomas’ testimony that they searched for and found
                            Banes’ will on the evening of the day of his death (20 January
                            1829), suggests that the Best family may have been living at 3 Fountain
                            Court before Banes’ death. If Henry Banes had been ill for a
                            period of time before his death, Louisa, in all likelihood Banes’
                            only daughter, may have moved to Banes’ house along with her
                            husband and children in order to care for her father.</p>
            <p>If, as has been suggested above, Louisa Best was William and Catherine
                            Blake’s niece, her sons Thomas and Richard were two of the
                            Blakes’ grandnephews. In his testimony recorded in the probate
                            copy of Henry Banes’ will, Louisa Best’s 15-year-old son
                            Thomas describes himself as a “print colorer.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n110" type="note">83</ref> Twelve years later, in the 1841
                            census return for 3 Fountain Court, Thomas and Richard both gave their
                            occupation as “artist.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n111"
type="note">84</ref> Their parents Richard and Louisa Best were the recorded
                            rate-payers for 3 Fountain Court between 1829 and 1845. The fact that
                            Louisa Best was appointed sole executrix in Henry Banes’ will in
                            December 1826 suggests that Louisa and her family, if not immediate
                            relatives, were almost certainly fellow lodgers or regular visitors of
                            Henry Banes at Fountain Court during the early-mid-1820s. William Blake,
                            John Barrow and the artists who visited them at 3 Fountain Court between
                            1821 and 1838 may have inspired Thomas and Richard Best to become first
                            print colorers and later artists.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n112" type="note">85</ref>
                            Thomas and Richard, <pb id="p39-92" n="92"/>
who in August 1827 were
                            aged 13 and 12 respectively, whether they were the grandsons of Henry
                            Banes or merely the sons of Banes’ acquaintance Louisa Best,
                            could very well have visited the Blakes’ two rooms on the first
                            floor of 3 Fountain Court. On the panelled walls of the Blakes’
                            front room, which served as both reception room and printing studio, the
                            Best brothers would have seen a “good number” of temperas
                            and watercolors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113"
type="note">86</ref> They may also
                            have observed William and Catherine Blake as they drew and painted or
                            while they printed, colored and finished copies of the illuminated
                            books. <note id="n110">83. PRO PROB 11/1751.</note>
	<note id="n111">84. PRO HO 107/731/3 15. I have traced no record of
                                Richard Best Jr. as a print colorer. However, it seems likely that
                                as Thomas and Richard both described themselves as artists in 1841,
                                they were both (apprentice?) print colorers c. 1829. They may have
                                been employed as print colorers at Rudolph Ackermann’s
                                Repository nearby at 96 Strand. However, another source of training
                                and employment is discussed below. Between 1834 and 1839 a Thomas
                                Best, painter of domestic scenes, residing at Beaufort Buildings,
                                exhibited one painting at the Royal Academy and three at the Society
                                of British Artists (Graves, <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Artists</hi>
                                24). The eastern side of Beaufort Buildings backed onto the western
                                side of Fountain Court, Strand, which included the residence of the
                                Best family. The street was often used in trade and other
                                directories to distinguish Fountain Court, Strand, from the three
                                other Fountain Courts in early nineteenth-century London.
                                Best’s sole exhibit at the Royal Academy, “Miss
                                Cust” (exhibited 1834), may have been a portrait of
                                Charlotte, Mary or Emily, daughters of Christopher Cust, the
                                Bests’ (and formerly the Blakes’ and the
                                Banes’) neighbor at 7 Fountain Court, Strand (see Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal
Academy</hi> 1:187; <hi rend="i">IGI</hi>; St.
                                Clement Danes [Savoy Ward] rate books for 1822-29, e.g., COWAC,
                                B126-27). Another painting by Thomas Best, <hi rend="i">“Trentham,” a Bay
Race Horse Galloping up on
                                    Newmarket Heath</hi>, was auctioned at Christie’s,
                                London, on 21 November 1986 (information kindly supplied by the Witt
                                Library, Somerset House).</note>
	<note id="n112">85. Gilchrist observes that after Blake’s death,
                                “Aided by Mr. Tatham [Catherine Blake] also filled in, within
                                Blake’s lines, the colour of the engraved books”
                                (Gilchrist 357). See also references to Catherine’s coloring
                                of copies of Blake’s works in J. T. Smith, <hi rend="i">Nollekens and His
Times</hi> (1828) (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                [2] 609) and Frederick Tatham, ms. “Life of Blake” (c.
                                1832) (cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 690). Could the Best brothers
                                also have assisted Catherine and have been third and fourth hands in
                                the coloring and finishing of any copies of Blake’s
                                illuminated books still in Catherine’s possession c.
                                1827-31?</note>
	<note id="n113">86. See George Richmond’s description of the
                                interior of 3 Fountain Court, cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2)
                                753.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">John Barrow, Publisher of “Mrs Q”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Henry Banes’ will also provides new information concerning the
                            identity of the publisher of one of Blake’s last commercial
                            engravings. John Barrow’s signature as witness of Henry
                            Banes’ will in December 1826, and his testimony at the proving of
                            Banes’ will in February 1829, reveal that the wine cooper and the
                            artist, and later lodger at 3 Fountain Court, had been “well
                            acquainted . . . for several years.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n114" type="note">87</ref> It is now clear that in early-mid-1820, over
                            six years before witnessing Henry Banes’ will, John Barrow had
                            employed Banes’ brother-in-law William Blake to engrave the late
                            François Marie Huet Villiers’ portrait of George
                            IV’s former mistress, Mrs. Harriet Quentin (illus. 8). <note id="n114">87. PRO
PROB 11/1751. J. Barrow exhibited 21 works at the
                                Royal Academy between 1797 and 1836 (see Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal
                                    Academy</hi> 1:129-30). According to Graves, Barrow also
                                exhibited four enamels at the [Royal] Society of British
                                Artists’ gallery in Sussex Street (Graves, <hi rend="i">Dictionary of
Artists</hi> 16). However, Jane Johnson lists
                                eight works exhibited by Barrow at Sussex Street between 1824 and
                                1837 (Johnson 27). I wish to thank Catherine Taylor at Cambridge
                                University Library for this information. The Society of British
                                Artists was formed in 1824 and Barrow appears to have been a
                                founding member. Blake as well as Barrow would have been acquainted
                                with two of the society’s first presidents, Thomas Heaphy and
                                James Holmes (see E 773; <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 345). The Royal
                                Academy exhibition catalogues for 1831, 1835 and 1836 and the
                                Society of British Artists’ exhibition catalogues for 1832
                                and 1836 record Barrow as resident at Fountain Court (Graves, 
<hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi> 1:130, Johnson 27). David Worrall
                                has observed that “Remarkably, Barrow’s final
                                residence—between 1831 and 1836—was Fountain Court,
                                Strand, Blake’s last address” (see Worrall 180n1).
                                Even more remarkably, in <hi rend="i">Robson’s Directory</hi>
                                of 1832 (London: William Robson, 1832) n. pag., John Barrow is
                                recorded as an “artist” resident at 3 Fountain Court,
                                Strand. Barrow’s address in the Royal Academy exhibition
                                catalogue for 1829 is recorded as 26 Denton Street, St. Pancras
                                (Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi> 1:130). St. Pancras is the
                                parish in which Louisa Best and her family appear to have been
                                resident before moving to Fountain Court (see note 75). However, at
                                the proving of Banes’ will at Doctor’s Commons on 13
                                February 1829, Barrow testified that he was resident at
                                “ffountain Court Strand” (PRO PROB 11/1751). As stated
                                above, Barrow was sole recorded witness at the writing of Henry
                                Banes’ will. If, as Jane Cox suggests, “wills were
                                witnessed by whoever happened to be in the house” (Cox 24),
                                Banes’ choice of John Barrow as witness may suggest that
                                Barrow was a lodger at 3 Fountain Court as early as December 1826.
                                In that case it is possible that he may have moved to 3 Fountain
                                Court soon after Sarah Banes’ death in March 1824. However,
                                Banes’ house may not have provided adequate space for two
                                separate artists’ studios. Evidence suggests that Banes had
                                another lodger on the second floor of 3 Fountain Court (see 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 439). However, as I will demonstrate in a
                                forthcoming paper, this was unlikely to have been John Barrow.
                                Therefore, it seems likely that Barrow occupied the first floor of 3
                                Fountain Court only after Catherine’s removal in
                                mid-September 1827 (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 471). Even if
                                Barrow was not resident at Henry Banes’ house in December
                                1826 when witnessing Banes’ will, the fact that he was sole
                                witness to Banes’ will clearly suggests a friendship between
                                the two men. This relationship between Banes and Barrow, miniature
                                painter, Royal Academy exhibitor and member of the Society of
                                British Artists, suggests that Banes may have taken an active
                                interest in both Barrow and Blake’s works. It may be
                                significant that in his will, Henry Banes bequeathed Louisa Best
                                “pictures” (PRO PROB 11/1751).</note></p>
            <p>According to the engraving’s imprint, the publisher of
                            Blake’s engraving, entitled “Mrs Q,” was “I.
                            Barrow.” In <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William
                                Blake</hi> (1983), Robert Essick suggests that I. Barrow “was
                            either the J. Barrow who exhibited enamels and miniature portraits in
                            London from 1797 to 1836, or John Barrow, who exhibited portraits at the
                            Society of Artists from 1812 to 1816.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n115" type="note">88</ref> As David Worrall has observed, Essick’s
                            first identification is confirmed by the fact that between 1820 and 1825
                            J. Barrow, portrait painter, and J. Barrow, publisher, resided at the
                            same address.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n116"
type="note">89</ref> The
                            publisher’s address featured in the imprint of the second state
                            of “Mrs Q” and its companion print “Windsor
                            Castle” (1821) is “Weston Place, St. Pancras.”
                            According to the catalogue for the Royal Academy exhibition of 1822, J.
                            Barrow, miniature painter, is recorded as residing at 1 Weston Place,
                            St. Pancras.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n117"
type="note">90</ref> Nine years later, in
                            the Royal Academy exhibition catalogue of 1831, “J.
                            Barrow” is recorded as resident at “[3] Fountain Court,
                                Strand.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n118"
type="note">91</ref> As observed
                            earlier, at the proving of Banes’ will Barrow testified that he
                            had been “well acquainted with . . . Henry Banes . . . for
                            several years before and down to the time of his death.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n119" type="note">92</ref> It 
							<pb id="p39-93" n="93"/>
							<figure n="ESXLII.1.2D.SP" rend="file" width="718" height="1000">
								<figTranscr>Drawn by Huet Villiers.<lb/>
								Engraved by W. Blake.<lb/>
								Mrs Q<lb/>
								London Published 1st. June, 1820 by I. Barrow, Weston Place, St. Pancras.</figTranscr>
								<head>8. William Blake, “Mrs Q,” after François
                                    Huet Villiers.</head>
								<figDesc>Stipple etching/engraving with mezzotint. Second state
                                    (1820), impression 2C. British Museum Department of Prints and
                                    Drawings, BM cat. no. ps 293666. © Copyright, the
                                    Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
							</figure>
							<pb id="p39-94" n="94"/>
seems quite possible that during a period in
                            which little work was available for the majority of artists and
                            engravers, Henry Banes persuaded his friend John Barrow to commission
                            his brother-in-law, William Blake, to engrave “Mrs Q.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n120" type="note">93</ref>
	<note id="n115">88. Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 199. There
                                appears to be little evidence for G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s claim
                                that the publisher of “Mrs Q” was the
                                “notoriously radical print-seller” Isaac Barrow
                                (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 356).</note>
	<note id="n116">89. Worrall 180n1.</note>
	<note id="n117">90. Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi> 1:130.
                                Another “John Barrow, painter” is recorded as resident
                                at Weston Place, St. Pancras, in Royal Academy exhibition catalogues
                                from 1812 to 1816 and 1823 (Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi>
                                1:130). In 1815 John Barrow exhibited a painting of “Mr J.
                                Barrow, Senr.” at the Royal Academy exhibition for that year
                                (Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi> 1:130). Therefore, it seems
                                likely that “John Barrow” was the son or nephew (and
                                quite possibly the apprentice) of “J[ohn], Barrow.” It
                                is of course possible that “John Barrow” was the
                                publisher of “Mrs Q.” However, the established link
                                between John Barrow Sr. and Blake through Henry Banes, the use of
                                the initial “I.” for “J.” in the two
                                prints and “J.” in the Royal Academy exhibition
                                catalogue entries, and Banes, Barrow and Blake’s similarity
                                in age, suggest that John Barrow Sr. employed Blake.</note>
	<note id="n118">91. Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi> 1:130. Just
                                over two years after witnessing Henry Banes’ will, when
                                providing testimony at the proving of the will, Barrow was recorded
                                (alongside Richard Best, Louisa Best and their son Thomas) as a
                                fellow resident at 3 Fountain Court. According to his burial record,
                                Barrow, who resided at 3 Fountain Court until his death, was 81
                                years old when he was buried in St. Clement Danes’ churchyard
                                on 25 March 1838 (see COWAC, SCD 19, burial no. 1069). Therefore,
                                having been born around 1757, Barrow was an exact contemporary of
                                Blake.</note>
	<note id="n119">92. PRO PROB 11/1751.</note>
	<note id="n120">93. In his ms. “Autobiography” Linnell
                                describes Blake when he met him in June 1818 as “having
                                scarcely enough employment to live by at the prices he could obtain
                                everything in Art was at a low ebb then” (Linnell,
                                “Autobiography,” f. 57, cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
                                341). In 1822, William Collins RA wrote to the Royal Academy
                                Council, “recommending to the charitable consideration of the
                                President &amp; Council Mr William Blake an able Designer &amp;
                                Engraver laboring under great distress—” (Minutes of
                                the Royal Academy Council, 28 June 1822, cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                                [2] 384-85).</note></p>
            <p>It is intriguing to think of John Barrow, a miniature painter, first
                            employing Blake to engrave a commercial fancy print and then publishing
                            it. However, evidence suggests that Barrow was not just a miniaturist.
                            In May 1828 the 28-year-old Theodore Lane, widely regarded as a painter
                            and engraver of great promise, died when in a freak accident he fell
                            through a skylight at the horse repository in Gray’s Inn Road.
                            Three years after Lane’s death his associate, the sporting
                            journalist and author Pierce Egan, recalled that at the age of 14, Lane:
<q> was apprenticed to a Mr Barrow at Battle Bridge<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n121" type="note">94</ref> a colourer of expensive
                                prints, and who was considered a man of ability in that line. It was
                                during his apprenticeship that Lane first displayed a taste for
                                drawing. . . . His juvenile sketches on first being shown to Mr
                                Barrow, he (Mr B.) was very much pleased with them, and in the
                                kindest manner pointed out to Theodore those defects which first
                                arise from youth and inexperience. LANE gratefully profited by his
                                instructions.<lb/>
 Mr Barrow saw, or thought he saw, in those early
                                sketches that sort of talent indicative of future greatness; and he
                                therefore encouraged him to proceed with the most unremitting
                                industry until he overcame all the difficulties which every artist
                                has to surmount on his first entrance into life. Mr Barrow always
                                entertained an opinion that one day or another the proud initials of
                                R.A. might be added to his name.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n122" type="note">95</ref>
	<note id="n121">94. Battle Bridge is the former name of
                                    King’s Cross, an area which borders the parish of St.
                                    Pancras. 17 Spann’s Buildings, St. Pancras, is recorded
                                    as the address of J. Barrow, miniature painter, in the Royal
                                    Academy exhibition catalogues between 1808 and 1815 (Graves, 
<hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi> 1:129-30).</note>
	<note id="n122">95. Pierce Egan, “Biographical Sketch of the
                                    Life of the Late Mr Theodore Lane,” <hi rend="i">The Show
                                        Folks</hi> (London: M. Arnold, 1831) 34. Egan had provided
                                    the letterpress to accompany Lane’s 36 etchings entitled
                                        <hi rend="i">The Life of an Actor</hi> (1825) and Lane
                                    illustrated with etchings and woodcuts Egan’s <hi rend="i">Anecdotes of
the Turf, the Chase, the Ring and the
                                        Stage</hi> (1827). Lane appears to have been a neighbor of
                                    Barrow’s at Spann’s Buildings (see Egan, <hi rend="i">Show Folks</hi>
35). As observed above, Barrow
                                    appears to have lived at 17 Spann’s Buildings from 1808
                                    until sometime between 1815 and 1820 (see Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal
Academy</hi> 1:129-30). Lane is recorded as resident
                                    at this address in 1816 (see Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal
                                        Academy</hi> 2:381). Lane also painted a portrait of
                                    “Mr Barrow” exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1826
                                    (see Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi> 2:381). Another
                                    apprentice of Barrow appears to have been the miniaturist E.
                                    Preston, who between 1824 and 1843 exhibited 24 portraits at the
                                    Royal Academy, Society of British Artists and the New
                                    Watercolour Society. Preston also exhibited his portrait of
                                    “Mr Barrow” at the Royal Academy exhibition in
                                    1826, the year Lane exhibited his portrait of the same subject
                                    (see Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal Academy</hi> 3:202).</note></q>
It is
significant that Egan describes John Barrow as “a
                            colourer of expensive prints,” the profession to which
                            Barrow’s later fellow residents at 3 Fountain Court, Strand,
                            Thomas and Richard Best were apprenticed. John Barrow, print colorer and
                            miniature painter, may have been the J. Barrow who in 1782 traded as
                            printseller, publisher, and very possibly the engraver of satirical
                            prints at 11 St. Bride’s Passage, Fleet Street.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n123" type="note">96</ref> This address faced St. Bride’s Church,
                            where Henry and Sarah Banes would marry six years later. By November
                            1782, J. Barrow had moved a few blocks west to Dorset Street, Salisbury
                            Court, Fleet Street. It was from this address that he published a
                            satirical engraving, possibly his own, <hi rend="i">The American
                                Rattlesnake Presenting Monsieur His Ally a Dish of Frogs.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n124" type="note">97</ref> Detlef Dörrbecker refers
                            to this print as an example of serpent symbolism utilized in the early
                            1780s by “various British caricaturists to deride the rebellious
                            and ‘serpent form’d’ colonists” in America.
                            As Dörrbecker suggests, such a print may have been one of the
                            sources for Blake’s design for the title page of <hi rend="i">EUROPE a
PROPHECY</hi> (1794).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n125" type="note">98</ref> John Barrow
may also have been the “J.
                            Barrow” who designed, engraved and published a mezzotint portrait
                            on what appears to be a business flier or trade card for “John
                            Barrow, Jeweller” in 1813, suggesting markedly different
                            political sympathies (illus. 9). The imprint continues: “Drawn
                            &amp; Engraved by J. Barrow. / Whose Country is the World and / Whose
                            Religion is to do good. / John Barrow Jeweller &amp;c. / Published 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> Nov<hi rend="s">r</hi> 1813.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n126"
type="note">99</ref> The second and third lines of the
                            imprint are a slight misquotation from “WAYS AND MEANS of
                            Improving the Condition of Europe, Interspersed with Miscellaneous
                            Observations,” chapter 5 of part two of Thomas Paine’s <hi rend="i">Rights of
Man</hi>, published in 1792. “Independence
                            is my happiness, and I view things as they are without regard to place
                            or person; my country is the world, and my religion is to do
                                good.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n127"
type="note">100</ref> No
                            publisher’s address is 
                <pb id="p39-95" n="95"/>
                <figure n="JohnBarrow.BM.1872-11-9-423.bqscan" rend="file" width="257" height="450">
                    <figTranscr>Drawn &amp; Engraved by J. Barrow.<lb/>
                    Whose Country is the World and<lb/>
                    Whose Religion is to do good.<lb/>
                    JOHN BARROW JEWELLER &amp;c.<lb/>
                    Published 1st. Novr. 1813.</figTranscr>
                    <head>9. J[ohn].</head>
                    <figDesc>Barrow, “John Barrow” [possibly Thomas
                                    Paine], 1813, mezzotint/etching, British Museum Department of
                                    Prints and Drawings, BM cat. no. 1872-11-9-423. ©
                                    Copyright, the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
                </figure> included in the imprint. However, it is significant that the
                            print has the initial appearance of a non-satirical portrait, while at
                            the same time containing the tangible if oblique radical dimension of a
                            (mis)quotation from Paine. As discussed below, “Mrs Q” and
                            “Windsor Castle,” while similarly at first glance
                            non-satirical commercial fancy prints, in their subject matter, titling
                            and dates of publication suggest a publisher with radical
                                sympathies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n128"
type="note">101</ref>
	<note id="n123">96. See George 5:846n3 and cat. nos. 6010 and 6014. For
                                other prints published by J. Barrow, see George, cat. 5, 5985, 5986,
                                6004, 6023, 6029, 6167, 6168, 6175, 6208, 6229, 6251, 6261.</note>
	<note id="n124">97. George, cat. 5, 6039.</note>
	<note id="n125">98. See Detlef Dörrbecker, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Continental Prophecies</hi>,
Blake’s
                                Illuminated Books, vol. 4 (London: Tate Gallery Publications/William
                                Blake Trust, 1995) 171. The engraving is reproduced in the same
                                volume (251, supplementary illustration 3).</note>
	<note id="n126">99. British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings,
                                cat. no. 1872-11-9-423. I have been unable to trace a John Barrow,
                                jeweller, trading in London in 1813. However, entries for a Henry
                                Barrow, wholesale jeweller of 12 Thavies Inn, Holborn, appear in 
<hi rend="i">Underhill’s Biennial Directory for the Years
                                    1816 and 1817</hi> (London: Underhill, 1816) n. pag., and 
<hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory, 1817</hi> 25. According to the
                                Royal Academy exhibition catalogues, John Barrow lived in Leather
                                Lane, Holborn, between 1797 and 1801 (see Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal
                                    Academy</hi> 1:129). There is also a will for a John Barrow,
                                jeweller, of Tottenham Court Road, PRO PROB 11/989 (proved 26 July
                                1773).</note>
	<note id="n127">100. Thomas Paine, <hi rend="i">Rights of Man</hi>
                                (Harmondsworth, Middlesex: Penguin, 1969) 228. For the significance
                                of the second part of Paine’s <hi rend="i">Rights of Man</hi>
                                for Blake two decades earlier, see Michael Phillips, <hi rend="i">William
Blake: The Creation of the Songs From Manuscript to
                                    Illuminated Printing</hi> (London: British Library, 2000) 47.
                                This quotation and the fact that the engraving bears some
                                resemblance to Paine suggest that the second and third lines of the
                                imprint may apply to Paine and not to “J[ohn].
                                Barrow.” Compare Thomas Sharp’s engraving of Paine,
                                after George Romney (1793) (National Portrait Gallergy, D15322). See
                                also James Godby’s engraving of Paine, after an unknown
                                artist (1805) (NPG, D5445).</note>
	<note id="n128">101. A number of satirical prints on the subject of
                                “the Queen’s affair” (discussed below) have
                                been attributed to Barrow’s apprentice Theodore Lane. See the
                                series of etchings <hi rend="i">The Queen’s Alphabet: Horrida
                                    Bella! Pains and Penalties Versus Truth and Justice</hi>
                                (London: G. Humphrey, 1820) (George, cat. 10, 13948).</note></p>
            <p>Essick has described “Mrs Q” as “a conventional
                            fancy print of very little importance to Blake’s graphic
                                oeuvre.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n129"
type="note">102</ref> However, as
                            Worrall has suggested, the subject and date of publication of this print
                            indicate the likelihood that “Mrs Q” acquired radical
                            connotations absent in the majority of contemporary color-printed
                            portraits of Regency ladies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n130"
type="note">103</ref>
                            Bentley has observed that by the time of her return to England and her
                            trial in mid-1820, Queen Caroline had become for a significant portion
                            of the middle and lower orders of British society “a symbol of
                            suffering from arbitrary power, the darling of English democrats and
                                republicans.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n131"
type="note">104</ref> George
                            IV, already far from popular, was, in the light of his own numerous
                            infidelities, widely condemned for his hypocrisy in bringing charges of
                            adultery against his wife. The King’s more notorious extramarital
                            affairs were publicly recalled in satirical prints. For example, Harriet
                            Quentin, the wife of Colonel George Quentin of the 10<hi rend="s">th</hi> Hussars,
and former mistress of George IV, was represented
                            as the infamous “Mrs Q” in numerous prints published
                            between June 1820 and February 1821.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n132" type="note">105</ref> The date of Barrow’s publication of William
                            Blake’s engraving of “Mrs Q,” 1 June 1820, four
                            days before Caroline’s landing at Dover after six years in
                            negotiated exile and five days before she reached London, suggests that
                            Blake had completed the plate in or before May 1820. As Worrall
                            concedes, the probable date of the plate’s execution and
                            publication is slightly early for an explicit identification of
                            “Mrs Q” as an expression of popular support for Caroline
                            on her return to England.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n133"
type="note">106</ref>
                            However, a 
                <pb id="p39-96" n="96"/>
                <figure n="GeorgesMaile.WindsorCastle.BM.bqscan" rend="file" width="325" height="450">
                    <figTranscr>Drawn by I.B.<lb/>
                        Engraved by G. Maile.<lb/>
                        London Published<lb/>
                        by I. Barrow, Weston Place St. Pancras.<lb/>
                        Windsor Castle</figTranscr>
                    <head>10. Georges Maile, “Windsor Castle,” [Elizabeth
                                    Henrietta Conyngham, Lady Conyngham] after “I. B.”
                                    [John Barrow?].</head>
                    <figDesc>Stipple etching/engraving with mezzotint (undated proof).
                                    British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings, BM cat. no.
                                    C.IX/Sub 1/P.5 [1852/10/9/580]. © Copyright, the Trustees
                                    of the British Museum.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <pb id="p39-97" n="97"/>
closer exploration of the subject and date of
                            the companion print may provide further evidence of a political, as well
                            as financial, motivation in Barrow’s publication of “Mrs
                            Q.” <note id="n129">102. Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate
                                    Plates</hi> xxvii.</note>
	<note id="n130">103. “Mrs Q,” the title the print was
                                published under, had gained popular currency by summer 1820 (see
                                Worrall 176).</note>
	<note id="n131">104. Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 356. Linda
                                Colley describes the championing of Caroline as a “nationwide
                                campaign” (Linda Colley, <hi rend="i">Britons: Forging the
                                    Nation 1707-1837</hi> [New Haven: Yale UP, 1992] 365). In the
                                summer of 1820, although Samuel Taylor Coleridge considered himself
                                a “Queenite,” Henry Crabb Robinson described himself
                                as merely “an anti-Kingite” (Hibbert 576).</note>
	<note id="n132">105. See George, cat. 10, 13733, 13785, 13889, 13891,
                                13896, 13897, 13986, 13991, 14023.</note>
	<note id="n133">
                                106. However, the Milan Commission, the
                                    government’s official inquiry into Caroline’s
                                    conduct, had been progressing for some years (see Hibbert
                                    528-42). By the late spring of 1820, Caroline, provoked by the
                                    decision of her husband and the British government to exclude
                                    her from the liturgy and not to recognize her as Queen, had
                                    started on her journey from Rome back to England (Hibbert 549).
                                    Thus the likely return of the Queen must have been public
                                    knowledge for some time before she reached Dover in early June.
                                    Essick describes “Mrs Q” as executed in
                                    “Stipple etching/ engraving with mezzotint”
                                    (Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 191). In addition,
                                    much of the top half of the plate has not been engraved. If free
                                    of other work, Blake would have been able to finish such a plate
                                    relatively quickly. It is therefore possible that he was
                                    employed by Barrow to complete the stipple engraving of
                                    “Mrs Q” in the weeks preceding Caroline’s
                                    arrival in order to capitalize on the renewed topicality of the
                                    subject.
                                <p>François Huet Villiers died in late July 1813. Therefore
                                    his portrait of Harriet Quentin must have been painted at least
                                    seven years before Blake’s engraving of it (see Essick,
                                        <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 198-99). As a fellow
                                    miniature painter possibly acquainted with Villiers, Barrow may
                                    have had access to or perhaps even owned the portrait and may
                                    have regarded the approaching trial of and the widespread
                                    sympathy for the Queen as an opportunity to market an engraving
                                    of Villiers’ miniature. Whether or not this was the case,
                                    Worrall successfully demonstrates that the image was later
                                    recontextualized by radical publishers in the light of
                                    subsequent events (see Worrall). It is unclear if Blake played
                                    any part in the subsequent mezzotint engraving, printing and
                                    hand coloring of this plate. It is possible that Maile was
                                    responsible for the mezzotint work and Blake for the stipple
                                    work on both plates (see Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate
                                        Plates</hi> 198).</p></note></p>
            <p>Barrow was almost certainly the designer, as well as the publisher, of
                            the companion print to “Mrs Q,” “Windsor
                            Castle,” engraved by Georges Maile, which bears the imprint date
                            1 June 1821 (illus. 10).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n134"
type="note">107</ref> The
                            significance of this companion print has not been explored. In 1906
                            Joseph Grego remarked, “It is regrettable that but little is
                            known to have been recorded of the charmer introduced as ‘Windsor
                                Castle.’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n135"
type="note">108</ref>
                            Geoffrey Keynes identified “Windsor Castle” as a portrait
                            of the Marchioness of Huntly.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n136" type="note">109</ref>
                            However, Elizabeth Henrietta Conyngham, Lady Conyngham, eldest daughter
                            of the first Marquis Conyngham, did not become the Marchioness of Huntly
                            until her marriage to Charles (Gordon), tenth Marquis of Huntly, at the
                            Royal Lodge, Windsor, on 20 March 1826.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n137" type="note">110</ref> By the early autumn of 1820, Lady Elizabeth’s
                            mother Elizabeth, Marchioness Conyngham, began to be portrayed in
                            satirical prints as George IV’s current mistress.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n138" type="note">111</ref> The King’s lavish gifts
                            to the Marchioness and other members of the Conyngham family provoked
                            widespread comment.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n139"
type="note">112</ref> It was even
                            suggested that the young and attractive Lady Elizabeth Conyngham was the
                            true object of the King’s affections.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n140" type="note">113</ref> Barrow’s design for “Windsor
                            Castle” portrays young Lady Conyngham at a piano, presumably at
                            the King’s “overblown rural retreat”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n141" type="note">114</ref> (in itself a subject of
                            contemporary controversy) in Windsor Great Park. Windsor Castle is
                            visible in the background. The title of the plate may also allude to the
                            political crisis of April 1821, three months before George IV’s
                            coronation, caused by the King’s proposed appointment, without
                            government consultation, of the Rev. Charles Richard Sumner, tutor to
                            Marchioness Conyngham’s three sons, to a vacant canonry at
                            Windsor. The King’s preferment of a member of the Conyngham
                            household to such a position was widely regarded as an infringement of
                            ministers’ privileges and almost forced the resignation of Lord
                            Liverpool’s government.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n142"
type="note">115</ref>
                            It seems quite possible that “Windsor Castle” could have
                            been engraved, <pb id="p39-98" n="98"/>
printed and hand colored in the
                            six weeks between the controversy over the proposed appointment of
                            Sumner in mid-April and the publication of this plate in early June
                            1821. <note id="n134">107. The imprint of “Windsor Castle”
                                indicates that the designer was “I. B.” The publisher
                                is the same as that on the imprint of “Mrs Q,”
                                “I. Barrow” of Weston Place, St. Pancras. On both
                                plates, the detailed work on the face compared with the
                                significantly less detailed engraving on the rest of the plate might
                                suggest that the engraver was working from a design of the
                                sitter’s head and shoulders (perhaps a miniature) rather than
                                a three-quarter-length drawing.</note>
	<note id="n135">108. Joseph Grego, <hi rend="i">Mrs Q__ and
                                    “Windsor Castle” with a Note on the Plates by
                                    Joseph Grego and Memoirs of the Life of the Celebrated Mrs Q__ by
                                    Edward Eglantine, Esq.</hi> (London: Kegan Paul, Trench,
                                Trübner &amp; Co. Limited, 1906) 11.</note>
	<note id="n136">109. Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by William
                                    Blake: The Separate Plates</hi> (Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956) 84.
                                Essick and Worrall follow Keynes’ identification. See Essick,
                                    <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 198; Worrall 175. Worrall
                                briefly discusses the plate in order to underline “the cross
                                reference between Windsor and Quintin” (Worrall 175).</note>
	<note id="n137">110. Vicary Gibbs, H. A. Doubleday, Duncan Warrand, Lord
                                Howard de Walden, eds., <hi rend="i">The Complete Peerage of
                                    England, Scotland and Ireland, Great Britain and the United
                                    Kingdom</hi>, 14 vols. (Gloucester: Alan Sutton, 1982
                                [microprint edition]) 2:685. An engraver’s proof of
                                “Windsor Castle” (illus. 10) is labelled in an
                                unidentified hand: “A daughter of the Marquis
                                Conyngham” (British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings,
                                C.IX/Sub 1/P.5). This suggests the sitter is Lady Elizabeth or, less
                                probably, her younger sister Lady Harriet Maria Conyngham. Freeman
                                O’Donohue identifies the sitter as Elizabeth Henrietta
                                (Conyngham), Marchioness of Huntly, “When Lady E.
                                Conyngham” (Freeman O’Donohue, <hi rend="i">Catalogue
                                    of Engraved British Portraits, Preserved in the Department of
                                    Prints and Drawings in the British Museum</hi>, 6 vols. [London:
                                British Museum, 1908-25] 2:594). This may partially explain the
                                mistitling of G. Engelmann’s later lithograph (?) based on
                                Blake’s “Mrs Q.” See Worrall 183n28. See also
                                Sir Thomas Lawrence’s portraits of Lady Elizabeth Henrietta
                                Conyngham with a small harp (finished 1824), oil on canvas (the
                                Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation, Lisbon); and Lady Harriet Maria
                                Conyngham (c. 1825), oil on canvas (the Metropolitan Museum of Art,
                                New York), reproduced in Kenneth Garlick, <hi rend="i">Sir Thomas
                                    Lawrence: A Complete Catalogue of the Oil Paintings</hi>
                                (Oxford: Phaidon, 1989) 172.</note>
	<note id="n138">111. The relationship appears to have begun in mid-1820.
                                However, those close to the King believed the relationship to be
                                “warmly affectionate rather than hotly passionate”
                                (see Hibbert 629). See the satirical prints <hi rend="i">K__G CUPID
                                    in the Corner—Playing Bopeep</hi>, published 16 September
                                1820, Benbow, St. Clements Church Yard, Strand; <hi rend="i">The
                                    R__l Cascade or Pumping Ship on Board the Yatch</hi>, published
                                October 1820, J. Fairburn, Broadway, Ludgate Hill; George, cat. 10,
                                14030. See also the following publications: “Lady C<hi
rend="s">*******</hi>m,” <hi rend="i">The Memoirs of Lady
                                        C<hi rend="s">*******</hi>m</hi> (London: H. Price, 1820);
                                Anon., <hi rend="i">New Inventions! The Conyngham Trap . . . De
                                    monts’ Machine . . . The Majocchi Mouthpiece; or, Non Mi
                                    Ricordo Whistle</hi> ([London?] 1820).</note>
	<note id="n139">112. See Hibbert 628-29 for the cost of the numerous
                                items of jewellery George IV bestowed upon Marchioness Conyngham.
                                See also George, cat. 10, 13893 [October 1820].</note>
	<note id="n140">113. See Hibbert 631; Parissien 91. For a satirical
                                print on the subject, see “The Royal Foraging Cap or New
                                Windsor Uniform” [W. Heath], published 11 October 1820 by S.
                                W. Fores, 41 Picadilli. Dorothy George has described the print as
                                follows: “A fashionably dressed man, walking in Hyde Park,
                                draws back in astonishment on meeting Lord Conyngham, riding a
                                spirited horse and wearing a marquess’s coronet, surmounted
                                by antlers with bells. The former says: <hi rend="i">Why my Lord I
                                    never saw you so <hi rend="u">Gracefully</hi> set off in my life
                                    before, where the Devil did you get that beautiful 
<hi rend="u">Charger</hi>. Conyngham: It was a present from the ____ to my
                                    wife &amp; a rare stallion it is, he has also presented my
                                    daughter with a <hi rend="u">similar</hi> poney. Answer: 
<hi rend="u">Indeed</hi>!!! Why I never heard before that he had
                                        <hi rend="u">mounted</hi> them both!!!</hi>” (George,
                                cat. 10, 13892). For satirical prints on the influence of the
                                Conyngham family on George IV, see George, cat. 10, 13826, 14181,
                                13889 and 14366. A year earlier George had been portrayed in more
                                than one publication dallying “not only with Mrs Quintin but
                                also with her two daughters” at the Royal Cottage at Windsor
                                (see Worrall 174-75).</note>
	<note id="n141">114. The phrase is Steven Parissien’s; see
                                Parissien illus. 15.</note>
	<note id="n142">115. See Hibbert 633-34.</note></p>
            <p>Both “Mrs Q” and “Windsor Castle” are
                            examples of the widely popular early nineteenth-century genre of the
                            commercial fancy print. These companion prints bear little resemblance
                            to the numerous political caricatures targeting George IV that
                            circulated during this period. However, both prints portray women who
                            were widely considered notorious recipients of the King’s lavish
                            favor, if not examples of his infidelities, past and present.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n143" type="note">116</ref> Significantly, John Barrow chose
                            to publish each print at a moment of political crisis early in the reign
                            of George IV. Barrow’s commission and publication of both
                            “Mrs Q” and “Windsor Castle” can therefore
                            be interpreted in the context of the widespread criticism of George
                            IV’s infidelities, extravagance and what was widely perceived as
                            the pernicious influence of members of his intimate circle.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n144" type="note">117</ref> In the light of events preceding
                            and succeeding the engraving, printing and publication of “Mrs
                            Q” and “Windsor Castle,” John Barrow and William
                            Blake can be seen, as David Worrall has suggested, as “caught up
                            . . . in the latest phase of English radical activism.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n145" type="note">118</ref> However, although William Blake
                            was clearly the engraver of “Mrs Q,” his own opinions
                            concerning “the Queen’s affair” are unknown.
                            Bentley observes that “The Queen’s progress across France
                            to defend herself against the scandalous divorce proceedings i the House
                            of Lords was eagerly reported in <hi rend="i">The Courier</hi> and
                            elsewhere in May and June of 1820.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n146" type="note">119</ref> However, the <hi rend="i">Courier’s</hi>
                            discussion of the Queen’s departure from France on the Dover
                            packet on the evening of Sunday 4 June 1820, which George Cumberland
                            read to Blake two days later at 17 South Molton Street, can hardly be
                            described as eager reporting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n147" type="note">120</ref>
                            The writer explicitly questions Caroline’s wisdom in hastily
                            rejecting Lord Hutchinson’s proposal and Henry Brougham’s
                            advice that she should remain abroad and avoid a public trial and
                            instead choosing to return to England under the wing of the radical MP
                            Alderman Matthew Wood. “Her MAJESTY may perhaps find herself in
                            the hands of a faction to whom it is a matter of equal indifference
                            whether they celebrate their orgies under the name of Radical Reform,
                            the Manchester Massacre, or the Queen of ENGLAND.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n148" type="note">121</ref> No record has survived of Blake
                            and Cumberland’s reaction to the <hi rend="i">Courier’s</hi> account.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n149" type="note">122</ref> In the publication of “Mrs Q” and
                            “Windsor Castle,” John Barrow appears to have expressed
                            support for Queen Caroline and criticism of George IV, sentiments held
                            by numerous working and middle class British citizens. However, although
                            his motives for engraving “Mrs Q” in 1820 are likely to
                            have been primarily commercial, Blake’s own opinions concerning
                            the return and trial of Queen Caroline remain unclear.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n150" type="note">123</ref>
	<note id="n143">116. Although it was common practice to omit the names
                                of sitters from such prints, the particular titles of both companion
                                prints (presumably decided upon by Barrow) also suggest that neither
                                “Mrs Q” nor “Windsor Castle” are merely
                                fancy prints, but rather explicitly make reference to contemporary
                                controversies concerning the monarchy.</note>
	<note id="n144">117. An anonymous copy of Blake’s engraving was
                                used as an illustration to “Edward Eglantine” [William
                                Benbow], <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Life of the Celebrated Mrs
                                    Q</hi> (London: William Benbow, 1822). See Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate
Plates</hi> 199-200; Worrall 177-79.</note>
	<note id="n145">118. See Worrall 180.</note>
	<note id="n146">119. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 370.</note>
	<note id="n147">120. BL Add. MSS. 36520H, f. 384, cited <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 370.</note>
	<note id="n148">121. “The Queen’s Journey,” <hi rend="i">Courier</hi> Tuesday evening, 6 June
1820.</note>
	<note id="n149">122. George Cumberland’s son, Sydney Cumberland,
                                wrote to his mother Elizabeth Cumberland on 29 June 1820 that the
                                following day his father would go “to the opera with Mr
                                Norton when he expects a view of the Queen who it is reported will
                                be there ....” BL Add. MSS. 36507, f. 311. See also David V.
                                Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 3rd ed.
                                (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1977) 524.</note>
	<note id="n150">123. This appears to be one of the few commercial
                                engraving commissions acquired and executed by Blake after June 1818
                                without Linnell’s assistance in any capacity (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
823).</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Conclusion</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In this paper, I have discussed new information principally derived from
                            the will of Henry Banes which throws light on our knowledge and
                            understanding of the last years of William and Catherine Blake at 3
                            Fountain Court and those of Catherine Blake in widowhood. The date of
                            the commencement of Henry Banes’ period of residence at and as
                            ratepayer of 3 Fountain Court, Strand, has been established. I have
                            identified Banes’ trade and cited evidence that suggests that
                            William and Catherine Blake were not Henry and Sarah Banes’ first
                            lodgers at 3 Fountain Court. An examination of Banes’ will has
                            established the month and year of the death of Sarah Banes, the sister
                            of Catherine Blake and the wife of Henry Banes. It is now clear that
                            Sarah Banes was living at 3 Fountain Court when William and Catherine
                            Blake moved there as lodgers in 1821, but that she died approximately
                            three years later. The same source has provided the correct date for the
                            death of Henry Banes.</p>
            <p>Henry Banes’ will also reveals that, in the spring of 1829,
                            Catherine Blake almost certainly received a significant legacy. I have
                            suggested that this legacy is likely to have been an important factor in
                            Catherine’s decision to move from Frederick Tatham’s
                            residence to her own lodgings in the early spring of 1829. The will also
                            contains a brief reference to William Blake the complements other
                            contemporary allusions to Blake’s state of dress in the mid-1820s
                            and suggests a seemingly cordial relationship between Banes and his
                            brother- and sister-in-law. On the basis of evidence derived from
                            Banes’ will, I have suggested that the “sole
                            Executrix” of Banes’ estate, Louisa Best, may very well
                            have been Henry and Sarah Banes’ only surviving child. If this is
                            the case, then Louisa Best, née Banes, daughter of Sarah Banes,
                            née Boucher, is the only traced child of either William or
                            Catherine Blake’s siblings and therefore the only known niece of,
                            as well as a second traced surviving 
<pb id="p39-99" n="99"/>
immediate
                            relative of, William and Catherine Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n151" type="note">124</ref> Finally, the discovery that the miniaturist, print
                            colorer and engraver John Barrow was witness to Henry Banes’ will
                            and well acquainted with him for some years throws light upon the
                            identity and political sympathies of the publisher of Blake’s
                            “Mrs Q” and the designer and publisher of its companion
                            print “Windsor Castle.” Blake’s employment by John
                            Barrow as engraver of “Mrs Q” can also be set in a new
                            context. It is likely that Barrow’s choices of publication date
                            and subject (two attractive young women publicly associated with the
                            King’s lavish lifestyle and infidelities) of both “Mrs
                            Q” and its companion print “Windsor Castle” reflect
                            his own political opinions concerning George IV and Queen Caroline
                            during 1820 and 1821. Therefore, William Blake’s employment as
                            engraver for a publisher of John Barrow’s sympathies may indeed
                            indicate an association between Blake and radical print culture in the
                            early 1820s. However, Blake’s own motives in accepting and
                            completing this commission remain ambiguous. <note id="n151">124.
                                William Blake’s sister, Catherine Elizabeth Blake
                                (1764-1841), is the only immediate relation of William and Catherine
                                Blake known to have survived them (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
                                555). If Louisa was William and Catherine Blake’s niece, then
                                she as well as Catherine Elizabeth Blake had some claim on the
                                Blakes’ estate. Frederick Tatham claimed, with no
                                corroborating evidence, that Catherine Blake bequeathed “The
                                remaining stock of [Blake’s] works, still considerable . . .
                                [and] her few effects” to Mrs. Tatham and himself (Gilchrist
                                357; see also <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 690).</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> 2nd ed. New Haven:
                            Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, Yale UP, 2004.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William
                                Blake.</hi> New Haven: Yale UP, 2001.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of
                            Publications and Discoveries in 2004.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 4-37.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman, with commentary by Harold Bloom.
                            Rev. ed. Berkeley: U of California P, 1982.</p>
            <p>Cox, Jane. <hi rend="i">Affection Defying the Power of Death: An
                                Introduction to Wills, Probate and Death Duty Records.</hi>
                            Birmingham: Federation of Family History Societies, 1993.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
                                Catalogue.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983.</p>
            <p>George, Dorothy M. <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Political and Personal
                                Satires Preserved in the Department of Prints and Drawings in the
                                British Museum.</hi> 11 vols. [vols. 5-10, published 1935-52,
                            consulted]. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1870-1954.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> Ed.
                            Ruthven Todd. London: J. M. Dent &amp; Sons, 1945.</p>
            <p>Graves, Algernon. <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of Artists Who Have Exhibited
                                in the Principal London Exhibitions from 1760 to 1893.</hi> 1901.
                            Weston-super-Mare: Kingsmead P, 1969.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Royal Academy of Arts: A Complete Dictionary
                                of Contributors and Their Work from Its Foundation in 1769 to 1904,
                                etc.</hi> 8 vols. London: Henry Graves &amp; Co. and George Bell
                            &amp; Sons, 1905-06.</p>
            <p>Hibbert, Christopher. <hi rend="i">George IV.</hi> London: Penguin,
                            1976.</p>
            <p>Johnson, Jane, comp. <hi rend="i">Works Exhibited at the Royal Society of
                                British Artists, 1824-1893.</hi> Woodbridge: Antique
                            Collector’s Club, 1975.</p>
            <p>Linnell, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell &amp; Co.: The Life
                                of John Linnell.</hi> Lewes, Sussex: Book Guild, 1994.</p>
            <p>Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Edward Calvert.</hi> London: G. Bell &amp;
                            Sons Ltd., 1962.</p>
            <p><corr type="emend">Parissien, Steven.</corr> <hi rend="i">George IV: The Grand Entertainment.</hi>
                            London: John Murray, 2001.</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael. “The Printing of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of
Job.” Print Quarterly</hi> 22.2
                            (June 2005): 138-59.</p>
            <p>Story, Alfred T. <hi rend="i">The Life of John Linnell.</hi> 2 vols.
                            London: Richard Bentley and Son, 1892.</p>
            <p>Whitehead, Angus. “William Blake’s Last Residence: No. 3
                            Fountain Court, Strand, George Richmond’s Plan and an Unrecorded
                            Letter to John Linnell.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi>
                            6.1 (spring/summer 2005): 21-30.</p>
            <p>Worrall, David. “The Mob and ‘Mrs Q’: William Blake,
                            William Benbow, and the Context of Regency Radicalism.” <hi rend="i">Blake,
Politics and History.</hi> Ed. Jackie DiSalvo, G.A.
                            Rosso, and Christopher Z. Hobson. New York: Garland Publishing, 1998.
                            169-84.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
