<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.2.vankleeck</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">“Tenderness &amp; Love Not Uninspird”: Blake’s Re-Vision of Sentimentalism
in The Four Zoas</title>
        <author n="Van Kleeck">Justin Van Kleeck</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2005</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
              <name>Joyce H. Townsend</name>
              <name>Bronwyn Ormsby</name>
              <name>Julia Jönsson</name>
              <name>Mark Evans</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
      <pb id="p39-60" n="60"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Tenderness &amp; Love Not Uninspird”: Blake’s
                            Re-Vision of Sentimentalism in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Justin <name>Van Kleeck</name></docAuthor></byline>
		<q> For Mercy has a human heart<lb/>
 Pity, a human face:<lb/>
 And Love, the
                        human form divine,<lb/>
 And Peace, the human dress.<lb/>
 William Blake,
                        “The Divine Image” </q>
		<q> Pity would be no more,<lb/>
 If we did not make somebody Poor:<lb/>
 And Mercy
                        no more could be,<lb/>
 If all were as happy as we;<lb/>
 Blake, “The
                        Human Abstract” </q>
          <p>William Blake’s epic poem <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> has been
                        read in varying ways: as a dream, as a psychological account of fragmented
                        consciousness, and as an attack on Newtonian science, to name a few.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref> For
                        those critics also focusing on the physical state(s) of the manuscript
                        itself, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is everything from an abandoned and
                        tragic failure to a remarkable experiment with flexible poetics.
                        Blake’s eclectic, syncretic mythology and the
                        “unstable” status of this unfinished work welcome these
                        readings. Begun c. 1797 (the date on the title page) and revised until
                        possibly 1810 or even later (see Bentley 157-66), the epic grows out of a
                        revolutionary decade for society and for the literary practices that
                        influenced many of Blake’s earlier writings. One such revolution that
                        has been largely overlooked in studies of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is
                        the changing view of sentimentalism, which was a philosophical and literary
                        movement especially prominent throughout the eighteenth century.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Riding a wave started by earlier critics
                        who targeted sentimentalism, radical writers focused on its emphasis on
                        emotion and sympathetic benevolence between individuals. But they also
                        attacked the tendency of sentimentalism, unless guided by reason, to weaken
                        or (as some saw it) “feminize” society, to encourage hypocrisy
                        and self-gratifying charity, and to foster a predatory system of
                        victimization. Their attack often took a gendered form, for critics saw
                        sentimentalism as a dividing force between the sexes that also created weak
                        victims or crafty tyrants within the sexes. <note id="n0">* I would like to thank
Dennis Welch at Virginia Tech and John
                            O’Brien and Jerome McGann at the University of Virginia for their
                            helpful comments and suggestions during the preparation of this
                            essay.</note>
	<note id="n1">1. Although some
                            scholars have noted the connection between Blake and sentimentality,
                            most treatments of this subject are portions of a larger discussion,
                            often related to gender and sexuality in Blake’s poetry (see my
                            bibliography). One noteworthy article is Andrew Lincoln’s
                            “Alluring the Heart to Virtue: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>,” in which
the author examines “the rise
                            of affective devotion or ‘the religion of the
                            heart,’” “a religion grounded in affection [that
                            was] seen as a most effective instrument of social harmony and
                            control” (622, 623). Other helpful studies include Mary Kelly
                            Persyn’s article on sensibility, chastity, and sacrifice in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and Judith Lee’s discussion of
                            Blake’s Emanations.</note></p>
          <p>Blake points out these negative characteristics of sentimentalism in
                        mythological terms with his vision of the fragmentation and fall of the
                        Universal Man Albion into male and female parts, Zoas and Emanations. In the
                        chaotic universe that results, sentimentalism is part of a
                        “system” that perpetuates suffering in the fallen world,
                        further dividing the sexes into their stereotypical roles. Although
                        “feminine” sentimentality serves as a force for reunion and
                        harmony, its connection with fallen nature and “vegetated”
                        life in Blake’s mythology turns it into a trap, at best a Band-Aid on
                        the mortal wound of the fall. For Blake, mutual sympathy in the fallen world
                        requires the additional strength and guidance of inspired vision (initiating
                        a fiery Last Judgment) in order to become truly redemptive, 
<hi rend="i">effective</hi> rather than merely <hi rend="i">affective.</hi> When
                        recounting humanity’s “Resurrection to Unity” and
                        “Regeneration” in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (4:4-5, E
                        301), Blake frequently uses sentimental conventions both to characterize
                        fallen disorder and to show how it can be healed when incorporated into
                        spiritual vision.</p>
          <p>Although critics speak of the “Age of Sensibility,” the
                        “cult of sensibility,” “sentimental literature,”
                        and so forth, sensibility and/or sentimentality are often easier to describe
                        than to define. Indeed, as Janet Todd points out in <hi rend="i">Sensibility: An
Introduction</hi>, writers in the eighteenth century
                        used the terms interchangeably and inconsistently (6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> However, we can identify some crucial distinctions
                        between these terms and, even more importantly, distinguish many of the
                        overall movement’s other key terms and features that will appear
                        again when we look at <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>
	<note id="n2">2. Todd’s book serves its titular purpose extremely
                            well for the general features of sentimentalism. For readers wishing to
                            pursue this topic, some other important works on specific aspects of
                            sentimentalism, such as its relation to culture/consumerism, politics,
                            and sexuality, are listed in my bibliography.</note></p>
          <p>In general, “sensibility” refers most directly to physical
                        feelings and emotions, as well as to the reification and display of
                        emotional refinement. Sensibility thus values delicacy and associated acts
                        such as crying, kneeling, fainting, and charity, and it is—as
                        sensibility makes clear—based on the natural responsiveness of the
                        bodily senses. “Sentimentality” also emphasizes emotions and
                        the body, but in a slightly different way. Sentiments are rational or moral
                        reflections, in sentimentalism usually connected to or inspired by the
                        emotions and related to the propriety of certain behaviors; thus,
                        sentimentality brings the mind into closer relationship with the natural
                        senses. As Jerome McGann succinctly puts it, “sensibility emphasizes
                        the mind in the body, sentimentality the body in the mind” (7).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> The close connection between these two
                        terms grows even closer because “The adjective
                        ‘sentimental’” 
                        <pb id="p39-61" n="61"/>
became a catchall phrase for sensibility 
<hi rend="i">and</hi> sentimentality (Todd 9). What is most important to
                        recognize is the emphasis given to the body, to the physical senses, as a
                        legitimate source of behavior and knowledge.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n3">3. Jane Austen exploits the varying connotations of
                            sentimental terms in <hi rend="i">Sense and Sensibility</hi> (begun
                            1797, published 1811) so as to critique/ parody the latter in contrast
                            to the former; however, her novel still retains a great deal of
                            sentimentality, positive and negative.</note>
	<note id="n4">4. For this paper, I will use “sentimentality”
                            for the faculty and “sentimentalism” for the movement that
                            it fostered. For extended discussions and definitions of sentimental
                            terminology, see Brissenden, chapter 2 and 98-118, and Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">Sex
and Sensibility</hi> 5-10.</note></p>
          <p>Given this prominence of the body, it makes sense that a key starting point
                        for the sentimental movement in England is the empiricist, or
                        “sensational” (Barker-Benfield 3), philosophy of John Locke.
                        In his <hi rend="i">Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi> (1690), Locke
                        identifies the physical senses as the source of our ideas. Subsequent
                        philosophers, such as the third Earl of Shaftesbury and Francis Hutcheson,
                        developed Locke’s views with the addition of morality and aesthetics,
                        helping to define sentimentalism as a distinct movement by advocating the
                        cultivation of virtue. Benevolence is probably the most crucial element of
                        the Shaftesbury-Hutcheson brand of sentimentalism, especially since
                        benevolence was “in this period a ‘manly’ attribute
                        opposing ‘womanish’ self-interest and fear” (Todd 25).
                        David Hume and Adam Smith are other important figures, the latter especially
                        so with his <hi rend="i">Theory of Moral Sentiments</hi> (1759). In this
                        work, Smith views the emotions and sympathy between individuals as valid
                        social forces: by “entering into” another person via our
                        imagination, we can sympathize with that person and form a relationship (2).
                        More strikingly, his discussion of “unsocial,”
                        “social,” and “selfish” passions (part 1,
                        chapters 3, 4, and 5 respectively) and their role as determinant factors in
                        one’s “merit” or “demerit” in society
                        (part 2) goes far toward systematizing sentimentality in regard to public
                        displays of sentiment and subsequent social <hi rend="i">status.</hi> Given
                        Smith’s apparent exchange-value approach to human feelings, it is not
                        surprising that he later authored the great economic treatise <hi rend="i">The Wealth
of Nations</hi> (1776).</p>
          <p>With these developments in sentimentalist philosophy, as well as in religion
                        in general and Methodism in particular, literature became probably the most
                        prominent venue in which the “cult of sensibility” practiced
                        its art and expounded its principles.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n5" type="note">5</ref> In
                        France, Jean-Jacques Rousseau united sentimental philosophy with fiction and
                        confessional, emphasizing the natural, sensual component of human nature,
                        and he had a strong influence on English sentimentalists. In England, Samuel
                        Richardson, Sarah Fielding, and Laurence Sterne in fiction, and Hannah More,
                        Thomas Gray, and Edward Young in poetry, were just a few of the authors
                        contributing to the vast corpus of sentimentalism and establishing a
                        distinctive “language of affective meanings” (McGann 6).
                        Although the amount of sentimental literature was enormous, we can cull out
                        some of the specific values that are crucial for understanding
                        Blake’s approach to sentimental literature. Sentimental writers
                        sought a heightened sense of <hi rend="i">pathos</hi> through stock
                        characters—virtuous heroines, benevolent heroes, wizened beggars,
                        distressed children—and trademark scenes of weeping, charity, and
                        especially hostility reconciled by emotional interaction among said
                        characters. Authors tried to forge a sympathetic, <hi rend="i">affective</hi>
relationship between text and reader by depicting these
                        “natural victims” and the antagonistic society or characters
                        hounding them (Todd 3); a good reader was expected to respond with the
                        appropriate sentiment, while neophytes gained valuable instruction through
                        reading. What sentimental literature exploits, even <hi rend="i">requires</hi>, for
its effect/affect, then, is a dichotomy of victim
                        and victimizer. It codifies, as it were, a “system” of
                        suffering and division while trying to create (and teach) sympathetic
                        affections. This dichotomy, however problematic it may be for
                        sentimentalism’s ostensible goals of mutual benevolence, most clearly
                        manifests in relation to gender—the expected qualities and behaviors
                        of each sex. Gender differences, in fact, largely define the system of
                        (sexual) virtue and antagonism, be it within a domestic family setting or
                        within society as a whole. As R. F. Brissenden famously puts it, “The
                        paradigm cliché” of sentimental literature is “virtue
                        in distress” (94), the situation in which we find the two most
                        enduring sentimental stereotypes: the chaste but embattled woman and the
                        good-hearted but doomed man of feeling. <note id="n5">5. Barker-Benfield
                            rightly identifies the “cult” (and its constituent cults)
                            as not just a literary trope, but also as an
                            “epiphenomenon” extending across the eighteenth-century
                            cultural spectrum, from religion to social behavior; he is most
                            concerned with this sentimental culture’s relationship to
                            “the rise of a consumer society” (xix). Along with
                            Barker-Benfield on sentimental religion, see Lincoln,
                            “Alluring.”</note></p>
          <p>The status of women in sentimental literature is indeed a <hi rend="i">pitiful</hi> one. Largely
because of women’s “unique
                        sexual suffering” and “bodily authenticity,”
                        sensibility “stressed those qualities considered feminine in the
                        sexual psychology of the time: intuitive sympathy, susceptibility,
                        emotionalism and passivity” (Todd 110). In the foundational novels of
                        Richardson especially, weak and chaste women become ideal sentimental,
                        virtuous heroines. Clarissa Harlowe, for example, “is the symbol of
                        virtuous sensibility” in <hi rend="i">Clarissa</hi> because of her
                        “ailing body,” which signifies that she is “too good
                        for the world, and feels too much” (Mullan 111). Helping to clarify
                        this ideal and set the sentimental standards, a dichotomy exists even within
                        representations of women: wicked women, to contrast with the ideal heroines,
                        “simply lacked femininity and acquired masculine traits” (Todd
                        80). What we most commonly find in sentimental fiction, then, are laudably
                        passive women who face threats to their “virtue” from males or
                        some masculine antagonistic presence—victims and victimizers, such as
                        Clarissa and the rapist Lovelace. In the face of such victimization, we also
                        frequently find women (Pamela and Mrs. Jervis in <hi rend="i">Pamela</hi>,
                        for instance) who come together to share the heroine’s suffering,
                        which surely plays off stereotypical views of women as more emotional and
                        closer to the body. And all too often, the chaste embodiment of virtue
                        struggles in vain against her victimizer until she finds “no place to
                        rest but the grave” (Allen 128). The sinister nature of sentimental
                        femininity emerges in what these views imply: sentimental heroines 
<hi rend="i">need</hi>, as it were, to be persecuted “because
                        sensibility, <pb id="p39-62" n="62"/>
and therefore virtue, is most excited,
                        and therefore most manifest, when threatened” (Mullan 124).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> And the sexual dimension of
                        virtue’s distress is crucial, Hagstrum makes clear, because in many
                        cases rape (threatened or carried out), “far from spoiling the
                        sensuality [in a novel], actually heightens it for both sexes” (<hi rend="i">Sex and
Sensibility</hi> 201). There is thus a dark subtext, as
                        it were, in sentimental literature: much as occurs in some shocking views of
                        rape (“She was asking for it”), the sentimental victim often
                        seems complicit in, or even responsible for, her attack. <note id="n6">6.
                            Richardson, writing to Lady Bradshaigh, is even more explicit on this
                            dire necessity in his sentimental fiction: “Clarissa has the
                            greatest of Triumphs even in this world. The greatest, I will venture to
                            say, even <hi rend="i">in</hi>, and <hi rend="i">after</hi> the Outrage
                            [of her rape], and <hi rend="i">because</hi> of the Outrage that ever
                            Woman had” (qtd. in Mullan 66).</note></p>
          <p>The “man of feeling” fares little better than his female
                        counterpart. Because sentimentalism was originally a male construct (from
                        Shaftesbury, Hutcheson, et al.) that appropriated “feminine”
                        qualities of emotional and bodily responsiveness, male sentimental
                        characters face fates similar to those of sentimental women. The man of
                        feeling fills his role by his “outflowings of emotion,” which
                        “teach response more than virtuous action” (Todd 92), so any
                        charitable acts play second fiddle to his hyperbolic sympathy. He therefore
                        sheds tears at almost every turn and is nearly incapacitated by any and
                        every scene that stirs his affections; he is mastered by, rather than master
                        of, his overpowering senses and feelings. For example, during a pitiful
                        story told by an insane mother, Harley in Henry Mackenzie’s <hi rend="i">The Man of
Feeling</hi> (1771) paid “the tribute of some
                        tears,” “bathed [her hand] with his tears,” and then
                        “burst into tears” when departing (26, 27).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Weakened like Harley, the male sentimental
                        “hero” can hardly stand up to the hostile and unfeeling
                        society that opposes him, so that his heartfelt expressions of benevolence
                        and tenderness make him an easy victim. In general, then, a man of feeling
                        is irrevocably alienated from society because of his sentimentality, or he
                        inevitably meets an early death, in either case accomplishing little or
                        nothing for the greater good. Once again, the system of suffering becomes
                        self-indulgent and self-sustaining, and the victims “invite”
                        the forces attacking them in order to function as sympathetic 
<hi rend="i">characters.</hi> Gender identity and difference, both for female and
                        male characters, thus play determinant roles in the “order” of
                        this sentimental system. <note id="n7">7. An “Index to Tears”
                            appeared in the first edition of <hi rend="i">The Man of Feeling</hi>,
                            giving line and page citations for readers who wanted to study up on
                            cause and effect, scene and response, in the sentimental system of
                            weeping. See Mackenzie 110-11.</note></p>
          <p>When we turn to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, we find a similarly divided
                        and antagonistic situation. In Blake’s cosmological myth, the unity
                        of Albion has given way to warfare between the sexes and all of the
                        characters, wreaking havoc in the entire universal order and growing ever
                        more calamitous. Blake begins his epic <hi rend="i">in medias res</hi>, in
                        the world as we know it, and things are far from harmonious or Edenic. The
                        division of the androgynous Zoas into male Zoas and female Emanations is the
                        most glaring evidence that something has gone horribly wrong. Besides the
                        Zoas and Emanations, Blake’s mythology grows chaotically larger as
                        these parts of Albion’s ailing (sentimental) body split and transform
                        into Spectres, Shadows, Spirits, Orc the “reborn” Luvah, and
                        countless sons and daughters of various sorts. As is implied here, the key
                        concept is fragmentation.</p>
          <p>The very presence of divided sexes is in fact catastrophic. This is the case,
                        according to Blake, because in Eternity Albion is androgynous. However, the
                        exact natures of Albion and the Zoas are only known by “the Heavenly
                        Father,” which makes the Eternal Self eternally tricky, especially
                        when an “Individual” tries to understand it from below (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
3:7-8, E 301). While Blake asserts Albion’s
                        androgyny, his language and general presentation of Eternal life create a
                        great deal of difficulty in regard to the “sex” of Eternal
                        beings. Specifically, Blake’s is a masculine (at least
                        linguistically, at most ontologically) Eternity of Albion the
                        “Man” and the “Eternal Brotherhood.” As Leopold
                        Damrosch explains, the consequence is that it appears as if “the
                        female is fully integrated into the male” and that “The
                        androgynous self [Albion] is, in effect, a male self with a female element
                        within it” (182).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref> The female is
                        not separate but integrated, internalized, even more obviously than the
                        male. Blake’s writings frequently seem to bear this opinion out,
                        especially when he deals with fallen life. For example, Ahania becomes
                        Urizen’s “Shadowy Feminine Semblance,” and Urizen is
                        “Astonishd &amp; Confounded” to see “Her shadowy form
                        now Separate,” for now “Two wills they had two intellects
                        &amp; not as in times of old” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 30:23, E 319;
                        30:45-48, E 320). The separation of an originally integrated portion of the
                        self, whether that self is androgynous or to some extent masculine, makes
                        the female extremely problematic in Blake’s mythology, since he
                        emphasizes its emanated, secondary nature. In its most negative forms, the
                        female will becomes the dreaded “Female Will,” while
                        femininity itself is “a symbol of otherness” representing
                        “Whatever Blake cannot reconcile himself to in the phenomenological
                        world—bodies, matter, nature, physical space” (Damrosch 183,
                        188). Thus, Blake’s females have a status similar to that of women in
                        sentimental literature, being linked to the body, senses, and emotions, and
                        in turn to the physical world, nature, and generation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> Just as writers and critics of sentimentalism
                        characterize the (emotional) body as a “feminine” realm, Blake
                        associates the 
<pb id="p39-63" n="63"/>
female identity with material,
                        corporeal reality. As we shall see, although the female Emanations serve a
                        crucial role in the fallen world (as its very “ground,” as it
                        were), they are essentially anomalies and indicators of its fallenness. But,
                        as Helen P. Bruder also asserts, in “giving a form to sexual
                        error,” Blake was as much “a searching critic of
                        patriarchy” as a “hectoring misogynist” (182).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Although the female sex carries much
                        of the fallen world’s negative burden, the fallen male Zoas are by no
                        means exemplars of “redemptive” behavior, and their depravity
                        is inherently tied to their separate sexual identity <hi rend="i">as
                            males.</hi> With the fall, and only with the fall, do the sexes become
                        distinct. <note id="n8">8. Critical opinion has long been divided on this
                            issue and its implications for Blake’s opinions, cosmology, and
                            poetics. For instance, Irene Tayler sheds a more positive light than
                            Damrosch on the gender equality of Blake’s Eternal androgyne,
                            while Anne K. Mellor and Susan Fox emphasize Blake’s
                            subordination of the female and the feminine.</note>
	<note id="n9">9. For instance, Otto identifies Enitharmon as “the
                            form/body of the fallen world” and “the shape of [all] the
                            Zoas’ loss,” as well as “the body of
                            imagination,” while Vala is “the sexual body” and
                            Enion “the sensitive body” (85, 79).</note>
	<note id="n10">10. Alicia Ostriker gives a fine treatment of Blake and the
                            woman question in her outline of the “four Blakes.” While
                            Blake’s misogyny or lack thereof is an important topic, it is not
                            crucial to my discussion.</note></p>
          <p>But how does the presence of two sexes in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
                        indicate both that Blake recognized the sexual tensions fostered and
                        exploited by sentimental literature, and that he critiqued the sentimental
                        system as a whole? We can answer this question by first examining reactions
                        to sentimentalism, in particular the criticisms made by radical writers.
                        These writers decried the negative influence of sentimentalism on human
                        nature, an influence that they often traced back to the movement’s
                        conventional characters and behaviors. In turn, the harmful effects that
                        radical writers censured shed light on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
                        because they correspond in significant ways to Blake’s portrayal of
                        the fallen world and its sexually divided inhabitants.</p>
          <p>Despite its enduring presence, even by the 1770s
                        “sentimentality” was a derogatory label indicating
                        affectation, self-indulgence, and overbearing shows of emotion. Particularly
                        troubling for many was the feminized quality of sentimentalism, creating
                        hyper-feminine women and effeminate men and thus weakening society as a
                        whole. Sentimentalism’s fetishizing of the feminine created a
                        cultural dichotomy, with one group valuing the community-building power of
                        “female qualities” and another group fearing effeminacy,
                        advocating male dominance, and seeing woman’s nature as
                        “contingent” (Todd 20). The critics found feminine
                        “self-indulgent physicality and . . . self-contemplating
                        vanity” in sentimental literature as a whole (62); even worse, they
                        scorned it for adversely influencing readers—largely women.</p>
          <p>The revolutionary events of the 1790s ushered in a new group of critics <hi rend="i">and</hi>
sentimentalists, with radical writers fighting for
                        social change and systemic reform rather than the indulgent cultivation of
                        feelings. According to Chris Jones, “Radical writers of sensibility
                        stressed qualities in direct contrast to the popular degenerate model of the
                        ‘man of feeling’ in emphasizing action and
                        intervention,” retaining an emphasis on the emotions but dismissing
                        “self-centred passions” for more <hi rend="i">universal</hi>
                        feelings under the aegis of rational benevolence (9). Because “the
                        whole [sentimental] movement had been branded with weakness and
                        irresponsibility” (17), it was both attacked and modified by
                        revolutionaries such as William Godwin and Mary Wollstonecraft, as well as
                        later Romantics such as Jane Austen and William Wordsworth. As shown in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789), Blake absorbed the culture of
                        sentiment: his innocent speakers and pastoral lyrics, such as in “The
                        Lamb” and “Nurse’s Song,” depict a heartfelt
                        sympathy between individuals similar to the ideal of sentimentalism. Yet he
                        also critiqued sentimental culture, as in <hi rend="i">Visions of the
                            Daughters of Albion</hi> (1793) and <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Experience</hi> (1794). In <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, the main
                        characters both reflect and respond to sentimental stereotypes. We find the
                        sentimental triangle of (here emboldened) rape victim, tyrannical rapist,
                        and emotionally self-absorbed male in Oothoon, Bromion, and Theotormon. In
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, Blake’s weeping chimney
                        sweeps (“The Chimney Sweeper”) or fussy infants
                        (“Infant Sorrow”), while pathetic images, confront a cold
                        society—typified in “The Human Abstract”—that
                        often professes sympathetic bonds but produces only a land of misery. These
                        works, along with some of his commercial book illustrations,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> help to place Blake within the
                        cultural debate surrounding sentimentalism in the 1790s, even if he did not
                        follow some of his contemporaries and launch an explicit campaign for or
                        against the tradition. <note id="n11">11. Lincoln observes that Blake did
                            engravings for works by sentimental novelists such as Richardson,
                            Sterne, and Sarah Fielding (“Alluring” 630n30).</note></p>
          <p>Because Wollstonecraft attacks sentimental conventions while occasionally
                        incorporating them into her arguments, her <hi rend="i">Vindication of the
                            Rights of Men</hi> (1790) and <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of
                            Woman</hi> (1792) provide excellent touchstones for the radical
                        reworking of sentimentalism and for Blake’s later critiques. As
                        Dennis Welch has pointed out, she likely had some influence on Blake, who
                        designed and engraved illustrations for her <hi rend="i">Original Stories
                            from Real Life</hi> (1788). And although Michael Ackland suggests that
                        Blake owed much to her <hi rend="i">Rights of Woman</hi> for his view of
                        sexual relationships and his attempts to create harmony between the sexes,
                        Ackland does not recognize some of the specific parallels between both of
                        the <hi rend="i">Vindications</hi> and Blake’s works.</p>
          <p>In the <hi rend="i">Rights of Men</hi>, Wollstonecraft upbraids Edmund Burke
                        for using “sentimental jargon, which has long been current in
                        conversation, and even in books of morals, though it never received the 
<hi rend="i">regal</hi> stamp of reason” “(62; all italics in
                        the original henceforth unless noted otherwise). She identifies this jargon
                        as an expression of blatant “<hi rend="i">sensibility</hi>,”
                        which she attacks for making men “resigned to their fate” and
                        unable “to labour to increase human happiness by extirpating error,
                        [which] is a manly godlike affection” (89). Sentimentalism values
                        “sympathetic emotion” and “mechanical instinctive
                        sensations” so much that it interferes with reason and active virtue.
                        Wollstonecraft also finds that sentimentalism has created a split between
                        and within the sexes, which has in turn corrupted society. Responding to the
                        excesses of sentiment in 
<pb id="p39-64" n="64"/>
Burke’s 
<hi rend="i">Reflections</hi>, she ridicules this “good natured
                        man” for the “<hi rend="i">amiable</hi> weakness of his
                        mind” (81). But the man of feeling is only one male creature crawling
                        out of the sentimental swamp, for “mild affectionate sensibility only
                        renders a man more ingeniously cruel” (79), thus creating overly
                        malicious as well as overly weak men.</p>
          <p>In the <hi rend="i">Rights of Woman</hi>, Wollstonecraft especially laments
                        how women “become the prey of their senses, delicately termed
                        sensibility”—she calls them mere “creatures of
                        sensation”—as a result of “Novels, music, poetry, and
                        gallantry” (177). Just as men are made either weak or cruel by
                        sentimentalism, so women are made “either abject slaves or capricious
                        tyrants” (158). The latter exhibit “artificial
                        weakness” and have “a propensity to tyrannize” with
                        their “cunning” in order to “excite desire” in
                        men, who in their own right need to become “more chaste”
                        (113). But, deluded by sentimental notions of ideal feminine chastity, men
                        force women to be chaste and yet indulge themselves in novels,
                        “whilst men carry the same vitiated taste into life, and fly for
                        amusement to the wanton” after abandoning virtue (333). Clearly,
                        Wollstonecraft recognizes how “the reveries of the stupid
                        novelists” foster the debilitating “romantic twist of the
                        mind, which has been very properly termed <hi rend="i">sentimental</hi>” (330). But
when she speaks of a poet or artist
                        “vibrating with each emotion” as he/she works (309) or makes
                        her own impassioned appeals to sensibility (rational here, more traditional
                        in her novels), it is hard not to see the continued influence of
                        sentimentalism even on this radical writer.</p>
          <p>Ackland is convincing, then, as he traces Blake’s “protracted
                        exploration of embattled sexuality” to Wollstonecraft (172), but he
                        misses the strong critique of sentimentalism in Wollstonecraft’s
                        treatises and in Blake’s poetry. Judith Lee comes much closer when
                        she points to Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Rights of Woman</hi>
                        “as a paradigm for [Blake’s] portrayal of women in an attempt
                        to resolve the contradictions between traditional stereotypes and his
                        revolutionary vision” (132). Sentimentalism is, I think, a key
                        concern in Blake’s writings because he addresses all of the major
                        problems that fellow radicals found in this movement: sexual tensions,
                        weakened or tyrannical men, victimized or manipulative women, and a system
                        of self-indulgent suffering. We can see such problems in <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas</hi>, which treats contemporary social conditions in
                        cosmological, mythological, and psychological terms.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> At the most basic thematic level, Albion’s
                        fragmentation into the four Zoas and their further fragmentation into
                        warring male and female identities point to what recent critics are
                        beginning to see as a consequence of sentimentalism. According to Marshall
                        Brown, “The sensible self is an unfathomable mystery,” whose
                        “Protean fragmentation” eighteenth-century writers treat at
                        great length (86). Because sentimentality “reduces self as well as
                        society to pure sentiment,” a “fragmentation of
                        personality” results “that forces us to adopt Sentimental
                        responses” and puts us at the mercy of our senses and emotions (Allen
                        128, 122). The fragmentation of the sentimental self is also related to the
                        divisions of the sexes in sentimental literature in a continual interplay of
                        cause and effect, making it nearly impossible to pinpoint one as cause or
                        effect. Similarly, for Blake, “sexual identity is the most defining
                        yet problematic aspect of selfhood” (Bruder 183), and Albion’s
                        self becomes both sexed and problematic with the fall. Blake’s
                        awareness of the sexual nature of selfhood helps us to answer our question
                        of how the two sexes in his mythology relate his work to sentimental
                        literature: the personalities and behaviors of Blake’s characters
                        often seem to exhibit some of the trademarks of sentimentalism. In turn, the
                        presence of sentimentality within the fallen world marks it as such, a sign
                        that the androgynous Eternal Self has divided into two separate, alienated
                        sexes. Blake’s starting point in the myth of fragmented Albion thus
                        projects the personal and social consequences of sentimentalism to a cosmic
                        level and defines them as concomitant with the fall. <note id="n12">12.
                            Marshall Brown argues that Blake “resolutely continued the vein
                            of sensibility,” struggling to “convert the psychic
                            economy of sensibility directly into a blinding vision of universal
                            truth” (103). I feel that Brown is a little too enthusiastic and
                            misses Blake’s evident criticisms of sentimentalism, as well as
                            the importance of the “psychic economy” evident in the
                            fourfold myth of the Zoas, which are interdependent—harmoniously
                            in Eternity and discordantly when fallen. Nevertheless, Brown’s
                            argument remains plausible in light of a letter that Blake wrote to his
                            patron William Hayley on 16 July 1804 (and so after his time at
                            Felpham). Thanking Hayley for some books, Blake writes, “[Samuel]
                            Richardson has won my heart I will again read Clarissa &amp;c they must
                            be admirable I was too hasty in my perusal of them to percieve all their
                            beauty” (E 754). Blake’s statement here seems to put him
                            entirely in sympathy with the sentimentality expressed (and codified) by
                            Richardson, which could make him less likely to criticize sentimentalism
                            in his writings. It also suggests that, despite engraving illustrations
                            for sentimental authors (and perhaps reading some of their works along
                            the way?), Blake actually read sentimental literature long after
                            beginning his poem <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi> But because of this relative
                            lateness, the majority of the poem itself still may be imbued with the
                            radical spirit and its critique of sentimentalism as both a literary and
                            a cultural phenomenon; later material, such as Night VIII, may be in
                            question. In addition, we should also consider Blake’s audience.
                            Blake’s positive comments on Richardson’s novels, sent by
                            Hayley with other books, may reflect his appreciation for
                            Hayley’s continuing support. This is not to charge Blake with
                            disingenuousness or to ignore his obviously favorable response, but I
                            think it is important to recognize that his opinions and views expressed
                            in letters may at times be complicated. Finally, Blake’s
                            sentiments here also may be part of his personal development that
                            culminated in a renewal of distinctly Christian vision in 1804, which he
                            recounts in a letter to Hayley on 23 October 1804 (E 756-57) and which
                            might make him more “susceptible” to the piety expressed
                            by Richardson’s heroines. Taking into account all of these
                            factors, I think that we must rely primarily on internal evidence from
                                <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> to gauge Blake’s views on
                            sentimentalism as they developed over the course of the poem’s
                            composition and revision.</note></p>
          <p>Indeed, the opening scene of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> resembles many
                        scenes in sentimental fiction. The action begins “with Tharmas Parent
                        power” pouring out a flood of sorrow: 
						<q> Lost! Lost! Lost! are my
                            Emanations Enion O Enion<lb/>
 We are become a Victim to the Living We
                            hide in secret<lb/>
 I have hidden Jerusalem in Silent Contrition O Pity
                            Me<lb/>
 I will build thee a Labyrinth also O pity me (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 4:7-10, E 301) </q>
	<pb id="p39-65" n="65"/>
            <figure n="BB209.1.5.MS" rend="file" width="747" height="1000">
				<figTranscr>In Eden, Females sleep the winter in soft silken veils<lb/>
					Woven by their own hands to hide them in the darksom grave<lb/>
					But Males immortal live renewd by female deaths. in soft<lb/>
					Delight they die &amp; they revive in spring with music &amp; songs<lb/>
					Enion said Farewell I die I hide. from thy searching eyes<lb/>
					<lb/>
					So saying—From her bosom weaving soft in Sinewy threads<lb/>
					A tabernacle for Jerusalem she sat among the Rocks<lb/>
					Singing her lamentation. Tharmas groand among his Clouds<lb/>
					Weeping, then bending from his Clouds he stoopd his innocent head<lb/>
					And stretching out his holy hand in the vast Deep sublime<lb/>
					Turnd round the circle of Destiny with tears &amp; bitter sighs<lb/>
					And said. Return O Wanderer when the Day of Clouds is oer<lb/>
					<lb/>
					So saying he sunk down into the sea a pale white corse<lb/>
					In torment he sunk down &amp; flowd among her filmy Woof<lb/>
					His Spectre issuing from his feet in flames of fire<lb/>
					In gnawing pain drawn out by her lovd fingers every nerve<lb/>
					She counted. every vein &amp; lacteal threading them among<lb/>
					Her woof of terror. Terrified &amp; drinking tears of woe<lb/>
					Shuddring she wove—nine days &amp; nights Sleepless her food was tears<lb/>
					Wondring she saw her woof begin to animate. &amp; not<lb/>
					<lb/>
					As Garments woven subservient to her hands but having a will	<lb/>
					Of its own perverse &amp; wayward Enion lovd &amp; wept<lb/>
					<lb/>
					Nine days she labourd at her work. &amp; nine dark sleepless nights<lb/>
					But on the tenth trembling morn the Circle of Destiny Complete<lb/>
					Round rolld the Sea Englobing in a watry Globe self balancd<lb/>
					A Frowning Continent appeard Where Enion in the Desart<lb/>
					Terrified in her own Creation viewing her woven shadow<lb/>
					Sat in a dread intoxication of Repentance &amp; Contrition<lb/>
					<lb/>
					{He spurnd Enion with his foot he sprang aloft in Clouds<lb/>
					Alighting in his drunken joy in a far distant Grove}<lb/>
					<lb/>
					There is from Great Eternity a mild &amp; pleasant rest<lb/>
					Namd Beulah a Soft Moony Universe feminine lovely<lb/>
					Pure mild &amp; Gentle given in Mercy to those who sleep<lb/>
					Eternally. Created by the Lamb of God around<lb/>
					On all sides within &amp; without the Universal Man<lb/>
					The Daughters of Beulah follow sleepers in all their Dreams<lb/>
					Creating Spaces lest they fall into Eternal Death<lb/>
					The Circle of Destiny complete they gave to it a Space<lb/>
					And namd the Space Ulro &amp; brooded over it in care &amp; love<lb/>
					<lb/>
					They said The Spectre is in every man insane &amp; most<lb/>
					Deformd Thro the three heavens descending in fury &amp; fire<lb/>
					We meet it with our Songs &amp; loving blandishments &amp; give<lb/>
					To it a form of vegetation But this Spectre of Tharmas<lb/>
					Is Eternal Death What shall we do O God pity &amp; help<lb/>
					So spoke they &amp; closd the Gate of the Tongue in trembling fear<lb/>
					<lb/>
					What have I done! said Enion accursed wretch! What deed.<lb/>
					Is this a deed of Love I know what I have done. I know<lb/>
					Too late now to repent. Love is changd to deadly Hate<lb/>
					A[ll] life is blotted out &amp; I alone remain possessd with Fears<lb/>
					I see the Shadow of the dead within my Soul wandering<lb/>
					In darkness &amp; solitude forming Seas of Doubt &amp; rocks of Repentance<lb/>
					Already are my Eyes reverted. all that I behold<lb/>
					Within my Soul has lost its splendor &amp; a brooding Fear<lb/>
					Shadows me oer &amp; drives me outward to a world of woe<lb/>
					So waild she trembling before her own Created Phantasm<lb/>
					<lb/>
					{Who animating times on times by the Force of her sweet song}<lb/>
					{But standing on the Rocks her woven shadow glowing bright}<lb/>
					<lb/>
					Reard</figTranscr>
				<head>1. William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (British Library manuscript Add. 39764), page
5.</head>
				<figDesc>All reproductions by permission of the British Library.</figDesc>
			</figure>
								<pb id="p39-66" n="66"/>
Tharmas concludes his grief (temporarily) by
                        saying, “The Men have recieved their death wounds &amp; their
                        Emanations are fled / To me for refuge &amp; I cannot turn them out for
                        Pitys sake” (4:15-16, E 301). With his repetition of
                        “Pity” and his sense of victimization, it seems as if we are
                        meeting a true man of feeling. Moreover, Tharmas appears “Trembling
                        &amp; pale” as he sits “weeping in his clouds” (4:28,
                        E 301), which the illustration for page 5 depicts clearly enough (illus. 1;
                        note the presence of the water, perhaps a “sea of tears”?).
                        His debilitating “Despair” leads him to fear “self
                        murder” (4:37-38, E 302), as if his sympathy for the Emanations is so
                        strong that he cannot survive it. Tharmas’s ensuing inability to
                        act—which so often happens to a weakened, effeminate man of
                        feeling—occurs many times throughout the poem, as for example when he
                        argues with Los in Night IV and suffers an emotional chiasmus of tears,
                        wrath, pity (“with many a sigh”!), wrath again, and then more
                        tears (48:21-24, E 332). Since Tharmas is usually interpreted as the senses
                        and “the organizing principle of the self” (Damrosch 141), his
                        condition is a terrible and consistent indicator of the state of things in
                        Albion and in the poem.</p>
          <p>So here we have Tharmas, the sensory bedrock of humanity and the first male
                        character we meet in the fallen world, pouring out his sea of tears and
                        bewailing the pity that washes over him. And in the same opening scene,
                        Tharmas’s Emanation Enion responds affectively to his woe with her
                        equally troubled emotions. “Thy fear has made me tremble thy terrors
                        have surrounded me,” she says, and these terrors lead her to expect
                        (or resign herself to?) destruction: “I am almost Extinct &amp; soon
                        shall be a Shadow in Oblivion / Unless some way can be found that I may look
                        upon thee &amp; live” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 4:17, 22-23, E 301).
                        This threatening loss of identity manifests the serious danger of excess
                        sentiment pointed out by Brown and Allen. Enion’s affective sympathy
                        for, and with, Tharmas is so complete that it puts her under the control of
                        her feelings, leaving her unable to maintain her sense of self against the
                        onrushing tide of his woe and fear. Although Enion cries out to him, he is
                        powerless to help her, completely divided and himself a victim of
                        humanity’s disorder. He can only turn “round the circle of
                        Destiny” before sinking “down into the sea a pale white corse
                        / In torment” and flowing “among [Enion’s] filmy
                        Woof” (5:11, 13-14, E 302). The direct result of this dissolution is
                        even more tragic: the Spectre of Tharmas (“insane &amp; most /
                        Deformd” [5:38-39, E 303]) is born from his corpse and is clothed by
                        Enion’s <hi rend="i">laboring</hi> for “Nine days” and
                        “nine dark sleepless nights” at her loom (5:23, E 302). In his
                        spectrous form, Tharmas becomes a tyrannical male, “pure” and
                        “Exalted in terrific Pride,” while describing Enion as a
                        “Diminutive husk &amp; shell” and as “polluted”
                        (6:8-10, E 303). As with so many persecuted heroines of sentimental fiction,
                        her pollution does not dissuade him from “Mingling his horrible
                        brightness with her tender limbs,” a rape that in turn transforms her
                        into “a bright wonder that Nature shudder’d at / Half Woman
                        &amp; half Spectre” (7:8-10, E 304)—and then into a
                        mother.</p>
          <p>This first scene of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> incorporates three of the
                        most prominent sentimental stereotypes: the weakened man of feeling, the
                        abused woman driven to destruction, and the brutally abusive male, a cast
                        hearkening back to that of <hi rend="i">Visions.</hi> One example of a
                        comparable interaction between such types appears in Mackenzie’s <hi rend="i">The
Man of Feeling</hi>, which shows that these gender
                        stereotypes are both sentimental in nature and part of a sentimental
                        exchange system.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> The scene in question
                        occurs when Miss Atkins, a prostitute, narrates her woeful tale to the hero,
                        Harley. In this sentimental economy, the price of goods is paid with tears,
                        so Harley dutifully weeps himself to the point of being dumb, which in turn
                        causes Miss Atkins’s “fortitude . . . to fail at the
                        sight” (Mackenzie 50). Although the bartering begins with the woman
                        here, the affective exchange of a sad story and subsequent emotional
                        responses is similar to that in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>:
                        Tharmas’s lament, Enion’s fearful answer, and Tharmas’s
                        dissolution into Enion’s woof. When Miss Atkins’s father
                        bursts into the room and explodes with rage over the lost honor of his
                        daughter, we see the sort of antagonistic male that Blake transforms into
                        the Spectre of Tharmas. Miss Atkins, having established her status as victim
                        in her tale, faces further hardship as she falls “prostrate at [her
                        father’s] feet” and <hi rend="i">begs</hi> him for “the
                        death she deserves.” Unlike Blake’s Spectre, however, Miss
                        Atkins’s father “burst[s] into tears” and does not
                        punish (or rape!) her. Matters end happily when even this hostile male
                        “[mingles] his tears with hers” (51). Despite the different
                        endings—an exemplary sentimental encounter in the novel versus a
                        critical representation of sentimentalism’s dark side in the
                        poem—both Mackenzie and Blake depict how characters influence each
                        other through an exchange of sentiment, and both do so by using three
                        sentimental stereotypes. <note id="n13">13. According to Barker-Benfield,
                            Smith’s social-exchange sentimentalism provided a major source
                            for Mackenzie: “Mackenzie lived in the Edinburgh of Hume and
                            Smith and his novels preached the latter’s theory of moral
                            sentiments” (142).</note></p>
          <p>Perhaps an even more striking instance of sentimental
                        “exchange” between characters in <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi> comes at the end of Night II. This scene opens with Los and
                        Enitharmon sowing contention between Urizen and Ahania as Enion laments and
                        Urizen—having already puffed himself up as “God the terrible
                        destroyer &amp; not the Saviour”—watches helplessly in dread
                            (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 12:26, E 307). Los begins with a self-pitying
                        account of being “forsaken” and “mockd” by the
                        very lowest creatures in nature (34:21, E 323). Less than sympathetic,
                        Enitharmon calls him her “slave,” paradoxically
                        “strong” while she is “weak” (34:46, E 323).
                        Because Los had earlier abused Enitharmon and then repented out of pity for
                        her suffering (11:3, E 306; 12:40-43, E 307), his subsequent
                        “enslavement” to her shows a remarkable parallel to
                        Wollstonecraft’s point about apparently weak, sentimental women often
                        being made tyrants by male oppression. Los has certainly fallen under
                        Enitharmon’s newfound power, for he can only languish “in deep
                        sobs . . . till dead he also fell” when she deserts him (34:54, E
                        323). Blake accentuates the 
<pb id="p39-67" n="67"/>
cunning nature of her
                        control, labeling her song of exaltation over Los’s grief a
                        “Rapturous delusive trance” produced by her delight at having
                        power over Los and other men (34:93, E 324). Responsive to his
                        counterpart’s rising emotions, Los revives through the song and finds
                        sufficient energy to drive Enion and Ahania (her female rivals?)
                        “into the deathful infinite” (34:97, E 324). This situation
                        exemplifies what Wollstonecraft so zealously argues, that sentimentality
                        pushes the sexes apart and fosters a system of emotional manipulation and
                        physical cruelty based on their gender differences.</p>
          <p>In this same scene, Enion utters her famous “Experience” lament
                        and paints a series of pathetic pictures such as “the dog . . . at
                        the wintry door, the ox in the slaughter house” and “the
                        captive in chains &amp; the poor in the prison, &amp; the soldier 
						<figure n="BB209.1.37.MS" rend="file" width="778" height="1000">
							<figTranscr>{1}<lb/>
							19<lb/>
							{18}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							VALA<lb/>
							Night the {Fourth} Third<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Now sat the King of Light on high upon his starry throne<lb/>
							And bright Ahania bow’d herself before his splendid feet<lb/>
							<lb/>
							O Urizen look on Me. {thy Wife, that} like a mournful stream<lb/>
							I Embrace{s} round thy knees &amp; wet{s her} My bright hair with {her} my tears:<lb/>
							Why sighs my Lord! are not the morning stars thy obedient Sons<lb/>
							Do they not bow their bright heads at thy voice? at thy command<lb/>
							Do they not fly into their stations &amp; return their light to thee<lb/>
							The immortal Atmospheres are thine, there thou art seen in glory<lb/>
							Surrounded by the ever changing Daughters of the Light<lb/>
							{Thou sitst in harmony for God hath set thee over all}<lb/>
							Why wilt thou look upon futurity darkning present joy<lb/>
							She ceas’d the Prince his light obscurd &amp; the splendors of his crown<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Infolded</figTranscr>
							<head>2. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 37.</head>
						</figure>
						in the field” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 36:4-10, E 325); these
                        are all sufferers whom she identifies and sympathizes with, in contrast to
                        those who rejoice in and ignore the misery. The affective power of
                        Enion’s song is clear, for Ahania hears and, as if haunted by the
                        images in Enion’s lament, “never from that moment could . . .
                        rest upon her pillow” (36:19, E 326). But when Ahania comes to Urizen
                        in the opening of Night III, it seems that Enion’s weakness (she
                        sings from “the margin of Non Entity” [36:17, E 326]) has also
                        affected her: Ahania subjects herself before Urizen’s throne,
                        pleading with her male counterpart in vain (illus. 2). While the sentimental
                        imagery employed by the Emanations in their songs is worth noting, more
                        important is the way in which the characters affect each other with that
                        imagery. Los cries and dies, Enitharmon sings in pride and 
						<pb id="p39-68" n="68"/>
						<figure n="BB209.1.8.MS" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
							<figTranscr>{4}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							6<lb/>
							Till with fierce pain she brought forth on the rocks her sorrow &amp; woe<lb/>
							Behold two little Infants wept upon the desolate wind.<lb/>
							{Then forms of horror howld}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							The first state weeping they began &amp; helpless as a wave<lb/>
							Beaten along its sightless way growing enormous in its motion to<lb/>
							Its utmost goal, till strength from Enion like richest summer shining<lb/>
							Raisd the bright {fierce} boy &amp; girl with glories from their heads out beaming<lb/>
							Drawing forth drooping mothers pity drooping mothers sorrow<lb/>
							<lb/>
							{But those in Great Eternity Met in the Council of God<lb/>
							As One Man hovering over Gilead &amp; Hermon<lb/>
							He is the Good Shepherd He is the Lord &amp; Master<lb/>
							To Create Man Morning by Morning to Give gifts at Noon day<lb/>
							Enion brooded, oer the rocks, the rough rocks groaning vegetate<lb/>
							Such power was given to the Solitary wanderer.<lb/>
							The barked Oak, the long limbd Beech; the Ches’nut tree; the Pine.<lb/>
							The Pear tree mild, the frowning Walnut, the sharp Crab, &amp; Apple sweet,<lb/>
							The rough bark opens; twittering peep forth little beaks &amp; wings<lb/>
							The Nightingale, the Goldfinch, Robin, Lark, Linnet &amp; Thrush<lb/>
							The Goat leap’d from the craggy cliff, the Sheep awoke from the mould<lb/>
							Upon its green stalk rose the Corn, waving innumerable<lb/>
							Infolding the bright Infants from the desolating winds}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							They sulk upon her breast her hair became like snow on mountains<lb/>
							Weaker &amp; weaker, weeping woful, wearier and wearier<lb/>
							Faded &amp; her bright Eyes decayd melted with pity &amp; love</figTranscr>
							<head>3. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 8.</head>
						</figure>
						revives him, Enion wails over Los’s antagonism, and Ahania
                        is moved to seek her counterpart in meekness. Much as he does in Night I,
                        when Tharmas melts into Enion’s woof and is immediately reborn as his
                        own antithesis (the hypocritical rapist Spectre), Blake here problematizes
                        our sympathetic identification with these characters, which is likely to be
                        our first reaction. Forced to question our emotional, heartfelt response, we
                        may also begin to question the validity of all such responses and their
                        causes. Further, Blake shows just how complicit each type of character is in
                        the suffering of the others, how they actually transform <hi rend="i">into</hi> each
other, and how they instigate each other’s
                        actions. The sentimental system of affective responsiveness is not only a
                        system of exploitation, but also a system to be exploited for selfish ends
                        rather than benevolent community building. And, as we saw above, the
                        novelist’s system of suffering feeds itself: just as every Clarissa
                        needs a Lovelace to threaten (and thus make manifest) her pathetic heroism,
                        so every Oothoon needs a Bromion and every Enion needs a Spectre of
                        Tharmas.</p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, sentimentalism is not only problematic
                        because of its fracturing, exploitative tendencies; it is also consistently
                        negative because of the “feminine” or
                        “feminizing” qualities that many eighteenth-century critics
                        decried. Fallen life is, in many ways, “sentimental” for Blake
                        because 
						<pb id="p39-69" n="69"/>
						<figure n="BB209.1.9.MS" rend="file" width="792" height="1000">
							<figTranscr>5<lb/>
							<lb/>
							{7}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							{embracd for}<lb/>
							{love}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							And then they wanderd far away she sought for them in vain<lb/>
							In weeping blindness stumbling she followd them oer rocks &amp; mountains<lb/>
							Rehumanizing from the Spectre in pangs of maternal love<lb/>
							Ingrate they wanderd scorning her drawing her {life; ingrate} Spectrous Life<lb/>
							Repelling her away &amp; away by a dread repulsive power     100<lb/>
							Into Non Entity revolving round in dark despair.<lb/>
							{Till they had drawn the Spectre quite away from Enion}<lb/>
							And drawing in the Spectrous life in pride and haughty joy<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Thus Enion gave them all her spectrous life {in dark despair}<lb/>
							Then {Ona} Eno a daughter of Beulah took a Moment of Time<lb/>
							And drew it out to {twenty years} Seven thousand years with much care &amp; affliction<lb/>
							And many tears &amp; in the {twenty} Every years {gave visions toward heaven} made windows into
Eden<lb/>
							She also took an atom of space &amp; opend its center<lb/>
							Into Infinitude &amp; ornamented it with wondrous art<lb/>
							Astonishd sat her Sisters of Beulah to see her soft affections<lb/>
							To Enion &amp; her children &amp; they ponderd these things wondring<lb/>
							And they Alternate kept watch over the Youthful terrors<lb/>
							They saw not yet the Hand Divine for it was not yet reveald<lb/>
							But they went on in Silent Hope &amp; Feminine repose<lb/>
							<lb/>
							But Los &amp; Enitharmon delighted in the Moony spaces of {Ona} Eno<lb/>
							Nine Times they livd among the forests, feeding on sweet fruits<lb/>
							And nine bright Spaces wanderd weaving mazes of delight<lb/>
							Snaring the wild Goats for their milk they eat the flesh of Lambs<lb/>
							A male &amp; female naked &amp; ruddy as the pride of summer<lb/>
							<lb/>
							p. 8<lb/>
							Ellis<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Alternate Love &amp; Hate his breast; hers Scorn &amp; Jealousy<lb/>
							{They kissd not for shame they embracd not}<lb/>
							In embryon passions. they kiss’d not nor embrac’d for shame &amp; fear     150<lb/>
							{Nor kissd nor em[braced]}<lb/>
							{hand in hand in a Sultry paradise}<lb/>
							{these Lovers swum the deep}<lb/>
							His head beamd light &amp; in his vigorous voice was prophecy<lb/>
							He could controll the times &amp; seasons, &amp; the days &amp; years<lb/>
							She could controll the spaces, regions, desart, flood &amp; forest<lb/>
							<lb/>
							But had no power to weave a Veil of covering for her Sins<lb/>
							She drave the Females all away from Los<lb/>
							And Los drave all the Males from her away<lb/>
							<lb/>
							They wanderd long, till they sat down upon the margind sea.<lb/>
							Conversing with the visions of Beulah in dark slumberous bliss<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Night the Second<lb/>
							<lb/>
							{Nine years they view the turning spheres {of Beulah} reading the Visions of Beulah}<lb/>
							But the two youthful wonders wanderd in the world of Tharmas<lb/>
							Thy name is Enitharmon; said the {bright} fierce prophetic boy<lb/>
							{While they} {Harmony}<lb/>
							While thy mild voice fills all these Caverns with sweet harmony<lb/>
							O how {thy} our Parents sit &amp; {weep} mourn in their silent secret bowers</figTranscr>
							<head>4. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 9.</head>
						</figure>
						“it is inseparable from the world of Generation, of mothers
                        and weeping babies, of the matter and substance which are supposed to be
                        nonentity but in fact seem all too real” (Damrosch 170). Mothers and
                        weeping babies are the stock in trade of sentimentalism, prototypically weak
                        creatures that so easily provoke affective responses. Thus, Blake
                        consistently associates sentimental images of birth, children, the family,
                        and nature with “vegetating” and the continual fall from
                        Eternity. The birth of Los and Enitharmon after Enion’s rape in Night
                        I is ostensibly a moment of potential happiness. Indeed, the illustration on
                        page 8 (illus. 3) depicts a rather beautiful image of two tiny babes
                        suckling their smiling mother’s breasts. But the text makes clear
                        that these babes are the physical manifestations of Enion’s
                        “sorrow &amp; woe” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 8:1, E 304). They
                        exploit her “drooping mothers pity” and, “in pride and
                        haughty joy,” they draw her “Into Non Entity” as she
                        gives “them all her spectrous life” (8:7-9:8, E 304), a
                        situation depicted in the very next illustration (illus. 4).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> In addition, Enitharmon’s song
                            <pb id="p39-70" n="70"/>
over the dead Los in Night II includes images
                        of nature and the “weeping babe,” and when she exclaims,
                        “For every thing that lives is holy,” the context throws a
                        remarkably negative light on this famous Blakean assertion (34:81, 34:80, E
                            324).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> As
Enitharmon sings of her
                        new power and her desire for control, following as it does the problematic
                        portrayal of her and Los’s birth, it is hard to join in and exclaim
                        that physical life is indeed “holy.” <note id="n14">14. Blake
                            washed a passage from this scene that more closely associates the birth
                            of the children with animal and vegetable life, all of which relate to
                            the verb “vegetate” (see E 823-24). Although likely
                            meaning to cancel this passage, Blake associates physical birth with
                            “vegetating” elsewhere, such as with the “vegetated
                            body” (104:37, E 378).</note>
	<note id="n15">15. This assertion is used much more positively at the close
                            of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (plate 27, E 45),
                            in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (8:10, E 51),
                            and in <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi> (8:13, E 54).</note></p>
          <p>The birth of Orc in Night V is particularly troubling in this respect. In
                        reaction to Orc’s too-close relationship with his mother Enitharmon,
                        Los the father “bound down her loved Joy” with “the
                        chain of Jealousy” out of “Love of Parent Storgous Appetite
                        Craving” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 60:22-61:10, E 341). However, both
                        parents suffer “all the sorrow Parents feel” and return in
                        vain to free their son; even the narrator is overcome, only capable of
                        making a trademark sentimental comment to the reader: “all their
                        lamentations / I write not here but all their after life was
                        lamentation” (62:10, E 342; 63:8-9, E 343). Once again, Blake makes
                        it impossible for us to feel true sympathy for his characters. As in
                        “Infant Sorrow,” we react negatively to these parents because
                        of their complicity in their bound child’s suffering; nor can we
                        fully sympathize with the child Orc, since birth itself is suspect as a
                        continual fragmentation of fragments. Rather than encourage our sympathy
                        with parents or child, Blake exploits sentimental conventions in order to
                        call them into question, here with babes and weeping parents as
                        representations of the <hi rend="i">basis</hi> of sentimentality, the
                        physical or “vegetated” body itself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n16">16. The problematic nature of childbirth in a world of
                            systematized sexuality is an enduring concern for Blake. David Aers
                            notes that, in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, “The activity of
                            begetting children is . . . engulfed in [a] closed world and the
                            infant’s sexual life is doomed [in the] ghastly circle of
                            ‘The Mental Traveller’” (“Blake: Sex,
                            Society and Ideology” 30).</note></p>
          <p>When in Night II Blake describes how “Luvah was cast into the Furnaces
                        of affliction &amp; sealed” while “Vala fed in cruel delight,
                        the furnaces with fire” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 25:40-41, E 317), he
                        shows how the war between the fallen sexes is itself the reason why birth in
                        the fallen world is vegetative and deformative.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> Once again, we can see here the sentimental system at work,
                        with a male subjected to a cruel, cunning female whom he himself
                        “nurturd” and “fed . . . with my rains &amp;
                        dews” until she mutated from an “Earth-worm” to
                        “A scaled Serpent” to “a Dragon” to “a
                        little weeping Infant” (26:7-27:2, E 317). Although this male figure
                        pities a smaller, fragile creature (the worm), his actions are part of a
                        system that transforms pitiable and sentimental objects into deadly dragons.
                        Indeed, his complicity is obvious (albeit not to him), for he proudly calls
                        himself the “King” of the female as he narrates her
                        metamorphosis (26:5, E 317). The sexual symbolism and tension in this
                        passage are powerful, becoming almost disturbing in the illustration of
                        deformed sexual creatures accompanying it (illus. 5).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> Blake also presents a situation that Wollstonecraft
                        describes in her attack on sentimental literature: male oppression,
                        especially in the form of improper education and reading, produces conniving
                        women who exploit male desire so as to gain power. Blake, however,
                        articulates this argument in nightmare images. The females in Blake’s
                        fallen world are, like Wollstonecraft’s, most often either helpless
                        or deceitful, while the males are weak, hypocritical, or cruel. Despite
                        sentimental sympathies, there is no true harmony. <note id="n17">17.
                            “Infant Sorrow” is again a helpful parallel, exemplifying
                            how tensions between parents are directly “reborn” in
                            their offspring.</note>
	<note id="n18">18. In this series of designs from manuscript p. 26, perhaps
                            the most famous and most reproduced, we can see breasts on the top
                            figure, a woman gripping an erased penis and scrotum in the next figure,
                            and a vagina in the next figure. Many other illustrations to the poem,
                            especially in Nights II and III, are even more dramatically
                            representative of the sexual strife that characterizes the fallen world.
                            These accompanying designs, with their various bodiless and fetishized
                            genitalia or their startling acts of copulation, only manifest and
                            intensify the fighting, frustrations, and entrapments that occur between
                            characters in the text.</note></p>
          <p>I have spoken of sentimentalism and its sexual strife as a negative, even
                        predatory “system” in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> because
                        I think that Blake compels us to see it in this way. Although characters of
                        both sexes are guilty of powermongering, sentimentalism by Blake’s
                        time is closely aligned with femininity. But Blake will not let us forget
                        that pity and sentimentality have also become bound up in a social
                        “law” operating under the moral law of Urizen, fallen reason.
                        The social exchanges of Adam Smith and “bartering” with tears
                        in <hi rend="i">The Man of Feeling</hi> are only two examples of what Blake
                        seems to recognize. Even worse, in fallen life, the Pity that has “a
                        human face” too easily becomes the hypocritical Pity that
                        “would be no more / If we did not make somebody Poor”
                        (“The Divine Image” 18:10, E 12; “The Human
                        Abstract” 47:1-2, E 27). Sympathy degenerates into a source of
                        control, not of affection.</p>
          <p>This law of sentimentality appears most explicitly in <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi> during Urizen’s travels in Nights VI and VII. In Night
                        VI, the tyrannical Urizen at one moment looks like a sympathetic character,
                        “Writing in bitter tears &amp; groans,” except that he writes
                        “in books of iron &amp; brass” containing his laws of moral
                        virtue (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 70:3, E 347). (It is inviting to see
                        Urizen’s tears and groans as part of what he writes, as if he were
                        truly codifying laws of sentimentality like one of Wollstonecraft’s
                        “stupid novelists.”) While doing so, he views “The
                        ruind spirits once his children &amp; the children of Luvah” in the
                        Abyss (70:6, E 347). In what follows, Blake again sets up a sentimental
                        tableau only to undercut it quickly. As if fed by Urizen’s woe, each
                        soul in the Abyss “partakes of [another’s] dire woes &amp;
                        mutual returns the pang” (70:16, E 347). Despite these affective
                        responses, which would potentially ease the terrors of the void, the
                        ultimate response is the outbreak of war! When Urizen later comes upon Orc
                        and expresses sympathy, the chained boy calls his bluff: “Curse thy
                        hoary brows. What dost thou in this deep / Thy Pity I contemn scatter thy
                        snows elsewhere” (78:42-43, E 354). But Urizen is persistent, 
						<pb id="p39-71" n="71"/>
						<figure n="BB209.1.26.MS" rend="file" width="792" height="1000">
							<figTranscr>6th page<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Vala incircle round the furnaces where Luvah was clos’d<lb/>
							In joy she heard his howlings, &amp; forgot he was her Luvah<lb/>
							With whom she walkd in bliss, in times of innocence &amp; youth<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Hear ye the voice of Luvah from the furnaces of Urizen<lb/>
							<lb/>
							20<lb/>
							Ellis<lb/>
							<lb/>
							If I indeed am {Luvahs Lord} Valas King &amp; ye O sons of Men<lb/>
							The workmanship of Luvahs hands; in times of Everlasting<lb/>
							When I calld forth the Earth-worm from the cold &amp; dark obscure<lb/>
							I nurturd her I fed her with my rains &amp; dews, she grew<lb/>
							A scaled Serpent, yet I fed her tho’ she hated me<lb/>
							Day after day she fed upon the mountains in Luvahs sight        50<lb/>
							I brought her thro’ the Wilderness, a dry &amp; thirsty land<lb/>
							And I commanded springs to rise for her in the black desart<lb/>
							{But} Till she became a {de[mon]} Dragon winged bright &amp; poisonous<lb/>
							I opend all the floodgates of the heavens to quench her thirst<lb/>
							<lb/>
							And<lb/>
							<lb/>
							BRITISH<lb/>
							MUSEUM</figTranscr>
							<head>5. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 26.</head>
						</figure>
						<pb id="p39-72" n="72"/>
and when he begins to instruct his captive audience
                        (Orc), the “Moral Duty” (80:3, E 355) that this lawgiver
                        expounds includes rules for manipulating the powerless and poor with false
                        shows of emotion until they are “as spaniels . . . taught with
                        art” (80:9-21, E 355). “Spaniels” could apply equally
                        to men of feeling and to helpless female victims in the “art”
                        “art” of sentimental literature. What is most interesting here
                        is that Urizen’s laws, his freezing “snows” of pity,
                        are the very same as Ahania’s “laws of obedience &amp;
                        insincerity,” which Urizen abhorred in Night III (43:10-11, E 329).
                        However, to be more accurate, Ahania’s laws are in fact
                        Urizen’s laws, since she is his feminine portion now separated from
                        him. Thus, when she confronted him in Night III with his own sublimated
                        laws, hoisting him on his own (phallic) petard, he reacted with typical
                        violence by throwing her “from his bosom” and “far into
                        Non Entity” (43:24-44:5, E 329).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref> Again we find the fragmented self and the sexes caught in a
                        sort of whirlpool of origins and causality. <note id="n19">19. See Otto on
                            the significance of the phallus in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and
                            its relation to Urizen’s religion/law.</note></p>
          <p>For Blake, all systems and laws, especially of morality and human behavior,
                        are threads in the web of Urizen and are thus dangerous. This is
                        particularly true of sentimentalism because, as Urizen’s lesson to
                        Orc in Night VII makes clear, affect can be manipulated for tyrannical ends
                        far too effectively. The “sexual code” of sentimental law is
                        also troubling in relation to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, since it
                        inculcated self-repressive “delicacy” even while praising
                        natural responses and maintaining an intimate association between that
                        virtue and sensual desire (Barker-Benfield 299; Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">Sex
                            and Sensibility</hi> 75). But sentimentalism is even more craven and
                        harmful when one engages in its practices for the wrong reasons. The case of
                        Los in Night IV illustrates this point. Los and Tharmas confront each other,
                        each recounting his tale of woe and pity at the separations that have
                        occurred, and then Tharmas bids Los to build the universe—that is, to
                        give Urizen a <hi rend="i">physical body.</hi> Completing his task in seven
                        ages of woe, Los sees the form that he has created and, “terrifid at
                        the shapes / Enslavd humanity put on <hi rend="i">he became what he
                            beheld</hi> / He became what he was doing he was himself
                        transformd” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 55:21-23, E 338; my italics).
                        Through Los’s calamity, Blake presents the ultimate danger of trying
                        to “enter into” another along the lines expounded by
                        sentimentalists, who based the act on a sympathetic reaction to another
                        individual’s worldly, visible hardship and, in the case of Smith,
                        connected it with social standing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
                        Because Los reacts to Urizen’s <hi rend="i">physical</hi> shape as it
                        forms before him, he cannot penetrate the suffering, pathetic body, and so
                        he gets trapped by the superficial. To become what one beholds in this way
                        “defines a lapse of imagination. It is a romantic figure of 
<hi rend="i">visionary</hi> catastrophe” (McGann 66; my italics), so
                        Los actually loses his vision and gets transfixed by pity and fear—he
                        himself becomes an object of physical suffering. Blake shows the
                        impossibility of Smith’s sentimental “entering into”
                        another by making Los a failed visionary, doomed by his own sympathy and
                        infected by the object of his pity. In terms of sentimentalism, this would
                        correspond to acting out of sympathetic benevolence but not looking deeper
                        into the causes of such suffering, an error that, Blake implies, drags the
                        sympathizer farther into the miserable (fallen) system. That is, it is
                        ineffective and essentially self-indulgent sympathy, emotion for its own
                        sake. For Blake, as we shall see, Los’s (physical rather than
                        visionary) response also corresponds to pitying the
                        “vegetated” body of error that suffers rather than the
                        spiritual individual within.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n20">20. Stephen Cox calls Smith’s <hi rend="i">Theory of
                                Mortal Sentiments</hi> “a treatise on the educational process
                            that enables people of sensibility to internalize social expectations
                            and incorporate them into consciousness, idealizing yet personalizing
                            them” (67).</note>
	<note id="n21">21. It is worth noting briefly here that the truly <hi rend="i">visionary</hi> “entering
into” others that
                            Los does and advocates in Blake’s later epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
reflects the central, heroic role that he gained in
                            Blake’s mythology from the minor Prophecies and <hi rend="i">The
                                Four Zoas</hi> to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
Los seems to have learned much between the
                            epics.</note></p>
          <p>Although sentimentality in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is a telltale sign
                        of fallenness, Blake’s attitude at times seems ambivalent, and he is
                        not wholly committed to exposing it as a Urizenic corruption. The deciding
                        factor is how it is used. Further, the connection of sentimentality to the
                        female Emanations does not automatically lead Blake to reject <hi rend="i">all</hi>
forms of sentiment as pernicious. Ahania and Enion play
                        crucial roles in the epic’s push toward regeneration precisely 
<hi rend="i">because</hi> of their emotional, affective, and sympathetic
                        natures (in contrast to Enitharmon and Vala, the manipulative females). They
                        are truly the most consistent voices calling for unity, while the males only
                        remind them of their emanated being, wallow in helpless self-pity, or lash
                        out in destructive wrath and war. Although these Emanations are raped,
                        beaten, and driven to non-existence for their efforts, they are like a
                        sentimental “glue” that keeps Albion’s fragments from
                        separating completely. Along with the song of Enion discussed above and her
                        first speech in Night I, in which she laments her separation from Tharmas,
                        Ahania’s speech to Urizen in the opening of Night III is significant.
                        Indeed, Ahania is the first character to speak of the “Eternal
                        Brotherhood” that has been lost, and she begs Urizen to
                        “Listen to her who loves thee lest we also are driven away”
                            (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 41:9, E 328; 42:8, E 328). Urizen, of course, will
                        have none of this, so her appeal gets her promptly cast into Non Entity.
                        Nevertheless, as the chaos within Albion grows ever more perilous, Ahania
                        and Enion lurk in the shadows as reminders of the real reason for the
                        suffering that every character endures.</p>
          <p>Interestingly, Ahania and Enion have positive roles by virtue of their
                        relation to nature and the fallen world. While this relationship reflects
                        the social (and sentimental) view associating the emotions and the physical
                        body with femininity, McGann points out that “the destructive nature
                        of nature” is also part of the Christian tradition Blake writes
                        within (151). As a result, nature has a “redemptive
                        mechanism”—hence the incarnation, <pb id="p39-73" n="73"/>
the
                        belief that the spiritual/divine is born through the corporeal body in order
                        to redeem it. In this respect, even Enitharmon and Vala (including her most
                        fallen forms, Rahab and Tirzah) are “positive” or
                        “redemptive.” As Ackland notes, Enitharmon’s
                        “realm is nature, and nature remains part of the Divine
                        Humanity”; even “the triumph of Vala [in Night VIII; see
                        below] can serve paradoxically as a prelude to apocalypse, for any
                        consolidation of error makes it more readily identifiable and
                        remediable” (180). The feminine realm of corporeality, physical
                        emotion, and sentiment is, like the fallen body of Albion that it comprises,
                        potentially redeemable, a stage (or even an early form of a Blakean
                        “State”) in the regenerative process.</p>
          <p>While McGann and Ackland are both correct in identifying the positive
                        function of the females and nature in Blake’s myth, Ackland in
                        particular is too prone to stress their “redemptive role” and
                        to miss the larger point that Blake makes with his use of Emanations and a
                        gendered, generative nature. Although he wrote poems like “On
                        Anothers Sorrow” and chided a cold, unfeeling culture, Blake was
                        equally aware that “Innocence” in the world is the state of
                        childhood, not of Eternity. Consequently, fallen existence is a reality, but
                        it is <hi rend="i">not</hi> a positive reality; it is a trap, a slumber or
                        death of Albion and every individual that must be overcome for a return to
                        Eternity. Again, it is all too easy in a fallen world to “become what
                        one beholds,” to see one’s vegetative body as the real body,
                        and to remain “dead.” In a society practicing the <hi rend="i">art</hi> of
sentiment, this lapse of spiritual vision becomes even
                        easier. Thus, sentimental pity and benevolence, however positive they may be
                        in ameliorating fallen hardship, are not enough for regeneration in
                        Blake’s works. For him, regeneration (poetic, personal, and
                        universal) requires <hi rend="i">inspired</hi> vision, which the weakening
                        and exploitative tendencies of sentimentalism, along with its reification of
                        the physical or natural, prevent. Social misery does gain Blake’s
                        critical attention, but, as Martin Price comments, “Blake is less
                        concerned with exposing injustice than with finding a vital response to
                        it” (401). In the examples I have discussed from <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas</hi> thus far, Blake has certainly exposed the problems
                        inherent in a system of sentiment, its part in the battle between the sexes,
                        and its use as a tool for oppression. And Ahania and Enion’s positive
                        sentimentality does not solve these problems, for it too is a product of the
                        fall; thus, they can only propose “facile modifications rather than
                        fundamental changes either in the behavior of the zoas or in their own
                        behavior” (Lee 134). The question, then, is how to move beyond the
                        sentimental world all together.</p>
          <p>We can answer this question by looking at the first step taken toward
                        Eternity in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> This moment comes with the
                        embrace of Los and the Spectre of Urthona in the conclusion of Night VIIa.
                        Although Blake’s incorporation of this material late in the
                        composition process creates many bibliographic, textual, and narrative
                        challenges, the scene is important here because it serves as a re-vision, in
                        both its success and its failure, of the sentimentality expressed thus far
                        in the poem. At this point in the plot, an unprecedented event occurs after
                        a vivid series of splits and unions and outbursts of the dead: 
						<q> But then
                            the Spectre enterd Los’s bosom Every sigh &amp; groan<lb/>
 Of
                            Enitharmon bore Urthonas Spectre on its wings<lb/>
 Obdurate Los felt
                            Pity Enitharmon told the tale<lb/>
 Of Urthona. Los embracd the Spectre
                            first as a brother<lb/>
 Then as another Self; astonishd humanizing
                            &amp; in tears<lb/>
 In Self abasement Giving up his Domineering
                            lust<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 95 [85]:26-31, E 367)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n22">22. Erdman’s edition contains an error for the
                                page numbering at this point: he prints “95 [87]” (E
                                367) for what should be “95 [85],” since the text is
                                from p. 85 of the manuscript. I have silently corrected the error in
                                subsequent citations.</note></q>
Enitharmon’s sighs and groans, as well as
her tale, seem to
                        precipitate this embrace, much as Los’s pity and tears do. The key,
                        however, is that Los embraces the Spectre “as another Self,”
                        perhaps implying that he sees the Spectre as a being who shares an intimate
                        bond with him, not as an <hi rend="i">object</hi> or <hi rend="i">other</hi>
                        whom he merely sympathizes with.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">23</ref> But
                        the Spectre speaks as a Spectre, calling himself Los’s “real
                        Self” (95 [85]:38, E 368) and Los a mere “form &amp; organ of
                        life” (86:2, E 368). Los responds furiously that he feels “a
                        World within / Opening its gates,” and he bids the Spectre to enter
                        his bosom <hi rend="i">with Enitharmon</hi> to learn “Peace”
                        and “repentance to Cruelty” (86:7-12, E 368). For the first
                        time, a male character urges action that is redemptive and
                        regenerative—and not out of simple pity, for himself or for another,
                        but because of something stronger “within.” <note id="n23">23.
                            As Dennis Welch points out to me, the meaning of “another
                            Self” is highly ambiguous here—is the Spectre an other
                            self or an aspect of Los’s self? The implication of
                            “humanizing” may also be important if we think of
                            Albion’s status as the “Universal Humanity,” so
                            that Los may be becoming eternally human rather than physically human;
                            compare Tharmas in Night IX (132:36ff., E 401). These instances of
                            ambiguity (so characteristic of Blake), along with the lateness of this
                            added passage, may help to explain why the embrace fails to initiate
                            regeneration directly.</note></p>
          <p>Unfortunately, the reunion of this fragmented fragment is incomplete because
                        (at least in part) “Enitharmon trembling fled &amp; hid beneath
                        Urizens tree” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 87:1, E 368). After she plays the
                        Eve to Los’s Adam and tempts him to eat the fruit of the Tree of
                        Mystery, all three of the characters fall into helpless self-blame for the
                        fall. But this is still a momentous occasion because Los experiences a
                        renewal, however fleeting, of vision. Continuing with his intimations of a
                        “World within,” he sees Enitharmon “like a shadow
                        withering / As on the outside of Existence” and tells her to
                        “look! behold! take comfort! / Turn inwardly thine Eyes &amp; there
                        behold the Lamb of God / Clothed in Luvahs robes of blood descending to
                        redeem” (87:41-44, E 369). The rest of this scene wavers between
                        positive and negative action, the latter most evident in Enitharmon’s
                        fear of the Lamb of God and her desire to use the spectres of the dead as
                        “ransoms” (98 [90]:24, E 370). But, after the ambiguous
                        refusal of Los and Enitharmon to sacrifice their children (discussed below),
                        Los draws Urizen out of the war raging around 
<pb id="p39-74" n="74"/>
them
                        and feels “love &amp; not hate,” beholding Urizen as
                        “an infant” in his hands (98 [90]:65-66, E 371). Los is now
                        able to envision the regenerated Urizen, to perceive the spiritual body
                        within the hoary old man who has been stirring up universal antagonism,
                        rather than the mere corporeal form.</p>
          <p>What this scene indicates is that sentimental sympathy is essentially
                        stagnant without Blakean vision. When Los appropriates sentimental qualities
                        like pity, benevolence, and a desire for reunion with his suffering
                        counterparts, he does so on the basis of his vision of “the Lamb of
                        God” within every individual, not just because those counterparts are
                        miserable. He sees their shared error and the need to rectify it. His
                        visionary moment may be fleeting, but it is truly the first indicator of a
                        potential regeneration to come. Blake’s use in this scene of the same
                        sentimental conventions and discourse that have caused so much trouble in
                        the earlier Nights serves to revitalize them, for they are now a part of
                        vision, inspiration, and prophecy—they introduce hope into a world
                        that is still fallen and at war.</p>
          <p>Because Los’s moment of vision in Night VIIa is powerful for the light
                        of hope it brings into <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, it seems fitting and
                        yet troubling that the next Night opens with the creation of Albion’s
                        fallen body and the descent of “the Lamb of God clothed in Luvahs
                        robes,” i.e., Jesus the Savior in physical form (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
                        101:1, E 373). The first moment of redemptive vision by Los the Eternal
                        Prophet serves as a catalyst, as it were, for the final consolidation of
                        error. Although Los can “behold the Divine Vision thro the broken
                        Gates / Of [Enitharmon’s] poor broken heart,” and Enitharmon
                        can “see the Lamb of God upon Mount Zion,” Urizen can only see
                        his enemy Luvah and gather forces for more war (99:15-17, E 372).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> Jesus comes as the “pitying
                        one” to “Assume the dark Satanic body” and to give
                        Albion “his vegetated body / [which is] To be cut off &amp;
                        separated [so] that the Spiritual body may be Reveald” (104:14, E
                        377; 104:13, E 377; 104:37-38, E 378), but this can only occur when human
                        existence has reached its nadir. In other words, Jesus must suffer
                        crucifixion by the forces of Mystery or Rahab, who is both a degenerated
                        form of Vala (the “Dragon” that Luvah nurtured and the
                        exemplar of a female tyrant) and the “Fruit of Urizens tree”
                        (109 [105]:20, E 378). This crucifixion is “the triumph of
                        Vala” (Ackland 180) and the final consolidation of error, the dead
                        body of Jesus providing the most visible form of error possible. <note id="n24">24. It
seems significant here that Los beholds the divine
                            vision <hi rend="i">through</hi> Enitharmon’s heart, again
                            intimating that he has gained the vision necessary to see into the
                            physical body to find the spiritual body within—and to see 
<hi rend="i">through</hi> that body to the divine. Enitharmon, on the
                            other hand, sees the Lamb of God as external, outside herself (and
                            others) at this point; only after weaving bodies for the spectres into
                            “the Female Jerusa[le]m the holy” can she see “the
                            Lamb of God within Jerusalems Veil” (104:1-2, E 376).</note></p>
          <p>Arguably, the crucifixion also largely results from the hypocritical system
                        of sentiment (moral law) that Rahab practices and Urizen inspires. The song
                        of the Females of Amalek, Rahab’s daughters, evidences Rahab and
                        Urizen’s hypocritical sentimentality at its most obvious, which seems
                        fitting in the context of this Night. “O thou poor human form O thou
                        poor child of woe / Why dost thou wander away from Tirzah why me compell to
                        bind thee,” the Females of Amalek sing over their bound victims,
                        terrifying them with knives <hi rend="i">and</hi> tears (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 109
[105]:31-32, E 378). Their song eerily recalls
                        Enion’s song in Night II, which makes the image of demonic,
                        knife-wielding singers even more startling; it also heightens our awareness
                        of how crocodile tears of pity can be frightfully hard to distinguish from
                        true tears. Blake later punctuates this ambiguity, making such crocodile
                        tears truly degenerative when Urizen’s pity for, and embrace of, the
                        Shadowy Female causes him to mutate into a scaly monster (106:22ff., E 381;
                        illustrated on page 70 of the manuscript).</p>
          <p>Blake problematizes sentimentality once again, here in the form that the
                        Females of Amalek give it, by directly following the song (as if the two
                        were causally related) with the crucifixion of the Lamb of God on the Tree
                        of Mystery, the tree of Rahab and Urizen (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 110
                        [106]:1-3, E 379). The sight is catastrophic, leaving even the newly
                        inspired Los “despairing of Life Eternal” while Rahab glories
                        “in Delusive feminine pomp questioning him” (110 [106]:16, E
                        379; 105 [113]:43, E 380). But Los struggles through his despair and
                        persists in advocating self-recognition and repentance even to Rahab,
                        speaking to her “with tenderness &amp; love not uninspird”
                        (105 [113]:44, E 380). His inspiration leads him to pity her <hi rend="i">for her
error</hi>, an error that he himself shares but can now work to
                        rectify (105 [113]:51-52, E 380). Although Rahab refuses to heed his words,
                        his hope remains. And later, when Ahania cries out at the death around her,
                        Enion seems to draw on Los’s hope as she comforts Ahania, her fellow
                        sufferer, with a prophecy of the universal return to “ancient
                        bliss” (114 [110]:28, E 385).</p>
          <p>These positive threads woven into the vegetated fabric of Night VIII are,
                        with the hypocritical and negative threads, all tied to sentimentalism, with
                        Los’s tear shed for Rahab’s stubborn persistence in error and
                        Enion’s sympathy for her companion in misery. But the proliferation
                        of the word “vision” in these events further emphasizes the
                        change that has occurred in that sentimentalism.
                        “Sentimentality,” as it is now practiced by Los the inspired
                        prophet, has in fact been remade into “vision” by being taken
                        to a spiritual level, by piercing the vegetated body in order to sympathize
                        with and work to redeem the trapped spiritual body.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> But the vegetated body remains, and the vegetated
                        things in the natural world that serve as the objects of systematized
                        sentiment have to be burned 
<pb id="p39-75" n="75"/>
away like the error
                        that they manifest. There has to be a Last Judgment. Thus, as Night IX
                        opens, Jesus stands over Los and Enitharmon and separates “Their
                        Spirit from their body” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 117:4, E 386).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> This separation seems to liberate and
                        inspire Los anew, for he initiates the Last Judgment by tearing down the sun
                        and moon, “cracking the heavens” so that the “fires of
                        Eternity” can spread over the material universe and consume the error
                        that has been given final form via the crucifixion (117:9-10, E 386). 
<note id="n25">25. This emphasis on “vision” in Night VIII
                            combines with Blake’s increased, and to some extent disjunctive,
                            focus on Jesus “the pitying one” in this Night to help
                            reveal Blake’s attitudes towards sentimentalism that his July
                            1804 letter to Hayley makes even more problematic. Blake’s
                            renewed Christian vision/faith seems to make him more convinced of the
                            need for forgiveness of sins and pity for sinners, but this forgiveness
                            and pity must be <hi rend="i">spiritual</hi> acts born from a
                            recognition of “the Lamb of God” within each
                            person.</note>
	<note id="n26">26. The fact that Jesus then disappears as an agent in Night
                            IX, both in the text and in the drawings (he appears once, on p. 129,
                            while Blake presents him in four large drawings in Night VIII), is
                            significant, from an interpretational perspective, in light of what is
                            to come. It is as if the blood and gore of Blake’s Last Judgment
                            cannot directly incorporate the presence of the “pitying
                            one,” however much the divine hand may be guiding what occurs.
                            From a bibliographic perspective, this change of Jesus from visible
                            victim/savior to a <hi rend="i">deus absconditus</hi> also seems to
                            support Bentley when he gives the current Night VIII a later date than
                            the greater part of Night IX (164-66); such a late date would make the
                            centrality of Jesus in Night VIII a reflection of the increasing
                            Christian focus in Blake’s later writings (as in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>).</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s apocalypse is almost beautifully frightful in its violence,
                        far surpassing his source in Revelation and implying just how powerful error
                        is to him. His own prophetic wrath is unmistakable, and he often seems
                        deliberately to target the figures that sentimentalism reified and realized
                        in its culture. While Blake gives victims such as slaves, prisoners, and
                        suffering families the chance to torment their oppressors in the opening
                        melee (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 122:38-123:32, E 392-93), even these victims, as
                        vestiges of fallen human life and objects of worldly <hi rend="i">pathos</hi>, have to
go along with everything else. To accomplish this,
                        the Zoas and Emanations must all join together to play their rightful roles.
                        Although the labors of Urizen, Tharmas, and Urthona are quite striking as
                        humanity and the fallen world get completely “reprocessed”
                        into a feast for the Eternals, the most frightening apocalyptic image that
                        Blake presents here is the winepresses of Luvah. To prepare the Last
                        Vintage, the sons and daughters of Luvah dance and laugh, accompanied by
                        various creatures around the presses, as they tread upon “the Human
                        Grapes [that] Sing not nor dance” but instead “howl &amp;
                        writhe in shoals of torment in fierce flames consuming” and amidst
                        various instruments of torture (136:5-39, E 404-05).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> Then, at last, with the world as we know it utterly
                        annihilated, “the evil is all consumd” and Albion is again
                        “Man”—regenerated, visionary, and alive with the
                        harmony and order of the universe within him (138:22, E 406). <note id="n27">27. In
Revelation 14:20, the winepress in John’s vision seems
                            almost banal compared to Blake’s: “And the winepress was
                            trodden without the city, and blood came out of the winepress, even unto
                            the horse bridles, by the space of a thousand and six hundred
                            furlongs.”</note></p>
          <p>I have focused here on the violence of Blake’s Last Judgment and its
                        human tinder because the apocalypse presents, I think, his ultimate revision
                        of sentimentality and the entire movement that it fostered. Every human
                        life—from victim to victimizer, from youth to elder—has to be
                        trodden in the winepresses or baked in the ovens of the Zoas—and, as
                        the feast implies, actually consumed by Eternal beings. Blake challenges us
                        to mimic Los, to use our visionary capacity to see through the vegetated
                        world and the (necessary) violence of its consummation in order to reveal
                        the spiritual “World within.” Because even Los, the most
                        inspired Zoa, fails to maintain that redemptive vision continuously and to
                        change the system of error, something more extreme is required. Blake
                        therefore envisions existence falling to its nadir with the crucifixion,
                        which then must be followed by the utter transformation and redemptive
                        consumption of those familiar objects that might otherwise elicit sympathy
                        and prevent such a Last Judgment.</p>
          <p>We can, I think, see the persistence of this fallen sentimentality in Los and
                        Enitharmon’s refusal to sacrifice their children at the end of Night
                        VIIa. Their pity for their children seems praiseworthy, especially when
                        contrasted with the “Storgous Appetite” that leads to
                        Orc’s binding in Night V. However, those newborn human souls that
                        they pity in Night VIIa have to be thrown into the winepresses or sown in
                        the ruins of the universe; even parental love is a tie to the fallen world.
                        Their pity may be another critique of sentimentalism because, as
                        Barker-Benfield observes, “the aggrandizement of the affectionate
                        family and, at its heart, mothering,” were central components of
                        sentimentalism through their cultivation of desired social affections (276).
                        However, as he also describes, the emphasis placed on a sentimental family
                        often led to “parental self-indulgence” and disabling
                        sensibility instead of greater communal sentiments. Wollstonecraft speaks to
                        this very problem when she condemns spoiling mothers who “for the
                        sake of their <hi rend="i">own</hi> children . . . violate the most sacred
                        duties, forgetting the common relationship that binds the whole family of
                        earth together” (290). Admittedly, Blake is more extreme, but it
                        seems that Los and Enitharmon are still guilty of an affection that holds
                        them back from their Eternal places and from working for the greater good.
                        These parents pity their children as pathetic, corporeal beings, as spectres
                        with physical bodies; they refuse to make the sacrifice of <hi rend="i">all</hi>
physical things—and of all sympathetic attachments to
                        them—that the final Night shows is required for the regeneration of
                        humanity.</p>
          <p>According to Blake’s mythology, the status of the Emanations and of
                        (sentimental) females as a whole necessitates that they become
                        undifferentiated from their male counterparts in order to reconstitute the
                        androgynous Zoas. Blake expresses this point in the poem’s closing
                        lines: “Urthona is arisen in his strength no longer now / Divided
                        from Enitharmon no longer the Spectre Los” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
                        139:4-5, E 407). Once again whole, Urthona can forge the armor that Albion
                        wears in the “intellectual War” of Eternity (139:8-9, E 407).
                        But what exactly does “whole” imply for Urthona and the other
                        Eternals in terms of the sexes, specifically the female sex? Blake does say
                        that both Enitharmon <hi rend="i">and</hi> the male “Spectre
                        Los” have disappeared as distinct, sexed identities. Nevertheless,
                        here again we meet one problem of describing Eternity from the 
<pb id="p39-76" n="76"/>
realm of Generation, since the
                        “fallen” language that Blake uses is also gendered language.
                        The masculine singular pronoun “his” in lines 4 and 8,
                        referring to “arisen” and undivided Urthona, further casts the
                        Eternal state as vigorous and masculine in contrast to the delusive,
                        “feminine” lower states that have been the major arena for the
                        poem’s action. While both of the separated sexes have apparently
                        reunited into single androgynous beings, Blake’s masculinized
                        language here and throughout makes it <hi rend="i">most</hi> apparent that
                        the females have been reintegrated or re-internalized. And, as Albion tells
                        Urizen shortly before the Last Judgment occurs, the Zoas are
                        “Immortal” while the Emanations are simply
                        “Regenerate” (122:12, E 391). Peter Otto thus questions the
                        ending of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, which he sees as representing
                        “a Urizenic ideal” in part because the Emanations are
                        “now indistinguishable from their male counterparts” (337-38).
                        However, the poem contains numerous reminders—some from the
                        Emanations themselves—that the Emanations are <hi rend="i">emanated</hi> and hence
secondary, just like the physical body they are
                        associated with. Indeed, this “disappearance” of the female is
                        in many ways the most telltale sign of regeneration based on Blake’s
                        association of femininity with the entire fallen world. As a result, he
                        makes it apparent that the Emanations have returned to their places as
                        portions of the Zoas after the apocalypse; once this is accomplished, the
                        Zoas can function harmoniously within Albion and Albion can rejoin the
                        “Eternal Brotherhood.”</p>
          <p>The re-internalization of the Emanations, with the destruction of sentimental
                        stereotypes, is the final move that Blake makes in his re-vision of
                        sentimental conventions and the sentimental system. This re-vision, an
                        incorporation of passive sentimentality into active inspired vision, is by
                        no means Blake’s central agenda in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
                        but it is as much a part of his “Dream” as it is a part of the
                        fallen world. Sentimentality may, at its best, reduce the sting of the fall,
                        but it can do nothing to regenerate humanity without the strength of vision
                        to guide it. In his later prophecies and other writings, Blake emphasizes
                        this point more explicitly against the backdrop of Eternity, as Los’s
                        inspired mission and message come to center on pity and forgiveness of sin
                        amidst continued sentimental, hypocritical oppression. Only through the
                        regeneration of worldly sentimentality, which Blake seems to trace through
                        the nine Nights of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, can a visionary prophet
                        redeem the fallen world with tenderness and love that are inspired, not
                        selfishly or superficially pitying, not tools for manipulation. As Blake
                        puts it in terms of his mythology, “Tharmas gave his Power to Los
                        Urthona gave his strength” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 111 [107]:31, E
                        383).</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Bibliography</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ackland, Michael. “The Embattled Sexes: Blake’s Debt to
                            Wollstonecraft in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 16.3 (winter 1982-83):
                            172-83.</p>
            <p>Aers, David. “Blake: Sex, Society and Ideology.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Ideology:
Studies in English Writing
                                1765-1830.</hi> Eds. David Aers, Jonathan Cook, and David Punter.
                            London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1981. 27-43.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake and the Dialectics of Sex.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 44 (fall 1977):
500-14.</p>
            <p>Allen, Richard O. “If You Have Tears: Sentimentalism as Soft
                            Romanticism.” <hi rend="i">Genre</hi> 8.2 (June 1975):
                            119-45.</p>
            <p>Ault, Donald. <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound: Re-Visioning William
                                Blake’s</hi> The Four Zoas. Barrytown, NY: Station Hill P,
                            1987.</p>
            <p>Barker-Benfield, G. J. <hi rend="i">The Culture of Sensibility: Sex and
                                Society in Eighteenth-Century Britain.</hi> Chicago: U of Chicago P,
                            1992.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Vala or The Four
                                Zoas: A Facsimile of the Manuscript, a Transcript of the Poem and a
                                Study of Its Growth and Significance.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P,
                            1963.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman, with commentary by Harold Bloom.
                            Newly rev. ed. New York: Anchor Books-Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p>Brissenden, R. F. <hi rend="i">Virtue in Distress: Studies in the Novel
                                of Sentiment from Richardson to Sade.</hi> New York: Barnes &amp;
                            Noble Books-Harper &amp; Row Publishers, Inc., 1974.</p>
            <p>Brown, Marshall. <hi rend="i">Preromanticism.</hi> Stanford, CA: Stanford
                            UP, 1991.</p>
            <p>Bruder, Helen P. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Daughters of
                                Albion.</hi> London and New York: Macmillan P Ltd. and St.
                            Martin’s P, Inc., 1997.</p>
            <p>Clark, S. H. “Blake and the Female Reason.” <hi rend="i">Sordid Images: The Poetry of
Masculine Desire.</hi> London:
                            Routledge, 1994. 138-87.</p>
            <p>Cox, Stephen. “Sensibility as Argument.” <hi rend="i">Sensibility in Transformation:
Creative Resistance to Sentiment
                                from the Augustans to the Romantics: Essays in Honor of Jean H.
                                Hagstrum.</hi> Ed. Syndy McMillen Conger. Rutherford, NJ: Fairleigh
                            Dickinson UP; London: Associated UP, 1990. 63-82.</p>
            <p>Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s
                                Myth.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1980.</p>
            <p>Ellis, Markman. <hi rend="i">The Politics of Sensibility: Race, Gender
                                and Commerce in the Sentimental Novel.</hi> Cambridge Studies in
                            Romanticism 18. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996.</p>
            <pb id="p39-77" n="77"/>
            <p>Fox, Susan. “The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s
                            Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 3 (spring 1977):
                            507-19.</p>
            <p>Freeman, Kathryn. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Nostos: Fragmentation and
                                Nondualism in</hi> The Four Zoas. Albany, NY: State U of New York P,
                            1997.</p>
            <p>Hagstrum, Jean. “Babylon Revisited, or the Story of Luvah and
                            Vala.” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays
                                on</hi> The Four Zoas, Milton, Jerusalem. Eds. Stuart Curran and
                            Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. Madison, WI: U of Wisconsin P, 1973.
                            101-18.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Sex and Sensibility: Ideal and Erotic Love from
                                Milton to Mozart.</hi> Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1980.</p>
            <p>Johnson, Claudia L. <hi rend="i">Equivocal Beings: Politics, Gender, and
                                Sentimentality in the 1790s : Wollstonecraft, Radcliffe, Burney,
                                Austen.</hi> Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1995.</p>
            <p>Jones, Chris. <hi rend="i">Radical Sensibility: Literature and Ideas in
                                the 1790s.</hi> London: Routledge, Inc., 1993.</p>
            <p>Lee, Judith. “Ways of Their Own: The Emanations of Blake’s
                                <hi rend="i">Vala, or The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 50 (spring
1983): 131-53.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew. “Alluring the Heart to Virtue: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Romanticism</hi> 38.4 (winter 1999): 621-37.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Spiritual History: A Reading of William
                                Blake’s</hi> Vala <hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas. Oxford:
                            Clarendon P, 1995.</p>
            <p>Mackenzie, Henry. <hi rend="i">The Man of Feeling.</hi> Oxford
                            World’s Classics. Ed. Brian Vickers. Oxford: Oxford UP, 2001.</p>
            <p>Magno, Cettina Tramontano and David V. Erdman, eds. The Four Zoas <hi rend="i">by William
Blake: A Photographic Facsimile of the
                                Manuscript with Commentary on the Illustrations.</hi> Lewisburg, PA:
                            Bucknell UP; London: Associated UP, 1987.</p>
            <p>McGann, Jerome. <hi rend="i">The Poetics of Sensibility: A Revolution in
                                Literary Style.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1998.</p>
            <p>Mellor, Anne K. “Blake’s Portrayal of Women.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 16.3 (winter 1982-83):
                            148-55.</p>
            <p>Mullan, John. <hi rend="i">Sentiment and Sociability: The Language of
                                Feeling in the Eighteenth Century.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P,
                            1988.</p>
            <p>Ostriker, Alicia. “Desire Gratified and Ungratified: William Blake
                            and Sexuality.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                            16.3 (winter 1982-83): 156-65.</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence: Love,
                                Jealousy, and the Sublime in</hi> The Four Zoas. Oxford: Oxford UP,
                            2000.</p>
            <p>Persyn, Mary Kelly. “‘No Human form but Sexual’:
                            Sensibility, Chastity, and Sacrifice in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi>
                            10.1 (winter 1999): 53-83.</p>
            <p>Pierce, John B. <hi rend="i">Flexible Design: Revisionary Poetics in
                                Blake’s</hi> Vala <hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas.
                            Montreal: McGill-Queen’s UP, 1998.</p>
            <p>Price, Martin. <hi rend="i">To the Palace of Wisdom: Studies in Order and
                                Energy from Dryden to Blake.</hi> Garden City, NY: Doubleday &amp;
                            Company, Inc., 1964.</p>
            <p>Rosso, George Anthony, Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic
                                Workshop: A Study of</hi> The Four Zoas. Lewisburg, PA: Bucknell UP;
                            London: Associated UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>Skinner, Gillian. <hi rend="i">Sensibility and Economics in the Novel,
                                1740-1800: The Price of a Tear.</hi> Basingstoke: Macmillan,
                            1999.</p>
            <p>Smith, Adam. <hi rend="i">The Theory of Moral Sentiments; or, An Essay
                                towards An Analysis of the Principles by which Men naturally judge
                                concerning the Conduct and Character, first of their Neighbours, and
                                afterwards of themselves, to which is added, A Dissertation on the
                                Origin of Languages.</hi> 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> ed. Dublin: J.
                            Beatty and C. Jackson, 1777.</p>
            <p>Tayler, Irene. “The Woman Scaly.” <hi rend="i">Midwestern
                                Modern Language Association Bulletin</hi> 6 (spring 1973):
                            74-87.</p>
            <p>Todd, Janet. <hi rend="i">Sensibility: An Introduction.</hi> London:
                            Methuen &amp; Co., 1986.</p>
            <p>Welch, Dennis M. “Blake’s Response to
                            Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 13.1 (summer 1979):
                            4-15.</p>
            <p>Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson. <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi>
                            Four Zoas: <hi rend="i">The Design of a Dream.</hi> Cambridge, MA:
                            Harvard UP, 1978.</p>
            <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary. <hi rend="i">A Vindication of the Rights of Men and
                                A Vindication of the Rights of Woman.</hi> Broadview Literary Texts.
                            Eds. D. L. Macdonald and Kathleen Scherf. Ontario: Broadview P,
                            2001.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
