<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.3.white</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Resolution to the War Between Science and Philosophy</title>
        <author n="White">Harry White</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2005/2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005-06</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Harry White</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>David Fuller</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005/2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
    <pb id="p39-108" n="108"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Resolution to the War Between Science and Philosophy</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Harry <name>White</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>As our understanding of Blake has progressed from madman to mystic to visionary artist, there is
still a widespread tendency to read him as holding “anti-scientific views,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> expressing “strong anti-scientific sentiments,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> and being unflagging in his “exploration of
anti-scientific doctrines.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> It is
said that “Blake did not love science, even feared and despised it,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> even though he himself objected to “those who pretend to
despise the labours of Art &amp; Science, which [he believed] alone are the labours of the Gospel . . .
[adding that] to Labour in Knowledge. is to Build up Jerusalem: and to Despise Knowledge, is to Despise
Jerusalem &amp; her Builders” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 77, E 232).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Indeed, Blake claimed for scientific work what he never said
about religion or morals: “Arts &amp; Sciences,” he wrote, “are the Destruction of Tyrannies or Bad
Governments” (annotations to Reynolds, E 636). If Blake hated and feared science, how explain the fact that
he believed “The Primeval State of Man, was Wisdom, Art, and Science” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 3, E
146) and that the very last line of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> proclaims a future wherein the “dark
Religions are departed &amp; sweet Science reigns”? For after all is said and done, “What is the Life of
Man but Art &amp; Science?” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 77, E 232). <note id="n1">1. See Toulmin.</note>
	<note id="n2">2. Weinberg 101.</note>
	<note id="n3">3. Schorer 49.</note>
	<note id="n4">4. Dawkins 17.</note>
	<note id="n5">5. Blake’s writings are quoted from <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi>, ed. David Erdman (New York: Anchor Books, 1988), hereafter “E”.</note></p>
          <p>Blake did not fear that the “power of scientific thought” might “replace
imagination,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> nor did he attack the
“debilitating influences” of “analytical philosophy . . . and empirical science,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> for it was not scientific thought, but
“Abstract Philosophy” which he said was “warring in enmity against Imagination” 
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 5:58, E 148) and doing so in opposition to both art and science. Believing that the
power of scientific thought actually derived from the imagination, the “true faculty of knowing” 
(<hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>, E 1), Blake felt that “Bacons <hi rend="i">Philosophy</hi> has Destroyd
all Art &amp; Science” (annotations to Reynolds, E 656; my italics); he showed how the theoretical systems
Bacon and other natural philosophers created were no different from traditional systems of thought in their
general disregard for the evidence of human experience. <note id="n6">6. Bloom, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Apocalypse</hi> 424.</note>
	<note id="n7">7. Emery 23.</note></p>
          <p>In 1936, A. J. Ayer’s influential <hi rend="i">Language, Truth, and Logic</hi> was published.
Ayer’s aim, we are told, was “to liberate science and common sense from philosophy, to free it from
‘system builders.’ There is no source of truth, Ayer argued, but experience.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> It is high time we recognized that that can serve as a pretty
good description of what Blake attempted almost one hundred and fifty years earlier and, for his time, with
greater daring and originality: “Striving with Systems to deliver Individuals from those Systems” by
showing how “Knowledge is not by deduction but Immediate by Perception or Sense at once” and can therefore
be acquired only through “the faculty which experiences” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 11:5, E 154;
annotations to Berkeley, E 664; <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>, E 1). <note id="n8">8. Rogers
120.</note></p>
          <p>Blake set “Downright Plain Truth” against “Reasoning [which] is Nothing” and said in
opposition to those who contended that “Truth should be Confined to Mathematical Demonstration” that any
man could “Know Truth at Sight” (annotations to Watson, E 618; annotations to Reynolds, E 659). Clearly
Blake wished above all else to give expression to his visionary imagination, but he also felt compelled to
address the radical changes philosophy was undergoing (“Urizen who was Faith &amp; Certainty is changd to
Doubt,” and the “idiot Reasoner [now] laughs at the Man of Imagination” [<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi>
27:15, E 318; <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32:6, E 131]), and he was informed and insightful enough to turn the
tables on the new philosophers and show how it was they and not men of imagination who were propounding truths
that were unreal. A significant and important portion of Blake’s writings was devoted to a critical analysis
of what he identified as “Truth the result of Reasoning” (annotations to Bacon, E 621). Blake sought to
clarify the differences between rational truth and empirical knowledge, which he understood to be any and all
knowledge gained immediately through experience and which encompassed everything from a grain of sand to
worlds of imagination.</p>
          <p>Berkeley had dismissed “philosophers [who] distrust their senses, and doubt the existence . . .
of everything they see or feel [and who . . .] are forced to own we cannot attain to any self-evident . . .
knowledge of the existence of sensible things.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> Similarly Blake ridiculed anyone “who Doubts from what he sees” and called him a knave
who inquired “into the truth of a self evident thing” (<hi rend="i">Auguries of Innocence</hi> 107, E 492;
annotations to Watson, E 613-14). He insisted that there could not be any doubt regarding the self-evident
truths of human experience—the worlds of sensation, feeling, and imagination that we all experience but
which rational philosophy called into question: “Did Jesus teach Doubt or did he / Give any lessons of
Philosophy[?]” No, because “Rational Truth is not the Truth of Christ but of Pilate” 
(<hi rend="i">Everlasting Gospel</hi> p. 48, part of an abandoned section, E 525; annotations to Bacon, E 621).
<pb id="p39-109" n="109"/>
Only a fool or an idiot would doubt anything men experience, but to doubt the abstractions and generalizations
of speculative philosophy was another matter altogether. “That the things I see with my eyes and touch with
my hands do . . . really exist, I make not the least question,” Berkeley wrote. “The only thing whose
existence we deny is that which <hi rend="i">philosophers</hi> call matter . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> As we will see, there were many more “things” Blake
denied, for he encouraged everyone to doubt the reality of all truths of reason as well as those figures of
authority who took advantage of the abstract non-entities philosophers created to enslave the vulgar (see 
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 11, E 38). There is no inconsistency between Blake’s acceptance of
every image of truth men can possibly envision and his skeptical attitude with respect to the truths of
reason, nor should we be misled by his aphoristic approach into thinking he “gives low priority to detailed
investigation of logics other than his own.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> His critiques, where they occur, are never extended, but the details are there, scattered
throughout his writings, and just need to be pulled together. <note id="n9">9. Berkeley, 
<hi rend="i">Treatise</hi> 553.</note>
	<note id="n10">10. Berkeley, <hi rend="i">Treatise</hi> 534.</note>
	<note id="n11">11. Cox 29.</note></p>
          <p>This paper, then, will attempt to situate much of Blake’s writing where I believe it properly
belongs, not alongside the complaints of opponents of science, but in line with the great British tradition of
empirical-analytic philosophy represented by thinkers like Berkeley or Ayer, who questioned the conclusions of
speculative philosophy and insisted that experience remains the only basis for all our knowledge, and next to
many leading scientists who, like Blake, looked with skepticism at certain influential but unwarranted
philosophical assumptions respecting classical physics. I will also attempt show how Blake sketched an
alternative view of science based on our actual experience of living forms, which anticipated the great
scientific revolution that occurred not long after he ceased writing.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Material World</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Causal determinism was arguably the most important creation of the new philosophy, and Blake
knew that it had been shown utterly to lack any basis in experience. His contention that “a Natural Cause
only seems” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 26:45, E 124) may at first seem wildly dismissive, but as Thomas Reid
had noted in 1788, “Natural philosophers . . . have never discovered the efficient cause of any one
phenomenon . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Both
statements are perfectly in keeping with Hume’s still troublesome critique of causality. The
<q>
particular powers, by which all natural operations are performed never appear to the senses . . . . In
reality, there is no part of matter, that does ever, by its sensible qualities, discover any power or energy .
. . . [T]he power of [or] force which actuates the whole machine, is entirely concealed from us . . .
.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n12">12. Reid 47.</note>
	<note id="n13">13. Hume, <hi rend="i">Enquiry</hi> 609, 623, 627. For additional parallels and affinities
between Blake and Hume, see Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
Press, 1970) 26-27.</note></q></p>
            <p>It is no sure sign of mystification or anti-scientific prejudice on Blake’s part to say, as
he did, that we have no experience of any thing being the cause of any other thing. Hume for one had already
said it, and Karl Pearson, one of the first major contributors to theoretical statistics, would later note
that the “law of causation . . . is a useful concept, but in no sense a reality,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> while Niels Bohr believed the advent of atomic physics
required “a final renunciation of the classical ideal of causality.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> However, well before statistical analysis undermined the
concept of causality, Newton himself wrote to Richard Bentley regarding the greatest of all causes, “You
speak of gravity as being essential &amp; inherent in matter, pray do not ascribe that notion to me, for ye
cause of gravity is what I do not pretend to know . . .” (17 Jan. 1692/93).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n14">14. Pearson 154.</note>
	<note id="n15">15. Bohr 60.</note>
	<note id="n16">16. Newton, <hi rend="i">Correspondence</hi> (hereafter cited solely in the text by addressee
and date) 3: 240.</note></p>
            <p>Blake did not wish to escape from “Humean skepticism” with its doubts regarding “the idea
of causation”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref>; rather, he employed
such skepticism to expose the difficulties surrounding causal determinism. When he wrote that “There is no
Such Thing as a . . . Natural Cause” (annotations to Bacon, E 626), he, like Hume before him and others
after them, was merely stating that the term <hi rend="i">natural cause</hi> does not refer to any 
<hi rend="i">thing</hi> that we know to exist. A natural cause is a non-entity which only seems to exist—just
one example of “a Delusion / Of Ulro” in which people commonly mistake what “only seems” for what
actually exists (see <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 26:45-46, E 124). “We deceive ourselves,” Reid observed,
“if we conceive, that we can point out the real efficient cause” of any “phenomenon that falls within
the compass of natural philosophy.” The “grandest discovery ever made in natural philosophy, was that of
the law of gravitation . . . . But the author of this discovery was perfectly aware, that <hi rend="i">he
discovered no real cause</hi>, but only the law or rule, according to which the unknown cause operates” (my
italics).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n17">17. Bloom, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi> 16.</note>
	<note id="n18">18. Reid 45-46.</note></p>
            <p>As Bertrand Russell put it, the “reason why physics has ceased to look for causes is that, in
fact, there are no such things.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
Russell was of course referring to twentieth-century physics, but in fact scientists in Blake’s time had
already methodically avoided looking for causes. Blake thus understood Newton’s aims and accomplishments
correctly, since Newton himself wrote in his great work, “I here design to give a mathematical notion of
these forces, <hi rend="i">without considering their</hi>
            <pb id="p39-110" n="110"/>
            <hi rend="i">physical causes and seats.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n20" type="note">20</ref> His <hi rend="i">Opticks</hi> also makes it clear that science gives us the
“general Laws of Nature,” even “though their Causes be not yet discover’d”; Newton never scrupled
“to propose Principles of Motion” and “leave their Causes to be found out.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> His researches were perfectly in keeping with the
revolutionary change Galileo brought to scientific study. As Galileo wrote in his <hi rend="i">Dialogues
Concerning Two New Sciences</hi> (1638), the purpose of science is “to investigate and to demonstrate . . .
the properties of [things like] accelerated motion,” but “it is not really worthwhile” to “obtain a
proper solution of the problem discussed by philosophers, namely, what causes the acceleration.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> Thus, when Blake contended that scientists
have not discovered true or ultimate causes, he was not charging them with having failed in their purpose.
Galileo, Newton, and others had already pointed out that scientific investigation does not propose to resolve
what are in fact philosophical problems. Philosophers who puzzle over causes should not be thought of as doing
the work of science; above all, as Blake repeatedly pointed out, philosophers should not claim what leading
scientists had specifically denied, that natural philosophy had in fact solved philosophic issues regarding
things like ultimate causes. Blake thus understood the responsibility for the war that was raging between
philosophy and science to rest with the philosophers, and he sought to end it by showing that what he and
others objected to had nothing to do with actual scientific work (such as the kind, as we shall see, he showed
Los engaged in), but with the misguided claims philosophers (like Urizen) made for their own rational systems
of thought. <note id="n19">19. Russell 180.</note>
	<note id="n20">20. Newton, <hi rend="i">Mathematical Principles</hi> 5.</note>
	<note id="n21">21. Newton, <hi rend="i">Opticks</hi> 401-02.</note>
	<note id="n22">22. Galilei 524-25.</note></p>
            <p>Laplace would title his great work <hi rend="i">Celestial Mechanics</hi> (1799-1825), but
Newton understood himself to be writing about mathematical principles of philosophy and insisted that “we
cannot yet prove by Experiments that all the Phaenomena in Nature can be solved by meer Mechanical
Causes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Most, however, did
understand Newton’s work to be providing physical explanations, so Blake had to remind his readers that the
reliability of Newton’s mathematical principles could not be taken as valid proof of the actual existence of
mechanical causes. (Indeed, to this day there is no proof that any such mechanisms as <hi rend="i">force,
inertia, cause</hi> or <hi rend="i">gravity</hi> really do exist in nature.) Blake’s denial of any proof or
knowledge of a physical reality of mechanical causes contradicted those philosophers like Locke who thought it
necessary to assume the existence of mechanical causes, but that denial did not contradict the design of
Newton’s work or Newton’s characterization of it as not revealing true causes (<hi rend="i">verae
causae</hi>). <note id="n23">23. Newton, “Account” 164.</note></p>
            <p>Against the view of science that was becoming popular in his day, but not contrary to the view
of scientists like Galileo or Newton, Blake repeatedly described scientific formulations as “creations,”
“fictions,” “allegories,” “abstractions,” or “non-entities,” which oftentimes led to delusions
respecting a physical reality of mechanical determinism. He proposed and dramatized the idea that, as Hawking
would remark, a scientific “theory . . . exists only in our minds and does not have any other reality . . .
.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> And he anticipated Einstein’s
observation that the “tremendous practical success of [Newton’s] doctrines . . . may well have prevented
him and the physicists of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries from recognizing the fictitious character of
the foundations of his system.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> A
scientist, Einstein generally noted, is apt to treat “the products of his imagination . . . not as the
creations of his thoughts but as given realities.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">26</ref> This, according to Max Planck, was “a fundamental mistake” of classical physics, the
belief that it furnished “a direct glimpse into the real happenings of things.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> Niels Bohr went so far as to state that it “is wrong to
think that the task of physics is to find out how Nature <hi rend="i">is.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n24">24. Hawking, <hi rend="i">Brief History</hi> 10.</note>
	<note id="n25">25. Einstein, “Method” 273.</note>
	<note id="n26">26. Einstein, “Method” 270.</note>
	<note id="n27">27. Planck, “Scientist’s Picture” 95.</note>
	<note id="n28">28. Quoted in Norris 44.</note></p>
            <p>In line with those scientists from Newton to Hawking who either refuse to speculate on the
ontological status of the terms they successfully employ or deny the validity of their formulas with respect
to some reality beyond thought, Blake understood that natural philosophy, or what we might nowadays call
theoretical physics, functioned and could function well enough by describing what seems without having to
commit the fundamental mistake of proclaiming it had discovered what is. Eden is just such a state of mind, in
which one recognizes that what appears to be without is actually within, whereas Ulro is the opposite state,
based upon the delusive ontology fostered by classical physics: in Ulro, “What seems to Be: Is: To those to
whom / It seems to Be, &amp; is productive of the most dreadful / Consequences to those to whom it seems to
Be” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 32:51-53, E 179). As Blake made clear to Crabb Robinson, atheistic
materialism was the most dreadful consequence of mistaking what seems to be for what is: 
“<hi rend="u">Bacon, Locke &amp; Newton</hi> are the three great teachers of Atheism . . . Every thing is 
<hi rend="u">Atheism</hi> which assumes the reality of the natural &amp; unspiritual world.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref> By defining atheism as belief in the reality
of a natural world, Blake identified himself as neither an opponent of science nor a traditional theist, but
specifically as someone opposed to belief in scientific realism. <note id="n29">29. Quoted in Bentley
414.</note></p>
            <p>Blake’s anti-realist position with respect to scientific theories is evident in the way he
employed a simple word like <hi rend="i">thing</hi> to distinguish what exists from what doesn’t: “every
thing,” he wrote, “exists,” and so “Every thing possible to be believ’d is an image of truth,” and
“Mental Things are alone Real,” but on the other hand, “What is General Nature is there Such a Thing”
and “There is no Such Thing as a . . . Natural Cause for any Thing in any Way” 
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 13:66, E 158; <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 8:38, E 37; <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last
Judgment</hi>, E 565; annotations to Reynolds,
<pb id="p39-111" n="111"/>
E 648; annotations to Bacon, E 626). In 1686 the physicist and chemist Robert Boyle had questioned “whether
nature be a <hi rend="i">thing</hi> or a name,” whether “it be a real existent being, or a notional entity
somewhat of kin to . . . fictitious terms” (my italics).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n30" type="note">30</ref> Reid later contended that “<hi rend="i">Nature</hi> is the name we give to
the efficient cause of innumerable effects which fall daily under our observation,” and he, like Boyle and
Blake, also called it “a fiction.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">31</ref> Among English-speaking writers, the term is still being used to describe scientific
theories. In 1973, Hugh Everett (the scientist who originated the many-worlds interpretation of quantum
mechanics) wrote that, like “any other theory,” the “constructs of classical physics are . . . fictions
of our own minds.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n30">30. Boyle 32.</note>
	<note id="n31">31. Reid 34, 45.</note>
	<note id="n32">32. Everett 133.</note></p>
            <p>At the time Blake wrote, the success of science had been well established even as philosophers
debated (as many to this day still do) whether its formulas were human creations or discoveries of real,
material entities. If nothing else, the fact that these philosophic issues remained unresolved in the midst of
tremendous scientific advance proved that science could maintain itself without having to succumb to the
“delusion of Ulro” (see <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 29:16, E 127) with all its accompanying “unreal
forms” (<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 28:2, E 318). It did not have to presume that its formulations were
anything other than what Blake said they were, fictional creations of the rational faculty and not existing
entities dwelling in some obscure place. In sum, Blake adopted a then-familiar 
<hi rend="i">instrumentalist</hi> or <hi rend="i">functionalist</hi> approach to scientific theories, accepting
their usefulness, but denying the validity of the philosophic conclusions derived from them. It is the
approach Berkeley, for one, insisted on throughout his writings. The “natural philosopher,” he wrote,
ought not to pretend to “explain things by corporeal causes.” Rather, the “knowledge of nature”
consists in making “sure and well-grounded predictions”; these “observations and experiments” are made
because “they are of use to mankind.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">33</ref>
	<note id="n33">33. Berkeley, <hi rend="i">Treatise</hi> 545-46, 542, 560.</note></p>
            <p>An instrumentalist approach was regularly adopted not only by scientists like Boyle, but
especially by the astronomers (who were the first modern scientists). Thus Bacon could write that Copernicus,
Ptolemy, and Tycho Brahe did not mean to say by their theories that “the things they allege, are actually
true, but only that they are convenient hypotheses for calculations . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">34</ref> As the introduction to Copernicus’ <hi rend="i">De
Revolutionibus</hi> states, the astronomer does not think up causes and hypotheses “in order to persuade
anyone of their truth but only in order that they may provide a correct basis for calculation.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref> As Galileo knew and testified at his trial,
such was the church’s position, that “since the opinion of Copernicus, taken absolutely, contradicted Holy
Scripture, it could not be held or defended, but . . . it might be taken and used hypothetically,” and he
tried to claim that his own <hi rend="i">Dialogues Concerning the Two Chief World Systems</hi> likewise did
not hold or defend any opinion regarding the actual motion of the earth or the stability of the sun.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref> Thus, by the time Blake wrote, the
distinction between factual truths and hypothetical fictions (as they were sometimes called) was firmly in
place at the center of the philosophic controversy dividing realists from skeptics regarding scientific
proofs. When Blake called scientific theories fictions or scientific laws false appearances to make the case
that neither should be taken to be factually true, he was clearly siding with the skeptics, among whom, it
should be noted, were a number of leading scientists; he never denied the reality of these theories for the
reason the churchmen insisted upon, that they are contradicted by biblical cosmology. Blake denied their
validity on purely empirical grounds, because experience does not confirm the existence of the things they
allege. <note id="n34">34. Quoted in Urbach 128.</note>
	<note id="n35">35. Copernicus 7.</note>
	<note id="n36">36. Quoted in Sobel 248-49.</note></p>
            <p>Hume had demonstrated that the nature of mathematical principles and all other rational truths
is that they are discoverable “without dependence on what is anywhere existent in the universe,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">37</ref> and Blake was utterly relentless in
discrediting any and all claims that what he called “Truth the result of Reasoning” could and did exist
anywhere in the universe, placing reason’s “unreal forms” in Ulro, “the Void Outside of Existence”
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 41:37, E 143). Blake’s response to the claims of natural philosophy was to draw a
clear line of distinction between knowledge of existence and the logical relations of abstract ideas: “Self
Evident Truth is one Thing and Truth the result of Reasoning is another Thing” (annotations to Bacon, E
621). He was very much an empiricist to the extent that he believed “the true faculty of knowing must be the
faculty which experiences” and that “Knowledge is . . . Immediate by Perception or Sense at once” 
(<hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>, E 1; annotations to Berkeley, E 664). While he recognized that there may
be general truths of reason, he could not accept that there is “such a Thing” as “General Knowledge”
since “All Knowledge [as distinguished from the general truths of reason] is Particular” because all 
<hi rend="i">things</hi> we experience are particular, and “Unless. You Consult. Particulars. You Cannot. even
Know or See . . . any Thing . . .” (annotations to Reynolds, E 648, 645). Taken together, the annotations to
Berkeley and Reynolds give us a good idea of the limitations Blake sought to impose on knowledge. Simply put,
knowledge is immediate and particular. Any deductions of the reasoning faculty, whether they are conducted
prior to experience (pure speculative reasoning) or even after the immediate sense or perception of things
(inductive reasoning), do not qualify as knowledge. They represent truths of reason, but such truths never
give us knowledge of experience. (We will continue to examine Blake’s distinction between truth and
knowledge throughout the upcoming discussion.) <note id="n37">37. Hume, <hi rend="i">Enquiry</hi>
598.</note></p>
            <pb id="p39-112" n="112"/>
            <p>When Blake insisted that “Mental Things are alone Real,” the crucial distinction is not
fundamentally or simply between the mental and the physical, but between the reality of the things we know and
see and the non-entities of which we have neither experience nor knowledge: “what is Calld Corporeal Nobody
Knows of its Dwelling Place . . . Where is it but in the Mind of a Fool” (<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last
Judgment</hi>, E 565)—a fool perhaps like John Locke, who accepted that there was something like material
substance even though he admitted “that if anyone will examine himself concerning his notion of pure
substance in general, he will find he has no other idea of it at all, but only a supposition of he knows not
what . . . . [It] is plain, then, that the idea of <hi rend="i">corporeal substance</hi> in matter is . . .
remote from our conceptions and apprehensions . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">38</ref>
	<note id="n38">38. Locke 294-96.</note></p>
            <p>Blake was thought by some to be a madman for his fantastic visions, and yet it was the sober
John Locke who admitted that corporeal substance was he knew not what and still foolishly supposed it to exist
even though he had no idea of it. But, said Blake, “Deduct from a rose its redness. from a lilly its
whiteness from a diamond its hardness from a spunge its softness from an oak its heighth from a daisy its
lowness . . . &amp; then we shall return to Chaos” (annotations to Lavater, E 595). Ernst Mach would make
similar deductions so that he too might eliminate all unwarranted metaphysical assumptions from science: “By
omitting now this, now that sensory element . . ., we can easily jump to the conclusion that, even if we
eliminated all the elements, there would always be something left. We imagine . . . a 
<hi rend="i">carrier</hi> of qualities, a <hi rend="i">substance</hi> of the object . . . . This idea has no
foundation in the [sensory] elements . . .; it is purely a product of creative fantasy.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref>
	<note id="n39">39. Mach 42.</note></p>
            <p>Berkeley had insisted on that very point, that science does not need to suppose a material
know-not-what in order to work. It was, he said, generally supposed that “whatever advances have been made .
. . in the study of nature do all proceed on the supposition that corporeal substance or matter doth really
exist,” but he answered this by saying that “there is not any one phenomenon explained on that supposition
which may not as well be explained without it . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">40</ref> In fact, Newton himself had already dismissed material explanations as necessary to the
design of his work. Since such explanations aren’t required—or as Pearson later put it, “matter is a
metaphysical entity . . . meaningless for science”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">41</ref>—it would be wrong to assume that Blake’s denial of materialism meant he opposed
science itself. Rather, what he proposed was a positivist correction to the new <hi rend="i">philosophy</hi>
of science, if we understand positivism in the way the physicist, Pierre Duhem, understood it when he wrote in
1905: “Our interpretation of physical theory is . . . essentially positivist in its origins . . . . [T]he
doctrines which proclaimed that everything in the material world reduced to matter and motion are
metaphysical.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">42</ref>
	<note id="n40">40. Berkeley, <hi rend="i">Treatise</hi> 539.</note>
	<note id="n41">41. Pearson 278-79.</note>
	<note id="n42">42. Duhem 279.</note></p>
            <p>Although Comte is credited with coining the term <hi rend="i">positivism</hi>, Hume arguably
originated the approach in philosophy so that by 1788, at the onset of Blake’s great creative decade,
philosophers like Thomas Reid could employ positivist thinking to prevent conclusions he, like Blake, also
called “atheistic”: “Natural philosophers, when they think accurately, . . . and when they pretend to
show the cause of any phenomenon of nature, they mean by the cause, a law of nature of which that phenomenon
is a necessary consequence.” To “discover the laws of nature” is all that Newton “attempted, and all
that he thought attainable”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref>—and,
we might add, all that Galileo thought “worthwhile” in scientific investigation. <note id="n43">43. Reid
46.</note></p>
            <p>Much of what Blake wrote needs to be placed in the context of what Heisenberg identified as
“the starting point for the empiristic philosophy . . . and positivism” which was first formulated in
response to the “difficulty of metaphysical realism”—the assumption, which Blake repeatedly attacked,
that scientific formulations represent things that really have independent existence. The empiricists and
positivists reacted (as did Blake) to “classical physics [which] started from the belief—or should one say
the illusion?—that we could describe the world . . . without any reference to ourselves.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">44</ref> As Eugene Wigner noted, the “very study of
the external world led to the conclusion that the content of the consciousness is an ultimate reality.”
Paradoxically, the belief in a material world soon produced the “principal argument against materialism . .
. [which is] that our knowledge of the external world is the content of our consciousness . . . .”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">45</ref>
	<note id="n44">44. Heisenberg 83, 55.</note>
	<note id="n45">45. Wigner 172, 176-77.</note></p>
            <p>In Blake’s day, Berkeley attributed endless difficulties to the metaphysics of the natural
philosophers. “All this scepticism,” he noted, “follows from our supposing . . . 
<hi rend="i">things</hi> . . . have a subsistence without the mind or unperceived.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">46</ref> From the beginnings of modern science to our own day,
numerous scientists and philosophers have taken the position that certain laws of science, however usefully
they function, do not reveal the ultimate truths of existence: Newton would adopt it to protect his
theosophical beliefs, as Galileo did to protect himself from the Inquisition, Kant so he could maintain his
free rational will, Duhem for his Catholicism, and Einstein so that God would not play dice with the universe.
Blake took an anti-realist approach to science precisely because he too wished to protect his own visions of
truth from any possible encroachment by natural philosophy; whatever his motivation or whatever his beliefs,
Blake’s critique of natural philosophy remains quite sound and is consistent with the assessment of many
important and knowledgeable thinkers from his time to the present. He, like others, was led to the conclusion
that what science
<pb id="p39-113" n="113"/>
studied was nothing if not the content of consciousness, because the natural philosophers claimed that they
had acquired knowledge of an objective reality as it existed external to the minds of men. “[A]ll you
behold,” Blake said, “tho it appears Without it is Within” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 71:18, E 225).
Statements like “Where man is not nature is barren” (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 10:68, E 38) attack the
very supposition that science had discovered and was describing the natural world as it actually existed
before men ever came to know it. <note id="n46">46. Berkeley, <hi rend="i">Treatise</hi> 553.</note></p>
            <p>By the turn of the century, a number of leading scientists were coming round to expressing very
“Blakean” views on science. In 1920 Arthur Eddington wrote, where “science has progressed the farthest,
the mind has but regained from nature that which the mind has put into nature.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">47</ref> In 1892 Pearson would explain how “the laws of science are
inherent in ourselves . . . .” They are “products of the human mind rather than factors of the external
world . . . . The law of gravitation is not so much the discovery of Newton . . . as his invention . . .
.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">48</ref> A century before, Blake
regularly placed the creation of the material world after the fall to demonstrate that the natural world with
its “globes of attraction” was a hypothetical fiction that had no reality—it did not exist and was not
thought to exist—before (fallen) men created it. To assume that gravity existed prior to Newton’s
formulation of the laws of gravity was a foolish and unnecessary supposition; by showing that all of creation
is just that, a creation of the minds of men, Blake attacked the metaphysics of materialism to reveal that
what philosophers identify as corporeal does not appear in sense experience, but it is often a “false
appearance which appears to the reasoner . . . .” Its supposed appearance is based on a “Fallacy &amp; its
Existence an Imposture Where is the Existence Out of Mind or Thought” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 29:15, E
127; <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, E 565). <note id="n47">47. Eddington, “New Law”
247.</note>
	<note id="n48">48. Pearson 110, 36, 86.</note></p>
            <p>It was clear to Blake that material substance and natural cause, the two elements supposed to
be the foundation of the sciences of his day, did not appear to the mind of any man—not even Newton’s or
Locke’s. Ault, however, says that Blake “accepts necessity as an undeniable aspect of the ‘physical’
world, even though this necessity is in a real sense fictitious.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n49" type="note">49</ref> Maybe we should turn the wording around and say that the physical world is a
product of the belief in necessity; otherwise, we might miss Blake’s very important point that what was
thought to be the physical world was mostly a fiction (a “creative fantasy,” as Mach called it) created by
the power of scientific reasoning. Blake did not accept necessity as an aspect of the physical or any other
world. He agreed with Berkeley and Hume that no such thing as causal necessity could be known to exist (and,
as we shall see, he showed how ideas about it were not logically sound either). We have “no experience
[that] can teach us what necessarily must be,” wrote Reid.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">50</ref> In works like <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, Blake showed that
necessity was actually an <hi rend="i">a priori</hi> assumption that so impressed would-be scientists that
they, like Urizen, needlessly “sought for” a world that would justify their deterministic theories. Urizen
literally creates a physical world that will validate his unfounded conviction that principles of rational
determinism actually do describe reality. “Single vision &amp; Newtons sleep” (letter to Butts, 22 Nov.
1802, E 722) create formulas, terms, and phrases, such as <hi rend="i">corporeal substance</hi>, and then
idiot reasoners like Urizen erroneously assume that the creations of natural philosophy denote real entities,
despite the fact that there is no empirical evidence for their existence from any realm of experience. 
<note id="n49">49. Ault 92.</note>
	<note id="n50">50. Reid 39.</note></p>
            <p>Urizen’s mistake represents the rationalist’s fallacy of presuming that there has to be a
physical world that validates the idealized abstractions natural philosophy creates, even though neither
reason, observation nor experiment can discover any such world. That is why Blake depicted Urizen as creating
it. The rise of empiricism is the distinguishing feature of modern science, but Urizen is not an empiricist,
not even a bad or mistaken one. That is not the problem as Blake understood it. As his name implies, Urizen is
a figure devoted to reason rather than to that which can be observed through experience, and Blake depicted
him as a philosophic rationalist fraudulently pretending to be doing empirical, scientific research. Urizen
holds as a matter of rational faith that the world is a fixed one of solid obstruction, and, lo and behold,
that is what he claims to discover, when in fact what he does is literally create the entire fiction of a
physical world of causal necessity to justify his theories—a delusory world of solid obstruction not at all
grounded in observation, but erected in defiance of all the variety, change and movement he has observed and
cannot tolerate. Urizen’s so-called explorations have actually been predetermined so that he will
“discover” only what conforms to reason. His observations are, as we now say, theory laden. That in itself
does not have to be a problem, so long as one is willing “to have the foundations of his knowledge changed
by new experience,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">51</ref> to acknowledge
evidence that might disconfirm, refute or falsify his theories (cf. Karl Popper’s theory of falsification).
However, what Urizen does is tamper with the evidence. The world he sees is composed of fire, wind, torrents
and waves; that is what Urizen observes, but he binds and holds back these elements—suppresses the
evidence—in order to create a world of “solid obstruction” that will falsely appear to confirm his
notion of what the world ought to be like (<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> chap. II, E 71-72). That what Urizen
observes, or thinks he observes, is a world composed of the four basic elements of ancient Greek thought might
show how outdated his theory of reality is, which in turn would suggest that all theories (such as, for
example, Newton’s gravity acting at a distance in absolute space and time) will eventually be revised
<pb id="p39-114" n="114"/>
or become dated with the advent of new theories (more on this in a moment). <note id="n51">51. Heisenberg
140.</note></p>
            <p>Newton admittedly published his mathematical truths concerning force or inertia without
evidence of their existence, and Urizen is like Newton insofar as he will not permit his “self-closed”
truths of reason to be modified in any way by knowledge of existence, but he tends to go beyond Newton, or at
least to ignore several of Newton’s warnings, by claiming that his rational abstractions denote actual
physical causes. He does so by creating a delusory existence of non-entities to fit theories that are not only
without empirical foundation, but are also, in fact, disconfirmed by what he knows of the world. Newton had
repeatedly warned that “hypotheses ought to be applied only in the explanation of the properties of things,
and not made use of in determining them . . .” (to Oldenburg, 10 June 1672; <hi rend="i">Correspondence</hi>
1: 169), and Blake showed how Urizen’s theories do not attempt to explain what he has observed, but are used
to determine the properties of a delusion: the physical world of solid obstruction he creates. Urizen does not
follow Newton’s advice of proceeding “upon the Evidence” and stopping where “Evidence is
wanting.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">52</ref> Blake showed him
committing the cardinal sin of any researcher or experimenter when he manufactures evidence rather than
collecting it. <note id="n52">52. Newton, “Account” 163.</note></p>
            <p>Yet Blake realized that despite his warnings to stick to phenomena, Newton himself was mistaken
if he thought his theories actually did proceed upon the evidence. In his famous statement, 
<hi rend="i">hypotheses non fingo</hi>, Newton had contended that he framed no hypotheses. The trouble with
hypotheses, he said, is that they “are not deduced from the phenomena” and therefore they “have no place
in experimental philosophy. In this philosophy, particular propositions are inferred from the phenomena, and
afterwards rendered general by induction.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">53</ref> By the time Blake began writing, Hume had shown (and, as we shall see, Blake well
understood) how inductive generalizations and therefore the formulations that had become basic to physics
could not be reasonably derived from any number of experiences or observations. As Einstein put it, physical
concepts “cannot be distilled . . . from experience by an inductive method, but can only be obtained by free
invention.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">54</ref> They “are free
creations of the human mind and are not, however it may seem, uniquely determined by the external
world.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">55</ref> Newton’s 
<hi rend="i">Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy</hi> in fact presented a logical system that
synthesized the theories of men like Kepler and Galileo and was conceived for the most part while Newton
pondered by himself. His reputation for having a mind “Voyaging through strange seas of Thought, alone”
(as Wordsworth characterized him in <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi> 3:63) was well known in Blake’s day. The
approach Blake had Urizen take in <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> is therefore as much parody as
satire, revealing how Urizen—and by implication, Newton—working alone, withdrawn, self-closed, all
repelling, hidden, and set apart, frames hypotheses without conducting any experiments or consulting
particular phenomena. What Urizen, like Newton, has “written in solitude” are pure creations of the
reasoning faculty which were neither derived from nor tested against any observation or experience. Urizen’s
creative endeavors are meant to reveal that Newton’s formulas were, in fact, freely created hypotheses
framed by his reasoning power and not generalizations that proceeded or could proceed from anything he or
anyone else could or did observe. Blake believed and portrayed through Urizen’s methods what John Maynard
Keynes later sensed about Newton: “His experiments,” Keynes wrote, “were always, I suspect, a means, not
of discovery, but always of verifying what he knew already.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n56" type="note">56</ref>
	<note id="n53">53. Newton, <hi rend="i">Principles</hi> 547.</note>
	<note id="n54">54. Einstein, “Physics and Reality” 322.</note>
	<note id="n55">55. Einstein and Infeld 31.</note>
	<note id="n56">56. Keynes 541.</note></p>
            <p>What Blake confronted with respect to Newton’s <hi rend="i">Mathematical Principles</hi> was
the great philosophic mystery of modern science. Centuries after Newton’s mathematical principles were put
forth, even a Nobel Prize-winning physicist like Richard Feynman had to admit, “Why nature is mathematical .
. . is a mystery.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">57</ref> Blake’s
answer was that nature is mathematical because it is the creation of the process whereby “mathematic power /
[gives] a body to Falshood” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 12:12-13, E 155). He knew that science worked, and
to some extent he knew how it worked, but he, like everyone else, did not know why it worked. As Shelley,
following Hume, explained the problem in his “Mont Blanc,” the power animating all that we know to exist
dwells apart from human experience. This much, however, was certain for Blake: the mathematical proof of any
scientific hypothesis should not be mistaken for evidence of what really exists. As Einstein noted,
“Propositions arrived at purely by logical means [what Blake called the truths of reason] are completely
empty as regards reality”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">58</ref>—as
Blake himself realized, consigning scientific propositions to a dark void empty of any real forms and calling
it Ulro. In addition, Blake maintained, as did Boyle and Reid, that all scientific theories remained fictions,
including those that had been confirmed by experiment to be established as scientific law—they remained no
different from scientific hypotheses in terms of explaining the true nature of reality. As the mathematician
and physicist Leonhard Euler (1707-83) wrote: “to learn the true causes of phenomena is not allowed to us,
nevertheless . . . a certain fictive hypothesis may suffice for explaining many phenomena.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">59</ref> The theories describing—usually in
mathematical terms—certain regularities pertaining to existing things are constantly changing and are even
falsified: “Reason . . . is not the Same it shall be when we know More” (annotations to Reynolds, E 659);
“Establishment of Truth depends on destruction of Falshood
<pb id="p39-115" n="115"/>
continually” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 55:65, E 205). However, our experience of these things remains the
same: “Imagination is a Representation of what Eternally Exists. Really &amp; Unchangeably” 
(<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, E 554). That is the case because “The Imagination is not a State:
it is the Human Existence itself / . . . / . . . [while] the Reason is a State / Created to be Annihilated . .
. / Whatever can be Created can be Annihilated” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32:32-36, E 132); scientific
theories as well as scientific laws are forever being created and annihilated. In antiquity, Empedocles
reasoned that the world was composed of four basic elements; in Blake’s day the universe was thought to be
like a clock, operating according to Newton’s conception of absolute time and space; soon after it became
like a steam engine, with the advent of thermodynamics; nowadays, the same universe which we experience in the
same way because it really hasn’t changed is said to be a computer transmitting information as part of
Einstein’s space-time continuum. Many philosophers of Blake’s time, but not that many scientists,
confidently asserted the novel claim that science had finally provided <hi rend="i">the</hi> answer respecting
the ultimate nature of reality. Blake’s response to that claim was to point out what many scientists
believed, that there was no scientific evidence for it. The stunning progress of modern science and the
rapidity with which theories change have resulted in continual and, for many, disturbing reevaluations of the
nature of reality. Blake believed that any philosophic reevaluation was unnecessary, because scientific
progress didn’t require it, and unwarranted, because even though scientific theories and philosophical
explanations do change, our experience of reality does not. <note id="n57">57. Feynman 24.</note>
	<note id="n58">58. Quoted in Hawking, <hi rend="i">Shoulders of Giants</hi> 397.</note>
	<note id="n59">59. Quoted in Kline 2: 739.</note></p>
            <p>Now we are beginning to see that Blake not only attacked the errors of the new philosophy, but
also confronted problems respecting the scientific method itself. Before examining his critique of the method,
we might summarize Blake’s objections to the new philosophy. They have to do with his understanding of the
nature of knowledge, truth and falsehood, and they involve key concepts he employed throughout his
writings.</p>
            <p>For Blake there were basically two kinds of truth: <hi rend="i">truths of existence</hi> and
<hi rend="i">truths of reason.</hi></p>
            <p>The truths of existence are of two kinds: there are first of all <hi rend="i">self-evident
truths.</hi> They are what Blake also called <hi rend="i">downright plain truths.</hi> They are undeniable,
and no one can doubt them. Every man knows them on plain sight (like the hardness of diamonds or the redness
of a rose).</p>
            <p>Secondly, there are the <hi rend="i">contraries</hi>, those various irreconcilable differences
among individuals. <hi rend="i">A contrary is an existing quality or characteristic opposed to some other
existing quality or characteristic, but not logically negating or falsifying it because no contrary can
possibly contradict any other.</hi> While it is true with respect to the contraries that ancient and modern
“accounts of polar metaphysics . . . were readily available” to Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">60</ref> it is also true that philosophers like Hume were showing how
the “contrary of every matter of fact is still possible; because it can never imply a contradiction, and is
conceived by the mind with the same facility and distinctness . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">61</ref> As Newton observed, “Those things wch men understand by .
. . contradictious phrases may be sometimes really in nature without any contradiction at all” (to Bentley,
25 Feb. 1692/93; <hi rend="i">Correspondence</hi> 3: 254). When Blake similarly noted that “Contraries
mutually Exist” or that “Contrarieties are equally True” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 17:33, E 162; 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 30:1, E 129), he aimed to point out that nothing which actually does exist necessarily
contradicts by its existence or its qualities anything else that exists. That is why, when Blake listed a
number of what were for him erroneous conceptions—that energy is alone from the body, for example—he
insisted that “the following Contraries to these are True”—that man has no body distinct from his soul,
for example (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 4, E 34). That both sets of beliefs concern matters of fact, even if
the first set is composed of what Blake thought were erroneous beliefs, means that the contrary conception is
possible—many do conceive the body as distinct from the soul—and there is no <hi rend="i">logical</hi>
contradiction between them. <note id="n60">60. Nurmi 73.</note>
	<note id="n61">61. Hume, <hi rend="i">Enquiry</hi> 598.</note></p>
            <p>One of the fundamental rules of logic is the law of non-contradiction, which says that if you
conjoin a proposition and its negation the result is a contradiction and the statement is necessarily false.
However, Blake understood that this and other rules of logic cannot and should not be applied to matters of
fact and existence which can never be logically “contradictious.” To hold “all Wisdom / To consist. in
the agreements &amp; disagree[me]nts of Ideas” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 70:7-8, E 224) does little more
than foolishly reduce “the variety of nature to the abstract idea” (see Reynolds in annotations to
Reynolds, E 649). No abstract rational system can ever fully and accurately describe the reality we observe,
consisting of downright plain truths and, taken together, the contraries of these various minute particulars.
What this means for science (as we shall see) is that however many observations we make, we can never arrive
at demonstrable certainty with respect to any laws we formulate regarding matters of fact and existence.</p>
            <p>To speak as Fisher does of Blake’s objection to “systems of knowledge”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">62</ref> is not quite right because Blake denied there
ever could be systematic knowledge of human experience. Nor is it likely, as Bloom claims, that Blake allowed
for a need, under conditions where reason has been corrupted, for a “systematic vision of all
existence.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">63</ref> Blake was relentless
in attacking what he understood to be a fundamental error of corrupt reason: the presumption that anyone’s
system was valid for <hi rend="i">all</hi> existence—or for all persons. He insisted that all systems are
created precisely because they have to be, since they have little or no basis in what we know to exist. 
<note id="n62">62. Fisher 6.</note>
	<note id="n63">63. Bloom, Commentary 931.</note></p>
            <pb id="p39-116" n="116"/>
            <p>What concerned Blake might be better identified as systems of truth, and what he objected to
was the mistaken belief that these rational systems were actually providing systematic knowledge of all
existence. The various systems of philosophic, religious or scientific truth which the reasoning power creates
are true or false by virtue of the fact that they are logical or illogical, coherent or incoherent—whether,
as Blake wrote, the ideas in them are in agreement or disagreement; logical agreement within a system does not
mean that it is therefore true in the sense that it corresponds to the things we experience. The problem Blake
had with Urizen was not that he is rational, but that he believes existence must conform to the laws the
reasoning power formulates—the “one Law” he would impose on everyone and everything (see 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 4:40, E 72). Those things which we do experience, the minute particulars that any
scientist seeking knowledge of the world must consult, exist either individually as plain truths or in
relation to each other as contraries, and insofar as contraries can mutually exist and be equally true, they
can’t possibly contradict each other. There is no logical relation among the minute particulars we
experience—individually, of course, it is impossible, and collectively we know them to exist together in no
rational or logical way. Thus, despite what scientists or priests or kings claim, not only can there be no
knowledge beyond what men experience for the simple reason that nothing can be known to exist if it does not
exist within human experience, but also the things we do experience, from the guinea sun to the heavenly host
of angels (<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, E 565-66), simply do not add up in any systematic
way. By the same token, because there is no logical agreement or disagreement among the various and contrary
facts we do observe, any rational system that does achieve demonstrable certainty does so by virtue of the
fact that it fails fully to take into account the variety of different particulars we experience.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="i">truths of reason</hi> are also of two kinds. They correspond to what are
commonly understood in philosophy as deductive <hi rend="i">a priori</hi> and inductive <hi rend="i">a
posteriori</hi> truths.</p>
            <p>The first result in what Blake identified as <hi rend="i">creations, fictions, allegories,
abstractions</hi> and <hi rend="i">non-entities</hi>; so long as these truths of pure deductive reasoning are
recognized as fictional non-entities, Blake had no problem with them. The error Blake repeatedly challenged
involved what linguistic philosophers now call a “category mistake”—mistaking one kind of category
(abstract non-entities) for another (existing entities); for Blake the mistake usually occurred whenever the
reasoning power misrepresented its creations, such as corporeal substance or Nobodaddy, as existing entities.
Those truths of reason that are mistaken to be part of existence, Blake called <hi rend="i">negations.</hi> A
negation is a “false appearance which appears to the reasoner” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 29:15, E 127) and
is created whenever the reasoning faculty mistakes or misrepresents the creation of rational abstractions for
the discovery of real entities. “Negations Exist Not” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 17:34, E 162). They are
abstract non-entities which are oftentimes erroneously presumed to provide us with objectively true knowledge
of existence. That misunderstanding is what turns a truth of reason into an untrue, false, erroneous, delusive
negation. Negations negate self-evident truths by ignoring, dismissing, denying or suppressing them, replacing
life’s minute particulars with mathematical formulas and fictitious mechanical laws. That is what the new
philosophy did whenever it failed to understand that its “mathematical symbols [do not] represent . . .
entities of the external world . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">64</ref> Yet ever since its inception, philosophy has been in the business of reifying its
abstractions, of giving what Blake called “a body to Falshood” and inventing some often remote,
transcendent place where these falsehoods supposedly exist, but as Moritz Schlick remarked, “There is . . .
no domain of ‘philosophical’ truths.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">65</ref> The embodied falsehoods of natural and other philosophies Blake called negations; the
delusive domain outside of existence where they reside he named Ulro. <note id="n64">64. Eddington, 
<hi rend="i">Philosophy</hi> 50.</note>
	<note id="n65">65. Schlick 56.</note></p>
            <p>The <hi rend="i">a posteriori</hi> truths of reason Blake distinguished with the term the 
<hi rend="i">ratio.</hi> The ratio is a product of inductive reasoning which results not in the creation of 
<hi rend="i">fictions</hi>, but in <hi rend="i">generalizations</hi> drawn from experience. Reason, so defined, is
“the ratio of all we have already known,” a “Ratio / Of the Things of Memory,” which functions to
“compare &amp; judge of what [one] has already perciev’d” (<hi rend="i">There is No Natural
Religion</hi>, E 2; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 74:11-12, E 229; <hi rend="i">There is No Natural
Religion</hi>, E 2). At one point Los identifies the difference between the two methods when he rejects
inductive reasoning in favor of pure, <hi rend="i">a priori</hi> rationalism: “I will not Reason &amp;
Compare,” he says, “my business is to Create” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 10:21, E 153); as we shall
see, <hi rend="i">creation</hi> in Blake usually refers to a purely rational and not necessarily an
imaginative process.</p>
            <p>Because the ratio derives from experience, Blake did not question its 
<hi rend="i">validity</hi>—its correspondence to the things we know and see—in the way he did the creations of
<hi rend="i">a priori</hi> reasoning. Rather, his doubts concerned its <hi rend="i">reliability</hi> as a
predictor of future experience. This was Blake’s fundamental challenge to the scientific method, to
Bacon’s contention that one could derive “the most general axioms” from “the senses and
particulars.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">66</ref> When Blake said that
the ratio “is not the same that it shall be when we know more” (<hi rend="i">There is No Natural
Religion</hi>, E 2), he denied that knowledge derived from past experience can be retained as axioms for
future knowledge. By claiming that knowledge of the unknown could reasonably be arrived at on the basis of
already acquired knowledge, the new philosophy put itself in the wholly illogical position of supposing it
could deduce knowledge of all existence before it had experienced all of existence. Blake contended to the
contrary that from “already acquired knowledge Man could not acquire more” (<hi rend="i">All Religions are
One</hi>, E 1). If science is to progress, the ratio of what we know must not be established so as to fix,
circumscribe and limit all further knowledge. Scientific progress cannot be based, as Bacon claimed,
<pb id="p39-117" n="117"/>
on past experience. The acquisition of new knowledge comes through new experience (which is the only means by
which knowledge can be acquired); coming to know more must inevitably change what we understand by the ratio.
<note id="n66">66. Bacon 31.</note></p>
            <p>Blake understood that the progress of science, which he argued for in opposition to those
“Sciences [which] were fixd” (<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 73:21, E 350), requires that we not keep
traversing old lands like a mill horse going round in circles, and that by remaining open to new experiences
what we are looking for should not be the confirmation of fixed systems of thought, which is what all systems
of thought tend to look for. Rather, we must be prepared to reject cherished theories as false in the light of
any new evidence we find. In science, “the rise, acceptance and fall of theories is an everyday
occurrence”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">67</ref> and “in a day . . .
[a] hardly-won position is assailed and made untenable . . . . Therefore, the experimenter cannot afford to
close his eyes to a new discovery.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">68</ref> As Blake put it, “Science cannot exist . . . / . . . in generalizing Demonstrations of
the Rational Power. / . . . / Establishment of Truth depends on destruction of Falshood continually” 
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 55:62-65, E 205). <note id="n67">67. Born 57.</note>
	<note id="n68">68. Planck, “Dynamical Laws” 90.</note></p>
            <p>The most glaring problem respecting the ratio is therefore not that it is a limited reflection
of experience, but that when the rational and mathematic powers operate without regard for imaginative
experience, they come to a standstill, preventing the discovery of new information by fixing the ratio of all
past experience as a permanent and closed system of thought: “The Spectre is the Reasoning Power in Man;
&amp; when separated / From Imagination, and closing itself as in steel, in a Ratio / Of the Things of Memory.
It thence frames Laws &amp; Moralities / To destroy Imagination!” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 74:10-13, E
229). Therefore, if “it were not for the Poetic or Prophetic character. [which Blake identified as the
faculty that experiences] the Philosophic &amp; Experimental would soon be at the ratio of all things &amp;
stand still, unable to do other than repeat the same dull round over again” (<hi rend="i">There is No
Natural Religion</hi>, E 3). Blake was willing to accept what he called the ratio to the extent that it did
not prohibit the acquisition of new knowledge based on new experience: “the Reason is a State / Created to
be Annihilated &amp; a new Ratio Created” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32:34-35, E 132). In response to those
who gave primacy in natural philosophy to the rational power and the supposedly permanent systems it created,
Blake offered a description of how reason could function within a genuinely empirical and progressive science.
He described it this way (for the first time in response to Reynolds’ contention that “reason is something
invariable”): “Reason or A Ratio of All We have Known is not the Same it shall be when we know More”
(annotations to Reynolds, E 659).</p>
            <p>Furthermore, in accordance with his belief that knowledge is of the things we sense and that
philosophy was destroying science, Blake evaluated the “Philosophic &amp; Experimental” components of
science quite differently: when Blake wrote that “the true method of knowledge is experiment” involving
our “experiences” (<hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>, E 1), he was of course being ironic, but the
point of his irony has to do with his use of the definite article. What Blake could not tolerate was the
implication that “Science such as is Weighed or Measured” was of superior value to all other methods of
knowledge (annotations to Reynolds, E 659)—that it was <hi rend="i">the</hi> only true method. While he
opposed the delusions of abstract reason themselves, when considering experimentalism he targeted those
individuals who dismissed as incredible or doubtful all images of truth that could not be proved by
experimentation; his opposition was to those “Who teach Doubt &amp; Experiment” on the assumption that men
cannot “believe without Experiment” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 54:18, 22, E 203, 204).</p>
            <p>Thanks to the work of critics like Northrop Frye, much has been written about the different
visionary states in Blake, but to say that Blake understood that “the abstract reasoner attempts to give
independent reality to the qualities of the things he sees” or that he finds that “the tree is 
<hi rend="i">more</hi> real to the wise man than it is to the fool”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n69" type="note">69</ref> overlooks perhaps the most important categorical distinction Blake made,
which was not between levels of perception and vision, but between the fictions we create and what is
eternally true in human experience. All visionary states, however limited, are real, and so are all the things
they include: “A fool sees not the same tree that a wise man sees,” and he sees it maybe as “only a
Green thing that stands in the way” (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 7:8, E 35; letter to Trusler, 23 Aug. 1799,
E 702), but it is still a thing he sees. Though “he sees all things thro’ narrow chinks of his cavern”
(<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 14, E 39), everything the fool sees and knows in his world of experience, while it
may be less rich, cannot be any less real. It is not the fool (or the experimenter) but the abstract reasoner
who deals in unrealities. The fool’s tree is a real thing. <hi rend="i">Nobodaddy</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">material substance</hi> are not. They are delusions created by priests and philosophers, but no one
has created the fool’s tree for him and then demanded that he believe what he does not see. 
<note id="n69">69. Frye 20, 21.</note></p>
            <p>Blake described the material world as a <hi rend="i">creation</hi> to emphasize that he
understood it to be largely a creation of, that is to say a product of, the reasoning power. Before the advent
of natural philosophy “Earth was not: nor globes of attraction” (<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 3:36, E
71)—they were not thought to exist before Urizen, following Newton’s principles of universal gravity,
created that “delusion of Ulro” of “a Globe rolling thro Voidness” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 29:16, E
127). To say that for “Blake, to create [truth] <hi rend="i">is</hi> to find it”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">70</ref> turns completely upside down Blake’s central contention
that “Error is Created Truth is Eternal” and ignores the fact that what he exposed throughout his writings
was “Error or Creation” (<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, E 565). Systems are created by an
Aquinas or a Newton, but not eternal truth. <note id="n70">70. Birenbaum 43.</note></p>
            <pb id="p39-118" n="118"/>
            <p>Blake responded to the “idiot Reasoner” who laughed “at the Man of Imagination” 
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 32:6, E 131) by insisting over and again that the reasoning faculty creates fictitious
non-entities whereas the imagination deals with existing realities: “All Things Exist in the Human
Imagination”; “Imagination [is] the real &amp; eternal World”; “Eternal Realities . . . Exist in the
Human Imagination” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 69:25, E 223; 77, E 231; <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last
Judgment</hi>, E 562). Because the things in the imagination have existed eternally, prior to any imaginative
act, Blake tended to describe the imaginative process not in terms of creation, but as an act of sensing,
seeing, representing and copying: “This World Is a World of Imagination &amp; Vision I see Every thing I
paint In This World . . . . Imagination . . . is Spiritual Sensation”; “Imagination is a Representation of
what Eternally Exists. Really &amp; Unchangeably”; “Copiers of Imagination are Correct” (letter to
Trusler, 23 Aug. 1799, E 702-03; <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, E 554; <hi rend="i">Public
Address</hi> 59, E 575). In Blake’s writings, the term creation tends to be associated with what does not
really exist, with <hi rend="i">abstractions, allegories, systems</hi>, and <hi rend="i">non-entities</hi>,
and with what is not true, with <hi rend="i">delusions</hi> and <hi rend="i">falsehoods</hi>, and with the
greatest delusion of all, the Nobodaddy who created this entire world out of nothing.</p>
            <p>In Blake’s scheme of things, the man who reasons <hi rend="i">a posteriori</hi> from the
qualities of the things he sees is operating from the real world of experience, whereas the abstract reasoner
is operating <hi rend="i">a priori</hi>, in “a Void, outside of Existence” with “the unreal forms of
Ulros night” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 1:1, E 144; <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 28:2, E 318). By
describing Ulro as a dark delusive void and those who enter it as being in a state of sleep (see, for example,
<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 85:21, E 360; <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 29:16, E 127; 37:16, E 137; 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 4:1, E 146), Blake was indicating that those who fall into Ulro have dropped out of
human existence into a state where they are not conscious and/or have no experience or vision of anything.
Shelley thought “the deep truth is imageless” (<hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi> 2.4.116), but Blake
thought that nothing could be said to be true which men could not imagine in some definite form: “it is
impossible to think without images” (annotations to Lavater, E 600). The state of Ulro, being imageless,
contains nothing for anyone to imagine and believe in, and anyone who does believe he has seen or discovered
anything there is deluding himself with false appearances. Ulro is therefore categorically different from the
states of consciousness or vision, identified as Eden, Beulah, and Experience. The products of it are unlike
the tree of either the wise man or the fool. The latter are images true to human perception and vision,
whereas in Ulro there is only darkness and void. Filling this void are the pure creations and delusions of the
reasoning power, such as the fictitious creations of Newton’s sleep (<hi rend="i">gravity, force</hi>, or
<hi rend="i">inertia</hi>) which exist neither in eternity nor experience, and the “false appearance which
appears to the reasoner,” like those images we think we see while asleep, as “when a man dreams, he
reflects not that his body sleeps” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 15:1, E 109).</p>
            <p>The problem with Frye’s description of what he identified as the abstract reasoner is that
while it does describe <hi rend="i">a posteriori</hi> reasoning, it fails to take into account that, first of
all, Blake typically described the abstract reasoner as operating <hi rend="i">a priori</hi> and without
concern for the real qualities or characteristics of anything he or anyone else actually sees, and that,
secondly, he recognized that inductive generalizations drawn from experience involved a different type of
reasoning with different problems.</p>
            <p>Blake’s most insightful analysis of the fallacy of inductivism comes in <hi rend="i">There is
No Natural Religion</hi> and <hi rend="i">All Religions are One.</hi> In defense of empiricism, Blake insisted
that knowledge can be acquired only through experience and not at all by the deductions of the reasoning
power. The powers of reason, being analytic and circular, are limited to analyzing already acquired knowledge
and cannot possibly synthesize new knowledge: “Man by his reasoning power. can only compare &amp; judge of
what he has already perciev’d. From a perception of only 3 senses or 3 elements none could deduce a fourth
or fifth” (<hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, E 2; Shelley similarly contrasted reason and
imagination at the beginning of his <hi rend="i">Defence of Poetry</hi>).</p>
            <p>Blake hit upon the fundamental problem with the inductive method, which is that however large
the sample, no finite number of known sensations or elements we consult can ever guarantee with certainty the
general conclusion that all sensations or elements of that kind which we encounter in the future will without
exception appear or act in exactly the same way. Seeing a hundred or a thousand white lambs is no
demonstration of the generalization that all lambs are white. Tomorrow we could encounter a black lamb—or
maybe be surprised by a white tiger. “The induction cannot be perfect till every simple idea that can enter
into the human mind be examined . . . . No man can pretend to have made this examination of all our simple
ideas without exception; and, therefore, no man can . . . assure us, that [his] conclusion holds without any
exception.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">71</ref> Or, as Blake put it,
our perception of two or three elements cannot guarantee what our perception of a fourth or fifth will be
like. Without seeing or consulting the latter we cannot rationally “deduce” it from the former in the way
that we can deduce that Socrates is mortal if all men are. Newton himself pointed out that arguing by
“Induction [can] be no Demonstration of general Conclusions,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n72" type="note">72</ref> and, more generally, Hume noted how all inquiries regarding matters of
“fact and existence . . . are evidently incapable of demonstration”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">73</ref>; however, many ignored these warnings and readily assumed
the certainty of general conclusions regarding matters of fact and existence. Blake had to remind his readers
that it would be “ignorance to view a small portion &amp; think that All, / And call it Demonstration: blind
to all the simple rules of life” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 65:27-28, E 216). In his annotations to
Reynolds, he noted that demonstration is certainly an object of reason (annotations
<pb id="p39-119" n="119"/>
to Reynolds, E 659), but inductive generalizations from experience, unlike the conclusions of deductive
reasoning, cannot reasonably rise to the level of demonstrations. A scientific method that “takes portions
of existence and fancies that the whole” (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 16, E 40) remains wholly illogical and
cannot reasonably prove or demonstrate anything with any certainty. <note id="n71">71. Reid 26.</note>
	<note id="n72">72. Newton, <hi rend="i">Opticks</hi> 404.</note>
	<note id="n73">73. Hume, <hi rend="i">Enquiry</hi> 688.</note></p>
            <p>The problem of induction has been called the problem of the uncertain future, which Hume put
this way: all “our experimental conclusions proceed upon the supposition that the future will be conformable
to the past . . . . If there be any suspicion that the course of nature may change . . . all experience
becomes useless, and can give rise to no inference or conclusion.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n74" type="note">74</ref> The problem one faces is that if nature changes, then from “already
acquired knowledge Man could not acquire more”; Blake showed how Urizen’s unscientific method gets around
the difficulty of induction through the creation of a “world of solid obstruction” in which the course of
nature does not change: “all futurity [is] bound in his vast chain / And the Sciences were fixd” 
(<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 73:20-21, E 350), and so are the inhabitants of Urizen’s world: “Beasts &amp;
Birds &amp; Fishes, &amp; Plants &amp; Minerals / Here fixd into a frozen bulk” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
34:53-54, E 135). The only way induction can be logically guaranteed is if the future will in all particulars
conform to the past. Then and only then can the ratio of all we have already known demonstrate with absolute
certainty all that we will ever come to know. Urizen is shown creating a world that is bound, frozen and fixed
because he realizes that it is only on condition that there will be no change in the world or its inhabitants
that he can insure for all time the general validity of inductive reasoning and causal determinism. Urizen’s
world is reason’s and not science’s world—a world in which human experience is frozen and scientific
progress cannot possibly occur. <note id="n74">74. Hume, <hi rend="i">Enquiry</hi> 606.</note></p>
            <p>To represent certain axioms of science “as things given independently of our senses” did
“not necessarily damage science,” but it “easily led into the error of believing that these notions,
whose origin is forgotten, are necessary and unalterable accompaniments of our thinking . . . .”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">75</ref> Much of Blake’s effort was directed against
the erroneous philosophic conclusion that the axioms of science originate independently of our thinking, but
he also recognized that true science cannot work the way he described Urizen practicing it, not because
scientists mistake the source of their inventions (that is a philosophical, not a scientific, error), but
because they presume that “reason is something invariable” and go about “Fixing their Systems,
permanent: by mathematic power” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 12:12, E 155). If we truly desire to know more,
we cannot accept a Urizenic pseudo-science of stubbornly invariable rationalism established without regard for
observed and observable features of human experience. <note id="n75">75. Einstein, “Physics and Reality”
299.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Living World</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In Blake’s day important thinkers began seeking, through what Comte called social physics
(<hi rend="i">physique sociale</hi>), universal laws of social behavior, and they tried to eliminate personal
characteristics in the quest for the ideal of a mean average man (Quetelet’s <hi rend="i">l’homme
moyen</hi>). Since “the French Revolution,” Blake observed, “Englishmen are all Intermeasurable One by
Another Certainly a happy state of Agreement to which I for One do not Agree” (letter to Cumberland, 12
April 1827, E 783). Much of his writing needs to be seen as reacting to a type of radicalism that would model
society on the physical sciences, in the hope that each “Individual” within society would appropriate to
himself “Universal Characteristics” and “Universal Attributes” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 90:28-33,
E 250) so that every member of society, like every object in the material world, would be intermeasurable with
every other. Indeed, <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> presents one of the first satires on social
engineering, showing how Urizen, as both natural philosopher and primeval priest, bases his laws of society on
the same principles of fixity and uniformity that he has imposed on the physical world.</p>
            <p>The idea that human behavior could be measured in the way physicists measured the material
world was not limited to radical Enlightenment thinkers. Following the success of Newtonian physics, many,
believing that “<hi rend="i">natural</hi> and <hi rend="i">moral</hi> evidence . . . are of the same nature,
and [are] derived from the same principles,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">76</ref> wished to establish a science of human nature modeled after the physical sciences.
Although the Newtonian revolution looked for “universal laws . . . [and] the ultimate truth of everything as
embodied in these laws . . .,” it overlooked the problem that though there are regularities in the living
world, “most of these regularities are not universal and without exception . . . .”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">77</ref> It ignored the fact that “Man varies from
Man” and triumphed because it erroneously “supposes all Men alike” and believed there could be “One
Law for the Lion &amp; Ox” (annotations to Reynolds, E 656; annotations to Bacon, E 621; 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 24, E 44). <note id="n76">76. Hume, <hi rend="i">Enquiry</hi> 640.</note>
	<note id="n77">77. Mayr 27, 62.</note></p>
            <p>Denying the existence of the world without exceptions that natural philosophy had created,
Blake showed how its laws remained “blind to all the simple rules of life” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
65:28, E 216) because they ignored those “minutely organized Particulars” and individual variations that
were self-evident to any honestly observant individual and foolishly “reduced the variety of nature to . . .
abstract idea[s]” (see Reynolds in annotations to Reynolds, E 649). Blake’s numerous comparisons between
the living worlds of men and animals do not represent merely a poet’s simile or metaphor, but an answer to
the Newtonian revolution of his day. When men were looking to the regularities of celestial mechanics to
comprehend human behavior, Blake did something quite unusual for his
<pb id="p39-120" n="120"/>
time. He turned from the large-scale material world of physical objects to the minutely organized particulars
of animal life to illustrate the kind of rules that might truly describe human behavior.</p>
            <p>Specifically, Blake showed that the living world cannot be comprehended by the same laws
natural philosophers employed to explain the material world they created, because every living thing acts in
accordance with a variety of intentions, propensities, and purposes of its own that are not the effect of and
therefore cannot be explained in terms of efficient, mechanistic causality. To say that from the time of Bacon
on, “nobody before Darwin managed to anticipate,” that “final causes could and would . . . be employed
very usefully in biology . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">78</ref> is
a pretty large claim. However, it is one that cannot be maintained after anyone considers the works of William
Blake, for they repeatedly insist that all biological life needs to be understood in terms of final rather
than efficient causes. <note id="n78">78. Urbach 101.</note></p>
            <p>Moreover, since every living thing behaves in accordance with different purposes and not any
one law, since the “apple tree never asks the beech how he shall grow, nor the lion. the horse; how he shall
take his prey” (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 9:50, E 37), the simple rules of life, as distinguished from the
complex rules of abstract philosophy, tell us that there can be no valid inductive generalizations regarding
biological existence, such as, for example, the growth of plants or the eating habits of animals (unlike apple
trees, beech trees grow only in southern England, and horses aren’t predators). The “Emmets Inch &amp;
Eagles Mile / Make Lame Philosophy to smile” (<hi rend="i">Auguries of Innocence</hi> 105-06, E 492), since
one cannot conclude from observing a portion of existence, like the emmet’s inch, what the rest of the
world, like the eagle’s mile, will be like. With statistics and the rules of chance and probability, the
social sciences in the late eighteenth century and the biological sciences in the nineteenth and twentieth
would successfully challenge the mechanistic determinism of classical physics, and with the advent of atomic
physics even the physicists started playing dice with the universe. However, by the 1790s Blake was already
illustrating how biological existence provided living proof that the determinism of Bacon, Newton and Locke
was fundamentally flawed.</p>
            <p>Blake’s response to Newtonianism was thus a lot simpler, more direct and obvious than Donald
Ault’s elaborate and complex work, <hi rend="i">Visionary Physics</hi>, would lead us to believe. However
intimate Blake was with Newtonian physics, he did not need to offer an intricately detailed refutation of it.
All he felt he had to do to stop the new philosophy dead in its tracks was to remind his readers of what
everyone well knew and what the philosophers chose to overlook: consider the living world of man and animals
that we are all familiar with. Does it conform to Newtonian principles of natural philosophy? Not at all. So
how can any system of scientific laws that does not explain life itself claim to be a fundamental and
universal explanation comprehending all existence? Blake insisted over and again that the “Sciences of
Urizen” triumphed “at the cost of every thing that breathes” (<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 102:22, E
375), and he did not have to create his own system to counter Newton’s. The alternative universe he kept
illustrating was no fictional creation, but something that had always existed: a living, breathing world that
operated by its own internal causes, but that the natural philosophers refused to consult because it could not
be explained in Newtonian terms.</p>
            <p>The stranglehold that Newtonian formulations have had on modern thought may be measured by the
fact that as late as 1944 a physicist like Erwin Schroedinger still had to remind his audience that the
workings of living organisms “cannot be reduced to the laws of physics.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">79</ref> Over a century and a half before that, Blake kept insisting
that this kind of reductionism was more than just foolish. It was unscientific. In the living world, causality
originates from <hi rend="i">within</hi> each thing and does not operate as some scientists presumed it to
operate in the physical world, where every thing was being viewed as the cause of every other thing but never
as its own cause: “Every thing in Eternity shines by its own <hi rend="i">Internal</hi> light” 
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 10:16, E 104; my italics), and that light remains within us while we are in the world of
experience. What the “Philosophy of Causes &amp; Consequences” refused to recognize was that in the living
world “Each thing is its own cause” and instead by “Demonstration” made “Accident” the
“Substance &amp; Principle” of human behavior (annotations to Lavater, E 601; <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
29:35-36, E 128). In other words, Blake understood that a perfectly realistic explanation for the behavior of
living things could be given in terms of teleology or purposive causality (as in Eden, where “Wheel within
Wheel in freedom revolve,” motivating from within and without hindrance from external forces) instead of
efficient or mechanical causality (as in Experience, where natural philosophers find only “wheel without
wheel, with cogs tyrannic / Moving by compulsion each other” [<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 15:18-20, E
159]—the cogwheels here might refer to those of a clock and to the then popular clock-work view of the
universe). In “a teleological system, its behavior involves . . . the expenditure of energy derived from a
local source rather than from the environment. The teleological system is . . . not goaded by the
environment,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">80</ref> or, as Blake put it,
a teleological system “is its own cause.” <note id="n79">79. Schroedinger 81.</note>
	<note id="n80">80. Beckner 134.</note></p>
            <p>It is by the same mechanisms of sense perception carried on with the identical sense organs
that the chicken and the hawk receive impressions from the physical world, but they do not respond in
identical ways to the identical impressions as sensationist psychology would have us believe, because each is
impelled not by natural causes external to it, but is guided by its own “internal light.”
<pb id="p39-121" n="121"/>
	<q>
With what sense is it that the chicken shuns the ravenous hawk?<lb/>
With what sense does the tame pigeon measure out the expanse?<lb/>
With what sense does the bee form cells? have not the mouse &amp; frog<lb/>
Eyes and ears and sense of touch? yet are their habitations.<lb/>
And their pursuits, as different as their forms and as their joys:<lb/>
Ask the wild ass why he refuses burdens: and the meek camel<lb/>
Why he loves man: is it because of eye ear mouth or skin<lb/>
Or breathing nostrils? No. for these the wolf and tyger have.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> 3:2-9, E 47)
</q>
One cannot apply a cause and effect determinism to study the actions of wolves or camels or men because the
law of the living world is that for every action there is an opposite and <hi rend="i">unequal</hi> reaction.
Strike a rock with another rock, and it will react pretty much like any other rock. Strike a chicken and a
tiger with the same rock, and you will immediately notice the difference, but you will have to strike the
chicken first. Lockean psychology had overlooked what everyone obviously knew, that even the mind of a chicken
is not originally a blank slate that will be shaped entirely by sense impressions.</p>
            <p>Similarly, Blake argued that one could not arrive at “General Knowledge” of men based on
the fact that they have identical sense organs: “Every Man has Eyes Nose &amp; Mouth this Every Idiot knows
but he who enters into &amp; discriminates most minutely the Manners &amp; Intentions the . . . Characters in
all their branches is the alone Wise or Sensible Man . . .” (<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>,
E 560). “Man varies from Man more than Animal from Animal of Different Species” (annotations to Reynolds,
E 656) because the manner of each person’s behavior, even more than that of each animal, is the outcome of
his various intentions (purposive causality) and not the effect of what every man similarly senses in the
world he experiences (efficient causality). Because man is not “Naturally . . . only a natural organ subject
to Sense” (<hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, E 2), it is therefore not possible to predict
according to environmental circumstances how various persons will behave under similar or identical
conditions: “Want of Money &amp; the Distress of A Thief can never be alledged as the Cause of his Thievery.
for many honest people endure greater hard ships with Fortitude We must therefore seek the Cause elsewhere
than in want of Money . . .” (letter to Trusler, 23 Aug. 1799, E 702). The identity of sense organs,
combined with the irregularity of behavior in men and animals, reveals that sense experience does not
determine and therefore cannot possibly explain the actions of men or animals. The obvious differences in
their behavior means that any science of living beings has to look to what is different about them to
understand why they act the way they do: it has to understand their different “propensities,”
“intentions” and “pursuits.”</p>
            <p>Ever since antiquity, scientists had searched for the laws of the universe because of their
faith in a God who was both creator and lawgiver. Newtonianism seemed to be the ultimate vindication of that
search and the faith that inspired it, and the natural religion of the Enlightenment put the capstone on this
almighty edifice. “Look round the world: . . . you will find it to be nothing but one great machine,
subdivided into an infinite number of lesser machines” each accurately adjusted to one another, all of which
proves “at once the existence of a Deity, and his similarity to human mind and intelligence.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">81</ref> With the Age of Reason, the endeavor of
natural philosophers to create a solid universe of fixed laws culminated with such a pervasive intensity,
affecting all aspects of thought—Urizenic thinking took over everything, suppressed all thought, vision,
imagination, passion—that Blake felt the falsity of it all would soon become clear: Los sees “the finger
of God . . . / . . . / Fixing their Systems, permanent: by mathematic power / Giving a body to Falshood that
it may be cast off for ever” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 12:10-13, E 155). <note id="n81">81. Hume, 
<hi rend="i">Dialogues</hi> 701.</note></p>
            <p>Indeed in 1831, twenty-seven years after Blake printed those words and just four years after he
died, the <hi rend="i">Beagle</hi> set sail. It is impossible to tell exactly how Blake would have responded
to Darwin’s great work, much of which he no doubt would have found repugnant. However, we do know that he
had no trouble defending Paine against Bishop Watson’s attack on his <hi rend="i">Age of Reason</hi>, a work
with which Blake certainly had much disagreement, and he readily interpreted the Bible in his infernal way so
as to overlook what was disagreeable and highlight what he favored, so there is good reason to suppose that he
also would have extracted from Darwin whatever suited his purposes. There is much that would have delighted
Blake, who thought “the Creator of this World is a very Cruel Being” (<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last
Judgment</hi>, E 565).</p>
            <p>When Blake inquired “Did he who made the Lamb make thee?” he knew that it is not credible
to say that God made the lamb and not the tyger, the implication being that there is no moral plan according
to which God made only what the religious call good qualities (lamb-like meekness) and did not also create and
even smile upon what they call evil (tyger-like wrath). We are not “put on earth” to fulfill any
providential design or plan, such as, for example, learning as slaves “to bear the beams of [God’s]
love” (“Little Black Boy,” E 9). Priests who proclaim that the “Gods had orderd such things” merely
take advantage of the vulgar (see <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 11, E 38), for in truth no God preordained,
planned or created anything.</p>
            <p>Perhaps, then, the best answer to the question regarding the making of tygers and lambs is not
that God made both, but that no distant hand or eye created either. Blake thoroughly rejected the Genesis
account of creation, along with its Creator God. He was an anti-creationist who held that “Eternity Exists
and All things in Eternity” and found the supposition that all was once “Solitude &amp; Chaos” to be
“the most pernicious Idea” (<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, E 563). He therefore might very
well have loved much that Darwin achieved after he returned from his momentous voyage. Darwin destroyed not
only the Creator God, but also “conceptions that had reigned in the philosophy of nature and knowledge for
two thousand years [which] . . . rested on the assumption of the fixed and final . . .
<pb id="p39-122" n="122"/>
[The] ‘Origin of Species’ introduced a mode of thinking that in the end was bound to transform the logic
of knowledge, and hence the treatment of morals, and religion.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n82" type="note">82</ref>
	<note id="n82">82. Dewey 1-2.</note></p>
            <p>Blake’s realization that “All Knowledge is Particular,” that “Unless. You Consult.
Particulars. You Cannot. even Know or See . . . any Thing . . .” and that “Science cannot exist but in
minutely organized Particulars / And not in generalizing Demonstrations of the Rational Power” 
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 55:62-63, E 205) derived in large part from his understanding of the behavior of men
and animals. These insights could very well have served as guidelines for the research methods Darwin
employed. Certainly no scientist before Darwin consulted minutely organized particulars, every inch and mile
of creation, more than he did. Darwin’s painstaking research into the living world of plants and animals did
not lead him to reduce the variety of nature to fixities and uniformities, as all those Urizenic scientists
before him did. His writings are filled with terms Blake used or would certainly have appreciated—words like
<hi rend="i">individual differences and variations</hi>—and he showed how and why minute particulars are
organized the way they are. Darwin’s work was the hammer of Los that destroyed the Urizenic error that had
been misleading scientists for millennia.</p>
            <p>Blake was one of the very few prior to Darwin who understood the error of fixity and finality.
He hammered away at perhaps the fundamental mistake of all pre-Darwinian thinking as it affected science, as
well as society’s moral and religious beliefs. He recognized just why there was so much secrecy surrounding
God’s “words and laws”—because there were no universal, preestablished laws that religion could
discover. They were merely priestly inventions. Once natural philosophers similarly claimed to have discovered
fixed and final abstract laws, Blake noted that these laws were equally fictitious creations and not the stuff
of real science. For Blake, true science must give us knowledge of those minutely organized images of truth
that we all experience, and if it does not, then the so-called new philosophy is just the same old philosophy
all over again.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">“The labours of Art &amp; Science”</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Nowadays we tend to divide art and science into different cultures—their studies are located
in different parts of most universities. However, Blake’s contemporaries considered science to be a branch
of philosophy. Blake responded by seeking to differentiate both art and science, which he viewed as related
endeavors, from all philosophy, including natural philosophy. The phrase “art and science” appears over
seventeen times in his writings (too many times to list—five appear in the first two paragraphs of this
essay—so the reader interested in all of them should consult David Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Blake
Concordance</hi>). As Blake understood it, science, along with art, was one of the intellectual gifts of
humanity; its aims were to be distinguished not only from natural philosophy, but also from all moral and
religious concerns, since those who “trouble Religion with Questions concerning Good &amp; Evil” and all
such “Knowledges or Reasonings” despise and hinder “Imaginative Art &amp; Science &amp; all Intellectual
Gifts all the Gifts of the Holy Ghost” (<hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, E 554). For Blake,
what has marked the two warring cultures of Western civilization have been the attempts of moralists and
theologians to hinder the work of artists and scientists, with the dark religions and abstract philosophy (the
frequent handmaiden of religion) opposing art and science. “Laws &amp; Moralities / . . . destroy
Imagination” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 74:12-13, E 229). Throughout his writings, Blake called for the
liberation of both art and science from their traditional hindrances.</p>
            <p>What kind of science could he possibly have been thinking of? And who was practicing it? As
Blake saw it, science is one of the eternal arts of humanity, and from science every earthly occupation
derives: “in Eternity the Four Arts: Poetry, Painting, Music, / And Architecture which is Science: are the
Four Faces of Man. / Not so in Time &amp; Space: there . . . only / Science remains . . . &amp; by means of
Science, the Three / Become apparent in Time &amp; Space, in the Three Professions / Poetry in Religion:
Music, Law: Painting, in Physic &amp; Surgery: / That Man may live upon Earth . . ., / And from these Three,
Science derives every Occupation of Men. / . . . Science is divided” and “Some Sons of Los” build
“porches of iron &amp; silver” while “Others; Cabinets richly fabricate” and “the Artist [takes] his
clay / . . . to mould artful a model for golden ornaments” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 27:55-28:15, E
125-26).</p>
            <p>These are the words of a professional artisan who represented the poetic genius not as someone
sitting on an old grey stone for the length of half a day or invoking inspiration from the wind (cf.
Wordsworth’s “Expostulation and Reply” and Shelley’s “Ode to the West Wind”), but as Los, the
smithy continuously working at and giving concrete form to his art and not off generalizing about abstractions
as Urizen does. As science has become increasingly specialized and theoretical, Blake’s description might
first strike us as out of date, but when attempting to understand what he meant by the art of science, we
should recall that Leonardo practiced science and Goethe worked at it in Blake’s day. Later still, Borodin
was a chemist, Chekhov a physician, and Kafka an excellent lawyer. In a lecture at the Royal Institution
(given on 16 June 1836), Constable contended, “Painting is a science . . . a branch of natural philosophy,
of which pictures are but experiments.” Not an opinion Blake would entirely have agreed with, because he
sought to distinguish art and science from philosophy, but it shows that other artists in Blake’s day also
considered art and science to be allied disciplines.</p>
            <p>Moreover, as science developed it continued to go in the direction Blake wished to move it,
divorcing itself from speculative philosophy and its concerns and claims, but not necessarily from the
occupations of the artist. At the end of the twentieth century, the paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould offered
<pb id="p39-123" n="123"/>
his opinion as to the nature of science and how it differs from philosophy: “Maybe philosophers do sit in
their armchairs and think about the nature of reality,” he said. “But I don’t think most practicing
scientists do, I think they just get on with their work.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n83" type="note">83</ref> The physicist Freeman Dyson agrees that “science has more in common with
art than it has with philosophy.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">84</ref>
At the end of the eighteenth century, Blake struggled to establish a view of science as a practical discipline
completely separate from the concerns and claims of philosophy. By the end of the twentieth century, his
assessment has become the one accepted by a number of scientists and philosophers. <note id="n83">83. Gould
80.</note>
	<note id="n84">84. Dyson 139.</note></p>
            <p>In the West, the only science worth speaking of prior to the scientific revolution of the
Renaissance occurred in ancient Greece, and it pretty much died there, in part because it was largely
something studied by an aristocratic class of philosophers who had little or no interest in its practical
applications and who would not have understood what Berkeley meant when he wrote that the “study of
nature” serves to frame “artificial things for the use and ornament of life.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">85</ref> Significantly Blake’s poetic genius, Los, is a member of
the working class for whom science and art is an occupation he labors at and not simply something that he sits
thinking about at his leisure. He is the perfect embodiment of Berkeley’s description of the nature and
purpose of real science, as distinguished from the musings of natural philosophers:
<q>
the end of speculation [should] be practice, or the improvement or regulation of our lives and actions; yet
those, who are most addicted to speculative studies, seem as generally of another mind . . . . [Men] of
leisure . . . lay themselves out in fruitless disquisitions, without descending to the practical parts of
life, or informing themselves in the more necessary and important parts of knowledge.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">86</ref>
	<note id="n85">85. Berkeley, <hi rend="i">Treatise</hi> 544.</note>
	<note id="n86">86. Berkeley, <hi rend="i">Dialogues</hi> 103.</note></q></p>
            <p>Modern science is distinguished by its insistence on empirical observation and proof, and that
advancement in learning is due, to an extent not fully appreciated, to the interests and work of a class of
ordinary artisans, among whom were the painters, silversmiths and blacksmiths, ironworkers and cabinetmakers
Blake listed as doing the work of science. To take a few examples from many: in 1698 an English merchant,
Thomas Savery, patented a steam device for clearing water from coal mines; an instrument maker, James Watt,
perfected the engine; and in 1824, a French military engineer, Sadi Carnot, published a treatise on the steam
engine, <hi rend="i">Reflexions on the Motive Power of Fire</hi>, all of which eventually made the science of
thermodynamics possible, as the science of aerodynamics was advanced by two brothers who ran a bicycle shop in
Dayton, Ohio. It is of no small significance that Galileo, often considered the father of modern science,
placed his last and most important scientific dialogue (<hi rend="i">Concerning Two New Sciences</hi>) in a
shipyard.</p>
            <p>Examining the rise of empiricism in his <hi rend="i">Mathematical Thought from Ancient to
Modern Times</hi>, Morris Kline noted: “While reformers of science urged the return to nature . . .,
practically oriented artisans, engineers, and painters[!] were actually obtaining the hard facts of
experience.” They “dealt with particulars, rather than generalities [“To Generalize is to be an
Idiot”; “Science cannot exist but in minutely organized Particulars / And not in generalizing
Demonstrations of the Rational Power” (annotations to Reynolds, E 641; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 55:62-63,
E 205)], and they added to science instead of defining it . . . .” The “pure empiricism of the
artisans,” working with “mechanical ideas and properties of materials” provided “new physical insights
[that] were impressive.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">87</ref> Indeed,
one of those artisans not only wrote about science but also demonstrated how art and science actually work
together—how every occupation of man derives from and involves real scientific work. Experimenting with
copper, gum arabic, and acid, he made his own impressive discovery. In 1972 I met with a printer and happened
to ask him if he knew the work of William Blake. He could hardly sit still. “Oh, William Blake!” he
exclaimed. “That is printing of the 21st century!” <note id="n87">87. Kline 1: 227-28.</note></p>
            <p>In the end, I hope this essay has shown that, for all that’s been written to explain and
celebrate Blake as a mystic or visionary, he was a child of the Enlightenment who sought, as did the finest
thinkers of the age, to free men from their numerous “mind-forg’d manacles” (“London,” E 27) which
served only to hinder art and science, whose work he believed formed the basis of any good society. He, like
other Enlightenment figures, sought to reevaluate those eternal verities that custom, tradition and law
required men to believe in, and to redefine what individuals can sense to be true and what they know is not;
in the process he defined for himself and others a quite modern version of truth which, in the best spirit of
the Enlightenment, was at once accepting, tolerant and critically very astute. Blake examined ancient and
modern conceptions of the truths of reason to show that rational truths were neither true nor false with
respect to all those images of truth we experience, and anyone who claimed that they were true in that sense
was speaking falsely, since there was no foundation in experience for any such belief or claim. On the other
hand, everything that humans do experience is true, has to be true, and cannot possibly be untrue; no one, no
philosopher, nor king or priest, has any right to reject or condemn anything humans experience as being false
or wrong, for “every thing that lives is holy!” (<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>
8:10, E 51).</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p39-124" n="124"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ault, Donald D. <hi rend="i">Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton.</hi> Chicago:
University of Chicago Press, 1974.</p>
            <p>Bacon, Francis. <hi rend="i">Novum Organum.</hi> Burtt 24-123.</p>
            <p>Beckner, Morton. <hi rend="i">The Biological Way of Thought.</hi> Berkeley: University of
California Press, 1968.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E, Jr. <hi rend="i">The Stranger From Paradise: A Biography of William Blake.</hi>
New Haven: Yale University Press, 2001.</p>
            <p>Berkeley, George. <hi rend="i">Three Dialogues.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">A Treatise Concerning the Principles of Human Knowledge.</hi> Burtt
507-79.</p>
            <p>Birenbaum, Harvey. <hi rend="i">Between Blake and Nietzsche.</hi> Lewisburg: Bucknell
University Press, 1992.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Ed. David
Erdman. Newly rev. ed. New York: Anchor Books, 1988.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse.</hi> Garden City, NY: Doubleday &amp; Co.,
1965.</p>
            <p>—. Commentary. Blake 894-970.</p>
            <p>Bohr, Niels. “Discussion with Einstein.” <hi rend="i">Atomic Physics and Human
Knowledge.</hi> New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1958. 32-66.</p>
            <p>Born, Max. “On the Meaning of Physical Theories.” Weaver 1: 56-75.</p>
            <p>Boyle, Robert. <hi rend="i">A Free Enquiry into the Vulgarly Received Notion of Nature.</hi>
Ed. Edward B. Davis and Michael Hunter. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996.</p>
            <p>Burtt, Edwin A, ed. <hi rend="i">The English Philosophers from Bacon to Mill.</hi> New York:
Random House, 1939.</p>
            <p>Copernicus, Nicolaus. <hi rend="i">On the Revolution of Heavenly Spheres.</hi> Hawking, 
<hi rend="i">Shoulders of Giants</hi> 7-388.</p>
            <p>Cox, Stephen. <hi rend="i">Love and Logic.</hi> Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press,
1992.</p>
            <p>Dawkins, Richard. <hi rend="i">Unweaving the <corr type="emend">Rainbow.</corr></hi> London: Penguin Books, 1998.</p>
            <p>Dewey, John. <hi rend="i">The Influence of Darwin on Philosophy.</hi> Amherst, NY: Prometheus
Books, 1997.</p>
            <p>Duhem, Pierre. <hi rend="i">The Aim and Structure of Physical Theory.</hi> Tr. Philip P.
Weiner. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1991.</p>
            <p>Dyson, Freeman. “In Praise of Diversity.” Kayzer 105-40.</p>
            <p>Eddington, Arthur. “The New Law of Gravitation and the Old.” Weaver 2: 235-47.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Philosophy of Physical Science.</hi> Ann Arbor: University of Michigan
Press, 1978.</p>
            <p>Einstein, Albert. “On the Method of Theoretical Physics.” <hi rend="i">Ideas and
Opinions.</hi> New York: Crown Publishers, 1982. 270-76.</p>
            <p>—. “Physics and Reality.” <hi rend="i">Ideas and Opinions.</hi> New York: Crown
Publishers, 1982. 290-323.</p>
            <p>Einstein, Albert, and Leopold Infeld. <hi rend="i">The Evolution of Physics.</hi> New York:
Simon &amp; Schuster, 1938.</p>
            <p>Emery, Clark. Introduction. William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>
Coral Gables: University of Miami Press, 1963.</p>
            <p>Everett, Hugh. “Remarks on the Role of Theoretical Physics.” <hi rend="i">The Many-Worlds
Interpretation of Quantum Mechanics.</hi> Ed. Bryce DeWitt and Neill Graham. Princeton: Princeton University
Press, 1973. 133-37.</p>
            <p>Feynman, Richard. “The Uncertainty of Science.” <hi rend="i">The Meaning of It All.</hi>
Reading, MA: Perseus Books, 1998. 1-28.</p>
            <p>Fisher, Peter. <hi rend="i">The Valley of Vision.</hi> Toronto: University of Toronto Press,
1961.</p>
            <p>Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry.</hi> Boston: Beacon Press, 1965.</p>
            <p>Galilei, Galileo. <hi rend="i">Dialogues Concerning Two New Sciences.</hi> Hawking, 
<hi rend="i">Shoulders of Giants</hi> 399-626.</p>
            <p>Gould, Stephen Jay. “Unanswerable Questions.” Kayzer 75-104.</p>
            <p>Hawking, Stephen. <hi rend="i">A Brief History of Time.</hi> New York: Bantam, 1989.</p>
            <p>—, ed. <hi rend="i">On the Shoulders of Giants.</hi> Philadelphia: Running Press, 2002.</p>
            <p>Heisenberg, Werner. <hi rend="i">Physics and Philosophy.</hi> New York: Harper &amp; Row,
1958.</p>
            <p>Hume, David. <hi rend="i">Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion.</hi> Burtt 690-764.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding.</hi> Burtt 583-689.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">A Treatise of Human Nature.</hi> 2 vols. New York: E. P. Dutton &amp; Co.,
1962.</p>
            <p>Kayzer, Wim. “<hi rend="i">A Glorious Accident</hi>”<hi rend="i">: Understanding Our Place
in the Cosmic Puzzle.</hi> New York: W. H. Freeman &amp; Co., 1995.</p>
            <p>Keynes, John Maynard. “Newton, the Man.” Weaver 1: 539-47.</p>
            <p>Kline, Morris. <hi rend="i">Mathematical Thought from Ancient to Modern Times.</hi> 3 vols.
Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1972.</p>
            <p>Locke, John. <hi rend="i">An Essay Concerning Human Understanding.</hi> Burtt 237-402.</p>
            <p>Mach, Ernst. “The Guiding Principles of My Scientific Theory of Knowledge.” 
<hi rend="i">Physical Reality.</hi> Ed. Stephen Toulmin. New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1970. 28-43.</p>
            <p>Mayr, Ernst. <hi rend="i">This Is Biology.</hi> Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press,
1997.</p>
            <p>Newton, Isaac. “An Account of the Book entituled <hi rend="i">Commercium Epistolicum.
Newton.</hi> Ed. I. Bernard Cohen and Richard S. Westfall. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Co., 1995. 161-64.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Correspondence of Isaac Newton.</hi> 7 vols. Ed. H. W. Turnbull, A. R.
Hall, and L. Tilling. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1959-77.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy.</hi> Tr. Andrew Motte [London,
1729], rev. Florian Cajori. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1960.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Opticks.</hi> New York: Dover Publications, 1952.</p>
            <p>Norris, Christopher. <hi rend="i">Quantum Theory and the Flight from Realism.</hi> New York:
Routledge, 2000.</p>
            <p>Nurmi, Martin K. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Kent, OH: Kent State University Press,
1976.</p>
            <p>Pearson, Karl. <hi rend="i">The Grammar of Science.</hi> New York: Meridian Books, 1960.</p>
            <p>Planck, Max. “Dynamical Laws and Statistical Laws.” Weaver 1: 90-100.</p>
            <p>—. “The Scientist’s Picture of the Physical Universe.” <hi rend="i">Where Is Science
Going?</hi> Ed. and trans. James Murphy. Woodbridge, CT: Ox Bow Press, 1981. 84-106.</p>
            <p>Reid, Thomas. <hi rend="i">Essays on the Active Powers of the Human Mind.</hi> Ed. Baruch Body.
Cambridge: MIT Press, 1969.</p>
            <p>Rogers, Ben. <hi rend="i">A. J. Ayer: A Life.</hi> New York: Grove Press, 1999.</p>
            <p>Russell, Bertrand. “On the Notion of Cause.” <hi rend="i">Mysticism and Logic.</hi> New
York: W. W. Norton &amp; Co., 1929. 180-208.</p>
            <p>Schlick, Moritz. “The Turning Point in Philosophy.” <hi rend="i">Logical Positivism.</hi>
Ed. A. J. Ayer. New York: Free Press, 1959. 53-59.</p>
            <pb id="p39-125" n="125"/>
            <p>Schorer, Mark. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Politics of Vision.</hi> New York: Random House,
1959.</p>
            <p>Schroedinger, Erwin. <hi rend="i">What is Life; Mind and Matter.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press, 1967.</p>
            <p>Sobel, Dava. <hi rend="i">Galileo’s Daughter.</hi> New York: Penguin Books, 1999.</p>
            <p>Toulmin, Stephen E. “Science, Philosophy of.” <hi rend="i">Britannica Online. Encyclopædia
Britannica.</hi> 26 May 2003. &lt;http://www.britannica.com&gt;.</p>
            <p>Urbach, Peter. <hi rend="i">Francis Bacon’s Philosophy of Science.</hi> La Salle, IL: Open
Court, 1993.</p>
            <p>Weaver, Jefferson Hane, ed. <hi rend="i">The World of Physics.</hi> 3 vols. New York: Simon and
Schuster, 1987.</p>
            <p>Weinberg, Steven. <hi rend="i">Facing Up: Science and Its Cultural Adversaries.</hi> Cambridge:
Harvard University Press, 2001.</p>
            <p>Wigner, Eugene. <hi rend="i">Symmetries and Reflections.</hi> Woodbridge, CT: Ox Bow Press,
1979.</p>
            <p>Williams, Roger J. <hi rend="i">Free and Unequal: The Biological Basis of Individual
Liberty.</hi> Austin: University of Texas Press, 1953.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
