<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.3.groves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake and the Sheffield Iris</title>
        <author n="Groves">David Groves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2005/2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005-06</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Harry White</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>David Fuller</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005/2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
	  <pb id="p39-125" n="125"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake and the <hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>David <name>Groves</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris</hi> was a weekly eight-page newspaper, founded in 1794 by the
poet and reformer James Montgomery (1771-1854). Its enlightened political views gave the 
<hi rend="i">Iris</hi> an influence far beyond the English manufacturing city of Sheffield. Although
Montgomery’s role as editor ended in 1825, he continued to take an interest in the paper, and to contribute
occasional pieces to it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n88">1. See John Holland and James Everett, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James
Montgomery, Including Selections from His Correspondence</hi>, 7 vols. (London: Longman, 1856) 1: 175 and 7:
95. Montgomery had some interest in Blake, and in the 1808 edition of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, with
designs by Blake (see Holland and Everett 1: 38 and G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
[Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969] 194). In the review that follows, however, there seems to be no evidence of
Montgomery’s pen. See also the valuable discussion of the Cromek-Montgomery-Blake nexus in Robert N. Essick
and Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave <hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake: A
Study with Facsimile</hi> (London: Scolar P, 1982) 23-25.</note></p>
          <p>When the second volume of Allan Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British
Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi> appeared in 1830, it was reviewed in the <hi rend="i">Iris</hi>, with
special attention to Cunningham’s chapter on Blake. The anonymous review has never been reprinted or
mentioned in print, until now:
<q>
FAMILY LIBRARY.—PAINTERS.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n89">2. Anon., <hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris</hi> 9 February 1830: 4. The opening words, “NUMBER X.
of this interesting work,” refer to the “Family Library” series, of which number ten was the second of
Cunningham’s six-volume <hi rend="i">Lives.</hi> “Albemarle-street” was the location of Cunningham’s
London publisher, John Murray. “Swedenberg” was of course the mystic Emanuel Swedenborg.</note>
	<lb/>
<lb/>
NUMBER X. of this interesting work, which we have on a previous occasion introduced to our readers, is just
published, and comprises the lives of seven painters—West, Barry, Blake, Opie, Morland, Bird, and Fuseli,
with likenesses, more or less highly finished, of each. To say, that the memoirs contained in this neat
volume—the second of “British Painters, Sculptures [sic], and Architects,” are from the fascinating pen
of Allan Cunningham, and the far-famed depot of Albemarle-street, leaves nothing else to be added in the way
of praise. What a singular being was William Blake! A painter, an engraver, a poet, and a visionary,—in the
last character perhaps little less singular than Swedenberg [sic] himself. “To describe” says the
biographer “the conversations which Blake held in prose with demons, and in verse with angels, would fill
volumes, and an ordinary gallery could not contain all the heads which he drew of his visionary visitants.
That all this was real, he himself most sincerely believed; nay, so infectious was his enthusiasm, that some
acute and sensible persons who heard him expatiate, shook their heads, and hinted that he was an extraordinary
man, and that there might be something in the matter.” The spirits, however, who thus obeyed the artist’s
bidding, came not to reveal any secrets, save the secrets of their own countenances—in short they came as
might be expected at the call of a painter—to have their portraits taken! and many of the likenesses of
these spiritual sitters did poor Blake delineate, from the heroic Wallace to the “ghost of a flea!”
Instead of transcribing the narrative of these unearthly vagaries, we shall copy the brief account of the
enthusiast’s procedure and luck in a transaction incident to the greater part of mankind: but in which few
engage so inconsiderately, and fewer still, when that is the case, with such exemplary good fortune:—
</q>
(The two paragraphs that follow are the ninth and tenth paragraphs of Cunningham’s chapter on Blake, from
the first edition of the <hi rend="i">Lives.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
type="note">3</ref> The only substantive change is the spelling of the names of Blake’s wife as
[alternatively] “Katharine Boucher” and “Catharine Boucher.” Blake was in fact 24, not 26, when he
married.) <note id="n90">3. The second edition of Cunningham’s life of Blake is reprinted in Bentley
476-507.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
