<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.3.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">A (Self?) Portrait of William Blake</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2005/2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2005-06</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Harry White</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>David Fuller</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2005/2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-3-0007">
        <pb id="p39-126" n="126"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A (Self?) Portrait of William Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The monochrome wash drawing (illus. 1) at the center of this essay has had an interesting career
since it first came to public notice in 1974.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0"
type="note">*</ref> No one has seriously doubted that it is a portrait of William Blake, but its authorship
has remained an open question. The first reasonably definite attribution, proposed by a distinguished art
historian, has received less than universal assent. Perhaps this mystery, coupled with the hypnotic and
hieratic character of the drawing, has contributed to its becoming one of the most reproduced, and hence most
familiar, representations of Blake’s visage. My purpose here is to argue that this work is a self-portrait,
a view that has been noted in several earlier publications but not presented in detail. My proposal is clearly
self-serving, since I own the drawing. Consequently, I have hesitated to publish my views on the portrait’s
attribution for over 30 years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">1</ref> It is
time to come clean. I trust that my arguments will be judged on their merits rather than their source. 
<note id="n0">This essay is dedicated to Dr. Elizabeth B. Bentley. I am grateful to Warren Cariou, Alexander
Gourlay, Sarah Jones, and Joseph Viscomi for their suggestions, and to John Sullivan and Devonne Tice of the
Huntington Library for their assistance with electronic imaging.</note> <note id="n91">1. I have been less
restrained in conversations and correspondence with people who have requested photographs of the
portrait.</note></p>
          <p>The detailed “review of previous research,” once standard in scholarly articles, has in
recent times been honored in the breach. I’ll return to that antiquated genre to set my opinions in context.
This overview of almost everything that, to my knowledge, has been written about the portrait may also provide
some general insights into the vagaries of reception history, the rhetoric of attribution, and the
relationship between material facts and the connoisseur’s eye.</p>
          <p>The drawing came to light in Christie’s London auction catalogue of 5 March 1974. Accompanied
by a black and white illustration, lot 77 was ascribed not to an individual, or even to the ever-productive
“Anonymous,” but to “Circle of William Blake” and titled “Portrait of the Artist.” Anticipating an
after-sale dispute over the identity of either the artist or the subject, Christie’s cleverly hedged its
bets. The “Circle” is expandable, and might even be extended well beyond Blake’s lifetime, and there are
of course men other than the artist and poet with the name “William Blake.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92" type="note">2</ref> The “Artist” portrayed might be anyone in that circle,
not just the person at its center. In spite of Christie’s quibbling rhetoric, I was immediately taken with
the image and believed it to be a portrait of the engraver, artist, and poet William Blake, although at the
time I had no idea as to its creator. The catalogue description included the following point: “on paper
watermarked G. Pine 1802.” The name of the paper manufacturer is incorrect, as I will discuss below, but the
date is both correct and significant. Watermarks provide only a <hi rend="i">terminus a quo</hi>, but
comparison with some known portraits of Blake convinced me that this work, with some idealization and added
youthfulness, might well be datable to c. 1802-04, when the man was 44-47 years old. My interest, however, had
little to do with reasoned arguments and facts. My immediate response, aesthetic and subjective, mastered
other considerations. Even though my instincts were based only on the catalogue reproduction, having never
seen the original, I commissioned the London firm of Baskett &amp; Day to bid for me, and was successful at
800 guineas (then about $1930). <note id="n92">2. See the account of other William Blakes living in London,
1740-1830, in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale UP, 2004) 829-45,
hereafter cited as “<hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2)” followed by page number.</note></p>
          <p>I was not the only Blake enthusiast interested in the drawing. Sir Geoffrey Keynes was preparing
his catalogue of portraits of William and Catherine Blake and contacted me about his work in
progress.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93" type="note">3</ref> With Christie’s help,
Keynes had contacted its vendor, a “Mrs. Isaacs,” not otherwise identified. Keynes informed me, in a
letter of 4 April 1974, that he had written to Mrs. Isaacs, “who replied that her late husband had bought it
at an unknown time &amp; she could tell me nothing.” The provenance trail had grown cold all too quickly.
<note id="n93">3. Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">The Complete Portraiture of William and Catherine Blake</hi>
(London: Trianon P for the William Blake Trust, 1977), hereafter cited as “Keynes” followed by page
number.</note></p>
          <p>Martin Butlin was the next person to contact me about my acquisition. With admirable industry, he
wrote the first—and until the present effort the only—article specifically on the portrait, published in
the journal <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> in 1975 with the drawing reproduced on the front cover.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94" type="note">4</ref> Although brief, the essay is packed with
information and a sophisticated argument for attribution. Butlin begins and ends with high praise for the
drawing: it “is probably one of the most fascinating known representations of an artist [and] represents the
‘Spiritual Form’ of Blake and as such is his most striking portrayal” (101, 103). He is “immediately
impressed by its Blakean qualities” (101), finds striking similarities between the portrait and Blake’s
Visionary Head of c. 1819-20, <hi rend="i">The Man Who Taught Blake Painting in His Dreams</hi>,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95" type="note">5</ref> and notes that this pencil drawing is “an
idealised self-portrait” (102). These views might seem to lead to an attribution of the wash portrait to
Blake, but Butlin takes a sharp turn away from that possibility, warning us “against the temptation to see
the drawing as the work of Blake himself” (102). The parallels with <hi rend="i">The Man Who Taught Blake
Painting in His Dreams</hi> were “most obvious” (102) to Butlin when he studied not Blake’s original 
                        <pb id="p39-127" n="127"/>
            <figure n="K35.1.1.WD" rend="file" width="786" height="1000">
	<head>1. <hi rend="i">Portrait of William Blake</hi>, recto.</head>
	<figDesc>Pencil with black, white, and gray washes, 24.3 × 20.1 cm. On wove paper with an “[E]DMEADS &amp;
PINE / 1802” watermark. Collection of Robert N. Essick.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p39-128" n="128"/>
but a replica tentatively attributed to John Linnell (illus. 2). Further, “the ‘painterly’ treatment of
the coat and kerchief” and, “in the face,” the “somehow cold and brittle rather than bounding and
alive” quality of the “otherwise Blakean line” lead Butlin to claim that Linnell is “the most likely
author” of the portrait (102). Although he does not say as much directly, Butlin implies that Linnell based
the portrait partly on <hi rend="i">The Man Who Taught Blake Painting in His Dreams</hi>, converting it into a
portrait of the man whose features were already present in a stylized form in the Visionary Head. Given the
watermark date, Linnell was using a rather old sheet of paper. As Butlin points out, however, “the length of
time between the date of the watermarks in the sketchbook [i.e., the Smaller Blake-Varley Sketchbook], 1806,
and Blake’s use of it in 1819, is not much less than that between the watermark of this drawing, 1802, and
the probable date when Linnell would have executed it, c. 1819-25” (102-03).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96" type="note">6</ref> One further feature associates the portrait with Linnell and
John Varley, both of whom were involved in Blake’s production of the Visionary Heads and the engravings of a
select few in Varley’s <hi rend="i">Treatise on Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi> (1828). “Linnell’s involvement
with Varley’s <hi rend="i">Treatise</hi> is particularly significant in relation to the rough sketches on
the back of the drawing [illus. 4], which have parallels in Varley’s own work, including the drawings he
made in the [Smaller] Blake-Varley Sketchbook before Blake used it for some of the Visionary Heads” (102).
<note id="n94">4. Martin Butlin, “A New Portrait of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 7 no.
2 (1975): 101-03.</note>
	<note id="n95">5. Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New
Haven: Yale UP, 1981) 1: 526, #753, hereafter cited as “Butlin” followed by entry number for the work
referenced.</note>
	<note id="n96">6. Linnell did not meet Blake until the spring or early summer of 1818. By 24 June the two men
were working together on an engraved portrait of James Upton (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 340-41).</note></p>
          <p>I find Butlin’s arguments more compelling for their cleverness, even brilliance, than for the
evidence marshaled in their support. Indeed, the main reason for accepting the attribution to Linnell is
Butlin’s authority as a skilled art historian who has spent decades studying and cataloguing paintings and
drawings by Blake and his circle. As a general rule, the educated eye of the connoisseur is primary; the
evidentiary support comes later, not as an inductive method for leading the connoisseur to an opinion, but as
a deductive strategy for convincing others that his views are correct. Thus it was with my decision to bid on
the drawing, and thus I believe it was for Butlin. By placing <hi rend="i">The Man Who Taught Blake Painting
in His Dreams</hi> as an intermediary between the author of the portrait and Blake’s actual visage, Butlin
can simultaneously accept the “Blakean qualities” of the drawing and resist an attribution to Blake
himself. Unlike the counterproofs and replicas of Blake’s Visionary Heads produced by Varley and
Linnell,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97" type="note">7</ref> the portrait is not a line
for line copy of any preexisting design. Given Butlin’s perspective, the portrait is a complex amalgam of a
work by Blake and the man’s actual face—a face that had already influenced the drawing used as a model.
Linnell presumably submerged his own stylistic characteristics beneath Blake’s in a pictorial equivalent of
ventriloquism, for Butlin makes no mention of any Linnellean qualities in the drawing. The result is a
double-likeness, one that captures both Blake’s face and his own conception of that face. But is Butlin’s
theory too convoluted, too clever by half? I will return later to his observations, point by point. 
<note id="n97">7. They probably used an ocular instrument to produce these copies; see Martin Butlin, “Blake, the
Varleys, and the Graphic Telescope,” <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey
Keynes</hi>, ed. Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1973) 294-304.</note></p>
          <p>Keynes’ catalogue of portraits of Blake, containing an almost full-size black and white
reproduction of the drawing, appeared only two years after Butlin’s essay and is much indebted to it. After
some hesitation, as indicated by the comment that the drawing is “highly finished by a skilled, though not
certainly known, hand,” Keynes assents to Butlin’s view with the statements that “the most probable
author is . . . John Linnell” and that “it . . . is quite certainly based” on <hi rend="i">The Man Who
Taught Blake Painting in His Dreams</hi> (Keynes 24). Keynes adds two observations of his own. “The dress is
the same as he [Blake] habitually wore,” but the portrait “was not necessarily done in his lifetime”
(Keynes 24-25). Consequently, in his catalogue entry on the drawing, Keynes dates it to “c. 1820-1830”
(Keynes 140). He records the watermark, as cited in the auction catalogue, but makes no comment on its early
date.</p>
          <p>Neither Butlin in his essay nor Keynes in his catalogue mentions the possibility that the wash
portrait of Blake is the untraced and otherwise unrecorded “Portrait of W. Blake” exhibited by “W.
Fraser” at the Royal Academy in 1809.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98"
type="note">8</ref> I raise the issue here merely to dismiss it—or at least put it aside until the
concluding paragraphs of this essay. Very little is known about William Fraser other than his exhibition of
works at the RA. There is no record of contact between him and Blake, the RA catalogue gives neither the
medium nor the size of the work, and it is possible that the “W. Blake” he pictured is not the poet and
artist (see note 2 for other candidates). In these circumstances, further speculation would serve little
purpose. <note id="n98">8. <hi rend="i">The Exhibition of the Royal Academy, M.DCCCIX. The Forty-First</hi>
(London: Printed by B. McMillan [for the Royal Academy, 1809]) 22, item 472, hung in the “Antique Academy”
room (20). Fraser’s address is given as “17, Woodstock street, Bond street” ([41]).</note></p>
          <p>The brevity of catalogue entries and illustration captions does not prevent those genres from
being important chapters in the portrait’s reception history. A black and white reproduction serves as the
frontispiece to Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> of 1977.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n99" type="note">9</ref> The caption differs from Butlin and Keynes on two counts: “Anonymous
Portrait of William Blake (1802?) aged about 45.” Bentley has not accepted the attribution to Linnell, but
has no alternative to suggest. He takes the watermark date as the probable, but questionable, date of
execution, and believes that Blake looks about 45 years old in the portrait. If Bentley is correct about the
sitter’s age, then an attribution to Linnell can be maintained only if one assumes that he purposely
portrayed Blake as a man much younger
<pb id="p39-129" n="129"/>
            <figure n="BUT755.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="806" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>The Portrait of a Man who instructed<lb/>
                Mr. Blake in Painting &amp;c. in his Dreams<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Imagination of a Man whom. Mr Blake has recd.<lb/>
                instruction in Painting &amp;c from.</figTranscr>
              <head>2. Blake, <hi rend="i">The Man Who Taught Blake Painting in His Dreams, Replica Perhaps by
John Linnell.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pencil, 26.0 × 20.6 cm., based on Blake’s original, datable to c. 1819-20, with
right and left reversed. Inscribed by Linnell lower left, “The Portrait of a Man who instructed M<hi
rend="s">r</hi>. Blake in Painting &amp;c. in his Dreams,” and lower right, “Imagination of a Man who<hi
rend="s">m</hi>. M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Blake has rec<hi rend="s">d</hi>. instruction in Painting &amp;c
from.” Butlin #755. Tate Collection, London. Blake’s original drawing is in the Keynes Collection,
Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge (Butlin #753); a counterproof—with right and left reversed and probably the
basis for this replica—is also in the Tate Collection (Butlin #754).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p39-130" n="130"/>
than the 60-year-old whom Linnell met in 1818. The portrait next graced the cover of Johnson and Grant’s
paperback selection of Blake’s works, justifiably one of the most frequently used classroom texts of his
writings and designs. Johnson and Grant follow Bentley in attributing the portrait to “anonymous” and
state that it represents “William Blake at about forty-five years of age.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n99">9. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977).</note>
	<note id="n100">10. Mary Lynn Johnson and John E. Grant, eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and
Designs</hi>, Norton Critical Edition (New York: Norton, 1979). The caption is printed on the back cover. The
portrait is not reproduced in the hardbound issue. The portrait is also attributed to an “Anonymous
Artist,” without reference to the date of execution or the age of the sitter, in [Gert Schiff], 
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, catalogue of the exhibition at the National Museum of Western Art, Tokyo, 22
September through 25 November 1990 (Tokyo: National Museum of Western Art, 1990) caption to the illustrated
“Reference Work” facing p. 5. The portrait was not included in the exhibition.</note></p>
          <p>In an entry for an exhibition catalogue of 1987, I began to dissociate myself, briefly and
tentatively, from Butlin’s attribution.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n101"
type="note">11</ref> I noted that there were “several similarities in conception”—not further
explained—between the portrait and Blake’s tempera painting <hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts</hi>
(illus. 3) that could prompt “the notion that this work may be a self-portrait” (8). To this I added two
observations about the style of the drawing I will return to later. “The stipple-like brushwork on the face
suggests the technique of miniature portraiture Blake began to practice in 1800; the freer rendering of the
costume is not characteristic of Blake’s style, but shows some parallels with his <hi rend="i">Drawing of
William Cowper after Romney</hi> (c. 1801)” (8-9; see illus. 8). In his 1991 biography of Blake, James King
moves yet a step closer to the attribution I’m proposing here.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n102" type="note">12</ref> The following caption appears beneath his frontispiece reproduction of the
drawing: “William Blake[.] Likely a self-portrait of about 1802.” Continuing the trend evident in the
comments surveyed here, and in hopeful anticipation of the present essay, I titled the drawing “William
Blake, Self-Portrait, c. 1802” in 2002.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103"
type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n101">11. [Essick], <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries and Followers: Selected Works
from the Collection of Robert N. Essick</hi>, exhibition catalogue, Henry E. Huntington Library and Art
Gallery, November 1987 through February 1988 (San Marino: Huntington Library, 1987) 8-9, item 1,
illustrated.</note>
	<note id="n102">12. James King, <hi rend="i">William Blake His Life</hi> (London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson,
1991). The caption, quoted here, also appears in the list of “Plates,” p. ix.</note>
	<note id="n103">13. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, ed. Essick (San
Marino: Huntington Library, 2002) frontispiece. Denise Vultee’s biography of Blake, included as part of the
online William Blake Archive (www.blakearchive.org), ed. Morris Eaves, Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, similarly
labels the drawing as a “Self-Portrait of William Blake” and dates it to “c. 1802.”</note></p>
          <p>The caption—a mini-essay of over 200 words—accompanying the reproduction of the portrait in
Bentley’s 2001 biography, <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise</hi>, deserves special attention.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104" type="note">14</ref> Bentley begins cautiously, placing a
question mark after both “Blake” (as the subject) and “Self-portrait,” but these hesitations are
allayed by what follows. “This strange portrait . . . surely represents William Blake,” for the coat, the
“stock” or cravat, “the domed forehead, piercing eyes, arched eyebrows, and hair receding from a peak
are very similar” to the 1807 portrait by Thomas Phillips,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n105" type="note">15</ref> although that painting “shows a rounder chin, wider mouth, and greyer
hair.” Bentley also compares the monochrome wash portrait to John Flaxman’s pencil sketch of Blake, dated
1804 on the verso, and finds that the two portraits are similar in “costume and hair peak,” but that the
pencil drawing shows an “older and more solid” Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n106" type="note">16</ref> Bentley concludes as follows: “The portrait was probably made by Blake
when working on his portrait-miniatures about 1803. Notice the oval shape of the picture, traditional for
miniatures . . . . The eyes, which to the self-portraitist are most conspicuous, are awesomely compelling.
This is a portrait of Blake as he saw himself ‘not with but through the eye.’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n104">14. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William
Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 2001) caption to plate 88. The same caption, with a different placement of one
sentence, accompanies the reproduction in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2), plate 30.</note>
	<note id="n105">15. Keynes 121-23 and plate 7.</note>
	<note id="n106">16. Keynes 120-21 and plate 6. This portrait, and another pencil sketch by Flaxman of c. 1804
(Keynes 120 and plate 5), show a much fuller, heavier face in the cheeks and chin.</note>
	<note id="n107">17. In his concluding phrase, bracketed with quotation marks, Bentley is adapting Blake’s
line, “When we see [With] not Thro the Eye,” in “Auguries of Innocence.” See David V. Erdman, ed., 
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (New York: Doubleday, 1988) 496,
line 126 and the textual note on 860 (“With” is a deletion). Hereafter cited as “E” followed by page
number.</note></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of Adam</hi>, I reproduced the portrait but made
no attempt to dissent from Butlin’s attribution.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108"
type="note">18</ref> Rather, my interest was in claiming that the face of Adam in <hi rend="i">Adam Naming the
Beasts</hi> (illus. 3) is an idealized self-portrait. I’ll now reverse the direction of my argument and
flesh out my earlier observations about the portrait drawing and its relationship to a painting indisputably
from Blake’s hand. There are of course differences between the two works, including the youthfulness of Adam
and the more elongated cheek and jawline in the drawing. The hair is different, yet Adam’s curly locks form
a peak above his forehead, surround his head, and cover his ears much like the sparser hair in the portrait.
The most striking similarities are the nose (particularly the bowed lower edges of the nostrils), eyes,
eyebrows, and upper lip. Indeed, these features are almost identical in their stylization and an exaggerated
symmetry unlikely to be found in any living face. <note id="n108">18. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake and
the Language of Adam</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1989) plate 2 and caption on p. ix (“Portrait of William
Blake, perhaps by John Linnell after 1818”). The portrait is discussed on p. 7. My coeditor and I were
similarly accepting of Butlin’s attribution in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed. Essick and Donald
Pearce (Bloomington: Indiana UP, 1978) caption to the frontispiece (“Portrait of William Blake. Possibly by
John Linnell”).</note></p>
          <p>Several features in the portrait drawing are closer to Blake’s Adam than to <hi rend="i">The
Man Who Taught Blake Painting in His Dreams</hi> (illus. 2). Blake in the portrait and Adam share a
<pb id="p39-131" n="131"/>
            <figure n="BUT667.bqscan" rend="file" width="388" height="500">
              <head>3. Blake, <hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Tempera painting, 75.0 × 62.2 cm., signed and dated 1810. Detail of Adam’s face,
approx. 38.0 × 34.5 cm. Butlin #667. Pollok House, Glasgow; copyright © Glasgow City Council
(Museums).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p39-132" n="132"/>
            <figure n="port.verso.1.100" rend="file" width="958" height="507">
	<head>4. <hi rend="i">Portrait of William Blake</hi>, verso pencil sketch.</head>
	<figDesc>This rough sketch, only about 4.5 × 9.0 cm., is just above the lower edge of the sheet, with a
top/bottom orientation the same as the recto portrait. Collection of Robert N. Essick.</figDesc>
</figure>
straight line between the lips; the mouth turns up in the Visionary Head. The eyebrows of the painting
instructor rise at a slight curve from their inner termination, form a dramatic peak or angle a little more
than halfway along their length, and then descend on a new curve toward their outer ends. In both the portrait
drawing and the tempera, the eyebrows are a continuous curve throughout their entire span. Similarly, the
upper eyelids of Adam and Blake lack the sudden angle of the instructor’s upper lids just before they arch
over the pupils. In the portrayals of Blake and Adam, the outer corners of the eyes, particularly the left eye
in each case, are drawn out into a thin line. No such extensions appear in the Visionary Head. Finally, the
faces in the portrait and the tempera lack the phrenological segmentations so apparent in the instructor’s
forehead.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n109" type="note">19</ref> If the portraitist had
used one of Blake’s own works as a model, <hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts</hi> would seem a better
candidate than <hi rend="i">The Man Who Taught Blake Painting in His Dreams.</hi> Linnell may have seen the
tempera while it was in the collection of Thomas Butts, but neither Butlin nor any other scholar has argued
for its direct influence on the portrait.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n110"
type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n109">19. For a study of the influence of this pseudoscience on the Visionary Heads, see Anne K.
Mellor, “Physiognomy, Phrenology, and Blake’s Visionary Heads,” in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>
53-74.</note>
	<note id="n110">20. The tempera painting was acquired, possibly as early as 1810, by Thomas Butts and was
never in Linnell’s collection (see Butlin #667).</note></p>
          <p>One could go on and on with comparisons and contrasts among these three works (illus. 1-3). I
trust it is already evident that such comparisons lead us not only to a common origin in Blake’s own
features, but also to a similar manner of conceiving of and idealizing the human countenance. It is difficult
to believe that two different artists designed and executed the portrait and the tempera painting,
particularly if there is no evidence that the portraitist used the tempera as a model. The stylistic parallels
between the portrait drawing and <hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts</hi> suggest the presence of Blake’s
hand as much as his face.</p>
          <p>Butlin’s one-sentence comment on the “rough sketches” (illus. 4) on the verso of the
portrait is another attempt to link the object to the Linnell-Varley circle, and thus to the production of the
Visionary Heads c. 1819-25. But just what is represented, so lightly and crudely, on the back of the portrait?
There is a good deal of accidental soiling on the verso; in a black and white illustration, it is difficult to
distinguish between these smudges and purposely created pencil strokes. Accordingly, in illus. 5 I have drawn
over in black ink all lines which careful inspection of the original convinces me are in pencil. There is a
single composition, not multiple “sketches.” On the left are buildings, or a single structure with several
bays including an arched entry. From this cluster stretches a colonnade, gradually diminished in size to show
its extension into the distance on the right. Above the colonnade are a few lines suggestive of background
hills; similar horizontals below the colonnade indicate a foreground landscape. On the far right are two
standing figures, rigidly composed of simple verticals and a few lines to indicate heads and arms. Both would
seem to be gowned. The figure on the left has its arms at its side, with the lower left arm and hand extended
at a shallow angle;
<pb id="p39-133" n="133"/>
            <figure n="port.verso.2.100" rend="file" width="958" height="576">
	<head>5. <hi rend="i">Portrait of William Blake</hi>, verso pencil sketch (see illus. 4).</head>
	<figDesc>The pencil lines have been traced in black ink to distinguish them from accidental smudges, thereby
highlighting the drawn image.</figDesc>
</figure>
the figure on the right may have its arms folded over its chest. Both figures seem disproportionately large in
comparison to the structures—unless we imagine them standing well forward of even the nearest reaches of the
building on the left. The artist has attempted linear perspective with mixed results.</p>
          <p>Butlin does not specify which drawings by Varley in the Smaller Blake-Varley Sketchbook are
similar to the verso drawing on the portrait. The only clear parallel I can find is
<figure n="BUT692.40.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="347">
	<head>6. John Varley (or Blake?).</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">A Gothic Tower and Walls.</hi> Pencil, approx. 9.5 × 14.0 cm. Page 40 in the Smaller
Blake-Varley Sketchbook. Butlin #692.40, where the sketch is attributed to Varley. Iris and B. Gerald Cantor
Center for Visual Arts at Stanford University, 1971.57, Museum Purchase Fund.</figDesc>
</figure>
a lightly drawn sketch on page 40, showing an archway with a castellated top, a building or wall extending to
the left, a large castle rising above the arch, and, on the far right, a rectangular building with a tall,
narrow door or window (illus. 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n111" type="note">21</ref>
These
<pb id="p39-134" n="134"/>
            <figure n="K24.1.1.RM" rend="file" width="784" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>Portrait of<lb/>
                Wm. Blake 1820.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                J. L. fecit</figTranscr>
              <head>7. John Linnell, <hi rend="i">Portrait of William Blake.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pencil on sheet 20.1 × 15.5 cm., signed with initials and inscribed “Portrait of
W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake 1820.” Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</figDesc>
            </figure>
drawings are similar in motifs and the awkward management of a pencil. But is the sketchbook example really by
Varley? The drawings indisputably by Varley in the sketchbook were executed in chalk or soft pencil. Both
yielded rather thick lines. The sketch on page 40 was made with a harder, sharper pencil of the sort we also
find in Blake’s Visionary Heads on other pages. Varley’s architectural drawings are on rectos; page 40 is
of course a verso. Drawings by Varley in the sketchbook offer fewer parallels with the composition on page 40
than the battlemented walls behind a crowned figure on page 74 of the Smaller Blake-Varley Sketchbook and a
hesitant sketch of battlements accompanying the Visionary Head of James Hepburn, 4th Earl of Bothwell, on
pages 27-28 of the Larger Blake-Varley Sketchbook. Both of these sketches have been confidently attributed to
Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n112" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n111">21. For a facsimile of the entire sketchbook, see <hi rend="i">The Blake-Varley Sketchbook of
1819 in the Collection of M. D. E. Clayton-Stamm</hi>, intro. and notes by Martin Butlin, 2 vols. (London:
Heinemann, 1969).</note>
	<note id="n112">22. Butlin #692.74 (“A Standing King Holding a Sceptre, a Fortified Town Behind,” in the
smaller sketchbook). For the attribution of the drawing in the larger sketchbook and a reproduction of both
pages, see Christie’s auction catalogue, London, 21 March 1989, p. 23. The larger sketchbook is now in the
collection of Alan Parker, London.</note></p>
          <p>Several works by Blake, particularly among his Job illustrations of c. 1805-06,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113" type="note">23</ref> offer motifs reminiscent of the verso sketch
on the portrait. Many of the Job compositions feature Job and his wife as two large foreground figures,
distant hills or mountains, and architectural elements (including columns and in one design an arch) in the
middle distance. Pillar-like figures, such as the two in the verso sketch, can be found throughout Blake’s
rougher pencil drawings. And was Varley ever quite so awkward, even in his hastiest doodles? To revise
slightly one of Butlin’s own, only half-joking, methods for attributing a work to Blake, one can justifiably
argue that a drawing too bad to be by, say, Linnell or Varley can nevertheless, other things being equal, be
by Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n114" type="note">24</ref> An attribution of the
portrait’s verso sketch to the man whose likeness commands the recto would not be unreasonable. Perhaps the
<pb id="p39-135" n="135"/>
same ascription could be mooted for the composition on page 40 of the Smaller Blake-Varley Sketchbook without
provoking guffaws. At the very least, the sketchbook drawing is a questionable touchstone for attributing the
portrait’s verso design to Varley. <note id="n113">23. The so-called “Butts Set” of watercolors; see
Butlin #550.</note>
	<note id="n114">24. Martin Butlin, “Cataloguing William Blake,” in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>:
“With Blake, one can justifiably argue that a drawing too bad to be by, say, [John] Flaxman or [Thomas]
Stothard can nevertheless, other things being equal, be by Blake” (81).</note></p>
          <p>The watermark recorded in Christie’s auction catalogue has heretofore been assumed to be
accurate. Only the word “PINE” and the date are clearly visible because of dark washes to the left of that
word. Careful inspection with a strong backing light reveals the full watermark to be “[E]DMEADS &amp; PINE
/ 1802,” with what must surely be the first letter of the first word trimmed off by the edge of the
sheet.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n115" type="note">25</ref> Blake used papers produced
by Edmeads and Pine in many of his illuminated books printed in the 1790s. An “EDMEADS &amp; PINE 1802”
watermark appears in copies P and Q of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, both printed in 1804; the same
“EDMEADS &amp; PINE / 1802” watermark of the portrait appears in three proof impressions of plates from
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (possibly among those printed in 1807) in the Pierpont Morgan Library, New
York.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n116" type="note">26</ref> The wove paper on which the
portrait was drawn is a type Blake used frequently over many years. <note id="n115">25. I am grateful to
Alexander Gourlay for suggesting the possibility that the watermark has been consistently misread.</note>
	<note id="n116">26. See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 226, 366 for these watermarks. Copy
designations for the illuminated books follow Bentley. For printing dates, see the chart in Joseph Viscomi,
<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993) 376-81.</note></p>
          <p>In his essay on the portrait, Butlin warns us against assuming that the watermark establishes a
date of composition by pointing out the gap between the 1806 watermark in the Smaller Blake-Varley Sketchbook
and Blake’s first use of it c. 1819. That case is not quite equivalent, however, since Varley may have used
the sketchbook many years earlier for his own drawings. The main issue, however, is not the watermark date of
the portrait but the apparent age of the sitter. Although Blake, because of the fuller cheeks and chin, looks
somewhat older in the Flaxman portraits of 1804 (see note 16), he looks a great deal older in Linnell’s 1820
portrait (illus. 7—compare to illus. 1). The hairline has receded considerably, the wrinkles increased. All
of Linnell’s other portraits of Blake show a man at least as old.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n117" type="note">27</ref> Linnell’s fine work also indicates his typically naturalistic way of
conceiving of and rendering the human face, so distinctly different from the wash portrait. He gives us
Blake’s physical face as he saw that face with his physical eyes at a specific moment in the sitter’s
life, the head and light at specific angles. This face is set fully in time and space as we experience them in
our daily lives. Nothing could be further in conception from a “Spiritual Form” (Butlin) seen “not with
but through the eye” (Bentley). Even if <hi rend="i">The Man Who Taught Blake Painting in His Dreams</hi>
served as his model, could Linnell so thoroughly hide any trace of his very different sensibility as a
portraitist, and at the same time make Blake look far more youthful than he was when Linnell knew him? 
<note id="n117">27. See the portraits datable to c. 1820-21 in Keynes 135-39 and plates 25, 26, 28-33. All these
portraits share the conceptual orientation exemplified by illus. 7.</note></p>
          <p>According to several people who knew Blake, his eyes were his most prominent feature. For
Frederick Tatham, Blake’s “Eye” was “most unusually large &amp; glassy, with which he appeared to look
into some other World” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 684). Samuel Palmer was equally impressed: “His
[Blake’s] eye was the finest I ever saw: brilliant, but not roving, clear and intent, yet susceptible; it
flashed with genius, or melted in tenderness. It could also be terrible.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n118" type="note">28</ref> As Butlin, Keynes, and Bentley have noted, the wash
portrait captures this reported intensity of Blake’s actual gaze.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n119" type="note">29</ref> To such observations Bentley, in his caption in <hi rend="i">Stranger from
Paradise</hi>, adds the idea that self-portraiture contributes to a concentration on the eyes. A survey of
self-portraits from the Renaissance through the twentieth century supports Bentley’s claim, particularly in
the case of full-frontal self-portraits.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n120"
type="note">30</ref> As the artist/subject studies his face in a mirror, the eyes open more widely than normal
and intensify, becoming fixed on their own reflection. A striking example from the circle of Blake’s
so-called “followers” is Samuel Palmer’s self-portrait now in the Ashmolean Museum, Oxford.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n121" type="note">31</ref> The representation of the eyes in the wash
portrait of Blake may be in part the product of how those eyes looked not to others—but to themselves in a
mirror. <note id="n118">28. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 392. See also Alexander Gilchrist’s 1863 description of
Blake’s eyes, very probably based on reports from those who knew him: “His eyes were fine—‘wonderful
eyes,’ some one calls them; prominently set, but bright, spiritual, visionary; not restless or wild, but
with ‘a look of clear heavenly exaltation’” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 390).</note>
	<note id="n119">29. They describe the “intense gaze” in the wash portrait (Butlin in <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi> 101), the “penetrating gaze” (Keynes 24 and 140), and the “piercing eyes” (Bentley,
caption in <hi rend="i">Stranger from Paradise</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n120">30. Among British artists, see, for example, the self-portraits by John Ruskin, Aubrey
Beardsley, Stanley Spencer, Jacob Epstein, and David Hockney, all conveniently reproduced and discussed in 
<hi rend="i">The Artist by Himself: Self-Portrait Drawings from Youth to Old Age</hi>, ed. Joan Kinneir, intro.
David Piper (New York: St. Martin’s P, 1980).</note>
	<note id="n121">31. Dated to c. 1826 and reproduced in Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Catalogue Raisonné of
the Works of Samuel Palmer</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1988) 55, #63. Several similarities between
Palmer’s self-portrait and the Blake wash portrait might even lead one to speculate that Palmer saw and was
influenced by the latter.</note></p>
          <p>If we provisionally place the wash portrait in the context of Blake’s life a few years before
and after the watermark date, when he was in his mid-40s, we find a context of work and thought in which
self-portraiture seems more likely than at any other period in his life. During his years in Felpham under
William Hayley’s often burdensome patronage, 1800-03, Blake was involved in the art of portraiture to a
surprising extent. Even before Blake’s arrival, Hayley had commissioned him to engrave a portrait medallion
of Hayley’s natural son, Thomas Alphonso, as an illustration for Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Essay on
Sculpture</hi>, published in 1800. Once in Felpham, Blake soon began to execute a series of 18 tempera
paintings, the so-called “Heads of the Poets,” to decorate Hayley’s library (Butlin #343, dated to c.
1800-03). Although these works are elongated
<pb id="p39-136" n="136"/>
rectangles, the portraits themselves are set within circular or oval framing motifs. Blake’s engravings for
Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life, and Posthumous Writings, of William Cowper</hi>, published in 1803-04, include
three portraits.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n122" type="note">32</ref> Preparatory to his
execution of one of these, a portrait of Cowper after a pastel by George Romney, Blake carefully copied
Romney’s work (illus. 8). As I briefly noted in the 1987 exhibition catalogue mentioned earlier, this pen
and wash drawing exemplifies Blake’s habits when copying a portrait and offers some significant parallels
with the wash portrait of Blake. <note id="n122">32. For reproductions, descriptions, and an overview of the
documents relating Blake’s considerable labors on these portraits, see Essick, <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1991) 85-90 and figs. 199-202.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s portrait of Cowper is not a servile reproduction of Romney’s pastel.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n123" type="note">33</ref> There are many slight differences, and the
man looks slightly younger in Blake’s version, particularly around the eyes. In the original, the cloth at
Cowper’s neck is tied with a small bow that hangs down in three folds. Blake has altered this considerably,
enlarging the bow and giving it two “wings,” juxtaposed horizontally, that are similar to the bow in the
wash portrait of Blake. As we would expect with any copy, the lines and contours of the face are more studied,
and hence rigid, than in the original. Cowper has lost a touch of liveliness evident in the original. As is
typical of most portraiture of the time, Romney’s drawing shows careful draftsmanship in the face, but a
much looser handling of the costume. Blake has preserved—perhaps even inadvertently increased—this
difference in his copy. Thus, his version of the Cowper portrait exemplifies the exact stylistic features in
the wash portrait of Blake—the “somehow cold and brittle” quality of the “otherwise Blakean line . . .
in the face,” and “the ‘painterly’ treatment of the coat and kerchief”—that Butlin 
(<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 102) found to be uncharacteristic of Blake’s work. It might be objected that
these styles and their combination are present only when Blake is copying a portrait,
            <figure n="BUT351.1.1.WD" rend="file" width="724" height="1000">\
              <figTranscr>William Cowper Esqr<lb/>
                Given by the Poet; to his friend Hay[ley]</figTranscr>
              <head>8. Blake, <hi rend="i">Portrait of William Cowper after Romney.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pen and washes, approx. 18.8 × 14.7 cm. Inscribed by William Hayley, “William Cowper
Esqr / Given by the Poet; to his friend Hayley.” Butlin #351, where the drawing is dated to c. 1801 (the
engraving of the same portrait is dated November 1802 in its imprint). As Butlin notes, Hayley’s inscription
“would rule out Blake’s participation but presumably is the result of a later confusion with Romney’s
original.” Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, DC.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="BUT376.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="778" height="1000">
	<head>9. Blake, <hi rend="i">Miniature of Thomas Butts.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Watercolor on ivory, oval, 8.4 × 6.3 cm. Butlin #376, where the painting is tentatively dated to
“1801(?).” British Museum, London.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p39-137" n="137"/>
already reduced to the two dimensions of canvas or paper, rather than a living face in three dimensions. But a
version of this same perceptual and compositional situation also pertains if Blake is copying his own face
represented in a mirror. <note id="n123">33. For a reproduction of Romney’s drawing, now in the National
Portrait Gallery, London, see Morchard Bishop, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Hayley: The Life, Works, and Friendships
of William Hayley</hi> (London: Gollancz, 1951), seventh plate following p. 160.</note></p>
          <p>In earlier publications, Bentley and I have independently related the wash portrait of Blake to
his learning miniature portraiture. This context deserves more consideration. In a letter to Romney of 3
February 1801, Hayley states that he has “taught Him [Blake] he says to paint in Miniature, &amp; in Truth
he has made a very creditable Copy from yr admirable Portrait of the dear departed Bard [Cowper].”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n124" type="note">34</ref> Hayley was himself not a miniaturist; as he
implies in a letter to Romney of 21 April 1801 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 106-07), Blake probably learned the
rudiments of the art from Jeremiah Meyer, a friend of Hayley’s and miniature painter to the Queen.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="nE" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="nE"><supplied type="emend">* <hi rend="i">Correction by Robert N. Essick (Spring 2006):</hi>
Jeremiah Meyer died in 1789, and thus Blake’s instructor must have been Jeremiah’s son, William, also a
miniaturist.</supplied></note> Blake apparently began this new endeavor with enthusiasm: “my present
engagements are in Miniature Painting Miniature is become a Goddess in my Eyes &amp; my Friends in Sussex say
that I Excell in the pursuit” (10 May 1801 letter to Thomas Butts, E 715). The miniatures Blake painted—at
least nine in all, of which six are extant—are hardly masterpieces in the genre, but all follow its
conventions dutifully. His portrait of Thomas Butts nicely exemplifies the lot (illus. 9). The oval shape and
small size are of course standard, as are the detailed rendering of the face and broader brushwork on the
costume. Even the looser handling of the hair is typical of late eighteenth- and early nineteenth-century
miniatures. The face is executed, as in so many miniatures of the period, with very short, stipple-like
strokes of a small, pointed brush.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n125" type="note">35</ref>
	<note id="n124">34. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 104. The “Copy” to which Hayley refers is probably one of
Blake’s two miniatures of Cowper (Butlin #353-54), or, just possibly, the wash portrait reproduced here
(illus. 8).</note>
	<note id="n125">35. This combination of techniques is typical of the influential miniatures of Richard Cosway
(1742-1821), who “worked carefully with stipple in the features, but adopted a romantic sketchiness in his
linear handling of hair, costumes and background . . . .” Quoted from Jim Murrell, “The Craft of the
Miniaturist,” in John Murdoch, Murrell, Patrick J. Noon, and Roy Strong, <hi rend="i">The English
Miniature</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1981) 19-20, where George Engleheart is also described as using similar
styles. See also Murrell’s comment that Ozias Humphry, who commissioned the “Small” and “Large”
Books of Designs from Blake, “usually finished his miniatures with careful stippling” (19). According to
Christopher Lloyd and Vanessa Remington, “the stippling process [in portrait miniatures] is, in fact, not
unrelated to contemporary engraving techniques in seventeenth-century France” (<hi rend="i">Masterpieces in
Little: Portrait Miniatures from the Collection of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II</hi> [London: Royal
Collection Enterprises, 1996] 28). Blake was an expert stipple engraver; see, for example, his “Venus
Dissuades Adonis from Hunting” after Cosway (1787) and his engraving of “Mirth” after his own design
(first state, c. 1816-20). These and other works in stipple are described and reproduced in Essick, 
<hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983).</note></p>
          <p>By early 1803, Blake’s growing disenchantment with Hayley and his assignments included a turn
against portraiture. As he told his brother James, “he [Hayley] thinks to turn me into a Portrait Painter as
he did Poor Romney, but this he nor all the devils in hell will never do” (letter of 30 Jan. 1803, E 725).
In spite of this attitude, Blake continued to practice miniature painting, for he inscribed his miniature of
Mrs. Butts “1809” (Butlin #377), and the portrait of Thomas Butts, Jr., probably also dates from that year
(Butlin #378). Painting with stipple-like strokes also appears to have influenced the hand coloring of
post-1800 printings of Blake’s illuminated books. Alexander Gilchrist describes Blake’s “finishing the
plates like miniatures” in one such copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 207). In 1809, Blake claimed that his own “fresco” paintings are “properly
Miniature, or Enamel Painting; every thing in Fresco is as high finished as Miniature . . . .”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n126" type="note">36</ref> As for portraiture in general, the many
Visionary Heads of c. 1819-25 testify to Blake’s continued interest in a special form of that art. Finally,
we have Tatham’s testimony that Blake’s concluding act as an artist, in the last few hours of his life,
was to draw a portrait of his beloved wife Catherine (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 682). <note id="n126">36.
Advertisement for “Exhibition of <hi rend="i">Paintings in Fresco</hi>, Poetical and Historical
Inventions” (E 527). See also Blake’s annotation to Joshua Reynolds’ <hi rend="i">Discourses</hi>:
“Fresco Painting is Like Miniature Painting; a Wall is a Large Ivory” (E 653).</note></p>
          <p>Returning to the wash portrait of Blake (illus. 1), we can find in it many characteristics of
miniature, even if the size might seem to exclude it from that category.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n127" type="note">37</ref> Bentley has pointed to its oval shape, so characteristic of
miniatures. It is of course possible that someone cut it to an oval after the drawing left the artist’s
hands, but the shadow on the right and the framing of the costume make it difficult to imagine how the image
could have looked anything other than awkward if extended to four corners. Blake’s arms, for example, would
reach almost to the elbows and be oddly cut off at that point. Even the direction of the soft lighting, coming
from left to right, bespeaks miniaturist conventions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n128"
type="note">38</ref> The most telling feature is the use of fine, stipple-like brushstrokes to represent the
contours of Blake’s face. As in the miniature of Butts (illus. 9), the hair and costume are handled more
freely. The artist who produced the wash portrait was influenced by the styles and techniques of miniature
portraiture that Blake had learned while in Felpham. <note id="n127">37. In the nineteenth century, so-called
“miniatures” tended to increase in size; see, for example, Robert Thorburn’s 32.4 × 26.0 cm. stippled
painting, <hi rend="i">Queen Victoria and Edward Prince of Wales</hi> of c. 1845. Even some earlier miniatures
were only a little smaller than the Blake wash portrait—e.g., Richard Crosse’s 17.4 × 13.3 cm. 
<hi rend="i">Mrs. Siddons</hi> of 1783. Both are reproduced in Murdoch et al.</note>
	<note id="n128">38. See Lloyd and Remington: “Assuming the artist to be right-handed, the light was
admitted from the left” (27).</note></p>
          <p>I trust that my observations and arguments to this point, coupled with the comments by Bentley
and others I’ve summarized, can lead us all to agree that the Scottish verdict of “not proven” is an
appropriate response to Butlin’s attribution of the wash portrait to Linnell. I suspect, however, that many
may find the same verdict justified in regard to my attribution to Blake. One feature of the portrait will tip
the scales away from Linnell, Fraser, or anyone else other than Blake himself.</p>
          <pb id="p39-138" n="138"/>
          <figure n="LifeMaskofWilliamBlake.Essick.bqscan" rend="file" width="323" height="500">
            <head>10. James S. Deville, Life Mask of William Blake.</head>
            <figDesc>Plaster, surface partly gilt. Head, measured face-on, approx. 19.5 × 14.0 cm. A copy
mold-made from the original in the National Portrait Gallery, London. Original incised “PUBD AUG. 1, 1823”
on the back of the neck. Collection of Robert N. Essick.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>To paint a self-portrait, one must look into a mirror (as I’ve already noted in passing,
without attention to all the implications). It is of course possible for someone to paint a mirror image of
another’s face, but this is an exceedingly remote possibility in the present instance. A mirror image is
subject to “bilateral inversion”—that is, the reversal of right and left. David Piper has described the
situation adroitly:
<q>
At once, we are confronted by the conditioning agent which distinguished self-portraiture from the mainstream
of portraiture, apart from the fact that the subject is the artist himself. That agent is the mirror, and it
is easy to forget that, apart from any technical flaws there may be in any particular mirror, its reflection
is not only not the object itself but a reproduction of its three-dimensional existence on a two-dimensional
plane, but, further, that it reverses the object. Our own faces as we know them in daily life, are the wrong
way round and no face, once it develops from childhood, is symmetrical. We do not “see ourselves as others
see us.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n129" type="note">39</ref>
	<note id="n129">39. Introduction to <hi rend="i">The Artist by Himself</hi> 12. Perhaps Piper overstates the
two-dimensional qualities of a mirror image. It projects a sense of depth greater than a work on
paper.</note></q></p>
          <p>Can we find in the wash portrait of Blake, in spite of its stylized symmetry, any asymmetrical
features that are inverted in comparison to other representations of his face?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n130" type="note">40</ref> To answer that question, we will need a picture of
Blake’s face as free as possible from stylistic distortions. His life mask, mold-made in three dimensions by
the phrenologist James S. Deville from Blake’s head in the summer of 1823, offers the best possibilities
(illus. 10).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n131" type="note">41</ref> Such works create
their own distortions, for the drying plaster has pulled down the corners of Blake’s mouth, giving him a
stern and pained expression, and flattened his nose a little. Straws or tubes of some sort were very probably
inserted into Blake’s nostrils so that he could breathe while the plaster dried. A life mask, however, does
not create (or erase, in deference to vanity) wrinkles and creases, nor does it reverse asymmetries. 
<note id="n130">40. Blake’s coat shows no bilateral inversion, for the left side overlaps the right side, as is
standard for men’s coats. I suspect that the costume was drawn freely, without any reference to a mirror
reflection. If a self-portrait, Blake was probably not wearing his formal coat and cravat while composing the
work. Some of the self-portraits reproduced by Kinneir show a reversal of the conventional overlapping of
shirts or coats; others do not.</note>
	<note id="n131">41. The casts in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, and the National Portrait Gallery,
London, appear to have been made from the original mold. Keynes illustrates the Fitzwilliam cast, plates
23a-b, and a facsimile mold-made from the National Portrait Gallery cast, plates 23c-d. The illustrations here
(illus. 10-12) are photographs of another one of these second-generation facsimiles. None of these moldmaking
and casting procedures reverses right and left. As Keynes notes, the Fitzwilliam cast “is unsigned and seems
unfinished, the surface being rough and somewhat mottled. It is, so to speak, a ‘proof’ copy, or
prototype” (133). The National Portrait Gallery cast “has a cleaner and smoother surface and is signed on
the back of the neck representing Deville’s finished intentions, such as he would have sold to his
customers, though only one example is known to have survived” (133).</note></p>
          <p>The life mask shows that Blake had a very symmetrical face. Only two right/left differences are
clearly evident. I suspect that the use of breathing straws and the flattening of Blake’s nose have flared
his nostrils unnaturally, but this distortion helps reveal a difference in the “cut” or shape of the lower
edge of each nostril (technically, the <hi rend="i">ala nasi</hi>) that could not have been created by the
mold-making procedure. The right nostril (on the viewer’s left) rises at a steeper angle from the tip of the
nose than the left nostril (illus. 11, top). The right is more arched, and gives the appearance of being
slightly higher than the left. A more prominent asymmetry is the deep crease in Blake’s forehead that begins
vertically, above his nose just left of center from the viewer’s perspective, and then arches horizontally
to our left (that is, over Blake’s right eye) with
<pb id="p39-139" n="139"/>
perhaps a much less visible branch to the right (illus. 12, left). Linnell pictures this same crease in his
1820 drawing of Blake (illus. 7), although with less precision than the life mask.</p>
          <p>If we now turn back to the wash portrait, we can see these same features—but reversed. The
artist has made the nostrils more symmetrical than the life mask reveals they actually were, just as he has
almost certainly made the mouth, eyes, and eyebrows more symmetrical than we are likely to find in any living
face. Further, the light coming in from the left side of the drawing casts Blake’s left nostril in shadow.
In spite of these stylistic features, we can still see that the angle at which the left nostril (on the
viewer’s right) rises from the tip of the nose is steeper than the same portion of the right nostril (illus.
11, bottom). Recall that this reverses the nostril asymmetry in the life mask (illus. 11, top). The forehead
crease begins vertically just right of the center of Blake’s nose and arches horizontally to our
right—that is, over Blake’s left eye in the wash portrait (illus. 12, right). Again, the reverse of the
life mask (illus. 12, left). The artist who drew the wash portrait was looking at Blake’s face in a mirror.
That artist was William Blake.</p>
          <p>The sojourn in Felpham and the decade following were for Blake years of psychological turmoil and
introspection. Those experiences found expression in some of his greatest works, including <hi rend="i">Milton
a Poem</hi>, with its meditations on the nature of the human self in all its conflicted complexity. His
self-portrait emerged from this same context and is, quite literally, a self-reflection. It is a continuation
of his long-standing interest in physiognomy, a supplement (as it were) to the “Heads of the Poets,” and a
prelude to (not a copy of) the Visionary Heads. Blake found a “Divine countenance in such men as Cowper and
Milton” (letter to Hayley of 28 May 1804, E 750). Through an idealizing transformation of his own face,
Blake attempts to articulate a similar union of the physical and the spiritual/imaginative (the two being one
in Blake’s thought). In “A Vision of the Last Judgment,” he asks the viewers of his painting to
“attend to the Hands &amp; Feet to the Lineaments of the Countenances they are all descriptive
of Character” (E 560). Through self-portraiture Blake attends to the character of his own countenance and
thereby follows his advice in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: “Judge then of thy Own Self: thy Eternal Lineaments
explore” (E 132). The self-portrait is Blake’s most direct and personal attempt to “leave” for us his
“destind lineaments permanent” even as the “generations of men run on in the tide of Time” 
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, E 117).</p>
          <figure n="DetailofNostrils.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="345">
            <head>11. Top: detail of the nostrils in Blake’s life mask, illus. 10. Bottom: detail of the
nostrils in the wash portrait of Blake, illus. 1.</head>
            <figDesc/>
          </figure>
          <figure n="detailofeyebrow.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="225">
            <head>12. Left: detail of the right forehead (viewer’s left) in Blake’s life mask, illus. 10.
Right: detail of the left forehead (viewer’s right) in the wash portrait of Blake, illus. 1.</head>
            <figDesc/>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
