<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.4.fischer</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert D. Denham, Northrop Frye: Religious Visionary and Architect of the
Spiritual World</title>
        <author n="Fischer">Michael Fischer</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Magnus Ankarsjö</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
      <pb id="p39-187" n="187"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-4-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEW</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert D. Denham. <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye: Religious Visionary and Architect
of the Spiritual World.</hi> Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2004. xiv + 373 pp. $45.00,
hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Michael <name>Fischer</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye: Religious Visionary and Architect of the Spiritual World</hi>,
Robert D. Denham argues that we cannot understand Frye “without considering the ways Frye’s views on
religion interpenetrate practically everything he wrote” (2). Denham supports this point with extensive
references to Frye’s diaries, notebooks, and letters, as well as his published work. These references
document Frye’s deep interest not only in Christianity but also in Buddhism, Taoism, Gnosticism, and
Confucianism, not to mention many other forms of thought that detect spiritual influences on the visible
world, such as astrology, alchemy, numerology, the Tarot, and even channeling. When Frye put down his Blake or
Milton, he picked up his Herbert B. Greenhouse (<hi rend="i">The Astral Journey</hi>) or Guy Lyon Playfair and
Scott Hill (<hi rend="i">The Cycles of Heaven: Cosmic Forces and What They Are Doing to You</hi>).</p>
          <p>Frye served as an ordained minister in the United Church of Canada for 55 years. In one of his
later notebooks, he describes himself as “an architect of the spiritual world” (qtd. Denham 3), adding,
“I’m no evangelist or revivalist preacher, but I’d like to help out in a trend to make religion
interesting and attractive to many people of good will who will have nothing to do with it now” (qtd. Denham
13). Denham shows how religion infuses everything that defines Frye as a critic: his critical vocabulary, his
schematic thinking, his ongoing concern with such issues as vision, redemption, and inner growth, even his
allegiance to Blake—according to Denham, “a deeply religious poet” (3) whom Frye often acknowledges as
the source of his critical ideas. In Denham’s view, religion was not just important to Frye, it was
“central to practically everything Frye wrote, the foundation on which he built the massive superstructure
that was his life’s work” (3).</p>
          <p>No one can deny Frye’s lifelong engagement with religious thought, at least not after
Denham’s painstaking research. Nevertheless, despite my considerable interest in the materials that Denham
so thoroughly analyzes, I would still place greater emphasis on the role of literature in Frye’s thought
than does Denham. I see Frye as a critic defending the autonomy of literature and the other arts throughout
his published work. His strictures against value judgments in criticism in the <hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi>, for
example, argue against tethering literature to external expectations. According to Frye, standards of taste,
established canons, and privileged artistic models reinstate social biases; they limit the imaginative freedom
that Frye wants to encourage. Commenting in the <hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi> on how modern critical fashions
promote some writers while demoting others, Frye writes, “we can see that every increase of appreciation has
been right, and every decrease wrong”; “criticism,” he continues, “has no business to react against
things, but should show a steady advance toward undiscriminating catholicity” (25). In literature, he
concludes in <hi rend="i">The Critical Path</hi>, “there are no negative visions: all poets are potentially
positive contributors to man’s body of vision” (127).</p>
          <p>This commitment to boundless curiosity and open-ended aesthetic exploration informed some of the
wide-ranging reading that Denham chronicles, in particular Frye’s fascination with what he affectionately
called his “kook books,” or texts that traffic in the paranormal, the occult, and the mystical. As Denham
points out, Frye often found imaginative life in texts that had been discredited in other disciplines. What
Frye regarded as pseudoscience, bad anthropology, and dubious psychology could still stimulate his
imagination. Similarly, as much as Frye respected logic, fact, and evidence, he also welcomed speculation and
daring in criticism. As he puts it in one notebook entry, “[C]riticism (which is energetic response to
literature) must itself be imaginative, not afraid of humor or paradox, which latter are as essential to
poetic truth as accuracy of observation is to botany” (qtd. Denham 191). In that spirit, he loved Frances
Yates’ <hi rend="i">The Art of Memory</hi>: “Francis Yates is wonderful,” he writes in his notebook,
“the combination of sober documentation and the wildest guesswork is very exhilarating” (qtd. Denham
196).</p>
          <p>Much is at stake in Frye’s commitment to the independence of the imagination. Imaginative
writers not only enact human freedom, they keep it alive as a possibility for everyone else. As Frye observes
in the <hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi>,
<q>
We live in a world of threefold external compulsion: of compulsion on action, or law; of compulsion on
thinking, or fact; of compulsion on feeling, which is the characteristic of all pleasure whether it is
produced by the <hi rend="i">Paradiso</hi> or by an ice cream soda. But in the world of imagination a fourth
power, which contains morality, beauty, and truth but is never subordinated to them, rises free of all their
compulsions. The work of imagination presents us with a vision, not of the personal greatness of the poet, but
of something impersonal and far greater: the vision of a decisive act of spiritual freedom, the vision of the
recreation of man. (94)
</q>
Pressure to limit the imagination must be resisted because it is always pressure to exempt the status quo from
dissent or, what comes to the same thing, to let our fear of change and losing control get the better of our
hope.</p>
          <p>According to Frye, the freedom of literature from preestablished external controls applies also
to religion, an important historical influence on law, morality, and views of knowledge. As a literary critic,
especially in the <hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi>, Frye is more interested in opening literature to limitless
possibility than in deriving it from any source outside itself, religion included:
<pb id="p39-188" n="188"/>
	<q>
[I]t is of the essence of imaginative culture that it transcends the limits both of the naturally possible and
of the morally acceptable. The argument that there is no room for poets in any human society which is an end
in itself remains unanswerable even when the society is the people of God. For religion is also a social
institution, and so far as it is one, it imposes limitations on the arts just as a Marxist or Platonic state
would do. . . . Religions, in spite of their enlarged perspective, cannot as social institutions 
<hi rend="i">contain</hi> an art of unlimited hypothesis. The arts in their turn cannot help releasing the
powerful acids of satire, realism, ribaldry, and fantasy in their attempt to dissolve all the existential
concretions that get in their way. (127)
</q>
Although Frye understands irritation with the restless questioning and endless exploration exemplified by
literature and the other arts (“nobody wants a poet in the perfect human state” [<hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi>
128]), he insists that “between religion’s ‘this is’ and poetry’s ‘but suppose 
<hi rend="i">this</hi> is,’ there must always be some kind of tension” (<hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi> 127-28),
lest social institutions harden into ostensibly finished products rather than remain always imperfect works in
progress.</p>
          <p>Frye’s unwavering defense of the autonomy of literature, then, is a central emphasis of his
writing, expressed most eloquently in the <hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi> (still his most influential book) but
resonating throughout his published work. Denham calls attention to a more private, less well-known side of
Frye, the voice that we hear in the notebooks and diaries. Here Frye reflects on the restraint that has
discomfited some of his critics who seek something more affirmative from literature: “I can’t indefinitely
go on saying that literature refuses to affirm or deny the identification of the verbal universe with Christ.
Sooner or later . . . I have to come to grips with the total form of human creative power” (qtd. Denham 58).
Frye wants to go beyond what he calls “the suspended judgment of the imaginative” (qtd. Denham 125) and
find some “existential reality beyond the hypothetical” (qtd. Denham 113), some “resolution of the
‘is’ and the ‘as though’ I’ve circled around since at least the AC [<hi rend="i">Anatomy of
Criticism</hi>]” (qtd. Denham 103). Whereas the <hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi> stresses the centripetal
interdependence of literary works within the self-contained realm of literature, the notebooks track Frye’s
centrifugal movement outward from literary experience toward something else that literature puts us in touch
with. Borrowing from Frye, Denham variously calls this “something else” spiritual vision, kerygma, faith,
higher consciousness, revelation, the reality of the spiritual world, “the total identity of Word and
Spirit” (260), among other terms.</p>
          <p>As Denham notes, Frye had little interest in systematic theology and deep reservations about
institutionalized religion, formal religious creeds, and dogmatic assertions of belief. He consequently uses
terms like “faith,” “revelation,” and “spiritual vision” metaphorically, by which I mean that the
insight suggested by these terms originates in literary experience and retains its imprint. Committed to the
independent power of literature, Frye does not start from a religious position that he then finds confirmed or
illustrated in literary works. Instead, his cumulative experience of literature leads him to feel that life at
some deep intuited level makes sense, that the creativity expressed in literature is somehow reinforced, not
in another world or a redemptive future but here and now in this one. Pressed to elaborate, as, for example,
when Bill Moyers asked him in an interview “What do you mean by the divine?” Frye makes complex statements
like these: “I think that in human terms it means that there is no limit toward the expansion of the mind or
of the freedom and liberty of mankind. . . . [T]he feeling that the genuine things you want, like freedom, are
inexhaustible and that you never come to the end of them—that’s the beginning of the experience of the
divine, for me” (qtd. Denham 56-57). Or as Frye puts it in one of his note-books,
<q><hi rend="i">My</hi> approach to faith turns it into <hi rend="i">gaya scienza</hi>, a joyful wisdom: most
of the conventional approaches turn it into a burden of guilt feelings. Critics who distrust me because I
don’t seem too worried about inconsistencies . . . can’t tune into this notion of faith as a dancing
ballet of intuitions, affirmations, counter-affirmations, “doubts” or retreats from dogma, &amp; a
pervading sense of “anything may be ‘true’ or ‘false,’ but whatever it is, the whole pattern has a
design and a movement.” (qtd. Denham 104)
</q></p>
          <p>There is a tension, in short, between Frye’s defense of the autonomy of literature in his
published works and his sense, expressed in his notebooks, that literary experience leads to some larger
revelation. I do not want to overstate this tension. Passages in his published writings recall the spiritual
affirmations of the notebooks, such as this comment in <hi rend="i">The Critical Path</hi>:
<q>
Nobody would accept a conception of literature as a mere dictionary or grammar of symbols and images which
tells us nothing in itself. Everyone deeply devoted to literature knows that it says something, and says
something as a whole, not only in its individual works. In turning from formulated belief to imagination we
get glimpses of a concern behind concern, of intuitions of human nature and destiny that have inspired the
great religious and revolutionary movements of history. Precisely because its variety is infinite, literature
suggests an encyclopaedic range of concern greater than any formulation of concern in religious or political
myth can express. (103)
</q>
Just as his published writings occasionally gesture toward some larger vision, the private notebooks keep that
vision deliberately suggestive, open-ended, and literary—the vision of someone who describes his principles
as “a) the less we believe the better b) nothing should be believed that has to be believed in” (qtd.
Denham 262).</p>
          <p>Even as I do not want to make too much of the tension between the public and private Frye, I also
do not want to resolve it in favor of Frye’s fidelity to religion, as I think Denham does when he refers to
“the religious base of Frye’s thought” (2) or when he claims that Frye’s “religious ideas emerge
unmistakably,
<pb id="p39-189" n="189"/>
though often behind a Blakean mask, in <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>” (2). Blake was not so much a mask
for Frye as a key source of everything he had to say. As Frye puts it in one of his notebooks, “My Christian
position is that of Blake reinforced by Emily Dickinson” (qtd. Denham 262). That is not an ordinary
Christian position. I would go so far as to say that Frye inherited from Blake, Dickinson, and other writers a
productive tension between asserting and questioning one’s deepest beliefs, or say between commitment and
uncertainty, a tension that saved Frye from sterile aestheticism in his literary criticism and from mindless
dogmatism in his religious views. Keeping that tension alive may be one of the best ways of carrying on his
work.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Anatomy of Criticism.</hi> 1957. Princeton: Princeton UP,
1971.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Critical Path: An Essay on the Social Context of Literary Criticism.</hi>
1971. Bloomington: Indiana UP, 1973.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
