<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.4.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">William Blake in “The Vanguard of the Age”</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Magnus Ankarsjö</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
	<pb id="p39-185" n="185"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-4-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake in “The Vanguard of the Age”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In 1887 there appeared in <hi rend="i">The Architect: A Weekly Illustrated Journal of Art, Civil
Engineering, and Building</hi> an illustrated series of articles entitled “The Vanguard of the
Age.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">1</ref> Written by Hugh Stannus and
illustrated by reproductions of drawings by Herbert Johnson after paintings by Edward Armitage, R.A., these
articles were a tribute to Henry Crabb Robinson on the subject of a monument to his memory. The monument
comprised a series of paintings commissioned by Robinson’s friends and painted by Armitage in 1870-71 on the
walls of University Hall, London. Robinson (1775-1867), a founder of the University of London, had also been a
moving
<pb id="p39-186" n="186"/>
            <figure n="vanguard.39.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="294" height="500">
              <figTranscr>Wordsworth.<lb/>
                W. Blake.<lb/>
                Flaxman.</figTranscr>
              <head>Detail from <hi rend="i">The Vanguard of the Age</hi>, ink-photo reproduction of a drawing
by Herbert Johnson after a painting by Edward Armitage.</head>
              <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the New York Public Library.</figDesc>
            </figure>
spirit behind University Hall, a University College dining hall founded in celebration of the Dissenters’
Chapels Act of 1844.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">2</ref> (The building,
in Gordon Square, is now occupied by Dr. Williams’s Library.) Armitage’s paintings deteriorated and were
papered over, but the illustrations and verbal descriptions that compose “The Vanguard of the Age” now
serve as a record of its original. One of its numerous interesting features<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">3</ref> is the place given to William Blake. <note id="n24">1. 37
(Jan.-June 1887): 9-10, 23-24, 35, 42-44.</note>
	<note id="n25">2. For information about University Hall I am grateful to David Bindman.</note>
	<note id="n26">3. The image of Coleridge in “The Vanguard of the Age” is discussed in my 
<hi rend="i">Portraits of Coleridge</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1999) 122-23. Some factual material is
necessarily repeated here.</note></p>
          <p>The large foldout illustration in which Blake appears follows page 22 in <hi rend="i">The
Architect</hi> for 14 January 1887. In the lower right of the reproduction is printed “INK-PHOTO, SPRAGE
&amp; CO. 22 MARTINS LANE. CANNON ST, LONDON, E.C. ILLUSTRATIONS: THE VANGUARD OF THE AGE.” The ink-photo
process, which was introduced by Sprage and Co., has been described as involving “collotypes, made initially
on a surface of reticulated gelatine on a glass base.” A photo negative was printed on this surface, and,
after a good many steps, a “lithographic printing surface” was made “from which the actual impressions
were taken.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">4</ref> Blake is represented
in a manner deriving from the Thomas Phillips portrait of 1807 (National Portrait Gallery), which was well
known through graphic reproductions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">5</ref>
Blake is shown as one of a group around Robinson, of which the others are Charles and Mary Lamb, Robert
Southey, William Wordsworth, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, and John Flaxman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">6</ref> Stannus writes:
<q>
Art is represented in the group by two men. William Blake may have seen more visions than any other seer since
the days of Swedenborg. Robinson was his friend also, and often went to the room in Fountain Court where Blake
and his wife lived in a simplicity that was ideal. Flaxman, the sculptor, will always be identified with
University College, with which the Hall is associated, for there alone is it possible to form an idea of what
he was as a sculptor.
</q>
The last sentence refers, of course, to University College’s great collection of full-sized plaster models
of Flaxman’s sculptures, and although Stannus gets some facts about Blake slightly wrong—the Fountain
Court apartment consisted of more than one room, and Robinson may have visited less frequently than
“often”—the featuring of Blake in such proximity to Robinson in the original<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">7</ref> shows how closely they were associated in the minds of the
latter’s friends. As “one who is very much delighted with being in good Company,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">8</ref> Blake appears very much at home among the
Vanguard of the Age. <note id="n27">4. See Geoffrey Wakeman, <hi rend="i">Victorian Book Illustration: The
Technical Revolution</hi> (Detroit: Gale Research Co., 1973) 142-43. I thank Robert N. Essick for supplying
this reference.</note>
	<note id="n28">5. Louis Schiavonetti’s engraving after Phillips had appeared as the frontispiece to the
editions of Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> published by R. H. Cromek in 1808 and by R. Ackermann
in 1813, and the image had been re-engraved by A. L. Dick for editions published in New York in 1847 and
1858.</note>
	<note id="n29">6. The group occupies half of the foldout, design area 14 ¼ × 8 ⅞ in.</note>
	<note id="n30">7. In Armitage’s painting, Robinson was pictured as “an old man seated at a table,” an
image based on a photograph of 1868 (National Portrait Gallery), according to Richard Walker, 
<hi rend="i">Regency Portraits</hi> (London: National Portrait Gallery, 1985) 1: 416-17. This image was not
reproduced in <hi rend="i">The Architect.</hi></note>
	<note id="n31">8. Blake’s autograph, <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed.
David V. Erdman, newly rev. ed. (New York: Doubleday, 1988) 698.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
