<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>39.4.ward</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Building Jerusalem: Composition and Chronology</title>
        <author n="Ward">Aileen Ward</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">39.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Magnus Ankarsjö</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_39">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-39-4-0007">
        <pb id="p39-183" n="183"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Building <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: Composition and Chronology</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Aileen <name>Ward</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Of all the puzzles surrounding the dates of Blake’s poems, that of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
seems the most intractable. 
          In the absence of a draft, and with only a few contemporary references whose interpretation itself
is problematic, critics 
          and editors have settled for the stretch of time from 1804, the date on the title page, to 1820, the
latest watermark in the 
          first four complete copies printed, as the probable limits between which Blake composed, etched,
revised and printed the hundred 
          plates of the volume.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">1</ref> But
within these limits there is great disagreement as to the specific 
          years in which Blake actually composed <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">2</ref>—and indeed, exactly what 
          is meant by the composition of any of Blake’s illuminated works. The process includes a number of
stages separable from each 
          other by varying lengths of time: initial inspiration, whether verbal or visual; drafts of text,
sketches of designs; inscribing 
          more or less finished portions of text and accompanying designs on copper; possible revision;
etching the plates; printing, coloring, 
          then arranging and binding the printed pages. Indeed, one of Blake’s descriptions of the process
raises doubts about the reliability 
          of any of his reports on the composition of a specific work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n4" type="note">3</ref> His apparent references to 
          <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are too vague to be useful—whether in his 1803 letters to Butts, once
alluding to a “long Poem” 
          descriptive of his “Spiritual Acts” during his three years at Felpham, and two months later to
“a Sublime Allegory which is 
          now perfectly completed into a Grand Poem” speaking of his “three years trouble,” or in his
<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> 
          of 1809, where he refers to a “voluminous” work which he “will, if God please, publish,” or
in his <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi> 
          of 1810 mentioning a “Poem concerning my Three years &lt;Herculean&gt; Labours at Felpham,” soon
to be published: all these allusions 
          point more clearly to either <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> or <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">4</ref> In fact, 
          his only direct reference to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> occurs in a letter to George Cumberland of
12 April 1827 mentioning it as 
          “the Last Work” he produced, one copy of which he has “Finishd,” i.e., colored (E 784). Two
possible allusions also occur in 
          <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> (1810), where his statement “Imagination is
Surrounded by the daughters of 
          Inspiration who in the aggregate are calld Jerusalem” (E 554) sounds remarkably like a description
of the title page to 
          <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, while his later reference to Jerusalem as the Emanation of Albion,
which he immediately cancels 
          to identify her as the daughter of Albion and Brittannia (E 558), suggests a stage in the
composition of the poem before her 
          role was fixed. <note id="n2">1. See the table in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977; 
          henceforth <hi rend="i">BB</hi>) 226.</note>
	<note id="n3">2. Both Christine Gallant (<hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos</hi> 
          [Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1978] 49) and James King (<hi rend="i">William Blake: His
Life</hi> 
          [New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1991] 172-74) argue that it was begun even earlier, at Felpham,
1800-03, as Peter Ackroyd also implies 
          (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [London: Sinclair-Stevenson, 1995] 174). Ackroyd thinks it was started
“at the same time” as Richard Brothers 
          published <hi rend="i">A Description of Jerusalem</hi>, i.e., 1801 (cf. Morton D. Paley, “William
Blake, the Prince of the Hebrews, 
          and the Woman Clothed with the Sun,” <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey
Keynes</hi>, ed. Morton D. Paley 
          and Michael Phillips [Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973] 273).</note>
	<note id="n4">3. “When I am commanded by the Spirits then I write, 
          And the moment I have written, I see the Words fly about the room in all directions[.] It is then
published[.]—The Spirits can read 
          and my MS: is of no further use[.]” Henry Crabb Robinson, <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi> (1852),
in G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
          <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969; henceforth <hi rend="i">BR</hi>)
547.</note>
          <note id="n5">4. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V.
Erdman, newly rev. ed. 
          (New York: Doubleday Anchor, 1988; henceforth E) 728, 730, 543 (cf. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 457),
572.</note></p>
          <p>However, a more precise dating of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> was offered by G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
in his 
          <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> of 1969 which has since been widely adopted. In 1964 Bentley
discovered in an 1807 notebook 
          of George Cumberland’s an isolated entry that “Blake has eng<hi rend="s">d</hi>. 60 Plates of a
new Prophecy!” This, 
          he concluded, must refer to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, since it is the only poem of Blake’s
containing sixty plates 
          or more (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 187 and n4). He communicated his discovery to David Erdman, who noted
it in his 1964 article 
          on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> but did not adopt Bentley’s conclusion as to the date in his
edition of Blake’s works 
          in 1965 or thereafter—nor did Geoffrey Keynes in his 1966 edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">5</ref> However, in 1977 
          Bentley extended his argument by specifying thirty-seven “late” plates which for various reasons
of internal evidence he 
          believes were added to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> after 1807,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">6</ref> leaving some sixty-three 
          as the “early” plates supposedly shown to Cumberland in 1807. Since then, most scholars and
editors have followed Bentley’s 
          hypothesis that more than half of the work was completed and etched by the summer of 1807.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">7</ref>
          <note id="n6">5. David V. Erdman, “The Suppressed and Altered Passages in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” 
          <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 17 (1964): 1-54 and E 730; Geoffrey Keynes, ed., 
          <hi rend="i">The Complete Writings of William Blake</hi>, 2nd ed. (London: Oxford University Press,
1966) 918.</note>
          <note id="n7">6. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 225-28: pls. 8, 10, 11, 16, 19, 33, 34, 35, 42, 43, 46, 47,
53, 55, 56, 59, 60, 
          61, 63, 64, 65, 66, 67, 70, 71, 72, 77, 78, 82, 89, 92, 93, 94, 95, 96, 99, 100.</note>
          <note id="n8">7. Most importantly, Morton D. Paley, ed., <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake’s
Illuminated Books, 
          vol. 1 (Princeton: Princeton University Press/Blake Trust; London: Tate Gallery/Blake Trust, 1991)
12, and in 
          <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1983)
2.</note></p>
          <p>Yet there are strong reasons for disagreeing with Bentley’s theory. First, there are twenty-six
plates containing 
          references to Hand scattered through the poem, which must have been written after Robert Hunt’s
devastating review of 
          <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> in 1808 (followed by his still crueler notice of Blake’s 1809
Exhibition),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">8</ref> 
          but of these twenty-six plates only ten are
<pb id="p39-184" n="184"/>
in the group of thirty-seven that Bentley identifies as “later,” i.e., post-1807.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">9</ref> 
The other sixteen plates mentioning Hand (in twenty-two separate occurrences) are in the remaining group of
sixty-three plates 
which Bentley would presumably designate as “early” (i.e., 1804-07).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">10</ref> In addition to these 
sixteen problematic “early” plates should be added a group of six other “early” plates alluding to
events occurring after 1807. 
Plate 27:25-26 refers to excavations in Paddington in 1811;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">11</ref> plate 38:6-7 refers to the 
War of 1812 and the executions of Mexican insurgents in 1811 and 1813 (<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 482); plate
40:19-24 describes 
the abolition of the slave trade in 1807 (<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 429); plate 45:25 alludes to the new (1815)
Bethlehem Hospital 
as well as to the Battle of Waterloo (lines 55-56), and includes one of many warnings against taking vengeance
on the defeated 
French (lines 36ff.) (<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 469, 466, 470). Plate 68:10ff. contains a song of victory for
1814 or 1815 as well 
as an allusion to the Russian campaign of 1812 (line 52) like that of plate 86:46.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">12</ref> 
Beside these post-1807 allusions, the character of Erin (mentioned seventeen times in twelve different
plates)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">13</ref> 
symbolizes the new hope for freedom springing up in England with the revival of the cause of Irish
independence in the decade of 1810, 
as Erdman suggests (<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 481-84), while the repeated warnings to Albion not to take
vengeance on his defeated enemy 
(<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 462, 470) must date from 1815 onward.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">14</ref> Thus a total of thirty-four or 
more plates which apparently were written in 1808 and after should be added to Bentley’s group of
thirty-seven “later” plates. 
If approximately seventy-one out of the hundred plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are then to be dated
after 1807, 
Cumberland’s 1807 memorandum that “Blake has eng.d 60 plates of a new Prophecy!” cannot refer to 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
<note id="n9">8. The Blake concordance (ed. Erdman, 2 vols. [Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1967] 1: 860)
lists twenty-five 
plates (to which 43:50 should be added) referring to “Hand (Symbolic Name),” in thirty-seven separate
lines: 5, 7, 8*, 9, 15, 
17, 18, 19*, 21, 26, 32, 34*, 36, 42*, 43*, 58, 60*, 67*, 70*, 71*, 74, 80, 82*, 83, 84, 90. The ten plates
marked with asterisks 
are from Bentley’s “later” group.</note>
<note id="n10">9. The ten “later” plates referring to Hand are 8:41, 43, 44; 19:18; 34:22, 36; 42:47;
43:50; 60:14, 43; 67:62; 70:1; 71:11, 22; 82:63.</note>
<note id="n11">10. 5:25; 7:18, 71; 9:21; 15:1; 17:62; 18:36, 39; 21:28; 26; 32:10; 36:15, 23; 58:29; 74:49;
80:57; 83:30, 86; 84:20; 90:23, 40, 49. 
Bentley notes that “The references throughout to Hand, who evidently represents the three Hunt brothers,
must date from 1808 or later” 
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 228-29), but does not correlate these references with his division of early-late
plates.</note>
<note id="n12">11. David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 3rd ed. (Princeton:
Princeton University 
Press, 1977; hereafter <hi rend="i">BPAE</hi>) 474.</note>
	<note id="n13">12. <hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 466, 482. Note also pl. 63:5-6, 
alluding to the Peace of Paris (<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 466), previously counted (note 6).</note>
<note id="n14">13. Pls. 9*, 11*, 12, 44, 48, 50, 72*, 74*, 78*, 86, 88, 94*. Asterisks indicate plates counted
previously, 
leaving eight new post-1807 allusions.</note>
	<note id="n15">14. Pls. 25:3-6, 36:41-42, 45:29-38, 47:12-16*, 63:8, for a total 
of four additional post-1807 allusions, not counting pl. 47 (cf. note 6).</note></p>
          <p>It has been suggested that Blake simply revised many of these sixty etched plates in the years
following 1807 
          to incorporate the thirty-odd references to Hand and post-1807 events.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">15</ref> 
          But both Robert Essick and Joseph Viscomi, with their expert knowledge of Blake’s printing
methods, have described 
          the “extreme difficulty” of making revisions on already etched plates,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">16</ref> 
          and none of the small number of such revisions which they detect involves the allusions cited above.
If it is 
          supposed that Blake revised his text after 1807 by simply discarding already etched plates for new
ones, it must 
          be countered that no evidence of such discarded plates survives, and that he was of necessity
extremely 
          parsimonious with copper. Almost all of the plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (like those of
most of 
          the other illuminated works) were etched back-to-back in order to save expense, and it appears he
was running 
          out of copper as he completed Chapter IV.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">17</ref> As for revising previously etched 
          or “early” plates to incorporate the twenty-two lines referring to Hand (to say nothing of all
the other post-1807 
          references), it should be noted that only seven “etched variants” are listed by Bentley,
including none of these 
          allusions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">18</ref> Moreover, Hand
is an integral part of the poem from the beginning: 
          he first appears on the sixtieth line of the text (5:25), and the thirty-seven separate allusions to
him are 
          scattered fairly evenly throughout the poem as a whole. Revising the etched plates of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 
          to incorporate such a number of textual additions after 1807 is thus a virtual impossibility: the
“new Prophecy” 
          cannot have been <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and can therefore only have been 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>
          <note id="n16">15. E.g., W. H. Stevenson, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi> (London:
Longman, 1971) 622: 
          “To include Hand as an important figure B, must have revised the poem after 1808.”</note>
          <note id="n17">16. Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi> 
          (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1980) 109, demonstrating the difficulty of adding new relief
          lines to the already etched text of pl. 25 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>; Joseph Viscomi, 
          <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1993) 278,
342.</note>
          <note id="n18">17. Cf. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 113, 145, 166, 208, 235-36, 308-09, 335, 381-82; also
225-28 on Blake’s 
          shortage of “other, more perfect” plates in etching pls. 33, 56, 63, 71-72, 92-93, and
100.</note>
          <note id="n19">18. Bentley, <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 237, adds seven other plates containing pen-and-ink
variants 
          and mentions about thirty more minor variations in the designs in his catalogue of the separate
plates (238-58); 
          none of these makes significant changes in the text except for the deleted mottos on pl. 1. Viscomi
(338-39) 
          claims forty-six plates bear deletions but mentions specifically only a few of them, such as the
notable 
          gougings-out on pl. 3; the few additions to etched plates consist of page numbers, corrected
spellings, 
          and two lines (37/33:1, last four words, and 45:40) etched in white line on a raised area 
          (Viscomi 254, 256, 340-41, 354; cf. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 246, 248; Essick 110-11, 156; Paley, ed., 
          <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 188, 203).</note></p>
          <p>How then are we to interpret Cumberland’s statement? First the possibility of human error or
misunderstanding 
          in one form or another should be admitted. Cumberland may have misremembered sixty for fifty, in
which case his 
          statement readily applies to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, which may well have contained nearly fifty
plates in the 
          summer of 1807. Or, since it does not appear from Cumberland’s statement that Blake actually
showed him sixty 
          plates of an unnamed “new prophecy” but merely mentioned the figure, he may have simply been
referring to intermediate 
          stages of its design. Or the “new prophecy” may have denoted an amorphous state in the evolution
of both 
          <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, in which portions of both were
mingled.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">19</ref>
          <note id="n20">19. Bentley, <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 307, suggests the existence in draft of 
          “a poem which comprehended the actions that were later divided between <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”; 
          Essick and Viscomi (eds., <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, Blake’s Illuminated Books, vol. 5
[Princeton: Princeton University Press/Blake Trust; 
          London: Tate Gallery/Blake Trust, 1993] 36) describe “both <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as a single project” at one point.</note></p>
          <pb id="p39-185" n="185"/>
          <p>But it is also possible that <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> at one time may have contained something
like sixty plates, 
          as Bentley himself has thought possible (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 187n4). <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
clearly went through 
          several stages of expansion and contraction during the course of its composition, as reflected in
the varying number 
          of plates in the different copies, and one of the early stages apparently included material about
the English Civil War 
          (<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 423-24), subsequently deleted, which linked it with the Lambeth Prophecies
as one more chapter 
          in the history of revolution. Erdman’s speculations on “the missing ten books of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>” (<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 423-24) 
          which linger in the background of “the early and late versions,” i.e., the “revolutionary
version” and the pacifistic 
          version (<hi rend="i">BPAE</hi> 425-27), suggest that at least a few pages of the early twelve-book
form were committed 
          to copper before being erased. In 1845 J. T. Smith recalled that Blake often “rubbed out”
already etched plates 
          “to enable him to use them for other subjects.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">20</ref> Though he did not describe 
          how these etched plates were erased, presumably an already etched plate could be polished to a clean
surface like 
          a new one more readily than it could be revised for corrections or additions.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">21</ref> 
          If so, this would supply the ten or more pages added to the existing forty-five to fifty pages of 
          <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (copies A-C) to make up the mysterious “60.” 
          <note id="n21">20. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 26n†, and cf. Viscomi 389-90n4 and <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
225-28, 335.</note>
          <note id="n22">21. See Viscomi 48-49 on the preparation of the plate for etching or engraving.
Viscomi nowhere 
          refers to Smith’s statement quoted above, from his 1845 <hi rend="i">Book for a Rainy
Day.</hi></note></p>
          <p>One final consideration in the case against the half-finished <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> of 1807
is the 
          date on the title page. How is the date of 1804, inscribed at the bottom of the page, to be
understood if the 
          poem was not actually begun until at least 1808? Butlin has commented on Blake’s “habit of
pre-dating works 
          unparalleled until its adoption by some of the pioneers of the modern movement,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">22</ref> 
          which may well be the case here. In fact, the only reason for taking 1804 as the date at which Blake
started work on 
          <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is simply the date “1804” of the title page, squeezed in above the
signature in a cramped 
          space at the bottom of the page, looking almost like an afterthought. The date is not an integral
part of the design 
          of the page, as it is so strikingly in the title page of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, or even of the
signature itself, 
          as in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (“Printed by Will: m Blake : 1793.”),
          <hi rend="i">The Song of Los, The First Book of Urizen, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los.</hi> 
          Instead, the date “1804” is etched in white line, i.e., incised on a large dark area, which
could readily be done 
          any time after 1804, if indeed the page as a whole was designed and etched that year rather than in
1808 or 1809 
          or whenever he did in fact begin <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The addition of the 1804 date
presumably was caused 
          by his desire to link the two poems, as they seem to have been linked in their gestation, or perhaps
to tie them 
          both to a significant date in Blake’s life, the rebirth of inspiration following his return from
Felpham and his 
          acquittal at his January 1804 trial, or still more the mysterious experience of renewal at the
Truchsessian Gallery 
          in October 1804. <note id="n23">22. Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: Tate
Gallery, 1978) 27.</note></p>
          <p>To place <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> firmly in the decade of the 1810s sets it in a far more
meaningful context 
          of Blake’s life than that of the mid-1800s. It links the poem to the mood of contrition and
forgiveness of his last 
          work, as contrasted with the spirit of condemnation and self-justification of the ending of 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> 
          It also answers the question of what Blake was doing in the years from 1810 to 1818, when he
virtually disappeared 
          from the London art world and apparently produced little work of significance compared with that of
the decades 
          immediately preceding and following. Only the hundred plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, in both
its verbal 
          and visual dimensions, fill this puzzling gap in the output of a major artist at the height of his
powers. 
          Its record of profound spiritual struggle and triumph in the face of worldly defeat was a labor
calling forth 
          all of Blake’s imaginative strength. Seen from this perspective, the composition of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 
          appears a striking example of what Charles Lamb was the first to describe as the sanity of true
genius: as the 
          creative means by which Blake regained his creative wholeness after the crisis of the years
preceding 1810.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
