<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.1.grant</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Discussing the Arlington Court Picture, Part II</title>
                <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>August 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
			<pb id="p04-12" n="12"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-1-0007">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">DISCUSSION</hi></title>
                </head>
                <head>
                    <title type="section-subtitle">
                        “With Intellectual Spears and Long-winged Arrows of Thought”</title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">1. Discussing the <hi rend="u">Arlington Court Picture</hi><lb/>
                        Part II: Studying Blake’s Iconography for Guidance in Interpreting the Picture</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>John E. <name>Grant</name>
                        </docAuthor> The University of Iowa</byline>
                    <p><ref type="article" issue="3.4.grant">When I began these remarks</ref> my intention was chiefly to
<pb id="p04-13" n="13"/>
report on the discussion of the <hi rend="u">Arlington Court Picture</hi> at the MLA Meeting last year,
especially to summarize the new interpretation of the picture presented by Janet Warner, and to add some
observations that I had made while thinking about the meaning of the picture. I was particularly anxious not
to challenge the Warner-Simmons theory since they had not put their ideas in final shape and I also wanted to
avoid arguing for a theory of my own, partly because I did not have one that satisfied me. But after finishing
my report, which was published in the previous issue of the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi>, it seemed that many
questions had been raised that ought to be considered in more detail; these included methodological as well as
substantial considerations. As I was writing down these observations, an interpretation of the picture
occurred to me which is quite different from any other so far proposed, though certain elements in it are
indebted to Digby, Damon, and Warner-Simmons, the most illuminating previous interpreters. On consideration it
seemed desirable to publish the rest of my methodological remarks in <hi rend="u">BNL</hi> but to seek
publication in another journal for both the Warner-Simmons article and an outline of my interpretation in
order that the readers would be able to judge for themselves which seems more satisfactory. Happily 
<hi rend="u">Studies in Romanticism</hi> has agreed to print both interpretations in a forthcoming issue.</p>
                    <p>In the first part of this discussion I mentioned Bronzino’s 
<hi rend="u">Allegory</hi> as an example of a major painting in which the artist’s intellectual concerns
evidently led him to disregard the “usual” canons of compositional symmetry. I proposed, indeed that critics
should entertain the idea that there may be an “art of clutter,” which has its own validity, and that 
<hi rend="u">ACP</hi> is an example of it. Such a theory will hardly seem bold in a time like our own when the Art
Scene has found such “Invisible Art” as Conceptual and Street Art to be quite acceptable. But even if Blakists
wish to disregard this anachronistic lesson in aesthetic anarchism, they are driven to reconsider the
standards of Bronzino’s age, implicit and explicit, as manifested in actual pictorial structures. Then it
will be recognized that it is precisely such “usual” standards as compositional symmetry which came into
question during Bronzino’s age in the Mannerist movement. How the example of Bronzino may be germane to our
subject becomes clearer when we recall that the school of Blake and Fuseli is not infrequently referred to as
“Neo-Mannerist.” It is possible that paintings of comparable periods may tend to be mutually illuminating even
when there is no question of “influence” involved.</p>
                    <p>I suppose many Blakists have read the interpretation of Bronzino’s painting in
Panofsky’s <hi rend="u">Studies in Iconology</hi> (1962 ed., pp. 86-91) where Bronzino’s subject is
described as “The Exposure of Luxury.” Both because of Panofsky’s deserved
<pb id="p04-14" n="14"/>
eminence and because his interpretation appears to correspond with the inadequate reproduction of the picture,
most readers have been satisfied with what Panofsky had to say. But recently a quite different, less
moralistic, interpretation has been put forward by Michael Levey in “Sacred and Profane Significance in Two
Paintings by Bronzino” in <hi rend="u">Studies in Renaissance and Baroque Art</hi> presented to Anthony Blunt
(London and New York, 1967), pp. 30-33. By accurately observing that a figure taken by Panofsky to represent
Lady Truth actually depicts a mask of Fraud, Levey arrives at what is unquestionably a more satisfactory
interpretation of Bronzino’s allegory, properly called <hi rend="u">Venus Disarming Cupid</hi>, than
Panofsky had.</p>
                    <p>For a Blakist Levey’s mode of scholarship is no less note-worthy than his
conclusions. One must admire the precision, quiet vigor, and range of reference Levey deploys in calling
attention to real excellences in the painting as well as in correcting Panofsky’s errors. After all, the
mask of Fraud cannot seem a very accomplished image of Lady Truth, but it must be a brilliant success as a
mask since it has proven to be so plausible. As is often the case, an intellectual break-through leads the way
to aesthetic validation of the picture and a vindication of the artist. The worst thing about inadequate
allegorical theories is that their propounders feel compelled to say, when they encounter some symbolic detail
which doesn’t fit, that the artist must have nodded while imagining this particular. Scholarship has a
special obligation to free itself from such imputations when they are not undoubtedly justified.</p>
                    <p>It should be clear that I am holding up Levey’s piece for praise because it is
excellent, not because it is an inimitable accomplishment. Since even Panofsky could err, no superhuman
standard of scholarship need be assumed, but Blakists ought to demand a higher norm than has recently been
evidenced in a number of publications. I refer particularly to unreliable books such as Miss Raine’s huge
<hi rend="u">Blake and Tradition</hi> and Beer’s <hi rend="u">Blake’s Humanism</hi>, as well as to unsound
articles such as Mrs. Kostelanetz-Mellor’s piece on the color prints in the <hi rend="u">Festschrift</hi>
for Damon. To be sure, none of these is totally useless or motivated by an antipathy to Blake such as is
evident in Matthew Corrigan’s “Metaphor in William Blake: A Negative View,” <hi rend="u">JAAC</hi>, XXVIII
(1969). But the extreme caution that must be exercised while reading such uneven work can hardly be justified
and the fact that these pieces have actually been commended by some reviewers is regrettable.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">1</ref>
                        <note id="n13">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> In the first part of this discussion I mentioned the general
dissatisfaction with Miss Raine’s interpretation of <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> expressed by American Blakists at
the MLA. In the same issue of the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> was a note from Miss Raine declaring that Sir
Geoffrey Keynes had “confirmed in writing his agreement with my interpretations” (p. 90). To have persuaded so
distinguished a Blakist is greatly to Miss Raine’s credit. The same week I saw her note, however, I also
read that Frank Sinatra, who had previously supported a succession of liberal Democrats, had become an avid
campaigner for Governor Ronald Reagan in California. Hopefully both English and American Blakists will now be
prepared to fly to the mountains of Atlantis to resolve their outstanding differences.</note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p04-15" n="15"/>
                    <p>Yet another book in this class, the author’s second in two years, is John Beer’s
<hi rend="u">Blake’s Visionary Universe</hi>, which contains a lengthy discussion of our subject, 
<hi rend="u">ACP</hi>; (pp. 286-294). Such productivity leads one nostalgically to recall Max Plowman’s wonder
at how fast his friend Murry was getting along with Blake, as well as Murry’s still impressive book, which
was published within a couple of years of his becoming interested in Blake. But, apart from other
considerations, Murry was exceedingly gifted and in those days a critic of Blake was less clearly obligated to
learn thousands of things about Blake’s pictorial art. At least one of the critical inadequacies of Beer’s
book could not, however be rectified by mere diligence—its frequent failure to describe a picture
accurately. Evidently because he had happened on an engraving by Ghisi that looks a little like 
<hi rend="u">U</hi> 25 and <hi rend="u">J</hi> 75, Beer declares that the people in Blake’s pictures are men,
whereas the crucial figures are obviously female in both. Since every previous commentator had got the gender
of Blake’s figures correct, such mistakes are especially deplorable.</p>
                    <p>This interpretation of <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> is never deterred by negative evidence.
For example, Beer quotes <hi rend="u">VLJ</hi> pp. 85+90 (E552) and then comments: “The scene described is
palpably <hi rend="u">not</hi> the one in the present design; but the individual elements correspond 
<hi rend="u">so</hi> closely <hi rend="u">as to suggest</hi> a community of <hi rend="u">theme</hi>” (p. 291—my
ital. in the same clause). As stated, this is not quite self-contradiction on though the soft spots and fuzzy
connections begin to appear in the words of the second clause I have italicized. And this, alas, is the part
of the sentence that purports to justify the allusion in the first place. As the reader studies the succeeding
sentences of amplification, he becomes aware that the proliferation of words like “appear” and “perhaps” allow
the argument to drift into an equivocal world (which is confused with “vision”) in which the wirey bounding
line of rectitude becomes invisible. Intellectually the fundamental point is that the quoted passage is 
“<hi rend="u">not</hi>” relevant, but the subsequent expatiation tends to suggest
<pb id="p04-16" n="16"/>
there must be some significant connection, though none is ever forthcoming.</p>
                    <p>The same tactics of claiming <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> is significantly illuminated by some
literary text are repeated with the example of Rev. 22: 13-17; Beer even declares that “the picture as a whole
<hi rend="u">may</hi> be described as Blake’s vision of the Book of Revelation as miniatured within these
verses” (p. 294; my ital.). He finds the call in verse 17, “The Spirit and the Bride say ‘Come’”—to the
thirsty man who would drink, particularly relevant. But whatever the central man and woman in 
<hi rend="u">ACP</hi> are doing, they are not inviting anyone to drink. Even if the gesture of the man in the
finished painting were taken to be an offer (an improbable interpretation), the gesture in the preliminary
drawing (which Beer alludes to) could not possibly be construed as an invitation; moreover, since the water he
gestures to is undoubtedly salt—hardly the “water of life”—such an invitation could only be malicious. And
certainly the lady is indicating nothing attractive—except herself as she appears in the final version—but
rather warns of disasters. The connections Beer claims to see between the text and the picture are without
exception insubstantial, but he also tells the reader that, <hi rend="u">after</hi> he had become persuaded as
to the validity of his theory, he ran across Keynes’s article on the picture which informed him that on the
verso of the pencil drawing is the inscription, written by another hand, from Rev. 17, “The Spirit and the
Bride say ‘Come’.” This he took to be a corroboration of his interpretation. Alas for scholarship, there
is no such inscription and Keynes never reported its existence; what he did say is that the picture is
inscribed, not in Blake’s hand, “The River of Oblivion,” and also (in a sentence of parallel structure) that
some unnamed person (actually in the Philadelphia Catalogue, no. 205) had attempted, unpersuasively, to
connect the drawing with the Biblical text.</p>
                    <p>It would hardly be worth dwelling on these blunders if the only moral to be drawn is
that “haste makes waste.” But it is instructive to recognize the root premise that encourages an informed
person to propound an interpretation that has neither surface plausibility nor deep persuasiveness. The key
word (which is also repeated on the dust jacket) I have italicized: “Blake’s <hi rend="u">idiosyncratic</hi>
interpretations” (p. 294). Without denying that Blake was sometimes “idiosyncratic,” particularly about small
things, we ought to observe how much pseudo-criticism seeks to justify itself by some form of 
<corr type="emend">this hypothesis.</corr> That is, when what Blake did does not correspond to the theory being
presented by the expositor, the contradiction is merely dismissed as an example of Blake’s odd way of going
at things. This, in essence, is the difference between experiencing art and looking into
<pb id="p04-17" n="17"/>
occultism, a distinction Blake insisted on in <hi rend="u">MHH</hi>. With art the only possible assumption is
that the artist makes sense, even if one happens not to agree with everything the artist has to say. But with
occultism, which Beer seems to have read considerably, one encounters material that really is idiosyncratic
and, at least intermittently meaningless. It ordinarily has no infinite implications, as art does, and, if one
is to read it at all, he must be content to get an obscure sense or a drift. To ask so little of Blake is to
get nothing.</p>
                    <p>To insist that a distinction can, nay <hi rend="u">must</hi>, be made between sound and
unsound scholarship is not to demand that all scholars come to the same conclusions or even that they use
exactly the same methods. It does, however, presuppose that there is a difference between valid and invalid
argumentation, as Blake himself sometimes insisted when he was confronted by the obfuscations of Reynolds. If
one is committed to standards of scholarship, he must be unwilling to tolerate shoddy published work. On
occasion this may lead him to be as relentless and even impolite as Ralph Nader. Naturally a scholar must be
prepared to have his own work judged with comparable rigor. Once readers recognize that unsound books and
articles are no more inevitable than unsound automobiles, it is possible to hope, manufacturers and dealers of
scholarship may be persuaded to slow down and create more reliable products.</p>
                    <p>I see no contradiction between striving to improve critical procedures by identifying
unsound scholarship and attempting to achieve a more pluralistic conception of the ethical vision implicit in
Blake’s iconography. As interpreters we should heed Blake’s exhortations, early and late, to stop dividing
things up into cloven fictions, such as good and evil; we must expect that the Spectator is probably not going
to understand <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> as Blake did if he studies the picture attempting to put his finger on a
villain. Take the chief women in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi>, for example; some interpreters have contended that the
Veiled Lady is pernicious, some that it is the Sea Goddess, and some have felt that the Water Carrier is up to
no good. A review of several considerations indicates that these suspicions are unfruitful because they lead
to a captiousness not based on things “in” the picture, even by implication. If we reconsider the interpretive
perspective offered by the picture of Vala and Jerusalem in <hi rend="u">J</hi> 46 [32], we see how precisely
the attributes in this polarized confrontation have been mixed in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi>. Evidently 
<hi rend="u">J</hi> 47 shows the two women getting entangled again, because they have turned Albion’s head, and
they do not get satisfactorily sorted out for many more pages of the poem. While the Veiled Lady is in a
posture very like that of Jerusalem in <hi rend="u">J</hi> 46, she is wearing
<pb id="p04-18" n="18"/>
a filmy costume with a head-covering that resembles that of Vala in the confrontation. Notice further,
however, that whereas Vala holds up her veil to obscure her face from Jerusalem, the Lady in 
<hi rend="u">ACP</hi> has her veil pushed back so as to <hi rend="u">reveal</hi> her face and chest. For anyone
aware of the traditional symbolism of the Veiled Lady Who is Truth (See Colin Still, 
<hi rend="u">Shakespeare’s Mystery Play</hi>, etc.), the difference is profoundly significant: Truth is told
when the Lady parts her Veils; indeed, Truth <hi rend="u">is</hi> the face revealed by parted veils. It is
possible that the Conjurer may already have turned quite around and seen the Lady’s face before he directs
his attention back toward both the chaotic sea and the unmobilized Spectator. Such an interpretation would not
require the Spectator to reprobate the Sea Goddess, even if the clouds she exudes seem soporific and the
horses she drives are, at this point, divisive. Her energy, her connection with the musical group above, and
her nudity, as well as some of her resemblances to other figures, to be mentioned later, all indicate that she
is a Vala with a place in the Eternal economy.</p>
                    <p>The third most important woman, the Water Carrier, is probably also blameless, in spite
of the scaled bucket of Storge water she carries in her right hand. I think the specially “musculated” look of
her dress, which was commented on inconclusively at the <hi rend="u">MLA</hi>, is intended to be a “wet look,”
indicative of her having been immersed in the river Storge, like the sleeping Nixie, but probably more deeply.
It is worth recalling that in Blake’s time ladies of fashion were known to have poured water over their
Empire-style dresses in order to achieve a more beguiling appearance. But lest we conclude that the Water
Carrier must be that doxy Rahab, we should consider that in the Melbourne version of the <hi rend="u">Creation
of Eve</hi> Christ himself wears a garment no less clinging and musculated. It is true that the left arm of
the Water Carrier, as I mentioned in the first part of this discussion, is rather underdeveloped and perhaps
deformed (cf. the right arm of the distorted figure at the left in <hi rend="u">J</hi> 45 [31]), but this
gesture almost exactly repeats that of the woman at the right in <hi rend="u">The Baptism of Christ</hi>, the
second design for <hi rend="u">Paradise Regained</hi> (Figgis, pl. 24), a presumably impeccable figure, who
witnesses with joy this blessed deed that is effected with a vessel of water, while warding off the
unregenerate devil who is flying away in frustration. To be sure this witness raises her 
<hi rend="u">right</hi> arm and she <hi rend="u">faces</hi> the Spectator, whereas the Water Carrier is 
<hi rend="u">back to</hi> the Spectator, but this difference does not seem decisive in the context of 
<hi rend="u">ACP</hi> where the women being encountered by the Water Carrier must be more sinister than she is.
Nevertheless, life requires that she overcome this
<pb id="p04-19" n="19"/>
trial, which seems formidable from the perspective of fallen innocence, and also that of Enitharmon and her
daughters, the three frenetic weavers, and enter the cave where the furnaces of Los will burn the Storge
scales from her bucket and her eyes. I am indebted to Beer (<hi rend="u">BVU</hi> p. 293) for the suggestion
that these flames are from Los’s forge. When she has risen above this trial she can carry her bucket in the
organized procession of Innocence in the topmost bowery cavern above. Possibly the lineage of these buckets
could be traced back to the enormous hats worn by a number of figures in Piero della Francesca’s great
murals at Arezzo as they may have been reported (or copied?) by Fuseli or Flaxman to Blake. In any case, if
she succeeded in bringing the Water of Death through a transformation into the Water of Life, fit for Beulah,
this nymph should also be able to say “Father &amp; Mother I return from the flames of fire tried &amp; pure
&amp; white” (E 730).</p>
                    <p>When dealing with Blake’s iconography one can make quite a consistent and useful
distinction between “<hi rend="u">symbolic</hi> similarities” where the figures may be closely connected even
though they look quite different, and “<hi rend="u">visual</hi> similarities,” in which the figures or objects
look much alike whether or not they are supposed to represent the same thing. An example of the former is
“Urizen,” who may be represented either as the aged whiskery man in <hi rend="u">M</hi> 15 or (if we follow
Damon) the beardless cloud-unfolding Apollo of <hi rend="u">Job</hi> 14. But visual similarities tend to be a
somewhat more reliable guide to meaning. In the first part of this discussion I mentioned the resemblance
between the posture of the Conjurer in Red in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> and the posture of Philoctetes in 
<hi rend="u">Philoctetes and Neopotolemus</hi>, though the latter is depicted from the front and is under obvious
duress. But in this case there is a visual parallel as well, since the two look much alike. There is no doubt
that Philoctetes is defying Neopotolemus, the youthful recruiting officer, and that Blake considered such
resistance to be admirable, whereas the Conjurer in Red, as I see him, is probably complicitous with the
(un-)Veiled Lady who stands behind him. But the visual parallels indicate to me that the Conjurer in Red is on
the side of freedom, like Philoctetes, and I have already suggested reasons for thinking his Lady is on his
side. From this perspective one might hazard a guess that the Conjurer in Red in gesturing over the water
toward the Pentagon with the intention of raising that home of sneaking villains fifty feet in the air.</p>
                    <p>One should also observe the symbolic rather than visual connection between the Sun God
in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> and the figure of the patriarch Enoch in Blake’s only lithograph 
(<hi rend="u">Separate Plates</hi>, pl. 26, no. 16) is related to both in spite of his
<pb id="p04-20" n="20"/>
differences in appearance. Obviously he has a longer beard, is presumably older, has his left foot thrust
forward and his right evidently drawn back, holds a great book across his legs, presides over an untroubled
scene, etc. When the picture is carefully studied, one first notices that Enoch’s hands hold the book down,
which is a different gesture from those of either of the other two, but then he notices that Enoch’s fingers
are in almost the same position as those of the Conjurer and that if Enoch raised his arms he would be making
the identical gesture. If he spread them, however, he would resemble the posture of the “Cherub Contemplation”
in the first design for <hi rend="u">Il Penseroso</hi>.</p>
                    <p>These symbolic connections are suggestive, but certain visual connections between Enoch
and figures in other designs indicate a fragility in the posture of Enoch which might, in turn, be taken to
qualify the prophetic image of the Conjurer in Red. Enoch certainly resembles the God of Job (as well as Job
himself, of course) particularly as he is depicted in <hi rend="u">Job</hi> pl. 16, with the book, and even
more as he appears in pl. 14, without the book, but with his <hi rend="u">right</hi> foot advanced. I take it
that Enoch is represented favorably, though a case could be made that this picture shows a fragile
prelapsarian condition of the Arts. Such an interpretation is strengthened when one recognizes that the
relationship between Enoch and his poetical scribe on the stepped platform is derived from the one between the
females Reason (<hi rend="u">right</hi> foot advanced) and Faith in <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> (no. 151,
engr. 41) in which the dominant figure is undoubtedly sinister. But there is a more decisive resemblance
between the Enoch design and the title page for <hi rend="u">ARO</hi> where the patriarchal figure must be
favorably presented. As is often the case, it is easier to discern a connection than to define the extent of
contrariety.</p>
                    <p>Another design in the Job series more directly related to <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> is 
<hi rend="u">Job</hi>, pl. 11, “With Dreams upon my bed thou scarest me &amp; affrightest me with Visions.” In
this picture, cloven-hoofed God-the-Satan points back and up at the tables of the Decalogue with his right
hand while pointing forward and down into the raging fire with his left. Job himself is shown stretched out on
Blake’s characteristic rolled funeral woven mat, holding up his hands to ward off the infernal deity he has
conjured up, and gazing with horror into the fire out of which two Satanic ministers have seized him, while a
third brings up a chain to bind him. The relational connections to the <hi rend="u">Philoctetes</hi> are
obvious, especially because Neopotolemus wears scaly armored drawers and a snaky strap over his shoulder,
while the hellish God of Job becomes entwined in the serpent, but many of the details have distinct
counterparts in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> as well. The Veiled Lady likewise points up and down, though her hands
are reversed,
<pb id="p04-21" n="21"/>
and her <hi rend="u">left</hi> indicates the flames in heaven, while her <hi rend="u">right</hi> points to the
flames below. In posture the figure of Job’s deity generally resembles both the Horned shell-helmeted Man
(shown from behind and on his back, of course), who manages the watery flames, as well as the Sea Goddess, who
rides in the vehicular wake of the Neptunian horses of passion. One is bound to observe the anatomical strain
involved in making the left leg of the former and the <hi rend="u">right</hi> leg of the latter so
unmistakably prominent. In the case of the man it is clear that he is striving to touch the huge root of the
tree with his toe (he does not touch a root in the preliminary drawing but there appears to be an
explosion—or a net—at his toe), whereas in the case of the woman there are only the small bubbles that
connect her with the Veiled Lady (in the drawing, where this figure is hardly developed, there is no
indication of them). The analogy of position indicated by the devilish God of Job, pl. 11, allows for the
suspicion that both the man and the woman may have something to hide, such as a cloven hoof, on their hidden
feet but I cannot imagine anything so drastically at odds with their healthy appearances.</p>
                    <p>Another connection with <hi rend="u">Job</hi> pl. 11 is that Job’s tormentors are
three, like the Fates, though they are shown working from beneath, rather than from above, on their intended
victim; their chain corresponds to the rope of the Fates. Doubtless this, Job’s most desperate plight, is a
product of his own self-righteousness and feelings of guilt, but note that there is a potential condition of
degradation as a result of superstition that Blake else where depicts but to which his Job does not fall. That
is, Job does not fall to <corr type="emend">worshipping</corr> Satan and his minions and, though he cannot exorcise, he can resist feebly
and save his life. This is a precondition to receiving the blessing by Job’s redemptive God in pl. 17, which
is bestowed with a gesture very like that of the Conjurer in Red in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi>.</p>
                    <p>In this perspective one might argue that the serpent covering of the nightmare God in
<hi rend="u">Job</hi> pl. 11 is the counterpart of the veil on the Veiled Lady and that one thus has a further
sign of her sinister influence. But I am not persuaded: a cloven-footed God can be no other than the Accuser,
but can the Veiled Lady be accusing the Man of having put the Sun God to sleep? I still see her neither as an
accuser nor as a temptress but as an admonisher, carrying out an authentic prophetic task, the burden of which
is expressed in the formula “If you go on So the result is So” (E 607). Or she may be saying, to whomever has
ears, “Since the Sun has doubted, his light has gone out; will you then allow yourself to be woman-dominated
like the nether god?”</p>
                    <pb id="p04-22" n="22"/>
                    <p>The manner in which an indubitable tempter works is exemplified by Satan in the Second
Temptation in the <hi rend="u">Paradise Regained</hi> series (<hi rend="u">Masters</hi>, pl. XII). Satan’s
crooked and insubstantial offer is partly expressed by the twist in his body and the sharp bends in the joints
of his arms, as well as by his unsupported position standing in the middle air; all this is in maximum
contrast with rigidly statuesque erect posture of Christ, whose hands (though reversed as to left and right)
indicate the same directions as do those of the Devil. Blake is also careful to delineate the three kingdoms
of this world that are the basis of this temptation, whereas the Veiled Lady in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> really
has nothing to offer that could seem desirable. In any case, Mrs. Warner, who called my attention to the
relevance of the <hi rend="u">Paradise Regained</hi> picture in this context, does not feel that the
similarities between Satan and the Veiled Lady are in themselves sufficient to discredit the Veiled Lady.</p>
                    <p>Positioned as he is between two women, it is natural to suppose that the Conjurer in
Red is being subjected to a choice between two contradictory life styles such as is, for example, shown in
Raphael’s famous <hi rend="u">Vision of a Knight</hi> (—in the National Gallery, London. The fact that
Raphael’s lady who offers love is clearly identical with the left nude in the companion picture of 
<hi rend="u">The Three Graces</hi> and that both resemble the Veiled Lady is also suggestive). But Blake’s point
seems to be different from what Mrs. Warner would make it; not only is the Conjurer in Red turned away from
the Sea Goddess, he is equally turned away from the Veiled Lady. If he had been absorbed into the Veiled
Lady’s sphere of influence he would have been turned wholly around like the spiritual portrait of Blake
discovering Los in <hi rend="u">M</hi> 21 or, even more, like the youth who is learning the wisdom of the
serpent from the malevolent lady teacher in <hi rend="u">A</hi> 14. Is it not more consistent with the
penetrating look he gives in the direction of the Spectator to suppose that the Conjurer in Red knows what we
need to know and that he is shown to be doing what needs to be done?</p>
                    <p>The Conjurer in Red must be related to another Watcher who also sits on a rock and eyes
the Spectator. In <hi rend="u">J</hi> pl. 78, the eagle-rooster headed man, in the position of 
<hi rend="u">The Thinker</hi>, is both a fallen eagle vigiling while the sun goes down and an awakening cock 
(<hi rend="u">M</hi> 28:24-26) or eagle (<hi rend="u">M</hi> 39) who attends its coming up. He is evidently an
avatar of Los (see <hi rend="u">FZ</hi> 7 a: 204-208, <hi rend="u">J</hi> 94:15, <hi rend="u">MHH</hi> 9:15),
as Wicksteed and others have supposed. But he is not yet engaged in redemptive action partly because the lines
depicted beneath him, which probably represent the Polypus, have not, at this point, been sorted out—the
task assigned
<pb id="p04-23" n="23"/>
to the Fates and their horned shell-helmeted companion in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi>. When this Watcher becomes
fully humanized, he will be ready to raise his hands to help, like the Conjurer in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi>. And
he will doubtless continue to look to the Spectator to lend a hand, knowing that if the Spectator goes on so,
refusing to get involved, there will be no result at all.</p>
                    <p>Some inconclusive evidence of what the Veiled Lady is capable of may be found in the
sketches for the <hi rend="u">Book of Enoch</hi> and in the drawings for <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi>. The
chief female in the first three sketches for <hi rend="u">Enoch</hi> (<hi rend="u">Pencil Drawings</hi> II,
pls. 45-47) rather closely resembles the Veiled Lady, in one way or another, particularly as she appears in
the preliminary drawing for <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> (<hi rend="u">Pencil Drawings</hi>, II, P1. 40) which was
presumably done about the same time. The fact that none of the women in the <hi rend="u">Enoch</hi> designs is
draped serves to distinguish them from the Veiled Lady, but it appears that in this series, nudity is not
necessarily a virtue. The fact that clothing is not an unambiguous guide to meanings is one of the many
complications in Blakean symbolism which upset ready and easy explanations of his “system.” But no moralist of
any stature would presume to pronounce on the general question as to whether nudity is a good or bad thing.
Obviously for the artist, it all depends.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Warner observed that in the drawing the Veiled Lady has stars in her veil and she
takes this to be a sinister symbol. I believe Mrs. Warner would agree that it is risky to reason forward from
the drawing to the much different picture, but in themselves the garment stars are not a propitious symbol.
Still, in one of the designs for Gray’s poems an indubitably Bardic figure wears a star-studded robe.
Moreover, careful study of the actual drawing indicates that there are as many as six stars, together with
what is perhaps an eye (comparison with other pictures makes this not improbable), and also four round objects
which are more likely to be grapes than anything else and, as such, would tend to counteract the possibly
sinister implication of the stars.</p>
                    <p>In the <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> designs there are a number of veiled admonitory
or witnessing women who wear a veil and keep track of the transgressions of male figures. Blake certainly did
not approve of all these avatars of “Conscience,” but it is not yet clear that he always disapproved of them
either. Toward the end of the series (IX, 83, no. 501) this figure is modulated into a huge impressive female
angel “Night,” who has a veil over her face and holds open before her a great book that contains the stars.
The record here is sublime, not petty or captious,
<pb id="p04-24" n="24"/>
and the record keeper worthy of admiration, not unlike the Sea Goddess in <hi rend="u">ACP</hi>, who also
brings on the night. (In the previous picture (no. 500) an impressive Diana is shown walking with a moon in
her hair, another connection with the Sea Goddess in her aspect as Hecate.)</p>
                    <p>But of all the designs in the <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> series the one that is
most closely connected to <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> is probably no. 465 (IX, 47), which illustrates the line
“Nature herself does Half the Work of Man.” Here Nature is shown as a huge woman who reaches her left hand up
to the crescent moon, and has her left leg still in the sea, while climbing up a cliff much like that in 
<hi rend="u">ACP</hi> with the assistance of her right hand and bent right leg. She is back to the Spectator but
her face is not sinister. The porticos of at least two classical temples are visible in the middle of the hill
she is climbing, and these are surmounted with church spires. The moral of this picture seems to be that if
without assistance Nature can make it to the level of natural religion, it ought not to be so difficult to get
her other foot free to achieve the next development for Mankind. But many of those who stop to rest in the
temples of the detestable gods of Priam, we may surmise, find it too hard to take the final step. The wonder
in this picture, however, is that so much progress has already been achieved. In the green foreground is a
tent, presumably a prophetic vantage point from which to observe so prodigious and efficad ous an event.</p>
                    <p>Probably the most decisive vindication of the Sea Goddess, in her being if not in all
her consequences, is to $e found in her close physical resemblance to the spiritual self-portrait of Blake
himself which is drawn with the Upcott autograph (Erdman, ed. il. 4). The Upcott figure is presumably of the
opposite sex (though it could be an androgyne), but its posture is very similar and its face might even be
that of the Conjurer in Red after he had had a rejuvenative shave. Moreover, the wirey bounding scroll wielded
by the Upcott figure must be related to the vortex cloud cover (or smoke screen) issuing from the right hand
of the Sea Goddess. Doubtless dark images of truth that must be read to be believed are written on both of
them. The Spectator’s success in reading part of this endless scroll will perhaps strengthen him to read
other parts that he needs to know, until that time when the scroll is rolled together (Rev. 6:14), a text
Blake must have thought about at least once a day.</p>
                    <p>Indeed I have come to believe that if one wishes to understand <hi rend="u">ACP</hi> he
should look for still another avatar of this figure of the Interpreter. From a different angle he
<pb id="p04-25" n="25"/>
appears in an important though a little-known picture identified by Essick as representing the “Genius of 
<hi rend="u">Shakespeare</hi>” (repr. <hi rend="u">Apollo</hi> N.S. LXXIX (1964), 321.) But the exact counterpart
of the Sea Goddess is to be found at the center of the “Whirlwind of Lovers” (<hi rend="u">Divine Comedy</hi>
nos. 10 and 10E) where she is working to overcome those deprivations which would forever forbid the return of
mankind into paradise. I shall maintain that this great picture acts as an explanatory sequel to 
<hi rend="u">ACP</hi>.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>