<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.1.works</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Works in Progress</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>August 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
        <pb id="p04-30" n="30"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-1-0009">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="u">WORKS IN PROGRESS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <p><corr type="emend">Adlard, John, <hi rend="u">The Sports of Cruelty</hi> (published by Cecil and 
				Amelia Woolf), primarily about folklore sources of William Blake.</corr></p>
                <p>Bogen, Nancy, a critical edition of <hi rend="u">The Book of Thel</hi> with a new
interpretation; a study of Blake’s development as a self-styled prophet in light of 18th century Bible
study; directing a thesis on Blake and Whitman as Visionaries.</p>
                <p>Duerksen, Roland A., a book-length study dealing with self and society in the poetry of
Blake, Coleridge, Keats and Shelley.</p>
                <p>Hagstrum, Jean, a collection of essays (some already published) on Meaning in Design and
Word; directing a dissertation: <corr type="emend">Elaine Kauvar,</corr> “Blake’s ‘Vegetable Universe’: A Study of Botanical
Imagery and its Context.”</p>
                <p>Helmstadter, Thomas, an article on Blake’s ideas and symbolism in selected 
<hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations.</p>
                <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn, a study of the relationship of the Bard’s song to the rest of the
poem in <hi rend="u">Milton.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Singer, June, <hi rend="u">The Unholy Bible</hi>, a psychological study of Blake (item
contributed by Mary Lynn Johnson).</p>
                <p>Spencer, Jeffry, a study of Blake’s illustrations to Milton’s poetry.</p>
                <p>Todd, Ruthven, a new, annotated edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="u">Life</hi>; a
“Pictureback” on Blake to be published by Studio Vista/Dutton; a study of Blake’s illustrative techniques to
be called <hi rend="u">William Blake: The Technical Man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Tolley, Michael J., Ph.D. thesis: “William Blake’s use of the Bible”; a project to edit
(for the Clarendon Press) Blake’s <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations, co-editor with John E.
Grant, Edward J. Rose (coordinated by David V. Erdman); articles: one on “The Fly” in the next issue of 
<hi rend="u">Blake Studies</hi> (an exchange with Hagstrum); one on <hi rend="u">Europe</hi> in the Princeton
collection edited by Erdman and Grant.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>