<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.1.tolley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Jerusalem 12: 25-29 - Some Questions Answered</title>
                <author n="Tolley">Michael J. Tolley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>August 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
	<pb id="p04-3" n="3"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-1-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">NOTES</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">1. <hi rend="u">JERUSALEM</hi> 12: 25-29 - SOME QUESTIONS
ANSWERED</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Michael J. <name>Tolley</name></docAuthor><lb/>
                        The University of Adelaide</byline>
					<q>
What are those golden builders doing? where was the burying place<lb/>
Of soft Ethinthus? near Tyburns fatal Tree? is that<lb/>
Mild Zions hills most ancient promontory; near mournful<lb/>
Ever weeping Paddington? is that Calvary and Golgotha?<lb/>
Becoming a building of pity and compassion? . . .
</q>
                    <p>The first question I shall answer is implicit: where was “Mild Zions hills most ancient
promontory”? I fancy that even a “king of quiz” would have some difficulty in rousing his faculties to answer
this one offhand. I think most of us get as far as assuming that it must be a reference to “Calvary and
<pb id="p04-4" n="4"/>
Golgotha”, but find it impossible to work back from there, neither name being mentioned in the Old Testament
(both are descriptive names only, meaning “a skull”). However, the student familiar with biblical typology
cannot complain that the question is unfair: finding its solution, we discover one of Blake’s characteristic
“poems-within-a-reference”. The answer is in the traditional interpretation of Genesis 22, the account of
Abraham’s intended sacrifice of Isaac. Briefly, this place of sacrifice, a mountain in “the land of Moriah”,
was identified with a hill in Sion (Jerusalem). The identification was common in Blake’s time, Isaac
naturally serving as a type of Christ crucified (though Swedenborg some-what tendentiously found the whole
story a type of Christ’s temptations, <hi rend="u">Arcana Coelestia</hi>, par. 2766ff). Matthew Poole, for
instance, whose commentary was first published in 1685 and republished throughout the eighteenth century,
noted that in Moriah “particularly there were two eminent hills, or rather tops or parts of the same mountain;
Sion where David’s palace was: and Moriah, where the temple was built”. Poole’s qualification suggests
that Blake’s word “promontory” was chosen with care (Robert Young, in his <hi rend="u">Analytical
Concordance</hi>, notes that “There is no sanction for the expression ‘Mount Calvary’ for it is only 18
feet high”). Various references could be cited, but it is sufficient to quote one of approximately the right
date for <hi rend="u">Jerusalem, the Christian’s Complete Family Bible</hi>, Liverpool, 1809, which has
notes by “several eminent divines” (this is a new and revised edition). On Genesis 22.2 is noted: “The word
<hi rend="u">Moriah</hi> signifies <hi rend="u">God manifested</hi>, and was so called from God’s appearing
to Abraham. Upon this very mountain the temple of Solomon was afterwards built, and upon one part of it,
namely, Mount Calvary, our blessed Saviour offered himself a sacrifice for the sins of mankind.” Moriah was
also translated as “Vision” (by Samuel Clark, for instance, in his <hi rend="u">Family Bible</hi> of 1760) and
if Blake accepted this meaning, he would have noted an interesting regression from Moriah, the place of the
Divine Vision, to Golgotha, the skull. One answer to the question, “What are those golden builders doing?” (in
building Golgonooza), is clearly that they are changing Tyburn-Golgotha back into a place of vision, where
divine pity intervenes to prevent human sacrifice. Golgonooza is also a version of the temple of Solomon: by
referring to Moriah through such an oblique antonomasia, Blake manages to suggest that the progression, place
of sacrifice to temple, is a type of the new Jerusalem that comes from Calvary and so of Golgonooza built near
Tyburn and Paddington. (David Erdman has suggested that Blake’s vision was prompted partly by the actual
expansion of home building in 1811 and has <corr type="emend">given some</corr> cogent reasons for Blake’s
specification of “ever-weeping Paddington” in <hi rend="u">Blake</hi>: <hi rend="u">Prophet Against
Empire</hi>, <corr type="emend">chapter</corr> 27, section 1.)</p>
                    <p>Although, in his recapitulation of this passage in Jerusalem 27:25ff, Blake avoids
further reference to the intended sacrifice of Isaac, the plate is much concerned with human sacrifice and
Abraham is mentioned twice in the prose address. $ere Abraham is called a Druid, but a contemporary reference
in <hi rend="u">A Descriptive</hi>
                        <pb id="p04-5" n="5"/>
                        <hi rend="u">Catalogue</hi>
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> gives his more specific function: “Abraham was called to succeed
the Druidical age, which began to turn allegoric and mental signification into corporeal command, whereby
human sacrifice would have depopulated the earth”. A similar movement, “From willing sacrifice of Self, to
sacrifice of (miscall’d) Enemies/ For Atonement”, is mentioned in <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> 28:20-21 and
in the following plate (in Keynes’ arrangement), lines 1-4,
<q>
Then the Divine Vision like a silent Sun appeared above<lb/>
Albions dark rocks: setting behind the Gardens of Kensington<lb/>
On Tyburns River, in clouds of blood: where was mild Zion Hills<lb/>
Most ancient promontory, and in the Sun, a Human Form appeared
</q>
The ensuing speech of “the Voice Divine” is partly concerned with Abraham’s problem of obedience, for Albion
“hath founded his reaction into a Law / Of Action, For Obedience to destroy the Contraries of Man” (14-15). A
third, perhaps less pointed mention of “Zion Hills most ancient promontary” is also in a context of human
sacrifice, <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> 80:36.</p>
                    <p>My answer to the other big question in this passage, “where was the burying-place / Of
soft Ethinthus?”, perhaps asks more questions than it solves. This time the answer is in Genesis 23,
recounting Abraham’s purchase of a “burying place” (verses 4, 9 and 20) for his family, following the death
of his wife Sarah. The association with the story of Abraham and Isaac is too close to be accidental, but I
can see little value in pressing an identification of Ethinthus with Sarah. Probably the original coining of
the name (which may have been pre-<hi rend="u">Europe</hi>, for all we know) had nothing to do with this
passage, but it is curious that this burying-place belonged to the sons of Heth (it is not likely that “soft
Ethinthus” is connected with the Hebrew, <hi rend="u">ethan</hi>, translated as “hard” once in A.V., Proverbs
13.15). The grave bought by Abraham was the “cave of the field of Machpelah” (verse 19), identified with
Hebron, 22 miles south of Jerusalem (and so near to Tyburn only by association with Abraham at Moriah). Blake
speaks of “the Caves of Machpelah” once, in <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> 64:38, a cryptic passage. Exploring
Blake’s cave-grave imagery would take me too far afield here, but we should not miss the typological link
with Joseph of Arimathea’s grave where Jesus was buried. It is not Joseph but Los who, in 
<hi rend="u">FZ</hi> 106 and 110, hews the Sepulcher “in the rock / Of Eternity for himself” and his motive
probably explains the significance Blake attached to Abraham’s concern for a tomb: “he hewd it despairing of
Life Eternal” (106:16). Thus to bury soft Ethinthus is to deny her a possibility of resurrection: Erdman notes
that the accidental digging up of Tyburn bones in 1811 “recalled that after the Restoration the bodies of
Cromwell, Ireton, and Bradshaw had been disinterred, hanged and beheaded, and then reburied here—another
denial of the Resurrection.”
<pb id="p04-6" n="6"/>
However, the tomb of Jesus was the place of Christ’s resurrection and Blake notes that, although the Western
Gate fourfold of Golgonooza is “clos’d up till the last day”, yet then “the graves shall yield their dead”
(13:11). A possible parallel to the burial of Ethinthus is that of Ahania “in a secret cave” in 
<hi rend="u">FZ</hi> 121:38, which Paul Miner has related to Sarah’s burial (<hi rend="u">William Blake Essays
for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld, Providence, 1969, p. 266).</p>
                    <p>Ethinthus remains a shadowy figure, but perhaps someone will be able to take these
suggestions further. It is noteworthy that Ethinthus immediately precedes Moab in the list of the daughters of
Los and Enitharmon (<hi rend="u">FZ</hi> 115:8), so being neatly contemporary with Sarah, for Moab was a son
[sic] of Lot, Abraham’s nephew (Genesis 19.37). (Moab is a daughter in Blake’s list because of Numbers
25.1, as Damon has explained in <hi rend="u">William Blake</hi>, 1924 p. 388.)</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>