<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.1.chayes</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Blake and Tradition: “The Little Girl Lost” and “The Little
Girl Found”</title>
                <author n="Chayes">Irene H. Chayes</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>August 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editors</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Andrew Griffin</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Pelfrey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
			<pb id="p04-25" n="25"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-1-0007">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">2. Blake and Tradition: “The Little Girl Lost” and “The Little Girl
Found”</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Irene H. <name>Chayes</name>
                        </docAuthor> Silver Spring, Maryland</byline>
                    <p>In his review of Kathleen Raine’s <hi rend="u">Blake and Tradition</hi> 
(<hi rend="u">BNL</hi>, Vol. III, Whole # 11), Daniel Hughes mentions my name in connection with a pair of
Blake’s poems on which I have taken a stand in print. Since Mr. Hughes does not examine any of the Raine
readings he commends, I would like to supplement my incidental criticism of seven years ago.</p>
                    <p>For at least some of us who have needed no introduction to Thomas Taylor and have
remained unconverted, what is at issue in the Neoplatonist chapters of <hi rend="u">Blake and Tradition</hi>
is what was at issue when they were published first as separate essays: not the “poetic process,” but critical
method; not whether Blake knew Taylor’s translations and commentaries (he probably did, as he knew other
books of the time), but how close they can or should be brought to his poetry; not what Taylor said, but what
Blake means. With respect to the Lyca poems, I still believe that there is something of the 
<hi rend="u">Dissertation on the Eleusinian and Bacchic Mysteries</hi> in “The Little Girl Lost”, and something
less and of a different kind in “The Little Girl Found.” The images in the first poem (I would not call them
“symbols”) of the moon and the caves, the desert, the “southern clime,” the animals and their ceremonial
behavior, do gain from the associations of both the Mysteries ritual and the Neoplatonic concept of the
descent of the soul, which Taylor brings together in a confused mixture of metaphor, abstraction, and allegory
compounded upon <corr type="emend">allegory</corr>. But I still maintain also that the <hi rend="u">Dissertation</hi> contributes 
<hi rend="u">less</hi> to the whole poem, and less to some of the same images, than such other sources of analogy
as the ballad “The Children in the
<pb id="p04-26" n="26"/>
Wood,” the first canto of the <hi rend="u">Inferno</hi>, and the episode of Una and the lion in 
<hi rend="u">The Faerie Queene</hi>—as I have already argued. Even the theme of initiation, which comes to the
fore in the second poem and could very well have been suggested by the general subject of the 
<hi rend="u">Dissertation</hi>, is dependent primarily on <hi rend="u">Inferno</hi> I when it first emerges.</p>
                    <p>Reading Kathleen Raine, Mr. Hughes thinks of the poetic process, which seems to concern
the poet less than the audience, and he is content to leave the poems themselves in the background. Miss
Raine, in turn is thinking of Thomas Taylor, and her method is to translate the poems into the rigid,
allegorical terms of the <hi rend="u">Dissertation</hi>. The “fullest possible content” that Taylor is able to
find in the Eleusinian Mysteries is considered full enough for Blake’s purposes, which are assumed not to
differ from Taylor’s; here, at least, the operation of “tradition” allows only one meaning, and by
implication turns any new work of poetry into a devotional exercise in repetition. Such a premise may be
useful to the commentator herself as a personal poetic, but in relation to Blake it is open to objections so
obvious they should not have to be raised in answer to a reviewer writing for an audience of Blake scholars
and critics. The least that can be said against the conception of Blake in these chapters of Miss Raine’s
book is that it makes the vigorously dissenting poet submissive to the arid and obsolete doctrines of
Neoplatonism as he never was to any still viable system of belief in his own time, and that it denies him the
subtlety, imagination, and independence we take for granted in the handling of received or borrowed material
by other poets, both earlier and later.</p>
                    <p>There are other considerations of importance to critics of Blake, which Mr. Hughes
neglects. Although it is the transaction between Miss Raine and her readers that interests him most, her
statements are about a text which has an objective existence and can be consulted, even without the guidance
of a Mystagogue; and checked against any convenient edition of the <hi rend="u">Songs</hi>, the Neoplatonist
reading of “The Little Girl Lost” shows signs of strain from the beginning. (About “The Little Girl Found”
Miss Raine finds relatively less to say, and less use for the <hi rend="u">Dissertation</hi> in her
discussion.) Lyca’s act of lying down to sleep, for example, can be fitted into the pattern only by being
made into both an effect and a cause, and the metaphor of a metaphor. The emphasis is continually on isolated
images taken out of their own context and delivered to Taylor and his Neoplatonists for a systematic reduction
in meaning. Repeatedly, from the first stanza to the last, Lyca is seen as the pre-existent soul descending by
various metaphorical means into the realm of “generation” and corporeal life, all without regard for time
<pb id="p04-27" n="27"/>
relations, allegorical consistency, or the narrative itself. In the last stanza, however, something
interesting happens: the text rebels against the commentator. Blake seems about to confess his allegiance by
using a standard Neoplatonic metaphor, but he immediately overturns it; whereas the soul descending from
eternity ends by putting on the mortal body as a garment, Lyca’s “slender dress” is “loos’d,” and when she
is carried to the caves, she is naked.</p>
                    <p>Such a jolt to conventional expectations (if Blake did indeed know the 
<hi rend="u">Dissertation</hi>, he would have been aware of how conventional they were to Taylor) would usually be
recognized as a signal from the author, and so I believe it should be here. Coming <corr type="emend">as
it</corr> does at the climax of a poem in which there have been earlier ambiguities and disparities
(unfortunately lost in Miss Raine’s absolutist reading), it is Blake’s indirect assertion of his own
meaning, an evocation of the <hi rend="u">Dissertation</hi> for the purpose of rejecting the values assumed
there. We are being notified, in effect, that the story of Lyca is to be separated from Taylor’s allegory
and understood according to a different set of values, which are also accessible through the imagery of the
poem. Lyca <hi rend="u">is</hi> “dying from this world,” not into it, and she is descending to an even lower
state, not like the space-travelling soul of the Neoplatonists but like Aeneas in the Underworld or like
Dante’s pilgrim, whose wandering and sleep she has reenacted in the earlier stanzas and who descended, going
by “another way,” so that ultimately he could rise out of his own lost state. It is at this point, through the
associations of the <hi rend="u">Inferno</hi> most especially, that the initiation theme comes to the surface
and reflects back to the opening prophecy to suggest how the sleeping earth one day may be able to “rise and
seek/ For her maker meek.”</p>
                    <p>The last stanza of “The Little Girl Lost” is a test of the kind of commentary to which
Miss Raine has committed herself, and she does not try to bridge the distance that opens up between Blake’s
poem and Taylor’s <hi rend="u">Dissertation</hi> at the very moment she is preparing to wind up a triumphant
demonstration that, in effect, Blake is Taylor versified. Instead of questioning either her premise or her
method, however, she responds by patronizing Blake. Lyca can only be the fallen soul, which necessarily puts
<hi rend="u">on</hi> a garment; therefore “it seems as though Blake, in attempting to keep all his multiple
meanings in mind simultaneously, has failed at this point....Yet the line is beautiful and imaginatively
satisfying, if we do not insist....In the total impression one would not wish....” This must be what Mr.
Hughes is remembering when he finds <hi rend="u">Blake</hi> “confused or even careless.”</p>
                    <pb id="p04-28" n="28"/>
                    <p>In the analogy he sets up between initiation into the Mysteries and “experiencing”
Blake, Mr. Hughes at first assigns the role of Mystagogue, the sponsor and guide of the initiate, to Blake
himself, although his, Mr. Hughes’s, own practical choice is Kathleen Raine speaking through her commentary.
A better role in the Mysteries ritual for the actual author of the poem would be that of the Hierophant, the
high priest of Eleusis, who at the supreme degree of initiation spoke the sacred words and exhibited the
sacred objects. Those were the “secrets,” neither concealed nor explained but uttered and
exhibited—presented for understanding directly to the initiate by their official guardian. Such a ritual
exhibition, the <hi rend="u">epopteia</hi>, takes place as part of the narrative in “The Little Girl Found”
when the transformed lion-king allows Lyca’s parents to see their sleeping daughter. There the formal
Hierophant is the “Spirit arm’d in gold,” who in the first poem, in his animal shape, has been an 
<hi rend="u">epopt</hi> himself, “viewing” the same sleeping figure. In both poems, presiding over the
enlightenment of the personages in the narrative and of the reader as well, the ultimate Hierophant is Blake,
and he too presents his meanings directly, in words and images that are the equivalent (according to the
analogy introduced by Mr. Hughes) of the sacred words and objects revealed during the 
<hi rend="u">epopteia</hi> at Eleusis.</p>
                    <p>It is such an exhibition, I submit, that is being offered in the last stanza of “The
Little Girl Lost,” and all the reader-initiate needs to learn for his “salvation” is contained in what Blake
the Hierophant puts before him. Mr. Hughes, alas, seems prepared to turn his back and join Kathleen Raine in
rearranging the objects in a counter-display.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>