<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.2.news</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">The Newsletter and the University of New Mexico</title>
				<author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <front>
            <pb id="p04-33" n="33"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-2-0003">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">NEWS AND WORKS IN PROGRESS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <p>Our first news item concerns the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> itself. As our readers
know all too well by now, the <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> has suffered from uncertainty about its future
since its inception in 1967, fourteen issues ago. Now our problems seem to have been solved by the English
Department of the University of New Mexico, which has generously agreed to meet part of the costs of
publication. At the same time we welcome as co-editor Morris Eaves, a member of that department. This new
arrangement enables us to produce an offset-printed issue, to double our run of copies to 500, and to publish
illustrations. The result should be to make possible a better <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> as well as a more
secure one. We are also now able to make plans to publish a reprint edition of early issues; more on this next
time.</p>
                <p>From now on, the <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> will be printed and mailed in Albuquerque;
all correspondence relating to subscriptions should be sent there. Manuscripts for submission or
correspondence in relation to editorial matters may be sent either to Berkeley or to Albuquerque.</p>
				<byline>(<docAuthor>MDP</docAuthor>)</byline>
            </div1>
        </front>
    </text>
</TEI.2>