<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.2.phillips</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake’s Corrections in Poetical Sketches</title>
                <author n="Phillips">Michael Phillips</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
	<pb id="p04-40" n="40"/>
            <div1>
            	<div2>
                    <byline>2. <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">MICHAEL</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">PHILLIPS</hi>
                            </name>:
                        </docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">UNIVERSITY OF EDINBURGH</hi>
                    <ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Blake’s Corrections in <hi rend="i">POETICAL SKETCHES</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>My primary purpose here is to provide a complete list of all corrections which Blake
made in copies of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi> What is offered are the results of a systematic
inspection and collation of the original emended copies of the poems. These findings anticipate a more
comprehensive study which will provide detailed descriptions of the individual corrections that are present in
each of the eight emended copies with photographs of the corrections in their varying states to complement my
discussion. Remarks on the author’s changing attitude toward specific corrections and also an attempt to fix
approximate dates to the various copies as to when they were corrected and presented will also be given,
together with a discussion which will present new material regarding the printing of the poems. Before listing
Blake’s corrections and their frequency of occurrence it will be of interest if a few introductory remarks
are <note id="n0">
                            <hi rend="i">Copyright</hi> © <hi rend="i">1970 by Michael C. Phillips.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p04-41" n="41"/>
made regarding Blake’s manner of proceeding with his poems following their return from the printer. I have
also chosen to discuss Blake’s attitude toward <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> after 1783. The attention
that is given here to Blake’s corrections in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> owes much to the textual
foundations established by Margaret Ruth Lowery and especially Sir Geoffrey Keynes in their respective studies
of the poems. To Sir Geoffrey Keynes and to David V. Erdman I am particularly grateful for advice and opinion
given at various stages in my researches.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> were returned to Blake from the printer in open
sheets and probably in an edition of fifty copies as Sir Geoffrey Keynes has surmised.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">1</ref> At the time of printing and periodically thereafter Blake
folded the sheets of his poems and hand-stitched them in plain blue-gray paper wrappers; copy B is extant as
issued. He then emended his text with care and precision, usually employing what appears to be an India ink
and frequently keeping the nib of his pen finely trimmed. During the course of his life Blake’s attitude
toward a number of specific corrections changed as the corrections themselves vary in number and kind from
copy to copy. For example, only two copies contain the same series of corrections. <note id="n8">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                1
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Blake Studies</hi> (London, 1949), p. 25.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>J. T. Smith recorded that <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> were “given to Blake to
sell to friends, or publish, as he might think proper.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">2</ref> Blake neither sold nor published his poems at any time; at least we have no evidence to
suggest the occurrence of either possibility. At the time of Blake’s death there still remained in his
possession a number of copies in their open unbound state.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">3</ref> This indicates that he must have bound and emended copies at a rate which
corresponded with demand, that is, on the occasion when he wished to give a copy of his first poems to a
newly-made friend or acquaintance. The suggestion that he only bound and emended a few copies at a time is
substantiated by the variation in the number and nature of corrections that are present in the eight emended
copies of the poems which have survived. <note id="n9">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                2
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Nollekens and his Times</hi> (London, 1828), II, 457; reprinted in
Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford, 1969), p. 457.</note>
                        <note id="n10">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                3
                            </hi> Three copies of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (G, H and N) in their
open unbound state were found by John Linnell in March 1890 in the house of Samuel Palmer; see 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, p. 36, notes to copy G.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>During the period immediately following the return of the sheets from the printer Blake
presented at least three emended copies of his poems to John Flaxman and his wife. Flaxman, of course, was
almost certainly instrumental in having <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> printed. Dr. William Long and
William Hayley both received emended copies of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (E and S) from Flaxman
toward the end of April 1784,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">4</ref> and on
15 May of the same year Mrs. Flaxman presented a third copy (F) which had been emended by Blake. This third
copy was almost certainly presented by Mrs. Flaxman to Isaac Reed, a close friend of both Long and Hayley. All
three men possessed considerable influence in the literary world of the day, and this could well suggest the
Flaxman’s purpose in bringing their attention to Blake’s first literary efforts. Although no evidence
exists which would substantiate the presentation of additional copies during the period 1783-84, it would be
reasonable to assume that at least a few other copies were presented at the time, probably to the Reverend and
Mrs. A. S. Mathew and perhaps to Stothard, Fuseli and Barry. <note id="n11">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                4
                            </hi> Refer to Flaxman’s letter to Hayley of 26 April 1784 as given in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> and see Bentley’s note (p. 27, n. 3). Flaxman’s presentations in April 1784
could indicate that <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> were printed very late in 1783, and perhaps not even
returned from the printer until after the first of the year. Of course it would have taken Blake time to bind
and then to carefully emend even a few copies in the midst of more pressing commercial tasks.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>After the Flaxmans, George Cumberland and Thomas Butts are the earliest of Blake’s
friends to whom copies of the poems can be traced. Copy D of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (uncorrected)
bears George Cumberland’s signature on the titlepage. Although the earliest extant letter that was written
by Blake to Cumberland is dated 6 December 1795, their friendship evidently began some years before, possibly
during the early 1780’s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">5</ref> Blake met
Thomas Butts during the early 1790’s<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">6</ref> and it may have been during the first years of their long association that Blake presented
Butts with his emended copy (B) of the poems. <note id="n12">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                5
                            </hi> Geoffrey Keynes, “Some Uncollected Authors XLIV: George Cumberland
1754-1848,” <hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi>, 19 (Spring 1970), 31-65.</note>
                        <note id="n13">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                6
                            </hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, ed. Ruthven
Todd (London, 1942), p. 96.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The copy of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (C) presented to Charles Tulk is
distinguished by Blake’s personal inscription:
<q>
“Charles Tulk Esq<hi rend="s">re</hi> from William Blake”
</q>
                        <pb id="p04-42" n="42"/>
Charles Augustus Tulk was born in 1786, three years after the printing of the poems. Tulk was educated at
Westminster School and Trinity College, Cambridge, and returned to London in 1805 aged nineteen to read for
the bar. It is probable that he did not become acquainted with Blake before 1810, when together with Flaxman
he assisted in founding the London society for publishing Swedenborg’s works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">7</ref> Blake also emended the copy of <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches</hi> which he presented to Tulk. An emended copy (T) can also be traced to John Linnell, and it is
well known that Blake first met Linnell at Rathbone Place in 1818.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">8</ref>
                        <note id="n14">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                7
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> DNB</hi> LVII, 303-04.</note>
                        <note id="n15">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                8
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, pp. 256 ff.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Unpublished entries in his diaries and correspondence disclose that Henry Crabb
Robinson owned two copies of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">9</ref> one of which may have been presented to him by the Flaxmans in 1810 and the
second by Blake himself shortly after the two men first met at the dinner party that was given by Mrs. Charles
Aders in December 1825. I believe one of these two copies to be that which is now in possession of University
College London (copy W), which contains corrections and other MS. addenda a few of which are in Blake’s
hand. This new knowledge of Crabb Robinson’s ownership of two copies of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>,
the consequent implications regarding their availability to Robinson’s circle of friends, and his subsequent
presentation of one of these copies to J. J. Garth Wilkinson, who in turn through Henry James, Sr., introduced
a number of the poems to American readers for the first time, is the subject of a separate article which
should be available shortly. <note id="n16">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                9
                            </hi> Refer especially to entries and corresponding letters from 16 April 1848 to
24 May 1848; Henry Crabb Robinson MS. Diary, vol. XXI, “December 2, 1846-January 19, 1850,” Dr. Williams’
Library, London.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>We also know that Blake showed his first poems to Benjamin Heath Malkin and that with
him he evidently discussed several of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> in detail. Their meeting and
subsequent discussions probably took place in 1805, but possibly earlier.</p>
                    <p>We can see that the presentations by Blake of just the copies which can be traced to
their original owners are spread almost equally over the four decades of his life that followed the printing
of the poems. The variation in corrections from copy to copy supports this and also manifests the care with
which Blake reread his first poems at varying intervals during his later life. This clearly reverses the
traditional view, which is still widely accepted by critics and scholars alike, that Blake abandoned or lost
interest in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> either before or at any time after they were printed.</p>
                    <p>For seventy pages of text Blake made only fifteen corrections in all, four of which are
recorded here for the first time. I have also recorded two additional corrections, but there is some doubt
still remaining as to whether they were made by the author. No single copy contains all of Blake’s
corrections and only two copies (B and F) contain the same series in kind and number. In copies E and S, for
example, which Blake gave to Flaxman in 1783-84, and who in turn presented them to Dr. Long and William
Hayley, there occur five and six corrections respectively. In the copy presented by Mrs. Flaxman (F) less than
a month following her husband’s presentations there occur only four corrections in Blake’s hand, but also
present in this copy in four other hands are a number of suggestions for corrections together with a few
sparse comments on individual poems written in adjacent margins. In the copy (B) which Blake presumably
presented to Butts in the early 1790’s there also occur only four corrections. In all four of these copies
(E, S, F and B) the same four corrections will be found, those made in “To Winter,” “Fair Elenor” (p. 9, 1.
61), and the two in “Mad Song.”</p>
                    <p>In the copy which Blake presented to Tulk (C) probably after 1810 there are also only
four corrections, but one of these appears in the Tulk copy for the first time. An even greater change in
Blake’s attitude toward specific corrections is evident in the copy which can be traced to John Linnell (T).
In the Linnell copy there occur six corrections in the author’s hand, but of these four are found for the
first time. Indeed, the four corrections that are present in the Linnell copy are not known to exist in any
other emended copy. In the University College London copy (W), which I believe to be one of the two copies
owned by Henry Crabb Robinson, there occur only four corrections
<pb id="p04-43" n="43"/>
in Blake’s hand. As I have already suggested, it is probable that one of Robinson’s two copies was
presented to him by the Flaxmans in 1810, and in the light of this probability it is interesting that the four
corrections that are present in copy W are identical with those which are to be found in the three emended
copies which Blake gave to the Flaxmans in 1783-84 to use for presentations.</p>
                    <p>The most interesting and perplexing copy is that which is now in possession of the
Preston Blake Library (Q). This copy contains ten corrections in Blake’s hand, three of which are unique. I
believe this copy to have been emended by Blake toward the end of his life; it may be Robinson’s second
copy, given to him by the author as late as 1825 or 1826. Until the original owner of copy Q is traced,
however, we shall have to look (with due caution) to the corrections that are present in the Linnell copy (T)
for what may be the author’s final judgements. However, the corrections which Blake was consistent and most
assured in making will be apparent from the list of corrections that is given below, where their frequency of
occurrence is recorded.</p>
                    <p>In the light of the relatively small number of corrections and the nature of the
corrections themselves it may be fairly deduced that Blake was pleased with the printed text and also that the
text must have been relatively faithful to his original fair copies. For the poet himself I think that we can
also say that his first poems evidently continued to hold a significant place in his esteem, probably as
representing an integral and important stage in his own development and in the development of his canon.</p>
                    <p>The findings that are given below have been obtained by my proceeding in the following
manner. The eight extant copies of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> that Blake emended have been located
and then carefully examined, either by myself, whenever possible, or by responsible scholars on my behalf. The
handwriting of corrections has also been compared with corresponding examples of Blake’s hand present in his
surviving manuscripts. If it has not been possible for me to examine a copy then photographs have been
requested and the copy has been inspected in facsimile. Questions concerning erasures, inks that have been
used and other factors that are not generally clear from a facsimile have then been clarified through
correspondence. I should like to acknowledge here my gratitude to those who gave such assistance, particularly
Professor D. F. McKenzie, who dealt expertly with the problems presented by copy F in possession of the
Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</p>
                    <p>The following is a list of the eight extant copies of <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches</hi> which have been emended by Blake. The ordering of these copies follows that of Sir Geoffrey
Keynes in his “Census of Copies” published in <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> (1949).</p>
                    <table rows="8" cols="2">
                        <row>
                            <cell>B</cell>
                            <cell>Thomas Butts copy. British Museum [Ashley No. 2366].</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>C</cell>
                            <cell>Charles Augustus Tulk copy. H. E. Huntington Library, San Marino, California
[57432].</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>E</cell>
                            <cell>William Long copy. (Owner has asked to remain anonymous).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">10</ref>
                                <note id="n17">
                                    <hi rend="s">
                                        10
                                    </hi> Cf. <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 27, n. 4.</note>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>F</cell>
                            <cell>Mrs. Anna Flaxman copy. Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New
Zealand.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Q</cell>
                            <cell>Graham Robertson copy. Preston Blake Library, City of Westminster Public
Reference Library, London.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>William Hayley copy. H. E. Huntington Library, San Marino, California [Dev.
80 30].</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>T</cell>
                            <cell>John Linnell copy. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Alverthorpe Gallery,
Jenkintown, Pennsylvania.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>W</cell>
                            <cell>University College London copy. University College Library, London.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </div2>
                <pb id="p04-44" n="44"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">BLAKE’S EMENDATIONS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Capital letters following individual corrections refer to the copies cited above in
which the correction will be found. Page numbers refer to the 1783 text, line numbers correspond with those of
the editions of Erdman, <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose</hi> (1965) and Keynes, <hi rend="i">Complete
Writings</hi> (1966). The descriptions of corrections given below are intended to be of a general nature, and
it is to be allowed that the same correction will vary in detail from copy to copy with regard to the manner
in which it has been accomplished. I have listed a few corrections present in copies F and W as being
Blake’s, as I am convinced of their authenticity. However, it is only correct to state that with regard to
the authenticity of these corrections in copies F and W, Sir Geoffrey Keynes remains “unconvinced” (letter to
the author, 31 August 1967).</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>1.</label> “To Winter,” p. 4, 1. 11: the word “in” has been deleted by
pen from “and in his hand.”</p>
                            <p>B, C, E, F, Q, S, T, W total: 8</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>2.</label> “To the Evening Star,” p. 5, 1. 2: the word “whilst” has
been altered by pen to “while.”</p>
                            <p>Q total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>3.</label> “Fair Elenor,” p. 7, 1. 6: the letter “s” in “cheeks” has
been scraped away or deleted by pen.</p>
                            <p>C, E, Q, S total: 4</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>4.</label> “Fair Elenor,” p. 9, 1. 61: “I am” has been scraped away or
partially scraped away and “behold” has been hand-lettered by pen in the text in imitation of the type.</p>
                            <p>B, E, F, Q, S, W total: 6</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>5.</label> “Song,” (“Love and harmony combine”), p. 12, 1. 16: the word
“her” has been altered by pen to “his,” or deleted and “his” has been written in above the line.</p>
                            <p>C, Q total: 2</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>6.</label> “Mad Song,” p. 15, 1. 4: the lefthand portion of the letter
“u” of “unfold” has been scraped away and a dot added over the remainder altering the word to “infold.”</p>
                            <p>B, E, F, Q, S, W total: 6</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>7.</label> “Mad Song,” p. 15, 1. 7: the word “beds” has been deleted by
several fine strokes of the pen and the word “birds” has been very neatly penned immediately above the
deletion.</p>
                            <p>B, C, E, F, Q, S, W total: 7</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>8.</label> “An Imitation of Spencer,” p. 24, 1. 14: the letter “s” in
“others” has been deleted by several fine strokes of the pen.</p>
                            <p>T total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>9.</label> “An Imitation of Spencer,” p. 24, 1. 15: the letter “c” of
the word “cares” has been altered by a single stroke of the pen to “e” changing the word to “eares.”</p>
                            <p>Q, T total: 2</p>
                        </item>
                        <pb id="p04-45" n="45"/>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>10.</label> “An Imitation of Spencer,” p. 25, 1. 44; “O warrior, maid
invincible” has been altered by pen to read “O warrior maid, invincible.” The comma following “warrior” has
been deleted by pen and a comma has been penned in following “maid.”</p>
                            <p>Q total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>11.</label> “Blind-Man’s Buff,” p. 28, 11. 64-65: the punctuation has
been altered by pen from
<q>
“Who on the blinded man impose. Stand in his stead as long a-gone”
</q>
to
<q>
“Who on the blinded man impose, Stand in his stead; as long a-gone”
</q>
The alteration of the full stop to a comma and the insertion of a semi-colon following “stand” have been made
very tidily in order to appear like printed type.</p>
                            <p>Q total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>12.</label> “King Edward the Third,” p. 29, sc. i: in the italic
description of the scene, the words “before / it” have been struck out by pen.</p>
                            <p>S total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>13.</label> “King Edward the Third,” p. 44, sc. iii, 1. 236: the word
“her” has been deleted by pen and “his” has been hand-lettered in imitation of the type in the adjacent
margin.</p>
                            <p>T total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>14.</label> “King Edward the Third,” p. 46, sc. iii, 1. 292: the word
“them” has been deleted by pen and the word “him” has been hand-lettered with pen in imitation of the type
near the deletion.</p>
                            <p>T total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>15.</label> “Contemplation,” p. 64, 11. 37-39: in the line “ . . . he
followed me up and down in the house when I grew up; he was my school-fellow . . . ” a colon has been penned
in between the words “house” and “when” and the semi-colon between the words “up” and “he” has been deleted by
pen. The emended line reads “ . . . he followed me up and down in the house: when I grew up he was my
school-fellow . . . ”</p>
                            <p>T total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">QUESTIONABLE EMENDATIONS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>1.</label> “To Spring,” p. 2, 1. 14: it would appear that the word
“soft” in “Thy soft kisses” has been deleted by pen, but this could either be a perforation that has become
discoloured or a genuine correction which has become discoloured. This correction, if genuine, is unique.</p>
                            <p>T total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>2.</label> “Fair Elenor,” p. 9, 1. 61: the “y” in the word “thy” has
been partially scraped
<pb id="p04-46" n="46"/>
away, the paper being rubbed through immediately below; the rub mark is soiled. This may be a manifestation of
Blake’s dissatisfaction with this line, viz., “I am” in the line altered in other copies to “behold.”</p>
                            <p>C total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>3.</label> “Mad Song,” p. 15, 1. 7: the word “beds” has been deleted by
pen and “birds” has been hand-printed by pen above the deletion. Some question still remains as to whether
Blake made this correction.</p>
                            <p>T total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>4.</label> “An Imitation of Spencer,” p. 24, 1. 15: the letter “c” of
the word “cares” appears to have been altered by a single stroke of the pen to “e” changing the word to
“eares.” The very small pen stroke that is involved here appears to have been smudged out.</p>
                            <p>W total: 1</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">PROLEGOMENON</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>I should like to note here what remains to be accomplished if a definitive text of 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> is to be established. There are at least fourteen copies of the poems which
are known to be extant but which it is assumed that they do not contain any corrections by Blake. All of these
copies must be carefully inspected again in the unlikely event that they do contain undiscovered corrections
by the author or any other contemporary MS notes or markings which could be of interest. I have tried to
accomplish these inspections whenever possible, but the location of several “uncorrected” copies is unknown,
at least to me. May I suggest that if anyone knows of the present location of an original copy, regardless of
how obvious that location may appear to be but given that it differs from the location given in Keynes’
census of 1949, would he please inform me so that arrangements for its inspection and the recording of
findings can be made. This information will also greatly assist in bringing Sir Geoffrey Keynes’ “Census of
Copies” of 1949 up to date.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p04-47" n="47" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>