<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.2.bindman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">An Unpublished Blake Pencil Drawing of the Lambeth Period</title>
                <author n="Bindman">David Bindman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1970</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1970"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
        <pb id="p04-38" n="38"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-2-0004">
                <figure n="BUT232.1.1r.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="484">
                    <figTranscr>W.B. The dead ardours</figTranscr>
                    <head>1 Drawing known as “The Dead Bad-Doers,” recto.</head>
                    <figDesc>In the collection of David Bindman.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure n="BUT232.1.1v.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="470">
                    <head>2 “The Dead Bad-Doers,” verso.</head>
                </figure>
                <pb id="p04-39" n="39"/>
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">NOTES</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <byline>1. <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">DAVID</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">BINDMAN</hi>
                            </name>:
                        </docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">WESTFIELD COLLEGE, LONDON</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">An Unpublished Blake Pencil Drawing of the Lambeth Period</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>A previously unpublished drawing by Blake appeared in a sale at Sotheby’s in London
earlier this year and was bought by the present writer. The drawing was described as “The Dead Bad-Doers” and
had been sold with the William Bell Scott collection under the same title in 1892.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> It had more recently been in the collections of Lord Nathan,
inserted in an extra-illustrated volume, and of Mr. F. L. Wilder. 
                        <note id="n1">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                1
                            </hi> W. B. Scott sale (14 July 1892), Sotheby’s, lot 135, bt. Ellis
(£1.13.0).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="i">recto</hi> [1] shows a group of three figures floating on a cloud in
various stages of wakefulness, and there is a rather faint inscription of probably four words in what is
certainly Blake’s own formal script underneath the bearded figure. This was read by Bell Scott or the
compiler of his sale catalogue as “The Dead Bad-Doers,” but in fact only the first two words “The Dead” can be
read clearly, and the words following could not be “Bad-Doers.” They are now indecipherable despite prolonged
attempts at reading them with ultra-violet light. A pencilled inscription “W. B.” to the left of the
inscription does not seem to be in Blake’s hand. The <hi rend="i">verso</hi> [2] contains a faint sketch
which Mr. Martin Butlin has identified as a study in reverse for the titlepage of <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi>, of Urizen reclining with his hand on a skull.</p>
                    <p>The drawing on the <hi rend="i">recto</hi> does not correspond to any known composition
by Blake, but it does have a general similarity in atmosphere and style to some of the plates in 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, notably plate 17. The drawing is quite highly finished in parts, especially
in the face of the Urizen-like bearded figure, which tends to suggest the first rather than the second half of
the 1790’s. A date of about 1793-95 would seem to be about right on stylistic grounds. The inscription “The
Dead” is an obvious clue to the subject, and the crouching position of the bearded figure as well as the
struggles of the lower figure to disengage himself from a burial-shroud suggest that the drawing depicts the
dead awakening from their slumber. In <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>: “The dead heard the voice of the
child / And began to awake from sleep / All things heard the voice of the child / And began to awake to
life.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> This passage occurs on plate
20, which has an illustration of the child Orc, and I can only suggest tentatively that the present drawing
may have been intended initially to illustrate the passage but was rejected in the final version. This can
only be a speculation, but the drawing does seem to point towards <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, and
certainly towards a Prophetic Book rather than an independent composition. 
                        <note id="n2">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                2
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> The Complete Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes
(London, 1957), p. 233.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>There is no record of where William Bell Scott acquired the drawing, and his collection
seems to have been gathered from various sources.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> There is, however, some circumstantial evidence of its previous history. It would seem to
correspond to drawing no. 116 in W. M. Rossetti’s list in the 1863 edition of Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life</hi>, which is described as “A Dying Man crouching, with floating figures.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> It is mentioned as being in the possession of
“Mr. Evans,” who is presumably the dealer to whom Tatham sold a number of Blake drawings,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> and who also sold some Blake items to the
British Museum in the 1850’s. “Mr. Evans” also owned the next drawing in the list, no. 117, “An Angel taking
a huge stride in the air,” which must be the drawing now in the Victoria and Albert Museum. Many of the
uncoloured works that follow the above two drawings in the list are described as belonging to “Mr. Harvey,”
i.e., the dealer Harvey of Cockspur Street. A number of these drawings as well as the “Angel taking a huge
stride” are now in the Victoria and Albert Museum, which purchased them in a bundle of twelve miscellaneous
drawings from the dealer Parsons in 1881.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> Most of the
<pb id="p04-40" n="40"/>
Victoria and Albert Museum drawings have, like the present example, a price scrawled on the 
<hi rend="i">verso</hi>, and in some cases crossed out and reduced. The present drawing has the price of two
guineas reduced to one, and furthermore the word “guinea” is incorrectly spelt “guinie” as on some of the
Victoria and Albert drawings. It is probable then that the prices were put on by Harvey, who must have sold
the residue of his Blake drawings to Parsons, and they seem to have been priced according to the degree of
finish. In the meantime he had sold a number of them previously to collectors, including a pencil drawing of
“A Squatted Devil” (Rossetti, no. 123) to Bell Scott.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> To sum up, the probable early provenance of the drawing is as follows: Mrs. Blake,
Frederick Tatham, Evans by 1863, Harvey before 1880, William Bell Scott. Most of Blake’s miscellaneous
drawings came through Tatham as Mrs. Blake’s executor so the provenance is hardly surprising, but if the
scrawled prices on the back of many of Blake’s drawings can be established as that of the dealer Harvey then
they could provide a link between existing drawings and the often cryptic descriptions in Rossetti’s list. 
                        <note id="n3">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                3
                            </hi> See W. B. Scott, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Etchings from his works</hi>
(London, 1878).</note>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                4
                            </hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, “Pictor
Ignotus”</hi> (London and Cambridge, 1863), II, 250.</note>
                        <note id="n5">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                5
                            </hi> See Tatham’s letter to W. M. Rossetti of 6 November 1862 (W. M. Rossetti,
<hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers</hi> [London, 1903], p. 16).</note>
                        <note id="n6">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                6
                            </hi> For example, Rossetti, nos. 121, 122, 143. The twelve drawings were bought
from E. Parsons in 1881 for £7.14.0 (accession nos. 8761-65).</note>
                        <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                7
                            </hi> K. Preston, ed., <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of W. Graham
Robertson</hi> (London, 1952), p. 239, no. 126, lot 138 in the Bell Scott sale of 14 July 1892.</note>
                	</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>  
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>