<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.3.chayes</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">John Beer, Blake’s Visionary Universe</title>
                <author n="Chayes">Irene H. Chayes</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
            <pb id="p04-87" n="87"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-3-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">John Beer. <hi rend="i">BLAKE’S VISIONARY UNIVERSE.</hi>
Manchester, England: Manchester University Press; New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, Inc., 1969. Pp. xiv + 394. 78
illus. 70s; $11.50.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="i">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">Irene H.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">Chayes</hi>
                            </name>,</docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">Silver Spring, Maryland</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <p>This book is the companion and continuation of <hi rend="i">Blake’s Humanism</hi>,
published just one year before; there are some overlappings, repetitions, and revisions, and some of the same
difficulties, beginning with the present title. The words “vision” and “visionary” were used in the earlier
volume, and in <hi rend="i">Coleridge the Visionary</hi> as well, with an evasive looseness that has not been
remedied. Blake’s “vision” here is not primarily, as some might expect, his creative imagination as a poet
or an artist. Sometimes the word is a synonym for “fantasy,” or it merges with the plural “visions” of
anecdote, which Beer refers to but makes no attempt to examine critically. (The Ancient of Days above the
staircase is invoked several times.) Often, “vision” seems to be no more than the quality inferred from a
passage of lyrical affirmation or moral exhortation, the effect of Blake’s poetic powers rather than the
cause. In his more general remarks, Beer stays close to Blake’s own language and juggles his terms, noun and
adjective, in sentences which reach completion without yielding up a definition. When Blake is said to stress
the “visionary element” of world myths, for example, he is seen arguing that “all alike were telling a common
story of the decline of Man from original Vision” (p. 15). Later, following the account of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the word-play is carried to the subject of the whole study: “Blake had come to
acknowledge that the most important point about his visionary universe was not that it was a universe but that
it was visionary” (p. 263).</p>
                    <p>Unlike “vision” and “visionary” alone, however, “visionary universe” does have a
practical equivalent in the specific discussions here. It is the not unfamiliar world of the prophetic books,
“a symbolic and interpretative landscape,” as Beer eventually calls it, whose traditional and mythological
elements have been well investigated by Damon, Percival, Raine, and Hirst, as well as by lesser workers in the
same vineyard. Beer has little to add to what is already known of Blake’s background in these matters, and
he does not fully develop the motifs he himself singles out for emphasis: “pathos” and “sublimity,” the
sceptre and crown, the shell, the “phallic lapse.” Instead, and rather surprisingly, the contribution of his
study turns out to be straightforward commentary, sustained over the three central chapters and covering both
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, book by book. Inevitably there are some
misreadings and distortions of Blake’s texts, balanced by felicities of observation and insight elsewhere; a
literate new reader who previously had only glanced at the poems undoubtedly would gain enlightenment from
Beer’s commentary, and the acknowledgments in the Preface suggest that it is such a reader who is being
addressed in the expository portions of the book. I leave a detailed critique of these chapters to other
reviewers. Instead, in this limited space I would like to consider Beer’s way of looking at Blake’s
pictures, which is more revealing than the commentary and more pertinent to current discussions in the 
<hi rend="i">Newsletter.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The interpretation of the Arlington Court painting which John E. Grant has
challenged<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">1</ref> is included in a chapter
dealing mainly, and conventionally enough, with the illustrations to Young, Dante, and the Book of Job. My
concern is with Beer’s interpretations
<pb id="p04-88" n="88"/>
in another section of his book, where the illustrations cited in the critical text are grouped according to a
private scheme of the author’s own, with a separate commentary. The terms used in the captions are from
Blake—“Innocence,” “Experience,” “energy,” “desire,” “moral law,” and of course “vision”—but the phrasing
and the combinations and contrasts are Beer’s, and to the hypothetical new reader who may have been won by
the chapters on the poetry the relation of the captions to the illustrations is likely to be as mysterious as
the relation of the plates to each other. Interpretive captions are usually assigned only to Blake’s
designs, although pictures from other sources are introduced for comparison; on occasion, Beer’s purposes
seem to be served by the comparative plates alone, without reference to those by Blake. (See, e.g., Figs. 17
and 18, “The Imposition of Law,” and 19, “Cruelty under the Law.”) 
                        <note id="n9">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                1
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (August 1970), 15ff. A neutral bystander
might note of this particular dispute that if Beer’s “vision of the Book of Revelation” tends to dissolve
the images of the painting into the prose of the King James Bible, Grant’s “minute” descriptions threaten to
replace the carefully organized whole by a Urizenic sum of its parts, and the parts of a number of other Blake
pictures. Perhaps the emphasis on composition promised for the Warner-Simmons essay will be a
corrective.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Beer perhaps would defend his arrangement and his captions by quoting what he asserts
in his last chapter about the work of the “visionary” painter: “the symbolic meaning is a guide to the
internal organization of the design” (p. 297). But even if it were possible, at the present stage of Blake
studies, for all to agree that a “symbolic meaning” is what must be sought in each Blake design, and that John
Beer has found the key: even so, objections would have to be made to Beer’s descriptions and interpretations
on elementary grounds. In <hi rend="i">Blake’s Humanism</hi>, every serpent entwining a human figure
(including the earthworm in “Elohim Creating Adam”) was an image of “self-hood”; here, serpents either coiling
in spirals or entangled with groups of human figures (Figs. 24-30) are designated “energies.” “The picture
actually changes for us as we learn what it is about,” Beer says of “visionary” painting; but the changes in
these designs that are implied by the captions are unacceptable. The opposition set up between men in 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 25 (Fig. 29) and women in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 75 (Fig. 30) is clearly wrong, as
John Grant also has pointed out, and it is doubtful that the creatures in Fig. 29 can be called serpents at
all. (The Ghisi engraving reproduced as Fig. 28 is identified only as “Serpents attacking men.” Actually, the
struggling group is a detail from a famous original, which itself is relevant to both Blake designs—but not
in Beer’s terms.)</p>
                    <p>Or there is Fig. 54, the design from Plate 4 of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> Evidently
recalling the verbal imagery of veiling and covering in the poetry, Beer labels this “Woman veiling child of
Vision,” in spite of the summons “Arise O Orc” in the text.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">2</ref> Fig. 53 is an engraving after Raphael’s “Madonna of the Veil,” offered in
contrast; yet if Enitharmon’s action is recognized as <hi rend="i">un</hi>veiling, there is not a contrast
between the two scenes but a parallel, which confirms and is confirmed by the Orc-Jesus analogy at the
beginning of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> In his picture commentary, however, Beer fuses the two figures as
“Jesus who has been veiled by the Church” (p. 374) and bewilderingly (unless it is a misprint) cites Fig. 53. 
                        <note id="n10">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                2
                            </hi> On <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 4, see my “The Presence of Cupid and Psyche” in
Erdman and Grant, eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ.
Press, 1970), pp. 218-19.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>On the other hand, when Beer seems to be reporting direct observation he may be equally
unreliable. There is <hi rend="i">no</hi> “extraordinary resemblance” (p. 370) between Blake’s three figures
in “Har and Heva Bathing” (Fig. 2) and “corresponding figures” in Piero della Francesca’s fresco “The Death
of Adam,” one of the series at Arezzo mentioned by Grant. In the fresco group Beer must be referring to but
does not illustrate, the resemblances are only general: staring eyes, a use of profiles, an archaic stiffness
of attitude, which in the case of Blake would be explained by the uncertainties of his early style. Otherwise,
in the setting, the placement of the figures and their relation to each other, and their individual poses,
Piero’s scene is very different from Blake’s; moreover, it is the mortality of Adam and Eve that he
emphasizes, their physical decline in old age, not the perpetual youthfulness Blake bestows on Har and Heva
along with their white hair. Since Beer adds that Blake “could hardly have Known” Piero’s fresco, what he
seems really to be saying is that the <hi rend="i">idea</hi> of the death of an aged Adam enables him, the
commentator, to leap ahead of his evidence and identify the white-haired corpses in his Fig. 3, the title page
of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, as Har and Heva “laid out in death.”</p>
                    <pb id="p04-89" n="89"/>
                    <p>At the beginning of his special commentary on the illustrations, Beer speaks of
exploring “the relationships between Blake’s visual symbolism and the images of earlier art.” Unfortunately,
such an exploration is precisely what is missing, although some of the pairings of Blake’s designs with
likely sources or models can be corroborated by those of us who, for different purposes, have been making
similar investigations. A recognition of “resemblance” or of Blake’s “different treatment” of a theme shared
with another artist is the most Beer has to offer the reader who is not committed to a search for symbolic
meanings but who may be curious about the pictures placed before him in juxtaposition. This critical default
damages even the best and most suggestive exhibits, none more strikingly than Figs. 31 and 32. I agree that
Michelangelo’s “The Fall of Phaethon” was surely Blake’s model for Plate 5 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi>, and that the particular version Beer has chosen—the last of three drawings on the same
subject, made for Michelangelo’s friend Tommaso Cavalieri—was probably the one Blake knew. (Beer publishes
an engraving. The original drawing is in the Royal Collection at Windsor Castle.) Something in the graphic
imagery or the composition of the two designs must have impressed Beer in some way when he first looked at
them; the relation he noted between them must have been based on something more than the idea of 
<hi rend="i">fall.</hi> Curiously, however, what he says about them he might have said without reference to an
illustration of any kind. In the text (pp. 150, 154) the fall of Phaethon, in terms of the myth, is mentioned
only as a simile. “The fall of visionary desire” is the caption assigned to <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 5 as Fig.
32, and it obviously comes from Blake’s capsule reading of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> in the text of
the same plate (“It indeed appear’d to Reason as if Desire was cast out”). When Beer says in his picture
commentary, “The Fall of Phaethon is for Blake a story of the failure of Desire under the Law” (p. 372), he is
forging a last link of his own to join the subject of Michelangelo’s drawing and Blake’s view of Miltonic
contrariety, and the result is a closed circle of abstraction which excludes the particularities of both
narratives no less than those of both designs.</p>
                    <p>“The symbolic meaning is a guide to the internal organization of the design.” It is
this principle, evidently, that enables Beer to make what is in effect his own prophetic book out of his
seventy-eight heterogeneous illustrations, for which the captions and the special commentary seem intended to
perform much the same function as Blake’s engraved inscriptions for the copied figures of Laocoon and the
pseudo-Joseph of Arimathea. In the instance of the design from <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 5, the caption actually
makes it unnecessary for the reader to devote more than a glance to the illustration itself, if, like the
exegete, he is impatient to uncover its “symbolic meaning.” Yet the design from <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 5, in
particular, if it were adequately seen and fully explored in relation to both Michelangelo’s drawing and 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, might demonstrate that “internal organization” and “visual effect” can have a
significance of their own which is not dependent on the kind of symbolic meaning Beer deduces, but which is
not a matter of merely technical description or the annotations of an art historian. An exploration of this
kind might in fact help to establish a concrete, practical, and definable meaning for “vision” in Blake’s
art.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p04-90" n="90" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>