<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.3.video</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">A Videotape of America Produced at York University</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-3-0003">
				<pb id="p04-65" n="65"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">A VIDEOTAPE OF <hi rend="u">AMERICA</hi> PRODUCED AT YORK
UNIVERSITY</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Janet Warner, John Sutherland, and Robert Wallace collaborated on a one-hour videotape
called <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> “<hi rend="i">America</hi>,” which was made in October, 1970 at the
television studio of York University. We wrote Mrs. Warner to find out more about the history, the nature, and
the availability of the tape, and this is her reply:</p>
                    <p>The tape was very much a joint effort of John Sutherland and myself, who wrote the
script, and Robert Wallace, my colleague at Glendon, who produced it. We wanted a program suitable for senior
students, that is, those who were already acquainted with Blake’s work, which would allow them to see all
the plates of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, hear the whole poem read dramatically, and at the same time interpret
the poem for them in a way that would link it to past and present historical events.</p>
                    <p>To this end, we obtained photographs of the black and white <hi rend="i">America</hi>
in the Rosenwald Collection, and we used slides and photographs of many other works of art, including some by
Blake, and many by early American painters. We also used pictures of modern student riots and other political
events which bore out the themes of political
<pb id="p04-66" n="66"/>
and psychological revolution.</p>
                    <p>The poem was read by Michael Gregory, our department chairman at Glendon, who is also
an experienced actor; his voice and that of another narrator were heard always off camera. We used no “live”
actors. Suitable music and sound effects were employed throughout to add emphasis and interpretation. The
music consisted mainly of snatches of Charles Ives’ “America Variations,” while the sound effects
concentrated upon both natural sounds (such as wind, thunder) and sounds of war and revolution (air raid
sirens, machine gun warfare, bugle calls).</p>
                    <p>Most of our problems during production arose from our limited budget and the fact that
York’s television studio does not have a camera with a special close-up lens, which would have facilitated
close examination of the plates and photographs. Consequently, because we could not afford to have all the
graphics blown up to a suitably large size, some visual effects could not be maintained for every plate.</p>
                    <p>In addition, copyright stipulations covering both music and some photographs inhibited
their expanded integration into the tape. Various other problems inherent to the process of adapting to a
visual and rhythmic medium could only be discussed properly in a more academic paper, which, incidentally, Mr.
Wallace is considering writing.</p>
                    <p>In general, we feel the tape was an artistic success and it has been well received at
York, Glendon (a separate campus) and Colby College, Maine. In fact, it is likely we will receive money to do
a second production on <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Regarding distribution rights and costs, any institutions interested in 
<hi rend="i">renting</hi> a copy of the tape can do so by supplying their own videotape to York, which will
transfer the production for a fee of $75, with the stipulation that the transfer be erased after it is shown.
Should enough institutions be interested in <hi rend="i">buying</hi> a copy of the tape, York would have it
transferred to film, which could then be bought for approximately $200.</p>
                    <p>It is interesting to find how suitable Blake’s work is for adapting to television. We
would be interested to hear if others have tried similar experiments.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>