<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.3.phillips</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">British Blake News</title>
                <author n="Phillips">Michael Phillips</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-3-0003">
					<pb id="p04-67" n="67"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">BRITISH BLAKE NEWS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>From <docAuthor>Michael <name>Phillips</name>
                        </docAuthor>, our Associate Editor at the University of Edinburgh:</byline>
                    <p>For students of Blake perhaps the most significant event of interest in some years will
be the Blake Exhibition due to open shortly at the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. The Keeper of Paintings and
Drawings, Mr. M. Cormack, has kindly written the following note with regard to the Exhibition and in
particular the Exhibition Catalogue:
<q>
    The exhibition is provisionally due to open on January 9th, but this may be changed. The paperback edition
of the catalogue will be on sale <hi rend="i">only</hi> at the Museum, price £1 and a hard cover edition will
be published by W. Heffer &amp; Sons Ltd., Trinity Street, Cambridge and be available from all booksellers,
price £3. The catalogue will comprise 96 pages of text including a supplement of the proposed bequest by Sir
Geoffrey Keynes plus 74 illustrations on 44 pages of plates, and a coloured frontispiece. This should be
available at the same time as the exhibition.
</q>
A review of the Fitzwilliam exhibition will appear in a forthcoming number of the 
<hi rend="i">Newsletter.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On Sunday, 15 November 1970, at 8:00 p.m. Jack Lindsay presented at the Mermaid
Theatre, London, an evening entitled “William Blake And Our World.” Sir Bernard Miles and Josephine Wilson
gave readings from Blake’s works to complement Mr. Lindsay’s discussion. The following note by Mr. Lindsay
gives some suggestion of the evening’s presentation:
<q>
William Blake, born in 1757 to a London hosier, early turned to art, and made his living as artist and
engraver. But he was opposed to the dominant art-forms of his world and sought to express an imaginative
vision, which he carried over into his poetry. He matured in the later 1780’s as the French Revolution was
breaking out, and found his inspiration in the conviction of vast changes going on which would culminate in a
Last Judgement, or total reversal of things. He began a semi-allegoric epic on the French Revolution, of which
a part got into proofs; but the extremely repressive situation of the 1790’s led him to print his own poems
with his designs by an etching process. He was thus led into a “prophetic” method in which he felt he could
express the human situation at multiple levels, in its full inter-connections. His work ranged from lyrics of
unparalleled intensity and simplicity, to the highly complex Prophetic Books. Disregarded in his own age,
taken up to some extent by Rossetti and Swinburne, he began to come into his own with the turn of the century;
and now, because of his utterly uncompromising spirit, is one of the few “great poets” of the past who
maintains a direct and powerful impact on the young people of today in their various revolts and in their
attempts to create their own art and poetry.
</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The rapidly increasing interest in Blake in Britain is further suggested by a new play
by David Hare, “What Happened to Blake,” recently performed at the Royal Court Theatre, London, and the poet
Adrian Mitchell’s play, “Tyger, Tyger,” which has been announced for future production at the National
Theatre.</p>
                    <p>In the <hi rend="i">Times</hi>, Tuesday, 10 November 1970, was a pen and pencil drawing
by Henry Fuseli which apparently was at one time in Blake’s possession. The drawing, which was to be sold at
auction at Christie’s on Tuesday, 17 November, was described as follows:
<pb id="p04-68" n="68"/>
						<q>
David and Goliath, by Henry Fuseli, R. A., bears Blake’s initials and date 1779, pencil, pen and grey ink,
grey wash, on Whatman paper dated 1794, 10 3/4 in. by 6 1/2 in.
</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Kathleen Raine’s <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> has been recently published by
Thames and Hudson for their “World of Art Library” and contains 156 illustrations, 28 in colour.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>