<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.3.publications</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Publications Received: The Golden Chain and Golgonooza Organ #1</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-3-0003">
					<pb id="p04-68" n="68"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">PUBLICATIONS RECEIVED</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">The Golden Chain / Lyrical Poems 1964-1969</hi> by Peter Russell. Venice,
1970. 48 pp. $5. Although it is not our practice to review contemporary poetry in the <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, Peter Russell’s book should be noted as being of unusual interest to our readers because of
the impact of Blake on some of the poems published here. The title poem has as its epigraph five lines from
the Fairy’s speech in the introductory lines to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>; a section called “Manuela’s
Poems” is arranged in nine short “Nights” and is also evidently indebted to Blake’s idea of the Emanation.
The book, published privately by the
<pb id="p04-69" n="69"/>
author, may be obtained from him at Castello 3611 / 30122 Venice / Italy. (Among Mr. Russell’s works in
preparation is <hi rend="i">Paysages Légendaires</hi>, Enitharmon Press, London).</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">The Golgonooza Organ #1</hi> by Aethelred Eldridge. R. R. #1, Millfield,
Ohio, 1970. 16 pp. + 2 inserts. “Published . . . no fewer than four times during the limitary course that
makes of substance by the use of birdlime an adhesive year. . . . Five dollars divested brings, in so many
words, The deterged ear out of Golgonooza.”</p>
                    <p>As Mr. Eldridge kindly invites us to quote from the pamphlet, we reproduce below the
opening of <hi rend="i">Golgonooza Organ:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <div2>
                        <head>
                            <title>GOLGONOOZA ORGAN</title>
                        </head>
						<q>
Drilling, no eye hath prepared this thing; no heart in learning<lb/>
Hath drily inclined; no hands hath taken up the measure of<lb/>
The doing — and none but new creatures need apply.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
Citizenry-citizens of Golgonooza, Spiritual Fourfold London!<lb/>
Latchet string espousers round the shaky walls of Blake’s<lb/>
Betrothal! Bowlahoola surrounds us: the law stercorous. I vie<lb/>
Reduced within the time it takes a single archer kneeled to<lb/>
Strike through generations along the worm of Merlin. I am the<lb/>
Utmost droning phonetic hid by the space of a Fool’s uncertain<lb/>
Days; and hid in lengthening night’s conjecture over mis-read<lb/>
Jars. There is no new dust in which sinners may perform. Nor<lb/>
Blindly shall the sentry when the tree shall be uprooted fall<lb/>
To American heroes.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
People obtaining discomfiture from air beneath their hats<lb/>
Have pointed me out. You! And yours; by courtesy of bodily<lb/>
Sickened eye appalled by one so lustrous small of flesh.<lb/>
How in woven jaws of periled, hardening cradle grass the cock<lb/>
Holds back the rose of fecund breathing clods; in this, blending<lb/>
Attar of brass to rose and patina of place, I anticipate you in<lb/>
Whom the wake of presumed men confuses historicity with tarnish<lb/>
On the dawn. And, I have gone hovered in resplendents off the<lb/>
True circulating men, further, by the flour of northern altering<lb/>
Light.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
Assyriologue, lard faded thaumaturgist, works his white, exquisite<lb/>
Dot everywhere. Gods and dwellings, goddesses, art built unpolished<lb/>
Of the noble, life exerting ilk; stamped, as it might appear, by<lb/>
Wearied intellect from building downward driven daughters; whose<lb/>
Doors are unbolted by sensories recruited, brooded by the best<lb/>
Wild-parrot, clanish cog advisement.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
Draw near, last mentioned Londoners. First, the voice filled human<lb/>
Whirpool; then, the crack of some immense contrivance falling; then,<lb/>
Surrounded features silenced on the Man resuming; then, three lines<lb/>
Are lopped, pregnate stem solidities, sub teeming very-molecules.<lb/>
Then, tears wiped, delight repeats in limbs that follow out beyond<lb/>
The reach within the riven skull.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
The bitter thing that loveth thee is dumbness beckoning all blades,<lb/>
Straining the capaciousness of the beetle within the blade that<lb/>
Wanders as it bends. Mothers are filling with oil; the doing of<lb/>
The heart’s repose on gentle, silent teeth.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
As for the stunt of weakened goddesses, since when has poetry,<lb/>
Since once it was revealed, or shone, brought barbed the child’s<lb/>
Swift diffusion? Or brought evoked upon a quantity of food<lb/>
The loudness of the rose mid-drifted, rarefied within the dragon?<lb/>
Nor has it been made visible that latitudes of consciousness,<lb/>
Inept around the heart spelled forth, are edible.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
A warning: No god, of those remains shown on the dagger turning<lb/>
Simple wrath within the worm, should be sniffed from the flint.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
Funerary table past acquaintance is no cause for parsimony’s<lb/>
Being held the helpmeet turning hawk in blue and ripening<lb/>
Fruit that boundaries the sun. Send miners. Yourself to send,<lb/>
Digging in the groin of a moth, is, by solemn, yellowed, nibbled<lb/>
Feast of day, needless. To a canary’s poppy laboured sleep of<lb/>
Wandered field belongs the thick, aurific sag of elephant costiveness.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
Risk not in me, teetotum teaspoon pictograph, your toxic body<lb/>
Snatch technique; about which dew-knit gripping clothes are bound.<lb/>
Excepting Anglicized exempting paraphrasts revolving wax in sound,<lb/>
The pathetic human dragon is a pig impersonating loins tripartite.<lb/>
And further, is a prodigal of gaggles, and a brooder to a poke of<lb/>
Hens- excepting naked beauty on the Angle who solitary synonymic<lb/>
Translates rustling into solar second joyous gear.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
Hear Ye, Londoners! The groan that voices abscess, death, and the<lb/>
Transport of angels as the carriage of germs is a breach of<lb/>
Etiquette.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
Puissant in the crouch of one demeanor was the word that walked<lb/>
In likeness of a Man. Send the sped speed dorsal waters of His<lb/>
Word, imbricated safe corrosive, to the raven’s tedium tor. Unstruggle<lb/>
Mountain maladjustments from the sister epicene retreat. Tedium.<lb/>
Tedium, tedium. We praise Thee scattered, O remotely middened God.<lb/>
Te Deum. Te Deum grass remembered men re-told. Te fibered Deum<lb/>
Cherished victim. Invincible Te levelled laboured Deum.
</q>
                    </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>