<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.3.bentley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">An Apocryphal Blake Engraving: The Minor’s Pocket Book (1814)</title>
                <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
	<pb id="p04-107" n="107"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-3-0008">
                <div2>
                <head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="i">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="i">BENTLEY</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="i">JR.</hi></docAuthor>: <hi rend="i">UNIVERSITY OF TORONTO</hi>
                    </byline>
                </head>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">An Apocryphal Blake Engraving: <hi rend="i">THE MINOR’S POCKET
BOOK</hi> (1814)</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>In 1859 the British Museum Print Room acquired an engraving which it catalogued as by
William Blake, “The World before the Flood . . . The Minors Pocket Book 1814.” Subsequently the engraving was
mislaid; at any rate, it is not now with the Blake Collection in the Print Room.</p>
                    <p>Since no such print by Blake is known to Blake scholars, my article describing the
above evidence (“A Fugitive or Apocryphal Blake Engraving”) was printed in the <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 2 (April 1969), 74, expressing not only doubt as to the authenticity of the attribution to
Blake but uncertainty about the subject and the work in which it appeared. The point of the present note is to
identify <hi rend="i">The Minor’s Pocket Book</hi> and the subject of the engraving and to lay the ghostly
attribution to Blake.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">The World Before the Flood</hi> is a poem by James Montgomery (1813)
which enjoyed some popularity (there was a third edition by 1814 and a seventh by 1826). <hi rend="i">The
Minor’s Pocket Book</hi> is a quite uncommon annual for children published by permutations of the firm of
Darton &amp; Harvey (Harvey &amp; Darton; W. &amp; T. Darton; W. Darton; W. Darton, Junr; Darton, Harvey,
&amp; Darton). I know of no comprehensive runs of the journal, but isolated issues may be found as follows:
<table rows="11" cols="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>1797</cell>
                                <cell>Osborne Collection, Toronto Public Library</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1804</cell>
                                <cell>Columbia University Library; Turnbull Library, Wellington, New
Zealand</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1805</cell>
                                <cell>Columbia</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1807</cell>
                                <cell>Columbia; Turnbull</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1808</cell>
                                <cell>Columbia</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1810</cell>
                                <cell>Columbia</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1811</cell>
                                <cell>Columbia</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1812</cell>
                                <cell>Columbia</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1813</cell>
                                <cell>Columbia</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1814</cell>
                                <cell>Mrs. Linda Hannas</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1829</cell>
                                <cell>Turnbull</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">The Minor’s Pocket Book</hi> is a small volume, ordinarily bound in
full red morocco with clasps to close it like a kind of envelope. It consists of a few sections of
miscellaneous interest, such as New &amp; Full Moons, Holidays, “Memorandum,” as well as pages with the date,
for a journal. The copies in the Turnbull Library, for example, were used as a journal by Ann Taylor (later
Gilbert), who contributed to early issues of the work. (Under 19 March 1807 is:
<table rows="3" cols="4">
                            <row>
                                <cell>1</cell>
                                <cell>11</cell>
                                <cell>6</cell>
                                <cell>Rec<hi rend="s">d</hi> of Darton for Minors PBk</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>3</cell>
                                <cell>8</cell>
                                <cell>3</cell>
                                <cell>for City Scenes</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>2</cell>
                                <cell>2</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>for Juvenile Anecdotes[.])</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
In some years there was a frontispiece, such as the one in 1829 designed by Stothard;
<pb id="p04-108" n="108"/>
in other years, an engraved vignette appeared on the titlepage.</p>
                    <p>The frontispiece for 1814 is identified at the top as having been 
“<hi rend="i">Engraved for the Minor’s Pocket Book 1814</hi>,” and at the bottom it is inscribed: 
“<hi rend="i">Nurst by that foster-sire, austere and rude, / Midst rocks and glens, in savage solitude. / The World
before the Flood. Canto 7, p. 136.</hi>” The design represents a child holding up a snake before a crouching
man. The plate is not signed with the name of either the designer or the engraver, and I see in it no reason
to attribute either role to Blake. The British Museum Print Room cataloguer who added Blake’s name to the
work seems to have been simply mistaken.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>