<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.3.warner</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">James Vine</title>
                <author n="Warner">Janet Warner</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
	<pb id="p04-106" n="106"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-3-0008">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">JANET</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">WARNER:</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">GLENDON COLLEGE, YORK UNIVERSITY, TORONTO</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">James Vine</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>James Vine, according to rumor, was supposed to have been one of Blake’s principal
patrons, and the man who commissioned <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> He is mentioned in the Keynes-Wolf 
<hi rend="i">Census</hi> (p. 102), and in Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> he turns up lunching with
Blake and Linnell (p. 275), and purchasing <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, but there is little evidence to date that he
was a principal patron, or is there even much certainty about his identity. However, I was able to discover a
few more details about him, while coincidentally spending last summer on the Isle of Wight.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="i">Census</hi> calls him James Vine, a merchant of Puckster, Isle of
Wight. For this information it refers to Bohns catalogue of 1843, which seems to be non-existent, according to
<hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> In any case, the proper address on the Isle of Wight is Puckster Cove. Vine
was buried in the churchyard of St. John the Baptist Church in Niton, Isle of Wight, on 16 July 1837 at the
age of 63. In this same church, a brass plaque has been erected to the memory of his daughter, Augusta, by her
son, Arthur.</p>
                    <p>Augusta was born in Puckster in 1821, implying that the Vines were living in the house
called Puckster Close at the time. This was presumably their country house, Blake and Linnell having lunched
in London. According to the church records, Augusta married Alexander Mitchell-Innes, but their son later took
the name of Arthur Vine Innes-Vine and lived on at Puckster Close. He is still remembered by the church sexton
at Niton. Arthur is said to have turned Roman Catholic and sold the house before he died, having been well
known as the local squire and benefactor. If James Vine did indeed purchase much of Blake’s work, it would
be interesting to find out if an Innes-Vine descendant has a book or painting hidden away.</p>
                    <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr. wrote me from England that he has recently found a few more
<pb id="p04-107" n="107"/>
incidental references to meetings between Mr. Vine and Linnell; perhaps the future will turn up something more
concrete about the actual purchases of this rather elusive patron.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>