<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.3.beer</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">A Reply to John Grant</title>
                <author n="Beer">John Beer</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
	<pb id="p04-103" n="103"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-3-0007">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">DISCUSSION</hi>
                    </title>
                    <title type="section-subtitle">
                        <hi rend="b">“With intellectual spears, &amp; long winged arrows of thought”</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">JOHN</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">BEER</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">: PETERHOUSE, CAMBRIDGE</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">A Reply to John Grant</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>In Part Two of his article on the Arlington Court picture (<hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 4 [August 1970], 12-25), John E. Grant devotes some time to my interpretation of the design
in my <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Universe.</hi> I hope that his very dismissive remarks about my work
will not deter the readers of the <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> from reading it and giving serious attention to
my ideas.</p>
                    <p>In one instance, to be sure, he has spotted a mistake. When I read Keynes’s article
on the preliminary drawing for the Arlington Court picture, I was pleased to find that this, also, had in the
past been described as possibly an illustration to Revelation 22:17. In memory, however, this ascription
became conflated with the fact that another ascription (“The River of Oblivion”) had actually been pencilled
by some-one on the back of the drawing itself. The point ought to have been picked up when I checked my
references, but I missed it; I hope that it may be possible to correct it
<pb id="p04-104" n="104"/>
in a later edition.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Grant also suggests, however, that I do not describe Blake’s pictures correctly,
claiming that I see the figures in plate 25 of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> as male, whereas they are
“obviously female”. Here the lack of strict accuracy is, I am afraid, his. If he will look again at the
figures in question, he will see that while the foremost figure and the nearly submerged one on the right have
fairly clear female characteristics, the figure near the top has the hair and lineaments of a Blakean male.
The design seems to refer to the process which begins near the end of the previous page, when Urizen “curs’d
/ Both sons &amp; daughters”. My caption, “Men gripped by spectrous Energies”, which deals with the process
more generally and uses “men” in the generic sense, is correct, therefore, whereas “Women gripped by spectrous
Energies” would not be.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Grant’s next point, that I see the figures in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem 75</hi> as
male, I find totally inexplicable. The plate is mentioned twice in my book: on the first occasion (p. 192) I
refer to the “women who control” dragons of energy and on the second (p. 372) to the “daughters of Jerusalem”.
Where does Mr. Grant find his “men”? His charge that it is <hi rend="i">I</hi> who am “hasty” and cannot
describe what is actually there strikes me as a little cool, to say the least.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Grant now moves to a different sort of criticism, claiming that in my discussion of
“A Vision of the Last Judgment” in connection with the Arlington Court picture, “the wirey bounding line of
rectitude becomes invisible”. I have re-read my discussion and can find no grounds for such a charge. What I
am saying there is that while the scene depicted in <hi rend="i">VLJ</hi> is clearly not 
<hi rend="i">identical</hi> with that in <hi rend="i">ACP</hi> there are enough resemblances between individual
elements in the two pictures to make one ask whether Blake’s interpretative commentary for the one may not
also be relevant to the other. Where is the lack of rectitude? One begins to suspect that Mr. Grant’s own
sense of sound argument sometimes falters—all the more so when one discovers him assuming that because my
second book appeared within two years of the first it must have been written in as short a period, allowing me
no time to study the full range of Blake’s visual art. For the record, it may be pointed out that the two
books were written together over twelve years, during which I examined every available design of
Blake’s.</p>
                    <p>When Mr. Grant turns to one of the chief points in my interpretation, the remarkable
series of parallels between items in the text of Revelation 22:14-17 and various features of the Arlington
Court picture, he is swiftly dismissive, referring merely to the verse “The Spirit and the Bride say, Come 
. . . ” and commenting that the figures in the centre of Blake’s picture cannot be saying “Come!,” that they
cannot be inviting anyone to drink, and that if they were they would be offering nothing more than sea-water.
There is more than one way of saying “Come!,” however, and the text in question does not say that they are
offering drink, at least directly:
<q>
And the Spirit and the Bride say, Come. And let him that heareth say, Come.<lb/>
And let him that is athirst come. And whosoever will, let him take the water of life freely.
</q>
The text states only that those who respond to the invitation will find their thirst satisfied. And this is
precisely what is beginning to happen to the figure who is rising from the river and who will shortly exchange
the waters of oblivion in her scaly bucket for the waters of life that are flowing in the paradisal landscape
above. What the Spirit and the Bride are inviting her to (as one might expect in Blake) is the exercise of
energy and an awakening to vision: and it is this that is indicated by their gestures.</p>
                    <pb id="p04-105" n="105"/>
                    <p>Mr. Grant does not bother to mention the other parallels which I have noted, except to
say that they are “without exception insubstantial”. Since the argument here is detailed and cumulative, I can
only refer the reader to my original chapter and leave him to judge for himself; it is time to turn to a
larger question raised at the end of the discussion.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Grant claims to find the key to my attitudes in my use of the word “idiosyncratic”
to describe Blake and goes on to maintain that, being “deeply read” in “occultism” I miss the “infinite
implications” of his art. At this point I begin to despair and to wonder whether he has really grappled with
my book at all. For my main argument, stressed again and again, is that Blake read occult literature 
<hi rend="i">not</hi> for its own sake but for its “infinite implications”. The point which I concede to his
hostile critics is that occultism in general tends to work through tradition of various kinds, thus providing
lines of communication for those who have begun to learn its language, and that Blake, by standing at an angle
to such traditions, forfeits this ease of communication, compelling his reader to learn a new language. It is
in this sense, and this sense alone, that I refer to him as “idiosyncratic” and I argue that it is precisely
this independence and concern with the infinity of energy and vision that gives him his unique power as an
artist. It is my theme from cover to cover.</p>
                    <p>Perhaps it is because he has missed this central argument that Mr. Grant is so
resistant to the idea that the Arlington Court picture is an illustration to verses from the Book of
Revelation. At first sight such an interpretation might seem to betray Blake back into the hands of orthodox
Christians and impose a narrowly pietistic framework upon his picture. But this danger passes as soon as it is
grasped that Blake is reading the Book of Revelation on his own terms, and that the Spirit and the Bride are
not the Holy Spirit and Church of orthodox biblical exegesis, but the Energy and Vision of his own universe.
So the red-clad figure of enduring creative energy folds out his hands over the sea to indicate his faith that
“the sea shall be no more” but will be displaced by the city of vision and desire when the sleeping figure in
the chariot above awakens to drive his chariot of fourfold vision. At present he is fore-shadowed by the naked
goddess of liberated sexual energy on the waters (Vala released from the hindrances of the law). The Bride,
meanwhile, expresses all that Blake has ever had to say about the relationship between nature and imagination.
The gestures of her hands indicate the extremes: the oblivion below of those who are totally pre-occupied with
birth, copulation and death, and the freedom of those above who minister to the energies of fourfold vision.
Her body, darkly veiled in parts, but also beautiful in face and crowned with stars, indicates the more
limited range between the single vision of analytic thinkers and the threefold vision of organized innocence.
Near her veiled part can be seen the wooded Greek temple which, as Mr. Grant points out, can be associated
with Blake’s critique of Greek philosophy and art: the latter is seen by him as a developed form of single
vision, its passion for beauty being restricted by its devotion to number and measurement. On the right of the
picture, on the other hand, is enacted the process by which the awakening spirit learns to embrace the energy
of twofold vision, passing through the fires of experience and emerging triumphant in creation; above, figures
thus initiated emerge into the clarified three-fold vision of Blake’s Beulah, from which, dwelling near the
waters of life, they can discern the potential triumph of fulfilled desire.</p>
                    <p>It is in this way, on my reading of the picture, that Blake works upon and reinterprets
the text of Revelation; and I find for my own part that such a reading structures the dynamics of the design
in a way that brings out its infinite dimension and makes it a pleasure to look at. It is natural that
interpretations should differ, of course, and I have no dispute with Mr. Grant on that score. I have dealt
with his remarks at length simply because he has chosen to go further: he has described <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Humanism</hi> as “unreliable” (and even rebuked the reviewers who found things to praise in
<pb id="p04-106" n="106"/>
it!) without producing a scrap of evidence in substantiation; and so far as <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary
Universe</hi> is concerned he has accused me of being “shoddy” and “unsound” in my scholarship and lacking in
“rectitude” in my arguments—all on the basis of what turns out, on examination, to be a single error. In
doing so, moreover, he has not always shown himself to be exactly impressive either for the accuracy of his
own scholarship or for his methods of argument. In all fairness, however, I should add that I found many of
the detailed points in the remainder of his articles interesting and persuasive, and I look forward to reading
his forthcoming interpretation. I hope that those who are interested in the Arlington Court picture will read
both that and others (including my own, in its full context) and work towards an interpretation which squares
with their own sense of the way in which Blake works as an artist.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>