<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.3.paley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blakes at Buffalo</title>
                <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
	<pb id="p04-81" n="81"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-3-0004">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Blakes at Buffalo</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="i">MORTON D. </hi><name><hi
rend="i">PALEY</hi></name></docAuthor><hi rend="i">:</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, BERKELEY</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <p>While teaching a seminar on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the Buffalo summer session
of 1970, I became aware of five Blake pictures the whereabouts of which are virtually unknown to present-day
students of Blake. Four of these are in the Lockwood Memorial Library of the State University of New York; one
is in the Rare Book Department of the Buffalo and Erie County Library. As these pictures have been lost track
of for at least several decades,
<pb id="p04-82" n="82"/>
and as at least two of them have never been reproduced, it is appropriate to note their existence here.</p>
                    <p>I was first informed of the Lockwood Library Blakes by Mr. K. C. Gay, curator of the
famous Poetry Collection there. No acquisition record could be found, but the pictures are described in 
<hi rend="i">A Selection of Books and Manuscripts in the Lockwood Memorial Library of the University of
Buffalo</hi> (New York, 1935). At some undetermined time, the pictures were placed in the Library vault, where
Mr. Gay came across them last year.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">1</ref>
All four items had been sold at auction in New York by the American Art Association on 2-3 April
1928.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">2</ref> They were part of a collection
owned by Emma W. Bucknell of Philadelphia, and they are described in the sale catalogue as follows:
<table rows="9" cols="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>[Fig. 1]</cell>
                                <cell>Original Watercolor Drawing by Blake for “Europe, A Prophecy”</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>56. Blake (William). Original Watercolor Drawing of “Shot from the
Heights of Enitharmon.” Height: 6 ½ inches; width: 6 ½ inches. Framed between 2 sheets of glass. Circa:
1794.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>This is the Final Illustration in Blake’s “Europe, A Prophecy,”
Published in 1794. The drawing depicts a nude figure of a man carrying an inanimate woman on his shoulder and
dragging a child by the arm; they are flying from a huge tongue of flame.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>[Fig. 2]</cell>
                                <cell>This drawing is tipped on to a sheet on the back of which is a pencil
drawing of a discus thrower, and the name “Mrs. Gilchrist” is written in the right hand margin.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>There is a slight variation in this drawing and the illustration in
“Europe”: the drawing depicts the man entirely nude, and the muscles of his body are clearly depicted, whereas
in the illustration as published the muscles of the body are not shown, a cloth is draped across his loins,
and the figure of the child is partially obscured by the flames.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">3</ref>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Important Blake Drawing</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>[Fig. 3]</cell>
                                <cell>57. Blake (William). Original Wash Drawing of a giant figure, seated on
the ground, in a hunched position, head resting on knees, arms entwining legs and hands clasped at ankles; in
the background is the blue sky; rocks to each side of figure; in the right hand margin is depicted a snake
wending its way down the side of the rock. Height: 7 ½ inches; length, 8 inches. Framed.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>58. Blake (William) Beggar’s Opera, Act III. “When My Hero in Court
Appears &amp; c.” <hi rend="i">Line engraving.</hi> Painted by Will<hi rend="s">
                                        <hi rend="i">m</hi>
                                    </hi> Hogarth. Engraved by Wm. Blake. Publish’d July 1, 1790 by J. &amp;
J. Boydell, Cheapside . . . London. Height, 24; length 30 inches. In black frame.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>The exceedingly rare first state of this engraving, with the following
scratched below the plate, — “Painted by Will<hi rend="s">
                                        <hi rend="i">m</hi>
                                    </hi> Hogarth, 1729. Etch’d by Will’<hi rend="s">
                                        <hi rend="i">m</hi>
                                    </hi> Blake, 1788.” No. 71 in A. G. B. Russell’s <hi rend="i">The
Engravings of William Blake.</hi>
                                    <ref target="n7" type="note">4</ref>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                1
                            </hi> They now hang in the office of the Associate Librarian. In addition to Mr.
Gay, I would like to thank Dr. Oscar Silverman and Professor Thomas Connolly for information about Thomas B.
Lockwood and his collection.</note>
                        <note id="n5">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                2
                            </hi> For which information I am grateful to Mr. Martin Butlin, Keeper of the
British Collection at the Tate Gallery.</note>
                        <note id="n6">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                3
                            </hi> This statement is puzzling. In the Trianon Press facsimile of 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, the male figure is nude (this page is from copy B, the Cunliffe copy); in the Huntington
Library copy he is nude; and in the proof plate in the Lessing J. Rosenwald collection, he is also nude (this
last is reproduced in the Philadelphia Museum of Art’s <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827/A Descriptive
Catalogue of an Exhibition of the Works of William Blake Selected from Collections in the United States</hi>,
1939, facing p. 38. In the Keynes-Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi>, p. 79, this figure is described as “a nude
man . . . .”</note>
                        <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                4
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> The Important Library of / PRESS BOOKS / LIBRARY SETS / FIRST
EDITIONS / Formed by the late / Emma W. Bucknell</hi> . . . The catalogue cover does not mention Blake, but
the title page includes “A Notable Collection of BLAKE ITEMS” and particular note is made of the Blake
collection in the foreword. The Blake items take up pp. 10-16 of the catalogue; page 15 is a reproduction of
the <hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi> The Blake section is headed “Extremely Important Series of Blake Items
Including Original Drawings / Numbers 56 to 85, Inclusive.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In the New York Public Library’s copy of the auction catalogue, sale prices have been
marked next to each item. If these figures are correct, number 56 brought the highest price in the Blake
section, going for $1,100. Number 57, the wash drawing,
<pb id="p04-83" n="83"/>
                        <figure n="europe.4.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="620">
                            <head>1 Watercolor drawing for <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>
                                <hi rend="i">Published by permission of Lockwood Memorial Library, State
University of New York at Buffalo.</hi>
                            </figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p04-84" n="84"/>                            
sold for $900; the <hi rend="i">Beggar’s Opera</hi> engraving (in truly beautiful condition) brought $525.
Among the other items in the Bucknell collection, the most important was surely number 76, one of the two
known pulls of the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> engraving.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">5</ref> It went for $610. There was also one autograph letter, Blake to Linnell, 31 March 1826,
“With portrait”; and there was a set of <hi rend="i">Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi> (#74, $280),
lacking the last plate. An example of <hi rend="i">The Prologue and Characters of Chaucer’s Pilgrims</hi>
(“London 1812, Not recorded in Keynes bibliog.”) went for $440. The rest of the collection consisted mainly of
books illustrated by or otherwise associated with Blake. At least two of these may have been acquired by
Thomas B. Lockwood and presented to the Library by him—Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> and Mary
Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real Life</hi>; the Lockwood Memorial Library has a copy
of each of these. <note id="n8">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                5
                            </hi> Presumably this could be the impression designated #2 by Sir Geoffrey Keynes
in <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake / The Separate Plates</hi> (Dublin, 1956), p. 56. However, this
example is described as “much damaged” (p. 57), and no damage is evident in the reproduction in the American
Art Association catalogue (p. 15). It should perhaps also be noted that of the four examples of the first
state of the <hi rend="i">Beggar’s Opera</hi> engraving listed by Keynes (p. 73), none could be the Buffalo
copy, as all four are accounted for elsewhere at some time between 1935 and the present.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Several minor conundrums attach to numbers 56 and 57. Why did Blake tip the 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> drawing on to the back of an unrelated pencil drawing? For what purpose was the picture
of the giant figure, too crude to be considered a finished work, intended?
<figure n="giantdrawing.4.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="690">
                            <head>2 Pencil drawing.</head>
                            <figDesc>
                                <hi rend="i">Published by permission of Lockwood Memorial Library, State
University of New York at Buffalo.</hi>
                            </figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p04-85" n="85"/>
Solutions to these questions must await study of the pictures by a scholar expert in Blake’s pictorial
techniques, but a tentative hypothesis may be offered here. The pencil drawing is so crude as to be almost
certainly one of Blake’s early productions, as the Flaxmanesque linear quality also suggests. Perhaps it is
a study from a plaster cast. In any event, the figure (as Mr. Ruthven Todd points out to me in correspondence)
is less likely to be a discus thrower than a boxer holding a cestus, and the catalogue appears to be mistaken
on this point, as was whoever wrote the pencilled inscription on the drawing. If this was a relatively
valueless piece of early work, Blake may well have regarded it as expendable, and he may simply have used it
as a mount to protect his later, highly finished <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> picture. As for the giant figure, he
is recognizably a version of a very small figure in <hi rend="i">America</hi>, plate 1, lower left. Blake may
have used cheap paper for this picture because he never intended it as a finished work: it could have been a
study for the <hi rend="i">America</hi> figure or, alternatively, an experimental blowup preliminary to a
possible finished design.</p>
                    <p>The Blake picture belonging to the Buffalo and Erie County Library is the illustration
to the “Preludium” plate of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (plate 1). It was given to the Library by James Fraser
Gluck, the benefactor who presented the manuscript of <hi rend="i">Huckleberry Finn</hi> to the same library.
The picture is described in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue of the Gluck Collection of Manuscripts and
Autographs in the Buffalo Public Library</hi> (Buffalo, July 1899):
<q>
Original water-color, one of the designs made by the gifted, but eccentric, artist-poet to illustrate 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, one of his so-called “prophetic” books published in Lambeth in 1794. The drawing
represents a distorted, Caliban-like figure hiding behind a rock with a dagger in his uplifted hand ready to
strike a young man who is approaching.
</q>
Miss Jane Van Arsdale, librarian of the rare book collection, tells me that for many years this picture was
kept in the vault of the Albright-Knox Gallery in Buffalo, after having been loaned to the Gallery for an
exhibition; it was only recently rediscovered and returned to the Library. Compared against the Trianon Press
facsimile of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, the picture appears to be the same size as the corresponding portion of
the top of plate 1. The coloration is different: foliage is colored yellow-brown rather than green, and some
details of the foliage behind the Pilgrim figure do not appear in the Buffalo picture. However, the latter is
in other respects very similar to the facsimile illustration, even in the configuration of shadows on the
rocks. As in the case of the Lockwood picture from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, it is to be hoped that someone
expert in Blake’s pictorial techniques will study this picture in order to give us a more precise account of
it.</p>
                    <pb id="p04-86" n="86"/>
                    <figure n="washdrawing.4.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="365">
                        <head>3 Wash drawing.</head>
                        <figDesc>
                            <hi rend="i">Published by permission of Lockwood Memorial Library, State
University of New York at Buffalo.</hi>
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>