<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.4.eassoncatalogue</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">A Catalogue Raisonné of Blake’s Book Illustrations</title>
                <author n="Easson">Roger R. Easson</author>
                <author n="Easson">Kay Easson</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
	<pb id="p04-115" n="115"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-4-0002">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">A CATALOGUE RAISONNÉ OF BLAKE’S BOOK ILLUSTRATIONS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>From <docAuthor>Roger</docAuthor> and <docAuthor>Kay
<name>Easson</name>:</docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>The American Blake Foundation is pleased to announce the pending publication of the
first volume in its series of Blake reproductions (announced earlier this year in the 
<hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi>). Robert N. Essick and Roger R. Easson are editing a three volume work, 
<hi rend="i">A Catalogue Raisonné of William Blake’s Book Illustrations</hi>, collecting and reproducing
Blake’s plates and giving a complete bibliographical description of the books in which they appear.</p>
                    <p>The first of the three volumes is expected to go to press in October and should be
ready for sale in late November or early December. This first volume will contain 124 plates, 59 of which have
never been reproduced. Included are all plates from Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, Hayley’s 
<hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> 1802 and 1805, Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil, Royal Universal Family Bible</hi>,
Wedgwood’s <hi rend="i">Catalogue, Prologue . . . Of Chaucer’s Pilgrims.</hi> This volume is a collection
of all the plates Blake both designed and engraved that were published as parts of books during his
lifetime.</p>
                    <p>The two succeeding volumes will reproduce 257 plates, of which 165 have never been
<pb id="p04-116" n="116"/>
reproduced since the original publication. These two volumes will contain both the plates that Blake himself
designed and another engraved, and those that another designed and Blake engraved. The plates will be
presented in chronological order with complete bibliographic entries.</p>
                    <p>The Foundation has decided to offer a special prepublication price of $7 for the first
volume or $18 for the three volumes. Upon publication the volumes will be sold at $8 each or $24 for the
three.</p>
                    <p>To receive the prepublication price of $18 for the three volumes or $7 for the first
volume, please send remittance to:<lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="i">The American Blake Foundation</hi>
                        <lb/>
Department of English<lb/>
Illinois State University<lb/>
Normal, Illinois 61761<lb/>
                        <lb/>
If invoicing is requested, please add $1 to the prepublication rate. European orders should add $1 for postage
and handling.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>