<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.4.house</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Blake under the House</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-4-0002">
            	<pb id="p04-114" n="114"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">BLAKE UNDER THE HOUSE</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>According to a recent issue of <hi rend="i">The Book-of-the-Month Club News</hi>, Blake
is the pivot on which the plot turns in <hi rend="i">Crawlspace</hi>, a novel by Herbert Lieberman:
<q>
Albert and Alice Graves, a retired, childless couple, live in a quaint 18th-century farmhouse in New England.
One fall day they are visited by a personable young man from the fuel oil company, whom they ask to stay for
dinner and who, before leaving, is allowed to borrow a rare edition of William Blake. A few weeks later, the
young man, Atlee, returns without the Blake, but is allowed to borrow more books. Not long after that, Mr.
Graves discovers that someone is living in a crude nest in the crawlspace under the house. He also finds some
well-gnawed animal bones and the missing Blake. A call to the oil company reveals that Atlee has not worked
there for months. . . . It all ends with the Gravesses living in terror of both Atlee and a marauding band of
neighborhood toughs. There is murder, vandalism and finally a blood thirsty manhunt. Here, then, is a chilling
story—a thoughtfully chilling story—in the tradition of <hi rend="i">Night Must Fall</hi> or even 
<hi rend="i">The Collector.</hi> Not at all recommended for retired couples who live on remote farms. [David W.
McCullough]
</q>
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>