<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>4.4.phillipsnews</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">British Blake News</title>
                <author n="Phillips">Michael Phillips</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1971</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">04.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_04">
        <body>
	<pb id="p04-112" n="112"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-04-4-0002">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">BRITISH BLAKE NEWS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>From Michael Phillips, our Associate Editor at the University of Edinburgh:</p>
                    <p>On 15 June 1971 the Blake-Varley Sketchbook is to be broken up and sold at auction at
Christie’s. And Jeudwine, the purchaser of copy C of <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> at the
Britwell Court Library sale at Sotheby’s 29 March 1971 (see above, and see the last issue of the 
<hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> [#15], pp. 69-70), is also threatening to break up that work in order to enhance its
re-sale value. The following account appeared in <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> Wednesday, 19 May 1971:
<q>
Scholars and art historians are becoming disturbed by the growing practice among dealers and owners of
dismembering works of art for which they cannot find
<pb id="p04-113" n="113"/>
a market when intact.
</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Sketchbooks, hand-printed books, and even paintings are being “broken” or cut down for
sale because they often fetch more nowadays as separate items than if sold whole.</p>
                    <p>The latest case to arouse scholarly concern is that of the celebrated Blake-Varley
sketchbook, which is due to be sold as 30 separate lots at Christie’s on June 15. This important William
Blake work, which contains his famous “Ghost of a Flea” drawing and his visionary head of Job, was discovered
four years ago in Scotland. It had been missing for nearly a century. It contains drawings by Blake’s close
friend, the water-colourist Varley.</p>
                    <p>It had to be “broken” for exhibition at the Tate and its owner, Mr. David
Clayton-Stamm, decided to sell it as a series of separate drawings. These could fetch anything up to £50,000,
considerably more than if sold intact.</p>
                    <p>One Blake scholar, Miss Kathleen Raine, the poet, yesterday described the breaking and
selling of the individual drawings separately as “shocking.” She said it ought to be kept as one work. She was
far less concerned about its being lost to Britain, as a result of auction, than about its being broken up.
She hoped there might still be time to save it.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Clayton-Stamm defends his decision on the ground that a facsimile edition of the
sketchbook has been published, and also because small museums and collectors who could not otherwise afford to
buy original works by Blake will now be in the market for them.</p>
                    <p>Sir Geoffrey Keynes, another authority on Blake, said he thought it was already too
late to save this particular work, since drawings had been removed in the past. However, he thought it would
be “monstrous—like demolishing an historic house”—if Blake’s <hi rend="i">First Book of Urizen</hi>,
another work by the visionary poet and artist on the market, were to be broken up. The owner, who paid
£27,000 for it at Sotheby’s recently, has said that if he cannot find anyone to buy the complete book,
hand-printed and hand-painted by Blake, it will have to be broken and sold in separate lots.</p>
                    <p>These two examples, which highlight the question of breaking up, promise to bring to a
head controversy over the ethics and wisdom of this growing practice.</p>
                    <p>Hundreds of printed books containing hand-coloured engravings are being broken up by
print sellers for framing and selling individually. The economics of book-selling make this an inevitable
temptation. A book for which an antiquarian book dealer expects £50 may contain 50 colour plates which can be
sold for anything up to £5 each.</p>
                    <p>The result is that these books, once abundant, are rapidly disappearing from the
market, making it increasingly difficult for specialized libraries and collectors to obtain them. Many
antiquarian booksellers who feel strongly about the practise refuse to sell to known print sellers, except
where the book is already deficient.</p>
                    <p>I shall record the outcome of the sale at Christie’s of the Blake-Varley Sketchbook
and the eventual fate of copy C of <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> in a forthcoming issue of the
<hi rend="i">Newsletter.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p04-114" n="114"/>
                    <p>Recent publications in Britain of interest to Blake scholars include a splendidly
illustrated and documented catalogue of the Tate Gallery collection of Blake drawings, paintings, and
associated items. The Tate Gallery catalogue, substantially revised by Martin Butlin, together with the
Fitzwilliam Museum catalogue of their Blake collection place at the disposal of Blake scholars accurate and
detailed reference to two of the major Blake collections in Great Britain. A review of the Fitzwilliam Blake
Exhibition and Catalogue will appear in the <hi rend="i">Newsletter.</hi>
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>