<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.1.matheson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Vaughan, Elizabeth E. Barker, Colin Harrison, et al., Samuel Palmer 1805-1881: Vision and Landscape</title>
        <author n="Matheson">C. S. Matheson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>C.S Matheson</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>William Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Betteridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
      <pb id="p40-42" n="42"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEW</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Vaughan, Elizabeth E. Barker, Colin Harrison, et al. 
<hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer 1805-1881: Vision and Landscape.</hi> Catalogue of the exhibition at the British
Museum, 21 October 2005-22 January 2006, and at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 7 March-29 May 2006. British
Museum Press, 2005. 256 pp., 230 color illus. £25.00/$45.00, paperback.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>C. S. <name>Matheson</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>My first face-to-face encounter with Samuel Palmer was rather clandestine. It involved a
theologian, a spare bedroom and a return trip from France.</p>
          <p>Once, on my way back from the Loire Valley after a holiday with friends, S. invited me to stop
over in London at his parents’ home in Highgate. His father is an ecclesiastical publisher, with distant
ties to the Palmer family. S. knew I was working on Blake—was I interested in Samuel Palmer too? Yes, of
course, I replied, my mind’s eye suddenly full of cloisonné sheep, tipsy half-moons and darkling fields
with their furrows running aslant. We have an original painting, S. said, but we keep it hidden because the
insurance is so ruinous. I followed him into a dim guest room, waiting to see from where the small picture
would be conjured. Behind a copy of Virgil’s <hi rend="i">Eclogues</hi>? Folded modestly with the linen?
Under here, he said, hauling the corner of a substantial swaddled rectangle from beneath the bed, give me a
hand. We heaved it onto the embroidered counterpane.</p>
          <p>Its size was the first shock. I had always thought of Palmer’s work as being on a very modest
scale, as if his distillation of place and emotion was so intense that the physical dimensions of the work
were inevitably distilled down too. This was someone, after all, who included a “diminishing mirror” in
his outdoor sketching kit. I had thought of Palmer as an artist whose visions were naturally adapted to the
page and the portfolio—someone whose sensibility was most happily circumscribed by the woodcut and the
etching. But this painting, in its solid nineteenth-century frame and glazing, bore heavily down on all my
little assumptions. The second shock was the color. It was a sunrise landscape so vivid, so intense that the
adjective “lurid” immediately came to mind. It showed a restlessly brilliant sky, its pinks, oranges, and
yellows utterly unsubdued by the dark suggestiveness of the hill and trees and rural labor plodding forward
below. It was the violent dawn of a new day in an very old world—“An image of mysterious wisdom won by
toil,” as Yeats muses in “Phases of the Moon.” I hope I am betraying no confidence by identifying the
work as an illustration to “Lycidas.”</p>
          <p>The aptness of this little private view strikes me now after all these years, not the least
because its contradictions seem writ large in the exhibition Samuel Palmer: Vision and Landscape. Curator
William Vaughan has divided Palmer’s art and life into the broad, unequal categories of “Visionary” and
“Victorian”—divisions which variously reflect the tendencies, chronology and reception of Palmer’s
work. As the first major retrospective of the artist in almost 80 years (the last was at the Victoria &amp;
Albert Museum in 1926), this exhibition and the catalogue are great achievements, not to mention a timely
intervention in the evolution of Palmer’s reputation.</p>
          <p>To mark the bicentenary of Palmer’s birth, paintings, drawings, prints and artifacts have been
assembled from public and private collections in North America, Britain, Europe and Australia. The greatest
concentration of work is drawn from the collections of the British Museum, Ashmolean Museum, and Yale Center
for British Art. Roughly a quarter of the exhibits in the UK show are not at the Met., principally leaves from
the 1824 sketchbook (an updated edition of which has just been published by Thames &amp; Hudson in association
with the William Blake Trust), and a clutch of “blacks,” innovative monochrome ink and wash landscapes
that date from the early Shoreham period. John Linnell’s compelling pencil portrait <hi rend="i">William
Blake at Hampstead</hi> is not traveling westward. Met. viewers might also regret the omission of Palmer’s
<hi rend="i">Cornfield Bordered by Trees</hi>, c. 1833-44, his smallest surviving oil.</p>
          <p>It seems churlish, however, to protest these omissions when the show is so rich and
revealing—not of a narrowly canonical Samuel Palmer, but a Samuel Palmer broadened beyond
<pb id="p40-43" n="43"/>
the corrective presence of his (pyromaniacal) son, Alfred Herbert. (Before A. H. Palmer emigrated to Canada in
1910, he burned masses of what he considered his father’s equivocal work; the fire, he said, lasted for
days.) A long, long career of innovation, struggle and acute observation is chronicled here. Two catalogue
essays on Palmer’s materials and techniques, one by Alexandra Greathead and the other by Marjorie Shelley,
are particularly welcome accounts of Palmer’s career-long experimentation with pigments and effects.
Technically and psychologically Vision and Landscape seems a comprehensive answer to the charge of escapism
that has dogged assessments of Palmer’s production. One is guided, in fact, to see Palmer as a unique bridge
between romanticism, impressionism and post-impressionism—“essentially the English Van Gogh,” as Graham
Sutherland once described.</p>
          <p>Each room establishes a major phase of Palmer’s life, from his prodigious early years (Palmer
was 14 when he first exhibited at the British Institution and Royal Academy), to the articulation of a
“primitive vision” between 1823 and 1826. “Early” Shoreham and Palmer’s involvement with Blake and
the Ancients (here named “Britain’s first artistic community”) are carefully documented, along with
“later” Shoreham, 1830-35, “the high point of his individuality,” as Colin Harrison observes, and the
period of such seminal works as <hi rend="i">The Magic Apple Tree, In a Shoreham Garden, The Bright
Cloud.</hi> In contrast to these Shoreham rooms, the spaces devoted to Palmer’s picturesque travels in the
West Country and Wales, and his Italian interlude of 1837-40, feel less intense, in spite of the ambitious
size and scope of the landscape compositions. The Italian scenes paradoxically reinforce Palmer’s gifts as a
<hi rend="i">domestic</hi> landscape artist: at his best in England, Palmer blends a naturalist’s eye with a
sense of place so deep it could only form through accretion. Only in the study of <hi rend="i">The Cypresses
at the Villa d’Este</hi> does Palmer approach the same level of rootedness in his environment.</p>
          <p>It is a cliché in Palmer studies to lament the waning of Palmer’s creativity post-Shoreham.
Happily, the exhibition does not acquiesce in this view, but gives serious treatment to the products of
Palmer’s extended involvement with the Society of Painters in Water-Colours and with the Etching Club of
London. Elizabeth E. Barker’s essay on Palmer and printmaking, “‘The excitement of gambling, without its
guilt and its ruin,’” presents the technical and commercial aspects of this latter work with admirable
clarity. The last two decades of Palmer’s life (c. 1865-81) are represented through a magisterial series of
illustrations to Milton, and, in a circle back to Blake, 11 etchings to illustrate an English translation of
Virgil’s <hi rend="i">Eclogues.</hi> Palmer’s last great cycle of watercolors and etchings for
“L’Allegro” and “Il Penseroso” is best characterized as an engagement with the author—although on
more moderate terms than Blake’s correction of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> Commissioned by Ruskin’s
solicitor L. R. Valpy, the series is also representative of Palmer’s late critical success and his standing
amongst the pre-Raphaelites and their circle. I was disappointed to find that Palmer’s complementary work on
“Lycidas” was not addressed in the show or catalogue.</p>
          <p>Palmer’s relationship to Blake and the nature of his debt to Blake are certainly things that
trouble the division between the categories “Visionary” and “Victorian.” Vaughan describes Blake as
the second most important mentor in Palmer’s life after his father-in-law Linnell, and characterizes
Palmer’s 1824 introduction to Blake as the most influential encounter of his life. (Blayney Brown in his
essay ranks Blake as the third greatest influence on Palmer’s literary life after his nurse Mary Ward and
<hi rend="i">her</hi> favorite author, Milton). Much stress is given throughout the exhibition and catalogue
to the lasting impact on Palmer of Blake’s Job illustrations and his wood engravings for Thornton’s 
<hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi> and, to a lesser degree, Blake’s designs for the <hi rend="i">Inferno</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> Less acknowledged are traces of Blake’s graphic methodology
throughout Palmer’s work, even in unexpected places like the 1828 <hi rend="i">Oak Trees, Lullingstone
Park.</hi> Vaughan notes that the form and presence of Palmer’s study of these ancient trees may owe
something to Blake’s Wood of Self-Murderers from the Dante illustrations, but I would argue that Palmer’s
awareness of Blake goes beyond literal content here and into the surface tension of the piece. The texture of
<hi rend="i">Oak Trees</hi> is a revelation firsthand. Palmer has built up the furrows and edges of the
foreground oak with gouache and ink: heightened lines course the length of the tree like the sap within its
limbs and time in its aspect. It’s as if the energies of the organism itself are squeezing the marks up in
relief from the paper—a powerful enactment of Blake’s “determinate and bounding” line that not only
“distinguish[es] the oak from the beech,” but reveals the very nature of what it represents.</p>
          <p>The implication here, however, is that Palmer seemed to value Blake more for what he represented
as a type of artist than for what he produced as an artist. Blake is cast as a singular creative genius,
independent, original and spiritual, who privileged the imagination over observation. Palmer’s lifelong
mandate was to reconcile natural observation and imagination. But one of his most prized possessions was
William Blake’s spectacles.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
