<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.1.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake and Kate Greenaway</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>C.S Matheson</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>William Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Betteridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
      <pb id="p40-44" n="44"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake and Kate Greenaway</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Kate Greenaway, Randolph Caldecott, and Walter Crane are generally considered to be the most
important children’s book illustrators in Britain during the second half of the nineteenth century. In their
biography of Greenaway (1846-1901), Spielmann and Layard state that, in spite of her illness in the last year
of her life, “she was full of schemes for books—not merely projected schemes, but plans fully matured,
first sketches made, and pages fully ‘set-out.’” Among these “was a new <hi rend="i">Blake’s Songs
of Innocence</hi>, to be published at a shilling net, each song with at least one drawing; this was so fully
worked out that for certain of the designs several sketches were made.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">1</ref> I have not been able to locate any such sketches by Greenaway
illustrating individual poems in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, but I reproduce here what I
believe to be her design for the projected book’s front cover, dust jacket, or both (illus. 1). 
<note id="n71">1. M. H. Spielmann and G. S. Layard, <hi rend="i">Kate Greenaway</hi> (London: Adam and Charles
Black, 1905) 251. It is unlikely that the project ever went beyond the sketching stage. There is no edition of
any work by Blake listed in Thomas E. Schuster and Rodney Engen, <hi rend="i">Printed Kate Greenaway: A
Catalogue Raisonné</hi> (London: T. E. Schuster, 1986).</note></p>
          <p>Those familiar with Greenaway’s often saccharine but carefully executed watercolors and
published designs might find it odd to attribute this bold and awkward sketch to her hand. This style,
however, can be found among many of her first thoughts on paper. Even more indicative of her authorship is her
distinctive handwriting at the bottom of the design.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">2</ref> Hastily written with at least two letters elided, this inscription reads as follows:
“blue Paper Cover[.] Label Cream[.] Gr[a]pes and / leaves bo[r]der[.] white letters -”. These are
instructions, or perhaps simply aides-mémoire for the artist herself, for the color scheme of the cover and a
description of the border design of grapes and leaves for the vignette below “BLAKE.” The border motifs
were sketched so awkwardly that they might be misinterpreted without verbal notation. The author and title
inscriptions are clearly written, although Greenaway probably began to write “BLACK,” for the “K” of
“BLAKE” is written over a “C.” <note id="n72">2. For reproductions of some examples of Greenaway’s
rough preliminary sketches, and a reproduction of her handwriting, see <hi rend="i">Kate Greenaway: Catalogue
of an Exhibition . . . at the Hunt Institute</hi>, ed. Robert Kiger (Pittsburgh: Hunt Institute, 1980) 51 (an
illustration of page 61 of Greenaway’s journal), 54, 81, 83.</note></p>
          <p>The center of the vignette apparently pictures two seated figures facing each other. They are as
minimally represented as the border, but would presumably be developed in more detail in subsequent drawings.
Behind and slightly overlapping the back of the figure on the left is a capital “B.” Greenaway probably
began to write Blake’s name in this space, and then changed to the name above with the two figures in the
vignette. Three facsimiles of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, including William Muir’s of 1884, had been
published by 1901, and thus Greenaway need not have had access to an original copy to have been influenced by
the leaves, vines, and grape clusters pictured in Blake’s designs for “On Anothers Sorrow,” “The
School Boy,” and both plates of “The Ecchoing Green.” Electrotype reproductions of three of these
plates, absent only the second plate of “The Ecchoing Green,” were also available in Alexander
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 1863 and 1880. The human figures are less easily
related to Blake’s imagery. The closest parallel is the two very small figures, seated on a tendril and
facing each other, below the second word of the title to “Nurses Song.” None of these similarities is
sufficient to prove that Greenaway was responding to Blake’s own illustrations in <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence.</hi></p>
          <p>David Bindman gave me the drawing in 1980. It languished half-forgotten in a drawer until a house
cleaning returned it to notice in February 2005.</p>
          <figure n="Greenaway.drawing.40.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="532">
            <figTranscr>BLAKE.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              SONGS<lb/>
              OF<lb/>
              INNOCENCE<lb/>
              <lb/>
              blue Paper Cover Label Cream Gr[a]pes and<lb/>
              leaves bo[r]der white letters</figTranscr>
            <head>1. Kate Greenaway.</head>
            <figDesc><hi rend="i">A Cover Design for Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence. Pencil, 17.2 × 12.7
cm. (including the inscription at the bottom), on cream-colored wove paper without watermark, 19.2 × 14.2 cm.
Datable to 1901. Collection of Robert N. Essick.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
