<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
2005</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
        <author n="Sato">Hikari Sato</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>C.S Matheson</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>William Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Betteridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
    <pb id="p40-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in
2005</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor><lb/>
          With the Assistance of <docAuthor>Hikari <name>Sato</name></docAuthor> for Japanese Publications</byline>
          <div3>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake Publications and Discoveries in 2005</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The collections of books, manuscripts, prints, and drawings of Dr. A. E. K. L. B. Bentley and
G. E. Bentley, Jr., have been given to the library of Victoria University in the University of Toronto. The
gift includes (1) writings by Blake, including <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (M), the “Riddle” manuscript,
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (o) pl. 39, electrotypes, and pls. 22, 28, 30, 40, 44-46, 48<hi rend="s">a-b</hi>,
plus modern editions and facsimiles; (2) Blake’s commercial engravings, such as Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> (1797), Thornton’s Virgil (1821), <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1826), and Dante (1968), plus modern
reproductions and facsimiles; (3) Blake scholarship and criticism (1806-2004), especially works with
references to Blake before 1863;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> (4)
the Cumberland manuscripts;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> (5) books
by John Flaxman, especially his classical designs;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> and (6) books before 1835, especially illustrated books and works Blake is known to have
read or annotated (but of course not his copies). The collections are accompanied by a catalogue describing
them in detail. <note id="n1">1. The Bentley books associated with Blake before 1863 are listed (with other
locations) in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995), and
“William Blake and His Circle,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994 ff.).</note>
	<note id="n2">2. See G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of George Cumberland (1754-1848):
Comprehending His Published Books (1780-1829) and Articles (1769-1847) and His Unrecorded Works in Manuscript
Including a Novel (?1800), a Play (?1800), a Biography (?1823), a Long Poem (1802-3), and Works on Art (?1788,
?1816, ?1820)</hi> (New York: Garland Publishing, Inc., 1975).</note>
	<note id="n3">3. See G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Early Engravings of Flaxman’s Classical Designs:
A Bibliographical Study with a Note on the Duplicating of Engravings by Richard J. Wolfe</hi> (New York: New
York Public Library, 1964).</note></p>
              <p>The unfinished group portrait, attributed without evidence to Thomas Phillips, including an
allegation without evidence or plausibility that one of the figures represents William Blake, was offered with
the collection of Roy Davids at Bonhams, 3 October 2005, lot 14 (reproduced, estimate £4,000-6,000). It was
reproduced on the cover of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 26.4 (spring 1993).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Writings</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>2005 was a slow year for Blake’s writings. His letter of 12 March 1804, 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (M), the “Riddle” ms., and loose plates from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> were given to public institutions. A new transcript of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> was discovered as published by Jacques Raverat in 1910 in a run of 24 copies, and a facsimile of the
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> with a translation into Portuguese was published in Brazil (2004). 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> was translated into Catalan (2004), and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> was issued on a CD-ROM (2003). There were separate printings of “The Lamb” (as a Christmas
card, 1952) and “The Tyger” (1931), and Amelia Munson’s collection of Blake’s poetry (1964) was
reissued in a pretty little reprint (1999). Some of Blake’s works in illuminated printing were translated
into Portuguese by Manuel Portela (2005), and there were trifling editions of poems from the 
<hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> And the William Blake Archive continues to grow.</p>
              <p>The only drama about Blake’s own writings concerned <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
of Albion</hi> (N), which has never been described or perhaps even seen by a Blake scholar. It was acquired by
Mrs. Harry Payne Whitney before 1921 and remained obscurely in her family for three-quarters of a century. Its
mate, <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (E), was offered for sale by the Whitney family in 1999 and bought for a record
price, but an assiduous search of the Whitney houses did not reveal the <hi rend="i">Visions.</hi> Then a
mysterious stranger brought it in to Swann Galleries in New York to offer it for auction, apparently without
the knowledge of the Whitney family. Legal wheels were set in motion, the book was withdrawn from sale, and it
has now returned to the Whitney family, perhaps to resume its long, undisturbed, and peaceful sleep. It would
be wonderfully agreeable if some scholarly prince could bring it back to life with the kiss of knowledge.</p>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Some News Is Bad News</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>The extraordinarily valuable English Short Title Catalogue (formerly Eighteenth Century
Short Title Catalogue) online records copies (though not microfilms) of (1) <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>
(1789) in Southampton University Library; (2) <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783) in Mount Holyoke; (3)
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1794) in University of Kent; and (4-5) 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1793) in University of California (Davis) and Columbia
University. However, none of these is recorded in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), <hi rend="i">Blake
Books Supplement</hi> (1995), and their sequels in “William Blake and His Circle” (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
[1994 ff.]). They are all ghosts; the Southampton <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> proves to be the 1971 facsimile, the
Mount Holyoke <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> is the Griggs facsimile of 1890, the Kent 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> is the Blake Trust (1955) facsimile, and the California (Davis) and Columbia 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> are facsimiles of the Blake Trust (1959) and Muir (1884, copy no. 50).</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Art</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The Folio Society’s stupendous facsimile of the 537 watercolors for Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> is the most beautiful, the most aesthetically satisfying, the most unexpected,
the biggest (25 pounds), and the most expensive new book (Canadian $2,180) on Blake in many years. Even its
binding is sumptuous, in handcrafted Nigerian goatskin with buckram covers incorporating designs from Blake
and a buckram-covered solander box.</p>
              <pb id="p40-5" n="5"/>
              <p>It is a true facsimile, in that it attempts a very close reproduction of an original named
copy including size of image, color of printing and of tinting, size, color, and quality of paper, with no
deliberate alteration as in page order or numbering or obscuring of paper defects or centering the image on
the page. It is true-size, 42.0 × 32.5 cm.; the Modigliani Neve paper is appropriate and a joy to handle,
with an agreeably three-dimensional texture,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> the attempt to give the impression of the original is so faithful that the reproductions
are bound in two volumes as Blake’s watercolors were with no new typeset title page and no intrinsic
indication save the same one-page colophon in each volume that this is a modern reprint.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> From the facsimile one can appreciate as never
before save with the originals that the watercolors were often designed as two-page spreads, diptychs, with
orange on verso echoing orange on facing recto or grey echoing grey. The fidelity is so minute that one can
see the type show-through from the other side of the leaf. Indeed, on one leaf (Night VII, pp. 43-44), a
clearly visible crease in the paper has been incorporated into Blake’s cloud outline, as Robin Hamlyn points
out (xviii).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n4">4. In the original, leaves from the early editions of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> were set
in cut-out windows of “J WHATMAN 1794” paper from a half-century later, but here in the 2005 Folio Society
facsimile the inset design leaves are reproduced on the same leaf of paper as the text leaves.</note>
	<note id="n5">5. The title supplied here derives from the commentary volume by Robin Hamlyn.</note>
	<note id="n6">6. Hamlyn (Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> . . . Commentary by Robin Hamlyn [2005]
xviii) also identifies on Night VII, p. 55, “the marks left by two sides of a sheet of paper placed on a
design on which the watercolour was still wet,” which I cannot see here.</note></p>
              <p>It is a gorgeous book, a joy for both scholars and aesthetes.</p>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">No News Is Bad News</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>The drama of the 19 watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> was still playing in
2005. Whether one describes it as a tragedy (the set’s being broken up for crass commercial gain), a comedy
(so many different claims being made about them by the vendor, or perhaps by the agent of the vendors), or a
farce (how can one take seriously the presumption of moral and aesthetic integrity of the vendors?) may depend
upon the inclination of individual members of the audience. The set of drawings may (as has been variously
claimed, apparently on the authority of the vendor) belong to a US collector with a castle in Scotland who
intends to make them public, to a London collector with vaulting financial ambitions, to a Swiss
corporation—or to all of the above. However, the dismal fact is that they apparently remained throughout
2005 in a bank vault, inaccessible to scholars. But, to whet your appetite, at the time these words are
written the dénouement is imminent and the last act of the drama about the set of drawings for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> as a tragedy/comedy/farce will shortly occur.</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake’s Commercial Book Engravings</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The most exciting discovery in 2005 about Blake’s commercial book engravings was a new
printing in <hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi> (1799) of Blake’s engraving in the very rare 
<hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi> (1793)—only three copies of <hi rend="i">Bellamy</hi> have
been traced in public collections. (The last discovery of a new book with a Blake engraving was Elizabeth
Blower’s <hi rend="i">Maria</hi> [1785], described in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> [2001].) The presence of the
Blake plate in <hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi> was discovered by Robert N. Essick by pure
serendipity; he bought the previously unknown book for a risible sum for its engravings after Stothard, and
only after he received it did he find the Blake print in it. But Blake’s print after C. R. Ryley entitled
“F: REVOLUTION” in the Essick copy is not in the copy in the British Library or the two copies in the Yale
Center for British Art.</p>
              <p>It was very unusual for a print by Blake to be issued again in a work with a different title:
<table rows="9" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>First Printing</cell>
<cell>Second Printing</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Kimpton, <hi rend="i">History of the Holy Bible</hi> (1781)</cell>
<cell>Josephus, <hi rend="i">Works</hi> ([?1785-86])</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Seally and Lyons, <hi rend="i">Geographical Dictionary</hi> ([?1784])</cell>
<cell>Adams, <hi rend="i">New Royal Geographical Dictionary</hi> ([?1793]) and Adams, <hi rend="i">New Royal
System of Universal Geography</hi> ([?1794])</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> (1791)</cell>
<cell>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> (1806)</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi> (1793)</cell>
<cell><hi rend="i">Cabinet of the Arts</hi> (1799)</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> (1796)</cell>
<cell>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Outlines from the Ancients</hi> (1829)</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Shakspeare, <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi> (1802)</cell>
<cell><hi rend="i">Boydell’s Shakespeare</hi> ([?1803])</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808)</cell>
<cell>Mora, <hi rend="i">Meditaciones Poeticas</hi> (1826)</cell>
</row></table>
The prints in <hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi> (1799) are restrikes of the plates, new printings, not
remainders tucked into a new work. Notice that <hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi> (1793) was
published by Bellamy but that <hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi> acknowledges no publisher.</p>
              <p>A new advertisement for Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi> (1796) helps to establish
exactly when it was published, and the copperplates of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1826) are described, largely in
the dissertation of Mei-Ying Sung, with much more detail than was previously available. A curious survival of
printing which should have been trimmed off indicates that at least one of Blake’s engravings for Mary
Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> (1796) was printed on paper previously used for a
typeset text.</p>
              <p>Colored copies B and J of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797) were reproduced
for the first time in 2004, but only on CD-ROM.</p>
              <p>And, with the aid of COPAC (see below), 327 new locations are identified for books bearing
Blake’s commercial engravings.</p>
              <p>This is a strikingly good harvest.</p>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p40-6" n="6"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Blake Catalogues</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Several new catalogues are worth recording. There is a new reprint (2003) of the Blake Trust
<hi rend="i">Illustrations to the Bible</hi> (1957) with its scores of invaluable reproductions. The
exhibition Cloud &amp; Vision, of works inspired by Blake at the Museum of Garden History, on the other hand,
was not well received; Andrew Lambirth in the <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi> called the exhibition “feeble”
and “vulgar.”</p>
              <p>John Windle’s <hi rend="i">Catalogue Forty: William Blake and His Circle: Books of
Scholarship, Books of Beauty</hi> (2005) is wonderfully exciting, one of the most extensive, original,
handsome, and meticulous catalogues of Blake materials which has appeared in the last hundred years. Some of
the works in it are unique, many are comparatively rare, and some of the most remarkable, such as Blake’s
engravings for Job, Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, and Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, appear
in multiple copies. Of course an increasing number of them are listed as “Price on application,”
presumably meaning that the price is embarrassingly high—and negotiable. The catalogue is a joy to handle, a
valuable work even for those not tempted or able to acquire its riches. Notice how often it is cited in the
entries below.</p>
              <p>For me, one of the most notable scholarly discoveries of the past year was COPAC, the British
and Irish online union catalogue corresponding on a smaller scale to the North American National Union
Catalog.</p>
              <p>COPAC is a catalogue of the National Libraries of Ireland, Scotland, Wales, and the British
Library, plus British and Irish academic research libraries<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n7" type="note">7</ref> (including the independent college libraries of Cambridge and Oxford), plus
numbers of specialized research libraries (all I have noticed in London) including, for Blake, the Institute
of German Studies, London School of Economics, School of Oriental and African Studies, the Warburg Institute,
and Wellcome Library, but not of major art libraries (the British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings,
Fitzwilliam Museum, or National Art Library in the Victoria and Albert Museum), or the great public libraries
(e.g., Birmingham, Liverpool, Manchester). Doubtless it has been in existence for some time, but I only came
across it very recently when a bookseller traced a book he was offering to only one library in COPAC. (I do
not know what COPAC stands for; the online version does not seem to say.) <note id="n7">7. Aberdeen,
Birmingham, Bradford, Bristol, Cambridge, Durham, Edinburgh, Essex, Glasgow, Imperial College, King’s
College (London), Lampeter, Leeds, Liverpool, London, London School of Economics, Manchester, Newcastle,
Nottingham, Oxford (Bodleian and Taylorian), Reading, St. Andrews, School of Advanced Studies (not otherwise
identified), School of Oriental and African Studies, Sheffield, Southampton, Trinity College (Dublin),
University College (London), and Warwick.</note></p>
              <p>From COPAC I record the locations of contemporary copies of books with Blake’s writings or
commercial engravings not given in <hi rend="i">Blake Books, Blake Books Supplement</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994 ff.)—327 in all.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Books Owned by Blake the Poet</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The copy of John Quincy’s <hi rend="i">English Dispensatory</hi> (1733) associated with
William Blake was sold to an anonymous British collector by John Windle with some additional evidence not very
persuasively associating the work with William Blake.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Books Owned by the Wrong William Blake</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The edition of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> edited by Richard Bentley (1732) bearing the
initials “WB” has been demoted by Alexander Gourlay, Jason Snart, and GEB from Books Owned by William
Blake of London (1757-1827) to Books Owned by the Wrong William Blake (1770-1827)—indeed there is no good
reason to assume that this “WB” is a William Blake at all.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Scholarship and Criticism</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>The spate of writing about Blake continues unabated, as a comparison of works in this
checklist for recent years indicates:
<table rows="5" cols="6"><row>
	<cell/>
	<cell>Books,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> including 
<note id="n8">8. The books include reprints.</note>
	</cell>
	<cell>Editions &amp;</cell>
	<cell>Catalogues</cell>
	<cell>Essays</cell>
	<cell>Reviews</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>2003</cell>
<cell>50</cell>
<cell>17</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>205</cell>
<cell>47</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>2004</cell>
<cell>31</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>153</cell>
<cell>81</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>2005</cell>
<cell>43</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>139</cell>
<cell>79</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>2006</cell>
<cell>54</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>164</cell>
<cell>73</cell>
</row></table></p>
              <p>The languages recorded here for 2005 include Afrikaans (1), Catalan (1), Chinese (1), French
(4), Galician<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> (one of the four chief
languages of Spain, which include also Basque, Catalan, and Spanish), German (4), Italian (6), Japanese (16),
Korean (1), Portuguese (2, including the first recorded book on Blake published in Brazil), Russian (1), and
Spanish (4), and there are works in English published not only in Japan but in Oslo, Prague and Lebanon. 
<note id="n9">
                                   9. *“William Blake (1757-1827).” 33-37 in section 3, “O romanticismo
na gran Bretaña” of Eduardo Álvarez González, Aurora Bermúdez Canosa, María Xesús Dono González,
Carlos Gómez Blanco, Juana López Beiras, Antonio Pichel Lorenzo, Dorinda Rivera Pedredo, Elisa Santamarina
Fernández, Pilar Vázquez Castro, <hi rend="i">O movemento romántico</hi>, Proxecto didáctico da AS-PG;
Coordinación: Eduardo Álvarez González (Coruña [Spain]: Baía Edicións, 2003) Literatura universal
contemporánea, I; ISBN: 8496128199. In Galician.
                                    <p>A school text for “curso de Bacharelato,” with English and Galician
texts of “The Lamb” and “The Tyger” and classroom questions, e.g., is this tiger “o animal dun zoo
ou como unha criatura espericual?”</p></note></p>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Books</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Aside from reprints, there were very few books about Blake. John Beer’s 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: A Literary Life</hi> is, despite its title, a sensitive critical work organized
chronologically. It does not pretend to biographical originality.</p>
                <pb id="p40-7" n="7"/>
                <p>Jeremy Tambling’s <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night Thoughts</hi> is little more than a
collection of “reason[s] for linking Blake and night” (11), scarcely related to Blake’s extraordinary
illustrations of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> by Edward Young. Far more satisfying is Robin Hamlyn’s
substantial book accompanying the magnificent facsimile of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors,
with its sane, workmanlike, but necessarily brief analysis of each of the 537 drawings.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Essays</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>The essays on Blake were much more fruitful. Essays, reviews, etc., on Blake were collected
in <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> (18), the <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> (14), in the
exhibition catalogue called <hi rend="i">Cloud &amp; Vision</hi> (14), in <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton
and Blake</hi> (29), in <hi rend="i">Voyages of Conception</hi>, ed. Eiji Hayashi et al. (4), and in Shoichi
Matsushima et al., <hi rend="i">Ekkyo suru Geijutsuka—Ima, Blake wo Yomu: William Blake: A Bordercrossing
Artist—Reading His Works Now</hi> (5).</p>
                <p>Doctoral dissertations on Blake were completed in Canada (1, in Alberta), Denmark (1),
England (3, at Birmingham and Nottingham Trent), Spain (1, in Madrid), and the United States (2, in Indiana
and Tennessee). Probably the most distinguished of these—or at any rate the only one I have seen—is
Mei-Ying Sung’s “Technical and Material Studies of William Blake’s Engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations
of The Book of Job</hi> (1826),” which records very rewardingly the changes Blake’s copperplates went
through as he developed his masterpiece. In particular, it details, with photographs, the corrections Blake
made by hammering out mistakes from the back of the plates. It will be splendid to see the work in published
form.</p>
                <p>Some thirty years ago, Robert N. Essick acquired a mysterious portrait whose provenance,
subject, and painter were scarcely known beyond speculation. It was immediately recognized as a powerful
image, particularly in the intense, compelling eyes, and it has been widely reproduced as a portrait of
William Blake, e.g., in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977). In all that time Essick has been brooding about
how to demonstrate satisfactorily his conclusion that Blake is both the subject and the painter of the
portrait. He has now achieved this triumphantly in his essay called “A (Self?) Portrait of William Blake”
in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, and we can now confidently omit the query in his title. It <hi rend="i">is</hi> a
self-portrait. The most convincing evidence is an asymmetry in Blake’s features; above his nose is a slight
crease slanting slightly over his right eyebrow, quite clear in the life mask of 1823. In a mirror the crease
would appear to slant over his <hi rend="i">left</hi> eyebrow, and so it appears in the self-portrait. How
satisfying to have a venerable mystery so convincingly solved.</p>
                <p>The most prolific discoverer of minute particulars about William Blake is Angus Whitehead,
who has not yet submitted his dissertation on Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> He reports from George Richmond’s comment in a copy of Gilchrist’s biography (1863)
that Richmond associated the Kitty of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> with Catherine Blake—and he
assumes that Blake did also. Much of his most fruitful evidence comes from directories and rate books. From
these, he is able to give a full context to Blake’s casual reference to “Mrs Enoch” in 1804,
demonstrating that she was the wife of Blake’s landlord and that Blake would have been familiar with her
baby. His very full and satisfying essay on Blake’s last residence, at 3 Fountain Court, leads into the most
original essay of them all. In this he identifies Henry Banes not only as Blake’s brother-in-law (the
husband of his wife’s sister, which was previously known) but as a vintner, as a fellow-resident at 3
Fountain Court, as Blake’s benefactor, and as the father of a niece and grandnephews of whom we had not
known at all before. Further, Whitehead demonstrates that the radical artist and printer John Barrow, who
published one of Blake’s engravings, was intimate with the family and resident in the same building. Such
details allow us to form a far richer picture of Blake’s last years. It would be admirable if Whitehead
would put these discoveries together into a book on Blake’s last years. <note id="n10">10. See entries in
Part VI under <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> and Whitehead, as well as reviews under Cox and Paley.</note></p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">The Tools of Scholarship</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>There are the usual workhorses of scholarship, Robert N. Essick’s invaluable “Blake in
the Marketplace” and this “William Blake and His Circle,” both in <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Critics and
scholars regularly visit them, but the number who harness and ride them systematically must be very
limited.</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Roads Not Taken: The Nuts in the Fruitcake</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Some writing on Blake cries out for protest: you can’t write about Blake like that. Well,
of course you can, and students regularly do, but grown-ups shouldn’t, or at least they should be prepared
for subsequent readers to protest. Richard Holmes says in the introduction to his edition of Gilchrist that
Blake engraved the texts of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> and Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,
though Blake did not publish any engraving of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> at all, and the text of the
edition of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797) which he illustrated has the text set entirely in
type. And Jeremy Tambling in his <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night Thoughts</hi> misnames Blake’s mother
Catherine Armitage as “Harmitage” and his friend Thomas Stothard as “Stodhard,” and he confuses
himself almost inextricably as to the differences in Blake’s works between “plate,” “page,” and
leaf.</p>
                <p>The annual checklist of scholarship and discoveries concerning William Blake and his circle
records publications and discoveries for the current year (say, 2005) and those for previous years which are
not recorded in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995), and
“William Blake and His Circle” (1994-2005). Installments of “William Blake and His Circle” (1994 ff.)
are continuations of <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>, with similar
principles and conventions.</p>
                <p>I take <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>, faute de
mieux, to be the standard bibliographical books on Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> and have noted significant differences from them. <note id="n11">11. Except for the
states of the plates for Blake’s commercial book engravings, where the standard authority is Robert N.
Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (1991). Significant further details,
especially about collations, are given in Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake
Book Illustrator: A Bibliography and Catalogue of the Commercial Engravings, Volume 1: Plates Designed and
Engraved by Blake</hi> (Normal, Illinois: American Blake Foundation, 1972); <hi rend="i">Volume 2: Plates
Designed or Engraved by Blake 1774-1796</hi> (Memphis, Tennessee: American Blake Foundation, 1979); volume 3
never appeared.</note></p>
                <pb id="p40-8" n="8"/>
                <p>The organization of Division I of the checklist is as in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>:</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <table rows="6" cols="2">
                <row>
                  <cell>Part I:</cell>
                  <cell>Editions, Translations, and Facsimiles of Blake’s Writings<lb/>
Section A: Original Editions, Facsimiles, Reprints, and Translations<lb/>
Section B: Collections and Selections</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part II:</cell>
                  <cell>Reproductions of His Drawings and Paintings<lb/>
Section A: Illustrations of Individual Authors<lb/>
Section B: Collections and Selections</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part III:</cell>
                  <cell>Commercial Book Engravings</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part IV:</cell>
                  <cell>Catalogues and Bibliographies</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part V:</cell>
                  <cell>Books Owned by William Blake the Poet<lb/>
Appendix: Books Owned by the Wrong William Blake in the Years 1770-1827</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Part VI:</cell>
                  <cell>Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies<lb/>
Note: Collections of essays on Blake and issues of periodicals devoted entirely to him are listed under the
titles; their authors may be recovered from the index.</cell>
                </row>
              </table>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
                  <ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
                  <note id="n12">12. There is nothing in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995) corresponding to Division II: Blake’s Circle.</note>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>This division is organized by individual (say, William Hayley or John Flaxman), with works by
and about Blake’s friends and patrons, living individuals with whom he had significant direct and
demonstrable contact. It includes Thomas Butts and his family, Robert Hartley Cromek, George Cumberland, John
Flaxman and his family, Henry Fuseli, Thomas and William Hayley, John Linnell and his family, Samuel Palmer,
James Parker, George Richmond, Henry Crabb Robinson, Thomas Stothard, John Varley, and Thomas Griffiths
Wainewright. It does <hi rend="i">not</hi> include important contemporaries with whom Blake’s contact was
negligible or non-existent, such as John Constable and William Wordsworth and Edmund Burke. Such major figures
are dealt with more comprehensively elsewhere, and the light they throw upon Blake is very dim.</p>
              <p>Reviews, listed here under the book reviewed, are only for works which are substantially
about Blake, not for those with only, say, a chapter on Blake. The authors of the reviews may be recovered
from the index.</p>
              <p>I have made no systematic attempt to record manuscripts and typescripts, “audio books”
and magazines, CD-ROMs,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> chinaware,
comic books, computer printouts, radio and television broadcasts, calendars, exhibitions without catalogues,
festivals and lecture series, furniture with inscriptions, lectures on audio cassettes,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> lipstick, microforms, mosaic pavements,
music, pillows, poems, postage stamps, postcards, posters, published scores, recorded readings and singings,
rubber stamps, stained-glass windows, stickers, T-shirts, tattoos, tiles, video recordings, or e-mail related
to Blake. <note id="n13">13. For instance, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, commentary
by Stuart Curran (2003); see entry under Part I, Section A.</note>
	<note id="n14">14. For instance, Jack Herbert, “William Blake: Poet, Painter, Visionary,”* “Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Song of Liberty &amp; America</hi>”*; Grevel Lindop, “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vision of the
Last Judgement</hi>”*; Kathleen Raine, “William Blake’s Fourfold Vision of London” (presumably related
to her “The Spiritual Fourfold London,” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Critical Miscellany</hi> 5 [1992]: 181-98,
and her <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Fourfold London</hi> [1993], “William Blake—Prophetic Voice of
England,” “The Imagination According to William Blake”; Jonathan Wordsworth, “William Blake &amp; the
Romantic Imagination,” according to <hi rend="i">Temenos Academy Recorded Lectures: A Catalogue of Over
Three Hundred Lectures on Audio Cassette, from Our Programmes 1992-2005</hi>—an asterisk indicates “with
slides.”</note></p>
              <p>The status of electronic “publications” becomes increasingly vexing. Some such works seem
to be merely electronic versions of physically stable works, and some suggest no more knowledge than how to
operate a computer, such as reviews invited for the listings of the book sale firm of Amazon.com, which are
divided into those by (1) the author, (2) the publisher, and (3) other, perhaps disinterested,
remarkers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> I have not searched for
electronic publications, and I report here only those I have happened upon which appear to bear some
authority.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Of course many
periodicals are now issued online as well as in hard copies. <note id="n15">15. For instance, Blake is in the
“Self-Publishing Hall of Fame” online, and there is a web site called “Home-Essays” with more than 30
essays on Blake for “All Grade Levels”; volunteers can submit essays (6 March 2006).</note>
	<note id="n16">16. E.g., G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Blake and the Xenoglots: Strange-Speaking Critics and
Scholars of Blake,” online <corr type="emend">(<ref type="article" issue="bonus.bentley"><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 
bonus content</ref> 2004).</corr></note></p>
              <p>In transliterations from Chinese and Japanese, foreign proper names are given as they are
represented in our script (e.g., “William” and “Blake”) rather than as they would be pronounced in
Chinese and Japanese (“Iriamu” and “Bureiku”).</p>
              <p>The chief indices used in compiling this 2005 checklist were <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography
of English Language and Literature</hi> 79 (2005) #8675-8717; <hi rend="i">Books in Print 2005-2006</hi>
([Sept.] 2005) titles, subjects, authors; <hi rend="i">Book Review Index</hi> (2005); “Citation Information
by [Japanese] Institute of Informatics”; Japanese National Diet Library Online Catalogue; COPAC (union
online catalogue of British and Irish national and university research libraries); <hi rend="i">2003 MLA
International Bibliography of Books and Articles in the Modern Languages and Literatures</hi> (2004 [received
26 Jan. 2005]) 1: #4058-4126 and online (last viewed 22 Feb. 2006); Noah Heringman, “Recent Studies
<pb id="p40-9" n="9"/>
in the Nineteenth Century,” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi> 45 (2005): 961-1037; and 
<hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 83 (2005): 593-603.</p>
              <p>It is not always easy to ascertain from these fairly rough indices the relevance of a work to
the poet-painter William Blake. Two of those which I have ignored, perhaps erroneously, as irrelevant are
Ariel Dorfman, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Therapy</hi> (New York: Seven Stories Press, 2004) 192 pp., ISBN:
1583220704 and 1583224793; and Etrulia R. Lee, <hi rend="i">Blake the Duck</hi> (Fort Washington [Maryland]:
Chamike, 1994) 24 pp., ISBN: 1884876099.</p>
              <p>I am indebted for help of many kinds to Dr. E. B. Bentley, Mr. Martin Butlin, Professor
Robert N. Essick (especially for showing me the final typescript of his “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,”
for <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> and his <hi rend="i">Cabinet of the Arts</hi> [1799]), Dr. Francisco Gimeno
Suances, Ms. Sarah Jones at <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (for extraordinarily meticulous editing), Mr. Jeff Mertz
(our man at the Bodleian), Museum of Garden History, Palgrave Macmillan (publishers), Mr. Paul Miner,
Professor Joseph Viscomi, Mr. Angus Whitehead, and Mr. John Windle.</p>
              <p>I should be most grateful to anyone who can help me to better information about the unseen
(§) items reported here, and I undertake to thank them prettily in person and in print.</p>
              <p>Research for “William Blake and His Circle, 2005” was carried out in the Huntington
Library, the Bibliotheca La Solana, the University of Toronto Library, and the Toronto Public Library.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Symbols</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>* Works prefixed by an asterisk include one or more illustrations by Blake or depicting him.
If there are more than 19 illustrations, the number is specified. If the illustrations include all those for a
work by Blake, say <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> or his illustrations to <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>, the work is
identified.</p>
              <p>§ Works preceded by a section mark are reported on secondhand authority.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <table rows="5" cols="2">
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                    <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                  </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell><hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2)</cell>
                  <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (2004)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Butlin</cell>
                  <cell>Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>
(1981)</cell>
                </row>
              </table>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Division I: William Blake</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part I: Blake’s Writings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title><hi rend="b">Section A: Original Editions, Facsimiles</hi>,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref>
                      <hi rend="b">Reprints, and Translations</hi>
	<note id="n17">17. In this checklist, “facsimile” is taken to mean “an exact copy” attempting very
close reproduction of an original named copy including size of image, color of printing (and of tinting if
relevant), and size, color, and quality of paper, with no deliberate alteration as in page order or numbering
or obscuring of paper defects, or centering the image on the page.</note>
	</title>
                    </head>
                    <table rows="5" cols="2">
                      <head>Table of Collections of Contemporary Copies of Blake’s Writings</head>
                      <row>
                        <cell>
                          <hi rend="i">Anonymous</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 1 (see “Order” of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>)</cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <cell>Morgan (J. Pierpont)</cell>
                        <cell>Letter (12 March 1804)</cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <cell>Library</cell>
                        <cell/>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <cell>Victoria University</cell>
                        <cell>Illuminated Works: <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (M), <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (o)
pl. 39, electrotypes, and pls. 22, 28, 30, 40, 44-46, 48<hi rend="s">a-b</hi></cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <cell>Library in the University of Toronto</cell>
                        <cell>Manuscript: “Riddle” manuscript</cell>
                      </row>
                    </table>
                    <table rows="1" cols="2">
                      <head>Watermarks in Paper Used by Blake &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> pp. 71-73, 
<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 40, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1998, 2004, 2005)&gt;</head>
                      <row>
                        <cell>EDMEADS &amp; PINE | 1802</cell>
                        <cell>Self-portrait (?1802) Essick Collection</cell>
                      </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Private Owners and Public Institutions Which Have Disposed of Original Blakes since the
Records Were Made for <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>
(1995)</p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">Bentley, Dr. A. E. K. L. B. and G. E.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="i">Mary E. Malone</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> (1795)</p>
                    <p>Pls. 1 and 5, 2 and 6, and 3 and 4 are etched back-to-back, and pls. (2, 6), (3, 4)
each have one rounded corner, according to Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>
(1993) 287. Therefore the five plates of <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> (1795) plus 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 3 cannot be on the versos of <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, as in 
<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 113, 145.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> (1795)</p>
                    <p>If, as Viscomi argues (<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 287), the six
plates of <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> were on only three copperplates, etched back-to-back, the 
<hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> versos cannot have had <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> pls. 1-5 and 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 3 (pace <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 145, 113). <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> plates are
so similar in size—9.7 to 9.9 cm. wide by 13.5 to 13.7 cm. high—that any one of them could have been on
the verso of any other of them. Perhaps four plates were etched back-to-back, and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl.
3 (13.4 × 9.6 cm.), the only <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> plate without a copperplate-maker’s mark, was on the
recto of the fifth plate.</p>
                    <pb id="p40-10" n="10"/>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794)</p>
                    <table rows="2" cols="6">
                      <head>Table</head>
                      <row>
                        <cell>Copy</cell>
                        <cell>Plates</cell>
                        <cell>Leaves</cell>
                        <cell>Watermark</cell>
                        <cell>Leaf size in cm.</cell>
                        <cell>Printing color</cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <cell>Anon.</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Wove paper</cell>
                        <cell>24.2 × 17.7</cell>
                        <cell>dark grey-Blue</cell>
                      </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Pl. 1 (The Ancient of Days [A], Rosenbach Museum) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #10&gt;</p>
                    <p>“The [brick-red] ink color and flat printing suggest that this is probably a
posthumous impression. The broad, thin [grey] washes are similar to those found in some posthumous impressions
of plates from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>,” e.g., copy h, pl. 40 (“The
Fly”), according to Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4
(spring 2006): 149n1.</p>
                    <p>Pl. 1 (The Ancient of Days [D])</p>
                    <p>Binding: “Printed by Blake, but probably hand colored, at least in part, by someone
other than Blake or his wife Catherine”—note “the careless handling of the rose-red tints on the
clouds”—though “the coloring on the figure is more controlled and convincing; perhaps two different
artists were responsible for these different styles.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref> The leaf with a hand-drawn brown ink border just beyond the print was mounted, probably
for George A. Smith about 1853, in a window cut in a larger sheet 30.7 × 23.7 cm., with stitch marks at the
left of the host leaf and inscribed (probably by George A. Smith about 1853) “2” and “From Europe,
frontispiece.” <note id="n18">18. Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 149, 150, the source of all the information here.</note></p>
                    <p>History: See the “Order” of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
                    <p>If, as Joseph Viscomi argues (<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 287),
the six plates of <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> were etched back-to-back on three copperplates, 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 3 cannot be on the verso of one of them (pace <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 145, 113). Perhaps
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 3, the only <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> plate without a platemaker’s mark 
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 145), has a <hi rend="i">Book of Los</hi> plate etched on the verso. Note that 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 3 appears only in copies H and K printed in 1795 and 1821 (Viscomi 279, 376,
380).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> (1794)</p>
                    <p>Platemaker’s marks on pls. 2, 19, and 28, which I have not observed, are reported by
Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (1993) 413n9.</p>
                    <p>Letters</p>
                    <p>1804 March 12 to William Hayley</p>
                    <p>History: Mrs. John Malone (Mary E. Malone) sold it (according to the Pierpont Morgan
Library’s records) in 1976 to Charles Ryskamp, who gave it in January 2005 to the Pierpont Morgan
Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n19">19. Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4
(spring 2006): 156.</note></p>
                    <p>1825 November 25</p>
                    <p>Found by Virginia Murray for Michael Phillips in the John Murray Archive and reproduced
in (1) the catalogue of the Wordsworth Trust exhibition of Milton (6 July-31 Oct. 2004) (recto); (2) G. E.
Bentley, Jr., “William Blake and His Circle,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): cover (recto)
and 11 (verso); (3) Angus Whitehead, “William Blake’s Last Residence: No. 3 Fountain Court, Strand, George
Richmond’s Plan and an Unrecorded Letter to John Linnell,” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.1
(2005): 27 (recto); and (4) Michael Phillips, “The Printing of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the
Book of Job</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi> 22 (2005): 139 (recto) (“a previously unrecorded
letter . . . not . . . known to scholars before” [138, 140]).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> ([?1790])</p>
                    <p>Copy C</p>
                    <p>History: Apparently reproduced in the Brazilian facsimile (2004).</p>
                    <p>Copy M</p>
                    <p>History: Dr. A. E. K. L. B. Bentley and G. E. Bentley, Jr., &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2001)&gt; gave it in October 2005 with the rest of their collections to Victoria University Library in the
University of Toronto.</p>
                    <p>Editions</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> (Chelsea: [Printed by Jacques
Raverat] 1910) 8°, i, 21 pp. (plus 5 blank leaves at each end).</p>
                    <p>According to the colophon, it was “Printed at Chelsea by J.P. Raverat. January
1910”; a ms. note in the copy “ex dono impressionis” to “Sydney Cockerell” (in the collection of
James Schaffner) says it was printed in “24 copies” “by M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Hornby’s permission at
the Ashendene Press. | SCC”.</p>
                    <p>§*<hi rend="i">El Matrimonio del Cielo y del Infierno (The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell) (1790-1792).</hi> Estudio preliminar, traducción y notas de José Luis Palomares. (2000) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt; C. 3<hi rend="s">a</hi> ed. (2005).</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Matrimônio do Céu e do Inferno.</hi> Tr. Julia Vidili. (São Paulo
[Brazil]: Madras, 2004) 8°, 59 pp.; ISBN: 8573748028. In Portuguese.</p>
                    <p>A color facsimile [unidentified but apparently of copy C] with translation on facing
pages.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (1804[-11])</p>
                    <p>Edition</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Milton Un Poema.</hi> Edició Bilingüe. Traducció i postfaci d’Enric
Casassas Figueres. (Barcelona: Edicions dels Quaderns Crema, 2004) In Amicorum Numero 20, 4°, 252 pp.; ISBN:
8477274223. In English and Catalan.</p>
                    <p>English and Catalan text, plate by plate, on facing pages, with an “Appendix: Planxes
Suplementàries” including the Preface (226-35). There are also “Postfaci del Traductor” (237-42) and
“Notes” (in Catalan) (243-52).</p>
                    <pb id="p40-11" n="11"/>
                    <p>“The Order in which the Songs of Innocence and Experience ought to be paged”
(?after 1818)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 1 (The Ancient of Days [D])</p>
                    <p>Binding: See the entry under <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, above.</p>
                    <p>In the collection of leaves including the “Order” of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>,
(S1), the leaf numbered 97 with Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Designs to A Series of Ballads</hi> (1802) pl. 14 and
the “Riddle” manuscript acquired by Dr. A. E. K. L. B. Bentley and G. E. Bentley, Jr. &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #135&gt;, was given by them with the rest of their collections in October 2005 to (S2)
Victoria University Library in the University of Toronto.</p>
                    <table rows="2" cols="4">
                      <head>Receipts Signed by Blake</head>
                      <row>
                        <cell>Payer</cell>
                        <cell>Date</cell>
                        <cell>Sum</cell>
                        <cell>Location of ms.</cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                        <cell>5 July 1805</cell>
                        <cell>£5.7.0</cell>
                        <cell>Kenneth Rendell</cell>
                      </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>1805 July 5</p>
                    <p>History: Acquired by Joseph Holland; offered with the collection of Joseph Holland and
Vincent Newton in John Windle, Catalogue 26 (Dec. 1995), lot 1 (with Keynes [1921] and other ephemera,
reproduced, price on enquiry [sold], i.e., kept for the Windle collection) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1996)&gt;; sold by Windle in June 1996 (according to “Blake in the Marketplace, 1996,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 30.4 [spring 1997]: 102) to the autograph dealer Kenneth Rendell &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1997)&gt;; offered on consignment in John Windle, Catalogue 40 (Nov. 2005), lot 1
(“Price on application”), for (Windle tells me) $45,000; returned to Kenneth Rendell.</p>
                    <p>“Riddle” ms. (?1802)</p>
                    <p>See the “Order” of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (1795)</p>
                    <p>The 8 prints of <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> derive from 4 copperplates; pls. 1 and 8
are recto and verso of a plate 17.6 × 23.5 cm.; pls. 2 and 5 are recto and verso of a plate 17.3 × 24.2 cm.;
pls. 3-4 are side by side on a plate 27.2 × 21.4 cm.; and pls. 6-7 are side by side on a plate 28.0 × 22.2
cm.—see Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 287, and <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 39. The
weight would have been 3,014.9 g and the cost £2.0.5¼.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1794)</p>
                    <p>Copy C</p>
                    <p>History: Reproduced on the CD-ROM (2003).</p>
                    <p>Copy T</p>
                    <p>History: The first copy of Muir’s facsimile of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
was colored after copy T in the British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings and sent in October 1884 to
the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> (according to Muir’s letter of 28 November 1885 to the editor of the 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> in the collection of Robert N. Essick), but the other copies were colored after copy U
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> p. 422&gt;.</p>
                    <p>Copy Z</p>
                    <p>History: Reproduced on the CD-ROM (2003).</p>
                    <p>Copy o</p>
                    <p>Pl. 39 History: Dr A. E. K. L. B. Bentley and G. E. Bentley, Jr., &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #139; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 129&gt; gave it with the rest of their collections in October
2005 to Victoria University Library in the University of Toronto.</p>
                    <p>Electrotypes (?1861)</p>
                    <p>History: (2Di) Dr A. E. K. L. B. Bentley and G. E. Bentley, Jr., &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #139; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 130&gt; gave their set with the rest of their collections in
October 2005 to Victoria University Library in the University of Toronto.</p>
                    <p>Pls. 22, 28, 30, 40, 44-46, 48<hi rend="s">a-b</hi></p>
                    <p>History: Dr A. E. K. L. B. Bentley and G. E. Bentley, Jr., &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#139; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 131&gt; gave them with the rest of their collections in October 2005 to
Victoria University Library in the University of Toronto.</p>
                    <p>Edition</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [copy C] <hi rend="i">London,
1794</hi> [copy Z] <hi rend="i">London, 1826.</hi> Commentary by Stuart Curran. 1 CD-ROM. (Octavo Editions:
Oakland [California], 2003); ISBN: 1891788892.</p>
                    <p>Review</p>
                    <p>§Steve Clark, <hi rend="i">European Journal of English Studies</hi> 8 (2005):
255-57.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1793[-1831])</p>
                    <p>Copy N</p>
                    <p>Binding: Inscribed in pencil on the front flyleaf: “1848 | 12 8th paid 70s | for this
to | A Evans &amp;[?] Son[?] | London | RT [<hi rend="i">or perhaps</hi> RL] | 4 guineas was 
<hi rend="u">asked</hi> for it”.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n20">20. According to John Windle, as reported in Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace,
2005,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 148.</note></p>
                    <p>History: . . . Bought 12 Aug. [or 8 Dec.] 1848 from A. Evans &amp; Son, London, for
£3.10.0 (£4.4.0 was asked) by RT (or perhaps RL—see the inscription above) . . . The anonymous individual
who said he had acquired <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (N) from an antique dealer and offered to sell it in 2004
at Swann Galleries (New York) was sued for possession of it by a member or members of the Whitney family; the
suit was settled out of court, and the book is again in the possession of a member or members of the Whitney
family, who do not plan to sell it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n21">21. According to Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 148. The information about the lawsuit, ownership, and plan not to
sell came to Essick from Christine von der Linn of Swann Galleries (now Swann). For more details about the
history of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (N), see <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #213, <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 143, and 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2005).</note></p>
                    <p>Edition</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> Ed. Robert N. Essick. (2002)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                    <p>Review</p>
                    <p>Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 27
(2004): 126-27.</p>
                  </div7>
                  <pb id="p40-12" n="12"/>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section B: Collections and Selections</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Divine Image.</hi> ([?New York, ?1948]) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p.
151 dates it ?1949&gt; B. §<hi rend="i">The Divine Image.</hi> (New York, 1949) C. <hi rend="i">The Divine
Image.</hi> Printed by Valenti Angelo for the Zamorano-Roxburghe joint meeting, San Francisco, 1976.</p>
                    <p>A and B bear a note: “25 copies printed and illuminated by Valenti Angelo”
(1897-1982).</p>
                    <p>“The Edition of the Works of Wm. Blake” by “The Blake Press at Edmonton,” vol.
1.</p>
                    <p>(d) <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>: See entry under <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>,
copy T, in Part I, Section A.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Lamb.</hi> A Christmas Greeting to their friends printed by Betty
&amp; Ralph Sollitt at The Redcoat Press, Westport, Conn. [1952]. A folded sheet making 4 leaves; text
only.</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">El Matrimonio del Cielo y del Infierno, y Cantos de Inocencia y de
Experiencia.</hi> Tr. Soledad Capurro. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 158, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002,
2004)&gt; C. §3<hi rend="s">a.</hi> ed. (1997) D. §4<hi rend="s">a.</hi> ed. (2001) E. Prólogo de Luis
Cernuda. 5<hi rend="s">a.</hi> ed. (2003); ISBN: 8475220878.</p>
                    <p>The translation is from the Keynes text, “aceptada generalmente como edición
canónica.”</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Obra poética.</hi> Tr. Pablo Mañé Garzón (Barcelona: Ediciones 29,
1992) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994, 1999, 2003)&gt; D. 4<hi rend="s">a.</hi> ed. (2004) 8°, 258 pp.</p>
                    <p>The copyright date for Ediciones 29 is 1980, apparently referring to <hi rend="i">Obra
Completa en Poesía</hi>, tr. Pablo Mañé Garzón (1980) Libros Río Nuevo &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p.
159&gt;.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake.</hi> Ed. W. B. Yeats. (1893) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #293A-E&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 161&gt; G. (New York: Carlton House [c. 1950]) viii,
278 pp. H. (1969) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #293F&gt; I. (1979) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 161&gt; J. (2002)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Poems of William Blake.</hi> Selected by Amelia H. Munson. (New York,
1964) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #295&gt; B. Illustrations by William Blake. Collector’s Edition Bound in
Genuine Leather. (Norwalk, Connecticut: Easton Press [1999]) 139 pp.</p>
                    <p>“William Blake” (1-9).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Portable Blake.</hi> Ed. Alfred Kazin. (1946) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#306&gt;</p>
                    <p>See entry in Part VI under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>,
chapters 7 and 8.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Selected Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Northrop Frye. (1953)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #319&gt;</p>
                    <p>See entry in Part VI under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>,
chapter 13.</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">Sete Livros Iluminados.</hi> Tr. Manuel Portela. (Lisboa [Portugal]:
Antígona, 2005) 8°, 175 pp., 32 good color reproductions; ISBN: 9726081815. In Portuguese.</p>
                    <p>Manuel Portela, “Introdução: Oficina gráfica &amp; forja divina: a gravura como
cosmogonia” (5-22); “Notas da introdução” (23-24); “Notas textuais” (25-31); “Pequeno glossário
mitológico de William Blake” adapted from Damon’s <hi rend="i">Blake Dictionary</hi> (1965)
(159-73)—with a loose leaf of “Errata.”</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">All Religions are One, There is No Natural Religion, The Book of Thel,
America, Europe, Song of Los</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Book of Los</hi> are given, with English and Portuguese on
facing pages.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience Shewing the Two Contrary States of
the Human Soul.</hi> Engraved by Derek Cowan. (Cumberland [British Columbia]: Cowan &amp; Tetley, 2001)
edition of 20, horizontal folio, 13 leaves printed on one side only; no ISBN.</p>
                    <p>Text and un-Blake-like white-line designs for 3 poems from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>
and 11 from <hi rend="i">Experience.</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> [pls. 3, 6, 8, 16, 18, 24, 27] and 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> [pls. 29, 33-34, 36, 43, 46-48, 53]. (Manchester [England]: Manchester
Etching Workshop, 1983) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 135-36&gt;</p>
                    <p>According to a flyer of “Aug. 2005,” Jacqueline Marshall (of Lymm, Cheshire), “a
colourist for the Manchester Etching Workshop” edition of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, still has “a few
prints [which] were never coloured” and which she would be “willing to colour . . . to order . . . from my
own master set”: 2 complete sets at £2,500, plus individual prints of all save “The Divine Image” at
£60 (“A Cradle Song,” pl. 1) to £300 (“The Little Girl Found,” pl. 2, which “takes well over five
hours” to color).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">The Tiger.</hi> Illustration by Theodore Ross and printed by Carl J. H.
Anderson, Franklin Printing Company, Philadelphia. The paper is Linweave Text, White Antique Finish. ([No
place:] Linweave Limited Editions, 1931). A sheet folded to make 4 leaves with a strange design.</p>
                    <p>William Blake Archive &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;</p>
                    <p>The Archive announced in 2005 catalogues of the Blake holdings in the Ashmolean Museum
(Oxford), Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery, British Museum, collection of Robert N. Essick (Altadena,
California), Fitzwilliam Museum (Cambridge), Fogg Art Museum (Harvard), J. Paul Getty Museum (Los Angeles),
Glasgow University Library, Houghton Library (Harvard), Huntington Library and Art Gallery (San Marino,
California), Library of Congress (Washington, DC), Metropolitan Museum (New York), Museum of Fine Arts
(Boston), National Gallery of Art (Washington, DC), National Gallery of Victoria (Melbourne), New York Public
Library, Pierpont Morgan Library, Royal Institution of Cornwall, Tate (London), Victoria &amp; Albert Museum
(London), Whitworth Art Gallery (Manchester), and Yale Center for British Art (New Haven).</p>
                    <p>In 2005 the Archive was “designated an Approved Edition by the Modern Language
Association,” its first electronic “seal.”</p>
                  </div7>
                </div6>
                <pb id="p40-13" n="13"/>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part II: Reproductions of Drawings and Paintings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section A: Illustrations of Individual Authors</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, watercolors</p>
                    <p>History: The 19 watercolors were sold by the London dealer Libby Howie in February or
March 2005 for £6,000,000 to “Marburg BVI,” said to be a Swiss corporation but perhaps a private
collector not necessarily Swiss; the export of the drawings was stopped by the British Arts Minister, Estelle
Morris, until 30 May, extended to 30 September 2005, to enable a British institution to purchase the drawings,
valued at £8,800,000 in the Reviewing Committee report of 16 March 2005
(&lt;http://213.225.138.141/resources/assets//R/revcom_case043_note_doc_6927. doc&gt;); the watercolors were
sent to Switzerland.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n22">22. The details above are from Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 154. For information about the Blair designs in 2005, see British
Department for Culture, Media and Sport 30 March 2005
(&lt;http://www.culture.gov.uk/global/press_notices/archive_2005/dcms051_05. htm&gt;); entries for media
reports in Part VI under Anon., Blackstock, Demetriou, Kennedy, Noah, and Reynolds.</note></p>
                    <p>The leaf with sketches for an alternative title page (two versions, recto and verso)
&lt;Butlin #614&gt; was given in 2001 by Gertrude Weyhe Dennis to the Pierpont Morgan Library (according to
Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 [spring 2006]: 154).</p>
                    <p>Dante</p>
                    <p>Reproductions of Blake’s watercolors were added to the William Blake Archive in
2005.</p>
                    <p>Thomas Gray</p>
                    <p>Reproductions of Blake’s watercolors were added to the William Blake Archive in
2005.</p>
                    <p>Edward Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797)</p>
                    <p>*Young, Edward. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts: The Poem Illustrated with Water Colours by
William Blake.</hi> Commentary by Robin Hamlyn. [3 vols.] (London: Folio Society, 2005) folio (two volumes of
color facsimiles without title page) and 4° (the Hamlyn volume which supplies the title page), xx, 362
pp.</p>
                    <p>According to the colophons in vols. 1-2, “This facsimile edition of Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> has been reproduced by digital photography . . . printed by Bath Press, Blantyre,
on Modigliani Neve paper.” 1,000 numbered copies for sale to members of the Folio Society and 20 lettered
copies which are not for sale. The leaves (16½″ × 12 13/16″) are virtually the same as the leaves on
which Blake made his drawings (c. 16½″ × 12 7/8″) and significantly smaller than the leaves onto which
the drawings are mounted (20½″ × 15½″).</p>
                    <p>Hamlyn, with a workmanlike critical commentary on each watercolor, notes “how
carefully Blake usually followed Edward Young’s words” (vii).</p>
                  </div7>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Section B: Collections and Selections</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>*Stevens, Bethan. <hi rend="i">The British Museum: William Blake.</hi> (London: British
Museum Press, 2005) square 12°, 96 pp., 56 reproductions, mostly in color; ISBN: 0714126454 and ISBN 13:
9780714126456.</p>
                    <p>Each reproduction is generally preceded by a page of description or quotation of the
text illustrated.</p>
                    <p>Reviews</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Sunday Herald</hi> [Glasgow] 27 Nov. 2005 (One of the “Greatest Reads
of 2005”).</p>
                    <p>§<hi rend="i">Antiques Magazine</hi> 14-20 Jan. 2006.</p>
                    <p>*<hi rend="i">William Blake Stained Glass Colouring Book.</hi> Rendered by Marty Noble.
(Mineola [New York]: Dover Publications, 2005) 4°, 16 leaves and images; ISBN: 0486446670.</p>
                  </div7>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part III: Commercial Book Engravings</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Adams, Michael, <hi rend="i">New Royal Geographical Magazine</hi> (1793, 1794)</p>
                  <p>1793 New Location: Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>1794 New Location: Cambridge (in 48 parts).</p>
                  <p>Adams, Michael, <hi rend="i">New Royal Geographical Magazine</hi> (?1794)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Cambridge; also reproduced by Primary Source Microfilm.</p>
                  <p>Adams, Michael, <hi rend="i">New Royal System of Universal Geography</hi> (Hogg,
?1794)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Cambridge, Leeds.</p>
                  <p>Allen, Charles, <hi rend="i">Roman History</hi> (1797)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: British Library, Cambridge, Edinburgh.</p>
                  <p>Allen, Charles, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi> (1797)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Cambridge (2; 1 from Keynes Collection).</p>
                  <p>Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando Furioso</hi> (1783, 1785, 1791, 1799)</p>
                  <p>1783 New Location: Edinburgh.</p>
                  <p>1785 New Locations: Glasgow, National Library of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>1791 New Location: Oxford (Taylorian).</p>
                  <p>1799 New Locations: National Library of Wales, Trinity College (Dublin).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi> (1793)</p>
                  <p>Primary Source Microfilm reproduced it in their Eighteenth Century Collection series (by
2005).</p>
                  <p>Blake’s engraving was reprinted in <hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi>
(1799).</p>
                  <p>Bible</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-14" n="14"/>
                  <p>Under the terms of the “Memorandum of Agreement between William Blake and John Linnell.
March 25<hi rend="s">th</hi> 1823,” “J.L. [was] to find Copper Plates” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 386).
According to his “Account of Expenses of the Book of Job,” Linnell paid for 3 lots each of “6 copper
Plates for Job” in “1823” at £1.0.0, £1.2.0, and £1.3.7, and for 2 more in 1825 [by 3 March] at 6<hi
rend="i">s</hi> (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 804).</p>
                  <p>The 18 <hi rend="i">Job</hi> plates acquired in 1823 were almost certainly the 18 plates
(pls. 3-14, 16, 18-22) of uniform width (17.0 to 17.2 cm.), height (21.8 to 22.1 cm.), and thickness (0.145 to
0.160 cm.), all bearing the same copperplate-maker’s mark slanting down from the top left corner of R
PONTIFEX &amp; C | 22 LISLE STREET | SOHO LONDON. Crossing marks on the versos of these plates show that they
were cut from 3 large sheets of copper which already bore these crossing marks.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> The cost of the 18 plates was at the rate of 11.6 g for a
penny. <note id="n23">23. Mei-Ying Sung, “Technical and Material Studies of William Blake’s Engraved 
<hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi> (1826),” Nottingham Trent University PhD (2005) 148-51,
generously sent to me.</note></p>
                  <p>The 2 plates acquired early in 1825 are almost certainly pls. 15 and 17, which are on the
versos of plates originally used for pls. II-III of Henri Louis Duhamel du Monceau, <hi rend="i">A Practical
Treatise of Husbandry</hi>, [tr. John Mills] (1762), which differ significantly from the first 18 plates in
width (16.6 cm.), height (20.8 and 20.2 cm.), and thickness (0.100 and 0.106 cm.). The cost of the Duhamel
plates was at the rate of 8.6 g for a penny.</p>
                  <p>The 2 plates not accounted for in Linnell’s “Account of Expenses of the Book of
Job” are apparently pls. 1-2, the title page and the first design, which are narrower (16.5 and 16.6 cm.),
shorter (21.3 and 20.0 cm.), and thinner (0.143 and 0.114 cm.) than the first 18 plates purchased. Pl. 1 bears
vertically at the bottom right corner the copperplate-maker’s mark of G HARRIS | N<hi rend="s">o</hi>
31<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> | SHOE LANE | LONDON (part of the
first line cut off), and pl. 2 has the PONTIFEX mark. At least the second of them, pl. 2, must have been
acquired before 1825, for at Samuel Palmer’s “never-to-be forgotten first interview” with Blake, “the
copper of the first plate—‘Thus did Job continually’ [<hi rend="i">Job</hi> pl. 2]—was lying on the
table where he had been working at it” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 391); the date must be before 9 October
1824 when Palmer called on Blake with Linnell (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 400). At the rate of the other
PONTIFEX plates (11.6 g for a penny), the cost would have been 5<hi rend="i">s</hi> 8<hi rend="i">d.</hi>
	<note id="n24">24. Not “N” 3″ as in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> p. 518.</note></p>
                  <p>Blair, Robert, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808, 1813 . . .)</p>
                  <p>1808 A-B New Locations: Aberdeen, Birmingham, Glasgow, Leeds, Manchester, National
Library of Wales, Newcastle, Sheffield, Trinity College (Dublin).</p>
                  <p>1813 C-D New Location: Southampton.</p>
                  <p>Blower, Elizabeth, <hi rend="i">Maria</hi> (1785)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Bristol.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Boydell’s Graphic Illustrations of the Dramatic Works of Shakspeare</hi>
([?1803])</p>
                  <p>New Location: Birmingham.</p>
                  <p>Brown, John, <hi rend="i">Elements of Medicine</hi> (1795)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Birmingham, Cambridge, Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p>Burger, Gottfried Augustus, <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi> (1796)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Cambridge (3 from Keynes Collection), Institute of German Studies.</p>
                  <p>New Entry</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi> (1799)</p>
                  <p>Title page 1: THE | CABINET of the ARTS. | - | A SERIES OF ENGRAVINGS, | BY | 
<hi rend="i">English Artists</hi>, | FROM ORIGINAL DESIGNS, BY | <hi rend="i">Stothard, Burney, Harding, Corbould,
Van Assen, Potter</hi> [sic], | <hi rend="i">Cosway, Paul Sandby, Mather Brown, Catton, &amp;c.</hi> | = |
[<hi rend="i">Vignette</hi>: London: Published by Castildine &amp; Dunn, Copper-Plate Printers, N<hi
rend="s">o</hi> 9, Bagnio Court, Newgate Street, February 3, 1796.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n25" type="note">25</ref> | | = | London, | M.DCC.XCIX. [1799] | PRICE FIVE GUINEAS, BOUND. 
<note id="n25">25. The design is assigned to Stothard by A. C. Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard</hi> (1906)
38.</note></p>
                  <p>Title page 2: THE | CABINET | OF THE | <hi rend="i">ARTS.</hi> | = | A SERIES OF
ENGRAVINGS; | BY |
<table rows="5" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>STOTHARD,</cell>
<cell>BURNEY,</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>HARDING,</cell>
<cell>CORBOULD,</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>VAN ASSEN,</cell>
<cell>PORTER [sic],</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>COSWAY,</cell>
<cell>PAUL SANDBY,</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>MATHER BROWN,</cell>
<cell>CATTON, |</cell>
</row></table><hi rend="i">&amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi> | - | London, | M.DCC.XCIX. [1799] | PRICE FIVE
GUINEAS.</p>
                  <p>Copies: Bibliothèque Nationale (Paris, with 95 prints), British Library (shelfmark
1401.i.25, with 94 prints), Essick (with 64 separate prints), Yale Center for British Art (2; 1 with 117
engravings printed on rectos, 1 with 160 prints on 117 leaves, including duplicates of some portraits).</p>
                  <p>Size: 24.5 × 17.1 cm., varying slightly (Essick copy).</p>
                  <p>Paper: Uniform off-white wove paper with watermarks (in the Essick copy) of 1794 | J
WHATMAN (fragments on ff. 9, 16, 25, 49, 52, 55-56, 63, 66), and widely spaced “5” and “6” (f. 4,
apparently a single inserted leaf). Many leaves show three deckled edges, indicating that these leaves have
not been cut or trimmed and that they are halves of a small sheet, though only a few leaves are visibly
conjugate. (The size alone would have suggested that it was a quarto.)</p>
                  <p>Contents: The prints bear no number or indication of where they should be placed, and the
only description of the contents is on the two title pages—prints designed by Mather Brown, Burney, Catton,
Corbould, Cosway, Harding, Potter or Porter, Paul Sandby, Stothard, Van Assen, “&amp;c.” However, the
Essick copy has no print with the name of Burney, Corbould, Cosway, Harding, or Paul Sandby, and two-thirds of
the prints are by others: Anon. (19, some of which could be by
<pb id="p40-15" n="15"/>
the named artists), G. Bickham, Jr. (2), C. H. Coypel (1), Isaac Cruikshank (3), Gillot (2), Sir Joshua
Reynolds (1), Charles Reuben Ryley (2, including one engraved by Blake), Tassie (1), I. Taylor (2), and W.
Turner (10).</p>
                  <p>Sources of the Prints: The prints with dates or which have been traced to dated works
appeared in <hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi> (London: T. Bellamy and T. Evans, 1793), 
<hi rend="i">Harrison’s British Magazine</hi> (1782-83), Samuel Johnson, <hi rend="i">Rasselas</hi> (London: E.
and S. Harding, 1796), Thomas Townshend, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (London: E. and S. Harding, 1796) (8 Stothard
prints), and 1797 (f. 42).</p>
                  <p>Half the prints (31) seem to come from three books: Townshend (8), a book on the English
royal family (10), alternating roughly with a book on English places (13).</p>
                  <p>Note that the plates identified were originally commissioned by several different
booksellers—T. Bellamy and T. Evans, Castildine and Dunn, E. and S. Harding, and Harrison. Apparently an
anonymous bookseller—none is named on the two title pages—acquired a miscellaneous collection of
copperplates originally commissioned by various different booksellers and had them printed on sheets of
uniform paper, two prints per sheet as in a small folio.</p>
                  <p>The prints in <hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi> (1793) are on soft wove
paper 28.2 × 22.5 cm.; those in <hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi> (1799) are on paper watermarked
1794 | J WHATMAN. The prints in <hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi> are therefore not remainders from
<hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi> but new printings. Description: The work consists of two
title pages plus 64 prints printed on rectos only (in the Essick copy).</p>
                  <p>All the prints probably appeared in previous publications; another print of “French
Revolution” (C. R. Ryley-Charles Grignion) appeared in <hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi>
(1793), and 8 of the Stothard plates previously appeared in Thomas Townshend, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (1796).
<hi rend="i">The Cabinet of the Arts</hi> (1799) seems to be a nonce collection, a pair of title pages
followed by prints chosen irregularly for their availability without much regard for the artists named on the
title pages. Copies vary disconcertingly after the title pages, with 64, 94, 95, 117, and 160 prints. Only the
copy in the Essick Collection includes Blake’s print of “F: Revolution” for <hi rend="i">Bellamy’s
Picturesque Magazine</hi> (1793) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #418&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Blake’s connection with the work was first identified in the copy acquired by Robert N.
Essick in the eBay auction of July 2005 (£88) and reported in his “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (2006): 158-61, with reproductions of the first title page and the Blake print.</p>
                  <p>The leaf with the first title page was printed twice, once with the typeset text in black
and once with the engraving in brown.</p>
                  <p>Catullus, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (1795)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>Chaucer, Geoffrey, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> (1782)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, Leeds, Manchester, Newcastle.</p>
                  <p>Commins, Thomas, <hi rend="i">An Elegy, Set to Music</hi> (1786)</p>
                  <p>A copy of Blake’s print was given in 1998 by Charles Ryskamp to the Pierpont Morgan
Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n26">26. Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4
(spring 2006): 181.</note></p>
                  <p>Cumberland, George, <hi rend="i">An Attempt to Describe Hafod</hi> (1796)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: British Library, Cambridge, Glasgow, National Library of Scotland,
Sheffield, Southampton, Trinity College (Dublin).</p>
                  <p>Cumberland, George, <hi rend="i">Outlines from the Ancients</hi> (1829)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Birmingham, Cambridge, Edinburgh, Manchester.</p>
                  <p>Cumberland, George, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> (1796)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Cambridge (2; 1 from Keynes Collection), Edinburgh, Manchester.</p>
                  <p>Dante, Blake’s Illustrations of (1838)</p>
                  <p>New Location: London.</p>
                  <p>Reproductions of Blake’s engravings (Essick set) were added to the William Blake
Archive.</p>
                  <p>Darwin, Erasmus, <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> (1791, 1795, 1799)</p>
                  <p>1791 New Locations: Aberdeen, Birmingham, Glasgow, King’s College (London), National
Library of Wales, Sheffield, Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p>1795 New Locations: Birmingham, Cambridge, Liverpool, Manchester, Southampton, Wellcome
Library.</p>
                  <p>1799 New Locations: Birmingham, Durham, Edinburgh, Glasgow, National Library of Wales,
Newcastle, Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p>Darwin, Erasmus, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> (1806)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, Birmingham, Edinburgh, London, Nottingham, Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p>Earle, James, <hi rend="i">Practical Observations
                  on the Operation for the Stone</hi> (1793, 1796, 1803)</p>
                  <p>1793 New Locations: British Library, Cambridge, King’s College (London), Leeds,
Liverpool.</p>
                  <p>1796 New Locations: King’s College (London), Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p>1803 New Locations: Edinburgh, Glasgow, Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p>Emlyn, Henry, <hi rend="i">A Proposition for a New Order in Architecture</hi> (1781,
1784)</p>
                  <p>1781 New Location: Bodleian.</p>
                  <p>Enfield, William, <hi rend="i">The Speaker</hi> (1774, 1781, 1785, 1795, 1797)</p>
                  <p>1781 New Locations: Aberdeen, National Library of Wales.</p>
                  <p>1797 New Locations: Cambridge, Liverpool.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-16" n="16"/>
                  <p>Euler, Leonard, <hi rend="i">Elements of Algebra</hi> (1797)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, Birmingham, Cambridge, Edinburgh, Newcastle.</p>
                  <p>Flaxman, John, <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> (1817)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Birmingham.</p>
                  <p>Flaxman, John, <hi rend="i">The Iliad</hi> (1805)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Birmingham, Brasenose College (Oxford), Bristol, Cambridge, Edinburgh,
Glasgow, Liverpool, Manchester, Newcastle, Queen’s College (Oxford).</p>
                  <p>Flaxman, John, <hi rend="i">A Letter to the Committee</hi> (1799)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>Fuseli, John Henry, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting</hi> (1801)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Leeds, Liverpool, Warburg Institute.</p>
                  <p>Gay, John, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793, [1811])</p>
                  <p>Copies of unrecorded date New Locations: Birmingham, Durham, Edinburgh, Leeds, London,
Nottingham, Sheffield.</p>
                  <p>[1811] New Locations: Durham, Manchester.</p>
                  <p>[Gough, Richard], <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments in Great Britain</hi>, III (1786)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Cambridge, Newcastle.</p>
                  <p>See Jerome Bertram, <hi rend="i">Gough’s Sepulchral Monuments: Being a Catalogue of
Material Relating to Sepulchral Monuments in the Gough Manuscripts of the Bodleian Library</hi> (Oxford: J.
Bertram, 2004) 241 pp.</p>
                  <p>Hamilton, G., <hi rend="i">The English School</hi> (1831-32)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, British Library (French title page only), Edinburgh.</p>
                  <p>Hartley, David, <hi rend="i">Observations on Man</hi> (1791)</p>
                  <p>1791 two versions New Locations: Aberdeen, Cambridge (2; 1 from Keynes Collection),
Edinburgh, National Library of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Leeds, National Library of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Designs to A Series of Ballads</hi> (1802)</p>
                  <p>New Location: National Library of Wales (52 pp.).</p>
                  <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi> (1800)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Birmingham, Warburg Institute.</p>
                  <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">The Life . . . of William Cowper</hi> (1803-04)</p>
                  <p>1803-04 New Locations: Leeds, Manchester, National Library of Wales, Newcastle.</p>
                  <p>Second edition of vols. 1-2 New Locations: Aberdeen, Cambridge (Keynes Collection),
Glasgow.</p>
                  <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi> (1809)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Birmingham, Glasgow, King’s College (London), Manchester, Queen’s
College (Oxford).</p>
                  <p>Hayley, William, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi> (1803, 1807)</p>
                  <p>1803 New Locations: Birmingham, Leeds, Manchester, National Library of Wales.</p>
                  <p>Henry, Thomas, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Albert de Haller</hi> (1783)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Birmingham, Imperial College, Leeds, National Library of Wales, Wellcome
Library.</p>
                  <p>Hoare, Prince, <hi rend="i">Academic Correspondence</hi> (1804)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>Hoare, Prince, <hi rend="i">An Inquiry</hi> (1806)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: British Library, Cambridge, London, National Library of Wales.</p>
                  <p>Hogarth, William, <hi rend="i">Works</hi> (1788 ff.)</p>
                  <p>1795 New Locations: Ashmolean Museum, London.</p>
                  <p>The copperplate in Houghton Library is 45 cm. wide, 58 cm. high, and 0.3 to 0.5 cm.
thick, and is stamped on the verso on the center and lower left with the name of the copperplate maker: JONES
N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 48 | SHOE LANE LONDON.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n27">27. As I am told by Caroline Duroselle-Melish, Assistant Curator, Houghton Library, Harvard
University.</note></p>
                  <p>Hunter, John, <hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi> (1793)</p>
                  <p>1793 4° and 8° New Locations (A and B not distinguished): Aberdeen, Glasgow, School of
Oriental and African Studies, Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p>1793 B New Locations: London, National Library of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>Josephus, Flavius, <hi rend="i">Works</hi> (1785-1800?)</p>
                  <p>A New Locations: Bodleian, Leeds, National Library of Wales, University College
(London).</p>
                  <p>B New Locations: Aberdeen, Manchester.</p>
                  <p>D New Location: Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>E New Locations: Aberdeen, Bodleian (“Date of publication from the Denby Mercury, 1
February 1792”), Cambridge, Durham, National Library of Scotland, University College (London).</p>
                  <p>Note: The descriptions of most of these works in COPAC are so vague as to make it very
difficult to identify them with editions listed in <hi rend="i">BB.</hi></p>
                  <p>Kimpton, Edward, <hi rend="i">History of the Holy Bible</hi> (1781)</p>
                  <p>A New Location: Manchester.</p>
                  <p>Lavater, John Caspar, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi> (1788, 1789, 1794)</p>
                  <p>1788 New Locations: Aberdeen, Warburg Institute.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-17" n="17"/>
                  <p>1789 New Locations: Birmingham, Cambridge (2), Institute of Germanic Studies, Wellcome
Library.</p>
                  <p>1794 New Locations: Cambridge, National Library of Wales, Trinity College (Dublin).</p>
                  <p>Lavater, J. C., <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> (1788-99; 1792; 1810)</p>
                  <p>1788-99 New Locations: Aberdeen, Birmingham, Cambridge (2; 1 from Keynes Collection),
Glasgow (“1789-1810”), Institute of Germanic Studies, National Library of Wales.</p>
                  <p>1792 [i.e., ?1817] New Locations: Christ Church (Oxford), Liverpool (vols. 1-2), National
Library of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>1810 New Locations: British Library, Glasgow, Manchester, Newcastle, Warburg
Institute.</p>
                  <p>Malkin, Benjamin Heath, <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi> (1806)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Cambridge (2; 1 from Keynes Collection), Liverpool, National Library of
Wales, Sheffield.</p>
                  <p>Nicholson, William, <hi rend="i">Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi> (1782, 1787,
1790, 1796)</p>
                  <p>1782 New Locations: Imperial College, Manchester, National Library of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>1787 New Locations: Aberdeen, Cambridge, Imperial College, King’s College (London),
Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, Vol. VIII (1782, 1784, 1792)</p>
                  <p>1784 New Location: Edinburgh.</p>
                  <p>Locations of indeterminate date in COPAC: Bristol, National Library of Wales.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, Vol. IX (1782, 1785, 1793)</p>
                  <p>1782 New Location: Bodleian (2).</p>
                  <p>1785 New Location: Edinburgh.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, Vols. X-XI (1783, 1785, 1793)</p>
                  <p>1783 New Location: Edinburgh.</p>
                  <p>1785 New Location: Edinburgh.</p>
                  <p>Olivier, J., <hi rend="i">Fencing Familiarized</hi> (1780)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>Rees, Abraham, <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> (1820)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, Cambridge, Edinburgh, Imperial College, Leeds, Liverpool, London
School of Economics, Manchester, Wellcome Library.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi> (1825, 1826)</p>
                  <p>1825 New Location: National Library of Wales.</p>
                  <p>Ritson, Joseph, ed., <hi rend="i">A Select Collection of English Songs</hi> (1783)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, Birmingham, Cambridge (2; 1 from Keynes Collection), Edinburgh,
Glasgow, Newcastle.</p>
                  <p>Scott, John, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> (1782, 1786)</p>
                  <p>1782 New Locations: Aberdeen, Cambridge, Edinburgh, Sheffield, Trinity College.</p>
                  <p>1786 New Locations: Birmingham, Liverpool, National Library of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>Seally, John, and Israel Lyons, <hi rend="i">A Complete Geographical Dictionary</hi>
(?1784, 1787)</p>
                  <p>?1784 New Location: Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>1787 New Location: British Library.</p>
                  <p>Shakespeare, William, <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi> (1802, 1832)</p>
                  <p>1802 New Locations: Birmingham, Durham, Leeds, New College (Oxford).</p>
                  <p>1832 New Locations: British Library, Manchester.</p>
                  <p>Shakespeare, William, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi> (1802, 1805, 1811)</p>
                  <p>A in Parts New Locations: British Library (perhaps this is the 10 plays without title
page but with a prospectus).</p>
                  <p>B 10 vols. 1805 New Location: Aberdeen.</p>
                  <p>C 9 vols. 1805 New Locations: Leeds, National Library of Scotland, National Library of
Wales, Nottingham.</p>
                  <p>D 1811 New Locations: British Library, Cambridge, Edinburgh, Nottingham, Sheffield.</p>
                  <p>Stedman, J. G., <hi rend="i">Narrative, of a Five Years’ Expedition, against the
Revolted Negroes of Surinam</hi> (1796, 1806, 1813)</p>
                  <p>1796 New Locations: Aberdeen, All Souls College (Oxford), Cambridge, Edinburgh, Imperial
College, Institute of Commonwealth Studies, London, Rhodes House (Oxford), Southampton, Trinity College
(Oxford).</p>
                  <p>1806 New Locations: Glasgow, Liverpool, Rhodes House (Oxford).</p>
                  <p>1813 New Locations: Manchester, New College (Oxford).</p>
                  <p>1796</p>
                  <p>According to an advertisement in the <hi rend="i">Morning Chronicle</hi> for 21 July 1796
(discovered by Angus Whitehead),
<q>
In a few days will be published, in two vols. large quarto, price three Guineas in boards, ornamented with 80
Copper Plates, consisting of Maps and Views, Figures of the Natives, Subjects of Natural History and
Curiosity, &amp;c. all from Drawings made on the Spot by the Author, and executed by Bartolozzi, Blake,
Holloway, Benedetti, &amp;c.
</q></p>
                  <p>NARRATIVE of an EXPEDITION against the Revolted Negroes in the Colony of Sarinam [i.e.,
Surinam], in South America; from the Year 1772 to 1777; with some Elucidations of the Natural History of that
Country, and a Description of its Productions. Also, an Account of the Indians of Guiana, and the Negroes of
Guinea.</p>
                  <p>By Lieut. Col. STEDMAN, then on actual service in that Colony.</p>
                  <p>Printed for J. Johnson, in St. Paul’s Church Yard.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-18" n="18"/>
                  <p>The ad. abbreviates and paraphrases the title; to <hi rend="i">“drawings made by the
Author”</hi> it adds, after <hi rend="i">“made,” “on the Spot”</hi>; the engravers are not named on
the title page, but they are so listed in the ad. in Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> 24 (Feb.
1796). Johnson deposited the statutory nine copies in Stationers’ Hall on 25 July 1796 
(<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 256), and the book was reviewed in the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> 24 (Sept. 1796):
237, suggesting that it was indeed published within “a few days” of 21 July 1796. Stedman was promoted to
Lieutenant Colonel on 3 May 1796 (<hi rend="i">DNB</hi>), too late to alter the engraved title page where he
is entitled Captain.</p>
                  <p>1813</p>
                  <p>A copy of the 1813 edition offered at Christie’s (New York), 14 June 2005, lot 214, is
colored in the style of the 1796 edition, not the different style of coloring in the 1806 and 1813 editions;
perhaps the colored prints were remainders from the 1796 edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n28">28. According to Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 162.</note></p>
                  <p>Stuart, James, and Nicholas Revett, <hi rend="i">Antiquities of Athens</hi>, vol. 3
(1794)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, All Soul’s College (Oxford), Bristol, Bodleian, Cambridge,
Corpus Christi College (Oxford), King’s College (London), New College (Oxford), Newcastle, Sheffield,
University College (London).</p>
                  <p>Varley, John, <hi rend="i">A Treatise on Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi> (1828)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, Bodleian, Cambridge, Manchester.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Vetusta Monumenta</hi>, vol. 2 (?1789)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Birmingham, British Library (4), Cambridge, Edinburgh, King’s College
(London), Lampeter, Liverpool, National Library of Scotland, Newcastle.</p>
                  <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">Pastorals</hi> (1821)</p>
                  <p>New Location: Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>Whitaker, John, <hi rend="i">The Seraph</hi> (1818-28; 1819-28; 1825-28)</p>
                  <p>A-B ?1818-28 and ?1819-28 New Locations: Birmingham, Glasgow, King’s College (London),
Manchester.</p>
                  <p>C 1825-28 New Locations: British Library, King’s College (London), Leeds, National
Library of Wales.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The Wit’s Magazine</hi> (1784-85)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: California State University (Fresno), Cambridge (2; 1 from Keynes
Collection), Free Library of Philadelphia, Sheffield.</p>
                  <p>Primary Source Microfilm reproduced it in their Eighteenth Century Collection.</p>
                  <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary, <hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real Life</hi> (1791, 1796)</p>
                  <p>1791 New Locations: Birmingham, Bodleian (2), Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>1796 New Locations: Bristol (2), Cambridge (Keynes Collection).</p>
                  <p>A copy of the 1796 edition offered in John Windle Catalogue 40 (Nov. 2005), #64, has
“plates . . . so well-margined that in one plate the edge of the margin has text from another book, perhaps
indicating that the plates were printed on paper left over from another printing.” Windle generously sent me
a reproduction of the print (“Be calm, my child”) at p. 94 which shows quite clearly at the outer (right)
margin of the print the initial letters of a page, at the top half with fragments too small to identify, at
the bottom half with “r”, “f”, “r”, “t”, “t”, blank, “n”, “E”, two blanks,
“ri”, “p”, “d”, two blanks, and “a”. The page and font size are larger than those for Mary
Wollstonecraft. Presumably the blank part of the leaf was the inner margin; Blake himself used the wide inner
margins of his quarto <hi rend="i">Designs to A Series of Ballads</hi> (1802) for sketches (see 
<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #466)—but not, so far as we know, for printing copperplates.</p>
                  <p>This use of paper for the engravings with previously printed text seems extraordinary.
Copperplates and letterpress were printed on different presses and by different printers; for instance, the
printer of the letterpress for Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Designs to A Series of Ballads</hi> (1802) and his life
of Cowper (1803) was Joseph Seagrave in Chichester, but the printer of the engravings was Catherine Blake in
Felpham. Further, the paper for prints was ordinarily thicker and better than that for letterpress. It was
remarkably casual to use paper previously printed with letterpress for the prints for Mary Wollstonecraft’s
<hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> (1796).</p>
                  <p>We do not know the printers of either the letterpress or the engravings for her book, and
I have not identified the previously printed letterpress text on the plate paper.</p>
                  <p>Young, Edward, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797)</p>
                  <p>New Locations: Aberdeen, British Library, Cambridge (Keynes Collection), London,
Manchester, National Library of Scotland, Newcastle.</p>
                  <p>The only recorded copy in contemporary binding without engravings &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 270, 389&gt; was given in October 2005 by Dr. A. E. K. L. B. Bentley and G. E. Bentley,
Jr., with the rest of their collection to Victoria University Library, University of Toronto.</p>
                  <p>Colored Copies</p>
                  <p>Copies B and J were reproduced in Edward Young, <hi rend="i">The Complaint, and the
Consolation; or, Night Thoughts: Illustrations by William Blake</hi> (Oakland [California]: Octavo Editions,
2004) “digital edition” on CD-ROM.</p>
                  <p>Edition</p>
                  <p>§Young, Edward. <hi rend="i">The Complaint, and the Consolation; or, Night Thoughts:
Illustrations by William Blake.</hi> (Oakland [California]: Octavo Editions, 2004) “digital edition” on
CD-ROM.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-19" n="19"/>
                  <p>Reproductions of colored copies B and J, both in the Rosenwald Collection, with an
18-page commentary by Nicolas Barker.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>§Evans, Jean, <hi rend="i">Library Journal</hi> 129 (2004): 83-84.</p>
                  <p>Sheila A. Spector, <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 16 (2005): 519-23 (Barker
“failed to take advantage of the intellectual progress made in the field over the last century”).</p>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part IV: Catalogues and Bibliographies</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>1957</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Bible: A Catalogue Compiled by
Geoffrey Keynes.</hi> (1957) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #681&gt; §(2003) xii, 53 pp.; ISBN: 0758130732.</p>
                  <p>The 1957 edition includes reproductions of 174 Bible illustrations.</p>
                  <p>2002 May 22-June 22</p>
                  <p>*Ian McKeever. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s ‘Jerusalem,’ The Emanation of the Giant
Albion</hi>: [an exhibition] 22 May-22 June 2002. (London: Alan Cristea Gallery, 2002) 4°, 63 pp.; no
ISBN.</p>
                  <p>Frances Carey, “Ian McKeever, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Jerusalem The Emanation of
the Giant Albion</hi>” (7-13).</p>
                  <p>McKeever’s 21 carborundum etchings are said to be based on (but they do not visually
echo) Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> except that some of them are on typeset pages of Blake’s
text.</p>
                  <p>2005 May</p>
                  <p>§<hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> List of Henry Sotheran Ltd. (London, May 2005).</p>
                  <p>2005 August-September 4</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Cloud &amp; Vision.</hi> Curated by Danielle Arnaud, Jordan Kaplan and
Philip Norman and presented at the Museum of Garden History, London, summer 2005. (London: Parabola, 2005)
4°, 44 pp.; ISBN: 095476174X.</p>
                  <p>The “catalogue” includes:</p>
                  <p>Danielle Arnaud, Jordan Kaplan, and Philip Norman. “The Harmony of Opposition.” 1-2.
(“Why commission artists and writers to produce new works exploring his [Blake’s] ten years living and
working in Hercules Road.”)</p>
                  <p>*Michael Phillips. “Blake’s Lambeth.” 3-11. (The accompanying flyer says that this
is “an edited form of his essay ‘William Blake in Lambeth’” [<hi rend="i">History Today</hi> 50, #11
(Nov. 2000): 18-25].)</p>
                  <p>Jon Newman. “William’s Footprint.” 12-17. (“We look in vain within Blake’s work
for a . . . sense of Lambeth” similar to that of Felpham [12].)</p>
                  <p>Tim Heath. “To Be Divine in a Digital Age.” 18-21. (“Blake would have enjoyed our
multimedia age” [19].)</p>
                  <p>Polly Gould. “The Floating Press.” 22-23. (“I work at a copperplate printing press
. . . on view to the public.”)</p>
                  <p>Manuela Ribadeneira. “Without Contraries is no progression.” 24-25. (“Like almost
all great poets, he [Blake] was an enemy of dualism”; “This text is taken from ‘Innocence and
Experience’ written by Keith Sagar in 2002 as it appears on www.keithsagar.co.uk”.)</p>
                  <p>*Brian Catling. “Lambeth Tenant Extracted Reflections on Blake’s Ghost of a Flea.”
26-27. (Illustrated by juxtaposed representations of Disney’s Jiminy Cricket and Blake’s Ghost of a
Flea.)</p>
                  <p>Phil Coy. Untitled specifications for Auto-cue Monitor and Manual. 28-29. (According to
the first essay above, “Phil Coy’s <hi rend="i">Auto-Cue</hi> (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>) works to
include the audience as participants in the recitations of Blake’s lyrics. The words scrolling through the
auto-cue are presented backwards.”)</p>
                  <p>David Burrows. Untitled page from “Comic Book, work in progress, 2005.” 30-31.</p>
                  <p>David Burrows. “The Sick Rose.” 32-33. (A commentary.)</p>
                  <p>Annie Whiles. Untitled. 34-35. (“I came across <hi rend="i">Glad Day</hi> 1794.”)</p>
                  <p>Andy Harper. Untitled. 36-37.</p>
                  <p>Sarah Woodfine. Untitled. 38-39. (Visual thoughts on Blake’s garden, presumably in
Lambeth.)</p>
                  <p>Tracy Chevalier. “Blake’s Garden.” 40-42. (She is “writing a novel about Blake”
called <hi rend="i">Blake’s Neighbours</hi> which begins with the Blakes naked in their garden, even though
“Blake scholars have effectively demolished the Adam and Eve story as apocryphal” [40].)</p>
                  <p>The exhibits are by David Burrows, Brian Catling (one of the three “new collections of
writings”; <hi rend="i">The Pittancer</hi>, on which he is working “is centred around [sic] Blake”),
Tracy Chevalier, Phil Coy, Polly Gould, Andy Harper, Tim Heath, Jon Newman, Michael Phillips, Manuela
Ribadeneira, and Annie Whiles (“She works with embroidery and appliqué”).</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Andrew Lambirth, “Celebrating William Blake: Andrew Lambirth visits an exhibition in
the first museum of garden history,” <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi> 6 Aug 2005: 39 (The exhibits by 21<hi
rend="s">st</hi>-century artists are “feeble” and “vulgar,” the pamphlet is of “staggering banality
and awfulness,” and the catalogue “is the best thing about the project.”)</p>
                  <p>2005 November</p>
                  <p>*<hi rend="i">Catalogue Forty: William Blake and His Circle: Books of Scholarship, Books
of Beauty.</hi> [Ed. Robert N. Essick.] (San Francisco: John Windle, Antiquarian Bookseller, [Nov.] 2005) 4°,
104 pp., 431 lots; no ISBN.</p>
                  <p>An admirable catalogue, including Blake’s receipt of 5 July 1805 (#1), the copy of
Quincy’s <hi rend="i">English Dispensatory</hi> (1733) with “William Blake his Book” on the title page
(#68), multiple sets of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (#11-13), Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (#20-23), and
Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797) (#65-67), plus “Works by Blake’s Circle: John Flaxman,
Henry Fuseli, and Thomas Stothard” (#405-12), “Blake’s Followers, Including Samuel Palmer, Edward
Calvert, and George Richmond” (#413-23), and “The Wrong William Blake” (#424).</p>
                </div6>
                <pb id="p40-20" n="20"/>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part V: Books Owned by William Blake of London (1757-1827)</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Quincy, John, <hi rend="i">English Dispensatory</hi> (1733)</p>
                  <p>According to John Windle’s catalogue 40 (2005), #68,
<q>
Blake has also noted the price at the front on the free endpaper. Although only a couple of pages bear
markings in ink (underlinings, not writings), over twenty leaves are folded down to emphatically mark those
pages, and numerous other leaves are less obviously dog-eared. . . . Of especial interest is the fact that the
one underlined remedy in the entire book is for itching skin and skin disease. Ackroyd (p. 273) notes that
Blake suffered from a nervous skin condition called “the Erisepilas.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref> . . . Bentley agrees [“uneasily”] that the copy belonged
to Blake, and Essick has pointed out several similarities in letter formation between the signature in this
book and known Blake signatures. <note id="n29">29. The quotation is from Ozias Humphry’s letter of 15 June
1806 to “William” in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969) 178, but <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) xxvii
dismisses the connection of the poet with this letter as a “red herring.”</note></q></p>
                  <p>History: Acquired by the bookseller John Windle &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2001)&gt;;
sold from Windle’s catalogue 40 (2005), #68 (“Price on application”), to an anonymous British
collector.</p>
                  <div7>
                    <head>
                      <title>
                        <hi rend="b">Appendix: Books Owned by the Wrong William Blake (1770-1827)</hi>
                      </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Milton, John</p>
                    <p><hi rend="i">Milton’s Paradise Lost</hi>, ed. Richard Bentley (1732) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 322&gt;</p>
                    <p>The association of the poet with the “WB” whose initials appear in the copy owned
by Michael Phillips is convincingly rejected by Alexander Gourlay, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.2 (fall 2002):
70-71, GEB (pace <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 322), and Jason Snart, “Blake’s Milton: Did Blake Own and
Annotate the 1732 Bentley Edition of Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>?” <hi rend="i">European
Romantic Review</hi> 16 (2005): 79-91, and defended again by Michael Phillips, “Blake’s Annotations in
Context,” <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 16 (2005): 93-95.</p>
                  </div7>
                </div6>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Part VI: Criticism, Biography, and Scholarly Studies</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>Ackroyd, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> (1995) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1996, 1998,
2003, 2004)&gt; F. §<hi rend="i">William Blake: Dichter, Maler, Visionär.</hi> Tr. Thomas Eichhorn.
(München: Albrecht Knaus, 2004). In German.</p>
                  <p>*Ackroyd, Peter. “Oh Come, All Ye Faithful: Inspired by Milton’s formidable personal
piety, William Blake sought to create his own system in words and images to rouse the nation from spiritual
slumber.” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> [London] 26 April 2003, online
&lt;http://arts.guardian.co.uk/features/story/0,,943631,00.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Blake and Yeats: The Contrary Vision.</hi> (1955) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #776&gt; C. §(Temecula [California]: Textbook Publishers, 2003) xvii, 328 pp.; ISBN:
0758144725.</p>
                  <p>*Anon. “Arts Minister Defers Export of William Blake’s Works.” 
<hi rend="i">Artdaily.com</hi> [now defunct] 19 April 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The works are his watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. “Beyond the Grave: Ban saves lost Blake paintings.” <hi rend="i">Herald</hi>
[Glasgow] 30 March 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The Blake paintings are his watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. “Bid to Keep Paintings in Britain.” <hi rend="i">IcScotland.co.uk</hi> [?March
2005], online.</p>
                  <p>About the watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>*Anon. “Bid to Save Blake Art for Nation.” <hi rend="i">BBC News</hi> 31 March 2005,
online &lt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4396725.stm&gt;.</p>
                  <p>The Blake art is the drawings for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. [Associated Press]. “Britain Forbids Export of Blake Watercolors.” 
<hi rend="i">Relish</hi> [Winston-Salem, North Carolina] 3 April 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>Watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. “Britain Halts Export of Rediscovered William Blake Watercolors.” 
<hi rend="i">Baltimore Sun</hi> 30 March 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The watercolors are for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. “Britain Stops Export of Blake Paintings.” <hi rend="i">Kansas City Star</hi>
30 March 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The Blake paintings are his watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. [Associated Press]. “Britain Stops Export of Blake Paintings.” 
<hi rend="i">Newsday</hi> 30 March 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The paintings are watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. “Entertainment: Blake Watercolours Barred from Leaving Country.” 
<hi rend="i">Keralanext.com</hi> [India] 31 March 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The watercolors are those for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. “Export of Lost Blake Watercolours Held Up.” <hi rend="i">Toronto Star</hi> 31
March 2005: A31.</p>
                  <p>“A British buyer now has until May 30 to ante $16.5 million (U.S.) to keep the works
[drawings for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>] in Britain.”</p>
                  <p>*Anon. “Export Stop to Save Blake Watercolours.” <hi rend="i">Rare Book Review</hi>
online, 2005 &lt;www.rarebookreview.com&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Caledonia Books (Glasgow) sold Blake’s 19 Blair watercolors to Paul Williams and
Jeffery Bates for £950, who valued them at £1,000,000, offered them to the Tate for £4,900,000, paused to
settle a lawsuit with Caledonia Books “who said
<pb id="p40-21" n="21"/>
they had not recognized the true significance of the items they had sold,” and sold them for “more than
£5 million” to “an anonymous collector living in America”; “their price has now spiralled to £8.8.
million,” and “Tate Britain is said to be reviewing its position on the paintings.”</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Family Library.—Painters.” <hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris</hi> 9 February 1830:
4.</p>
                  <p>A review of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters,
Sculptors, and Architects</hi> (1830) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1433&gt;: “What a singular being was William
Blake!” The review was first identified and quoted in David Groves, “Blake and the <hi rend="i">Sheffield
Iris</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.3 (winter 2005-06): 125.</p>
                  <p>Anon. “Government Bans Export of William Blake Engravings.” 
<hi rend="i">InTheNews.co.uk</hi> 1 April 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The “engravings” are Blake’s watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Anon. “William Blake: The Illustrator of the Grave, &amp;c.” <hi rend="i">Literary
Gazette</hi> no. 552 (18 Aug. 1827): 540-41. &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1071A&gt;</p>
                  <p>Note: The volume title and the running heads identify the journal as the 
<hi rend="i">Literary Gazette</hi>, but the issue titles give the <hi rend="i">London Literary Gazette.</hi></p>
                  <p>§Antonielli, Arianna. “Trapassare la superficie fenomenica: Il sostrato cristiano e
cabalistico nell’opus blakiano.” <hi rend="i">Confronto Letterario</hi> [University of Pavia] 21, no. 42
(2004): 391-414. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>§Barfoot, C. C. “‘Jerusalem’ as City and Emanation: Places and People in Blake’s
Poetry.” 59-75 of <hi rend="i">Babylon or New Jerusalem? Perceptions of the City in Literature</hi>, ed.
Valeria Tinkler-Villani (Amsterdam: Rodopi, 2005) DQR Studies in Literature.</p>
                  <p>*Beer, John. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Literary Life.</hi> (Basingstoke: Palgrave
Macmillan, 2005) 8°, xi, 250 pp., 23 plates; ISBN: 1403939543 and ISBN 13: 9781403939548.</p>
                  <p>Critically sensitive and rewarding, but with no attempt to add new biographical
details.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Michael O’Neill, “Glory Bound,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 2 Dec.
2005: 32 (“Beer conveys readable information about Blake’s life”).</p>
                  <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> 2nd ed. (2004) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2005)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Addenda</p>
                  <p>See *G. E. Bentley, Jr., “William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and
Discoveries in 2004,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005) with an appendix, “Corrigenda and Addenda
to <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, Second Edition (2004),” 32-33.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>James Fenton, “In My Good Books: James Fenton on the many Lives of William Blake,”
<hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> [London] 24 Dec. 2005: 19 (“Put Gilchrist alongside <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> and you already have an amazing library”).</p>
                  <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “A Portrait of Milton Engraved by William Blake ‘When Three Years
of Age’? A Speculation by Samuel Palmer.” <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 51 (1981):
28-35. &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 368&gt;</p>
                  <p>Palmer’s speculation is merely “idle,” for the etching of the bust of Milton in 
<hi rend="i">The Memoirs of Thomas Hollis</hi> (1780) is identical to copies which Hollis gave away in 1762 and
1765—see David Wilson, “An Idle Speculation by Samuel Palmer: William Blake’s Involvement in
Cipriani’s Portrait of John Milton,” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.1 (spring/summer 2005):
31-36.</p>
                  <p>§Bidney, Martin. “Neo-Blakean Vision in the Verse of Historian E. P. Thompson: The
‘Abstraction’ of Labor and Cultural Capital.” <hi rend="i">Science and Society</hi> 68 (winter
2004-2005): 396-420.</p>
                  <p>§Billigheimer, Rachel V. “Interrelations: Blake and Yeats.” <hi rend="i">ABEI
Journal: Brazilian Journal of Irish Studies</hi> 5 ([São Paulo] 2003): 13-25.</p>
                  <p>*Blackstock, Colin. “William Blake Illustrations Are Found after 165 Years.” 
<hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> [London] 31 Jan. 2002, online
&lt;http://books.guardian.co.uk/news/articles/0,,642281,00.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>The illustrations are for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Blackstone, Bernard. <hi rend="i">English Blake.</hi> (1949) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1212&gt;</p>
                  <p>See entry under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>, chapter
11.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 38, no. 4 (spring [April]
2005)</p>
                  <p>*Robert N. Essick. “Blake in the Marketplace, 2004.” 124-50. (An invaluable
survey.)</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>*Karl Kroeber. Review of <hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed.
Morris Eaves (2003). 150-54. (“The most attractive aspect of the <hi rend="i">Companion</hi>” is its
demonstration that “confronting its [Blake’s art’s] difficulties is the best way” [154].)</p>
                  <p>Jason Whittaker. Review of John B. Pierce, <hi rend="i">The Wond’rous Art: William
Blake and Writing</hi> (2003). 155-57. (“What <hi rend="i">Wond’rous Art</hi> does is to tease interesting
potential from the new bibliography” [156].)</p>
                  <p>*Sibylle Erle. Review of David Weir, <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West: William Blake and
the Oriental Renaissance</hi> (2003). 157-59. (Weir “argues convincingly for Blake’s participation in the
Oriental Renaissance [in London]” [159].)</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 39, no. 1 (summer [July]
2005)</p>
                  <p>*G. E. Bentley, Jr., with the Assistance of Hikari Sato for Japanese Publications.
“William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist
<pb id="p40-22" n="22"/>
of Publications and Discoveries in 2004.” 4-37. (With an appendix, “Corrigenda and Addenda to 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, Second Edition (2004),” 32-33.)</p>
                  <p>*Justin Van Kleeck. “Blake’s Four . . . ‘Zoa’s’?” 38-43. (He remarks,
virtually for the first time, “the presence of an [apparent] apostrophe between the ‘a’ and ‘s’ of
‘Zoas’ on the title page” [39].)</p>
                  <p>*Robert N. Essick. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">A Pastoral Figure</hi>: Some Newly
Revealed Verso Sketches.” 44-47. (His “purpose . . . is to reproduce the heretofore unpublished verso
sketches . . ., describe them, and suggest some ways they can be situated within Blake’s career as an artist
and poet” [44].)</p>
                  <p>David Groves. “‘Great and Singular Genius’: Further References to Blake (and
Cromek) in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine.</hi>” 47-48. (Puffs for Blake’s designs for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> in July 1807 and September 1808.)</p>
                  <p>Howard Jacobson. “Blake’s Proverbs of Hell: St. Paul and the Nakedness of Woman.”
48-49. (Compares Blake’s Proverb of Hell, “The nakedness of woman is the work of God,” with St. Paul’s
first Letter to the Corinthians: “Every woman that prayeth or prophesieth with her head uncovered
dishonoureth her head . . .”.)</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>*Alexander Gourlay. Review of <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work</hi>, ed.
Joyce H. Townsend (2003). 49-54. (“The perspectives are refreshing and often startling, the discoveries are
numerous, and the consequences are substantial for everyone who studies Blake’s art” [49].)</p>
                  <p>Warren Stevenson. “Cold Colloquy.” 54. (A poem.)</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 39, no. 2 (fall [October]
2005)</p>
                  <p>*Justin Van Kleeck. “‘Tenderness &amp; Love Not Uninspird’: Blake’s Re-Vision of
Sentimentalism in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” 60-77.</p>
                  <p>*Angus Whitehead. “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’: The
Will of Henry Banes, Landlord of 3 Fountain Court, Strand, the Last Residence of William and Catherine
Blake.” 78-99. (A remarkably fine essay with fascinating new details about individuals who lived, like
William and Catherine Blake in 1821-27, at 3 Fountain Court, Strand, chiefly Henry Banes [d. 20 Jan. 1829],
“wine cooper” or “vintner,” and his wife Sarah Boucher Banes [1757-March 1824], sister of Catherine
Blake, Richard Best [d. 1839?], watch finisher and escapement maker, and his wife Louiza or Louisa
[1790?-1845?], probably the daughter of Henry and Sarah Banes, and Louisa’s children Charles [b. 1 April
1805], Charlotte Louisa [b. 16 Aug. 1807], Elizabeth [b. 19 Dec. 1809], Thomas [b. 4 Dec. 1813], print colorer
and painter, and Richard John [b. 20 March 1815], painter, nephews and nieces of Catherine Blake, and John
Barrow [1757-1838], print colorer, printseller [e.g., of Blake’s “Mrs Q” (1820)], and artist. The will
of Henry Banes [drawn 9 Dec. 1826, proved 14 Feb. 1829] was witnessed by John Barrow, the executrix was Louiza
Best, and the beneficiaries were Catherine Blake, William Blake, and Louiza Best.)</p>
                  <p>*Joyce H. Townsend, Bronwyn Ormsby, Julia Jönsson, and Mark Evans. “Blake’s Only
Surviving Palette?” 100-03. (The palette, reproduced in black and white here and in color on 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>’s web site, is inscribed round the thumbhole “William Blake | 28 | Broad Street |
1780” [where Blake then lived]; it is said to have come from the dealer Francis Harvey [who sold Blakes
acquired from Catherine Blake by Blake’s disciple Frederick Tatham]; it was given in 1927 to the V&amp;A by
the dealer Gabriel Wells. Chemical analyses “suggest a date of use of c. 1834-45 for the palette. . . . The
only certain conclusion is that the paint on the palette could not have been used by William Blake”
[103].)</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> Volume 39, no. 3 (winter [January 2006]
2005-06)</p>
                  <p>Harry White. “Blake’s Resolution to the War Between Science and Philosophy.”
108-25. (Blake “questioned the conclusions of speculative philosophy” in “the great British tradition of
empirical-analytic” philosophers from Berkeley to Ayer and “sketched an alternative view of science based
on our actual experience of living forms” [109] “completely separate from the concerns and claims of
[abstract] philosophy,” a view widely accepted today [123].)</p>
                  <p>David Groves. “Blake and the <hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris.</hi>” 125. (Points out a
review of Cunningham [1830] focusing on Blake in the <hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris</hi> for 9 February
1830.)</p>
                  <p>*Robert N. Essick. “A (Self?) Portrait of William Blake.” 126-39. (On the basis of
similarities shared by the wash portrait of Blake [Essick Collection], Blake’s tempera of <hi rend="i">Adam
Naming the Beasts</hi>, and the life mask of Blake, particularly in asymmetrical features such as the deep
vertical crease slightly to the right of Blake’s forehead and the slight flaring of his right nostril
[features of course on the left in the mirror portrait], Essick demonstrates conclusively that his drawing is
a self-portrait of Blake of about 1802.)</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>David Fuller. Review of Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening</hi>
(2003). 140-43. (“Paley shows in an exemplary way what a range of knowledge and modes of thought can be
brought to bear on contemplating these heterogeneous creations” of Blake [143].)</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> [Number] 9 [June 2005]</p>
                  <p>Charles Hobday. “Blake and Lafayette.” 4-18. (Blake “intended to make Lafayette the
hero” of <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> [1791], modeling the poem on <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi>, but when on 17 July 1791 “Lafayette ordered the National Guard to open fire” on a crowd
assembled to sign a “petition . . . for the deposition of the king,” killing and wounding many, “Blake
withdrew the first book of <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> and destroyed the other six” [13, 14].)
Susanne Sklar. “Transfiguration.” 19. (A poem.)</p>
                  <p>*David Fallon. “‘My left foot’: Milton and Blake.” 20-35. (Concerned with the
“specific anatomical sense of ‘tarsus’ and its relationship to symbolism used in Genesis, 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
	<pb id="p40-23" n="23"/>
and antinomian theology”; “Blake uses this motif to stress the palpable humanity of Christ” [20,
33].)</p>
                  <p>Brian Louis Pearce. “Bunhill Fielders.” 36-37. (A poem.)</p>
                  <p>*Will Easton. “William Blake and the Culture of Slavery in the Late 1780s and 1790s.”
38-60. (About the extent to which <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> and “The Little Black
Boy” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> “were influenced by a poetic and cultural context of slavery,”
with “some possible sources of African influence on Blake” [38, 40].)</p>
                  <p>Bill Goldman. “The Other Side (one word more for Robert Browning).” 61-62. (A
poem.)</p>
                  <p>Susanne Sklar. “Jacob Boehme &amp; Blake’s Jerusalem.” 63-73. (“Jacob Boehme’s
apocalyptic imagery has much in common with Blake’s” [63].)</p>
                  <p>*Charlotte Davies. “Blake and Costume in the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</hi>” 74-86. (Vague “point[s] of commonality between Blake’s work and contemporary
fashion”; Blake depicted in his work “fashionable dress during his lifetime” [83, 85].)</p>
                  <p>*Angus Whitehead. “<hi rend="i">But, Kitty, I better love thee</hi>: George
Richmond’s Annotation to ‘Song [I love the jocund dance]’ in Volume II of Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1863).” 87-97. (George Richmond annotated the word “Kitty” as
“his good Wifes name,” suggesting that the “Song” refers to Catherine Blake and was written or revised
after Blake’s “twentieth year” [i.e., 1777], when, according to the integral “Advertisement,” Blake
no longer touched the poems in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> [88, 97]. The annotations in the first
volume of Richmond’s Gilchrist, belonging then to Anthony W. Richmond, were reported in G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
“William Blake, Samuel Palmer, and George Richmond,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 2.2 [1970]: 43-50;
both volumes now belong to Stephen Keynes.)</p>
                  <p>Jennifer Schofield. “Encounters with Blake.” 98-101. (Agreeable poems.)</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Angus Whitehead. Review of Judy Cox, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Scourge of
Tyrants</hi> (2004). 103-09. (A “very readable book [which] is excellent on contemporary context,” though
with “frequent grammatical errors and typos” and frequent “attempts to impose upon Blake too rigorous a
socialist reading” [107, 103].)</p>
                  <p>Andrew Solomon. Review of Morton Paley, <hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening: The
Last Works of William Blake</hi> (2003). 110-14. (“Even if it does not convey the full depth of Blake’s
vision, it contains much that is interesting and valuable” [114].)</p>
                  <p>Susanne Sklar. Review of Kevin Fischer, <hi rend="i">Converse in the Spirit: William
Blake, Jacob Boehme, and the Creative Spirit</hi> (2004). 114-16. (It “contains some of the best insights
about Jacob Boehme I’ve yet encountered” [114].)</p>
                  <p>Minne Tanaka. Review of John B. Pierce, <hi rend="i">The Wond’rous Art: William Blake
and Writing</hi> (2003). 116-17.</p>
                  <p>Bode, Christoph. “Schreiendes Baby! Grausamer Mann! William Blake, entwickelt
(anglistische Perspektiven).” <hi rend="i">Anglistik</hi> 15 (2004): 119-35. In German.</p>
                  <p>§Braida, Antonella. “William Blake: The Romantic Illustrator of Dante.” Chapter 6
(151-78) of her <hi rend="i">Dante and the Romantics</hi> (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2004).</p>
                  <p>§Cabañas Alamán, Rafael. “Del tigre de la ira al tigre del ensueño: William Blake y
Jorge Luis Borges.” <hi rend="i">Revista de Filología y Lingüística de la Universidad de Costa Rica</hi>
30 (2004): 9-18. In Spanish.</p>
                  <p>§Chauvin, Danièle. “Images de l’Apocalypse: William Blake et Victor Hugo.”
Grenoble, Thèse de troisième cycle en Littérature Générale et Comparée, 1981. In French.</p>
                  <p>§Chauvin, Danièle. “William Blake et l’Apocalypse: le Verbe et l’Image.”
Grenoble, Thèse d’état en Littérature Générale et Comparée, 1987. In French.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi rend="i">L’oeuvre de William Blake: Apocalypse et Transfiguration</hi>
(Grenoble: Ellug, 1992) is based on the Thèse d’état.</p>
                  <p>§Church, Michael. “The Story Behind: Jerusalem.” <hi rend="i">Times Educational
Supplement</hi> 28 March 2003: 15.</p>
                  <p>On the background of the “Jerusalem” lyric from <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi></p>
                  <p>§Ciompi, Fausto. “Le introduzioni ai <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> di William Blake: Sulle soglie dell’ispirazione romantica.” <hi rend="i">Anglistica
Pisana</hi> ½ [Pisa] (2004): 21-56. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>*Ciseri, Ilaria. <hi rend="i">Il Romanticismo: 1780-1860: La nascita di una nuova
sensibilità: Joseph Wright of Derby, Heinrich Füssli, Francesco Goya, Jacques-Louis David, William Blake
....</hi> (Milano: Mondadori, 2003). In Italian.</p>
                  <p>A picture book with scattered references and reproductions of Blake, Fuseli, and the 16
other artists named on the title page.</p>
                  <p>Connolly, Tristanne J. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Body.</hi> (2002) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Mark Lussier, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 35 (2004 [April 2005]): 168-69 (with
Shirley Dent and Jason Whittaker, <hi rend="i">Radical Blake</hi> [2002], Alexander Gourlay, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Prophetic Character</hi> [2002], and Peter Otto, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of
Transcendence</hi> [2000]).</p>
                  <p>§Jeffrey Longacre, <hi rend="i">College Literature</hi> 31 (2004): 197-99.</p>
                  <p>§Jeremy Tambling, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 99 (2004): 752-54.</p>
                  <p>§*Corti, Claudia. <hi rend="i">Rivoluzione e rivelazione: William Blake tra profeti,
radicali e giacobini.</hi> (Napoli: Giannini, 2000) Biblioteca di anglistica “Fernando Ferrara” no. 2, 165
pp. In Italian.</p>
                  <p>*Cox, Judy. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Scourge of Tyrants.</hi> (London: Redwords,
2004) Revolutionary Portraits no. 6, 12°, 96 pp.; ISBN: 1872208215.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-24" n="24"/>
                  <p>“Blake was a Jacobin” (12); a simplistic and assertive work which is often right.</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Angus Whitehead, <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> 9 (2005): 103-09 (A “very readable
book [which] is excellent on contemporary context,” though with “frequent grammatical errors and typos”
and frequent “attempts to impose upon Blake too rigorous a socialist reading” [107, 103]).</p>
                  <p>Davies, J. G. <hi rend="i">The Theology of William Blake.</hi> (1948) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1466&gt;</p>
                  <p>See entry under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>, chapter
10.</p>
                  <p>Demetriou, Danielle. “Export Bar Placed on Blake Paintings.” 
<hi rend="i">Independent</hi> [London] 31 March 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The Blake paintings are his watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>Dent, Shirley, and Jason Whittaker. <hi rend="i">Radical Blake.</hi> (2002) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Mark Lussier, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 35 (2004 [April 2005]): 168-69 (with
Tristanne J. Connolly, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Body</hi> [2002], Alexander Gourlay, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Prophetic Character</hi> [2002], and Peter Otto, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of
Transcendence</hi> [2000]).</p>
                  <p>*De Selincourt, Basil. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> (1909) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1480&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt; B. §(London: Duckworth; New York: Scribner’s, 1911).</p>
                  <p>Directories</p>
                  <p>§William <hi rend="i">Bailey’s Western and Midland Directory or, Merchant’s and
Tradesman’s Useful Companion for the Year 1783</hi> (Birmingham, 1783) 14, gives “Blake, Stephen, 
<hi rend="i">Haberdasher</hi>, Carnaby Market.”</p>
                  <p>§William <hi rend="i">Bailey’s British Directory or, Merchant’s and Trader’s
Useful Companion, For the Year 1784</hi> (1784) gives “Blake, James, and Son, <hi rend="i">Hosiers and
Haberdashers</hi>, Carnaby-market.”</p>
                  <p>§William <hi rend="i">Bailey’s British Directory or, Merchant’s and Trader’s
Useful Companion, For the Year 1785</hi> (London: dedication dated June 1785) 32, 144 lists</p>
                  <p>Blake, James, <hi rend="i">Haberdasher</hi>, 28, Broad-Str. Carnaby-Market</p>
                  <p>Blake and Parker, <hi rend="i">Print-sellers</hi>, 27, ditto . . .</p>
                  <p>Stephen Horncastle, Stationer, 29 Broad Street, Carnaby Market.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref>
	<note id="n30">30. See Angus Whitehead, “A Reference to William Blake and James Parker” (entry in Part
VI).</note></p>
                  <p>§Doce, Jordi. “Tiriel.” <hi rend="i">Cuadernos Hispanoamericanos</hi> 660 (2005):
73-91. In Spanish.</p>
                  <p>*Dörrbecker, D. W. “Schriftbilder und Bildzeichen. William Blakes Experimente.” 
<hi rend="i">Paragrana: Internationale Zeitschrift für Historische Anthropologie</hi> 1 (2005): 41-70. In
German.</p>
                  <p>Doyle, Brian. “Billy Blake’s Trial.” <hi rend="i">American Scholar</hi> 63 (1994):
557-68 &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt; B. §“Billy Blake’s Trial: The Exuberant Poet William
Blake.” In his <hi rend="i">Spirited Men: Story, Soul, &amp; Substance</hi> (Cambridge, Massachusetts:
Cowley Publications, 2004).</p>
                  <p>Eaves, Morris, ed. <hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake.</hi> (2003)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>D. W. Dörrbecker, <hi rend="i">BARS Bulletin &amp; Review</hi> 25 (March 2004): 30-31
(expresses “huge respect for the achievement of Eaves and his contributors”). &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2005)§&gt;</p>
                  <p>Karl Kroeber, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (spring 2005): 150-54 (“The most attractive
aspect of the <hi rend="i">Companion</hi>” is its demonstration that “confronting its [Blake’s art’s]
difficulties is the best way” [154]).</p>
                  <p>§W. H. Stevenson, <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 55 (2005): 270-75.</p>
                  <p>El-Hage, George Nicolas. “William Blake and Kahlil Gibran: Poets of Prophetic
Vision.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 41 (1981): 4024A. State University of New York (Binghamton) PhD, 1981.
&lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 461&gt; B. <hi rend="i">William Blake &amp; Kahlil Gibran: Poets of Prophetic
Vision.</hi> (Louaize [Lebanon]: NDU [Notre Dame University], 2002).</p>
                  <p>In 2002 is Boulos A. Sarru’, “Preface” (7-8).</p>
                  <p>“This is a study of influences” (14), with little revision, for the latest work in
the bibliography is 1979. “Ever since, I have published the dissertation in a series of articles and also
translated and published selected chapters in Arabic” (13), but these by-blows are not recorded in his
bibliography or in <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> or <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994 ff.).</p>
                  <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire.</hi> (1954) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1561&gt;</p>
                  <p>See entry under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>, chapter
14.</p>
                  <p>§Erle, Sibylle I. “From Face Values to Inner Visions: Blake and Lavater’s Perception
of Body and Soul.” Nottingham Trent PhD, 2004.</p>
                  <p>Fischer, Kevin. <hi rend="i">Converse in the Spirit: William Blake, Jacob Boehme, and the
Creative Spirit.</hi> (2004) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2005)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Susanne Sklar, <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> 9 (2005): 114-16 (It “contains some of
the best insights about Jacob Boehme I’ve yet encountered” [114]).</p>
                  <p>§Bryan Kirby, <hi rend="i">German Quarterly</hi> 78 (2005): 385-86.</p>
                  <p>Fisher, Peter F. <hi rend="i">The Valley of Vision: Blake as Prophet and
Revolutionary.</hi> Ed. Northrop Frye. (1961) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1611&gt; C. §(Temecula [California]:
Textbook Publishers, 2003) 261 pp.; ISBN: 0758115156.</p>
                  <p>See also entry under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>, chapter
19.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-25" n="25"/>
                  <p>§Freedman, Carl. “London as Science Fiction: A Note on Some Images from Johnson,
Blake, Wordsworth, Dickens, and Orwell.” <hi rend="i">Extrapolation: A Journal of Science Fiction and
Fantasy</hi> 43 (2002): 251-62.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake: A Collection of Critical Essays.</hi> (1966)
&lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1643; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 477&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> below, chapter 21.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “Blake after Two Centuries.” (1957) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1642;
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1995)&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> below, chapter 17.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “Blake, William.” (1967) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #A1643&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> below, chapter 23.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “Blake’s Bible.” (1990) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 477&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> below, chapter 29.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “Blake’s Bible Illustrations.” (1990) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p.
477; <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> below, chapter 28.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “Blake’s Introduction to Experience.” (1957) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1644; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 416, 477; <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2001)&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> below, chapter 18.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “Blake’s Treatment of the Archetype.” (1951) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1645; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 329, 331, 478; <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994, 2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> below, chapter 9.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “The Keys to the Gates.” (1966) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1647; 
<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> pp. 414, 415, 478; <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> below, chapter 22.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake.</hi> Ed. Angela
Esterhammer. (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2005) Collected Works of Northrop Frye, vol. 16, 4°;
ISBN: 0802039197.</p>
                  <p>The essays on Blake are in chapters</p>
                  <p>7 “Blake on Trial Again.” Reviews<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n31" type="note">31</ref> of Mark Schorer, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Politics of Vision</hi>
(1946) and of <hi rend="i">The Portable Blake</hi>, ed. Alfred Kazin (1946). (From <hi rend="i">Poetry: A
Magazine of Verse</hi> 69 [1947]: 223-28.) 185-88, 446-47. <note id="n31">31. Reviews are not reported in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) and <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995).</note></p>
                  <p>8 Review of <hi rend="i">The Portable Blake</hi>, ed. Alfred Kazin (1946). (From 
<hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 17 [1947]: 107.) 189. (Quite different from the review in 
<hi rend="i">Poetry.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>9 “Blake’s Treatment of the Archetype.” (From <hi rend="i">English Institute
Essays</hi>, ed. Alan S. Downer [1950].) 190-206, 447.</p>
                  <p>10 Review of J. G. Davies, <hi rend="i">The Theology of William Blake</hi> (1948). (From
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> 1 [1950]: 77-78.) 207-08, 447-48.</p>
                  <p>11 Review of Bernard Blackstone, <hi rend="i">English Blake</hi> (1949). (From 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 66 [1951]: 55-57.) 209-11, 448.</p>
                  <p>12 “Poetry and Design in William Blake.” (From <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and
Art Criticism</hi> [1951].) 212-20, 448.</p>
                  <p>13 “Introduction to <hi rend="i">Selected Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> [ed.
Northrop Frye (1953)].” 221-36, 448-50.</p>
                  <p>14 Review of David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi> (1954).
(From <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 34 [1955]: 273-74.) 237-38.</p>
                  <p>15 “Notes for a Commentary on <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” (From <hi rend="i">The
Divine Vision</hi>, ed. Vivian de Sola Pinto [1957].) 239-65, 450-54.</p>
                  <p>16 “William Blake (I).” (From <hi rend="i">The English Romantic Poets and Essayists:
A Review of Research and Criticism</hi>, ed. Carol W. and Lawrence H. Houtchens [1957].) 266-89, 454-55.</p>
                  <p>17 “Blake after Two Centuries.” (Originally in <hi rend="i">University of Toronto
Quarterly</hi> [1957].) 290-302, 455-56.</p>
                  <p>18 “Blake’s Introduction to Experience.” (From <hi rend="i">Huntington Library
Quarterly</hi> [1957].) 303-12, 456.</p>
                  <p>19 Preface to Peter Fisher, <hi rend="i">The Valley of Vision</hi> (1961). 313-15,
456-57.</p>
                  <p>20 “The Road of Excess.” (From <hi rend="i">Myth and Symbol: Critical Approaches and
Applications</hi>, ed. Bernice Slote [1963].) 316-29, 457-58.</p>
                  <p>21 Introduction to <hi rend="i">Blake: A Collection of Critical Essays</hi>, ed. Northrop
Frye (1966). 330-36.</p>
                  <p>22 “The Keys to the Gates.” (From <hi rend="i">Some British Romantics: A Collection
of Essays</hi>, ed. James V. Logan, John E. Jordan, and Northrop Frye [1966].) 337-359, 458.</p>
                  <p>23 “William Blake (II).” (From <hi rend="i">The Encyclopedia of Philosophy</hi>, ed.
Paul Edwards [1967].) 360-63, 459.</p>
                  <p>24 “Comment on <hi rend="i">Adam and Eve and the Angel Raphael.</hi>” (From 
<hi rend="i">Man and His World</hi>, Montreal exhibition 28 April-27 October 1967.) 364-65, 459.</p>
                  <p>25 “Blake’s Reading of the Book of Job (I).” (From <hi rend="i">William Blake:
Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld [1969].) 366-77, 459. (Revised in no. 27 below.)</p>
                  <p>26 “William Blake (III).” (From the typescript of a lecture [25 August 1971],
recorded for the BBC Open University program, “reprinted” [sic] in Frye, <hi rend="i">Reading the World:
Selected Writings, 1935-1976</hi>, ed. Robert D. Denham [1990].) 378-86, 459.</p>
                  <p>27 “Blake’s Reading of the Book of Job (II).” (Rewritten from no. 25 above and
printed in Frye, <hi rend="i">Spiritus Mundi: Essays on Literature, Myth, and Society</hi> [1976].) 387-401,
460.</p>
                  <p>28 “Blake’s Biblical Illustrations.” (Printed from the typescript of his address to
the Blake Symposium at the Art Gallery of Ontario, Toronto; published in <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye
Newsletter</hi> [1990] and in Frye, <hi rend="i">The Eternal Act of Creation: Essays, 1979-1990</hi>, ed.
Robert D. Denham [1993].) 402-18, 460.</p>
                  <p>29 “Blake’s Bible.” (Printed from the typescript of his address to the Blake
Society of St. James [2 June 1987]; first printed in Frye’s <hi rend="i">Myth and Metaphor: Selected
Essays</hi>,
<pb id="p40-26" n="26"/>
	<hi rend="i">1974-1988</hi>, ed. Robert D. Denham [1990].) 419-35, 460-61.</p>
                  <p>Of course it omits Frye’s <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, which is volume 14 of the
Collected Works of Northrop Frye series.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “Poetry and Design in William Blake.” (1951) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#1648&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> above, chapter 12.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “The Road of Excess.” (1963) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1650; 
<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 479&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> above, chapter 20.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “William Blake.” (1957) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1651; 
<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 479&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> above, chapter 16.</p>
                  <p>Frye, Northrop. “William Blake.” (1990) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> above, chapter 26.</p>
                  <p>F[rye], N[orthrop]. “William Blake. 1757-1827, Adam and Eve and the Angel Raphael.
1808: Adam et Eve et l’Archange Raphael. 1808.” (1967) &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 479&gt;</p>
                  <p>See <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi> above, chapter 24.</p>
                  <p>*Garrido, Luis and Carol. “William Blake’s Final Resting Place.” (Unpublished
printout, 2005) 96 pp., 70 figures and illustrations.</p>
                  <p>Meticulous details of his grave site in Bunhill Fields.</p>
                  <p>Gaunt, William. <hi rend="i">Arrows of Desire: A Study of William Blake and His Romantic
World.</hi> (1956) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1671&gt; B. §(Temecula [California]: Textbook Publishers, 2003)
200 pp.; ISBN: 0758179162.</p>
                  <p>§Ghita, Catalin. “Poetic Quaternaries: William Blake’s Unsystematic System.” 
<hi rend="i">Shiron</hi> 42 (2004): 19-39.</p>
                  <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, “Pictor Ignotus.”</hi> 2
vols. (1863) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1680&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 484&gt; &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (1999)&gt; O. §<hi rend="i">Gilchrist on Blake: Life of William Blake Pictor
Ignotus.</hi> Ed. with an introduction by Richard Holmes. (London: Harper Perennial, 2005) 8°; ISBN:
0007111711.</p>
                  <p>A reprint of vol. 1 of the 1863 edition, replacing the “Supplementary” section with
the letters from Blake to Butts in vol. 2: 178-98.</p>
                  <p>The introduction, mostly about Gilchrist, is full of wonderful new information, such as
that Coleridge, Wordsworth, and Lamb read Blake’s poems in manuscript and that Blake engraved the
“texts” of poems by Young and Blair.</p>
                  <p>Gimeno Suances, Francisco. “Imaginaciön, deseo y libertad en William Blake.” Tesis
Doctoral, Universidad Nacional de Educaciön a Distancia (Madrid, 2004). 913 pp., 40 reproductions. In
Spanish.</p>
                  <p>Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">The Piper and The Bard: A Study of William Blake.</hi>
(1959) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1702&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 487&gt; C. §(Temecula [California]:
Textbook Publishers, 2003) 200 pp.; ISBN: 0758106459.</p>
                  <p>§Gnappi, Carla Maria. “The Sunflower and the Rose: Notes Towards a Reassessment of
Blake’s Illustrations of Dante.” 55-68 of <hi rend="i">British Romanticism and Italian Literature:
Translating, Reviewing, Rewriting</hi>, ed. Laura Bandiera and Diego Saglia (New York: Rodopi, 2005)
Internationale Forschungen zur Allgemeinen und Vergleichenden Literaturwissenschaft, no. 92.</p>
                  <p>Gourlay, Alexander, ed. <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William Blake in
Honor of John E. Grant.</hi> (2002) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>§James Harris, <hi rend="i">Romantic Circles Reviews</hi> 8.1 (winter 2005):
&lt;http://www.rc.umd.edu/reviews/current/gourlay.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Alice G. den Otter, <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 14 (2003): 490-93
(“richly resonant,” “an impressive collection of essays”).</p>
                  <p>Mark Lussier, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 35 (2004 [April 2005]): 168-69 (with
Tristanne J. Connolly, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Body</hi> [2002], Shirley Dent and Jason Whittaker,
<hi rend="i">Radical Blake</hi> [2002], and Peter Otto, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence</hi>
[2000]).</p>
                  <p>§Graves, Roy Neil. “Blake’s ‘London.’” <hi rend="i">Explicator</hi> 63 (2005):
131-36.</p>
                  <p>Green, Matthew. “Outlining the ‘Human Form Divine’: Reading Blake’s Thoughts on
Outline and Response to Locke alongside Lavater and Cumberland.” <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi>
15 (2004): 511-32.</p>
                  <p>Green, Matthew J. A. <hi rend="i">Visionary Materialism in the Early Works of William
Blake: The Intersection of Enthusiasm and Empiricism.</hi> (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005) 8°, x, 218
pp.; ISBN: 1403942315 and ISBN 13: 9781403942319.</p>
                  <p>Halmi, Nicholas. “New Impressions X: Northrop Frye’s <hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 55 (2005): 159-72.</p>
                  <p>About the history of the book both before and after 1947; “<hi rend="i">I</hi>t has
long been almost impossible to read Blake except through the lenses of Frye’s criticism” (171).</p>
                  <p>Harper, George Mills. <hi rend="i">The Neoplatonism of William Blake.</hi> (1961) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #1793&gt; B. §(Temecula [California]: Textbook Publishers, 2003) 324 pp.; ISBN:
0758118252.</p>
                  <p>Hartigan, David Sean. “‘Listen to My Vision’: William Blake and Orality.” 
<hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 64 (2003): 2499A. Alberta PhD, 2003.</p>
                  <p>Hastings, Sheena. “William Blake and the Book Dealer.” <hi rend="i">Yorkshire
Post</hi> 1 April 2005, online
&lt;http://www.yorkshiretoday.co.uk/ViewArticle2.aspx?SectionID=105&amp;ArticleID =98768&gt;.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-27" n="27"/>
                  <p>About Dr. Paul Williams (age 76) of Ilkley who found Blake’s watercolors [which he then
thought were colored engravings] in a Glasgow bookshop.</p>
                  <p>Haywood, Peter. “Joseph Johnson and William Blake: With a Mention Also of Fuseli.”
Chapter 5 (15-27) of his <hi rend="i">Joseph Johnson, Publisher 1738-1809</hi> ([Aberystwyth]: College of
Librarianship Wales, 1976) Student Project no. 6, 4°, 62 pp.; ISBN: 0904020010.</p>
                  <p>Hazlitt, William. “On the Old Age of Artists.” <hi rend="i">New Monthly Magazine</hi>
8 (Sept. 1823): 33.</p>
                  <p>Hazlitt’s essay referring to Blake in his <hi rend="i">Plain Speaker</hi> (1826), 1:
223-24 &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1817&gt;, originally appeared three years earlier in the <hi rend="i">New
Monthly Magazine.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n32">32. The earlier Hazlitt reference was generously pointed out to me by Angus
Whitehead.</note></p>
                  <p>Heringman, Noah. “Recent Studies in the Nineteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
English Literature</hi> 45 (2005): 961-1037.</p>
                  <p>*Ima-Izumi, Yoko. <hi rend="i">Blake Shuseisareru Onna—Shi to E no Fukugo Geijutsu:
Blake’s Re-vision of the Female.</hi> (2001) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;</p>
                  <p>It includes “Blood and Sexuality” (289-310), which was revised as “Blood,
Sexuality, and the Will to Power—Blake’s Composite Art,” 99-130 of Shoichi Matsushima et al., 
<hi rend="i">Ekkyo suru Geijutsuka—Ima Blake wo Yomu: William Blake: A Border-Crossing Artist—Reading His
Works Now</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> (see entry under
Matsushima, below) and expanded as “Blood in Blake’s Poetry,” 56-72 of <hi rend="i">Voyages of
Conception: Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, ed. Eiji Hayashi et al. (Tokyo: Published by Japan Association
of English Romanticism, Distributed by Kirihara Shoten, 2005). <note id="n33">33. Ima-Izumi gives the title as
<hi rend="i">Reading Blake the Transgressive Artist.</hi></note></p>
                  <p>“I will explore, in the present essay, the ways in which blood becomes sexual in the
relations between men and women and . . . how the major bodily fluids, milk and semen, relate to blood” 
(<hi rend="i">Voyages of Conception</hi> 57).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">The International Blake Conference “Blake in the Orient”:
Programme.</hi> (2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>See under Nakamura, below.</p>
                  <p>Ishizuka, Hisao. “‘Why Wilt Thou Create a Female Will?’ Blake’s Idea of ‘Female
Will’ and the Cultural Sensibility.” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi> [Japan] no. 46
(2005): 1-18.</p>
                  <p>§Iwasaki, Toyotaro. <hi rend="i">Roman shugi no shi to kaiga</hi> [<hi rend="i">The
Poetry and Paintings of Romanticism</hi>]—<hi rend="i">Blake, Wordsworth, Turner to</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">and</hi>] <hi rend="i">Constable.</hi> (2002) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2005)§&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Noriko Kawasaki, <hi rend="i">Eibungaku Kenkyu: Studies in English Literature</hi> 81
(2005): 213-18 (in Japanese).</p>
                  <p>§Jasper, David. “Desert Theology and Total Presence: The Poets William Blake and Yves
Bonnefoy Meet Hegel and Tom Altizer.” Chapter 10 (142-59) of his <hi rend="i">The Sacred Desert: Religion,
Literature, Art, and Culture</hi> (Oxford: Blackwell, 2004).</p>
                  <p>§Kaplan, Carter. “Fractal Fantasies of Transformation: William Blake, Michael
Moorcock, and the Utilities of Mythographic Shamanism.” <hi rend="i">Extrapolation: A Journal of Science
Fiction and Fantasy</hi> 45 (2004): 419-36.</p>
                  <p>§Kawasaki, Noriko. “Iburi dasareru Orc: Blake no Milton Dai 18 [20] yo kohan bu [Orc
Smoked Out: The Latter Part of Plate 18 [20] of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Gifu
Shiritsu Joshi Tanki Daigaku Kenkyu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Gifu City Women’s Junior
College</hi>] 54 (2004): 11-16. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>*Kennedy, Maev. “Art Historian Dents Image of William Blake, Engraver: Research shows
how artist ‘fumbled and bungled.’” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> [London] 18 April 2005: 10 and online
&lt;http://arts.guardian.co.uk/news/story/0,,1462047,00.html&gt;. B. “William Blake’s Secrets and
Lines.” <hi rend="i">Globe and Mail</hi> [Toronto] 19 April 2005: R4.</p>
                  <p>“Mei-Ying Sung . . . has made the first systematic study of the backs of dozens of
surviving plates, and has revealed the repeated mistakes in the engravings which he toiled to correct . . . by
<hi rend="i">repoussage</hi> or beating out the plate from the back to knock out the mistakes.”</p>
                  <p>*Kennedy, Maev. “Export Bar on Blake Pictures.” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> [London]
31 March 2005, online &lt;http://arts.guardian.co.uk/news/story/0,,1448929,00.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Export ban on Blake’s watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>§Kim, Minho. “[Blake’s Cultural Criticism by ‘Contraries’: The Class Differences
on the Cultural Signifier ‘Liberty’].” <hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century Literature in English</hi>
[Seoul] 9 (2005): 5-34. In Korean.</p>
                  <p>§Kitamura, Kensuke. “Suwodoringu [Swaddling] to [and] William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Hikaku Bunka Kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Studies in Comparative Culture</hi>] 56 (2002): 81-89. In
Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Kotani, Mayumi. “William Blake no Muku to Keiken no Uta [William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Philokalia</hi> [Osaka Daigaku Daigakuin
Bungaku Kenkyuka Geijutsu Gaku Geijutsu Shi Koza (Department of Art and Art History, Graduate School of
Letters, Osaka University)] 22 (2005): 121-43. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Larrissy, Edward. “Blake’s Orient.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism</hi> 11 (2005):
1-13.</p>
                  <p>Presumably related to his lecture on <corr type="emend">“Blake and Orientalism”</corr> at the conference on
Blake in the Orient (2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 2004)&gt;.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-28" n="28"/>
                  <p>§Lee, Seunghun. “Yanagi Muneyoshi no Blake rikai: ‘Sozo’ to ‘Chokkan’ no
gainen who chushin ni [Yanagi Muneyoshi’s Interpretation of William Blake: ‘Imagination’ and
‘Intuition’].” <hi rend="i">Shukyo Kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of Religious Studies</hi>] 127.4
(2004): 989-90. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Lindop, Grevel. “A Golden String: Kathleen Raine, Blake, and Tradition.” 
<hi rend="i">Temenos Academy Review</hi> 7 (2004): 129-44.</p>
                  <p>Linnell, John. “Autobiography of John Linnell.” Ms. (1850s-1864).</p>
                  <p>The manuscript with its references to Blake (see <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969]
256-57 and fn; <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 341-42 and fn) has passed from the collection of John S. Linnell to
the Fitzwilliam Museum.</p>
                  <p>§*Lucas, E. V. [On Blake]. 4 pp. in <hi rend="i">A Petworth Posie.</hi> Arranged by Lady
Leconfield for the Petworth Park Fete, 5th August 1918 In aid of the Sussex County Prisoners of War Fund.
([1918]) Price One Florin.</p>
                  <p>Makdisi, Saree. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Impossible History of the 1790s.</hi>
(2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>§Alexander S. Gourlay, <hi rend="i">Albion</hi> 36 (2003): 313-14.</p>
                  <p>§Roger Whitson, <hi rend="i">Clio</hi> 33 (2004): 483-86.</p>
                  <p>§Michael Scrivener, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 46 (2004): 151-65.</p>
                  <p>Kenneth Johnston, “‘Enough! or Too much’: Probable, Possible, and Impossible
Histories,” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 35 (2004 [April 2005]): 210-15.</p>
                  <p>Mark Lussier, <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 16 (2005): 505-11 (with John B.
Pierce, <hi rend="i">The Wond’rous Art: William Blake and Writing</hi> [2003]: they are “among the most
important Blake books in the last decade” [509]).</p>
                  <p>Malvern, Jack. “Lost Grave of William Blake Found in London.” <hi rend="i">Times</hi>
16 April 2005.</p>
                  <p>Carol Garrido and her husband Luis have established that “Blake’s grave now lies
unmarked beneath a patch of grass” in Bunhill Fields.</p>
                  <p>§Martin, Julia. “The Speaking Garden in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel</hi>: Metaphors of Wisdom and Compassion.” <hi rend="i">Journal of Literary Studies/Tydskrif vir
Literatuurwetenskap</hi> 19 (2003): 53-81. With a summary in Afrikaans.</p>
                  <p>Matsushima, Shoichi. “Bara to Mushi Blake ‘Yameru Bara’ko [A Rose Versus a Worm:
Reading ‘The Sick Rose’ by Blake].” <hi rend="i">Gakushuin Daigaku Bungakubu Kenkyu Nenpo</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Annual Collection of Essays and Studies, Faculty of Letters, Gakushuin University</hi>] 11 (2004):
151-63. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Matsushima, Shoichi, Hisao Ishizuka, Masashi Suzuki, Yoko Ima-Izumi, Hiroko Takahashi.
<hi rend="i">Ekkyo suru Geijutsuka—Ima, Blake wo Yomu: William Blake: A Bordercrossing Artist—Reading His
Works Now.</hi> (2002) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)§&gt;</p>
                  <p>It consists of five essays:</p>
                  <p>Shoichi Matshushima. “Blake no shiso-teki [The Source of Blake’s Ideas]—Ranters,
Muggletonians, Gnosis sonata [and so on].” 3-34.</p>
                  <p>Hisao Ishizuka. “Fururu shintai no display—Blake to 18 seiki shinkei bunka [Display
of a Trembling Body—Blake and Eighteenth-Century Nerve Medicine].” 35-66.</p>
                  <p>*Masashi Suzuki. “Yahweh to futari no musuko Satan to Adam—‘The Laocoon’ to
‘shi wa e no gotoku’ no shuen matawa gansei [Yahweh and His Two Sons Satan and Adam—‘The Laocoon’
and the Ending or Completion of ‘Ut Pictura Poesis’].” 67-98.</p>
                  <p>*Yoko Ima-Izumi. “Ketsueki, Sexuality, Shuken eno yokubo—Blake no fukugo geijutsu
[Blood, Sexuality, and the Will to Power—Blake’s Composite Art].” 99-130. It is a revised version of
“Blood and Sexuality,” 289-310 of her <hi rend="i">Blake Shuseisareru Onna—Shi to E no Fukugo Geijutsu:
Blake’s Re-vision of the Female</hi> (2001) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2003)&gt;, and was expanded as
“Blood in Blake’s Poetry,” 56-72 of <hi rend="i">Voyages of Conception: Essays in English
Romanticism</hi>, ed. Eiji Hayashi et al. (2005); see entry under Ima-Izumi, above.</p>
                  <p>*Hiroko Takahashi. “Bijutsu-shi no naka no William Blake—20 seiki ni okeru hyoka to
eikyo [William Blake in the History of Art—His Evaluation and Influence in the 20th Century].” 131-62.</p>
                  <p>§Mee, Jon. “‘Image of Truth New Born’: Iolo, William Blake, and the Literary
Radicalism of the 1790s.” In <hi rend="i">A Rattleskull Genius: The Many Faces of Iolo Morganwg</hi>, ed.
Geraint H. Jenkins (University of Wales Press, 2005) Iolo Morganwg and the Romantic Tradition in Wales, vol.
1.</p>
                  <p>§Mee, Jon. <hi rend="i">Romanticism, Enthusiasm and Regulation: Poetics and the Policing
of Culture in the Romantic Period.</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2003).</p>
                  <p>There is a section on Blake.</p>
                  <p>Miner, Paul. “Blake and the Sinful Arts of Forgiveness.” <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi> 86 (2005): 399-423.</p>
                  <p>A dense and richly allusive study of Blake’s dense and richly allusive wordplay.</p>
                  <p>§Nagashima, Kazuhiko. “Blake no vision ni okeru kodomo to yorokobi ‘Hajime no uta’
ni okeru kyo jaku kaku no yoho [Children and Joy in Blake’s Vision: The Use of Stress in “Introduction”
(to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>?)].” <hi rend="i">Kawamura Gakuen Joshi Daigaku Kenkyu Kiyo</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Journal of Kawamura Gakuen Women’s University</hi>] 16 (2005): 63-78. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Naito, Takako. “Skellig in Mirareru William Blake no Vision [The Vision of William
Blake Observed in Skellig].” <hi rend="i">Shirayuri Joshi Daigaku Jido Bunka Kenkyu Center Kenkyu Rombun
Shu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Studies of the Research Center for Children’s Literature and Culture, Shirayuri
College</hi>] 7 (2003): 11-25. In Japanese.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-29" n="29"/>
                  <p>Nakamura, Hiroko. “Blake’s Influence on Muneyoshi Yanagi and His Pilgrimage to
Buddhism.” 73-85 of <hi rend="i">Voyages of Conception: Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, ed. Eiji Hayashi
et al. (Tokyo: Published by Japan Association of English Romanticism, Distributed by Kirihara Shoten,
2005).</p>
                  <p>The text of the paper given at the international conference on Blake in the Orient (2003)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Noah, Sherna. “Blake Paintings Barred from Leaving U.K.” 
<hi rend="i">News.Scotsman.com</hi> 30 March 2005, online.</p>
                  <p>The paintings are his watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
                  <p>§Nosková, Martina. “The Eternal Female: A Contribution to the Gendered Reading of
William Blake’s Thel and Oothoon.” <hi rend="i">Brno Studies in English</hi> [Prague] 30 (2004):
159-78.</p>
                  <p>Otto, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence.</hi> (2000) &lt;<hi
rend="i">Blake</hi> (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>Mark Lussier, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 35 (2004 [April 2005]): 168-169 (with
Tristanne J. Connolly, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Body</hi> [2002], Shirley Dent and Jason Whittaker,
<hi rend="i">Radical Blake</hi> [2002], and Alexander Gourlay, ed., <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character</hi>
[2002]) (Otto’s is an “insightful commentary” [169]).</p>
                  <p>Otto, Peter. “A Sublime Allegory: Blake, Blake Studies, and the Sublime.” 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 43 (2002): 61-84. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2005)§&gt;</p>
                  <p>Deals especially with <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
                  <p>Paglia, Camille. “The Chimney Sweeper” and “London.” Chapters 11 and 12 (52-57,
58-62) of her <hi rend="i">Break, Blow, Burn</hi> (New York: Pantheon Books, 2005).</p>
                  <p>Text and explication de texte.</p>
                  <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening: The Last Works of William
Blake.</hi> (2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2005)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>§T. Hoagwood, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 42 (2004): 102-03.</p>
                  <p>Angus Whitehead, “‘Free to be inconsistent,’” <hi rend="i">Cambridge
Quarterly</hi> 34 (2005): 65-71 (“It is gratifying to encounter such solid and pioneering scholarly detail
in so readable a form, helped not least by Paley’s admirable clarity and quirky humour. . . . an outstanding
contribution” [71]).</p>
                  <p>Sheila A. Spector, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 35 (2004 [April 2005]): 164-67
(“Paley’s narrative is suffused with a tangible sense of grace” [167]).</p>
                  <p>Andrew Solomon, <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> 9 (2005): 110-14 
(“<hi rend="i">E</hi>ven if it does not convey the full depth of Blake’s vision, it contains much that is
interesting and valuable” [114]).</p>
                  <p>David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.3 (winter 2005-06): 140-43 (“Paley shows in an
exemplary way what a range of knowledge and modes of thought can be brought to bear on contemplating these
heterogeneous creations” of Blake [143]).</p>
                  <p>Phillips, Michael. “Blake’s Annotations in Context.” <hi rend="i">European Romantic
Review</hi> 16 (2005): 93-95.</p>
                  <p>A defense of his identification of the “WB” initials and annotations in his copy of
the Bentley Milton (1732) as those of the poet, in answer to Jason Snart (see entry below).</p>
                  <p>*Phillips, Michael. “The Printing of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book
of Job.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi> 22 (2005): 138-59.</p>
                  <p>Particularly useful for details of copperplate printers of Blake’s time.</p>
                  <p>Phillips, Michael. “William Blake in Lambeth ....” <hi rend="i">History Today</hi>
50, no. 11 (Nov. 2000): 18-25. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2001)&gt;</p>
                  <p>An “edited form” of the essay appears in the summer 2005 exhibition catalogue of
Cloud &amp; Vision.</p>
                  <p>Pierce, John B. <hi rend="i">The Wond’rous Art: William Blake and Writing.</hi> (2003)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Jason Whittaker, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (spring 2005): 155-57 (“What 
<hi rend="i">Wond’rous Art</hi> does is to tease interesting potential from the new bibliography” [156]).</p>
                  <p>Minne Tanaka, <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> 9 (2005): 116-17.</p>
                  <p>Mark Lussier, <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 16 (2005): 505-11 (with Saree
Makdisi, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Impossible History of the 1790s</hi> [2003]: they are “among the
most important Blake books in the last decade” [509]).</p>
                  <p>*Pinto, Vivian de Sola, ed. <hi rend="i">The Divine Vision.</hi> (1957) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #2402A-B&gt; C. §(Temecula [California]: Textbook Publishers, 2003) 216 pp.</p>
                  <p>See also entry under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>, chapter
15.</p>
                  <p>Plotnitsky, Arkady. “Chaosmic Orders: Nonclassical Physics, Allegory, and the
Epistemology of Blake’s Minute Particulars.”
&lt;http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/complexity/plotnitsky/plotnitsky.html&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2005)§&gt;</p>
                  <p>The essay is “an investigation of the epistemology of Blake’s poetic vision and
practice,” “an exploration of the connections between Blake’s epistemology and key epistemological
aspects of quantum physics and of chaos theory,” and “a discussion of Blake’s illuminated manuscripts
[sic] as the artists’ books [sic].”</p>
                  <p>§Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">The Little Girl Lost and Found and the Lapsed Soul.</hi>
[Apparently the printed text of a lecture given at Girton College, Cambridge, when she was a fellow there in
1955-61.]</p>
                  <p>*Reynolds, Nigel. “Export Ban on Blake’s Vision of ‘Blair’s Grave’: 19
watercolours commissioned for the poet (not the Prime Minister) could stay in Britain—if £8m can be
found.” <hi rend="i">Telegraph</hi> [London] 31 March 2005 and online
&lt;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/03/31/npoet31.xml&gt;.</p>
                  <pb id="p40-30" n="30"/>
                  <p>The “anonymous collector living in America . . . recently applied to remove them from
Britain but Miss Morris [Arts Minister] announced a temporary export stop of up to six months yesterday to
allow a public collection in this country to come up with a ‘matching’ offer of £8.8 million, excluding
VAT.”</p>
                  <p>§Rix, Robert William. “William Blake, Thomas Thorild and Radical Swedenborgianism.”
<hi rend="i">Nordic Journal of English Studies</hi> [Oslo] 2 (2003): 97-128.</p>
                  <p>§Röden, Peter Ulrick. “William Blake’s ‘Imagination’: Blake’s Role in English
Romanticism.” Copenhagen thesis, 2005.</p>
                  <p>Rosenfeld, Alvin A., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon.</hi>
(1969) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2565; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 626&gt;</p>
                  <p>See also entry under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>, chapters
25 and 27.</p>
                  <p>Rudd, Margaret E. <hi rend="i">Organiz’d Innocence: The Story of Blake’s Prophetic
Books.</hi> (1956) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2586&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 629&gt; D. §(Temecula
[California]: Textbook Publishers, 2003) 266 pp.; ISBN: 0758145942.</p>
                  <p>Rudy, John G. “Blake and the Void of <hi rend="i">Koan</hi> [meditative] Practice.”
Chapter 4 (93-126) of his <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Zen Buddhism</hi> (Lewiston [New York]: Edwin Mellen
Press, 2004) Studies in Comparative Literature, vol. 56.</p>
                  <p>Mostly based on <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi></p>
                  <p>§Rutland, Laura Ellen. “Hindrance, Act, and the Scapegoat: William Blake, Kenneth
Burke, and the Rhetoric of Order.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 64 (2003): 2098A. Tennessee PhD, 2003.</p>
                  <p>§Ryu, Son-Moo. “Imagining Society: William Blake, William Wordsworth, and George
Eliot.” <hi rend="i">DAI</hi> 66 (2005): 1010-11A. Indiana PhD, 2005.</p>
                  <p>Sato, Hikari. “Prophets Interviewed in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>: Blake, Religion and Relativism.” 104-117 of <hi rend="i">Voyages of Conception: Essays in English
Romanticism</hi>, ed. Eiji Hayashi et al. (Tokyo: Published by Japan Association of English Romanticism,
Distributed by Kirihara Shoten, 2005).</p>
                  <p>“Blake’s Isaiah and Ezekiel are akin to these rational theologists [Lowth, Geddes,
and Unitarian thinkers] in their approach to the Bible” (113).</p>
                  <p>Schneider, Matthew. “The Anxiety of Innocence in Blake and Kierkegaard.” 
<hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 16 (2005): 351-59.</p>
                  <p>§Schock, Peter A. <hi rend="i">Romantic Satanism: Myth and the Historical Moment in
Blake, Shelley and Byron.</hi> (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2004)§&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>§Simon Bainbridge, <hi rend="i">Romanticism</hi> 10 (2004): 258-60.</p>
                  <p>Schorer, Mark. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Politics of Vision.</hi> (1946) &lt;<hi
rend="i">BB</hi> #2672, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1994)&gt;</p>
                  <p>See also entry under Frye, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Milton and Blake</hi>, chapter
7.</p>
                  <p>§Schott, G. D. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, John Birch’s
‘Electrical Magic’, and the ‘falling star.’” <hi rend="i">Lancet</hi> [London] 362 (2003):
2114-16.</p>
                  <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith. “William Blake and the Jewish Swedenborgians.” Chapter 3
(61-86) of <hi rend="i">The Jews and British Romanticism: Politics, Religion, Culture</hi>, ed. Sheila A.
Spector (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005).</p>
                  <p>“Blake’s complex and ambivalent attitude toward the Jews was rooted in his early
Moravian-Swedenborgian religious background and developed through his access to a Jewish-Christian subculture
within Illuminist Freemasonry” (62).</p>
                  <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith. “Rediscovering William ‘Hurricane’ Gilbert: A Lost Voice
of Revolution and Madness in the Worlds of Blake and the Romantics.” Romantic Revelations conference, Keele
University (July 1999), online &lt;http://www.williamgilbert.com/Gilbert_Schuchard.htm&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Sínger, June. <hi rend="i">The Unholy Bible: A Psychological Interpretation of William
Blake.</hi> (1970) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2707&gt; &lt;<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> p. 640&gt; D. §*<hi
rend="i">Blake, Jung e o Inconsciente Coletivo: O Conflito entre a Razão e a Imaginação.</hi> Tr. Milena
Soares Carvalho. (São Paulo [Brazil]: Madras, 2004) 287 pp.; ISBN: 8573747757. In Portuguese.</p>
                  <p>Snart, Jason. “Blake’s Awareness of ‘Blake in a Newtonian World’: William Blake,
Isaac Newton, and Writing on Metal.” <hi rend="i">History of European Ideas</hi> 31 (2005): 237-49.</p>
                  <p>*Snart, Jason. “Blake’s Milton: Did Blake Own and Annotate the 1732 Bentley Edition
of Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>?” <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 16 (2005):
79-91.</p>
                  <p>“The annotations, while attributed to William Blake by Michael Phillips, in whose
possession the volume currently resides, in fact neither sound nor look like other of Blake’s
annotations”; a careful examination of the handwriting demonstrates that “the annotations in the Milton
volume are not by William Blake, the poet” (79, 80).</p>
                  <p>See the reply by Michael Phillips (entry above).</p>
                  <p>Spector, Sheila A. “<hi rend="i">Glorious incomprehensible</hi>” (2001); 
“<hi rend="i">Wonders Divine</hi>” (2001) &lt;Blake (2002)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>Mark Lussier, <hi rend="i">Romantic Circles Reviews</hi> 8.1 (winter 2005):
&lt;http://www.rc.umd.edu/reviews/current/spector.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Stephen C. Behrendt, <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 16 (2005): 384-88 (they
“add immeasurably to our understanding of Blake” [388]).</p>
                  <pb id="p40-31" n="31"/>
                  <p>§Sturrock, June. “Lark, Wild Thyme, Crowing Cock, and Waterfall: The Natural, the
Moral, and the Political in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and Vaughan’s <hi rend="i">Silex
Scintillans.</hi>” 329-50 in <hi rend="i">Of Paradise and Light: Essays on Henry Vaughan and John Milton in
Honor of Alan Rudrum</hi>, ed. Donald R. Dickson and Holly Faith Nelson (Newark: University of Delaware Press,
2004).</p>
                  <p>§Suied, Alain. <hi rend="i">Blake et Dante, un malentendu poétique: Conférence à la
Maison de la poésie, Paris, 20 février 2001; suivi de Penser avec l’autre.</hi> (Juillan: éditions de
l’improbable, 2001) 49 pp.; ISBN: 2847390030. In French.</p>
                  <p>*Sung, Mei-Ying. “Technical and Material Studies of William Blake’s Engraved 
<hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi> (1826).” Nottingham Trent University PhD, April 2005, 255
pp., 99 reproductions.</p>
                  <p>“The aim of this thesis is to lay out the overlooked importance of Blake’s overlooked
original copper plates” (abstract). The reproductions include the rectos and versos of each of Blake’s 22
Job engravings plus prints from the rectos.</p>
                  <p>§Suzuki, Masashi. “18 Seiki Igirisu ni okeru Geijutsu ni Ikai to sono Shometsu:
William Blake to ut pictura poesis [The Status of Art in Eighteenth-Century Britain and Its Decline: William
Blake and ut pictura poesis].” <hi rend="i">Seiyo Bijutsu Kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Studies in Western
Art</hi>] 7 (2002): 76-89. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Symons, Arthur. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> (1907) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
2804A-C&gt; D. §(London: Cape, 1940) St. Giles Library E. §(New York, 1970) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
2804D&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Tambling, Jeremy. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night Thoughts.</hi> (Basingstoke: Palgrave
Macmillan, 2005) 8°, x, 202 pp.; ISBN: 1403942846.</p>
                  <p>A wayward, self-indulgent book with sporadic “reason[s] for linking Blake and night”
(11). He writes of the poet’s mother as “Catherine Harmitage” (not “Armitage”), of his friends
“Thomas Stodhard” (i.e., “Stothard”) and John Flaxman “engraver” (i.e., sculptor), he refers to
“plate [i.e., page] 53” of “The manuscript of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> [which] is of 70 pages
[i.e., leaves]” (118, 119, 56, 184).</p>
                  <p>“Part of the material on Dante and Blake, now dispersed in the book, comes from my
essay ‘Dante and Blake: Allegorizing the Event’ edited by Nick Havely (London: Macmillan, 1998), pp. 33-48
[<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2005)], and a draft of Chapter 7 [‘Dante’s “Deep and Woody Way’”] called
‘Illustrating Accusation: Blake on Dante’s <hi rend="i">Commedia</hi>’ in <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 37 (1998), 395-420” (viii).</p>
                  <p>Tambling, Jeremy. “Illustrating Accusation: Blake on Dante’s 
<hi rend="i">Commedia.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 37 (1998): 395-420.</p>
                  <p>See preceding entry.</p>
                  <p>§Tokareva, G. “Zhestokaia starost’ i prokliataia iunost’ v monomife Uil’iama
Bleika [Cruel Old Age and Damned Youth in William Blake’s Personal Mythology].” <hi rend="i">Voprosy
Literatury</hi> no. 3 (2005): 245-62. In Russian.</p>
                  <p>*Townsend, Joyce H., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work.</hi> (2003)
&lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004§, 2005)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Reviews</p>
                  <p>§Nadine Dalton Speidel, <hi rend="i">Library Journal</hi> 129 (1 April 2004): 92.</p>
                  <p>*Alexander Gourlay, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 49-54 
(“<hi rend="i">T</hi>he perspectives are refreshing and often startling, the discoveries are numerous, and the
consequences are substantial for everyone who studies Blake’s art” [49]).</p>
                  <p>§Townsend, Joyce H., Bronwyn Ormsby, Julia Jönsson, and Mark Evans. “William
Blake’s Only Surviving Palette?” <hi rend="i">V&amp;A Conservation Journal</hi> 49 (2005): 20-21.</p>
                  <p>A longer version appears in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 100-03.</p>
                  <p>Wada, Ayako. “Revisions of Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and Their Meaning.”
86-103 of <hi rend="i">Voyages of Conception: Essays in English Romanticism</hi>, ed. Eiji Hayashi et al.
(Tokyo: Published by Japan Association of English Romanticism, Distributed by Kirihara Shoten, 2005).</p>
                  <p>A discussion of “the dating of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, . . . the post-1793
development of the work, and . . . the latent implications of the revisions” (86).</p>
                  <p>Wada, Ayako. “The Rise and Fall of the Myth of Orc (1) Orc’s Origin Traced to
Blake’s Poems Composed between 1789 and 1792 [(2) Mythogenesis in Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and in
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>] [(3) Realization of the Central Myth in Blake’s “The
Tyger”, <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Tottori Daigaku
Kyoiku Gakubu Kenkyu Kiyo</hi>: <hi rend="i">Journal of the Faculty of Education Tottori University Cultural
and Social Science</hi> 48 (1997): 277-87; 49 (1998): 113-21; 123-33.</p>
                  <p>“<hi rend="i">T</hi>he process by which <hi rend="i">America</hi> was perfected
reflects the gradual crystallization of the myth of Orc” (part 2, 113).</p>
                  <p>Wardi, Eynel. “Space, the Body, and the Text in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Orbis Litterarum</hi> 58 (2003): 253-70. &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(2005)§&gt;</p>
                  <p>“The notion, projected by <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, that the
textual space spatializes to the embodied movement of the imagination saves that space from such
self-referential closure as worried Blake in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>” (268, all sic).</p>
                  <p>Warner, Janet. <hi rend="i">Other Sorrows, Other Joys: The Marriage of Catherine Sophia
Boucher and William Blake.</hi> (2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>§Matthew Beaumont, “Help for the Helpmate,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 24-31 Dec. 2004: 26</p>
                  <p>Weir, David. <hi rend="i">Brahma in the West: William Blake and the Oriental
Renaissance.</hi> (2003) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2004)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>*Sibylle Erle, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4 (spring 2005): 157-59 (Weir “argues
convincingly for Blake’s participation in the Oriental Renaissance [in London]” [159]).</p>
                  <pb id="p40-32" n="32"/>
                  <p>*Wethered, Newton. “William Blake and the Imagination.” Chapter 6 (80-99) of his 
<hi rend="i">From Giotto to John: The Development of Painting</hi> (London: Methuen &amp; Co., 1926).</p>
                  <p>Blake was clairvoyant.</p>
                  <p>Whitehead, Angus. “New Information Concerning Mrs Enoch, William and Catherine
Blake’s ‘Fellow Inhabitant’ at 17 South Molton Street.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 250 [ns
52] (2005): 460-63.</p>
                  <p>The Blakes’ “Kind &amp; attentive fellow inhabitant, the young &amp; very amiable
M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Enoch, who gave my wife all the attention that a daughter could pay to a mother” until
Blake’s triumphant return from his trial on 14 January 1804, was probably Mary Enoch (née Naylor), the wife
of Blake’s landlord William Enoch, a tailor, and mother of their son William (christened 18 May 1801).</p>
                  <p>Whitehead, Angus. “A Reference to William Blake and James Parker, Printsellers, in 
<hi rend="i">Bailey’s British Directory</hi> (1785).” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 250 [ns 52] (2005):
32-35.</p>
                  <p>A “Correction” by eds. (Sept. 2005): 381, alters “James Parker . . . was a bachelor
in 1748” to “. . . 1784.”</p>
                  <p>*Whitehead, Angus. “William Blake’s Last Residence: No. 3 Fountain Court, Strand,
George Richmond’s Plan and an Unrecorded Letter to John Linnell.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi>
6.1 (spring/summer 2005): 21-30.</p>
                  <p>A wonderfully original, thorough, and valuable account. A “Correction,” 
<hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.2 (2005): 88, says that on 30n49, “the measurements for Blake’s
printing studio at Felpham should apply to the westernmost room <hi rend="i">not</hi> the easternmost
room.”</p>
                  <p>Whittaker, Jason. “Blake.” Section 5 (593-603 and passim) of “The Nineteenth
Century: The Romantic Period,” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 83 [“Covering work
published in 2002”] (2004 [i.e., 2005]).</p>
                  <p>*Wilson, David. “An Idle Speculation by Samuel Palmer: William Blake’s Involvement in
Cipriani’s Portrait of John Milton.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.1 (spring/summer 2005):
31-36.</p>
                  <p>Blake could not have worked, while an apprentice with Basire in 1772-79, on Cipriani’s
etching of the bust of Milton published in <hi rend="i">The Memoirs of Thomas Hollis</hi> (1780), as suggested
by Samuel Palmer (reported in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 51 [1981]:
28-35 and <hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 428-29), for the copies of the print given away by Hollis in 1762 and 1765
are identical with those in the <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> of 1780.</p>
                  <p>*Wood, Marcus. “John Gabriel Stedman, William Blake, Francesco Bartolozzi and
Empathetic Pornography in the <hi rend="i">Narrative of a Five Years Expedition against the Revolted Negroes
of Surinam.</hi>” Chapter 6 (129-49) of <hi rend="i">An Economy of Colour: Visual Culture and the Atlantic
World, 1660-1830</hi>, ed. Geoff Quilley and Kay Dian Kriz (Manchester: Manchester University Press; New York:
Palgrave, 2003).</p>
                  <p>Scarcely related to Blake.</p>
                  <p>Wright, Julia M. <hi rend="i">Blake, Nationalism, and the Politics of Alienation.</hi>
(2004) &lt;<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (2005)&gt;</p>
                  <p>Review</p>
                  <p>§David Baulch, <hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi> nos. 36-37 (Nov. 2004-Feb.2005):
&lt;http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/2004/v/n36-37/011146ar.html&gt;.</p>
                  <p>Jack Bushnell, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 44 (2005): 274-77 (it is
“dense, jargon-laden” but “tightly woven, impressively researched, and often genuinely original”
[274]).</p>
                  <p>§Yamazaki, Yusuke. “Futari no yogensha ga ataeta Blake eno aihansuru kannen: Emanuel
Swedenborg to John Wesley [Contrary Conceptions that Two Prophets Gave to Blake: Emanuel Swedenborg and John
Wesley].” <hi rend="i">Hikaku Bunka Kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Studies in Comparative Literature</hi>] 64
(2004): 43-53. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>§Yamazaki, Yusuke. <hi rend="i">Kami to Ningen: Jesus no Ningen sei: William Blake
Rombun Shu</hi> [<hi rend="i">God and Human: Humanity of Jesus: Essays on William Blake</hi>]. (Tokyo: Kindai
Bungei Sha, 2004) 129 pp.; ISBN: 4773372117. In Japanese.</p>
                  <p>Yoder, R. Paul. “Blake and the Book of Numbers: Joshua the Giant Killer and the Tears
of Balaam.” Chapter 4 (87-102) of <hi rend="i">The Jews and British Romanticism: Politics, Religion,
Culture</hi>, ed. Sheila A. Spector (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005).</p>
                  <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 38 “brings together three important events from the
book of Numbers: the sending of the spies in advance of the army, the attempt of Balak to hire Balaam to curse
the Israelites, and the battle of Peor” concerning “how to distinguish valid claims of divine authority
from invalid claims” (90-91, 99).</p>
                  <p>§Zeng, Fangrong. “Bulaike shi ge zhong de lun li si xiang.” <hi rend="i">Foreign
Literature Studies/Wai Guo Wen Xue Yan Jiu</hi> 6 (2005): 20-27, 170. In Chinese.</p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>
                    <hi rend="b">Division II: Blake’s Circle</hi>
                  </title>
                </head>
                <p>Cumberland, George (1754-1848)</p>
                <p>Dilettante, polymath, friend of Blake</p>
                <p>Manuscript Geological Commonplace Book</p>
                <p>Description: Large folio, with notes by Cumberland and others, mss. from Italy, etc.,
letters from geologists, lists of dealers in, and collectors of, fossils, etc., with some printed George
Cumberland ephemera, some of which are also in the Bristol
<pb id="p40-33" n="33"/>
Library collections of cuttings<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">34</ref> on
coal, ichthyosaurs, geological lectures, but apparently with nothing on Blake or the arts. <note id="n34">34.
G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of George Cumberland (1754-1848)</hi> (New York: Garland,
1975) 45; the geology commonplace book is not listed here.</note></p>
                <p>History: Sold by Cumberland with his other geological manuscripts (apparently including a
ms. catalogue of his fossil collection and mss. on fossil crinoids now not traced) to the philanthropist James
Heywood (1810-97) who gave these mss. in 1842 to the Manchester Geological Society,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref> to which Cumberland had sold in 1842 his fine collection of
fossils and two copies of his <hi rend="i">Reliquæ Conservatæ . . . with Popular Descriptions of . . . Some
Remarkable Encrinites</hi> (Bristol: J. M. Gutch; London: Harding, Lepard, and Co., 1826); the fossil
collection and <hi rend="i">Reliquæ Conservatæ</hi> went to the university’s Manchester museum, but the
society’s library was disbanded in 1965 and the contents scattered; the ms. Geological Commonplace Book was
acquired by a Wigan colliery office, whence it was purchased by Professor Hugh Torrens<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref> of the Keele University Department of Earth Sciences (from
whom all this information derives). <note id="n35">35. It is listed in J. Plant’s catalogue of the
Manchester Geological Society library (1875) 14.</note>
	<note id="n36">36. Hugh Torrens, a distant connection of Blake’s patron Major General Sir Henry Torrens
(see BR [2] 441, 786, 800), also has Cumberland’s heavily annotated copy of Johann Samuel Müller’s 
<hi rend="i">Crinoidea</hi> (1821), which had also escaped from the society’s library. He intends to do some
justice to Cumberland’s interests in science.</note></p>
                <p>A previously unrecorded portrait in pen, ink, and black wash by George Cumberland,
apparently of Catherine Blake reading (c. 1783-85), on wove paper 23.1 × 17.8 cm. pasted to a sheet of
unwatermarked paper 23.7 × 18.0 cm., inscribed in pencil on the verso “64”, loose in an old mat inscribed
“M<hi rend="s">rs.</hi> Blake by George Cumberland” and “10”, was sold by William Drummond in 2005 to
Robert N. Essick. (Cumberland’s hand is almost certain, the subject somewhat less so, but it is very like
Cumberland’s portrait of Catherine in the Fitzwilliam Museum.) Catherine, who signed her marriage register
with an X in 1782 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 27-28), had apparently learned to read by the time of the
portrait. The portrait is described and reproduced in Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,”
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 164-65 and cover illustration.</p>
                <p>Johnson, Joseph (1738-1809)</p>
                <p>Bookseller, patron of Blake</p>
                <p>Braithwaite, Helen. <hi rend="i">Romanticism, Publishing and Dissent: Joseph Johnson and
the Cause of Liberty.</hi> (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2003).</p>
                <p>A worthy book, originally a Birmingham PhD dissertation.</p>
                <p>Haywood, Peter. See entry under Part VI, above.</p>
                <p>Palmer, Samuel (1805-81)</p>
                <p>Artist, disciple of Blake</p>
                <p>2005 February</p>
                <p>§<hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: 1860s Books.</hi> Adam Mills catalogue (Feb. 2005).</p>
                <p>2005 October 21-2006 January 22;7 March-29 May</p>
                <p>William Vaughan, Elizabeth E. Barker, Colin Harrison, with contributions by David Bindman,
David Blayney Brown, Alexandra Greathead, Marjorie Shelley, and Scott Wilcox. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer
1805-1881: Vision and Landscape.</hi> [Catalogue . . . to accompany an exhibition shown at the British Museum
from 21 October 2005 to 22 January 2006 and at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, from 7 March 2006 to
29 May 2006]. (London: British Museum Press, 2005) 4°, 256 pp., 211 reproductions, mostly in glorious color;
ISBN: 0714126411 and ISBN 13: 9780714126418.</p>
                <p>“The exhibition was selected and organized by William Vaughan . . . in collaboration with
Elizabeth E. Barker, [and] . . . Constance McPhee” (7). The book consists of:</p>
                <p>Neil MacGregor and Philippe de Montebello. “Directors’ Foreword.” 7.</p>
                <p>William Vaughan. “Introduction.” 10-16.</p>
                <p>William Vaughan. “‘Brothers in art, brothers in love’: The Ancients as an Artistic
Community.” 17-21.</p>
                <p>David Blayney Brown. “‘To fancy what is lost to sight’: Palmer and Literature.”
22-27.</p>
                <p>David Bindman. “The Politics of Vision: Palmer’s <hi rend="i">Address to the Electors
of West Kent</hi>, 1832.” 28-32. (The text of the <hi rend="i">Address</hi> was given by Bindman in 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19.2 [fall 1985]: 56-68.)</p>
                <p>Alexandra Greathead. “Samuel Palmer’s Materials and Techniques: The Early Years.”
33-35.</p>
                <p>Marjorie Shelley. “Samuel Palmer’s Materials and Techniques: The Later Years.”
36-41.</p>
                <p>Scott Wilcox. “Poetic Feeling and Chromatic Madness: Palmer and Victorian Watercolour
Painting.” 42-46.</p>
                <p>Elizabeth E. Barker. “‘The excitement of gambling, without its guilt and its ruin’:
Palmer and Printmaking.” 47-54.</p>
                <p>Colin Harrison. “The Artistic Rediscovery of Samuel Palmer.” 55-61.</p>
                <p>Catalogue: Part One: The Visionary</p>
                <p>William Vaughan. “Early Years (1805-23).” 66-74, nos. 1-8.</p>
                <p>William Vaughan. “The Primitive Vision (1823-5).” 75-104, nos. 9a-t, 10-27.</p>
                <p>William Vaughan. “Shoreham and the Ancients (1825-30).” 105-36, nos. 28-64.</p>
                <p>Colin Harrison. “Later Shoreham (1830-35).” 137-68, nos. 65-95.</p>
                <p>Part Two: The Victorian</p>
                <p>Elizabeth E. Barker. “The Traveller (1835-7).” 170-78, nos. 96-103.</p>
                <p>Elizabeth E. Barker. “Italy (1837-40).” 179-91, nos. 104-13.</p>
                <p>Elizabeth E. Barker. “Sketches and Idylls (1840-<hi rend="i">c.</hi>1865).” 192-223,
nos. 114-44.</p>
                <pb id="p40-34" n="34"/>
                <p>William Vaughan. “The Lonely Tower (<hi rend="i">c.</hi>1865-81).” 224-44, nos.
145-64.</p>
                <p>The occasion was the 200th anniversary of Palmer’s birth; the reproductions include works
by Blake, Linnell, Calvert, and Richmond.</p>
                <p>Reviews</p>
                <p>§Kathy Brewis, “Burning Love,” <hi rend="i">Sunday Times Magazine</hi> [London] 16
Oct. 2005: 38, 43; &lt;http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2099-1813696,00.html&gt;.</p>
                <p>Richard Dorment, “The Joyful Visions of Britain’s Most Lovable Artist: Exhibition:
Samuel Palmer’s Vision and Landscape,” <hi rend="i">Telegraph</hi> [London] 18 Oct. 2005
&lt;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/arts/main.jhtml?xml=/arts/2005/10/18/ bapalmer18.xml&gt;.</p>
                <p>Simon Jenkins, “Skip the Secular Rituals of the Turner Prize for a Real Radical: The
British Museum’s exhibition of the painter Samuel Palmer is an exhilarating vision of archaic beauty,” 
<hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> [London] 21 Oct 2005: 32 and
&lt;http://arts.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,,1597156,00.html&gt;.</p>
                <p>Souren Melikian, “Samuel Palmer: A Versatile Visionary Who Lost His Way,” 
<hi rend="i">International Herald Tribune</hi> 21 Oct. 2005
&lt;http://www.iht.com/articles/2005/10/21/opinion/melik22.php#&gt; (“The brilliant show” ranges from an
early “true masterpiece” down to “insipid kitsch”).</p>
                <p>Frances Wilson, “Beauty with a Pinch of Salt: The strange and double flowering of Samuel
Palmer,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 4 Nov. 2005: 16-17 (“a richly researched and deeply
fairminded exhibition”; the author has discovered a Blake proverb unknown to previous scholars: “‘Talent
thinks,’ Blake said, ‘Genius sees’” and a new “mentor, John Liddell”; Adam Johns, “Samuel
Palmer,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 18 Nov 2005: 17 deplores the misspelling and
denigration of John Linnell in Frances Wilson’s review).</p>
                <p>Brian Sewell, “English Eccentric Who Put Poetry in Pictures: The British Museum’s
Samuel Palmer exhibition shows him to be one of Europe’s greatest romantic artists,” <hi rend="i">Evening
Standard</hi> [London] 4 Nov. 2005: 36-37.</p>
                <p>Robin Blake, “Landscape Ancient and Modern: Samuel Palmer’s unique, intensely felt
vision of rural life is evident even in his earliest works,” <hi rend="i">Financial Times</hi> 7 Nov.
2005.</p>
                <p>Palmer, Samuel. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer’s Sketch-Book.</hi> An Introduction and
Commentary by Martin Butlin with a Preface by Geoffrey Keynes. ([London?], 1962) &lt;<hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2356&gt; B. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: The Sketchbook of 1824.</hi> Ed. with an Introduction and Commentary
by Martin Butlin and with a Foreword by William Vaughan. (London: Thames &amp; Hudson in association with the
William Blake Trust,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">37</ref> 2005) oblong
8°, 221 pp., including color reproductions of the sketchbook; ISBN: 0500976511 and ISBN 13: 9780500976517.
<note id="n37">37. The book was “Edited, designed and produced by the William Blake Trust” (5).</note></p>
                <p>It consists of:</p>
                <p>Anon. “Preface: The William Blake Trust.” 6.</p>
                <p>William Vaughan. “Foreword: Palmer and the ‘Revival of Art.’” 7-16.</p>
                <p>Martin Butlin. “Introduction: The 1824 Sketchbook.” 17-31. (Butlin has made
“extensive revision of his introduction and commentary of 1962” [6].)</p>
                <p>Sketchbook reproductions. 34-199.</p>
                <p>[Butlin.] “Commentary on the Sketchbook Pages.” 201-19.</p>
                <p>[Butlin.] “Appendix A: Leaves Removed from the Sketchbook.” 220. (The pages removed are
pp. 3-4, 15-16, 19-22, 25-26, 31-32, 49-50, 125-26, 137-38, 179-82.)</p>
                <p>[Butlin.] “Appendix B: Media Use in the Sketchbook.” 220.</p>
                <p>Wilcox, Timothy. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer.</hi> (London: Tate Publishing, 2005) British
Artists, 4°, 80 pp.; ISBN: 1854375636.</p>
                <p>Stothard, Thomas (1755-1834)</p>
                <p>Book illustrator, sometime friend of Blake</p>
                <p>A pencil portrait by Stothard of Blake (c. 1780), 4.5 × 4.0 cm. on laid paper 21.2 × 19.0
cm., inscribed in pencil probably by George Cumberland “Mr Blake Engraver by | Stothard”, was bought from
William Drummond in 2005 by Robert N. Essick and reproduced and described in his “Blake in the Marketplace,
2005,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 178-79.</p>
                <div6>
                  <head>
                    <title>
                      <hi rend="b">Appendix: Addenda to <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (2004)</hi>
                    </title>
                  </head>
                  <p>The most extensive and important discoveries of contemporary references to William Blake
and his relations since the second edition of <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> went to press concern the
Moravian faith of his mother before he was born<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">1</ref> and the will and family of his wife’s brother Henry Banes after his death.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n38">1. Keri Davies and Marsha Keith Schuchard, “Recovering the Lost Moravian History of William
Blake’s Family,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.1 (summer 2004): 36-43.</note>
	<note id="n39">2. Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’: The Will
of Henry Banes, Landlord of 3 Fountain Court, Strand, the Last Residence of William and Catherine Blake,”
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 78-99.</note></p>
                  <p>P. xix</p>
                  <p>Owners and Repositories of Unique Materials</p>
                  <p>Fitzwilliam Museum (including the ms. “Autobiography of John Linnell” formerly in the
collection of John S. Linnell).</p>
                  <p>P. xxxiv</p>
                  <p>To Boucher-Butcher genealogy for Catherine’s sister Sarah,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">3</ref> substitute fig. 1. <note id="n40">3. The new information
about the Banes and Best families derives from Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my
wearing apparel’ . . .,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 78-99.</note></p>
                  <p>Pp. 62fn, 741, 816, 894</p>
                  <p>For “Callisto” read “Calisto.”</p>
                  <pb id="p40-35" n="35"/>
                  <figure n="Boucher.genealogy.40.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="261">
                    <figTranscr>Sarah Boucher<lb/>
                      Battersea<lb/>
                      (1757-March 1824)<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      [married] 10 Nov. 1788<lb/>
                      St. Bride’s<lb/>
                      London<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      [to] Henry Banes<lb/>
                      St. Bride’s<lb/>
                      (d. 20 Jan. 1829)<lb/>
                      Wine cooper<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      [parents of] Louisa<lb/>
                      (?1790-?1845)<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      [married to] Richard Best<lb/>
                      (d. ?1839)<lb/>
                      Watch finisher<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      [parents of]<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      Charles<lb/>
                      St. Pancras<lb/>
                      (b. 1 April 1805)<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      Charlotte Louisa<lb/>
                      St. Pancras<lb/>
                      (b. 16 Aug. 1807)<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      Elizabeth<lb/>
                      St. Pancras<lb/>
                      (b. 19 Dec. 1809)<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      Thomas<lb/>
                      St. Pancras<lb/>
                      (b. 4 Dec. 1813)<lb/>
                      Print colorer, artist<lb/>
                      (exhibited 1834-39)<lb/>
                      <lb/>
                      Richard John<lb/>
                      St. Pancras<lb/>
                      (b. 20 March 1815)<lb/>
                      Artist</figTranscr>
                    <head>Fig. 1. Boucher-Butcher genealogy substitution for Sarah Boucher.</head>
                    <figDesc>Mrs. Best’s given name is spelled “Louisa” in the baptismal records of her
children, in the rate books of 3 Fountain Court (1839-44) and in the 1841 census; it appears as “Louiza”
in the transcripts of the will of Henry Banes (1826) and its proving (1829). Probably the correct spelling is
“Louisa” as in the name of her daughter Charlotte Louisa. Louisa’s age is derived from the census of
summer 1841 (reported by Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’ . .
.,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 [fall 2005]: 90, 91) in which she is said to be 50 years old and “ind”
(i.e., of independent means). The 1841 census identifies Thomas and Richard Best as artists.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>P. 67</p>
                  <p>For an advertisement in the <hi rend="i">Morning Chronicle</hi> for 21 July 1796 for
Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, see “William Blake and His Circle,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.1
(summer 2006): 17-18.</p>
                  <p>P. 246</p>
                  <p>Cromek industriously touted Blake’s designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> He
took them on a tour which included Edinburgh and arranged for a puff in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi>
for July 1807, quoted in David Groves, “‘Great and Singular Genius’: Further References to Blake (and
Cromek) in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 47.</p>
                  <p>The statement in the notice that “Mr Cromek . . . proposes to engrave them” means
“proposes to have them engraved,” for in May 1807 Cromek wrote to Blake about “Mr Schiavonetti . . .
etching a plate” for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and on 21 July 1807 Schiavonetti wrote to Cromek about
engraving “the last judgment.” The “beautiful painting of the procession of Chaucer’s pilgrims”
which Cromek exhibited was Stothard’s, not Blake’s.</p>
                  <p>P. 264</p>
                  <p>In September 1808, an advertisement appeared among a list of “New Works Published in
Edinburgh” in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi> 70 (1808): 683: “Illustrations of Blair’s Grave, in
12 Etchings, executed by Louis Schiavonetti, from the Original Inventions of William Blake, 4to. 2<hi
rend="i">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="i">s.</hi>6<hi rend="i">d.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n41" type="note">4</ref> And a long, generous review appeared in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi>
for November 1808 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 274-75). <note id="n41">4. Reported by David Groves (see article
under entry for p. 246).</note></p>
                  <p>P. 386</p>
                  <p>After “£49.6.8 in 1825,” see <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> in
“William Blake and His Circle,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.1 (summer 2006): 13-14.</p>
                  <p>P. 387</p>
                  <p>William Hazlitt’s essay “On the Old Age of Artists” (excerpt quoted in 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2] 446-47) was originally published in 1823; see “William Blake and His Circle,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.1 (summer 2006): 27.</p>
                  <p>P. 388</p>
                  <p>Sarah Banes, the sister and landlady of Catherine Blake, died in March 1824. She had been
the “sole Executrix and Legatee named in the . . . former Will” of her husband Henry Banes. 
<ref target="n42" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n42">5. Information about the death of Sarah Banes derives from the authentication (6 Feb. 1829) of
the will (9 Dec. 1826) of Henry Banes reproduced in Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of
my wearing apparel’ . . .,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 84-85.</note></p>
                  <pb id="p40-36" n="36"/>
                  <p>P. 399</p>
                  <p>After “Purgatorio, and Paradiso” add:</p>
                  <p>There is no record of the original cost of the copperplates for Dante, but it seems very
likely that Linnell acquired them, as he did those for <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1823, 1825), but neglected to
record them in his account books. As the weight of the 7 Dante plates (11,209 g) was more than that of the 22
plates for <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (10,516 g), the cost is likely to have been more than that for 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> (£3.11.7, not counting 2 plates unaccounted for).</p>
                  <p>P. 418</p>
                  <p>Footnote to “he fetched the porter for dinner himself, from the house at the corner of
the Strand.” <ref target="n43" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n43">6. The public house was the Coal Hole, beside the alley from the Strand leading to Fountain
Court (Angus Whitehead, “William Blake’s Last Residence: No. 3 Fountain Court, Strand, George Richmond’s
Plan and an Unrecorded Letter to John Linnell,” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.1 [spring/summer
2005]: 21-30 [22]). Henry Banes, vintner, may have been at the Coal Hole public house where Blake got his
porter.</note></p>
                  <p>P. 418</p>
                  <p>Letter of 25 November 1825 recorded in “William Blake and His Circle,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 32-33; for “Banes may well have lived in the same building”
substitute:</p>
                  <p>Banes lived in the ground-floor flat. When the four-storey house was built about 1720 as
a single family unit, almost certainly the kitchen occupied most of the basement. This basement was probably
larger than the Blakes’ exhibition room, which was 19′ × 14′.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n44" type="note">7</ref> After the death of his wife in March 1824, Banes may not have made much use
of his kitchen. <note id="n44">7. Angus Whitehead, “William Blake’s Last Residence . . .,” 
<hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.1 [spring/summer 2005]: 30.</note></p>
                  <p>P. 428</p>
                  <p>Footnote to Crabb Robinson, “He thinks all men partake of it [the faculty of
Vision]—but it is lost by not being cultiv<hi rend="s">d</hi>.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n45">
                                            8. George Richmond wrote in his copy of Gilchrist (1: 326), “He
said to me that all children saw ‘Visions’ and the substance of that [?i.e., what] he added is that all
might see them but for worldliness[?] or unbelief, which blinds the spiritual eye. GR”.
                                            <p>Richmond’s annotations in Gilchrist vol. 1 were quoted in G.
E. Bentley, Jr., “William Blake, Samuel Palmer and George Richmond,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 2.2
(1970): 43-50; those in vol. 2 in Angus Whitehead, “<hi rend="i">But, Kitty, I better love thee</hi>: George
Richmond’s Annotation to ‘Song [I love the jocund dance]’ in Volume II of Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1863),” <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> no. 9 (2005): 87-97. Vol. 1,
the only one I saw, was in 1969 in the collection of Anthony W. Richmond; both volumes now belong to Stephen
Keynes. None was included in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969, 2004).</p></note></p>
                  <p>P. 429</p>
                  <p>In “first printed in the <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Thomas Hollis</hi>,” delete
“first” and, for “but, though the face does seem different in graphic style and engraving technique from
the others in the book, the differences are not so idiosyncratic as to make it possible to say with confidence
either that they are by William Blake or that they are not by Cipriani,” substitute:</p>
                  <p>However, the etching of the bust of Milton in <hi rend="i">The Memoirs of Thomas
Hollis</hi> (1780) is identical to copies given away by Hollis in 1762 and 1765;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">9</ref> neither Blake nor any one else altered Cipriani’s etched
bust of Milton between 1762 and 1780. <note id="n46">9. David Wilson, “An Idle Speculation by Samuel Palmer:
William Blake’s Involvement in Cipriani’s Portrait of John Milton,” <hi rend="i">British Art
Journal</hi> 6.1 (spring/summer 2005): 31-36.</note></p>
                  <p>Pp. 446-47</p>
                  <p>Omit the Hazlitt references, which originally appeared in September 1823.</p>
                  <p>P. 453</p>
                  <p>The lawyer Henry Crabb Robinson called on Blake on 7 December 1826 to talk about the
recent death of John Flaxman. Perhaps this stimulated Blake’s brother-in-law Henry Banes to draw up his will
two days later, replacing that in which he had named his wife Sarah (d. 1824) as his sole heir and executrix.
In the new will of 9 December 1826, Henry Banes wrote:
<q>
    I give &amp; bequeath to Catherine Blake half my household goods consisting of Bedsteads Beds &amp;
pillows Bolsters &amp; sheets &amp; pillow Cases Tables Chairs &amp; crockery &amp; £20 in lawful money of
Great Britain <hi rend="sub">^</hi>I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel<hi
rend="sub">^</hi>—I also give &amp; bequeath to Louiza Best the remaining part of my household goods as
aforesaid with the Clock &amp; my Watch &amp; silver plate<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n47" type="note">10</ref> (&amp; pictures [what is worth her acceptance <hi rend="i">del</hi>]) and
all the remainder of my property in money &amp; outstanding debts of whatever nature or description for her
whole and sole use or disposal I also constitute and appoint the said Louiza Best my sole Executrix of this my
last Will and Testament—H. Banes Dec<hi rend="s">r.</hi> 9<hi rend="s">th</hi> 1826 Witness John
Barrow<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n47">10. The clerical transcription of the will dutifully reproduces as an interlineation the
phrase “I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel,” but the phrase “&amp; silver plate” is
not so distinguished, though the authenticating document remarks “the interlineation of the words ‘I also
beg M<hi rend="s">r.</hi> Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’ between the 10<hi rend="s">th</hi> and
11<hi rend="s">th</hi> lines and the words ‘&amp; silver plate[’] between the 13<hi rend="s">th</hi> and
14<hi rend="s">th</hi> lines.”</note>
	<note id="n48">11. The will is reproduced in Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my
wearing apparel’ . . .,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 84-85.</note></q>
No other beneficiary is named. His property therefore went to his sister-in-law Catherine Blake, his
brother-in-law William Blake, and his daughter Louisa Best, though their relationships to him are not
specified.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n49">12. The relationship of Henry Banes to Louisa Best is merely a very probable hypothesis, based
chiefly on her roles as (1) executrix (replacing Sarah Banes in the former will), (2) chief legatee, and (3)
discoverer (with her son) of his will in Jan. 1829.</note></p>
                  <p>Did the pictures include any by his brother-in-law William Blake? And were the watch and
clock made by his son-in-law Richard Best, watch finisher?</p>
                  <pb id="p40-37" n="37"/>
                  <p>The specification that the bequests to Louisa Best were “for her whole and sole use”
was to ensure that they did not pass to the control of her husband, as they would otherwise have done by law
and convention.</p>
                  <p>The bequest to Blake of Banes’ “wearing apparel” suggests that they were similar in
size (Blake was 5′6″ tall and sturdy) and that for reasons of size or affection Banes preferred that his
clothes should go to Blake rather than to his son-in-law Richard Best.</p>
                  <p>P. 457fn</p>
                  <p>To the record of the burial of James Blake from Bunhill Fields Indexes in Somerset House
add:</p>
                  <p>According to the Bunhill Fields Burying Ground Order Book in Guildhall (reproduced in the
typescript of Luis and Carol Garrido’s excellent “William Blake’s Final Resting Place” [2005] 96, 98),
“James Blake [Age] 71 years [<hi rend="i">was</hi> Brought from] 7 Cirencester Place [<hi rend="i">and
buried in a</hi> Grave] 11 feet [<hi rend="i">deep</hi>] [E&amp;W] 52..53 [N&amp;S] 62.” This adds the house
number of the street from which the body was brought, and the exact location of the grave. Linnell had a house
at 6 Cirencester Place.</p>
                  <p>P. 464</p>
                  <p>Footnote to George Richmond’s letter to Samuel Palmer of 15 August 1827.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n50">13. Beside the version of this letter in Gilchrist (1: 362) without the names of recipient or
author, George Richmond wrote in his copy: “This note was written to Mr Palmer b<hi rend="i">y</hi> Geo.
Richmond.”</note></p>
                  <p>P. 493</p>
                  <p>20 January 1829</p>
                  <p>Henry Banes, Catherine’s brother-in-law, died on 20 January 1829, and his will was
authenticated on 6 February by his daughter Louisa Best and her son Thomas.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">14</ref> By its terms (see 9 December 1826), Catherine Blake was to
inherit “half my household goods consisting of Bedsteads Beds &amp; pillows Bolsters &amp; sheets &amp;
pillow Cases Tables Chairs &amp; crockery &amp; £20.” The “wearing apparel” bequeathed to Blake
probably stayed with Louisa Best, for her husband or sons—her firstborn, Charles, would have been 23 in
February 1829. The furniture Catherine did not much need,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">15</ref> as she was staying with Frederick Tatham and his wife. However, when she moved in the
spring of 1829 to lodgings with a baker at 17 Upper Charlotte Street<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n53" type="note">16</ref> the furnishings might have proved useful to her. By this time she was
accumulating significant resources, with the bequest of £20 from Henry Banes in February 1829 (presuming it
was paid) plus the £84 from Lord Egremont for Blake’s “The Characters of Spenser’s <hi rend="i">Fairie
Queene</hi>” in August 1829<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">17</ref> and
the sale of other works by Blake. These resources made her feel sufficiently comfortable to ask on 5 January
1830 that an application on her behalf to the charity of the Artists’ General Benevolent Association should
be withdrawn,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">18</ref> and some time “after
Blake’s death” she returned the “gift of £100” sent her by Princess Sophia.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n51">14. The will and its proving (Public Record Office: PROB 11/1751, Liverpool Quire 51-100) are
reproduced in Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’ . . .,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 84-85.</note>
	<note id="n52">15. Linnell paid her £1.10.0 in April 1828 for “Furniture sold” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> [2]
808).</note>
	<note id="n53">16. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 755.</note>
	<note id="n54">17. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 498.</note>
	<note id="n55">18. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 501-02.</note>
	<note id="n56">19. Seymour Kirkup reported by Swinburne (1868); see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2)
462-63.</note></p>
                  <p>P. 504</p>
                  <p>For the review in the <hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris</hi> for 9 February 1830 of
Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> (1830) with its account of Blake, see David Groves, “Blake and the
<hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.3 (winter 2005-06): 125.</p>
                  <p>It is striking that the same two paragraphs about Blake’s courtship and marriage are
quoted in this review and in the <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> (6 Feb. 1830), <hi rend="i">London Literary
Gazette</hi> (6 Feb. 1830), <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi> (13 Feb. 1830), 
<hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi> (20 Feb. 1830), <hi rend="i">Fraser’s Magazine</hi> (March 1830),
and <hi rend="i">New Jerusalem Magazine</hi> (Jan. 1832).</p>
                  <p>P. 534</p>
                  <p>Correct the entry in Linnell’s journal for “Friday 3<hi rend="s">d</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">August</hi>]” 1830 to “Friday 3<hi rend="s">d</hi> [<hi rend="i">September</hi>]” and omit the
duplicate entry for Friday 3 September 1830.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n57">
                                            20. The entry is correctly dated but only approximately
transcribed by John Linnell, Jr., as given in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969) 401. In Linnell’s
original journal, discovered by GEB in 1970, the dates are mostly implied rather than explicit, and I
misinterpreted the implied month as Aug. in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2). In 1830, 3 Aug. was a Tuesday and 3
Sept. a Friday.
                                            <p>The error was pointed out by Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg
Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’ . . .,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005):
88n58.</p></note></p>
                  <p>P. 570</p>
                  <p>Footnote to “Kitty, I better love thee.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n58">21. In his copy of Gilchrist (1863), 2: 6, George Richmond underlined the word “Kitty” and
annotated it in the margin: “His good Wifes name.” Angus Whitehead, “<hi rend="i">But, Kitty, I better
love thee</hi>: George Richmond’s Annotation to ‘Song [I love the jocund dance]’ in Volume II of
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1863),” <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> no. 9 (2005):
87-97, reproduces the page and argues that “Kitty” is Catherine Boucher whom Blake married in 1782, even
though, according to the Advertisement to <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783) in which the poem
appears, since “his twentieth year” (1777) Blake had not had “the leisure requisite to . . . revis[e] .
. . these sheets,”</note></p>
                  <p>P. 625</p>
                  <p>Footnote to J. T. Smith, “lighting the fire.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n59" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n59">22. By this passage in his copy of Gilchrist (1: 315), George Richmond wrote: “I remember
his saying to m<hi rend="i">e</hi>, that he saw the devil when lighting the fire. Not in the fire but in
himself. This was his way of confessing his natural impatience[.] | G R.” For Catherine’s drawing of
“something she saw in the fire,” see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 608fn.</note></p>
                  <pb id="p40-38" n="38"/>
                  <p>P. 626</p>
                  <p>Footnote to Blake “was buried in Bunhill-fields, . . . at the distance of about
twenty-five feet from the north wall.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n60">23. “Twenty-five feet” is a mistake for 25 yards or paces, as Luis and Carol Garrido point
out in “William Blake’s Final Resting Place” (2005) 49.</note></p>
                  <p>P. 704</p>
                  <p>Footnote to Crabb Robinson’s report of 13 June 1826, “He was as wild as
ever.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n61">24. Beside this passage in his copy of Gilchrist (1: 350), George Richmond wrote: “I must
say that Mr Crabb Robinson[’]s conclusion that Blake was mad was the very kindliest one he could come to, if
h<hi rend="i">e</hi> believes his own journal.”</note></p>
                  <p>P. 735</p>
                  <p>To “28 Broad Street” after <hi rend="i">“The New Complete Guide”</hi> add: and
William <hi rend="i">Bailey’s Western and Midland Directory</hi> (Birmingham, 1783) 14 (only “Carnaby
Market”).</p>
                  <p>P. 735</p>
                  <p>Under “28 Broad Street” at the beginning of the bottom paragraph, add:</p>
                  <p>“Blake, James, and Son, <hi rend="i">Hosiers and Haberdashers</hi>, Carnaby-market”
appears in William <hi rend="i">Bailey’s British Directory or, Merchant’s and Trader’s Useful Companion,
For the Year 1784</hi> (1784), and next year, after the death of the elder James Blake, “Blake, James, 
<hi rend="i">Haberdasher</hi>, 28, Broad-str. Carnaby-Market” appears in <hi rend="i">Bailey’s</hi>
(1785).</p>
                  <p>P. 741</p>
                  <p>Under “27 Broad Street” add at end:</p>
                  <p>“Blake and Parker, <hi rend="i">Print-sellers</hi>, 27, ditto [<hi rend="i">i.e.</hi>,
Broad-Str. Carnaby-Market]” are listed with James Blake, 28 Broad Street, in William Bailey, 
<hi rend="i">Bailey’s British Directory or, Merchant’s and Trader’s Useful Companion, For the Year 1785</hi>
(London: dedication dated June 1785) 32.</p>
                  <p>P. 742</p>
                  <p>To end of “29 Broad Street” add:</p>
                  <p>“Stephen Horncastle, Stationer, 29 Broad Street, Carnaby Market” is listed in William
<hi rend="i">Bailey’s British Directory or, Merchant’s and Trader’s Useful Companion, For the Year
1785</hi> (London: dedication dated June 1785) 144; he may have been a sitting tenant when Blake’s brother
John paid the rates (1784-93) for 29 Broad Street, for Stephen Horncastle (d. 14 Jan. 1792), Stationer, was
listed in directories at Broad Street, Carnaby Market (1763-88), 29, Broad Street (1779-88); 85, New Bond
Street (or New Broad Street) (1789-99), but trading as William Horncastle (1794-99).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n62">25. Ian Maxted, <hi rend="i">The London Book Trades 1775-1800: A Preliminary Checklist of
Members</hi> (Folkestone: Dawson, 1977) 115; Horncastle is not in William B. Todd, <hi rend="i">A Directory of
Printers and Others in Allied Trades London and Vicinity 1800-1840</hi> (1972) or <hi rend="i">Stationers’
Company Apprentices 1701-1800</hi>, ed. D. F. McKenzie (1978).</note></p>
                  <p>P. 749</p>
                  <p>For “The rates for 17 South Molton Street were paid by Mark Martin, who was presumably
Blake’s landlord,” read:</p>
                  <p>The rates for 17 South Molton Street while the Blakes lived there were paid in March 1804
by a tailor named “Will<hi rend="s">m</hi> Enoch”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">26</ref> and in March 1805-21 by Mark Martin. <note id="n63">26. All the information here about
the Enochs derives from Angus Whitehead, “New Information Concerning Mrs Enoch, William and Catherine
Blake’s ‘Fellow Inhabitant’ at 17 South Molton Street,” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 250 [ns
52] (2005): 460-63. The ratepayer information is from the rate books in Brook Street Ward, St. George’s,
Hanover Square, in the City of Westminster Archives, and the information that Enoch was a “taylor” is from
<hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory 1805-6-7</hi> (London, 1805) and . . . <hi rend="i">1808-9-10</hi>
(London, 1808). Information for the 1805 directory was presumably collected in 1804 or early 1805 and repeated
anachronistically in that for 1808.</note></p>
                  <p>P. 750</p>
                  <p>Under “17 South Molton Street,” for “There were other lodgers in the house as well,
including ‘our Kind &amp; attentive fellow inhabitant, the young &amp; very amiable M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>
Enoch, who gave my wife all the attention that a daughter could pay to a mother’ until Blake’s return from
his trial on 14 January 1804,” read:</p>
                  <p>Soon after the Blakes moved into 17 South Molton Street in the autumn of 1803, they
formed a close friendship with their landlord William Enoch, who probably lived above his ground-floor tailor
shop, and with his twenty-one year old wife Mary (née Naylor) and presumably with their son William (born
1801). When Blake went to Chichester for his trial for sedition in January 1804, his wife was prostrated with
worry and “near the Gate of Death as was supposed by our Kind &amp; attentive fellow inhabitant, the young
&amp; very amiable M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Enoch, who gave my wife all the attention that a daughter could pay
to a mother,” as Blake reported in his letter of 14 January 1804 on his triumphal return, a free man.</p>
                  <p>P. 750</p>
                  <p>Under “Cirencester Place” for James Blake, for “Cirencester Place” three times
read “7 Cirencester Place,” and at the end add “John Linnell had a house at 6 Cirencester
Place.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n64">27. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 477fn, 482, 854.</note></p>
                  <p>P. 751</p>
                  <p>Under “3 Fountain Court,” for “the rooms were small and dark,” delete “small
and” and add a paragraph after “the radiance of their occupants”:</p>
                  <p>The Blakes had “the most spacious rooms in the house.” The front room, which Blake
used to exhibit his pictures and probably to house his press, was 19′ × 13′6″, and the back room
leading from it, where the Blakes slept, cooked, and worked, was 12′ × 13′9″.</p>
                  <p>The Poor Rates were paid by Henry Ba[i]nes in 1803-22, 1826-28, by Mary Banes in 1823,
and by both in 1824-25.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">28</ref>
	<pb id="p40-39" n="39"/>
Richard Best paid the rates from 1829<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">29</ref> to 1838, when presumably he died, after which they were paid by Louisa Best until 1844,
when presumably she in turn died; in 1845 she was replaced as ratepayer by William Walker. <note id="n65">28.
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 751fn for 1820-29, supplemented by Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance
of my wearing apparel’ . . .,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 80, 82, 90. “Mary” Banes may
refer to Henry’s wife Sarah; however, since Sarah died in 1824, this suggests that the 1825 record was in
error, mechanically repeating the entry for the previous year.</note>
	<note id="n66">29. <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 751 fn.</note></p>
                  <p>P. 752</p>
                  <p>Footnote § describing Fountain Court, add at the end:</p>
                  <p>The building “was finally demolished <hi rend="i">c</hi>1902” (Angus Whitehead,
“William Blake’s Last Residence. . .,” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.1 [2005] 29).</p>
                  <p>P. 753</p>
                  <p>After “bar of gold” add:</p>
                  <p>Perhaps the plan was the one Richmond sketched in his copy of Gilchrist (1: 305) on the
page where the description of Fountain Court begins.</p>
                  <p>“Blake’s fellow lodgers [who] were humble but respectable”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">30</ref> presumably include his wife’s niece Louisa Best and her
family. Louisa Best may well have been the “humble female neighbour” who was Catherine’s “only other
companion” when Blake died. The children playing below the window of 3 Fountain Court of whom Blake said
“That is heaven,” may have been his wife’s grandnephews and grandnieces. <note id="n67">30. Gilchrist
(1863) 308 (one hopes based on Samuel Palmer) in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> (2) 752.</note></p>
                  <p>John Barrow (1757-1838) the artist and printseller (e.g., of Blake’s “Mrs Q”
[1820]) lived at 3 Fountain Court at least in 1831-38.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">31</ref> Perhaps he moved there after Catherine Blake moved out in September 1827, as Whitehead
suggests. <note id="n68">31. The entries for John Barrow in the exhibitions of the Royal Academy for 1831,
1835, and 1836 and for the Society of British Artists in 1832 and 1836 give his address as Fountain Court, and
<hi rend="i">Robson’s London Directory</hi> (London: William Robson, 1832) gives it at 3 Fountain Court,
(Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’ . . .,” <hi rend="i">Blake
39.2</hi> [fall 2005]: 92n87). John Barrow of 3 Fountain Court, age 81, was buried at St. Clement Danes on 25
March 1838 (Whitehead 92n91).</note></p>
                  <p>P. 754</p>
                  <p>For information on the Banes and Best families and on John Barrow, residents of the
apartments at 3 Fountain Court, Strand, while the Blakes lived there in 1821-27, see fig. 1 and the entries
for pp. 418, 439, 453, 493, 751 and 753 above.</p>
                  <p>Other residents at 3 Fountain Court probably included a family named Walker, for Martha
Walker of 3 Fountain Court, age 3 weeks, was buried at St. Clement Danes, Strand, on 8 January 1816, and
William Walker took over payment of the rates at 3 Fountain Court from Louisa Best in 1845.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n69">32. See Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’ . .
.,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 [fall 2005]: 82, 90n75.</note></p>
                  <p>P. 755</p>
                  <p>Under “Lisson Grove”:</p>
                  <p>Catherine Blake lived with Tatham from April 1828 until she removed to Upper Charlotte
Street by 11 April 1829 (not “early 1830”).</p>
                  <p>P. 778</p>
                  <p>Catherine Blake was bequeathed £20 in February 1829 in the will of her brother-in-law
Henry Banes.</p>
                  <p>P. 804</p>
                  <p>To footnote ‡ add:</p>
                  <p>See 25 March 1823.</p>
                  <p>P. 811</p>
                  <table rows="3" cols="2">
                    <row>
                      <cell>Payments to Catherine 1827-31<lb/>
1829 from Will of Henry Banes</cell>
                      <cell>
                        <hi rend="u">£20. 0. 0</hi>
                      </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>1827-31</cell>
                      <cell>£224.15.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <cell>1782-1831</cell>
                      <cell>£2,043.19.5</cell>
                    </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>P. 839</p>
                  <p>For “Eight engravings by W.S. Blake (1798-1809) are known,” read:</p>
                  <p>Twenty-five engravings (1783-1809) by W.S. Blake are known, including seventeen trade
cards.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">33</ref>
	<note id="n70">33. See <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 37 (1988): 127-33.</note></p>
                </div6>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Index</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Ackroyd, Peter 20</p>
              <p>Adams, Hazard 20</p>
              <p>Angelo, Valenti 12</p>
              <p>Antonielli, Arianna 21</p>
              <p>Arnaud, Danielle 19</p>
              <p>Bainbridge, Simon 30</p>
              <p>Barfoot, C. C. 21</p>
              <p>Barker, Elizabeth E. 33</p>
              <p>Barker, Nicolas 19</p>
              <p>Barrow, John 7, 22, 36, 39</p>
              <p>Baulch, David 32</p>
              <p>Beaumont, Matthew 31</p>
              <p>Beer, John 6, 21</p>
              <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. 30</p>
              <p>Bentley, A. E. K. L. B. 4, 9, 10, 11, 18</p>
              <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 4, 6, 9, 10, 11, 18, 20, 21, 23, 32</p>
              <p>Bidney, Martin 21</p>
              <p>Billigheimer, Rachel V. 21</p>
              <p>Bindman, David 33</p>
              <p>Blackstock, Colin 21</p>
              <p>Blackstone, Bernard 21</p>
              <p>Blake, Robin 34</p>
              <p>Blake, William:<lb/>
<hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> 12; <hi rend="i">America</hi> 12, 31; <hi rend="i">Book of Ahania</hi>
9, 10; <hi rend="i">Book of Los</hi> 9, 10, 12; <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> 4, 12, 28; <hi rend="i">Book of
Urizen</hi> 4, 10, 31; <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 9, 10, 12, 31; <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> 22, 29; 
<hi rend="i">French Revolution 22; Jerusalem</hi> 19, 32; Letters 4, 9, 10, 32; <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 4, 9,
10, 12, 30, 31; <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 4, 10, 23, 25, 27, 30, 31; <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> 4, 23;
Receipt 11; “Riddle” ms. 4, 9, 11;
<pb id="p40-40" n="40"/>
Self-portrait 7, 9, 22; <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> 11, 12; <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 4, 9, 10, 11, 12, 23,
26, 27, 28, 29, 31; <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> 12; <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> 24; 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 4, 11, 23, 31<lb/>
Illustrations/engravings of/for:<lb/>
Adams 13; Allen 13; Ariosto 13; <hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque Magazine</hi> 5, 13; Bible (Job) 4, 5, 6,
7, 13-14, 29, 31, 35, 36; Blair, <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> 5, 6, 13, 14, 20, 21, 22, 24, 26, 27, 29, 35; Blower
5, 14; <hi rend="i">Boydell’s Shakspeare</hi> 14; Brown 14; Bürger 14; <hi rend="i">Cabinet of the
Arts</hi> 5, 14-15; Catullus 15; Chaucer 15; Commins 15; Cumberland 15; Dante 4, 13, 15, 23, 26, 36; Darwin
15; Earle 15; Emlyn 15; Enfield 15; Euler 16; Flaxman 16; Fuseli 16; Gay 16; [Gough] 16; Gray 13; Hamilton 16;
Hartley 16; Hayley 16; Henry 16; Hoare 16; Hogarth 16; Hunter 16; Josephus 16; Kimpton 16; Lavater 16-17;
Malkin 17; Nicholson 17; <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi> 17; Olivier 17; Rees 17; 
<hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi> 17; Ritson 17; Scott 17; Seally and Lyons 17; Shakespeare 17; Stedman 5, 17-18, 32;
Stuart and Revett 18; Varley 18; <hi rend="i">Vetusta Monumenta</hi> 18; Virgil 4, 18; Whitaker 18; 
<hi rend="i">Wit’s Magazine</hi> 18; Wollstonecraft 5, 18; Young 4-5, 6, 7, 13, 18-19<lb/>
Burial 26, 28, 38<lb/>
Family 7, 22, 24, 31, 33, 34-39 passim<lb/>
Residences 7, 19, 29, 32, 36, 38, 39</p>
              <p>Bode, Christoph 23</p>
              <p>Boehme, Jacob 23, 24</p>
              <p>Borges, Jorge Luis 23</p>
              <p>Braida, Antonella 23</p>
              <p>Braithwaite, Helen 33</p>
              <p>Brewis, Kathy 34</p>
              <p>Brown, David Blayney 33</p>
              <p>Burrows, David 19</p>
              <p>Bushnell, Jack 32</p>
              <p>Butlin, Martin 34</p>
              <p>Cabañas Alamán, Rafael 23</p>
              <p>Capurro, Soledad 12</p>
              <p>Carey, Frances 19</p>
              <p>Casassas Figueres, Enric 10</p>
              <p>Catling, Brian 19</p>
              <p>Chauvin, Danièle 23</p>
              <p>Chevalier, Tracy 19</p>
              <p>Church, Michael 23</p>
              <p>Ciompi, Fausto 23</p>
              <p>Ciseri, Ilaria 23</p>
              <p>Clark, Steve 11</p>
              <p>Connolly, Tristanne J. 23</p>
              <p>Corti, Claudia 23</p>
              <p>Cowan, Derek 12</p>
              <p>Cox, Judy 23-24</p>
              <p>Coy, Phil 19</p>
              <p>Cumberland, George 4, 26, 32-33, 34</p>
              <p>Cunningham, Allan 21, 22, 37</p>
              <p>Curran, Stuart 11</p>
              <p>Davies, Charlotte 23</p>
              <p>Davies, J. G. 24</p>
              <p>Davies, Keri 34n</p>
              <p>Demetriou, Danielle 24</p>
              <p>den Otter, Alice G. 26</p>
              <p>Dent, Shirley 24</p>
              <p>De Selincourt, Basil 24</p>
              <p>Directories 24, 32, 38</p>
              <p>Doce, Jordi 24</p>
              <p>Dorment, Richard 34</p>
              <p>Dörrbecker, D. W. 24</p>
              <p>Doyle, Brian 24</p>
              <p>Easton, Will 23</p>
              <p>Eaves, Morris 21, 24</p>
              <p>Eichhorn, Thomas 20</p>
              <p>El-Hage, George Nicolas 24</p>
              <p>Erdman, David V. 24</p>
              <p>Erle, Sibylle 21, 24, 31</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert N. 5, 7, 10, 11, 13, 14-15, 18n, 20, 21, 22, 33, 34</p>
              <p>Esterhammer, Angela 25</p>
              <p>Evans, Jean 19</p>
              <p>Evans, Mark 22, 31</p>
              <p>Exhibitions:</p>
              <p>Cloud &amp; Vision 6, 19; McKeever 19; Palmer 33-34</p>
              <p>Facsimiles 4-5, 11</p>
              <p>Fallon, David 22</p>
              <p>Fenton, James 21</p>
              <p>Fischer, Kevin 23, 24</p>
              <p>Fisher, Peter F. 24</p>
              <p>Flaxman, John 4, 36</p>
              <p>Freedman, Carl 25</p>
              <p>Frye, Northrop 12, 25-26</p>
              <p>Fuller, David 22, 29</p>
              <p>Fuseli, Henry 27</p>
              <p>Garrido, Luis and Carol 26, 28, 37, 38n</p>
              <p>Gaunt, William 26</p>
              <p>Ghita, Catalin 26</p>
              <p>Gilchrist, Alexander 7, 23, 26</p>
              <p>Gimeno Suances, Francisco 26</p>
              <p>Gleckner, Robert F. 26</p>
              <p>Gnappi, Carla Maria 26</p>
              <p>Goldman, Bill 23</p>
              <p>Gould, Polly 19</p>
              <p>Gourlay, Alexander 6, 20, 22, 26, 28, 31</p>
              <p>Graves, Roy Neil 26</p>
              <p>Greathead, Alexandra 33</p>
              <p>Green, Matthew 26</p>
              <p>Groves, David 21, 22, 35, 37</p>
              <p>Halmi, Nicholas 26</p>
              <p>Hamlyn, Robin 5, 7, 13</p>
              <p>Harper, Andy 19</p>
              <p>Harper, George Mills 26</p>
              <p>Harris, James 26</p>
              <p>Harrison, Colin 33</p>
              <p>Hartigan, David Sean 26</p>
              <p>Hastings, Sheena 26-27</p>
              <p>Hayley, William 10</p>
              <p>Haywood, Peter 27, 33</p>
              <p>Hazlitt, William 27, 36</p>
              <p>Heath, Tim 19</p>
              <p>Heringman, Noah 27</p>
              <p>Hoagwood, T. 29</p>
              <p>Hobday, Charles 22</p>
              <p>Holmes, Richard 7, 26</p>
              <p>Hugo, Victor 23</p>
              <p>Ima-Izumi, Yoko 27, 28</p>
              <p>Ishizuka, Hisao 27, 28</p>
              <p>Iwasaki, Toyotaro 27</p>
              <p>Jacobson, Howard 22</p>
              <p>Jasper, David 27</p>
              <p>Jenkins, Simon 34</p>
              <p>Johnson, Joseph 27, 33</p>
              <p>Johnston, Kenneth 28</p>
              <p>Jönsson, Julia 22, 31</p>
              <p>Kaplan, Carter 27</p>
              <p>Kaplan, Jordan 19</p>
              <p>Kawasaki, Noriko 27</p>
              <p>Kazin, Alfred 12</p>
              <p>Kennedy, Maev 27</p>
              <p>Keynes, Geoffrey 19</p>
              <p>Kim, Minho 27</p>
              <p>Kirby, Bryan 24</p>
              <pb id="p40-41" n="41"/>
              <p>Kitamura, Kensuke 27</p>
              <p>Kotani, Mayumi 27</p>
              <p>Kroeber, Karl 21, 24</p>
              <p>Lambirth, Andrew 6, 19</p>
              <p>Larrissy, Edward 27</p>
              <p>Lavater, Johann Caspar 24, 26</p>
              <p>Lee, Seunghun 28</p>
              <p>Lindop, Grevel 28</p>
              <p>Linnell, John 14, 28, 32, 34, 36, 37, 38</p>
              <p>Locke, John 26</p>
              <p>Longacre, Jeffrey 23</p>
              <p>Lucas, E. V. 28</p>
              <p>Lussier, Mark 23, 24, 26, 28, 29, 30</p>
              <p>Makdisi, Saree 28</p>
              <p>Malone, Mary E. 9, 10</p>
              <p>Malvern, Jack 28</p>
              <p>Mañé Garzön, Pablo 12</p>
              <p>Marshall, Jacqueline 12</p>
              <p>Martin, Julia 28</p>
              <p>Matsushima, Shoichi 28</p>
              <p>McKeever, Ian 19</p>
              <p>Mee, Jon 28</p>
              <p>Melikian, Souren 34</p>
              <p>Milton, John 20, 21, 22, 29, 30, 32, 36</p>
              <p>Miner, Paul 28</p>
              <p>Munson, Amelia H. 4, 12</p>
              <p>Nagashima, Kazuhiko 28</p>
              <p>Naito, Takako 28</p>
              <p>Nakamura, Hiroko 29</p>
              <p>Newman, Jon 19</p>
              <p>Newton, Isaac 30</p>
              <p>Noah, Sherna 29</p>
              <p>Norman, Philip 19</p>
              <p>Nosková, Martina 29</p>
              <p>O’Neill, Michael 21</p>
              <p>Ormsby, Bronwyn 22, 31</p>
              <p>Otto, Peter 29</p>
              <p>Paglia, Camille 29</p>
              <p>Paley, Morton D. 22, 23, 29</p>
              <p>Palmer, Samuel 14, 21, 32, 33-34, 37</p>
              <p>Palomares, José Luis 10</p>
              <p>Pearce, Brian Louis 23</p>
              <p>Phillips, Michael 10, 19, 20, 29, 30</p>
              <p>Phillips, Thomas 4</p>
              <p>Pierce, John B. 21, 23, 29</p>
              <p>Pinto, Vivian de Sola 29</p>
              <p>Plotnitsky, Arkady 29</p>
              <p>Portela, Manuel 4, 12</p>
              <p>Quincy, John 6, 20</p>
              <p>Raine, Kathleen 28, 29</p>
              <p>Raverat, Jacques 4, 10</p>
              <p>Reynolds, Nigel 29-30</p>
              <p>Ribadeneira, Manuela 19</p>
              <p>Richmond, George 7, 23, 32, 36n, 37, 38n, 39</p>
              <p>Rix, Robert William 30</p>
              <p>Robinson, Henry Crabb 36, 38</p>
              <p>Röden, Peter Ulrick 30</p>
              <p>Rosenfeld, Alvin A. 30</p>
              <p>Ross, Theodore 12</p>
              <p>Rudd, Margaret E. 30</p>
              <p>Rudy, John G. 30</p>
              <p>Rutland, Laura Ellen 30</p>
              <p>Ryskamp, Charles 10, 15</p>
              <p>Ryu, Son-Moo 30</p>
              <p>Sato, Hikari 30</p>
              <p>Schneider, Matthew 30</p>
              <p>Schock, Peter A. 30</p>
              <p>Schofield, Jennifer 23</p>
              <p>Schorer, Mark 30</p>
              <p>Schott, G. D. 30</p>
              <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith 30, 34n</p>
              <p>Scrivener, Michael 28</p>
              <p>Sewell, Brian 34</p>
              <p>Shelley, Marjorie 33</p>
              <p>Singer, June 30</p>
              <p>Sklar, Susanne 22, 23, 24</p>
              <p>Snart, Jason 6, 20, 29, 30</p>
              <p>Solomon, Andrew 23, 29</p>
              <p>Spector, Sheila A. 19, 29, 30</p>
              <p>Speidel, Nadine Dalton 31</p>
              <p>Stevens, Bethan 13</p>
              <p>Stevenson, Warren 22</p>
              <p>Stevenson, W.H. 24</p>
              <p>Stothard, Thomas 14n, 34, 35</p>
              <p>Sturrock, June 31</p>
              <p>Suied, Alain 31</p>
              <p>Sung, Mei-Ying 5, 7, 14n, 27, 31</p>
              <p>Suzuki, Masashi 28, 31</p>
              <p>Swedenborg, Emanuel 32</p>
              <p>Symons, Arthur 31</p>
              <p>Takahashi, Hiroko 28</p>
              <p>Tambling, Jeremy 7, 23, 31</p>
              <p>Tanaka, Minne 23, 29</p>
              <p>Tatham, Frederick 22, 37, 39</p>
              <p>Thompson, E. P. 21</p>
              <p>Tokareva, G. 31</p>
              <p>Townsend, Joyce H. 22, 31</p>
              <p>Van Kleeck, Justin 22</p>
              <p>Vaughan, William 33, 34</p>
              <p>Vidili, Julia 10</p>
              <p>Viscomi, Joseph 9, 10, 11</p>
              <p>Wada, Ayako 31</p>
              <p>Wardi, Eynel 31</p>
              <p>Warner, Janet 31</p>
              <p>Watermarks 9</p>
              <p>Weir, David 21, 31</p>
              <p>Wethered, Newton 32</p>
              <p>Whiles, Annie 19</p>
              <p>White, Harry 22</p>
              <p>Whitehead, Angus 7, 17, 22, 23, 24, 27n, 29, 32, 34-39 passim</p>
              <p>Whitson, Roger 28</p>
              <p>Whittaker, Jason 21, 24, 29, 32</p>
              <p>Wilcox, Scott 33</p>
              <p>Wilcox, Timothy 34</p>
              <p>William Blake Archive 4, 12, 13, 15</p>
              <p>Wilson, David 21, 32, 36n</p>
              <p>Wilson, Frances 34</p>
              <p>Wilton, Andrew 11</p>
              <p>Windle, John 6, 11, 18, 19, 20</p>
              <p>Wood, Marcus 32</p>
              <p>Woodfine, Sarah 19</p>
              <p>Wright, Julia M. 32</p>
              <p>Yamazaki, Yusuke 32</p>
              <p>Yanagi, Muneyoshi 28, 29</p>
              <p>Yeats, W. B. 12, 20, 21</p>
              <p>Yoder, R. Paul 32</p>
              <p>Zeng, Fangrong 32</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
