<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.1.groves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“This Class of Impostors”: Robert Cromek’s View of London Booksellers and
Engravers</title>
        <author n="Groves">David Groves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>C.S Matheson</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>William Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Betteridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-1-0008">
        <pb id="p40-45" n="45"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“This Class of Impostors”: Robert Cromek’s View of London Booksellers and
Engravers</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>David <name>Groves</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Robert Hartley Cromek’s brief friendship with William Blake around 1805-06 is well known to
readers of <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> So, too, is Blake’s deep resentment of Cromek, after Cromek hired Luigi
Schiavonetti (rather than Blake himself) to engrave Blake’s designs for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The
Grave</hi>, which Cromek published in 1808. But no scholar has ever cited Cromek’s jaundiced account of
London publishers, which he wrote at about the same time in his edition of the <hi rend="i">Reliques of Robert
Burns.</hi> As Cromek himself had been an engraver in London, and was now making a living in publishing, his
observations have some weight.</p>
          <p>Cromek’s account occurs in a footnote to Robert Burns’s letter of 2 February 1790 to the
Edinburgh bookseller Peter Hill. In that letter, the Scottish poet is asking the bookseller to look for
“‘Banks’s new and complete Christian’s Family Bible,’ printed for C. Cooke, Paternoster-row,
London,” which was then coming out in installments. “He promises,” Burns explains, “to give . . . I
think it is three hundred and odd engravings, to which he has put the names of the first artists in
London.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">1</ref> Here it is interesting to
recall that William Blake did some engraving in his early years for similar works like the <hi rend="i">Royal
Universal Family Bible</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Protestants Family Bible.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">2</ref> Burns’s interest in the <hi rend="i">Christian’s Family
Bible</hi> provoked the following caustic comment from Cromek:
<q>
Perhaps no set of men more effectually avail themselves of the easy credulity of the public, than a certain
description of Paternoster-row booksellers. Three hundred and odd engravings!—and by the <hi rend="i">first
artists</hi> in London, too! No wonder that Burns was dazzled by the splendour of the promise. It is no
unusual thing for this class of impostors to <hi rend="i">illustrate</hi> the <hi rend="i">Holy
Scriptures</hi> by plates originally engraved for the <hi rend="i">History of England</hi>, and I have
actually seen subjects designed by our celebrated artist [Thomas] Stothard, from <hi rend="i">Clarissa
Harlowe</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, converted, with incredible dexterity, by these
Bookselling-Breslaws, into <hi rend="i">Scriptural embellishments</hi>! One of these vendors of “Family
Bibles” lately called on me, to consult me professionally, about a folio engraving he brought with him.—It
represented Mons. Buffon, seated, contemplating various groups of animals that surrounded him: He merely
wished, he said, to be informed whether by <hi rend="i">uncloathing</hi> the Naturalist, and giving him a
rather more <hi rend="i">resolute</hi> look, the plate could not, at a trifling expense, be made to pass for
“Daniel in the Lions’ Den!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n75">3. Note, signed “E.” (for editor), in Cromek’s <hi rend="i">Reliques of Burns</hi>
103-04n. I cannot explain Cromek’s term “Bookselling-Breslaws,” unless perhaps it refers to eastern
European publishers in London. “Mons. Buffon” was the famous French naturalist, Georges-Louis Leclerc,
Comte de Buffon (1707-87).</note></q>
	<note id="n73">1. <hi rend="i">Reliques of Robert Burns: Consisting Chiefly of Original Letters, Poems, and
Critical Observations on Scottish Songs, Collected and Published by R. H. Cromek</hi> (London: Cadell and
Davies, 1808) 103-05 (103).</note>
	<note id="n74">2. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969)
609.</note></p>
          <p>Without mentioning his former friend Blake, some of these details in Cromek’s account come
remarkably close to William Blake’s early experiences as a London engraver. In 1782-83, Blake engraved eight
of Thomas Stothard’s designs for the <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, including four that were
illustrations to Samuel Richardson’s <hi rend="i">Clarissa.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n76" type="note">4</ref> Quite possibly, then, Blake’s engravings of Stothard’s designs were among
the ones that Cromek saw “converted . . . into <hi rend="i">Scriptural embellishments</hi>!” In view of
the ease with which (according to Cromek) London publishers turned illustrations of English history into Bible
pictures, it may be relevant that Blake’s Prospectus of 1793 lists, among his engravings, “a Series of
subjects from the Bible, and another [series] from the History of England.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n76">4. Bentley 610-11.</note>
	<note id="n77">5. Bentley 423n.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
