<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.2.crosby</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">William Blake and the Age of Revolution: An Appreciation, Checklist of
Dissertations and Publications</title>
        <author n="Crosby">Mark Crosby</author>
        <author n="Patenaude">Troy Patenaude</author>
        <author n="Whitehead">Angus Whitehead</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2006</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Harry White</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>Mark Crosby</name>
              <name>Troy Patenaude</name>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-2-0007">
        <pb id="p40-72" n="72"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake and the Age of Revolution: The Interdisciplinary Blake MA Course,
Centre for Eighteenth Century Studies, University of York, 1998-2004</title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>An Appreciation, Checklist of Dissertations and Publications<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n59">1. The authors wish to thank Clare Bond, secretary for the Centre for Eighteenth Century
Studies, University of York, for her assistance with this note.</note>
	</title>
            </head>
            <byline>By <docAuthor>Mark <name>Crosby</name></docAuthor>, <docAuthor>Troy
<name>Patenaude</name></docAuthor>, and <docAuthor>Angus <name>Whitehead</name></docAuthor></byline>
            <p>In 1998 John Barrell, director of the Centre for Eighteenth Century Studies at the University
of York, invited Michael Phillips to design and teach a one-year interdisciplinary MA in English and History
of Art devoted to the life and work of William Blake. The course, William Blake and the Age of Revolution, was
first convened in October 1999. Michael’s hands-on investigations into Blake’s printmaking methods and
research into the creation of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> and Blake’s life in
Lambeth during the 1790s focused the course sharply upon how the illuminated books were produced in their
immediate biographical and historical contexts.</p>
            <p>During the first term, we concentrated on <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> This involved exploring the conception and evolution in manuscript of
Blake’s poems and designs and the development and mastery of the method he used to reproduce them in
“Illuminated Printing.” In the second term, we explored Blake’s life and work in Lambeth during the
first half of the 1790s, situating him in a detailed historical context. One seminar, composed of a multimedia
presentation detailing Michael’s reconstruction of Blake’s residence, studio and neighborhood in Lambeth,
had a profound influence on several students’ methodologies and the topics they later researched for their
dissertations.</p>
            <p>From the beginning, emphasis was also placed upon introducing students to museums, galleries
and libraries in preparation for primary archival research. With some variation from year to year, these
included the National Archives (PRO), British Library, British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings,
Lambeth Archive, City of Westminster Archives Centre, London Metropolitan Archive, St. Bride Printing Library,
Tate Britain, the Fitzwilliam Museum, Glasgow University Library, Hunterian Art Gallery, the Edinburgh
Printmaker’s Workshop and the Black Star Press. These field trips soon paid dividends, providing a unique
opportunity to examine original materials firsthand, including Blake’s manuscript Notebook and the
manuscript of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, multiple copies of the illuminated
books and separate prints, as well as manuscript and printed materials relating to the topographical,
political and cultural contexts of Blake’s life and work. Several students vividly recall how, one bright
December morning in Cambridge, there was a dazzling effect of sunlight reflecting off the gold material Blake
used to finish each plate of the King’s College copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>; others remember the visit to the National Archives at Kew and inspecting the huge folio
register of political prisoners in Newgate 1792-95.</p>
            <p>One of the most valuable aspects of the course was our exposure to the practicalities of
printmaking and eighteenth-century book production. During the initial years of the course, Michael provided
demonstrations at York in an improvised printing studio at the King’s Manor. These were conducted using his
own facsimile relief-etched copperplates of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and <hi rend="i">America</hi> and an
extremely rare nineteenth-century star-wheel rolling press. In later years, when the press was no longer
available, students traveled north to Scotland where Michael conducted similar printmaking sessions at the
professional Edinburgh Printmaker’s Workshop. These were unique, valuable, and at times frustrating
experiences, highlighting the care and, more importantly, the time required to ink a shallow relief-etched
plate in order to obtain even a relatively clean print.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">2</ref> The sessions complemented demonstrations and discussions with other experts in intaglio
and letterpress printing. <note id="n60">2. See Michael Phillips, “The Printing of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi> 21.1 (March 2004): 18-38.</note></p>
            <p>A day was spent engraving, inking and printing intaglio copperplates with Anthony Dyson,
professional printmaker, at his Black Star printmaking studio in Teddington. We enjoyed an afternoon in Soho
with the eighteenth-century print dealer Andrew Edmunds, where we examined his extensive collection of James
Gillray and other political caricatures. We also spent a day with Nigel Roche, a repository of knowledge
concerning print culture in the eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries and curator of the St. Bride
Printing Library and Museum off Fleet Street, who instructed us in printing from letterpress on a
seventeenth-century wooden screw press. David Alexander provided valuable insights on Blake’s apprenticeship
and later career in the context of contemporary fashions in printmaking. Exposure to these experts, grounding
us in different forms of print culture, was exciting, informative and inspiring.</p>
            <p>At conferences Michael ensured that students met and talked with such major Blake scholars as
Martin Butlin, Morton Paley, Detlef Dörrbecker, David Worrall and Keri Davies. During research trips students
also encountered important academics in the field of art history, paper conservators such as Rebecca Donnan,
Joyce Townsend, the senior conservation scientist at Tate Britain, and Stephen Lloyd, senior curator at
<pb id="p40-73" n="73"/>
<figure n="patenaude.40.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="324">
	<head>1. Rebecca Minnitt and Michael Phillips printing a relief-etched plate on a star-wheel rolling press,
the King’s Manor, York, autumn 2000 (photograph by Troy Patenaude).</head>
</figure>
the National Portrait Gallery of Scotland. Meeting specialists in the fields of paper conservation,
miniatures, and painting materials further enhanced our understanding of Blake’s life, works, use of
artistic techniques, choice of pigments, medium and media in the creation of his illuminated books and
separate prints.</p>
            <p>From this solid theoretical and practical preparation, Michael encouraged students to make
original choices in selecting the works and contexts they wished to explore in their two major essays and
15-20,000 word dissertation. The diversity and originality of the students’ choices are apparent in the
titles of the dissertations listed below. William Blake and the Age of Revolution was also very popular with
students as an optional module, where they would attend the course in either the first or the second term, and
attracted students from the Continent and America as well as from Britain. As external assessor and examiner
of the course, Andrew Lincoln, of Queen Mary College, University of London, generously gave of his time in
writing reports on our essays and dissertations. On completing the course, five students went on to pursue
doctoral studies in England or North America. A number of other students took up professional positions often
not unrelated to their area of study, such as editor of children’s literature at the Cambridge University
Press and associate editor of renaissance and eighteenth-century literature at the Arden Press and
subsequently Oxford University Press.</p>
            <p>However, due to the small numbers of students taking the MA, it was decided that it should
cease to be offered from the end of September 2004. The disappearance of this unique course has left a
substantial gap in postgraduate Blake studies. At present, we understand that no other academic establishment
offers a comparable interdisciplinary master’s degree course. It is to be hoped that a similar course may be
convened elsewhere.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>MA Dissertations:</title>
              </head>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>2000:</title>
                </head>
                <p>Jared Richman. “History, Prophecy and Protest: William Blake and the Idea of
America.”</p>
                <p>Bethan Stevens. “Blake’s Woodcut Illustrations: A Breach with Convention?”</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>2001:</title>
                </head>
                <p>Daniella Cardillo. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>: Emblems of
Discovery.”</p>
                <p>Rebecca Minnitt. “Words of Instruction, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>: Blake,
Wollstonecraft and Children’s Literature.”</p>
                <pb id="p40-74" n="74"/>
                <p>Troy Patenaude. “Window to the World: A Study of William Blake’s 1809 One-Man
Exhibition.”</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>2002:</title>
                </head>
                <p>Charlotte Carroll. “The Small and Large Books of Designs: Their Production and the
Aspiration They Inspired.”</p>
                <p>Angus Whitehead. “‘My present precincts’: A Recreation and Exploration of the Last
Living and Working Space of William Blake: 3 Fountain Court, Strand, 1821-1827.”</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>2003:</title>
                </head>
                <p>Adele Johnson. “Gods among Men: Blake’s Representations of Divinity in His Stedman
Illustrations.”</p>
              </div5>
              <div5>
                <head>
                  <title>2004:</title>
                </head>
                <p>Mark Crosby. “This Soldierlike Danger’: Rex v. Blake—The Trial of William
Blake.”</p>
                <p>Philippa Gallagher. “William Blake and Joseph Johnson, 1791-2.”</p>
                <p>Heather Milan. “A Study of the Public Identity of Maria Cosway between 1781 and 1789, Her
Most Productive Period.”</p>
              </div5>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>PhD Thesis:</title>
              </head>
              <p>Richard Angus Whitehead. “New Discoveries Concerning William and Catherine Blake in
Nineteenth Century London: Residences, Fellow Inhabitants, Neighbours, Friends and Milieux, 1803-1878.” 2
vols. University of York, May 2006.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>Publications:</title>
              </head>
              <p>Mark Crosby (with Jon Mee). “‘This Soldierlike Danger’: The Trial of William Blake for
Sedition.” <hi rend="i">Resisting Napoleon: The British Response to the Threat of Invasion, 1797-1815.</hi>
Ed. Mark Philp. Aldershot: Ashgate, 2006.</p>
              <p>Mark Crosby. “‘A Fabricated Perjury’ The [Mis]Trial of William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Journal of Legal History</hi> (forthcoming).</p>
              <p>—. “Manuscript Annotations Signed ‘WB’ in a Copy of Richard Bentley’s Edition of
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (1732). Were They Written by the William Blake?” <hi rend="i">Book
Collector</hi> (forthcoming).</p>
              <p>—. “‘The Sweetest Spot on Earth’: Reconstructing William Blake’s Cottage in
Felpham, Sussex.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> (forthcoming).</p>
              <p>Troy R. C. Patenaude. “‘The glory of a Nation’: Recovering William Blake’s 1809
Exhibition.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 4.1 (spring 2003): 52-63.</p>
              <p>Bethan Stevens, during 2004, compiled computer catalogue entries for the Blake collection of
prints in the British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings, amounting to over 1,000 entries. (Entries for
the collection of nearly 400 drawings had been completed previously.) The catalogue is currently available
only at the museum, but will go online in two or three years’ time. Based upon the collection, her
introductory book, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, was published by British Museum Press, October 2005.</p>
              <p>Angus Whitehead. “‘William Blocke’: New References to Blake in <hi rend="i">Boyle’s
City Guide</hi> (1797) and <hi rend="i">Boyle’s City Companion</hi> (1798).” <hi rend="i">Blake
Journal</hi> 8 (2004): 30-46.</p>
              <p>—. “A Reference to William Blake and James Parker, Printsellers, in 
<hi rend="i">Bailey’s British Directory</hi> (1785).” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 52.1 (March
2005): 32-35.</p>
              <p>—. “‘But Kitty, I better love thee’: George Richmond’s Annotation to 
<hi rend="i">Song</hi> [<hi rend="i">I Love the Jocund Dance</hi>] in Volume II of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
of William Blake</hi> (1863).” <hi rend="i">Blake Journal</hi> 9 (2005): 87-97.</p>
              <p>—. “William Blake’s Last Residence: No. 3 Fountain Court, Strand. George Richmond’s
Plan and an Unrecorded Letter to John Linnell.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.1 (spring/summer
2005): 21-30.</p>
              <p>—. “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’: The Will of Henry Banes,
Landlord of 3 Fountain Court, Strand, the Last Residence of William and Catherine Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 78-99.</p>
              <p>—. “New Information Concerning Mrs Enoch, William and Catherine Blake’s ‘Fellow
Inhabitant’ at 17 South Molton Street.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 52.4 (December 2005):
460-63.</p>
              <p>—. “A Quotation from Lord Byron’s <hi rend="i">The Two Foscari</hi> in William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 53.3 (September
2006): 325-26.</p>
              <p>—. “William Blake’s Subsidiary Design of a Dog in His ‘Heads of the Poets’ Tempera
of William Cowper (c. 1800-1803): An Identification.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 53.3 (September
2006): 316-20.</p>
              <p>—. “The Arlington Court Picture: A Surviving Example of William Blake’s Framing
Practice.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> (forthcoming).</p>
              <p>—. “‘This extraordinary performance’: William Blake’s Use of Gold, Silver and Other
Metals in the Creation of His Paintings and Illuminated Books and a Possible Source of Blake’s Metal c.
1821-27.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> (forthcoming).</p>
              <p>—. “‘Visions of Blake, the Artist’: An Early Reference to William Blake in the 
<hi rend="i">Times.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> (forthcoming).</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
