<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.3.schuchard</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Young William Blake and the Moravian Tradition of Visionary Art</title>
        <author n="Schuchard">Marsha Keith Schuchard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2006/2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006-07</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Marsha Keith Schuchard</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006/2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
      <pb id="p40-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Young William Blake and the Moravian Tradition of Visionary Art</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Marsha Keith <name>Schuchard</name></docAuthor></byline>
		<q>
The Scripture says that our entire work of the Gospel is to portray Jesus, to paint Him before the eyes, to
take the spirit’s stylus and etch—yes, engrave—the image of Jesus in the fleshly tablets of the
heart....<lb/>
Zinzendorf, <hi rend="i">Nine Lectures</hi> 81<lb/>
<lb/>
I would choose <hi rend="i">Fancy</hi> rather than <hi rend="i">Philosophy.</hi> Feeling is ascertained by
Experience; Reasoning is hurtful, or makes us lose ourselves.<lb/>
Zinzendorf in Rimius, <hi rend="i">Candid Narrative</hi> 48<lb/>
<lb/>
Thank God I never was sent to school<lb/>
To be Flogd into following the Style of a Fool<lb/>
                        Blake (E 510)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0"
type="note">*</ref></q>
          <p>In the months following the publication of Davies and Schuchard, “Recovering the Lost Moravian
History of William Blake’s Family,” more material on Blake’s mother and first husband was discovered in
the Moravian Church Library, Muswell Hill, London. We learn that Catherine and Thomas Armitage had a child,
Thomas, who died in March 1751; thus, William Blake is actually her fourth, not third, child.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> We also learn that the Armitages were
intimately and practically involved in Moravian affairs and that Peter Boehler, the charismatic leader of the
Congregation of the Lamb, made a special effort to help Catherine after her husband died on 19 November
1751.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> An intriguing note on 20 March
1753 urges Brother West, an Armitage-Blake family friend, to speak to “Sr. Arm.” (Sister Armitage?) about
some financial matter, thus suggesting that she continued her contacts with the Moravians even after she
married James Blake in October 1752.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
Perhaps she withdrew only from the highly selective, time-consuming congregation and not from a less formal
association with the Brothers and Sisters. If the John Blake who appealed to Boehler for membership in the
congregation was indeed the brother of James Blake, Catherine’s new husband, then William Muir’s claim
(made to Thomas Wright) that William Blake’s “parents attended the Moravian Chapel in Fetter Lane” gains
new plausibility, for they could have attended the services which were open to the public (Wright 1: 2, Lowery
14-15, 210n57).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Wright’s further
assertion that “Blake’s father had adopted the doctrines of Swedenborg, whose followers, however, did not
separate from other religious bodies till later” gains a new historical context, for the Armitages and
Blakes could have known or heard about Swedenborg, who also attended services at Fetter Lane in the 1740s and,
even after breaking with the Brethren, continued to have Moravian friends and to utilize Moravian
publishers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> While the
Moravian-Swedenborgian milieu raises many questions and provokes many speculations concerning William
Blake’s spiritual and intellectual development, I will here focus on the possible Moravian
influence—especially through his mother—on his early artistic development.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n0">*All citations from Blake are from <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, newly rev. ed. (New York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988), abbreviated
“E”.</note>
	<note id="n1">1. Moravian Archive, Moravian Church House, London: C/36/7/5, p. 10 (1 March 1751). I am
grateful to Lorraine Parsons, archivist, for assisting me with research and for sharing the new findings with
me.</note>
	<note id="n2">2. Moravian Archive: C/36/14/2 (13 August 1750); C/36/11/6 (12 September, 20 November, 4, 11,
and 19 December 1751).</note>
	<note id="n3">3. Moravian Archive: C/36/11/6 (20 March 1753).</note>
	<note id="n4">4. Keri Davies is currently investigating the many references to Blakes in the archives, which
suggest—but do not yet prove—that some of James Blake’s relatives were Moravians.</note>
	<note id="n5">5. For Swedenborg’s Moravian experiences in London in 1744-45, see Swedenborg, 
<hi rend="i">Dream Diary</hi> 12-17, 30-38, 54-58. He wrote more about the London Moravians in his 
<hi rend="i">Spiritual Diary</hi> (1746-65). Swedenborg used the Moravian publisher John Lewis and, after
Lewis’s death in 1758, his Moravian widow Mary Lewis continued to sell Swedenborg’s works. Many of his
readers (in England and Sweden) had Moravian parents (such as C. B. Wadström and the Nordenskjöld brothers),
while Dr. Husband Messiter, Jacob Duché, and Richard Cosway were interested in Zinzendorf’s
teachings.</note>
	<note id="n6">6. For background on the Moravian-Swedenborgian milieu, see Schuchard, “Why Mrs. Blake
Cried,” written before my discovery of the Armitage-Blake documents at Muswell Hill, and <hi rend="i">Why
Mrs. Blake Cried</hi> passim.</note></p>
          <p>In 1828 John Thomas Smith recalled that Blake as a child showed “an early stretch of mind, and
a strong talent for drawing,” while also demonstrating the ability to compose and perform “singularly
beautiful” songs, despite being “entirely unacquainted with the science of music” (Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 605-06). Two years later, Allan Cunningham wrote that “the love of art came early upon
the boy,” who “it seems, was privately encouraged by his mother.” It was “his chief delight to retire
to the solitude of his room, and there make drawings, and illustrate these with verses, to be hung up together
in his mother’s chamber” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 628, 631-32). From his earliest years, he also
revealed his visionary tendency, reporting at age four that he saw God put his forehead to the window and,
when he played outdoors, he saw a tree filled with angels and the prophet Ezekiel under a tree. Despite his
mother’s worry at such excited claims, she usually protected him from a “thrashing from his honest
father” (Gilchrist, quoted in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 19-20). Unfortunately, nothing more
emerged about this important maternal influence, leading Alexander Gilchrist to lament in 1863 that after the
death of Blake’s mother at age seventy in 1792, “She is a shade to us, 
                        <pb id="p40-85" n="85"/>
alas! In all senses: for of her character, or even her person, no tidings survive” (Gilchrist 1: 95).</p>
          <p>Fortunately, the new Moravian documents allow us to put some flesh on the shade of Catherine
Armitage Blake and to recover the religious milieu that rendered her so sympathetic to her son’s development
as a visionary artist. In order to bring to the surface this submerged history, it will be necessary to
discuss briefly the career of Count Nikolaus Ludwig von Zinzendorf, leader of the renewed Unitas Fratrum, and
the spiritual-artistic ethos of the “Sifting Time” (c. 1743-53), a turbulent and creative period of
spiritual, sexual, and artistic experimentation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> That Catherine and Thomas Armitage, John Blake, and possibly James Blake were attracted to
the Moravian Chapel during the most intense years of the Sifting Time would become relevant to William
Blake’s later radical and antinomian beliefs about eroticized spirituality. Through this association, they
enjoyed unusual—even unique—access to an international network of ecumenical missionaries, an esoteric
tradition of Christian Kabbalism, Hermetic alchemy, and Oriental theosophy, along with a European “high
culture” of religious art, music, and poetry. <note id="n7">7. Moravian historians differ on the length of
the Sifting Time, but I date it generally from 1743, when Zinzendorf returned from Pennsylvania, to 1753, when
a publishing campaign against him began in England. Though some Moravian officials attempted to suppress the
radically eroticized spirituality from 1749 on, the themes continued to attract many members in London and
elsewhere but were handled with much greater secrecy.</note></p>
          <p>The beliefs and activities of Count Zinzendorf (1700-60) continue to provoke controversy among
historians, with most praising him as an innovative theologian and pioneer of religious and racial toleration
and some condemning him as a Gnostic heretic and sexual pervert.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">8</ref> Born in Dresden, Saxony, to an aristocratic Lutheran family, he rejected his
Pietist mentors’ emphasis on ascetic self-denial and morbid spiritual struggle. In 1722 he welcomed to his
estate a band of Moravian refugees, heirs to the Protestant reform movements stimulated by Jan Hus in the
fifteenth century and Jan Amos Comenius in the seventeenth. Known as the Unitas Fratrum, the persecuted
Moravians preserved “the Hidden Seed” of their irenic spiritual traditions, while they assimilated
concepts and symbols developed by Boehmenist and Pietist writers. Under Zinzendorf’s leadership at Herrnhut
and other communities, the Moravians developed a passionate <hi rend="i">Herzensreligion</hi> (religion of the
heart), which affirmed that Jesus’s <hi rend="i">Menschwerdung</hi> (“humanation”) made him experience
the full range of human pain and pleasure and that his self-sacrifice and intense suffering on the cross were
sufficient to fully redeem fallen human beings. Thus, pious and self-righteous standards of behavior, which
led to hypocrisy and joylessness, were not the proper expressions of Christian worship, for one should utilize
one’s <hi rend="i">Herz</hi> (heart) to <hi rend="i">sensate</hi> Jesus’s love and to identify
            <figure n="eccehomo.40.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="399">
	<figTranscr>EGO PRO TE HÆC PAS SUS SUM<lb/>
            TU VERO QUID FECISTI PRO ME</figTranscr>
	<head>1. Domenico Feti, <hi rend="i">Ecce Homo</hi> (seventeenth century).</head>
	<figDesc>Unitätsarchiv, GS 036. Archiv der Brüder-unität, Herrnhut.</figDesc>
</figure>
with his bloody wounds—from the first wound of circumcision to the final wound in his side. <note id="n8">8.
For an introductory biography, see Arthur Freeman. For the most accurate histories of the Sifting Time, see
Podmore; Peucker, “Blut”; Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Drawing on his Hebrew studies and discussions with mystical Jews, Zinzendorf identified the
German <hi rend="i">Herz</hi> with the Hebrew <hi rend="i">Lev</hi>, the location of emotion and intellect:
“In the Old Testament, heart [<hi rend="i">Lev</hi>] is the point of contact with God. ‘Heart’ is more
visceral and affective than the Greek word for the personality [<hi rend="i">Psyche</hi>]” (Atwood, 
<hi rend="i">Community</hi> 32-33). Moreover,
<q>
Zinzendorf defined “Heart” as the inner person which had five senses as did the outer person. The
“Heart,” especially when it has been brought to life by the Holy Spirit, can perceive the Savior
objectively and directly. In modern terms we might speak of this as “intuition” or “extrasensory
perception.” Zinzendorf’s approach is very similar to Teresa of Avila’s “intellectual vision.”
(Arthur Freeman 7)
</q>
In a typically irenic assimilation, Zinzendorf affirmed that the sensually perceptive <hi rend="i">Lev</hi>
could be stimulated to “intellectual vision” by meditating upon great religious art, especially the
Catholic art produced by Renaissance and Baroque painters. Thus, he argued against the Old Testament
prohibition of “graven images,” which influenced the intense iconoclasm of
<pb id="p40-86" n="86"/>
most British Dissenters, and praised the Lutheran rejection of that commandment:
<q>
In the New Testament this commandment is at an end: we have seen. Therefore the Lutherans are right in leaving
this commandment out of the catechism, for it no longer has any relation on earth to us. This makes the
particular distinction between us and the Reformed, for they combine the ninth and tenth commandments to make
room for the commandment forbidding images, which we Lutherans . . . leave out of the Decalogue. We do not
hold that a person should make himself no picture or image in the New Testament; a person may make an image,
no, he should. (Zinzendorf 81)
</q></p>
          <p>Zinzendorf preached this anti-iconoclastic sermon at Fetter Lane to counter the hostile attacks
of Dissenting and Methodist critics, who claimed that Moravian artistic practices were crypto-Papist. Thus, he
recounted his life-changing experience in which art first opened his heart (<hi rend="i">Herz-Lev</hi>).
During his student travels, he visited a gallery in Düsseldorf, which featured Domenico Feti’s 
<hi rend="i">Ecce Homo</hi>, a poignant painting of Jesus’s suffering under the crown of thorns before his
crucifixion. Under the wounded body scrolled a Latin caption: “All this I have suffered for you, but what
have you done for me?” (Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 97) (illus. 1). An emotional Zinzendorf recalled
that “My blood rushed because I was not able to give much of an answer, and I prayed to my Saviour to make
me ride in the comradeship of his suffering with force.” The rushing blood, yearning for forced intimacy,
comradeship in suffering—religious passions stimulated by a work of art—intensified the young nobleman’s
determination to serve Jesus and to identify with his fully humanized nature, which he came to believe
included not only suffering but sexuality. An admirer of Catholic doctrines of confession and forgiveness of
sins, he hoped to utilize Catholic artistic traditions to invigorate the ecumenical 
<hi rend="i">Herzensreligion.</hi></p>
          <p>What made his commitment to religious art so creative and controversial was his injection of
Kabbalistic concepts of sacramental
<figure n="the-endless.40.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="635">
	<figTranscr><rtl>אין סוף</rtl><lb/>
  THE ENDLESS<lb/>
<lb/>
  <rtl>כתר</rtl><lb/>
  CROWN<lb/>
<lb/>
  <rtl>חכמה</rtl> WISDOM<lb/>
<lb/>
  <rtl>בינה</rtl><lb/>
  INTELLIGENCE<lb/>
<lb/>
  <rtl>חסד</rtl><lb/>
  LOVE<lb/>
  <rtl>תפארת</rtl><lb/>
  BEAUTY<lb/>
<lb/>
  <corr><rtl>צדק</rtl></corr><lb/>
  JUSTICE<lb/>
<lb/>
  <rtl>יסוד</rtl><lb/>
  FOUNDATION<lb/>
<lb/>
  <rtl>נצח</rtl><lb/>
  FIRMNESS<lb/>
<lb/>
  <rtl>הוד</rtl><lb/>
  SPLENDOUR<lb/>
  <rtl>מלכות</rtl><lb/>
  KINGDOM</figTranscr>
	<head>2. “Adam Kadmon.”</head>
	<figDesc>Frontispiece of Christian Ginsburg, <hi rend="i">The Essenes: Their History and Doctrines; The
Kabbalah: Its Doctrines, Development and Literature</hi> (1863-64; London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul,
1955).</figDesc>
</figure>
sexuality into his portrayal of the fully incarnated Jesus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">9</ref> He drew on Jewish mystical beliefs concerning the sexual dynamics of the
male-female emanations (the <hi rend="i">Sephiroth</hi>) that bodied forth the Divinity, and transformed the
Christian all-male Trinity into a male-female divine family. Thus, he argued that the Holy Spirit is female (a
Christianized version of the Kabbalists’ <hi rend="i">Shekhinah</hi>, or female potency within God), and
described a <hi rend="i">hieros gamos</hi> in which the Holy Spirit is the wife of God and mother of Jesus,
the God-Man (the Kabbalists’ microcosmic <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi>) (illus. 2). Influenced by
Kabbalistic and Jesuit meditation techniques, he urged the Moravians to focus intently on the bloody wounds of
the crucified Jesus, which he interpreted in highly eroticized language—i.e., as the centurion’s phallic
spear penetrated the vaginal side-wound, new souls were birthed in the gushing blood from this mystical
intercourse.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Because all human souls
are female (<hi rend="i">animas</hi>), both men and women can achieve a psychoerotic consummation with Jesus,
the divine bridegroom, as they are enfolded into “the sidehole” (a figurative back-to-the-womb
experience). Because Jesus was conceived in a female womb and was born with male genitals, these organs should
be honored and utilized sacramentally within human marriage, which reenacts the divine marriage and the sexual
reintegration of the God-Man. <note id="n9">9. For Jewish and Kabbalistic influences on Zinzendorf, see
Deghaye, Dithmar. He implemented the <hi rend="i">Judenmission</hi>, which appealed to Jews in London,
Amsterdam, Hamburg, New York, and other cities, and many Jews attended Moravian services.</note>
	<note id="n10">10. For Moravian sexual theosophy, see Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 185-94 and
“Sleeping” 25-51; also Podmore 130-31.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-87" n="87"/>
          <p>In the process, Zinzendorf revived the Renaissance artistic tradition that linked the 
<hi rend="i">ostentatio vulnerum</hi> (showing forth of the wounds) with the <hi rend="i">ostentatio
genitalium</hi> (showing forth of the genitals), a linkage which stressed the full “humanation” of Jesus
(Steinberg 3, 16, 18, 57, 83, 373). In 1750 the count predicted that “one of these days” artists will
portray the crucified Jesus in a new way, fully nude without a cloth covering his sexual organs; his genitals
will again express “his honor and innocence,” for “he is no fallen Adam” (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder”
137).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Though no records of such
paintings survive, the portrayals may have been used more privately, within Zinzendorf’s family and inner
circle, for in 1748 his niece, Sophie Reuss, made a miniature drawing of a nude Christ on the cross, with no
covering cloth and with blood flowing profusely from his five wounds. This religiousartistic belief perhaps
found an echo in Blake’s affirmation, “The head Sublime, the heart Pathos, the genitals Beauty, the hands
&amp; feet Proportion” (E 37). <note id="n11">11. I am grateful to Paul Peucker, Moravian archivist formerly
at Herrnhut and now at Bethlehem, PA, for sending me this important article and for help with
identifications.</note></p>
          <p>As a highly educated and basically skeptical intellectual, Zinzendorf spoke about his own
struggle to move beyond speculative abstraction to imaginative visualization. He granted that the capacity for
vision—“that extraordinary state” when one is “in the Spirit”—was not equally shared by every
Brother and Sister:
<q>
This may happen with more or less sense experience, with more or less distinctness, with more or less
visibility, and with as many kinds of modifications as the different human temperaments and natural
constitutions can allow in one combination or another. One person attains to it more incontestably and
powerfully, the other more gently and mildly; but in one moment both attain to this, that in reality and truth
one has the Creator of all things . . . standing . . . in the form of one atoning for the whole human
race—this individual object stands before the vision of one’s heart, before the eyes of one’s spirit,
before one’s inward man. (Zinzendorf 82-83)
</q>
One should be able to say, “I see him as clearly as if he were here; I could paint him right now,” for
then “He remains engraved in one’s heart. One has a copy of this deeply impressed there; one lives in it,
is changed into the same image” (Zinzendorf 84-85). By focusing intensely and reverently on Jesus’s body
and the intercourse between phallic spear and vaginal wound, the Moravian devotee could achieve a state of
trance, of psychosexual euphoria, in which he or she “shook with love’s fever” and experienced the
“mystical marriage” (Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 219).</p>
          <p>To increase the congregation’s capacity to “see,” “paint,” and “engrave,”
Zinzendorf recruited and commissioned artists to create vivid portrayals of Christ’s life and sufferings for
the Brothers and Sisters to study while powerful hymns, guitars, violins, and trombones provided background
music. At the chapel in Fetter Lane and at Lindsey House in Chelsea (the count’s headquarters), the
whitewashed walls were covered with paintings of biblical and allegorical scenes, as well as portrayals of
Moravian history and international missionary work. Adding to the mystical atmosphere were watercolored
transparencies, through which lanterns and candles projected luminous visions into the congregation rooms.
Given the often bloody and sometimes sensual symbolism of the paintings and hymns, these scenes would provoke
much controversy and hostile attacks from critics. However, the passionate letter of Catherine Armitage, which
reveals her deep immersion in the spiritual-erotic themes of the Sifting Time, suggests that Blake’s mother
responded positively to the Moravians’ stress on the role of art and music in the development of visionary
spirituality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> As she encouraged the
artistic productions of her imaginative son, she was perhaps implementing Zinzendorf’s peculiar but
progressive notions of “infant education.” <note id="n12">12. Moravian Archive: C/36/2/159.</note></p>
          <p>Zinzendorf admired the “pansophic” educational theories of Comenius, whose portrait was
displayed at Lindsey House, and he implemented them in his voluminous sermons, songs, and lessons for children
(Meyer 94-105). Comenius stressed the innocence of childhood, the importance of parental affection, the
healthy effects of outdoor free play, and, most importantly, the use of pictorial images to inculcate
religious sentiments. What was surprisingly modern or Freudian in the count’s pedagogy was his belief that
even embryos and infants were receptive to his sex, blood, and wounds theology and that “the process of
religious education and socialization began <hi rend="i">in utero</hi>” (Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi>
178-83; “Blood” 192-93). Within the “embryo choir,” the pregnant mother was pampered and counselled;
after birth, she and her infant became part of the “suckling choir,” and joyous love feasts were held for
them. In order to sensate the “assembled image” of the God-Man in one’s heart, mother and child must
“view, picture, and meditate about the saviour from head to foot.” These injunctions were sung by the
mother in the home and by the children in catechistical hymns. In a Moravian drawing from 1754, Zinzendorf’s
two-year-old daughter is shown meditating upon a painting of the crucified Jesus (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder”
170).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n13">13. Because Elizabeth von Zinzendorf was born in 1740, the 1754 portrayal probably had a
pedagogical purpose for current infant education.</note></p>
          <p>Zinzendorf was evidently familiar with sixteenth-century paintings that portrayed the infant
Christ with an erect penis and giving a flirtatious “chin-chuck” to his adoring mother, and there were
hints of such themes in his lyrics for children.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> When Blake wrote his provocative “Cradle Song,” he seemed to draw on the Moravians’
maternal and infant sexual psychology.
<pb id="p40-88" n="88"/>
In Blake’s song, the mother strokes the soft limbs, the babe’s face and heart respond with smiles and
peaceful beat, and she recognizes the erotic pleasure stimulated in the infant:
<q>
Sweet Babe in thy face<lb/>
Soft desires I can trace<lb/>
Secret joys &amp; secret smiles<lb/>
[Such as burning youth beguiles <hi rend="i">del.</hi>] (E 468, 852)
</q>
	<note id="n14">14. The occasional erection of the infant penis is a normal and natural phenomenon, but many
Renaissance artists stressed it as proof of the full “humanation” of Jesus. Steinberg (3, 10, 76-79 and
plates 83-88) gives examples such as Alvise Vivarini’s <hi rend="i">Madonna and Child with Saints</hi> (c.
1500), Perino del Vaga’s <hi rend="i">Holy Family</hi> (c. 1520), Perugino’s <hi rend="i">Madonna and
Child</hi> (c. 1500), Correggio’s <hi rend="i">Madonna of the Basket</hi> (c. 1523-25), etc.</note></p>
          <p>Though Blake deleted the last line, he went even further in his paean to free love, 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, where Oothoon proclaims:
<q>
Take thy bliss O Man!<lb/>
And sweet shall be thy taste &amp; sweet thy infant joys renew!<lb/>
<lb/>
Infancy, fearless, lustful, happy! nestling for delight<lb/>
In laps of pleasure .... (E 49)
</q>
Blake’s “laps of pleasure” takes on a new connotation when placed in a context of Zinzendorf’s
pedagogical instruction that the school of the female Holy Spirit was “a family school, that is, a school on
the lap, in the arms of the eternal Mother.” In German, the same word (<hi rend="i">Schoss</hi>) is used for
lap and womb, and the mother’s “school” for her infant took on a spiritualerotic connotation, which was
vividly expressed in hymns for the embryo and suckling choirs. Blake’s lustful, nestling infant recalls the
sung injunction to each mother, “That your child lay naked and bare on your lap” (Atwood, 
<hi rend="i">Community</hi> 178-79). Following Comenius’s teaching, the Moravians advocated maternal breast
feeding rather than farming infants out to wet nurses. Blake’s mother may well have heard Peter Boehler’s
talks to the married Sisters, when he stressed that “suckling” must be done with “gracious ideas as a
Divine Worship.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Decades later,
Blake would lament that so many selfish parents reject this beneficial practice: “The child springs from the
womb . . . / The young bosom is cold for lack of mother’s nourishment, &amp; milk / Is cut off from the
weeping mouth” (E 285). <note id="n15">15. Moravian Archive: C/36/7/3 (28 May 1749). Boehler was the main
“marriage counsellor” for the Brothers and Sisters, and he spoke frankly about intercourse, orgasm,
conception, etc., in a surprisingly modern way.</note></p>
          <p>Determined to make the sensating of Jesus a joyous experience, Zinzendorf advocated that parents
and children—of every age, class, and background—should participate in a rich Renaissance-Baroque culture
of painting, poetry, and music. Remembering his own unhappy childhood, when he was sent away to boarding
school and instructed by puritanical pedants, he urged the Moravians to home-school their children. Preaching
at Fetter Lane in 1753, he instructed the parents to build a home “for a Christian family life which will
make possible the ideal church in the home with proper religious training of children”; moreover,
“parental training is the natural method as compared with institutional training which is artificial”
(Meyer 138, 142). Unusually for the time, he believed that an affectionate mother was the best teacher for a
young child, and that she should inculcate a love of art and music to stir the visionary senses of the 
<hi rend="i">Herz-Lev.</hi></p>
          <p>From infancy on, a Moravian child was exposed to religious art and script, including the German
artistic technique of <hi rend="i">Frakturschriften</hi>, the ornamental breaking or fracturing of letters,
which Zinzendorf and Boehler had observed when they visited the Boehmenist-Rosicrucian community at Ephrata,
Pennsylvania (Sachse 1: 354-64, 401-02). In the Ephratans’ mystical calligraphy, the scribe represented the
breaking of the artist’s self-will and opening to union with Christ by breaking the letters and surrounding
them with swirling ornamentation, which created the “sprouting of a florid paradise” (Bach 182-84). The
“illuminations” were usually “drawn with pen and ink, and then embellished with vigorous colors.” The
actual practice of <hi rend="i">Fraktur</hi>, with its intense concentration and visualization, could produce
mystical states, for “each scribe has the birthing process in himself after rebirth.” In the magnificently
illuminated <hi rend="i">Ephrata ABC</hi> book, Sisters Anastasia and Efigenia drew capital letters
<q>
constructed with a series of swinging, voluptuous curves, all interstices of the letters filled with
additional scrollings and floral forms. A passionate devotion to the work caused the individual calligrapher
to further elaborate all possible areas with minute stipplings and dottings, in the manner of steel engraving.
Significant symbolistic motifs also entered into the enrichment of the capitals. (Frances Lichten, quoted in
Alderfer 125-26)
</q>
Alderfer adds that
<q>
some of them, such as the <hi rend="i">A</hi> and the <hi rend="i">O</hi>, make use of the human form to
portray a provocative symbolism. . . . The <hi rend="i">O</hi> suggests Anastasia’s vision of Beissel [the
community leader] being crowned with the Holy Spirit . . .; it may also reflect her sublimated love for him. .
. . The borders are astonishing .... (126) (illus. 3)
</q></p>
          <p>Despite their opposition to the Ephratans’ policy of celibacy (they believed that earthly
marriage would prevent divine marriage with Sophia), the Moravians borrowed liberally from the sect’s
mystical art and symbolism (Stoudt 94-96). Like Conrad Beissel, Zinzendorf believed that “art, literature,
and music were not [to be] regarded as separate disciplines; they united in one common spiritual experience”
(Alderfer 125). Thus, a comment by the Pennsylvanian art historian John Stoudt becomes suggestive; referring
to the <hi rend="i">Ephrata ABC</hi> book, he observes that the frontispiece “is a drawing much like those
of William Blake” (Stoudt 138) (illus. 4 and 5). At this time in London, the walls at Fetter Lane and
Lindsey House were hung with papers and canvases of Moravian poetry and hymns, ornamented with painted letters
(often in elaborate German Gothic script), whose twisting and curving gave them “a florid quality”
(Podmore 133, 151-52; Atwood,
<pb id="p40-89" n="89"/>
“Blood” 171) (illus. 6). Paintings and drawings were often surrounded with 
<hi rend="i">Spruchbänder</hi>, sayings or aphorisms that illustrated the text (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 166).
Catherine Armitage Blake would have seen these elaborate and charming “illuminations,” which also
decorated private rooms. The Moravians’ love of religious art provoked iconoclastic Dissenters to criticize
“our innocent pictures and crucifixes in
<figure n="40.3.der.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="500">
	<figTranscr>O</figTranscr>
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">Der Christen ABC</hi> (1750), letter O. Ephrata Cloister, Pennsylvania Historical and
Museum Commission.</head>
</figure>
our Rooms” (Podmore 152). It was probably no coincidence that Catherine’s young son William loved to make
drawings and illustrate them with verses to be “hung up together in his mother’s chamber.”</p>
          <p>At Fetter Lane, Catherine Armitage was also exposed to the Jesuit emblem tradition of
“iconomysticism.” Thomas Armitage had written his application letter to John Cennick, a
<pb id="p40-90" n="90"/>
            <figure n="ChristenABC.frontispiece.40.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="498">
              <figTranscr>Dies ist mein lieber<lb/>
                Sohn, an dem ich<lb/>
                wohlgefallen habe<lb/>
<lb/>
                WER DA GLAUBET U[ND] GETAUFFT WIRD DER WIRD SELIG WERDEN X<lb/>
                WER ABER NICHT GLAUBET DER WIRD VERDAMMT WERDEN<lb/>
<lb/>
                Folget mir nach, ich bin das A, u[nd] das O, der<lb/>
                Anfang u[nd] das Ende, der Erste u[nd] der Letzte.</figTranscr>
	<head>4. <hi rend="i">Der Christen ABC</hi> (1750), frontispiece.</head>
	<figDesc>Ephrata Cloister, Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission.</figDesc>
</figure>
talented poet and composer, who often discussed Hermann Hugo’s <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria</hi>, a
seventeenth-century Jesuit emblem book, with the Brothers and Sisters (Cennick 24). Cennick and Zinzendorf
agreed with Comenius’s advocacy of emblem books, which can “explain the whole of pansophy” and which
function like the “signatures” of Paracelsus and Boehme (Sadler 28, 42-43, 201, 282). From descriptions in
the Congregation Diaries of “our little childlike Hieroglyphicks,” “many childlike emblematical Doings,
with Candles, Leaf-work,” and “emblematical Pictures, suddenly shifting &amp; successively presenting
themselves to the Eye,” it is clear that Cennick encouraged the implementation of Hugo’s
theories.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> According to Mario Praz,
Jesuit emblematics follows “the tracks of hieroglyphics” and “aims at establishing a mode of expression
which only a few may understand; in a word, an esoteric language”—and thus relevant to Zinzendorf’s
frequent use of an encoded secret language (Praz 1: 155). At the same time, emblematics “aims at being a way
of making ethical and religious truths accessible to all, even to the illiterate and to children, through the
lure of pictures.” While Catherine Blake home-schooled her children, did she introduce them to Hugo’s
“little books of emblems,” which offer to the eyes “charming <hi rend="i">Zinnepoppen</hi>,
            <figure n="s-inn.b.p2-3" id="s-inn.b.illbk.02" work-copy="s-inn.b" rend="db" width="649" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>SONGS<lb/>
              of<lb/>
              Innocence<lb/>
<lb/>
              1789<lb/>
<lb/>
              The Author &amp; Printer WBlake</figTranscr>
	<head>5. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789), copy B, title page.</head>
	<figDesc>Library of Congress.</figDesc>
</figure>
or dolls for the spirit . . . the toys of a bewitched kindergarten” (Praz 1: 136)? <note id="n16">16.
Moravian Archive: C/37/7/3 (30 December 1749; 19, 24 May 1751).</note></p>
          <p>Cennick, who greatly admired the Moravian paintings and engravings he observed in Germany and
England, would have recognized the relevance of Jesuit emblematic techniques to Zinzendorf’s
artistic-pedagogic goals. As Praz observes, the “didactic properties” of emblems were “calculated to
further the Ignatian technique of the application of the senses, to help the imagination to picture to itself
in the minutest detail circumstances of religious import”:
<q>
They made the supernatural accessible to all by materializing it. Rather than mortifying the senses in order
to concentrate all energies in an ineffable tension of the spirit, according to the purgative way of the
mystics, the Jesuits wanted every sense to be keyed up to the pitch of its capacity, so as to conspire
together to create a psychological state pliant to the command of God. (Praz 1: 156)
</q>
Similarly, Moravian artists were instructed to arouse and utilize all the senses, so the viewer would move
beyond mere understanding and would fully participate in, fully <hi rend="i">sensate</hi>, Jesus’s
experiences from crucifixion to resurrection (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 169).</p>
          <p>The fine engravings in <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria</hi>, by Boëce van Bolsvert, drew on the
Jesuits’ spiritual-sensual interpretation of the techniques of engraving. As Praz observes,
<pb id="p40-91" n="91"/>
            <figure n="lief.40.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="440">
              <figTranscr>Lief heim<lb/>
                Mein Seidelein<lb/>
                Lief heim ins Seitelein<lb/>
<lb/>
                Christian Gottfried Beidel. Ann: MDCCXLVIII. di 5.Febr: Ætat: 30.</figTranscr>
	<head>6. “Lief heim ins Seitelein.”</head>
	<figDesc>Unitätsarchiv, R.20.E.36.12. Archiv der Brüder-unität, Herrnhut.</figDesc>
</figure>
<q>
The fixity of the emblematic picture was infinitely suggestive; the beholder little by little let his
imagination be eaten into as a plate is by an acid. The picture eventually became animated with an intense,
hallucinatory life, independent of the page. The eyes were not alone in perceiving it; the depicted objects
were invested with body, scent, and sound .... (Praz 1: 156)
</q></p>
          <p>In Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, he employed a similar engraving
metaphor of acid eating into plate. He may also have drawn on the Moravians’ iconomystical and antinomian
sense of erotic visualization, which reversed the orthodox Christian denigration of the senses and sexuality:
<q>
. . . the whole creation will be consumed, and appear infinite, and holy whereas it now appears finite &amp;
corrupt.<lb/>
This will come to pass by an improvement of sensual enjoyment.<lb/>
But first the notion that man has a body distinct from his soul, is to be expunged; this I shall do, by
printing in the infernal method, by corrosives, which in Hell are salutary and medicinal, melting apparent
surfaces away, and displaying the infinite which is hid.<lb/>
If the doors of perception were cleansed every thing would appear to man as it is: infinite. (E 39)
</q></p>
          <p>Praz’s description of iconomysticism reveals why it was such an effective vehicle for Moravian
concepts of the mystical marriage, for this Jesuit “cult was wonderfully suited to a society accustomed to
picture human love under the guise of the Alexandrian Eros” (1: 132). Hugo’s great popularity arose from
his use of the Song of Solomon and the Psalms,
<q>
texts whose metaphors inevitably suggested emblems with the Oriental lusciousness of their appeal to the
senses. Tears and sighs, . . . voluptuous swoonings and sweet and subtle pains, what a part they play in the
<hi rend="i">Pia Desideria</hi>! In a nocturnal garden, heavy with perfume, Anima feels her knees give way
under her, . . . while from her bared breast burning ejaculations <hi rend="i">Ah! Utinam! Heu!</hi> shoot
like arrows towards the ears of God. . . . Suddenly the garden is all a-bubble with springs. . . . Love darts
from his mouth a quivering tongue of flame, and, caressed by that heat, Anima exudes huge drops from head to
foot. . . . What wild races through that nocturnal garden heavy with perfumes! (Praz 1: 133-34)
</q>
Zinzendorf similarly compared the Moravians’ visualization of Christ to the bride’s in the Song of Songs.
Quoting the lines “This is my beloved,” he stressed that her lover is actually Christ, and “there He is
painted piece by piece” (Zinzendorf 81). In May 1749 at Fetter Lane, his birthday was celebrated with
“illuminated Pictures” which showed “Fountains springing” and the count “solacing himself in a
Garden where the Fountains spouted Blood” (Stead 300).</p>
          <pb id="p40-92" n="92"/>
          <p>Hugo’s most famous illustration, “Anima Trying to Soar on Wings, but Held Back by a Weight
Tied to Her Foot,” perhaps finds an echo in Blake’s tiny emblem book, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural
Religion</hi> (Hugo 334) (illus. 7). On the plate designated V, Blake drew a figure soaring with hands raised,
while the inscription reads, “More! More! Is the cry of a mistaken soul, less than All cannot satisfy Man”
(E 31). On the plate headed VI, he drew a naked man chained and fettered by his ankles, with the text, “If
any could desire what he is incapable of possessing, despair must be his eternal lot” (E 31) (illus. 8).
Hugo’s Jesuit work had been expurgated and published in English translations by Protestant writers, such as
Frances Quarles and Edmund Arwaker, who de-emphasized the pictorial “iconomysticism” and added more
moralistic and puritanical literary comments (R. Freeman 114, 133, 140-42, 207). But for Cennick and
Zinzendorf, it was the Jesuitic stress on intense visualization and the arousal of spiritualerotic desire that
was the most important aspect of Hugo’s mystical emblems.</p>
          <p>In 1806 Blake’s friend Benjamin Heath Malkin reported that the artist, “very early in life,
had the ordinary opportunities
            <figure n="pia.40.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="227" height="400">
	<figTranscr>Coarctor autem e duobus; desiderium habens dissolui<lb/>
              et esse cum Christo. Ad Philip. 1.<lb/>
              39.</figTranscr>
	<head>7. Hermann Hugo, <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria</hi>, Editio 6. emendata (1624; Antuerpia: apud Henricum
Aertssens, 1634), plate 39.</head>
	<figDesc>Engraving by Boëce van Bolsvert. Robert W. Woodruff Library, Emory University.</figDesc>
</figure>
of seeing pictures in the houses of noblemen and gentlemen, and in the king’s palaces,” (Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 562) which perhaps included Lindsey House and other residences of Zinzendorf’s
aristocratic friends. Since these visits took place before his tenth birthday in 1767, Blake must have been
taken by a parent, probably his mother, who would have been aware of the vivid paintings at Lindsey House and
Fetter Lane, as well as their pedagogical role.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> When Catherine and Thomas Armitage raised their son Thomas, they would have known Brother
Christopher Henry Müller, who had “much discourse with
            <figure n="nnr.l.p7-b8" id="nnr.l.illbk.07" work-copy="nnr.l" rend="db" width="796" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>VI<lb/>
              If any could de-<lb/>
              -sire what he is in-<lb/>
              -capable of posses-<lb/>
              sing. despair must<lb/>
              be his eternal<lb/>
              lot</figTranscr>
	<head>8. William Blake, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> VI (1788), copy L.</head>
	<figDesc>Pierpont Morgan Library and William Blake Archive.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p40-93" n="93"/>
Brother Boehler,” Catherine’s protective friend.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref> A German immigrant, who had earlier ministered to the black slaves in Georgia, Müller
had “the Care of the Children’s Oeconomy” in London, in which charge “he acted with great
Faithfulness.” Significantly, part of this care was instruction in art and engraving. <note id="n17">17. In
<hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried</hi> 144-45, 270-71, I discuss the Moravian-Swedenborgian interests of Dr.
Husband Messiter and Richard Cosway, who were both associated with Henry Pars’s Drawing School, where Blake
studied from age ten to fourteen. During Blake’s apprenticeship and studies at the Royal Academy, he
possibly knew the young Moravian artist and architect Benjamin Henry Latrobe, whose radical politics
eventually led to his emigration to America (in 1795). Talbot Hamlin, who was unaware of the mutual Moravian
background of Latrobe and Blake, notes the unusual Blakean qualities in the former’s watercolor paintings
(Hamlin 246, 540-41).</note>
	<note id="n18">18. Moravian Archive: C/36/7/5 (1 March 1751). I am grateful to the Reverend Kai Dose for
sending me the full account of Müller in the Congregation Diary.</note></p>
          <p>Having studied at Herrnhaag, the most radical center of Sifting Time theosophy, Müller was
familiar with the daring experiments in sexual, ritual, poetic, and artistic innovation which occurred there
(and which led to the Moravians’ expulsion).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref> When Zinzendorf moved to London in 1749, Müller took over “the oeconomical Care of
Bloomsbury-House,” while continuing his artistic and engraving work. According to his obituary, “The last
Piece of Work he did in his own Art, (wherein he was very ingenious) was ingraving a small Picture of the
Ordinary [Zinzendorf].” Having become sick with “a malignant fever,” Müller “was kissed home into the
Sidehole” on 9 March 1751, apparently at the same time that “Thomas, the Child of Br + Sisr Armitage”
died. Their shared funeral notice reports that the Armitage child “was buried in the Ground near
Bloomsbury,” while Müller was carried from Bloomsbury “and deposited in the Earth at Chelsea,” thus
becoming the first interment in the new Moravian cemetery. According to the German church historian Kai Dose,
who is researching Müller’s life, he was a talented artist whose surviving portraits and engravings are
worth renewed interest.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n19">19. On the “poetic world” of “spiritualized sexuality” at Herrnhaag, see Erbe. The
radical leader of the “youth movement” at Herrnhaag was Zinzendorf’s charismatic son, Christian Renatus,
who in 1749 moved to London, where he was revered by the Fetter Lane congregation, who considered his death in
1752 at age twenty-four a great tragedy.</note>
	<note id="n20">20. Another Moravian artist, Johann Jakob Müller, spent a brief period in London in the
1740s, where he opposed “daubers of reason” and “naturalists”; he then moved to Herrnhut, where he
became “director of the Wound and Nailhole Painting Academy” (Peucker, “Painter”).</note></p>
          <p>Because of the sale of Lindsey House in 1774 and the Nazi bombing of the Fetter Lane Chapel in
1941, the great Zinzendorfian collection of paintings and engravings was dispersed or destroyed (Kroyer
50-63). However, from pre-1941 descriptions and surviving paintings at the Brethren’s other centers, we can
learn more about the Moravian artists who moved in the Armitage-Blake milieu in the 1750s and 60s. More famous
than Müller was Abraham Louis Brandt (1717-97), a talented Franco-Swiss engraver and painter (“Brandt”;
“Lebenslauf”). He was the brother of Louise Hutton, who had earlier been a member of the “French
Prophets” before marrying the English minister James Hutton and converting to Moravianism (Benham 95,
194-96, 375). She shared with her brother an interest in Boehmenist and mystical writers, and he expressed
these themes in the religious paintings he produced for Zinzendorf in England, before moving on to a Moravian
community in Russia in 1764. Less famous was John Cooke, a Catholic artist from Leghorn (called “the
Italian”), who acted as ship’s mate on Moravian voyages to America, where his joyous temperament, violin
playing, and artistic productions made him a beloved visitor (Hamilton 171-72, Nelson et al. 19, 48). After
participating in the Fetter Lane Society in the 1740s, Cooke moved on to the “Pilgrim Congregation” in
Germany.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Even more intriguing—and
more relevant to Blake—was the Dantzig-born Johan Valentin Haidt (1700-80), whose significant role in the
London art world is receiving new attention from scholars (Nelson, <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi>). As we shall see,
a Moravian art historian suggests that Blake was influenced by one of Haidt’s paintings. <note id="n21">21.
Moravian Archive: Box A2, Pilgrim House Diary (1743-48), p. 8; C/36/5/1, p. 4.</note></p>
          <p>Originally apprenticed as a goldsmith, the young Haidt determined to follow his real love,
religious and historical painting. After traveling through Europe to study the Old Masters, he moved to London
in 1724, married a Huguenot woman, and, while practising his craft, opened an “academy” in his home, where
he and his students studied “live nudes.” His comment about the importance of the nude model “may be the
earliest such reference in English art” (Nelson, “Haidt’s Theory”). He eventually befriended George
Michael Moser (1704-83), a Swiss-born gold-chaser, who shared his yearning to participate in higher art. The
two men “seemed to have started a predecessor to the Royal Academy of Arts in Haidt’s house,” which
influenced Moser’s later role as a founding member of the Royal Academy. When William Blake applied to study
at the Royal Academy in 1779, it would be Moser, “the venerable Keeper,” who evaluated his work and
oversaw his subsequent studies (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 49-51). However, it was Haidt’s role as
a Moravian artist—known as “the painting Preacher”—which is most suggestive when exploring the Blake
family’s attitudes towards art.</p>
          <p>Attracted by the passionate preaching he heard at Fetter Lane in 1738-39, Haidt experienced a
“heart-warming” similar to that of John Wesley, who was intensely attracted to the Moravians at that time.
In 1740 Haidt traveled to Herrnhaag, where he achieved “a mystical experience which he remembered all his
life” (Nelson, <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi> 9-13). Though Wesley had been rejected by the Germans as a 
<hi rend="i">homo perturbatus</hi>, Haidt was eventually accepted into the congregation. Moving between Germany
and England, he began the painting of large symbolic works with life-size figures, sometimes influenced by the
Jews he observed at Moravian services. Deeply infused with the “blood and wounds” theosophy, Haidt’s
emphasis on the role of art in the spiritual development of children inspired much of the creative and
imaginative teaching in Moravian families. Catherine Armitage could have heard about Haidt’s impressive
paintings from John Cennick, who studied and admired those exhibited in Moravian halls in Germany (Peucker,
“Kreuzbilder” 138). In 1749, when Zinzendorf moved to London, he commissioned Haidt to paint dozens of
portrayals of events in Jesus’s life and in Moravian history, to be displayed
<pb id="p40-94" n="94"/>
            <figure n="haidt.40.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="408">
	<head>9. Johann Valentin Haidt, <hi rend="i">The Cruxifiction.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Collection of the Moravian Historical Society, Nazareth, PA.</figDesc>
</figure>
at Fetter Lane and Lindsey House. In 1754 Haidt emigrated to Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, where he became known as
America’s “first religious painter,” but his artistic teachings continued to influence parents and
children in London.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n22">22. Haidt took some of his London paintings with him to Pennsylvania, and they provide a clue
to the content and style of the pictures that were destroyed by the 1941 bombing of Fetter Lane.</note></p>
          <p>According to Haidt, young students should first master drawing with a firm outline before
attempting painting, and they should study classical sculpture and copper engravings of the Old Masters.
Though Blake’s mother is credited as the primary inspiration for his artistic interests, his father
eventually supported William’s artistic bent: “The love of designing and sketching grew upon him, and he
desired anxiously to be an artist” (Cunningham, in Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 628). James Blake began
to encourage William’s drawing, bought plaster casts of classical sculpture, and funded his purchases of
engravings of Old Masters. Possibly more important for James, who initially intended his son for the
hosier’s shop, was Haidt’s insistence on the importance of an independent religious spirit in the young
artist, for talent “is a gift from God, and whoever is sure of that and convinced of it, he can paint.”
Moreover, “each one knows best what his inclinations are, and he should follow them.” Zinzendorf preached
and Haidt taught that engraving was a form of “high art,” which required sophisticated and erudite
training in order to capture the soul and beauty of drawings and paintings. It also had a spiritual resonance,
for the image of Jesus should be engraved in one’s <hi rend="i">Herz/Lev.</hi> When the adolescent Blake,
with his parents’ blessing, decided to apprentice himself as an engraver, he may have absorbed such lofty
ambitions for his craft.</p>
          <p>Haidt shared Zinzendorf’s reverence for Mary Magdalene, and they maintained the medieval
tradition that she was a prostitute and adulteress, until Jesus cast out the seven devils, who plagued her
with illicit erotic desires. They also seemed familiar with a controversial theme in that tradition—i.e.,
“all things that she had willingly done before in the service of the flesh she now in sorrow turned to the
service of her Lord” (Phipps 139). At Fetter Lane, Zinzendorf preached that Christ
<pb id="p40-95" n="95"/>
            <figure n="but495.1.1.wc" id="but495.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="753" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
              WB 1800<lb/>
              John XIX c. 23 &amp; 24 v</figTranscr>
	<head>10. William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Soldiers Casting Lots for Christ’s Garments</hi> (1800).</head>
	<figDesc>Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</figDesc>
</figure>
occupies himself “with the harlot who had seven devils,” for “He is the rightful Husband of . . . even
the most detestible [sic] prostitute” (Zinzendorf 4, 15). Moravian hymns included many references to the
<corr type="emend">Magdalene,</corr> which stress her intense attraction to Jesus, sometimes with hints of Jewish sexual mysticism: for
example, “Comes <hi rend="i">Mary</hi>, by Love’s Power drawn, With other two still weeping, To see where
<hi rend="i">Rabbi</hi> lies” (Hutton 64). During the most radical period at Herrnhaag, Zinzendorf praised
the high-spirited, eroticized youth culture as “<hi rend="i">So siindermassig spielerisch, so Maria
Magdalenerlich</hi> (so moderately sinfully playful, so Mary Magdalenish)” (Erbe 121). Blake’s mother may
have heard (and sung) an especially provocative hymn, in which Mary is called “The Lamb’s Sinner Bride,”
who plants a “Thousand Magde’len kisses” on Jesus’s body: “Lamb and Saviour, / Take from me, from
Head to Feet all over; / All thy Skin, each Pore and Hair, / Take of my Salutes to Share” 
(<hi rend="i">Collection of Hymns</hi> 2: 344). Such lines led Zinzendorf’s critics to charge that he implied a
romantic relationship between Jesus and the Magdalene. Even worse, they claimed that his erotic descriptions
of her were “intended to justify the Count’s strolling about with Anna Nitschman,” leader of the Sisters
and his frequent traveling companion, whom they accused of having an adulterous relationship with him (Rimius,
<hi rend="i">Supplement</hi> xxiv).</p>
          <p>Given this context, Haidt’s painting <hi rend="i">The Crucifixion</hi> seems to express
Zinzendorf’s version of the Jesus-Magdalene relationship, for he portrayed her sensuously with long yellow
hair and emotionally attached to Jesus. Vernon Nelson, who was unaware of the Moravian association of
Blake’s mother, observes that in Haidt’s painting “the pose of the soldiers gambling for Jesus’ cloak
should be compared to that in Blake’s portrayal of the Crucifixion” (Nelson, <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi> 21;
Butlin #495) (illus. 9 and 10).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
Nelson points out that in another Haidt painting, <hi rend="i">At the Foot of the Cross</hi>, the Magdalene
kisses Jesus’s feet, thus revealing the artist’s immersion in the Sifting Time ethos, with its
eroticization of spiritual relationships (Nelson, <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi> 21) (illus. 11).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> In Blake’s picture <hi rend="i">Mary
Magdalene Washing Christ’s Feet</hi>, she is actually kissing his feet (Butlin #488) (illus. 12); Martin
Butlin notes that in Blake’s painting, <hi rend="i">Christ the Mediator: Christ Pleading before the Father
for St. Mary Magdalene</hi>, the subject is not biblical but possibly from John Bunyan; however, “the
apparent application of the theme to the Magdalene is Blake’s own” (Butlin #429). It is suggestive that
Blake produced these paintings during a period (c. 1800-07) of friendly contact with two liberal Moravians,
the artist Jonathan Spilsbury and the poet James Montgomery, who both participated in services at Fetter
Lane.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> Could they have taken Blake to
his mother’s former church, where Haidt’s paintings were still exhibited?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n23">23. Unfortunately, the photo in Nelson’s <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi> is misnumbered, for the
description of plate 35 should refer to a painting which includes the gambling soldiers (not reproduced in the
catalogue), which is owned by the Moravian Historical Society in Nazareth, PA. I am grateful to the archivist,
Mark Turdo, for sending me a photo of the correct picture.</note>
	<note id="n24">24. For other Moravian paintings of Mary Magdalene kissing and embracing Jesus’s feet, see
Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 135, 142.</note>
	<note id="n25">25. Blake possibly knew Spilsbury when both exhibited at the Royal Academy in the 1780s, and
he described his conversation with the Moravian artist in 1804 (E 755). For Spilsbury’s career, see Young.
On Blake’s association with Jonathan Spilsbury and its Moravian significance, see Keri Davies, “Jonathan
Spilsbury and the Lost Moravian History of William Blake’s Family” [in this issue—Eds.]. Blake may have
met Montgomery during the radical writer’s visits to the London Corresponding Society in the 1790s. Though
we have no definite evidence for their acquaintance, Bentley notes that Robert Cromek’s letter to Montgomery
in 1807 “suggests a connexion between Blake and James Montgomery” and “implies an easy and personal
contact between the two men”; see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 234-35, 262, 277. For Montgomery’s career and
Moravian association, see Montgomery, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> and Everett. I provide more information on the
Oriental interests of Spilsbury, Montgomery, and Blake in <hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried</hi>
322-29.</note>
	<note id="n26">26. The striking similarities between Blake’s “tempera series” of “the Life of
Christ” for Thomas Butts and the surviving description of Haidt’s thirty-four paintings of the 
“<hi rend="i">sacramentlichen Handlungen des Heylands</hi>” (Jesus’s life-story from conception to
resurrection) is worth further study. Haidt’s series was discussed and commissioned at “a conference in
Bloomsbury, 2 October 1749,” when Blake’s mother was a participant in Moravian affairs. After the sale of
Lindsey House in 1774, many of these paintings were moved to the Fetter Lane Chapel, where they survived until
the 1941 bombing. See Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 172-73; Kroyer 52; Bindman 121-31.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-96" n="96"/>
          <figure n="footcross.40.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="504">
            <figTranscr>INRI</figTranscr>
            <head>11. Johann Valentin Haidt, <hi rend="i">At the Foot of the Cross.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Collection of the Moravian Historical Society, Nazareth, PA.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Recent biographers of the engraver and caricaturist James Gillray (1756-1815), who was raised and
educated as a Moravian, have inaccurately characterized the Unitas Fratrum as “an austere and unattractive
religious sect,” who “deplored all joy and pleasure” and who provided children with a “grim”
upbringing (Godfrey and Hallett 12). However, Moravian notions of child rearing were actually and unusually
benevolent. In 1766, when the Moravian minister James Hutton was questioned by Lord Shelburne—“Pray, how
do your children go on? Do they take after their parents?”—he answered emphatically, “Yes, God be
praised!” Hutton then described the Moravian pedagogical methods with children:
<q>
Ingenuous and affectionate treatment, without force and violence, we find has a blessed effect on their
education. We once thought otherwise; but we succeeded better by gentleness. We do all we can to prevent that
servile imitation and hypocrisy which severity always or, at least, is most likely, to produce. O! My Lord,
could you but see the heartiness of our children, you would be touched. (Benham 417)
</q></p>
          <p>As she home-schooled her children, Blake’s mother seems to have adopted this notion of
educational “gentleness,” for she was “a tender and sympathetic mother, more inclined to overlook faults
than to punish them” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 5). For Moravians, the “heartiness” of their
children was a resonant, multileveled quality; <hi rend="i">Herzlichkeit</hi> meant passionate, enthusiastic,
and imaginative visualization of and engagement with the body of the God-Man. Unaware of the erotic-artistic
emphasis of Zinzendorf’s pedagogy, the Gillray scholar Draper Hill lamented that “at the threshold of
understanding,” Moravian four-year-olds “were pushed to terrifying heights of introspection” (Hill 8).
But it was more the <hi rend="i">terribilità</hi> of Michelangelo (who was revered by Zinzendorf and his
artists); it was a transforming, energizing, imaginative passion to which the children were “pushed.” When
Isaac Disraeli later observed that “Blake often breaks into the ‘<hi rend="i">terribil via</hi>’ of
Michael Angelo,” he meant <hi rend="i">terribilità</hi> (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 329fn).</p>
          <p>The Moravian-educated poet and art critic, James Montgomery, attributed his own youthful
“heartiness” to the vivid paintings
<pb id="p40-97" n="97"/>
and powerful music he studied at the Moravian school in Fulneck, Yorkshire, in 1777-87, while his missionary
parents served (and died) in the West Indies. The schoolboys assembled and stood for a few minutes in front of
“a superb painting of a dead Christ,” rendered more dramatic by the illuminating rays of a strategically
placed lantern (Montgomery, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> 1: 31, 59). In his dormitory, Montgomery meditated upon
a “huge painting of the Entombment of Christ, by the old Moravian
            <figure n="but488.1.1.wc" id="but488.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="958" height="971">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
              WB</figTranscr>
	<head>12. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Mary Magdalene Washing Christ’s Feet</hi> (c. 1805).</head>
	<figDesc>Philadelphia Museum of Art: Gift of Mrs. William Thomas Tonner, 1964.</figDesc>
</figure>
Brandt,” as well as others which depicted striking events in the history of the Brotherhood. To heighten the
children’s passionate response, their concentration on the pictures was intensified by “the full-toned
piano, accompanied by a French bugle,” which broke the silence with profound music. As a young adult,
Montgomery left the Moravians and pursued a career as a radical writer and publisher, but he later returned to
them and remembered with some nostalgia his early schooling:
<pb id="p40-98" n="98"/>
	<q>
There is no system of religion, which I have yet seen, which, taking all in all, has half the charm for a
young, a warm, and a feeling heart, as that professed by these people. I <hi rend="i">once</hi> believed; I
<hi rend="i">once</hi> enjoyed its blessings; I <hi rend="i">once</hi> was happy! . . . The hymns of the
Moravians are full of ardent expressions, tender complaints, and animated prayers; these were my delight. As
soon as I could write and spell, I imitated them, and before I was thirteen I had filled a little volume with
sacred poems. (Montgomery, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> 1: 46)
</q></p>
          <p>Was it a similar early influence that inspired the adolescent Blake to write poems of 
<corr type="emend">spiritual</corr> and romantic yearning? Bentley notes that in Blake’s precocious love poems,
the “sexual suggestiveness is astonishing” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 260-61). The adult Montgomery was an
early admirer of Blake’s “wild &amp; wonderful genius,” especially in his illustrations to Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808), which critics scorned for their “libidinous” combination of carnality with
spirituality (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 260-61; Essick and Paley 23-25). Montgomery probably knew that
Zinzendorf had also been criticized for expressing a “<hi rend="i">Fleischlische Spiritualität</hi>”
(fleshly spirituality) (Deghaye 167n41). Blake, in turn, praised Montgomery’s publication, <hi rend="i">The
Wanderer of Switzerland, and Other Poems</hi> (1806), assuring him that it will command the applause of “all
Lovers of the Higher Kinds of Poetry” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 236). In this volume, Montgomery
praised the Moravians’ renewed missionary and abolitionist efforts, and he made a provocatively Blakean
allusion to the “Daughters of Albion,” whom he exhorted to “Weep!” (in his autobiographical account of
a frustrated, youthful love affair) (Montgomery, <hi rend="i">Wanderer</hi> 11, 167, 135, 147).</p>
          <p>Fortunately, a new generation of Moravian scholars is lifting up the blanket of darkness that was
thrown over the Sifting Time by conservative church historians after Zinzendorfs death in 1760.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> As they shed new light on the historical
realities of that fascinating and controversial period, they make it possible to uncover the equally
suppressed artistic history of the Sifting Time, whose painters, engravers, and poets may have influenced
Catherine Armitage Blake and her visionary son William. Thus, it will be fitting to conclude with a tribute to
Blake’s mother by quoting lines from a Moravian hymn, the “Te Matrem,” which Zinzendorf believed was
especially effective at instilling “heartiness” in children.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">28</ref> Praising the creative and inspirational power of the Divine Mother, wife of
God and mother of the God-Man, the congregation joyfully sang to “Thee, that Mother of Christ his Bride”:
<q>
Thou didst inspire the Martyrs tongues,<lb/>
In the last Gasp to raise their songs,<lb/>
Thou dost impel the four <hi rend="i">Zoa</hi>,<lb/>
Who singing rest not night nor day . . .<lb/>
Thou Mother of God’s Children all,<lb/>
Thou Sapience archetypal! . . .<lb/>
That thou the Prophets dost ordain,<lb/>
And gifts and wonders to them deign.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Collection of Hymns</hi> 2: 297-98)
</q>
	<note id="n27">27. Vernon Nelson began the recovery of Haidt’s artistic career, while the revisionist works
of Colin Podmore, Craig Atwood, and Paul Peucker shed new light on the theology and art of the Sifting Time.
Christiane Dithmar contributes important new Jewish material relevant to the psychoerotic themes of the
“mystical marriage.”</note>
	<note id="n28">28. For the once central but then censored role of the “Te Matrem” hymn, see Atwood,
“Mother.”</note></p>
          <p>In 1797 Blake gave the title <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> to his visionary, prophetic epic, which
begins with the words, “The Song of the Aged Mother,” whose verses herald “the day of Intellectual
Battle”:
<q>
Four Mighty Ones are in every Man; a Perfect Unity<lb/>
Cannot Exist. but from the Universal Brotherhood of Eden<lb/>
The Universal Man. To Whom be Glory Evermore Amen<lb/>
(E 300)
</q>
Around 1807, at a time of friendly Moravian contacts, he changed the title to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
and “those Living Creatures” (<hi rend="i">zoa</hi>, Greek plural) subsequently became “the Four Eternal
Senses of Man”—senses contained within the earthly man and the God-Man (Albion) (Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 198, 310). Did Blake remember the reference to “the four <hi rend="i">Zoa</hi>” in
the Moravian hymn to the Divine Mother, while he revised his phantasmagoric tale of psychoerotic
disintegration and reintegration within the human and divine worlds?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">29</ref> This and similar questions, provoked by ongoing discoveries in the
international archives of the Unitas Fratrum, suggest that new answers and new perspectives will emerge, as we
continue to explore the esoteric, erotic, and artistic underworld of Moravian “heartiness” and 
<hi rend="i">terribilità.</hi>
	<note id="n29">29. Justin Van Kleeck points to the previously unnoticed apostrophe between the “a” and
“s” of the “Zoas” (i.e., “Zoa’s”) on Blake’s title page (Van Kleeck 39). This may reflect a
mnemonic slip from the “four <hi rend="i">Zoa</hi>” of the Moravian hymn, or his uncertainty about how to
anglicize the Greek plural.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-99" n="99"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Alderfer, Everett Gordon. <hi rend="i">The Ephrata Commune: An Early American
Counterculture.</hi> Pittsburgh: U of Pittsburgh P, 1985.</p>
            <p>Atwood, Craig. “Blood, Sex, and Death: Life and Liturgy in Zinzendorf’s Bethlehem.” Diss.
Princeton Theological Seminary, 1995.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Community of the Cross: Moravian Piety in Colonial Bethlehem.</hi> University
Park: Pennsylvania State UP, 2004.</p>
            <p>—. “The Mother of God’s People: The Adoration of the Holy Spirit in the
Eighteenth-Century Brüdergemeine.” <hi rend="i">Church History</hi> 68 (1999): 886-909.</p>
            <p>—. “Sleeping in the Arms of Jesus: Sanctifying Sexuality in the Eighteenth-Century Moravian
Church.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Sexuality</hi> 8 (1997): 25-51.</p>
            <p>Atwood, Craig, and Peter Vogt, eds. <hi rend="i">The Distinctiveness of Moravian Culture:
Essays and Documents in Moravian History in Honor of Vernon H. Nelson on His Seventieth Birthday.</hi>
Nazareth: Moravian Historical Society, 2003.</p>
            <p>Bach, Jeff. <hi rend="i">Voices of the Turtledoves: The Sacred World of Ephrata.</hi>
University Park: Pennsylvania State UP, 2003.</p>
            <p>Benham, Daniel. <hi rend="i">Memoirs of James Hutton.</hi> London: Hamilton, Adams &amp; Co.,
1856.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> 2nd ed. New Haven: Yale UP, 2004. Cited as
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2).</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William Blake.</hi> New Haven:
Yale UP, 2001.</p>
            <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi> Oxford: Phaidon, 1977.</p>
            <p>“Brandt, Abraham Ludwig.” <hi rend="i">Saur Allgemeines Künstlerlexikon.</hi> München: K.
G. Saur, 1996. 13: 632.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New
Haven: Yale UP, 1981.</p>
            <p>Cennick, John. <hi rend="i">The Life of Mr. John Cennick.</hi> 2nd ed. Bristol: Printed for the
Author, 1745.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">A Collection of Hymns of the Children of God in All Ages . . . Designed Chiefly
for the Use of the Congregations in Union with the Brethren’s Church.</hi> London, 1754.</p>
            <p>Davies, Keri, and Marsha Keith Schuchard. “Recovering the Lost Moravian History of William
Blake’s Family.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 38.1 (summer 2004): 36-43.</p>
            <p>Deghaye, Pierre. <hi rend="i">La doctrine ésotérique de Zinzendorf.</hi> Paris: Klincksieck,
1969.</p>
            <p>Dithmar, Christiane. <hi rend="i">Zinzendorfs nonkonformistische Haltung zum Judentum.</hi>
Heidelberg: C. Winter, 2000.</p>
            <p>Ellis, Samuel. <hi rend="i">Life, Times, and Character of James Montgomery.</hi> London:
Jackson, Walford and Hodder, 1864.</p>
            <p>Erbe, Hans-Walter. “Herrnhaag: Eine religiöse Kommunität im 18. Jahrhundert.” 
<hi rend="i">Unitas Fratrum</hi> 23/24 (1988): 13-224.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> London: Oxford UP, 1975.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N., and Morton D. Paley. <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave 
<hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake: A Study with Facsimile.</hi> London: Scolar P, 1982.</p>
            <p>Freeman, Arthur. <hi rend="i">An Ecumenical Theology of the Heart: The Theology of Count
Nicholas Ludwig von Zinzendorf.</hi> Bethlehem: Moravian Church in America, 1998.</p>
            <p>Freeman, Rosemary. <hi rend="i">English Emblem Books.</hi> 1948. New York: Octagon, 1966.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. Rev. ed. 1880. New York:
Phaeton, 1969.</p>
            <p>Godfrey, Richard, and Mark Hallett. <hi rend="i">James Gillray: The Art of Caricature.</hi>
London: Tate Publishing, 2001.</p>
            <p>Hamilton, Kenneth, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">The Bethlehem Diary, Vol. I, 1742-1744.</hi>
Bethlehem: Archives of the Moravian Church, 1971.</p>
            <p>Hamlin, Talbot. <hi rend="i">Benjamin Henry Latrobe.</hi> New York: Oxford UP, 1955.</p>
            <p>Hill, Draper. <hi rend="i">Fashionable Contrasts: Caricatures by James Gillray.</hi> London:
Phaidon, 1966.</p>
            <p>Hugo, Hermannus. <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria.</hi> 1624. Antwerp: Henry Aertssens, 1632.</p>
            <p>[Hutton, James, ed.] <hi rend="i">A Collection of Hymns: Consisting Chiefly of Translations
from the German, Part III. Hymnbook of the Moravian Brethren.</hi> 2nd ed. London: Printed for James Hutton,
Bookseller in Fetter Lane, 1749.</p>
            <p>Kroyer, Peter. <hi rend="i">The Story of Lindsey House, Chelsea.</hi> London: Country Life,
1956.</p>
            <p>“Lebenslauf des Bruders Abraham Louis Brandt, heimgegangen den 23. Juli 1797 in Sarepta.”
<hi rend="i">Nachrichten aus der Brüdergemeine</hi> (1857): 49-56.</p>
            <p>Lowery, Margaret. <hi rend="i">Windows of the Morning: A Critical Study of William
Blake’s</hi> Poetical Sketches, <hi rend="i">1783.</hi> New Haven: Yale UP, 1940.</p>
            <p>Meyer, Henry. <hi rend="i">Child Nature and Nurture according to Nicolaus Ludwig von
Zinzendorf.</hi> New York: Abingdon, 1928.</p>
            <p>Montgomery, James. <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James Montgomery.</hi> Ed.
John Holland and James Everett. 7 vols. London: Longmans, 1854-56.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Wanderer of Switzerland, and Other Poems.</hi> London: Verner and Hood,
1806.</p>
            <p>Nelson, Vernon. <hi rend="i">Johann Valentin Haidt.</hi> Williamsburg: Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
Folk Art Collection, 1966.</p>
            <p>—. “John Valentine Haidt’s Theory of Painting.” <hi rend="i">Transactions of the
Moravian Historical Society</hi> 23 (1984): 71-78.</p>
            <p>Nelson, Vernon, Otto Dreydoppel, Jr., and Doris Rohland Yob, eds. <hi rend="i">The Bethlehem
Diary, Vol. II, January 1, 1744-May 31, 1745.</hi> Trans. Kenneth Hamilton and Lothar Madeheim. Bethlehem:
Archives of the Moravian Church, 2001.</p>
            <p>Peucker, Paul. “‘Blut auf unsre grüne Bändchen’: Die Sichtungszeit in der Herrnhuter
Brüdergemeine.” <hi rend="i">Unitas Fratrum</hi> 49/50 (2002): 41-94.</p>
            <p>—. “Kreuzbilder und Wundenmalerei: Form und Funktion der Malkunst in der Herrnhuter
Brüdergemeine um 1750.” <hi rend="i">Unitas Fratrum</hi> 55/56 (2005): 125-74.</p>
            <p>—. “A Painter of Christ’s Wounds: Johann Langguth’s Birthday Poem for Johann Jakob
Müller.” Atwood and Vogt 19-33.</p>
            <p>Phipps, William E. <hi rend="i">The Sexuality of Jesus.</hi> Cleveland: Pilgrim P, 1996.</p>
            <p>Podmore, Colin. <hi rend="i">The Moravian Church in England, 1728-1760.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon
P, 1998.</p>
            <p>Praz, Mario. <hi rend="i">Studies in Seventeenth-Century Imagery.</hi> 2 vols. London: Warburg
Institute, 1939.</p>
            <p>Rimius, Henry. <hi rend="i">A Candid Narrative of the Rise and Progress of the
Herrnhuters.</hi> London: A. Linde, 1753.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">A Supplement to the Candid Narrative of the Rise and Progress of the
Herrnhuters.</hi> London: A. Linde, 1755.</p>
            <pb id="p40-100" n="100"/>
            <p>Sachse, Julius. <hi rend="i">The German Sectarians of Pennsylvania, 1742-1800.</hi> 2 vols.
1899-1900. New York: AMS, 1971.</p>
            <p>Sadler, John. <hi rend="i">J. A. Comenius and the Concept of Universal Education.</hi> London:
Allen and Unwin, 1966.</p>
            <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith. “Why Mrs. Blake Cried: Swedenborg, Blake, and the Sexual Basis of
Spiritual Vision.” <hi rend="i">Esoterica: The Journal of Esoteric Studies</hi> 2 (2000): 45-93.
&lt;http://www.esoteric.msu.edu&gt;.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried: William Blake and the Sexual Basis of Spiritual
Vision.</hi> London: Century-Random House, 2006.</p>
            <p>Sessler, Jacob John. <hi rend="i">Communal Pietism among Early American Moravians.</hi> New
York: Henry Holt, 1933.</p>
            <p>Stead, Geoffrey and Margaret. <hi rend="i">The Exotic Plant: A History of the Moravian Church
in Britain, 1742-2000.</hi> Peterborough: Epworth, 2003.</p>
            <p>Steinberg, Leo. <hi rend="i">The Sexuality of Christ in Renaissance Art and In Modern
Oblivion.</hi> 2nd ed. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1996.</p>
            <p>Stoudt, John Joseph. <hi rend="i">Pennsylvania Folk-Art.</hi> Allentown: Schlechter’s,
1948.</p>
            <p>Swedenborg, Emanuel. <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Diary.</hi> Trans. Alfred Acton. 1962. London:
Swedenborg Society, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Swedenborg’s Dream Diary.</hi> Ed. Lars Bergquist, trans. Anders
Hallengren. West Chester: Swedenborg Foundation, 2001.</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck, Justin. “Blake’s Four . . . ‘Zoa’s’?” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 38-43.</p>
            <p>Wright, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. 1929. New York: Burt
Franklin, 1969.</p>
            <p>Young, Ruth. <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter: Jonathan and Maria Spilsbury, 1737-1812:
1777-1820.</hi> London: Epworth, 1952.</p>
            <p>Zinzendorf, Nikolaus Ludwig von. <hi rend="i">Nine Public Lectures on Important Subjects in
Religion Preached in Fetter Lane Chapel in London in the Year 1746.</hi> Trans. and ed. George Forell. Iowa
City: U of Iowa P, 1973.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
