<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.3.frosch</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">An Analogue to the “Greatest Men” Passage in The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</title>
        <author n="Frosch">Thomas R. Frosch</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2006/2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006-07</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Marsha Keith Schuchard</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006/2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
      <pb id="p40-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">An Analogue to the “Greatest Men” Passage in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Thomas R. <name>Frosch</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In teaching <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, I always found a stumbling block in the Devil’s
speech on plates 22-23: “The worship of God is. Honouring his gifts in other men each according to his
genius. and loving the greatest men best, those who envy or calumniate great men hate God, for there is no
other God.” If “every thing that lives is Holy” (pl. 27), if, as in <hi rend="i">The French
Revolution</hi>, all men are the equals of the king (line 193), how can there be great men—not just great
gifts or great works, not just the particular genius of every individual—that should be worshiped?</p>
          <p>It was not until I visited the Panthéon in Paris that the passage appeared to me in a different
light. The building that became the Panthéon had originally been conceived as a church dedicated to St.
Geneviève, patron saint of Paris, but in April 1791, just before its completion, it was converted into a
secular temple for the remains of great men, with Mirabeau and Voltaire the first to be interred. Emmet
Kennedy points to the desanctification of the church and its rededication to honor great men as the
“ultimate expression” of a revolutionary “religion of humanity” (xxv).</p>
          <p>The question of what constituted greatness provoked considerable debate, and indeed that debate
and the interest in, or cult of, “grands hommes” had predated the Revolution, with Diderot, Voltaire, and
Rousseau among the contributors. In general, though, a great man, in what Jean-Claude Bonnet calls a
“métamorphose de la gloire” (29), was no longer a military hero, much less a man of status and wealth,
but a man who had superior inner powers and had contributed in a disinterested way to the common
good.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n111" type="note">1</ref> For the French
revolutionaries, patriots and martyrs of the Revolution were particularly qualified. <note id="n111">1. This
was specifically the formulation of the Abbé de Saint-Pierre; see Bonnet 34.</note></p>
          <p>For some, the “pantheonized” were even divine. In the radical <hi rend="i">Révolutions de
Paris</hi>, Jesus was a prophet, Marat a God (Kennedy 336). As for Jesus, Leonard Bourdon called him no more
than a man but a great one, “a friend of the people,” Marat’s sobriquet, and “the first sansculotte”
(Kennedy 336). The Marquis de Villette, who had first suggested the idea of a Panthéon, spoke of making a
cross into a lyre (Bonnet 267), and Quatremère, the architect in charge of remodeling the Church of
Sainte-Geneviève into the Panthéon, envisioned a new religion of arts and artists (Kennedy 333). Meanwhile,
as E. P. Thompson has documented, English radical tradition had included such as John Reeve, who said that
there was no other God but the man Jesus (157), and other partisans of a “humanist and antinomian Jesus
Christ” (228). Blake of course was fond of citing the humanity of Jesus and the divinity of one’s own
humanity: “Thou art a Man God is no more / Thy own humanity learn to adore” (<hi rend="i">The Everlasting
Gospel</hi>, E 520).</p>
          <p>Blake’s concept of greatness differed in basic ways from the greatness that figured in the
Panthéon. His great man was not a patriot and, unlike the great men of the Panthéon, who had to be French,
was not associated with the glory of a nation, nor was he incorporated into an institutionalized, ceremonial
form of worship. Blake was not engaged with either revolt against or transformation of specifically Catholic
traditions, and he was interested not in any reverence of the dead but in the potentiality within the living.
Blake’s concept of greatness did include Jesus the sansculotte, as the passage in <hi rend="i">The
Marriage</hi> goes on to make clear: “If Jesus Christ is the greatest man, you ought to love him in the
greatest degree”; his Jesus broke several of the Ten Commandments and “was all virtue, and acted from
impulse: not from rules” (pls. 23-24). And <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> develops a concept of the
prophetic artist as central man, who reveals “the infinite which was hid” (pl. 14) and brings about
apocalyptic human change. Later, in the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> engraving, “Jesus &amp; his Apostles
&amp; Disciples were all Artists” (E 274).</p>
          <p>Mirabeau and Marat were soon “depantheonized.” The Panthéon became a church again, was later
resecularized and then once again resanctified. It then served as an arsenal for the Communards in the
insurrection of 1871 before being established once and for all with the interment of Victor Hugo in 1885 as a
secular temple of the great. Meanwhile, in England the debate on greatness took many famous literary forms,
including Byron’s satire of heroes, Carlyle’s hero worship, and Wordsworth’s democratization of
greatness.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n112" type="note">2</ref> Blake went on to give his
concept of greatness epic elaboration in the figures of Los and Jesus. <note id="n112">2. See Gaull for a
discussion of some of the attitudes towards the hero in the romantic period (145-72). Abrams (91) formulates
succinctly the romantic tendency to diminish and at the extreme to eliminate the role of God, leaving as
“the prime agents man and the world.”</note></p>
          <p>This is the context in which the passage on the greatest men in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>
belongs, the context of a humanistic, and volatile, redefinition of greatness, a contemporary example of which
was the reconceptualization of the Church of Sainte-Geneviève, with its implication of the replacement of God
by humanity.</p>
          <pb id="p40-111" n="111"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Abrams, M. H. <hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism: Tradition and Revolution in Romantic
Literature.</hi> New York: Norton, 1971.</p>
            <p>Bonnet, Jean-Claude. <hi rend="i">Naissance du Panthéon: Essai sur le Culte des Grands
Hommes.</hi> Paris: Fayard, 1998.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> New
York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988. All Blake quotations are from this edition, abbreviated “E”.</p>
            <p>Gaull, Marilyn. <hi rend="i">English Romanticism: The Human Context.</hi> New York: Norton,
1988.</p>
            <p>Kennedy, Emmet. <hi rend="i">A Cultural History of the French Revolution.</hi> New Haven: Yale
UP, 1989.</p>
            <p>Thompson, E. P. <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast: William Blake and the Moral Law.</hi>
New York: New P, 1993.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
