<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.4.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake in the Marketplace, 2006</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
      <pb id="p40-116" n="116"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake in the Marketplace, 2006</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The 2006 Blake market began auspiciously with the January auction of a
                        watercolor drawing, <hi rend="i">Oberon and Titania on a Lily</hi> (illus.
                        9). Sotheby’s New York placed a brave estimate of $400,000 to
                        $600,000 on this small work, for many years in the collection of the great
                        book and print collector Philip Hofer (1898-1984) and, since his death,
                        apparently in the possession of one or more of his descendants. Not for the
                        first time, my suspicion that a work by Blake was overestimated proved
                        unfounded. Bidding began at $200,000, rose rapidly to $400,000, paused for
                        about seven seconds at that level, and then jumped two more steps of $25,000
                        each to reach a successful bid of $450,000 ($520,000 inclusive of the
                        buyer’s premium). The winner was John Windle, the San Francisco book
                        dealer who specializes in Blake, acting on behalf of the artist and writer
                        Maurice Sendak. The whole process took about ninety seconds. Given his
                        earlier acquisitions, including copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, Sendak must be
                        considered one of the major Blake collectors of our time.</p>
          <p>Loyal readers of this journal will have learned of the dispersal of
                        Blake’s nineteen watercolors illustrating Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The
Grave</hi> from E. B. Bentley’s lively and
                        insightful essay in the fall 2006 issue.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
                        This report will necessarily repeat information provided by Bentley, but
                        will add a few new facts and speculations. Sotheby’s New York offered
                        the drawings at a special auction, devoted exclusively to the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
illustrations and with each design in its own lot, on 2 May
                        2006 (illus. 2-5, 8). This was the most spectacular Blake sale since the
                        legendary auction of W. Graham Robertson’s collection at
                        Christie’s London in 1949. The supposed sale of the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs
in 2005 to a firm in Switzerland was simply a way
                        for the London dealer Libby Howie and her financial backers to get the
                        designs out of Britain. If sold individually in a London auction, each would
                        require an export license, and this might have had a chilling effect on any
                        non-British bidders. That concern, combined with the fact that most
                        important Blake collectors reside in North America, prompted the New York
                        venue. <note id="n1">1. Bentley, “<hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
                            Indignities: Greed, Hucksterism, and Oblivion: Blake’s
                            Watercolors for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.2
(fall 2006): 66-71. For the recent history
                            of the watercolors, see also the sales reports for 2002, 2003, and 2005
                            in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 116; 37.4 (spring 2004):
                            116; and 39.4 (spring 2006): 154. For discussions of the designs, see
                            Martin Butlin, “New Risen from the Grave: Nineteen Unknown
                            Watercolors by William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 35.3
                            (winter 2001-02): 68-73; G. E. Bentley, Jr., “William Blake and
                            His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 2001,”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.1 (summer 2002): 13-16; and Alexander S.
                            Gourlay, “‘Friendship,’ Love, and Sympathy in
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> Illustrations,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.3
(winter 2003-04): 100-04. For good
                            overviews of the history of the designs since their rediscovery, see
                            Martin Bailey, “Dealer’s Decision to Break Up William
                            Blake Album Branded ‘philistine,’” <hi rend="i">Art
                                Newspaper</hi>, posted 16 March 2006
                            &lt;http://www.theartnewspaper.com/article01.asp?id=216&gt;; and
                            R. M. Healey, “Grave Mistakes: ‘Discovered’ William
                            Blake Set Broken Up at Auction,” <hi rend="i">Rare Book
                                Review</hi> 33.2 (April/May 2006): 6-7, with three color illus. The
                            May 2006 auction is summarized in Carol Vogel, “Rare Watercolor
                            Collection Auctioned Piece by Piece,” <hi rend="i">New York
                                Times</hi> 3 May 2006: B5; and in Martin Bailey and Georgina Adam,
                            “‘The break-up could and should have been
                            avoided,’” <hi rend="i">Art Newspaper</hi>, posted 1 June
                            2006
                            &lt;http://www.theartnewspaper.com/article01.asp?id=288&gt;.</note></p>
          <p>The pending auction attracted a good deal of attention in the press. The
                        first news story, by Carol Vogel, appeared in the 16 February issue of the
                            <hi rend="i">New York Times</hi>, complete with four illustrations, two
                        in color. The title of the story, “Art Experts Protest Sale of Rare
                        Set of Blakes,” indicates its general thrust. Vogel’s
                        well-researched essay was followed by an unsigned editorial in the 20
                        February <hi rend="i">Times</hi> claiming that “to sell the
                        watercolors one by one is, at the very least, to misconstrue Blake’s
                        art.” The contentious relationship between art and commerce, so much
                        a part of Blake’s life and writings, continues into our own time.
                        John Windle also believed that the impending auction would mean the tragic
                        dispersal of an integrated series of designs. Accordingly, in March he wrote
                        to a number of Blake collectors, asking them to form a consortium to make a
                        presale offer for all nineteen designs (or, failing that, bid on each at
                        auction) and donate the series to an institution, such as the Tate
                        Collection or the Huntington Library, which already had a significant Blake
                        collection. This worthy effort came to naught.</p>
          <p>Sotheby’s went all out to promote the auction. Selling nineteen highly
                        valued Blakes at one time could easily overwhelm the niche market for such
                        material. Thus, it was incumbent upon Sotheby’s to attract bidders
                        from the much larger pool of collectors of British and Old Master drawings,
                        most of whom had demonstrated no prior interest in Blake. In mid-March,
                        potential bidders were sent a handsome brochure with color reproductions of
                        five designs and of the red morocco case in which the entire group had been
                        housed, possibly for over 180 years. The watercolors were displayed at
                        Sotheby’s facilities in London (9-15 March), Paris (20-24 March),
                        Chicago (27-28 March), New York (31 March-5 April), and Los Angeles (11-12
                        April). The catalogue for the sale, sure to become a collector’s item
                        in its own right, was published as a hardbound book with all nineteen
                        watercolors reproduced in color, supplementary illustrations of related
                        designs, and a scholarly text by Nancy Bialler, Sotheby’s senior vice
                        president for Old Master prints, drawings, and paintings.</p>
          <p>On 1 May, a number of Blake collectors, dealers, and scholars assembled in
                        New York to view the designs and witness the events of the next day. The
                        group included Elizabeth B. Bentley, G. E. Bentley, Jr., David Bindman,
                        Georgia and Morris Eaves, Alexander Gourlay, John and Mary Lynn Grant, Sarah
                        Jones, Roger Lipman, Karen Mulhallen, Alan Parker, Joseph Viscomi and Maria
                        Fernandez, Chris and John Windle, and your intrepid reporter. The auction
                        opened precisely at 
<pb id="p40-117" n="117"/>
10:15 a.m. on 2 May. The sale
                        began triumphantly—from the vendor’s perspective—with
                        the title page (illus. 2) fetching a hammer price $390,000 above the high
                            estimate.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
The estimate range of
                        $180,000 to $260,000 for this lot seemed low to many interested parties.
                        When I inquired about it, Sotheby’s told me that the presence of
                        writing on the watercolor would depress its marketability to drawings
                        collectors. A very odd reason, it seemed to me—and apparently to the
                        several bidders who drove the work to $650,000 plus fees. <note id="n2">2.
                            The “hammer price” is the bid at which the auctioneer
                            sells a lot, exclusive of the buyer’s premium or any other fees.
                            In this discussion I am referring to these hammer prices at which a lot
                            is “knocked down” by the auctioneer; the net prices,
                            including buyers’ premiums, are given in the sales listings
                            below.</note></p>
          <p>Healthy bidding continued for the second lot, <hi rend="i">The Meeting of a
                            Family in Heaven</hi>, which fetched $140,000 over high estimate. The
                        next lot, <hi rend="i">Death of the Strong Wicked Man</hi>, sold within the
                        estimate range, but matters began to slip with the fourth lot, <hi rend="i">The Grave
Personified</hi>, selling at a hammer price $200,000 below
                        low estimate. The purchaser was probably simply bidding against the
                        unannounced reserve price.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> The suspicion
                        that lot 5, <hi rend="i">Whilst Surfeited upon Thy Damask Cheek</hi> (illus.
                        3), was overestimated at $700,000 to $1 million proved prescient when the
                        work failed to sell. <hi rend="i">The Reunion of the Soul and the Body</hi>,
                        lot 6, was knocked down to a bidder on the telephone at the low estimate of
                        $900,000. At this point, the auction went decidedly sour—again, from
                        the point of view of the vendor and the auction house. No bidders stepped
                        forward to meet the reserves on the next four lots, a group that included
                        two of the most highly estimated works, <hi rend="i">The Day of
                            Judgment</hi> at $1.5 to $2 million, and <hi rend="i">Death’s
                            Door</hi> (illus. 5) at $1 to $1.5 million. Lot 11, <hi rend="i">The
                            Soul Exploring the Recesses of the Grave</hi>, found a new owner, but at
                        a price well below the estimate range. The next three lots failed to sell,
                        but the final five watercolors all found purchasers. Of these, all but one
                        failed to achieve the low estimate. The exception was the final drawing, 
<hi rend="i">Friendship</hi>, which exceeded the same low estimate range
                        granted the first lot. The now-empty portfolio in which the designs were
                        housed for many decades also went well beyond its high estimate to reach
                        $4200, sold to Windle for stock. <note id="n3">3. The
                            “reserve” is the price below which the vendor and the
                            auction house have agreed not to sell a lot. Given the below-estimate
                            yet successful bids on several lots, it seems as though the reserves
                            were roughly twenty percent below the low estimates.</note></p>
          <p>Eight of the nineteen drawings were bought in; another six sold for less than
                        low estimate. Thus, fourteen of the twenty lots (counting the portfolio)
                        were very probably considered to be disappointments by the seller. The total
                        hammer price for the sold lots was $6,184,200—considerably less than
                        the roughly $8.6 million Howie is reported to have paid for the whole group.
                        Of course she still had eight drawings to sell. By the end of June,
                        Sotheby’s had arranged sales to anonymous private collectors for
                        three of the works unsold at auction: <hi rend="i">The Soul Hovering over
                            the Body Reluctantly Parting with Life, The Day of Judgment</hi>, and
                            <hi rend="i">Death’s Door</hi> (lots 7, 9, 10). If I am right in
                        estimating that the reserves were twenty percent below low estimate, and
                        assuming that these three drawings were sold in the neighborhood of these
                        reserve prices, then Howie gained roughly $2.5 million through after-auction
                        sales (less Sotheby’s fees of about 20%). She was still short of
                        recovering her initial costs by about $415,000. The remaining five unsold
                        lots (5, 8, 12-14) were returned to Howie by early July 2006. Any profits
                        would have to come from their future sale.</p>
          <p>Lacking serious offers for the unsold drawings, Howie and her backers may
                        decide to retain them for the immediate future. The rule of thumb is to wait
                        at least five years before attempting another auction, although this is
                        often honored in the breach in today’s hot art markets. If
                        Sotheby’s retained for itself the $918,440 in buyers’
                        premiums, plus fees for arranging the three after-auction sales, that was
                        probably sufficient to cover costs plus a little profit. The auction house
                        may have also received a vendor’s premium from Howie, although some
                        sales contracts waive that customary provision.</p>
          <p>Did potential bidders demur because of the controversy surrounding the
                        dispersal of the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors? I doubt that this was
                        a significant factor, at least for private collectors. Three of the five
                        major Blake collectors active today participated in the auction; each took
                        home at least one design. The absentees were Leon Black and Maurice Sendak:
                        the former may have been one of the anonymous purchasers, while the latter
                        was a bit out of pocket due to his purchase of <hi rend="i">Oberon and
                            Titania on a Lily</hi> in January. Two drawings were acquired by
                        Continental collections, thereby indicating Blake’s growing
                        reputation as an artist beyond the Anglo-American community.
                        Sotheby’s and its vendor simply overestimated the value of too many
                        lots. The market could not absorb nineteen expensive Blake drawings at a
                        single auction, even with the widening of the circle of Blake collectors
                        through the addition of a few new participants. Perhaps the lesson to be
                        learned from the proceedings is the old adage that investing in art for
                        short-term profit is a risky business, even for professionals like Libby
                        Howie.</p>
          <p>The dispersal of the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors, some into anonymous
                        private collections, will make studying all the originals arduous, even
                        impossible. Fortunately, the William Blake Archive, available online at
                        &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;, has recently published all
                        nineteen watercolors, plus one removed from the original group of twenty at
                        an unknown time but now in the Yale Center for British Art. The 300 dpi
                        enlargements in the Archive will make close study of details possible. The
                        Archive also includes Schiavonetti’s engravings, published in R. H.
                        Cromek’s 1808 edition of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and
                        Blake’s white-line etching of “Deaths Door” (illus.
                        6).</p>
          <p>The lively 2006 Blake market continued into the fall auction and catalogue
                        season. On 23 November, Sotheby’s London offered one of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> illustrations, <hi rend="i">Tiriel
                            Led by Hela</hi> (illus. 10). This was the first <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> wash
drawing to come to market since two were sold at a
                        Christie’s auction in 1971. The widely held opinion in the trade that
                        the work was overestimated at £150,000 to £200,000 proved wrong,
                        for the drawing fetched 
<pb id="p40-118" n="118"/>
a hammer price of
                        £145,000, just below the low estimate, but £170,400 when the
                        auction-house fees are included. A few hours after the auction, I was
                        informed by Emmeline Hallmark of Sotheby’s that “there is some
                        confusion surrounding the sale of the Blake.” I was not able to
                        unravel this mysterious “confusion” by January 2007, but will
                        report any further information in my 2007 sales review.</p>
          <p>At the end of November, Windle issued another in his series of impressive
                        catalogues of Blake and Blake’s circle. Catalogue 42 is devoted
                        exclusively to engravings and etchings by Blake, including some great
                        rarities. Each of the ninety-three items is accompanied by at least one
                        thumbnail illustration; every item is included in the listings below.</p>
          <p>Readers of the 2005 sales review may have noticed that works by Thomas
                        Stothard, and particularly his book illustrations, were beginning to consume
                        more space than Blake’s. To avoid having to change my title to
                        “Stothard in the Marketplace,” I have instituted a new policy
                        for that prolific artist. Beginning with this review, I continue to list
                        sales of all drawings, separate prints, and prepublication proofs of book
                        illustrations by Stothard that have come to my attention, but I include only
                        those editions of books illustrated by Stothard that are not mentioned in
                        the standard reference works: A. C. Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard,
                            R.A.</hi> (London: Bullen, 1906) and Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Thomas
Stothard: The Mechanisms of Art Patronage in England circa
                            1800</hi> (Columbia: U of Missouri P, 1988). Thus, newly discovered book
                        illustrations will still be recorded.</p>
          <p>The year of all sales and catalogues in the following lists is 2006 unless
                        indicated otherwise. Works offered online and previously listed in either of
                        the last two sales reviews are not repeated here. In my 2005 review, I
                        failed to include several works by Blake’s circle and followers
                        offered in John Windle’s catalogue 40 of November 2005. These
                        materials are listed below. The auction houses add their purchaser’s
                        surcharge to the hammer price in their price lists. These net amounts are
                        given here, following the official price lists. The value-added tax levied
                        against the buyer’s surcharge in Britain is not included. Late 2006
                        sales will be covered in the 2007 review. I am grateful for help in
                        compiling this review to Martin Bailey, Emma Baudey, Nancy Bialler, Martin
                        Butlin, Alex Chappell, John E. Grant, Mary Lynn Grant, Emmeline Hallmark,
                        Donald Heald, Barbara Hinde, Tim Linnell, Richard Nathanson, Alan Parker,
                        Justin Schiller, Steven Tabor, Carol Vogel, David Weinglass, and John
                        Windle. My special thanks go to Alexander Gourlay for his generosity in
                        keeping me abreast of internet auctions. Once again, Sarah Jones’
                        editorial expertise and John Sullivan’s electronic imaging have been
                        invaluable.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <table rows="23" cols="2">
              <row>
                <cell>BA</cell>
                <cell>Bloomsbury Auctions, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford:
                                    Clarendon P, 1977). Plate numbers and copy designations for
                                    Blake’s illuminated books follow <hi rend="i">BB.</hi></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books
                                    Supplement</hi><lb/>
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1995)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>BH</cell>
                <cell>Bonhams, auctioneers, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)</cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd
                                    ed.<lb/>
(New Haven: Yale UP, 2004)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Butlin</cell>
                <cell>Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of
                                        William Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New Haven: Yale UP,
                                    1981)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>cat.</cell>
                <cell>catalogue or sales list issued by a dealer (usually followed
                                    by a number or letter designation)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">CB</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                                        Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P,
                                    1991)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CL</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CNY</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Coxhead</cell>
                <cell>A. C. Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi>
                                    (London: Bullen, 1906)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CSK</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, South Kensington</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>E</cell>
                <cell><hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
                                        Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, newly rev. ed. (New York:
                                    Anchor-Doubleday, 1988)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>EB</cell>
                <cell>eBay online auctions</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>illus.</cell>
                <cell>the item or part thereof is reproduced in the catalogue</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>PBA</cell>
                <cell>Pacific Book Auction Galleries, San Francisco</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>pl(s).</cell>
                <cell>plate(s)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>SL</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>SNY</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">SP</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William
                                        Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP,
                                    1983)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>st(s).</cell>
                <cell>state(s) of an engraving, etching, or lithograph</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Swann</cell>
                <cell>Swann, auctioneers, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>#</cell>
                <cell>auction lot or catalogue item number</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Illuminated Books</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, pl. 9. Color printed with
                            hand coloring, a single pen and black ink framing line approx. 8 mm.
                            from the edge of the image. Wove paper without watermark, leaf 17.0
                            × 12.7 cm. Probably printed c. 1794-96, the framing lines added
                            by Blake c. 1818 or later. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 169, 184
                            (“untraced”); Butlin #279 (“Private Collection,
                            U.S.A.”). On loan in 2006 from Dorothy Braude Edinburg of
                            Brookline, Massachusetts, to the Chicago Art Institute as a promised
                            gift to the Harry B. and Bessie K. Braude Memorial Collection at the
                            institute, accession no. 94.1998. Apparently Edinburg (and possibly a
                            forebear) is the private collector who has owned the print since shortly
                            after its auction at CL, 14 March 1967, #85, illus. (£770 to
                            Agnew’s).</p>
            <p>“Introduction” (pl. 30) to <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                Experience.</hi> A posthumous impression in gray-black ink on wove
                            paper without watermark, the leaf trimmed to 17.9 × 11.0 cm. to
                            match the leaf size of a copy of William Pickering’s 1839 ed. of
                                <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, into which
                            this impression is bound 
<pb id="p40-119" n="119"/>
as a frontispiece.
                            Sold Feb., still bound in the book, by John Windle to Roger Lipman. For
                            further information on this impression, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4
                            (spring 2006): 150.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, posthumous copy
                            o, 3 pls. only: “Nurses Song” (pl. 24) from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (black
ink, leaf 13.8 × 9.9 cm.),
                            “Nurses Song” (pl. 38) from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
                            (reddish-brown ink, leaf 27.9 × 18.7 cm.), and “The School
                            Boy” (pl. 53, orange ink, leaf 28.0 × 18.4 cm.). Acquired
                            Aug. by John Windle from N. W. Lott of Larkhall Fine Art; offered
                            individually in Windle’s Nov. cat. 42, #77-79, illus. (prices on
                            request). For additional information and earlier sales offers, see 
<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 112, 129-30; <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 24.4 (spring
                            1991): 118; 28.4 (spring 1995): 121; 29.4 (spring 1996): 111.</p>
            <figure n="S-Inn.Spring.trimmed.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="355">
              <head>1. “Spring,” pl. 23 from <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                    Innocence</hi>, trimmed to the design only 2.8 × 7.5 cm.
                                (including the vine extensions left and right).</head>
              <figDesc>Etched in relief 1789, color printed and hand colored c.
                                1794-96. One of only 3 pls. from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> with
                                color printing; the others are the designs only of pls. 5
                                (“The Shepherd”) and 22 (the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> pl.
                                of “Spring”), now both at the Yale Center for British
                                Art. This is the only Blake etching known to me which has been cut
                                along a design element—in this case, a vine—to create
                                a decorative frame. Blake may have printed the designs only, and
                                masked the texts, of these 3 pls. as part of, or as an experiment
                                leading up to, his <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi> of 1796.
                                I suspect, however, that someone else trimmed the pl. reproduced
                                here to its present configuration, one which also eliminated the
                                vine at the bottom of the pl. Provenance: sold “The Property
                                of a Lady,” Sotheby’s Belgravia, 5 April 1977, #207
                                (£280 to a dealer on behalf of the American Blake Foundation);
                                on consignment with John Windle, Sept. 2006; offered for sale in
                                Windle’s Nov. 2006 cat. 42, #76, illus. color (price on
                                request). The 2 color prints now at the Yale Center were also sold
                                from the same “Property” in the same auction, #209-10.
                                The previous 3 lots, all Blake materials, were sold “The
                                Property of John Linnell, Esq.”—probably John
                                Stainforth Linnell, a descendant of Blake’s patron. Perhaps
                                the “Lady” was also connected with the Linnell family.
                                Photo courtesy of John Windle.<lb/>
<lb/>
 This pl. has been
                                consistently misdescribed, beginning with Sotheby’s 1977
                                auction cat. in which it was said to be the design only on the 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> pl. of “Spring,” pl. 22. Bentley,
                                not knowing who acquired the print and thus apparently relying on
                                this erroneous cat. description, repeats the error in <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
112, 130.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>“Spring,” pl. 23 from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>,
                            trimmed to the design only, 2.8 × 7.5 cm. Color printed with hand
                            coloring. On consignment from the American Blake Foundation with John
                            Windle, Sept.; offered in Windle’s Nov. cat. 42, #76, illus.
                            color (price on request). See illus. 1.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, copy G<hi rend="s">1</hi>. Plates a4, a6, and
b3 only, printed for the abridged issue in
                            12 pls. of c. 1794 in olive-brown ink on wove paper without watermark.
                            With rudimentary color printing in reddish-brown and black. Leaves 13.5
                            × 11.5 cm. (pl. a4), 13.7 × 9.5 cm. (pl. a6), and 13.5
                            × 10.7 cm. (pl. b3). On consignment from the American Blake
                            Foundation with John Windle, Aug.; offered individually in
                            Windle’s Nov. cat. 42, #85-87, illus. (prices on request; all 3
                            acquired by Robert Essick). For further information on these
                            impressions, see <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 80, 445; <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                            137.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p40-120" n="120"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Drawings and Paintings</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">Christ the Mediator.</hi> Tempera, 26.4 × 37.8 cm.,
                            datable to c. 1799-1800. Butlin #429. Acquired at auction in June 2005
                            by Leon Black, New York. For discussion and illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
39.4 (spring 2006): 148, 151.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Nineteen Watercolors Illustrating Robert Blair’s</hi>
                            The Grave. SNY, 2 May, in a sale devoted to just these works, all from
                            the stock of the London art dealer Libby Howie. Each design, illus. in
                            color, sold separately in the following lots. The designs in lots 1-3,
                            6-11, 13, 14, and 18 were engraved by Louis Schiavonetti for Robert
                            Cromek’s 1808 ed. of <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> Lots 4, 5, 12,
                            15-17, and 19 were not engraved, but some (as noted below) were included
                            among the 15 “subjects proposed to be engraved” in
                            Cromek’s 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> prospectus of Nov. 1805. The 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> prospectus, of the same date, alters the number of
                            illustrations to 12 but does not include a list of subjects. Lots 1-19
                            are pen and ink and watercolor drawings over at least traces of pencil.
                            See illus. 2-5, 8, a group that includes all designs not published in
                            the 1808 edition of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> and not previously
                            reproduced in this journal. <list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1. <hi rend="i">Title Page</hi>, inscribed by Blake,
                                        “The Grave / a Poem / By Robert Blair / Illustrated
                                        with 12 Engravings / by Louis Schiavonetti / From the
                                        Original Inventions / of / William Blake, / 1806.”
                                        33.2 × 26.6 cm. $744,000 to a bidder on the
                                        telephone; estimate $180,000-260,000. The only engraved
                                        design not included in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> prospectus,
                                        but perhaps originally intended as the
                                        “characteristic Frontispiece” listed there;
                                        see also #4, 17. I have not been able to confirm the rumor
                                        in the New York art world that the purchaser was
                                        Salander-O’Reilly Galleries, New York, acting for
                                        David Thomson, Toronto. David Thomson is the son of Kenneth
                                        Roy Thomson, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> Baron Thomson of Fleet
                                        (1923-2006). See illus. 2.</p></item>
	<item><p>2. <hi rend="i">The Meeting of a Family in Heaven.</hi> 23.4
                                        × 13.3 cm. $576,000 to a bidder in the room; estimate
                                        $280,000-360,000. According to Bailey and Adam (see my note
                                        1), the purchaser was Hinrich Sieveking; if so, he was
                                        probably acting for the Winterstein Collection, Munich.</p></item>
	<item><p>3. <hi rend="i">Death of the Strong Wicked Man.</hi> 20.2
                                        × 25.5 cm. $1,584,000 to La Société des
                                        Amis du Louvre, Paris, and at least one other supporter of
                                        the Louvre, Antoine Prat, for presentation to the museum;
                                        estimate $1,000,000-1,500,000. A record auction price for a
                                        Blake watercolor and the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> work by Blake
                                        to enter the Louvre’s collection.</p></item>
	<item><p>4. <hi rend="i">The Grave Personified.</hi> 20.3 ×
                                        29.7 cm. Possibly the “characteristic
                                        Frontispiece” listed in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
                                        prospectus, although the horizontal format argues against
                                        that notion; see also #1, 17. $912,000 to H. Charles and
                                        Jessie Price, Dallas, Texas; estimate $1,000,000-1,500,000.
                                        For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 35.3 (winter
                                        2001-02): 73. The back of the cardboard mount bears a light
                                        pencil sketch, not recorded prior to the auction cat. The
                                        sketch pictures a Blakean figure in a posture similar to the
                                        woman’s on the recto, squatting and hunched over,
                                        with her(?) head between very prominent knees. Possibly by
                                        someone attempting to imitate Blake?</p></item>
	<item><p>5. <hi rend="i">Whilst Surfeited upon Thy Damask Cheek, the
                                            High-Fed Worm in Lazy Volumes Roll’d, Riots
                                            Unscar’d.</hi> 19.6 × 13.3 cm. Not sold;
                                        highest bid $520,000 on an estimate of $700,000-1,000,000.
                                        Returned to Howie in July. See illus. 3.</p></item>
	<item><p>6. <hi rend="i">The Reunion of the Soul and the Body.</hi>
                                        23.7 × 17.5 cm. $1,024,000 to an anonymous bidder on
                                        the telephone; estimate $900,000-1,200,000.</p></item>
	<item><p>7. <hi rend="i">The Soul Hovering over the Body Reluctantly
                                            Parting with Life.</hi> 16.0 × 22.7 cm. Not sold;
                                        highest bid $520,000 on an estimate of $700,000-1,000,000.
                                        Sold by the end of June to a private collector.</p></item>
	<item><p>8. <hi rend="i">The Descent of Man into the Vale of
                                            Death.</hi> 23.4 × 13.5 cm. Not sold; highest bid
                                        $480,000 on an estimate of $700,000-1,000,000. Returned to
                                        Howie in July. For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.2
                                        (fall 2006) front cover.</p></item>
	<item><p>9. <hi rend="i">The Day of Judgment.</hi> 27.0 × 22.2
                                        cm. Not sold; highest bid $1,100,000 on an estimate of
                                        $1,500,000-2,000,000. Sold by the end of June to a private
                                        collector.</p></item>
	<item><p>10. <hi rend="i">Death’s Door.</hi> 23.9 × 13.8
                                        cm. Not sold; highest bid $750,000 on an estimate of
                                        $1,000,000-1,500,000. Sold by the end of June to a private
                                        collector. See illus. 5-7.</p></item>
	<item><p>11. <hi rend="i">The Soul Exploring the Recesses of the
                                            Grave.</hi> 23.5 × 11.9 cm. $632,000 to Florence
                                        and Noel Rothman, Chicago; estimate $700,000-1,000,000. The
                                        purchasers are the husband and wife who have, over the last
                                        25 years, assembled the finest Blake collection in private
                                        hands.</p></item>
	<item><p>12. <hi rend="i">The Gambols of Ghosts According with Their
                                            Affections Previous to the Final Judgment.</hi> 26.9
                                        × 20.7 cm. Not sold; highest bid $520,000 on an
                                        estimate of $700,000-1,000,000. Returned to Howie in July.
                                        For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 35.3 (winter
                                        2001-02): 69.</p></item>
	<item><p>13. <hi rend="i">The Counseller, King, Warrior, Mother and
                                            Child, in the Tomb.</hi> 15.0 × 23.4 cm. Not
                                        sold; highest bid $500,000 on an estimate of
                                        $700,000-1,000,000. Returned to Howie in July.</p></item>
	<item><p>14. <hi rend="i">The Death of the Good Old Man.</hi> 20.2
                                        × 25.8 cm. Not sold; highest bid $420,000 on an
                                        estimate of $550,000-700,000. Returned to Howie in July.</p></item>
	<item><p>15. <hi rend="i">A Father and Two Children beside an Open
                                            Grave at Night by Lantern Light.</hi> 17.5 × 23.5
                                        cm. $329,600 to an anonymous bidder in the room; estimate
                                        $350,000-550,000. See illus. 4.</p></item>
	<item><p>16. <hi rend="i">Heaven’s Portals Wide Expand to Let
                                            Him In.</hi> 23.7 × 12.8 cm. $329,600 to John
                                        Windle acting for Robert Essick; estimate $350,000-550,000.
                                        See illus. 8.</p></item>
	<item><p>17. <hi rend="i">Our Time Is Fix’d, and All Our Days
                                            Are Number’d.</hi> 23.4 × 17.7 cm.
                                        Possibly the “characteristic Frontispiece”
                                        listed in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> prospectus; see also #1,
                                        4. $318,400 to an anonymous bidder in the room; estimate
                                        $350,000-550,000. For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                                        35.3 (winter 2001-02): 72; 37.3 (winter 2003-04): 101 (where
                                        the design is titled “Friendship”); and 40.2
                                        (fall 2006): 71.</p></item>
	<item><p>18. <hi rend="i">Christ Descending into the Grave.</hi> 23.0
                                        × 12.4 cm. $329,600 to Alan Parker, London; estimate
                                        $350,000-550,000. For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                                        40.2 (fall 2006): 71.</p></item>
	<item><p>19. <hi rend="i">Friendship</hi> (so inscribed on the mount).
                                        23.8 × 17.6 cm. Listed as #10 in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
prospectus. $318,400 to Alan Parker, London;
                                        estimate $180,000-260,000. For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
35.3 (winter 2001-02): 70; 37.3 (winter
                                        2003-04): 103 (where the 
<pb id="p40-121" n="121"/>
design
                                        is titled “There’s no bye-road / To
                                        bliss”); and 40.2 (fall 2006) back cover.</p></item>
	<item><p>20. The red morocco wallet-style case in which the designs
                                        have been housed, possibly for over 180 years. Stamped on
                                        the catch for the clasp, “Designs for /
                                        Blair’s Grave,” and lined with red paper
                                        showing a “Beilby &amp; Knotts 1821”
                                        watermark. $5040 to John Windle; estimate $1000-1500. Sold
                                        July by Windle to a California private collector.</p></item>
</list></p>
            <figure n="butwba10.1.1.wc" id="butwba10.1.wc.01" work-copy="butwba10.1" rend="db" width="803" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>The Grave<lb/>
              a Poem<lb/>
              By Robert Blair<lb/>
              Illustrated with 12 Engravings<lb/>
              by Louis Schiavonetti<lb/>
              From the Original Inventions<lb/>
              of<lb/>
              William Blake<lb/>
              1806.</figTranscr>
              <head>2. <hi rend="i">Inscribed Title-Page Design for</hi> The Grave
                                    (<hi rend="i">The Skeleton Re-Animated</hi>).</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and gray and black inks and watercolor over traces of
                                pencil, 33.2 × 26.6 cm. The angel of the last trump recalls
                                the skeleton to animate life. Although the design may have been
                                executed along with other illustrations to Blair’s poem in
                                the fall of 1805, Blake could not have added the text before he had
                                learned, in late Nov. or early Dec. 1805, that Schiavonetti had been
                                hired to engrave the designs. The “1806” date would in
                                that case have been anticipatory or not added until that year. It is
                                also possible that this watercolor was a later addition to the
                                group, executed in the same year as the inscribed date. There is a
                                small patch of abrasion just right of the second line (“a
                                Poem”) of the inscription, but nothing further that might
                                indicate an alteration in the wording. The leaf is larger than any
                                of the other designs in the original group of 20 and is backed with
                                stiff paper rather than mounted on a backing board with framing
                                lines. An alternative title page in the Huntington Library and Art
                                Collections (Butlin #616) is also dated “1806.” That
                                work is inscribed “A Series of Designs . . . Invented &amp;
                                Drawn by William Blake” and may have been intended as a title
                                page for a portfolio of drawings rather than prints.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p40-122" n="122"/>
            <figure n="butwba10.1.7.wc" id="butwba10.1.wc.07" work-copy="butwba10.1" rend="db" width="684" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
              <head>3. <hi rend="i">Whilst Surfeited upon Thy Damask Cheek, the
                                    High-Fed Worm in Lazy Volumes Roll’d, Riots
                                    Unscar’d.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pen and gray and black inks and watercolor over traces of
                                pencil, 19.6 × 13.3 cm., datable to the fall of 1805. Like
                                    <hi rend="i">The Widow Embracing Her Husband’s Grave</hi>
                                (Yale Center for British Art, Butlin #633), once part of the series
                                of mounted <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors, this is a
                                contemporary scene, although the costuming of the man follows
                                Blake’s predilection for tight-fitting (and partly
                                see-through) jumpsuits. The subject of the design is indicated by
                                the small, spiraling worm just above the man’s extended left
                                foot. The woman gestures to her “damask cheek” with
                                her right hand and to the worm with her left; the man strides
                                towards and stares into the open grave. Perhaps the shadows
                                extending behind his feet, executed with the same black wash
                                picturing the depths of the pit before him, indicate the inevitable
                                fate even for a robust youth. His arms and hands, crossed over and
                                grasping his chest, suggest that he has just realized that binding
                                truth. The gothic church, however, offers a different portal, one
                                suggesting an alternative vision of death as a transition to
                                immortal spirit. See the similar use of gothic motifs in illus. 8.
                                Is the sun pictured just above the distant mountain setting or
                                rising? The passage illustrated does not specify the time of 
                                day.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p40-123" n="123"/>
            <figure n="butwba10.1.19.wc" id="butwba10.1.wc.19" work-copy="butwba10.1" rend="db" width="958" height="714">
	<figTranscr/>
              <head>4. <hi rend="i">A Father and Two Children beside an Open Grave at
                                    Night by Lantern Light.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pen and gray and black inks and watercolor over pencil, 17.5
                                × 23.5 cm., datable to the fall of 1805. The design does not
                                illustrate any specific passage in Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> but would
                                seem to form a contrastive pair with <hi rend="i">The Widow Embracing Her Husband’s Grave</hi>
                                (Yale Center for British Art, Butlin #633). Like several of the 
                                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations, Blake has recycled a
                                composition he first executed years earlier, in this case <hi rend="i">Burial
                                Scene</hi>, a wash drawing datable to c. 1780-85
                                (McGill University Library, Butlin #137 recto). John E. Grant and
                                Mary Lynn Grant have suggested in conversation that the adult male
                                in the design reproduced here might be a clergyman, rather than the
                                father of the title, and the youthful but mature woman the mother of
                                the boy to her right. The father would then presumably be in the
                                grave to which the clergyman gestures. When in 1794 Blake used a
                                similar composition to illustrate “The Garden of Love”
                                in <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, the adult male became a
                                tonsured ecclesiastic. Sotheby’s catalogue of 2 May 2006,
                                #15, comments interestingly on the style of this watercolor:
                                “<hi rend="i">A Father and Two Children</hi> is more
                                loosely executed than any of the other watercolors offered here.
                                While the faces are worked up in some detail, the surroundings are
                                indicated by quick brush strokes, thereby leaving the trees and the
                                lantern rather two dimensional.” These features are similar
                                to those in <hi rend="i">Churchyard Spectres Frightening a
                                Schoolboy</hi> (Essick collection, Butlin #342), a design also
                                illustrating <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (for discussion and illus.,
                                see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 33.4 [spring 2000]: 106-08).<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p40-124" n="124"/>
            <figure n="butwba10.1.16.wc" id="butwba10.1.wc.16" work-copy="butwba10.1" rend="db" width="583" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
              <head>5. <hi rend="i">Death’s Door.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pen and black ink and watercolor over pencil, 23.9 ×
                                13.8 cm., datable to the fall of 1805. The mortal body enters the
                                tomb; the ever-youthful spiritual body rises above.<gap type="emend"/> 
                                See illus. 6-7.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="esxiii.1.1.sp" id="esxiii.1.spb.01" work-copy="esxiii.1" rend="db" width="653" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>DEATHS<lb/>
              DOOR</figTranscr>
              <head>6. “Deaths Door.”</head>
              <figDesc>White-line etching with touches of India ink, 18.6 ×
                                11.7 cm., datable to the fall of 1805. Essick collection. This is
                                probably the “Specimen of the Stile of Engraving”
                                which was on display at “the Proprietor’s, Mr.
                                Cromek,” according to the first prospectus of Nov. 1805 for
                                his edition of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> According to
                                Robert T. Stothard, Thomas Stothard’s son, Cromek found
                                Blake’s print “etched . . . so indifferently and so
                                carelessly . . . that he employed Schrovenetti [sic] to
                                engrave” the designs (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 219). In his
                                white-line etching, reversed in comparison to the watercolor (illus.
                                5), Blake has replaced the small plants behind the old man’s
                                back with a thorny branch and added some spiky leaves lower right
                                (left in the watercolor). The slight indications of vegetation above
                                the tomb have also been altered. These changes, however, are
                                inconsequential in comparison to the quantum shift in sensibility
                                and style. It is not difficult to imagine Cromek’s reaction
                                to the etching, so different in feeling and mode of expression from
                                the watercolor he probably had already approved for publication. Its
                                aesthetic is more akin to the purposeful primitivisms of early
                                modernism, such as Paul Gauguin’s and Edvard Munch’s
                                wood engravings or the work of German expressionists, than to
                                anything within the compass of early nineteenth-century tastes.
                                Blake’s print is so foreign to those tastes that no publisher
                                of the time would have included such a work in a book intended to
                                make money. As is typical of his efforts as an experimental
                                printmaker, Blake uses white-line etching as an opportunity for
                                transformation and reinvention, not simply as a means of replicating
                                an image invented and already executed in a different medium.
                                Further, Blake allows the intrinsic properties of the medium to
                                express themselves—darkness, crepuscular illumination, rugged
                                forms that signal their production through the scraping-out of
                                resist and the biting of acid. The image is caverned out of metal,
                                like the recesses of the tomb. Blake’s work forces upon our
                                apprehension its means of execution—overwhelmingly so, from
                                Cromek’s perspective.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p40-125" n="125"/>
            <figure n="bb435.1.12-11.com" id="bb435.1.comdes.12" work-copy="bb435.1" rend="db" width="603" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>P.32.<lb/>
<lb/>
              Drawn by W. Blake.<lb/>
              Etched by L. Schiavonetti.<lb/>
<lb/>
              Death’s Door.<lb/>
<lb/>
              ’Tis but a Night, a long and moonless Night,<lb/>
              We make the Grave our Bed, and then are gone!<lb/>
<lb/>
              London, Published May 1st. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.</figTranscr>
              <head>7. “Death’s Door.”</head>
              <figDesc>Intaglio etching/engraving by Louis Schiavonetti after Blake,
                                    2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> published state with verses added below
                                the title and dated May 1808 in the imprint, 24.3 × 13.9 cm.
                                Essick collection. The earliest known proof bears a Feb. 1806
                                imprint and may have been the first <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
                                illustration executed by Schiavonetti. Perhaps Cromek wanted to see,
                                before proceeding further with his project, the differences between
                                Blake’s and Schiavonetti’s work. In contrast to
                                Blake’s white-line etching (illus. 6), Schiavonetti’s
                                print is an accurate graphic translation of the watercolor (illus.
                                5). His work is readily apprehended, with each motif clearly
                                indicated, whereas Blake’s print disconcerts such easy
                                “reading” of the image. To this day, many people to
                                whom I have shown the two prints side by side prefer
                                Schiavonetti’s.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p40-126" n="126"/>
            <figure n="butwba10.1.13.wc" id="butwba10.1.wc.13" work-copy="butwba10.1" rend="db" width="544" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
              <head>8. <hi rend="i">Heaven’s Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pen and gray and black inks and watercolor over pencil, 23.7 × 12.8 cm., datable to
the fall of 1805. Essick collection.
                                The figure of the ascending Christ is very similar to <hi rend="i">The
Ascension</hi> (Fitzwilliam Museum, Butlin #505), one of
                                the biblical watercolors Blake painted for Thomas Butts c. 1803-05.
                                That work includes the apostles standing below Christ, replaced in
                                the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> design by “his train” of
                                “followers,” as Blair’s text specifies. These
                                include, from left to right, the (right?) hand of a figure otherwise
                                not pictured (suggesting that the group is a small portion of a much
                                larger gathering, as with the arms and hands of the marginal angels
                                in Blake’s Job engravings, pl. numbered 14); a small female
                                (or boy with long hair), probably younger than the larger figures;
                                an embracing couple, similar to the father and mother in “The
                                Meeting of a Family in Heaven,” a published <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
illustration, but the man is bearded and would
                                appear to be older than the woman in this design; a woman with a bun
                                or coil of hair on the back of her head; probably a male with wavy
                                hair; a woman with two strands of loose hair dangling down her back;
                                another woman with slight indications of the same coiffure; a female
                                or male with long hair, symmetrically placed with the similarly
                                sized (and youthful) figure on the left; and only the legs and a bit
                                of the body and head of a figure cut off by the right margin. The
                                sense of weightlessness is common to all the figures. The gothic
                                arches above Christ, decorated with praying angels and (palm?)
                                fronds, continue the portal imagery central to the entire series of
                                illustrations. These architectural motifs hint at Blake’s
                                concept that imaginative art is one of the routes to, or even one
                                with, the spiritual world. This watercolor is free of the foxing
                                that slightly mars others in the series; its delicate colors are
                                particularly fresh and unfaded. A preliminary pencil sketch, on the
                                back of a sketch for <hi rend="i">The Death of the Strong Wicked
                                    Man</hi>, is in the Victoria and Albert Museum (Butlin #624
                                verso).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p40-127" n="127"/>
            <p><hi rend="i">Oberon and Titania on a Lily.</hi> Watercolor, 21.1 ×
                            16.2 cm. Butlin #245, dating the work to c. 1790-93. SNY, 25 Jan., #130,
                            illus. color original size ($520,000 to John Windle acting for Maurice
                            Sendak). See illus. 9.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Tiriel Led by Hela.</hi> Pen and gray washes, 17.8 ×
                            26.9 cm., datable to c. 1788. Butlin #198.10. SL, 23 Nov., #192,
                            “the Property of a Family [of Mrs. Louise Y. Kain],”
                            illus. color (£170,400). See illus. 10.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Visionary Head.</hi> Pencil and black chalk, 36.0 ×
                            26.0 cm. SL, 7 June, #320, illus. color (£9000 to John Windle).
                            Sold July by Windle and Maggs Bros. to a British private collector. The
                            auction cat. suggests that this may be the work sold from the Graham
                            Robertson collection, CL, 22 July 1949, with 2 other works in #58,
                            described as “a slight sketch of a head in a tall hat of the
                            Italian renaissance” (£18.18s. to Maggs). That drawing,
                            however, measured only “8 in. by 13 in.” (20.3 ×
                            33.0 cm.); note particularly that its height is less than its width
                            (just the reverse of the drawing sold SL). Previously offered
                            Agnew’s, <hi rend="i">130<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual Exhibition
                                of Watercolours and Drawings</hi>, 5-28 March 2003, #18, illus.
                            color (£15,000). For illus. and discussion, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.4
(spring 2004): cover, 119-20.</p>
            <p>Might this head of a sullen soldier bear some relation to Blake’s
                            confrontation with John Scofield in August 1803 (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2]
158-66)? Scofield was a private soldier in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> Regiment of Dragoons. In his letter to
Thomas Butts
                            of 16 Aug. 1803, Blake states that Scofield “put himself into a
                            Posture of Defiance” (E 732) when Blake evicted him from his
                            garden. The phrase nicely fits the man’s expression in this
                            Visionary Head. The incident and subsequent trial for sedition haunted
                            Blake for decades, as indicated by the many references to those events
                            and personalities in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (1804-20). At the very
                            least, I suspect that it would be difficult for Blake to draw a
                            soldier’s head of this sort without calling to his mind some
                            recollection of Scofield. The canted cylinder forming the upper
                            structure of the man’s hat in this drawing resembles several
                            varieties of helmets worn by horse-mounted soldiers during the
                            Napoleonic era. The griffin decorating the hat recalls the eagle-headed
                            and winged men in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 46.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Separate Plates and Plates in Series</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>“Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims.” Swann, 7 March, #167, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., thread
margins top and on both sides, imprint
                            and quotation from Chaucer (right of the imprint) apparently trimmed
                            off, “cream wove paper . . . time stain[ed] and linen-backed with
                            tears and handling creases,” possibly a much-abused Sessler
                            impression, illus. ($1800). Clars auction, Oakland, California, 9 July,
                            #6438, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., apparently a Colnaghi impression on
                            laid India, “laid down to board, mat burn,” India paper
                            becoming detached lower right, illus. color online ($900). John Windle,
                            Nov. cat. 42, #7, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st. on laid India, probably a
                            Colnaghi impression, framed, illus. ($22,500).</p>
            <p>Dante engravings. CL, 20 Sept., #18, complete set, probably the 1892
                            printing, foxed, creases and a few tears in margins, illus. color
                            (£20,400; estimate £8000-12,000). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42,
                            #15, complete set, probably the 1892 printing, illus. color (price on
                            request); #16-20, pls. 1-2, 4-6 only, offered individually, probably the
                            1892 printing, illus. (from $7500 to $17,500); #21-26, pls. 2-7, offered
                            individually, 1968 printing, illus. (from $2750 to $5000). Sims Reed,
                            Dec. cat., #33, complete set, “marginal indications of watermarks
                            suggest that this set is from the first printing,” apparently not
                            bound, illus. color (£35,000).</p>
            <p>“Idle Laundress,” Blake after Morland. EB, Dec. 2005-Jan.,
                            imprint trimmed off (or at least not shown in the illus.) and thus st.
                            not identifiable (probably 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi>), color printed with
                            additional hand coloring, marginal stains, framed, illus. color
                            ($550).</p>
            <p>“Industrious Cottager,” Blake after Morland. EB, Dec.
                            2005-Jan., imprint trimmed off (or at least not shown in the illus.) and
                            thus st. not identifiable (probably 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> or 4<hi
rend="s">th</hi>), color printed with additional hand coloring,
                            marginal stains, framed, illus. color ($550).</p>
            <p>Job engravings. Ursus Books, April online cat., complete set, 1826
                            printing on Whatman paper after the removal of the “Proof”
                            inscription, half Russia, rebacked and repaired, illus. color ($45,000).
                            CNY, 1 May, #49, pl. numbered 7 only, 1826 published
                            “Proof” impression on laid India, framed, illus. color
                            (not sold; estimate $2000-4000). Swann, 4 May, #195, pl. numbered 16
                            only, 1826 published “Proof” impression on laid India,
                            illus. ($3200). Edwin Epps, July private offer, pl. numbered 9 only,
                            apparently a published “Proof” impression on laid India
                            ($2500; sold to the University of South Carolina Library). Swann, 14
                            Sept., #101, pl. numbered 6 only, 1826 printing on Whatman after the
                            removal of the “Proof” inscription, illus. ($1600). CNY,
                            26 Sept., #46, pl. numbered 7 only, published “Proof”
                            impression on laid India, slight stains, illus. color (not sold;
                            estimate $1000-1500). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #29, complete set, 1826
                            published “Proof” impressions on so-called
                            “French” paper, some foxing, “original blue paper
                            boards as issued,” illus. (price on request); #30, complete set,
                            1826 published “Proof” impressions on laid India, later
                            full morocco “slightly faded,” illus. (price on request);
                            #31, pl. numbered 5 only, 1826 published “Proof”
                            impression on so-called “French” paper, 3 small creases,
                            illus. ($2950); #32, pl. numbered 19 only, 1826 published
                            “Proof” impression on so-called “French”
                            paper, illus. ($3950); #33-54, complete set, 1874 printing on laid
                            India, each pl. offered individually, illus. (from $1500 to $3500).</p>
            <pb id="p40-128-129" n="128-129"/>
            <figure n="OberonTitania.watercolor.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="603">
              <head>9. <hi rend="i">Oberon and Titania on a Lily.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Watercolor, 21.1 × 16.2 cm. Butlin #245, dating the work
                                to c. 1790-93. Photo courtesy of Sotheby’s New York, where
                                the drawing was sold on 25 Jan. to Maurice Sendak. Clearly, the
                                sleeping female reclines, and the alert male sits, on two separate
                                lilies, not the single “lily” of the title first given
                                to the work by William Michael Rossetti in his catalogue of
                                Blake’s drawings and paintings in Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of
William Blake</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1863) 2:
                                237, #213. A third, unopened flower rises above the female figure.
                                Rossetti’s association of the design with
                                Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night’s
                                    Dream</hi> seems reasonable. As Sotheby’s cataloguer
                                points out, the nearest point of textual contact is in act 2, scene
                                2, when Oberon “has just sprinkled her [Titania’s]
                                eyes with a potion that will cause her to fall in love with the
                                first living creature she sees when she awakes.” There are
                                many references to flowers, including one to “lily
                                lips,” throughout the play, but there is no indication in
                                this or any other scene that the king and queen of the fairies rest
                                on flowers. Additional evidence supporting Rossetti’s title
                                is provided by the similarity between the two figures and Oberon and
                                Titania in <hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania, and Puck with Fairies
                                    Dancing</hi> (Butlin #161, dating the work to c. 1785), a design
                                firmly connected with Shakespeare’s text. Oberon also wears a
                                crown and a cloak, the latter fastened at the shoulder with a
                                brooch, and holds a scepter in <hi rend="i">Oberon and Titania,
                                    Preceded by Puck</hi> (Butlin #246, dating the work to c.
                                1790-93). I suspect that most viewers will perceive the figures in
                                the watercolor reproduced here as diminutive fairies resting on
                                flowers of normal size, but Blake’s many transformations in
                                perspective, from the minute to the cosmic, might also warrant our
                                seeing the figures as humans in a world of gigantic plants.<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Oberon and Titania on a Lily</hi> is William
                                Blake’s variation on a design first executed by his brother
                                Robert in the notebook they both used (Butlin #201.5[13]). In
                                Robert’s pen and wash drawing, a man and woman, both probably
                                crowned and neither asleep, recline on a poppy. A ring of
                                hand-holding figures, hovering beneath a partly opened flower above
                                and behind the couple, is probably a portrayal of the
                                “roundel” of Titania’s attendants at the
                                beginning of act 2, scene 2 of <hi rend="i">A Midsummer
                                    Night’s Dream.</hi> The relationship between poppies and
                                sleep, such as Titania’s in act 2, scene 2, is a
                                long-standing convention. The iconographic significance of
                                William’s shift to lilies—traditional emblems of
                                purity, the Virgin Mary, and the Bourbon monarchy of
                                France—is not easily deciphered. A slightly altered version
                                of William’s watercolor, reversed, appears as a full-pl.
                                design in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los.</hi> That literary context
                                offers little assistance to the interpreter. Perhaps the closest
                                point of contact with the text of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
                                is the “valleys of delight” from which “Antamon
                                call’d up Leutha” (E 67). In <hi rend="i">Europe a
                                    Prophecy</hi>, Antamon is “prince of the pearly
                                dew” and Leutha the “Soft soul of flowers” (E
                                65); the latter is also intimately associated with flowers and
                                female sexuality in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                                    Albion.</hi> Whatever the composition’s symbolic import,
                                its connection with his beloved brother may have been its main
                                attraction for William.<lb/>
<lb/>
 Blake’s method of composing
                                pls. for his illuminated books did not require detailed preliminary
                                drawings. Thus, it is highly unlikely that this watercolor was
                                executed as part of the production of <hi rend="i">The Song of
                                    Los</hi>, dated 1795 on its title page. Butlin’s dating
                                of the watercolor to c. 1790-93 suggests as much, and also implies
                                that the design’s meaning in the context of the illuminated
                                book may not be relevant to the watercolor. I see nothing in the
                                style of the drawing, and in particular the rather careless handling
                                of Oberon’s face, to prohibit an even earlier date than
                                Butlin’s, closer to the execution of Robert’s version
                                or his death in 1787. The figures in <hi rend="i">Oberon and
                                    Titania, Preceded by Puck</hi> are particularly crude and thus
                                would warrant a date much earlier than Butlin’s c. 1790-93.
                                Perhaps William and Robert began to work together in the early- or
                                mid-1780s on images inspired by <hi rend="i">A Midsummer
                                    Night’s Dream.</hi></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p40-130" n="130"/>
            <figure n="but198.1.10.wd" rend="file" width="500" height="362">
              <head>10. <hi rend="i">Tiriel Led by Hela.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pen and gray washes over pencil, 17.8 × 26.9 cm.,
                                datable to c. 1788. Butlin #198.10, then in the collection of Mrs.
                                Louise Y. Kain, Louisville, Kentucky. The vendor at SL on 23 Nov.,
                                listed as a “Family,” probably inherited the work from
                                Mrs. Kain. One of 12 finished illustrations to Blake’s poem
                                <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, and 1 of only 3 remaining in private
                                hands (3 are untraced since 1863 when the entire group was dispersed
                                at auction). Tiriel’s daughter, Hela, leads her blind father
                                through a wooded but open landscape. Tiriel’s curse has
                                caused some of Hela’s hair to turn into snakes that spring
                                from the top of her head. Like all the finished <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>
                                designs, this example was very probably prepared as
                                a preliminary for an intaglio etching/engraving never executed.
                                Blake may have had in mind for his illustrated poem a format similar
                                to the one he describes at the end of the <hi rend="i">Island in the
                                Moon</hi> manuscript: “Then said he I would have all the
                                writing Engraved instead of Printed &amp; at every other leaf a
                                high finishd print . . .” (E 465).<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>“The Man Sweeping the Interpreter’s Parlour,” <hi rend="i">SP</hi> impression 2L. Sold
            				July by John Windle and Maggs Bros. to a British private collector.</p>
            <p>“Morning Amusement” and “Evening Amusement,”
                            the pair, Blake after Watteau. CL, 20 Sept., #17, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi>
                            sts., printed in brown, “touches of hand-colouring in blue and
                            rose,” margins (including the imprints) folded over the backing
                            cards, margins water stained, other minor defects, folded portions in
                            very poor condition, “Evening Amusement” illus. color (not
                            sold; estimate £800-1200). Acquired immediately after the sale by
                            John Windle for stock; offered in Windle’s Nov. cat. 42, #90,
                            restored, “Evening Amusement” illus. ($7500 the pair).</p>
            <p>“M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Q,” Blake after Villiers. EB, Jan.,
                            framed, poorly illus. color ($202.50); Jan., stained, illus. color
                            (offered only at the “buy it now” price of £240).
                            Either or both of these prints may be the convincing lithographic
                            reproduction of 1906.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake,
                                    Including Prints Extracted from Such Books</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Allen, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi>, 1798. John Windle, Nov. cat.
                            42, #1-3, pls. 1, 3, 4 only, offered individually, illus. ($350
                            each).</p>
            <p>Allen, <hi rend="i">Roman History</hi>, 1798. John Windle, Aug. private
                            offer, pl. 1 only, a prepublication proof (acquired by Robert Essick).
                            For details, see Appendix: <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                                Commercial Book Illustrations.</hi></p>
            <p>Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando Furioso.</hi> Grant &amp; Shaw, Dec. 2005
                            cat. 68, #3, 1783 ed., 5 vols., contemporary calf, joints repaired
                            (£325). EB, Dec. 2005-Jan., 1785 ed., 5 vols., slight browning of
                            the pls., contemporary calf, illus. color ($346.87); June, 1783 ed.,
                            vol. 3 (with Blake’s pl.) only, contemporary calf worn, illus.
                            color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $499.99); same copy, Oct.,
                            offered only at the “buy it now” price of $499.99;
                            June-July, 1799 ed., 5 vols., some browning, contemporary calf very
                            worn, some covers loose, illus. color ($136.50); Sept., same copy(?),
                            but now with modern calf spines and labels, illus. color ($306); Oct.,
                            1785 ed., 5 vols., a few leaves loose, contemporary calf very worn, some
                            covers detached, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of
                            $195). Bernard 
<pb id="p40-131" n="131"/>
Shapero, Oct. online cat.,
                            1783 ed., 5 vols., contemporary calf ($1680). North American Rarities,
                            Oct. online cat., 1785 ed., 5 vols., full calf worn ($700). James
                            Cummins, Oct. online cat., 1799 ed., 5 vols., contemporary calf worn
                            ($600). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #4, Blake’s pl. only, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi>
st., illus. ($200).</p>
            <p>Bible, <hi rend="i">The Royal Universal Family Bible</hi>, 1780. Victoria
                            Bookshop, Oct. online cat., apparently vol. 1 only, “leather . .
                            . boards detached” (£205). Only 1 of Blake’s 5 pls.
                            is in vol. 1.</p>
            <p>Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, colored copies. John Windle, Nov.
                            cat. 42, #5, pl. 1 (title page) only, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> published
                            st. from the 1808 folio issue, tinted with watercolors, illus. (price on
                            request). The hand coloring shows some skill on the descending figure,
                            but amateurish carelessness in the coloring of the flames. This colorist
                            would not seem to be the same as the artist who colored all the Blake
                            pls. in a copy of the 1808 quarto issue now in the Huntington
                            Library.</p>
            <p>Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, uncolored copies. EB, Dec. 2005, 1813
                            quarto, browning or foxing on some pls., particularly the engraved title
                            page, near-contemporary quarter calf, illus. color ($787.99). Skinner
                            auction, Boston, 7 Jan., #699, pl. 12 only, 1813 imprint, foxed and
                            stained, illus. color online ($300). Book Alley, Jan. private offer,
                            1870 ed., publisher’s cloth, hinges worn ($800). James Cummins,
                            March cat. 95, #64, 1813 quarto, some slight foxing on pls., half calf,
                            illus. ($2000). EB, April, pl. 9 only, 1813 imprint, illus. color
                            (£49.99). BA, 15 June, #517, 1808 quarto, a few pls. foxed, no
                            description of the binding, illus. color (£714). Thomas Goldwasser,
                            June private offer, 1808 quarto, uncut in original boards with cover
                            label, recased with new endpapers ($5000). Jeffrey Stern, Oct. online
                            cat., 1808 quarto, slight foxing, uncut in original boards with cover
                            label, engraved portrait of Schiavonetti by Cardon inserted
                            (£1450). Lipper Books, Oct. online cat., 1808 quarto, some foxing
                            and darkening of pl. margins, contemporary calf restored ($2496).
                            Contact Editions, Oct., probably the 1870 folio, damp staining,
                            publisher’s cloth worn ($1350). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #6,
                            pl. 5 only from the [1870] ed., “margins slightly soiled and
                            worn,” illus. ($275). EB, Nov.-Dec., pl. 8 only, 1813 imprint,
                            illus. color ($100).</p>
            <p>Bonnycastle, <hi rend="i">Introduction to Mensuration</hi>, 1794. Acorn
                            Bookshop, April online cat., full calf worn ($125).</p>
            <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Graphic Illustrations of . . . Shakspeare</hi>, c.
                            1803. EB, Jan.-Feb., with “nearly 100 Fine Engravings,” no
                            mention of Blake’s pl. but presumably present, margins of pls.
                            water stained, no description of binding other than “cover is
                            quite tatty,” illus. color (£102—plus £50 for
                            shipping if destined for the United States). Eveleigh Books, Oct. online
                            cat., slight foxing and damp staining, “original boards”
                            rebacked ($3324.09).</p>
            <p>Bryant, <hi rend="i">New System . . . of Ancient Mythology.</hi> Richard
                            Smith, Oct. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., 1774-76, 3 vols.,
                            light foxing and browning, modern half calf (£630). The Bookshop
                            (Chapel Hill, NC), Oct. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., 1774-76,
                            3 vols., scattered foxing, calf very worn ($850). Hoffman’s
                            Bookshop, Oct. online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1775-76, 3 vols.,
                            modern buckram ($650).</p>
            <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, 1796. John Windle,
                            Nov. cat. 42, #8-14, pls. 1-5, 7-8 only, offered individually, pls. 7-8
                            with stains, illus. (from $350 to $550).</p>
            <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden.</hi> Grant &amp; Shaw, May cat. 70,
                            #48, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791), 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
                            ed. of Part 2 (1789), 2 vols. in 1, pls. foxed and some trimmed into,
                            contemporary calf, hinges repaired (£2750); another copy, Sept.
                            cat. 71, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791), 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> ed. of
Part 2 (1794), foxed, contemporary quarter morocco
                            worn (£600). Lyon &amp; Turnbull auction, Edinburgh, 11 July,
                            #1345, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791), 4<hi rend="s">th</hi>
                            ed. of Part 2 (1794), 2 vols. in 1, foxed, contemporary quarter morocco
                            worn, binding illus. color online (£269.50). Hordern House, Oct.
                            online cat., apparently 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791), no
                            indication for Part 2, 2 vols. in 1, light foxing, contemporary calf
                            ($5026). Thomas Macaluso, Oct. online cat., 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of
                            Part 1 (1795), 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2 (1791), 2 vols. in 1,
                            slight foxing, boards rebacked with calf ($1350). ASP Art &amp; Science
                            Projects, Oct. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791),
                                2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. of Part 2 (1790), 2 vols., moderate
                            foxing, half calf (£1200). Second Time Around, Oct. online cat.,
                                2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791), 4<hi rend="s">th</hi>
                            ed. of Part 2 (1794), 2 vols. in 1, lacking 1 (non-Blake) pl.,
                            contemporary calf rebacked (£800). Barter Books, Oct. online cat.,
                                3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1795), no indication for Part
                            2, 2 vols. in 1, some browning, “leather” worn
                            (£720). Peter Grosell, Oct. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed.
                            of Part 1 (1791), 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2 (1791), lacking
                            subtitle to Part 1, 2 vols. in 1, contemporary calf worn ($868). Gaston
                            Renard, Oct. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791),
                                3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2 (1791), 2 vols. in 1, light
                            foxing, contemporary Russia ($12,257—a record asking price).
                            Argosy Book Store, Oct. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1
                            (1791), 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. of Part 2 (1790), 2 vols. in 1,
                            scattered foxing, modern three-quarter morocco ($1500). EB, Oct., 1799
                            ed., apparently Part 1 only, “an excellent candidate for repair
                            or re-binding” (i.e., a wreck), illus. color (£103). For a
                            preliminary drawing for the frontispiece to Part 1 (“The Economy
                            of Vegetation”) of <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>, engraved
                            by Anker Smith, see <hi rend="i">Flora Surrounded by the Four
                                Elements</hi> under Fuseli, below.</p>
            <p>Earle, <hi rend="i">Practical Observations on the Operation for the
                                Stone</hi>, 1793. Staniland Booksellers, Sept. online cat., pls.
                            browned and stained, original boards uncut, rebacked with paper
                            (£245). The 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> copy to come on the market since
                            1990.</p>
            <p>Enfield, <hi rend="i">The Speaker</hi>, 1781. John Windle, Oct. online
                            cat., contemporary calf worn ($678.50).</p>
            <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Classical Compositions</hi>, 1870. Heritage Book
                            Shop, Oct. online cat., contemporary morocco worn ($1500); same copy and
                            price, Dec. cat., #120.</p>
            <pb id="p40-132" n="132"/>
            <p>Flaxman, Hesiod designs, 1817. EB, Feb., bound with Flaxman’s
                            designs for the <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> (1805), <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> (1805),
and Aeschylus (1831), presentation inscription
                            dated 1864, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century calf worn, illus. color
                            ($999). BA, 24 Aug., #460, with Flaxman’s designs for the 
<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> (1793), <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> (1793), and
                            Aeschylus (1795), all foxed, uniformly bound in contemporary calf very
                            worn, some covers detached (£520). W. Hornby, Oct. online cat.,
                            foxed, quarter calf worn (£350). Sotheby’s Devon, 24 Oct.,
                            #291, cloth, with “twenty-five facsimiles of drawings by Flaxman,
                            selected by J. H. Foley, RA privately printed (50 copies only)
                            1863” (£168).</p>
            <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs, 1805. EB, March-April,
                            Blake’s pl. 1 only, water stained in upper margin, illus. color
                            ($18.63). PBA, 29 June, #111, bound with Flaxman’s designs for
                            the <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> (1805) and Aeschylus (1795), foxed and
                            damp stained, later quarter calf very worn, front cover detached, illus.
                            (not sold; estimate $800-1200). Lyon &amp; Turnbull auction, Edinburgh,
                            11 July, #1013, bound with Flaxman’s designs for the <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>
(1805) and Aeschylus (date not recorded but possibly
                            the c. 1818 ed.), foxed, half calf very worn, illus. color online
                            (£98). EB, July, apparently bound with Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>
designs (1805), foxed, heavily on some pls.,
                                19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century quarter calf worn, illus. color
                            ($102.50). See also Flaxman, Hesiod designs, above.</p>
            <p>Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, 1793. EB, Jan., 2 vols., described as
                            lacking the pl. for fable 17 in vol. 2, but no pl. was published for
                            that concluding fable, contemporary calf worn, illus. color (£243);
                            another copy, 2 vols., contemporary calf very worn, parts of backstrips
                            missing, covers loose, illus. color ($212.50). BA, 5 Oct., #115, 2
                            vols., foxed and browned, contemporary calf rebacked, worn (£180);
                            #116, foxed and browned, contemporary morocco worn (£110). Heritage
                            Book Shop, Oct. online cat., 2 vols., half calf ($1250). Staniland
                            Booksellers, Oct. online cat., 2 vols., small water stains, modern half
                            morocco (£600). Wittenborn Art Books, Oct. online cat., 2 vols.,
                            contemporary quarter calf ($1100). Truepenny Books, Oct. online cat., 2
                            vols., full calf ($825). Thornton’s Bookshop, Oct. online cat., 2
                            vols., contemporary calf (£250). Hermitage Bookshop, Oct. online
                            cat., 2 vols., full calf worn ($1250). A Book By Its Cover, Oct. online
                            cat., 2 vols. in 1, light foxing, “leather-bound” ($1200).
                            Sanctuary Books, Oct. online cat., 2 vols. in 1, scattered foxing,
                            contemporary sheep worn ($750). Argosy Book Store, Oct. online cat., 2
                            vols., contemporary calf worn ($1200).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, 1805. Ursus Books, April online cat.,
                            sts. of the pls. not recorded, later morocco ($2250).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>, 1803-04. EB, Dec. 2005, pl. 2
                            only, st. uncertain but probably 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi>, imprint trimmed
                            off, illus. color (£19.50); pl. 3 only, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.,
                            imprint trimmed off, slight foxing, illus. color (£62); Dec.
                            2005-Jan., pl. 1 only, title and imprint trimmed off, st. not
                            identifiable, illus. ($129); another impression, with title and imprint,
                            st. not identifiable, illus. color (£19.99). Lyon &amp; Turnbull
                            auction, Edinburgh, 11 July, #1225, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 3 vols.,
                            foxed, contemporary half calf worn, with <hi rend="i">The Private
                                Correspondence of William Cowper</hi>, 1824, 2 vols., bindings
                            illus. color online (£98). Second Life Books, Oct. online cat.,
                                1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., 3 vols., light foxing, contemporary calf
                            rebacked ($1100). Aquila Books, Oct. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
                            ed., 3 vols., contemporary calf rebacked ($500).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi>, 1809. PBA, 17 Aug., #35,
                            imprint trimmed off Blake’s pl., some soiling, later half morocco
                            worn, illus. color online ($175). Heritage Book Shop, Oct. online cat.,
                            contemporary calf ($1350). Powell’s Books, Oct. online cat.,
                            contemporary calf very worn, damaged ($500). James Fenning, Oct. online
                            cat., slight foxing, half morocco (£650). John Windle, Nov. cat.
                            42, #27, Blake’s pl. only, illus. ($450).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 1803. Grant &amp; Shaw,
                            Feb. cat. 69, #40, apparently the small-paper issue, pls. foxed,
                            contemporary calf rebacked (£395). EB, Sept., small-paper issue,
                            some foxing, contemporary calf rebacked, illus. color (no bids on a
                            required minimum bid of £175). James Fenning, Sept. cat. 231, #117,
                            small-paper issue, contemporary calf (£450). Bohemian Bookworm,
                            apparently small-paper issue, pls. offset, no information on binding
                            ($850). EB, Oct., contemporary calf rebacked, slight foxing on pls.,
                            illus. color (£139). BA, 16 Nov., #375, large-paper issue, some
                            foxing, A. E. Newton’s bookplate, uncut in original boards
                            rebacked and worn, later slipcase, illus. color (£420). See also
                            Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>, below.</p>
            <p>Hoare, <hi rend="i">Inquiry</hi>, 1806. Sims Reed, March cat. of
                            “British Illustrated Books,” #49, half cloth
                            (£285).</p>
            <p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">The Beggar’s Opera by Hogarth and
                            Blake</hi>, 1965. John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #28, original folding case
                            “slightly worn,” illus. ($975).</p>
            <p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> Sims Reed, Feb. cat. of “Sixty
                            Books,” #11, undated Boydell issue of “c. 1790,”
                            107 pls., no mention of Blake’s pl. but presumably with the 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> or 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st., contemporary calf
                            repaired (£9000); same copy and price, March cat. of
                            “British Illustrated Books,” #51. EB, Feb., Blake’s
                            pl. only, probably 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., slight foxing in the top
                            margin, water stained along the lower edge, illus. color (a bargain at
                            £14.99). CSK, 6 June, #69, 1822 ed., water stained, a few tears,
                            contemporary half roan very worn, covers detached (£720).</p>
            <p>Hunter, <hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi>, 1793. CSK, 13 April, #187,
                            quarto issue, later quarter roan worn (£840). Grant &amp; Shaw,
                            May cat. 70, #83, quarto issue, later half calf (£3200). Peter
                            Harrington, Oct. online cat., quarto issue, occasional foxing, recent
                            calf (£4750). Time Booksellers, Oct. online cat., quarto issue,
                            recent calf ($5855). James Cummins, Oct. online cat., quarto issue,
                            contemporary calf rebacked ($4250). St. Mary’s Books &amp;
                            Prints, Oct. online cat., octavo issue, minor soiling, <pb id="p40-133" n="133"/>
contemporary calf worn (£1800). Berkelouw, Oct.
                            online cat., octavo issue, modern half calf ($2674).</p>
            <p>Josephus, <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> EB, April, issue “E” in
                                <hi rend="i">BB</hi>, scattered foxing, contemporary calf worn,
                            nicely rebacked, illus. color (£160). Swann, 24 April, #150, issue
                            “B” in <hi rend="i">BB</hi>, some stains and browning,
                            marginal foxing on pls., contemporary calf worn ($550). EB, July, issue
                            “E” in <hi rend="i">BB</hi>, contemporary calf worn,
                            illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $775); probably the
                            same copy, Sept., same result. Second Story Books, Oct. online cat.,
                            possibly issue “A” in <hi rend="i">BB</hi>, some foxing,
                            contemporary calf rebacked, “leather slipcase” worn
                            ($2000).</p>
            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms.</hi> EB, Feb., 1789 ed., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st. of the pl.,
contemporary calf very worn, half of spine
                            missing, illus. color (£37). SL, 13 July, #435, 1794 ed., st. of
                            the pl. not recorded, contemporary calf very worn, head of spine
                            missing; with Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 1803 ed.,
                            contemporary calf rebacked, and Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of
                                Morality</hi>, 1792 ed., 3 vols., lacking 3 leaves of text and 2
                            pls., spotting and browning, contemporary calf very worn
                            (£240).</p>
            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy.</hi> EB, Jan., pl. 2 only,
                            foxed, illus. color (£28). Ursus Books, April online cat., 1810
                            ed., 3 vols. in 5, later three-quarter morocco, illus. color ($3500).
                            Gallery at Knotty Pine auction, West Swanzey, New Hampshire, 27 May,
                            #2090, 1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century quarter
                            calf worn, illus. color online ($300). Thomas Goldwasser, June online
                            cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, half morocco very worn, spines damaged
                            and covers detached ($1250). EB, July, pl. 2 only, illus. color (no bids
                            on a required minimum bid of $199). Antiquariat Nikolaus Weissert, Oct.
                            online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, contemporary calf restored
                            ($3762). Abbey Antiquarian Books, Oct. online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols.
                            in 5, later half calf worn (£1705). John Gatch, Oct. online cat.,
                            1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, marbled boards with new “leather
                            spines” ($2750). B &amp; L Rootenberg, Oct. online cat., vols.
                            1-2 (1789, 1792), vol. 3 (1810), 3 vols. in 5, minor foxing,
                            contemporary calf ($2750). Austwick Hall Books, Oct. online cat.,
                            1789-98 ed., number of vols. not given, boards rebacked (£1400).
                            Asher Rare Books, Oct. online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century calf ($2460). Thomas Goldwasser, Oct.
                            online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, leaves uncut, three-quarter
                            morocco very worn, spines defective and covers detached ($1289).
                            Wittenborn Art Books, Oct. online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5,
                            contemporary calf ($950). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #55-58,
                            Blake’s 4 pls., offered individually, illus. (from $125 to
                            $200).</p>
            <p>Malkin, <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi>, 1806.
                            Frontispiece only, designed in part by Blake, a proof before all letters
                            intermediate between the 2 previously recorded proof sts., acquired July
                            by David Bindman from a print stall on Portobello Road, London. The
                            central portrait medallion corresponds to the image in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
proof st., but the surrounding design corresponds to the
                                2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> proof st. (design finished, but lacking all
                            letters). For the previously recorded proofs and information on the
                            engravers who worked on the pl., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 34.4
                            (spring 2001): 120 (illus. 5, 6), 126-27. Johnnycake Books, Oct. online
                            cat., foxed, original boards heavily soiled and worn, 2 impressions of
                            Blake’s pl., presentation inscription by Malkin to “M and
                            L Ellis” ($1575). Holybourne Books, Oct. online cat., uncut,
                            later cloth worn (£275).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine.</hi> Adrian Harrington, Oct.
                            online cat., vol. 8 only, 1782, contemporary roan worn (£350). John
                            Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #59, vol. 9, pl. 2 only, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
                            st., illus. ($100); #60, vol. 8, Blake’s 2 pls. only, pl. 1
                            trimmed to the image (1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st.), pl. 2 full leaf (2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> st.), illus. ($150 the pair); #61, vol. 8, pl. 2
                            only, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., illus. ($100); #62-66, vol. 10,
                            Blake’s 3 pls. only, offered individually, 3 impressions of pl. 3
                            (1 trimmed to image), all 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st., illus. (from $75 to
                            $100); #67, vol. 9, pl. 3 only, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st., illus.
                            ($100); #68, vol. 9, pl. 1 only, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st., illus.
                            ($100).</p>
            <p>Olivier, <hi rend="i">Fencing Familiarized</hi>, 1780. Second Life Books,
                            Oct. online cat., later calf rebacked, worn ($1368). Roger Middleton,
                            Oct. online cat., rebound in “leather” (£525). John
                            Price, Dec. cat., #86, recent pigskin (£950).</p>
            <p>Rees, <hi rend="i">The Cyclopædia</hi>, 1820. CSK, 16 March, #421,
                            “46” (an error for 45?) vols. including all pls. vols.,
                            some browning, contemporary half calf worn (£2880; estimate
                            £800-1200).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi>, [1824] for 1825. SNY, 12 Dec., #41,
                            publisher’s calf, lacking some pls., Blake’s pl. illus.
                            color ($10,200 to John Windle for stock; estimate $3500-5000). The
                            auction cat. failed to point out that this copy lacks 1 leaf of
                            text.</p>
            <p>Ritson, <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi>, 1783. EB,
                            April, vols. 1-2 of 3 only, contemporary calf very worn, illus. color
                            (£107.55); same copy?, Sept., illus. color ($127.50). Bonhams
                            auction, Oxford, 6 June, #885, 3 vols., contemporary calf worn, covers
                            detached (£47); #886, 3 vols., contemporary calf rebacked
                            (£141). Galerie Bassenge auction, Berlin, 12 Oct., #1194, 3 vols.,
                            contemporary calf worn, illus. color online (no bids on a required
                            minimum bid of €400). Travis &amp; Emery Music Bookshop, Oct.
                            online cat., 3 vols., recent quarter leather (£386). Kenneth
                            Karmiole, Oct. online cat., 3 vols., contemporary calf worn ($1250).
                            Argosy Book Store, Oct. online cat., 3 vols., contemporary calf rebacked
                            ($750). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #69-73, Blake’s pls. 1, 4, 6-8
                            only, offered individually, illus. ($75 each). Blake’s pls. are
                            in vols. 1-2.</p>
            <p>Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>, 1792. Adrian Greenwood,
                            Oct. online cat., 3 vols., lacking 2 pls. (1 attributed to Blake), and
                            pp. xiii-xiv, 9-16, some browning on pls., later calf, vols. 1-2
                            rebacked, front cover of vol. 3 loose (£295); same copy, EB, Oct.,
                            illus. color (£195). See also Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>,
                            above.</p>
            <p>Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, 1782. John Windle, Nov. cat. 42,
                            #74-75, Blake’s pls. 1 and 3 only, offered individually, illus.
                            ($100 each).</p>
            <pb id="p40-134" n="134"/>
            <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi>, 1802. SL, 13 July, #87, 9
                            vols., pls. spotted, contemporary Russia (£3360). Peter Harrington,
                            Oct. online cat., 9 vols., scattered foxing, contemporary Russia
                            rebacked in calf (£8750). Bookhouse, Oct. online cat., 9 vols.,
                            foxed, with a few annotations by the actor Henry Irving (1838-1905),
                            three-quarter “leather” ($25,000).</p>
            <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, 1805. EB, Feb.-March, vol. 10 only,
                            described as containing “engravings” and thus presumably
                            including Blake’s pl. 2, pls. stained, contemporary calf very
                            worn, illus. color (£0.99); Nov., 31 (of 37) pls. only, including
                            Blake’s pl. 1, marginal stains, illus. color ($249).</p>
            <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, colored copies. Reg and Philip
                            Remington, July cat. 37, #91, 1806 ed., 2 vols., contemporary calf
                            rebacked (£8500). EB, Sept., pl. 9 only, hand colored (but not the
                            publisher’s coloring) on the monkeys’ faces, stained and
                            foxed, illus. color (£10.50). CL, 27 Sept., #71, 1806 ed., 2 vols.,
                            contemporary Russia rebacked, 2 pls. illus. color (£3840). EB,
                            Oct., pl. 12 only, partly hand colored (not the publisher’s
                            coloring), margins stained, illus. color (£7.95). The coloring in
                            the copy sold CL is in the earlier of 2 styles, originally executed for
                            the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of 1796. There seem to have been some
                            remainder impressions bound into a few 1806 copies.</p>
            <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, uncolored copies. Peter Harrington,
                            Feb. Los Angeles Book Fair, 1796 ed., 2 vols., contemporary calf
                            ($7875). The 19<hi rend="s">th</hi> Century Shop, March cat. 110, p. 16
                            (no item #), 1796 ed., 2 vols., “one minor tear, one
                            repair,” contemporary half calf, illus. color ($7000). BA, 24
                            May, #601, 1796 ed., 2 vols., some foxing, contemporary calf worn,
                            rebacked, illus. color (£1190). CL, 7 June, #214, 1796 ed., 2
                            vols., 1 pl. torn, some imprints cropped, marginal foxing, contemporary
                            half calf worn, illus. color (£1800). Christie’s Rome, 15
                            June, #495, 1796 ed., 2 vols., scattered foxing, later calf, illus.
                            color (not sold; estimate €2000-3000). EB, July, 1813 ed., 2 vols.,
                            some pls. lightly foxed, contemporary quarter calf very worn, illus.
                            color ($775). Krul Antiquarian Books, Oct. online cat., 1806 ed., 2
                            vols., some pls. browned, full calf ($7451). Antiquariaat Gert Jan
                            Bestebreurtje, Oct. online cat., 1806 ed., 2 vols., later half calf
                            ($5216). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #80-84, pls. 3, 4, 9, 11-12 only,
                            offered individually, all from the 1813 ed., illus. (from $100 to
                            $150).</p>
            <p>Stuart and Revett, <hi rend="i">Antiquities of Athens</hi>, vols. 1-3,
                            1762-94. CNY, 15 Dec. 2005, #549, worm holes in vol. 2, browning and
                            staining throughout, later half calf “broken,” illus.
                            ($6600; estimate $2000-3000). SL, 9 May, #176, a few pls. with minor
                            damage, contemporary Russia rubbed, binding illus. color (£10,200;
                            estimate £3500-5000). Donald Heald, Oct. online cat., modern
                            buckram ($17,500). Tim Bryars, Oct. online cat., with vol. 4 (1816),
                            occasional spotting, modern half calf (£15,000). SL, 16 Nov., #198,
                            1 pl. torn, contemporary Russia worn, “covers becoming
                            detached,” binding illus. color (£8400). Blake’s 4
                            pls. are in vol. 3.</p>
            <p>Varley, <hi rend="i">Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi>, 1828. CL, 15 Nov., #153,
                            pls. 2-3 in 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> sts., corner repairs on a few leaves,
                            with the “Balcarres” book label of the Earls of Crawford,
                            later half morocco, original wrappers bound in, pl. 3 illus. color
                            (£6000; estimate £2000-3000). The same copy was sold SL, 12
                            Dec. 2002, #246 (£2032 to Arthur Freeman).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Vetusta Monumenta</hi>, c. 1789. Hugh Pagan, June cat. 55,
                            #99, with the Ayloffe essay, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century boards
                            rebacked (£850).</p>
            <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">Pastorals</hi>, 1821. CL, 29 March, #57, 16 of the
                            17 wood engravings designed and executed by Blake, lacking the 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> engraving, so-called “Linnell
                            impressions” printed after publication in the 1821 book, each on
                            a separate leaf of thin wove paper, some slight staining and other minor
                            defects, in 4 frames, illus. color (£3600). John Windle, Nov. cat.
                            42, #88, Blake’s 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> wood engraving only, with
                            a copy of Essick, <hi rend="i">A Troubled Paradise</hi>, 1999, 1 of 13
                            deluxe copies, cloth box, illus. ($3500).</p>
            <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">The Wood Engravings of William Blake for
                                Thornton’s Virgil</hi>, 1977. Larkhall Fine Art, June online
                            cat., publisher’s box, prospectus laid in, from the collection of
                            Raymond Lister, illus. (£3200). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #89,
                            publisher’s box, illus. ($6500).</p>
            <p>Whitaker, <hi rend="i">The Seraph.</hi> EB, Sept., vol. 2 (with the pl.
                            after Blake’s design) only, issue “A” in <hi rend="i">BB</hi>, dated to c.
1818-28, contemporary quarter calf
                            very worn, backstrip missing, illus. color (no bids on a required
                            minimum bid of $75). John Windle, Nov. cat. 42, #91, the pl. after
                            Blake’s design only, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., from issue
                            “C” in <hi rend="i">BB</hi>, dated to c. 1825-28, illus.
                            ($125).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Wit’s Magazine</hi>, 1784. John Windle, Nov. cat. 42,
                            #92-93, pls. 4-5 (pls. 3-4 in <hi rend="i">CB</hi>) only, offered
                            individually, illus. ($400 each).</p>
            <p>Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, 1791. Phillip
                            Pirages, cat. for the Feb. Los Angeles Book Fair, #153, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> sts.
of the pls., modern calf ($5500).</p>
            <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, 1797, uncolored copies. Maggs,
                            Dec. 2005 cat. 1384, #290, with the “Explanation” leaf, a
                            few marginal tears repaired, “a very good and unusually
                            generously-margined copy in twentieth century brown half morocco with
                            brown cloth sides by Riviere &amp; Son,” top edge gilt, others
                            uncut (£5000). Gateway Galleries, Jan. online cat.,
                            “excellent margins,” with the “Explanation”
                            leaf, contemporary or near-contemporary vellum, illus. color ($18,500).
                            Bonhams &amp; Butterfields auction, San Francisco and Los Angeles, 19
                            Feb., #1056, lacking the “Explanation” leaf, “some
                            mild offsetting, . . . partially untrimmed,” modern half calf,
                            illus. color ($7170). Sims Reed, March cat. of “British
                            Illustrated Books,” #9, no mention of the
                            “Explanation” leaf (because not present?), recent half
                            morocco, illus. color (£7000). Heritage Book Shop, April cat. for
                            the New York Book Fair, p. 1 (no entry #), no mention of the
                            “Explanation” leaf, half morocco, “an exceptionally
                            nice copy” ($10,000); <pb id="p40-135" n="135"/>
same copy and
                            price, Oct. cat. 219, #32, now described as containing the
                            “Explanation” leaf, top edge gilt, others uncut, illus.
                            color. Sotheby’s Paris, 11 Oct., #64, no mention of the
                            “Explanation” leaf, no description of condition,
                            “binding by Zaehnsdorf,” illus. color (not sold; estimate
                            €6000-8000).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Interesting Blakeana</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>J. Meyer, miniature portrait of William Hayley. Oval, 5.1 cm. high,
                            datable to c. 1765 (when Hayley was 20 years old). Judy &amp; Brian
                            Harden, as advertised and illus. color in <hi rend="i">Country Life</hi>
                            (1 Dec. 2005): [32], “in the original gold locket” (not
                            priced). Jeremiah Meyer’s son, William, apparently helped Blake
                            learn miniature portraiture—see William Hayley’s letter to
                            George Romney of 21 April 1801 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 106-07).</p>
            <p>J. Basire (Blake’s engraving master), “The Encampment of
                            the English Forces near Portsmouth,” 63.0 × 190.5 cm.,
                            published 1778. CSK, 3 Oct., #261, illus. color (£1200; estimate
                            £600-800). One of the large panoramic prints engraved in
                            Basire’s shop during Blake’s apprenticeship that may have
                            influenced the format of his “Chaucers Canterbury
                            Pilgrims” (30.6 × 94.9 cm.) years later.</p>
            <p>J. and A. Taylor, <hi rend="i">City Scenes</hi>, 1818. Hobbyhorse Books,
                            Sept. cat. 48, #222, quarter roan worn ($450). Contains Blake’s
                            “Holy Thursday” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>,
                            illus. with an engraving which, although showing the children being led
                            out of the church by beadles, is not directly related to Blake’s
                            design.</p>
            <p>Old Wyldes, the house where John Linnell lived, 1824-28, then known as
                            Collins’ Farm and frequently visited by Blake (see, e.g., 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 395-96, 448; E 775, 779, 780, 785). North End,
                            Hampstead, London NW3. Listed grade II*, in excellent order, much of the
                            original timber framing of c. 1593 intact, 5 bedrooms, 3 reception
                            rooms, 3 bathrooms, kitchen/breakfast room, secure parking for several
                            cars, “large stunning gardens.” Offered by Goldschmidt
                            &amp; Howland property company, Hampstead Village office, web site
                            &lt;http://www.g-h.co.uk/&gt; accessed March, illus. color
                            (guide price £2,750,000 for the leasehold).</p>
            <p>G. Cumberland, <hi rend="i">An Essay on the Utility of Collecting the
                                Best Works of the Ancient Engravers of the Italian School</hi>,
                            1827. E. M. Lawson, Feb. cat. 316, #29, light foxing, original boards
                            with hinges repaired (£165). Cumberland records in his notebook
                            that he “Lent Blake [his] Catalogue to read” in November
                            1823 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 388).</p>
            <p>J. T. Smith, <hi rend="i">Nollekens and His Times.</hi> EB, Jan., 1829
                            ed., 2 vols., contemporary quarter calf very worn, spine missing and
                            covers loose, illus. color ($0.95); Feb., 1828 ed., 2 vols., later
                            quarter calf very worn, some covers detached, illus. color ($57). E. M.
                            Lawson, Feb. cat. 316, #30, 1828 ed., 2 vols., light foxing,
                            contemporary half calf (£125). EB, Aug., 1828 ed., 2 vols.,
                            contemporary half calf worn, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum
                            bid of £59.99). Vol. 2 contains an important early biography of
                            Blake; see <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2723.</p>
            <p>William Twopeny (or Twopenny, antiquary and barrister, 1797-1873), letter
                            of 19 Nov. 1828 to John Thomas Smith asking “Can you tell me
                            where the Widow of Blake the artist lives?” BH, 28 March, #105,
                            included as part of an extra-illus. copy of Smith’s <hi rend="i">Nollekens and
His Times</hi>, 1828, with “numerous prints,
                            drawings,” and letters from Henry Fuseli, Thomas Frognall Dibdin,
                            John Varley, Ozias Humphry, and others, “loose in bundles”
                            (£3120; estimate £300-600).</p>
            <p>A. Cunningham, <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British
                                Painters.</hi> EB, March, New York ed., 1835, 3 vols.,
                            publisher’s boards worn, illus. color (no bids on a required
                            minimum bid of $19.95); May, New York ed., 1833, 3 vols.,
                            publisher’s boards worn, illus. color (no bids on a required
                            minimum bid of $25.99); July, London ed., 1829-33, pls. foxed, later
                            half calf, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of
                            £165). Contains an important early biography of Blake.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, Pickering ed.,
                            1839 (1<hi rend="s">st</hi> letterpress ed.). Manhattan Rare Book
                            Company, April online cat. and advertisement in <hi rend="i">Rare Book
                                Review</hi> 33.2 (April/May 2006): [14], issue without “The
                            Little Vagabond,” full calf, binding illus. color ($8000). Even
                            rebound copies are becoming pricey.</p>
            <p>A. Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> Sims Reed, March
                            cat. of “British Art Reference Books,” #150, 1863 ed., 2
                            vols., extra-illus., including 26 pls. by Blake, contemporary calf
                            rebacked, publisher’s front covers bound in, illus. color
                            (£1800). The same copy offered EB, Nov. 2003 (not sold) and
                            Feb.-March 2004 (not sold)—see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.4
                            (spring 2004): 127 for a list of the added pls. The 19<hi rend="s">th</hi> Century
Shop, March cat. 110, p. 16 (no item #), 1880 ed.,
                            2 vols., publisher’s cloth and dust jackets, “we have
                            never seen or heard of another example in the original dust
                            jackets,” jackets with minor tears, illus. color ($7500—an
                            extraordinary asking price). At least 1 other copy with the dust jackets
                            has been recorded—see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 24.1 (summer 1990):
                            231.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Poems of</hi>, ed. R. H. Shepherd, published by
                            Pickering, 1874. John Hart, March cat. 14, #44, with a presentation
                            inscription from the editor to John Ruskin dated 6 Aug. 1874,
                            publisher’s cloth (£450).</p>
            <p>B. M. Pickering, <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Editors</hi>, 1874.
                            Charles Cox, Aug. cat. 53, #48, inserted in a copy of the 1874 Pickering
                            ed. of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, publisher’s later
                            blue cloth stamped “Pickering &amp; Chatto” on the spine
                            (£85). Pickering’s 4-page pamphlet criticizing the Rossetti
                            brothers’ editorial methods 
<pb id="p40-136" n="136"/> (see next
                            entry) is rare; I have seen only 2 other copies on the market in the
                            last 35 years.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, ed. W. M. Rossetti, 1874.
                            Charles Cox, Aug. cat. 53, #49, publisher’s cloth, presentation
                            inscription by Rossetti dated 1875 to “the mountaineer Charles
                            Edward Mathew” (the uncommon 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> issue, but
                            aggressively priced at £180—because of the mountaineering
                            connection?).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Hamilton Palace Libraries</hi>, the collection of William
                            Beckford, auction cats., Sotheby’s, 1882-83. Forest Books, Jan.
                            cat. 105, #21, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> through 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> parts
                            in 1 vol., contemporary quarter morocco repaired (£375). Important
                            works by Blake were sold as lots 950-57 in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
                            part and as lot 764 in the supplement to the 4<hi rend="s">th</hi>
                            part.</p>
            <p>W. Muir facsimiles of Blake’s illuminated books and prints. EB,
                            Dec. 2005, “The Ancient of Days” or “The Act of
                            Creation,” c. 1885, watercolor without a lithographic base and
                            thus without printed framing lines, leaf 30.5 × 25.0 cm. pasted
                            to a backing mat, Muir’s signature and number (if ever present)
                            trimmed off, matted close to the image, framed and glazed, illus. color
                            (£47 to Robert Essick). Book Alley, Jan. private offer, <hi rend="i">There is No
Natural Religion</hi> (1886) bound with <hi rend="i">On Homers Poetry [and] On Virgil</hi> (1886), modern
cloth,
                            original wrappers not retained ($1450). See comments on “The
                            Ancient of Days” in the appendix.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Rowfant Library. A Catalogue of the Printed Books, . . .
                                Drawings and Pictures, Collected by Frederick Locker-Lampson</hi>,
                            1886. Forest Books, May cat. 106, #285, with the <hi rend="i">Appendix</hi> of
1900, 2 vols., original quarter morocco rubbed
                            (£295). Important works by Blake are listed in the 1886 vol., pp.
                            138-41; the 1900 vol. lists a few engravings by Blake, p. 180.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Illustrations of Milton’s</hi> Comus, 8
                            chromolithographs by W. Griggs, published by Quaritch, 1890. BA, 20
                            July, #13, modern quarter morocco, original wrappers bound in
                            (£360). Rare, and getting expensive.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Blake His</hi> Songs of Innocence, printed by H.
                            Daniel, Oxford, 1893. William &amp; Nina Matheson, Feb. cat. 13, #31, 1
                            of 100 copies, original wrappers worn ($700).</p>
            <p>W. B. Yeats, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi>, 1893.
                            James Jaffe, July cat., #11, large-paper issue, light foxing to
                            frontispiece and title page, publisher’s quarter vellum, covers
                            “a bit dust-soiled” ($2250). A new record asking price.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Savoy</hi>, 1896. James Cummins, March cat. 95, #61, 8
                            issues in 3 vols., publisher’s boards (issues 1-2) and wrappers
                            (issues 3-8), a complete run ($3500). Sims Reed, March cat. of
                            “British Illustrated Books,” #215, 8 issues (in 3 vols.?),
                            “original boards or wrappers,” a complete run, illus.
                            color (£2000). Issues 3-5 contain W. B. Yeats’ essay,
                            “William Blake and His Illustrations to the <hi rend="i">Divine
                                Comedy</hi>” (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #3051A).</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Ausgewählte Dichtungen</hi>, translated by
                            Adolf Knoblauch, Berlin: Oesterheld &amp; Co., 1907. CNY, 28 June,
                            #680, 2 vols., “bound by the Wiener Werkstatte Bindery in tanned
                            frog skin,” cover illus. color ($7800; estimate $2000-3000). A
                            record price for a translation of Blake’s writings, although the
                            binding was the crucial factor.</p>
            <p>J. R. Smith, <hi rend="i">A Complete Catalogue of Plates Published by
                                Him. A Facsimile of the Only Copy Known</hi>, 1914. Sims Reed, March
                            cat. of “British Illustrated Books,” #399, half morocco,
                            illus. color (£425). Items 195-96 in Smith’s cat. (of c.
                            1800?) are “Industrious Cottager” and “The Idle
                            Laundress,” engraved by Blake after Morland.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the</hi> Pastorals
                                <hi rend="i">of Virgil.</hi> Platinotype enlargements by Frederick
                            H. Evans, [London], 1919. Larkhall Fine Art, Sept. private offer, signed
                            by Evans, 1 of 12 copies, from the collection of Raymond Lister,
                            original portfolio (£850).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed. Keynes, 1925.
                            Collinge &amp; Clark, summer cat. 29, #226, 3 vols. in 1, Oxford India
                            paper issue, inscribed by Francis Meynell of the Nonesuch P, “Out
                            of series, for the file of N.P.” Full morocco, spine slightly
                            darkened (£850). In the view of many, the handsomest letterpress
                            ed. of Blake ever produced.</p>
            <p>L. Binyon, manuscript of an unpublished lecture titled “William
                            Blake; Painter, Poet, Seer.” James Cummins, Nov. cat. 97, #10,
                            written out by Binyon’s wife, Cicily, and signed by Binyon.
                            Rectos only of 19 leaves, approx. 5000 words, dated by Cummins to c.
                            1932-35. Housed in a cloth slipcase, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> page illus.
                            ($2000). Formerly thought to be autographic, this manuscript has been in
                            Cummins’ stock for about a decade.</p>
            <p>L. Powys, <hi rend="i">The Book of Days</hi>, illus. by Elizabeth
                            Corsellis, Golden Cockerel P, 1937. BA, 9 June, #199, with an extra set
                            of the etched pls., publisher’s morocco, 1 pl. illus. color
                            (£238). The illus. were clearly influenced by Samuel
                            Palmer’s Shoreham period work.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Trianon P/Blake Trust facsimile of copy E,
                            1951. BA, 11 Nov., #475, “publisher’s dummy or specimen
                            copy,” 48 of 100 pls. only, publisher’s wrappers and
                            folding case, “with a companion volume to one of the Trianon
                            Press editions” (£420).</p>
            <p>L. Baskin, “Portrait of William Blake,” wood engraving,
                            1964. EB, Dec. 2005, signed by Baskin in pencil, illus. color ($224.72);
                            Jan., another impression, signed by Baskin in pencil, illus. color
                            ($152.50); Feb., another impression, signed by 
<pb id="p40-137" n="137"/>
Baskin
in pencil, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of
                            $120); Feb., same impression ($120). This portrait was published in
                            Baskin’s ed. of <hi rend="i">A Letter from William Blake</hi>,
                            1964. I have not recorded further EB sales of this print, all from the
                            same California vendor who appears to have a near-inexhaustible supply.
                            Or is the vendor buying the same impression from himself to give the
                            appearance of sales at good prices?</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Poems from William Blake’s</hi> Songs of
                            Innocence, illus. Maurice Sendak, 1967. Jo Ann Reisler, Jan. cat. 73,
                            #450, original wrappers, illus. color ($4500).</p>
            <p>Francis Bacon (British artist, 1909-92), <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi>
                            Color lithograph, 1991, signed and numbered 178 of 180. CL, 10 Feb.,
                            #451, illus. color (£8400; estimate £1500-2500). The auction
                            cat. claims that this portrait is based on Blake’s life mask, but
                            there is only a slight similarity between the two. The cat. also quotes
                            Bacon as follows: “I do find that his [Blake’s] poetry is
                            better than his painting or drawing, which I really don’t like at
                            all. . . . I loathe his mystical side. . . . I don’t like
                            anything which comes too close to Religion.”</p>
            <p>Miniature blank book, 1.9 × 1.3 cm., probably produced 2005, the
                            cover and spine reproducing the decorations on Alexander Gilchrist, 
<hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 1880 (but lacking the vol.
                            number on the spine). EB, March, illus. color (offered only at the
                            “buy it now” price of $6).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Blake’s Circle and Followers</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Works are listed under artists’ names in the following order:
                            paintings and drawings sold in groups, single paintings and drawings,
                            letters and manuscripts, separate plates, books by (or with plates by or
                            after) the artist.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">BARRY, JAMES</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">King Lear Weeping over the Body of Cordelia.</hi> Oil,
                                102.0 × 128.0 cm., signed, exhibited at the Royal Academy in
                                1774. SL, 11 May, #3, illus. color (£982,400; estimate
                                £300,000-400,000). The basis for Barry’s
                                etching/engraving (with aquatint in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> 3
                                sts.) of 1790. Almost certainly a world-record price for a work by
                                Barry.</p>
              <p>Barry, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, 1809. Gallery at Knotty Pine auction,
                                West Swanzey, New Hampshire, 27 May, #2200, 2 vols., foxed,
                                ex-library copy in modern buckram, illus. color online ($200).</p>
              <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Collection of Prints . . . Illustrating . . .
                                    Shakspeare</hi>, c. 1803. EB, Oct., “King Lear”
                                only, Legat after Barry, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum
                                bid of $250).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">CALVERT, EDWARD</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Nine Early Engravings by Edward Calvert. Facsimiles . .
                                    . by Frederick H. Evans</hi>, 1925. Maggs, Dec. 2005 cat. 1384,
                                #293, 1 of 15 copies, “nine mounted platinotypes loose in a
                                marbled board folder” (£1200).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">FLAXMAN, JOHN</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>See also Flaxman under Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after
                                Blake, above.</p>
              <p>Two pencil drawings mounted on a single leaf, <hi rend="i">Study of
                                    the Tomb of Elizabeth Norris</hi> and <hi rend="i">Profile of a
                                    Man’s Head.</hi> The tomb study, 9.5 × 13.0 cm.,
                                inscribed “Mrs: Elizth: Norris, 1779, Finchley”; the
                                head 13.0 × 9.0 cm.; the mount inscribed “From John
                                Flaxman’s sketch book when a boy. The writing of later
                                date—the book sold to America 1920.” Dominic Winter
                                auction, Cirencester, Gloucestershire, 27 July, #153, illus. color
                                online (£360).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Angels Rescuing a Soul from the Ranks of the Dead.</hi>
                                Pen and gray ink and gray wash, 48.2 × 71.0 cm., possibly
                                dating from the mid-1790s. CL, 5 June, #6, illus. color
                                (£14,400 to Colnaghi; estimate £4000-6000). The cat. entry
                                suggests that this large, highly finished drawing may have a
                                Swedenborgian subject.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Battle Scene.</hi> Pen and ink over chalk, 14.6 ×
                                25.8 cm., with the collection stamps of the A. A. de Pass and
                                Cornwall County Museum collections. Swann, 25 Jan., #285, illus.
                                ($800). Possibly an illus. of the war in heaven from <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost.</hi></p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Dante and Virgil Encountering Francesca and Paolo.</hi>
                                Plaster relief designed by Flaxman, 65.0 × 95.0 cm.
                                Sotheby’s Devon, 24 Oct., #111, framed, minor damage, illus.
                                color (not sold; estimate £1200-1800).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Design for the Shield of Achilles.</hi> Pencil, 10.8
                                × 17.8 cm., inscribed “153.W” top right, paper
                                evenly browned. Trinity Fine Arts auction, Boston, 22 April, #1338,
                                illus. color online ($300). Previously sold Skinner auction, Boston,
                                1 Oct. 2005, #169, illus. color online ($200). This drawing is not
                                related to any section of the finished design for the shield.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Group of Young People.</hi> Pencil, 16.8 × 13.7
                                cm. W/S Fine Art, June cat., #20, illus. color (£2250).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Illustration to Homer’s</hi> Odyssey: <hi rend="i">Hermes Conducting the Souls
of the Suitors to the
                                    Infernal Region.</hi> Pencil, pen and brown ink, 21.0 ×
                                30.8 cm. CL, 16 Nov., #4, illus. color (£2640).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Illustration to Homer’s</hi> Odyssey: <hi rend="i">Odysseus Terrified by the
Ghosts.</hi> Pencil, pen and
                                brown ink, 21.0 × 30.8 cm., inscribed “N<hi rend="s">o</hi>. 17.—.” CL,
16 Nov., #3, illus. color
                                (£4200).</p>
              <pb id="p40-138" n="138"/>
              <p><hi rend="i">Jupiter Sends Agamemnon the Fatal Vision.</hi> Pen and
                                brown ink, 17.8 × 27.3 cm. EB, April, illus. color
                                (£385). Possibly a copy of Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs, pl.
6.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Mother upon Parting Surrending</hi> [sic] <hi rend="i">Her Two Children to the
Guardian Angel.</hi> Pen and brown ink,
                                18.5 × 25.2 cm., signed and titled in ink. Swann, 25 Jan.,
                                #287, illus. ($1200).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Sleeping Child.</hi> Pencil, 13.3 × 17.8 cm.,
                                inscribed 1803. W/S Fine Art, June cat., #18, illus. color
                                (£2250); another with the same title, pencil, 9.2 × 13.7
                                cm., #19, illus. color (£2250).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of Two Women Grieving.</hi> Pen and gray ink,
                                washes, 34.0 × 24.0 cm. SL, 7 June, #326, illus. color
                                (£18,000; estimate £8000-12,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Acts of Mercy</hi>, etchings with aquatint by Lewis,
                                1831. Sotheby’s Devon, 24 Oct., #283, complete set of 8,
                                illus. color (£384).</p>
              <p>Aeschylus designs, 1795. EB, Oct., later half calf very worn, illus.
                                color (£99.99). John Windle, Nov. 2005 cat. 40, #405, pls. on
                                pale blue paper, early half vellum ($3000).</p>
              <p>Dante designs, 1807. PBA, 29 June, #110, foxed, later quarter calf
                                very worn, front cover detached, illus. (not sold; estimate
                                $800-1200).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Eight Illustrations of the Lord’s Prayer</hi>,
                                1835. EB, Nov., marginal stains, “hardback cover” (no
                                bids on a required minimum bid of £150).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs. John Windle, Nov. 2005 cat. 40,
                                #407, 1793 ed., pls. on pale blue paper, contents leaf torn but
                                repaired, early half vellum ($2750). EB, Jan., 1803 ed., bound with
                                the <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> (n.d.), Aeschylus (n.d.), and Hesiod
                                designs (published by Bance in Paris, 1821), all but the last the
                                Dufresne eds. published in Paris, later quarter calf, illus. color
                                ($472.32).</p>
              <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Anatomical Studies</hi>, 1833. EB, Jan., leaves
                                water stained and spotted, original cloth with cover label, illus.
                                color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £14.99). Sims Reed,
                                March cat. of “British Illustrated Books,” #38,
                                original cloth rebacked (£350).</p>
              <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Sculpture</hi>, 1829. John Windle,
                                Nov. 2005 cat. 40, #406, later cloth ($185).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">FUSELI, HENRY</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Conversion of St. Paul.</hi> Pen and brown ink,
                                washes, 18.0 × 30.0 cm. SL, 7 June, #324, illus. color (not
                                sold; estimate £10,000-15,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Courtesan Bending Forward.</hi> Pencil, 21.1 ×
                                17.2 cm., datable to the 1790s. SL, 23 Nov., #191, illus. color
                                (£3000). Previously unrecorded.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Eriphyle.</hi> Pen and ink, black chalk, gray and black
                                washes, 17.0 × 27.0 cm., inscribed “Fusili,”
                                datable to c. 1810. EB, May, illus. color ($3730). The figure and
                                background curtain in this previously unrecorded drawing are very
                                similar to those in <hi rend="i">The Erinyes beside
                                    Eriphyle’s Corpse</hi>, a monochrome wash drawing now in
                                the Louvre (see Gert Schiff, <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich
                                    Füssli</hi> [Zurich: Verlag Berichthaus, 1973] #1807,
                                dated to 1810). The drawing recorded by Schiff shows an “IVY
                                MILL 1804” watermark; the drawing on EB shows what may be the
                                first 3 letters of the same mark. I am grateful to David Weinglass
                                for assistance on this entry.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Flora Surrounded by the Four Elements.</hi> Pencil
                                drawing in an inscribed oval, 23.8 × 18.2 cm., datable to
                                1791. Lowell Libson, Sept. cat. “Of the Moment,” #50,
                                illus. color ($34,000). The design was engraved in 1791 by Anker
                                Smith and published as the frontispiece to Part 1 (“The
                                Economy of Vegetation”) of Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The Botanic
Garden.</hi> Previously offered in
                                Libson’s May 2002 cat. of “British Master
                                Drawings,” #14, illus. color ($42,000). The drawing contains
                                left-handed hatching, typical of Fuseli’s drawings, but is
                                somewhat stiff, like a copy. David Weinglass believes that the
                                drawing is probably by Fuseli, but might be by Gideon Fairman, who
                                engraved the design for the New York 1807 ed. of <hi rend="i">The
                                    Botanic Garden.</hi></p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Male Figures and [an] Angel</hi>, attributed to Fuseli.
                                Pencil, leaf 44.0 × 58.5 cm. EB, March, light foxing, framed,
                                illus. color ($11,600). The attribution seems reasonable, although
                                far from certain. The price indicates that at least 2 bidders
                                believed that this very lightly sketched outline drawing is from
                                Fuseli’s hand.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Fuseli</hi>, attributed to George Henry
                                Harlow. Oil, 50.8 × 39.4 cm. SL, 15 Dec. 2005, #68,
                                “appears to derive from the portrait in the Paul Mellon
                                Collection (Center for British Art, Yale University),”
                                framed, with a carved inscription on the back stating that the
                                portrait was “painted from the life by George Henry Harlow in
                                May 1818 for me Robert Balmanno,” illus. color (not sold;
                                estimate £6000-8000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Lavinia de Irujo.</hi> Pencil and charcoal
                                with touches of white, 20.4 × 14.4 cm., datable to c.
                                1810-15. SNY, 25 Jan., #135, illus. color (not sold; estimate
                                $15,000-20,000).</p>
              <p>Bible, Macklin ed., 1800. EB, March, 1 pl. only, “St.
                                John’s Vision of the Seven Lights” by Thomson after
                                Fuseli, light foxing in borders, illus. color (£17); June,
                                vols. 1-7 only, contemporary calf worn, some covers stained, illus.
                                color ($4801). The single pl. after Fuseli is in vol. 6.</p>
              <pb id="p40-139" n="139"/>
              <p>Bonnycastle, <hi rend="i">Introduction to Astronomy</hi>, 1807. EB,
                                Feb., foxed, contemporary calf, illus. color (£160.20).</p>
              <p>Boothby, <hi rend="i">Sorrows Sacred to the Memory of Penelope</hi>,
                                1796. EB, July, frontispiece only, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> published
                                st. from the small-paper issue, illus. color (£18). J &amp; S
                                Wilbraham, Sept. online cat. 61, #173, some spotting, contemporary
                                calf rebacked (£150).</p>
              <p>[Boydell], <hi rend="i">The American Edition of Boydell’s
                                    Illustrations of the Dramatic Works of Shakspeare</hi>, 1852.
                                EB, June, 2 pls. after Fuseli only, “Macbeth” and
                                “The Tempest,” marginal stains on the former, sold
                                individually, illus. color ($119.17 for the first, no bids on a
                                required minimum bid of $99.95 for the second).</p>
              <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Collection of Prints . . . Illustrating . . .
                                    Shakspeare</hi>, c. 1803. Sims Reed, March cat. of
                                “British Illustrated Books,” #10, 2 vols.,
                                “some plates proofs before letters,” contemporary
                                morocco, illus. color (£12,000); #11, another copy, 2 vols. in
                                1, recent quarter morocco (£6500). EB, Oct., single pls. after
                                Fuseli, offered individually, all illus. color: “Midsummer
                                Night’s Dream,” engraved Simon, framed (no bids on a
                                required minimum bid of $499.99, and no bids when the minimum was
                                lowered to $399.99); “King Henry the Fourth,” engraved
                                Leney (no bids on a required minimum bid of $225); “King
                                Henry the Fifth,” engraved Thew (no bids on a required
                                minimum bid of $175); “King Lear,” engraved Earlom (no
                                bids on a required minimum bid of $325); Nov.-Dec., “King
                                Lear” only, engraved Earlom, marginal tears and stains,
                                illus. color ($54); “Tempest” only, engraved Simon,
                                hand colored, tears into image, stained, illus. color ($56.55).</p>
              <p>Cowper, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1808. EB, Dec. 2005, vol. 1 (of 2)
                                only, contemporary calf worn, front cover detached, illus. color
                                ($34.99).</p>
              <p>Fuseli, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting</hi>, 1820. Francis
                                Edwards, Oct. online cat., some spotting, contemporary half calf
                                rebacked, worn (£237).</p>
              <p>Gray, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, Du Roveray ed., 1801. John Windle,
                                Nov. 2005 cat. 40, #408, original boards worn ($450).</p>
              <p>Homer, <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, translated by Cowper, 1810. EB,
                                April, 2 vols., 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century quarter calf, illus.
                                color ($639).</p>
              <p>Hume, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi>, 1852. EB, pl. by Rogers
                                after Fuseli only, “The Death of Cardinal Beaufort,”
                                light stains, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of
                                £4.99).</p>
              <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi>, Dublin, 1790. EB,
                                June-July, marginal stains, contemporary calf very worn, illus.
                                color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £24.99).</p>
              <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, vol. 2, 1792. EB,
                                March, portrait of Fuseli only, engraved by Bromley after Lips,
                                illus. color (£16.75).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, 1817. John Windle, Nov. 2005
                                cat. 40, #409, extra-illus., including 6 pls. after Fuseli’s
                                designs from Du Roveray’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> of
                                1802, full morocco “a little tired” ($225).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works.</hi> EB, March, 1840 Bohn ed.,
                                some pls. with minor foxing, contemporary calf, illus. color
                                (£19); 1855 Bohn ed., three-quarter calf rubbed (offered only
                                at the “buy it now” price of $75); Aug., 1844 Chidley
                                ed., half calf, illus. color (£6.50); Oct., 1840 Churton ed.,
                                contemporary calf, illus. color (£28). The 1855 ed., with
                                Fuseli’s “Silence” engraved by Rogers, is not
                                listed in D. H. Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Prints and Engraved
                                    Illustrations by and after Henry Fuseli</hi> (Aldershot: Scolar
                                P, 1994)—but see Weinglass #284A for earlier Chidley and Bohn
                                eds. with this pl., 1836-52. The 1840 Churton ed., the 1852 Bohn
                                ed., and probably other Bohn eds. contain a plate by Rogers after
                                Fuseli, “Satan and Beelzebub,” not listed in
                                Weinglass.</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, 1805. EB, Feb.-March, vols. 5,
                                8, 9 only, sold individually, pls. stained (some badly),
                                contemporary calf very worn or disbound, illus. color (£0.99
                                each); June, vols. 3, 4, 6 only, offered individually, scattered
                                foxing, contemporary calf worn, illus. color (no bids on required
                                minimum bids of £9.99 each); same copies of vols. 3, 4, June
                                (no bids on required minimum bids of £4.99 each). See also
                                under Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake,
                                above.</p>
              <p>Sotheby, <hi rend="i">Oberon</hi>, 1805. John Hart, June cat. 16,
                                #89, 2 vols., contemporary calf slightly worn (£150).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Spectator</hi>, published by Sharpe, 1803. EB,
                                April, vol. 5 only, contemporary calf, spine worn, illus. color
                                (£7.50); June, vols. 2, 4-6, 8 only, contemporary calf very
                                worn, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $35). The
                                single pl. after Fuseli is in vol. 5.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Tatler</hi>, published by Sharpe, 1804. EB, June,
                                vols. 1, 3, 4 only, contemporary calf very worn, illus. color ($25).
                                The single pl. after Fuseli is in vol. 3.</p>
              <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the . . . Collection of . . .
                                    Angerstein</hi>, 1823. EB, Feb., 2 pls. after Fuseli only,
                                “Satan Starting from the Touch of Ithuriel’s
                                Spear” and “Birth of Eve,” offered
                                individually, illus. color (£4.99 for the former; no bids on a
                                required minimum bid of £4.99 for the latter); May, the 3 pls.
                                after Fuseli only, offered individually, illus. color (pl. 1, $14;
                                pl. 2, no bids; pl. 3, $12); June, “Birth of Eve”
                                only, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $14); July,
                                marginal foxing, quarter roan worn, illus. color (no bids on a
                                required minimum bid of £169.99).</p>
              <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Pictures . . . in the Possession . .
                                    . of Sir John Fleming Leicester</hi>, 1821. BA, 2 March, #113,
                                foxed and stained, contemporary morocco worn (not sold; estimate
                                £150-200).</p>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p40-140" n="140"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">LINNELL, JOHN</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">An Angler on a Riverbank.</hi> Watercolor, 28.0 ×
                                38.0 cm., signed. CL, 16 Nov., #95, illus. color (£10,200;
                                estimate £3000-5000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Farmer’s Boy.</hi> Oil, 62.0 × 45.5
                                cm., signed and dated 1830. Hy. Duke &amp; Son auction, Dorchester,
                                6 July, #299, illus. color online (£35,000). Previously offered
                                SL, 1 July 2004, #18, illus. color (not sold; estimate
                                £100,000-150,000); 24 Nov. 2005, #75, illus. color (not sold;
                                estimate £60,000-80,000). The basic design was developed by
                                Linnell and Samuel Palmer, the two working together on separate but
                                directly related versions.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Keg.</hi> Oil, 45.0 × 60.0 cm., signed and
                                dated 1862. SL, 7 June, #200, illus. color (£13,200).
                                Previously offered SL, 30 June 2005, #65 (not sold; estimate
                                £20,000-30,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Landscape in Snowdonia with a Tree in the
                                    Foreground.</hi> Watercolor, 23.7 × 37.4 cm., signed and
                                dated 1813. Lowell Libson, Sept. cat. “Of the Moment,”
                                #34, illus. color ($17,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Lymington Quay.</hi> Oil, 27.9 × 38.1 cm., signed
                                and dated 1826. Lowell Libson, May cat., #14, illus. color (not
                                priced). Previously offered as <hi rend="i">Isle of Wight from
                                    Lymington Quay</hi>, Martyn Gregory, autumn 1992 cat. 60, #9,
                                illus. color (£18,000), and Lowell Libson, Jan. 2004 private
                                offer (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait Miniature of John Rawkin of Reigate.</hi>
                                Watercolor on ivory, signed on the reverse of the frame, 7.5
                                × 6.2 cm. BA, 27 Oct., #187, illus. color (not sold; estimate
                                £500-700).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of a Seated Girl.</hi> Pencil and watercolor,
                                38.1 × 30.5 cm., dated to c. 1835. Abbott and Holder, June
                                online cat. 375, #38 (£1000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Mrs. Henry Stephen.</hi> Oil, 26.0 ×
                                20.0 cm., signed and dated 1830. SL, 23 Nov., #50, illus. color (not
                                sold; estimate £4000-6000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Rainbow.</hi> Oil, 14.6 × 22.0 cm., signed.
                                Doyle auction, New York, 25 Jan., #1040, illus. color ($8400;
                                estimate $3000-5000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Storm in Autumn.</hi> Oil, 91.0 × 134.0 cm.,
                                signed and dated 1856. Lyon &amp; Turnbull auction, Edinburgh, 26
                                Jan., #63, illus. color (£140,000; estimate
                                £50,000-70,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Street Children</hi> (recto); <hi rend="i">Cows</hi>
                                (verso). Pen and sepia ink, 17.8 × 10.2 cm. Abbott and
                                Holder, June online cat. 375, #39 (£450).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Trees, Kensington Gardens.</hi> Watercolor, 14.2
                                × 13.1 cm., signed. Lowell Libson, Sept. cat. “Of the
                                Moment,” #33, illus. color ($28,000). An early work, probably
                                c. 1811-14.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Whiskered Gentleman Seated Three-Quarter Face.</hi>
                                Red, black, and white chalk, 27.9 × 35.6 cm. Abbott and
                                Holder, Aug. online cat. 376, #68 (£225).</p>
              <p>“Sheep at Noon,” etching. Weston Gallery, April online
                                cat., finished st. with the imprint, illus.
                                (“Sold”).</p>
              <p>Linnell, <hi rend="i">Michael Angelo’s Frescoes in the Sistine
                                    Chapel</hi>, [1834]. J &amp; S Wilbraham, Feb. online cat. 56,
                                #203, 42 mezzotints by Linnell printed in sepia on India paper,
                                margins with light water stains, contemporary half morocco
                                (£1000).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">MORTIMER, JOHN HAMILTON</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Bardolph</hi>, after Mortimer’s etching among his
                                series of Shakespeare characters. Pen and ink, black and gray
                                washes, oval, approx. 32.0 × 15.0 cm., inscribed
                                “Designed by J. Mortimer.” EB, Jan.-Feb., framed,
                                illus. color ($128.50).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Figure Studies</hi>, attributed to Mortimer. Pen and
                                ink, leaf 21.0 × 22.0 cm. EB, Jan., illus. color (offered
                                only at the “buy it now” price of £120).
                                Previously offered EB, April-May 2005 (offered only at the
                                “buy it now” price of £280).</p>
              <p>“Beaching a Fishing Boat in a Gale,” etching, Blyth
                                after Mortimer. EB, March, full margins, illus. color (no bids on a
                                required minimum bid of $99).</p>
              <p>“The Coke and Perkin,” engraving, Williams after
                                Mortimer. EB, May, hand colored, framed, illus. color (no bids on a
                                required minimum bid of £49.99); Oct., uncolored, illus. color
                                (£32.07).</p>
              <p>“The Discovery of Prince Arthur’s Tomb by the
                                Inscription on the Leaden Cross,” engraving, Ogborne after
                                Mortimer. EB, Nov.-Dec., slight stains in margins, illus. color
                                ($41).</p>
              <p>“Dying Female Monster,” etching, Haynes after Mortimer.
                                EB, March, framed, illus. color ($64 Australian).</p>
              <p>“Fifteen Etchings Dedicated to Sir Joshua Reynolds,”
                                1778. EB, Sept., frontispiece (dedication page) only, illus. color
                                ($18.50).</p>
              <p>“The Frere and Thomas,” engraving, Hogg after Mortimer.
                                EB, Oct., illus. color (£12.50).</p>
              <p>“Miller of Trompington and Two Scholars,” engraving,
                                Sharp after Mortimer. EB, Oct., illus. color (£12.50).</p>
              <p>“Nicholas the Carpenter and Robin,” engraving, Chesham
                                after Mortimer. EB, Oct., illus. color (£28.07).</p>
              <pb id="p40-141" n="141"/>
              <p>Shakespeare character heads, etchings. EB, May,
                                “Beatrice” only, illus. color (£14.99); Aug., 5
                                heads only, each illus. color and offered individually:
                                “Edgar,” “Lear,” “Richard
                                II,” “Shylock,” and “York” (no
                                bids on a required minimum bid of £39 each).</p>
              <p>“Six Banditti with Dog,” etching, Haynes after
                                Mortimer. EB, Nov.-Dec., illus. color (£9.95).</p>
              <p>“The Sompnour[,] Devil and Old Woman,” engraving, Hogg
                                after Mortimer. EB, Oct., illus. color (£12.50).</p>
              <p>“Three Gamblers and Time,” engraving, Hogg after
                                Mortimer. EB, Oct., illus. color (£27.07).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">PALMER, SAMUEL</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Crossing the Common—Sunset.</hi> Watercolor, 18.4
                                × 40.6 cm., datable to 1848. Lowell Libson, Sept. cat.
                                “Of the Moment,” #39, illus. color ($85,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Dolbadarn Castle, Llanberis, North Wales.</hi>
                                Watercolor, 34.8 × 47.0 cm., datable to c. 1835-36. W/S Fine
                                Art, June cat., #45, illus. color (£55,000). Previously offered
                                Agnew’s, <hi rend="i">128<hi rend="s">th</hi> Annual
                                    Exhibition of English Watercolours and Drawings</hi>, March
                                2001, #93, illus. color (£75,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Goatherd.</hi> Watercolor, lightly squared in
                                pencil, 19.2 × 27.7 cm., date uncertain, but perhaps
                                1860s-70s. CL, 5 June, #58, from the collection of George Goyder,
                                illus. color (£21,600). Previously offered CL, 3 June 2004,
                                #72, illus. color (not sold; estimate £50,000-80,000).</p>
              <p>Palmer, portrait of. See <hi rend="i">Portrait of Samuel Palmer</hi>
                                under Richmond, below.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Poet.</hi> Watercolor and body color, 19.5 ×
                                42.0 cm., signed, datable to the early 1860s. SL, 7 June, #414,
                                illus. color (£45,600). Previously sold SL, 9 April 1992, #115,
                                illus. color (£33,000); previously offered SL, 29 Nov. 2001,
                                #14, illus. color (not sold; estimate £40,000-60,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Rising Moon.</hi> Pencil and watercolor with gum
                                arabic, heightened with touches of body color, 32.5 × 70.8
                                cm., signed on the artist’s label pasted to the back of the
                                original gilt-composition frame and inscribed “[Ri]sing
                                Moon,” datable to c. 1857. CL, 5 June, #57, illus. color
                                (£96,000 to John Windle acting for Robert Essick; estimate
                                £40,000-60,000). See illus. 11-12.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Sailing Vessel in a Squall off a Headland.</hi> Gray
                                wash, 9.0 × 9.8 cm., datable to c. 1821. CL, 5 June, #29,
                                from the collections of George Cumberland and George Goyder, illus.
                                color (£7800; estimate £4000-6000). Previously offered CL,
                                3 June 2004, #73, illus. color (not sold; estimate
                                £10,000-15,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Shearers.</hi> Oil and tempera on panel, 51.5
                                × 71.2 cm., datable to c. 1833-34. Richard Nathanson, April
                                private offer (price on application). One of Palmer’s finest
                                paintings still in private hands. For a color illus. and discussion,
                                see <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer 1805-1881: Vision and Landscape</hi>,
                                exhibition cat. by William Vaughan, Elizabeth E. Barker, and Colin
                                Harrison (London: British Museum P, 2005) 160-61.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A View of Modern Rome during the Carnival.</hi>
                                Watercolor, 40.6 × 57.2 cm., signed and dated 1838. Lowell
                                Libson, May cat., #5, illus. color (not priced).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">La Vocatella near Corpo di Cava in the Neighbourhood of
                                    Salerno and Naples.</hi> Watercolor, 26.8 × 37.5 cm.,
                                datable to 1838. SL, 23 Nov., #245, illus. color (not sold; estimate
                                £20,000-30,000). Previously offered Agnew’s, Feb.-March
                                2002 “Watercolours and Drawings” cat., #53, with the
                                dimensions given as 27.3 × 37.8 cm., illus. color
                                (£30,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Windmill near Pulborough, West Sussex.</hi>
                                Watercolor, 12.0 × 16.3 cm., datable to c. 1851. Lowell
                                Libson, May cat., #4, illus. color (not priced). Previously sold CL,
                                21 Nov. 2002, #31, illus. color (£6572).</p>
              <p>“The Cypress Grove,” etching. EB, Aug., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., illus. color
(£205).</p>
              <p>“The Early Ploughman,” etching. Swann, 12 Jan., #75,
                                    5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. color online ($700). EB, Feb.,
                                    5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., probably removed from P. G. Hamerton,
                                    <hi rend="i">Etching and Etchers</hi>, 1868, illus. color
                                ($610). C.G. Boerner, Feb. online cat., an unrecorded proof on heavy
                                wove paper between sts. 1 and 2, leaf 29.0 × 42.1 cm., illus.
                                (price on request). Rachel Davis Fine Arts auction, Cleveland, 17
                                June, #1458, st. not indicated but probably 5<hi rend="s">th</hi>,
                                illus. online ($720). Swann, 22 June, #83, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.
                                ($550). EB, Sept., described as “final state” but
                                probably 5<hi rend="s">th</hi>, illus. color ($499.99).</p>
              <p>“The Herdsman’s Cottage,” etching. Allinson
                                Gallery, April online cat., 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st. from the 
<hi rend="i">Portfolio</hi>, 1872, illus. ($850). EB, July, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st., illus. color (no bids on a
required
                                minimum bid of $749.99).</p>
              <p>“Moeris and Galatea,” etching. EB, April, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., full margins, illus.
color (£250).</p>
              <p>“The Morning of Life,” etching. Rachel Davis Fine Arts
                                auction, Cleveland, 17 June, #1459, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
                                margins trimmed and with some stains, illus. online ($570). EB,
                                Sept., 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. color ($651).</p>
              <p>“Opening the Fold,” etching. EB, Sept., 8<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. color
(£335).</p>
              <p>“The Sepulchre,” etching. EB, Sept.-Oct., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., illus. color
(£185).</p>
              <pb id="p40-142" n="142"/>
              <figure n="Palmer.RisingMoon.40.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="408">
                <head>11. Samuel Palmer.</head>
                <figDesc><hi rend="i">The Rising Moon.</hi> Pencil and watercolor
                                    with gum arabic, heightened with touches of body color, 32.5
                                    × 70.8 cm., signed by Palmer on a damaged label attached
                                    to the back of the original frame and inscribed “[Ri]sing
                                    Moon,” datable to c. 1857. Essick collection. Unrecorded
                                    until its offer at auction, CL, 9 June 2005, #45 (not sold;
                                    estimate £50,000-80,000). Provenance: Given by Palmer to
                                    George Richmond (according to Christie’s 2005 and 2006
                                    cats.); William Fothergill Robinson, who married
                                    Richmond’s daughter, Julia, in 1869; by descent to the
                                    vendor at CL, 5 June 2006, #57. The gilt-composition frame,
                                    damaged top left but now repaired, was probably selected by
                                    either Palmer or Richmond. Palmer referred to works of this size
                                    as his “large long” watercolors; this may be one
                                    of the earliest examples. The building on the left recalls
                                    Ightham Mote in the Shoreham Valley, while the reclining
                                    shepherd, lower right, may owe something to Colinet’s
                                    posture in Blake’s 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> Virgil wood
                                    engraving. The rocky mountains on the left show the influence of
                                    the Devonshire tors; the highest peak, oddly tilted on its axis,
                                    may also be indebted to the outcrop supporting Tintagel Castle
                                    in Cornwall. Palmer visited Devon several times, beginning in
                                    the summer of 1834, and drew views of the Tintagel promontory in
                                    1848. Although an idealized English pastoral, the design
                                    incorporates the cypress trees Palmer encountered on his
                                    extended honeymoon trip to Italy, 1837-39.<lb/>
<lb/>
 This
                                    watercolor is similar to, and possibly the basis for,
                                    Palmer’s 1857 etching of the same title (see illus. 12).
                                    A presumably related watercolor, also titled <hi rend="i">The
                                        Rising Moon</hi> and measuring 19.7 × 42.5 cm.
                                    (Palmer’s “little long” format), has been
                                    untraced since 1928; see Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Catalogue
                                        Raisonné of the Works of Samuel Palmer</hi>
                                    (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1988) #552. Palmer produced several
                                    other variants on the basic composition: <hi rend="i">The
                                        Sunset</hi>, datable to 1857 (Lister #546); <hi rend="i">Sheepfold at
Sunset</hi>, signed and dated 1871 (Lister
                                    #658); and a c. 1880 brown wash drawing illustrating Virgil, 
<hi rend="i">Eclogue II: Homeward from Labour’d
                                        Furrows</hi> (Lister #V4).<lb/>
<lb/>
 The watercolors with
                                    gum arabic and the use of body color are confined to the
                                    landscape and figures. The sky is a watercolor wash with little
                                    if any thickening agent. Palmer was evidently trying to combine
                                    the density of oils for the landscape with the translucency of
                                    watercolors for the sky. Like several other Victorian artists,
                                    Palmer has moved far from the eighteenth-century tradition of
                                    watercolor <hi rend="i">drawing</hi> to create watercolor 
<hi rend="i">painting</hi> with a wide variety of effects
                                    carefully deployed.<lb/>
<lb/>
 Why did the work reproduced here
                                    fail to sell, on an estimate of £50,000-80,000, in June
                                    2005 but achieve a hammer price of £80,000 a year later in
                                    the same auction rooms? One significant factor may be the Palmer
                                    exhibition at the British Museum and the Metropolitan Museum of
                                    Art, New York, 21 Oct. 2005 through 28 May 2006. After viewing
                                    the exhibit, several collectors changed their minds about the
                                    course of Palmer’s artistic career. The show demonstrated
                                    that the differences in quality between his famous
                                    “Shoreham” period work and the best of his later
                                    watercolors are not as great as previously surmised. This is a
                                    good example of how well-mounted scholarly exhibitions can
                                    influence the market.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p40-143" n="143"/>
              <figure n="Palmer.RisingMoon.etching.40.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="459">
                <figTranscr>Samuel Palmer</figTranscr>
                <head>12. Samuel Palmer.</head>
                <figDesc>“The Rising Moon.” Etching, 11.7 ×
                                    19.0 cm., 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st. (but lacking the inscribed
                                    “10” bottom center), datable to 1857. Essick
                                    collection. There are many differences between the recently
                                    rediscovered watercolor (illus. 11) and this print, including
                                    the substitution of the standing shepherd on the right for the 2
                                    reclining shepherds, the addition of a square tower and the
                                    reconfiguration of the background mountains upper left, the
                                    enlargement and rearrangement of the sheep and their feeding
                                    trough lower right, and the elimination of the white bird and
                                    evening star (center left and upper left in the
                                    watercolor).</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p40-144" n="144"/>
              <p>“The Skylark,” etching. BA, 27 Oct., #409, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. color
(£900).</p>
              <p>“The Sleeping Shepherd,” etching. BA, 27 Oct., #408,
                                    4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. color (£950).</p>
              <p>“The Weary Ploughman,” etching. CSK, 12 April, #16,
                                    8<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., scattered foxing, illus.
                                (£360).</p>
              <p>“The Willow,” etching. CSK, 25 Oct., #172, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. (not sold; estimate
£200-300).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Book of Favourite Modern Ballads</hi>, published Ward,
                                Lock, &amp; Tyler, n.d. EB, Feb., page with pl. 1 (wood engraving
                                by Evans after Palmer) only, color printed, illus. color
                                (£9.50).</p>
              <p>P.G. Hamerton, <hi rend="i">Examples of Modern Etching</hi>, 1876.
                                Sims Reed, March cat. of “British Illustrated Books,”
                                #44, with Palmer’s etching “The Herdsman’s
                                Cottage,” half morocco (£850).</p>
              <p>A. H. Palmer, <hi rend="i">Life and Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>,
                                1892. John Windle, Nov. 2005 cat. 40, #422, large-paper issue,
                                original cloth with “minor wear” ($975). EB, Dec.
                                2005, pl. foxed, small-paper issue, original cloth rehinged, illus.
                                color (offered only at the “buy it now” price of
                                £375). Allinson Gallery, April online cat., small-paper issue,
                                original cloth ($650). Contains Palmer’s etching, “The
                                Willow,” 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.</p>
              <p>S. Palmer, <hi rend="i">English Version of the</hi> Eclogues <hi rend="i">of Virgil</hi>,
1884. CSK, 12 April, #17, “The
                                Cypress Grove” and “The Sepulchre” only, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> sts.
(£168).</p>
              <p>S. Palmer, <hi rend="i">The Shorter Poems of John Milton</hi>, 1889.
                                Cheffins auction, Cambridge, 26 Oct., #304, small-paper issue, with
                                A. H. Palmer, <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: A Memoir</hi>, 1882, and 2
                                other works about Palmer, illus. color online (£1600). EB,
                                Oct., small-paper issue, publisher’s cloth badly stained,
                                illus. color (£142).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">RICHMOND, GEORGE</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Elijah at the Mouth of the Cave.</hi> Pen and brown ink,
                                18.8 × 14.3 cm., with a 3-line quotation from 1 Kings
                                19.12-13, inscribed 1827 on the verso. W/S Fine Art, June cat., #47,
                                illus. color (£7500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Gathering at Fulham Palace, Including John Keble,
                                    Samuel Rogers, Bishop Blomfield, Archdeacon Manning, and William
                                    Gladstone.</hi> Pen and ink, brown wash, 22.9 × 18.8 cm.,
                                characters’ names inscribed in pencil. W/S Fine Art, Nov.
                                cat., not numbered, illus. color (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Profile, red chalk, 18.5
                                × 14.3 cm., datable to c. 1825-30. CL, 16 Nov., #209, illus.
                                color (£13,200).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Self Portrait</hi> (recto), <hi rend="i">Anatomical
                                    Study</hi> (verso). Recto a profile, pen and ink with wash, 13.3
                                × 18.1 cm., datable to the 1840s. SL, 23 Nov., #253, illus.
                                color (not sold; estimate £3000-5000).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">ROMNEY, GEORGE</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Fortune Teller.</hi> Pencil, 38.0 × 55.0 cm.
                                SL, 9 March, #33, illus. color (£1080). Previously offered SL,
                                30 Nov. 2005, #110, illus. color (not sold; estimate
                                £1000-1500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">John Howard Visiting the Lazaretto.</hi> Pencil, 15.2
                                × 22.9 cm., dated to c. 1790-94. Abbott and Holder, June
                                online cat. 375, #54 (£950).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Lamentation: A Huddle of Despairing Figures</hi>,
                                probably related to John Howard visiting a lazaretto. Pen and ink,
                                10.2 × 15.2 cm., dated to c. 1790-94. Abbott and Holder,
                                Sept. online cat. 377, #77 (£875).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Emma Hamilton as Miranda, Head and
                                    Shoulders.</hi> Oil, 46.0 × 39.0 cm., datable to 1786.
                                CL, 8 June, #8, illus. color (£72,000; estimate
                                £25,000-35,000). A study for Miranda in Romney’s
                                painting of <hi rend="i">The Tempest</hi> for Boydell’s
                                Shakespeare Gallery.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of a Mother and Child.</hi> Pen and brown ink,
                                round, 13.5 cm. diameter. SL, 7 June, #317, illus. color
                                (£6960). W/S Fine Art, Nov. cat., not numbered, illus. color
                                (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Three-Quarter-Length Study of a Gentleman.</hi> Pencil
                                and brown wash, 36.5 × 26.5 cm. CL, 5 June, #32, illus. color
                                (£2760; estimate £1200-1800).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Titania Reposing with Her Indian Votaries.</hi> Oil,
                                116.8 × 148.6 cm. SL, 23 Nov., #67, illus. color
                                (£30,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Titania’s Attendants Chasing Bats.</hi> Oil,
                                119.4 × 149.9 cm. SL, 23 Nov., #68, illus. color
                                (£38,400).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">STOTHARD, THOMAS</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Book illustrations in published states are listed only for editions
                                not recorded in the standard reference works, A. C. Coxhead, 
<hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London: Bullen, 1906) and
                                Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard: The Mechanisms of
                                    Art Patronage in England circa 1800</hi> (Columbia: U of
                                Missouri P, 1988).</p>
              <p>Twelve watercolors of costumes of the Turkish nobility, each approx.
                                40.5 × 32.5 cm., datable to c. 1790. CSK, 16 May, #442,
                                individually framed, illus. color (£10,800). The subject, not
                                the artist, probably led to the high price.</p>
              <pb id="p40-145" n="145"/>
              <p>Two oil paintings, possibly based on scenes from Laurence
                                Sterne’s <hi rend="i">A Sentimental Journey</hi>, a pair of
                                ovals, each 21.0 × 27.1 cm. SL, 13 July, #14, entitled
                                “Merrymaking” and “Music,” 1 illus.
                                color (not sold; estimate £2000-3000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Cottage Door</hi> (or <hi rend="i">Domestic
                                    Happiness</hi>). Oil, 21.0 × 16.0 cm., datable to c.
                                1827. Cheffins auction, Cambridge, 26 Oct., #13, framed, illus.
                                color online (£280). The design was engraved by A. W. Warren
                                and published, with the inscribed title “Domestic
                                Happiness,” in an annual, the <hi rend="i">Pledge of
                                    Friendship</hi>, for 1828.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Design for a Book Plate</hi>, attributed to Stothard.
                                Brown wash, pen and ink, 10.2 × 7.6 cm., inscribed “T.
                                Stothard.” Halls auction, Shrewsbury, 8 Sept., #317-B, from
                                “the collection of John Flaxman,” illus. color online
                                (£30). The inscription looks suspiciously like the
                                “Spencer signatures” added to a good many small
                                drawings c. 1900. Some of these works are by Stothard, others are
                                not. It is difficult to make an attribution for such a small
                                vignette devoid of human figures.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Figure Studies</hi>, apparently a confrontation among
                                soldiers with studies of heads, attributed to Stothard. Pen and
                                brown ink, 17.0 × 23.0 cm. EB, April, illus. color (reserve
                                not met; highest bid £50). If the attribution is correct, this
                                is probably a work of the 1780s in Stothard’s loose and
                                sketchy style.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Leaving Home</hi>, an illustration to Oliver Goldsmith,
                                    <hi rend="i">The Deserted Village.</hi> Oil, 48.0 × 64.0
                                cm., exhibited at the R.A. in 1811. SL, 23 Nov., #70, illus. color
                                (not sold; estimate £3000-4000). The design was engraved by W.
                                Greatbach; this may be the illustration published in an edition of
                                1818 and described (or slightly misdescribed?) in Coxhead 118. A
                                different version of the scene was published in an edition of 1797
                                (Coxhead 118).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Man Reclining under a Tree.</hi> Watercolor, size not
                                recorded. PBA, 17 Aug., #38, bound in an extra-illus. copy of Bray,
                                    <hi rend="i">Life of Stothard</hi>, 1851, full morocco, the
                                drawing illus. in color online ($575).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Wedding.</hi> Oil, 35.0 × 64.5 cm. SL, 13
                                July, #15, illus. color (not sold; estimate £1000-1500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Young Girl Playing a Guitar.</hi> Watercolor, 7.7
                                × 6.8 cm. W/S Fine Art, Nov. cat., not numbered, illus. color
                                (price on request).</p>
              <p>“Amyntor and Theodora,” engraving by Tomkins after
                                Stothard. EB, Jan., cut close?, illus. color (offered only at the
                                “buy it now” price of £60); Feb., color printed
                                with hand coloring, margins torn, stained, scratches in the design
                                area, all in all a miserable wreck, illus. color ($41.11).</p>
              <p>“The Canterbury Pilgrimage,” a low-relief bronze plaque
                                based on Stothard’s design. EB, May, “Published Jan
                                1828 by Samuel Henning, Somers Place West New Road London.... S
                                Henning Sculpt.,” 15.0 × 39.3 cm., framed, illus.
                                color (£29.99). Not previously recorded.</p>
              <p>A domestic scene of 5 ladies, a separate plate (apparently) by James
                                Parker after Stothard, circular, approx. 20.3 cm. diameter. EB,
                                Jan., probably a proof before title or imprint but with signatures,
                                printed in reddish-brown ink on leaf 28.0 × 25.4 cm., illus.
                                color (£31). I have not been able to identify the subject of
                                this print; possibly not previously recorded.</p>
              <p>“Finding of Moses,” Robert Scott after Stothard,
                                published by Blackie &amp; Son, Glasgow, n.d. EB, Dec. 2005, illus.
                                color ($9.99). Probably a book illus.; not previously recorded.</p>
              <p>“The Gipsy Fortune-Teller” and “The Prediction
                                Fulfilled, or the Wedding-Day,” a pair, engraved by Granger
                                after Stothard, 1798. EB, Oct., offered separately, skillfully hand
                                colored, framed, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of
                                £0.99 for each); same pair, Nov., offered individually
                                (£41 and £82 respectively).</p>
              <p>“La Sortie de L’École,” Sainder after
                                Stothard. EB, Feb., illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid
                                of $29 Australian). Apparently a separate plate, not previously
                                recorded.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Cameo: A Melange of Literature and the Arts Selected
                                    from the</hi> Bijou, published Pickering, 1831. EB, Jan., foxed,
                                early (original?) calf worn, illus. color (£1.20). Not
                                previously recorded. The vol. apparently contains 1 or more of the
                                10 pls. designed by Stothard and first published in
                                Pickering’s <hi rend="i">Bijou</hi>, 1828-30.</p>
              <p>[Day], <hi rend="i">The History of Sandford and Merton</hi>,
                                published by Stockdale, 1786 (vols. 1-2), 1789 (vol. 3). EB, July, 3
                                vols., contemporary calf very worn, covers detached with 1 missing,
                                illus. color (£16.51). Two frontispieces are engraved by
                                Skelton (vol. 1, dated 1786 in the imprint) and Medland (vol. 3,
                                dated 1786) after designs by Stothard. Coxhead 178 briefly describes
                                only the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> of these and does not indicate the
                                ed. in which it was published.</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">A New Edition of Shakespeare’s
                                    Plays</hi>, published by Heath and Robinson, 1802-04. EB, Feb.,
                                1 pl. only, the full-page pl. for <hi rend="i">A Midsummer
                                    Night’s Dream</hi>, Heath after Stothard, etched proof,
                                title cut into and imprint trimmed off, a few stains, illus. color
                                (£20).</p>
              <p>Swift, <hi rend="i">Select Works of Jonathan Swift</hi>, published by
                                Hector McLean, 1823. EB, April, 5 vols., with at least 2 pls. after
                                Stothard reengraved from designs first published in the 
                                <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, 1782, contemporary morocco,
                                illus. color ($521). These reengravings have not previously been
                                recorded.</p>
              <p>Tasso, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem Delivered</hi>, 1802. EB, Jan., 2
                                vols., contemporary calf worn, illus. color (£10.50). The 2
                                pls. after Stothard, 
<pb id="p40-146" n="146"/>
								1<hi rend="s">st</hi> published in 1792, have not previously been recorded in
                                this 1802 ed.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Appendix: New Information on Blake’s
                                    Engravings</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Listed below are substantive additions or corrections to Robert N.
                            Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
                                Catalogue</hi> (1983), and Essick, <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (1991).
                            Abbreviations and citation styles follow the respective volumes, with
                            the addition of “Butlin” according to the list of
                            abbreviations at the beginning of this sales review. Newly discovered
                            impressions of previously recorded published states of Blake’s
                            engravings are listed only for the rarer separate plates.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Pp. 125-31, “Morning Amusement” and “Evening
                            Amusement,” after Watteau. For previously unrecorded impressions
                            of these companion prints, see Separate Plates and Plates in Series,
                            above.</p>
            <p>Pp. 258-60, “The Ancient of Days.” The main purpose of this
                            entry in the cat. is to demonstrate that there is no copperplate of
                            “The Ancient of Days” distinct from the one Blake used to
                            print the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi>, and that
                            the two examples of the design, then in the collections of Geoffrey
                            Keynes (now Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge) and George Goyder, long
                            thought to be original impressions from the presumed second copperplate,
                            are actually facsimiles produced by William Muir c. 1885. Their coloring
                            is modeled on the frontispiece in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy D, since
                            1859 in the British Museum. In the cat. I further claim, or at least
                            imply, that the Keynes and Goyder works are lithographs, extensively
                            hand colored. A careful examination of another example of the Muir
                            facsimile, sold on EB in Dec. 2005 and now in my collection, prompts me
                            to revise that claim. The recently acquired Muir was executed completely
                            by hand, as a watercolor drawing, without any lithographic base. A
                            reexamination of color reproductions of the Keynes and Goyder works
                            leads me to conclude that they were also executed completely by hand by
                            Muir. These three examples vary considerably among themselves, including
                            differences in portions of the image that are printed in Blake’s
                            original impressions. In the latter, these printed passages are close to
                            identical, except for slight inking variations. Further, these three
                            Muir facsimiles vary—in their supposedly printed but actually
                            hand drawn passages—from the printed image in original
                            impressions, from the lithograph of the frontispiece Muir included in
                            his 1887 facsimile of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, and from a version of
                            Muir’s “The Ancient of Days” in my collection
                            printed in golden-yellow ink from the same lithographic matrix as
                            Muir’s <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> facsimile but colored like the
                            completely hand-drawn examples. This last print, like those in
                            Muir’s <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, includes printed framing lines
                            about 6 mm. outside the image. I suspect that all the Muir facsimiles of
                            “The Ancient of Days” with framing lines have a
                            lithographic base, while those lacking the framing lines were executed
                            completely by hand. In all completely hand-executed examples I have
                            seen, the figure’s windblown beard does not extend beyond the
                            left side of the circle surrounding him. In copies with a lithographic
                            base, the beard is much longer and extends beyond the circle, as in
                            Blake’s originals and Muir’s <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                            facsimile. Both the Keynes and Goyder works are of the short-beard type
                            and lack framing lines.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">William Blake’s Commercial Book
                                    Illustrations</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>P. 75, The <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>, 1797, only plate by Blake,
                            “the late M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Wright of Derby.” In
                            William Bemrose, <hi rend="i">The Life and Works of Joseph Wright,
                                A.R.A., Commonly Called “Wright of Derby”</hi>
                            (London: Bemrose &amp; Sons, 1885) 106, the author states that
                            “amongst the effects of the late Mr. Geo. Cumberland, who was an
                            intimate friend of Blake’s, was found an etching, evidently the
                            one that served Blake as his copy [in the <hi rend="i">Monthly
                                Magazine</hi>], on which is written, ‘Wright, of Derby;
                            etched by himself.’ This is the only instance known of Wright
                            having used the etching point.” This self-portrait etching,
                            rather crude in its execution, is reproduced on the same page, lacking
                            the “written” inscription but with the letterpress caption
                            “Joseph Wright. Etched by himself.” Although the
                            attribution of the etching to Wright might be questioned, it seems very
                            probable that Bemrose is right about the etching in Cumberland’s
                            possession being the basis for Blake’s etching/engraving in the
                                <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine.</hi> I have not been able to locate
                            Cumberland’s print, or any other impression of the etched
                            portrait. I am grateful to Martin Butlin for pointing out this reference
                            to me.</p>
            <p>P. 77, Allen, <hi rend="i">A New and Improved Roman History</hi>, 1798,
                            pl. 1, “Mars and Rhea Silvia.” A proof, now in the RNE
                            collection, has Blake’s signature but lacks the title inscription
                            below the image and “P. 2.” top right. The proof is
                            trimmed 1.1 cm. below the lower edge of the image, thereby including the
                            position of the title but not the imprint.</p>
            <p>Pp. 117-18, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Hollis</hi>, 1780. David Wilson has
                            found that impressions of the bust of John Milton, engraved by J. B.
                            Cipriani and given by Hollis to the Society of Antiquaries in 1762 and
                            to Christ’s College, Cambridge, in 1765, are identical to
                            impressions published in the <hi rend="i">Memoirs.</hi> Thus, there is
                            no possibility that “Cipriani’s plate . . . was reworked
                            in Basire’s shop . . .” (117). See Wilson, “An Idle
                            Speculation by Samuel Palmer: William Blake’s Involvement in
                            Cipriani’s Portrait of John Milton,” <hi rend="i">British
                                Art Journal</hi> 6.1 (spring/summer 2005): 31-36.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
