<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>40.4.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Marsha Keith Schuchard, Why Mrs Blake Cried: William Blake and the Sexual Basis
of Spiritual Vision</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">40.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>J.B. Mertz</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <body>
      <pb id="p40-150" n="150"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEW</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Marsha Keith Schuchard. <hi rend="i">Why Mrs Blake Cried: William
                                Blake and the Sexual Basis of Spiritual Vision.</hi> London:
                            Century-Random House, 2006. xv + 448 pp., 54 illus. £18.99,
                            hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>,
                        Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Marsha Keith Schuchard’s <hi rend="i">Why Mrs Blake Cried: William
                            Blake and the Sexual Basis of Spiritual Vision</hi> is a book which will
                        be eagerly read and widely cited. It has many features which will attract a
                        popular readership—sex, drugs, magic, secret societies, conspiracy,
                        and sensational discoveries. It had instant éclat from before the day
                        of publication. While it was still in page proof, the editors of Michael
                        Bedard’s biography of Blake, then also in page proof, telephoned him
                        in agitation because his book did not record the “sexual
                        shenanigans” (53) detailed in <hi rend="i">Why Mrs Blake Cried.</hi>
                        It is therefore important to evaluate it carefully.</p>
          <p>This is a genuinely learned book, with quotations from works in English,
                        Danish, French, German, Hebrew, Italian, Latin, and Swedish. Research for it
                        has been remarkably diligent, with genuine discoveries in far-flung and
                        unfamiliar collections, such as manuscripts in the Academy of the New Church
                        (Bryn Athyn, Pennsylvania), Alnwick Castle, Grand [Masonic] Lodge Library
                        (London), Riksarkiv (Stockholm), Stiftsbibliothek (Linköping), and
                        Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine (London). Schuchard has
                        enviable gifts, flair, and energy.</p>
          <p>It is impressively wide-ranging, letting Observation with extensive View
                        Survey Phalli from China to Peru, or at least from London to Paris, Rome,
                        Lithuania, Saxony, West Africa, India, and Tartary. It is lavishly endnoted
                        (345-406), though often the relationship of note to text is obscure, indeed
                        invisible to me.</p>
          <p>It is extraordinarily eclectic, with much from animal magnetism, the Electric
                        Celestial Bed, Kabbala, Masons, Moravians, “Perpetual Virile
                        Potency” (chapter 18), Tantra, the Temple of Hymen, Yoga, and Yogic
                        Yonis (chapter 22).</p>
          <p>Because the subject matter is unfamiliar, a good deal of background is
                        presented. There are long desert wastes of text where Blake is not even
                        mentioned (in my reading and according to the index), except for casual
                        references like “as we will see”; for instance, chapters 5-9
                        (59-121), on “Swedenborg and Kabbalistic Science,”
                        “Erotic Dreams and Ecstatic Visions,” “Sacramental
                        Sexuality,” “Judaised Yoga,” and “Phallic Feet
                        and Tantric Toes,” are almost entirely Blake-free. This seems odd in
                        a book ostensibly about Blake.</p>
          <p>The principal thesis is that when Blake proposed to introduce a concubine
                        into his household, with exotic and sensational sexual rituals, “Mrs
                        Blake Cried.” Schuchard even proposes a candidate as concubine:
                        “Was Elizabeth Butts [the wife of his patron] the proposed second
                        wife who sent Catherine Blake into floods of tears?” (261). These
                        floods of tears created marital disharmony, episodes of which are narrated
                        with surprising precision, supported chiefly by reading Blake’s poems
                        as if they were autobiographical. “Catherine Blake often seemed
                        baffled and frightened by her husband’s sexual demands . . .”
                        (257).</p>
          <p>The primary problem of the book is that the biographical evidence for
                        Catherine Blake’s tears is extraordinarily slight. In <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> (2nd ed.), the only reference to Catherine in tears
                        is in the account of Blake’s deathbed given by Cunningham (1830)
                        §48. There are no “floods of tears” at all, and she
                        neither “weeps” nor “wept.” The first reference
                        to a concubine in the Blake household appeared more than forty years after
                        Blake’s death when Swinburne, who was not born until ten years after
                        Blake died, wrote (1868) that Blake “propose[d] to add a second
                        wife,” which elicited “tears” from Catherine, and Ellis
                        and Yeats (1893) took this up: “Blake wished to add a concubine to
                        his establishment . . . but gave up the project when it made Mrs Blake
                        cry” (Schuchard 3). This is a remarkably frail foundation on which to
                        erect such a mighty superstructure.</p>
          <p>There are a number of real discoveries here. Schuchard establishes an
                        important alchemical connection with the discovery of the “collection
                        of alchemical books” of Blake’s friend John Augustus Tulk in
                        Linköping, Sweden (401n5) which make it plain that Tulk “was a
                        practising alchemist. . . . John and Nancy Flaxman collaborated with him.
                        When Nancy Flaxman gave a talk, ‘On the Summary of Alchemy’,
                        to their Attic Chest Club, she was not just theorising” (316).
                        Schuchard quotes (328) a Moravian hymn by Count Zinzendorf called “Te
                        Matrem” printed in 1754: 
						<q> Thou didst inspire the Martyrs
                            tongues,<lb/>
 In the last gasp to raise their songs.<lb/>
 Thou dost
                            impel the four Zoa,<lb/>
 Who singing rest not night nor day. </q></p>
          <p>But many of her claims are unproved or implausible. She cites the practices
                        of the Hasidim of Vilna (Lithuania) as if relevant to the Fetter Lane
                        Moravians and Blake (49). She thinks that Blake’s fellow-apprentice
                        and partner “James Parker . . . may have come from a Moravian family,
                        for several Parkers are listed as members of the Congregation from 1745 to
                        1752” (161), though Parker is probably an even more common name than
                        Blake. She speaks of Blake’s “experiments in Animal
                        Magnetism” which “were probably connected” with his
                        “recurrent bouts of mania, depression and paranoia” (261).
                        “Blake . . . read Edward Moor’s <hi rend="i">The Hindu
                            Pantheon</hi> (1810)” (305), and a copy of <hi rend="i">A
                            Collection of Hymns: Consisting</hi>
	<pb id="p40-151" n="151"/>
	<hi rend="i">Chiefly of Translations from the German Hymnbook of the
                            Moravian Brethren</hi> (London: James Hutton, Bookseller in Fetter Lane,
                        1749) was “apparently owned by Catherine Armitage” (351n18),
                        merely because she quotes the hymn. The evidence for all this is very
                        slight.</p>
          <p>There is proliferating “evidence” in <hi rend="i">Why Mrs Blake
                            Cried</hi> of influence by association—Blake’s friend
                        Richard Cosway was a sexual free-thinker, John Augustus Tulk was an
                        alchemist, George Cumberland met Cagliostro.</p>
          <p>Among the welter of scholarship in <hi rend="i">Why Mrs Blake Cried</hi>,
                        learned footnotes, and references to arcane archives, there are just two
                        previously unrecorded pieces of evidence related to William Blake and his
                        family. All the rest is context—very frequently a context in which
                        Blake’s role is invisible or incredible.</p>
          <p>The two new pieces of evidence, complete with scholarly apparatus, are (1)
                        Blake’s mother was still active in the Moravian congregation in 1753,
                        when the Moravian Brother West “was instructed to speak to
                        ‘Sis. Arm.’ about some financial matter” (126) and (2)
                        Blake was shown the priapic sculptures in Charles Townley’s
                        collection.</p>
          <p>The Moravian reference is surprising for several reasons. First, it occurs
                        two years after the death of Thomas Armitage in 1751, when, according to the
                        Moravian records, Catherine Armitage “Became a Widow &amp; left the
                            Congregation.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">1</ref> Second, it
                        refers to her as “Sis. Arm.”, though no previous known record
                        of her in the Moravian archives abbreviates her name thus. Third, it refers
                        to her by the name of her first husband, though she had married James Blake
                        in 1752. <note id="n48">1. Moravian Church Archives: Church Catalogue
                            C/36/51/1, 36.</note></p>
          <p>In fact, the Moravian reference is not to Blake’s mother at all. What
                        it says is: “Bro. West will care that Sis. Orm is spoken to to know
                        her Resolution abt. Lending Bro. Rob the money he wants.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">2</ref> Sister Orm was a member of the Fetter
                        Lane Moravian Church at the time; Sister Blake (formerly Armitage) probably
                        was not. <note id="n49">2. Moravian Archives: Helpers Conference Minutes
                            (C/36/11/6) for 20 May 1753, generously transcribed for me by the
                            Moravian archivist Lorraine Parsons. She tells me that Keri Davies
                            agrees with her that the name is “Orm”, not
                            “Arm.”</note></p>
          <p>The other new biographical fact about William Blake is that “the
                        Priapic collectors [Sir William] Hamilton, [Charles] Townley and [Richard
                        Payne] Knight discreetly displayed their Indian [priapic] <hi rend="i">objets
d’art</hi> to friends—including Blake, Cumberland,
                        Flaxman, Hayley and [General Charles] Rainsford” (295). The evidence
                        given for this statement is “British Museum, Townley Papers: MSS. TY
                        7/1802, 1803, 1985; TY 8/59” (396-97n7), with no indication of what
                        the manuscripts represent.</p>
          <p>This was so precise that I drafted a note incorporating the priapic
                        information to be added to the <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (2nd ed.)
                        addenda. In the meanwhile I obtained reproductions of these Townley papers.
                        They consist of: <list type="ordered">
	<item><p>(1) a letter from S.[?] Stevenson to Roger Wilberforce, 8 Feb.
                                    (no year) asking if “My Friend Hayley” might see
                                    books on statues “in Townley’s Collection”
                                    (TY 7/1802);</p></item>
	<item><p>(2) a letter from W. Hayley to “Dear Sir”
                                    (?Townley), 31 May 1794, asking permission to borrow books on
                                    statues via “our Friend Stevenson” (TY
                                    7/1803);</p></item>
	<item><p>(3) a letter from Charles Rainsford to “— Townley
                                        Esq<hi rend="s">r</hi>.,” 5 July 1798, thanking him
                                    briefly “for a beautiful Print of your
                                    Sarcophagus” and chatting at length about military and
                                    naval matters (TY 7/1985); and</p></item>
	<item><p>(4) a receipt from J. Flaxman to Mr. Townley, 3 Oct. 1785, for 18
                                    medals (one of them representing George II and his queen) at
                                    £2.10.0. (TY 8/59).</p></item>
</list></p>
          <p>There is no reference of any kind in these mss. to Sir William Hamilton,
                        Richard Payne Knight, William Blake, George Cumberland, or priapic
                        “Indian <hi rend="i">objets d’art.</hi>” This kind of
                        discontinuity between evidence and argument is common in the sections of 
<hi rend="i">Why Mrs Blake Cried</hi> relating to William Blake.</p>
          <p>All serious readers of Blake will wish to read <hi rend="i">Why Mrs Blake
                            Cried.</hi> If they pay close attention to the evidence, they will come
                        away enlightened, puzzled, and frustrated.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
