<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>41.1.whitehead</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Visions of Blake, the Artist”: An Early Reference to William Blake in the
Times</title>
        <author n="Whitehead">Angus Whitehead</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">41.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Magnus Ankarsjö</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <body>
	<pb id="p41-46" n="46"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-1-0008">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Visions of Blake, the Artist”: An Early Reference to William Blake in the
<hi rend="i">Times</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Angus <name>Whitehead</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>John Clark Strange, the nineteenth-century collector and prospective biographer of William Blake,
recorded in his manuscript journal that on 6 April 1859, following a conversation with Samuel Palmer’s
brother William at the British Museum, he “pursued inquiries abt Blake in various books in the Library and
made extracts therefrom viz. Stothards Life—Songs of Innocence &amp; Experience by Blake—B’s
illustrations to Dante—Hayleys Life—Times Newspaper.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n60" type="note">1</ref> In an annotation
<pb id="p41-47" n="47"/>
to this journal entry G. E. Bentley, Jr., observes that “no account of Blake in <hi rend="i">The Times</hi>
is known before 1901.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">2</ref> In fact an
account of William Blake had appeared in this newspaper 70 years earlier. On Wednesday 27 January 1830 the 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> printed an extract from Allan Cunningham’s “Life of Blake,” recently published in
the second volume of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and
Architects</hi> (1830).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">3</ref> In this
extract, which the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> titled “Visions of Blake, the Artist,” Cunningham describes
Blake’s drawing of the Visionary Heads of William Wallace and Edward I:
<q>
Visions of Blake, the Artist.—He was requested to draw the likeness of Sir William Wallace—the eye of
Blake sparkled, for he admired heroes. “William Wallace!” he exclaimed, “I see him now—there, there,
how noble he looks—reach me my things!” Having drawn for some time, with the same care of hand and
steadiness of eye as if a living sitter had been before him, Blake stopped suddenly, and said, “I cannot
finish him—Edward the First has stepped in between him and me.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n63" type="note">4</ref></q>
The article ends: “<hi rend="i">Family Library: Lives of the Artists.</hi>” Perhaps the 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi>’ excerpt from Cunningham’s biography was the account of William Blake that Strange
encountered “and made extracts therefrom” at the British Museum in April 1859. <note id="n60">1. G. E.
Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2004) [hereafter
referred to as <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)] 717.</note>
	<note id="n61">2. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 717fn.</note>
	<note id="n62">3. <hi rend="i">Times</hi> Wednesday 27 January 1830, page 3, column E. This reference was
discovered with the assistance of <hi rend="i">Palmer’s Full Text Online</hi>
&lt;http://historyonline.chadwyck.co.uk/info/pfto.htm&gt;, which contains a reference to “‘Blake, the
Artist, His Visionary Portraits’ 27? 1830 (page 3 col. e) [full date/reference not supplied].” The article
was traced to the 27 January 1830 edition of the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> using a microfilm of the newspaper
for that year. The passage is exactly the same as that printed in the first edition of Cunningham’s 
<hi rend="i">The Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi>, 6 vols. (London: John
Murray, 1829-33) 2: 140-79, except for three minor details: the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> prints “stopped”
instead of Cunningham’s “stopt”, “stepped” instead of “stept”, and places a comma and dash after
“The answer was” instead of a colon. Cunningham’s life of Blake (2nd ed.) is reprinted in 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 628-60.</note>
	<note id="n63">
                            4. The excerpt in the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> continues:
                            <p>“That’s lucky,” said his friend, “for I want the portrait of Edward
too.” Blake took another sheet of paper, and sketched the features of Plantagenet; upon which his majesty
politely vanished, and the artist finished the head of Wallace. “And pray, Sir,” said a gentleman who
heard Blake’s friend tell his story—“was Sir William Wallace an heroic-looking man? And what sort of
personage was Edward?” The answer was,—“There they are, Sir, both framed and hanging on the wall behind
you, judge for yourself.” “I looked (says my informant) and saw two warlike heads of the size of common
life. That of Wallace was noble and heroic,—that of Edward stern and bloody. The first had the front of a
god, the latter the aspect of a demon.”</p>
	<p>Blake’s companion was almost certainly John Varley, for whom Blake drew numerous Visionary Heads (c.
1819-25) (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 346-69 and pl. 54).</p></note></p>
          <p>Bentley observes that Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> “had an extraordinarily powerful
effect in bringing the poet-artist’s name before the public”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n64" type="note">5</ref> and “provoked a spate of comment upon Blake ....”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">6</ref>
          <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> cites six reviews published during February and early March 1830
which featured discussion of Blake and excerpts from Cunningham’s life of Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">7</ref> The extract from Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>
published in the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> in January 1830, ten days before the <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> and
the <hi rend="i">London Literary Gazette</hi> reviews of the same work, must have introduced the name of
“Blake, the artist” to an even wider audience. <note id="n64">5. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 504.</note>
	<note id="n65">6. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 503.</note>
	<note id="n66">7. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 503-10.</note></p>
          <p>The article may also have assisted Blake’s widow, Catherine Blake. The first edition of
Cunningham’s “Life of Blake” concludes:
<q>
The affection and fortitude of this woman [Catherine Blake] entitle her to much respect. She shared her
husband’s lot without a murmur, set her heart solely upon his fame, and soothed him in those hours of
misgiving and despondency which are not unknown to the strongest intellects. She still lives to lament the
loss of Blake—and <hi rend="i">feel</hi> it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n67">8. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 657.</note></q></p>
          <p>By January 1830, Catherine lived independently in lodgings (according to George Cumberland, “at
a Bakers”) at either 17 Upper Charlton Street, 17 Charlton Street, or 17 Upper Charlotte Street, Fitzroy
Square.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">9</ref> Catherine’s move from
Frederick Tatham’s residence to this address approximately nine months earlier may have been facilitated by
a small legacy from her brother-in-law and former landlord at 3 Fountain Court, Henry Banes.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">10</ref> G. E. Bentley, Jr., suggests that Catherine
Blake’s sale of Blake’s large watercolor drawing of “The Characters of Spenser’s <hi rend="i">Faerie
Queene</hi>” to his former patron George O’Brien Wyndham, third Earl Egremont, in late July 1829 “is
likely to have kept Catherine out of want for the rest of her life.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n70" type="note">11</ref> However, on 25 February 1830 the collector Haviland Burke showed John
Linnell a letter from Rev. Dr. John Jebb, Bishop of Limerick “enquiring | how he c.<hi rend="s">d</hi> best
serve M.<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Blake.” Linnell advised Burke “to recommend to the B—[ishop] | to purchase
the works of M<hi rend="s">r</hi> B— | from M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> B.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">12</ref> Catherine’s sale of her stock of her late husband’s
works therefore continued after July 1829, ensuring that she could continue to live independently. The 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi>’ excerpt from Cunningham’s “Life of Blake” of January 1830 must have served to
advertise extensively <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi>
and make known to a wider audience the life and work of William Blake. It may also have been indirectly
responsible for drawing wider attention to the plight of Blake’s widow and therefore for an increased number
of inquiries from potential buyers regarding Catherine Blake’s remaining stock of her husband’s paintings,
drawings and engravings. <note id="n68">9. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 754, 498, 546, 495.</note>
	<note id="n69">10. See Angus Whitehead, “‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of my wearing apparel’: The
Will of Henry Banes, Landlord of 3 Fountain Court, Strand, the Last Residence of William and Catherine
Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 78-99.</note>
	<note id="n70">11. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 499.</note>
	<note id="n71">12. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 509. In a paper currently in preparation, I will explore Catherine
Blake’s marketing (as well as finishing and reprinting) of her late husband’s works still in her
possession, March 1829-October 1831.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
