<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>41.1.davies</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake in the Times Digital Archive</title>
        <author n="Davies">Keri Davies</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">41.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Magnus Ankarsjö</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <body>
	<pb id="p41-45" n="45"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake in the <hi rend="i">Times Digital Archive</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Keri <name>Davies</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>According to G. E. Bentley, Jr., relying, one presumes, on the printed volumes of Palmer’s 
<hi rend="i">Index to the Times</hi>, “no account of Blake in <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> [London] is known
before 1901.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">1</ref> However, since late
2003, the online <hi rend="i">Times Digital Archive, 1785-1985</hi> has not only incorporated every page of
every issue of the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> newspaper from 1785 to 1985, but has made available the means to
search its full text.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">2</ref> The 
<hi rend="i">Times Digital Archive</hi> uses character recognition software to read a sequence of digitized images
of the actual pages of the newspaper (including graphics and pictures). <note id="n50">1. G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2004) 717fn. Palmer’s 
<hi rend="i">Index</hi> is now conveniently available as <hi rend="i">Palmer’s Index to the Times, 1790-1905, on
CD-ROM</hi>, 2nd ed. (Cambridge: Chadwyck-Healey, 1995) or as an online resource
&lt;http://historynews.chadwyck.com&gt;.</note>
	<note id="n51">2. For further information, go to &lt;http://www.galegroup.com/Times/index.htm&gt;.</note></p>
          <p>For the first time, users of the <hi rend="i">Times Digital Archive</hi> are able to search not
just for home and international news, but can scan City pages, court pages, law reports, letters to the
editor, book and theatre reviews, display and classified advertising, obituaries, and much material ignored by
Palmer’s <hi rend="i">Index.</hi> (There is one small caveat. As users of similar online sources such as 
<hi rend="i">EEBO</hi> and <hi rend="i">ECCO</hi> will be aware, the search software does generate a small
percentage of misreadings and failed readings.)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n52">3. <hi rend="i">EEBO: Early English Books Online</hi> &lt;http://eebo.chadwyck.com&gt;; 
<hi rend="i">ECCO: Eighteenth Century Collections Online</hi>
&lt;http://www.gale.com/EighteenthCentury&gt;.</note></p>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Times Digital Archive</hi> makes newly possible an extensive search for
references to William Blake (and his friends and acquaintances), whether these references appear in news
items, advertisements, book reviews, or in any other apparently irrelevant pages of the newspaper. I leave it
to others to explore all 56,317 references to “blake” in the full <hi rend="i">Archive</hi>, but by
restricting one’s search by date (for example, to the years before the publication of Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> in 1863), and by utilizing Boolean combinations of keywords such as
“blake AND engraver,” it becomes possible to reduce the number of references to be checked to manageable
proportions.</p>
          <p>It was, in fact, use of the search string “blake the engraver” that led me to a 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> article that showed early knowledge of Blake’s spiritualist drawings—the Visionary
Heads—and that, remarkably for the time, rejected the view that these were evidence of Blake’s
madness.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">4</ref> The <hi rend="i">Times</hi>
for 3 January 1829, I found, included a lengthy review, spread over two columns, of “<hi rend="i">LODGE’S
PORTRAITS AND MEMOIRS.</hi> | FURTHER NOTICE.”, of no obvious connection to Blake, but incorporating a Blake
reference that a twenty-first-century researcher could only have located with the aid of the 
<hi rend="i">Times Digital Archive.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n53">4. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William
Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2001): “After 1820, most accounts of Blake refer to his
Visionary Heads either as evidence of his madness or as something to be explained away” (379).</note>
	<note id="n54">5. <hi rend="i">Times</hi> 3 January 1829 (issue 13793): 4, col. A.</note></p>
          <p>Edmund Lodge (1756-1839), Clarenceux King of Arms, began issuing his <hi rend="i">Portraits of
Illustrious Personages of Great Britain</hi> in 1814. It was completed in 1834 in 40 folio parts.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">6</ref> The parts already completed were reissued in
12 volumes, quarto, in 1823. The <hi rend="i">Times</hi> reviewer, however, is concerned with the “Cabinet
edition,” published by William Smith in 6 volumes, octavo, in 1828. The review opens conventionally enough:
<pb id="p41-46" n="46"/>
	<q>
This magnificent work, which has hitherto been confined, owing to its size and costliness, to the libraries of
persons of opulence, has just made its appearance in a form and at a price which place it within the reach of
the most moderate means.
</q>
The reviewer goes on to commend the value of biography:
<q>
We are desirous of knowing the particulars of the domestic lives, the personal habits, and daily customs of
men whose names are as familiar in our mouths as household words, and of whom, although they had become dust
before we drew breath, we have as distinct and individual a notion as if we had personally talked with them.
Biographical history satisfies this natural craving; separates the man from the events which he controlled or
was controlled by, and holds his character up to an exclusive consideration. The lesson which his life teaches
is then felt in its full force; it comes home to the business and bosoms of men, because every human being
perceives that the same impulses that have governed the actions of the object of his contemplation, throb in
his own heart, and influence his own conduct; and he learns, by a practical example, whether their issues are
of good or of evil.
</q>
He adds:
<q>
Closely associated with the desire of knowing the exclusive history of such personages, is the wish to be
acquainted with their external appearance, and the fashion of the human form they wore. Nothing is more
natural than to covet the power of calling them up<lb/>
“In their shapes and state majestical,<lb/>
“That we may wonder at their excellence,”<lb/>
and verify or correct the images which fancy has formed by the true copy which the art that confers
immortality has preserved of them.
</q>
The quotation is from Christopher Marlowe, <hi rend="i">Doctor Faustus</hi>, act 4, scene 2, in which Faustus
and Mephistophilis conjure up the shade of Alexander the Great for the German emperor. <note id="n55">6. Lucy
Peltz, “Lodge, Edmund (1756-1839),” <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi> (Oxford:
Oxford University Press, 2004).</note></p>
          <p>We then get the following comment on Blake:
<q>
The late Mr. Blake, the engraver, whose genius was subject to a kind of morbid excitement, was so possessed
with this notion, that he had contracted a belief that he could, almost at will, bring before his actual
physical eyesight the forms of the great men of this and other countries, whose existence he could only know
by means of history. Under this delusion, which, however, was of no kin to madness, and could not have
happened to any but a person of exalted imagination, he had frequent interviews with his distinguished buried
acquaintance, and used to relate his imaginary conversations with them in perfect conviction of their truth
and reality.
</q></p>
          <p>This review appeared during the editorship of Thomas Barnes (1785-1841), whose view was that
anonymous journalism, subordinating the personality of the journalist, “was the only kind that would be read
seriously.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">7</ref> The anonymous reviewer
(and, of course one would still like to know his identity) gives us a much more sober account than Dibdin’s
nonsense about Blake “shaking hands with Homer.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">8</ref> The <hi rend="i">Times</hi> persisted with anonymous reporting as late as January 1967,
when the first staff bylines appeared. In this review, it is the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> that, corporately, is
expressing a view of Blake that is surprisingly friendly and well disposed. It is assumed that the 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> readership will know, at least vaguely, of “Mr. Blake, the engraver,” and perhaps of
the imputation of madness, which is then denied, admitting no more than that his “genius was subject to a
kind of morbid excitement.” By way of comparison, the search string “keats the poet” calls up a death
notice in 1821, but nothing equivalent to the Blake comment until a concert review in 1868.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">9</ref> What the article thus suggests is that Blake
was part of what the average reader of the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> was expected to know about without
explanation, that he was by no means <hi rend="i">pictor ignotus</hi>, at least for the reviewer and his
editor. Moreover, all this precedes Allan Cunningham’s account of Blake in the second volume of his 
<hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi> in 1830.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">10</ref> It raises some interesting questions about
public acquaintanceship with Blake’s work in the years immediately following his death in 1827. 
<note id="n56">7. Gordon Phillips, “Barnes, Thomas (1785-1841),” <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National
Biography</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004).</note>
	<note id="n57">8. Thomas Frognall Dibdin, <hi rend="i">The Library Companion, or, The Young Man’s Guide and
the Old Man’s Comfort in the Choice of a Library</hi>, 2 vols. (London: Printed for Harding, Triphook and
Lepard, 1824) 2: 334.</note>
	<note id="n58">
                            9. <hi rend="i">Times</hi> 23 March 1821 (issue 11201): 3, col. F “Deaths”; 5
October 1868 (issue 26247): 10, col. E “Crystal Palace Concert.”
                            <p>Sarah Jones tells me that the search string “john keats” retrieves an 1848
<hi rend="i">Times</hi> reference to Monckton Milnes’s biography of Keats. I would suggest that this further
bears out my argument; the Blake reference is both early (within a few months of his death) and is in a
casual, almost irrelevant context. Knowledge of “Blake the engraver” is part of the common currency of the
well-educated <hi rend="i">Times</hi> reader.</p></note>
	<note id="n59">10. Allan Cunningham, <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and
Architects</hi>, vol. 2 (London: John Murray, 1830) 140-79.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
