<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>41.1.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">41.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Magnus Ankarsjö</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <front>
      <pb id="p41-1-2" n="1-2"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.041.01.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="334">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            Blake Books: Publications and Discoveries, 2006<lb/>
            VOLUME 41<lb/>
            NUMBER 1<lb/>
            SUMMER 2007</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-1-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="8" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
				<head>
				  <title>CONTENTS</title>
				</head>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.1.bentley">William Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of
Publications and Discoveries in 2006</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By G. E. Bentley, Jr., with the Assistance of Hikari Sato for Japanese Publications</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">4</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Review</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.1.ankarsjo">Blake Society Annual Lecture, 28 November 2006:
Patti Smith at St. James’s Church, Piccadilly</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Magnus Ankarsjö</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">44</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particulars</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.1.davies">Blake in the <hi rend="i">Times Digital
Archive</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Keri Davies</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">45</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.1.whitehead">“Visions of Blake, the Artist”: An Early
Reference to William Blake in the <hi rend="i">Times</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Angus Whitehead</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">46</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-1-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p41-3" n="3"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-1-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., is a recovering book collector but is still addicted to scholarship, at the
moment to Blake’s heavy metal and bibliomania (a confession) and Blake’s murderesses.</p>
        <p>Magnus Ankarsjö (magnus.ankarsjo@ntu.ac.uk) is a lecturer at Nottingham Trent University and
Loughborough University. He is the author of <hi rend="i">William Blake and Gender</hi> (2006) and is
currently completing the manuscript of <hi rend="i">Reconstructing Blake</hi>, on the substantial changes that
Blake studies are now undergoing in the wake of recent discoveries about Blake’s life, particularly his
Moravian family background.</p>
        <p>Keri Davies (keri.davies@ntu.ac.uk) has been for many years secretary of the Blake Society. He is
currently a research fellow in English at Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <p>Angus Whitehead (whitehead65_99@yahoo.co.uk) is a researcher based at the Centre for Eighteenth
Century Studies, University of York, and is organizer of the three-day international Blake at 250 conference
in celebration of the 250th anniversary of Blake’s birth. He is currently on the trail of Blake’s guest
and customer Mrs. Chetwynd.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-1-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Alexander S. Gourlay</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sarah.jones@rochester.edu TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX:585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Alexander S. Gourlay, Department of English, Rhode Island School of Design, 2 College Street,
Providence RI 02903-2717<lb/>
Email: agourlay@risd.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham
NG11 8NS UK<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are 60 for institutions, 30 for individuals. All
subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the US, Canada, and
Mexico require a 15 per volume postal surcharge for surface delivery, or 20 for airmail. Credit card payment
is available. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all
subscription orders and related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English,
University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for
information on issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>Manuscripts are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to
either of the editors. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope.
For electronic submissions, you may send a disk, or send your article as an attachment to an email message;
please number the pages of electronic submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are usually
acceptable.</p>
        <p>International Standard Serial Number: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, Humanities International Complete,
Arts and Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of
Art.</hi>
	<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2007 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
