<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>41.2.crosby</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Sketch on the Verso of Blake’s Self-Portrait: An Identification</title>
        <author n="Crosby">M. Crosby</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">41.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>M. Crosby</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <body>
      <pb id="p41-92" n="92"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <figure n="port.verso.1.100" rend="file" width="650" height="344">
          <head>1. <hi rend="i">Portrait of William Blake</hi>, verso pencil sketch.</head>
          <figDesc>By kind permission of Robert N. Essick.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Sketch on the Verso of Blake’s Self-Portrait: An Identification</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>M. <name>Crosby</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>ROBERT Essick has persuasively argued that a portrait of William Blake in his collection is a
self-portrait and that it may be dated to the period Blake executed a number of miniature portraits under the
guidance of his Sussex patron, William Hayley.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">1</ref> On the verso of the self-portrait is a rough pencil sketch (illus. 1). The subject of the
sketch is difficult to ascertain due to extensive soiling. In 1975, Martin Butlin suggested that the pencil
lines on the verso constitute more than one sketch.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">2</ref> In order to facilitate his reading, Essick traced over the pencil lines in black ink
(illus. 2), revealing, as he states,
<q>
a single composition, not multiple “sketches.” On the left are buildings, or a single structure with
several bays including an arched entry. From this cluster stretches a colonnade, gradually diminished in size
to show its extension into the distance on the right. . . On the far right are two standing figures, rigidly
composed of simple verticals and a few lines to indicate heads and arms.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">3</ref></q>
	<note id="n27">1. Robert N. Essick, “A (Self?) Portrait of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.3
(winter 2005-06): 126-39.</note>
	<note id="n28">2. Martin Butlin, “A New Portrait of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 7.2
(1975): 101-03.</note>
	<note id="n29">3. Essick 132.</note></p>
          <p>Essick suggests that the sketch is by Blake while Butlin intimates that it may have been drawn by
either John Varley or John Linnell. Butlin was the first to attempt an identification of the pencil lines,
suggesting that there are parallels in “the [Smaller] Blake-Varley sketchbook.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">4</ref> Butlin uses this rather imprecise identification to support
his main contention that the portrait was executed c. 1819-25 by Linnell, but, as Essick points out, Butlin
does not identify a particular drawing or drawings in the Blake-Varley sketchbook. Essick offers a tentative
identification, suggesting a lightly drawn sketch on page 40 of the sketchbook, which depicts an arched
doorway and castellated walls. Essick also suggests that the sketch shares similar motifs with the Job
illustrations of 1805-06, but does not claim to find an exact parallel or offer a precise identification of
the subject.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">5</ref> There are two drawings
by the miniature painter George Engleheart that appear to offer a more likely identification of the sketch
than those hitherto mentioned. <note id="n30">4. Butlin, “New Portrait” 102.</note>
	<note id="n31">5. Essick 133-34. Also see Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Blake-Varley Sketchbook of 1819</hi>, 2
vols. (London: Heinemann, 1969).</note></p>
          <pb id="p41-93" n="93"/>
          <figure n="port.verso.2.100" rend="file" width="650" height="391">
            <head>2. <hi rend="i">Portrait of William Blake</hi>, verso pencil sketch with lines traced in
ink.</head>
            <figDesc>By kind permission of Robert N. Essick.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="Engleheart.TurretHouse.pencil.41.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="451">
            <head>3. George Engleheart, pencil sketch of Turret House, c. 1810.</head>
            <figDesc>From George C. Williamson and Henry L. D. Engleheart, <hi rend="i">George Engleheart,
1750-1829, Miniature Painter to George III</hi> (London: George Bell &amp; Sons, 1902).</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p41-94" n="94"/>
          <figure n="Engleheart.TurretHouse.penandink.41.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="412">
            <figTranscr>D A L<lb/>
              F<lb/>
              E C B</figTranscr>
            <head>4. George Engleheart, watercolor, pen and ink drawing of Turret House, c. 1810.</head>
            <figDesc>From George C. Williamson and Henry L. D. Engleheart, <hi rend="i">George Engleheart,
1750-1829, Miniature Painter to George III</hi> (London: George Bell &amp; Sons, 1902).</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Engleheart was a close friend of Hayley and frequently visited Felpham.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">6</ref> During these visits, Engleheart executed two drawings, a
pencil sketch (illus. 3) and a watercolor, pen and ink drawing (illus. 4) of Hayley’s marine villa, known
locally as Turret House due to the large turret that formed the entrance.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">7</ref> Both drawings date c. 1810 and depict the Turret House from
the southerly aspect. The drawings were first reproduced in George C. Williamson’s 1902 biography of
Engleheart. The pencil sketch only was reproduced in Morchard Bishop’s 1951 biography of Hayley and also in
1969, as the cover illustration to Elizabeth Johnston and William Wells’s catalogue of Blake’s portraits
for Hayley’s library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">8</ref> Both drawings
depict a single-storey colonnade constructed of at least six bays that appears analogous to the colonnade
depicted in the rough sketch on the verso of the self-portrait. <note id="n32">6. Morchard Bishop suggests
that Engleheart and Hayley became friends during the period of Hayley’s second marriage; see Bishop, 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Hayley: The Life, Works, and Friendships of William Hayley</hi> (London: Victor Gollancz,
1951) 324. Bishop’s evidence is based on Hayley’s extant correspondence in the Fitzwilliam Museum,
Cambridge. There is no mention of Engleheart in Hayley’s published <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> or manuscript
autobiography, although, as the editor of the <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> explains, Hayley ceased to keep his
manuscript diary after his second marriage; see William Hayley, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Life and Writings
of William Hayley, Esq., the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself. With Extracts from His
Private Correspondence and Unpublished Poetry. And Memoirs of His Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young
Sculptor</hi>, ed. John Johnson, 2 vols. (London: H. Colburn, 1823) 2: 194.</note>
	<note id="n33">7. The house was demolished in the 1960s, but the two Engleheart drawings, the surviving
correspondence between Hayley and his architect, including numerous plans of the house, and the 1876 Ordnance
Survey map of Felpham allow Turret House and its grounds to be reconstructed.</note>
	<note id="n34">8. William Wells and Elizabeth Johnston, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s “Heads of the
Poets” for Turret House, Residence of William Hayley, Felpham</hi> (Manchester: Manchester City Art Gallery,
n.d.). This booklet is undated, but was produced for the exhibition “For Friendship’s Sake”: William
Blake and William Hayley at the Manchester City Art Gallery in 1969.</note></p>
          <p>Hayley employed Samuel Bunce, architect to the Admiralty, to design and oversee the construction
of his Turret House.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">9</ref> In a letter of 1
May 1797, Bunce tells Hayley of his intention to proceed with the construction of “a colonnade protruding
from the turret, or being formed of the turret.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">10</ref> By June 1798, this idea had changed, with Bunce recommending that the
<pb id="p41-95" n="95"/>
coach house be kept as low as possible so that it can be joined onto the proposed colonnade. Bunce asks
Hayley: “What do you think of giving up the small room over the coach house &amp; letting the arcade run
thro thus?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">11</ref> There is no mention of
the colonnade in their later correspondence, which suggests that the matter may have been resolved during one
of Bunce’s many visits to Felpham. According to the 1876 Ordnance Survey map of Felpham, which was the first
topographical survey of the village to use the 25-inch to one-mile scale, the colonnade was approximately 47
meters long, running between the main house and a small building that, according to Bunce’s letter of June
1798, served as the coach house.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n35">9. For a brief biography of Bunce, see H. Colvin, <hi rend="i">A Biographical Dictionary of
British Architects, 1600-1840</hi>, 2nd ed. (London: J. Murray, 1978) 15.</note>
	<note id="n36">10. Fitzwilliam Museum, Hayley Letters, XXXII, f. 7.</note>
	<note id="n37">11. Fitzwilliam Museum, Hayley Letters, XXXII, f. 27.</note>
	<note id="n38">12. Hayley’s friend, John Johnson, recalls this building being used as a porter’s lodge
after 1800; see Hayley, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> 2: 198.</note></p>
          <p>The similarity between the colonnade depicted in both Engleheart drawings and the rough sketch on
the verso of the self-portrait suggests a possible identification. The sketch appears to depict the northwest
aspect of Hayley’s house. The structure on the left of the sketch may be an extremely hasty delineation of
the rear of Turret House, with the horizontal and vertical lines above the arched doorway representing the
turret at the front of the house.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">13</ref>
According to the plans of the house in the Hayley-Bunce correspondence, there was no rear doorway in the
house. However, the plans do not include the colonnade and the extended west wing, which are depicted in both
Engleheart drawings. The 1876 OS map indicates that the colonnade extended approximately five meters beyond
the main structure of the house, although this is not evident in either of the Engleheart drawings. It is
possible that the arched doorway on the sketch depicts the northern entrance to the colonnade. The colonnade
stretches to the right, terminating in the coach house, which is either represented, or more likely obscured,
by the vertical lines on the right of the sketch. Essick suggests that the vertical lines could represent two
figures standing “well forward of even the nearest reaches of the building.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">14</ref> If this is the case, the coach house may be obscured behind
the figures, who could possibly represent Blake and Hayley. <note id="n39">13. The doorway to Turret House was
a brick arch that was constructed over what Hayley refers to as a “Trilithon” formed of “three great
stones.” In later correspondence Bunce refers to the “Trilithon” entrance, describing Hayley’s newly
built house as “the Druidical seat.” It is possible that Blake’s depiction of trilithons in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> was in part influenced by the entrance to Hayley’s
Turret House. See Fitzwilliam Museum, Hayley Letters, XXXII, f. 3 and f. 19.</note>
	<note id="n40">14. Essick 133.</note></p>
          <p>Alternatively, like Engleheart’s drawings, the sketch may depict the southern aspect of
Hayley’s Turret House, albeit rendered from a position further back than Engleheart’s pencil drawing. In
this case, the structure with the arched doorway may represent the coach house, with the colonnade running to
the right and disappearing behind the vertical lines on the right of the sketch, which possibly depict the
main structure of the house, although the vertical lines appear to show two structures, or two figures, rather
than one turret as in Engleheart’s drawings.</p>
          <p>The key feature of the rough sketch on the verso of the self-portrait is the single-storey
colonnade that begins at the building, or cluster of buildings, on the left and gradually diminishes until
terminating in the vertical lines on the right of the sketch. The similarity between the colonnade and
Engleheart’s two depictions of Hayley’s colonnade suggests that both artists were working from the same
source. Blake is known to have executed a small number of landscapes while in Felpham. For example, there is
an unfinished pencil and watercolor drawing that depicts the southern aspect of the village, including St.
Mary’s Church, Hayley’s turret and Blake’s cottage, partially hidden behind trees and bathed in a ray of
sunlight.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">15</ref> The rough sketch may be a
prefatory drawing for a planned picture of Hayley’s marine villa that was never begun or is now lost. An
identification of the sketch with Hayley’s Turret House reinforces Essick’s dating of the self-portrait to
the period Blake was resident in Felpham and learning the techniques of miniature portraiture.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n41">15. See Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New
Haven: Yale University Press, 1981) cat. nos. 368-73, 375.</note>
	<note id="n42">16. The extant portrait miniatures Blake executed in Felpham are examined by the author in
“A Minute Skirmish: Blake, Hayley and the Art of Miniature Painting,” <hi rend="i">Blake and
Conflict</hi>, ed. Jon Mee and Sarah Haggarty (forthcoming from Palgrave Macmillan).</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
