<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>41.2.viscomi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s “Annus Mirabilis”: The Productions of 1795</title>
        <author n="Viscomi">Joseph Viscomi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">41.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>M. Crosby</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <body>
    <pb id="p41-52" n="52"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Blake’s “Annus Mirabilis”: The Productions of 1795</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Joseph <name>Viscomi</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">
            <hi rend="i">Author’s note: An online version of this article, with six more illustrations, all
illustrations in color, and a slightly longer first section, is available on the journal’s web 
site<corr type="emend">.</corr> Illustrations that appear only online are indicated in the print
version by the online illustration number preceded by an “e” (e.g., illus. e4).</hi>
          </note>
          <p>IN 1795, Blake produces <hi rend="i">The Song of Los, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, executes 12 large color-printed drawings, color prints a few etchings, reprints
8 copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, reprints most of his illuminated canon to
date in a deluxe, large-paper set, and begins the 537 watercolor drawings of <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n00" type="note">*</ref> The first period of
illuminated book production, 1789-95, culminates, new experiments in combining printmaking and painting are
begun and perfected, and work as designer and painter begins to dominate Blake’s energies and time for the
next 10 years. In this essay, the second of a two-part study, I focus on the last of Blake’s illuminated
books from this period, <hi rend="i">The Song of Los, The Book of Los</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of
Ahania</hi>, trying to sequence them from a purely materialist perspective—by recreating the large copper
sheets from which the individual plates were cut—to see how Blake’s creative process, including changes of
mind and false starts, unfolded through production and how these particular works and their techniques might
relate to one another, to the color-printed drawings, and to the experiments in color printing that lie behind
them both.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n00">*I would like to thank Robert Essick for reading an early draft of this essay and Todd
Stabley, multimedia consultant, formerly of the Center for Instructional Technology, University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill, for his assistance in digitally recreating Blake’s copper sheets and virtual
designs.</note>
	<note id="n1">1. Part 1, “Blake’s Virtual Designs and Reconstruction of <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi>,” uses digital imaging to recreate Blake’s original designs for the text plates of 
<hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> and to realize the virtual designs in this and a few other illuminated books.
Blake’s virtual designs are designs we create mentally by recombining an illuminated book’s related
images.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> is generally thought to precede the two other books, which is
to say, Blake is thought to have returned to <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi> (1793) and 
<hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi> (1794) with “Africa” and “Asia,” the two parts of <hi rend="i">The
Song of Los</hi>, rather than continuing <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> (1794), because he began
the “continental” books before the “Urizen” books.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref><hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> are thought to
be last because they are intaglio and short, supposedly representing a decreased focus on illuminated book
production. An easy symmetry and progression, from large format to small, relief etching to intaglio—and
then no more illuminated books until <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (c. 1804-11)—helps make this sequence
attractive. But when examined in terms of their production, these books reveal a much different sequence, one
in which <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> is executed last, the “Urizen” project is completed
uninterrupted, and the return to the “continental” project is possibly an afterthought. <note id="n2">2.
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> are both dated 1794 by Blake, but the order in which he
produced them is not immediately clear. Keynes sequences the books <hi rend="i">America, Urizen, Europe, The
Song of Los, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> (222-48). By placing 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> between <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, he implies that the
continental cycle was Blake’s most recent project when working on <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> and that
he postponed work on the subsequent books of <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi> Erdman and other editors are less clear
about the sequence of the 1794 and 1795 books; they group the related books together, even though that means
placing <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> after <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> so it can be read with 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
can be read with <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> In the Blake Archive, we place 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> before <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, assuming a chronological contiguity with 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> because the works are physically, visually, and thematically alike, but also because the
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> plates were executed in terms of color printing, the printing technique Blake had
begun using in 1794, and the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> plates were not (see Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the
Idea of the Book</hi>, chapter 29).</note></p>
          <p>I will begin by recapitulating the main argument of my bibliographical analysis of 
<hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, in which I realize digitally the book’s virtual designs and original format,
then proceed to examine the technique of the color-printed drawings, reconstruct the sheet of copper from
which Blake cut <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, provide new
information about the trial proof for <hi rend="i">Pity, Albion rose</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Large</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi>, and conclude by speculating on the sequence of the three illuminated
books and their relations to the large color-printed drawings.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">I. Blake’s Reconstruction of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi></hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, dated 1795 on its title page, is Blake’s most oddly shaped
illuminated book, consisting of four full-page illustrations (including the title page) and four text plates,
which are about 4 cm. narrower than the illustrations and 1 to 2 cm. shorter. As I have shown elsewhere,
illuminated plates are never perfectly uniform or square, because Blake cut most from larger sheets by
hand.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> But the variance among plates is
greatest in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>—and, as we shall see, is actually much greater than it first
appears. The frontispiece (illus. 1), picturing Urizen kneeling at an altar under a globe inscribed with
strange markings, is the exact same size as the endplate (illus. 2), picturing Los kneeling above the sun,
hammer in hand. Figures with globes in mirrored position pair the designs visually and thematically and
suggest a new, conflated virtual design (illus. 3). Plates 1 and 8 are the same size because 
              <pb id="p41-53" n="53"/>
              <figure n="s-los.b.p1" id="s-los.b.illbk.01" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="763" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>1. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 1.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="s-los.b.p8" id="s-los.b.illbk.08" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="753" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>
                11
              </figTranscr>
<head>2. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 8.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="3.sl.1.8.100" rend="file" width="397" height="802">
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, virtual design of plates 1 and 8, based on copy E.</head>
<figDesc>These items are reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p41-54" n="54"/>
<figure n="s-los.b.p2" id="s-los.b.illbk.02" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="716" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>
                2<lb/>
                THE<lb/>
                SONG of<lb/>
                LOS<lb/>
                Lambeth    Printed by W Blake    1795
              </figTranscr>
<head>5. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 2.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="s-los.b.p5" id="s-los.b.illbk.05" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="735" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>
                7
              </figTranscr>
                <head>6. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 5.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
they are executed on the front and back of the same copper plate. This may not be apparent comparing just the
height and width of the plates, but four measurements reveal their shared shape. The copy B impression of
plate 1 is 23.6 cm. left side, 23.6 cm. right, 17.8 cm. top, and 17.5 cm. bottom. Plate 8 has the same
measurements, indicating that it is the verso of plate 1 (illus. e4). <note id="n3">3. See Viscomi, 
<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>, chapter 5, and “Evolution” 306-07.</note></p>
            <p>Blake typically etched both sides of relief-etched plates: <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> plates
are on the versos of <hi rend="i">Innocence, Europe</hi> on <hi rend="i">America, Urizen</hi> on 
<hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi> Thus, discovering that plates 1 and 8 were etched recto/verso was not surprising.
Finding plates 2 (illus. 5) and 5 (illus. 6), the other two full-page illustrations, apparently not
recto/verso, however, was surprising. They have the same shape and width, but plate 5 is 9 mm. shorter. The
discrepancy is an illusion, however, caused by the top of plate 5’s having been masked 9 mm. upon
printing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> The plates are recto/verso,
with the top of plate 5 being the bottom of plate 2. Together, this recto/verso pair form a virtual design in
which Urizen is imprisoned behind the leaves of the lilies holding Titania and Oberon (illus. 8), calling to
mind the imprisonment of another eternal in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> plate 4 (illus. 9) and the body behind
              <figure n="8.sl.2.5.100" rend="file" width="609" height="800">
	<head>8. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, virtual design of plates 2 and 5, based on copy A.</head>
<figDesc>© Copyright the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <pb id="p41-55" n="55"/>
              <figure n="urizen.G.P4" rend="file" width="958" height="598">
	<figTranscr>-tals<lb/>
              Have written the secrets of wisdom<lb/>
<lb/>
              In whirlwinds of sulphurous smoke:<lb/>
              And enormous forms of energy;<lb/>
              All the seven deadly sins of the soul</figTranscr>
<head>9. <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> copy G, plate 4.</head>
<figDesc>Collection of Robert N. Essick. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used with
permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="but313.1.1.cpd" id="but313.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="689">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>10. Small <hi rend="i">Pity.</hi></head>
<figDesc>© Copyright the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <pb id="p41-56" n="56"/>
              <figure n="s-los.b.p6" id="s-los.b.illbk.06" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="614" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>8<lb/>
                ASIA<lb/>
                The Kings of Asia heard<lb/>
                The howl rise up from Europe!<lb/>
                And each ran out from his Web;<lb/>
                From his ancient woven Den;<lb/>
                For the darkness of Asia was startled<lb/>
                At the thick-flaming, thought-creating fires of Orc.<lb/>
<lb/>
                And the Kings of Asia stood<lb/>
                And cried in bitterness of soul.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Shall not the King call for Famine from the heath?<lb/>
                Nor the Priest, for Pestilence from the fen?<lb/>
                To restrain! to dismay! to thin!<lb/>
                The inhabitants of mountain and plain;<lb/>
                In the day of full-feeding prosperity;<lb/>
                And the night of delicious songs.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Shall not the Councellor throw his curb<lb/>
                Of Poverty on the laborious?<lb/>
                To fix the price of labour;<lb/>
                To invent allegoric riches:<lb/>
<lb/>
                And the privy admonishers of men<lb/>
                Call for Fires in the City<lb/>
                For heaps of smoking ruins,<lb/>
                In the night of prosperity &amp; wantonness<lb/>
<lb/>
                To turn man from his path,<lb/>
                To restrain the child from the womb,</figTranscr>
<head>11. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 6.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="s-los.b.p7" id="s-los.b.illbk.07" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="630" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>10<lb/>
                To cut off the bread from the city,<lb/>
                That the remnant may learn to obey.<lb/>
<lb/>
                That the pride of the heart may fail;<lb/>
                That the lust of the eyes may be quench’d:<lb/>
                That the delicate ear in its infancy<lb/>
                May be dull’d; and the nostrils clos’d up:<lb/>
                To teach mortal worms the path<lb/>
                That leads from the gates of the Grave.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Urizen heard them cry;<lb/>
                And his shudd’ring waving wings<lb/>
                Went enormous above the red flames<lb/>
                Drawing clouds of despair thro’ the heavens<lb/>
                Of Europe as he went:<lb/>
                And his Books of brass iron &amp; gold<lb/>
                Melted over the land as he flew,<lb/>
                Heavy-waving, howling, weeping.<lb/>
<lb/>
                And he stood over Judea;<lb/>
                And stay’d in his ancient place;<lb/>
                And stretch’d his clouds over Jerusalem;<lb/>
<lb/>
                For Adam, a mouldering skeleton<lb/>
                Lay bleach’d on the garden of Eden;<lb/>
                And Noah as white as snow<lb/>
                On the mountains of Ararat.<lb/>
                Then the thunders of Urizen bellow’d aloud<lb/>
                From his woven darkness above.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Orc raging in European darkness<lb/>
                Arose like a pillar of fire above the Alps<lb/>
                Like a serpent of fiery flame!<lb/>
                The sullen Earth<lb/>
                Shrunk!<lb/>
                Forth from the dead dust rattling bones to bones<lb/>
                Join: shaking convuls’d the shivring clay breathes<lb/>
                And all flesh naked stands; Fathers and Friends;<lb/>
                Mothers &amp; Infants; Kings &amp; Warriors;<lb/>
<lb/>
                The Grave shrieks with delight, &amp; shakes<lb/>
                Her hollow womb, &amp; clasps the solid stem;<lb/>
                Her bosom swells with wild desire;<lb/>
                And milk &amp; blood &amp; glandous wine,<lb/>
                In rivers rush &amp; shout &amp; dance,<lb/>
                On mountain, dale and plain.<lb/>
                The SONG of LOS is Ended.<lb/>
                Urizen Wept.</figTranscr>
<head>12. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 7.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="s-los.b.p3" id="s-los.b.illbk.03" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="660" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>4<lb/>
<lb/>
                AFRICA<lb/>
<lb/>
                I will sing you a song of Los, the Eternal Prophet:<lb/>
                He sung it to four harps at the tables of Eternity.<lb/>
                In heart-formed Africa.<lb/>
                Urizen faded! Ariston shudderd!<lb/>
                And thus the Song began<lb/>
<lb/>
                Adam stood in the garden of Eden:<lb/>
                And Noah on the mountains of Ararat;<lb/>
                They saw Urizen give his Laws to the Nations<lb/>
                By the hands of the children of Los.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Adam shudderd! Noah faded! black grew the sunny<lb/>
                African<lb/>
                When Rintrah gave Abstract Philosophy to Brama in the East.<lb/>
                (Night spoke to the Cloud!<lb/>
                Lo these Human form’d spirits in smiling hipocrisy. War<lb/>
                Against one another; so let them War on; slaves to the<lb/>
                eternal Elements)<lb/>
                Noah shrunk beneath the waters:<lb/>
                Abram fled in fires from Chaldea;<lb/>
                Moses beheld upon Mount Sinai forms of dark delusion;<lb/>
<lb/>
                To Trismegistus. Palamabron gave an abstract Law;<lb/>
                To Pythagoras Socrates &amp; Plato.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Times rolled on o’er all the sons of Har, time after time<lb/>
                Orc on Mount Atlas howld. chain’d down with the Chain of Jealousy<lb/>
                Then Oothoon hoverd over Judah &amp; Jerusalem<lb/>
                And Jesus heard her voice (a man of sorrows) he recievd<lb/>
                A Gospel from wretched Theotormon.<lb/>
<lb/>
                The human race began to wither. for the healthy built<lb/>
                Secluded places, fearing the joys of Love<lb/>
                And the disease’d only propagated;<lb/>
                So Antamon call’d up Leutha from her valleys of delight:<lb/>
                And to Mahomet a loose Bible gave.<lb/>
                But in the North, to Odin, Sotha gave a Code of War.<lb/>
                Because of Diralada thinking to reclaim his joy.</figTranscr>
<head>13. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 3.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="s-los.b.p4" id="s-los.b.illbk.04" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="690" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>6<lb/>
<lb/>
                These were the Churches: Hospitals: Castles; Palaces;<lb/>
                Like nets &amp; gins &amp; traps to catch the joys of Eternity<lb/>
                And all the rest a desart;<lb/>
                Till like a dream Eternity was obliterated &amp; erased.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Since that dread day when Har and Heva fled.<lb/>
                Because their brethren &amp; sisters liv’d in War &amp; Lust;<lb/>
                And as they fled they shrunk<lb/>
                Into two narrow doleful forms:<lb/>
                Creeping in reptile flesh upon<lb/>
                The bosom of the ground:<lb/>
                And all the vast of Nature shrunk<lb/>
                Before their shrunken eyes.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Thus the terrible race of Los &amp; Enitharmon gave<lb/>
                Laws &amp; Religions to the sons of Har binding them more<lb/>
                And more to Earth: closing and restraining:<lb/>
                Till a Philosophy of Five Senses was complete<lb/>
                Urizen wept &amp; gave it into the hands of Newton &amp; Locke<lb/>
<lb/>
                Clouds roll heavy upon the Alps round Rousseau &amp; Voltaire:<lb/>
                And on the mountains of Lebanon round the deceased Gods<lb/>
                Of Asia; &amp; on the desarts of Africa round the Fallen Angels<lb/>
                The Guardian Prince of Albion burns in his nightly tent</figTranscr>
<head>14. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 4.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <pb id="p41-57" n="57"/>
              <figure n="15.SL3.4.E.100" rend="file" width="900" height="720">
	<figTranscr>AFRICA<lb/>
<lb/>
                I will sing you a song of Los, the Eternal Prophet:<lb/>
                He sung it to four harps at the tables of Eternity.<lb/>
                In heart-formed Africa.<lb/>
                Urizen faded! Ariston shudderd!<lb/>
                And thus the Song began<lb/>
<lb/>
                Adam stood in the garden of Eden:<lb/>
                And Noah on the mountains of Ararat;<lb/>
                They saw Urizen give his Laws to the Nations<lb/>
                By the hands of the children of Los.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Adam shudderd! Noah faded! black grew the sunny<lb/>
                African<lb/>
                When Rintrah gave Abstract Philosophy to Brama in the East.<lb/>
                (Night spoke to the Cloud!<lb/>
                Lo these Human form’d spirits in smiling hipocrisy. War<lb/>
                Against one another; so let them War on; slaves to the<lb/>
                eternal Elements)<lb/>
                Noah shrunk beneath the waters:<lb/>
                Abram fled in fires from Chaldea;<lb/>
                Moses beheld upon Mount Sinai forms of dark delusion;<lb/>
<lb/>
                To Trismegistus. Palamabron gave an abstract Law;<lb/>
                To Pythagoras Socrates &amp; Plato.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Times rolled on o’er all the sons of Har, time after time<lb/>
                Orc on Mount Atlas howld. chain’d down with the Chain of Jealousy<lb/>
                Then Oothoon hoverd over Judah &amp; Jerusalem<lb/>
                And Jesus heard her voice (a man of sorrows) he recievd<lb/>
                A Gospel from wretched Theotormon.<lb/>
<lb/>
                The human race began to wither. for the healthy built<lb/>
                Secluded places, fearing the joys of Love<lb/>
                And the disease’d only propagated;<lb/>
                So Antamon call’d up Leutha from her valleys of delight:<lb/>
                And to Mahomet a loose Bible gave.<lb/>
                But in the North, to Odin, Sotha gave a Code of War.<lb/>
                Because of Diralada thinking to reclaim his joy.<lb/>
<lb/>
                These were the Churches: Hospitals: Castles; Palaces;<lb/>
                Like nets &amp; gins &amp; traps to catch the joys of Eternity<lb/>
                And all the rest a desart;<lb/>
                Till like a dream Eternity was obliterated &amp; erased.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Since that dread day when Har and Heva fled.<lb/>
                Because their brethren &amp; sisters liv’d in War &amp; Lust;<lb/>
                And as they fled they shrunk<lb/>
                Into two narrow doleful forms:<lb/>
                Creeping in reptile flesh upon<lb/>
                The bosom of the ground:<lb/>
                And all the vast of Nature shrunk<lb/>
                Before their shrunken eyes.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Thus the terrible race of Los &amp; Enitharmon gave<lb/>
                Laws &amp; Religions to the sons of Har binding them more<lb/>
                And more to Earth: closing and restraining:<lb/>
                Till a Philosophy of Five Senses was complete<lb/>
                Urizen wept &amp; gave it into the hands of Newton &amp; Locke<lb/>
<lb/>
                Clouds roll heavy upon the Alps round Rousseau &amp; Voltaire:<lb/>
                And on the mountains of Lebanon round the deceased Gods<lb/>
                Of Asia; &amp; on the desarts of Africa round the Fallen Angels<lb/>
                The Guardian Prince of Albion burns in his nightly tent</figTranscr>
<head>15. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, digitally recreated design for plates 3-4, based on copy
E.</head>
<figDesc>These items are reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
the tall grasses in the trial proof for <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (illus. 10), which I will refer to throughout
this essay as small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and which, as we will see below, was executed before 
<hi rend="i">The Song of Los.</hi>
	<note id="n4">4. The masking is very difficult to detect, but the plate’s embossment is visible in the
verso of the copy C impression, which reveals the plate’s true size as well as a 4-5 mm. dent in the
plate’s edge (illus. e7), which would have been unsightly and distracting had it been printed as part of the
heavily color-printed plate 5. The bottom of plate 2, however, was not color printed and thus could be printed
without showing the dent. This is not the first time Blake masked top or bottom of a design. He had masked the
bottom of <hi rend="i">America</hi> plate 4 in its first printings of 1793 so that the last five lines did not
print (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 87).</note></p>
            <p>Erdman sees a virtual design formed of plates 6 (illus. 11) and 7 (illus. 12). He notes that
plate 7 “seems to continue the forest of plate 6; the boughs that crowd the left margin—an unusual
effect—can be the ends of those bent down in the right margin of 6” (<hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi>
180). Envisioning plate 7 to the right side of plate 6 actually corresponds to Blake’s design as originally
executed. These two plates, which form the poem or section entitled “Asia,” are actually the left and
right sides of one horizontal design, as are plates 3 (illus. 13) and 4 (illus. 14), which form the poem or
section entitled “Africa.” The “Africa” design is 21.5 cm. left, 21.5 cm. right, 27.3 cm. top, 27.2
cm. bottom; the “Asia” design is 22.2 cm. left, 22.2 cm. right, 27.2 cm. top, 27.4 cm. bottom. Instead of
being recto/verso, as one would expect, the text plates are actually only half their original designs; as
conceived and etched, “Africa” and “Asia” are autonomous designs clearly related to one another
visually but not materially. I discovered these interesting material facts in 1991 and published them two
years later 
<pb id="p41-58" n="58"/>
              <figure n="16.s-los.6.7.E.100" rend="file" width="900" height="767">
	<figTranscr>ASIA<lb/>
                The Kings of Asia heard<lb/>
                The howl rise up from Europe!<lb/>
                And each ran out from his Web;<lb/>
                From his ancient woven Den;<lb/>
                For the darkness of Asia was startled<lb/>
                At the thick-flaming, thought-creating fires of Orc.<lb/>
<lb/>
                And the Kings of Asia stood<lb/>
                And cried in bitterness of soul.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Shall not the King call for Famine from the heath?<lb/>
                Nor the Priest, for Pestilence from the fen?<lb/>
                To restrain! to dismay! to thin!<lb/>
                The inhabitants of mountain and plain;<lb/>
                In the day of full-feeding prosperity;<lb/>
                And the night of delicious songs.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Shall not the Councellor throw his curb<lb/>
                Of Poverty on the laborious?<lb/>
                To fix the price of labour;<lb/>
                To invent allegoric riches:<lb/>
<lb/>
                And the privy admonishers of men<lb/>
                Call for Fires in the City<lb/>
                For heaps of smoking ruins,<lb/>
                In the night of prosperity &amp; wantonness<lb/>
<lb/>
                To turn man from his path,<lb/>
                To restrain the child from the womb,<lb/>
<lb/>
                To cut off the bread from the city,<lb/>
                That the remnant may learn to obey.<lb/>
<lb/>
                That the pride of the heart may fail;<lb/>
                That the lust of the eyes may be quench’d:<lb/>
                That the delicate ear in its infancy<lb/>
                May be dull’d; and the nostrils clos’d up:<lb/>
                To teach mortal worms the path<lb/>
                That leads from the gates of the Grave.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Urizen heard them cry;<lb/>
                And his shudd’ring waving wings<lb/>
                Went enormous above the red flames<lb/>
                Drawing clouds of despair thro’ the heavens<lb/>
                Of Europe as he went:<lb/>
                And his Books of brass iron &amp; gold<lb/>
                Melted over the land as he flew,<lb/>
                Heavy-waving, howling, weeping.<lb/>
<lb/>
                And he stood over Judea;<lb/>
                And stay’d in his ancient place;<lb/>
                And stretch’d his clouds over Jerusalem;<lb/>
<lb/>
                For Adam, a mouldering skeleton<lb/>
                Lay bleach’d on the garden of Eden;<lb/>
                And Noah as white as snow<lb/>
                On the mountains of Ararat.<lb/>
                Then the thunders of Urizen bellow’d aloud<lb/>
                From his woven darkness above.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Orc raging in European darkness<lb/>
                Arose like a pillar of fire above the Alps<lb/>
                Like a serpent of fiery flame!<lb/>
                The sullen Earth<lb/>
                Shrunk!<lb/>
                Forth from the dead dust rattling bones to bones<lb/>
                Join: shaking convuls’d the shivring clay breathes<lb/>
                And all flesh naked stands; Fathers and Friends;<lb/>
                Mothers &amp; Infants; Kings &amp; Warriors;<lb/>
<lb/>
                The Grave shrieks with delight, &amp; shakes<lb/>
                Her hollow womb, &amp; clasps the solid stem;<lb/>
                Her bosom swells with wild desire;<lb/>
                And milk &amp; blood &amp; glandous wine,<lb/>
                In rivers rush &amp; shout &amp; dance,<lb/>
                On mountain, dale and plain.<lb/>
                The SONG of LOS is Ended.<lb/>
                Urizen Wept.</figTranscr>
<head>16. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, digitally recreated design for plates 6-7, based on copy
E.</head>
<figDesc>These items are reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
(<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 287), and Detlef Dörrbecker, in his 1995 edition of the
poem, was the first to arrange black and white photographs of the conjunct pages to give an idea of what the
original relief-etched plates looked like (320n29, 345-46). The digital recreations here (illus. 15, 16),
however, are the first reproductions to join the plates seamlessly and present them color printed in their
entirety.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5">5. Why not etch both sides of plates 3-4 and 6-7, or cut the plates in half instead of masking?
Putting the two text plates on separate plates freed the versos for <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>-size color prints.
Masking instead of cutting the plates kept the versos intact should Blake ever want to use them for
designs.</note></p>
            <p>Blake initially divided his text into two columns, but very unlike the columns in 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, these being very loosely placed across a horizontal—or “landscape”—format, a
format used for paintings and prints but not the text of books. By masking one side of the design, probably
with a sheet of paper, he was able to print each text column separately. Hence, he transformed a coherent
design 27.2 cm. wide into two seemingly independent designs/pages approximately 13.6 cm. wide, which is nearly
4 cm. narrower than the four illustration pages. He produced <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> using just four
plates, but two are portrait format and executed recto/verso and two are landscape format and apparently
executed using one side only. Why create pages in oblong folio format, with double columns, so visually
different from the pages of <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>? Why print the columns of
text separately after composing and etching them as part of the same design?</p>
            <pb id="p41-59" n="59"/>
            <p>Given the two distinct sets of plates, <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> appears to have
emerged from two distinct stages of production, with the text plates coming first. This sequence seems the
most likely, because if Blake had the two portrait plates on hand, intending to use them for the designs of
his new book, then he would have acquired plates for texts to match. If, along with the portrait plates, he
also had the 27.2 cm. plates on hand, then he probably would have cut them approximately 17.5 cm. wide and
etched both sides to create four text plates to match the width of his illustrations, thereby producing a book
of eight pages much nearer in size and shape to <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> It
seems reasonable to assume, then, that the two portrait plates were not yet on hand, that the two 27.2 cm.
wide plates were acquired first, and that the text plates preceded the illustrations. (As we shall see, the
shared width of these plates is not a coincidence; at least four other plates from 1795 share the exact
measurement of 27.2 cm., including the sheets that yielded the plates for <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>
and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania.</hi>) Moreover, from this perspective, Blake appears to have set out to
fuse poetry, painting, and printmaking in ways even more radical than the illuminated books. “Africa” and
“Asia,” as originally executed, function autonomously as painted poems or written paintings, with text
superimposed on a landscape design. Each design could have been matted, framed, viewed, and read like a
separate color print or painting. They do not, however, function as book pages.</p>
            <p>Blake created relief etching as a way to work as a printmaker with the tools of the poet and
painter, that is to say, with pens, brushes, liquid ink, and colors, rather than the burins and needles
conventionally required of metal. Blake worked <hi rend="i">on</hi> rather than <hi rend="i">in</hi> the metal
surface, as though it were paper, with tools that enabled him to work outside the conventions and codes of
printmaking and indulge his love of drawing and writing. His new medium encouraged the autographic gesture,
the calligraphic hand of the poet with the line and
                            <figure n="17.SL3-4_6-7.E.100" rend="file" width="958" height="455">
	<figTranscr>AFRICA<lb/>
                            ASIA</figTranscr>
<head>17. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, digitally recreated design for plates 3-4 and 6-7 as pages
stitched together to form a diptych, based on copy E.</head>
<figDesc>These items are reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
brushwork of the painter. As he says in his prospectus (1793), his is a “method of Printing which combines
the Painter and the Poet,” but he notes also that it is a “method of Printing both Letter-press and
Engraving” (Erdman, <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry</hi> 692), by which he means printing text and illustration
in the service of book production. Between 1789 and 1794, Blake printed illuminated plates as book pages; in
his later style, beginning with the color-printed designs of 1794, he printed the plates more like miniature
paintings. But whether he printed them as poems or elaborately colored them as miniatures, Blake designed
illuminated plates with reference to the codex form and in portrait format.</p>
            <p>Blake did not, however, design “Africa” and “Asia” as book pages; he transformed them
into book pages through a trick of printing. Horizontal formats were commonly used for print series,
particularly aquatints of picturesque views, but also for works like George Cumberland’s 
<hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, eight of whose illustrations Blake engraved in late 1795 and 1796. But, as
mentioned, horizontal formats were not used for texts of books, nor does any book in oblong folio before 1795
with pages in double columns come readily to mind. Even stitched together to form a long open diptych (illus.
17), the two designs seem less like facing pages in a book than a long panel, pair of broadsides, or a
horizontal scroll. Perhaps Blake used a non-Western book format to evoke Africa and Asia. For example, the
Chinese horizontal scroll, usually on silk or paper, fuses calligraphy and painted image. It reads right to
left, starting with the title panel, which names the work, and has a colophon panel, at the end of the scroll
or juxtaposed over the image, which contains the poem or notes pertaining to the work. Blake titles his poems
“Africa” and “Asia” and thus does not need a title page, which is a book convention. If he meant the
poems to be read as parts of one work entitled “The Song of Los,” then that too is effected without a
title page. “Africa” begins with “I will sing you a song of Los, the Eternal
<pb id="p41-60" n="60"/>
              <figure n="19.sl.3-4.6-7.B.100" rend="file" width="958" height="427">
	<figTranscr>AFRICA<lb/>
                ASIA</figTranscr>
<head>19. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, digitally recreated design for plates 3-4 and 6-7 as horizontal
scroll or two-part broadside, based on copy E.</head>
<figDesc>These items are reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
Prophet,” and “Asia” ends with “The Song of Los is Ended. / Urizen Wept.” Moreover, if treating the
poems as autonomous designs or parts of the same panel or scroll, Blake could have signed and dated the work
in pen and ink on its surface as he did paintings and color-printed drawings (usually with “WB inv.” in
monogram, with a date; illus. e18). Thus, these works did not need a title page for date and author.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the two designs were meant to be joined and printed on one sheet to form a panorama, a
format the landscape painters Paul Sandby and Francis Towne were experimenting with in the 1780s and 1790s,
or, as noted, to suggest an ancient scroll, the predecessor of the printed codex, and thus a fitting medium
for the Eternal Prophet. Indeed, “in the context of Romantic textual ideology,” according to Mitchell,
“the scroll is the emblem of ancient revealed wisdom, imagination, and the cultural economy of hand-crafted,
individually expressive artifacts” (65). For Blake, “the scroll represents writing as 
<hi rend="i">prophecy</hi>: it is associated with youthful figures of energy, imagination, and rebellion” (65).
Printed together on one sheet of paper the designs form a long, narrow, perpetually open composition
approximately 22.5 × 54.5 cm., which is half the size of most of the color-printed drawings; if given a
centimeter between and around the images (illus. 19), the resulting two-part panel would be approximately half
the size of <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (46 × 60 cm.) or <hi rend="i">Good and Evil Angels</hi> (44.5 × 59.4
cm.), among the largest of the color-printed drawings. As originally designed, however, the two poems
continuing Blake’s continental myth do not resemble the previous installments in size, shape, number, or
structure. <hi rend="i">America</hi> with 18 plates and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> with 17 plates are matched in
size, shape, and structure: both begin with frontispiece, title page, two-page preludium 
(<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>’s plate 3 is a late addition, though one that gave <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 18 pages),
a heading of “A Prophecy,” and “finis” as the last word. The titles of <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi> sections clearly connect the poems/panels to the earlier works, but the horizontal format marks a
break with them as well. The full visual extent of that break was not realized; instead, Blake executed four
illustration pages exactly the size of <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and printed each
of the four text columns separately. The resulting eight pages of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> are
frontispiece, title page, “Africa,” full-page design, “Asia,” end-piece; headings of “A Prophecy”
or endings of “finis” are not present. As reconstructed, <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> is unevenly
shaped and oddly structured, being two poems in one book to form a quartet of continental works within a
trilogy of artifacts.</p>
            <p>Proofs of the text plates in their original condition, or “first state,” are not extant,
which may suggest that Blake abandoned his experiment in rethinking text and image soon after completing the
text plates. This, however, cannot be proven, since other plates are also without proofs. But it does seem
reasonable to suggest that Blake reconstructed the text plates to salvage an experiment about which he had
changed his mind. We can sequence and speculate upon the stages in the production of <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi>, but can we sequence those stages within the year’s worth of productions and discover the relation
of the books to one another and to the color-printed drawings? These are the main questions I try to answer in
the following five sections.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">II. The Large Color Prints</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The large color prints are, “as a group, the first really mature individual works in the
visual arts that Blake created. Moreover they are, as a group, probably the most accomplished,
<pb id="p41-61" n="61"/>
forceful, and effective of Blake’s works in the visual arts” (Butlin, “Physicality” 2). Technically,
they are monotypes, which are in effect printed paintings. Frederick Tatham described the process to Gilchrist
accurately enough, stating that when Blake
<q>
wanted to make his prints in oil . . . [he] took a common thick millboard, and drew in some strong ink or
colour his design upon it strong and thick. He then painted upon that in such oil colours and in such a state
of fusion that they would blur well. He painted roughly and quickly, so that no colour would have time to dry.
He then took a print of that on paper, and this impression he coloured up in water-colours, re-painting his
outline on the millboard when he wanted to take another print. This plan he had recourse to, because he could
vary slightly each impression; and each having a sort of accidental look, he could branch out so as to make
each one different. The accidental look they had was very enticing. (Gilchrist 1: 376)
</q>
To W. M. Rossetti, Tatham added that the printing was done
<q>
in a loose press from an outline sketched on paste-board; the oil colour was blotted on, which gave the sort
of impression you will get by taking the impression of anything <hi rend="i">wet.</hi> There was a look of
accident about this mode which he afterwards availed of, and tinted so as to bring out and favour what was
there rather blurred. (Rossetti 16-17)
</q>
Tatham is mistaken about the medium, which was gum and glue-based colors and not oil-based inks or colors, as
are commonly used today for monotypes, and Blake would not have had to work too quickly or worry too much if
his colors dried to the touch on the support, because he almost certainly printed on dampened paper, whose
moisture would have reconstituted the colors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> The colors, though, he applied “strong and thick” to create a unique spongy opaque
paint film, but also to enable a second and sometimes a third impression to be pulled from the millboard
without having to replenish the colors. Generally speaking, depending on the paper’s dampness and thickness
and the amount of printing pressure, the colors are strongest in first impressions and less intense in
subsequent pulls. The presence of lighter outline and colors in second impressions is proof that outline and
colors were both printed together for the first impressions as well, even for the one color-printed drawing
with a relief-etched outline, as will be demonstrated in illustrations below. Tatham is correct, then, to
assume that Blake “drew . . . his design . . . [and] then painted upon that . . . [and] then took a print of
that on paper,” as opposed to printing outline (“design”) and colors separately.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> He is also correct that Blake “tinted” the impressions
“to bring out and favour what was there rather blurred.” As with his color-printed illuminated book
impressions, Blake finished the large color-printed drawings in watercolors and pen and ink, clarifying forms
in the blots and blurs. Translucent and transparent washes over mottled colors could also transform printed
colors, making more colors appear to have been printed than actually were. Given that the method is primarily
painting on a flat support and pressing that painting into paper, differences among impressions were
inevitable if not also intentional, hence the oxymoronic term of monoprint, a print that is unique rather than
exactly repeatable. <note id="n6">6. Blake used damp paper to print both intaglio plates—which is standard
practice—as well as his relief etchings (Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 99-100).
The facsimile of <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> and the color prints (illus. 18, 19, 21) in Essick and Viscomi,
“Blake’s Method,” were printed on damp paper after the colors had dried. McManus and Townsend come to
the same conclusion: “The paper was not prepared with any priming, but would have been wetted to make it
more receptive to printing” (83; see also Ormsby and Townsend 44). For analyses of Blake’s colors in the
large color prints, see McManus and Townsend 86-99, and Townsend 186.</note>
	<note id="n7">
                                7. To print outline and colors separately calls for printing the plate twice.
For Blake, this would have required printing the outline onto a sheet of paper, somehow fastening the paper in
place on the press bed, marking the position of the plate, removing the plate to apply its colors, returning
the plate <hi rend="i">exactly</hi> to its position (a hair-width variance at top or sides will reveal
itself), and dropping the paper over the plate exactly where it was. Because the shape of the dampened paper
is slightly altered by its first pass through the press, perfect (i.e., undetectable) registration is near
impossible under the best of conditions. Evidence of a plate’s having been printed twice by hand is nearly
always visible if you know where to look; the absence of such evidence signifies single-pull printing and is
not evidence of Blake’s genius for hiding his hand in color printing. If outline and colors of lighter
second impressions were printed separately, then both first and second impressions underwent a procedure that
doubled the likelihood of misregistration. The first impression, instead of being fastened to the press, is
removed so a second impression can be printed, thus the sheet of paper as well as the plate with colors must
be aligned exactly, top and sides, to their marked positions, greatly increasing the chances of misalignment.
No one explicitly argues for this mechanical and labor-intensive procedure for second impressions, which is
wise, since no second impression among the large color-printed drawings or the <hi rend="i">Large</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi> (see section V of this essay) shows any misalignment of color and outline.
Yet such a procedure is implied because it is the inevitable and logical result of printing outline and colors
separately. Hence, the premise of two pulls collapses when tested this far in practice, which in turn supports
the one-pull hypothesis for both second and first impressions.
                                <p>For the fullest presentation of the hypothesis that Blake color printed his
outline (which includes text when it is part of the relief-line system) and colors (which could be printed
from relief lines and/or shallows) separately, registering the second pull on top of the first exactly,
consistently, and without traces of this production method, see Phillips’ <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>
and “Correction” and Butlin’s “War.” For a refutation, see Essick and Viscomi’s “Inquiry” and
“Blake’s Method.”</p></note></p>
            <p>To use millboard to print colors requires at least minimal sealing of its porous surface. Blake
could have done this with a coating of glue size or gesso, which is chalk or whiting mixed with size and
painted over panels or canvas to produce a very white ground. Smith, Tatham, and Linnell mention Blake’s
using this mixture to prepare his tempera paintings. According to Smith, “his ground was a mixture of
whiting and carpenter’s glue, which he passed over several times in thin coatings” (Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 622). In his manuscript on the life of Blake, Tatham says “3 or 4 layers of
whitening &amp;
<pb id="p41-62" n="62"/>
              <figure n="20.striations.demo.100" rend="file" width="716" height="800">
	<head>20. Paint printed from a gessoed millboard, detail.</head>
</figure>
<figure n="21.hectate.striations.det.but318.100" rend="file" width="900" height="863">
	<head>21. <hi rend="i">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</hi>, detail.</head>
<figDesc>This item is reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
carpenters Glue” were used (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 671). Linnell told Gilchrist that it
was a “plaster ground (literally glue and whiting); but he always called it either fresco, gesso, or
plaster. And he certainly laid this ground on too much like plaster on a wall” (1: 368). One can sand gesso
smooth or leave the striations created by brushing it on for a rougher feel for brushes. Colors printed from
such a textured ground will replicate that texture if they are thin or pressed hard enough, or hide it if they
are thick or opaque enough. The sample of three color strips (illus. 20) demonstrates this: at the top of the
image, the first and second strips (red and yellow ochre) reveal the same striations, indicating that this
texture is from the millboard and not the paint layers; the opacity of the third strip (green) hides most of
that texture. At the bottom of the strips, the gesso was applied with a stump brush rather than brushed on,
and its textures are also revealed in the printed colors.</p>
            <p>The striations in the surfaces of <hi rend="i">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</hi> (illus. 21)
and <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing to the Apostles</hi> (illus. 22) suggest that Blake painted his large
color-printed drawings on gessoed grounds. Butlin notices “a striated” effect in <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>,
as well as in impressions of <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (cat. 311, 307,
302), but believes it may have been “produced by only partial adherence” of paint to paper “as if the
paper were slightly oily” (“Physicality” 17). The striations, though, appear not to have been created by
the paint layer, but by the textured surface of the millboard, because the same striated patterns are visible
across different printed colors, as is clear
<pb id="p41-63" n="63"/>
<figure n="22.striations.christ.enh.326.100" rend="file" width="900" height="772">
	<head>22. <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing to the Apostles</hi>, detail.</head>
<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Yale Art Gallery Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
in the Metropolitan Museum’s copy of <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (illus. 23).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> Gesso is used in fresco painting, and if Blake “always
called” his “plaster ground” “fresco, gesso, or plaster,” as Linnell states, then Blake’s writing
“Fresco” on five of his large color prints in an “Indian-type ink” (McManus and Townsend 82) is
fitting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n8">8. The large digital images of the color-printed drawings in the William Blake Archive have
enabled us to examine details heretofore impossible to see in print reproductions and not always visible in
the originals to the naked eye.</note>
	<note id="n9">9. According to J. T. Smith, “Blake’s modes of preparing his ground, and laying them over
his panels for painting, mixing his colours, and manner of working, were those which he considered to have
been practised by the earliest fresco-painters . . .” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 622).
Apparently, this was, to Blake, true of both the color-printed drawings as well as the temperas. For an
insightful examination of the meaning Blake attached to the word “fresco” in theory and practice, see
Hamlyn 20-27, 30-33.</note></p>
            <p>But whether he used glue size or gesso, or thought of the millboard surface as canvas or panel
or plaster wall, he needed an outline to know what to paint. Chalk or charcoal serves this purpose in oil
painting, but lines made with either medium could be ruined in color printing and thus make returning to the
design years later (as we know Blake did, around 1805) impossible (Butlin, “Newly Discovered Watermark”
101). He could have perhaps relied on the thin dried colors on the millboard, but it is more likely that he
had an impervious outline to guide his hand. Some X-radiographs reveal traces of a lead-based paint, which may
have been used for outlining, while others show no traces of lead, supporting the idea that the outline was
executed in an ordinary water-based “Indian ink,” which is lead-free and thus not detectable (McManus and
Townsend 87). Indeed, the “Indian ink” used to sign color
                            <figure n="23.pity.met.striations.100" rend="file" width="958" height="799">
	<head>23. <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, detail.</head>
<figDesc>Metropolitan Museum of Art, gift of Mrs. Robert W. Goelet, 1958 (58.603). Photograph © copyright
1979, Metropolitan Museum of Art.</figDesc>
</figure>
prints works for the purpose, because when dry it is not disturbed by the wet black paint and colors laid over
it or by printing (Essick and Viscomi, “Blake’s Method” 62). With a fixed outline, Blake could, as
Tatham says, return to the design “when he wanted to take another print,” presumably years later, by
“re-painting his outline on the millboard,” painting in the forms, and printing “that on paper.”</p>
            <p>What Tatham describes is planographic printing, that is, printing outline and colors not only
together but also from the same <hi rend="i">flat</hi> surface, with outlines neither raised—as in woodcuts
or relief etching—nor incised—as in etchings and engravings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Blake had tried his hand at planographic printing before 1795, possibly as
early as 1789, in a print entitled <hi rend="i">Charity.</hi> Identified as a “planographic transfer
print” (Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 10), the image was first painted on a sheet of paper or
millboard and transferred to the paper while the ink was wet. Counterproofing (placing face down) newly
printed impressions—regardless of matrix—works the same way, wet ink transferred from a flat surface to
paper, reproducing all marks and forms, albeit in reverse. Blake did not, however,
<pb id="p41-64" n="64"/>
systematically experiment with printing <hi rend="i">painted images</hi> until he color printed the etching
<hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, which, as I argue below, was in 1795 and not 1794, as is supposed (Butlin,
“Physicality” 3; Bindman 476), and which was executed with small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (illus. 10), the
trial proof for the large color print. Until then, Blake had color printed only illuminated books with
relief-etched plates. He inked outlines with dabbers and on and in small areas added colors, probably with
stump brushes (brushes with the tips cut off) or <hi rend="i">poupées</hi> (tightly rolled felt), to small,
well-defined forms. This is, as I have demonstrated elsewhere, a variation on <hi rend="i">à la poupée</hi>
printing, in which an intaglio plate is inked in numerous colors (<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the
Book</hi>, chapter 13). It differs from conventional color printing, however, in that Blake put colors in
spaces meant to be white and negative spaces defining forms, whereas in conventional color printing colors are
applied to the lines of the design itself and not surfaces or white spaces. Adding colors to shallows and
printing them with inked outline is radical,
              <figure n="but294.1.1.cpd" id="but294.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="796">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
                WB 1795</figTranscr>
<head>24. <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam.</hi></head>
<figDesc>© Copyright Tate, London 2006.</figDesc>
</figure>
but, in terms of performance, it is still more printing than painting. The result is indeed a monotype, in
that the prints are never exactly repeatable, but Blake is still thinking—given the medium, size, and
tools—more like a printmaker coloring plates than a painter working broadly with brushes on a large, flat
surface, blocking out forms by colors as well as line. <note id="n10">10. Printing <hi rend="i">exactly
repeatable</hi> images planographically is, of course, lithography, invented accidentally in 1798 by Alois
Senefelder and initially called “polyautography” to suggest the autographic gestures of writing, drawing,
and sketching. Senefelder intended initially to etch designs in low relief on metal or limestone and only
accidentally discovered that designs drawn on soft limestone in a greasy ink absorb the printing ink while all
untouched areas repel ink if first covered with a thin film of water. The basis of lithography, in other
words, is the separation of water and oil. For more on Senefelder and lithography’s similarities to
Blake’s relief etching, see Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 24-25, 171-72; for
information on Blake’s lithograph, <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi>, see Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi>
55-59.</note></p>
            <p>At least one of the 12 large color-printed drawings, however, was not printed planographically.
<hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> (illus. 24) has traces of an embossed outline, indicating that the support
was metal, probably copper, and that the outline was etched in low relief; it also has a platemaker’s mark
(illus. e25), indicating that it was printed from the sheet’s verso. For the only color-printed drawing
known for sure to have been relief etched to be on a sheet’s verso suggests that Blake was probably unsure
of himself, continuing the experiments started with the small trial proof for <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, which
was also etched in low relief (see below), and intending to preserve the recto, the side normally used for
engravings and etchings, should the experiment not work out.
<pb id="p41-65" n="65"/>
	<hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> is 43.2 × 53.5 cm. Because it is the only impression certainly to have
come from a metal plate—and metal is much more expensive than millboard—Essick believes it was most likely
the first of the large color-printed drawings executed (“Supplement” 139).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> This is probably so, as will be shown below, but its place
in the sequence is suggested by its technical connections to earlier experiments in color printing and not by
its support, for two other designs may also have been printed from metal. Though printed planographically, 
<hi rend="i">Satan Exulting over Eve</hi>, at 43.2 × 53.4 cm., and <hi rend="i">elohim Creating Adam</hi>, at
43.1 × 53.6 cm., are the same size as <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>, raising the possibilities that one
of these designs is on its recto and the other on a copper sheet acquired at the same time.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> If either <hi rend="i">Satan</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Elohim</hi> was printed from a copper matrix, then Blake not only used metal before millboard, but he
also printed planographically from metal before millboard. <note id="n11">11. Today, an 18 × 24 in. sheet of
copper (16 gauge) for etching costs almost $100; millboard nearly twice that size is less than $5.</note>
	<note id="n12">12. These measurements are from Butlin’s catalogue raisonné; I did not have the opportunity
to measure each side of the impressions, which I assume would vary slightly.</note></p>
            <p>The detail of the horses’ heads in the first impression of <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>
(illus. 26) reveals clearly that Blake applied a black paint to the low relief outline and shallows
simultaneously and then added a brownish red to the shallows forming the neck and shoulder and a bright red to
the manes. These steps in the painting process are even clearer in the second impression (illus. 27), which
is, as noted, proof that both outline and colors were printed simultaneously here as well as in the first
impression (see note 7). He probably applied the black with a small dabber, as in the illuminated plates,
touching down in the shallows but not depositing color along the base of the relief lines, which produces a
thin unpainted line on both sides of the outline. A yellow wash applied over the colors on the second
impression is very bright in this line because it adheres to the untouched white of the paper. This halo-like
line is evidence of a relief outline as well as of outline and colors’ having been printed together, as is
demonstrated by an impression printed in one pull from a design etched in low relief, inked with a dabber in
black, and painted in brownish red (illus. 28a). Had outline and colors been printed separately, the fine
white line could not parallel the outline exactly, even with perfect registration, because the paper’s shape
and dampness are slightly altered by its being pulled through the press, which is particularly noticeable in
large sheets. Even when paint is deposited with a brush along the base of a relief line, paper is unlikely to
pick the color up as it bends over the relief line onto the shallow, unless the paint is very thick. On 
<corr type="emend">plate 7 of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy E,</corr> for example, Blake most likely used a
brush to apply color to the tendrils dividing the verses, depositing paint on both sides of the relief line
(illus. 28b), which, when printed, produced the telltale white lines and two tendril-like lines that printed
from the shallows. Had Blake deposited color on one side of the outline only, the tendril-like
                            <figure n="26.god.tate.horses.det.100" rend="file" width="885" height="1000">
	<head>26. <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>, detail of horses’ heads.</head>
<figDesc>© Copyright Tate, London 2006.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="27.god.met.horses.det.100" rend="file" width="893" height="1000">
	<head>27. <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>, detail of horses’ heads.</head>
<figDesc>Metropolitan Museum of Art, Rogers Fund, 1916 (16.38). Photograph © copyright 2000, Metropolitan
Museum of Art.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p41-66" n="66"/>
              <figure n="28.whiteline.demo.100" rend="file" width="958" height="276">
	<head>28a. Design etched in low relief, inked with dabber in black and gone over in brownish-red color,
printed in one pull producing thin white line at base of relief lines, detail.</head>
</figure>
              <figure n="28b.sl.E.7.100" rend="file" width="958" height="349">
              	<figTranscr>That the delicate ear in its infancy<lb/>
                May be dull’d; and the nostrils clos’d up.<lb/>
                To teach mortal worms the path<lb/>
                That leads from the gates of the Grave.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Urizen heard them cry;<lb/>
                And his shudd’ring waving wings<lb/>
                Went enormous above the red flames<lb/>
                Drawing clouds of despair thro’ the heavens<lb/>
                Of Europe as he went:<lb/>
                And his Books of brass iron &amp; gold<lb/>
</figTranscr>
                <head>28b. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> <corr type="emend">copy E, plate 7,</corr>
detail.</head>
                <figDesc><corr type="emend">Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</corr></figDesc>
              </figure>
line would appear as the result of a misregistered second pull, an easy misreading of the material
evidence.</p>
            <p>As noted, Blake did not need or intend to print outlines separately, not in illuminated books
or color-printed drawings. In the latter, he only needed <hi rend="i">fixed</hi> guidelines for painting and
for ensuring that the design, however it was colored in and/or finished, was repeatable. But when and how did
Blake realize that if he “drew. . .his design. . . [and] then painted upon that” he could take “a print
of that on paper,” that outline and colors could be on the same surface and he could paint over the outline
with a brush rather than use a dabber? When did he realize that he was no longer painting a print but printing
a painting? To answer these questions requires knowing where <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> fits into this
evolution and how it connects to <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> and the small trial proof of 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, which have a heretofore unknown connection to Blake’s intaglio books of 1795.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">III. <hi rend="i">The Book of Los, The Book of Ahania</hi></hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Three color-printed drawings, <hi rend="i">God, Satan</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Elohim</hi>,
possibly all from metal and the first executed, are approximately 43.2 × 53.5 cm. This is a large but
apparently not uncommon sheet size. Blake’s engraving of <hi rend="i">Beggar’s Opera Act III</hi> (1788)
is 40.1 × 54.2 cm.; <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> engravings of 1793 and 1794 are 46 ×
54 cm. and 46.4 × 54 cm. respectively; the plates for Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, 16 executed by
Blake between 1792-94, average 27 × 20 cm., which suggests that they were quarters of a 40 × 54 cm. sheet of
copper.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> The larger widths, up to
<pb id="p41-67" n="67"/>
              <figure n="29.SL3-4_over_SL6-7_final.100" rend="file" width="675" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>AFRICA<lb/>
                ASIA</figTranscr>
<head>29. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> plates 3-4 and 6-7 as half sheet, based on copy E.</head>
<figDesc>These items are reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
60 cm. for <hi rend="i">Newton, Lamech, House of Death</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi>, are
presumably from millboards and likely come later in the series. Recall that the two <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi> text plates share the same width, 27.2 cm., though they vary in height by about 8 mm. If joined at
their shared measurement of 27.2 cm., then they formed a sheet of copper approximately 43.5 × 27.2 cm.
(illus. 29), which is half the size of these large metal sheets. The full sheet would have been 43.5 × 54.4
cm. That two plates are 27.2 cm. wide is unlikely to be a coincidence. The shared measurement strongly
suggests that the plates are quarters of a sheet the size of those used for the first color-printed drawings.
But if so, what were the other two quarters? I initially suspected the quarters were the sheets that yielded
the plates for <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, not because they
are also 1795 productions, but because both sheets
              <pb id="p41-68" n="68"/>
<figure n="30.BL_quarter_with_margins.100" rend="file" width="958" height="716">
	<figTranscr>THE<lb/>
                BOOK of<lb/>
                LOS<lb/>
<lb/>
                LAMBETH<lb/>
                Printed by W Blake 1795<lb/>
<lb/>
                LOS<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap. I<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: Eno aged Mother.<lb/>
                Who the chariot of Leutha guides.<lb/>
                Since the day of thunders in old time<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: Sitting beneath the eternal Oak<lb/>
                Trembled and shook the stedfast Earth<lb/>
                And thus her speech broke forth.<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: O Times remote!<lb/>
                When Love &amp; Joy were adoration:<lb/>
                And none impure were deem’d.<lb/>
                Not Eyeless Covet<lb/>
                Nor Thin-lip’d Envy<lb/>
                Nor Bristled Wrath<lb/>
                Nor Curled Wantonness<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: But Covet was poured full:<lb/>
                Envy fed with fat of lambs:<lb/>
                Wrath with lions gore:<lb/>
                Wantonness lulld to sleep<lb/>
                With the virgins lute.<lb/>
                Or sated with her love.<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: Till Covet broke his locks &amp; bars.<lb/>
                And slept with open doors:<lb/>
                Envy sung at the rich mans feast:<lb/>
                Wrath was follow’d up and down<lb/>
                By a little ewe lamb<lb/>
<lb/>
                And Wantonness on his own true love<lb/>
                Begot a giant race:<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: Raging furious the flames of desire<lb/>
                Ran thro’ heaven &amp; earth, living flames<lb/>
                Intelligent, organizd; arm’d<lb/>
                With destruction &amp; plagues. In the midst<lb/>
                The Eternal Prophet bound in a chain<lb/>
                Compell’d to watch Urizens shadow<lb/>
<lb/>
                7: Rag’d with curses &amp; sparkles of fury<lb/>
                Round the flames roll as Los hurls<lb/>
                his chains<lb/>
                Mounting up from his fury, condens’d<lb/>
                Rolling round &amp; round. mounting on high<lb/>
                Into vacuum: into non-entity.<lb/>
                Where nothing was! dash’d wide apart<lb/>
                His feet stamp the eternal fierce-raging<lb/>
                Rivers of wide flame; they roll round<lb/>
                And round on all sides making their way<lb/>
                Into darkness and shadowy obscurity<lb/>
<lb/>
                8: Wide apart stood the fires; Los remain’d<lb/>
                In the void between fire and fire<lb/>
                In trembling and horror they beheld him<lb/>
                They stood wide apart, driv’n by his hands<lb/>
                And his feet which the nether abyss<lb/>
                Stamp’d in fury and hot indignation<lb/>
<lb/>
                9: But no light from the fires all was<lb/>
<lb/>
                Dark<lb/>
<lb/>
                Darkness round Los: heat was not; for<lb/>
                bound up<lb/>
                Into fiery spheres from his fury<lb/>
                The gigantic flames trembled and hid<lb/>
<lb/>
                10: Coldness, darkness, obstruction, a Solid<lb/>
                Without fluctuation. hard as adamant<lb/>
                Black as marble of Egypt; impenetrable<lb/>
                Bound in the fierce raging Immortal.<lb/>
                And the seperated fires froze in<lb/>
                A vast solid without fluctuation.<lb/>
                Bound in his expanding clear senses<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: II<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: The Immortal stood frozen amidst<lb/>
                The vast rock of eternity; times<lb/>
                And times; a night of vast durance:<lb/>
                Impatient, stifled, stiffend, hardned.<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: Till impatience no longer could bear<lb/>
                The hard bondage. rent; rent. the vast<lb/>
                solid<lb/>
                With a crash from immense to immense<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: Crack’d across into numberless frag-<lb/>
                -ments<lb/>
                The Prophetic wrath, strug’ling for vent<lb/>
                Hurls apart. stamping furious to dust<lb/>
                And crumbling with bursting sobs; heaves<lb/>
                The black marble on high into fragments<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: Hurl’d apart on all sides, as a falling<lb/>
                Rock; the innumerable fragments away<lb/>
                Fell asunder; and horrible vacuum<lb/>
                Beneath him &amp; on all sides round<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: Falling, falling! Los fell &amp; fell<lb/>
                Sunk precipitant heavy down down<lb/>
                Times on times, night on night, day on day<lb/>
                Truth has bounds. Error none; falling<lb/>
                falling:<lb/>
                Years on years, and ages on ages<lb/>
                Still he fell thro’ the void, still a void<lb/>
                Found for falling day &amp; night without<lb/>
                end.<lb/>
                For tho’ day or night was not; their spaces<lb/>
<lb/>
                Were measurd by his incessant whirls<lb/>
                In the horrid vacuity bottomless.<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: The Immortal revolving; indignant<lb/>
                First in wrath threw his limbs, like the<lb/>
                babe<lb/>
                New born into our world: wrath subsided<lb/>
                And contemplative thoughts first arose<lb/>
                Then aloft his head rear’d in the Abyss<lb/>
                And his downward-borne fall. chang’d oblique<lb/>
<lb/>
                7: Many ages of groans; till there grew<lb/>
                Branchy forms. organizing the Human<lb/>
                Into finite inflexible organs.<lb/>
<lb/>
                8: Till in process from falling he bore<lb/>
                Sidelong on the purple air. wafting<lb/>
                The weak breeze in efforts oerwearied<lb/>
<lb/>
                9: Incessant the falling Mind labour’d<lb/>
                Organizing itself: till the Vacuum<lb/>
                Became element. pliant to rise.<lb/>
                Or to fall, or to swim, or to fly:<lb/>
                With ease searching the dire vacuity<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: III<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: The Lungs heave incessant, dull and<lb/>
                heavy<lb/>
                For as yet were all other parts formless<lb/>
                Shiv’ring: clinging around like a cloud<lb/>
                Dim &amp; glutinous as the white Polypus<lb/>
                Driv’n by waves &amp; englob’d on the tide.<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: And the unformed part crav’d repose<lb/>
                Sleep began: the Lungs heave on the wave<lb/>
                Weary overweigh’d, sinking beneath<lb/>
                In a stifling black fluid he woke<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: He arose on the waters. but soon<lb/>
                Heavy falling his organs like roots<lb/>
                Shooting out from the seed, shot beneath;<lb/>
                And a vast world of waters around him<lb/>
                In furious torrents began.<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: Then he sunk, &amp; around his spent Lungs<lb/>
                Began intricate pipes that drew in<lb/>
                The spawn of the waters. Outbranching<lb/>
<lb/>
                An<lb/>
<lb/>
                An immense Fibrous form, stretching out<lb/>
                Thro’ the bottoms of immensity raging.<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: He rose on the floods: then he smote<lb/>
                The wild deep with his terrible wrath,<lb/>
                Seperating the heavy and thin.<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: Down the heavy sunk; cleaving around<lb/>
                To the fragments of solid; up rose<lb/>
                The thin, flowing round the fierce fires<lb/>
                That glow’d furious in the expanse.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: IV:<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: Then Light first began; from the fires<lb/>
                Beams, conducted by fluid so pure<lb/>
                Flow’d around the Immense: Los beheld<lb/>
                Forthwith writhing upon the dark void<lb/>
                The Back bone of Urizen appear<lb/>
                Hurtling upon the wind<lb/>
                Like a serpent! like an iron chain<lb/>
                Whirling about in the Deep.<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: Upfolding his Fibres together<lb/>
                To a Form of impregnable strength<lb/>
                Los astonish’d and terrified, built<lb/>
                Furnaces; he formed an Anvil<lb/>
                A Hammer of adamant then began<lb/>
                The binding of Urizen day and night<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: Circling round the dark Demon, with<lb/>
                howlings<lb/>
                Dismay &amp; sharp blightings; the Prophet<lb/>
                Of Eternity beat on his iron links<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: And first from those infinite fires<lb/>
                The light that flow’d down on the winds<lb/>
                He siez’d; beating incessant, condensing<lb/>
                The subtil particles in an Orb.<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: Roaring indignant the bright sparks<lb/>
                Endur’d the vast Hammer; but unwearied<lb/>
                Los beat on the Anvil; till glorious<lb/>
                An immense Orb of fire he fram’d<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: Oft he quench’d it beneath in the<lb/>
                Deeps.<lb/>
                Then surveyd the all bright mass: Again<lb/>
                Siezing fires from the terrific Orbs<lb/>
                He heated the round Globe, then beat<lb/>
                While roaring his Furnaces endur’d<lb/>
                The chaind Orb in their infinite wombs<lb/>
<lb/>
                7: Nine ages completed their circles<lb/>
                When Los heated the glowing mass, cast-<lb/>
                -ing<lb/>
                It down into the Deeps: the Deeps fled<lb/>
                Away in redounding smoke; the Sun<lb/>
                Stood self-balanc’d. And Los smild<lb/>
                with joy.<lb/>
                He the vast Spine of Urizen siez’d<lb/>
                And bound down to the glowing illusion<lb/>
<lb/>
                8: But no light. for the Deep fled away<lb/>
                On all sides. and left an unform’d<lb/>
                Dark vacuity; here Urizen lay<lb/>
                In fierce torments on his glowing bed<lb/>
<lb/>
                9: Till his Brain in a rock, &amp; his Heart<lb/>
                In a fleshy slough formed four rivers<lb/>
                Obscuring the immense Orb of fire<lb/>
                Flowing down into night: till a Form<lb/>
                Was completed. a Human Illusion<lb/>
                In darkness and deep clouds involvd.<lb/>
<lb/>
                The End of the<lb/>
                Book of LOS</figTranscr>
<head>30. <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> plates 2, 3, 4, and 5 as quarters of a copper sheet, based on copy
A.</head>
<figDesc>© Copyright the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="31.BA_quarter_with_margins.100" rend="file" width="958" height="717">
	<figTranscr>AHANIA<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: Ist<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: Fuzon. on a chariot iron-wing’d<lb/>
                On spiked flames rose; his hot visage<lb/>
                Flam’d furious! sparkles his hair &amp; beard<lb/>
                Shot down his wide bosom and shoulders<lb/>
                On clouds of smoke rages his chariot<lb/>
                And his right hand burns red in its<lb/>
                cloud<lb/>
                Moulding into a vast globe. his wrath<lb/>
                As the thunder-stone is moulded<lb/>
                Son of Urizens silent burnings<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: Shall we worship this Demon of smoke.<lb/>
                Said Fuzon. this abstract non-entity<lb/>
                This cloudy God seated on waters<lb/>
                Now seen. now obscur’d; King of sorrow?<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: So he spoke. in a fiery flame,<lb/>
                On Urizen frowning indignant,<lb/>
                The Globe of wrath shaking on high<lb/>
                Roaring with fury. he threw<lb/>
                The howling Globe: burning it flew<lb/>
                Lengthning into a hungry beam. Swiftly<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: Oppos’d to the exulting flam’d beam<lb/>
                The broad Disk of Urizen upheav’d<lb/>
                Across the Void many a mile.<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: It was forg’d in mills where the winter<lb/>
                Beats incessant: ten winters the disk<lb/>
<lb/>
                Unremitting endur’d the cold hammer.<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: But the strong arm that sent it. remem-<lb/>
                -ber’d<lb/>
                The sounding beam; laughing it tore through<lb/>
                That beaten mass: keeping its direction<lb/>
                The cold loins of Urizen dividing.<lb/>
<lb/>
                7: Dire shriek’d his invisible Lust<lb/>
                Deep groan’d Urizen! stretching his awful hand<lb/>
                Ahania (so name his parted soul)<lb/>
                He siez’d on his mountains of Jealousy,<lb/>
                He groand anguishd &amp; called her Sin,<lb/>
                Kissing her and weeping over her:<lb/>
                Then hid her in darkness in silence;<lb/>
                Jealous tho’ she was invisible.<lb/>
<lb/>
                8: She fell down a faint shadow wandring<lb/>
                In chaos and circling dark Urizen.<lb/>
                As the moon anguishd circles the earth;<lb/>
                Hopeless! abhorrd! a death-shadow.<lb/>
                Unseen. unbodied. unknown,<lb/>
                The mother of Pestilence.<lb/>
<lb/>
                9: But the fiery beam of Fuzon<lb/>
                Was a pillar of fire to Egypt<lb/>
                Five hundred years wandring on earth<lb/>
                Till Los siezd it and beat in a mass<lb/>
                With the body of the sun.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: II:d<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: But the forehead of Urizen gathering.<lb/>
                And his eyes pale with anguish, his lips<lb/>
                Blue &amp; changing; in tears and bitter<lb/>
                Contrition he prepar’d his Bow.<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: Form’d of Ribs: that in his dark solitude<lb/>
                When obscur’d in his forests fell monsters.<lb/>
                Arose. For his dire Contemplations<lb/>
                Rush’d down like floods from his mountains<lb/>
                In torrents of mud settling thick<lb/>
                With Eggs of unnatural production<lb/>
                Forthwith hatching; some howl’d on his hills<lb/>
                Some in vales; some aloft flew in air<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: Of these: an enormous dread Serpent<lb/>
                Scaled and poisonous horned<lb/>
                Approach’d Urizen even to his knees<lb/>
                As he sat on his dark rooted Oak.<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: With his horns he push’d furious.<lb/>
                Great the conflict &amp; great the jealousy<lb/>
                In cold poisons: but Urizen smote him<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: First he poison’d the rocks with his blood<lb/>
                Then polish’d his ribs, and his sinews<lb/>
                Dried: laid them apart till winter;<lb/>
                Then a Bow black prepar’d; on this Bow.<lb/>
                A poisoned rock plac’d in silence:<lb/>
                He utter’d these words to the Bow.<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: O Bow of the clouds of secresy:<lb/>
                O nerve of that lust form’d monster!<lb/>
                Send this rock swift, invisible thro’<lb/>
                The black clouds, on the bosom of Fuzon<lb/>
<lb/>
                7: So saying, In torment of his wounds.<lb/>
                He bent the enormous ribs slowly;<lb/>
                A circle of darkness! then fixed<lb/>
                The sinew in its rest: then the Rock<lb/>
                Poisonous source! plac’d with art, lifting dif-<lb/>
                -ficult<lb/>
                Its weighty bulk: silent the rock lay.<lb/>
<lb/>
                8: While Fuzon his tygers unloosing<lb/>
<lb/>
                Thought Urizen slain by his wrath.<lb/>
                I am God. said he. eldest of things!<lb/>
<lb/>
                9: Sudden sings the rock. swift &amp; invisible<lb/>
                On Fuzon flew. enter’d his bosom;<lb/>
                His beautiful visage, his tresses.<lb/>
                That gave light to the mornings of heaven<lb/>
                Were smitten with darkness. deform’d<lb/>
                And outstretch’d on the edge of the fo-<lb/>
                -rest<lb/>
<lb/>
                10: But the rock fell upon the Earth,<lb/>
                Mount Sinai. in Arabia.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: III:<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: The Globe shook; and Urizen seated<lb/>
                On black clouds his sore wound anointed<lb/>
                The ointment flow’d down on the void<lb/>
                Mix’d with blood; here the snake gets<lb/>
                her poison<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: With difficulty &amp; great pain; Urizen<lb/>
                Lifted on high the dead corse:<lb/>
                On his shoulders he bore it to where<lb/>
                A Tree hung over the Immensity<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: For when Urizen shrunk away<lb/>
                From Eternals, he sat on a rock<lb/>
                Barren; a rock which himself<lb/>
                From redounding fancies had petrified<lb/>
                Many tears fell on the rock,<lb/>
                Many sparks of vegetation;<lb/>
                Soon shot the pained root<lb/>
                Of Mystery. under his heel:<lb/>
                It grew a thick tree; he wrote<lb/>
                In silence his book of iron:<lb/>
                Till the horrid plant bending its boughs<lb/>
                Grew to roots when it felt the earth<lb/>
                And again sprung to many a tree.<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: Amaz’d started Urizen! when<lb/>
                He beheld himself compassed round<lb/>
                And high roofed over with trees<lb/>
                He arose but the stems stood so thick<lb/>
                He with difficulty and great pain<lb/>
                Brought his Books. all but the Book<lb/>
<lb/>
                Of<lb/>
<lb/>
                Of iron. from the dismal shade<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: The Tree still grows over the Void<lb/>
                Enrooting itself all around<lb/>
                An endless labyrinth of woe!<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: The corse of his first begotten<lb/>
                On the accursed Tree of Mystery:<lb/>
                On the topmost stem of this Tree<lb/>
                Urizen nail’d Fuzons corse.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: IV:<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: Forth flew the arrows of pestilence<lb/>
                Round the pale living Corse on the tree<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: For in Urizens slumbers of abstraction<lb/>
                In the infinite ages of Eternity:<lb/>
                When his Nerves of Joy melted &amp; flow’d<lb/>
                A white Lake on the dark blue air<lb/>
                In perturb’d pain and dismal torment<lb/>
                Now stretching out. now swift conglobing.<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: Effluvia vapor’d above<lb/>
                In noxious clouds: these hover’d thick<lb/>
                Over the disorganiz’d Immortal.<lb/>
                Till petrific pain scurfd o’er the Lakes<lb/>
                As the bones of man, solid &amp; dark<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: The clouds of disease hover’d wide<lb/>
                Around the Immortal in torment<lb/>
                Perching around the hurtling bones<lb/>
                Disease on disease, shape on shape.<lb/>
                Winged screaming in blood &amp; torment.<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: The Eternal Prophet beat on his anvils<lb/>
                Enrag’d in the desolate darkness<lb/>
                He forg’d nets of iron around<lb/>
                And Los threw them around the bones<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: The shapes screaming flutter’d vain<lb/>
                Some combin’d into muscles &amp; glands<lb/>
                Some organs for craving and lust<lb/>
                Most remain’d on the tormented void:<lb/>
                Urizens army of horrors.<lb/>
<lb/>
                7: Round the pale living Corse on the<lb/>
                Tree<lb/>
                Forty years flew the arrows of pestilence<lb/>
<lb/>
                8: Wailing and terror and woe<lb/>
                Ran thro’ all his dismal world:<lb/>
                Forty years all his sons &amp; daughters<lb/>
                Felt their skulls harden: then Asia<lb/>
                Arose in the pendulous deep.<lb/>
<lb/>
                9: They reptilize upon the Earth.<lb/>
<lb/>
                10: Fuzon groand on the Tree.<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: V<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: The lamenting voice of Ahania<lb/>
                Weeping upon the void.<lb/>
                And round the Tree of Fuzon:<lb/>
                Distant in solitary night<lb/>
                Her voice was heard. but no form<lb/>
                Had she: but her tears from clouds<lb/>
                Eternal fell round the Tree<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: And the voice cried: Ah Urizen! Love!<lb/>
                Flower of morning! I weep on the verge<lb/>
                Of Non-entity; how wide the Abyss<lb/>
                Between Ahania and thee!<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: I lie on the verge of the deep.<lb/>
                I see thy dark clouds ascend,<lb/>
                I see thy black forests and floods,<lb/>
                A horrible waste to my eyes!<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: Weeping I walk over rocks<lb/>
                Over dens &amp; thro’ valleys of death<lb/>
                Why didst thou despise Ahania<lb/>
                To cast me from thy bright presence<lb/>
                Into the World of Loneness<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: I cannot touch his hand:<lb/>
                Nor weep on his knees, nor hear<lb/>
                His voice &amp; bow. nor see his eyes<lb/>
                And joy. nor hear his footsteps, and<lb/>
                My heart leap at the lovely sound!<lb/>
                I cannot kiss the place<lb/>
                Whereon his bright feet have trod,<lb/>
<lb/>
                But<lb/>
<lb/>
                But I wander on the rocks<lb/>
                With hard necessity.<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: Where is my golden palace<lb/>
                Where my ivory bed<lb/>
                Where the joy of my morning hour<lb/>
                Where the sons of eternity. singing<lb/>
<lb/>
                7: To awake bright Urizen my king:<lb/>
                To arise to the mountain sport,<lb/>
                To the bliss of eternal valleys:<lb/>
<lb/>
                8: To awake my king in the morn:<lb/>
                To embrace Ahanias joy<lb/>
                On the breath of his open bosom:<lb/>
                From my soft cloud of dew to fall<lb/>
                In showers of life on his harvests.<lb/>
<lb/>
                9: When he gave my happy soul<lb/>
                To the sons of eternal joy:<lb/>
                When he took the daughters of life.<lb/>
                Into my chambers of love:<lb/>
<lb/>
                10: When I found babes of bliss on my beds.<lb/>
                And bosoms of milk in my chambers<lb/>
                Fill’d with eternal seed<lb/>
                O! eternal births sung round Ahania<lb/>
                In interchange sweet of their joys.<lb/>
<lb/>
                11: Swell’d with ripeness &amp; fat with fatness<lb/>
                Bursting on winds my odors.<lb/>
                My ripe figs and rich pomegranates<lb/>
<lb/>
                In infant joy at thy feet<lb/>
                O Urizen sported and sang;<lb/>
<lb/>
                12: Then thou with thy lap full of seed<lb/>
                With thy hand full of generous fire<lb/>
                Walked forth from the clouds of morning<lb/>
                On the virgins of springing joy,<lb/>
                On the human soul to cast<lb/>
                The seed of eternal science,<lb/>
<lb/>
                13: The sweat poured down thy temples<lb/>
                To Ahania return’d in evening<lb/>
                The moisture awoke to birth<lb/>
                My mothers-joys, sleeping in bliss.<lb/>
<lb/>
                14: But now alone over rocks. mountains<lb/>
                Cast out from thy lovely bosom:<lb/>
                Cruel jealousy: selfish fear!<lb/>
                Self-destroying: how can delight.<lb/>
                Renew in these chains of darkness<lb/>
                Where bones of beasts are strown<lb/>
                On the bleak and snowy mountains<lb/>
                Where bones from the birth are buried<lb/>
                Before they see the light.<lb/>
<lb/>
                FINIS</figTranscr>
<head>31. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> plates 3, 4, 5, and 6 as quarters of a copper sheet, based on
copy A.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <pb id="p41-69" n="69"/>
are 27.2 cm. wide. The former sheet was 19.85 cm. left, 19.60 cm. right, 27.2 cm. top, 27.25 cm. bottom; it
yielded plates 3-2/4-5 (illus. 30), with plate 1 etched on the verso of plate 4. The latter sheet was 19.65
cm. left, 19.75 cm. right, 27.2 cm. top, 27.25 cm. bottom; it yielded plates 4-3/6-5 (illus. 31), with plates
1 and 2 on the versos of plates 6 and 3 respectively. <note id="n13">13. Eleven of the 16 plates are between
27.2 and 27.5 cm. in height, 3 are between 26.5 and 26.9 cm., and 2 are between 25.7 and 26.4 cm. Widths range
only between 19.6 and 20.5 cm. I am indebted to Robert Essick for measuring his uncut copy of Blake’s
engravings for Stedman. In most copies, the prints were trimmed to the design and thus shorn of their
platemarks. If the Stedman plates, which were commissioned by the publisher Joseph Johnson, were quarters,
then the platemaker from whom Blake bought the plates was most likely responsible for quartering the sheets,
presumably according to either Johnson’s or Blake’s instructions, and may also have been responsible for
preparing them for intaglio etching by beveling the sides and rounding the corners. According to Mei-Ying
Sung, most of the Book of Job plates were cut by the platemaker, but crossing marks on the versos make it
possible to reassemble them into their original sheets (“Technical and Material Studies of William Blake’s
Engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> [1826],” Nottingham Trent University PhD, 2005,
appendix 1). In some cases, in other words, Blake’s plates can be reconstructed into their original sheets
whether Blake cut the sheets or had them cut for him.</note></p>
            <p>These plate arrangements are not from <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>, where I
used just two measurements per plate and thought the sheet was larger and cut into sixths rather than quarters
(414n26); they are from research done soon afterwards for David Worrall’s <hi rend="i">The Urizen
Books.</hi> I used four measurements per plate and tracings of their shapes to reconstruct the sheets, the
technique I had used to reconstruct the sheets that yielded the 27 plates of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Worrall agreed
with <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> arrangement (191) but not with <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>
arrangement (223n13), which is understandable since measurements, even with tracings, can support different
results. With digital imaging, however, and the expert assistance of Todd Stabley, media consultant for my
university, I was able to verify my earlier findings and to raise the bar for proof. Though it was no easy
task, we were able to put the pieces back together. We verified the recto/verso plates by superimposing them,
as with <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> plates 3 and 2 (illus. e32), to reveal their matched shapes. We
demonstrated, by revolving the plates, how their edges fit together, as evinced by the inside edges of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> plates 3 and 4 (illus. 33) paralleling one another exactly, one curving with the
other. <note id="n14">14. This information about sheet reconstruction was first presented as a plenary address
for William Blake 1794/1994, a conference at St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill, London, 14 July 1994, and
later published as “Evolution.”</note></p>
            <figure n="33.BL3-BL4_intersection.100" rend="file" width="258" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>[o]wn true love<lb/>
<lb/>
                [fla]mes of desire<lb/>
                [l]iving flames<lb/>
                [arm]’d<lb/>
                In the midst<lb/>
                [boun]d in a chain<lb/>
                shadow<lb/>
<lb/>
                [sp]arkles of fury<lb/>
                Los hurls<lb/>
<lb/>
                condens’d<lb/>
                [mounti]ng on high<lb/>
<lb/>
                wide apart<lb/>
                fierce-raging<lb/>
                roll round<lb/>
                [ma]king their way<lb/>
                [shadow]y obscurity<lb/>
<lb/>
                [fir]es; Los remain’d<lb/>
                [an]d fire<lb/>
                [the]y beheld him<lb/>
                [driv]’n by his hands<lb/>
                [neth]er abyss<lb/>
                [in]dignation<lb/>
<lb/>
                [fire]s all was<lb/>
<lb/>
                Dark<lb/>
<lb/>
                Darkness rou[nd]<lb/>
                bound<lb/>
                Into fiery sph[eres]<lb/>
                The gigantic<lb/>
<lb/>
                10: Coldness, d[arkness]<lb/>
                Without fluctu[ation]<lb/>
                Black as mar[ble]<lb/>
                Bound in the<lb/>
                And the seper[ated]<lb/>
                A vast solid<lb/>
                Bound in his<lb/>
<lb/>
                Ch[ap]<lb/>
<lb/>
                1: The Immort[al]<lb/>
                The vast rock<lb/>
                And times; a<lb/>
                Impatient, stif[led]<lb/>
<lb/>
                2: Till impatie[nce]<lb/>
                The hard bon[dage]<lb/>
                solid<lb/>
                With a crash<lb/>
<lb/>
                3: Crack’d ac[ross]<lb/>
                -ments<lb/>
                The Prophetic<lb/>
                Hurls apart.<lb/>
                And crumblin[g]<lb/>
                The black ma[rble]<lb/>
<lb/>
                4: Hurl’d apar[t]<lb/>
                Rock; the inn[umerable]<lb/>
                Fell asunder;<lb/>
                Beneath him<lb/>
<lb/>
                5: Falling, fa[lling]<lb/>
                Sunk precipit[ant]<lb/>
                Times on times<lb/>
                Truth has bou[nds]<lb/>
                falling:<lb/>
                Years on year[s]<lb/>
                Still he fell<lb/>
                Found for fal[ling]<lb/>
                end.<lb/>
                For tho’ day o[r]</figTranscr>
              <head>33. <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> copy A, plates 3 and 4, detail of edges fitting
together within the sheet of copper.</head>
              <figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake
Archive. Used with permission.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>With four plates 27.2 cm. in width (two for <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, one each for 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>), it seemed reasonable to assume that
they were quarters of a sheet the size of—and perhaps acquired at the same time as—those used for the
first color-printed drawings. The problem here, though, was an approximately 8 mm. difference in the heights
of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> plates. If the measurements were correct, then one or both did not fit
into the larger sheet. Moreover, the small, unfinished color print of <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (illus. 10),
recorded as 19.7 × 27.5 cm. (Butlin, cat. 313), was the same height as <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>
sheet, though 2 or 3 mm. wider, which I suspected was mistaken. The similarity of its size to the size of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> made small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> seem likely to have been one of the
quarters or, possibly, a quarter that was cut up to provide the plates for <hi rend="i">The Book of
Ahania.</hi> Superimposing small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> over <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> plates
revealed no convincing traces of small <hi rend="i">Pity.</hi> The digital reconstruction was beginning to
reveal what combination of quarters was likely and unlikely to have come from the same sheet, as well as to
reveal exactly what works I needed to reexamine. In the Morgan Library, I reexamined the height of the text
plates in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy C, along with the size and shape of proofs of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> plates 4 and 5, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> plate 5; in the Library
of Congress, I reexamined <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B and again made tracings of the plates of
the only complete extant copy of <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>; most importantly, in the British
Museum, I examined <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copies A and D, traced the plates of the only extant copy
of <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, and determined exactly the size of the small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> plates.</p>
            <p>This new data enabled me to disprove my initial hypothesis that <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi> plates 3-4 and 6-7 and the plates for <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book
of Los</hi> were quarters of the same large sheet. It enabled me also to ascertain that small 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> was not the <hi rend="i">exact</hi> size of <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> sheet but
that it was one of the quarters. Two measurements for small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> proved insufficient to see
this connection, but with four it became clear: 19.75 cm. left, 19.5 cm. right, 27.2 cm. top, 27.4 cm. bottom.
These are approximately the same measurements as the color-printed impression of <hi rend="i">Albion
rose</hi>, which are 27.2 cm. left, 27.3 cm. right, 19.75 cm. top, 19.95 cm. bottom.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Turn small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> upside down and 
<hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> on its left side, place them on top
<pb id="p41-70" n="70"/>
of <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> sheets (illus. 34), and you have
the four quarters of a sheet that is 39.35 cm. left, 39.7 cm. right, 54.7 cm. top, 54.5 cm. bottom. Along the
middle, vertically and horizontally, the sheet is 39.4 × 54.4 cm. This sheet was cut exactly in half and each
half was cut in half, hence each of the four quarters has a side 27.2 cm. wide or high. <note id="n15">15.
Essick records the plate size as 27.2 × 19.9 cm. (<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 24); Butlin records the
Huntington impression as 27.2 × 19.9 cm. and the British Museum impression as 27.5 × 20.2 cm. (cat. 284,
262.1).</note></p>
            <p>Why did Blake purchase a 39.4 × 54.4 cm. sheet of copper? At first, it may seem that he needed
copper plates for his two new poems, <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of
Los.</hi> The former has 239 lines and the latter has 176 lines, for a total of 415. <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>
is on 28 plates, 11 of which, including the title, are full-page illustrations, leaving 17 text plates for 517
lines. If Blake intended to etch his new poems in relief to match the style and structure of 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, then he would have needed at <hi rend="i">least 22 plates for the two books. Quartering
each quarter of</hi> the large sheet produces 16 plates (or 32 if versos are used), slightly smaller than 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, whose size was determined by its being on the verso of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>
plates, the size of which was determined by <hi rend="i">Approach of Doom</hi> quartered (see Viscomi,
“Evolution” 307).</p>
            <figure n="34.BL-Ahania-Pity-AR_qtr_no_margins.100" rend="file" width="958" height="707">
              <figTranscr>THE<lb/>
                BOOK of<lb/>
                LOS<lb/>
<lb/>
                LAMBETH<lb/>
                Printed by W Blake 1795<lb/>
<lb/>
                LOS<lb/>
<lb/>
                AHANIA</figTranscr>
              <head>34. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania, The Book of Los</hi>, small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>,
and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> digitally reconstructed as quarters into a sheet of copper.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Deducing motive from end results, however, clearly does not work here. The sheet does not
produce plates exactly the size of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, forcing one to ask why not if that was Blake’s
intent. More troubling is that Blake appears to have changed his mind after he quartered the sheet. Three of
the quarters he intended to use for etchings or engravings, as indicated by their rounded corners and beveled
sides, features designed to remove sharp edges that could tear the paper when intaglio plates are printed
under the required pressure. One quarter he intended to use as a relief etching, as indicated by the absence
of these features, which are unnecessary for relief etchings, because they are printed with less pressure.
Given the manner in which the quarters were prepared—whether by Blake or a platemaker following Blake’s
instructions (see note 13)—Blake appears not to have acquired this copper sheet as a poet needing many small
<hi rend="i">relief-etched plates for an illuminated book; he appears to have</hi> acquired it as a
printmaker, with at least two designs, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> and small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, in
mind, as a creative graphic artist who, to date, had executed many separate etchings and engravings, including
<hi rend="i">Head of a Damned Soul</hi> (c. 1790), <hi rend="i">The Accusers (1793), Edward and Elenor</hi>
(1793), <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1793), and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> (1794).</p>
            <pb id="p41-71" n="71"/>
            <p>What Blake originally intended for the other two quarters prepared for intaglio designs is not
known. It is interesting to speculate, though, that the designs may have been <hi rend="i">The Night of
Enitharmon’s Joy</hi> (24.2 × 27.8 cm.) and <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (20.4 × 26.3 cm.), which are the only
other drawings extant that fit the quarters—or could be trimmed to fit—that were also executed, like small
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, approximately four times their size as large color-printed drawings. But whatever the
original plans were for these quarters, Blake changed his mind. He quartered the two quarters and used the
resulting plates for <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania.</hi> This sequence
of events is indicated by the fact that each small plate has just one rounded corner (illus. e35), that of its
original sheet, which, in addition to the plates’ uneven and rough inside edges (illus. 33), is why the
plates can be reconstructed like pieces of a puzzle back into their original quarter sheets (illus. 30, 31).
The edges are rough because Blake did not file them at an angle (the bevel), and though he appears to have
pounded down the sharp edges of the new corners, he did not round them. In other words, Blake did not prepare
the small plates for etching.</p>
            <p>Was he in such a hurry to print his new poems and designs that he ignored these crucial steps
in preparing plates for intaglio printing? Or did he know that he would print with
              <figure n="ahania.a.p6" id="ahania.a.illbk.06" work-copy="ahania.a" rend="db" width="742" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>But I wander on the rocks<lb/>
                With hard necessity.<lb/>
<lb/>
                6: Where is my golden palace<lb/>
                Where my ivory bed<lb/>
                Where the joy of my morning hour<lb/>
                Where the sons of eternity. singing<lb/>
<lb/>
                7: To awake bright Urizen my king:<lb/>
                To arise to the mountain sport,<lb/>
                To the bliss of eternal valleys:<lb/>
<lb/>
                8: To awake my king in the morn:<lb/>
                To embrace Ahanias joy<lb/>
                On the breath of his open bosom:<lb/>
                From my soft cloud of dew to fall<lb/>
                In showers of life on his harvests.<lb/>
<lb/>
                9: When he gave my happy soul<lb/>
                To the sons of eternal joy:<lb/>
                When he took the daughters of life.<lb/>
                Into my chambers of love:<lb/>
<lb/>
                10: When I found babes of bliss on my beds.<lb/>
                And bosoms of milk in my chambers<lb/>
                Fill’d with eternal seed<lb/>
                O! eternal births sung round Ahania<lb/>
                In interchange sweet of their joys.<lb/>
<lb/>
                11: Swell’d with ripeness &amp; fat with fatness<lb/>
                Bursting on winds my odors.<lb/>
                My ripe figs and rich pomegranates<lb/>
<lb/>
                In infant joy at thy feet<lb/>
                O Urizen sported and sang;<lb/>
<lb/>
                12: Then thou with thy lap full of seed<lb/>
                With thy hand full of generous fire<lb/>
                Walked forth from the clouds of morning<lb/>
                On the virgins of springing joy,<lb/>
                On the human soul to cast<lb/>
                The seed of eternal science,<lb/>
<lb/>
                13: The sweat poured down thy temples<lb/>
                To Ahania return’d in evening<lb/>
                The moisture awoke to birth<lb/>
                My mothers-joys, sleeping in bliss.<lb/>
<lb/>
                14: But now alone over rocks. mountains<lb/>
                Cast out from thy lovely bosom:<lb/>
                Cruel jealousy: selfish fear!<lb/>
                Self-destroying: how can delight.<lb/>
                Renew in these chains of darkness<lb/>
                Where bones of beasts are strown<lb/>
                On the bleak and snowy mountains<lb/>
                Where bones from the birth are buried<lb/>
                Before they see the light.<lb/>
<lb/>
                FINIS</figTranscr>
<head>36. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> copy A, plate 6.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="bb85.a.1.ps" id="bb85.a.spb.01" work-copy="bb85.a" rend="db" width="738" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>37. <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, from <hi rend="i">The Large Book of Designs</hi> copy A.</head>
<figDesc>© Copyright the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
less pressure than normal since he planned to use the surface area for color printing, which he did with 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> plates 1, 2, and 6 (illus. 36), and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> plates
1, 2, and 5?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> In <hi rend="i">The
Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> title plates, Blake etched the letters and inked
them locally, wiping the surface around them clean of ink and painting the image between the inscription and
title, presumably following a lightly scratched outline. Blake used the same combination of printing from the
surface and incised lines in the endplates to both books. He knew printing from the surface of an etching
would work, since—as I argue below—he had already done
<pb id="p41-72" n="72"/>
so with <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> (illus. 37), and knew also that he could print surface areas with
incised lines because he had done so in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi>
	<note id="n16">16. If the platemaker had quartered the sheet and beveled the three quarters for Blake, then
Blake’s not beveling the small plates may seem less inconsistent, but it is still highly unorthodox behavior
for an intaglio etcher. I have not encountered intaglio plates with such rough, unbeveled sides before.
Equally unconventionally, Blake etched three of his new plates recto/verso; as we have seen, in relief etching
this was his common practice and something Blake could get away with aesthetically because scratches across
relief lines fill in with ink, whereas scratches across the surface of an intaglio plate fill in with ink and
print as black lines on a white background. Blake was smart, though, in using the versos for the
frontispieces, which he very heavily color printed, and for <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> title plate,
whose background he filled with a dense pattern of swirling lines.</note></p>
            <p>Using the small plates for intaglio etching instead of relief etching enabled Blake to condense
his texts, averaging 59.5 lines per plate for <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and 58.6 for 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, versus 30.4 for <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, and thus use far fewer copper plates.
Using two of the quarters initially prepared for single intaglio designs (as is indicated by the four original
rounded corners per quarter) from this sheet for illuminated plates appears to have been an afterthought,
perhaps reflecting a decision to enlarge the designs originally intended for the quarters in another medium.
Blake’s decision to etch the small plates in intaglio rather than in relief appears to reflect the influence
of another quarter from the sheet, <hi rend="i">Albion rose.</hi> But before we can examine how those three
quarters as used connect with one another, we need to understand the role played by small 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, the quarter that appears to have been the first executed.</p>
            <figure n="urizen.c.p17-19" id="urizen.c.illbk.17" work-copy="urizen.c" rend="db" width="689" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>They call’d her Pity, and fled<lb/>
<lb/>
                11. “Spread a Tent. with strong cur-<lb/>
                -tains around them<lb/>
                “Let cords &amp; stakes bind in the Void<lb/>
                That Eternals may no more behold them”<lb/>
<lb/>
                12, They began to weave curtains of<lb/>
                darkness<lb/>
                They erected large pillars round the Void<lb/>
                With golden hooks fastend in the pillars<lb/>
                With infinite labour the Eternals<lb/>
                A woof wove. and called it Science<lb/>
<lb/>
                Chap: VI.<lb/>
<lb/>
                1. But Los saw the Female &amp; pitied<lb/>
                He embrac’d her, she wept, she refus’d<lb/>
                In perverse and cruel delight<lb/>
                She fled from his arms, yet he followd<lb/>
<lb/>
                2, Eternity shudder’d when they saw,<lb/>
                Man begetting his likeness.<lb/>
                On his own divided image.<lb/>
<lb/>
                3, A time passed over, the Eternals<lb/>
                Began to erect the tent;<lb/>
                When Enitharmon sick,<lb/>
                Felt a Worm within her womb.<lb/>
<lb/>
                4. Yet helpless it lay like a Worm<lb/>
                In the trembling womb<lb/>
                To be moulded into existence<lb/>
<lb/>
                5, All day the worm lay on her bosom<lb/>
                All night within her womb<lb/>
                The worm lay till it grew to a ser-<lb/>
                -pent<lb/>
                With dolorous hissings &amp; poisons<lb/>
                Round Enitharmons loins folding,<lb/>
<lb/>
                6, Coild within Enitharmons womb<lb/>
                The serpent grew casting its scales<lb/>
                With sharp pangs the hissings began<lb/>
                To change to a grating cry,<lb/>
                Many sorrows and dismal throes,<lb/>
                Many forms of fish, bird &amp; beast,<lb/>
                Brought forth an Infant form<lb/>
                Where was a worm before.<lb/>
<lb/>
                7. The Eternals their tent finished<lb/>
                Alarm’d with these gloomy visions<lb/>
                When Enitharmon groaning<lb/>
                Produc’d a man Child to the light,<lb/>
<lb/>
                8. A shriek ran thro’ Eternity:<lb/>
                And a paralytic stroke;<lb/>
                At the birth of the Human shadow,<lb/>
<lb/>
                9. Delving earth in his resistless<lb/>
                way;<lb/>
                Howling, the Child with fierce flames<lb/>
                Issu’d from Enitharmon.<lb/>
<lb/>
                10. The Eternals, closed the tent<lb/>
                They beat down the stakes the cords</figTranscr>
              <head>38. <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> copy C, plate 19.</head>
              <figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">IV. Small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi></hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>For small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> to have been printed from a quarter of a large copper sheet
means, of course, that its matrix is copper and not millboard, but neither is it a “completely bare
plate”. (Butlin, “Physicality” 4). The evidence that small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> is from a metal plate
lies also in the faintly embossed lines in the horses’ hind legs, tail, and front leg, and at the head of
the supine figure (visible in the verso), the very slight embossment of the relief plateau. Knowing that small
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> is from a copper plate in slight relief and not completely bare helps to explain an
apparent anomaly in the sequencing of the large color prints and to verify Butlin’s initial intuition
regarding their evolution.</p>
            <p>Butlin initially believed that <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> was Blake’s first large color-printed
drawing, because it “developed from the small trial print, the only such try-out that is known, and this in
turn was preceded by two composition sketches . . . the first of which is an upright composition, showing that
at this stage Blake had
<pb id="p41-73" n="73"/>
not yet evolved the format for the series of large prints.” In these works (sketches, trial proof, finished
impression), “one does seem to see Blake developing a completely new composition in a relatively short time
from upright drawing to large horizontal color print in a way that suggests a direct evolution rather than the
reuse of earlier material as found in others of the prints, and hence the real point of origin for the
series.” And yet, if so, why is small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, “the . . . trial print,” followed by 
<hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>, the first color-printed drawing, and not <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>? This Butlin
cannot answer: “Whether this origin, in a totally new design, has any significance for the meaning of the
series as a whole I leave for others to speculate” (“Physicality” 5).</p>
            <p>Treating small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> as a sketch that immediately preceded the larger 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> is logical, especially if you think that it too is from a “bare plate.” On the other
hand, placing the trial proof <hi rend="i">after</hi> the first color-printed drawing makes no sense,
especially if it is the “real point of origin for the series,” for it then becomes a “try-out” for 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> alone and not the “experiment” in color printing “on a larger scale” that Butlin
also assumes (cat. 313). The material evidence, however, indicates that both the experimental small 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and the first color-printed drawing are from copper plates, each etched in very slight to
low relief, the former leading technically and materially to the latter. Indeed, small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>
is the “experiment” and “origin” that Butlin assumes. The mystery, however, lies not in Blake’s
following small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> with a “totally new design” (many sketches are not fully realized
until much later), or moving from “bare plate” to relief outline to bare plates or millboards (that
progression is an illusion), but rather in his following small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>’s failure at defining
form through blocks of color with a return to reliefetched outline, as used in illuminated books, before
figuring out true planographic printing. As an experiment, small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> is specifically about
working out how best to define forms in large color prints, which is to say, less about format and composition
than technique and style.</p>
            <p>True, small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> differs in format and design from everything color printed
to that point; it is horizontal and a tryout for prints four times its size. It borrows from earlier works,
though, even while attempting new things. Small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> is divided into top and bottom halves
that were inked in different colors (illus. 10). This in itself was not unusual, since two inks, as in sky and
ground, were commonly used in color printing aquatint landscapes. Moreover, in 1794 Blake had color printed
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> in this style, with page designs divided into texts and vignettes and inked in
different colors. For example, he inked the bottom half (text) of plate 19 from <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> copy
C (illus. 38) in an olive green and the top half (figures) in yellow ochre; one can see that his dabber inked
the figures’ outlines and touched down in their shallows, creating a wide white line along the base of the
outline, indicating that he inked shallows and outlines together and that the relief was slightly higher here
than in <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam.</hi> He went over the background in an olive green ink or color,
defining the yellow ochre figures as negative spaces, or cavities within the ground. Plate 23 demonstrates
more clearly this style of defining form (illus. 39).
              <figure n="urizen.c.p20-23" id="urizen.c.illbk.20" work-copy="urizen.c" rend="db" width="706" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>1 Urizen. C. VIII.<lb/>
                Of life on his forsaken mountains<lb/>
<lb/>
                2, And his world teemd vast enormities<lb/>
                Frightning: faithless; fawning<lb/>
                Portions of life; similitudes<lb/>
                Of a foot, or a hand, or a head<lb/>
                Or a heart, or an eye, they swam mis<lb/>
                -chevous<lb/>
                Dread terrors! delighting in blood<lb/>
<lb/>
                3. Most Urizen sicken’d to see<lb/>
                His eternal creations appear<lb/>
                Sons &amp; daughters of sorrow on mountains<lb/>
                Weeping! wailing! first Thiriel appear’d<lb/>
                Astonish’d at his own existence<lb/>
                Like a man from a cloud born, &amp; Utha<lb/>
                From the waters emerging, laments!<lb/>
<lb/>
                Grodna rent the deep earth howling<lb/>
                Amaz’d! his heavens immense cracks<lb/>
                Like the ground parch’d with heat; then<lb/>
                Fuzon<lb/>
                Flam’d out! first begotten, last born.<lb/>
                All his eternal sons in like manner<lb/>
                His daughters from green herbs &amp; cattle<lb/>
                From monsters, &amp; worms of the pit.<lb/>
<lb/>
                4, He in darkness clos’d, view’d all his<lb/>
                race<lb/>
                And his soul sicken’d! he curs’d<lb/>
                Both sons &amp; daughters; for he saw<lb/>
                That no flesh nor spirit could keep<lb/>
                His iron laws one moment.<lb/>
<lb/>
                5. For he saw that life liv’d upon<lb/>
                death</figTranscr>
<head>39. <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> copy C, plate 23.</head>
<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="40.urizen.C.23.100" rend="file" width="679" height="1000">
	<head>40. <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> copy C, plate 23, digitally enhanced to appear as a
relief-etched copper plate and to emphasize relief areas and cavities.</head>
<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p41-74" n="74"/>
<figure n="41.BUT313.1.1.CPD.100" rend="file" width="958" height="688">
	<head>41. Small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, digitally enhanced to appear as a shallowly etched relief copper
plate and to emphasize relief areas and cavities.</head>
<figDesc>© Copyright the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
Again, Blake inked the plate’s top and bottom halves in different colors and went over the bottom with a
darker color to differentiate background and figure, carefully leaving the white of the paper to form
Urizen’s robe (it is finished in white and gray colors in other impressions). Note, from the waist down,
Urizen is a blank triangular shallow defined by its background, by solid blocks or areas painted in stop-out
varnish and etched in relief (illus. 40). Blake had used this style of defining form in 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, also of 1794, plates 5, 8, and 14, and very rudimentarily in <hi rend="i">America</hi>
plate 2.</p>
            <p>Small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> uses this style to define form on a larger scale. Instead of bold
outlines to delineate figures, it uses blocks of colors, leaving the forms as white or negative space to be
finished in pen and ink and watercolors (illus. 41). In other words, production is divided into two stages,
each stage producing a different visual effect: in the print stage, forms are blocked out in thick, mottled
colors printed from the relief surface; in the finishing stage, forms left unprinted are washed in and defined
in pen and ink. Small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> fails as a technical experiment because too much is left
unprinted—nearly 50% of the composition—leaving too much for finishing, resulting in white areas whose
flat, thin watercolors contrast poorly with thick, mottled, <hi rend="i">alla prima</hi> paint surfaces. The
combination of water-colors over or adjacent to thick colors in the smaller illuminated plates works well, but
here, on the larger surface plane, the allocation of the different media to different areas makes the surface
visually incoherent.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> In short, small
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> printed but left uncolored is incomplete in ways that are not true of illuminated
plates, etchings, or color-printed drawings. <note id="n17">17. Perhaps Blake’s painting the horse’s rump
sky blue was sign enough that the forms were poorly defined. He could have fixed the mistake by going over the
blue in darker colors, but he chose to leave the impression unfinished, probably because even dark washes over
a relatively large space would have appeared flat next to the thick, mottled paint printed from the
plate.</note></p>
            <p>Large color-printed drawings require finishing in pen and ink and watercolors (particularly in
second impressions), often to keep the images from looking like blots and blurs, but it is just that,
finishing; printing and coloring are not separate stages, but are instead integrated in the initial execution
of the design in paint on the plate. Form is defined through line and 
<pb id="p41-75" n="75"/>
colors together on the plate and then clarified, strengthened, and/or adorned further on the paper. The design
on the matrix, in other words, already closely resembles the painting it will become rather than the basis for
one. Matrix as organically unfolding painting would have described <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> (though
of course not if its outline were printed separately from its colors), and most evidently the millboard
designs that followed. As a design, small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> could not be realized or completed without an
inordinate amount of additional work that went far beyond the usual finishing, which is presumably why Blake
left it unfinished, realizing that constructing designs out of printing and painting produced aesthetically
inchoate textures and was not analogous to producing illuminated prints, where watercolor washes supplemented
autonomous designs instead of completing them. His experiment was moving him in the opposite direction from
the large painterly compositions he was envisioning.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n18">18. In the Tate’s version of <hi rend="i">Lamech and His Two Wives</hi>, “virtually the
whole image has been printed, with no reserves of paper left for finishing in watercolour.” This “seems to
be a considerably more developed form of the technique” than used in <hi rend="i">Naomi Entreating Ruth and
Orpah</hi>, “which argues that this print [<hi rend="i">Lamech</hi>] was made late in the series” (McManus
and Townsend 96). In <hi rend="i">Naomi, God Judging Adam</hi>, and other prints, Blake left the figures or
parts of them unprinted/unpainted to use the white of the paper, often in conjunction with white pigments, for
highlights and contrast, but these are small areas relative to the composition and do not produce visually
discordant surface textures.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">V. <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Book</hi>[<hi
rend="i">s</hi>] <hi rend="i">of Designs</hi></hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Butlin believes that <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> also influenced the large color-printed
drawings, and again he is right, but not entirely as he supposes. <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> is one of two
etchings and 30 illuminated plates with masked-out texts color printed on papers of two different sizes for
Ozias Humphry. Blake refers to the impressions only as “a selection from the different Books of such as
could be Printed without the Writing” (Erdman, <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry</hi> 771); we refer to them as
the <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Large Book of Designs.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref><hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, from the
latter, was color printed from the surface, with its incised lines not printed but used as guidelines for
painting. In the catalogue, Butlin dates copies A of <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> and <hi rend="i">Large
Book</hi> 1794 because the date on <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> plate 1 in the former was left as printed,
“1794.” He dates copies B of both <hi rend="i">Book</hi>[<hi rend="i">s</hi>] 1796 because the printed
date was altered in pen to “1796” (cat. 260). Bindman does the same and believes the two copies of 
<hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> represent different projects and motives years apart, with copy A serving as a
“sampler of his best designs” to “demonstrate his colour-printing process,” and copy B possibly
“some kind of emblem book [compiled] out of a selection of his designs” (476). Most of the B impressions,
however, are second pulls, impressions pulled from the plate while ink and colors were still wet, which means
they cannot be years apart. Butlin recognizes this fact in a later article (“Physicality” 3), but uses the
unaltered 1794 date on the <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> title plate in copy A for both sets of impressions. Thus,
he considers 1794 as the date when “the illustrations literally broke free” of the accompanying texts. He
also notes that <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> included three subjects “based on independent engravings; the
distinction between books and independent works was beginning to break down” (3). But a printed date does
not date a printing session, as nearly any reprinted illuminated book demonstrates. The altered date of 1796
is more trustworthy than the printed “1794” because it bears Blake’s autograph (a similarly penned-in
date of “1790” on plate 3 of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> copy F proved reliable); even if treated like the
“1795” written on color prints produced c. 1804, it would signify the conception of the series and not the
individual parts. Moreover, a project such as this one, where a selection of plates was reprinted without
text, would have been an anomaly in 1794, because Blake was just beginning to reprint books and had not yet
color printed from the surface of intaglio plates. <note id="n19">19. The <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi>
consisted of 23 impressions pulled from <hi rend="i">Urizen, Marriage, Thel</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, on Whatman 1794 paper 26 × 19 cm.; the <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> consisted of
plates from <hi rend="i">Urizen, Visions</hi>, separate relief plates of <hi rend="i">America</hi> plate d and
<hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching</hi>, and two etchings, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, on Whatman 1794 paper cut to 34.5 × 24.5 cm. Humphry, a renowned miniaturist,
appears to have already owned color-printed <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy H and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy D
as well as monochrome <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy H, which may explain why plates from these books were not
in the <hi rend="i">Book</hi>[<hi rend="i">s</hi>] <hi rend="i">of Designs</hi>, despite the obvious
suitability of <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> designs for such a project. For more
information about the <hi rend="i">Book</hi>[<hi rend="i">s</hi>] <hi rend="i">of Designs</hi> and their
connection to the large color-printed drawings, see Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>
302-04.</note></p>
            <p>Neither color-printed impression of <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> could have been printed in
1794, since the plate appears not to have been cut from its sheet until 1795, along with the plates for small
<hi rend="i">Pity, The Book of Los</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania.</hi> Both color-printed
impressions are in the first state and “were very probably produced in 1795-1796 when Blake seems to have
done most of his work in that medium” (Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 28). No monochrome
impression of the first state is extant. On the basis of the similarity in style to <hi rend="i">The
Accusers</hi> (1793) and <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> (1793), Essick dates the first state of 
<hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> c. 1793 (<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 28). This date can now be changed to 1795
and may explain why no monochrome impressions in the first state are extant: Blake color printed the plate
before printing it in intaglio (though he probably proofed the plate during its progress and the proofs, like
most proofs, are not extant). On the basis of textual and graphic evidence, Essick dates the second state of
the plate (illus. 42a) no earlier than c. 1804 and possibly later than c. 1818. Albion, mentioned in the
inscription, does not appear as a person in “Blake’s poetry until some of the later revisions of 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript, probably made after 1800, and in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, begun about
1803” (<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 28). Moreover, the inscription has a left-pointing serif on the
letter g, which, according to Erdman’s hypothesis, Blake used consistently between c. 1791 and
1803.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> However,
<pb id="p41-76" n="76"/>
visual effects such as the burnished halo behind Albion’s head Essick associates with the influence of
Linnell, leading him to suggest a possible post-1818 date as well (private correspondence). <note id="n20">20.
See David V. Erdman, “Dating Blake’s Script: The ‘g’ Hypothesis,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 3.1
(1969): 8-13. The inscription reads: “Albion rose from where he labourd at the Mill with Slaves / Giving
himself for the Nations he danc’d the dance of Eternal Death.” Essick notes that the imagery in the
inscription echoes that used in a letter to William Hayley, 23 October 1804, in which he likens himself to
“a slave bound in a mill among beasts and devils” who has been “again enlightened with the light [he]
enjoyed in [his] youth” (<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 28). The inscription reveals Blake returning to
an earlier image and reinterpreting it (or remembering it as an idealized self-portrait), as he did with 
<hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi> (1773, c. 1810-20), <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>
(1793, c. 1805-10), and <hi rend="i">Mirth</hi> (c. 1816-20, 1820-27).</note></p>
            <p>Yet something is not quite right here. Because the etched lines are visible in the second,
lighter color-printed impression when examined in strong light, Essick could ascertain that the first state
“lacked the bat-winged moth, worm, and shafts of light radiating from the figure .... The horizontal
hatching lines of the background seem to have extended much closer to the head and shoulders of the figure . .
.” (<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 24). He also notes that Blake added a hill under the figure’s right
foot without deleting the horizontal background lines, as he did when he added the moth. While the inscription
may be c. 1804 or later, these design changes—halo, shafts of light, and hill—are likely to have been c.
1795, because they follow the color print’s coloring so closely, as is demonstrated by placing a
transparency of the color print over the second state (illus. 42b). Blake appears to have used the color print
as a model for the changes he made in the plate, but he is unlikely to have waited nine or more years to make
these changes. The copy A impression was in Humphry’s possession by 1796 and the copy B impression appears
to have been “one of the prints by Blake acquired in August 1797 by Dr. James Curry, a friend of
Humphry’s” (Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 25; see also Bentley, “Dr. James Curry as a Patron
of Blake,” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 27 [1980]: 71-73). Also, Blake seems to have used scrapers
and burnishers conventionally, to erase lines and smooth surfaces so he could etch new forms, like the moth,
and not radically, as he did in the second states of <hi rend="i">Mirth, Job</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, where he created dramatic and painterly visual effects that do indeed appear to reflect
the influence of Linnell.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n21">21. For Blake’s radical use of burnishers to create stark contrasts of blacks and whites and
its association with Linnell, see Essick, <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>, chapters 13 and 16, and Essick,
“John Linnell.” The technique’s use in <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, however, seems more practical than
painterly, and the resulting play of light less dramatic than in those others revised late in life.</note></p>
            <figure n="42a.ESVII.1.2C.SP.100" rend="file" width="743" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>WB inv 1780</figTranscr>
              <head>42a. <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, second state.</head>
              <figDesc>© Copyright the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="42b.albion.rose.cp.mono.100" rend="file" width="743" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>WB inv 1780</figTranscr>
              <head>42b. <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, transparency of color print laid over second state of
the plate to show alignment of colors with changes made in the second state.</head>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p41-77" n="77"/>
            <p>Moreover, the worm, whose significance may be explained by a passage in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 55:36-37 (Essick, <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 29), is visually similar to the
worms in <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi> (1793) plates 1 and 18 and in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
plate 3. More interestingly, the bat-winged moth in the second state (illus. 42a) may have been influenced by
the bat-winged moth in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> plates 3-4 (illus. 43). This image has heretofore
been unrecorded because it appears in the middle of the horizontal plate and was masked out during printing;
it is digitally recreated from traces in the plate 3 impression of copy E and plate 4 of copy B. The first
state of <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> has always been thought to precede <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>,
but knowing that both works are from 1795 requires rethinking their sequence. If the second state of 
<hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> was influenced by <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>’s moth, then the first state
of <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> was executed <hi rend="i">before The Song of Los</hi> text plates, which in
turn suggests that the plates cut from the same sheet as <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>—including those for
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>—also precede <hi rend="i">The
Song of Los.</hi> This sequence for the books agrees with other, stronger evidence given below.</p>
            <p>Blake appears to have color printed <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> before printing it in
intaglio. More importantly, it is the first intaglio plate he color printed. Misdating <hi rend="i">Large
Book</hi>, with its two etchings, 1794 instead of 1796 has obscured this likelihood and its significance.
Blake color printed only two other etchings, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi> and <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the
Pope in Hell</hi>, and appears to have done so after <hi rend="i">Albion rose.</hi> The first state of the
former is dated 5 June 1793; the two color-printed impressions extant are in the second state (Essick, 
<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 31) and were part of the <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi>, which Blake appears to
have put together in 1796 by commission. No monochrome impressions of the second state are extant, which
suggests that the color printing of <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi> for <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> may have
provided the opportunity to make changes in the plate. <hi rend="i">Lucifer</hi> exists in a touched proof,
with lots of pencil work in the first state and a monochrome impression in the second state.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> The one color-printed impression is
presumably in the second state (the colors are too thick to see through and the image is pasted down on a
thick sheet of paper). Essick dates the plate c. 1794 because it seems to share themes and motifs with 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794), but he also recognizes that it differs stylistically from the other political
prints, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, in that, while executed in their
energetic etched 
              <figure n="43.sl.butterfly.100" rend="file" width="592" height="757">
	<figTranscr>[Afri]can<lb/>
<lb/>
                And all t[he]<lb/>
                Before th[eir]<lb/>
<lb/>
                Thus the terr[ible]<lb/>
                Laws &amp; Re[ligions]<lb/>
                And more to<lb/>
                Till a Philos[ophy]<lb/>
                Urizen wept<lb/>
<lb/>
                Clou[ds]<lb/>
                And<lb/>
                Of A[sia]<lb/>
                The</figTranscr>
<head>43. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, butterfly in recreated design for plates 3-4, detail, based on
copies E and B.</head>
</figure>
style, it makes “more use of enlarged versions of such conventional patterns as worm lines and cross
hatching, much as in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> plates of 1796-1797” (<hi rend="i">Separate
Plates</hi> 43). I agree and think <hi rend="i">Lucifer</hi> is c. 1796 and probably color printed that year,
along with the other works for the <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> and <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi>, though it
was not part of either series, no doubt excluded for having a horizontal rather than vertical format. 
<note id="n22">22. The recently rediscovered proof is in the Essick Collection; it was unknown at the time Essick
wrote his <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> catalogue, which lists only one state for the plate
(41-42).</note></p>
            <p>In 1796, Blake appears to have built a series of color prints around <hi rend="i">Albion
rose</hi>, taking stock of his etchings and relief etchings and transforming 30 of them into miniature
paintings to make up the two series for Humphry. Twenty-two years later, in a 9 June 1818 letter to Dawson
Turner, he remembered the project this way:</p>
            <p>Those I Printed for M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Humphry are a selection from the different Books of
such as could be Printed without the Writing tho to the Loss of some of the best things[.] For they when
Printed perfect accompany Poetical Personifications &amp; Acts without which Poems they never could have been
Executed[.]</p>
            <p>He then describes the color-printed drawings as:</p>
            <p>12 Large Prints Size of Each about 2 feet by 1 &amp; 1/2 Historical &amp; Poetical Printed in
Colours[.] . . . These last 12 Prints are unaccompanied by any writing[.] (Erdman, <hi rend="i">Complete
Poetry</hi> 771)</p>
            <p>For Blake, the illuminated plates “Printed without the Writing” and the large color prints
“unaccompanied by any writing” are clearly related projects. They are also, as Blake tells Turner,
“sufficient to have gained me great reputation as an Artist which was the chief thing Intended.” Butlin
recognizes that the projects are connected and has done more to champion their importance to Blake’s
reputation as an artist than any other Blake scholar. He has argued, though, that the small works evolved into
the larger works and thus, as noted, considers 1794 as the start of Blake’s illustrations breaking free of
text (“Physicality” 3). But, as shown here, the smaller monotypes are from 1796, not 1794, and found their
precedent and inspiration in the larger monotypes of 1795. And like their prototypes, the later, smaller
impressions were colored “with a degree of splendour and force, as almost to resemble sketches in
oil-colours . . . all of which are peculiarly remarkable for their strength and splendour of
colouring.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Indeed, the
color-printed drawings,
<pb id="p41-78" n="78"/>
large and small, are to oil sketches what relief etchings are to drawings. They are prints in which Blake
incorporated the tools and techniques of painting, just as in illuminated prints he used the tools and
processes of drawing and writing. The prints in the <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> and <hi rend="i">Large
Book</hi> are not only “free of text,” but they differ even from the color-printed illuminated plates of
1794 by having been produced in a more overtly painterly manner, no doubt influenced by the larger prints of
1795. This painterliness in the small and large monotypes is no mere illusion, as it would be if the
impressions were assembled from separately printed outline and colors. <note id="n23">23. Richard Thomson’s
description of the <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> for J. T. Smith’s <hi rend="i">Nollekens and His Times</hi>,
as quoted in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 621.</note></p>
            <p>Butlin’s premise that the large monotypes of 1795 grew out of smaller works is correct, but
his choice of smaller works is partly mistaken. The candidates are the illuminated books color printed in
1794, or small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> of 1795. Blake first prints in colors
in 1794, printing the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> sections of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copies F, G, H, T, and
B, C, D, and E (the two sets in that order); <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copies B, C, D, E, F, and G; 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> copies A, C, D, E, F, and J; and possibly <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi> copies F and R and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> copies E and F.
He color printed <hi rend="i">The Book of Los, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
in 1795. The last of these, as we shall see, is likely to have been executed concurrently with or after the
large color-printed drawings and under the influence of their format and technique, whereas the first two
books are etchings that appear to have been executed before the color-printed drawings but after 
<hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, as indicated by Blake’s change of mind regarding the original quarter sheets used
to provide their plates. Many significant differences exist between color printing relief etchings and
intaglio etchings. With the former, Blake is inking plates as prints and adding colors to inked and uninked
areas. He behaved even more radically with the latter works. Blake is not inking the plate; he is painting it,
using etched lines as guidelines, but he is also free to improvise at will, as he did with hill and halo in
<hi rend="i">Albion rose.</hi> Nothing like these had ever been produced before and no analogous printing
process exists.</p>
            <p>Recognizing <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> as a product of 1795 rather than 1794, as the first
color-printed intaglio plate, and as cut from the same sheet as small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> helps us to see
it and small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> more clearly as experiments in color printing that reveal the technical
problem Blake is attempting to solve. He, as intaglio etcher and relief etcher, quarters a large sheet of
copper and prepares three plates for intaglio and one for relief. He uses the relief etching to experiment
with creating a matrix capable of being color printed as a relatively large composition. He needs to scale up
in size his earlier experiments; to date, he has color printed from both the surface and from the surface and
shallows simultaneously of relief etchings. He needs to figure out how to define forms on larger surfaces in
the new marriage of print and painting that he was then envisioning. Were forms to be blocked out in low flat
relief, as in small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, in relief outline, as in illuminated plates, or in incised
outline, as in <hi rend="i">Albion rose? Albion rose</hi> can be printed without colors or finishing, but
small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> cannot; the latter work was designed with color printing in mind while the former
probably was not. As Blake was beginning to experiment with scaling up his color prints, however, he put 
<hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> to double use, testing its suitability for large printed paintings by painting the
design and printing it. The idea to color print <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> from its surface instead of
printing it as an etching may have occurred to Blake during its execution or after recognizing the failure of
small <hi rend="i">Pity.</hi></p>
            <p>The basic principle, one could argue, for inventing large monotypes is present in color
printing relief etchings, but, in practice, Blake is closer to working up flat areas and defining forms
through colors when color printing intaglio etchings. Does this mean <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> was more
influential in what followed than small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>? Yes and no. The intaglio etching appears
directly to have influenced the choice of medium and color printing technique of <hi rend="i">The Book of
Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>—works one quarter the size of <hi rend="i">Albion
rose</hi>—but not the color-printed drawings, which are four times its size. Interesting, in this regard, is
Blake’s never having color printed the intaglio engravings that are the size of the color prints, like 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, perhaps finding the dense line systems unsuited for the open
and painterly compositions he was then creating—or because such surfaces proved more difficult to use than
gesso’s striated surfaces. In any event, he apparently decided not to use etched outlines for his large
printed paintings, following small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> with <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam.</hi> What, then,
leads to true planographic printing, which lies, technically speaking, somewhere between small 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>?</p>
            <p>Blake possibly went from small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> to <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> and
returned to <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> to think more on the problem of defining form. The idea of a
non-printable outline—neither in relief nor intaglio—but paintable along with blocks of colors could have
grown out of painting and printing <hi rend="i">Albion rose.</hi> Alternatively, it could have grown out of
painting over a low relief outline of <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> and realizing that the outline’s
function could be served planographically, that it was the painting over the outline rather than printing the
outline that mattered most. Once Blake made that discovery, returning to color print an intaglio etching or
moving to the planographic printing of <hi rend="i">Elohim</hi> or <hi rend="i">Satan</hi> and then to
millboards must have come quickly.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">VI. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> Reconsidered</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Determining the exact sequence of development in Blake’s monotyping may be impossible,
because planographic printing can evolve out of painting the surface of an etching, using the incised lines as
guidelines, or vice versa. However, the use of one sheet of copper to produce both small 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, two plates representing different technical solutions to
defining forms needed for printing large monotypes, does help us sequence the illuminated books of 1795. The
size of the sheet may have influenced the size of the subsequent sheets acquired for the color prints. Recall
that Blake described the “Size of Each” of his “12 Large Prints” at “about 2 feet by 1 &amp; 1/2”
(Erdman, <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry</hi> 771). Since these 
<pb id="p41-79" n="79"/>
<figure n="44.song.of.los.B.8.striations.100" rend="file" width="958" height="879">
	<head>44. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 8, detail.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
works are horizontal, we should record this as 18 × 24 in. This is a rough approximation, but each work is
within one and a quarter inch in height and three inches in width of this approximation. The smallest, 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, is 16.75 × 21.25 in. (42.5 × 53.9 cm.), approximately the same size as <hi rend="i">God
Judging Adam</hi>, presumably the first, which is 17 × 21 in. (43.2 × 53.5 cm.); the largest, 
<hi rend="i">House of Death</hi>, is 19 × 24 in. (48.5 × 61 cm.); the widest, <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi>,
is 17.5 × 24.4 in. (44.6 × 62 cm.).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">24</ref> At 39.4 × 54.4 cm. (15.5 × 21.4 in.), the copper sheet yielding small 
<hi rend="i">Pity, Albion rose, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> fits squarely
within the average of the first color-printed drawings, but is shorter, on average, by 3.5 cm. Assuming the
copper sheet used for <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> plates 3-4 and 6-7 was a half sheet, then the full
sheet, at 43.5 × 54.4 cm., fits within both height and width of color-printed drawings. Relative to the
copper sheets and millboards used in 1795, it fits the series while the shorter sheet, which yielded works
whose printing directly influenced the technique and printing of the large color-printed drawings, does not.
Similarly sized sheets for a projected series suggest a similar date of purchase; the shorter sheet appears
not only to have been worked on before those of the series, but also to have been acquired apart from them,
which further supports the thesis that <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of
Ahania</hi> were composed and executed before the larger relief-etched text plates of <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi>, which in turn preceded their illustrations, plates 1, 2, 5, and 8. <note id="n24">24. The widths
vary 8.5 cm., ranging from approximately 53.5 cm. (four), 57.5 cm. (one), 58.1 cm. (two), 59.4 cm. (one) to
60-62 cm. (four); height varies only 6 cm., ranging from 42.5 to 44.6 cm. (ten), and 46 to 48.5 cm.
(two).</note></p>
            <p>Assuming Blake treated the sheet yielding <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> plates 3-4 and 6-7
like the one for <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, i.e., cutting it
in half, then the unused half would also be approximately 43.5-8 × 27.2-5 cm. Cutting this half to provide
the coppers for <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> plates 2/5 and 1/8 appears logical, but to have done so
would have meant wasting precious metal, because 24.2 × 17.4 cm. (2/5) and 23.6 × 17.5 cm. (1/8) do not fit
without lots of awkward trimming. Moreover, plates 2/5 and 1/8 do not fit together; they were not conjoined in
a sheet. Thus, while technically possible, economically it made no sense—and as his recto-verso etching
demonstrates, Blake was very practical in his use of copper. He may have bought just half the sheet, intending
to halve it for <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> text plates, or bought the whole sheet and used the other
half or pieces from it later.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref>
However he used it, plates 2/5 and 1/8 appear certainly not to have been cut out of it, which supports the
evidence below that they were not copper but millboards. <note id="n25">25. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Child of
Nature</hi> (1818), known from a unique impression, is 43.3 × 27.5 cm., the size of the half sheet. Other
possible configurations include the <hi rend="i">Moore &amp; Co. Advertisement</hi>, c. 1797-98 (Essick, 
<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 47), along with some practice plates for Thomas Butts (see Essick, 
<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 211-12). Blake reused parts of the <hi rend="i">Moore</hi> plate years later for
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 64, which is the recto of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 96 (Essick, 
<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> 48).</note></p>
            <p>Plates 1 and 8 were planographically printed; no relief lines or marks are present in the
versos of any impressions from either plate. No traces of incised lines are seen through the impression in
strong light, as can be seen in the copy B impression of <hi rend="i">Albion rose.</hi> Blake either lightly
etched or scratched
<pb id="p41-80" n="80"/>
<figure n="s-los.a.p5" id="s-los.a.illbk.05" work-copy="s-los.a" rend="db" width="762" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>45a. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy A, plate 5.</head>
<figDesc>© Copyright the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="s-los.b.p5" id="s-los.b.illbk.05" work-copy="s-los.b" rend="db" width="735" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>7</figTranscr>
<head>45b. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 5.</head>
<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
              <figure n="46.sl.letter.N.100" rend="file" width="958" height="750">
	<figTranscr>[S]ON[G]<lb/>
                [S]ON[G]<lb/>
                [S]ON[G]<lb/>
                [S]ON[G]<lb/>
</figTranscr>
<head>46. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copies A, B / D, C, plate 2, detail of the letter “N” from
title.</head>
<figDesc>© Copyright the Trustees of the British Museum. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of
Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used with permission. Morgan Library and Museum, New York.
PML 77236.</figDesc>
</figure>
the outline in metal, as suggested by Essick (<hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi> 128), or he used millboard, which
seems more likely, given the very wavy cut of the plate along the top edge (illus. 2), something more likely
in board than metal. More significant are the striations in clouds and arms visible in plate 8 of copy B
(illus. 44). These patterns, typical of gessoed millboard, are also in copies E and A and thus are not
repetitions in the paint layer of a first pull within a second.</p>
            <p>Plates 2 and 5 are also planographically printed. In plate 5 (illus. 45), figures, lily petals,
and stems are consistent in each impression and carefully finished in watercolor washes and pen and ink. The
broad green and brown leaves under the lilies, however, differ in number, form, and placement in each
impression, signs of improvisation, of having been painted broadly and energetically directly on the plate
rather than painted within an outline. Here, Blake paints each design anew, creating prints with both the
miniature’s exactness of form and the freedom and boldness of the oil sketch.</p>
            <p>Essick was first to recognize that plate 2 is the only illuminated plate with planographic
lettering, though he acknowledges that the letters may have had “lightly incised” outlines 
(<hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi> 128). Dörrbecker agrees and adds that the letters
<pb id="p41-81" n="81"/>
<figure n="47.sl.2.B.C.L.100" rend="file" width="958" height="496">
	<figTranscr>L<lb/>
	L</figTranscr>
	<head>47. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copies B and C, plate 2, detail of letter “L” from
title.</head>
	<figDesc>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. Used
with permission. Morgan Library and Museum, New York. PML 77236.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="48.sl.C.2.whiteline.100" rend="file" width="958" height="778">
	<head>48. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy C, plate 2, detail.</head>
	<figDesc>Morgan Library and Museum, New York. PML 77236.</figDesc>
</figure>
of the inscription may have been relief etched (319n28). Comparing all six impressions in great detail,
however, reveals that the letter forms are too inconsistent to have been outlined or relief etched. Note, for
example, the letter “N” (illus. 46) in copies A and B (top row) and D and C (bottom row): B and C differ
slightly from one another but are exactly like A and D respectively, only lighter, because they are second
impressions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> Incised lines and
relief etching are also ruled out because the matrix is almost certain to have been millboard, as indicated by
the striated texture under the colors forming the letter “L” in the non-sequential B and C impressions
(illus. 47). The copy C impression is telling in other ways as well; a second pull, it reveals thin white
lines (illus. 48) that at first appear to be part of an incised outline, thus suggesting a metal plate. Closer
inspection, however, reveals the white lines are the spaces between adjoining blocks of colors; we see the
same effect in the second impression of <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (illus. 49) and many of the other color-printed
drawings. <note id="n26">26. The six extant impressions of the title plate can be sequenced: F, A, B, D, C,
E[?]. The E impression is very poorly and lightly printed and has so much handwork that sequencing is
difficult and the possibility of a missing impression, of which this is a second or even third pull, is
raised.</note></p>
            <p>The accepted sequence of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> has Blake returning to the continental myth before finishing the Urizen cycle.
It pictures him creatively experimenting in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> with page format and text design
and using small color-printed drawings as book illustrations, only to return in the intaglio books to the
earlier text format of <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi> We now can see that <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> is last
in this sequence and that Blake completed the Urizen poems first and without interruption, with two much
shorter books whose planographically printed images were directly influenced by the color printing of 
<hi rend="i">Albion rose. The Song of Los</hi> plates 3-4 and 6-7 are horizontal compositions influenced
apparently by the format of Blake’s new invention, the large
<pb id="p41-82" n="82"/>
              <figure n="49.pity.whiteline.but311.100" rend="file" width="900" height="736">
	<head>49. <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, detail.</head>
<figDesc>Metropolitan Museum of Art, gift of Mrs. Robert W. Goelet, 1958 (58.603). Photograph © copyright
1979, Metropolitan Museum of Art.</figDesc>
</figure>
color monotypes. Their double columns were influenced by <hi rend="i">Urizen, The Book of Ahania</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, but differ significantly, being widely spaced and almost free flowing in a
format that combined poetry, printmaking, and painting in a new and radical way. <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los</hi> was Blake’s last illuminated text until <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and Blake probably began it while
working on the color-printed drawings, conceiving of his new texts as paintings with—or of—poems,
presented as horizontal scrolls, panels, or broadsides.</p>
            <p>With <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> as originally conceived, Blake returned to his
continental cycle using the same relief-etched print medium but in a painting format. For whatever reason, he
changed his mind and decided that his “Africa” and “Asia” needed to be reformatted. He masked one side
of the horizontal plate when printing to transform texts into book pages. He executed full-page illustrations
on millboard after the text plates and designed them to match in shape and size the plates of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> In doing so, he appears to have salvaged an experiment he
abandoned by extending what he learned about planographic printing from millboard into book production. The
fact that <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> are not to 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> as <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> is to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, but are clearly
related parts differently formatted, may have freed Blake from thinking that “Asia” and “Africa” had
to match <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> exactly. The non-symmetrical relation within
the Urizen cycle may have enabled him to reconstruct <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> into a book with two
“continents” and fewer than half the number of pages in <hi rend="i">America</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Europe.</hi></p>
            <p>Butlin is surely correct that “1795 can be seen as a vital year in Blake’s evolution, that
in which his pictorial art finally achieved maturity with works of the highest quality while, conversely, his
production of illuminated books suffered a hiatus for over ten years ....” I hope, however, in light of new
information about how small <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> was designed and executed, when and how <hi rend="i">Albion
rose</hi> was printed, the size of the copper sheet and manner in which it was cut to yield their plates and
the plates for <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, how the small
intaglio illuminated plates were printed, how the large color prints evolved and were executed and influenced
the <hi rend="i">Large</hi> and <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi>, and, mostly, how <hi rend="i">The
Song of Los</hi> began as texts designed in landscape format and was recreated as a book by the masking of
these plates during printing and the inclusion of small color-printed drawings, that the last illuminated
books of this period can be thought of as more than “the three relatively unambitious books of 1795”
(“Physicality” 6).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> 2nd ed. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2004.</p>
            <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake.</hi> London: Thames
and Hudson, 1978.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. “‘Is This a Private War or Can Anyone Join in?’: A Plea for a Broader
Look at Blake’s Color-Printing Techniques.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 36.2 (fall
2002): 45-49.</p>
            <p>—. “A Newly Discovered Watermark and a Visionary’s Way with His Dates.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 15.2 (fall 1981): 101-03.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New Haven: Yale
University Press, 1981.</p>
            <p>—. “The Physicality of William Blake: The Large Color Prints of ‘1795.’” 
<hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 52 (1989): 1-18.</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker, D. W., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Continental Prophecies.</hi> Blake’s
Illuminated Books, vol. 4. Princeton: Princeton University Press/Blake Trust; London: Tate Gallery/Blake
Trust, 1995.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed., with commentary by Harold Bloom. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and
Prose of William Blake.</hi> Newly rev. ed. New York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> Garden City, NY: Anchor-Doubleday, 1974.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Adam.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University
Press, 1989.</p>
            <p>—. “John Linnell, William Blake, and the Printmaker’s Craft.” <hi rend="i">Huntington
Library Quarterly</hi> 46 (1983): 18-32. Also published in <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers.</hi>
San Marino: Huntington Library, 1983.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi> Princeton: Princeton
University Press, 1983.</p>
            <pb id="p41-83" n="83"/>
            <p>—. “A Supplement to <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17.4 (spring 1984): 139-44.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press,
1980.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N., and Joseph Viscomi. “Blake’s Method of Color Printing: Some Responses
and Further Observations.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 36.2 (fall 2002): 49-64. Online
version, with color illustrations, at the journal’s website: &lt;http://www.blakequarterly.org&gt;.</p>
            <p>—. “An Inquiry into William Blake’s Method of Color Printing.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 35.3 (winter 2001-02): 74-103. Online version, with 81 color illustrations, at the
journal’s website: &lt;http://www.blakequarterly.org&gt;.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, “<hi rend="i">Pictor Ignotus.</hi>”
2 vols. London: Macmillan, 1863.</p>
            <p>Hamlyn, Robin. “William Blake at Work: ‘Every thing which is in Harmony.’” Townsend
12-39.</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake, Complete Writings.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University
Press, 1966.</p>
            <p>McManus, Noa Cahaner, and Joyce H. Townsend. “The Large Colour Prints: Methods and
Materials.” Townsend 82-99.</p>
            <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. “Visible Language: Blake’s Wond’rous Art of Writing.” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer. Ithaca, NY:
Cornell University Press, 1986. 46-86.</p>
            <p>Ormsby, Bronwyn, and Joyce H. Townsend, with Brian Singer and John Dean. “The State of
Knowledge on William Blake the Painter.” Townsend 40-44.</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael. “Color-Printing <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> and Blake’s Method
of Registration: A Correction.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 36.2 (fall 2002):
44-45.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Creation of the</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience
<hi rend="i">from Manuscript to Illuminated Printing.</hi> London: British Library, 2000.</p>
            <p>Rossetti, William Michael, comp. <hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers 1862 to 1870.</hi> London: Sands
&amp; Co., 1903.</p>
            <p>Townsend, Joyce H., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work.</hi> London: Tate
Publishing; Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2003.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> Princeton: Princeton
University Press, 1993.</p>
            <p>—. “Blake’s Virtual Designs and Reconstruction of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi> 41-42 (2006).
&lt;http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/2006/v/n41-42/013151ar.html&gt;.</p>
            <p>—. “The Evolution of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 58.3-4 (1997): 281-344.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The William Blake Archive.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
Viscomi. &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;.</p>
            <p>Worrall, David, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Urizen Books.</hi> Blake’s Illuminated
Books, vol. 6. Princeton: Princeton University Press/Blake Trust; London: Tate Gallery/Blake Trust, 1995.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
