<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>41.2.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">41.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>M. Crosby</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <front>
      <pb id="p41-49-50" n="49-50"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.041.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="333">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            Fitting the Pieces Together: The Works of 1795<lb/>
            VOLUME 41<lb/>
            NUMBER 2<lb/>
            FALL 2007</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-2-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="10" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
				<head>
				  <title>CONTENTS</title>
				</head>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.2.viscomi">Blake’s “Annus Mirabilis”: The Productions of
1795</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Joseph Viscomi</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">52</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.2.mulhallen">Folio Society Edition of <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts: The Poem by Edward Young Illustrated with Watercolours by William Blake</hi></ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Karen Mulhallen</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">84</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.2.bentley">Michael Bedard, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
Gates of Paradise</hi></ref><lb/>
				<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Elizabeth B. Bentley</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">91</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particular</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.2.crosby">The Sketch on the Verso of Blake’s Self-Portrait:
An Identification</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By M. Crosby</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">92</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Newsletter</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="41.2.news"><hi rend="i">Companion of Angels</hi>
Performances</ref></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">95</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Zürich</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p41-51" n="51"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi is the James G. Kenan Distinguished Professor of English and Comparative Literature
at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. He coedits the William Blake Archive with Morris Eaves and
Robert N. Essick, with whom he also coedited volumes 3 and 5 (1993) of the Blake Trust’s William Blake’s
Illuminated Books. He is the author of <hi rend="i">Prints by Blake and His Followers</hi> (1983), 
<hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (1993), and numerous essays on Blake’s illuminated printing,
color printing, and mid-nineteenth century market and reputation.</p>
        <p>Karen Mulhallen (karenmulhallen@rogers.com) is professor of English at Ryerson University and at
the University of Toronto, as well as professor in the Joint Graduate Programme in Communication and Culture
at Ryerson and York Universities. After many decades of thoughts by day, she has returned to her earlier work
in night thinking and is now completing a critical study of the whole composite Blake-Young <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> series.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth B. Bentley has worked on Blake with her husband in libraries around the world; she
specializes in research on long-lost (sometimes still lost) works, including <hi rend="i">The Ladies New and
Polite Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi> (1782), <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> (E), “The Ancient
Britons,” and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors.</p>
        <p>M. Crosby (mark.crosby@university-college.oxford.ac.uk) is just completing his DPhil at Oxford on
the three-year period Blake spent in Felpham under the patronage of William Hayley.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Alexander S. Gourlay</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sarah.jones@rochester.edu TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX:
585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Alexander S. Gourlay, Department of English, Rhode Island School of Design, 2 College Street,
Providence RI 02903-2717<lb/>
Email: agourlay@risd.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham
NG11 8NS UK<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the US, Canada, and
Mexico require a $15 per volume postal surcharge for surface delivery, or $20 for airmail. Credit card payment
is available. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all
subscription orders and related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English,
University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for
information on issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>Manuscripts are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to
either of the editors. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope.
For electronic submissions, you may send a disk, or send your article as an attachment to an email message;
please number the pages of electronic submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are usually
acceptable.</p>
        <p>International Standard Serial Number: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, Humanities International Complete,
Arts and Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the Bibliography of the History of Art.</p>
        <p>Cover: Photo illustration from <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy B, plate 8. Lessing J.
Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. © Copyright 2005, William Blake Archive. 
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2007 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
    	<pb id="p41-96" n="96"/>
    	<div1>
    		<div2>
		    	<div3 type="in-memoriam">John Howard<lb/>
		    	1934-2007</div3>
		    </div2>
	    </div1>
	</body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
