<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>41.3.ferber</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Jennifer Davis Michael, Blake and the City</title>
        <author n="Ferber">Michael Ferber</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2007-08</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007-08</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">41.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>C.S. Matheson</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
              <name>G.A. Rosso</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007/2008"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <body>
      <pb id="p41-125" n="125"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Jennifer Davis Michael. <hi rend="i">Blake and the City.</hi> Lewisburg:
Bucknell University Press, 2006. 235 pp., 14 b&amp;w illus. $55.00/£31.95, hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Michael <name>Ferber</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>THIS interesting and perceptive if somewhat uneven book repays careful reading. Its subject, the
various cities Blake dwelled in and on (London, Jerusalem, Babylon, and Golgonooza), is large and important
enough to warrant a booklength study. It is attentive to details, accurate in paraphrasing, and lucid and
unpretentious in manner. It interprets chastely, for the most part, keeping close to the texts: simply by
collating two or three scattered passages it often illuminates them all. It is up to date with Blake
scholarship, and courteously engages with it intermittently throughout. It could serve as an advanced
introduction to Blake, for graduate students, say, beginning a serious study of him; indeed I think the
chapter on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> contains one of the clearest and most useful brief guides to that
nine- or tenfold mess of a poem. The book also offers much of interest to scholars, both in little
observations about individual passages or citations of historical contexts and in larger, if sometimes
questionable, frameworks for conceiving whole works. It consistently grinds no particular theoretical ax,
though it submits to the hegemony of “text”; it cites Bachelard and de Certeau a few times, but Derrida,
Foucault, and Lacan are refreshingly absent, even as absent presences.</p>
          <p>Michael’s introduction canvasses Blake’s uneasy place in the romantic canon, and
distinguishes his view of nature from Wordsworth’s. The contrast between natural and artifical, between
rural and urban, is not found in Blake, she argues, because “all human environments are constructed, be they
urban or rural, and the idea of a pristine nature does not even exist outside the human mind” (18). (I would
have dropped “the idea of,” for as it stands the second clause is tautological.) She does not distinguish
between rural and wild, and so the unexceptionable claim that humans construct the rural environment leaks
into the highly debatable claim that they construct nature. But of course Blake did not usually distinguish
them either, as we see right from the start in the contradiction between the opening line of the
“Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (“Piping down the valleys wild”) and the frontispiece
that shows a flock of sheep reconstructing the wild by removing the grass. “All that appears external,”
Michael says, “is for Blake internal” (16). This seems about right, but one substantial thread running
through this book is “the physical city” (21), the real London, about which Michael comes up with some
interesting data, new to me at least, and we may wonder how well this gritty given London intersects with the
idealist or constructed city. This is a deep problem in Blake, of course, not just for Michael. She seems to
think Blake has worked it all out consistently, whereas I think Blake often conflates collective social
construction (by “Albion,” for instance) and individual idealist projection, even leaving aside his
extreme claim that the not-human or “nature” is in the end only a projection of a fallen state of a human
mind. In general, while she helpfully contrasts Blake’s ideas with Wordsworth’s, Swift’s, or others’,
she seems to think within Blake’s horizon of thought; he always has the last word. This sort of empathy or
ventriloquism can be useful and encouraging, and I know how hard it is to resist sounding Blakean when one has
devoted the time that it takes to feel capable of writing well about him, yet it tempts one to neglect or
finesse his real difficulties and contradictions.</p>
          <p>The conclusion of the introduction is a good summary of Blake’s life in London, his eight
residences and their neighborhoods, and how things were changing, “ever building, ever falling.” Each of
the four chapters that follow centers on a work and a theme or approach. The first deals with some of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> a through a recasting of the pastoral mode into a kind of urban “communal space.” It
reminds us that there were quite a few parks, fields, and other open areas inside greater London, if not the
City proper, so Blake did not have to escape London to enjoy some of the delights of rural life; the parks
break down the country/city dichotomy. Nor does he distance himself from that life in his poems, which seem
more intimate and engaged than both traditional, and Wordsworthian, pastoral. Michael thinks “Spring,”
“Laughing Song,” and “Ecchoing Green” have an urban setting (47), though surely that is not something
that was likely to occur to readers, even Londoners, familiar with the pastoral genre, and it is not clear
what difference it makes in how we read each poem. More telling, I think, is her point that “Holy
Thursday” of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> seems to have both an urban setting, like its Innocence
counterpart, and a rural one, with its invocation of “land” and “fields” and “thorns” (49).
Anticipating her approach to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the final chapter, which she pursues with a
vengeance, Michael argues that some late copies, with their “elaborate frames . . . outside the designs,”
“draw attention to the created quality of this pastoral world” (40-41) within a city. Her comments on
several of the poems are often subtle and well worth pondering, though occasionally I was left unconvinced. In
the “Introduction,” she writes, “the song appears to ‘fall’ from pure music to written text,”
though the shift “reverses itself” as the song is offered to every child (43). Why “fall”? Is this
still the effect of Edward Said’s mistake in <hi rend="i">Beginnings</hi> that “I stain’d the water
clear” describes a fall, a metaphysical or spiritual stain, as if there were some purer way to make ink? She
seems to want every conceivable meaning of “mark” to be operative in “London,” including “make a
mark,” and allows the marks in both Ezekiel and Revelation to be part of the background of the poem, though
I would have thought them mutually exclusive. But these are minor distractions from much that is rich and
interesting.</p>
          <pb id="p41-126" n="126"/>
          <p>Her second chapter, on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, moves, as she says, from pastoral to
georgic, being concerned with labor, the aesthetic labor of building Golgonooza and the degraded or enslaved
labor of building the real London in time of war. I found this the most satisfying chapter, though perhaps the
least ambitious or experimental in approach, both because its theme is so central to the poem and because, as
I said, it includes a helpful tour of the poem. Chapter 3 argues that in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> the city
appears more as an organism or body than as a construction of labor, while organic nature is described as
works of art. It includes a brief history of organic metaphors for the city, mainly of the “body politic”
sort, and some good remarks on just what “body” and “organic” mean in Blake’s usage. The final
chapter, on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, dwells on the textuality of the city, and the difficulty of reading
the multitude of signs in the real London as well as (and in much the same way as) in the composite
text-and-designs of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> It includes a longish discussion of what Wordsworth says
about London in <hi rend="i">The Prelude.</hi></p>
          <p>Let me say in passing that, given the intractable problem of writing usefully about Blake’s
three long poems in fewer than 200 pages, Michael acquits herself surprisingly well. Neither 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> nor the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> chapter deals much with the main plots (hard to
discern in the latter, in any case) nor the themes of love, jealousy, self-sacrifice, and brotherhood; while
at times I was thus left a little frustrated, I can appreciate that she wanted to avoid having to examine the
whole tangled mass of interconnected plots and themes, which would have required another hundred pages and
risked wearying the reader with predigested commonplaces or endless minute particulars. Among the themes
central to these poems, the one she chooses, the city, opens a gate (to borrow the metaphor) that leads to
many revealing vistas. She leaves it largely to us to reintegrate these vistas into the poems’ larger
structures and meanings.</p>
          <p>In her final chapter, Michael claims that a city, a real city such as London, is a text: it must
be “‘read,’ in order to understand some meaning within it . . . and at the same time ‘written’ so as
to create a meaning . . .” (161). Whatever may be said for this idea, it is now rather a commonplace. Since
<hi rend="i">texte</hi> arrived from France over 40 years ago it has colonized every department of humanities
and social sciences. Everything has become a text. Everything must be read, and, since meaning is indefinitely
displaced and postponed, everything must be reread, reinterpreted, and rewritten endlessly. The ideology, as
Melville would say, of a sub-sub-librarian. Over 30 years ago Paul de Man pronounced that “All wars are
texts,” which led a group of Yale graduate students to pass out buttons saying “Veterans of Foreign
Texts.” But no mockery stopped the tsunami of textuality. In recent years, I think, the tide has receded,
for it turns out that some things are not very much like texts after all, and even if they were, we would have
to make distinctions among city-texts, landscape-texts, war-texts, and so on, and would soon be left about
where we were before the flood.</p>
          <p>Michael does not claim everything is a text, but in claiming that cities are texts she seems
unaware of the history of “Theory” and its pretensions during the last 40 years, and to some of us who
lived through them this innocence is a little annoying. Perhaps she has in mind a younger set of readers, who
feel distant from all that, and will consider her metaphor (and more than metaphor) with fresh eyes. And it is
true that cities are at least a little like texts, especially to a first-time tourist, and the comparison may
strike illuminating sparks, as does her earlier comparison of the city to a body. With her usually steady
attention to details, Michael is still a helpful guide, as when she discusses the four gates of Golgonooza or
the relationship of the lyric “From Islington to Marybone” to the larger poem that contains it, but she
plays this role less often in this chapter than in the earlier ones. She is after big concepts, and the
biggest is the inverse of the city-as-text metaphor: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the text itself,
is a city! (164). She is drawing from De Luca here, who likened <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to “a wall of
words,” but she goes much further, comparing streets and canals to lines of poetry, shores and walls to
borders of pages, quarters or districts to chapters, junctions and crossings to the four prefaces, and
landmarks to the full-page designs (167-68). That, certainly, is not banal; I found it rather brave and
charming, though over the top. She doesn’t do much with it, of course (how far could you take it?), content
to let it widen our foreheads for a moment before moving on to other implications of the text taken as a
city.</p>
          <p>She wants to show that Blake imagines or conjures up a reader of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> who
is rather like a large-minded visitor to a large city, baffled at first, but willing to explore and
contemplate the labyrinth until it takes meaningful shape, whether revealed (read) or created (written), and
becomes a habitable home while the visitor becomes a citizen. If we can learn to be such readers we will know
how to “converse” with other citizens, entering each other’s bosoms, and there-by continually rebuild
the city. It is an attractive idea. It is Blake’s utopian vision of Jerusalem, and hard to resist, but
whether Blake embodied this vision somehow in the form of his poem is quite another matter. I have my doubts.
I grant that a reader of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> with Michael’s metaphor in mind might feel encouraged
to plunge in, and I don’t underestimate the value of that state of mind, but her argument in this final
chapter remains more a pep talk than a Baedeker, and after a while even the most hopeful reader will need the
latter. In my experience, even after many years of reading <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and excellent
commentaries on it such as Morton Paley’s, the walls of words remain discouraging barriers (we might call
them wailing walls), the poetry is often clunky and clumsy, the narrative has little momentum or discernible
direction, some passages are of adamantine obscurity, and the tone is often unpleasantly hectoring or
jeremiahing. Though some sectors of it are wondrous and inspiring, the whole thing, if it is a city, is
Babylonish or Knossian. I’ll revisit it from time to time, as I’ll revisit Michael’s interesting book,
but I’ll keep my Athenian passport.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
