<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>41.3.matheson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert C. Brandeis, William Blake and His Contemporaries: An Exhibition Selected
from the Bentley Collection at Victoria University, Victoria University Library, Toronto</title>
        <author n="Matheson">C. S. Matheson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2007-08</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007-08</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">41.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>C.S. Matheson</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
              <name>G.A. Rosso</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007/2008"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <body>
	<pb id="p41-131" n="131"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">[Robert C. Brandeis.] <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries</hi>:
An Exhibition Selected from the Bentley Collection at Victoria University, Victoria University Library,
Toronto. 30 October-15 December 2006. Toronto: Victoria University, 2006. 36 pp., 36 b&amp;w illus. Canadian
$15.00, paperback.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>C. S. <name>Matheson</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>As a student at Oxford I earned a bit of money working part-time in the college library. The
hourly wage was small, but the labor wasn’t taxing, except for locking up and shutting down the lights in a
long gallery reputedly haunted by the ghost of someone disappointed at Finals (a person, incidentally, who
turned up well albeit wrinkled at a gaudy in my last term).</p>
          <p>But the shelving and the cataloguing and the reserve requests were really made tolerable by the
possibility of an outing with the college librarian. Periodically the librarian would receive word that
someone had donated his or her library to the college and then she—and sometimes to my delight she and
I—would be dispatched to examine the books and carry away our selections. These alumni seemed to favor the
environs of North Oxford, or else they had followed the Woodstock Road along a bit further and daringly
settled in the Cotswolds. They inhabited similar houses—not architecturally similar of course, but eerily
alike in their proportion of armchairs to reading lights, cretonnes to bookrests, and well-used dictionaries
to presentation copies. In the librarian’s venerable Morris Minor we would travel at an unflappable 30 mph
towards these quiet houses and their expectant libraries. I was always waiting for the bright moon to drop
behind the cottage roof.</p>
          <p>These excursions were my first proper lesson in the deep autobiography that is serious book
collecting. They taught me just how many layers of self are manifested in a library, and the extreme
generosity of selves who can project their libraries forward into another sphere and towards another set of
readers. I learned that bookshelves stand at the convergence of dense, humming lines of testimony: not just to
a person’s subject and expertise and interests, but to his or her travels, experiences, consolations and
connections; not just to the provenance of rare volumes, but the point at which a book’s passage through the
world merges with the whole journey of a collector. A life lived with books can be wholly different from a
career enacted through them. There are times when geomancy seems a more necessary science than
bibliography.</p>
          <p>Now imagine how these issues are amplified when the collection in question is “one of the three
most important Blake collections, institutional or private, formed in the second half of the twentieth
century” (Robert Essick, quoted in the “Introduction”).
<pb id="p41-132" n="132"/>
And when the collector is not only our foremost Blake biographer (<hi rend="i">Stranger from Paradise</hi>
[2001]), but a scholar whose work forms part of the superstructure of Blake studies. Here indeed is a “Web /
Of Ages &amp; Generations, folding &amp; unfolding,” which is a rather more pleasant image when taken out of
context. The books, paintings, manuscripts, drawings and artifacts brought together by G. E. Bentley, Jr., and
E. B. Bentley over nearly six decades form a remarkable production in their own right. The works (more than
2500) parallel and embody Bentley’s meticulous reconstruction in his numerous books and articles of
Blake’s associations, circles, and working practices. This is a collection that recreates the sociability
and productivity—not to mention the dizzying interconnectivity—of the book and art worlds in Blake’s
lifetime. Recently gifted to the E. J. Pratt Library of Victoria University at the University of Toronto, the
Bentley collection was show-cased in the fall of 2006 through a fine exhibition curated and catalogued by
chief librarian Robert C. Brandeis.</p>
          <p>The exhibition begins with the visage of Blake himself. A copy of Deville’s life mask, in which
Blake’s habitual sweetness of expression was soured by the weight of the plaster, is paired with
Schiavonetti’s engraving after the Phillips portrait, a print used as the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">The
Grave</hi> in 1808. It is an apposite choice, not only because it answers our wish to greet Blake himself, but
also for the many layers of reproduction and transmission manifested in these works. Everything follows from a
desire to translate the imaginative faculty.</p>
          <p>The first movement of the exhibition shows the range of Blake’s graphic production, from sketch
and manuscript to engraving on copper and wood to relief etching. It’s instructive to see three
electrotypes—“London,” “Infant Sorrow,” and “The Divine Image”—from the 16 made after
Gilchrist’s c. 1861 electrotype copies of Blake’s plates. There are three sets of these electrotype copies
now extant, and I feel rather subdued when I think of <hi rend="i">printing from them</hi> in Bentley’s
seminar. Blake’s designs for and after the work of other artists (including the wonderful engraved portrait
of Lavater, beaky and exacting as a Renaissance princeling) ready us for the exquisite Virgil illustrations
and the magisterial <hi rend="i">Dante</hi> and <hi rend="i">Job</hi> suites that fill the South Gallery. The
latter is a splendid 1826 “proof” copy on India paper. A pencil drawing in the “Visionary Heads”
mode—representing Prince Arthur or perhaps an unusually svelte Henry VIII—and an autograph riddle
manuscript penned on the verso of a proof of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi>
direct us to the calligraphic vigor of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> Copy M of 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, one of the collection’s greatest treasures, consists of <hi rend="i">A Song of
Liberty</hi> printed, as the catalogue describes, “on one sheet forming four pages with the first page left
blank” (9). Together with copy L (in the collection of Robert Essick), this work provides important evidence
that the <hi rend="i">Song</hi> was not just the tailpiece of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, but may have been
intended for distribution as a separate pamphlet.</p>
          <p>Copy M of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> dramatizes a tendency within the Bentley collection as a
whole to illuminate artists and audiences,
            <figure n="Bentleys1.41.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="232" height="400">
	<figTranscr>
              William Blake<lb/>
              &amp; His
            </figTranscr>
</figure>
<figure n="Bentleys2.41.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="319">
	<head>E. B. Bentley and G. E. Bentley, Jr., at the reception to mark the opening of the exhibition.</head>
	<figDesc>Photographs courtesy of Alex McKay.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p41-133" n="133"/>
issues of production and reception in the period. The professional sphere that Blake (periodically) inhabited
is embodied in the exhibition through the work and biographies of some of Blake’s key associates:
Cumberland, Flaxman, Fuseli, Linnell, Stothard, and Tresham. These six men, or alternatively, “Men who
occupied the sixth chamber,” appear here as artists in their own right as well as patrons, readers, or
peers. Sometimes of course these roles converged, as in the case of Cumberland, whose literary manuscripts,
scrapbooks, and sketches live alongside books embellished with engravings by Blake. Linnell is represented by
an oil portrait sketch of Mrs. George Stephen (wife of a solicitor consulted by Linnell over the Blake
estate), a kindly, intimate image that seems consistent with Linnell’s handling of Blake himself.
Stothard’s tender watercolor <hi rend="i">Infancy</hi> (c. 1802) makes the sharp dealing of the Canterbury
Pilgrims affair seem almost impossible. And Tresham’s oil painting <hi rend="i">Anthony and Cleopatra</hi>,
executed for Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, calls up the aspirations and disappointments of a whole decade
of British art.</p>
          <p>The Bentley collection is both an entity and the emanation of a distinguished scholarly
collaboration. As a “working library” in its richest sense, one that documents the material and spiritual
labor of the subject, the biographer, and the collectors, its relocation to the Pratt Library at Victoria
University in Toronto seems very appropriate. Here it is in close proximity to an important holding of
Coleridge materials and the Northrop Frye papers, not to mention Douglas Martin’s portrait of Frye
composedly levitating. And here the lines of the collection are extended magnetically towards a new set of
readers, scholars, and students. William Blake and His Contemporaries was opened in late 2006 with a gala
reception, memorable on many counts, not the least for hearing a university president quote “When the
morning stars sang together” rather than the passages of Job more habitual to administrators. But what
struck me most forcibly was that the qualities that converge in successful collecting—knowledge and insight,
judgment and good fortune—also shape the community one collects in turn. In a life lived with books the
notion of provenance, like the “little lovely Allegoric Night” in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, may be
“stretchd abroad, expanding east &amp; west &amp; north &amp; south.”</p>
          <note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">Editors’ note: Information on ordering the
catalogue is available at</hi> &lt;<hi rend="i">http://library.vicu.utoronto.ca/libpubs.htm</hi>&gt;.</note>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
