<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>41.4.scott</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Tracy Chevalier, Burning Bright</title>
                <author n="Scott">Grant F. Scott</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 2008</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>2008</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">41.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Sarah Jones</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                            <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
                            <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
                            <name>Grant F. Scott</name>
                            <name>Aileen Ward</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="2008"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_41">
        <body>
			<pb id="p41-163" n="163"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-41-4-0008">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Tracy Chevalier. <hi rend="i">Burning Bright.</hi> London:
HarperCollins; New York: Dutton-Penguin, 2007. 311 pp. £15.99/$24.95, hardcover; £7.99/$14.00, paperback
(2008).</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Grant F. <name>Scott</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>TRACY Chevalier is best known for <hi rend="i">Girl with a Pearl Earring</hi> (1999),
an ekphrastic novel based on Vermeer’s famous portrait that was adapted into a modestly successful film a
few years ago. The novel became a bestseller for its convincing depiction of seventeenth-century Delft and its
winsome protagonist, a young girl who works as a servant in the Vermeer household and eventually becomes the
painter’s apprentice and model. A lot of the book trades in the soft eroticism of the central encounter, the
innocent wide-eyed maid initiated in the ways of love and art by the experienced painter. But there is
something to be said for Chevalier’s evocation of Vermeer’s aesthetic, her instinct for reflecting in
prose the stillness and simplicity of his paintings. The transparency of her language ideally suits the pure
stream of light bathing his solitary female subjects from every window. And the keen verbal sketches of the
paintings effectively convey the spirit of Vermeer’s art.</p>
                    <p>Unfortunately this is not the case with William Blake, who figures much less
prominently in <hi rend="i">Burning Bright.</hi> In spite of publicity claims that the novel “tells the tale
of an artistic genius and the lives around him as he writes his famous <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
Experience</hi> [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>],” it is the fictive Kellaway and Butterfield families who take
center stage, Blake who flickers dimly in the margins. The protagonists are a pair of 12-year-olds: Jem
Kellaway, who travels to London from Dorsetshire with his family, and Maggie Butterfield, a street urchin who
lives in the city. Jem is the innocent country boy who spends a lot of the novel blushing and gaping, Maggie
the experienced girl with a “hard, shrewd veneer” (65) who knows the back lanes of Lambeth and conceals a
dark secret. Philip Astley employs Jem’s father as a carpenter in his famous circus and secures the family a
room in no. 12 Hercules Buildings, next door to William and Catherine Blake. The novel thus opens showing the
two contrary states of the human soul, but like the volume of poetry it adapts and broadly interprets it
gradually blurs the boundaries between them. Jem gains experience, Maggie softens into innocence as both
children verge toward “the middle” in their journey toward adulthood. In a symbolic moment sure to delight
eighth-grade readers, Blake gives Maggie a gift of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs
of Experience.</hi> One volume is for Jem, but she forgets which one: “Well, I mixed ‘em up in my pocket.
I don’t know which is yours and which mine” (306).</p>
                    <pb id="p41-164" n="164"/>
                    <p>And so it goes. There is the exuberant Philip Astley who mesmerizes the London populace
with his circus and fireworks displays, his philandering son who seduces and impregnates Jem’s sister, and
Mrs. Kellaway, grieving over the loss of her boy, who fell out of a pear tree. There is also John Roberts of
the Lambeth Association for the Preservation of Liberty and Property against Republicans and Levellers, who in
response to the September massacres in France bullies people into signing an oath of loyalty to King George.
Predictably he gravitates toward Blake’s house and demands that he sign the document. In one of the
novel’s silliest moments, Roberts and his mob are paralyzed by Maisie Kellaway’s dramatic reading of
“London.” Blake himself then takes the cue and begins to recite the third stanza “in a sonorous voice
that froze the men at his door” (255). The plot then degenerates into Disney comedy as Maggie heaves a
rotten cabbage at Roberts and the kids go to work.</p>
                    <p>The novel’s most serious shortcoming for those interested in Blake is that it never
finds a language adequate to convey the complexity of his art nor a means of limning the fiery eccentricity of
the man himself. Unlike Vermeer in the earlier book, Blake’s character is one-dimensional, kindly and
avuncular, a bit too reminiscent of Grandpa Walton or Burl Ives (he says things like “Well, now, Maggie, . .
. Kate tells me you have something you want to say to us” [281]). He invites our heroes into his home, shows
them his workshop, rescues Jem’s sister from a tricky situation in the stables and eventually takes her in
as a housekeeper. He’s the stock figure of the wise artist, living peacefully in his cottage with his loyal
wife, etching away at his little projects and dispensing moral lessons to the neighborhood children. In this
sense he’s strangely bland, domesticated and relieved of his rage. He does wander through the early pages
wearing a <hi rend="i">bonnet rouge</hi> but he has none of the fire or energy of the dissident Blake, the man
violently at odds with his own times. The spectacular explosion of Astley’s fireworks depot burns far
brighter than Blake’s ideas. And it’s the symmetry of “The Tyger”—stripped of its fearfulness—that
structures the novel’s action.</p>
                    <p>It is true that the book is sprinkled here and there with stanzas from the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and thus on the surface appears to be an homage to the artist and his work. But another
source of disappointment for Blake enthusiasts is the book’s failure to imagine a style or a form that
acknowledges the rich complexity of Blake’s multimedia art. Because of his visual designs, even the simplest
of lyrics like “Infant Joy” bring with them a satisfying depth. The semiotic exchange between text and
image always produces multiple meanings that happily vex easy understanding of the plates. The novel, by
contrast, has little to say about the visual element of the poems, and the US hardcover version features only
one image, the cover design, which reproduces an enlarged image of plate one of “The Little Girl Lost.” It
is faded, impossible to read in parts, and boldly overwritten in red by the author’s name and the title of
the book. The standard format of a prose novel combined with the absence of any imaginative visual concept for
integrating text and image not only defeats the uniqueness of Blake’s idiom, but also takes us back 30 years
to the anthologies that divorced Blake’s words from his pictures. In its omission and implicit subjection of
the visual, the novel is deeply reactionary.</p>
                    <p>It may be argued that a clear strength of the book is its historically accurate
rendering of Georgian London. As the acknowledgments reveal, Chevalier has consulted a number of scholarly
resources to ensure the book’s verisimilitude. At times, however, it feels as if there’s a great deal of
wandering through each chartered street and not enough exploration of character. Long stretches of the book
unfold like a moderately interesting walk through a reconstructed set. We pass the traditional tourist
sites—Astley’s Amphitheater, Bedlam, Westminster Abbey and Bridge, the London Wall—pause for refreshment
at pubs and are treated to lengthy descriptions of artisans at work on Windsor chairs and Dorset buttons. But
the pace is slow, the exposition often laborious and dull. There’s simply not enough at stake in the plot,
no urgency or sense of impending crisis that would warrant these excursions. Although the novel seems to side
with Blake when he says that “the tension between contraries is what makes us ourselves. We have not just
one, but the other too, mixing and clashing and sparking inside us” (177), it does not provide enough clash
and spark or offer enough risk to hold our interest. Not fireworks but fire is what this novel needs, the
howling of Orc, his flames and fierce embrace. By the end, we’ve spent too much time in the protected bower
of “The Lamb,” numbed by its lulling symmetries.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
