<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>41.4.mellor</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Helen P. Bruder, ed., Women Reading William Blake</title>
                <author n="Mellor">Anne K. Mellor</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 2008</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>2008</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">41.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Sarah Jones</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                            <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
                            <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
                            <name>Grant F. Scott</name>
                            <name>Aileen Ward</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="2008"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_41">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-41-4-0008">
				<pb id="p41-164" n="164"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Helen P. Bruder, ed. <hi rend="i">Women Reading William Blake.</hi>
Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2007. xx + 286 pp., 7 b&amp;w illus. £50.00/$69.95, hardcover.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Anne K. <name>Mellor</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>WHERE has the study of Blake and gender come since the first explicitly feminist
interpretations of Blake’s poetry and art? Susan Fox’s groundbreaking “The Female as Metaphor in William
Blake’s Poetry” in 1977, followed by Alicia Ostriker’s “Desire Gratified and Ungratified: William
Blake and Sexuality” and my “Blake’s Portrayal of Women” in 1982-83, appeared 30 years ago.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">1</ref> Helen Bruder is to be congratulated for
raising this question now, in the aftermath of her own and several other recent books on gender and sexuality
in Blake’s art and poetry (most notably by Tristanne Connolly and Christopher Hobson). Among the 30 short
essays
<pb id="p41-165" n="165"/>
included in this volume—which is deeply marred by unskilled editing and poor organization—are several that
advance our understanding of Blake’s conception of gender and/or sexuality. <note id="n12">1. 
<hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 3.3 (spring 1977): 507-19 (Fox); <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 16.3 (winter 1982-83): 156-65 (Ostriker) and 148-55 (Mellor).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>If one is in the mood for autobiographical memoirs, there are charming essays of the
“what Blake has meant to me through the years” variety. Addie Stephen provides a detailed memoir of her
personal sexual history as inspired by Blake’s concept of free love. The late and much lamented Janet Warner
summarizes the intense “Blake Moments” in her life while Alicia Ostriker movingly recounts the connections
between Blake’s work and her own poetry, especially her recent concern with the <hi rend="i">Shekinah.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Several essays usefully place Blake’s work in the context of the leading women
writers of the day. Julia Wright explores Blake’s and Joanna Baillie’s mutually illuminating
understandings of eighteenth-century sensibility. Harriet Kramer Linkin insightfully analyzes Blake’s
relationship to such female poets as Ann Batten Cristall (a relationship also discussed at greater length in
this volume by Tristanne Connolly), Charlotte Smith, Mary Tighe and, most perceptively, Felicia Hemans.
Jacqueline Labbe again places Blake’s work in meaningful dialogue with that of Charlotte Smith and Mary
Robinson. And Shirley Dent takes us forward into the Victorian period, to discuss the impact of Anne Gilchrist
on both her husband’s biography of Blake and the Pre-Raphaelite reception of Blake’s vision.</p>
                    <p>Other essays offer genuinely new insights into Blake’s representation of women in his
art and poetry. Catherine McClenahan provides a statistical overview of British working-class women’s labor
from 1750 to 1830 as background for her fascinating claim that Blake managed to locate the experience of the
sublime in quotidian labor, especially that of women. June Sturrock develops a brilliant argument for the
equation of the calumniated female figures of Dinah, Erin, and Jerusalem with Blake’s vision of a way to
overcome British nationalist chauvinism and Francophobia in the war years of 1800-15. These females, whom
Sturrock might also have linked to the reviled Marie Antoinette, through their “fallenness,” redemption,
and capacity for forgiveness offer a model for a new British society that is “inclusive and interactive”
(232). And Mary Lynn Johnson convincingly identifies and reevaluates the figures of Mary Magdalen and Martha
in Blake’s illustrations to the Bible, in particular <hi rend="i">The Hymn of Christ and the Apostles</hi>
(Butlin #490).</p>
                    <p>Only a few essays take up the real challenge of such a volume: was Blake a misogynist?
Can feminists learn anything useful from his work? Brenda Webster once again insists, as she did in her
earlier Freudian book, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology</hi> (1983), that Blake’s portrayal of
Oothoon in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> is a male rape and harem fantasy with which
feminists cannot sympathize. Claire Colebrook offers a deconstructive analysis of sexual difference in
Blake’s work, relocating his feminism in his redefinition of sexual difference as the distinction between
the (female) letter and the (male) spirit. Irene Tayler offers a more nuanced argument that Blake wrestled
throughout his career, not always successfully, with two inherited modes of thought concerning gender: that
the female is innately inferior to the male, and that “Woman” is that which is veiled, and thus to be
dis/covered. As does Sturrock, Tayler suggests that Blake, in the final pages of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
was able to overcome his lifelong struggle with his own “selfhood” and find communion with the female
other in the forgiven <hi rend="i">human</hi> body. Tayler’s essay echoes what, to my mind, remains the most
perceptive analysis of Blake’s changing visions of gender and sexuality, Alicia Ostriker’s “Desire
Gratified and Ungratified: William Blake and Sexuality.” And finally, Susan Wolfson, in what is perhaps the
most thoughtful and telling contribution to this volume, suggests through her subtle interrogation of “The
Little Girl Lost” that the question of whether Blake is or is not a feminist depends not so much on the
content of Blake’s poetry and art as on the mindset with which a given reader encounters Blake’s work.</p>
                    <p>The multiple problems with this volume lie primarily with the editor, not the
contributors. Clearly wishing to attract a larger crossover audience, Helen Bruder—as the splashy banner on
the cover of the book proclaims (“Featuring contributions from Germaine Greer and Tracy
Chevalier”)—invited a disparate group ranging from novelists to feminist critics who have not hitherto
worked on Blake to serious Blake scholars to contribute. The result is, predictably, a hodge-podge. Since
Bruder could find no coherent way to organize these multifarious essays, she simply put them in alphabetical
order by author’s last name. Thus one bumps from Bruder’s substantive consideration of Blake’s
relationship with Ann Flaxman to Tracy Chevalier’s shameless puff for her forthcoming novel on Blake (now
published as <hi rend="i">Burning Bright</hi>) to serious essays on Blake’s similarities to various women
writers of the period to Addie Stephen’s sexual confessions to Germaine Greer’s ungrounded speculations
concerning Blake’s infertility to the state of feminist Blake studies in Japan and South Africa—and so on.
Several of the essays do not even belong in this volume. Except for the fact that they happen to be written by
women, they have almost nothing to say about Blake’s visual or verbal construction of gender and/or
sexuality—although they are informative about Blake’s knowledge of lucid dreaming, Moravianism, Hinduism,
Lavater, and Old Norse mythology. Even the serious essays on Blake and gender are so short (none more than 10
pages) as to be little more than introductions to their topics. Some, most notably Nancy Goslee’s otherwise
provocative analysis of Enitharmon in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, lack the illustrations that would be essential
to persuade a reader of their claims.</p>
                    <p>In all then, this volume is deeply disappointing. Even the best work is hampered by its
brevity, missing illustrations, and, most significantly, its lack of placement within an overall coherent
argument concerning the state of feminist Blake studies at the present moment, the argument that the editor
should have provided in her woefully inadequate introduction.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
