<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>41.4.ward</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Reply to G. E. Bentley, Jr.</title>
                <author n="Ward">Aileen Ward</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 2008</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>2008</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">41.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Sarah Jones</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                            <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
                            <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
                            <name>Grant F. Scott</name>
                            <name>Aileen Ward</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="2008"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_41">
        <body>
            <pb id="p41-166" n="166"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-41-4-0009">
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Reply to G. E. Bentley, Jr.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>By <docAuthor>Aileen <name>Ward</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>FIRST, I wish to thank G. E. Bentley, Jr., for his careful reading of my paper and his
thoughtful reply. However, I must respectfully disagree with a number of his points. Though he states it is
“exceedingly difficult to ascertain what <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> consisted of in 1804 or even in
1807,” he stands by his earlier argument that George Cumberland’s 1807 memorandum stating that Blake
“has eng[rave]d 60 Plates of a new Prophecy!” must refer to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the only poem by
Blake of over 60 plates (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 246 and fn), and dismisses my conclusion that it refers to
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (“Building <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” 185), which, as he notes, “consists of
a maximum of only 50 plates” in its final form.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">1</ref> Rather, he concludes from the evidence of the 1804 date on the title page and other
considerations that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as a whole “was written and probably at least partly etched
then,” that is, by 1804. <note id="n17">1. Yet Bentley has previously stated the possibility of a longer
form of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> in a composite version with <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in draft c. 1803-05
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 307; see also Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi, eds., <hi rend="i">Milton a
Poem</hi>, Blake’s Illuminated Books, vol. 5 [Princeton: Princeton UP/Blake Trust; London: Tate
Gallery/Blake Trust, 1993] 36), a possibility explored by David V. Erdman (<hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet against
Empire</hi>, 3rd ed. [Princeton: Princeton UP, 1977] 423-24). See also “Building 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” 184 and n19.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>However, the 1804 title-page date is not plain evidence for the composition of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, as Bentley implies, but problematical,
<pb id="p41-167" n="167"/>
as I have argued and as Bentley himself earlier suggested (“misleadingly dated ‘1804’,” 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 246fn). When its design is compared to those of Blake’s other poems containing
title-page dates, the “1804” looks like an afterthought rather than an integral part of the whole page,
and thus was quite possibly added after the poem was finished some years later (“Building 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” 185). Bentley’s other evidence for an early date (i.e., before 1807) consists of
the existence of several contradictory chapter references (corrected in the final version) as well as the 1802
watermark on some proofs duplicating those of copy Q of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, dated c. 1804 by
Viscomi. But in pulling these proofs (pls. 9, 28, 45, 56) some time later it seems quite likely that Blake
merely used paper on hand left over from the 1804 printing of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> Bentley
further argues that some of the events mentioned in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> also support an early
(pre-1807) date: for example, Blake’s residences in Lambeth, Felpham, and South Molton Street, where he
moved in the autumn of 1803 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 748), as well as the various allusions to Blake’s trial
for sedition (1803-04) in the mentions of Scolfield, Cock, Hulton, Brereton, Peachey, and Quantock scattered
throughout <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> But these events, recollected several years later, are hardly precise
enough to prove that Cumberland’s 1807 mention of a “new Prophecy” refers to 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Rather, the allusions to the devastating review of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> in
August 1808 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 258-61) scattered throughout <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the 26 plates
with references to “Hand” provide a surer clue (“Building <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” 183n8; 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 286fn). Bentley concedes that “these 26 plates must have been finished after 1807,”
that is, 1808 and after. But it should be noted that 17 of these post-1807 plates mentioning Hand are found in
the first 60 plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">2</ref> which cannot have been written until after August 1808 and which cannot therefore have
been the “60 Plates of a new Prophecy” which Blake is said to have shown to Cumberland in 1807.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">3</ref> Since the “new Prophecy” cannot have been
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, it can only have been <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, which was well underway by the
summer of 1807. Bentley also cites Blake’s “vague” reference to “My long Poem” in his letter to
Butts of 25 April 1803 as evidence of the early composition of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> However, the
allusion is not vague but fairly clear: the long poem descriptive of “the Spiritual Acts of my three years
Slumber on the banks of the Ocean” (E 728) must refer to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, which was probably
drafted during the Felpham years (E 728-30, 806) but not etched till after his return to London in the autumn
of 1803. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, on the other hand, appears not to have been begun until at least 1808,
as its early references to Hand would indicate. <note id="n18">2. Pls. 5, 7, 8, 9, 15, 17, 18, 19, 21, 26, 32,
34, 36, 42, 43, 58, 60. See <hi rend="i">A Concordance to the Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V.
Erdman, 2 vols. (Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1967) 1: 860.</note>
                        <note id="n19">3. It might also be noted that Cumberland’s 1807 visit to Blake is
itself hypothetical. In the summer of 1807 Cumberland “apparently came to London . . . and called on
Blake” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 246): there is no corroboratory evidence for the call. The information in a
series of notes about Blake, which Cumberland made in his notebook at this time, may well have come from
Cromek, with whom he was on familiar terms, and not from Blake himself: his diary notation about the “new
Prophecy” may be hearsay, or a piece of literary gossip.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>To turn from textual matters to historical, the contemporary allusions in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are mostly to events which occurred after 1811 (“Building 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” 184nn11-14). Bentley does not consider the biographical question of what Blake
might have been doing in the years between his return from Felpham in September 1803 and the summer of 1807
which would make the writing and engraving of 60 plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> practically impossible:
first, the completion of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as a “Grand Poem” (E 730), continuing with minor
revisions until at least the autumn of 1808;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">4</ref> second, his labors on the manuscript of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, on which he
continued to work until at least 1807,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">5</ref> and perhaps the mysterious composite version of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> with 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (see note 1, above); third, almost 30 commercial engravings (see table, 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 820-21) executed between 1803 and 1806, as well as the engraving of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (first printed c. 1810) during these years. A similar question arises concerning
Blake’s activity between 1810 and 1818 (“Building <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” 185), when he produced
little original art of significance after completing <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> in 1808 and <hi rend="i">The
Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> in 1810: rather, he was occupied with illustrations for the Wedgwood 
<hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> and the Rees <hi rend="i">Cyclopædia</hi>, as well as engraving Flaxman’s 37
designs for Hesiod, <hi rend="i">Works and Days</hi> (1816-17), and making a copy of his large drawing of 
<hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi>, on which he labored for almost eight years (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 320fn).
This is the time in which he most probably composed the better part of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
                        <ref target="n22" type="note">6</ref> Indeed, it is hard to imagine otherwise—six or
eight years in the life of a major artist and poet at the height of his powers with little to show for them
beyond routine illustrations for a pottery catalogue and an encyclopedia, the engraving of Flaxman’s Hesiod
designs (see table, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 821-22), and yet another copy of <hi rend="i">The Last
Judgment.</hi>
                        <note id="n20">4. Essick and Viscomi 36.</note>
                        <note id="n21">5. Essick and Viscomi 36.</note>
                        <note id="n22">6. In 1812, however, he contributed a set of “Detached Specimens of
an original illuminated Poem, entitled ‘<hi rend="i">Jerusalem the Emanation of the Giant Albion</hi>’”
to the annual exhibition of the Associated Painters in Water Colours (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 311-12 and
312fn). The exact number of these plates is a matter of speculation, perhaps half a dozen, and none is higher
than pl. 53 in the final numeration. In any case, this shows Blake’s work on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
well advanced by 1812.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>To conclude: the balance of evidence suggests that the “60 Plates of a new
Prophecy” of George Cumberland’s 1807 note cannot refer to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Quite apart from
the basic improbability that over half of Blake’s major work was completed two decades before his death, to
view the first 60 plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as arising from his experience prior to 1807 is to
miss the profound spiritual transformation in Blake’s life occurring in the years between the composition of
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, recorded in the change from the attack on his
enemies in the “Public Address” (1809) pp. 51-56 and the self-justification in the ending of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, pls. 40-43, to the spirit of contrition of the prologue of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem:</hi>
the confession of “the most sinful of men” in the proem to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and the glimpse of
the Heavenly City with which it ends.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
