<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>41.4.essick</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">Blake in the Marketplace, 2007</title>
                <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 2008</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>2008</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">41.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Sarah Jones</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                            <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
                            <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
                            <name>Grant F. Scott</name>
                            <name>Aileen Ward</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="2008"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_41">
        <body>
            <pb id="p41-140" n="140"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-41-4-0006">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Blake in the Marketplace, 2007</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">Editors’ note: 
<ref type="html-issue" issue="bonus.essick">Color images</ref> of all eight</hi> Songs of Innocence 
<hi rend="i">copy Y prints sold at Sotheby’s New York on 1 November 2007 are on the <corr type="emend"><ref
type="html-issue" issue="bonus.toc">Bonus Content</ref> page</corr></hi></note>
                    <p>THE hyperactive 2006 Blake market continued through 2007. In the first month of the
year, John Windle—“the foremost dealer in Blake,” according to one member of the trade<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>—managed the sale of the only copy of 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> remaining in private hands. To no one’s surprise, the price set a record for
a letterpress edition of Blake’s writings. Bonhams, the London auction house, offered two Blake drawings in
its 6 February sale catalogue. They were oddly estimated, with the more interesting drawing (illus. 6) given a
lower range than the rather conventional drawings of a baby’s head (illus. 7). Unfortunately, I was not able
to test my sense of their actual market value: on 31 January I was informed by Bonhams that both drawings were
withdrawn. I will report any further information I can obtain about their destiny in future reviews. 
<note id="n1">1. Michael Taylor, April <hi rend="i">Catalogue 65: Wood Engravings</hi>, item 1.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In mid-January I learned that an “important Blake” had been sold (presumably late
in 2006) to a private collector for something over $2 million, with Sotheby’s New York acting as the
intermediary. I was able to confirm, from a reliable source, that this work was copy N of <hi rend="i">Visions
of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, formerly in the Whitney family collection. This late and beautiful copy
disappeared for many years, only to reemerge under mysterious circumstances at Swann, the New York auction
house, in August 2004.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> I have not been
able to confirm the rumored price. <note id="n2">2. For further information, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 38.4
(spring 2005): 124, and 39.4 (spring 2006): 148.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Nancy Bialler of Sotheby’s New York informed me on 6 September that eight (of
fifteen) plates from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy Y, for many years on deposit at the
Wallraf-Richartz-Museum in Cologne, would be offered in six lots at auction on 1 November (illus.
1-5).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> I had assumed that the museum
would be the permanent home for copy Y, but I learned on 7 September from Detlef Dörrbecker that the owners
of the work, apparently members of the Neuerburg family, had reclaimed the book in 2004 or 2005. Why only
eight prints, and not all fifteen, were offered for sale remains unexplained. In December, Bialler told Windle
that the “owners” (note the plural) had no plans to sell the remaining seven plates. <note id="n3">3. For
information on copy Y and its rediscovery, see <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 119-20 and Detlef W. Dörrbecker,
“Innocence Lost and Found: An Untraced Copy Traced,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 15.3 (winter 1981-82):
125-31, with illus. of “The Shepherd,” “The Little Black Boy” (2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> pl.), “The
Little Boy Found,” and “Cradle Song” (2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> pl.).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Windle and I, the only dedicated Blakeans in attendance, viewed the prints an hour
before the auction. The color reproductions in the catalogue were pale, suggesting that the color washes had
faded. The originals proved to be in good condition with delicate, unfaded coloring. Most of the plates had
highlights in liquefied gold, a medium not mentioned in the catalogue. Although not as brightly tinted as
copies of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> Blake produced in the 1820s, copy Y includes splendid examples
of his mature style. Perhaps miniature portraiture, which Blake began to practice in 1801, influenced the
subtle coloring effects evident in the copy Y impressions at Sotheby’s.</p>
                    <p>We believed that all lots would easily exceed their surprisingly modest estimates. Our
prediction proved accurate, as the prices recorded below indicate. Most lots attracted three or four bidders
in the early rounds, but bidding on each lot evolved into a contest between Windle, acting on my behalf, and
the collector Alan Parker on the telephone from London. Windle won four lots, with Parker the underbidder on
each; the roles were reversed on the remaining two lots. “The Divine Image” established a record price for
a single plate from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> or <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>; “The
Little Black Boy” set a record for any two plates from one of Blake’s illuminated books. Two lots fetched
over ten times high estimate, a rare occurrence at any auction. It was a spirited contest lasting about eight
minutes.</p>
                    <p>No sales review would be complete without a few words about Blake’s watercolors
illustrating Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, offered for sale at Sotheby’s New York on 2 May
2006.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> On 2 April 2007, Windle saw 
<hi rend="i">The Day of Judgment</hi> watercolor hanging in Sam Fogg’s book and antique shop, 15d Clifford
Street, London. Fogg stated that the work was “not presently for sale,” but would give no further
information. His comment makes me suspect that he does not own the drawing; perhaps a friend or customer left
it in the shop to spice up the décor. Fogg may have been one of the agents for the collectors who acquired
three of the designs shortly after their failure to sell at auction, including <hi rend="i">The Day of
Judgment.</hi> The latest rumors in London are that one or two were bought by David Thomson, Toronto, and one
by Leon Black, New York. As of April 2007, the London dealer Libby Howie and her financial backer still had
five <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors: <hi rend="i">Whilst Surfeited upon Thy Damask Cheek, The Descent of
Man into the Vale of Death, The Gambols of Ghosts, The Counseller, King, Warrior, Mother and Child, in the
Tomb</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Death of the Good Old Man.</hi> Howie has not placed prices on these drawings
but will consider substantial offers. <note id="n4">4. For details, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.4 (spring
2007): 116-17, 120-26, and the various articles listed in 116n1 of that issue.</note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p41-141" n="141"/>
                    <p>The April/May 2007 issue of <hi rend="i">Rare Book Review</hi> offers an essay by R. M.
Healey, “First Impressions,” about a plate-printing and publishing firm, “The Thomas Ross Collection,”
located in Binfield, Berkshire. A sentence on page 52 caught my attention: “The plates by William Blake,
which are the most valuable in the [Ross] Collection, and which are secreted away in another part of the
building, also required more notice to retrieve, and so I had to be content with seeing one of the Turner
aquatint plates. . . .” The context indicates that the references are to metal “plates,” not impressions
from them. the only Blake print offered in the Ross online catalogue &lt;http://www.thomasross.co.uk&gt; is a
reduced reengraving (or photogravure or zincograph) of “Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims” in the third state
(of five) with a platemark of 20.3 × 48.3 cm. The original copperplate, measuring 35.7 × 97.05 cm., has been
in the Yale University Art Gallery since 1973. The Ross Collection is the successor to Dixon &amp; Ross, the
printers of Blake’s Dante engravings in 1838 who later operated under the name Thomas Ross &amp; Son, at
least until the 1980s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> All of the
“Blake” plates in the Ross Collection are reproductions, as will be explained in an article by G. E.
Bentley, Jr., forthcoming in this journal. <note id="n5">5. See <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 544-45 and Anthony Dyson,
<hi rend="i">Pictures to Print: The Nineteenth-Century Engraving Trade</hi> (London: Farrand P, 1984)
xxvi.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>An article by Harriet Rubin in the 21 July issue of the <hi rend="i">New York
Times</hi> includes the following paragraph:
<q>
Until recently when Steven P. Jobs of Apple sold his collection, he reportedly had an “inexhaustible
interest” in the books of William Blake—the mad visionary 18th-century mystic poet and artist. Perhaps
future historians will track down Mr. Jobs’s Blake library to trace the inspiration for Pixar and the
grail-like appeal of the iPhone.
</q>
I have received several inquiries about Jobs’s collection, presumed to contain significant works. I cannot
trace any original work by “the mad visionary” to his ownership and I had never heard of this collection
until learning of the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> article. Some readers assumed that the two-word quotation in the
passage above was uttered by Windle, quoted elsewhere in the essay about non-Blakean matters. He tells me that
he never said any such thing and that he has never met Jobs or sold anything to him. A digital legend in the
making?</p>
                    <p>In my 2006 sales review I noted that there was a mysterious “confusion surrounding
the sale” of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tiriel Led by Hela</hi> (Butlin #198.10) at Sotheby’s London, 23
November 2006, #192.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> In August 2007 I
learned from Sotheby’s that this wash drawing had not been sold and remains in the ownership of Connie,
David, and Richard Kain, the heirs of Mrs. Louise Y. Kain of Louisville, Kentucky. Sotheby’s had hoped to
offer the drawing again at a New York auction in January 2008, but negotiations with the owners came to
naught. <note id="n6">6. <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.4 (spring 2007): 117-18, 127, and illus. 10.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The London art world was abuzz, through the summer and fall of 2007, with rumors about
yet another major Blake discovery. On 13 November, Tim Linnell told me about a story in the 11 November issue
of the <hi rend="i">Observer</hi> concerning these works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> The author of the article, Vanessa Thorpe, reports that Tate Britain is exhibiting eight
recently discovered color prints by Blake. She does not indicate as much, but the group was clearly once part
of <hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi> copy B (and/or a previously unidentified copy C?). I have learned
from another source that the present owner, who acquired the works at a furniture auction many years ago,
brought the prints to the Victoria and Albert Museum, where they were identified. Thorpe states that the
following lines are written “beside an image” of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> pl. 23: “Fearless
though in pain I travel on”; <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> pl. 16 is captioned “Who
shall set the prisoners free?” According to the Tate’s web site, all eight prints are included in an
exhibition entitled William Blake: “I still go on / Till the Heavens and Earth are gone,” running at Tate
Britain from 3 November 2007 through 1 June 2008.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref> The color prints are described only as “the private loans of recently discovered works
which have never before been exhibited.” I suspect that the Tate is attempting to purchase the group. 
<note id="n7">7. &lt;http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,2209033,00.html&gt;, accessed 13 Nov. Another
story appeared on the CBC.ca arts web site on 12 Nov. &lt;http://www.cbc.ca/arts/artdesign/story/2007/11/12/
blake-watercolours-tate.html&gt;. The latter repeats much of the information in the <hi rend="i">Observer</hi>
article, but adds that the prints “were discovered after someone tried to sell them at an auction earlier in
2007.” I have no independent information about such an auction.</note>
                        <note id="n8">8. &lt;http://www.tate.org.uk/britain/exhibitions/blake/&gt;, accessed
13 Nov. The subtitle of the exhibition is quoted from Blake’s Notebook poem beginning “The Caverns of the
Grave Ive seen” (E 480).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Robin Hamlyn, the curator at Tate Britain in charge of the Blake collection, has very
kindly sent me a list of the newly discovered prints, each on a leaf of wove paper ranging between 25.0 ×
18.2 and 26.7 × 18.7 cm. Seven of the eight designs bear pen and ink inscriptions by Blake. All include
multiple ink framing lines, as with other impressions from <hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi> copy B;
each is numbered by Blake, as with five previously recorded impressions in copy B. The group includes the
designs on the following illuminated-book plates: <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> pl. 7; <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> pl. 16; and <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> pls. 7, 11, 12, 17, 19, 23.
All but <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 17 are inscribed on the verso, “This Coloured print by W<hi
rend="s">m</hi> Blake / Was given to me by his widow / Frederick Tatham Sculptor.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> Except for <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 12, impressions
(probably the first pulls) of these designs appear in <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> copy A in the British
Museum. Another impression of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 12, now in the Morgan Library and Museum (Butlin
#261.10), has been included as part of <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> copy B by modern scholars, but it is
trimmed to the image and thus lacks framing lines and an inscribed number (if once present). Yet a third
color-printed
<pb id="p41-142" n="142"/>
impression of pl. 12 (Butlin #280, British Museum) has not been associated with either copy of 
<hi rend="i">Small Book.</hi> Two impressions of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 3 are included in modern
reconstructions of <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> copy B. Two plates are numbered “9,” 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> pl. 14 in the National Gallery of Art, Washington (Butlin #261.3), and 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 7 in the new group. These several repetitions lead me to speculate that Blake may
have begun, c. 1818 or later, to assemble two sets of <hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi>—copy B and
what we might call copy C—using illuminated-book illustrations color printed c. 1794-96.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Hamlyn and Martin Butlin are preparing an
essay on the newly discovered color prints for publication in this journal. <note id="n9">9. Tatham wrote the
same inscription on the verso of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 1 in <hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi>
copy B (Butlin #261.1, Keynes Family Trust).</note>
                        <note id="n10">10. <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> copy A, and the second pulls that
constitute most of copy B, were printed in 1796. <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pls. 9, 12, and 22 (Butlin
#261.9-11) are considered to be part of copy B but they are not present in copy A. All three examples (I have
not seen the impression of pl. 12 in the new group) have thinner color printing, but more extensive hand
coloring, than their companions. These full-page designs may have been printed as part of Blake’s production
of color-printed copies of <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> in 1794 and not incorporated into 
<hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> until c. 1818 or later.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The year of all sales and catalogues in the following lists is 2007 unless indicated
otherwise. Dates for online catalogues are the dates accessed, not the dates of publication. Works offered
online and previously listed in either of the last two sales reviews are not repeated here. The auction houses
add their purchaser’s surcharge to the hammer price in their price lists. These net amounts are given here,
following the official price lists. The value-added tax levied against the buyer’s surcharge in Britain is
not included. Late 2007 sales will be covered in the 2008 review. I am grateful for help in compiling this
review to G. E. Bentley, Jr., Nancy Bialler, Detlef Dörrbecker, Emmeline Hallmark, Robin Hamlyn, Tim Linnell,
David Redden, Robert Smith, Steven Tabor, Joseph Viscomi, and John Windle. My special thanks go to Alexander
Gourlay for his generosity in keeping me abreast of internet auctions. Once again, Sarah Jones’s editorial
expertise and John Sullivan’s electronic imaging have been invaluable.</p>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <table rows="25" cols="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P,
1977). Plate numbers and copy designations for Blake’s illuminated books follow <hi rend="i">BB.</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (Oxford:
Clarendon P, 1995)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>BH</cell>
                                <cell>Bonhams, auctioneers, London</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>BL</cell>
                                <cell>Bloomsbury Auctions, London</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>BNY</cell>
                                <cell>Bloomsbury Auctions, New York</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)</cell>
                                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven:
Yale UP, 2004)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Butlin</cell>
                                <cell>Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New Haven: Yale UP, 1981)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>cat.</cell>
                                <cell>catalogue or sales list issued by a dealer (usually followed by a number
or letter designation)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="i">CB</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
Illustrations</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1991)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>CL</cell>
                                <cell>Christie’s, London</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>CNY</cell>
                                <cell>Christie’s, New York</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Coxhead</cell>
                                <cell>A. C. Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London: Bullen,
1906)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>CSK</cell>
                                <cell>Christie’s, South Kensington</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>E</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed.
David V. Erdman, newly rev. ed. (New York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>EB</cell>
                                <cell>eBay online auctions</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="i">F</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Early Engravings of Flaxman’s
Classical Designs</hi> (New York: New York Public Library, 1964)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>illus.</cell>
                                <cell>the item or part thereof is reproduced in the catalogue</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>PBA</cell>
                                <cell>Pacific Book Auction Galleries, San Francisco</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>pl(s).</cell>
                                <cell>plate(s)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>SL</cell>
                                <cell>Sotheby’s, London</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>SNY</cell>
                                <cell>Sotheby’s, New York</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="i">SP</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
Catalogue</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>st(s).</cell>
                                <cell>state(s) of an engraving, etching, or lithograph</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Swann</cell>
                                <cell>Swann, auctioneers, New York</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>#</cell>
                                <cell>auction lot or catalogue item number</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Illuminated Books</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy Y. SNY, 1 Nov., 8 pls. only (of 15) on 8
leaves of wove paper, printed in light-brown ink (pls. 4, 5, 10, 12, 16, 17), reddish-brown ink (pl. 9), and
blue ink (pl. 18), each leaf bearing the blind-stamped collection mark of Heinrich Neuerburg lower
right.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Relief etchings, some with
white-line etching, hand colored and with pen and black ink border lines contiguous with the edges of the
images. Selected motifs on all pls. outlined in pen and black ink; highlights added in liquefied gold on pls.
4, 5, 9, 12, 17, 18. Numbered in pen and black ink by Blake. Sold in the following lots, all illus. color:
<note id="n11">11. For illus., see Frits Lugt, <hi rend="i">Les Marques de Collections de Dessins et
d’Estampes: Supplément</hi> (La Haye: Martinus Nijhoff, 1956) 190 #1344a. Heinrich Neuerburg died in 1956.
Apparently his heir, Walter Neuerburg, who acquired copy Y in March 1962, continued to use the Heinrich
Neuerburg collection mark. Dr. Walter Neuerburg is recorded as the owner of copy Y in Dörrbecker (see note 3,
above) and <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 120.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>#16. Pl. 4, “Introduction,” numbered “3” top right. Image 11.9 × 7.9 cm.
on leaf 20.3 × 14.5 cm. with a BUTTA[NSHAW] watermark. $28,000 to John Windle acting for Robert Essick;
estimate $3000-5000. See illus. 1.</p>
                        <pb id="p41-143-144" n="143-144"/>
                        <figure n="s-inn.RY.P2-4" rend="file" width="669" height="1000">
                            <figTranscr>
                                3 <lb/>
<lb/>
                                Introduction <lb/>
<lb/>
                                Piping down the valleys wild<lb/>
                                Piping songs of pleasant glee<lb/>
                                On a cloud I saw a child.<lb/>
                                And he laughing said to me.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                Pipe a song about a Lamb:<lb/>
                                So I piped with merry chear,<lb/>
                                Piper pipe that song again__<lb/>
                                So I piped, he wept to hear.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                Drop thy pipe thy happy pipe<lb/>
                                Sing thy songs of happy chear<lb/>
                                So I sung the same again<lb/>
                                While he wept with joy to hear<lb/>
<lb/>
                                Piper sit thee down and write<lb/>
                                In a book that all may read__<lb/>
                                So he vanish’d from my sight<lb/>
                                And I pluck’d a hollow reed.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                And I made a rural pen,<lb/>
                                And I stain’d the water clear,<lb/>
                                And I wrote my happy songs<lb/>
                                Every child may joy to hear
                            </figTranscr>
                            <head>1. “Introduction” (pl. 4), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy
Y.</head>
                            <figDesc>Relief etching, possibly with touches of white-line etching. Hand tinted
with watercolors and liquefied gold, some motifs outlined in pen and black ink. Numbered “3” top right in
pen and black ink. Image 11.9 × 7.9 cm. on leaf 20.3 × 14.5 cm. (the reproduction here has been cropped to
the etched image and the inscribed number). Essick collection.<lb/>
                                <lb/>
In most early impressions, Blake did not print the part of the copperplate, approximately 6 mm. high, below
the base of the large intertwined vines. This strip is printed in copies I, L, O, T<hi rend="s">2</hi>-W, Y,
Z, and AA of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>; all show at least printed fragments of
the reliefetching dike at the bottom margin of the pl. The ghostly outline of the upper edge of the dike is
barely visible in copy C of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and in some posthumous impressions (e.g.,
copy h). Blake lightly printed the strip here in copy Y of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, but the inked edges of
the etching dike are almost completely obscured by the brown watercolor wash that apparently represents the
earth from which the vines grow. In this same area in some copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>, Blake added grass (e.g., the green washes in copy L), or earth with possibly a bit of green
grass (e.g., copy I), or water (e.g., copies O, R [even though the strip is not printed], T<hi
rend="s">2</hi>-W, Y, Z, AA).<lb/>
                                <lb/>
Copies R and Y of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> were almost certainly issued by Blake as a single, complete copy
of the book. The fragments of a Buttanshaw (probably Buttanshaw 1802) watermark on several pls. in copy Y
suggest a printing date of c. 1802 for the impressions in light-brown ink. The brown ink of “A Dream” and
“On Anothers Sorrow” in copy R, and “The Lamb,” “Laughing Song,” and the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> pl.
of “The Little Black Boy” in copy Y, is noticeably darker and more reddish; these 5 pls. may have been
printed at some later time in order to have a supply of prints sufficient to make up a complete copy of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi> The 5 impressions in copies R and Y in blue ink were probably also produced at a
later time, possibly c. 1807 when Blake may have been printing <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy M and some
proofs from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in that color. Blake numbered the pls. in copy R/Y consecutively, 1
through 28 top right in black ink, and used the same ink (and possibly the same pen or stylus) to outline most
of the pls. with framing lines contiguous with the edges of the pls. and to strengthen the outlines of some
motifs in the designs.<lb/>
                                <lb/>
The sequence of pen and ink numbers allows us to reconstruct the original contents and plate sequence of copy
R/Y. Four numbers are missing: 2, 20, 21, and 26. Number 2 was the title page; number 20 must have been the
2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> pl. of “Night” since the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> pl. of that poem is numbered 19.
Numbers 21 and 26 were almost certainly “The School Boy” and “The Voice of the Ancient Bard.” This
sequence of plates is identical to <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy S and the 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> section of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy S, both printed
on paper with a Whatman 1808 watermark. All 3 copies were probably collated and numbered in the same order c.
1811, the date of printing ascribed to copy S of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and the 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> section of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy S in Joseph
Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993) 311, 378. The only
numbering variant among these 3 copies is the absence of a pen and ink number “1” on the frontispiece in
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy S. The sequence in these 3 copies—<hi rend="i">BB</hi> pls. 2-21,
53, 22-25, 54, 26, 27—accords with the arrangement in the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> section of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy R, mostly printed in 1795 and possibly collated at
that time (see Viscomi 311-12). In 7 late copies of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, beginning with
copies T<hi rend="s">2</hi> and U of 1818, Blake moved “The School Boy” and “The Voice of the Ancient
Bard” to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, but otherwise followed the sequence in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>
established by copy R of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and followed in copy R/Y of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi> Blake did not include “The Little Girl Lost” and “The Little Girl Found” 
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> pls. 34-36) in either copy R/Y or S of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>; in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copies R and S these companion poems appear in the 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> section. The c. 1811 dating for the numbering of the pls. in copy R/Y suggests that
the pen and black ink outlining in the designs was also executed at that time. The highlights in liquefied
gold on most plates in copy R/Y may have also been added at this late date when Blake was using gold in copy S
of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and copy S of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <lb/>
The use of impressions in 3 ink colors, possibly from 2 or 3 different printing sessions, and the weak
printing in some pls. suggest that copy R/Y may have been a reclamation project, like copy E of the combined
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, prepared for and sold to Thomas Butts in 1806. That is, to create copy R/Y in about
1811, Blake brought together impressions set aside after their original printing, colored them uniformly (or
added some touches if already colored), and, where necessary, augmented the texts with washes or pen and ink
work. For example, in the “Introduction” pl. of copy Y he wrote over the title in a mixture of brown wash
and liquefied gold to strengthen the letters. In “The Shepherd,” several words at the end of lines printed
lightly; Blake darkened these with pen and ink.<lb/>
                                <lb/>
We do not know when copy R/Y left Blake’s hands. The book was probably divided into 2 separate copies after
it was damaged in a fire in the 1890s. The absence of the 4 pls. noted above from copies R and Y may be
explained by the same accident. The earliest record of either copy is the sale of copy R, the “Property of
Major T. E. Dimsdale,” at SL, 24 Nov. 1952, #99 (£240 to “Armstrong,” probably a dealer acting for
Geoffrey Keynes). The statement in the 1952 cat. that the copy was “acquired by the first Baron Dimsdale
(1712-1800)” could not be true if a <hi rend="i">terminus a quo</hi> of 1802 is correct for the printing of
the pls. Copy Y was sold as “The Property of a Gentleman” at SL, 12 March 1962, #151 (£1000 to
“Fairbrother”—the Swiss dealer Nicolas Rauch acting for Walter Neuerburg). Sotheby’s 1 Nov. 2007 cat.,
offering 8 pls. from copy Y, states that it (or, more probably, copy R/Y) was acquired by “the Dimsdale
family, Hertfordshire, c. 1811.” This date is probably based on the belief that copy R/Y was collated at
that time, possibly after Blake had received a purchase order.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="s-inn.RY.P7-9" rend="file" width="614" height="1000">
                            <figTranscr>
                                8 <lb/>
<lb/>
                                The Little Black Boy <lb/>
<lb/>
                                My mother bore me in the southern wild,<lb/>
                                And I am black, but O! my soul is white.<lb/>
                                White as an angel is the English child:<lb/>
                                But I am black as if bereav’d of light.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                My mother taught me underneath a tree<lb/>
                                And sitting down before the heat of day.<lb/>
                                She took me on her lap and kissed me,<lb/>
                                And pointing to the east began to say.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                Look on the rising sun: there God does live<lb/>
                                And gives his light. and gives his heat away.<lb/>
                                And flowers and trees and beasts and men recieve<lb/>
                                Comfort in morning joy in the noon day.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                And we are put on earth a little space.<lb/>
                                That we may learn to bear the beams of love,<lb/>
                                And these black bodies and this sun-burnt face<lb/>
                                Is but a cloud, and like a shady grove.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                For
                            </figTranscr>
                            <head>2. “The Little Black Boy,” 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> pl. (pl. 9), 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy Y.</head>
                            <figDesc>Relief etching with touches of white-line etching. Hand tinted with
watercolors and liquefied gold, some motifs outlined in pen and black ink. Numbered “8” top right in pen
and black ink. Image 11.2 × 6.9 cm. on leaf 20.8 × 14.3 cm. (the reproduction here has been cropped to the
etched image and the inscribed number). Essick collection. Blake has carefully outlined the woman’s right
hand and extended index finger pointing toward the sun. Uncolored impressions show that her hand was not
etched (or at least not clearly etched) on the copperplate. The hand and finger are also added to 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copies L (1789) and O (c. 1802) and, less clearly, to a few 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi> -century copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (e.g., E, Y, Z,
AA). See the caption to illus. 1 for general comments on <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy Y.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p41-145" n="145"/>
                        <p>#17. Pl. 5, “The Shepherd,” numbered “4” top right. Image 11.1 × 7.0 cm.
on leaf 20.3 × 14.0 cm. with a deckle edge at the bottom. $109,000 to John Windle acting for Robert Essick;
estimate $35,000-45,000. For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 15.3 (winter 1981-82): 127.</p>
                        <p>#18. Pls. 9-10, “The Little Black Boy,” numbered “8” and “9” top right.
Images 11.2 × 6.9 cm. (pl. 9) and 10.5 × 6.7 cm. (pl. 10) on 2 leaves, 20.8 × 14.3 cm. (pl. 9) and 20.7 ×
14.2 cm. (pl. 10). $193,000 to John Windle acting for Robert Essick; estimate $45,000-65,000. The boy furthest
to the left in pl. 10 has a darker skin color than the other boy, as in some early copies (e.g., 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> L and Z; I, L, and R of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>) and most 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century copies (e.g., E, T<hi rend="s">2</hi>-W, Y, and Z of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
                            <figure n="s-inn.RY.P10-12" rend="file" width="434" height="668">
                                <figTranscr>
                                    11<lb/>
<lb/>
                                    The Chimney Sweeper<lb/>
<lb/>
                                    When my mother died I was very young.<lb/>
                                    And my father sold me while yet my tongue,<lb/>
                                    Could scarcely cry weep weep weep weep.<lb/>
                                    So your chimneys I sweep &amp; in soot I sleep.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                    Theres little Tom Dacre, who cried when his head<lb/>
                                    (That curl’d like a lambs back, was shav’d. so I said.<lb/>
                                    Hush Tom never mind it, for when your head’s bare.<lb/>
                                    You know that the soot cannot spoil your white hair.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                    And so he was quiet, &amp; that very night.<lb/>
                                    As Tom was a sleeping he had such a sight,<lb/>
                                    That thousands of sweepers Dick, Joe Ned &amp; Jack<lb/>
                                    Were all of them lock’d up in coffins of black,<lb/>
<lb/>
                                    And by came an Angel who had a bright key.<lb/>
                                    And he open’d the coffins &amp; set them all free.<lb/>
                                    (run<lb/>
                                    Then down a green plain leaping laughing they r<lb/>
                                    And wash in a river and shine in the Sun.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                    Then naked &amp; white, all their bags left behind,<lb/>
                                    They rise upon clouds, and sport in the wind,<lb/>
                                    And the Angel told Tom if he’d be a good boy.<lb/>
                                    He’d have God for his father &amp; never want joy.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                    And so Tom awoke and we rose in the dark<lb/>
                                    And got with our bags &amp; our brushes to work.<lb/>
                                    Tho’ the morning was cold, Tom was happy &amp; warm.<lb/>
                                    So if all do their duty, they need not fear harm.
                                </figTranscr>
                                <head>3. “The Chimney Sweeper” (pl. 12), <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> copy Y.</head>
                                <figDesc>Relief etching with touches of white-line etching. Hand tinted with
watercolors and liquefied gold, some motifs outlined in pen and black ink. Numbered “11” top right in pen
and black ink. Image 11.3 × 7.3 cm. on leaf 21.4 × 15.0 cm. (the reproduction here has been cropped to the
etched image and the inscribed number). By leaving a circle of uncolored paper around the head of “the
Angel” lower right, Blake has given him a halo. Blake used the same technique to add halos in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy O (c. 1802) and in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> copies R (1795), E (coloring completed in 1806), T<hi rend="s">2</hi> (printed and colored in
1818), and Y (printed and colored in 1825). The halo is a golden disc in copy V of the combined 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (1821). In copy W (1825), Blake left a narrow ring of uncolored paper at some distance
from this Christ-figure’s head; copies Z and AA (both 1826) include an uncolored area near the head and a
gold ring. See the caption to illus. 4 for similar halos and the caption to illus. 1 for general comments on
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy Y. Collection of Alan Parker, London; photo courtesy of Sotheby’s New
York.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
                            <hi rend="i">of Innocence and of Experience</hi>). The copperplate extends about 7
mm. below the relief image on pl. 10. Blake left this area uncolored in this impression and in most copies of
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (e.g., B, D, G, I, L, O, Z) and most early copies of the combined 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (e.g., A-C, F, R), but added watercolors to extend the earth or water at the bottom of the
design into this lower area in copies I and L of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (both
printed 1795) and most later copies (e.g., T<hi rend="s">2</hi>-W, Y, Z, AA). See illus. 2 (pl. 9) and 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 15.3 (winter 1981-82): 127 (pl. 10).</p>
                        <p>#19. Pl. 12, “The Chimney Sweeper,” numbered “11” top right. Image 11.3 ×
7.3 cm. on leaf 21.4 × 15.0 cm. $73,000 to Alan Parker, London; estimate $3000-5000. See illus. 3.</p>
                        <pb id="p41-146" n="146"/>
                        <p>#20. Pl. 18, “The Divine Image,” numbered “17” top right. Image 11.1 × 6.9
cm. on leaf 20.1 × 13.6 cm. $121,000 to John Windle acting for Robert Essick; estimate $5000-10,000. See
illus. 4.</p>
                        <p>#21. Pls. 16-17, “A Cradle Song,” numbered “15” and “16” top right.
11.3 × 7.2 cm. (pl. 16) and 11.3 × 7.1 cm. (pl. 17) on 2 leaves, 20.8 × 14.9 cm. (pl. 16) and 20.9 × 14.4
cm. (pl. 17), both with a BUTTA[NSHAW] watermark. $115,000 to Alan Parker, London; estimate $10,000-15,000.
See illus. 5 (pl. 16) and <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 15.3 (winter 1981-82): 129 (pl. 17).</p>
                        <p>See also comments above in the prefatory essay.</p>
                        <figure n="s-inn.RY.P16-18" rend="file" width="624" height="1000">
                            <figTranscr>
                                17<lb/>
<lb/>
                                The Divine Image. <lb/>
<lb/>
                                To Mercy Pity Peace and Love.<lb/>
                                All pray in their distress:<lb/>
                                And to these virtues of delight<lb/>
                                Return their thankfulness.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                For Mercy Pity Peace and Love,<lb/>
                                Is God our father dear;<lb/>
                                And Mercy Pity Peace and Love,<lb/>
                                Is Man his child and care.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                For Mercy has a human heart<lb/>
                                Pity, a human face:<lb/>
                                And Love, the human form divine.<lb/>
                                And Peace, the human dress.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                Then every man of every clime,<lb/>
                                That prays in his distress,<lb/>
                                Prays to the human form divine<lb/>
                                Love Mercy Pity Peace,<lb/>
<lb/>
                                And all must love the human form.<lb/>
                                In heathen, turk or jew,<lb/>
                                Where Mercy. Love &amp; Pity dwell,<lb/>
                                There God is dwelling too.
                            </figTranscr>
                            <head>4. “The Divine Image” (pl. 18), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
copy Y.</head>
                            <figDesc>Relief etching with whiteline etching. Hand tinted with watercolors and
liquefied gold, some motifs outlined in pen and black ink. Numbered “17” top right in pen and ink. Image
11.1 × 6.9 cm. on leaf 20.1 × 13.6 cm. (the reproduction here has been cropped to the etched image and the
inscribed number). Essick collection. Where thinly printed, the blue ink looks gray. With pen and ink
outlining, Blake has emphasized the narrow neck and flared mouth of the pitcher (or some such vessel) held in
the lowered left hand of the walking figure, upper left. The raised and extended hand of the standing figure,
lower right, is touched with a thin line of gold. Blake has also given a halo to this Christ-figure by leaving
an uncolored area around his head. Similar halos, executed with the same technique, appear in many 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century impressions, including <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copies Q and S and 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copies E, L, S, T<hi rend="s">2</hi>, V, Y, Z, and AA. The
halo in copy W of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> encompasses the figure’s upper body as well as his
head. See the caption to illus. 3 for similar halos and the caption to illus. 1 for general comments on 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy Y.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> posthumous copy o, 3 pls.
only: “Nurses Song” (pl. 24) from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, “Nurses Song” (pl. 38) from 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, and “The School Boy” (pl. 53). The impressions offered in John Windle’s Nov.
2006 cat. were acquired in Jan. by the Victoria University Library, Toronto. For further information about
these prints, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.4 (spring 2007): 119.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> copy N. Sold late 2006 by
private treaty through SNY to a private collector (probably over $2 million). See comments above in the
prefatory essay.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="p41-147" n="147"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Drawings and Paintings</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Paolo and Francesca(?).</hi> Pencil, approx. 19.0 × 11.0 cm. on leaf
21.3 × 37.4 cm. Butlin #816, dating the drawing to c. 1824-27. BH, 6 Feb., #90, illus. color (estimate
£6000-9000; withdrawn at least a week before the sale). See illus. 6.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">The Resurrection</hi> (recto), with studies of eyes, the head of an
eagle, a human face, and a lion (verso). Some of the verso sketches are related to Blake’s 1802 
<hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi> by William Hayley. Pen and gray ink, gray wash over pencil
(recto), pencil (verso), recto image and sheet 20.5 × 21.0 cm., recto datable to the mid-1780s. Butlin #610.
W/S Fine Art, Sept. flier, “Three Centuries of English, Scottish and Irish Oil Paintings and Works on
Paper,” no entry #, recto illus. color (not priced). For discussion, auction sale, and illus., see Martin
Butlin, “A Blake Drawing Rediscovered and Redated,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 34.1 (summer 2000): 22-24; and
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 120-21.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Two Studies of a Baby’s Head.</hi> Pencil, with touches of
watercolor on the lower head, leaf 37.4 × 26.2 cm. Butlin #788, dating the drawing to c. 1820. BH, 6 Feb.,
#91, illus. color (estimate £10,000-15,000; withdrawn at least a week before the sale). See illus 7.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">First Editions of Blake’s Writings First Published in
Letterpress in Blake’s Lifetime</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, 1783, <hi rend="i">BB</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">BBS</hi> copy E. Sold Jan. by James Edwards, Potomac, Maryland (the “American Collector” listed
in <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 107) to Alan Parker, London, through the San Francisco dealer John Windle ($250,000).
Edwards paid $170,000 for the book c. 1991, not the rumored “$265,000” noted in <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 107.
For an illus. of the title page, including Flaxman’s presentation inscription, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
40.4 (spring 2007), back cover.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <figure n="S-Inn.Y.CradleSong.41.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="620">
                        <figTranscr>
                            15<lb/>
<lb/>
                            A CRADLE SONG<lb/>
<lb/>
                            Sweet dreams form a shade<lb/>
                            O’er my lovely infants head.<lb/>
                            Sweet dreams of pleasant streams.<lb/>
                            By happy silent moony beams<lb/>
<lb/>
                            Sweet sleep with soft down.<lb/>
                            Weave thy brows an infant crown.<lb/>
                            Sweet sleep Angel mild,<lb/>
                            Hover o’er my happy child.<lb/>
<lb/>
                            Sweet smiles in the night,<lb/>
                            Hover over my delight<lb/>
                            Sweet smiles Mothers smiles<lb/>
                            All the livelong night beguiles.<lb/>
<lb/>
                            Sweet moans, dovelike sighs.<lb/>
                            Chase not slumber from thy eyes.<lb/>
                            Sweet moans, sweeter smiles.<lb/>
                            All the dovelike moans beguiles.<lb/>
<lb/>
                            Sleep sleep happy child.<lb/>
                            All creation slept and smil’d.<lb/>
                            Sleep sleep. happy sleep,<lb/>
                            While o’er thee thy mother weep<lb/>
<lb/>
                            Sweet babe in thy face.<lb/>
                            Holy image I can trace.<lb/>
                            Sweet babe once like thee.<lb/>
                            Thy maker lay and wept for me<lb/>
<lb/>
                            Wept
                        </figTranscr>
                        <head>5. “A Cradle Song,” 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> pl. (pl. 16), <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence</hi> copy Y.</head>
                        <figDesc>Relief etching with touches of white-line etching, hand colored and with some
motifs outlined in pen and black ink. Numbered “15” top right in pen and black ink. Image 11.3 × 7.2 cm.
on leaf 20.8 × 14.9 cm. (the full sheet is reproduced here). The plate is crooked, in relation to the edges
of the leaf, and thereby exemplifies Blake’s cavalier attitude toward conventional registration. See the
caption to illus. 1 for general comments on <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy Y. Collection of Alan Parker,
London; photo courtesy of Sotheby’s New York.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Separate Plates and Plates in Series</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>“Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims.” Larkhall Fine Art, Jan. private offer, 3<hi
rend="s">rd</hi> st., <hi rend="i">SP</hi> impression 3W, marginal tears (1 into the image) repaired
(£17,500). Cowan’s auction, Cincinnati, 13 Oct., #794, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., a Sessler impression with
the “France” watermark, illus. color online ($4500 to John Windle, who immediately sold it to the Victoria
University Library, Toronto).</p>
                        <p>Dante engravings. CNY, 30 Oct., #156, “The Circle of the Corrupt Officials”
only, some creases, marginal foxing and soiling, illus. color (not sold; estimate $6000-8000); #157, “The
Circle of the Falsifiers” only, some creases, marginal foxing and tears, illus. color (not sold; estimate
$6000-8000); #158, “The Circle of the Traitors” only, marginal tears and foxing, illus. color ($1625).</p>
                        <p>“George Cumberland’s Card.” One of 2 previously unrecorded impressions was on
consignment with John Windle by Oct. (price on request). For both impressions, see the appendix, 
<hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Job engravings. Skinner auction, Boston, 2 March, #42, pl. numbered 16 only, on
laid India, probably the 1874 printing since there is no clear evidence of the “Proof” inscription, foxed
(mostly in the margins), illus. color ($1600; estimate $300-350). Swann, 3 May, #244, pl. numbered 9 only,
1874 printing on laid India, illus. ($3200). Ursus Books, May cat. 262, #13, complete set, 1826 printing on
Whatman paper after the removal of the “Proof” inscription, tissue guards, later cloth-backed boards,
original cover label, housed in a later morocco box, previously offered for £40,000 by Sims Reed and for
$85,000 by Ursus, illus. ($85,000 again); same copy (?), Sims Reed, Aug. cat., #20, illus. color (£45,000).
BL, 11 June, #36, complete set, 1826 printing on Whatman paper after the removal of
<pb id="p41-148" n="148"/>
                            <figure n="PaoloFrancesca.41.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="296">
                                <figTranscr>
                                    Paolo &amp; Francesca<lb/>
                                    supposed for the Dante<lb/>
                                    by Wm. Blake<lb/>
                                    attested by Fred. Tatham
                                </figTranscr>
                                <head>6. <hi rend="i">Paolo and Francesca(?).</hi>
                                </head>
                                <figDesc>Pencil, approx. 19.0 × 11.0 cm. on leaf 21.3 × 37.4 cm. Inscribed
in ink lower right, “Paolo &amp; Francesca / supposed for the Dante / by W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake /
attested by Fred. Tatham.” Butlin #816, dating the drawing to c. 1824-27. The drawing can be dated to the
1820s on stylistic grounds, but Tatham’s supposition that it represents Paolo and Francesca is not supported
by their very different presentation in the Dante watercolor, <hi rend="i">The Circle of the Lustful</hi>
(Butlin #812.10), and the engraving based on it. Photo courtesy of Bonhams, London.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
the “Proof” inscription, modern cloth-backed boards, cover label initialed “J. L.” (John Linnell),
illus. color (£22,000). CL, 18 Sept., #163, complete set, 1826 printing on Whatman paper after the removal of
the “Proof” inscription, red pen and ink framing lines added just outside the platemarks, brown calf,
illus. color (£20,900). Swann, 20 Sept., 3 pls. in 3 lots, 1874 printing on laid India, all illus. color:
#103, pl. numbered 2 (not sold; estimate $2000-3000); #104, pl. numbered 3 ($1900); #105, pl. numbered 16
($3800); 31 Oct., #209, pl. numbered 6 only, 1874 printing on laid India, illus. color ($3400).</p>
                        <p>“Morning Amusement” and “Evening Amusement,” after Watteau. The previously
unrecorded impressions offered in John Windle’s Nov. 2006 cat. were acquired in Jan. by the Victoria
University Library, Toronto. For details, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.4 (spring 2007): 130.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, Including
Prints Extracted from Such Books</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Adams, <hi rend="i">New Royal Geographical Magazine</hi>, c. 1793. International
Book Sales, July online cat., with the 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> sts. of the 3 pls. by Blake first published in
Seally and Lyons, <hi rend="i">A Complete Geographical Dictionary</hi>, lacking the frontispiece (not by
Blake), pls. foxed and some with marginal tears, contemporary calf very worn, front cover detached, engraved
title page illus. color online ($1375). The only copy I have ever seen on the market. <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
252 locates only the copy in the Library Company of Philadelphia; the <hi rend="i">English Short-Title
Catalog</hi> &lt;http://estc.ucr.edu&gt; lists copies in the British Library, Cambridge University Library,
Dalhousie University, and Union Theological Seminary. See also comments in the appendix, <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando furioso.</hi> Valley Auctions, Dublin, Virginia, 13
April, #42, 1783 ed., 5 vols., scattered foxing, contemporary calf
<pb id="p41-149" n="149"/>
                            <figure n="BabysHead.41.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="604">
                                <figTranscr>
                                    Portrait of some<lb/>
                                    Infant by William Blake<lb/>
                                    vouched by Fredk. Tatham
                                </figTranscr>
                                <head>7. <hi rend="i">Two Studies of a Baby’s Head.</hi>
                                </head>
                                <figDesc>Pencil, with touches of watercolor on the lower head, leaf 37.4 ×
26.2 cm. Inscribed in ink lower right, “Portrait of some / Infant by William Blake / vouched by Fred<hi
rend="s">k</hi>. Tatham.” Butlin #788, dating the drawing to c. 1820. Blake pictures the same baby in a
pencil drawing of a single head, <hi rend="i">Study of a Baby’s Head</hi> (Butlin #789). Butlin, writing
about the version reproduced here, comments that “the date of the watermark, maddeningly illegible (if
indeed present at all) as the drawing is stuck down, might help to confirm a later date and so support
[Geoffrey] Keynes’s conjecture that the child was a member of the Linnell family.” Keynes’s comments
refer to the other drawing of the same head, but would seem reasonable if indeed both works date from the
1820s; see <hi rend="i">Drawings of William Blake: 92 Pencil Studies</hi>, ed. Keynes (New York: Dover, 1970),
#81. Tim Linnell, an expert on his family’s physiognomy, is dubious. Photo courtesy of Bonhams,
London.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
worn, illus. color online ($150). John Price, May cat., #2, 1785 ed., 5 vols., pls. foxed and browned,
contemporary calf worn (£300). EB, July-Aug., 1799 ed., 5 vols., marginal foxing on pls., contemporary half
calf worn, illus. color (£83). Calendula Horticultural Books, Sept. online cat., 1785 ed., 5 vols.,
contemporary calf very worn, covers detached ($195.95). Choice Books, Sept. online cat., 1799 ed., 5 vols.,
“covers worn” ($275). Bertrand Michel, Sept. online cat., 1799 ed., 5 vols., half calf very worn, spines
of 2 vols. missing ($1170.84). Taurus Books, Sept. online cat., 1785 ed., 5 vols., contemporary calf worn
($300). Adams &amp; Adams, Sept. online cat., 1783 ed., 5 vols., contemporary calf, binding illus. color
($1500). Havercroft Books, Sept. online cat., 1783 ed., 5 vols., Blake’s pl. detached, contemporary calf
worn (£385). Experienced Books, Sept. online cat., 1799 ed., vol. 3 only, presumably including Blake’s pl.,
“readable copy” ($19.50). First Place Books, Sept. online cat., 1783 ed., 5 vols. in 3, extra-illus. with
12 pls. (none related to Blake), later half calf ($1000). White Hills Farm, Sept. online cat., 1799 ed., 5
vols., later half calf worn, binding illus. ($400).</p>
                        <p>Blair, <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> EB, Dec. 2006-Jan., “1813” (actually 1870)
folio, some pls. stained, publisher’s cloth very worn, spine broken and leaves detached, illus. color
($500). Galerie Bassenge auction, Berlin, 26 April, #1182, 1813 quarto, half calf, illus. online ($955).
Brighton City Art, May online cat., pls. 7 and 12 only with 1813 imprints, illus. color (£139 each).
MacDonnell Books, June cat. 47, #10, 1808 quarto, “mild” foxing, “contemporary three-quarter [calf?] and
marbled boards” ($1500). EB, June, pl. 10 only, 1813 imprint, probably the 1870 printing, illus. color (no
bids on a required minimum bid of $249.95); same impression, also June, illus. color ($249.95); July, pl. 5
only, 1813 imprint, badly foxed and stained, illus. color ($184.20). Heritage Book Shop, Sept. online cat.,
1808 quarto, 1 pl. foxed, 3 with marginal stains, 20<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco ($2500). Old Tampa
Book Co., Sept. online cat., apparently the 1808 quarto, pls. browned and foxed, quarter calf ($2000). Stephen
Foster, Sept. online cat., 1813 quarto, pls. foxed, later quarter morocco (£850). Subun-So Book Store, Sept.
online cat., apparently the 1813 “folio” (but
<pb id="p41-150" n="150"/>
probably the quarto), some marginal foxing, original boards worn ($1779.39). PBA Galleries auction, San
Francisco, 13 Sept., #19, 1813 quarto, minor soiling, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco rebacked,
handsome binding illus. color online ($1440). EB, Oct., 1808 quarto, scattered foxing on the pls., pl. 1
(engraved title page) slightly trimmed into the image top and bottom, later quarter calf, illus. color (no
bids on a required minimum bid of £750); same copy, Nov. (£675). Leslie Hindman auction, Chicago, 30 Oct.,
#70, 1813 quarto, modern three-quarter calf, clamshell case, with Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Faber
Gallery, n.d., and Blake’s Job engravings, United Book Guild reproduction, 1947, binding of 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illus. ($700). PBA Galleries auction, San Francisco, 29 Nov., #19, 1808 quarto, imprint
trimmed off on title pl., scattered marginal foxing, contemporary calf very worn, rebacked, illus. color
online ($1300).</p>
                        <p>Bonnycastle, <hi rend="i">Introduction to Mensuration</hi>, 1794. Madoc Books, May
online cat., full “leather” worn (£75).</p>
                        <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Graphic Illustrations of . . . Shakspeare</hi>, c. 1803. BL,
14 Dec. 2006, #280, foxed, contemporary morocco rubbed, binding illus. color (not sold; estimate £300-500);
same copy, 17 May, #120, illus. color (£220). CSK, 21 March, #94, marginal browning and spotting, later cloth
(£288). Adrian Greenwood, Sept. online cat., minor marginal foxing, later buckram, illus. color (£595).</p>
                        <p>Bray, <hi rend="i">Life of Stothard</hi>, 1851. For an extra-illus. copy containing
14 pls. by Blake, see under Stothard, below.</p>
                        <p>Bryant, <hi rend="i">New System . . . of Ancient Mythology</hi>, 1774-76. EB, Feb.,
1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., 3 vols., contemporary calf repaired with new calf spines, illus. color (reserve not
met; highest bid $1000); same copy, Feb., offered at the “buy it now” price of $1900; same copy, April
($999); June, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 3 vols., marginal stains on some leaves, modern half calf, illus.
color ($797.03). Petersfield Bookshop, Sept. online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 3 vols., contemporary
calf rebacked (£550). Book Haven, Sept. online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 3 vols., some browning, later
calf ($400). Ian Hodgkins, Sept. online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 3 vols., contemporary half calf worn
(£280). Older Ways, Sept. online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., vols. 1-2 only, title page to vol. 1 illus.
color, no information on binding ($1000). Xerxes Books, Sept. online cat., apparently 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
ed., vols. 2-3 only, minor spotting, full calf ($200).</p>
                        <p>Catullus, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1795. Any Amount of Books, Sept. online cat., 2
vols., minor foxing, full calf worn (£104.50).</p>
                        <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Outlines from the Antients</hi>, 1829. Paul Grinke, June
cat. 2, #20, small-paper issue, “some foxing throughout,” later half morocco (£225).</p>
                        <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden.</hi> Jeff Weber, June cat. 140, #53, 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, both 1791, 2 vols. in 1, occasional
foxing, a few water stains, modern three-quarter calf, spine illus. color ($2500). Peace of Mind Bookstore,
Sept. online cat., 1799 ed., apparently 2 vols. in 1, foxed, “rebound” in cloth ($475). Grants Bookshop,
Sept. online cat., 1799 ed., apparently 2 vols. in 1, contemporary calf very worn ($327.19). Books on High,
Sept. online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, both 1791, 2
vols. in 1, pls. foxed, some pls. folded, contemporary quarter calf very worn, covers detached ($1050).
SessaBks, Sept. online cat., 1791 eds. (otherwise not described), lacking 3 pls. (including 2 by Blake of the
Portland Vase), modern buckram ($650). William H. Allen, Sept. online cat., apparently 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
ed. of Part 1, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, both 1791, 2 vols. in 1, half calf very worn, covers
detached ($700). EB, Oct., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, both
1791, 2 vols., at least 1 Portland Vase pl. trimmed into the image, occasional foxing, contemporary calf worn,
illus. color ($1225); Oct.-Nov., 1799 ed., Part 1 (“The Economy of Vegetation”) only, apparently with all
pls. by Blake, stains, contemporary calf worn, illus. color (£105.35).</p>
                        <p>Euler, <hi rend="i">Elements of Algebra</hi>, 1797. Beacon Books, Sept. online
cat., 2 vols., foxed, apparently quarter calf ($1400).</p>
                        <p>Flaxman, Hesiod designs, 1817. EB, Dec. 2006, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> issue with pl.
20 misnumbered “37,” foxed, contemporary calf, illus. color (£180.63); April-May, some foxing and water
staining, original boards with cover label very worn, back cover missing, illus. color ($272.82 to
“Oothoon,” presumably a pseudonym); July, scattered marginal foxing, later boards, illus. color (offered
only at the “buy it now” price of €545.95); same copy offered Sept., Oct., and Dec. at the same price.
BL, 12 July, #402, “browning throughout,” contemporary half morocco worn, front cover detached, illus.
color (not sold; estimate £300-500).</p>
                        <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs, 1805. EB, Feb., bound with Flaxman’s
<hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs, 1805, and his Aeschylus designs, 1795, scattered foxing and staining, 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century quarter calf, illus. color (£188). GDS Books, Sept. online cat., bound with
Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs, 1805, marginal tears, some into the images, quarter calf very
worn ($800). McLean Arts &amp; Books, Sept. online cat., foxed, modern three-quarter calf ($800). Kingswood
Books, Sept. online cat., dated to “1806” (probably an error for 1805), foxed, half calf worn (£250). EB,
Sept., foxed, three-quarter calf, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $750).</p>
                        <p>Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables.</hi> EB, Jan., 1793 ed., vol. 1 (of 2) only, contemporary
quarter calf very worn, spine broken, front cover detached, back cover missing, illus. color ($511—a
remarkable price for a complete wreck); March, [1811] ed., 2 vols. in 1, minor foxing to margins, contemporary
half calf, illus. color ($401.87). Swann, 17 May, #362, 1793 ed., 2 vols., scattered foxing, calf worn ($325).
BL, 11 June, #28, 1793 ed., 2 vols., slight offsetting, modern calf, illus. color (£600). John K. King, Sept.
online cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols., foxed, few leaves
<pb id="p41-151" n="151"/>
detached, contemporary calf very worn, vol. 1 covers detached ($747.50). Riverby Books, Sept. online cat.,
1793 ed., apparently vol. 2 only with 3 pls. by Blake, “full calf” ($400). Xerxes Books, Sept. online
cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols. in 1, three-quarter calf ($850). Ryan O’Horne, Sept. online cat., [1811] ed.,
apparently 2 vols. in 1, bound uniformly with Aesop, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, “1793” [also 1811?], 2
vols., scattered foxing, contemporary calf worn, illus. color (£1900). B. &amp; L. Rootenberg, Sept. online
cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols., bound uniformly with Aesop, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, 1793, 2 vols., “large paper
copy,” full calf ($4500). Rulon-Miller Books, Sept. online cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols., contemporary calf worn
($900); another copy, 2 vols., contemporary morocco, quarter morocco slipcase ($1500). Paul Foster, Sept.
online cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols., contemporary Russia worn (£950). Peter Harrington, Sept. online cat., 1793
ed., 2 vols., 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco worn (£1375). Alan Wofsy Fine Arts, Sept. online cat.,
1793 ed., 2 vols., contemporary quarter calf ($1100). Addyman Books, Sept. online cat., 1793 ed., 2 vols.,
lacking the title and contents page in vol. 1, final gathering “becoming separated,” foxed, contemporary
calf rebacked, worn (£300). Swann, 9 Nov., #110, 1793 ed., 2 vols., scattered foxing and damp staining,
“large-paper issue,” modern morocco ($950).</p>
                        <p>Hartley, <hi rend="i">Observations on Man</hi>, 1791. Rachel Lee Rare Books
(formerly Thoemmes Antiquarian Books), Sept. online cat., quarto issue, Blake’s pl. “spotted,”
contemporary half calf rebacked (£750).</p>
                        <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, 1805. EB, Jan., pl. 4 (“The Hermits Dog”)
only, slight stains in the inscription area, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $250).</p>
                        <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, 1800. Brand Books, Sept. online cat.,
later cloth very worn ($300).</p>
                        <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>, 1803-04. EB, Dec. 2006-Jan., vols. 1-2
(of 3) only, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., with Blake’s pls. 1-4, some spotting, contemporary calf very worn,
covers detached, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $137.50); Jan., pl. 1 only, title and
imprint trimmed off, illus. (no bids on a required minimum bid of $124). Brighton City Art, May online cat.,
pls. 3 (2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.) and 5 only, illus. color (£299 and £239). EB, May-June, pl. 1 only,
illus. color (£39.99); July, pl. 1 only, illus. color ($129); July, pl. 2 only, probably 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> st., illus. color ($124). BL, 19-20 July, #694, apparently 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., vols.
1-2 bound in 1, some foxing, later half calf (vols. 1-2) and contemporary calf (vol. 3), with the 1806
supplement in original boards worn (not sold; estimate £100-150).</p>
                        <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi>, 1809. James Fenning, Sept. cat. 236,
#210, minor foxing, half morocco slightly worn (£650). EB, Nov., Blake’s pl. only, marginal browning,
illus. color ($51).</p>
                        <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 1803. W. G. Stuart, Sept. online
cat., apparently the small-paper issue, contemporary calf rebacked ($450). Jarndyce, Sept. online cat.,
apparently the small-paper issue, some pls. spotted, later calf worn (£863). Kurt Gippert, Sept. online cat.,
apparently the small-paper issue, calf rebacked ($850). Thornton’s Bookshop, Sept. online cat., large-paper
issue, light foxing, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco rebacked (£1200); another copy, apparently the
small-paper issue, lacking pl. 1, foxed, disbound (£150).</p>
                        <p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">The Beggar’s Opera by Hogarth and Blake</hi>, 1965.
Antiquariaat Van Coevorden, Sept. online cat., with the restrike from Blake’s pl. as issued, original
folding box ($503).</p>
                        <p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> EB, July, Blake’s pl. only, said to be from
“the 1837 restrike edition,” probably 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> or 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. color
($102). Adrian Greenwood, Sept. online cat., 1822 ed., frontispiece and title page stained, contemporary half
morocco worn, illus. color (£1295). Subun-So Book Store, 1822 ed., three-quarter morocco ($6025). Christian
Heritage Museum, Sept. online cat., 1822 ed., half calf ($4200). Robert Frew, Sept. online cat., undated
Baldwin and Cradock issue, minor spotting, contemporary half morocco (£2250). Argosy Book Store, Sept. online
cat., undated Baldwin and Cradock issue, three-quarter calf worn ($4000). D &amp; E Lake, Sept. online cat.,
undated Baldwin and Cradock issue, contemporary half morocco worn ($4500). The “1822” eds. may be the
Quaritch reissue of c. 1880 dated “1822” on the title page.</p>
                        <p>Hunter, <hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi>, quarto issue, 1793. CNY, 17 April,
#272, some spotting, title page cropped into the text at the upper margin, contemporary calf repaired, illus.
color ($2400). Michael Sharpe, Sept. cat. 1, #64, title page cropped top and bottom, contemporary calf, joints
repaired, binding illus. color ($7500). Rambler Rare Books, Sept. online cat., no information on binding
($3750). Family Album, Sept. online cat., lacking the engraved title page and 2 pls. but apparently with
Blake’s pl., some pls. repaired with tape, foxed, disbound ($800). Kenneth Hince, Sept. online cat.,
contemporary half calf rebacked, recent cloth box ($3295). Grant &amp; Shaw, Sept. cat. 73, #80, “large
paper copy” trimmed to 29.5 × 23.8 cm., late 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century calf (£3200).</p>
                        <p>Josephus, <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> EB, April, probably <hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue
B, contemporary calf very worn, lacking front cover, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of
£150); same copy, May, same result on a required minimum bid of £135. BL, 19-20 July, #557, probably 
<hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue D or E (printed by C. Cooke), stained, some leaves repaired, later quarter morocco
(£150). Flora Books, Sept. online cat., probably <hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue A or B (printed by J. Cooke),
contemporary calf rebacked, worn (£320); another copy, probably <hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue D or E, modern
quarter calf (£250). Hudson City Books, Sept. online cat., probably <hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue D or E,
“hardcover” binding a wreck ($300). Best Buy Books, Sept. online cat., probably <hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue
B or later, contemporary calf very worn ($770). Heritage Auction Galleries, Dallas, 26 Oct., #30946, 
<hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue A, scattered foxing, contemporary calf
<pb id="p41-152" n="152"/>
worn, rebacked, worn slipcase, illus. color online ($600.25). EB, Nov., pl. 2 only, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st.,
illus. color ($22.50).</p>
                        <p>Kimpton, <hi rend="i">History of the Bible</hi>, c. 1781. Andersens Antikvariat,
Sept. online cat., 55 (of 61) pls. only, but possibly including 1 or more of Blake’s 3 pls., contemporary
calf ($263). EB, Oct.-Nov., apparently complete but in very poor condition with stains and foxing,
contemporary calf very worn, covers detached, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £9.99).</p>
                        <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms.</hi> EB, March, 1788 ed., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
st. of the pl., contemporary calf worn, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $300). Larry W.
Price, Sept. online cat., 1788 ed., pl. damp stained, calf repaired ($595). Malvern Rare Books, Sept. online
cat., 1789 ed., contemporary calf (£124). John Windle, Sept. online cat., 1788 ed., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st.
of the pl., contemporary calf rebacked ($695). Howes Bookshop, Nov. cat. 325, #8, 1788 ed., some pencil
annotations, contemporary half morocco rebacked (£125).</p>
                        <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy.</hi> EB, Jan.-Feb., Blake’s pl. 2
only, illus. ($174); March, 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, scattered minor foxing, contemporary calf rebacked,
illus. color ($1725). Lyon &amp; Turnbull auction, Edinburgh, 10 May, #644, 1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, light
browning and marginal stains in vol. 5, contemporary calf rebacked, binding illus. color online (£600). J
&amp; J Hanrahan, Aug. cat. 59, #135, 1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, some foxing, contemporary three-quarter calf
very worn, 1 cover detached ($500). Alexandre Antique Books, Sept. online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5,
contemporary calf rebacked ($2750). Peter Bichsel, Sept. online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, modern half
parchment (€2210). Röde Orm Antikvariat, Sept. online cat., “1792” (actually c. 1818) ed., 3 vols. in
5, some damp staining to preliminaries, contemporary calf worn ($4263). ABCD Books, Sept. online cat., 1789-98
ed., 3 vols. in 5, foxed, three-quarter calf very worn with missing spines and detached covers ($1200). Brunk
Auctions, Asheville, North Carolina, 3 Nov., #351, a mixed set of “1792” (vol. 2, actually c. 1818) and
1810 (vols. 1, 3), 3 vols. in 5, scattered light foxing, early boards rebacked in calf, binding illus. color
online ($300).</p>
                        <p>Malkin, <hi rend="i">Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi>, 1806. Jarndyce, Sept.
online cat., some spotting, uncut in original boards worn (£1380).</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>, vol. 4, 1797. Roger Collicott, Sept. online
cat., uncut in contemporary half calf worn (£40).</p>
                        <p>Mora, <hi rend="i">Meditaciones Poeticas</hi>, 1826. EB, Aug., bottom margin of pl.
1 (title page) folded over and the legs of the descending angel marred by the perforated collection stamp of
the “City Library / Springfield Mass.,” minor marginal soiling, contemporary half calf, illus. color
($1150.89). Only the second copy I have seen on the market in the last 30 years.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine.</hi> EB, Jan., vol. 8 (<hi rend="i">Don
Quixote</hi>) only, apparently with the <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi> title page removed and with it
the date, late 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century calf, illus. color ($450). John Price, Sept. cat., #69, 21
vols., 1780-88, lacking vols. 5 and 13 but with the Blake pls. in vols. 8-10, contemporary calf (£2500).</p>
                        <p>Olivier, <hi rend="i">Fencing Familiarized</hi>, 1780. BL, 16 Aug., #632, slight
browning and minor damage to margins, “some heavy underlining in text,” contemporary calf worn
(£120).</p>
                        <p>Rees, <hi rend="i">Cyclopædia</hi>, 1820. Barter Books, Sept. online cat., 4 vols.
of pls. only, lacking 152 unspecified pls. but possibly including some of Blake’s, calf very worn, spines
missing, “suitable for research[,] restoration or breaking” (£780); another copy, pls. vol. 2 only,
presumably including Blake’s pl. 2 (“Basso Relievo”), foxed and browned, calf worn and repaired
(£369.60). Evans the Book, Sept. online cat., an incomplete set, lacking 4 text vols., but with vol. 4 of the
pls., presumably including Blake’s pls. 4-7 (“Sculpture”), calf very worn, spines and covers missing
(£600). Antiquarischer Lexikonhandel, Sept. online cat., complete in 45 vols., contemporary half calf
(€11,900). Best Buy Books, Sept. online cat., vol. 1 of the pls. only, presumably including Blake’s pl. 1
(“Armour”), cloth rebacked ($1595). McConnell Books, Sept. online cat., complete in 45 vols., contemporary
half Russia worn (£5500). Schooner Books, Sept. online cat., pls. vol. 2 only, presumably including Blake’s
pl. 2 (“Basso Relievo”), foxed, tears, cloth very worn, front cover detached ($300). Steven Schuyler,
Sept. online cat., “complete plates in 3 volumes,” later “library buckram” ($1176.50).</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi>, [1824] for 1825. Publisher’s calf, lacking some
pls. (but with Blake’s), lacking 1 leaf of text, sold Dec. by John Windle to the Victoria University
Library, Toronto. Previously sold SNY, 12 Dec. 2006, #41, Blake’s pl. illus. color ($10,200 to Windle).</p>
                        <p>Ritson, <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi>, 1783. Adam Mills,
Sept. online cat., 3 vols., contemporary calf rebacked (£525). Church Green Books, Sept. online cat., 3
vols., calf (£300).</p>
                        <p>Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>, 1792. BL, 14 Nov., #317, 3 vols.,
some marginal tears, minor spotting, modern quarter calf, illus. color (not sold; estimate £800-1200).</p>
                        <p>Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works.</hi> Powell’s Books, Sept. online cat., 1782
ed., occasional foxing, contemporary calf rebacked, worn ($200). Kenneth Karmiole, Sept. online cat., 1786
ed., modern cloth ($250). David Kenyon, Sept. online cat., 1782 ed., some foxing, calf worn (£250).</p>
                        <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi>, 1802. Heritage Book Shop, Feb. cat.
of “Finely Bound Books,” #282, 9 vols., contemporary morocco rebacked, “some rubbing,” illus. color
($15,000). Swann,
<pb id="p41-153" n="153"/>
14 June, #181, 9 vols., scattered foxing and browning, “early” half morocco worn, illus. color ($1700).
Alexandre Antique Books, Sept. online cat., 9 vols., scattered foxing on pls., contemporary morocco rebacked,
worn ($7500). Arundel Books, Sept. online cat., 8 vols. only (lacking vol. 8, but presumably including
Blake’s pl. in vol. 9), foxed, “full leather” worn, back cover of vol. 9 detached ($1950). CL, 14 Nov.,
#145, 9 vols., scattered foxing (heavy on some pls.), contemporary morocco worn, illus. color (not sold;
estimate £2500-3500).</p>
                        <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, 1805. EB, July-Aug., large-paper issue, vol.
10 only, with Blake’s pl. 2 (“Romeo and Juliet”) after Fuseli, pls. foxed, contemporary calf worn,
illus. color ($25.50). Adrian Harrington, Sept. online cat., 9 vol. issue, some browning and staining,
contemporary calf rebacked, worn, no information on the pls. (£875). Aabenhus Aarhus Antikvariat, Sept.
online cat., 9 vol. issue, contemporary calf worn ($4622). EB, Oct., 9 vol. issue, contemporary calf rebacked,
illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $700); same copy, Oct.-Nov. (no bids on a required minimum
bid of $500); Oct., vol. 7 only, with Blake’s pl. 1 (“King Henry VIII”) after Fuseli, badly foxed,
contemporary calf very worn, front cover detached, illus. color ($15); Nov., vol. 7 only, with Blake’s pl. 1
(“King Henry VIII”) after Fuseli, badly foxed, contemporary calf very worn and repaired with tape, illus.
color (£9.99).</p>
                        <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, 1796 ed., uncolored copies. David Mason,
Sept. online cat., 2 vols., Blake’s pl. 13 “supplied from a later edition,” contemporary calf rebacked
($8299). Peter Harrington, Sept. online cat., 2 vols., marginal spotting on pls., contemporary half calf with
slight wear (£4500). EB, Oct.-Nov., 2 vols., lacking 2 pls. including 1 by Blake, pls. foxed and stained,
contemporary calf rebacked, illus. color ($1604.99).</p>
                        <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, 1806 ed., colored copy. Donald Heald, March
online cat., 2 vols., contemporary Russia, bindings illus. color ($13,500).</p>
                        <p>Varley, <hi rend="i">Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi>, 1828. CSK, 21 March, #284, all pls.
present, a few leaves detached, marginal stains, bound with <hi rend="i">The Horoscope; a Weekly Miscellany of
Astrology</hi>, 1834, contemporary half roan (£600). John Windle, Sept. online cat., all pls. present,
contemporary calf “restored” ($10,950; sold Oct. to the Victoria University Library, Toronto).</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Wit’s Magazine</hi>, 1784. EB, Nov., pl. 4 (“The Discomfited
Duellists”) only, with title and imprint although not shown in the illus. (no bids on a required minimum bid
of $299).</p>
                        <p>Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, 1791. Heritage Book Shop, Dec.
2006 cat., #408, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> sts. of the pls., contemporary sheep rebacked, illus. color
($5500).</p>
                        <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, 1797, uncolored copies. Ursus Books, March
online cat., no mention of the “Explanation” leaf (because not present?), all edges gilt, “near
contemporary” morocco ($25,000); same copy and price, May cat. 262, #12, illus. Juniper Books, April online
cat., with the “Explanation” leaf, “excellent margins,” “original” (i.e., contemporary?) vellum
slightly worn, illus. ($19,500); another copy, Oct. private offer, lacking the “Explanation” leaf, some
pls. cropped, contemporary vellum worn ($15,000). BL, 11 June, #29, with the “Explanation” leaf,
contemporary calf rebacked, modern cloth box, illus. color (£5500). EB, Oct., pl. 18 only, framed, illus.
color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $2500).</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Interesting Blakeana</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>[T. Percy, ed.], <hi rend="i">Reliques of Ancient English Poetry</hi>, 1765.
Quaritch, Oct. cat. 2007/16, #59, 3 vols., contemporary calf, joints repaired (£1250). Blake gave his copy to
Mary Ann Linnell, John Linnell’s wife. It was acquired at an unrecorded time by George Herbert Palmer
(1842-1933), an American-born professor at Harvard and apparently not related to the artist Samuel Palmer, and
is now in the Wellesley College Library, Wellesley, Massachusetts. See <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of Early and
Rare Editions of English Poetry Collected and Presented to Wellesley College by George Herbert Palmer</hi>
(Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1923) 379, and <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #736.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Minutes of a General Conference of the Members of the New Church
Signified by the New Jerusalem . . . Held in Great East Cheap, London, from the 13<hi rend="s">th</hi> to the
17<hi rend="s">th</hi> of April, 1789</hi> (London: R. Hindmarsh, 1789). Robert H. Rubin Books, Oct. cat. 61,
#142, 42 pp. “disbound,” with August Nordenskiöld, <hi rend="i">Församlings Formen uti det Nya
Jerusalem</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Form of Society in the New Jerusalem</hi>] (Copenhagen, 1790), contemporary
boards worn ($2250). William and Catherine Blake attended the first session of the general conference on 13
April (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 50-51).</p>
                        <p>George Augustus Baldwyn, <hi rend="i">A New, Royal, Authentic, Complete and
Universal System of Geography</hi> (London: A. Hogg, n.d. [c. 1794?]). EB, Jan., 1 pl. only, showing “A Man
of the Duke of York’s Island” (top panel) and “A Family of New South Wales” (bottom panel), hand
colored, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $129). The bottom panel is an unsigned version of
the design in Blake’s engraving, “A Family of New South Wales,” dated Nov. 1792 in the imprint and
published in John Hunter, <hi rend="i">An Historical Journal of the Transactions at Port Jackson and Norfolk
Island</hi> (1793). See also Hunter in the appendix, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
Illustrations.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>“For the Naval Monument,” an engraved admission ticket for a concert in support
of the naval monument at Greenwich, 21.0 × 14.6 cm., dated 28 May 1800 and signed “Blake sc. ‘Change
Alley.” Ken Spelman Books, April cat. 61, #24, printed in red, illus. (£120; acquired by the Victoria
University Library, Toronto). The address following the signature makes it certain that the engraver was
William Staden Blake (1748-c. 1817). 
<pb id="p41-154" n="154"/>
Thus, it is merely coincidental that our William Blake engraved pls. for John Flaxman’s proposal for the
monument, published in Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">A Letter to the Committee for Raising the Naval Pillar</hi>
(1799). This ticket is wrongly attributed to William Blake in Archibald G. B. Russell, <hi rend="i">The
Engravings of William Blake</hi> (London: Grant Richards, 1912) 169-70. In Russell’s copy of his cat., he
has lined through the entry in pencil and written next to it “Not Blake (By W. S. Blake).” The pl. is
correctly attributed in G. E. Bentley, Jr., “A Collection of Prosaic William Blakes,” <hi rend="i">Notes
and Queries</hi> ns 12 (1965): 175.</p>
                        <p>Pencil (and pen and ink?) drawing of Blake’s design for Young, <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>, pl. 10, the figure and chain only with a globe (the earth?) below. Wove paper, 22.9 × 17.8
cm., with a “J. Willmot 1805” watermark. With pen and ink verses in German carefully written in highly
decorative calligraphy below the design and pen and ink framing vines and leaves in the side margins. EB,
Nov., illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £125).</p>
                        <p>J. and A. Taylor, <hi rend="i">City Scenes.</hi> BL, 26 April, #327, 1818 ed., some
stains, “original roan-backed boards,” illus. (£200). EB, Nov., 1828 ed., lacking vignettes numbered
42-48, pls. hand colored, publisher’s cloth worn, illus. color (£42.30). Includes Blake’s “Holy
Thursday” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>J. S. Deville, life mask of William Blake, 1823. EB, Jan.-Feb., with the Deville
inscription dated 1 Aug. 1823 on the back of the neck, illus. color (£393). Very probably made from a
second-generation mold based on the National Portrait Gallery (London) original. Deville’s inscription on
the back of the neck was almost certainly incised with a stylus on the NPG cast and not inserted as raised
letters in the original mold itself. Thus, the fact that this EB cast exactly repeats the inscription on the
NPG example, even in the shape and placement of the letters, indicates that the former is a copy mold-made
from the latter. The EB cast, however, is made of gray plaster painted a cream color, whereas most modern
copies known to me are dead-white plaster of Paris, either unpainted or painted with a faux-copper patina in
dark green or black. The EB cast may have been made from an earlier mold than the one produced c. 1953 by the
NPG. EB’s vendor, Elliot Moran, tells me that the cast was “found . . . in a lot of period items,”
including a “Phrenological and Physiological Register” bearing the printed date 1889 and the date
“10/2/[18]90” in pen and ink. Another cast, painted a cream color and similar to the EB cast of Jan.-Feb.,
was offered by a vendor in Australia on EB in Dec., illus. color ($54.32).</p>
                        <p>J. T. Hacket, <hi rend="i">The Student’s Assistant in Astronomy and
Astrology</hi>, 1836. Krown &amp; Spellman, May online cat., publisher’s cloth worn ($225); another copy, a
few inner marginal stains, later cloth, original front cover label reattached ($125). Blake is listed among
“Patrons and Admirers of the science and doctrine of Astrology” (118-20; see <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1766).
His time of birth is recorded as precisely “Nov. 28, 7h. 45″ pm. 1757” (119). This information is very
probably taken from Anon. [R. C. Smith?], “Nativity of Mr. Blake, the Mystical Artist,” 
<hi rend="i">Urania; or, the Astrologer’s Chronicle, and Mystical Magazine</hi> no. 1 (1825): 70-72, where it is
explained that “the above horoscope is calculated for the <hi rend="i">estimate</hi> time of birth” 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 407). The author of this article was familiar with Blake’s Visionary Heads and his work
on the Job engravings; the source for the estimated time of birth may have been Blake himself. In his chapter
on “The Harmony of Astrology, Phrenology, and Physiognomy” (123-70), Hacket refers to “the several
plates and figures,” including the personifications of “Gemini” and “Cancer” (147), in Varley’s
<hi rend="i">Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi> of 1828. Both of these physiognomic portraits were based on drawings by
Blake (see <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #501). The only copies of Hacket’s book I have seen on the market in the
last 25 years.</p>
                        <p>H. G. Bohn, <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of Books</hi>, 1841. Jeff Weber, March cat.
137, #263, original half calf ($500). Copies of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of Thel, Songs of Innocence and of
Experience, Milton a Poem</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are included among the 23,208 items offered
for sale (see <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #554).</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Revue Britannique</hi>, vol. 5, 1862. EB, May, quarter calf, illus.
color (€12.50). Includes [Amédée Pichot], “Le Visionnaire Blake,” a slightly modified version of an
essay first published in 1833. For description and justifiably acerbic comments, see <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2392.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">The Century Guild Hobby Horse.</hi> Leonard Roberts, March cat. 1,
#27, issue 7 (July 1887), with a facsimile of Blake’s <hi rend="i">On Homers Poetry</hi> [and] 
<hi rend="i">On Virgil</hi>, original wrappers ($350 Canadian); #28, issue 11 (June 1888), with reproductions of 3
of Blake’s Virgil wood engravings, original wrappers ($350 Canadian).</p>
                        <p>“Bernard Quaritch’s Wholesale Stock. Annual Results.” A folio ledger of
business records, 1898-1912, approx. 270 pp. Charles Cox, Feb. cat. 54, #199, containing “the statistics on
[William Griggs’s 1892 facsimile of?] William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of Ahania</hi> (1895), [the E. J.
Ellis facsimile of?] <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (Quaritch, 1893) and the three-volume 
<hi rend="i">Works</hi> of 1893 edited by Yeats and Ellis (small and large paper),” half calf (£150).</p>
                        <p>Job engraving, pl. numbered 3. EB, Feb., lightly stained, framed and glazed, illus.
color ($651). The high bidder failed to make payment, and thus the vendor offered the print again on EB, March
(withdrawn). Probably a leaf extracted from the 1902 Dent facsimile, as the rounded platemark and grainy
texture of the paper indicate, but several bidders must have thought this was an original when it was first
offered.</p>
                        <p>W. M. Rossetti, ed., <hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers 1862 to 1870</hi>, 1903. Leonard
Roberts, March cat. 1, #86, publisher’s cloth ($200 Canadian). Includes interesting early references to
Blake.</p>
                        <pb id="p41-155" n="155"/>
                        <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Venetian Series 2,
London: E. Grant Richards, 1906. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #101. Madoc Books, Aug. online cat., printed
presentation card dated 1909 from Holbrook Jackson (British journalist, writer, and publisher, 1874-1948)
pasted to the front free endpaper, publisher’s decorated paper binding, printed front cover and spine labels
(£125). Apparently rare; the only copy I have ever seen on the market.</p>
                        <p>A collection of 24 auction and 3 dealers’ catalogues, 1922-78, all listing
original works by Blake. Jeffrey Eger Books, Oct. private offer, original bindings, some with price lists, 2
with manuscript annotations about prices and buyers ($378).</p>
                        <p>B. B. Macgeorge, auction cat. of his collection, SL, 1-9 July 1924. BL, 4 Oct.,
#506, issue with illus., annotated with prices, contemporary half calf, original wrappers retained (£75).
With 28 lots of Blake material, including illuminated books, drawings, and a letter to Flaxman.</p>
                        <p>Donald E. Boyd, head of Blake carved in apple wood, 23 cm. high, 1965. Ro Gallery
auction, Long Island City, New York, 14 April, #2015, signed and dated, mounted on a rod and plinth, illus.
color online ($350). This carving, with a (symbolic?) fissure through the middle of the forehead, was probably
influenced by Blake’s life mask and by Leonard Baskin’s wood-engraved portrait, “Blake: An Imagined
Death Mask,” first published in Baskin, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Youthful Ancients</hi> (Northampton:
Gehenna P, 1956).</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, ed. David Bindman, William
Blake Trust, 1987. Michael Kemp Bookseller, June online cat., 1 of 5 copies specially bound and with
additional materials, this copy for the printing and binding firm Smith Settle, 4 vols., half morocco, in 3
morocco-trimmed boxes (£12,000). I suspect that this is a record asking price for a book featuring
reproductions of Blake’s illustrations and for any 20<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century work on Blake.</p>
                        <p>F. Bacon, “William Blake,” color lithograph based on Blake’s life mask, 1991.
CL, 19 Sept., #498, “artist’s proof” signed in pencil, presentation inscription to Michel Archimbaud,
illus. color (£6500; estimate £1500-2500). EB, Oct., signed and numbered “29/60” by Bacon, framed,
illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $8999.95).</p>
                        <p>E. Paolozzi, “Newton after Blake,” lithograph, 26.5 × 37.0 cm., 1997. BL, 28
June, #634, signed, titled, and dated in pencil, inscribed “P/P” (printer’s proof), illus. color
(£380). Based on Blake’s 1795 color print and similar to Paolozzi’s monumental bronze of Newton in the
forecourt of the British Library.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Blake’s Circle and Followers</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Works are listed under artists’ names in the following order: paintings and
drawings sold in groups, single paintings and drawings, letters and manuscripts, separate plates, books by (or
with plates by or after) the artist.</p>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">BARRY, JAMES</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>“Orpheus,” etching. Hill-Stone Gallery, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st. of 3,
advertised in <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> (Nov. 2007): [2], illus. color (price on request).</p>
                            <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">The American Edition of Boydell’s Illustrations of the
Dramatic Works of Shakespeare</hi>, 1852. EB, Sept., 1 pl. only, “King Lear,” engraved by Legat, illus.
color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $250). The pls. in this work are the original British pls.,
“restored.”</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">CALVERT, EDWARD</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>CSK, 4 April, 3 prints in 3 lots, all probably from the 
<hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, 1893, all illus. color: #1, “The Cyder Feast,” wood engraving, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi>
st. (£1200); #2, “The Bride,” engraving, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st. (£1800); #3, “The Return Home,”
wood engraving, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. (£300).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">FLAXMAN, JOHN</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>See also Flaxman, Hesiod and <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs, under Letterpress
Books with Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Ulysses Terrified by the Ghosts</hi> and <hi rend="i">Venus
Presenting Helen to Paris</hi>, a pair. Pen and brown ink on buff paper, each 17.2 × 24.5 cm., datable to c.
1793 and c. 1795 respectively. CL, 5 June, #28, illus. color (£3120).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Angels Guiding a Soul to Heaven.</hi> Pen and gray ink and gray
wash, 48.2 × 71.0 cm., possibly dating from the mid-1790s. Advertised by W. M. Brady &amp; Co. in 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 149 (Jan. 2007): xi, illus. color (price on request). Previously sold CL, 5
June 2006, #6, titled <hi rend="i">Angels Rescuing a Soul from the Ranks of the Dead</hi>, illus. color
(£14,400 to Colnaghi; estimate £4000-6000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Giving Alms.</hi> Pencil, 11.4 × 8.9 cm., title inscribed in
pencil. EB, April, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $1300).</p>
                            <p>Aeschylus designs. EB, Dec. 2006, 1795 ed., foxed, contemporary calf, illus.
color (£172); Dec. 2006-Jan., 1831 ed., marginal browning, original boards (with cover label) very worn and
stained, leaves detached, illus. color ($39); May, 1795 ed., title pl. stained, no binding but stitched
pamphlet-style,
<pb id="p41-156" n="156"/>
                                <figure n="Fuseli.Nightmare.41.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="482">
                                    <figTranscr>
                                        Painted by H. Fusley.<lb/>
                                        Engraved by A. Laffonato.<lb/>
                                        THE NIGHT MARE.<lb/>
                                        ...on his Night-Mare thro the evening fog,<lb/>
                                        Flits the squat fiend oer fen and lake and bog,<lb/>
                                        Seeks some love wilderd maid by sleep opprest,<lb/>
                                        Alights and and grinning sits upon her breast.<lb/>
                                        Publish’d November 30th. 1795 by A. Suntach.
                                    </figTranscr>
                                    <head>8. Henry Fuseli, “The Night Mare,” engraved in stipple by “A.
Laffonato” (possibly “Lassonato,” with a double long “s,” or “Zaffonato”), published by “A.
Suntach,” 1795.</head>
                                    <figDesc>Laid paper, image 19.1 × 23.1 cm., leaf 25.0 × 24.2 cm. Essick
collection. The design is reversed in relation to Fuseli’s painting and to the prints engraved by Thomas
Burke (1783) and William Raddon (1827). Not recorded in D. H. Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Prints and Engraved
Illustrations by and after Henry Fuseli</hi> (Aldershot: Scolar P, 1994), but probably a pirated pl. like
Weinglass #67A: image 19.2 × 22.1 cm., engraved by “Laurede,” published by “le Noir,” and dated by
Weinglass to 1782. The width of the 2 prints indicates that they are probably not different states of the same
copperplate. I suspect that the engraver’s and publisher’s names are pseudonyms on both pls.
“Laffonato” or “Lassonato” may be a strained Italian pun on “the sinking one” (from 
<hi rend="i">affondàre</hi>, to sink) or “the sleeper” (from <hi rend="i">assonnàto</hi>, sleepy); both are
appropriate for the woman in Fuseli’s design. The inscribed verses from Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The
Botanic Garden</hi>, left and right of the title, in the pirated pls. repeat those in Burke’s engraving;
both may be copies of his print in spite of the date given by Weinglass for the Laurede pl. The presence of
inscriptions on Burke’s 1783 pl. from Part 2 of <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>, not published until
1789, may be explained by the fact that Fuseli was acting as an intermediary between Darwin and the poem’s
publisher, Joseph Johnson, as early as 1784 (see Weinglass 55). Thus, Fuseli may have read the poem in
manuscript in 1783 and requested Burke to add the lines from it. The engraver of the pl. reproduced here did
not bother to reverse the image on the copperplate so that it would print right way around.</figDesc>
                                </figure>
                                <pb id="p41-157" n="157"/>
illus. color ($134.63). Barter Books, Sept. online cat., 1831 ed., foxed, some leaves detached, cloth-backed
boards very worn (£160). Toby English, Sept. online cat., 1831 ed., lacking pls. numbered 5 and 7, severe
foxing, half morocco very worn (£200). Powell’s Books, Sept. online cat., 1831 ed., severe foxing, half
morocco worn, cover illus. color ($250). Skinner auction, Boston, 18 Nov., #365, 1795 ed., later cloth very
worn, illus. color online ($153.13).</p>
                            <p>Dante designs. EB, May, 1867 ed., modern cloth in period style, illus. color
(no bids on a required minimum bid of £149.95). Chapitre Books, Sept. online cat., 1867 ed., modern boards
(€150). Antiquariat Hammer, Sept. online cat., <hi rend="i">Umrisse zu Dante Alighieri’s Göttlicher
Komödie</hi>, n.d. (1830s?), contemporary calf (€150). EB, Sept., 38 pls. engraved by Réveil, Paris, n.d.
(1830s?), some light foxing, publisher’s wrappers, illus. color ($25.99).</p>
                            <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Anatomical Studies</hi>, 1833. CNY, 5 Oct., #166, minor
marginal staining, contemporary cloth rebacked, cover label, illus. color ($563).</p>
                            <p>Hesiod designs. Epsilon, Sept. online cat., with the Aeschylus and Dante
designs, Paris, 1847, no information on binding (€150).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs. EB, Dec. 2006, 1793 ed., foxed, contemporary
calf, illus. color (£180.69). Adam and Eve Books, Sept. online cat., 1793 ed., bound with the Aeschylus
designs, 1795, some pls. browned, three-quarter morocco (£200). Tombland Bookshop, Sept. online cat., 
<hi rend="i">Iliade D’Omero Rappresentata in Figure da Giovanni Flaxman Contenente xxxix Tavole in Rame Conforme
alla Edizione di Londra del mdcccv</hi> (Firenze [Florence]: Presso Luigi Piazzini Librajo in Porta Rossa,
mdcccxxvi [1826]), bound with the <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, Aeschylus, and Hesiod designs, all with similar
letterpress title pages dated 1826, 143 pls. in all, no engraver’s name given, slight scattered foxing,
19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century half morocco worn (£120). The 1826 Florence eds. are not recorded in 
<hi rend="i">F.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs, 1793. EB, Dec. 2006, foxed, contemporary
calf, illus. color (£172).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Oeuvres de Flaxman</hi>, engraved by Réveil, Paris, 1836.
Antiquariaat Van Coevorden, Sept. online cat., 2 vols., contemporary calf (€1000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Umrisse zu Homer’s Ilias und Odyssee</hi>, engraved by
Riepenhausen, Berlin, n.d. Galerie Bassenge auction, Berlin, 26 April, #1215, original wrappers, illus. online
($450). Resource Books, Sept. online cat., badly damp stained, boards with cloth spine very worn ($325). Dated
to c. 1840 by Galerie Bassenge, but possibly the work (or a later issue of the work) dated to “1817?” in
<hi rend="i">F</hi> 25 no. 6.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Umrisse zur Ilias von J. Flaxmann</hi>, engraved by Schnorr,
Leipzig, 1839. EB, Sept.-Oct., bound with <hi rend="i">Umrisse zur Odyssee von J. Flaxmann</hi>, engraved by
Schnorr, Leipzig, 1839, minor foxing, contemporary paper-covered boards, illus. color (€69). These issues
not in <hi rend="i">F</hi>, but probably reissues of the 1804 <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> and the 1807 
<hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> engraved by Schnorr (see <hi rend="i">F</hi> 34 no. 4 and 25 no. 5).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">FUSELI, HENRY</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">An Archer with a Companion, Taking Aim at a Warrior, the Sun
Rising above the Ocean Beyond</hi> (recto); <hi rend="i">Three Studies of a Leg</hi> (verso). Pen and brown
ink over pencil, 18.0 × 22.0 cm. SL, 6 June, #189, recto illus. color (£15,600; estimate £5000-7000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">A Naked Warrior Repelling Soldiers at the Entrance to a
Tent.</hi> Pen and brown ink over pencil, 15.0 × 16.6 cm. SL, 6 June, #190, illus. color (£7800).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Portrait of Harriet Mellon.</hi> Pen and brown ink, 17.8 × 11.3
cm., c. 1815. SL, 6 June, #184, illus. color (£9600).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">A Seated Male Nude</hi> (recto); <hi rend="i">A Study of Lovers
with a Further Study of a Woman Kneeling and a Chess Set Seen from Above</hi> (verso). Pen and brown ink, 21.7
× 17.7 cm., datable to c. 1795-1800. SL, 6 June, #187, recto illus. color (£3600).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Studies of a Male Nude.</hi> Pen and brown ink over pencil, 22.2
× 17.5 cm., datable to c. 1777-79. SL, 6 June, #186, illus. color (not sold; estimate £7000-10,000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Studies of Reclining Figures.</hi> Pen and brown ink, 24.7 ×
35.1 cm., letter by Francesco Bartolozzi on verso. SL, 6 June, #185, illus. color (£4800).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Study of a Male Nude, Seated.</hi> Pencil, 19.2 × 19.4 cm.,
datable to the 1770s. SL, 6 June, #188, illus. color (£3600).</p>
                            <p>“The Night Mare,” engraved by “A. Laffonato” (possibly “Lassonato,”
with a double long “s,” or “Zaffonato”), published by “A. Suntach,” 1795. EB, Sept., cut close on
3 sides, skinned on the verso, cleaned and pressed, illus. ($187.50). See illus. 8.</p>
                            <p>Bible. <hi rend="i">A Practical Family Bible</hi>, ed. Francis Willoughby,
1772-73. Christopher Mendez, Aug. private offer, 1 pl. only, “Jonah’s Indignation,” etched by Fuseli
after his own design, inscriptions trimmed off (£1800).</p>
                            <p>Bible. Notes by Matthew Henry, abridged by Thomas Smith, printed by Thomas
Kelly, London, 1815. EB, Dec. 2006-Jan., pl. after Fuseli only (“The Death of Golia[t]h,” engraved by
Grainger), illus. (€49.50).</p>
                            <pb id="p41-158" n="158"/>
                            <p>Bodmer, <hi rend="i">Die Noachide</hi>, 1765. Antiquariat A. Thomi, Nov. online
cat., complete with 12 pls. (8 after Fuseli), contemporary quarter calf (€253). Fuseli’s first book
illustrations, crudely etched by Christian Gottfried Matthes (or Mathes), 1738-c. 1805.</p>
                            <p>Boothby, <hi rend="i">Sorrows, Sacred to the Memory of Penelope</hi>, 1796. EB,
Feb., large-paper copy, frontispiece by Beneditti after Fuseli in 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> published st., half
calf over (original?) boards, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $359).</p>
                            <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">The American Edition of Boydell’s Illustrations of the
Dramatic Works of Shakespeare</hi>, 1852. EB, Sept., 1 pl. only, “King Lear,” engraved by Earlom, illus.
color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $325); 1 pl. only, “King Henry the Fifth,” engraved by Thew,
illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $175); 1 pl. only, “King Henry the Fourth,” engraved by
Leney, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $225). The pls. in this work are the original
British pls., “restored.”</p>
                            <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Collection of Prints . . . Illustrating . . .
Shakspeare</hi>, c. 1803. BL, 14 Dec. 2006, #688, 11 pls. only but including 1 (unidentified) after Fuseli,
incorrectly described as pls. from Boydell’s <hi rend="i">Graphic Illustrations of . . . Shakspeare</hi>,
foxed, marginal tears, illus. color (£260). EB, Jan., 1 pl. only, “Midsummer Night’s Dream,” engraved
by Simon, framed, illus. color ($199.99); 1 pl. only, “King Henry the Fourth,” engraved by Leney, illus.
color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $165); May, 1 pl. only, “Macbeth,” engraved by Caldwell, hand
colored, framed, illus. color (offered only at the “buy it now” price of $1150, reduced by July to $495);
July, 1 pl. only, “Midsummer Night’s Dream,” engraved by Simon, badly torn into the image and stained,
illus. color ($48.77). Donald Heald, Sept. online cat., 2 vols., extra-illus. with 8 “proof plates,”
near-contemporary morocco rebacked ($17,500). BL, 4 Oct., #73, vol. 2 only, presumably containing the 3 pls.
after Fuseli in that vol., tears, foxing, water staining, contemporary morocco very worn, covers
detached—all in all a wreck (£550). EB, Oct.-Nov., a group of single pls. sold individually, each with
marginal foxing and illus. color, as follows: “Midsummer Night’s Dream,” engraved by Simon
($799.10—probably a record price for a Boydell Shakespeare pl. in the published st.); “Midsummer Night’s
Dream,” engraved by Ryder ($787); “Macbeth,” engraved by Caldwell ($190.50); “King Henry the
Fourth,” engraved by Leney ($108.05); “King Henry the Fifth,” engraved by Thew ($43). EB, Nov., 2 vols.
in 1, scattered marginal foxing, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century three-quarter morocco, illus. color
($6500).</p>
                            <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi>, 1803. Jeff Weber, June cat.
140, #55, occasional foxing, modern three-quarter calf, spine illus. color ($2850). EB, July, “The Creation
of Eve” only, engraved by Haughton, illus. color (£24.99). CSK, 25 Oct., #27, some foxing, contemporary
half calf very worn, front cover detached (£250).</p>
                            <p>Fuseli, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting</hi>, 1820. Francis Edwards, Sept.
online cat., foxed, a few pencil annotations, contemporary half calf rebacked, worn (£150).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Heinrich Fuessli’s Sœmmtliche Werke</hi>, Zurich, 1807-09.
Moirandat Company, June cat. 19, #97, 2 vols., 16 pls. after Fuseli by J. H. Lips, publisher’s wrappers,
illus. color (9000 Swiss francs—about $7300).</p>
                            <p>Homer, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, translated by
Pope, Du Roveray ed., 1813. EB, May, 12 vols., contemporary morocco, binding illus. color ($405).</p>
                            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi>, Boston, 1790. Minnesota Bookman,
Nov. online cat., contemporary calf very worn, “spine about half perished,” front cover detached
($150).</p>
                            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, translated Hunter, 1789-98.
EB, June, 1 pl. only, “Satan,” engraved by Holloway, illus. color ($39.80); 1 pl. only, “The Daughter of
Herodias,” engraved by Holloway, illus. color ($139.14). See also under Letterpress Books with Engravings by
and after Blake, above.</p>
                            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, translated Moore, 1797. EB,
July, 4 vols. in 2, some pls. badly foxed, contemporary half calf, illus. color (£112).</p>
                            <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, published Suttaby, 1806. Spivey’s
Books, Nov. online cat., 2 vols., small tear into the image of the frontispiece after Fuseli, contemporary
half calf ($100).</p>
                            <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, Bohn editions. EB, Jan., 1848 ed.,
contemporary calf, binding illus. color (£27); March, 1855 ed., modern cloth, illus. color (no bids on a
required minimum bid of $15).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">A Series of Magnificent Engravings, to Illustrate . . .
Shakespeare and Milton</hi>, published H. M’Lean, 1818. Gallery at Knotty Pine auction, West Swanzey, New
Hampshire, 28 April, #113, some foxing, contemporary quarter calf very worn, illus. color online ($220). EB,
May, scattered marginal foxing, contemporary quarter morocco, illus. color ($525). BL, 19-20 July, #161,
foxed, contemporary half morocco very worn (£150). Contains a selection of Stothard’s large pls.
illustrating <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (executed 1792-93; see Coxhead 103-04) and 5 pls. after Fuseli
executed for earlier publications: “Oberon Squeezing the Flower on Titania’s Eyelids,” “Titania
Embracing Bottom,” “The Witches Appear to Macbeth and Banquo,” “Macbeth and Banquo Meet the Witches on
the Heath,” and “I’ve Done the Deed” (Macbeth and Lady Macbeth).</p>
                            <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, 1805. EB, Jan., 1 pl. only,
“Tempest,” engraved by Bromley, imprint trimmed off, badly stained at corners, illus. color ($9.99); Aug.,
vol. 4 only, light foxing, contemporary calf, illus. color ($15); Sept., vol. 5 only, foxed,
<pb id="p41-159" n="159"/>
contemporary calf worn, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $15); vol. 3 only, foxed,
contemporary calf worn, front cover detached ($15); vol. 1 only, foxed, contemporary calf worn, front cover
detached, illus. color ($22.50); Oct., vol. 6 only, foxed, contemporary calf very worn, illus. color ($16.50);
Oct.-Nov., vol. 9 only, pls. badly foxed, contemporary calf very worn, back cover detached, illus. color
($15); Nov., vol. 4 only, margins of pls. badly foxed, contemporary calf very worn and repaired with tape,
illus. color (£15.99). See also under Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
                            <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, Stockdale ed., 1807. EB, June, 6 vols.,
modern three-quarter calf, illus. color (offered only at the “buy it now” price of £395); July, 1 pl.
only, “I’ve Done the Deed” (Macbeth and Lady Macbeth), engraved by Heath, slight marginal staining,
illus. color (offered only at the “buy it now” price of £60). Bauman Rare Books, Sept. online cat., 6
vols., modern three-quarter morocco ($8200). Antiquariat Markus Wolter, Sept. online cat., 6 vols.,
“contemporary binding” worn ($5484). Peter Harrington, Sept. online cat., 6 vols., some browning,
contemporary Russia, bindings illus. color (£6500); another copy, 6 vols., contemporary calf rebacked, worn,
bindings illus. color (£2500).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">LINNELL, JOHN</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Beach and Boats</hi>, attributed to Linnell. Pencil and chalk,
13.5 × 19.0 cm., inscribed “J Linnell”. EB, May, illus. color (£148).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Figures on a Track, in an Extensive Landscape.</hi> Watercolor,
17.7 × 25.1 cm. SL, 22 Nov., #156, illus. color (not sold; estimate £3000-5000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Forest.</hi> Oil, 29.5 × 48.5 cm., signed and dated 1873. SL, 21
March, #32, illus. color (not sold; estimate £2000-3000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">A Gypsy Camp.</hi> Oil, 28.6 × 44.5 cm. Leslie Hindman auction,
Chicago, 15 Jan., #1104, 2 punctures in the canvas restored, illus. color online ($475). Possibly an early
work, datable to the 1820s or 1830s.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Heathland.</hi> Oil, 22.7 × 30.5 cm., signed. Gorringes auction,
Lewes, 25 April, #1256, illus. color online (£1200).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Portrait of J. Moseley Esq. of Suffolk.</hi> Oil, 127.0 × 101.3
cm., signed and dated 1843. SL, 22 Nov., #69, illus. color (£9375).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Portrait of William Coningham.</hi> Oil, 128.0 × 103.0 cm.,
signed and dated 1842. SL, 22 Nov., #70, illus. color (£24,500; estimate £8000-12,000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Storm in Harvest.</hi> Oil, 127.3 × 182.9 cm., signed and dated
1873. CL, 7 June, #102, illus. color (£57,600).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Study of a Young Child.</hi> Pencil, 12.5 × 9.1 cm., signed and
dated 1822. SL, 6 June, #172 (£960).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">A View near Hampstead.</hi> Oil, 20.3 × 29.3 cm., signed and
dated 1827. CL, 7 June, #101, illus. color (£7800).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Woodcutters in Windsor Forest.</hi> Oil, 18.0 × 27.0 cm.,
signed, datable to the 1820s. SL, 6 June, #89, illus. color (£15,600; estimate £6000-8000). Not to be
confused with several watercolors of the same subject and basic composition.</p>
                            <p>Autograph letter signed, 28 Aug. 1877, 1 p., to the editor of the 
<hi rend="i">Dublin University Magazine</hi> with a small self-portrait in pen and ink to indicate which
photograph should be used in a forthcoming publication about Linnell. Quaritch, Feb. cat. 2007/6, #35
(£180).</p>
                            <p>“Sheep at Noon,” etching. BL, 12 July, #423, with “Woodcutters in Windsor
Forest,” both “later impressions,” and “The Reverend John Martin,” framed, the Martin engraving
illus. color (£140).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">MORTIMER, JOHN HAMILTON</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Sleeping Baby</hi>, tentatively attributed to Mortimer. Pen and
ink, 10.5 × 17.3 cm. EB, Oct., framed, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $450).</p>
                            <p>“An Academy,” engraved by S. F. Ravenet. EB, Jan., apparently stained in
the inscription area below the design, illus. (offered only at the “buy it now” price of £90).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Fifteen Etchings Dedicated to Sir Joshua Reynolds</hi>, 1778.
Cheffins auction, Cambridge, 22 March, #258, 23 pls. in all, including additional etchings of banditti,
original boards lacking spine, illus. color online (£1400; estimate £50-100).</p>
                            <p>“Palamon and Arcita,” etching, no etcher named but probably Francis
Chesham. EB, Oct., brown ink on wove paper, illus. color ($62.37).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Shakespeare Character Heads</hi>, etchings. Thomaston Place
auction, Maine, 30 June, #568, 3 pls. only, “Bardolph,” “Beatrice,” and “Falstaff,” probably
Palser impressions, framed, some wrinkles, illus. color online ($175). EB, Aug., 1 pl. only, “Ophelia,”
with (probably later) hand coloring, marginal stains, illus. color ($31.19).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">PALMER, SAMUEL</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">The Broken Bridge.</hi> Watercolor, 40.0 × 50.8 cm., signed,
datable to c. 1846. W/S Fine Art, June-July cat., #34, illus. color (price on application).</p>
                            <pb id="p41-160" n="160"/>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Crossing the Common—Sunset.</hi> Watercolor, 18.4 × 40.6 cm.,
datable to 1848. Lowell Libson, April cat., #13, illus. color (not priced).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">The End of the Day: A Recollection of Italy.</hi> Watercolor,
14.3 × 21.0 cm., signed, datable to the early 1870s. W/S Fine Art, June-July cat., #35, illus. color (price
on application).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Gypsy Camp, Evening</hi>, attributed to Palmer. Watercolor, 19.7
× 27.9 cm. EB, Feb.-March, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £5000); May, now attributed to
a “Follower of Samuel Palmer” (no bids on a required minimum bid of $700).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Landscape with Sheep and Cattle and a Windmill in the
Distance.</hi> Watercolor, 18.1 × 41.0 cm., signed, datable to c. 1850. BH, 6 Feb., #107, illus. color (not
sold; estimate £15,000-20,000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Mark Yon Old Mansion</hi>, the preliminary drawing for an
illustration to Samuel Rogers, <hi rend="i">The Pleasures of Memory</hi>, n.d. (c. 1879). Pen and brown ink,
11.8 × 17.8 cm. CL, 5 June, #92, illus. color (not sold; estimate £4000-6000).</p>
                            <p>“The Bellman,” etching. CSK, 4 April, #7, 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
inscribed “Artist’s Proof” by A. H. Palmer, illus. color (£7200; estimate £3000-4000). CL, 18 Sept.,
#182, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., a working proof touched with pencil and Chinese white, with annotations in
pencil, illus. color (£6875). Galerie Bassenge auction, Berlin, 29 Nov., #5450, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
pencil signature, illus. color online (€9000).</p>
                            <p>“Christmas,” or “Folding the Last Sheep,” etching. CSK, 4 April, #5,
4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., “posthumous impression,” illus. color (£1140); #13, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
printed in 1926, illus. color (£960).</p>
                            <p>“The Early Ploughman,” etching. EB, July, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus.
color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $1000). CL, 18 Sept., #184, 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., some
staining and foxing. illus. color (not sold; estimate £1500-2000).</p>
                            <p>“The Herdsman’s Cottage,” etching. EB, Jan., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.,
illus. color ($309). Swann, 6 March, #177, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., with “The Rising Moon,” 9<hi
rend="s">th</hi> st., and “The Morning of Life,” 9<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., the last illus. ($1600). BH,
26 March, #5, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., a late impression, with “The Skylark,” 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
“The Sleeping Shepherd,” 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., and “The Early Ploughman,” 8<hi rend="s">th</hi>
st., all framed (£2640); #6, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., framed (£1020). CSK, 4 April, #10, 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> st., marginal foxing, illus. color (£660).</p>
                            <p>“The Lonely Tower,” etching. CSK, 4 April, #9, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
inscribed “Trial Proof” by A. H. Palmer, time stained, illus. color (£4800). Doyle auction, New York, 2
May, #4346, 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., published 1880, pencil signature, slight marginal stains, illus. color
online ($6000).</p>
                            <p>“The Morning of Life,” etching. CL, 18 Sept., #183, 6<hi rend="s">th</hi>
st., a working proof touched with pencil and pen and ink, illus. color (£3125).</p>
                            <p>“Opening the Fold,” etching. CSK, 4 April, #8, 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
framed, illus. color (£960); #11, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st., “with extensive proofing notes in pencil, with
a little retouching,” illus. color (£3840). EB, Sept., 10<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., 1926 impression from the
cancelled pl. with a vertical line through the center, illus. color (£97).</p>
                            <p>“The Rising Moon,” etching. CSK, 4 April, #6, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
laid India, crease in left margin close to the image, illus. color (£960); #12, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st.,
laid India, discoloration in margin, illus. color (£900).</p>
                            <p>“The Skylark,” etching. CSK, 4 April, #4, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., laid
India, narrow margins, illus. color (£1020).</p>
                            <p>“The Willow,” etching. CSK, 13 Dec. 2006, #2264, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.,
“post-humous impression” (not sold; estimate £150-200). Swann, 6 March, #178, with “The Herdsman’s
Cottage” and “The Early Ploughman,” sts. not recorded, the last illus. ($1700). EB, Aug., 4<hi
rend="s">th</hi> st., an impression from the cancelled pl. with a vertical line through the center, illus.
color (£44.95).</p>
                            <p>Dickens, <hi rend="i">Pictures from Italy</hi>, 1846. Blackwell’s, May cat.,
#36, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., original cloth (£110). BNY, 28 Nov., #103, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed.,
original cloth, presentation inscription from Dickens to “The Count d’Orsay,” binding illus. color
($70,000; estimate $18,000-25,000).</p>
                            <p>Hamerton, <hi rend="i">Etching and Etchers</hi>, 1880. Swann, 29 Nov., #57,
half pigskin worn ($1500). Contains Palmer’s etching, “The Herdsman’s Cottage,” 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi>
st.</p>
                            <p>A. H. Palmer, <hi rend="i">Life and Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>, 1892. BL, 16
Aug., #477, publisher’s cloth worn, later folding box (£200). Contains Palmer’s etching, “The
Willow,” 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.</p>
                            <p>S. Palmer, <hi rend="i">English Version of the Eclogues of Virgil</hi>, 1883.
BL, 14 Nov., #425, “one of 10 presentation copies,... large paper,” with “some illustrations not used in
the final book,” some foxing, original vellum soiled, illus. (£1000).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">PARKER, JAMES</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Blake’s fellow apprentice under James Basire and partner with Blake in a
printselling business in the early 1780s.</p>
                            <p>British ladies in India (?), a separate pl. engraved by Parker after Stothard.
See under Stothard, below. Not recorded in G. E. Bentley, Jr., “The Journeyman and the Genius: James Parker
and His Partner William Blake with a List of Parker’s Engravings,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Bibliography</hi> 49 (1996): 208-31.</p>
                            <pb id="p41-161" n="161"/>
                            <p>“The Pulse” and “Sterne Conducting Maria into Moulines,” a pair based
on scenes in Sterne’s <hi rend="i">A Sentimental Journey</hi>, engraved by Parker after James Northcote. BL,
25 Oct., #309, “The Pulse” printed in “bistre” and illus. color (£150).</p>
                            <p>Adams, <hi rend="i">New Royal Geographical Magazine</hi>, c. 1793. 2 pls.
engraved by Parker, “Burgos” and “Dantzick,” first published in Seally and Lyons, <hi rend="i">A
Complete Geographical Dictionary, c.</hi> 1784. See under Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after
Blake, above.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">RICHMOND, GEORGE</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Study of Harriet Tatham; Study of Frederick Tatham.</hi>
Apparently on 2 leaves, the former inscribed “G. Richmond 1826—Harriet Tatham” and the latter inscribed
“Fred Tatham.” Pen and ink over pencil, 20.6 × 14.0 cm. and 20.4 × 16.2 cm. BH, 6 Feb., #92, with 
<hi rend="i">Study of Two Standing Acolytes</hi> and <hi rend="i">Study of Female Figures</hi>, apparently on 2
leaves, pencil and brown wash, both 22.3 × 13.0 cm., <hi rend="i">Study of Harriet Tatham</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Study of Two Standing Acolytes</hi> illus. color (not sold; estimate £1000-1500).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Jesus.</hi> Chalk and charcoal drawing, 19.5 × 14.3 cm.,
inscribed “Sketched at Milan from the fresco” and signed “G. R.” EB, June, illus. color (offered only
at the “buy it now” price of £380).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Man’s Head in Profile.</hi> Pen and brown ink, 17.8 × 11.4
cm., pen and ink sketches of 2 (female?) heads on verso, possibly dating from the 1830s. EB, Nov., illus.
color (£8.50).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Portrait of Fra Girolamo Savonarola, after Fra Bartolommeo, Half
Length.</hi> Pencil, 30.5 × 20.7 cm., inscribed (probably at a later date) “4” and “Savonarola.” CL,
5 June, #170, illus. color (not sold; estimate £3000-5000).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">A Sheet of Figure Studies, Including an Angel and a Portrait Head
Study of Samuel Palmer</hi> (recto); <hi rend="i">A Figure Study</hi> (verso). Pencil on leaf with an 1838
watermark, 20.3 × 15.9 cm. CL, 5 June, #169, illus. color (not sold; estimate £3000-5000). I am not
convinced that the head is Palmer’s.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">ROMNEY, GEORGE</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">An Heroic Head: A Study from Life.</hi> Oil, 40.5 × 44.5 cm.,
datable to 1788-89. Lowell Libson, April cat., #8, illus. color (not priced). The face is closely related to
the portrayal of Prospero in Romney’s painting of <hi rend="i">The Tempest</hi> for Boydell’s Shakespeare
Gallery.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">The Infant Shakespeare Nursed by Tragedy and Comedy.</hi> Pencil,
pen and brown ink, brown wash, datable to c. 1783. CL, 21 Nov., #197, illus. color (£11,250).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Studies of Thelassie, the French Dancer, Reclining.</hi> Pen and
brown ink, 12.1 × 19.0 cm. CL, 21 Nov., #13, illus. color (£875).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Titania’s Attendants.</hi> Oil, 119.4 × 149.9 cm., datable to
c. 1792. Lowell Libson, April cat., #9, illus. color (not priced). Previously sold, under the title 
<hi rend="i">Titania’s Attendants Chasing Bats</hi>, SL, 23 Nov. 2006, #68, illus. color (£38,400).</p>
                            <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">The American Edition of Boydell’s Illustrations of the
Dramatic Works of Shakespeare</hi>, 1852. EB, Sept., 1 pl. only, “The Tempest,” engraved by B. Smith,
illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $295); 1 pl. only, “The Infant Shakspeare,” engraved by
B. Smith, marginal foxing, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $125). The pls. in this work are
the original British pls., “restored.”</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">RUNCIMAN, ALEXANDER</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>“Cormar Attacking the Spirit of the Waters,” etching. EB, Nov., trimmed to
the image and mounted on a backing sheet, illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of £28).</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">STOTHARD, THOMAS</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Book illustrations in published states are listed only for editions not
recorded in the standard reference works, A. C. Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London:
Bullen, 1906), and Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard: The Mechanisms of Art Patronage in
England circa 1800</hi> (Columbia: U of Missouri P, 1988).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Ghost Chamber.</hi> Watercolor, 33.0 × 25.0 cm., signed. SL, 17
May, #17, illus. color (not sold; estimate £1200-1800). Very probably a preliminary drawing for a book
illustration.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Study for Halloween.</hi> Watercolor, 19.5 × 16.0 cm. BL, 12
July, #92, framed, with “an English school scene of a romantic couple,” the latter (an unattributed work)
illus. color (£320). Stothard’s watercolor only, W/S Fine Art, 14 Nov.-7 Dec. cat., #18, illus. color
(price on request). <hi rend="i">Study for Halloween</hi> is a preliminary drawing for the pl., engraved by S.
Smith and inscribed “Halloween,” published in <hi rend="i">The Cabinet of Modern Art, and Literary
Souvenir</hi>, ed. Alaric A. Watts, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> series (London: Whittaker &amp; Co., 1836).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">The Wedding.</hi> Oil, 35.0 × 64.5 cm. EB, Dec. 2006, framed,
illus. color (£1031.76). Previously offered SL, 13 July 2006, #15, illus. color (not sold; estimate
£1000-1500).</p>
                            <p>“Amyntor and Theodora,” engraved by Tomkins. EB, July, illus. color (no
bids on a required minimum bid of $135).</p>
                            <pb id="p41-162" n="162"/>
                            <p>British ladies in India (?), I wearing a turban-like hat, circular design
engraved in stipple by James Parker. Image 19.2 cm. dia., platemark 26.7 × 23.8 cm. EB, Jan., a proof before
title and imprint, printed in reddish-brown, leaf of wove paper without watermark 29.5 × 24.5 cm., slight
marginal stains, illus. color (£15). Its size, stipple technique, and ink color suggest that this print is a
separate pl. or part of a suite of prints, not a book illustration. Probably the same impression sold EB, Jan.
2006 (£31). Not in Coxhead.</p>
                            <p>“Cecilia Overhear’d by Young Delvile,” engraved in stipple by Nutter. EB,
Nov., with a 1784 imprint, foxed, framed, illus. color (offered only at the “buy it now” price of $299.99
or “best offer”). The subject of this circular print is taken from Frances Burney’s 
<hi rend="i">Cecilia, or Memoirs of an Heiress</hi> (1782).</p>
                            <p>“The Fifth of November,” engraving after Stothard. EB, Jan., hand colored,
illus. color (£12.50). One from a set of 5 oval pls. (each about 18.0 × 21.5 cm.) picturing children at play
or in the classroom, published by J. F. Tomkins in Jan. 1790 (see Coxhead 180). Might Stothard have been
composing these designs at about the same time Blake was working on his <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
in 1789? Three pls. in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> picture children’s games.</p>
                            <p>“The Finding of Moses,” engraved by Dadley, 22.0 × 17.0 cm. EB, June,
illus. color (no bids on a required minimum bid of €1). Very probably a book illustration, perhaps for a
Bible.</p>
                            <p>“The Irish Volunteer,” stipple engraving by Delattre, 1786. EB, May, illus.
color (offered only at the ludicrous “buy it now” price of £3300); same impression, Sept.-Oct., illus.
color (no bids on a required minimum bid of $5450 Australian).</p>
                            <p>“Princess Catherine of France Presented to Henry V,” stipple engraving by
Cardon. BL, 12 July, #314, with another pl., the Stothard illus. color (not sold; estimate £150-200).</p>
                            <p>“The Wellington Shield,” etched by Stothard after his own design. Cheffins
auction, Cambridge, 22 March, #247, the circular design of the shield’s center and 5 border designs, 6 pls.
in all, lacking the outline etching of the entire shield, illus. color online (£4400; estimate
£100-200).</p>
                            <p>Bray, <hi rend="i">Life of Stothard</hi>, 1851, extra-illus. copies only. BNY,
24 Oct., #118, extended to 10 vols. small quarto, extra-illus. with 14 drawings attributed to Stothard, 1
letter by Stothard, and 1335 pls. after his designs, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco, bindings illus.
color (not sold; overestimated at $20,000-30,000). The vols. include the following pls. engraved by Blake:
Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando furioso</hi>, only pl., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.; Bonnycastle, 
<hi rend="i">Introduction to Mensuration</hi>, st. not recorded; <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, vol. 8,
both pls., vol. 9, pls. 2-3, and vol. 10, all 3 pls.; Ritson, <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English
Songs</hi>, pl. 7; Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, all 4 pls.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Diamond Pocket Prayer</hi> [<hi rend="i">Book</hi>], 
<hi rend="i">with Notes Explanatory</hi>, published by J. White, Boston, 1809. EB, April-May, 10 pls. after
designs by “Richard [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] Stothard,” contemporary morocco, illus. color (no bids on a
required minimum bid of $69.99); same copy, May ($39.99).</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">A Series of Magnificent Engravings, to Illustrate . . .
Shakespeare and Milton</hi>, published H. M’Lean, 1818. See under Fuseli, above.</p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">TATHAM, FREDERICK</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="i">Portrait of a Man, Half Length.</hi> Watercolor, 38.1 × 26.7
cm., c. 1830? EB, June, illus. color ($112.50). Works by Tatham rarely appear on the market.</p>
                        </div4>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Appendix: New Information on Blake’s Engravings</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Listed below are substantive additions or corrections to Robert N. Essick, 
<hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (1983), and Essick, <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (1991). Abbreviations and citation styles follow the respective
volumes, with the addition of “Butlin” according to the list of abbreviations at the beginning of this
sales review. Newly discovered impressions of previously recorded published states of Blake’s engravings are
listed only for the rarer separate plates.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Pp. 24-29, “Albion rose.” Joseph Viscomi has shown that the 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> state of “Albion rose” dates from no earlier than 1795 because its copperplate was cut
from the same large sheet of copper as <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and the pls. of <hi rend="i">The Book
of Ahania</hi>, both dated “1795” by Blake on their title pages. Viscomi also dates the two color-printed
impressions of “Albion rose” to 1795. This means that they were not printed as part of the 
<hi rend="i">Large Book of Designs</hi> of 1796, but were forerunners of that work and were later incorporated
into copies A and B of the <hi rend="i">Large Book.</hi> There is no compelling evidence, however, to rule out
a slightly different scenario: Blake cut the large sheet of copper into 4 pieces in 1795, executed “Albion
rose” as an intaglio etching in that year, but did not color print it until his production of the 
<hi rend="i">Large Book of Designs</hi> in the next year. Viscomi further suggests that some of the 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi>-state alterations in “Albion rose,” such as the burst of light around the figure’s
head, were immediate responses to the color-printed version and thus datable to c. 1795. See Viscomi,
“Blake’s ‘Annus Mirabilis’: The Productions of 1795,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.2 (fall 2007):
52-83, esp. 75-78.</p>
                        <p>Pp. 111-22, “George Cumberland’s Card.” Two newly discovered impressions:
<pb id="p41-163" n="163"/>
                            <list type="ordered">
                                <item>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="i">a. Professor Loretta Innocenti</hi>, Venice, Italy.
Printed in black ink (possibly with a slight greenish hue) on a card pasted into a copy of George Cumberland,
Jr., <hi rend="i">Bristol Beauties 1848.</hi> This work is “a made-up volume of works by George Cumberland
(Jr.) printed at various times (dated 1847, 1849, 1850, 1851, 1852, 1858, 1860) with different paginations;
the engraved titlepage applies only to the first 15 pages” (G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">A Bibliography
of George Cumberland</hi> [New York: Garland Publishing, 1975] 34). According to its owner, “the book has an
autograph dedication and is signed G. C. [George Cumberland, Jr.?] on the front page.” No provenance
information. Its card support and bibliographic context indicate that this impression was probably pulled
before most of those on thinner papers in black and brown inks. On consignment with John Windle by Oct.
2007.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="i">b. Joyce Passaro</hi>, Kingston, New York. Printed in
black ink on laid paper, size of sheet unknown. Acquired at auction by Passaro early in 2007 as part of a
collection of bookplates from the estate of George Viner, New York. Accompanied by manuscript notes by Viner
about the pl.</p>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pp. 125-31, “Morning Amusement” and “Evening Amusement,” after Watteau. See
under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, above.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Pp. 64-65, Hunter, <hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi>, 1793. For a c. 1794
version of the design pictured in Blake’s pl., dated Nov. 1792 in the imprint, see Baldwyn, the third entry
under Interesting Blakeana, above. Another version of this design, “Drawn [i.e., engraved?] from a Sketch
taken on the Spot” and signed by “Goldar” (John Goldar, 1729-95) as the engraver, appears in Michael
Adams, <hi rend="i">The New Royal Geographical Magazine</hi> (London: Alexander Hogg, [c. 1793]), facing p. 9.
The Goldar pl., titled “Man, Woman and Children of New South Wales,” may have been engraved some years
before its publication in Adams’s book. The pls. in the Baldwyn and Adams vols. have a horizontal format and
are much closer to each other than to Blake’s pl. One of these 2 horizontal pls. is probably a copy of the
other.</p>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
