<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>42.2.whitehead</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Mrs Chetwynd &amp; her Brother” and “Mr. Chetwynd”</title>
        <author n="Whitehead">Angus Whitehead</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2008</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2008</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">42.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Helen Patricia Bruder</name>
              <name>Robin Hamlyn</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2008"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_42">
    <body>
	<pb id="p42-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Chetwynd &amp; her Brother” and “M<hi
rend="s">r</hi>. Chetwynd”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Angus <name>Whitehead</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>IF,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">*</ref> as Keri Davies
suggests in a recent essay about Blake collector Rebekah Bliss, “every person who bought Blake’s work in
his lifetime is of significance to Blake scholarship,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">1</ref> the identity of another contemporary female purchaser of the poet-artist’s work, albeit
on a smaller scale, merits closer investigation. William Blake twice refers to “M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>
Chetwynd.” On 30 January 1803 Blake wrote from Felpham to his brother James at 28 Broad Street, Carnaby
Market, “I send with this 5 Copies of N4 of the Ballads for M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Flaxman &amp; Five more
two of which you will be so good as to give to M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Chetwynd if she should call or send for
them.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">2</ref> According to G. E. Bentley,
Jr., “Mrs Chetwynd took two copies of the fourth Ballad from James Blake . . . and probably had the
preceding numbers as well, eight in all (£1.0.0).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">3</ref> Eighteen months later, Mrs. Chetwynd, accompanied by her brother, called on Blake at his
lodgings and studio at 17 South Molton Street. On 28 September 1804 Blake wrote to William Hayley:
	<note id="n60">* I wish to thank Keri Davies and Catherine Taylor for their assistance with this note.</note>
	<q>
I had the pleasure of a call from M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Chetwynd &amp; her Brother. a Giant in body mild &amp;
polite in soul as I have in general found great bodies to be they were much pleased with Romneys Designs. M<hi
rend="s">rs</hi> C. sent to me the two articles for you &amp; for the safety of which by the Coach I had some
fears till M<hi rend="s">r</hi> [William] Meyer obligingly undertook to convey them safe ....<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">4</ref></q>
	<pb id="p42-76" n="76"/>
From Blake’s two brief allusions to her we may gather that Mrs. Chetwynd was a member of Hayley’s circle
who shared some interest in the poet and biographer’s literary pursuits. She also appears to have been on
good terms with Blake during the period 1803-04. Nevertheless, in Blake studies little else is known of either
Mrs. Chetwynd or her brother. She is not mentioned in William Hayley’s posthumously published 
<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> (1823), nor is she referred to in Morchard Bishop’s biography, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Hayley</hi> (1951). Of Blake’s numerous biographers, only Thomas Wright, in his <hi rend="i">Life of William
Blake</hi> (1929), attempts to provide new information concerning Mrs. Chetwynd. Wright describes her as a
pretty widow with two daughters from Ham, near Richmond, whom Hayley met about 1800.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">5</ref> According to Wright, Hayley also assisted Mrs. Chetwynd’s
eldest daughter with her Italian.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">6</ref> No
subsequent biographer of Blake has explored or expanded upon Wright’s claims. However, in a recent paper
that explores Catherine Blake’s relationship with William Hayley, Mark Crosby cites what must have been one
of Wright’s sources, a passage from the manuscript of Hayley’s autobiography, excised from the published
work presumably by the editor, John Johnson. 
                        <note id="n30">1. Keri Davies, “Rebekah Bliss: Collector of William Blake and
Oriental Books,” <hi rend="i">The Reception of Blake in the Orient</hi>, ed. Steve Clark and Masashi Suzuki
(London: Continuum, 2006) 38.</note>
	<note id="n31">2. E 727.</note>
	<note id="n32">3. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale University
Press, 2004) [hereafter <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)] 153.</note>
	<note id="n33">4. E 755.</note>
	<note id="n34">5. During the period 1800-09 Penelope Chetwynd and her children lived in the small village of
Ham Common near Richmond. See <hi rend="i">Ambulator: Pocket Companion of a Tour around London</hi>, 7th ed.
(London: J. Scatcherd, 1810) 103; <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> (1 August 1809): 104.</note>
	<note id="n35">6. Thomas Wright, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (Olney: Thomas Wright, 1929) 1:101.
See also 1:108, 111, 114. Sadly, Wright provides no identifiable source for his information. However, in an
endnote he refers to William Meyer’s letters (2:125). With minimal supporting evidence, Wright identifies
Mrs. Chetwynd with the Gwendolen of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (see, for example, 1:130, 2:57).
About 1803 Hayley appears to have taught Blake Latin, Greek, and Hebrew (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 681fn; E
727).</note></p>
          <p>In this passage Hayley claims that in 1800, immediately following a disappointment in love, he
was indebted to “a young female friend . . . for soothing the inquietude of his heart &amp; Mind with a . .
. tender filial affection.”
<q>
This young Lady of 15 was the eldest of an orphan family, that having lost a most amiable father by a
calamitous skirmish in Ireland, with circumstances of horror &amp; distress, was fortuitously conducted to
Felpham in the summer of 1800 by an excellent mother whose shattered nerves required seabathing. The desolate
parent &amp; her orphans soon became familiar with Hayley, ever ready to sympathise with the afflicted. The
eldest girl Penelope attended him to improve herself in Italian, which she had begun to learn, &amp; her
exemplary mother Mrs Chetwyn[d] had such generous confidence in the probity of her new friend that in
departing from the coast, she confided her young Penelope to his care. He restored the young Penelope to her
mother on Friday the 7 November. Such was his tender esteem &amp; affection that he would probably have made
her his wife.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n36">7. William Hayley, “Anecdotes of the Family Life and Writings of William Hayley the
Biographer of Cowper,” 3 vols., General MSS Vol. 352, James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection,
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University, 2:48-50, cited in Mark Crosby, “The Perfect
Helpmeet: Hayley’s Catherine,” unpublished conference paper delivered at the William Blake at 250
conference, York, 30 July-1 August 2007. I wish to thank Mark Crosby for allowing me to cite his discovery
here. Mrs. Chetwynd’s eldest daughter Penelope married Thomas Pearson Firmin at Kingston-upon-Thames,
Surrey, in December 1801 (<hi rend="i">International Genealogical Index</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">IGI</hi>]).</note></q>
Two recently published letters of the poet and novelist Charlotte Smith, to whom William Hayley had formerly
acted as patron and supporter, throw further light on the identity of Mrs. Chetwynd, and suggest that by early
1801 she herself had become the object of Hayley’s affections.</p>
          <p>In a letter to the Irish antiquary and acquaintance of Hayley’s, Joseph Cooper Walker, dated 14
April 1801, Smith observes,
<q>
It is now many months since I have heard of M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Hayley otherwise than by common report, which
says that he is going to be married to a M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Chetwynd, the widow of a Gentleman who was
killed in Ireland in the rebellion &amp; who has five children, none of them quite children.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n37">8. Judith Phillips Stanton, ed., <hi rend="i">The Collected Letters of Charlotte Smith</hi>
(Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2003) 371. I can find no evidence of Mrs. Chetwynd’s having a fifth
child (see note 23 below).</note></q>
On 7 October 1801, in a further letter to Walker, Smith writes, “You probably correspond with our old friend
M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Hayley and know the Lady of your Count[r]y with whom he is as I understand soon to be
united.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">9</ref> Although Hayley married
neither Mrs. Chetwynd nor her eldest daughter, he was certainly in regular contact with Mrs. Chetwynd and her
“orphan family” during the early 1800s. The editor of Smith’s correspondence, Judith Phillips Stanton,
identifies Mrs. Chetwynd as “Penelope Carleton Chetwynd, daughter of John Carleton of Woodside, Co. Cork. .
. .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">10</ref> As noted by Hayley and Smith,
she had recently been widowed. Stanton informs us that Penelope Chetwynd’s husband William Chetwynd
(1754-98), “grandson of the third Viscount Chetwynd, was killed in action with the Irish rebels near
Saintfield, Co. Down, 11 June 1798.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n38">9. Stanton 384. For a third reference to Hayley’s possible remarriage in an undated letter
from Smith to Walker, dated by Stanton to late March-early April 1802, see Stanton 416-17.</note>
	<note id="n39">10. Stanton 372n6. John Carleton was clearly a member of the Irish gentry. “John Carleton,
Esq, Woodside” is listed as a subscriber to <hi rend="i">The Post-Chaise Companion: or, Travellers
Directory, through Ireland. . . . To Which Is Added, a Dictionary, or Alphabetical Tables. Shewing the
Distance of All the Principal Cities, . . . from Each Other</hi> (Dublin: William Wilson, 1788) x. The same
volume mentions that, traveling from Cork to Tralee, “Near 4 miles from Cork on the L is Wood-Side, the seat
of Mr Carleton” (<hi rend="i">Post-Chaise Companion</hi> 354).</note>
	<note id="n40">11. Stanton 372n6.</note></p>
          <p>Crosby’s and Stanton’s information concerning Mrs. Chetwynd can be supplemented by other
sources. The <hi rend="i">International Genealogical Index</hi> (<hi rend="i">IGI</hi>) reveals that Penelope
Carleton was born near Cork about 1762. She married William Chetwynd, son and heir of Rev. Hon. John Chetwynd,
Precentor of Cork, and Judith Piggott, at Cork on 30 May 1783.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n41" type="note">12</ref> According to
<pb id="p42-77" n="77"/>
Henry Edward Chetwynd-Stapleton in his <hi rend="i">The Chetwynds of Ingestre</hi> (1892), when 44-year-old
William Chetwynd was killed at the battle of Saintfield, he “was a captain in the army but serving as a
paymaster of a York fencible regiment commanded by his cousin Granville Anson Chetwynd-Stapleton. . .
.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">13</ref> Of Captain Chetwynd’s role at
Saintfield, John Jones, in <hi rend="i">An Impartial Narrative of Each Engagement Which Took Place between His
Majesty’s Forces and the Rebels, during the Irish Rebellion, 1798</hi>, writes:
<q>
The valour of the officers that fell [at Saintfield] deserves to be publicly recorded, but that of the
amiable, gallant, and much-loved Capt. C ought not to be passed without particular notice.—This brave
fellow, at the head of his men, received no less than nine pike wounds! notwithstanding which, he maintained
his position, encouraging by his example his men to fight like loyal soldiers; till alas, two wounds from
musquets deprived this hero of his existence, and our country of his future services.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">14</ref></q>
On first becoming acquainted with Penelope Chetwynd and presumably her children, perhaps as early as September
1800, Blake probably learned from Hayley that the Chetwynd family comprised the widow and orphans of a
celebrated military hero killed during the Irish insurgency of 1798. <note id="n41">12. See 
<hi rend="i">IGI</hi>; Charles Mosley, ed., <hi rend="i">Burke’s Peerage and Baronetage</hi>, 106th ed. (Crans,
Switzerland: Burke’s Peerage [Genealogical Books] Ltd., 1999) 1:555. <hi rend="i">Alumni
Cantabrigiensis</hi> reveals that William Chetwynd attended Westminster School and was admitted as a
non-resident pensioner at Trinity College, Cambridge, on 29 May 1769 (see John Venn, J. A. Venn, eds., 
<hi rend="i">Alumni Cantabrigiensis: A Biographical List of All Known Students, Graduates and Holders of Office at
the University of Cambridge, from the Earliest Times to 1900</hi> [Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
1922-54] 2:25). Three years earlier Hayley had spent his final year as an undergraduate at Trinity 
(<hi rend="i">Alumni Cantabrigiensis</hi> 3:25; <hi rend="i">DNB</hi>). Chetwynd was admitted to Lincoln’s Inn on
24 June 1771, but at the beginning of October 1771 he migrated to Trinity College, Dublin, where he was
awarded his BA in 1775 (<hi rend="i">Alumni Dublinenses</hi> [Dublin: A. Thom and Co., 1935] 148).</note>
	<note id="n42">13. Henry Edward Chetwynd-Stapleton, <hi rend="i">The Chetwynds of Ingestre; Being a History
of That Family from a Very Early Date with Illustrations by the Author</hi> (London: Longmans, Green &amp;
Co., 1892) 251.</note>
	<note id="n43">14. [John Jones], <hi rend="i">An Impartial Narrative of Each Engagement Which Took Place
between His Majesty’s Forces and the Rebels, during the Irish Rebellion, 1798. . . . Carefully Collected
from Authentic Letters, by John Jones. Embellished with Engravings of the Battles of Arklow and
Tara-Hill</hi>, 4th ed. (Dublin: John Jones, 1800) 1:58-59. See also <hi rend="i">A History of the Irish
Rebellion, in the Year, 1798</hi> (Dublin, 1799) 86.</note></p>
          <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., identifies Mrs. Chetwynd’s brother, described by Blake as “a Giant in
body mild &amp; polite in soul as I have in general found great bodies to be,” as the “M<hi
rend="s">r</hi>. Chetwynd” mentioned by the traveler and writer John Carr in a letter to Hayley dated 9
September 1801.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">15</ref> Carr writes: “Pray
remember me warmly to M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Chetwynd. he is a noble Youth—You &amp; Blake have made a
Coxcomb of a wretched untutored Artist[.]”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">16</ref> But Mrs. Chetwynd’s brother cannot have been the Mr. Chetwynd referred to by Carr. We
have now established that Chetwynd was Penelope Carleton’s married name. Therefore, in all likelihood,
Penelope Chetwynd’s brother’s surname was Carleton.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n44">15. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 109; see also James King, <hi rend="i">William Blake, His
Life</hi> (London: Weidenfeld and Nicholson; New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1991) 149. In the index to 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2), John Carr’s reference to “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Chetwynd” and Blake’s reference
to Mrs. Chetwynd’s brother are listed under the heading George Chetwynd. A George Chetwynd revised Richard
Burn’s <hi rend="i">The Justice of the Peace, and Parish Officer</hi> (1825), a work Bentley cites in a
discussion of Blake’s entered plea of “not guilty” to the charge of sedition at the Michaelmas Quarter
Sessions, Petworth, 4 October 1803 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 170). See <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 108-09,
857n117.</note>
	<note id="n45">16. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 109. In suggesting that Hayley and Blake had “made a Coxcomb”
of Chetwynd, Carr seems to be joking, perhaps alluding to both Blake’s and Hayley’s possibly over-generous
praise of Mr. Chetwynd’s artistic efforts. Carr’s words may echo a passage in William Cowper’s letter to
John Johnson, 23 March 1790, with which Hayley, Blake, and Carr would have been familiar from Hayley’s
recent editing of Cowper’s correspondence: “If you should ever prove a coxcomb, from which character you
stand just now at a greater distance than any young man I know, it shall never be said that I have made you
one.” See William Cowper, <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of William Cowper</hi>, ed. James King
and Charles Ryskamp (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1979-86) 3:363-65. In his journal for Friday, 26 June
1801, John Marsh wrote: “we drove to Felpham &amp; drank tea with M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Hayley where we met
M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Blake y<hi rend="s">e</hi> artist &amp; young M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Chetwynd ...” 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 108).</note>
	<note id="n46">17. Conversely, Bentley may have assumed that Mrs. Chetwynd was single and that, in referring
to her so, Blake was using the title “Mrs.” as an honorific applied to single women of sufficient age,
rank, and wealth.</note></p>
          <p>Penelope Carleton Chetwynd had three younger brothers. Of the eldest, John Barry Carleton (born
c. 1771), I can trace no record after April 1791, when he was made freeman of Cork City. His brothers appear
in contemporary literature as resident at Woodside, so he may therefore have died some time before his
sister’s visit to Blake.</p>
          <p>The second brother, Edward Mitchell Carleton (born c. 1773), was ordained in 1792, and the
following year was licensed to the curacy of the parish of Carrigrohanebeg adjoining Woodside. He married
Elizabeth Withers in January 1799, with whom he produced a family of eleven. In early 1804, Edward Carleton
became prebendary of St. Michael’s, Cork, a position he held until his resignation in 1825. If not the
demands of his new post, then the responsibilities of his rapidly growing family may have made a social visit
to London in the late summer of 1804 problematic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n47">18. However, Blake’s reference to Mrs. Chetwynd’s brother as “mild &amp; polite in soul
as I have in general found great bodies to be” may just possibly refer to the eminent Cork clergyman Edward
Mitchell Carleton.</note></p>
          <p>It therefore seems likely that it was Penelope’s youngest brother who accompanied his sister to
the Blakes’. Webber (or Weber) Carleton was born about 1777, and although like his brothers he entered
Trinity College, Dublin, he did not graduate.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">19</ref> However, as a painter of some ability, by 1815 he was an established, if amateur, artist
as well as a prominent member of Cork’s arts scene. Certainly he was competent enough to have exhibited his
work at the first Munster exhibition of 1815. He was a member of the Cork Society for Promoting the Fine Arts
from its inception in 1816 until his death in 1832, regularly serving on its committee and exhibiting at the
society’s annual exhibition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">20</ref> The
likelihood that Webber
<pb id="p42-78" n="78"/>
Carleton, amateur Cork artist, visited the Blakes provides an intriguing context for Blake’s observation to
Hayley that both Penelope Chetwynd and her brother “were much pleased with Romneys Designs” that Blake had
borrowed from various sources to engrave for Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life of George Romney.</hi>
	<note id="n48">19. See <hi rend="i">Alumni Dublinenses</hi> 134. His elder brothers graduated in 1789 and
1791 respectively.</note>
	<note id="n49">
                            20. Peter Murray, “Cork Art History,” Crawford Art Gallery, Cork, accessed 12
April 2008 &lt;http://www.crawfordartgallery.com/1800-1825.html&gt;; see also Richard Sainthill, 
<hi rend="i">An Olla Podrida; or, Scraps, Numismatic, Antiquarian and Literary</hi> (London: Nicholls and Son,
1844) 227. Blake’s fellow printmaker and artist James Barry also hailed from Cork.
                            <p>On 2 April 1816 the <hi rend="i">Limerick General Advertiser</hi> reported that
on “Tuesday [26 March] morning a duel took place at the Dublin Turnpike, near Cork, between Walter Croker
Esq and Webber Carleton Esq and after exchanging shots without injury to either party, the business was
adjusted.” Webber’s involvement in this potentially fatal conflict sits strangely with Blake’s
estimation of Penelope Chetwynd’s brother as a man “mild &amp; polite in soul.”</p></note></p>
          <p>The “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Chetwynd” who, according to John Carr, was taught painting by
Blake and Hayley at Felpham in September 1801, can now be identified. Catharine Kearsley, in her 
<hi rend="i">Kearsley’s Complete Peerage, of England, Scotland and Ireland</hi> (1794), writes of “William
[Chetwynd] who married Penelope Carleton, by whom he has issue, a son and <corr type="emend">three</corr> 
daughters. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">21</ref> 
According to Hayley (cited above), Penelope Chetwynd’s eldest child Penelope was aged fifteen in 1800. 
She must therefore have been born about 1785, a year or two after her parents married. Penelope Chetwynd’s 
only son, John, can therefore have been no younger than eight and no older than fifteen in 
1801.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">22</ref> 
John Chetwynd was therefore old enough to be “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Chetwynd,” the
“noble Youth” referred to by Carr. Hayley and Blake taught painting not to Penelope Chetwynd’s brother,
but to her orphaned son, young John Chetwynd.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n50">21. Catharine Kearsley, <hi rend="i">Kearsley’s Complete Peerage, of England, Scotland and
Ireland; Together with an Extinct Peerage of the Three Kingdoms</hi> (London: C. and G. Kearsley, 1794)
397.</note>
	<note id="n51">22. See <hi rend="i">Burke’s Peerage and Baronetage</hi>, 92nd ed. (London: Burke’s
Peerage Ltd., 1934) 528.</note>
	<note id="n52">
                            23. As Marsh’s and Carr’s allusions to Mr. Chetwynd are dated June and
September 1801 and Charlotte Smith’s references to Mrs. Chetwynd date from April and October 1801, we may
infer that Penelope Chetwynd’s son John Chetwynd was staying with his mother and sisters Penelope, Lucy, and
Emily near Felpham, c. April-October 1801. John and his three sisters are listed in John Debrett, 
<hi rend="i">Debrett’s Peerage of England, Scotland and Ireland</hi> (London: William Pickering, 1840) 156.
                            <p>In a letter to Hayley dated 19 August 1800, John Flaxman writes of Blake’s
projected move to Felpham: “I see no reason why he should not make as good a livelihood there as in London,
if he engraves &amp; teaches drawing, by which he may gain considerably ...” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2]
94-95).</p></note></p>
          <p>In the light of the new information concerning Penelope Carleton Chetwynd discussed in this note,
it is clear that Mrs. Chetwynd is of significance to Blake studies. As a female member of the gentry she, like
Rebekah Bliss, challenges the commonplace view of Blake’s audience as male, radical, and dissenting. Her
nationality is also important. Previously, the only identified Irish customers for Blake’s work were Martin
Archer Shee (of Dublin) and Sir Richard Newcomen Gore-Booth (of Sligo), subscribers to Robert Hartley
Cromek’s edition of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> in 1808.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n53" type="note">24</ref> Even more significantly, we now know that Blake was in touch with someone
personally affected by the “horror &amp; distress” caused by the recent troubles in Ireland. Blake’s
relationship with Mrs. Chetwynd therefore provides a new perspective for his numerous references to Ireland in
his later illuminated books, including his writing of “the majestic form of Erin in eternal
tears.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">25</ref> Mrs. Chetwynd’s social
position is also telling. In <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi>, A. L. Morton suggests that “because
Blake was a working man he never lost his class passion or his faith in a revolutionary solution.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">26</ref> More recently, E. P. Thompson has suggested
that a politically radical and dissenting Blake maintained a “conscious posture of hostility to . . . polite
culture.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">27</ref> However, Blake’s brief
account of his meeting with Mrs. Chetwynd and Mr. Carleton in 1804 suggests that the poet-artist was at ease
with members of the gentry. The class distinctions Morton and Thompson look for seem curiously absent in
Blake’s encounter. Finally, Blake’s finding a buyer for his work in William Hayley’s intimate friend
Mrs. Chetwynd continues the revision of Blake scholarship’s perception of Hayley. Even when making love to
“M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> C.,” Hayley appears to have been looking out for Blake. <note id="n53">24. See 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 214; Robert N. Essick and Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave
<hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake: A Study with Facsimile</hi> (London: Scolar Press, 1982). Shee’s
student Martin Cregan of County Meath visited the Blakes at 17 South Molton Street in 1809 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 281). However, there is no evidence of his purchasing any of Blake’s works.</note>
	<note id="n54">25. E 245. Rather than Wright’s identification of Penelope Chetwynd with Gwendolen (see note
6 above), another passage from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in which Blake associates the neighborhood of South
Molton Street with sufferings in Ireland seems more pertinent in this context: “Dinah, the youthful form of
Erin / The Wound I see in South Molton S[t]reet &amp; Stratford place / Whence Joseph &amp; Benjamin rolld
apart away from the Nations” (E 230). See also Blake’s reference to “the [war?] Widows tear” in 
<hi rend="i">The Grey Monk</hi> (E 489).</note>
	<note id="n55">26. A. L. Morton, <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi> (London: Lawrence &amp; Wishart,
1958) 18.</note>
	<note id="n56">27. E. P. Thompson, <hi rend="i">Witness against the Beast: William Blake and the Moral
Law</hi> (New York: New Press, 1993) xviii.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
