<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>42.2.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2008</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2008</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">42.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Helen Patricia Bruder</name>
              <name>Robin Hamlyn</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2008"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_42">
    <front id="issue_02">
      <pb id="p42-49-50" n="49-50"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
      <figure n="cover.042.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="332">
        <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
          AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
          From Railway Timetable to Tate Exhibit:<lb/>
          New Prints from the <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi><lb/>
          VOLUME 42<lb/>
          NUMBER 2<lb/>
          FALL 2008</figTranscr>
      </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-2-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="10" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
				<head>
				  <title>CONTENTS</title>
				</head>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="42.2.butlin">Tate Britain Reveals Nine New Blakes and Thirteen
New Lines of Verse</ref>
            			<lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Martin Butlin and Robin Hamlyn</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">52</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Review</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="42.2.vankleeck">W.H. Stevenson, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake: The
Complete Poems</hi>, 3rd ed.</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Justin Van Kleeck</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">73</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particular</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="42.2.whitehead">“M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Chetwynd &amp; her
Brother” and “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Chetwynd”</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Angus Whitehead</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">75</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Discussion</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="42.2.bruder">Response to Anne K. Mellor</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Helen P. Bruder</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">78</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="42.2.mellor">Response to Helen P. Bruder</ref><lb/>
<hi rend="i">By Anne K. Mellor</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">79</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Zürich</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p42-51" n="51"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Helen Patricia Bruder has followed and contributed to debates about Blake and gender since the
early 1990s. She and Tristanne Connolly hope their collection <hi rend="i">Queer Blake</hi> (Palgrave,
forthcoming) and conference Blake, Gender and Sexuality in the Twenty-First Century (London, summer 2010) will
take these vital discussions further still.</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, former Keeper of the Historic British Collection at the Tate Gallery and author of
the standard catalogue of Blake’s paintings and drawings, is at present involved in the Blake Trust
publication of Blake’s illustrations to Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi></p>
        <p>Robin Hamlyn became the William Blake specialist at the Tate Gallery when Martin Butlin retired in
1989. His most recent Blake display at the Tate, in 2007-08, commemorated the 250th anniversary of the
artist’s birth; he wrote the introductory essay for the facsimile edition of <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches</hi> (copy Q) that accompanied the exhibition. His commentary on Edward Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> appeared in 2005.</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor is Distinguished Professor of English and Women’s Studies at UCLA. She is the
author of <hi rend="i">Blake’s Human Form Divine</hi> (1974), <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Gender</hi>
(1993), and many other books and articles on British romantic-era writing, especially by women, and on
feminist theory.</p>
        <p>Justin Van Kleeck is an independent scholar and freelance writer in Charlottesville, Virginia.</p>
        <p>Angus Whitehead is an assistant professor at Nanyang Technological University, National Institute
of Education, Singapore, and editor of the <hi rend="i">Blake Journal.</hi> He is currently working on a
microbiography focusing on William and Catherine Blake’s last years, derived from fresh archival research.
His essay “Rehabilitating the ‘Bad’ Ancient: The Life and Times of Frederick Tatham” is forthcoming in
<hi rend="i">Visual Culture in Britain.</hi></p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Alexander S. Gourlay</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sarah.jones@rochester.edu TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX:
585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Alexander S. Gourlay, Department of English, Rhode Island School of Design, 2 College Street,
Providence RI 02903-2717<lb/>
Email: agourlay@risd.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham
NG11 8NS UK<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the US, Canada, and
Mexico require a $20 per volume postal surcharge for airmail delivery. Credit card payment is available. Make
checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and
related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of
Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for information on issues
and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>Manuscripts are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to
either of the editors. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope.
For electronic submissions, you may send a disk, or send your article as an attachment to an email message;
please number the pages of electronic submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are usually
acceptable.</p>
        <p>International Standard Serial Number: 0160-628x.</p>
        <p>Cover: Verso of <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> pl. 19, color printed and hand colored
by Blake for the second copy (B) of <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi>, 1796, finished c. 1818. Private
collection. Photo courtesy of Tate. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2008 Copyright Morris Eaves
and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
