<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>42.3.rovira</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Wings of Fire: Exhibition at Muhlenberg College, 19 March-19 April 2008</title>
        <author n="Rovira">James Rovira</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2008-09</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2008-09</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">42.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>James Rovira</name>
              <name>Robert M. Ryan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2008/2009"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_42">
    <body>
	  <pb id="p42-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Wings of Fire: Exhibition at Muhlenberg College, 19 March-19 April 2008</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>James <name>Rovira</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>MUHLENBERG College’s Wings of Fire, an exhibition curated by Grant
                        Scott and his senior seminar students, offered a range of Blake originals
                        and historically significant facsimiles and other editions that collectively
                        represent <figure n="wingsfire.42.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="327">
	<figTranscr>
                          Opposition is true friendship.<lb/>
                          Eternity is in love with the productions of Time. <lb/>
<lb/>
                            [Go]ds or Geniuses, calling<lb/>
                            [properti]es of woods, rivers, mountains,<lb/>
                            [nu]merous senses could perceive.<lb/>
                            country, placing it under its<lb/>
                            &amp; enslav’d the vulgar<lb/>
                            [fr]om their objects: thus began<lb/>
                            [order]ed such things.<lb/>
                            [brea]st.<lb/>
<lb/>
                            And did those feet in ancient time.<lb/>
                            Walk upon Englands mountains green<lb/>
                            And was the holy<lb/>
<lb/>
                            And did the Countenance Divine.<lb/>
                            Shine forth upon our clouded hills?<lb/>
                            And was Jerusalem builded here,<lb/>
                            Among these dark Satanic Mills?
                        </figTranscr>
	<head>Image courtesy of Grant Scott, the Martin Art Gallery, and Paul
                                Pearson Photography.</head>
</figure> the complex history of Blake’s relationship with his
                        audiences. The core of the exhibition comprised two originals on permanent
                        loan to Muhlenberg’s Martin Art Gallery: a rare third-state
                        impression of the 1810 engraving of <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury
                            Pilgrims</hi> and a colored copy of the 1797 Edwards edition of
                        Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> with Blake’s
                        illustrations. Florence Foerderer Tonner collected <hi rend="i">Canterbury
                            Pilgrims</hi> and <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> in the early
                        twentieth century, eventually leaving most of her large Blake collection to
                        the Philadelphia Museum of Art; these two pieces were first donated to the
                        Lutheran Church of America then passed on to Muhlenberg College. A local
                        Blake scholar also loaned an uncolored copy of <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi>, a first edition of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> with
                        Blake’s illustrations, an 1874 edition of Blake’s engravings
                        of the Book of Job, editions of William Muir’s lithographic
                        reproductions from the 1880s, and high-quality facsimiles produced by the
                        Trianon Press between 1951 and 1979. Wings of Fire also featured such
                        additions as a beautifully bound copy of the Yeats edition of Blake’s
                        works and two replica printing plates based on electrotypes cast from
                        Blake’s original copperplates at the time of Gilchrist’s
                        biography. Joseph Viscomi loaned these plates to the exhibition, opening it
                        on 19 March with the lecture “Blake’s Enlightened Graphics:
                        Illuminated Books and New Technologies.” Muhlenberg alumni and
                        seniors closed the exhibition with a dance adaptation of “The
                        Tyger” and selections of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> set
                        to music.</p>
          <p>Scott and his Muhlenberg seniors playfully designed the exhibition space with
                        a spiral half-wall set up to display Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book
of Job</hi> toward the rear of the room.
                        Students stenciled lines of Blake’s text in large letters on the
                        walls and floor in the form of concrete poems. For example, the lines
                        “How do you know but ev’ry Bird that cuts the airy way, / Is
                        an immense world of delight, clos’d by your senses 
						<pb id="p42-111" n="111"/>
						five?” (E 35) were stenciled the length of an entire
                        wall in the shape of a bird’s wings, while other lines ran along the
                        baseboard and around display cases, swirling and diving across other walls.
                        The students working with Scott clearly loved their subject, their
                        playfulness a sure indicator of how much Blake’s work became their
                        own. It’s not hard to see why. If online images or print
                        reproductions inspire, Blake originals inspire even more. What is now called
                        book history has long occupied Blake scholars; seeing the Muhlenberg exhibit
                        reminded me how much of this history was a labor of love, both for Blake and
                        his readers.</p>
          <p>Scott, Grant. <hi rend="i">Wings of Fire: The Illuminated Books of William
                            Blake.</hi> Allentown: Martin Art Gallery, 2008. N. pag. [14 pp. + 17
                        illus., mostly color]</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
