<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>42.3.whitehead</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">“this extraordinary performance”: William Blake’s Use of Gold and Silver
in the Creation of His Paintings and Illuminated Books</title>
        <author n="Whitehead">Angus Whitehead</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2008-09</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2008-09</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">42.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Angus Whitehead</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>James Rovira</name>
              <name>Robert M. Ryan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2008/2009"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_42">
    <body>
    <pb id="p42-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“this extraordinary performance”: William
                            Blake’s Use of Gold and Silver in the Creation of His Paintings
                            and Illuminated Books</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Angus <name>Whitehead</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">
            <hi rend="i">Author’s note: <ref type="html-issue" issue="bonus.whitehead">Illustrations</ref>
showing Blake’s use of gold in Jerusalem copy E pls. 14, 63, and 97, as well as color photographs
demonstrating the gilding process, are <corr type="emend">available under 
<ref type="html-issue" issue="bonus.toc">Bonus Content</ref>.</corr></hi>
          </note>
          <p>EVIDENCE of how William and Catherine Blake displayed their watercolors,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref>
                        temperas, and intaglio and relief-etched prints at their final residence
                        together, two rooms on the first floor of 3 Fountain Court, Strand, is all
                        but non-existent.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref> However, a marginal
                        annotation by a member of their circle may provide some clues concerning the
                        Blakes’ last public viewing space. Almost forty years ago, G. E.
                        Bentley, Jr., discussed a faintly sketched plan of the Blakes’ rooms
                        drawn by George Richmond, a regular visitor between 1825 and 1827, in his
                        copy of Gilchrist’s 1863 biography of Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Bentley interprets the two rectangles on a wall in
                        the front room as the front windows of the flat. However, as Frederick
                        William Fairholt’s 1858 woodcut indicates, 3 Fountain Court was an
                        early Georgian terrace, built with two rooms on each floor, one directly
                        behind, rather than adjacent to, the other.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Therefore, the wall in question, rather than being the front of
                        the house, must have been the supporting wall between 3 and 4 Fountain
                        Court, and could not have featured windows.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n4" type="note">4</ref> The rectangles probably represent two of the “frescos,
                        temperas, and drawings of Blake’s” which, according to
                        Gilchrist, hung on the paneled walls of the front room.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> If this is the case, then the larger rectangle may
                        represent a lost painting and one of the few works identified as hanging on
                        the walls at Fountain Court, Blake’s seven-foot-high tempera of <hi rend="i">The
Last Judgment</hi> (c. 1810-27?).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
Blake may have chosen to hang it adjacent to the
                        right of the two front windows in order to capitalize on what northeastern
                        light there was available in this reportedly rather dark reception room and
                            showroom.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n0">*An earlier version of this
                            paper was read at the William Blake at Work conference, Tate Britain, 30
                            Apr. 2004. Much of the material derives from my MA dissertation,
                            “my present precincts,”’ and my PhD thesis,
                            “New Discoveries.” For help of various kinds I wish to
                            thank Anna Lou Ashby, Keri Davies, Sarah Jones, Tim Linnell, Bronwyn
                            Ormsby, Hattie Parry-Williams, Troy Patenaude, Carole Towers, Alex
                            Watson, and Scott Wilcox, and especially Martin Butlin, Rebecca Donnan,
                            Robert N. Essick, Michael Gregory, Joyce Townsend, Joseph Viscomi, and
                            my generous thesis supervisor, Michael Phillips.
                            <lb/>
<lb/>
I have had the opportunity to
                            examine carefully the plates of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                                Experience copy W at King’s College Library</hi>, Cambridge,
                            the tempera <hi rend="i">panel Winter during the William Blake</hi>:
                            Inspiration and Illustration exhibition at the Graves Art Gallery,
                            Sheffield, 9 Aug.-1 Nov. 2003, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E
                            and the tempera <hi rend="i">The Virgin and Child</hi> at the Yale
                            Center for British Art, New Haven. However, both my arguments concerning
                            Blake’s use of metal-based paints in parts 1 and 2 and the
                            tabulated information in tables 1 and 2 are largely derived from earlier
                            Blake scholarship and published and unpublished research at the Tate and
                            elsewhere. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work</hi>, ed.
                            Joyce Townsend, senior conservation scientist at the Tate, provides
                            important new information concerning Blake’s use of metal-based
                            paints in the temperas, based upon detailed materials analysis of a
                            number of works.
                            <lb/>
<lb/>
Although similarly thorough
                            analysis of Blake’s use of metal-based materials in the creation
                            and finishing of his illuminated books has yet to be carried out,
                            several scholars have briefly discussed the finishing of specific works.
                            See Phillips 108; Paley, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Jerusalem
                            15-16; Lincoln 22; Essick and Viscomi, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>:
                            Milton a Poem 38, 41; and the <hi rend="i">William Blake Archive</hi>,
                            “Update on the William Blake Archive” entries dated 17
                            Apr. 2000, 5 Mar. 2001, Mar. 2003
                            &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org/blake/public/all-updates.html&gt;.
                            In <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, Bentley has recorded the majority of
                            the illuminated books Blake finished in gold and silver. For the dating
                            in table 2, I have consulted Joseph Viscomi’s chronological table
                            in his <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi> This essay
                            discusses metal material Blake applied to the designs and/or texts of
                            his illuminated books during his lifetime, not gilding of the cut edges
                            of books or the posthumous application of gold and/or silver. Morton
                            Paley is judiciously cautious in his description of the nature of the
                            metal used on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E, but cites the
                            analytical research of Theresa Fairbanks, paper conservator at the Yale
                            Center for British Art, which indicates that “both gold coloured
                            metal leaf and silver coloured metal leaf were employed, as well as gold
                            coloured powder” (<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Jerusalem 15).
                            Although my discovery discussed in part 3 suggests that Blake could
                            indeed have used gold and silver material in a number of illuminated
                            books, further materials analysis is required to establish this
                            conclusively.</note>
	<note id="n1">1. In a letter to Alexander Gilchrist dated 23 Aug. 1855,
                            Samuel Palmer recalls that “[Blake] delighted in Ovid, and, as a
                            labour of love, had executed a finished picture from the 
<hi rend="i">Metamorphoses</hi>, after Giulio Romano. This design hung in his
                            [back] room, and, close by his engraving table, Albert
                            Dürer’s <hi rend="i">Melancholy the Mother of Invention .
                                . .</hi>” (quoted in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
                            [hereafter BR(2)] 752fn). However, no reliable account of works hanging
                            in the Blakes’ front room survives.</note>
	<note id="n2">2. Bentley, “William Blake” 44-45.
                            Richmond’s plan is reproduced in Whitehead, “No. 3
                            Fountain Court, Strand” 22 (pl. 4).</note>
	<note id="n3">3. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) pl. 67.</note>
	<note id="n4">4. For further information concerning the Blakes’ last
                            living space, see Whitehead, “No. 3 Fountain Court,
                            Strand.”</note>
	<note id="n5">5. A. Gilchrist 305.</note>
	<note id="n6">6. Whitehead, “No. 3 Fountain Court, Strand” 28
                            and n55.</note>
	<note id="n7">7. See Richmond’s comment to Herbert Harlakenden
                            Gilchrist (c. 1885), quoted in <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 753. The houses
                            on the opposite side of this narrow court also limited the light
                            reaching the front room; see Whitehead, “No. 3 Fountain Court,
                            Strand” 22 (pl. 3).</note></p>
          <p>In the months following Blake’s death, John Thomas Smith, keeper of
                        prints and drawings at the British Museum, called upon Catherine perhaps at
                        Fountain Court or, more probably, at her lodgings from mid-September 1827
                        until mid-1828 at the artist John Linnell’s town house and studio, 6
                        Cirencester Place, Fitzroy Square. During his visit, Smith examined The   
                        <pb id="p42-85" n="85"/>
	<hi rend="i">Last Judgment.</hi> In the second volume of his biography of
                        the sculptor Joseph Nollekens, published the following year, he observes:
						<q> Had [Blake] fortunately lived till the next year’s exhibition
                            at Somerset-house, the public would then have been astonished at his
                            exquisite finishing of a Fresco picture of the Last Judgment, containing
                            upwards of one thousand figures, many of them wonderfully conceived and
                            grandly drawn. The lights of this extraordinary performance have the
                            appearance of silver and gold; but upon Mrs. Blake’s assuring me
                            that there was no silver used, I found, upon a closer examination, that
                            a blue wash had been passed over those parts of the gilding which
                            receded, and the lights of the forward objects, which were also of gold,
                            were heightened with a warm colour, to give the appearance of the two
                                metals.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8">8. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 617.</note></q>
Catherine was clearly in a position to speak
knowledgeably of the
                        materials her husband had used. However, research carried out at the Tate
                        and discussed in <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at Work</hi>
                        demonstrates that Blake <hi rend="i">did</hi> use silver, gold-silver alloy,
                        and other metal-based paints as well as gold in a number of his
                        paintings.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1. Blake’s Use of Gold and Other Metals,
                                    1775-1827</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Henry Fuseli, writing around 1820, alludes to “Fresco” as
                            “a method of painting almost as much out of use as public
                            encouragement ....”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref>
                            Similarly, gold and other metal-based paints appear rarely to have been
                            utilized by British artists from the seventeenth to the early nineteenth
                                century.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> However, Blake used
                            such materials in a variety of works throughout his artistic career.
                            According to Martin Butlin, gold appears in Blake’s work as early
                            as c. 1775. It features in six of the designs for illustrations to
                            Joseph Ayloffe’s <hi rend="i">Some Ancient Monuments in
                                Westminster Abbey</hi> (1780), and has also been traced in four of
                            the drawings for Richard Gough’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral
                                Monuments of Great Britain</hi> part 1 (1786) (see table la). He
                            produced both sets of designs while still an apprentice to James Basire,
                            official engraver to the Society of Antiquaries.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Gold appears in Blake’s own designs in
                            the mid-to-late 1790s, towards the end of what appears to have been a
                            rare period of relative financial independence for the poet-artist and
                            his wife, while they resided at 13 Hercules Buildings, Lambeth (see
                            table 1b). Traces of gold leaf and shell gold (powdered gold leaf mixed
                            with honey and oxgall and applied as a paint) are evident on the first
                            pull of the large color print <hi rend="i">Naomi Entreating Ruth and
                                Orpah to Return to the Land of Moab</hi> (c. 1795).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Blake appears first to have used gold material
                            on a painting when creating one of the fifty-four surviving temperas on
                            a biblical theme painted for his patron Thomas Butts, <hi rend="i">Eve
                                Tempted by the Serpent</hi> (c. 1799-1800).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n9">9. Royal Academy “Lecture
                                IX.—Colour.—Oil Painting,” reprinted in Wornum
                                515.</note>
	<note id="n10">10. One exception appears to have been Joseph Wright of
                                Derby. Jones describes Wright’s use of gold and silver leaf,
                                with oil paint applied on top, to depict a lamp and glowing metal in
                                two pictures from the period 1768-71 (268). However, unlike
                                Blake’s works featuring gold or silver, “in neither
                                case is one meant to be aware of the gold with the naked
                                eye.” Jones suggests that Wright “did not think the
                                experiment worth pursuing.” She also cites a 1795 treatise on
                                painting which describes the use of metal leaf.</note>
	<note id="n11">11. Although staff at the Society of Antiquaries
                                (Ayloffe) and the Bodleian Library (Gough) have been unable to
                                confirm this, the gold in these works was almost certainly applied
                                as shell gold (see Lister 56; Mason and Gregory).</note>
	<note id="n12">12. Cahaner McManus and Townsend note that gold leaf was
                                applied “to the still-wet paint soon after printing. . . .
                                the shell gold . . . used more extensively in this print contains a
                                gold-silver alloy. . . . This would not have been as expensive as
                                pure gold” (“The Large Colour Prints” 94).
                                Although this has yet to be verified, gold-silver alloy appears to
                                have been used on several of the plates in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E
(for example, pl. 23, reclining winged
                                figure).</note>
	<note id="n13">13. Ormsby, Townsend, Singer, and Dean,
                                “Blake’s Use” 137.</note></p>
            <p>Blake may also have used gold during his residence at Felpham, Sussex, in
                            1800-03 under the poet and biographer William Hayley’s patronage.
                            In that period he probably painted three works believed to have been
                            created as mantels for a fireplace at Cowper’s cousin and
                            Hayley’s friend Rev. John Johnson’s rectory at Yaxham,
                            Norfolk. In his catalogue, Butlin dates the three panel paintings, 
<hi rend="i">Winter</hi> (illus. 1), <hi rend="i">Evening</hi> (illus.
                            2), and <hi rend="i">Olney Bridge</hi>, c. 1820-25.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Ormsby, Singer, and Dean cite these works as
                            examples of Blake’s “improved confidence and skill in the
                            handling of paint” in the period 1821-26.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> However, in response to my query, and drawing
                            upon stylistic and biographical evidence, Butlin now admits the
                            possibility that all three works were painted twenty years earlier,
                            during Blake’s years at Felpham.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">16</ref> The materials of <hi rend="i">Winter</hi>, acquired 
<pb id="p42-86" n="86"/>
<figure n="BUT808.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="327" height="1000">
	<head>1. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Winter</hi> (1800-03?), tempera
                                    on pine.</head>
	<figDesc>Tate T02387. § Tate, London.</figDesc>
</figure> by the Tate in 1979, have not been analyzed, but a 2003
                            condition report records “numerous . . . gilding . . .
                                losses.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> My own
                            examination, in October 2003, suggests that significant traces of gold
                            material remain on nine areas of the panel support, and that a great
                            deal more had originally been applied to the work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> In 1999 Rebecca Donnan, then Andrew W. Mellon
                            fellow in advanced paper conservation at the National Gallery of Art in
                            Washington, examined the companion work, <hi rend="i">Evening.</hi> She
                            observed that it also bears evidence of an application of a considerable
                            amount of gold, much of which appears to have dislodged from the surface
                            of the poor-quality pine support.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
                            It seems likely that Blake also applied a similar quantity 
<pb id="p42-87" n="87"/>
of gold to the lost companion frieze, <hi rend="i">Olney Bridge.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
                            <hi rend="i">Winter, Evening</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Olney Bridge</hi>
                            may therefore be some of Blake’s earlier, if not altogether
                            successful, experiments in a relatively extensive use of gold in tempera
                            painting. <note id="n14">14. Butlin, <hi rend="i">Paintings and
                                    Drawings</hi> [hereafter B] #808-10; see also Butlin, <hi rend="i">William
Blake</hi> 167.</note>
	<note id="n15">15. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 131-32.</note>
	<note id="n16">
                               16. “Looking at the reproductions of <hi rend="i">Winter</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Evening</hi> again I
                                    am not quite so absolutely definite that the pictures must be as
                                    late as I stated. There was a curious period in 1803 when
                                    Blake’s technique became very loose and it is just
                                    possible, given the difference in technique and the present
                                    state of the temperas, that they could have been painted at
                                    about the same time as such watercolours as <hi rend="i">The
                                        Angel of the Divine Presence Clothing Adam and Eve with
                                        Coats of Skins</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Dutiful
                                        Daughter-in-Law</hi>, both of which are signed and dated
                                    1803 (my numbers B. 436 and 456). This of course would put the
                                    paintings nearer to Blake’s known contacts with [John]
                                    Johnson” (letter to the author, 20 Oct. 2003).
                                <p>According to a letter from Mary Barham Johnson,
                                    great-granddaughter of John Johnson, to her cousin (?) Charles,
                                    8 Mar. 1971, 
<q> Yaxham Rectory was built in 1820-21, but as
                                        Johnny had been hoping to build for 20 years, Blake may have
                                        done the panels years earlier—They are never
                                        mentioned in the letters we have. The only hint is in one
                                        from Johnny to his wife when the house was nearly finished
                                        saying that he agreed that plain mantels were best. The ones
                                        erected were of black marble I think . . . I wonder if
                                        [William] Hayley commissioned them [i.e., Blake’s
                                        paintings] &amp; they were sent after his death [1820].
                                    </q>
My thanks to Martin Butlin for this information. His
                                    tentatively revised dating concurs with Bentley: see 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 116fn. The present owner of Yaxham
                                    rectory, David Wright, recalls a conversation with the previous
                                    owner, who said that before structural modifications took place
                                    in the second half of the twentieth century, the fireplaces were
                                    of black marble, as Mary Barham Johnson remembered (telephone
                                    conversation with the author, 12 June 2005).</p>
	<p>The possibility that these paintings were executed c. 1803
                                    potentially complicates any theory of uninterrupted progress in
                                    the development of Blake’s painting technique. The
                                    revised dating suggests that he had used a successful technique
                                    in the creation of his temperas twenty years earlier than
                                    previously thought and then apparently abandoned it until the
                                    last years of his life. This anomaly was perhaps born out of the
                                    unique nature of Johnson’s commission and the consequent
                                    necessity of using a pine support.</p>
	<p>Johnson was a cousin of Cowper, who had died at Johnson’s
                                    house in East Dereham on 25 Apr. 1800. The three works allude
                                    explicitly to sections of book 4 of Cowper’s <hi rend="i">The Task.</hi>
Between 1800 and 1802 Hayley researched his
                                    biography of Cowper; during the new year of 1802 Johnson visited
                                    Hayley at Felpham and met Blake, who painted a miniature of him
                                        (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 116-17). It is therefore likely
                                    that Johnson commissioned the works in early Jan.
                                1802.</p></note>
	<note id="n17">17. Susan Breen, condition report on <hi rend="i">Winter</hi> for loan to Graves Gallery,
Sheffield, summer 2003,
                                Tate Conservation Department records.</note>
	<note id="n18">18. I noted what appeared to be thick shell gold on the
                                top left-hand corner and at intervals along the left-hand edge of
                                the support. Gold-based paint was also evident on the top right-hand
                                fork and the base of the leafless branch/quill held by Winter, on
                                both of his sleeves, the rim of his hood, on the coils of the
                                serpent enveloping him, and on the hem of his robe. There are also
                                prominent traces of gold-based paint around the base of his throne,
                                described by Cowper as “A sliding car indebted to no wheels,
                                / But urged by storms along its slipp’ry way” (see <hi rend="i">The
Task</hi> 4:120-29).</note>
	<note id="n19">
                                19. Archibald G. B. Russell writes that
                                    “between [Evening’s] breasts is a crescent moon of
                                    gold, and around her are many golden stars” (<hi rend="i">William
Blake</hi> [1947] 25). Russell’s
                                    observations are confirmed by Donnan’s findings
                                    (telephone conversation, 21 Oct. 2002); her unpublished research
                                    is our most authoritative source of information on gold-based
                                    materials in this work. According to Pamela Betts, then Culpeper
                                    fellow in painting conservation at the National Gallery of Art,
                                    “there is no existing conservation file on the
                                    painting” (email, 22 Nov. 2004). In an examination of the
                                    work in Mar. 1990, conservator Ann Hoenigswald concluded,
                                    “there seems to have been very extensive loss of the
                                    gold” (email from Betts, 12 May 2005). Blake appears to
                                    have used gold to enhance his illustration of lines 251-58 from
                                    book 4 of <hi rend="i">The Task</hi>, in which Cowper describes
                                    Evening as 
<q> Not sumptuously adorn’d, nor needing
                                        aid<lb/>
 Like homely featur’d night, of
                                        clust’ring gems,<lb/>
 A star or two just twinkling on
                                        thy brow<lb/>
 Suffices thee; save that the moon is
                                        thine<lb/>
 No less than hers, not worn indeed on high<lb/>
                                        With ostentatious pageantry, but set<lb/>
 With modest
                                        grandeur in thy purple zone,<lb/>
 Resplendent less, but of
                                        an ampler round. </q>
Tate records suggest losses of gold
                                    leaf and other metal on other works by Blake. In her analysis of
                                        <hi rend="i">The Bard</hi>, Bronwyn Ormsby records that gold
                                    leaf “does not seem to have adhered well anywhere on the
                                    surface” (conservation report, 2001, Tate Conservation
                                    Department records).
                            </note>
	<note id="n20">20. <hi rend="i">Olney Bridge</hi> was “apparently
                                painted in a long format to run across the top of the same
                                chimney-piece as was flanked by [<hi rend="i">Winter</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Evening</hi>]” (B #810). It may have resembled
                                the engraving and description of the bridge in [E. W. Brayley,] 
<hi rend="i">Cowper, Illustrated by a Series of Views, in, or near,
                                    the Park of Weston-Underwood, Bucks</hi> (London, 1803), which
                                Blake may have seen and used as his source. See Wright 1:131;
                                Whitehead, “William Blake’s Subsidiary Design”
                                319.</note></p>
            <p>Metal leaf has also been traced on six of Blake’s surviving
                            temperas on canvas and one watercolor from the period c. 1800-09. He
                            showed five of the six temperas at his 1809-10 one-man exhibition on the
                            vacant first floor of the home and hosiery shop of his brother James at
                            28 Broad Street, Golden Square.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">21</ref> In
                            his commentary on <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of Pitt</hi> in the
                                <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> which accompanied the
                            exhibition, Blake wrote: 
<q> This Picture also is a proof of the power
                                of colours unsullied with oil or with any cloggy vehicle. . . . All
                                the genuine old little Pictures, called Cabinet Pictures, are in
                                fresco and not in oil. Oil was not used except by blundering
                                ignorance, till after Vandyke’s time, but the art of fresco
                                painting being lost, oil became a fetter to genius, and a dungeon to
                                art. But one convincing proof among many others, that these
                                assertions are true is, that real gold and silver cannot be used
                                with oil, as they are in all the old pictures and in Mr. B.’s
                                frescos. (E 530, 531) </q>
The paintings in the exhibition featuring
                            “real gold and silver”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref> were <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of Nelson, The
                                Spiritual Form of Pitt, Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the Nine and Twenty
                                Pilgrims on Their Journey to Canterbury, The Bard, from Gray</hi>,
                            and <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions</hi>—<hi rend="i">An Experiment
Picture.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
                            In <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi>
<figure n="BUT809.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="330" height="1000">
	<head>2. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Evening</hi> (1800-03?),
                                    tempera on pine.</head>
	<figDesc>1990.22.1./PA, gift of Mr. and Mrs. Gordon Hanes. Courtesy
                                    of the Board of Trustees, National Gallery of Art, Washington,
                                    DC.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p42-88" n="88"/>
and <hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi> a limited use of
                            metal leaf is evident. By contrast, a considerably more generous
                            application is apparent in <hi rend="i">Pitt, The Bard</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions.</hi> Around the time of the
                            exhibition, <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi> and <hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi> were
                            purchased by Butts, along with a watercolor featuring a similarly
                            restrained use of gold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">24</ref> The
                            likelihood that <hi rend="i">Pitt, The Bard</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Satan
                                Calling Up His Legions</hi> remained in Blake’s studio until
                            his death suggests the possibility that he added more gold material to
                            these paintings sometime during the period 1810-27. <note id="n21">
                                21. The sixth tempera is the Petworth House version of <hi rend="i">Satan
Calling Up His Legions.</hi> This has
                                    “a more restrained use of gold” than the earlier
                                    version (Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 126). Another work which may
                                    have featured gold is the untraced <hi rend="i">Spiritual Form
                                        of Napoleon</hi> (c. 1809?/1822?). Palmer may have purchased
                                    the work from Blake or his widow c. 1825-31.
                                <p>For a demonstration of the likelihood that “Blake had two
                                    exhibitions: one in 1809 and another in 1810,” see
                                    Patenaude 63n44.</p></note>
	<note id="n22">22. With the exception of <hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi>,
                                silver-based material is present in these works only in the form of
                                the cheaper gold-silver alloy Blake appears to have been using
                                during this period (see Townsend, appendix 6).</note>
	<note id="n23">23. In a note following the entry for <hi rend="i">Satan
                                    Calling Up His Legions</hi> in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
                                    Catalogue</hi>, Blake claims that this and other
                                “experiment Pictures have been bruized and knocked about . .
                                . to try all experiments” (E 548). The fact that he was
                                willing to or indeed could afford to use gold-based materials on
                                this “experiment Picture” with little hope of finally
                                selling the painting is interesting. It also anticipates his later
                                use of gold-based materials on works that appear to have had no
                                certain patron or market, such as the Genesis manuscript and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E (see below).</note>
	<note id="n24">24. <hi rend="i">Satan, Sin and Death: Satan Comes to the
                                    Gates of Hell</hi>, one of the twelve illustrations to
                                Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>: the large Butts
                                set.</note></p>
            <p>Troy Patenaude has recently attempted to recreate the arrangement of the
                            sixteen pictures in the exhibition. He suggests that it began with 
<hi rend="i">Pitt</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi>, hanging next to one
                            another, taking up most of the available horizontal space on the
                            partition wall in the smaller of the two rooms. They directly faced 
<hi rend="i">Chaucer.</hi> Patenaude concludes that <hi rend="i">Pitt</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi> “were
meant to be
                            hung together as companion pieces.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n25" type="note">25</ref> Pigment analysis undertaken at the Tate and tabulated in
                            appendix 6 of <hi rend="i">The Painter at Work</hi> indicates that Blake
                            used very similar materials in the creation of these two temperas. For
                            these reasons it seems likely that the pair appeared more similar when
                            exhibited side by side in 1809-10 than they do today. The difference may
                            be explained in part by the subsequent histories and present poor
                            condition of the two works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">26</ref>
                            However, it is also possible that Blake altered the appearance of 
<hi rend="i">Pitt</hi> and added metal leaf sometime after the
                                exhibition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">27</ref> About 1809 he also
                            painted a number of miniatures on enamel supports for Butts and his
                                family,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">28</ref> and it is very likely
                            that he followed the common practice of adding gold leaf to paint media
                            in order to enhance the luster of each miniature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n25">25. Patenaude 54. His findings therefore support
                                Paley’s earlier assertion concerning the two paintings; see
                                    <hi rend="i">Energy</hi> chapter 7: “The World without
                                Imagination: Blake’s Visions of Leviathan and
                                Behemoth.”</note>
	<note id="n26">26. Much of the original paint on <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi> was lost due to damage during the
Millbank flood in
                                1928 (Ormsby, technical report, 2002, Tate Conservation Department
                                records).</note>
	<note id="n27">
                                27. According to Ormsby, Singer, and Dean, Blake
                                    “applied [gold leaf] to an oil size and worked [it] into
                                    the surface, probably with a brush” (124). They also
                                    observe that “significant periods of time must have
                                    passed between paint applications, which is not surprising, as
                                    Blake is reported to have returned to his works for periods of
                                    years after they were commenced” (125). Blake may also
                                    have added gold material to his temperas years later.
                                <p>David Fallon suggests that the use of gold and silver in 
<hi rend="i">Pitt</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi> is
                                    significant “because of the critique [Blake] seems to be
                                    making regarding the idolatry of these public figures”
                                    (email, 16 Jan. 2006). He adds that through the use of gold and
                                    silver Blake may be making a biblical allusion to
                                    Nebuchadnezzar’s golden statue; see also
                                Fallon.</p></note>
	<note id="n28">28. See B #376-78; for evidence of all three
                                miniatures’ having been executed about 1809, see
                                Crosby.</note>
	<note id="n29">29. Lister 49.</note></p>
            <p>During the period 1810-15 Blake appears to have used metal-based paints
                            and leaf less frequently in the creation of his paintings (see tables 1b
                            and 1c).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref>
In just one instance, the
                            large tempera <hi rend="i">An Allegory of the Spiritual Condition of
                                Man</hi> (1811?), he made use of shell gold to sign the work.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> The few surviving biographical
                            records relating to the Blakes’ remaining years at 17 South
                            Molton Street suggest that this time of national economic depression was
                            also a period of considerable poverty and isolation for the couple.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> One contemporary record gives some
                            indication of just how expensive gold leaf would have been. In 1812 the
                            leading framemaker and carver and gilder John Smith of Swallow Street,
                            Piccadilly, recorded in his day book that fourteen books of gold leaf
                            (each comprising twenty-five sheets measuring three-and-a-quarter inches
                            square) had cost him £1.6.0.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">33</ref>
                            According to Bentley’s estimates of Blake’s accounts
                            during this period, such a figure is likely to have amounted to more
                            than a week’s income.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">34</ref> For
                            those temperas and drawings with gold and other metal leaf, Blake must
                            have used only a fraction of the material Smith needed to gild a picture
                            frame. Nevertheless, it seems unlikely 
<pb id="p42-89" n="89"/>
that
                            Blake often had the means to use gold and silver extensively during this
                                time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">35</ref>
	<note id="n30">30. However, gold material can be traced in two
                                illuminated books from this period (see table 2).</note>
	<note id="n31">31. See Keynes, <hi rend="i">Tempera Paintings</hi> 11;
                                Bindman, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> 32. This work, along with
                                several others featuring gold, appears to have been commissioned by
                                Butts (see tables 1b and 1c).</note>
	<note id="n32">32. George Cumberland called on Blake on the afternoon of
                                Friday 3 June 1813 and described him in his pocket book as
                                “still poor still Dirty” (BL Add. MSS. 36,520D, f.
                                182, quoted in <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 316). On the evening of
                                Thursday 20 Apr. 1815 Cumberland’s sons George and Sydney
                                found the Blakes “drinking Tea, durtyer than ever” (BL
                                Add. MSS. 36,505, f. 63, quoted in <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 320).
                                Anthony Dyson observes that “life was to be difficult for
                                many artists throughout the Napoleonic Wars [1800-15] and
                                beyond,” partly due to the “general economic
                                depression [and] . . . popularity of ‘old
                                masters’—or pictures which would pass for them”
                                (11-12). Linnell recalled that in 1818 “everything in Art was
                                at a low ebb then” (manuscript “Autobiography of John
                                Linnell,” quoted in <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 341).</note>
	<note id="n33">
                                33. V&amp;A National Art Library, 86.CC.1, John Smith
                                    day book, entry for 17 Mar. 1812, cited in Simon 144. I am
                                    grateful to Hattie Parry-Williams at Arnold Wiggins and Sons for
                                    bringing this information to my attention. In Aug. 1827 Smith
                                    made a frame for William Collins’s <hi rend="i">Scene at
                                        Folkestone</hi>, and noted that to gild the frame in oil and
                                    burnished gold required twelve books of gold and twelve leaves
                                    of another book (Simon 144).
                                <p>In his prospectus of 10 Oct. 1793, Blake advertises copies of
                                    “Songs of Innocence” and “Songs of
                                    Experience” at 5 shillings each (E 692). A quarter of a
                                    century later, in his letter to Dawson Turner of 9 June 1818 (E
                                    771), he offers copies of the same works at 3 guineas each. In a
                                    letter to Cumberland dated 12 Apr. 1827, Blake gives the price
                                    of a copy of “Songs of Inn. &amp; Exp.” as 10
                                    guineas (E 784). This is not merely, as is the case with other
                                    illuminated books priced for Cumberland, “one to two
                                    pounds higher than in 1818,” as Viscomi suggests (363).
                                    Rather, the work has almost doubled in price. This is the price
                                    that a customer, probably Thomas Griffiths Wainewright, paid for
                                    copy X of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, finished in gold, after Apr.
                                    1827 (E 784; Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> [hereafter
                                        <hi rend="i">BB</hi>] 423). Ten guineas is also the amount
                                    that John Jebb, Bishop of Limerick, paid Catherine for 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy W, also finished in gold-based
                                    paint, on 3 Mar. 1830 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 509). It is
                                    possible but by no means certain that the dramatic rise in price
                                    for <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> partly reflects Blake’s
                                    regular use of metal-based paint in the finishing of copies
                                    during this period. However, this theory is countered, or at
                                    least complicated, by the fact that Henry Crabb
                                    Robinson’s and Elizabeth Aders’s copies of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> Z
(featuring gold-based paint) and AA
                                    (featuring no gold), purchased in Apr. and July 1826
                                    respectively, both appear to have cost 5 guineas (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
704, 776).</p></note>
	<note id="n34">34. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 810. Of course, some records
                                of his income during this period are likely to have been
                                lost.</note>
	<note id="n35">35. From 1812 until 1818 Blake appears to have ceased
                                printing his illuminated books (Viscomi 379). Viscomi identifies ten
                                copies printed in 1818; of these, six were finished in gold (see
                                table 2). However, it is possible that these works were colored and
                                finished several years after they were printed. Two illuminated
                                books probably finished in gold-based paint before 1818 are 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copies R/Y and S. In the early 1820s the
                                financial situation became so extreme for Blake that he sold his
                                print collection. In late June 1822 the Royal Academy described
                                Blake as “an able Designer &amp; Engraver laboring under
                                great distress” and shortly afterwards awarded him the sum of
                                £25 (see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 395 and
                                fn).</note></p>
            <p>However, from about 1815 Blake began to use metal leaf, and especially
                            gold, in his paintings and illuminated books with unprecedented
                            frequency. Six temperas, five watercolors, two separate relief-etched
                            plates, and the second version of a title page of a manuscript feature
                            either small pieces of gold or silver leaf or shell gold or silver or
                            gold-silver alloy (see table 1c). Such works include the temperas <hi rend="i">The
Ghost of a Flea, The Virgin and Child, The Body of Abel
                                Found by Adam and Eve</hi>, and the watercolor <hi rend="i">Epitome
                                of James Hervey’s</hi> Meditations among the Tombs. In
                            addition, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Parable of the Wise and Foolish
                                Virgins</hi> is signed in gold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n36" type="note">36</ref> Nineteen illuminated books lavishly colored and finished
                            c. 1818-27 also have metal material, almost certainly gold and
                            occasionally silver (see table 2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">37</ref>
                            Such works include one copy each of <hi rend="i">America, Europe,
                                Jerusalem, The Book of Thel</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The First Book of
                                Urizen</hi>, two copies of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                                Hell</hi> and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,
                            three copies of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and six (or possibly seven)
                            copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi> The
                            metals appear to have been applied quite distinctively on a number of
                            works. On <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> copy I, which Blake appears to have
                            produced for the writer, painter, and poisoner Thomas Griffiths
                            Wainewright, and <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> copy G, the application of
                            gold is obvious.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">38</ref> In <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> copy I, thick shell gold has been applied (perhaps
                            smeared) in places almost indiscriminately. However, in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
copy W, unsold at Blake’s death and characterized
                            by Catherine as Blake’s own copy, grains of shell gold have been
                            applied in what Andrew Lincoln describes as “light granular
                            washes” on all fifty-four plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n39" type="note">39</ref> Such finishing is often only perceptible in reflected
                            natural sunlight and has yet to be captured fully in reproduction. 
<note id="n36">36. See B #480.</note>
	<note id="n37">37. Some are works probably printed at 13 Hercules
                                Buildings, Lambeth, three decades earlier (for example, 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> copy H, printed 1790/93; <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
                                copies R and N, printed 1795), or at 17 South Molton Street (for
                                example, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> copies B, C, and D; <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>
copy O; <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> copy G; <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> copies N and O). Such works may have been
hand
                                colored and finished at a later date. Essick and Viscomi suggest
                                that “the use of liquified gold in the colouring of 
[<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>] copy D may have stimulated Blake’s
                                return to copy C to add both gold and silver highlights” 
(<hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi> Milton a Poem 41 n 19). However,
                                there is evidence that metal-based paint was applied posthumously on
                                the leaves of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy K (Viscomi 299-302).
                                Townsend has observed that the term “liquified gold”
                                used by several Blake scholars is potentially misleading; liquified
                                gold would cool and set to metal at room temperature (email, 5 Mar.
                                2005). The metals appear to have been applied to Blake’s
                                illuminated books in the form of shell gold. However, Blake
                                occasionally used crushed gold leaf (for example, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
copy D, where gold leaf has been crushed into the
                                color-printed surface of areas of the title page and pls. 13, 18,
                                32, and 37; see <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of the Gifts of Lessing J.
                                    Rosenwald</hi>, no. 1810; Phillips 108). Between c. 1811 and
                                1812 and between c. 1818 and 1827 Blake finished twenty-two copies
                                of his illuminated books in gold and/or other metals (see table 2).
                                At least two copies were sold posthumously. Eight identified
                                customers purchased fifteen copies, and four of these customers
                                purchased more than one: John Linnell (four), Thomas Griffiths
                                Wainewright (three), James Vine (two), and Henry Crabb Robinson
                                (two). Often copies were finished in the same style for the same
                                customer. For example, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> copy D and 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> copy O were similarly colored and finished in
                                gold for Vine, and <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy O and 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy K for Linnell. Perhaps Blake offered Vine,
                                Linnell, and other customers the option of gold finishing when
                                discussing the commission. Interestingly, the earliest buyer of an
                                illuminated book featuring gold we can identify with some
                                confidence, John, second Baron Dimsdale (probable purchaser of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy R/Y, c. 1811), appears to have had
                                antiquarian interests; see John Leigh Corfield, “Oldfield,
                                Henry George (fl. c. 1785-1805),” <hi rend="i">Oxford
                                    Dictionary of National Biography</hi> [hereafter 
<hi rend="i">ODNB</hi>].</note>
	<note id="n38">38. <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy U, apparently sold
                                before Feb. 1822 to the barrister and Shakespeare scholar James
                                Boswell, Jr. (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 383n7), appears to feature a
                                similar amount of gold. According to Margaret Sherry Rich, reference
                                library archivist, Rare Books and Special Collections, Princeton
                                University Library, copy U “is lavishly decorated in gold. .
                                . . The gold is easily visible, thus I would say thickly
                                applied” (email, 22 Nov. 2004).</note>
	<note id="n39">39. Lincoln 22.</note></p>
            <p>Blake even utilized gold on the unfinished second title page of the
                            Genesis manuscript (c. 1826-27). This suggests either that the potential
                            supply was plentiful enough for use on an unfinished manuscript or that
                            he had already decided that this page was to be part of the final work.
                            In either case, Blake appears to be using gold not merely as a finishing
                            touch, but as an integral element in at least one work with no
                            prospective buyer. This also reinforces the argument that a limited
                            amount of metal leaf was freely available to Blake during this
                                period.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">40</ref>
	<note id="n40">40. In response to my inquiry, Robert Essick observed:
                                “I very much doubt that Blake would start the Genesis MS
                                project late in his life without a specific commission, very
                                probably from Linnell. As with the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and Dante
                                projects, payment from Linnell was not ‘on completion’
                                but throughout the project, with some up-front money for basic
                                costs. Thus, Linnell may have provided enough up-front funds to pay
                                for the gold—or any other needed supplies; he may even have
                                specified the use of gold. I can’t recall any payments for
                                the Genesis MS in the Linnell accounts [there are none], but I
                                don’t think that absolutely rules out Linnell’s
                                financial involvement” (email, 30 July 2004). However, Essick
                                also noted that “the use of gold in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E does
indicate that Blake was capable of
                                using that material in an ‘on spec’
                                project—that is, one for which he had no specific patron or
                                customer prior to completion.”</note></p>
            <p>However, the work on which Blake used metal material with the most
                            ingenuity and variety was <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E: he applied
                            shell gold to fifteen of the one hundred plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref> A careful examination of the first two plates
                            under magnification suggests that in some areas he applied shell gold
                            using a pen as if it were ink.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n42" type="note">42</ref>
                            Although in places the application seems as 
<pb id="p42-90" n="90"/>
                            clumsy and as indiscriminate as in plates of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>
                            copy I,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref>
on other plates gold
                            material is applied with dazzlingly innovative care.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">44</ref> In addition, it is evident that Blake utilized
                            at least four distinct shades of metal leaf in this work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">45</ref>
	<note id="n41">41. Pls. 1, 2, 14, 23, 25, 47, 59, 63, 75, 76, 81, 84,
                                94, 97, 100.</note>
	<note id="n42">42. See, for example, the ruled gold lines radiating from
                                the lamp in pl. 1, of the same width as the pen marks Blake uses to
                                highlight the plate, and the title written partly in gold (pl. 2)
                                (observed under magnification, Department of Prints and Drawings,
                                Yale Center for British Art, 11-12 Apr. 2006).</note>
	<note id="n43">43. See, for example, pls. 1, 23.</note>
	<note id="n44">44. See the profusion of carefully placed highlights in
                                the hair of the recumbent figure at the bottom of pl. 2. On the same
                                figure the middle section of her right wing features parallel pen
                                marks in gold which echo the effects of the line engraving from the
                                etched copperplate. See also pl. 47 where, in the space between the
                                right-hand figure’s left hand and head, Blake has gone over a
                                larger patch of lighter gold with a blue watercolor wash, producing
                                a silvery-blue effect. This is the only instance I have discovered
                                of Blake’s painting over gold material in an illuminated
                                book.</note>
	<note id="n45">45. These are gold leaf, the metal color used most
                                frequently (see plates listed in note 41). Paley suggests that Blake
                                uses gold and silver in this work (<hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi>
                                Jerusalem 15), but Blake appears to use a variety of colored metals.
                                In some plates a distinctly lighter gold (in some cases perhaps a
                                gold-silver alloy) is utilized (pls. 23, 25, 47, 59, 97). He also
                                uses silver (pls. 23, 75, and perhaps 97) and occasionally a reddish
                                gold (pls. 25, 59). In pl. 25 three small red-tinged specks,
                                flame-like in shape, have been applied just above the right-hand
                                figure’s pubic region. These specks appear to echo the
                                vegetal-looking lines in the background revealed in the space
                                between her waist and the back of her upper left arm.</note></p>
            <p>Beyond <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E and possibly the Genesis
                            manuscript there may have been other “on spec” projects
                            with gold-based paint. As noted, Blake’s tempera <hi rend="i">The
                                Last Judgment</hi> featuring gold was still in his widow’s
                            possession after August 1827. This is particularly significant if, as
                            Smith suggests, Blake intended to show the work at the Royal Academy
                            exhibition in May 1828, after not exhibiting at Somerset House for
                            almost two decades. At his death Blake also left <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
                            copy W finished in gold with no customer. After his death Palmer may
                            even have purchased from Catherine or from Frederick Tatham three works
                            featuring metal material: <hi rend="i">Pitt, The Bard</hi>, and the
                            “experiment Picture” <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His
                                Legions.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">46</ref> Each of these
                            works has metal-based paint, some of which may have been added as late
                            as the 1820s. <note id="n46">46. Between c. 1831 and 1863 the Cumbrian
                                barrister, landowner, and collector George Blamire (1788-1863)
                                purchased <hi rend="i">The Ancient of Days</hi> copy F from Tatham,
                                who had acquired the work from Blake just before the latter’s
                                death (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 109). In addition to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
copy E, Blamire also owned two other works by
                                Blake which feature metal material, the color print <hi rend="i">Naomi
Entreating Ruth and Orpah</hi> and the tempera <hi rend="i">The Virgin and Child</hi>, the latter acquired
after
                                Blake’s death, almost certainly via Catherine or Tatham (see
                                B #299, 674). Tatham appears to have acquired another work featuring
                                gold, <hi rend="i">The First Temptation</hi>, from Catherine on her
                                death in Oct. 1831 (B #546).</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2. Blake and Contemporary Gilding Techniques</hi>
                <ref target="n47" type="note">47</ref>
                <note id="n47">47. Much of this section draws upon the most reliable
                                    late-twentieth-century account of traditional gilding methods,
                                    Mason and Gregory’s <hi rend="i">Of Gilding.</hi></note>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In his study of Blake’s techniques, Raymond Lister suggests that
                            to apply gold to his works Blake would have needed to be a reasonably
                            proficient gilder.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">48</ref> However, in
                            most cases, Blake’s metal-based material appears to have been
                            applied as small pieces of leaf or as shell gold, and not as full sheets
                            of metal leaf as used by a trained carver and gilder of wooden furniture
                            or picture frames. Donnan’s examination of a number of works
                            suggests that Blake often used metal-based paints in an idiosyncratic
                            manner hardly resembling the methods of a professional gilder.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">49</ref> According to Donnan, he could have
                            applied scraps of metal leaf to a work’s surface with a moistened
                            brush, or even by hand, while the paint was still tacky. <note id="n48">48. Lister
56.</note>
	<note id="n49">49. Donnan examined <hi rend="i">Evening</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Overthrow of Apollo</hi> in
1999, while Mellon
                                fellow in advanced paper conservation, National Gallery of Art,
                                Washington. Blake’s experimentation is also evident in his
                                unorthodox use of materials when color printing his illuminated
                                books in the 1790s (see Phillips chapter 5: “Colour-Printing
                                    <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>”; Essick and
                                Viscomi, “An Inquiry” part 3: “Blake’s
                                Color Printing Methods”).</note></p>
            <p>Nevertheless, according to recent research conducted at the Tate, Blake
                            does appear to have emulated traditional gilding practices in several
                            works. Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Ghost of a Flea, Pitt, The
                            Bard</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Body of Abel</hi> suggests that Blake,
                            like a carver and gilder, gilded onto a preparatory surface of bole (or
                            oil size) over gesso.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50"
type="note">50</ref> He also
                            appears to have used a technique of both gilders and watercolor
                            painters, applying an underlayer of pigment such as vermilion before the
                            metal material in shell or leaf form in order to affect the appearance
                            of the gold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">51</ref> An examination of
                            other works indicates that Blake also occasionally used two recognizable
                            gilding techniques <hi rend="i">after</hi> he had applied gold leaf.
                                <note id="n50">50. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 124. See also
                                energy-dispersive X-ray analysis (EDX) notes by Ormsby for <hi rend="i">The
Bard</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Body of Abel</hi>,
                                2002, Tate Conservation Department records.</note>
	<note id="n51">51. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 124; Mason and Gregory.
                                Applying a vermilion underlayer would give the gold a reddish
                                appearance.</note></p>
            <p>The first is glazing, as described above in Smith’s account of <hi rend="i">The Last
Judgment.</hi> Ormsby, Singer, and Dean suggest
                            that the identification of a gold-silver alloy in <hi rend="i">The
                                Bard</hi> and <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions</hi>
                            “renders Smith’s rejection of Blake’s use of silver
                            leaf in . . . <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi> . . . a little less
                                certain.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">52</ref> However,
                            several factors suggest that Smith was correct in asserting that
                            “there was no silver used.” First, Catherine Blake, who
                            informed Smith that what he had mistaken for silver was actually gold,
                            should be considered a reliable source. She had lived and worked closely
                            with Blake for almost half a century, taking responsibility for printing
                            from their rolling press and preparing colors as well as coloring and
                            finishing a number of copies of the illuminated books. As Tatham, who
                            knew her well, especially during the last five years of her life,
                            describes in his “Life of Blake” (c. 1832): 
<q> She even
                                laboured upon his Works[,] those parts of them where powers of
                                Drawing &amp; form were not necessary, which 
<pb id="p42-91" n="91"/>
from her
excellent Idea of Colouring, was of no small use in the
                                completion of his labourious designs. This she did to a much greater
                                extent than is usually credited.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n53" type="note">53</ref>
	<note id="n52">52. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 125; see also Lister
                                    56.</note>
	<note id="n53">
                                   53. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 690. See also Smith,
                                            <hi rend="i">Nollekens and His Times</hi> (1828), vol.
                                        2, quoted in <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 609; Allan Cunningham,
                                            <hi rend="i">The Lives of the Most Eminent British
                                            Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi>, 2nd ed.
                                        (1830), vol. 2, quoted in <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 633.
                                        Hayley, in a letter to Lady Hesketh dated 15 July 1802,
                                        writes that Catherine “draws, . . . engraves, &amp;
                                        sings delightfully” (quoted in <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 140). Blake
alludes to Catherine’s press
                                        work in a letter to Hayley of 26 Nov. 1800, “my
                                        wife’s illness not being quite gone off, she has not
                                        printed any more since you went to London. . . . We mean to
                                        begin printing again tomorrow” (E 714). For
                                        references to Catherine’s printing from a rolling
                                        press before and after her husband’s death, see 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 131, 151, 482, 610fn, 676.
                                    <p>Catherine had technical knowledge of the materials used by
                                        her husband (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 294, 321fn, 622).
                                        The pigment “Blake’s white” is
                                        discussed by Ormsby, Townsend, Singer, and Dean, who cite
                                        Palmer’s reference in a letter to Henry Wentworth
                                        Acland of 29 Oct. 1866 (“State of Knowledge”
                                        42 and n25). Almost forty years earlier, a year after
                                        Blake’s death and during Catherine’s lifetime,
                                        Palmer refers to the same pigment in a letter to Richmond as
                                        “Mrs Blake’s white” (Ormsby, Singer,
                                        and Dean 118 and n32). This suggests that Catherine had
                                        learned how to manufacture this pigment successfully and
                                        that, in 1828, the recipe was considered her own. In Aug.
                                        1829 she advised Lord Egremont regarding the varnishing of
                                        Blake’s late watercolor drawing <hi rend="i">The
                                            Characters of Spenser’s</hi> Faerie Queene, which
                                        he had recently purchased from her (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 498).
Gilchrist claims that Catherine also
                                        designed and executed her own drawings (A. Gilchrist
                                        315-16). She appears to have produced at least two paintings
                                        of her own: the tempera <hi rend="i">Agnes</hi> dated c.
                                        1800 (B #C1) and the watercolor <hi rend="i">Head
                                            “Taken from Something She Saw in the
                                            Fire”</hi> dated c. 1830 (B #C2). Gilchrist
                                        refers to a further (untraced) painting by Catherine owned
                                        by Butts (A. Gilchrist 315-16).</p></note></q>
Therefore it is quite
possible that Catherine assisted her husband
                            in applying metal leaf, powder, and shell gold and silver before glazing
                            over the gilded area as Smith describes. Second, there is evidence that
                            Blake used this technique elsewhere. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean observe
                            that in <hi rend="i">The Ghost of a Flea</hi> Blake “glazed the
                            metal leaf with both warm and cool paints in order to alter their
                                tone.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">54</ref> He also appears
                            to have glazed several areas of works from the period 1805-09 that
                            feature gold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">55</ref>
	<note id="n54">54. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 129.</note>
	<note id="n55">55. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 123-27. Blake also glazed
                                metal on at least one illuminated book: <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                                copy E, pl. 47 (see note 44).</note></p>
            <p>Carvers and gilders would have utilized a similar process. Robert Dossie,
                            in his craftsman’s manual <hi rend="i">The Handmaid to the
                                Arts</hi> (1764), describes how yellow lacquer “when spread
                            on silver, gives it a colour greatly similar to that of
                                gold.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">56</ref> However, if
                            Smith was correct in his observation of glazing on the surface of <hi rend="i">The
Last Judgment</hi>, here Blake reversed the process by
                            glazing the metal material with a cool color in order to produce the
                            appearance of silver. He may have learned through reading <hi rend="i">The
Handmaid to the Arts</hi> or through conversations with a
                            carver and gilder that exposed silver leaf tarnishes rapidly.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">57</ref> Glazing gold leaf with a cool
                            color would have been a failsafe, if relatively costly, method of
                            producing the appearance of silver without the risk of tarnishing.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">58</ref>
	<note id="n56">56. Dossie 1:465.</note>
	<note id="n57">57. Dossie 1:471.</note>
	<note id="n58">58. Blake appears to have used silver-based paint (shell
                                silver) in the finishing of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> copy G, 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> copy C, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                                copy E. Michael Gregory believes that despite the unpopularity of
                                silver among gilders in the early nineteenth century (for the reason
                                just cited), it would not have been difficult for Blake to acquire
                                (telephone conversation, 1 Oct. 2002).</note></p>
            <p>The second gilding technique, probably used by Blake in at least two
                            works, is burnishing, in which gold leaf, after drying upon a support
                            surface for twenty-four hours, was “polished with the
                            dog’s tooth, or with the burnishers of agate or flint
                                ....”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">59</ref> Donnan has
                            suggested that areas of gold leaf in <hi rend="i">The Ghost of a
                                Flea</hi>, such as the larger falling star to the left of the
                            ghost’s right knee, could be the result of burnishing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">60</ref> Ormsby, Singer, and Dean observe
                            that the appearance of an area of gold leaf on <hi rend="i">Pitt</hi>
                            resembles “surface burnishing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n61" type="note">61</ref> It is unclear whether this effect was added at
                            the time the work was painted (1805?) or considerably later, perhaps as
                            one of the “many finishing touches” that Blake lavished on
                            works such as <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi> during his last
                                years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">62</ref>
	<note id="n59">59. Dossie 1:437, quoted in Mason and Gregory.</note>
	<note id="n60">60. Telephone conversation, 22 Oct. 2002.</note>
	<note id="n61">61. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 124, fig. 97.</note>
	<note id="n62">62. A. Gilchrist 349.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">3. A Possible Source of Blake’s Metal Leaf, c.
                                    1821-27</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ormsby, Townsend, Singer, and Dean state that “two features that
                            most of [Blake’s] pigments have in common are cheapness and
                            constant availability.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">63</ref>
                            However, Viscomi and Paley have separately observed that his use of gold
                            leaf on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E “may have been a
                            considerable expense.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">64</ref>
                            Viscomi suggests that this expense was “possibly underwritten by
                            the commissions of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy V by [James] Vine and
                                <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy O and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy K
                            by Linnell.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">65</ref> Indeed, the
                            commissions Blake received from 1821 onwards suggest that he may have
                            been able to afford occasionally to purchase books of metal leaf from a
                            local gold beater or artists’ colorman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n66" type="note">66</ref> However, it is unlikely that he would have
                            required such large amounts of metal leaf. Donnan has observed that on
                            the temperas she examined Blake used only scraps of metal leaf.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">67</ref> Similarly, in many later copies of
                            the illuminated books 
<pb id="p42-92" n="92"/>
where shell gold or
                            silver and occasionally crushed gold or silver leaf or gold or silver
                            powder were applied, only a small quantity of gold or silver leaf must
                            have been used at any one time. Blake, therefore, using limited amounts
                            of material over a period of perhaps six years, is unlikely to have
                            needed to outlay a large amount of money. Nevertheless, he appears to
                            have had access to a steady, if modest, supply of gold and silver leaf
                            during the 1820s, which he may have acquired from a neighboring
                            craftsman. <note id="n63">63. “Blake’s Use” 137.
                                The sole exception appears to be natural ultramarine (Cahaner
                                McManus and Townsend, “Watercolour Methods”
                                69).</note>
	<note id="n64">64. Viscomi 356; see also Paley, <hi rend="i">William
                                    Blake:</hi> Jerusalem 15.</note>
	<note id="n65">65. Viscomi 356. However, according to Anna Lou Ashby,
                                Andrew W. Mellon curator of printed books at the Morgan Library, 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> V does not feature gold (email, 3 Dec.
                                2004); see also <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 386.</note>
	<note id="n66">66. Using the “Blake Accounts” section of
                                    <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) (757-812) as a guide, I calculated
                                Blake’s finances during this period. Surviving records of his
                                income for 1821 amount to £5.19.0. The following year (with a
                                Royal Academy award and possible support from Thomas Lawrence) the
                                figure rises to £40. In 1823, the year of Linnell’s
                                commencement of payments for <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, £42. For
                                the final years of his life the figures are as follows: 1824:
                                £69.12.9; 1825: £57.8.0; 1826: £76.18.3; 1827 (until
                                Blake’s death, 12 Aug.): £58.16.0.</note>
	<note id="n67">67. Telephone conversation, 22 Oct. 2002.</note></p>
            <p>When gilding picture frames and other furniture, carvers and gilders
                            often needed to cut sheets of leaf to size. Perhaps, as Michael
                            Gregory—director of the last surviving traditional gilding firm
                            in London, Arnold Wiggins and Sons—has suggested, a neighboring
                            bookbinder or gilder may have agreed to sell Blake his offcuts, if not
                            the odd sheet, of metal leaf at a modest price.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">68</ref>
	<note id="n68">68. Telephone conversation, 1 Oct. 2002.</note></p>
            <p>Little evidence survives of the identity of those tradesmen who supplied
                            Blake’s materials. The branded stamp on the verso of the mahogany
                            support of Blake’s late tempera, <hi rend="i">The Virgin and
                                Child</hi> (<hi rend="i">The Black Madonna</hi>) (1825?), discussed
                            in <hi rend="i">The Painter at Work</hi>, bears the name of Robert Davy
                            of Wardour Street and Newman Street, artists’ colorman, millboard
                            manufacturer, and restorer of pictures. Davy is also listed in
                            contemporary London trade directories as a carver and gilder and so
                            could have supplied Blake with gold and other metal leaf.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">69</ref>
	<note id="n69">69. Ormsby, Singer, and Dean 131. Davy makes his first
                                appearance in trade directories as “Robert Davy, Carver and
                                gilder, 16 Wardour St, Soho” in <hi rend="i">Holden’s
                                    Triennial Directory</hi> 1805-06-07, including the year 1808
                                (1808) (n. pag.). He is “restorer of pictures” at 16
                                Wardour Street, Oxford Street, in <hi rend="i">Robson’s
                                    Directory</hi> 1819 (139); “Carver &amp; gilder, 16
                                Wardour St. [Soho]” in <hi rend="i">Robson’s</hi> 1820
                                (155). <hi rend="i">Kent’s Directory</hi> 1822 (25) and 1824
                                (95) give the address as “16 Wardour St. &amp; 83 Newman
                                St.” <hi rend="i">Robson’s</hi> 1823 (n. pag.) lists
                                him as carver and gilder at 83 Newman Street. In <hi rend="i">Pigot
                                    and Co.’s Directory</hi> 1823-24 Davy is given at 83
                                Newman Street under “colourman” (101) and
                                “carver and gilder” (88). He is also listed as
                                “Carver, gilder and panel preparer, 83 Newman Street, Oxford
                                Street,” <hi rend="i">Underhill Triennial</hi> 1822-23-24 (n.
                                pag.); “carver [same address],” <hi rend="i">Pigot’s</hi> 1826-27;
“Millboard Manufacturer, 83
                                Newman St.,” <hi rend="i">Kent’s</hi> 1827 and 1828
                                and <hi rend="i">Robson’s</hi> 1828 (n. pag.). In 
<hi rend="i">Pigot’s</hi> for 1827 (113) Davy is referred to
                                as “Carver and gilder, artist’s colourman and picture
                                repairer,” whilst in the same directory for 1828-29 he
                                returns to merely “Carver and gilder”
                            (113).</note></p>
            <p>Other sources suggest themselves. During Blake’s apprenticeship,
                            Basire must have provided the gold used in the Westminster Abbey
                            commissions for Ayloffe and Gough. During the 1790s patrons such as
                            Butts probably paid for the material on the few paintings which feature
                            gold. The proposed new dating of the three temperas <hi rend="i">Evening,
Winter</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Olney Bridge</hi> suggests
                            that they were executed around the time of Johnson’s visit to
                            Felpham (1802), when Blake painted his miniature. Hayley is likely to
                            have had leaf to hand, or would have had the funds to procure it. On his
                            return to London in autumn 1803 and while assisting Hayley with his
                            biography of George Romney, Blake was in regular contact with
                            Romney’s framer and picture dealer, the carver and gilder William
                            Saunders of 10 Great Castle Street.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n70" type="note">70</ref> As mentioned above, about 1809 Blake would probably have
                            followed the common practice of using gold in his miniatures to enhance
                            their color and finish; if so, perhaps Saunders supplied him with gold
                            leaf. Around the time of Blake’s move to South Molton Street, the
                            carver and gilder William Sloper conducted business virtually opposite,
                            at no. 59.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">71</ref> Between 1812 and 1821,
                            William Goslett ran a carver and gilder’s workshop at 32 South
                            Molton Street, an establishment Blake would regularly have passed when
                            walking to and from nearby Oxford Street.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n72" type="note">72</ref> From 1818, Blake is likely to have been on familiar terms
                            with another carver and gilder, John Linnell’s father James, who
                            framed Blake’s 1821 tempera <hi rend="i">The Sea of Time and
                                Space</hi> in a plain gilt frame.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n73" type="note">73</ref> He also appears to have taken a marginal role in the
                            printing and marketing of Blake’s twenty-one <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the
Book of Job.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">74</ref> John Linnell
commissioned several works featuring gold
                            material: <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy O, <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                            copy K, <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> copy H, and <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
                            copy R.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">75</ref>
James, via his son, may
                            have been a source for the gold material used to decorate them.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">76</ref>
	<note id="n70">70. See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 267; <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 178 and fn; Blake’s
letters to Hayley
                                of 26 Oct. and 13 Dec. 1803 (E 737, 739). Saunders is also included
                                in trade directories of the period: see the 1805-06-07 (1805) and
                                1805-06-07, including the year 1808 (1808) editions of <hi rend="i">Holden’s
Triennial Directory</hi> (n. pag.) and <hi rend="i">Johnstone’s London Commercial Guide and Street
                                    Directory</hi> for 1817 (102). Great Castle Street was six
                                blocks east of Blake’s new residence in South Molton Street
                                along Oxford Street. Gregory has described the picture-framing
                                community in London in the early nineteenth century as a small
                                fraternity who were all likely to have known one another (telephone
                                conversation, 1 Oct. 2002).</note>
	<note id="n71">71. There are entries for William Sloper, carver and
                                gilder, conducting business at 59 South Molton Street in 
<hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory</hi> for 1799 (665)
                                and 1802-03-04 (1802) (n. pag.). See also composite rate books for
                                St. George’s, Hanover Square, Brook Street Ward, 28 Mar. 1795
                                and 28 Mar. 1803 (City of Westminster Archive Centre [hereafter
                                COWAC] C 588 and C 596).</note>
	<note id="n72">72. There is an entry for Goslett conducting business at
                                32 South Molton Street in <hi rend="i">Johnstone’s London
                                    Commercial Guide and Street Directory</hi> for 1817 (459). See
                                also composite rate book entries for St. George’s, Hanover
                                Square, Brook Street Ward, 30 Mar. 1809 and 31 Mar. 1821 (COWAC C
                                603 and C 617).</note>
	<note id="n73">73. Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 197. The
                                frame in which this work was discovered in 1949, along with its
                                original packing (a copy of the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> dated Jan.
                                1820), is probably original. See Whitehead, “The Arlington
                                Court Picture.” Linnell may have consulted Blake as to how to
                                frame this work. James Linnell, framemaker, carver and gilder,
                                printseller and picture dealer, resided and worked at 2 Streatham
                                Street, Bloomsbury (see <hi rend="i">Pigot and Co.’s
                                    Directory</hi> 1823-24 [88]). John was apprenticed to his father
                                as carver and gilder in 1806, presumably as security in the event of
                                his failure as an artist; see David Linnell 13-14, 36, 132.</note>
	<note id="n74">74. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 433, 775.</note>
	<note id="n75">75. See <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 105, 300, 420.</note>
	<note id="n76">76. However, John Linnell is unlikely to have provided
                                gold for projects in which he had no financial interest. If he had
                                been involved, he would likely have recorded his supplying Blake in
                                his account book. As we shall see, from c. 1821 onwards there was a
                                constant supply of metal material potentially available to
                                Blake.</note></p>
            <p>Blake may have known one more gilder at South Molton Street. In April
                            1815 George Cumberland, Jr., wrote to his father of a visit to
                            Blake’s rooms during which Blake “shewed his 
<pb id="p42-93" n="93"/>
large
drawing in Water Colors of the last
                            Judgement[;] he has been labouring at it till it is nearly as black as
                            your Hat—the only lights are those of a <hi rend="i">Hellish
                                Purple.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">77</ref> Gilchrist
                            records that on another occasion “Blake, on looking up one day at
                            this fresco, which hung in his front room, candidly exclaimed, as one
                            who was present tells me: ‘I spoiled that—made it darker;
                            it was much finer, but a Frenchwoman here (a fellow lodger)
                            didn’t like it.”’ He adds that Blake was
                            “ill-advised, indeed, to alter <hi rend="i">colour</hi> at a
                            fellow lodger and Frenchwoman’s suggestion!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">78</ref> New evidence suggests that this
                            maligned fellow lodger was Eleanor Martin, née Larché, the
                            wife of Blake’s second landlord at 17 South Molton Street, Mark
                                Martin.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79"
type="note">79</ref> One of the witnesses
                            at their wedding in 1806 was Peter Larché, almost certainly the
                            Peter Larché who ran a gilder’s shop at Rathbone Place
                            during this period. Any of these five gilders might have supplied Blake
                            with scraps or the odd metal leaf at one time or another, if not a whole
                            book of gold or silver leaf. However, it appears that during the last
                            seven years of his life, Blake had a potential supplier even closer to
                            home. <note id="n77">77. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 320; see also
                                Tatham’s annotation to a tracing of a drawing of the Last
                                Judgment (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 320fn).</note>
	<note id="n78">78. A. Gilchrist 350.</note>
	<note id="n79">79. Whitehead, “New Discoveries”
                                1:95.</note></p>
            <p>In <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, Geoffrey Keynes suggests that when
                            the Blakes moved to the first floor of 3 Fountain Court, the landlord
                            Henry Banes, Catherine Blake’s sister’s husband, occupied
                            the remaining four stories of living space.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">80</ref> However, there is evidence of at least one other lodger,
                            possibly as early as 1821, and certainly between 1823 and 1827. In his
                            biography of his father, the artist and “Ancient” Edward
                            Calvert, Samuel Calvert records an incident that occurred while his
                            father was visiting Blake in Fountain Court: 
<q> On one occasion, as my
                                father has told the story, there came lumbering up the stairs with
                                heavy tread an uncouth visitor who bumped at the door. Blake,
                                somewhat disturbed, rose to open it, but with no ungentlemanly
                                impatience, for he never knew in what shape, or under what
                                circumstances his angels might appear. It was, however, “the
                                man with the coals,” who, humped up with sack, gigantic and
                                grimy, muttered out, “Are these ’ere coals for
                                you?” The gentle and commiserating voice of Blake replied,
                                “I believe not, my good man, but I’ll enquire,”
                                and, as my father regretfully said: “they were <hi rend="i">not</hi> poor
Blake’s coals—they were for the
                                lodger on the floor above.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n81" type="note">81</ref>
	<note id="n81">81. [Samuel Calvert,] <hi rend="i">A Memoir of Edward
                                        Calvert Artist</hi> (London, 1893) 21-22, quoted in 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 439. A condensed version is in Gilchrist
                                    (A. Gilchrist 308). Bentley suggests that the incident could
                                    have occurred in “the winter of 1826” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
438).</note></q>
	<note id="n80">80. Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>
                            176.</note></p>
            <p>The “lodger on the floor above” was a carver and gilder
                            named John George Lohr. He is first recorded as ratepayer of nearby 1
                            Fountain Court, Strand, in 1803,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n82" type="note">82</ref>
                            and between 1805 and 1819 he is listed as a carver and gilder conducting
                            business at this address in several London trade directories.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">83</ref> Lohr remained ratepayer at 1
                            Fountain Court until 1829, which suggests that he continued to live
                            there with his wife Letitia and their seven children.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">84</ref> However, sometime between 1819 and 1823 he
                            moved his workshop two doors south.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n85" type="note">85</ref>
	<note id="n82">
                                82. In several rate books of the period (for example,
                                    entry for Herbert’s Passage, Parish of St. Clement Danes
                                    poor rate ledger, 3 Jan. 1822, COWAC B 244) this building is
                                    listed as part of nearby Herbert’s Passage. In fact the
                                    house stood on the southwestern corner of Fountain Court and
                                    Herbert’s Passage; see Richard Horwood, <hi rend="i">The
                                        A to Z of Regency London</hi>, London Topographical Society
                                    publication no. 131 (London: London Topographical Society, 1985)
                                    13 Cd.
                                <p>Both Banes and Lohr are first recorded as ratepayers for
                                    properties in Fountain Court for the spring 1803 poor rate
                                    collection for Savoy Ward, Parish of St. Clement Danes (COWAC B
                                    224). “Henry Baines” replaces the previous
                                    ratepayer for no. 3, “Mary Wood,” widow of John
                                    Wood, who was last recorded as ratepayer in 1784 (COWAC B 203).
                                    “Lohr” replaces “Jas. Carstairs” for
                                    no. 1. Banes’s and Lohr’s added names are just
                                    visible in the 1803 St. Clement Danes rate book entries for
                                    Fountain Court reproduced in Whitehead, “‘<hi rend="i">I also beg Mr
Blakes
                                    acceptance</hi>’” 81 (illus. 2).</p></note>
	<note id="n83">83. See <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial
                                    Directory</hi> 1805-06-07 (1805) (n. pag.); <hi rend="i">Holden’s</hi>
1805-06-07, including the year 1808 (1808)
                                (n. pag.); <hi rend="i">Johnstone’s London Commercial Guide
                                    and Street Directory</hi> 1817 (210); <hi rend="i">Robson’s
Directory</hi> 1819 (322).</note>
	<note id="n84">
                                84. Lohr may have been a first or second-generation
                                    immigrant from the Alsace region of northeastern France. The
                                    only John George Lohr in the records of Familysearch 
(<hi rend="i">International Genealogical Index</hi>) of the right
                                    age to have been Banes’s neighbor in 1803 is a Johann
                                    Georg Lohr, baptized 5 Mar. 1776, Dettwiller, Bas Rhin, France.
                                    The contemporary English taste for gilding had been influenced
                                    by French fashions of the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.
                                    Lohr (or perhaps his father) may therefore have arrived in
                                    London attracted by this potentially lucrative market.
                                <p>Lohr married Letitia Lewis on 18 Jan. 1801 at St. Clement Danes
                                    Church, Strand (St. Clement Danes [SCD] marriage register, vol.
                                    37, COWAC) (see illus. 3). Their first child, Letitia, was
                                    baptized 14 Nov. 1802, St. Martin-in-the-Fields (St.
                                    Martin-in-the-Fields [SMIF] baptismal register, vol. 18, COWAC).
                                    There followed Rosetta Rebecka, baptized 4 Sept. 1808 (SCD
                                    baptismal register, vol. 14, COWAC); William Lewis, baptized 16
                                    Apr. 1810 (SMIF baptismal register, vol. 19, COWAC); Susanna
                                    Caroline, baptized 14 Mar. 1813 (SMIF baptismal register, vol.
                                    20, COWAC); Emma, baptized 17 Dec. 1815 (SCD baptismal register,
                                    vol. 22, COWAC); Hester Sophia, baptized 30 July 1818 (SCD
                                    baptismal register, vol. 22, COWAC); and John George, baptized
                                    10 Sept. 1820 (SCD baptismal register, vol. 23, COWAC). A search
                                    of the burial records for St. Clement Danes, St.
                                    Martin-in-the-Fields, and Bunhill Fields for 1801-27 reveals no
                                    evidence of burials of any member of the Lohr family. By the
                                    mid-1820s, therefore, the Lohrs were probably a family of nine.
                                    However, Letitia junior and perhaps Rosetta may have married
                                    and/or lived elsewhere by this date. Lohr’s wife Letitia
                                    (née Lewis) may have been related to John Ford Lewis, who
                                    appears to have run a tailor’s shop from 12 Fountain
                                    Court, directly opposite no. 3, during this period (Whitehead,
                                    “New Discoveries” 1:207). John Ford Lewis’s
                                    wife Lucy was the daughter of the landlord of the Coalhole
                                    Tavern (16 Fountain Court), William John Rhodes (“New
                                    Discoveries” 1:208). This may explain the signature of
                                    “W. Rhodes” as witness on the Lohrs’ entry
                                    in the marriage register.</p></note>
	<note id="n85">85. This may have been due to his growing family, or
                                perhaps the need to expand a prospering business. There is evidence
                                that another household lived at no. 1, presumably lodgers of the
                                Lohrs. William Burbidge, clerk in the Excise Office, Old Broad
                                Street, his wife Rachel, and their sons Robert Josiah and James
                                William lodged there between 1821 and 1824 (see entries for 7 Jan.
                                1821 and 29 Dec. 1824, SCD baptismal register, vol. 23, COWAC). Lohr
                                may therefore have moved his workshop to no. 3 in order to take in
                                lodgers in his own house.</note></p>
            <pb id="p42-94" n="94"/>
            <figure n="marriage.42.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="191">
              <figTranscr>
                No[.] } John George Lohr of this Parish Bach[elo]r. &amp;<lb/>
                Letitia Lewis of the same Parish Spins[te]r. were<lb/>
                Married in this Church by Banns<lb/>
                this Eighteenth Day of January in the Year One Thousand Eight Hundred<lb/>
                and One, By me George Lawrence Curate<lb/>
                This Marriage was solemnized between Us {<lb/>
                John George Lohr<lb/>
                Letitia Lewis X her Mark<lb/>
                in the Presence of {<lb/>
                M Cook<lb/>
                W Reader
              </figTranscr>
              <head>3. Entry for the marriage of John George Lohr and Letitia Lewis,
                                18 January 1801, St. Clement Danes marriage register, vol.
                                37.</head>
              <figDesc>Image by kind permission of the City of Westminster Archives
                                Centre.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>From 1823 until 1828, trade directories record the address of
                            Lohr’s workshop as 3 Fountain Court, William and Catherine
                            Blake’s last residence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86"
type="note">86</ref>
                            Between 1823 and 1827, living space at no. 3 was probably apportioned as
                            follows. Henry Banes and (until her death in March 1824) his wife Sarah
                            utilized the ground and basement floors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n87" type="note">87</ref> The location of the Blakes’ two-room flat on the
                            first floor is well documented.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n88" type="note">88</ref>
                            Lohr’s workshop, therefore, must have been located either in the
                            two rooms on the second floor, directly above the Blakes’ flat,
                            or in the garret rooms above.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89"
type="note">89</ref>
                            Although he and his family did not actually live on the upper floor,
                            Lohr, and probably at least one fellow carver and gilder or apprentice,
                            may have been employed in the workshop, as were other artisans of the
                            period, up to fourteen hours a day, six days a week.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90" type="note">90</ref> His younger children are likely to have played
                            either in the court between the family home and their father’s
                            workshop two doors down or in the communal yard at the back of the
                            terrace. Susanna, Emma, Hester, and John George Lohr, Jr., may therefore
                            have been among the group of “little children” at play
                            that Blake and a companion, probably Palmer, observed from a window and
                            of whom Blake said, “that is heaven.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n91" type="note">91</ref>
	<note id="n86">86. See <hi rend="i">Pigot and Co.’s
                                    Directory</hi> 1823-24 (1823) 88. In the section listing carvers
                                and gilders “Loho [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] Jno. Geo. 3
                                Fountain-ct, Stnd” is listed directly below “Linnell
                                Jas. 2 Streatham st. Blmsby.” Of course, Lohr may have moved
                                his workshop to no. 3 as early as 1819. See also <hi rend="i">Pigot’s</hi>
1826-27 (114) (cover illustration); <hi rend="i">Robson’s Directory</hi> 1828 (n. pag.). His
                                workshop appears to have remained at no. 3 for about eighteen months
                                after Catherine’s departure. In 1828 he is recorded as
                                ratepayer for both nos. 1 and 2 (see poor rate overseers’
                                accounts book, St. Clement Danes, Savoy Ward, 1828, COWAC B 126). In
                                1829, the year Henry Banes died and therefore ceased to be ratepayer
                                at no. 3, Lohr, by now probably in his fifties, was no longer
                                ratepayer for either nos. 1 or 2 (poor rate book for St. Clement
                                Danes, Savoy Ward, 1 Jan. 1829, COWAC B 249). In 1829 Lohr appears
                                to have moved his workshop from 3 to 2 Fountain Court 
(<hi rend="i">Robson’s</hi> 1829 [93]). According to the following
                                year’s edition, he again moved his studio, this time directly
                                opposite, to no. 13 (<hi rend="i">Robson’s</hi> 1830 [n.
                                pag.]). I have been unable to trace either Lohr or any member of his
                                family after this date. However, <hi rend="i">Robson’s</hi>
                                for 1826 (231) lists a “Lohr and son, Bombazine
                                Manufacturers” at nearby 1 Mitre Court, Fleet Street.
                                Lohr’s increasingly rapid movement within the court and then
                                disappearance from 1830 could suggest a decline in prosperity.
                                Perhaps the likely failure of his cottage industry reflected the new
                                economic pressures of competition from technological advances and a
                                shift in taste away from gilt furniture in the early 1830s. However,
                                by 1834 another carver and gilder was at no. 3: Edwin Robbins lived
                                and presumably worked here (or nearby) until 1837 (see 3 Aug. 1834
                                [which records Robbins and his family residing at no. 3] and 9 July
                                1837 [which records them at no. 2], SCD baptismal register, vols. 24
                                and 25, COWAC).</note>
	<note id="n87">87. For information concerning Henry Banes and Sarah
                                Banes, née Boucher, see Whitehead, “‘<hi rend="i">I also beg Mr Blakes
                                acceptance.</hi>’”</note>
	<note id="n88">88. Linnell, in his letter to the Quaker poet Bernard
                                Barton dated 3 Apr. 1830, describes Blake as having “occupied
                                the first floor” (quoted in <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 526).
                                John Varley also gives a specific reference to Blake’s last
                                address on his tracing of Blake’s visionary head of <hi rend="i">The
Egyptian Taskmaster Killed by Moses</hi> (B #696A;
                                Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 372fn).</note>
	<note id="n89">89. George Bloomfield, brother of the laboring-class poet
                                Robert, recalled that about 1781 he ran a shoemaker’s
                                business at “Mr. Simm’s, No. 7,
                                Pitcher’s-court, Bell-alley, Coleman-street” in a
                                garret “where we had two turn-up beds, and five of us worked
                                . . .” (Robert Bloomfield, preface, <hi rend="i">The Poems of
                                    Robert Bloomfield</hi>, 2 vols. [London: Robert Bloomfield,
                                Vernor, Hood and Sharpe, and Longman, Hurst, Rees and Orme, 1809]
                                1:vi).</note>
	<note id="n90">90. According to <hi rend="i">A General Description of
                                    All Trades</hi> (103), an apprentice gilder’s working
                                hours would be from six o’clock in the morning until eight
                                o’clock in the evening.</note>
	<note id="n91">91. A. Gilchrist 301. For references to Blake’s
                                kindness to and popularity with children, see also <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
382-83, 412, 415 and fn, 752.</note></p>
            <p>A gilder was employed to “cover [objects] entirely or partially
                            with a thin layer of gold . . . in the form of gold-leaf
                                ....”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92"
type="note">92</ref> However, Lohr is
                            listed in directories as a carver and gilder, a designation explained by
                            the contemporary demand for giltwood 
<pb id="p42-95" n="95"/>
<figure n="Laying.042.03.bonus" rend="file" width="600" height="399">
	<head>4. Laying the gold.</head>
	<figDesc>Image courtesy of Arnold Wiggins and Sons.</figDesc>
</figure> furniture. He would have carved and gilded furniture and
                            picture frames. From the late seventeenth century until the middle of
                            the nineteenth century, gilding was used to enhance carved furniture and
                            decoration in the houses of the wealthy. In his <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> (1807),
the dramatist Richard Cumberland recalls
                            visiting such a home: “Its magnificent owner had gilt and
                            furnished the apartments with a profusion of luxury.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93" type="note">93</ref> In an age still largely reliant
                            upon candlelight or oil lamps for domestic lighting, gilding could also
                            contribute to the illumination of a room. Few gilders of the period
                            would have been unable to carve. <note id="n92">92. <hi rend="i">Compact
                                    Oxford English Dictionary</hi>, 2 vols. (Oxford: Clarendon
                                Press, 1971) 1:1142.</note>
	<note id="n93">93. Richard Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> (1807),
                                quoted in the <hi rend="i">Compact Oxford English Dictionary</hi>
                                1:1142. In the mid-eighteenth century Campbell noted that
                                “gilders are generally Carvers . . . there is Employment but
                                for few Hands who do not understand Carving”
                            (108).</note></p>
            <p>Although gold and silver were expensive commodities, Lohr, prosperous
                            enough to pay the rates on one property and rent a floor in a
                            neighbor’s house, is likely to have been able to provide Blake
                            with scraps of gold leaf and other metal leaf at a price the poet-artist
                            could afford. He may have been happy to do so—he and Blake must
                            have been on familiar and probably friendly terms. Lohr and
                            Blake’s brother-in-law and landlord Henry Banes had been
                            neighbors for twenty years. In addition, from 1823 (and possibly
                            earlier) until Blake’s death in August 1827, Lohr, his employees,
                            and perhaps members of his family would have passed the two doors of the
                            Blakes’ first-floor apartment several times a day on their way to
                            and from the workshop above.</p>
            <p>A number of the tools and materials in Lohr’s workshop would have
                            been familiar to Blake. Lohr would have used size or bole as a base for
                            gilding. This was often mixed with red or yellow ochre to give a warm or
                            cool appearance before the application of gold leaf.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94" type="note">94</ref> Blake was familiar with these materials: he had
                            used them in his 1795 color prints as well as his temperas for Butts (c.
                            1799-1800). Like Blake as he engraved the copperplates for <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
in his back room below, Lohr would spend a significant
                            portion of his working day seated at a table. Here he would prepare and
                            cut gold leaf on a gilder’s cushion and apply it to picture
                            frames or furniture (illus. 4-6). Stalker and Parker suggest that a
                            gilder use 
<q> a Cushion made of Leather stufft very even with Tow, and
                                strained on a board 10 inches one way, and 14 the other. On this you
                                are to cut the gold and silver with a thin, broad, sharp, and
                                smooth-edged knife: To these, three or four Pencils of finer hair
                                than ordinary . . . the Artists use also the end 
<pb id="p42-96" n="96"/>
<figure n="Burnishing.042.03.bonus" rend="file" width="600" height="397">
	<head>5. Burnishing the gold.</head>
	<figDesc>Image courtesy of Arnold Wiggins and Sons.</figDesc>
</figure> of a Squirrels tail spread abroad, and fastened to a flat
                                pencilstick, which is broad at one end, and split, just like an
                                housepainter’s Graining-tool, but less; it serves for taking
                                up and laying on whole Leaves at a time, and is by them called a
                                Pallet: Cotton is also requisite, and some use nothing else.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95" type="note">95</ref>
	<note id="n94">94. See “Water Gilding” in Mason and
                                    Gregory.</note>
	<note id="n95">95. Stalker and Parker 55, quoted by Mason and
                                    Gregory.</note></q>
Near-transparent sheets of gold, silver, and
gold-silver alloy leaf
                            would be kept in books interleaved with tissue paper purchased from a
                            nearby gold-beater’s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96"
type="note">96</ref>
                            Although demanding less physical effort than a number of crafts of the
                            time, gilding required great skill, care, and patience. The slightest
                            draft could carry away the translucent sheets on the end of the
                            gilder’s brush. Stalker and Parker observe that 
<q> the Guilders
                                commonly border their Cushion at one end, and four or five inches
                                down each side, with a strip of parchment two inches high, intending
                                by this fence and bulwark to preserve their Gold from the assaults
                                of Wind, and Air, which if moved never so gently, carries away this
                                light body, which willingly complies with its uncertain motions.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97" type="note">97</ref>
	<note id="n96">96. For example, the firms of John Jeffrey and J.S.
                                    Vandenbergh were both in Shoe Lane, Fleet Street (<hi rend="i">Pigot
                                        and Co.’s Directory</hi> 1824 [86]).</note>
	<note id="n97">97. Stalker and Parker 55-56.</note></q>
It may have been for the sake of a peaceful and
draft-free
                            environment that Lohr moved his workshop to an upper floor at Henry
                            Banes’s house. The habits of the middle-aged Banes and Blakes are
                            likely to have been more conducive to his professional requirements than
                            those of his own crowded domestic space. The proximity of Lohr’s
                            workshop suggests that Blake may have had regular access to metal leaf
                            during the 1820s. This fact alone may explain the profusion of gold in
                            his work of the period, but there may be a further reason why he decided
                            to use an unprecedented amount of metal leaf in his later years.                  
                        </p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Di Cennino Cennini trattato della pittura</hi> was first
                            published in Rome in 1821. Over a quarter of a century earlier,
                            Cumberland had told Blake of the manuscript of Cennino’s
                            craftsman’s handbook and provided him with some of the recipes
                            for mixing pigments.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98"
type="note">98</ref> However,
                            Blake is likely first to have examined the full text in 1822, when
                            Linnell presented him with a copy of the Tambroni edition. Years later,
                            on 10 December 1862, Linnell wrote to Anne Gilchrist: “the first
                            copy of Cennino Cennini seen in England was the copy I obtained from
                            Italy &amp; gave to Blake who soon made it out &amp; was gratified to
                            find that he had been using the same materials &amp; <pb id="p42-97" n="97"/>
<figure n="doreur.42.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="718">
	<figTranscr>
                              Pl. IV.<lb/>
                              fig. 5. fig. 2. fig. 6. fig. 4. fig. 1. fig. 3.<lb/>
                              fig. 1. fig. 13. fig. 14. fig. 9. fig. 8. a b fig. 6 fig. 7<lb/>
                              fig. 2. fig. 10.<lb/>
                              fig. 17. fig. 5 a b fig. 14. fig. 15. fig. 16. fig. 17. fig. 18 b fig. 19.
a<lb/>
                              fig. 12. fig. 11. fig. 3. fig. 4. fig. 21. fig. 20. a<lb/>
                              Echelle de l’etablie du chevalet<lb/>
                              et du Baquet<lb/>
                              1 2 Pieds.<lb/>
                              Echelle pour tous les autres outils.<lb/>
                              .B.s<lb/>
                              Doreur, Sur Bois.<lb/>
                              189.
                            </figTranscr>
	<head>6. “Doreur, Sur Bois,” <hi rend="i">Encyclopédie, ou Dictionnaire raisonné des
                                        sciences, des arts et des métiers</hi>, ed. Denis
                                    Diderot and Jean d’Alembert, 3rd ed., 17 vols. (1770-75),
                                    accompanied by <hi rend="i">Recueil de planches, sur les
                                        sciences, les arts libéraux, et les arts
                                        méchaniques, avec leur explication</hi>, 3rd ed., 11
                                    vols. (1771-78).</head>
	<figDesc>The illustration is from the second part of vol. 2 of the
                                        <hi rend="i">Recueil de planches.</hi> Image courtesy of the
                                    Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, University of
                                    Rochester Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p42-98" n="98"/>
methods in painting as Cennini
                            describes—particularly the Carpenters glue.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99" type="note">99</ref> Cennino introduces his work,
<q>
                                Here begins the craftsman’s handbook, made and composed by
                                Cennino of Colle, in the reverence of God, and of The Virgin Mary .
                                . . and in the reverence of Giotto, of Taddeo and of Agnolo,
                                Cennino’s master; and for the use and good and profit of
                                anyone who wants to enter this profession.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100" type="note">100</ref></q>
As Blake leafed through his copy we know that he read
the several
                            short chapters on different kinds of glue. Within a dozen pages more he
                            would have found an even greater number of chapters on the various uses
                            and applications of gold in painting and decoration, a hallmark of the
                            art of fifteenth-century Florence that he held in the highest
                                regard.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n101"
type="note">101</ref> In the light of this
                            evidence, is it coincidence only that gold features in such profusion in
                            Blake’s paintings and illuminated books during the years in which
                            there was a professional gilder’s workshop in the rooms above his
                            own, and in which he finally read Cennino’s handbook for himself?
                            With an accessible source of metal leaf, Blake could not only emulate
                            the techniques that the medieval and early Renaissance masters used when
                            gilding panel paintings, as recounted in Cennino, but could also
                            potentially attempt to enhance and brighten earlier works still in his
                            possession whose paint had darkened.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n102" type="note">102</ref>
	<note id="n98">98. Stemmler 145.</note>
	<note id="n99">99. Linnell, ms. with the Ivimy mss., quoted in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 684.</note>
	<note id="n100">100. Cennino 1.</note>
	<note id="n101">101. Chapters 132-40 are specifically concerned with
                                gilding processes (Cennino 79-86). His description of gilding and
                                burnishing suggests how Lohr is likely to have worked. Cennino
                                recommends saving scraps of gold such as those Lohr may have given
                                to Blake (82). It is interesting that he suggests burnishing gold
                                with precious stones (82). Blake may have found the environment
                                Cennino recommends for summer burnishing (83) in Henry
                                Banes’s basement or “Kitchen” (for
                                “Kitchen,” see letter to Linnell, 25 Nov. 1825).
                                Cennino suggests that two trestle tables would be needed (84). Blake
                                could have found the space required for burnishing in either his
                                first-floor front-room printing studio, Banes’s basement
                                “Kitchen,” or perhaps Lohr’s workshop.</note>
	<note id="n102">102. In the years following his return from Sussex,
                                Blake wished to learn to execute, as well as design, paintings in
                                the style of Raphael and other fifteenth to sixteenth-century
                                artists (annotations to Reynolds, E 639). However, until reading
                                Cennino’s manual in 1822, he was probably unaware that many
                                early Renaissance artists used oil mixed with egg tempera in the
                                production of panel paintings. Writing in 1809 in his <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi>, Blake was also unlikely to have
                                foreseen that his own media for many of the temperas would rapidly
                                darken in a way reminiscent of his descriptions of the deterioration
                                of oil paintings.</note></p>
            <p>He appears to have practiced one such technique a decade before moving to
                            Fountain Court: around 1810, he produced a series of temperas for Butts,
                            two of which were on linen supports.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n103" type="note">103</ref> He had executed the majority of his earlier temperas for
                            Butts on canvas. The use of linen recalls the cloth paintings of
                            late-fifteenth and early-sixteenth-century artists such as Andrea
                            Mantegna and Dieric Bouts:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104"
type="note">104</ref> Blake
                            was familiar with engravings of their works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105" type="note">105</ref> However, in 1825 he was given the opportunity
                            to examine Charles and Mary Aders’ impressive collection of
                            fifteenth-century paintings from northern Europe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n106" type="note">106</ref> In many of these works, later catalogued by
                            Johann David Passavant, gold leaf is featured: 
<q><hi rend="i">Hubert</hi>, or 
<hi rend="i">Johann van Eyck.</hi> Head
                                of John the Baptist on a golden dish; a circular picture of about a
                                foot in diameter; the gold ground is shaded as to form the dish. . .
                                . <hi rend="i">Petrus Christophorus.</hi> The Virgin seated on a red
                                throne, embroidered with gold, with the infant Jesus .... <hi rend="i">From
the School of van Eyck.</hi> The Adoration of the
                                Kings . . . the elder King . . . attired in . . . a purple vest
                                embroidered with gold . . . on the floor stands the golden dish
                                containing frankincense. . . . the Moorish King . . . dressed in a
                                red vest, embroidered with gold. . . . Round the head of the Virgin
                                and Child, are rays, painted with gold .... [From the School of van
                                Eyck:] An “Ecce Homo” . . . [Christ’s] open
                                mantle is fastened with a clasp of gold . . . the gold ground so
                                shaded with spots and lines in black and red, as to form a glory
                                round the Saviour’s head. . . . <hi rend="i">Antonello da
                                    Messina.</hi> The Virgin and Child seated in a garden, with two
                                little cherubs hovering in the air, supporting a golden crown.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107" type="note">107</ref></q>
Blake is likely to have encountered
other paintings with gold
                            material. In 1856 the <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi> reported on the sale
                            by auction of a collection formerly belonging to the banker and poet
                            Samuel Rogers, a friend of John Flaxman and Thomas Stothard: “two
                            works by Cimabue, consisted of a small picture of ‘The Virgin
                            enthroned amid Saints,’ on a characteristic gold ground. . . .
                            The other represented ‘an Evangelist writing,’ and
                            formerly belonged to [Blake’s acquaintance William Young]
                                Ottley.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108"
type="note">108</ref>
	<note id="n103">103. The four surviving paintings from this series are
                                    <hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts</hi> (on linen), <hi rend="i">Eve
Naming the Birds</hi> (on linen), <hi rend="i">The
                                    Virgin and Child in Egypt</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Christ
                                    Blessing</hi> (B #667-70). According to Butlin, <hi rend="i">Christ
Blessing</hi> is on “fine canvas.” The
                                late watercolor <hi rend="i">The Characters in Spenser’s</hi>
                                Faerie Queene (c. 1825) was executed on a muslin support (B
                                #811).</note>
	<note id="n104">104. See Mantegna, <hi rend="i">Samson and Delilah</hi>
                                (glue size on linen) (c. 1490), National Gallery cat. no. 1145; 
<hi rend="i">The Introduction of the Cult of Cybele at Rome</hi>
                                (glue size on linen) (1505-06), NG902; Bouts, <hi rend="i">The
                                    Entombment</hi> (c. 1450-60) (glue size on linen, painted
                                surface), NG664. Bouts produced a series of cloth paintings (see
                                Dunkerton et al. 296); he may therefore have inspired Blake’s
                                own series.</note>
	<note id="n105">105. According to Bindman, “Cumberland was an
                                enthusiastic collector of early Italian prints . . . he owned . . .
                                a number of Mantegna prints” (<hi rend="i">Blake as an
                                    Artist</hi> 212). Mantegna’s <hi rend="i">Christ
                                    Descending into Limbo</hi> is a likely source for the
                                frontispiece for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (see Paley, 
<hi rend="i">Continuing City</hi> pls. 14 and 15). See also Kraus
                                155-56, in which Viscomi draws a parallel between the style of the
                                Dante engravings and Mantegna: “Job has Dürer in mind,
                                but the Dante engravings are simpler still, more Raimondi and
                                Mantegna, with more untouched, or white space, that is, more like
                                drawings, the original paradigm for engraving.” Blake and
                                Linnell may have encountered works by Mantegna when they visited the
                                British Museum on 24 Apr. 1823 (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
                                386).</note>
	<note id="n106">106. Blake and Linnell visited the Aders at 11 Euston
                                Square on Saturday 6 Aug. and Saturday 10 Dec. 1825 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
411, 419). For more information on the Aders’
                                collection, see Paley, <hi rend="i">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</hi>
                                83-92.</note>
	<note id="n107">107. Passavant 201-16.</note>
	<note id="n108">108. “The Collection of the Late Samuel
                                Rogers” 188.</note></p>
            <pb id="p42-99" n="99"/>
            <p>Linnell’s journal records that he and Blake visited the art dealer
                            Samuel Woodburn on 26 August 1821.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n109" type="note">109</ref> Blake may therefore have seen the latter’s gallery
                            at 112 St. Martin’s Lane. The remarkable preservation of the
                            surface of one work in Woodburn’s collection, Leonardo da
                            Vinci’s <hi rend="i">Holy Family</hi>, as noted by Passavant, may
                            have influenced Blake’s creation of late temperas, discussed
                            below, such as <hi rend="i">Satan Smiting Job with Sore Boils</hi>,
                            which have retained near-perfect surfaces.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n110" type="note">110</ref> Perhaps Blake also visited the museum of the East India
                            Company, where he would have seen gilded images of Hindu gods.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n111" type="note">111</ref> In addition, he encountered
                            medieval manuscripts featuring gold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n112" type="note">112</ref>
	<note id="n109">109. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 379.</note>
	<note id="n110">110. Passavant 245-46.</note>
	<note id="n111">111. Passavant 264.</note>
	<note id="n112">112. See Davies 19, 24, 27; Blunt 45; Hagstrum chapter
                                2: “The Art of Illumination.”</note></p>
            <p>As Mason and Gregory observe, in the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries
                            “the crafts of painting and gilding were closely allied.”
                            Lohr, if indeed he served his apprenticeship in London, would not have
                            been a member of a gilders’ guild, but would have joined the
                            Painter-Stainers’ Company, incorporated in 1502. However, gilding
                            had not been widely used in paintings in England since the sixteenth
                            century. In his use of gilding materials and techniques, particularly in
                            his later paintings, Blake reunified the two crafts. It should be
                            remembered that he received no formal training in either painting or
                            gilding, having been obliged to serve his apprenticeship as an engraver,
                            almost certainly due to financial constraints.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113" type="note">113</ref>
	<note id="n113">113. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 12, 665.</note></p>
            <p>The discovery that Lohr had a carving and gilding workshop on a floor
                            above William and Catherine Blake’s at 3 Fountain Court between
                            c. 1823 and 1829 reveals a possible relationship between the Blakes and
                            one household of “humble but respectable”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n114" type="note">114</ref> neighbors. Significantly, Lohr
                            must now be considered a credible source for the metal leaf used so
                            distinctively in Blake’s late temperas, watercolors, and
                            illuminated works. Blake’s potential interaction with his fellow
                            lodger may have played an instrumental role in enabling him to follow
                            closely the instructions for gilding and panel-painting techniques in
                            his newly acquired copy of Cennino. The proximity of the workshop and
                            materials, coupled with Linnell’s gift of Cennino’s manual
                            in 1822 and access to the Aders’ collection in 1825, may
                            therefore have provided the environment in which Blake could finally
                            create enduring temperas in the style of the early masters he admired.
                                <note id="n114">114. A. Gilchrist 308.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">4. Blake and the Ancients’ Use of Gold, Silver,
                                    and Other Metals, c. 1824-27</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Around 1826, Blake produced three temperas: <hi rend="i">Count Ugolino
                                and His Sons in Prison, The Body of Abel Found by Adam and Eve</hi>,
                            and <hi rend="i">Satan Smiting Job with Sore Boils.</hi> He appears to
                            refer to them in a letter to Linnell dated 25 April 1827: “as to
                            Ugolino &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> I never supposed that I should sell
                            them my Wife alone is answerable for their having Existed in any finishd
                            State—I am too much attachd to Dante to think much of any thing
                            else . . .” (E 784). These late temperas share the theme of
                            suffering, are versions of earlier works by Blake, have almost exactly
                            the same dimensions, and are all on mahogany supports. In addition, they
                            have a unique style of signature: in the bottom right-hand corner of
                            each panel, Blake incised through the paint surface to the support.
                            Finally, and of special relevance for this paper, all three feature
                                gold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n115"
type="note">115</ref> Butlin has concluded
                            that they form a series.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n116"
type="note">116</ref>
	<note id="n115">115. Although Butlin identifies gold on <hi rend="i">The
                                    Body of Abel</hi> and <hi rend="i">Count Ugolino</hi>, he
                                detects no gold on <hi rend="i">Satan Smiting Job.</hi> However,
                                Russell states that “there is gold upon the wings of Satan
                                and upon the arrows in his hand and upon the blue flames behind
                                them” (<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> [1947] 12). Donnan has
                                confirmed that there is “a considerable amount of
                                gold” on <hi rend="i">Satan Smiting Job</hi> (telephone
                                conversation, 21 Oct. 2002). This work was not examined in
                                Townsend’s study for <hi rend="i">The Painter at Work</hi>
                                (email, 3 Dec. 2004).</note>
	<note id="n116">116. See B #805.</note></p>
            <p>Donnan has closely examined <hi rend="i">Count Ugolino</hi> out of its
                            frame, and describes it as possessing a “perfect surface,”
                            probably because Blake, informed by Cennino’s manual, began to
                            use egg tempera.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n117"
type="note">117</ref> She believes
                            that the uniquely “perfect surface[s]” of <hi rend="i">Count Ugolino</hi> and
its two companion panels are explained by
                            Blake’s use of pure pigments mixed with egg yolk and then applied
                            as thin washes of watercolor. Such materials and techniques produced a
                            very different effect from his earlier “thick” paint
                                medium.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n118"
type="note">118</ref> These temperas are
                            three examples of the few Blake paintings which have survived in
                            excellent condition and which therefore are of key importance to
                            scholars in understanding his developing use of materials. <note id="n117">117.
See, for example, Cennino 87-89.</note>
	<note id="n118">118. Telephone conversation, 21 Oct. 2002.</note></p>
            <p>In the mid-1820s the Ancients, a group of young artists including
                            Richmond and Palmer, congregated around Blake. Richmond also appears to
                            have worked closely with Blake in the production of his own first
                            (panel) painting, <hi rend="i">Abel the Shepherd</hi> (1825, tempera on
                            oak). Bentley observes that “Blake not only inspired the young
                            men, but he taught them as well, as may be seen in a little sketch which
                            Richmond inscribed ‘drawn by W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Blake to help
                            me in my picture of “Abel.” 1825.”’<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n119" type="note">119</ref> The Ancients seem to have used
                            similar material to Blake in the creation of their works during this
                            period. Essick has asked, “might Blake have been influenced, in
                            some sense, by his . . . youthful followers?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n120" type="note">120</ref> Two prominent members also began to experiment
                            with metal: Richmond executed a tempera featuring metal leaf, <hi rend="i">The
Creation of Light</hi> (1826, gold on mahogany), and
                            also used gold on his <hi rend="i">Christ and the Woman of Samaria</hi>
                            (1828). It has been observed that Palmer makes two references to the
                            projected use of silver in annotations to sketches for paintings of
                            “A monastic figure with 
<pb id="p42-100" n="100"/>
much
                            background of Gothic Cathedral” and “S.
                            Hieronymous” in his 1824 sketchbook.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n121" type="note">121</ref> He also uses gold paint in a sketch of a
                            pastoral landscape, to depict the disk and rays of a setting sun,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n122" type="note">122</ref> as well as in his paintings <hi rend="i">A
Hilly Scene</hi> (c. 1826) and <hi rend="i">Coming from
                                Evening Church</hi> (1830).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n123" type="note">123</ref>
                            Richmond’s and Palmer’s similar choice of materials and
                                support<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n124"
type="note">124</ref> suggests that around
                            1826, in the light of Blake’s reading of Cennino, they and Blake
                            discussed and shared techniques such as experimenting with metal leaf
                            and with wood rather than canvas supports. <note id="n119">119. See
                                Bentley, “Blake and the Antients” 8; B #802.1; H. H.
                                Gilchrist 261.</note>
	<note id="n120">120. Essick 28.</note>
	<note id="n121">121. Palmer 1:6, 18, 46. The second of these was kindly
                                pointed out to me by Martin Butlin (letter to the author, 13 Jan.
                                2005).</note>
	<note id="n122">122. Palmer 1:163. Significantly, about 1826 Blake uses
                                gold material on two representations of the setting sun in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E (pls. 84, 94). Butlin suggests
                                that “the idea of using silver for the highlights in the
                                architectural background [see Palmer 1:18] may have been suggested
                                [to Palmer] by the German and Flemish primitives admired by Palmer
                                in the Aders collection” (Palmer 2:27). Linnell had also
                                taken Palmer to the Aders’ c. 1822-24 (Palmer 2:17).</note>
	<note id="n123">123. Ormsby, Townsend, Singer, and Dean,
                                “Blake’s Use” 145-49; Townsend, email, 2 June
                                2005.</note>
	<note id="n124">124. Palmer executed the following works on panel
                                supports: <hi rend="i">The Rest on the Flight to Egypt</hi>
                                (original title: <hi rend="i">Repose of the Holy Family</hi>)
                                (1824-25), <hi rend="i">A Hilly Scene</hi> (c. 1826), and slightly
                                later, <hi rend="i">The Gleaning Field</hi> (c. 1833), <hi rend="i">The Bright
Cloud</hi> (c. 1833-34), <hi rend="i">The
                                    Shearers</hi> (c. 1833-34), <hi rend="i">Scene at
                                    Underriver</hi> (c. 1833-34), <hi rend="i">The Sleeping
                                    Shepherd</hi> (c. 1833-34), <hi rend="i">A Pastoral Scene</hi>
                                (1835). Linnell produced the following works on panel during this
                                period: <hi rend="i">Isle of Wight from Lymington Quay</hi> (1825),
                                    <hi rend="i">Mid-day</hi> (1826), <hi rend="i">Mercury and
                                    Argus</hi> (1828), <hi rend="i">Milling</hi> (1828), <hi rend="i">Christ
and the Woman of Samaria</hi> (1829).</note></p>
            <p>The three artists’ use of gold and silver in the panel paintings
                            of this period—often containing a biblical or early Christian
                            subject—seems reminiscent of fifteenth-century panel paintings,
                            icons, or altarpieces. In such works, “gilding . . . serves to
                            glorify the subject-matter and, because of the cost and effort involved,
                            symbolizes an act of devotion on the part of the patron or
                                artist.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n125"
type="note">125</ref> The notion
                            of gilding as a form of worship may have appealed to Blake, Richmond,
                            and Palmer. Almost twenty years earlier, in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
                                Catalogue</hi>, Blake had written, “the above four drawings
                                [<hi rend="i">The Body of Abel Found by Adam and Eve: Cain, Who Was
                                about to Bury It, Fleeing from the Face of His Parents; The Soldiers
                                Casting Lots for Christ’s Garment; Jacob’s Ladder; The
                                Angels Hovering over the Body of Jesus in the Sepulchre</hi>] the
                            Artist wishes were in Fresco, on an enlarged scale to ornament the
                            altars of churches, and to make England like Italy, respected by
                            respectable men of other countries on account of Art” (E 549).
                            Significantly, Richmond is likely to have been the owner of most, if not
                            all three, of Blake’s final panel paintings: he owned <hi rend="i">Satan Smiting
Job</hi> and might have owned <hi rend="i">The Body of Abel.</hi> The early provenance of <hi rend="i">Count
                                Ugolino</hi> is unknown.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n126"
type="note">126</ref>
	<note id="n125">125. See Stephenson.</note>
	<note id="n126">126. See B #805-07.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">5. The Significance of Blake’s Use of Gold and
                                    Other Metals</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Essick has suggested that “the modern student of the graphic arts
                            should respond with a . . . sense of the unity of an artist’s
                            vision and the specific material and technical means he uses to
                            communicate that vision to us.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n127" type="note">127</ref> I will conclude with a consideration of Blake’s
                            intentions in his use of metals as a means of artistic expression in the
                            1820s. Since his earliest experiments with relief etching in the
                            mid-1780s, and probably earlier, Blake had freely experimented with
                            materials in the expression of his vision. The evolution of tempera
                            media, his Virgil woodcuts, and his return to pure line engraving in the
                            plates for <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and Dante are evidence of
                            experimentation even in his final years. His use of gold and other
                            metals on new as well as on previously painted or printed works is
                            another example of his willingness to experiment, to reinvent, and to
                            employ materials in unorthodox ways. However, Blake’s late and
                            frequent application of gold and other metal at Fountain Court parallels
                            his use of pure line engraving in <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and of egg
                            tempera in the last three temperas in that each involves a conscious
                            return to older techniques.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n128"
type="note">128</ref> His
                            use of gold, silver, and other metals is another instance of his
                            antiquarianism as an artist. <note id="n127">127. Essick 29.</note>
	<note id="n128">128. In 1810 Cumberland recorded in his pocket book that
                                “[Thomas] Stothard shewed me a Picture long ago painted in
                                yolk of Egg—instead of oil that looked crisp . . .”
                                (BL Add. MSS. 36,520A v. 17). He is likely to have shared this
                                information with Blake sometime between 1810 and 1827.</note></p>
            <p>In his temperas and in the late pure line engravings Blake attempted to
                            return to what he believed to be much earlier forms, almost certainly
                            the art of the medieval and Renaissance painters he had encountered at
                            the Aders’ collection and elsewhere.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n129" type="note">129</ref> However, in his use of metals he may have been
                            looking far beyond the fifteenth-century painters to earlier sources of
                            inspiration. In an inscription on the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>
                            plate (c. 1826), Blake states that “What we call Antique Gems are
                            the Gems of Aarons Breast Plate” (E 274). The aphorism recalls
                            Exodus 28.15-21: “And thou shalt make the breastplate of judgment
                            with cunning work. . . . And thou shalt set in it settings of stones. .
                            . . And the stones shall be with the names of the children of Israel,
                            twelve, according to their names, <hi rend="i">like</hi> the engravings
                            of a signet; every one with his name shall they be according to the
                            twelve tribes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n130"
type="note">130</ref> As Essick
                            and Viscomi have demonstrated, in the light of contemporary theories
                            concerning the origin of the art of antique gems, the aphorism is in
                            itself uncontroversial.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n131"
type="note">131</ref> However,
                            it also reflects Blake’s substitution of the biblical for the
                            classical as a source of inspiration.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n132" type="note">132</ref> As Paley has established, the original classical title of
                            the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> was replaced by “יה
                            &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam as they were copied from the
                            Cherubim of Solomons Temple 
<pb id="p42-101" n="101"/>
by three Rhodians
                            &amp; applied to Natural Fact, or History of Ilium.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n133" type="note">133</ref> Blake etched elsewhere on the
                            same plate “The Old &amp; New Testaments are the Great Code of
                            Art” (E 274), expressing his belief in an equation between art
                            and Christianity: a divine art.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n134" type="note">134</ref>
                            Therefore, a biblical reference to gold may have inspired him to
                            decorate his watercolors, temperas, and illuminated books with gold and
                            other metals in his final years. <note id="n129">129. Several plates in
                                the illuminated books such as the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> suggest
                                the stylistic influence of medieval illuminated manuscripts. See
                                Blunt 45; Hagstrum chapter 2: “The Art of
                                Illumination.”</note>
	<note id="n130">130. King James version.</note>
	<note id="n131">131. Essick and Viscomi, <hi rend="i">William
                                    Blake:</hi> Milton a Poem 276.</note>
	<note id="n132">132. He had substituted the classical for the biblical
                                from about the time of the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>
                                (1809) (see E 530-31, 536). See Eaves part 3, “Religion: A
                                Christian History of Engraving,” especially 109, 111-12,
                                118.</note>
	<note id="n133">133. See Paley, <hi rend="i">Traveller</hi> chapter 2:
                                “<hi rend="i">יה &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp;
                                    Adam.</hi>”</note>
	<note id="n134">134. See Essick and Viscomi, <hi rend="i">William
                                    Blake:</hi> Milton a Poem 269-70 (<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, lines 40,
50, and 97).</note></p>
            <p>In Exodus the gems on Aaron’s breastplate are set in gold, the ark
                            of the covenant is overlaid with gold, and the mercy seat, the place of
                            the Divine Presence, decorated with cherubs at either end, is made of
                            pure gold (28.20, 25.10-21). However, Blake’s biblical allusions
                            to gold can be traced even further back. In a letter to Hayley of 12
                            March 1804 referring to two commissioned plates for volume 3 of
                            Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>, he writes:
<q> the two
                                plates are almost finishd You will recieve proofs of them for Lady
                                Hesketh whose copy of Cowpers letters ought to be printed in letters
                                of Gold &amp; ornamented with Jewels of Heaven Havilah Eden &amp;
                                all the countries where Jewels abound. (E 743)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n135" type="note">135</ref>
	<note id="n135">
                                    135. This sentiment echoes Blake’s use of
                                        shell gold on <hi rend="i">Winter</hi>, where the nib of
                                        Winter’s quill (a detail not included in
                                        Cowper’s description in <hi rend="i">The Task</hi>)
                                        is tipped with gold. As observed above, Blake literally
                                        wrote in gold when finishing <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                                        copy E.
                                    <p>In his annotations to Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms
                                            on Man</hi> (translated by Fuseli), Blake praises a
                                        passage in which Lavater quotes Jesus’s words
                                        (Matthew 6.21; Luke 12.34), “<hi rend="i">Where thy
                                            treasure is, there will thy heart be also</hi>,”
                                        and comments “The object of your love is your
                                        God.” In his annotation, Blake asserts that
                                        “this should be written in gold letters on our
                                        temples” (E 584).</p></note></q>
The allusion to Havilah can be
traced to Genesis 2.10-12: 
<q> And a
                                river went out of Eden to water the garden; and from thence it was
                                parted, and became into four heads. The name of the first is Pison:
                                that <hi rend="i">is</hi> it which compasseth the whole land of
                                Havilah, where <hi rend="i">there</hi> is gold; And the gold of that
                                land <hi rend="i">is</hi> good: there <hi rend="i">is</hi> bdellium
                                and the onyx stone.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n136"
type="note">136</ref>
	<note id="n136">136. Onyx is a semiprecious agate with different
                                    colors in layers, often used in the creation of antique gems.
                                    Blake’s technique of painting transparent glazes over
                                    both temperas and color prints, reminiscent of onyx stone, is
                                    the reason for the jewel-like quality of some of his illuminated
                                    books and temperas. Bdellium is not a precious stone but a
                                    fragrant tree resin used in perfumes.</note></q>
In 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Havilah is referred to four times.
                            For Blake, gold appears to have had associations with the land of
                            Havilah, and by implication with Eden or Paradise.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n137" type="note">137</ref> The verses above are transcribed on page six
                            of Blake’s unfinished Genesis manuscript, the second title page
                            of which he had begun to decorate with gold. Little has been written
                            concerning the significance of Blake’s use of gold in this work,
                            but the subject has recently been explored by Rosamund Paice, who notes
                            that 
<q> A . . . deviation from the muted hues of this title-page is
                                present in the gold highlights that have been added to the
                                lettering—or rather to some of the lettering. Given that
                                Blake left this design in an unfinished state, it may be simply that
                                he never got around to adding these touches to the last three
                                letters of “G E / N E / S I S” or that he ran out of
                                this more expensive colour. Neither of these hypotheses seems
                                particularly convincing, however: the placement of the gold within
                                the lettering is determined in the letters “G E / N
                                E”, and it would have been a very quick task to continue on
                                in this pattern; moreover, given the small quantity of gold required
                                for the letters already decorated, it is hardly plausible that this
                                would have exhausted Blake’s supply. We must, therefore,
                                consider another possibility, one that has a justification within
                                the design itself. The letters “G E / N E” appear
                                above the division created by the . . . grey path or pavement that
                                seems to signify the line dividing the heavenly from the earthly;
                                the letters “S I S” inhabit the earthly space below.
                                In this context, the use of gold for only the first four letters
                                seems a reasonable device for emphasising the superior status of the
                                heavenly realm.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n138"
type="note">138</ref>
	<note id="n137">137. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 49:15 (E 198); see also
                                    19:42 (E 164), 55:22 (E 204), and 68:38 (E 222). <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,
or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> also includes a
                                    reference to “gold of Eden” (E 376); “an old
                                    Prophecy in Eden recorded in gold” is referred to in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (E 119).</note>
	<note id="n138">138. Excerpt from an unpublished paper; my thanks to
                                    Rosamund Paice for allowing me to quote from it here. Paice
                                    continues, . . . gold-embellished letters have a long history in
                                    the production of illuminated manuscripts—particularly
                                    Bibles and prayer books—for rich patrons. Blake’s
                                    colouring here, then, not only serves a meaningful function
                                    within the context of the design and subject matter, but also
                                    gestures to previous works of this type, and, by implication,
                                    acknowledges the status of his own patron in this commission,
                                    John Linnell.</note></q>
Paice’s findings suggest a way to interpret
Blake’s
                            application of gold to titles in other illuminated books, including the
                            words written partly in gold on the title page of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy
E. On plate 2, gold is applied to the letters
                            of the word “Jerusalem”, but not to “The”;
                            in the next line, to “Ema” and the left-hand side of
                            “n” but not to “ation of” or the second
                            “The.” There is gold on the “G” of
                            “Giant,” but not on the rest of the word, and on
                            “Albi” and the left-hand side of “o,” but
                            not on “n.” This is only apparent on examining the plate
                            in direct natural light; Blake used a yellow pigment on the letters
                            which do not feature gold. As Paice asks, in his selective use of gold
                            material, is Blake merely economizing, or attempting to convey a
                                message?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n139"
type="note">139</ref>
	<note id="n139">139. One might ask the same question of the gilded
                                titles in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy Y, where some titles have
                                been gilded with shell gold (for example,
                                “Introduction,” “Little Black Boy”)
                                while other titles feature no gold (for example, “Divine
                                Image,” “The Shepherd”). My thanks to Robert
                                Essick for this information (email, 5 Dec. 2008).</note></p>
            <p>Despite criticizing the teachings of Swedenborg in the 1790s, most
                            vigorously in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Blake
                            came to revaluate them in the early nineteenth century. He also adopted
                            (or adapted) a number of teachings such as the concept of Jesus as God,
                            rather than a facet of the trinity.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n140" type="note">140</ref> Most importantly in the context of the present 
<pb id="p42-102" n="102"/>
discussion, he apparently accepted
                            Swedenborg’s selection of inspired books of the Bible which may
                            be understood symbolically.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n141"
type="note">141</ref> It
                            is clear that Blake carefully read a number of translations of
                            Swedenborg’s works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n142"
type="note">142</ref> For
                            example, in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, Blake describes
                            his “experiment Picture,” <hi rend="i">The Spiritual
                                Preceptor</hi>, as a “subject . . . taken from the visions of
                            Emanuel Swedenborg. Universal Theology . . .” (E 546). As Bentley
                            demonstrates, he is alluding to Rev. John Clowes’s translation of
                                <hi rend="i">True Christian Religion: Containing the Universal
                                Theology of the New Church</hi>, published in 1781.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n143" type="note">143</ref> Blake notes that “the
                            works of this visionary are well worthy the attention of Painters and
                            Poets; they are foundations for grand things . . .” (E 546). He
                            appears to have drawn from the same volume in his portrayal of the Ijim
                            in his manuscript poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (1789?).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n144" type="note">144</ref> By 1809-10, he had also
                            consulted Clowes’s translations of Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">Of the Earths in
the Universe and of Their Inhabitants</hi>
                                (1787)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n145"
type="note">145</ref> and <hi rend="i">The
                                Delights of Wisdom concerning Conjugial Love</hi> (1794) when
                            composing <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (c. 1796-1807?).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n146" type="note">146</ref>
	<note id="n140">140. See E 274.</note>
	<note id="n141">141. Damon, <hi rend="i">Philosophy</hi> 454.</note>
	<note id="n142">142. See Damon, <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> 392-94
                                (entry for Swedenborg).</note>
	<note id="n143">143. Bentley, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                                    Writings</hi> 2:855n.</note>
	<note id="n144">144. Bentley, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                                    Writings</hi> 2:909n.</note>
	<note id="n145">145. Bentley, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                                    Writings</hi> 2:1349n.</note>
	<note id="n146">146. See Damon, <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> 393; Otto
                                65 and n16.</note></p>
            <p>Clowes was a Church of England minister and Swedenborgian preacher who,
                            significantly, remained within the communion of the established church
                            and opposed the formation of the New Church. In 1796-97 he had also
                            translated the Quietist Archbishop François de Salignac de la
                            Mothe-Fénelon’s <hi rend="i">Pious Reflections for Every
                                Day of the Month.</hi> In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
                            “Fenelon, Guion, Teresa, / Whitefield &amp; Hervey, guard that
                            Gate [towards Beulah]; with all the gentle Souls / Who guide the great
                            Wine-press of Love . . .” (E 227). Paley has suggested that
                            Blake’s friend and patron Charles Augustus Tulk may have been
                            involved in Blake’s renewed interest in Swedenborg.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n147" type="note">147</ref> In 1806 Clowes established the
                            Hawkstone meeting, an annual meeting of Swedenborgians (both
                            “separatists” in the New Jerusalem Church and
                            “non-separatists”) at Hawkstone Park in Shropshire. It was
                            through these meetings that Tulk originally became involved in the
                                church.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n148"
type="note">148</ref> Clowes had sided
                            with the printer Robert Hindmarsh, a figure probably known to Blake,
                            against the engraver and minister Samuel Noble over the nature of the
                                resurrection,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n149"
type="note">149</ref> and was also a
                            personal friend of Flaxman, Blake’s close friend, also a
                            Swedenborgian (though only briefly a member of the New Jerusalem Church,
                            1797-99) and co-founder of a project to publish translations of
                            Swedenborg’s works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n150"
type="note">150</ref>
	<note id="n147">147. Paley, <hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi> Jerusalem
                                207.</note>
	<note id="n148">148. Alexander Gordon, “Tulk, Charles Augustus
                                (1786-1849),” rev. Timothy C. F. Stunt (<hi rend="i">ODNB</hi>).</note>
	<note id="n149">149. Tulk had also clashed with Noble (<hi rend="i">ODNB</hi>). Clowes had desperately urged
Hindmarsh not to make
                                the move into sectarianism of founding the New Church.</note>
	<note id="n150">150. Jon Mee, “Clowes, John (1743-1831)”
                                    (<hi rend="i">ODNB</hi>).</note></p>
            <p>Swedenborg’s biblical exegesis <hi rend="i">Arcana Coelestia</hi>
                            was first published in London in 1749. Significantly, the eight volumes
                            deal only with Genesis and Exodus. According to Marsha Keith Schuchard,
                            Blake would have been present at meetings of the Swedenborg Society in
                            the 1780s when passages of <hi rend="i">Arcana Coelestia</hi> were
                            orally translated and discussed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n151" type="note">151</ref>
                            S. Foster Damon first cites evidence of Blake’s having read <hi rend="i">Arcana
Coelestia.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n152" type="note">152</ref> From 1784 Clowes
had published a translation, and it
                            seems likely that Blake’s reference to Swedenborg’s canon
                            of works<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n153"
type="note">153</ref> derived from his
                            reading of this translation. If so, Blake may also have read in the same
                            work Swedenborg’s discussion of the varied symbolism of gold in
                            the first two books in the Bible. For Genesis 2.11, 12, Swedenborg
                            states: 
<q> The first river, or Pison, signifieth the intelligence of
                                faith, originating in love; the land of Havilah signifieth the mind;
                                gold goodness; bdellium and the onyx-stone truth; the reason why
                                gold is twice mentioned is, because it signifies the good of love
                                and the good of faith originating in love; and the reason why
                                bdellium and the onyx-stone are mentioned is because one signifies
                                the truth of love, and the other the truth of faith originating in
                                love. Such is the celestial man.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n154" type="note">154</ref></q>
Such passages suggest that Blake’s late use of gold and
                            other metals may have a biblical origin influenced by his renewed
                            interest in Swedenborg. If so, it might also signify “the good of
                            love and the good of faith originating in love.” However, it
                            would be untypical for Blake’s use of gold to have one source and
                            one meaning. As Paley has observed, the gold in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E
has both positive and negative
                                connotations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n155"
type="note">155</ref>
	<note id="n151">151. Email, 4 June 2005. It is possible that Blake
                                derived some of the animal imagery deployed in his writings from the
                                same source (see Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy</hi> 77).</note>
	<note id="n152">152. Damon, <hi rend="i">Philosophy</hi> 454.</note>
	<note id="n153">153. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 48:8-11 (E 196).</note>
	<note id="n154">154. Swedenborg 2:49. See also 1:2, 115.</note>
	<note id="n155">155. Paley, <hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi> Jerusalem
                                15-16. Some of Blake’s applications of gold material are
                                idiosyncratic and perplexing. For instance, what is to be made of
                                the patches of gold surrounding and within the spokes of both
                                spinning wheels on pl. 59 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy
                                E?</note></p>
            <p>In this paper, I have provided a chronological overview of Blake’s
                            use of metal material in the creation of his paintings and illuminated
                            books during the five decades of his working career as artist and
                            printmaker, and especially during his final years in which he used gold
                            and silver with unprecedented frequency, despite modest finances.
                            Building upon the work of Mason and Gregory, Donnan, and Townsend,
                            Ormsby, and other conservation scientists at the Tate, I have discussed
                            Blake’s emulation of gilding techniques traditionally employed by
                            carvers and gilders. The paper has also explored Blake’s possible
                            sources of metal material, such as his rediscovered neighbor and fellow
                            lodger at 3 Fountain Court, <pb id="p42-103" n="103"/>
the carver and
                            gilder John George Lohr. I have discussed apparent similarities between
                            Blake’s use of gold, silver, and other metal material and that of
                            his younger followers, the Ancients. Finally, while recognizing the
                            complex motivations for Blake’s application of gold, I have
                            demonstrated that one likely source of inspiration for his renewed use
                            of gold material appears to lie at the very beginning of his
                            “Great Code of Art”: the first chapters of Genesis as
                            illuminated by Emanuel Swedenborg.</p>
            <table rows="11" cols="5">
              <head>
                <hi rend="b">Table 1 Temperas, Watercolors, and Separate Plates
                                    Featuring Metal Material, 1775-1827</hi>
              </head>
              <head>1a: Works Executed under James Basire, c. 1775<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n156" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n156">1. The Society of Antiquaries owns the works
                                    executed for its commission; those for Gough are in the Bodleian
                                    Library.</note>
	</head>
              <row>
                <cell>Title</cell>
                <cell>Date</cell>
                <cell>Metal</cell>
                <cell>Commission</cell>
                <cell>Reference</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Countess Aveline, Three Details from Her Tomb</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Society of Antiquaries</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #5</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Countess Aveline, Detail from Her Tomb</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Society of Antiquaries</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #6</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">King Sebert, the North Front of His Monument</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Society of Antiquaries</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #7</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">King Sebert, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia
                                        above His Monument</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Society of Antiquaries</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #8</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Henry III, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia
                                        above the Monument of King Sebert</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Society of Antiquaries</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #9</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">King Sebert, Heads and Ornaments from His
                                        Monument</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Society of Antiquaries</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #10</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Countess Aveline, Three Details from Her Tomb</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Richard Gough</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #14</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">King Sebert, from the Wall-Painting above His
                                        Monument</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Richard Gough</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #16</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Henry III, from the Wall-Painting above the
                                        Monument of King Sebert</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Richard Gough</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #17</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">King Sebert, Heads and Ornaments from His
                                        Monument</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1775</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Richard Gough</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #18</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <pb id="p42-104" n="104"/>
            <table rows="15" cols="6">
              <head>1b: Works Executed c. 1795-1811</head>
              <row>
                <cell>Title</cell>
                <cell>Date</cell>
                <cell>Location</cell>
                <cell>Metal</cell>
                <cell>Source of commission/purchaser/first owner</cell>
                <cell>Reference</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Naomi Entreating Ruth and Orpah</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1795</cell>
                <cell>V&amp;A</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold, gold leaf</cell>
                <cell>Unknown</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #299</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions—An Experiment
                                        Picture</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1795-1800</cell>
                <cell>V&amp;A</cell>
                <cell>Gold-silver alloy leaf</cell>
                <cell>Samuel Palmer</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #661</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Eve Tempted by the Serpent</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1799-1800</cell>
                <cell>V&amp;A</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #379</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Winter</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1800-03?</cell>
                <cell>Tate</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>John Johnson</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #808</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Evening</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1800-03?</cell>
                <cell>NGA</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>John Johnson</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #809</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Olney Bridge</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1800-03?</cell>
                <cell>Untraced</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold?</cell>
                <cell>John Johnson</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #810</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1800-05</cell>
                <cell>Petworth House</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold, gold-silver alloy leaf</cell>
                <cell>Countess of Egremont</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #662</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of Pitt</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1805?</cell>
                <cell>Tate</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold, gold leaf, gold-silver alloy</cell>
                <cell>Samuel Palmer</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #651</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of Nelson</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1805-09</cell>
                <cell>Tate</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #649</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Satan, Sin and Death</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1806?</cell>
                <cell>Huntington</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #536.2</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the Nine and Twenty
                                        Pilgrims on Their Journey to Canterbury</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1808?</cell>
                <cell>Pollok House</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold, pure silver leaf, shell silver</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #653</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Bard, from Gray</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1809?</cell>
                <cell>Tate</cell>
                <cell>Gold-silver alloy leaf, shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Samuel Palmer</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #655</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of Napoleon</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1809?/1822?</cell>
                <cell>Untraced</cell>
                <cell>Gold?</cell>
                <cell>Samuel Palmer</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #652</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">An Allegory of the Spiritual Condition of Man</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1811?</cell>
                <cell>Fitzwilliam</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #673</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <pb id="p42-105" n="105"/>
            <table rows="16" cols="6">
              <head>1c: Later Works, c. 1815-27</head>
              <row>
                <cell>Title</cell>
                <cell>Date</cell>
                <cell>Location</cell>
                <cell>Metal</cell>
                <cell>Source of commission/purchaser/first owner</cell>
                <cell>Reference</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">The Ancient of Days</hi> copy F</cell>
                <cell>c. 1794/1824 or 1827?</cell>
                <cell>Whitworth Gallery</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Frederick Tatham</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #271</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1810-27?</cell>
                <cell>Untraced</cell>
                <cell>Gold leaf?</cell>
                <cell>Mrs. Blake?</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #648</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Overthrow of Apollo and the Pagan Gods</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1815</cell>
                <cell>Huntington</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #542.4</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Night of Peace</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1815</cell>
                <cell>Huntington</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #542.6</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Ghost of a Flea</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1819-20</cell>
                <cell>Tate</cell>
                <cell>Gold-silver alloy leaf, shell gold</cell>
                <cell>John Varley</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #750</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Epitome of James Hervey’s</hi> Meditations
                                    among the Tombs</cell>
                <cell>c. 1820</cell>
                <cell>Tate</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #770</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The First Temptation</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1820-25</cell>
                <cell>Private collection</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Mrs. Blake?</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #546</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 51</cell>
                <cell>c. 1821</cell>
                <cell>National Gallery of Victoria</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>John Linnell?</cell>
                <cell><hi rend="i">BB</hi> 264</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1825</cell>
                <cell>YCBA</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>William Haines</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #480</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Vision of Queen Katherine</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1825</cell>
                <cell>NGA</cell>
                <cell>Gold over pencil</cell>
                <cell>Sir Thomas Lawrence</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #549</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Virgin and Child</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>1825?</cell>
                <cell>YCBA</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Mrs. Blake? Frederick Tatham?</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #674</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Count Ugolino and His Sons in Prison</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1826</cell>
                <cell>Fitzwilliam</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Unknown (George Richmond?)</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #805</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">The Body of Abel Found by Adam and Eve</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1826</cell>
                <cell>Tate</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Butts? George Richmond?</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #806</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Satan Smiting Job with Sore Boils</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>c. 1826</cell>
                <cell>Tate</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>George Richmond</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #807</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Genesis manuscript: second title page</cell>
                <cell>c. 1826-27</cell>
                <cell>Huntington</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>John Linnell</cell>
                <cell>Butlin #828.2</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <pb id="p42-106" n="106"/>
            <table rows="24" cols="5">
              <head>
                <hi rend="b">Table 2: Illuminated Books Finished in Metal Material
                                    by Blake</hi>
              </head>
              <row>
                <cell>Copy</cell>
                <cell>Dates of printing/finishing<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n157"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n157">1. The first (printing) date follows the
                                        appendix, “Extant and Known Copies of Illuminated
                                        Books” (375-81), in Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and
                                            the Idea of the Book;</hi> the second (finishing and
                                        adding of metal material) date is my suggestion based upon
                                        evidence in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake and
the Idea of the Book</hi> as to when the work
                                        was finally purchased.</note>
	</cell>
                <cell>Location</cell>
                <cell>Metal</cell>
                <cell>Source of commission/purchaser/first owner</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">America</hi> copy O</cell>
                <cell>1821/c. 1822-26</cell>
                <cell>Fitzwilliam</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>John Linnell</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy A</cell>
                <cell>1795/?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n158" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n158">2. Both Bindman and Viscomi are suspicious of
                                        the coloring of this copy (see Bindman, <hi rend="i">William
                                            Blake: His Art and Times</hi> [London: Thames and
                                        Hudson, 1982] 106, and Viscomi, “The Myth of
                                        Commissioned Illuminated Books: George Romney, Isaac
                                        D’Israeli, and ‘One Hundred and Sixty designs
                                        . . . of Blake’s,”’ <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23.2 [fall 1989]:
71n35). The gold finishing
                                        may therefore be posthumous.</note>
	</cell>
                <cell>YCBA</cell>
                <cell>Gold leaf</cell>
                <cell>George Romney?</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy K</cell>
                <cell>1821/c. 1822-26</cell>
                <cell>Fitzwilliam</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>John Linnell</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E</cell>
                <cell>1821/c. 1826-27</cell>
                <cell>YCBA</cell>
                <cell>Shell silver, shell gold, shell gold-silver alloy</cell>
                <cell>Frederick Tatham</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> copy H</cell>
                <cell>1790 or 1793<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n159"
type="note">3</ref>/by May 1821
                                        <note id="n159">3. In his forthcoming facsimile edition of
                                            <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> copy B (Bodleian Library),
                                        Michael Phillips reopens the question of the date of
                                        publication, presenting new evidence for 1793, nearer to the
                                        announcement in the prospectus of 10 October
                                    1793.</note>
	</cell>
                <cell>Fitzwilliam</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>John Linnell</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> copy I</cell>
                <cell>1827/1827</cell>
                <cell>Fitzwilliam</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Griffiths Wainewright</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Milton</hi> copy B</cell>
                <cell>1811/c. 1826</cell>
                <cell>Huntington</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Griffiths Wainewright</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Milton</hi> copy C</cell>
                <cell>1811/c. 1818</cell>
                <cell>NYPL</cell>
                <cell>Silver, gold</cell>
                <cell>William Beckford</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Milton</hi> copy D</cell>
                <cell>1818/c. 1818</cell>
                <cell>LC</cell>
                <cell>Crushed gold leaf</cell>
                <cell>James Vine</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy R/Y</cell>
                <cell>c. 1802-07<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n160" type="note">4</ref>/c.
1811 <note id="n160">4. See Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace,
                                        2007,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.4 [spring 2008]:
                                        143.</note>
	</cell>
                <cell>Fitzwilliam/Neuerburg/Essick/Parker</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>John, second Baron Dimsdale<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n161"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n161">5. Bentley and Essick have recently suggested
                                        that the first Baron Dimsdale, who died in 1800, is unlikely
                                        to have been the purchaser/first owner of copy R/Y (Essick,
                                        “Blake in the Marketplace, 2007,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.4
[spring 2008]: 144; Bentley,
                                        “William Blake and His Circle,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 42.1
[summer 2008]: 16n53). The first owner
                                        was probably his son, John, second Baron Dimsdale of
                                        Hampstead (1744-1820). Further information concerning the
                                        second Baron Dimsdale will be provided in a forthcoming
                                        note.</note>
	</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy S</cell>
                <cell>c. 1811/c. 1811</cell>
                <cell>Cincinnati</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold?</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Frognall Dibdin?</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy N (<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
                                    only)</cell>
                <cell>1795/?</cell>
                <cell>Huntington</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Unknown</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy R</cell>
                <cell>1795/c. 1819 or 1824</cell>
                <cell>Fitzwilliam</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>John Linnell</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy S</cell>
                <cell>1811, 1795/ before 1822</cell>
                <cell>Cincinnati</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Francis Chantry?</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy U</cell>
                <cell>1818/c. 1818-22</cell>
                <cell>Princeton</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>James Boswell, Jr.</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy W</cell>
                <cell>1825/c. 1825-27</cell>
                <cell>King’s College</cell>
                <cell>Diluted shell gold applied in washes?</cell>
                <cell>John Jebb</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy X</cell>
                <cell>1827/1827</cell>
                <cell>Anonymous</cell>
                <cell>Shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Thomas Griffiths Wainewright</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy Y</cell>
                <cell>1825/c. 1825-27</cell>
                <cell>Metropolitan</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Edward Calvert</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy Z</cell>
                <cell>1826/c. 1826</cell>
                <cell>LC</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Henry Crabb Robinson</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Thel</hi> copy O</cell>
                <cell>1818/c. 1818-22</cell>
                <cell>LC</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>James Vine</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> copy G</cell>
                <cell>1818/1818 or later</cell>
                <cell>LC</cell>
                <cell>Shell silver, shell gold</cell>
                <cell>Unknown</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Visions</hi> copy N</cell>
                <cell>1818/1818 or later</cell>
                <cell>Private collection</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>James Ferguson?</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Visions</hi> copy O</cell>
                <cell>1818/c. 1818-25</cell>
                <cell>BM</cell>
                <cell>Gold</cell>
                <cell>Henry Crabb Robinson</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p42-107" n="107"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Blake and the Antients: A Prophet with Honour
                            among the Sons of God.” Bentley et al. 1-17.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press,
                            1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> 2nd ed. New Haven: Yale
                            University Press, 2004.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William
                                Blake.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 2001.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake, Samuel Palmer, and George
                            Richmond.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 2.2 (spring 1970):
                            43-50.</p>
            <p>—, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> 2 vols.
                            Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., Robert N. Essick, Shelley M. Bennett, and Morton D.
                            Paley. <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers.</hi> [San Marino:]
                            Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1983.</p>
            <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi> Oxford: Phaidon,
                            1977.</p>
            <p>—, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in
                                the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge.</hi> Cambridge: Syndics of the
                            Fitzwilliam Museum, 1970.</p>
            <p>Blunt, Anthony. <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake.</hi> London:
                            Oxford University Press; New York: Columbia University Press, 1959.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
                                Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1981.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake, 1757-1827.</hi> Tate Gallery
                            Collections, vol. 5. London: Tate Gallery, 1990.</p>
            <p>Cahaner McManus, Noa, and Joyce H. Townsend. “The Large Colour
                            Prints: Methods and Materials.” Townsend 82-99.</p>
            <p>—. “Watercolour Methods, and Materials Use in
                            Context.” Townsend 61-79.</p>
            <p>Campbell, R. <hi rend="i">The London Tradesman.</hi> London, 1747.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">A Catalogue of the Gifts of Lessing J. Rosenwald to the
                                Library of Congress, 1943-1975.</hi> Washington: Library of
                            Congress, 1977.</p>
            <p>Cennini, Cennino d’Andrea. <hi rend="i">The Craftsman’s
                                Handbook: “Il Libro dell’ Arte.”</hi> Trans.
                            Daniel V. Thompson, Jr. New York: Dover Publications, 1960.</p>
            <p>“The Collection of the Late Samuel Rogers.” <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi> ns 2 (1856):
188.</p>
            <p>Crosby, Mark. “A Minute Skirmish: Blake, Hayley and the Art of
                            Miniature Painting.” <hi rend="i">Blake and Conflict.</hi> Ed.
                            Sarah Haggarty and Jon Mee. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2008.
                            164-84.</p>
            <p>Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols
                                of William Blake.</hi> Rev. ed., with a new foreword and annotated
                            bibliography by Morris Eaves. Hanover: University Press of New England,
                            1988.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols.</hi>
                            1924. London: Dawsons, 1969.</p>
            <p>Davies, Keri. “William Blake in Contexts: Family, Friendships, and
                            Some Intellectual Microcultures of Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-Century
                            England.” PhD diss. University of Surrey, 2003.</p>
            <p>Dossie, Robert. <hi rend="i">The Handmaid to the Arts.</hi> 2nd ed. 2
                            vols. London, 1764.</p>
            <p>Dunkerton, Jill, Susan Foister, Dillian Gordon, and Nicholas Penny. <hi rend="i">Giotto to
Dürer: Early Renaissance Painting in the
                                National Gallery.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press; London:
                            National Gallery Publications, Ltd., 1991.</p>
            <p>Dyson, Anthony. <hi rend="i">Pictures to Print: The Nineteenth-Century
                                Engraving Trade.</hi> London: Farrand Press, 1984.</p>
            <p>Eaves, Morris. <hi rend="i">The Counter-Arts Conspiracy: Art and Industry
                                in the Age of Blake.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell University Press,
                            1992.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed., with commentary by Harold Bloom. <hi rend="i">The
                                Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Newly rev. ed. New
                            York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. “John Linnell, William Blake, and the
                            Printmaker’s Craft.” Bentley et al. 18-32.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N., and Joseph Viscomi. “An Inquiry into
                            Blake’s Method of Color Printing.” 2002. Accessed 13 Feb.
                            2002
                            &lt;http://www.blakequarterly.org/inquiry/index.html&gt;.</p>
            <p>—, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Milton a Poem <hi rend="i">and the Final Illuminated
Works</hi>: The Ghost of Abel, On
                            Homers Poetry [<hi rend="i">and</hi>] On Virgil, Laocoön.
                            Blake’s Illuminated Books, vol. 5. Princeton: Princeton
                            University Press/Blake Trust; London: Tate Gallery/Blake Trust,
                            1993.</p>
            <p>Fallon, David. “‘That Angel Who Rides on the
                            Whirlwind’: William Blake’s Oriental Apotheosis of William
                            Pitt.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi> 31.2 (spring
                            2007): 1-28.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">A General Description of All Trades.</hi> London, 1747.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> Ed.
                            Ruthven Todd. Everyman’s Library, no. 971. London: J. M. Dent;
                            New York: E. P. Dutton, 1945.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Herbert Harlakenden. <hi rend="i">Anne Gilchrist: Her Life and
                                Writings.</hi> London: T. Fisher Unwin, 1887.</p>
            <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Poet and Painter: An
                                Introduction to the Illuminated Verse.</hi> 1964. Chicago:
                            University of Chicago Press, 1978.</p>
            <p>Jones, Rica. “Wright of Derby’s Techniques of
                            Painting.” <hi rend="i">Wright of Derby.</hi> Ed. Judy Egerton.
                            London: Tate Gallery, 1990. 263-71.</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">Blake Studies: Essays on His Life and
                                Work.</hi> 2nd ed. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Tempera Paintings of William Blake: A Critical
                                Catalogue.</hi> London: Arts Council of Great Britain, 1951.</p>
            <p>Kraus, Kari. “‘Once Only Imagined’: An Interview
                            with Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi.” <hi rend="i">Studies
in Romanticism</hi> 41.2 (summer 2002): 143-99.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Songs of Innocence
                            and of Experience. Blake’s Illuminated Books, vol. 2. Princeton:
                            Princeton University Press/Blake Trust; London: Tate Gallery/Blake
                            Trust, 1991.</p>
            <p>Linnell, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Palmer, Linnell and Co.: The Life of
                                John Linnell.</hi> Lewes: Book Guild, 1994.</p>
            <p>Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Infernal Methods: A Study of William
                                Blake’s Art Techniques.</hi> London: G. Bell &amp; Sons
                            Ltd., 1975.</p>
            <pb id="p42-108" n="108"/>
            <p>Mason, Pippa, and Michael Gregory. <hi rend="i">Of Gilding: An Essay on
                                the Traditional Techniques of Gilding, Silvering and Gold Beating in
                                England Published to Accompany an Exhibition of Craftsmen’s
                                Tools and Picture Frames.</hi> London: Arnold Wiggins and Sons Ltd.,
                            1989. N. pag.</p>
            <p>Ormsby, Bronwyn, Brain Singer, and John Dean. “The Painting of the
                            Temperas.” Townsend 110-33.</p>
            <p>Ormsby, Bronwyn, Joyce H. Townsend, Brian Singer, and John Dean.
                            “Blake’s Use of Tempera in Context.” Townsend
                            134-49.</p>
            <p>—. “The State of Knowledge on William Blake the
                            Painter.” Townsend 40-51.</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence: Love,
                                Jealousy, and the Sublime in</hi> The Four Zoas. Oxford: Oxford
                            University Press, 2000.</p>
            <p>Paice, Rosamund. “Title-Pages and Tensions in William
                            Blake’s Genesis Manuscript.” Centre for Reception History
                            of the Bible, Trinity College, Oxford. 9 Feb. 2004.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William
                                Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1983.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the
                                Development of Blake’s Thought.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press,
                            1970.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Samuel Taylor Coleridge and the Fine Arts.</hi>
                            Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2008.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening: The Last Works of
                                William Blake.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2003.</p>
            <p>—, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Jerusalem. Blake’s
                            Illuminated Books, vol. 1. Princeton: Princeton University Press/Blake
                            Trust; London: Tate Gallery/Blake Trust, 1991.</p>
            <p>Palmer, Samuel. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer’s Sketch-Book,
                                1824.</hi> Introduction and commentary by Martin Butlin. 2 vols.
                            Clairvaux: Trianon Press for the William Blake Trust, 1962.</p>
            <p>Passavant, M. [Johann David]. <hi rend="i">Tour of a German Artist in
                                England: With Notices of Private Galleries, and Remarks on the State
                                of Art.</hi> [Trans. Elizabeth Rigby.] London: Saunders and Otley,
                            1836.</p>
            <p>Patenaude, Troy R. C. “‘The glory of a Nation’:
                            Recovering William Blake’s 1809 Exhibition.” <hi rend="i">British Art
Journal</hi> 4.1 (2003): 52-63.</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Creation of the</hi>
                            Songs <hi rend="i">from Manuscript to Illuminated Printing.</hi> London:
                            British Library; Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2000.</p>
            <p>Simon, Jacob. <hi rend="i">The Art of the Picture Frame: Artists, Patrons
                                and the Framing of Portraits in Britain.</hi> London: National
                            Portrait Gallery, 1996.</p>
            <p>Stalker, John, and George Parker. <hi rend="i">A Treatise of Japaning and
                                Varnishing.</hi> London, 1688.</p>
            <p>Stemmler, Joan K. “Cennino, Cumberland, Blake and Early Painting
                            Techniques.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 17.4 (spring 1984):
                            145-49.</p>
            <p>Stephenson, Jonathan. “Gilding—II. Uses 1.
                            Painting.” <hi rend="i">The Dictionary of Art.</hi> Ed. Jane
                            Turner. 34 vols. London: Macmillan, 1996. 12:625.</p>
            <p>[Swedenborg, Emanuel.] <hi rend="i">Arcana Coelestia: or Heavenly
                                Mysteries Contained in the Sacred Scriptures or Word of the Lord
                                Manifested and Laid Open; Beginning with the Book of Genesis
                                Interspersed with Relations of Wonderful Things Seen in the World of
                                Spirits and the Heaven of Angels Now First Translated from the
                                Original Latin of Emanuel Swedenborg by a Society of Gentlemen.</hi>
                            13 vols. London: Aurora Printing House, 1802-16.</p>
            <p>Townsend, Joyce H., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter at
                                Work.</hi> London: Tate Publishing, 2003; Princeton: Princeton
                            University Press, 2004.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi>
                            Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1993.</p>
            <p>Whitehead, Angus. “The Arlington Court Picture: A Surviving
                            Example of William Blake’s Framing Practice.” <hi rend="i">British Art
Journal</hi> 8.1 (2007): 30-33.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">“‘I also beg Mr Blakes acceptance of
                                my wearing apparel’</hi>: The Will of Henry Banes, Landlord
                            of 3 Fountain Court, Strand, the Last Residence of William and Catherine
                            Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 78-99.</p>
            <p>—. “‘my present precincts’: A Recreation and
                            Exploration of the Last Living and Working Space of William Blake, 3
                            Fountain Court, Strand, 1821-1827.” Master’s thesis.
                            University of York, 2002.</p>
            <p>—. “New Discoveries concerning William and Catherine Blake
                            in Nineteenth Century London: Residences, Fellow Inhabitants,
                            Neighbours, Friends and Milieux, 1803-1878.” PhD diss. 2 vols.
                            University of York, 2006.</p>
            <p>—. “No. 3 Fountain Court, Strand: William Blake’s
                            Last Residence, George Richmond’s Plan and an Unrecorded Letter
                            to John Linnell.” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 6.1
                            (2005): 21-30.</p>
            <p>—. “William Blake’s Subsidiary Design of a Dog in
                            His ‘Heads of the Poets’ Tempera of William Cowper (c.
                            1800-1803): An Identification.” <hi rend="i">Notes and
                                Queries</hi> ns 53.3 (Sept. 2006): 316-20.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">William Blake (1757-1827).</hi> [Exhibition] Organized by
                            the British Council: Paris—Antwerp—Zürich. London:
                            Tate Gallery, 1947.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The William Blake Archive.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves, Robert N.
                            Essick, and Joseph Viscomi.
                            &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;.</p>
            <p>Wornum, Ralph N., ed. <hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting, by the Royal
                                Academicians: Barry, Opie, and Fuseli.</hi> London: Henry Bohn,
                            1848.</p>
            <p>Wright, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols.
                            Olney: Thomas Wright, 1929.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
