<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>42.4.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Man Who Married the Blakes</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2009</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">42.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mark Crosby</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_42">
    <body>
      <pb id="p42-153" n="153"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Man Who Married the Blakes</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>ON 18 AUGUST 1782 William Blake and Catherine Boucher were married in St. Mary’s Church,
Battersea, an event that is commemorated by a stained glass window in the church today. The clergyman
officiating was the Rev. John Gardnor, who in the words of Alexander Gilchrist “was also an amateur artist
of note in his day” (35). Gilchrist treats Gardnor’s artistic career with considerable irony, but Gardnor
was actually a competent landscape artist and engraver who also had some interesting educational, political,
and literary associations.</p>
          <p>John Gardnor (b. 1728 or 1729) kept a drawing school at 13 Kensington Square from c. 1763 to
1770, evidently a successful one because it expanded into the adjoining numbers 12 and 11. From 1763 to 1767
and again in 1769 he exhibited at the Free Society of Artists, showing a total of more than two dozen
paintings and drawings of landscapes and of such popular subjects as Windsor Castle and Chepstow Castle,
Monmouthshire.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n28">1. This information is from Cust, from Hobhouse, and from Graves, <hi rend="i">Society of
Artists</hi> 100.</note></p>
          <p>After taking holy orders he gave up his drawing school and became curate, then vicar of
Battersea, becoming vicar in 1778 and remaining until his death in 1808. He was the only ordained clergyman of
the Church of England who was also a practicing artist at that time, for although he had given up his school
he had not given up painting. He began exhibiting at the Royal Academy in 1778 with two landscapes in oil, and
exhibited every year, with the exceptions of 1792 and 1794, through 1796 (Graves, <hi rend="i">Royal
Academy</hi> 3: 203). He also hoped to become chaplain to the Royal Academy upon the resignation of the
incumbent, the Rev. Matthew William Peters (Williamson 201). In 1789 and again in 1790 Gardnor applied for the
position, but unsuccessfully; it went to the Rt. Rev. Thomas Barnard, later Bishop of Limerick, in
1791.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n29">2. For this information I thank Andrew Potter, research assistant at the Royal Academy
Library.</note></p>
          <p>The subject matter of Gardnor’s exhibited pictures changed after 1787. Through that year his
locales had been in England and Wales, but in 1788 his two entries were <hi rend="i">The Castle of Rheinfels
at St. Goar, on the Rhine</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Castle of Ober Lahnstein, near the River Rhine.</hi> These
pictures were among the products of a trip to the Continent earlier that year, as were, with one exception,
the fourteen works Gardnor showed in the exhibitions of 1789-91. They were among the originals for aquatints,
the planned publication of which was announced in a booklet published in 1788: <hi rend="i">Proposals for
Publishing by Subscription, a Collection of Views, Taken on and near the River Rhine, at Aix la Chapelle, and
on the River Maese; By the Reverend John Gardnor: To Be Engraved in Acqua</hi> [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] 
<hi rend="i">Tinta, by R. Dodd.</hi> Here it was stated that “the picturesque Beauties of the River Rhine, have
long been subjects of admiration, though never produced to the public by the Painter or Engraver.” There
were to be eight numbers, each containing four prints 20 × 17 in. in size, and accompanying text. The price
was one guinea per number to subscribers, colored copies
            <figure n="secondview.42.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="427">
	<figTranscr>
              Drawn by the Revd. J.Gardnor<lb/>
              Engrav’d by the Rev. J Gardnor &amp; Rd. Gardnor Junr.<lb/>
              THE Second VIEW of EHRENBREITSTEIN CASTLE. | LA Seconde VUE du CHATEAU d’EHRENBREITSTEIN.
            </figTranscr>
	<head>1. <hi rend="i">The Second View of Ehrenbreitstein Castle.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>John and Richard Gardnor after John Gardnor. <hi rend="i">Views</hi> (1791), print opposite 106.
California History Section, California State Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="gatecologne.42.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="434">
	<figTranscr>
              Drawn by the Rev J.Gardnor<lb/>
              Engrav’d by the Rev J.Gardnor &amp; Rd. Gardnor Junr.<lb/>
              THE GATE of COLOGNE. | LA PORTE de COLOGNE.
            </figTranscr>
	<head>2. <hi rend="i">The Gate of Cologne.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>John and Richard Gardnor after John Gardnor. <hi rend="i">Views</hi> (1791), print opposite 122.
California History Section, California State Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p42-154" n="154"/>
three guineas, and subscribers were invited to send their names to Mr. Walter, Bookseller, Charing Cross. The
folio was issued in parts that year, with aquatints after Gardnor’s originals by engravers including John
and Elizabeth Fletcher, Dodd, J. S. Robinson, Richard Gardnor, Jr. (Gardnor’s nephew), and Gardnor himself.
The plates were then re-executed by the Gardnors in smaller size and published with the text in 1791. An
unillustrated volume consisting of text alone also appeared that year, with an impressive list of subscribers,
including the Lord Mayor, John Wilkes, Sir William Chambers, Joseph Farington, and Edward Burney.</p>
          <p>Gardnor’s characteristic views are of architecture—for the most part castles, abbeys, and
churches—in natural settings. Among these are Ehrenbreitstein Castle (illus. 1), also to be a subject for
Byron and for Turner,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">3</ref> and the gate of
Cologne (illus. 2). At the outset Gardnor tells us that he traveled on the Rhine because he needed “a change
of climate” for his health (1-2), and indeed his health problems are a running theme in his
narrative.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">4</ref> He also offers ample
reflections on his own art, as when he explains the differences between his two views of <corr type="emend">Rheinfels Castle</corr>
according to the light at the time of day when the view was taken. Another theme is political. In connection
with <hi rend="i">Ruin of the Abbey of Bingen</hi> he wrote in 1788: “It is, I think, impossible, for the
most indifferent observer to survey the original, without lamenting its destruction, execrating the ambition
of Kings, and deprecating the wanton barbarities of military executioners” (plate 2). This general sentiment
is particularized in 1791, where toward the end of the book Gardnor says, “Among the wonders of the present
period, not the least remarkable is that the army in France has generally and warmly declared for liberty”
(153). Gardnor had known Jacques-Pierre Brissot de Warville during Brissot’s residence in London during
February to November 1783 (Dybikowski 194), and this association may have prepared the way for his
pro-revolutionary sympathy. <note id="n30">3. Powell (21) shows that Turner was familiar with Gardnor’s 
<hi rend="i">Views</hi> before his own Rhine journey.</note>
	<note id="n31">4. Unless otherwise indicated, references are to the edition of 1788.</note></p>
          <p>In 1793 the subjects of Gardnor’s RA exhibition pictures changed again, to one view of Wales
and three of Monmouthshire. He must by then have had in mind the illustrations to be provided for his friend
David Williams’s <hi rend="i">History of Monmouthshire</hi> (1796), engraved by Gardnor and J. Hill in 1793.
Williams, a prolific writer on religious and political subjects,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n32" type="note">5</ref> was also a supporter of the French Revolution in its early days, and another
link between the two men was that both were among the original members of the Royal Literary Fund, set up in
1790 to help destitute writers (and still existing today). Among the thirty-six plates Gardnor furnished were
views of Abergavenny Castle, Caerleon Castle, and Tintern Abbey, the last unusual in showing the abbey from
the north with everyday commercial activities on the river. Williams’s voluminous text includes translations
from Welsh manuscripts by Edward Williams, a translation of a poem by the bard Gyffyd Llwd, and an excerpt
from the “Sabrina” passage of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> headed “Milton’s Description of the Severn.”
Gardnor and Williams later had a falling-out about this venture. “Since that work was published,” noted
Farington, “Williams &amp; Gardnor have quarreled about the profits of the work.—Gardner 
[<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] professing to understand that Williams undertook to assist him as a 
<hi rend="i">friend</hi>, the other declaring that He looked for a reward” (<hi rend="i">Diary</hi> 4: 1406, 22
June 1800). <note id="n32">5. Erdman draws a parallel between an aspect of Blake’s political thought and
Williams’s (224). “David Williams . . . made diagrams showing no constitution healthy in which the 
<hi rend="i">senses</hi> of the body politic, i.e., the common people from whom all political ideas must flow to
the ‘head,’ were barred from political participation.” He cites Williams, <hi rend="i">Letters to a
Young Prince</hi> (London, 1791) 47, 73.</note></p>
          <p>One curious aspect of Gardnor’s career is represented by his <hi rend="i">Plan of the Academy,
at Battersea, in Surry</hi>, which the British Library catalogue conjectures to have been published in 1790.
It is difficult to see how he could have been able to fulfill his duties as a vicar, pursue his artistic
activities, and found a school at the same time, but this eight-page pamphlet speaks of the academy not as a
theoretical project but as a school “kept by” him. The author begins by saying that it is necessary to
have only a small number of students in order for the master “to attend to the Temper, Genius, and
Disposition, of every Individual” (1), and more than half the pamphlet is devoted to the importance of
“cultivating the Arts of Reading, Writing, and Speaking, our own Language with Energy and Propriety” (5).
Greek and Latin are “taught with equal Care and Assiduity,” as is French; among other subjects are
mathematics, geography, music, and fencing, all taught by resident masters. Did this academy actually exist?
Or is it an ideal academy written of as if it did exist?</p>
          <p>There is no evidence that William Blake and John Gardnor met again after August 1782, although
both showed pictures at the Royal Academy exhibitions of 1784 and 1785. Nevertheless, it is both interesting
and appropriate that the man who married the Blakes was both an artist and an early supporter of the French
Revolution.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Cust, L. H. “Gardnor, John (1728/9-1808).” Rev. Nicholas Grindle. <hi rend="i">Oxford
Dictionary of National Biography.</hi> Oxford University Press online ed., January 2008.
&lt;http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/10378&gt;. Accessed 2 June 2008.</p>
            <p>Dybikowski, J. <hi rend="i">On Burning Ground: An Examination of the Ideas, Projects and Life
of David Williams.</hi> Studies on Voltaire and the Eighteenth Century, no. 307. Oxford: Voltaire Foundation,
1993.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire.</hi> 2nd ed. Princeton: Princeton
University Press, 1969.</p>
            <p>Farington, Joseph. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi> Ed. Kenneth Garlick, Angus
D. Macintyre, and Kathryn Cave. 16 vols. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1978-1984.</p>
            <pb id="p42-155" n="155"/>
            <p>Gardnor, John. <hi rend="i">Hints of Occurrences on a Tour to Manheim, Mayence, Aix la
Chapelle, Brussels, etc. with Explanations of Views Taken on and near the Rivers Rhine, Maese, etc.</hi>
London: R. Noble, 1791.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Plan of the Academy, at Battersea, in Surry, Kept by the Rev. John
Gardnor.</hi> [London, 1790?].</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Views Taken on and near the River Rhine, at Aix la Chapelle, and on the River
Maese . . . Engraved in Aqua Tinta by Will<hi rend="s">m</hi> and Elizabe<hi rend="s">th</hi> Ellis.</hi>
London: W. Ellis and J. Walter, 1788.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Views Taken on and near the River Rhine, at Aix la Chapelle, and on the River
Maese . . . Engraved in Aqua Tinta by the Rev.<hi rend="s">nd</hi> J. Gardnor, and Richard Gardnor,
Jun.</hi><hi rend="s">r</hi>. London: J. Walter et al., 1791.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Ruthven Todd. Rev. ed.
London: J. M. Dent, 1945.</p>
            <p>Graves, Algernon. <hi rend="i">The Royal Academy of Arts: A Complete Dictionary of Contributors
. . . from Its Foundation in 1769 to 1904.</hi> 8 vols. 1905-06. New York: Burt Franklin, 1972.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Society of Artists of Great Britain, 1760-1791; The Free Society of
Artists, 1761-1783: A Complete Dictionary of Contributors and Their Work from the Foundation of the Societies
to 1791.</hi> London: G. Bell and Sons, 1907.</p>
            <p>Hobhouse, Hermione, ed. “Kensington Square and Environs: Individual Houses (South Side).”
<hi rend="i">Survey of London: Volume 42: Kensington Square to Earl’s Court.</hi> 1986. 16-29. 
<hi rend="i">British History Online.</hi> &lt;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=50305/&gt;.
Accessed 2 June 2008.</p>
            <p>Lysons, Daniel. “Battersea.” <hi rend="i">The Environs of London: Volume 1: County of
Surrey.</hi> 1792. 26-48. <hi rend="i">British History Online.</hi>
&lt;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=45371&gt;. Accessed 6 June 2008.</p>
            <p>Powell, Cecilia. <hi rend="i">Turner’s Rivers of Europe: The Rhine, Meuse and Mosel.</hi>
London: Tate Gallery, 1991.</p>
            <p>Williams, David. <hi rend="i">The History of Monmouthshire; Illustrated and Ornamented by Views
of Its Principal Landscapes, Ruins and Residences; by John Gardnor, Vicar of Battersea London.</hi> London: D.
Baldwin, 1796.</p>
            <p>Williamson, George C. <hi rend="i">Life and Works of Ozias Humphry, R.A.</hi> London: John
Lane, 1918.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
