<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>42.4.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake in the Marketplace, 2008</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2009</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">42.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mark Crosby</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_42">
    <body>
    <pb id="p42-116" n="116"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-42-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake in the Marketplace, 2008</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor><gap type="emend"/></byline>
          <p>A STEADY STREAM of significant works by Blake and his circle continued to flow through the
marketplace in 2008. A clipping of the design only from the second plate of “Spring” (<hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence</hi> pl. 23) changed hands twice. A tempera painting, <hi rend="i">The Flight into Egypt</hi>
(illus. 4), three drawings, and Blake’s rare “Enoch” lithograph made their way through the auction
rooms. Two watercolors, a pencil sketch (one of the auctioned drawings), a monochrome wash drawing, and a
manuscript were offered by dealers. Only the lithograph attracted much interest, as described below. The poor
condition of <hi rend="i">The Flight into Egypt</hi>, typical of Blake’s early temperas, and multiple layers
of restoration undermined its chances at auction. John Windle, acting on my behalf, was probably the only
bidder. The painting, with an estimate of £100,000-200,000, achieved £95,000 (£115,250 with the buyer’s
premium), presumably against the reserve. To put this price in proper perspective, the lot immediately
preceding, Jean-Antoine Watteau’s <hi rend="i">La Surprise</hi>, a painting about the same size as
Blake’s, fetched £12,361,250 on an estimate of £3-5 million.</p>
          <p>Libby Howie, the London art dealer who in 2002 acquired nineteen of Blake’s watercolors
illustrating Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> on behalf of Marburg Ltd., told Windle on 1 May that
<hi rend="i">The Gambols of Ghosts According with Their Affections Previous to the Final Judgment</hi>, one of
the designs that had failed to sell at auction in New York on 2 May 2006, was “no longer
available.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> I assume that this means
it has been sold, probably to a private collector. I acquired another of the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
watercolors from the unsold group, <hi rend="i">The Death of the Good Old Man</hi>, in June (illus. 1-2).
Marburg, headquartered in Tortola, British Virgin Islands, retains legal title to three of the 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors: <hi rend="i">Whilst Surfeited upon Thy Damask Cheek, The Descent of Man into
the Vale of Death</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Counseller, King, Warrior, Mother and Child, in the Tomb.</hi>
These remain in London with Howie under “bond”—meaning that they are physically in Britain but have not
been officially imported into the country after their attempted sale in New York. This means that an external
purchaser does not need to go through the UK’s fine-arts export procedure, with its potential for a
temporary hold and a matching offer from a British resident or institution. Color reproductions of the 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors are available in the William Blake Archive
&lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;. <note id="n1">1. In “Blake in the Marketplace, 2005,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 154, I reported that Howie had sold the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
watercolors to “Marburg BVI, a Swiss corporation,” in February 2005. I now think it probable that Marburg
was Howie’s financial backer, and the legal owner of the designs, since their sale in 2002. The private
investor(s) represented by Marburg remain unknown to me. For the 2 May 2006 auction at SNY, see E. B. Bentley,
“<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> Indignities: Greed, Hucksterism, and Oblivion: Blake’s Watercolors for Blair’s
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.2 (fall 2006): 66-71; and <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.4
(spring 2007): 116-17, 120-26.</note></p>
          <p>Windle, in association with Henry Sotheran Ltd., offered a selling exhibition of Blake materials
at Sotheran’s handsome bookshop on Sackville Street, London, in June. The opening on 3 June included a
presentation by the novelist Tracy Chevalier. The catalogue, <hi rend="i">William Blake: An Exhibition of
Prints, Books and Facsimiles</hi>, appeared online and in letterpress, with all entries illustrated (at least
in part) in color in both versions. Some of the items on offer had appeared in Windle’s earlier catalogues,
but all the original works are listed below under the designation “Windle/Sotheran” for the sake of
completeness. Highlights included a pencil sketch, <hi rend="i">Paolo and Francesca</hi>, and the impression
of the design from the second plate of “Spring.”</p>
          <p>Larkhall Fine Art of Bath held a selling exhibition from 11 July to 13 September entitled Samuel
Palmer: His Friends and His Influence. No catalogue was issued; only a bare-bones list of prints without
prices appeared on Larkhall’s web site &lt;http://www.larkhall.com&gt;. The works on display are briefly
noted in the lists below.</p>
          <p>In mid-October Windle acquired for stock the Blake reference library assembled by Roger and Kay
Easson that at one time belonged to the American Blake Foundation. The most important work, now in the
Victoria University Library, was a copy of Bray’s <hi rend="i">Life of Stothard</hi> extra-illustrated and
extended to ten volumes quarto. A small group of Blake’s commercial book illustrations, removed from their
bibliographic contexts, came from the same source. Windle intends to issue a sale catalogue of the collection
in 2009.</p>
          <p>On 15 October Windle received a letter from Richard Lloyd, head of the print department at
Christie’s London. Lloyd stated that he would offer at auction “a rare Blake” on 2 December, invited
Windle to view this treasure on display in New York in late October, and did not identify the object further.
Windle called Christie’s on 16 October and learned from Lloyd that his letter was referring to the
impression of the “Enoch” lithograph in Raymond Lister’s collection from 1972 to 1985. Interest in this
print extends beyond the small band of major Blake collectors because it is among the rarest “incunabula”
in the history of lithography. Condition problems with the impression on offer may have been the reason that
no lithography specialists ventured beyond the low estimate of £40,000. Subsequent bidding was a contest
between Windle, acting on my behalf, and the Chicago husband and wife who
<pb id="p42-117" n="117"/>
have assembled the finest private collection of Blake’s illuminated books. “Enoch” was knocked down to
Windle at a hammer bid of £80,000 (£97,250 with the buyer’s premium). I suspect that this is a record for
a British lithograph. In the same auction of Old Master prints, an exceptionally fine impression of
Rembrandt’s engraving and drypoint, “Christ Crucified between Two Thieves,” sold for £421,250.</p>
          <p>The Blake market has yet to register the full effects of the rolling financial crises that began
in September 2008. History suggests that the art and book market is a trailing indicator in such
circumstances, with a lag time of six to twelve months. As prices fall and lots fail at auction, the supply of
materials begins to dry up as potential sellers wait for better times and better prices. There may be fewer
important works on offer in 2009 than in 2008—unless forced onto the market by what auctioneers call “the
three Ds” (death, divorce, debt).</p>
          <p>I have subscribed to all relevant auction catalogues issued by Bloomsbury, Christie’s,
Sotheby’s, and Swann for many years. These printed catalogues have become increasingly expensive; at the
same time, the searchable online versions have become timely, detailed, and thoroughly illustrated. In summer
2008 I began to end my subscriptions and to rely on the online versions. The 2009 sales review will be based
on internet catalogues for all auctions.</p>
          <p>The year of all sales and catalogues in the following lists is 2008 unless indicated otherwise.
Dates for online dealers’ catalogues are the dates accessed, not the dates of publication. Works offered
online and previously listed in either of the last two sales reviews are not repeated here. All listings on EB
are illustrated in color unless noted otherwise. Most of the auction houses add their purchaser’s surcharge
to the hammer price in their price lists. These net amounts are given here, following the official price
lists. The value-added tax levied against the buyer’s surcharge in Britain is not included. Late 2008 sales
will be covered in the 2009 review. I am grateful for help in compiling this review to G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
David Bindman, Martin Butlin, Harriet Drummond, Jessica Gormley, Robin Hamlyn, Alan Jutzi, Jenijoy La Belle,
Richard Lloyd, Nicholas Lott, Christopher Mendez, Morton Paley, Anthony Payne, John Sutherland, Robert Tear,
David Weinglass, and John Windle. My special thanks go to Alexander Gourlay for his generosity in keeping me
abreast of internet auctions. Once again, Sarah Jones’s editorial expertise and John Sullivan’s electronic
imaging have been invaluable.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Abbreviations</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <table rows="24" cols="2">
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977). Plate
numbers and copy designations for Blake’s illuminated books follow <hi rend="i">BB.</hi></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">BBS</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P,
1995)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>BH</cell>
                <cell>Bonhams, auctioneers, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>BL</cell>
                <cell>Bloomsbury Auctions, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>BNY</cell>
                <cell>Bloomsbury Auctions, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)</cell>
                <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. (New
Haven: Yale UP, 2004)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Butlin</cell>
                <cell>Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 2 vols.
(New Haven: Yale UP, 1981)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>cat.</cell>
                <cell>catalogue or sales list issued by a dealer (usually followed by a number or letter
designation)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">CB</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1991)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CL</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CNY</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>CSK</cell>
                <cell>Christie’s, South Kensington</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>E</cell>
                <cell><hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman,
newly rev. ed. (New York: Anchor-Random House, 1988)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>EB</cell>
                <cell>eBay online auctions</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>GL</cell>
                <cell>Gorringes, auctioneers, Lewes, Sussex</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>illus.</cell>
                <cell>the item or part thereof is reproduced in the catalogue</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>PBA</cell>
                <cell>Pacific Book Auction Galleries, San Francisco</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>pl(s).</cell>
                <cell>plate(s)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>SL</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s, London</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>SNY</cell>
                <cell>Sotheby’s, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">SP</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi>
(Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>st(s).</cell>
                <cell>state(s) of an engraving, etching, or lithograph</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Swann</cell>
                <cell>Swann, auctioneers, New York</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>#</cell>
                <cell>auction lot or catalogue item number</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Illuminated Books</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>“Spring,” 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> pl. (pl. 23 from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>),
trimmed to the design below the text, 2.8 × 7.5 cm. Color printed with hand coloring. Windle/Sotheran, June
cat., #54, on consignment from Roger and Kay Easson (£60,500). Acquired from the Eassons by Windle in Sept.
for stock and sold in Oct. to the Victoria University Library, Toronto. Previously offered by Windle in his
Nov. 2006 cat. 42, #76, on consignment, illus. color (price on request). For illus. and comments, see 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.4 (spring 2007): 119.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Drawings and Paintings</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">Cumea</hi>, a copy, attributed to Blake, of Michelangelo’s fresco of the Cumean
Sibyl in the Sistine Chapel. Watercolor, 17.0 × 12.0 cm., study of 1 of Michelangelo’s 
<hi rend="i">ignudi</hi> on the verso. Arader Galleries, May online cat., dating the work to “1773,” recto
illus. color ($90,000). Not discovered until 2002 and thus not in Butlin. Previously offered SL, 28 Nov. 2002,
#236, dated to “circa 1773,” recto illus. color (£14,340). For illus. and discussion, see 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): front cover, 116-17, 119, 120.</p>
            <pb id="p42-118" n="118"/>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Death of the Good Old Man.</hi> Pen and ink and watercolor over traces of
pencil, 20.1 × 25.8 cm. Datable to 1805. Acquired June by Essick from Marburg Ltd., Libby Howie (for Marburg)
and John Windle (for Essick) acting as agents. Previously offered SNY, 2 May 2006, #14 (bought in at $420,000;
estimate $550,000-700,000). Not discovered until 2001 and thus not in Butlin. See comments on the 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors in the prefatory essay, above, and illus. 1-3.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Flight into Egypt.</hi> Tempera on canvas, 27.2 × 38.3 cm., inscribed “inv
/ WB 179[9?]” lower right. Butlin #404. CL, 8 July, #22, from the collection of the late George Goyder,
illus. color (£115,250 to John Windle acting for Essick). See comments in the prefatory essay, above, and
illus. 4.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Gambols of Ghosts According with Their Affections Previous to the Final
Judgment.</hi> Watercolor, 26.9 × 20.7 cm. Apparently sold no later than April by Marburg Ltd., probably to a
private collector. Previously offered SNY, 2 May 2006, #12 (bought in at $520,000; estimate
$700,000-1,000,000). Not discovered until 2001 and thus not in Butlin. See comments on the 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors in the prefatory essay, above; for illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 35.3
(winter 2001-02): 69.</p>
            <figure n="butwba10.1.14.wc" id="butwba10.1.wc.14" work-copy="butwba10.1" rend="db" width="958" height="754">
              <figTranscr>
                THE<lb/>
                NEW<lb/>
                TESTAMENT
              </figTranscr>
              <head>1. <hi rend="i">The Death of the Good Old Man.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Pen and ink and watercolor over traces of pencil, 20.1 × 25.8 cm. Datable to 1805.
Essick collection. An illustration for R. H. Cromek’s 1808 edition of Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The
Grave.</hi> See also illus. 2-3.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="i">Paolo and Francesca(?).</hi> Pencil, approx. 19.0 × 11.0 cm. on leaf 21.3 × 37.4
cm. Butlin #816, dating the drawing to c. 1824-27. BH, 11 March, #26, illus. color (£8880 to John Windle for
stock; estimate £6000-9000). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #55 (£38,000). Sold Sept. by Windle to Maurice
Sendak, Connecticut. For illus. and comments, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.4 (spring 2008): front cover,
140, 147, 148.</p>
            <pb id="p42-119" n="119"/>
            <figure n="OldManB08" rend="file" width="958" height="763">
              <figTranscr>
                THE<lb/>
                NEW<lb/>
                TESTAMENT
              </figTranscr>
              <head>2. <hi rend="i">The Death of the Good Old Man.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>The digital image has been electronically manipulated in Adobe Photoshop by John
Sullivan of the Huntington Library to erase accidental blemishes. The most prominent of these, visible in
illus. 1, are the light coffee-colored stain descending vertically (lower right) across the midpoint of the
dead man’s lower legs, a similar but much smaller stain about 4 cm. to the left, and another coffee-colored
vertical line running across the midpoint of the man’s forearm. A few small flaws, probably the result of
aging rather than spillage, have also been removed.<lb/>
<lb/>
A comparison of illus. 1 and 2 demonstrates how digital imaging can assist in making decisions about the
cleaning or conservation of a work of art. The drawing appears to be stable, with little if any accretion of
problems emerging from the backing mat. Thus, the major considerations are aesthetic. Would the watercolor
look better if successfully cleaned? Certainly it would, but would the improvement be worth the effort? There
are always risks involved in cleaning a delicate watercolor. The drawing could not be treated without removal
from the backing mat; the safest way to do this would be to peel away the mat, layer by layer. The original
mat and its framing lines are, however, significant historical documents that should be preserved. Thus, the
drawing and its mat would require immersion in water to float them apart. All things considered, I decided not
to take any action at this point. To my eyes, illus. 2 does not show sufficient visual improvement to justify
an attempt to clean the original. Other collectors or curators might come to a different conclusion.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p42-120" n="120"/>
            <figure n="bb435.1.11-10.com" id="bb435.1.comdes.11" work-copy="bb435.1" rend="db" width="958" height="839">
              <figTranscr>
                THE<lb/>
                NEW<lb/>
                TESTAMENT<lb/>
                Drawn by W. Blake.<lb/>
                Etched by L. Schiavonetti.<lb/>
                The Death of The Good Old Man.<lb/>
                ...............Sure the last end<lb/>
                Of the good Man is peace!    How calm His exit!<lb/>
                London Published May 1st. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.
              </figTranscr>
              <head>3. “The Death of the Good Old Man.”</head>
              <figDesc>Etching/engraving by Louis Schiavonetti after Blake. Second published state as printed
for the 1808 quarto issue of Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> Image 20.3 × 26.0 cm., platemark 23.9
× 27.6 cm. Essick collection. A comparison of this print with Blake’s watercolor (illus. 1-2) shows how
faithfully Schiavonetti followed his model, particularly if one allows for the intrinsic differences between
the two media. In the watercolor, Blake makes a telling difference between the lined, perhaps shrunken, right
hand of the old man’s material body in the lower half of the composition and the more youthful hands of the
spiritual body guided heavenward by angels. Schiavonetti renders this distinction, with only partial success,
by executing hatching strokes over the material hand while leaving the right hand unshaded in the figure
above.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p42-121" n="121"/>
            <figure n="but404.1.1.pt" id="but404.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="671">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB 179</figTranscr>
              <head>4. <hi rend="i">The Flight into Egypt.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Tempera on canvas, 27.2 × 38.3 cm., inscribed “inv / WB 179[9?]” lower right.
Essick collection. Butlin #404. The picture takes its subject from Matthew 2.13-14. Although the painting is
now darkened with age, Blake executed the design as a night scene, as specified in the Bible and indicated in
the picture by the crescent moon above and to the left of the Virgin’s head. Motifs are illuminated
principally by the light emanating from the Christ child in anticipation of what he would later say of
himself, “I am the light of the world” (John 9.5). Joseph stands on the left, partly behind the donkey’s
head, and looks back at his wife and child. The family is attended by six putti arrayed around the Virgin and
three winged angels, two on the right and one left of Joseph. An “angel of the Lord” appears to Joseph in
a dream and tells him to “flee into Egypt” (Matthew 2.13), but there is no indication in the Bible that
the family is accompanied by angels during its journey. Sky-borne putti and large guardian or guiding angels
are, however, traditional in portrayals of the scene—see, for example, the etchings and engravings based on
designs by Cherubino Alberti, Sébastien Bourdon, Jacob Jordaens, J. B. van Loo (engraved by Laurent Cars),
Claude Lorrain, Richard van Orley, Martin Schongauer, G. D. Tiepolo, and Marten de Vos. Hendrik Goudt’s
famous engraving, “The Flight into Egypt” (1613), based on a painting by Adam Elsheimer, is a very dark
night scene illuminated by a full moon. An avid print collector in his youth, Blake was very probably familiar
with these or similar works from the fifteenth through the eighteenth centuries.<lb/>
Roger E. Fry describes this tempera as follows:<lb/>
<q>The Flight into Egypt will at once recall Giotto’s treatment of the subject in the Arena chapel at Padua;
but the likeness is, in a sense, deceptive, for Giotto was working away from Byzantinism as fast as Blake was
working towards it, and the two pass one another on the road. For there is here but little of Giotto’s
tender human feeling, less still of his robust rationalism; what they have in common, what Blake rediscovered
and Giotto inherited, is the sentiment of supernatural dignity, the hieratic solemnity and superhuman
purposefulness of the gestures. Even more than in Giotto’s version, the Virgin here sits on the ass as
though enthroned in monumental state, her limbs fixed in the rigid symmetry which oriental art has used to
express complete withdrawal from the world of sense. No less perfect in its expressiveness of the strange and
exalted mood is the movement, repeated with such impressive monotony, in the figures of Joseph and the
archangel. It is absurd, we think, to deny to the man who discovered the lines of these figures the power of
draughtsmanship. Since Giotto’s day scarcely any one has drawn thus—simplification has been possible only
as the last effort of consummate science refining away the superfluous; but here the simplification of the
forms is the result of an instinctive passionate reaching out for the direct symbol of the idea. . . . Of this
language of symbolic form in which the spirit communicates its most secret and indefinable impulses Blake was
an eloquent and persuasive master. He could use it, too, to the most diverse ends; and though the sublimity
which is based upon dread came most readily to his mind, he could express, as we have seen in the Flight into
Egypt, the sublimity of divine introspection. (“Three Pictures in Tempera by William Blake,” 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 4 [1904]: supplement 205-06, reprinted in Fry, <hi rend="i">Vision and
Design</hi> [London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1920] 142-43)</q>
Few art historians today would deploy rhetoric like Fry’s; his comments, however, successfully place the
painting’s style in a grand historical context to highlight important dimensions of the sensibility Blake
expresses through his biblical paintings and drawings.<lb/>
The tempera was restored between 1863 and 1880 and again between 1904, when W. Graham Robertson acquired it,
and 1907. Stanley William Littlejohn of the British Museum probably undertook this second restoration. The
painting was restored for a third time by Johann Hell c. 1950 after George Goyder acquired it at the auction
of Robertson’s collection on 22 July 1949. The illustration accompanying Fry’s essay in 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> and several later reproductions show a large crack, above and to the right
of the Virgin’s head, now no longer visible. In spite of these efforts, <hi rend="i">The Flight into
Egypt</hi> retains many of the condition problems, including cracking and “cupping” (depressions in the
paint with surrounding ridges), common to Blake’s temperas of 1799-1800. Further conservation may be
necessary; the paint surface lower right is unstable.
                            </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p42-122" n="122"/>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Resurrection</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Last Trumpet</hi> (recto), with studies
of eyes, the head of an eagle, a human face, and a lion (verso). Recto datable to c. 1780-85; some of the
verso sketches related to Blake’s 1802 <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi> by William Hayley.
Pen and gray ink, gray wash over pencil (recto), pencil (verso), recto image and sheet 20.5 × 21.2 cm. Butlin
#617 (listed as untraced since 1922). W/S Fine Art, July cat., <hi rend="i">British Works on Paper</hi>, #10,
illus. color (£220,000). Previously sold SL, 4 July 2002, #183 (£144,150 to Agnew’s); offered several
times since by Agnew’s and W/S Fine Art. For illus. and comments, see Martin Butlin, “A Blake Drawing
Rediscovered and Redated,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 34.1 (summer 2000): cover and 22-24; and 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 121 (misidentified as Butlin #610). For a preliminary study, see 
<hi rend="i">The Resurrection of the Dead</hi>, next entry below.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Resurrection of the Dead.</hi> Pencil, 17.5 × 24.0 cm., datable to c.
1780-85, inscribed by Frederick Tatham. Butlin #79. SL, 4 Dec., #120, illus. color (£3500 to John Windle for
stock). Previously sold CL, 17 Nov. 1992, #16, illus. (£7150 to Salander-O’Reilly Gallery, New York).
Similar to, and probably a preliminary study for, <hi rend="i">The Resurrection</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Last
Trumpet</hi>, listed immediately above. For illus., see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 26.4 (spring 1993): 141.</p>
            <figure n="ethelbert.42.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="372">
              <head>5. <hi rend="i">St. Augustine Converting King Ethelbert of Kent.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Watercolor, 13.3 × 18.4 cm., datable to c. 1779. Butlin #57. Ethelbert sits on the
left holding a book (of laws?); an attendant holding keys (to the kingdom?) stands behind him. St. Augustine
is probably the tonsured ecclesiastic far right, the index finger of his left hand pointing upward to indicate
heavenly matters in his conversation with the king, whose left index finger points toward Augustine and
slightly downward (to worldly matters?). According to the early accounts, Ethelbert insisted that the meeting
be held outdoors (see Bede’s <hi rend="i">Historia ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum</hi>, very probably the
source for later historians such as Milton, Rapin de Thoyras, and Hume). The background drapery and pole (the
latter above and to the left of the king’s head) suggest that Blake has placed the event inside a
tent—unless this is simply a background curtain like the one in the second plate of “A Cradle Song” in
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> A much larger pencil sketch of the same subject is in the Rosenwald
Collection, National Gallery of Art, Washington (Butlin #58, dating the drawing to c. 1793).<lb/>
<lb/>
This is one of Blake’s nine small watercolors (eight traced) of c. 1779 picturing major events in English
history. These may have been the basis for “The History of England, a small book of Engravings” Blake
listed in his advertisement “To the Public” of October 1793 (E 693). No copy of that book, or any
engraving from it, has ever been found. In the design reproduced here, three figures gesture prominently with
their left hands. If Blake had copied the composition onto a copperplate without reversing it, impressions
would show right-hand gestures. Photo courtesy of David Tunick.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="i">St. Augustine Converting King Ethelbert of Kent.</hi> Watercolor, 13.3 × 18.4
cm., datable to c. 1779. Butlin #57. Acquired in 1978 from Colnaghi’s, London, by Neil Phillips, Montreal
(and later Montpelier, Virginia); by inheritance c. 2007 to a private owner; on consignment with the New York
dealer David Tunick by Jan. 2008 ($135,000). See illus. 5.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Two Studies of a Baby’s Head.</hi> Pencil, with touches of watercolor on the
lower head, leaf 37.4 × 26.2 cm. Butlin #788, dating the drawing to c. 1820. BH, 11 March, #27, illus. color
(£10,800; estimate £10,000-15,000). Acquired by a private collector, London. For illus. and comments, see
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.4 (spring 2008): 140, 147, 149.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Manuscripts</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Letter of 18 Jan. 1808 to Ozias Humphry, 4 pp. describing Blake’s <hi rend="i">Last
Judgment</hi> design. Returned to the dealer Roy Davids by a private customer who acquired the manuscript from
Davids in late 2002; offered by Davids to John Windle in Oct. (£55,000; Windle declined). Previously offered
Davids, March 2000 cat. for “The Artist as a Portrait” exhibition and sale
<pb id="p42-123" n="123"/>
(3-14 April 2000) at the Fine Art Society, London, #10, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> and last pp. illus. (£40,000).
Previously sold SNY, 14 Dec. 1988, #58 ($26,400 to the dealer John Wilson); SL, 14 Dec. 1992, #16, 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> p. illus. (£18,000, apparently to Davids).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Separate Plates and Plates in Series</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>“Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims.” Skinner auction, Boston, 7 March, #2028, 5<hi
rend="s">th</hi> st., probably a Sessler impression, “laid down, loss to corner u[pper] r[ight], toning and
staining,” illus. color online ($2700). Swann, 1 May, #286, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., laid India, very
probably a Colnaghi impression, “wide (full?) margins,” illus. color ($5400). Windle/Sotheran, June cat.,
#1, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., Colnaghi impression on laid India “mounted on heavy wove” (£15,500).</p>
            <p>Dante engravings. Swann, 1 May, #291, pl. 5 only, laid India, illus. color ($5400).
Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #21-25, pls. 1, 2, 4-6 offered individually, laid India (£10,500 for pl. 1,
others £4500-9000 each); #67, complete set, laid India, original label, later morocco case (£37,500). CNY,
31 July, #1, pl. 6 only, creases and soiling, laid India lifting in places, the same impression offered CNY,
30 Oct. 2007, #157 (not sold; estimate $6000-8000), illus. color ($1500). Swann, 31 Oct., #82, pl. 3 only,
laid India, illus. (not sold; estimate $10,000-15,000).</p>
            <p>“Enoch,” modified lithograph. CL, 2 Dec., #61, <hi rend="i">SP</hi> impression 1D, sheet
22.4 × 32.0 cm., repaired tear across the top left corner, the brown paper discolored to a lighter hue in
both top corners, small surface abrasion just inside the right center margin, tiny nick at the lower sheet
edge, framed, illus. color (£97,250 to John Windle acting for Essick; estimate £40,000-60,000). One of 4
recorded impressions, previously sold from Raymond Lister’s collection, SL, 11 Dec. 1985, #299, illus. color
(£28,600 to Laurence Witten, a Connecticut book dealer probably acting on behalf of a private collector). The
discoloration of the top corners was not present when this impression was sold at auction in 1985; I suspect
that the glue attaching the print to the present backing leaf caused (and perhaps is continuing to cause) this
problem. The auction cat. claims that Blake etched “away parts of the lithographic stone.” I know of no
evidence for this. George Cumberland’s description of Blake’s process on the verso of <hi rend="i">SP</hi>
impression 1B does not mention any etching, even though a shallow etch was conventional in early British
lithography. In <hi rend="i">SP</hi> p. 57, I speculate that a slight relief effect may have been produced by
Blake’s use of “asphaltum” (Cumberland), rather than conventional lithographic ink, to draw the design.
For illus. of this impression and comments, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 20.1 (summer 1986): 13, 19, 20. For
the dating of the work to 1806-07, see Essick, “Dating Blake’s ‘Enoch’ Lithograph Once Again,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 22.2 (fall 1988): 71-73.</p>
            <p>“The Fall of Rosamond,” after Stothard, 1783. EB, Jan., printed in sanguine, 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> st. (with the period after “Sculpt.”), trimmed close to the circular image with only the
signatures remaining among the inscriptions (£511 to John Windle for stock; sold Feb. to the Victoria
University Library, Toronto).</p>
            <p>“George Cumberland’s Card.” EB, Feb., printed in “brown ink” (according to the
vendor, Chandler and Reed Rare Books of Sunderland, Massachusetts) on laid paper with a partial watermark
(“17,” as in <hi rend="i">SP</hi> impression 1Z), leaf 9.5 × 15.2 cm., stained around the edges of the
leaf ($3650—probably a record auction price). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #69, printed in black ink on a
card pasted into a copy of George Cumberland, Jr., <hi rend="i">Bristol Beauties 1848</hi> (£10,300). For
more information on the Windle/Sotheran impression, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.4 (spring 2008): 163.</p>
            <p>Job engravings. Larkhall Fine Art, Dec. 2007 online cat., pls. numbered 2 and 3 only, 1826
printing on Whatman paper after removal of the “Proof” inscription, illus. color (£2750 each). Quaritch,
Dec. 2007 private offer, complete set, 1826 printing on Whatman paper after removal of the “Proof”
inscription, leaves trimmed to 30.0 × 24.5 cm. (untrimmed copies measure about 38.5 × 28.0 cm.), occasional
light browning,
<pb id="p42-124" n="124"/>
contemporary calf rebacked (£30,000); same copy, Feb. Los Angeles Book Fair ($60,000); same copy, Feb. cat.
1364, #17, illus. color (£30,000); same copy, March cat. for the New York Book Fair, #12 ($60,000). Swann, 1
May, 4 pls. offered individually, all on laid India, the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> lot probably the 1874 printing,
the others published “Proof” impressions of 1826, all illus. color: #287, pl. numbered 4 ($1500); #288,
pl. numbered 6 ($3600); #289, pl. numbered 11 ($4400); #290, pl. numbered 21 ($1800). Windle/Sotheran, June
cat., 1874 printing on laid India, pls. offered individually as follows: #2-18, title p. and pls. numbered 1,
3-10, 12, 13, 16-20 (£1200-1800 each); #19, pl. numbered 5, 1826 “Proof” printing on so-called
“French” paper (£1700); #20, pl. numbered 19, 1826 “Proof” printing on “French” paper (£2300);
#62, complete set, 1826 “Proof” impressions on laid India, the pls. “appear to have been professionally
cleaned,” later full morocco (£38,500; acquired by the book dealer Colin Franklin). Larkhall Fine Art,
July-Sept. exhibit, pl. numbered 21 only (price on request). Aspire Auctions, Cleveland, 11 Sept., #117, pl.
numbered 21 only, no description of the printing or paper but apparently an impression on Whatman paper after
the removal of the “Proof” inscription, illus. color online ($1408.75). Swann, 18 Sept., #1, complete set,
1826 printing on Whatman paper after removal of the “Proof” inscription, “paper wrappers with the
publisher’s label pasted on the front cover,” 8 pls. illus. color ($40,800 to Sims Reed for stock). GL, 23
Oct., #1091, pl. numbered 15 only, “Proof” printing on laid India, illus. color online (£700).</p>
            <p>“Rev. John Caspar Lavater.” EB, May-June, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st., apparently trimmed
within the platemark to 35.6 × 27.9 cm., tear in margin top left (no bids on a required minimum bid of
$499.99).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, Including Prints Extracted
from Such Books</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Allen, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi>, 1798. Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #48-49, pls. 1
and 3 only (£220 each).</p>
            <p>Allen, <hi rend="i">Roman History</hi>, 1798. Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #56, later 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century cloth worn (£650).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Archaeologia.</hi> See under Basire in Blake’s Circle and Followers, below.</p>
            <p>Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando furioso.</hi> Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #50, 1791 ed.,
Blake’s pl. only, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. (£130). Magers &amp; Quinn, June online cat., 1783 ed., 5
vols., contemporary calf worn ($600). Libreria Antiquaria Pregliasco, June online cat., 1785 ed., 5 vols.,
contemporary morocco, with fore-edge paintings (€5500). Hava Books, June online cat., 1783 ed., 5 vols.,
some staining, contemporary calf very worn, with Blake’s pl. “out of text” (£350). Poor Richard’s
Books, June online cat., 1783 ed., 5 vols., calf worn (£350). Fair Hope Books, June online cat., 1799 ed.,
vols. 3, 4, 5 only (presumably with Blake’s pl. in vol. 3), “fair” condition (which generally means very
worn), no description of binding ($200). Kenny’s Bookshop, June online cat., 1799 ed., 5 vols., contemporary
calf ($644).</p>
            <p>Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> BL, 29 Feb., #889, 1808 quarto, browned and foxed, later
morocco worn (not sold; estimate £400-600). EB, May, portrait frontispiece of Blake only, imprint trimmed
off, light stains and 1 tear in lower margin, framed (offered at the “buy it now” price of $750 or “best
offer”). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #57, 1808 quarto, slight browning or soiling, 2 pls. with marginal
repairs, later morocco (£1450); #58, 1808 quarto, slight scattered foxing, original boards rebacked, cover
label (£5000); #59, “1813” (actually 1870) folio, scattered foxing, quarter calf (£1420). BL, 11 June,
#423, described as a quarto of “1813” but probably the 1870 folio because in “original blind-stamped
cloth” rebacked, rubbed and stained (not sold; estimate £300-400). Manhattan Rare Book Co., June online
cat., 1808 quarto, scattered foxing, contemporary half morocco worn, illus. color ($2700). EB, June,
frontispiece portrait only, 1813 imprint, margins foxed (£117—probably a record price for a published st.).
Quaker Hill Books, July online cat., 1808 quarto, marginal damp staining, three-quarter morocco ($1760).
Waverley Books, July online cat., 1808 quarto, light foxing, “half leather” (£2000.50). Krown &amp;
Spellman, July online cat., “1813” (but actually 1870) folio, publisher’s cloth repaired ($1850).
Anthony Laywood, July online cat., 1808 “small folio” (probably the quarto), modern half calf (£1100).
George Robert Minkoff, July online cat., 1808 “quarto” (but probably the folio, since the frontispiece is
on laid India), “large paper with the plates in early states” (i.e., the folio sts.?), foxed,
“contemporary leather-backed boards, in damaged slipcase” ($5000). Peter L. Stern, July online cat., 1813
quarto, foxed, contemporary half morocco worn ($1750). Resource Books, July online cat., 1813 quarto, lacking
pl. 3, three-quarter calf very worn, covers detached ($950). BL, 4 Sept., #433, 1813 quarto, light soiling and
spotting, “last plate a little water-stained,” later half calf worn (£320). Hermitage Bookshop, Oct.
online cat., 1808 quarto, scattered browning and marginal foxing, later calf rebacked ($3000). Scrivener’s
Books, Oct. online cat., [1870] portfolio of the pls. only, slight foxing, original cloth folder repaired,
cover illus. color (£1100). Houle Rare Books, Oct. online cat., 1808 “small folio” (probably the quarto),
modern three-quarter morocco ($3750). Black Swan Books, Oct. online cat., [1870] portfolio of pls. only,
lacking pl. 3, some tears, original cloth folder worn ($825). BL, 10 Nov., #24, 1808 quarto, browned and
foxed, later morocco very worn (offered at £400 in a “fixed price” auction).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Boydell’s Graphic Illustrations of . . . Shakspeare</hi>, c. 1803. Charles
Agvent, July online cat., scattered foxing, contemporary half calf worn, covers detached ($3500). H. M.
Fletcher, July online cat., lacking the portraits, title p., and 2 unidentified pls., foxed, contemporary half
calf (£1500).</p>
            <pb id="p42-125" n="125"/>
            <p>Bryant, <hi rend="i">New System . . . of Ancient Mythology</hi>, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed.,
1775-76. Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #82, 3 vols., contemporary calf worn (£800).</p>
            <p>Catullus, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1795. Justin Croft Books, July online cat., 2 vols.,
contemporary calf repaired (£1000).</p>
            <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Outlines from the Antients</hi>, 1829. Windle/Sotheran, June cat.,
#83, foxed or browned throughout, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century quarter morocco (£500).</p>
            <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, 1796. Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #39-43,
Blake’s pls. 1, 4, 5, 7, 8 only (£220-350 each). Bonhams, Los Angeles and New York, 15 Oct., #1060, water
stains on 12 pls., original boards rebacked ($1200).</p>
            <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden.</hi> BL, 20 Dec. 2007, #624, Blake’s pl. 6
(“Tornado”) only from the 1795 ed., marginal tears, with “The Entombment,” an engraving attributed to
“circle of” Dürer, both framed (£120). Ken Spelman, April cat. 64, #129, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of
Part 1, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, both 1791, 2 vols., pls. foxed, full morocco rehinged (£495).
EB, May, Part 1 (“The Economy of Vegetation”) only, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., 1791, apparently with all
Blake pls., title p. badly stained, scattered foxing, contemporary calf very worn, front cover detached
($300). Bauman Rare Books, May online cat., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> eds. (Part 1, 1791; Part 2, 1789), 2 vols.
in 1, contemporary calf rebacked, illus. color ($4800). EB, June-July, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1,
3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, both 1791, 2 vols. in 1, scattered light foxing, signature of Robert Y.
Hayne (American politician, 1791-1839), contemporary calf worn, front cover detached ($560). Black Oak Books,
July online cat., 2 vols., apparently the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> or 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. of Part 1 and the
3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, both 1791, light foxing, contemporary calf worn, repaired ($1000). BL, 4
Sept., #510, ed. of Part 1 not indicated, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 2, both 1791, 2 vols. in 1, foxed
and browned, bookplate of Pamela Lister, contemporary calf rebacked and worn, color illus. placed with another
lot (£220). EB, Sept., 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1791), 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. of Part 2
(1790), 2 vols. in 1, some pls. trimmed at margins, scattered light foxing, contemporary calf rebacked ($770);
Oct., 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> ed. of Part 1 (1795), 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> ed. of Part 2 (1794), scattered
foxing, contemporary calf worn, back cover detached ($431.88). Swann, 11 Nov., #260, 4<hi rend="s">th</hi>
ed., 1799, 2 vols., “scattered pencil marginalia,” modern half calf ($450).</p>
            <p>Enfield, <hi rend="i">Speaker.</hi> EB, Jan., 1795 ed., contemporary calf very worn (no bids on
a required minimum bid of £29.99); same copy, March (£23.22); Feb., 1797 ed., contemporary calf worn (no
bids on a required minimum bid of £39.99). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #84, 1781 ed., “large-paper copy,”
contemporary calf worn (£350). James Cummins, July online cat., 1785 ed., contemporary calf rebacked
($750).</p>
            <p>Euler, <hi rend="i">Elements of Algebra</hi>, 1797. Librairie Crespin, July online cat., 2
vols., contemporary calf (€1573).</p>
            <p>Flaxman, Hesiod designs. EB, Dec. 2007, apparently the Bell &amp; Daldy 1870 reissue with the
1817 imprints erased, scattered light foxing, publisher’s(?) blue paper wrappers worn and stained, cover
label (no bids on a required minimum bid of £174.99); Jan.-Feb., same copy, same result. McLean Arts &amp;
Books, July online cat., 1817 ed., new three-quarter calf ($1200). The Lark, July online cat., 1817 ed.,
foxed, bound with Flaxman’s Aeschylus designs, n.d. (1818?), half “leather” ($900). BL, 17 July, #87,
1817 ed., browning throughout, contemporary half morocco very worn, front cover detached (£55). Quinn’s
&amp; Waverly auction, Falls Church, Virginia, 13 Nov., #1318, 1817 ed., lacking pl. 7, foxed, quarter morocco
worn, with Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs, both 1805, foxed, both
in “brown boards,” illus. color online ($260). For Flaxman’s Hesiod drawings, see the 37 drawings at the
beginning of the Flaxman entry under Blake’s Circle and Followers, below.</p>
            <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs, 1805. EB, Jan., considerable foxing on some pls.,
original boards worn and rebacked with cloth, cover label (€112.11); Aug.-Sept., bound with the 
<hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs, 1805, late 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco by Zaehnsdorf, both covers
detached, “crummy slipcase” (no bids on a required minimum bid of $350).</p>
            <p>Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, 1793. Rulon-Miller, Dec. 2007 cat. 135, #119, 2 vols., engraved
title p. (in vol. 1?) damp stained, contemporary morocco, later quarter morocco slipcase ($1500). EB, Jan., 2
vols., lacking 2 pls. but with all Blake pls., contemporary calf rebacked with new calf spines ($416.88).
Cheffins auction, Cambridge, 21 Feb., #2265, 2 vols., 11 (of 12) pls. by Blake, badly foxed, with Aesop, 
<hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, 1793, 2 vols., both contemporary morocco, illus. color online (£220). Swann, 7 April,
#78, 2 vols. in 1, damp stained, contemporary morocco very worn, front cover detached ($600). E. M. Lawson,
May cat. 324, #46, 2 vols., scattered foxing, from the library of Daniel Woodward (1931-2007), formerly
director of the library at the Huntington Library, contemporary calf rebacked (£240). Bauman Rare Books, May
online cat., 2 vols., scattered foxing, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century calf rebacked ($2500). EB, May,
Blake’s pl. 12 only, elaborately framed (withdrawn). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #86, 2 vols., scattered
browning, contemporary calf worn (£795). BL, 11 June, #133, 2 vols., “some pages brittle,” recent quarter
calf, with a Dublin, 1760, ed. of Gay’s <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (£400). James S. Jaffe, July online cat.,
2 vols., later morocco ($3500). Black Swan Books, July online cat., vol. 1 only, “full leather” worn
($400). William James, July online cat., 2 vols., light foxing, three-quarter “leather” worn ($750).
Art@home, July online cat., 2 vols., “full leather” very worn and repaired ($1175). D &amp; E Lake, July
online cat., 2 vols., margin of Blake’s pl. 1 stained, contemporary calf worn ($888). Books on the Green,
July online cat., 2 vols. in 1, foxed, “old calf” worn ($1430). EB, Aug., 2 vols. in 1, 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century calf very worn ($649.95); Nov., complete pls. and engraved title pp. only, scattered
foxing, modern cloth worn (£127.77). Some of these copies of the “1793” ed. may be the [1811] issue.</p>
            <pb id="p42-126" n="126"/>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, 1805. BNY, 12 Dec. 2007, #134, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> sts. of
the pls., some foxing, contemporary half morocco worn, illus. color (not sold; estimate $1800-2400); same
copy, 17 Sept., #245, illus. color ($1000). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #87, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> sts. of
pls. 1-3, later calf (£2950).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>, New York 1803 ed. with a wood engraving of Blake’s
“Weather House” design. Kelmscott Bookshop, July online cat., 2 vols. in 1, contemporary cloth ($45).
Hurley Books, July online cat., pls. water stained, “leather” binding ($100).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi>, 1809. Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #53, Blake’s pl.
only, apparently trimmed to the image and oddly dated to “1791” (£280); #89, “large-paper copy,”
modern half morocco (£2950). BL, 11 June, #148, contemporary calf, with Gray, <hi rend="i">Poems and
Letters</hi>, 1863 (not sold; estimate £280-320). Howes Bookshop, Nov. cat. 329, #15, “large paper copy”
described as having an “1808” watermark (probably an error for 1807—see appendix 1, below), uncut in
original boards, printed spine label, binding worn, upper cover detached (£550).</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 1803. Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #88, apparently
the small-paper issue, scattered foxing, contemporary calf rebacked (£410). EB, July, lacking pl. 3,
small-paper issue, contemporary half calf worn (no bids on a required minimum bid of £95); same copy, Oct.
(£109.77). James Fenning, Nov. cat. 243, #102, contemporary calf, “both boards eaten but binding sound and
strong” (£450). A voracious reader?</p>
            <p>Henry, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Albert de Haller</hi>, 1783. Acanthophyllum Books, July online
cat., Blake’s pl. damp stained along inner margin and “reattached,” text browned, recent “leather”
(£330).</p>
            <p>Hoare, <hi rend="i">Inquiry</hi>, 1806. Sotheran’s, July online cat., contemporary half calf
worn (£198).</p>
            <p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> Swann, 6 Dec. 2007, #232, undated Baldwin and Cradock issue,
contemporary half morocco, “needs rebinding,” illus. color ($950). CL, 30 April, #124, 1822 ed.,
contemporary half Russia worn (£2375). EB, May, Blake’s pl. only, probably 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., edges
of the leaf slightly browned (no bids on a required minimum bid of £34.50). Wittenborn Art Books, June online
cat., Blake’s pl. only, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> or 6<hi rend="s">th</hi> st. from an undated Baldwin and
Cradock ed., illus. ($250). Harry E. Bagley, July online cat., 1822 ed., minor foxing, half morocco worn
($3500). Weyhe Art Books, July online cat., 1822 ed., foxed and water stained, disbound ($4500). BL, 23 Oct.,
#328, 1822 ed., 2 vols., damp stained, contemporary half sheep very worn, front cover of vol. 1 detached
(£900); #374, undated Baldwin and Cradock ed., browning and spotting, “modern half-rexine over contemporary
marbled boards” worn (£750). “Rexine” is a heavy cloth coated to imitate leather.</p>
            <p>Hunter, <hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi>, 1793. Joseph Felcone, Feb. cat. 97, #99, quarto
issue, many leaves uncut, modern half calf ($5500). CL, 30 April, #82, quarto issue, some browning,
contemporary calf rebacked, illus. color (£1250). Gaston Renard, July online cat., quarto issue, pls.
slightly foxed, contemporary calf rebacked ($6750 Australian). Hordern Books, July online cat., quarto issue,
contemporary morocco rebacked, “fine large copy” ($11,500 Australian). Banfield House, July online cat.,
octavo issue, “half leather” ($4000 Australian). Bauman Rare Books, July online cat., quarto issue,
“large paper,” occasional foxing, uncut in “contemporary” (original?) boards rebacked ($12,000).</p>
            <p>Josephus, <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> EB, Dec. 2007, Blake’s pl. 3 only, 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi>
st., marginal stains ($38); May, probably an issue between <hi rend="i">BB</hi> issues A and B, lacking
“Whole” in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> line of the title (as in A) but with the reference to Kimpton (as in
B), contemporary calf very worn, front cover detached (£201). Krown &amp; Spellman, July online cat., 
<hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue D or E, some leaves torn, “old cloth” ($850). Vinyl UK, July online cat., 
<hi rend="i">BB</hi> issue B or later, contemporary calf worn, covers loose (£757.80).</p>
            <p>Kimpton, <hi rend="i">History of the Bible</hi>, c. 1781. Beckham Books, July online cat.,
lacking 2 unidentified pls., contemporary calf (£210).</p>
            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man.</hi> Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #90, 1788 ed.,
contemporary calf rebacked (£360). Worcester Rare Books, July online cat., 1789 ed., contemporary
“leather” rebacked (£125).</p>
            <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy.</hi> EB, Jan., 1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, minor
foxing, contemporary Russia (offered at the “buy it now” price of $3521 or “best offer”); May, 1789-98
ed., 3 vols. in 5, contemporary calf rebacked with new spines (£256). BL, 15 May, #495, “1792” (actually
c. 1818) ed., 3 vols. in 5, contemporary morocco, handsome binding illus. color (£2800). Windle/Sotheran,
June cat., #44-47, Blake’s 4 pls. only (£90-130 each). EB, June, Blake’s pl. 2 only, marginal foxing
(€9.90); July, a mixed set, “1792” (vol. 2), 1810 (all others), 3 vols. in 5, scattered light browning,
contemporary calf rebacked ($570). EOS Buchantiquariat, July online cat., 1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, foxed,
contemporary half calf very worn, spines detached ($1510). Alan Wofsy Books, July online cat., 1789-98 ed.,
vols. 1 and 3 only (but presumably with all 4 Blake pls. in vol. 1), contemporary calf ($950). Books for
Change, July online cat., apparently the 1789-98 ed. in 3 vols., light foxing, modern cloth ($750). Donald
Heald, July online cat., “1792” ed., 3 vols. in 5, fancy contemporary morocco ($12,000). James Cummins,
July online cat., “1792” ed., 3 vols. in 5, contemporary calf worn and rebacked ($2000). Krown &amp;
Spellman, July online cat., “1792” ed., 3 vols. in 5, scattered foxing, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century
<pb id="p42-127" n="127"/>
Russia rebacked ($1300). Jeremy Norman, July online cat., 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, minor foxing, 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century quarter morocco worn ($2750).</p>
            <p>Malkin, <hi rend="i">Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi>, 1806. Swann, 7 April, #21, John
Quinn’s copy (sold at auction in 1923 for $18), contemporary calf very worn, front cover detached ($550).
Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #91, contemporary morocco (£960). James Cummins, July online cat., uncut in
original boards rebacked, new endpapers ($1500).</p>
            <p>Mora, <hi rend="i">Meditaciones poeticas</hi>, 1826. BL, 15 May, #360, engraved title folded at
foot, 1 pl. damp stained, contemporary quarter morocco worn, modern folding box, illus. color (not sold;
estimate £1500-2000).</p>
            <p>Nicholson, <hi rend="i">Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi>, 1782. Scarthin Books, July
online cat., 2 vols., contemporary calf worn (£300). Bristow &amp; Garland, July online cat., 2 vols., some
leaves browned, contemporary calf very worn, 3 covers detached (£180). B &amp; L Rootenberg, July online
cat., 2 vols., some browning, contemporary calf rebacked ($950).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine.</hi> EB, May, vol. 8, 1782 ed., lacking the general title
p., contemporary calf very worn, covers amateurishly reattached with tape (£102). Windle/Sotheran, June cat.,
#26-33, Blake’s pls. only, vol. 8, pl. 2 in the 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., all others 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>
sts., offered individually as follows: vol. 8, pl. 2; vol. 9, pls. 1-3; vol. 10, pls. 1-3; another impression
of vol. 10, pl. 3 trimmed to the central image (£60 for the last, £70 each for all others). Best Buy Books,
July online cat., vol. 8, apparently lacking the general title p. and with the specific title p. dated
“1795” according to the vendor (thus a previously unrecorded issue?), later morocco worn, front cover
loose ($350); same copy, Vinyl UK, July online cat. (£383.74). EB, Oct., vol. 8, 1782 ed., contemporary calf
worn (offered at the “buy it now” price of $575 or “best offer”). J &amp; S Wilbraham, Nov. online
cat. 78, #164, vols. 10-11, 1783 (vol. 10) and 1793 (vol. 11) eds., contemporary calf worn (£75).</p>
            <p>Olivier, <hi rend="i">Fencing Familiarized</hi>, 1780. N1 Books, July online cat., some ink
underlining of text, contemporary calf worn, binding illus. color (£350). Possibly the same copy with “some
heavy underlining in text” sold BL, 16 Aug. 2007, #632 (£120).</p>
            <p>Rees, <hi rend="i">The Cyclopædia</hi>, 1820. BL, 3 April, #381, pls. vols. 2-6 only
(presumably including Blake’s pls. 2-7), scattered foxing, contemporary half calf very worn, some covers
lacking (£420). EB, June, Blake’s pl. 1 with 3 pls. not by Blake, marginal foxing ($9.99); another lot of 4
pls. including Blake’s pl. 1, slight browning ($31); another lot of 6 pls. including Blake’s pls. 4-7,
marginal browning ($24.99); July, pls. vol. 2 only (presumably including Blake’s pl. 2), light foxing,
“hardback,” covers loose ($114.49).</p>
            <p>Ritson, <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi>, 1783. Windle/Sotheran, June cat.,
#34-36, Blake’s pls. 2, 4, 6 only (£60 each).</p>
            <p>Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality.</hi> A. Parker’s Books, July online cat., 48 (of
50) pls. only, foxed, loose in portfolio, sts. not recorded ($3000). John Gach, July online cat., 1791 ed., 3
vols. in 1, lacking 9 pls. (including 8 attributed to Blake), early 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century half calf
worn ($850).</p>
            <p>Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, 1782. EB, Jan., contemporary calf (no bids on a
required minimum bid of $499); same copy, Feb., same result on a required minimum bid of $399.
Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #37-38, Blake’s pls. 1 and 3 only (£70 each). Ed Buryn, July online cat.,
“marbled leather boards” (i.e., mottled calf?) worn ($395).</p>
            <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi>, 1802. Michael Sharpe, Dec. 2007 cat. 2, #104, 9
vols., scattered light foxing, contemporary calf rebacked, binding illus. color ($25,000—a record asking
price). CSK, 19 March, #70, 9 vols., foxed, contemporary morocco worn, illus. color (£1250). Bauman Rare
Books, July online cat., 9 vols., contemporary calf rebacked ($16,000). BL, 17 July, #572, 9 vols., occasional
damp staining, with annotations by Henry Irving (actor and theater manager, 1838-1905), contemporary morocco
worn (not sold; estimate £1000-1500).</p>
            <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, 1811. Bookshop on the Heath, July online cat., 9 vols.,
contemporary calf (£1495).</p>
            <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, colored copies. CSK, 24 Sept., #235, 35 (of 80) pls.
only, including at least Blake’s pl. 10, loose in a box, Blake’s pl. 10 illus. color (£875; estimate
£400-600). The coloring of pl. 10 accords with hand-colored impressions in the 1796 ed.</p>
            <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, uncolored copies. EB, Dec. 2007, 1796 ed., 2 vols.,
lacking 1 pl. not by Blake, tears in several leaves, severe damp staining at the beginning of each vol., most
pls. badly foxed, modern buckram ($1681). BL, 24 April, #416, 1796 ed., vol. 2 only, foxed, uncut in original
boards rebacked (£220); #417, 1796 ed., 2 vols., scattered foxing, contemporary calf rebacked, illus. color
(£1600). Hindman auction, Chicago, 6 May, #2127, 1813 ed., vol. 1 only, contemporary calf worn, front cover
detached, illus. color online ($350). Peter Harrington, June cat. 57, #137, 1796 ed., 2 vols., some marginal
spotting on the pls., contemporary half calf, illus. color (£4500). Shaw’s Antiquarian Books, July online
cat., 1796 ed., 2 vols., occasional foxing, contemporary calf worn, vol. 1 rebacked (£3000). J. Tuttle
Maritime Books, July online cat., 1806 ed., 2 vols., contemporary three-quarter calf worn ($3000).</p>
            <p>Stuart and Revett, <hi rend="i">Antiquities of Athens.</hi> BNY, 5 April, #145, 1762-1830, 5
vols., browned and spotted, vols. 1-4 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century
<pb id="p42-128" n="128"/>
                            Russia rebacked, vol. 5 quarter morocco ($30,000); same copy, Sims Reed, July
online cat. (£35,000). Swann, 19 June, #255, 1762-94, 3 vols., some foxing, early 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century half calf, some covers detached ($6000); same copy?, Gonzalo Fernández Pontes, July
online cat., the binding “restored” (€16,500). SL, 13 Nov., #197, 1762-1830, 5 vols., some spotting and
offsetting, modern half calf, illus. color (£18,750). Blake’s 4 pls. are in vol. 3 of 1794.</p>
            <p>Tuer, <hi rend="i">Follies and Fashions of Our Grandfathers</hi>, 1886-87. BL, 11 June, #466,
large-paper issue, publisher’s boards, and another book, <hi rend="i">Victorian Illustrated</hi>, not dated
(£100). Includes a restrike of Blake’s pl. 3 from Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>,
1800.</p>
            <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">Pastorals</hi>, 1821. Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #94, vol. 1 only,
original sheep (£23,100); same copy, and 2 separate cuts by Blake, Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit
(prices on request). See also Essick, <hi rend="i">A Troubled Paradise</hi>, 1999, under Interesting Blakeana,
below.</p>
            <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">The Wood Engravings of William Blake for Thornton’s Virgil</hi>, 1977.
Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #81, publisher’s box (£3350).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Wit’s Magazine</hi>, 1784. EB, Feb., Blake’s pl. 4 only, with signatures and
title, no mention of the imprint (no bids on a required minimum bid of $299). Possibly the same impression
offered EB, Nov. 2007 (not sold). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #51-52, Blake’s pls. 4 and 5 only (£250
each).</p>
            <p>Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">Original Stories.</hi> BNY, 12 Dec. 2007, #374, 1791 ed., pl. 1 in
the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st., sts. of other pls. not recorded, later morocco worn, back cover detached,
illus. color ($1500). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #96, 1796 ed., 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> sts. of the pls., “a
little soiling and wear, but a wide-margined copy,” modern boards (£2450); #97, 1791 ed., 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> sts. of the pls., some slight browning, modern calf (£3500, mistakenly listed at
“£900”). Second Life Books, June cat. 163, #146, 1791 ed., “with the Blake plates in the first issue
[i.e., sts.?],” contemporary calf rebacked (“sold”). Books on the Green, July online cat., 1791 ed.,
“light stains” and “some foxing,” later three-quarter morocco worn, covers detached ($5720). Half Moon
Books, July online cat., 1796 ed., browned, “leather” binding very worn ($3500).</p>
            <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, 1797, uncolored copies. SNY, 11 Dec. 2007, #72, with
the “Explanation” leaf, pls. 5 and 26 before imprints, fore-edge and tail uncut, leaves 43.2 × 33.3 cm.,
later morocco, illus. color ($6875); same copy, John Windle, Oct. online cat. ($25,000). BL, 29 Feb., #888,
lacking the “Explanation” leaf, damp stained at lower edges, contemporary morocco rebacked, illus. color
(£4200). Bauman Rare Books, May online cat., with the “Explanation” leaf, uncut, 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century cloth rebacked in morocco, illus. color ($16,000). BL, 15 May, #254, with the
“Explanation” leaf, contemporary morocco, illus. color (£6500); same copy, Bernard Shapero, June cat. of
“50 Favourites,” #50, illus. color (£12,500), and Oct. cat. of “50 Fine Books,” #3, illus. color
(£13,500).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Interesting Blakeana</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>J. Boehme, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, the so-called “Law edition,” 1764-81. Ursus Books, May
cat. 274, #7, 4 vols., with marginalia by “Dr. Charles A. Muses, founder of the Jacob Boehme Society of
America,” modern calf, illus. color ($25,000). The ed. of Boehme known to Blake and perhaps owned by
him—see his comment to Henry Crabb Robinson on the beauty of the “figures” (i.e., the illus.) in
“Law’s transl<hi rend="s">n</hi>.” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 423).</p>
            <p>J. Meyer, portrait miniatures of the Hayley family, c. 1770. SL, 16 April, #19, Mrs. William
Hayley (née Elizabeth Ball), William Hayley’s 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> wife, 6.9 × 5.7 cm. oval, framed,
illus. color (not sold; estimate £6000-8000); #20, Mrs. Thomas Hayley (née Mary Yates), William Hayley’s
mother, 7.1 × 5.9 cm. oval, framed, illus. color (not sold; estimate £4000-6000).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine, and British Register</hi>, vol. 11, part 1, 1801. Givens Books,
July online cat., “leather” worn ($45). The April issue states that Thomas Macklin paid Blake £80 to
engrave “The Fall of Rosamond” after Stothard (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #987).</p>
            <p>J. Hassell, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of . . . George Morland</hi>, 1806. Quaritch, Feb. cat. 1363,
#58, some browning, contemporary half calf worn (£275). Hassell describes Blake’s prints after Morland,
“The Idle Laundress” and “Industrious Cottager” (78), and lists “Blake” as their engraver in the
“Catalogue of the Works of Morland” (170).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine, and British Register</hi>, vol. 26, part 2, 1808. Broad Street
Book Centre, July online cat., half calf very worn (£40). The 1 Dec. issue contains a brief anonymous review
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #951) of Blake’s illus. in the 1808 ed. of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> The
review is generally positive, but the author points out that the spiritual “conceptions” pictured in some
of the designs “admit of no just graphic representation.” Blake responded to this type of criticism in his
<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809: “The connoisseurs and artists who have made objections to
Mr. B.’s mode of representing spirits with real bodies, would do well to consider that the Venus, the
Minerva, the Jupiter, the Apollo, which they admire in Greek statues, are all of them representations of
spiritual existences of God’s immortal, to the mortal perishing organ of sight; and yet they are embodied
and organized in solid marble. Mr. B. requires the same latitude and all is well” (E 541). See 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 276 for the complete text of the review.</p>
            <p>W. Carey, <hi rend="i">Critical Description of the Procession of Chaucer’s Pilgrims . . .
Painted by Thomas Stothard</hi>, 1808, 1818. EB, March, 1818 ed., stains, “boards detached” (£25.99).
James Burmester, April cat. 71, #12, “1809” (probably an error for
<pb id="p42-129" n="129"/>
1808) ed., bound with Carey, <hi rend="i">Letter to I<hi rend="s">xxx</hi> A<hi rend="s">xxxx</hi></hi>, 1809,
contemporary half roan worn (£200). Both eds. include brief references to Blake’s designs for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Vaterländisches Museum</hi>, vol. 1, nos. 1-6, 1810, and vol. [2], no. 1, 1811.
Hamburger Antiquariat, Jan. online cat., contemporary quarter calf ($1099). The Jan. 1811 issue includes Henry
Crabb Robinson’s essay on Blake. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2538 locates the essay in vol. “I,” but 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) correctly places it in vol. “II” (573). For the complete German text and an English
translation, see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 573-603. Apparently rare; the only copy I have ever seen on the
market.</p>
            <p>J. Montgomery, ed., <hi rend="i">The Chimney-Sweeper’s Friend, and Climbing-Boy’s
Album</hi>, 1824. James Burmester, Jan. cat. 70, #49, modern half calf, title p. illus. (£475). Includes
Blake’s “The Chimney Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, “communicated [to Montgomery]
by Mr. Charles Lamb, from a very rare and curious little work” (343).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Annual Register . . . [for] 1827.</hi> Francis Edwards, Jan. cat. 108, #861, light
browning, contemporary calf worn (£50). Peter Bell, Jan. online cat., contemporary half calf worn (£15).
Includes an anonymous obituary of Blake reprinted from <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> of Oct.
1827.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, London: Pickering, 1839.
Quaritch, Feb. cat. 1364, #18, issue without “The Little Vagabond,” presentation letter from Gordon N. Ray
to John Hayward laid in, publisher’s cloth worn (£500). Bauman Rare Books, May online cat., issue without
“The Little Vagabond,” publisher’s cloth rebacked, illus. color ($15,000).</p>
            <p>J. Ruskin, <hi rend="i">The Elements of Drawing</hi>, 1857. Ken Spelman, Nov. cat. 65, #128,
publisher’s cloth repaired (£85). Includes a reference to Blake’s Job engravings; see appendix 2.</p>
            <p>B. Disraeli, autograph letter signed to Anne Gilchrist, 5 Nov. 1862. Lion Heart Autographs,
Nov. online cat., 4 pp. with references to Isaac D’Israeli’s Blake collection, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> and
last pp. illus. color ($1600). For a transcription and discussion of this letter, see Raymond Lister, “A
Letter from Benjamin Disraeli to Anne Gilchrist,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 14.2 (fall 1980): 99. The letter
was in Lister’s collection in 1980.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Art-Journal</hi>, vol. 4, 1865. Keogh’s Books, Feb. online cat., lacking some
contents pp., badly damp stained, calf very worn (£45). Books N More, Feb. online cat., lacking the 3<hi
rend="s">rd</hi> installment of Ruskin’s essay noted below, morocco worn ($99.95). Dust Jacket Books, Feb.
online cat., half calf worn ($250). Includes 3 installments of John Ruskin’s “The Cestus of Aglaia” with
references to Blake or his works; see appendix 2.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Camden Hotten facsimile, 1868.
PBA, 26 June, #2028, some foxing as usual, slightly later quarter cloth over boards, illus. color online
($800).</p>
            <p>E. C. Clayton, <hi rend="i">English Female Artists</hi>, 1876. Hobgoblin Books, Feb. online
cat., 2 vols., publisher’s cloth worn (£98). Internet Bookshop, Feb. online cat., 2 vols., publisher’s
cloth worn (£115). In addition to Ruskin’s letter of 1855 (see appendix 2) with a reference to Blake, cited
in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1400A, the book includes 11 paragraphs about Catherine Blake, 1: 370-75.</p>
            <p>A. Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1880. EB,
Dec. 2007, 2 vols., “small annotations to some margins in volume 2,” light scattered foxing in vol. 2,
publisher’s cloth, corners slightly bumped ($595). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #103, 2 vols., publisher’s
cloth (£660). EB, June, 2 vols., publisher’s cloth (offered at the “buy it now” price of $888 or
“best offer”). PBA, 26 June, #2029, 2 vols., publisher’s cloth, illus. color online ($600).
Rulon-Miller, June cat. 136, #76, 2 vols., publisher’s cloth ($1250). Getting pricey, even on EB. The
gilt-stamped front cover design for both vols., based on a drawing by Robert Blake in Blake’s Notebook, is
attracting the attention of binding collectors as a precursor to art nouveau. See illus. 6 and its caption for
more on Blake and art nouveau.</p>
            <p>J. Ruskin, <hi rend="i">The Art of England</hi>, 1884. Wahrenbrock’s Book House, Feb. online
cat., calf worn ($225). Sam Weller’s Zion Bookstore, Feb. online cat., calf worn ($250). Wonder Book, Feb.
online cat., “hardcover” ($45). Includes a brief reference to Blake’s Job engravings; see appendix
2.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>,
William Muir facsimiles, 1884-85. Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #73, 2 vols., <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy
no. 30 and <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> no. 13, the latter signed by Muir, quarter vellum, original wrappers
bound in (£6450).</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, William Muir facsimile datable to c. 1885 on
paper with an “Antique Note” watermark, 27 pls. with coloring based on the “Experience” pls. in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy T (in the British Museum since 1856). With a
lithographic(?) “Index” of the pls. and a reproduction of “A Divine Image” (from posthumous copy a?)
inserted as the 16<hi rend="s">th</hi> pl. (this pl. not in copy T). Publisher’s blue wrappers without
inscriptions. Offered Aug. for $6000 Canadian by a private collector, Toronto, to John Windle, who declined.
This is probably the unique(?) copy noted by Muir in a letter of 18 July 1916 to Kerrison Preston: “In
addition to these [facsimiles] I have <hi rend="i">one copy</hi> of the Songs of Experience coloured from the
Brit Mus copy. £5.5.0” (quoted in Keri Davies, “William Muir and the Blake Press at Edmonton with
Muir’s Letters to Kerrison Preston,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 27.1 [summer 1993]: 21). Possibly the
unnumbered copy of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> delivered by Muir to Bernard Quaritch, the London book dealer,
on 16 April 1918; see the records printed in G. E. Bentley, Jr., “‘Blake. . .Had No Quaritch’: The Sale
of William Muir’s Blake</p>
            <pb id="p42-130" n="130"/>
            <figure n="GannettCover.42.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="200" height="299">
              <figTranscr>
                WILLIAM BLAKE<lb/>
                By<lb/>
                RICHARD GARNETT, C.B., LL.D.
              </figTranscr>
              <head>6. Front cover of Richard Garnett, <hi rend="i">William Blake Painter and Poet</hi>
(London: Seeley and Co., 1895).</head>
              <figDesc>Full cover 27.3 × 18.0 cm., gilt-stamped lettering and design 15.3 × 10.0 cm. Essick
collection. Garnett’s eighty-page essay was published in at least three forms: as an issue of a journal, 
<hi rend="i">Portfolio</hi>, no. 22 (Oct. 1895), bound in light blue-gray paper wrappers; as part of the 1895
annual volume of <hi rend="i">Portfolio</hi> with two other essays, bound in maroon sand-grain cloth; as a
separate pamphlet, lacking any reference to <hi rend="i">Portfolio</hi>, bound in maroon rib-grain cloth. The
cover of this last issue, decorated with a modified version (11.1 × 6.3 cm.) of Blake’s design for
“Infant Joy” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, is reproduced here. The cover’s designer has
added extra flourishes to the tips of the open blossom on its left side, flattened the leftward arc of the
flower’s stem, and moved the pendant bloom under the open one to create a more compact, teardrop design.
These last two changes were made possible by the elimination of Blake’s text. The binding shows the
compatibility between some of Blake’s most famous images and the taste for the art-nouveau style in the
decorative arts of the late nineteenth century. For a discussion of how “Art Nouveau ornament was born in
Blake’s work,” see Robert Schmutzler, <hi rend="i">Art Nouveau</hi> (New York: Abrams, 1962) 35-53
(quotation from 47).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Facsimiles,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 27.1 (summer 1993): 9. I have not inspected the
facsimile itself, but digital images of the frontispiece and title p. suggest that the work has a lithographic
base, but not the same one used by Muir for his 1885 facsimile with hand coloring based on the
“Experience” section of copy U of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, William Muir facsimile, 1886.
Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #77, copy no. 26, signed by Muir, full morocco, original wrappers bound in
(£2320).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi>, 1886-87. Leonard Roberts, Feb. online cat., issue
no. 6 (April 1887), with references to Blake by Ruskin (see appendix 2), publisher’s wrappers ($385
Canadian). Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #66, issue no. 4 (Oct. 1886), containing Muir’s facsimile of 
<hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi> cut in half, publisher’s wrappers (£395).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Blake His Songs of Innocence</hi>, Oxford: H. Daniel, 1893. James Cummins, June
online cat., publisher’s wrappers worn ($450).</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, E. J. Ellis facsimile, 1893.
Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #74, hand-colored copy no. 42, contemporary morocco (£3465).</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, ed. Ellis and Yeats, 1893. SL, 13 Dec. 2007, #158, 3 vols.,
small-paper issue, publisher’s decorated cloth, binding illus. color (£1500). Windle/Sotheran, June cat.,
#101, 3 vols., large-paper issue, publisher’s half roan worn (£1420); #102, 3 vols., small-paper issue,
publisher’s decorated cloth (£1420).</p>
            <p>R. Garnett, <hi rend="i">William Blake Painter and Poet</hi>, 1895. EB, May, publisher’s
cloth, lower portion of front cover slightly stained with mildew (£16.95). See illus. 6.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel, Songs of Innocence and Songs of Experience</hi>,
illus. Ricketts, 1897. EB, Dec. 2007, 1 of 210 copies, publisher’s boards, cover and spine labels ($537-50).
Maggs, Sept. cat. 1425, #653, “proof” of the title-p. vignette, leaf 19.1 × 12.6 cm. (£150). One of the
more handsome typographic selections of Blake’s poems.</p>
            <p>W. B. Yeats, <hi rend="i">Ideas of Good and Evil</hi>, 1903. SL, 13 Dec. 2007, #167,
presentation inscription by Yeats to his uncle, George Pollexfen, publisher’s boards and cloth spine, some
spotting, presentation inscription illus. color (£7500); #168, another copy, presentation inscription by
Yeats to his literary agent, Alexander Pollock Watt, publisher’s binding, some spotting
<pb id="p42-131" n="131"/>
(£3000). Contains Yeats’s essays “William Blake and the Imagination” and “William Blake and His
Illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Divine Comedy</hi>” (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #3047B, 3051B).</p>
            <p>J. Ruskin, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, ed. Cook and Wedderburn, 1903-12. Contact Editions, Feb.
online cat., 39 vols., halfmorocco ($12,500). Townsend Booksellers, Feb. online cat., 39 vols., cloth with
library markings ($3250). Adrian Harrington, Feb. online cat., 39 vols., publisher’s morocco (£6000). James
Cummins, Feb. online cat., 39 vols., three-quarter morocco ($12,500). For the Blake references, see appendix
2.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">William Blake: Ausgewählte Dichtungen</hi>, translated by Adolf Knoblauch,
Berlin, 1907 (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #361). Buchantiquariat Heinz Tessin, Dec. 2007 online cat., vol. 2 (of 2)
only, 1 of 670 copies, publisher’s wrappers (€32). EB, Sept., 2 vols., publisher’s wrappers worn, front
cover of vol. 1 loose (€13.21). One of the earliest translations of Blake’s writings, to my knowledge
preceded only by brief selections in essays and books about Blake (e.g., Henry Crabb Robinson’s 1811 essay
[see entry above] and Helene Richter’s <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> of 1906 [<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2538,
2520], both in German), a 1900 French translation of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, and a
1906 Italian translation of “The Tyger” (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #110, 343). See the next entry for another
German translation of Blake’s selected works published in 1907.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">William Blake: Die Ethik der Fruchtbarkeit</hi>, translated by Otto Freiherr von
Taube, Jena, 1907 (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #363). Any Amount of Books, Dec. 2007 online cat., publisher’s cloth
(£25). See comments under the previous entry.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Poems by William Blake</hi>, ed. Alice Meynell, Red Letter Library series, London:
Blackie and Son, 1911 (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #289A). EB, Aug., publisher’s limp calf worn, front cover
detached (£16.01). In <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 169, I incorrectly reported that an undated
issue of this ed., sold on EB in May 2005, might be the 1911 issue. That undated issue may be 1 of at least 2
variant undated issues, 1 of which is dated to “[1927]” in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #289B.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to Thornton’s Pastorals of Virgil</hi>,
platinotypes by Frederick Evans, 1912. Paul Hertzmann/Margolis &amp; Moss, Aug. online cat., #61, no. 3 of 25
copies, signed and dated by Evans, limp “leather” rebacked, illus. ($7500).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Catalogue of an Exhibition of Original Water-Colour Drawings by William Blake to
Illustrate Dante</hi>, New York: Scott and Fowles, 1921 (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #616). EB, May-June,
publisher’s wrappers worn ($9.99). Apparently rare; the only copy I have ever seen on the market.</p>
            <p>A souvenir letter card, c. 1925, with a color reproduction, 9.5 × 29.8 cm., of a colored (?)
impression of Blake’s engraving, “Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims,” probably 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st. EB,
May ($4.99). A curious object, published by “J. G. Charlton, Photographer, Canterbury.” The vendor on EB
cites a 1925 advertisement by Charlton that lists “reproductions, in original and smaller sizes, of
Blake’s and Stothard’s celebrated picture of ‘Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims.”’ Some of the
coloring accords with the hand-colored impression of the 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. now in the Keynes
Collection, Fitzwilliam Museum (<hi rend="i">SP</hi> XVI impression 2B), but there are many exceptions (e.g.,
the Host wears a blue rather than brown jumpsuit with brown rather than blue belt and boots). Another coloring
scheme, closer to the Keynes impression, is represented in a photo-lithographic reproduction of the 3<hi
rend="s">rd</hi> st., 21.1 × 60.1 cm., published at an unknown time by the “Agnes Press.” Perhaps these
coloring schemes bear no direct relation to any original. The single recorded colored impression of Blake’s
3<hi rend="s">rd</hi> st. is <hi rend="i">SP</hi> impression 3P (now Morgan Library and Museum), tinted only
with flesh tones on exposed skin.</p>
            <p>W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, 1927, William Muir facsimile of pls. 2-27,
53-54 of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy A. EB, April, copy no. 29, bookplate of
Joseph Holland, rebound in cloth, worn, endpapers detached, original wrappers bound in ($910).</p>
            <p>Photographic postcards of Blake’s cottage in Felpham, 1930s? EB, Jan.-Feb., 3 cards in sepia
tones offered individually: south aspect from the southeast; a slightly more distant view showing the south
and east aspects from the southeast; the road in front of the house from the south, the south aspect of the
house, and the Fox Inn in the distance, with postmark dated 24 Aug. 1933 (75 pence each for the 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> 2, £1.99 for the 3<hi rend="s">rd</hi>). EB, July, 1 card showing the south aspect with a
long thatch canopy over the ground-floor windows (as in W. Graham Robertson’s drawing of 1904), a field (of
cabbages?) and low wall between the camera and the house (£3.70) (see cover illus.). These postcards,
produced for the tourist trade in Bognor Regis near Felpham, have some scholarly value as representations of
the cottage before the render was removed and other modifications were undertaken. The locations of windows,
doors, and chimneys are helpful in understanding how Blake and his wife Catherine lived and worked in Felpham.
For a fine essay on this topic, see M. Crosby, “‘The sweetest spot on earth’: Reconstructing Blake’s
Cottage at Felpham, Sussex,” <hi rend="i">British Art Journal</hi> 7.3 (winter 2006-07): 46-53.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Piper by William Blake</hi> [the “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi>], illus. Roberta F. C. Waudby, London: Medici Society, n.d. EB, Sept., publisher’s printed
wrappers (25 pence). Datable to the 1930s when Waudby was active. <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 160 dates this
pamphlet to “c. 1980,” either in error or in reference to a later issue.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, reproduction of posthumous copy
b, introduction by Ruthven Todd, 1947 (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #186A). EB, Jan., with the bookplate of Pamela and
Raymond
<pb id="p42-132" n="132"/>
Lister, hand tinted with watercolors, publisher’s cloth ($99 to John Windle for stock). Returned March by
Windle because of spilled watercolors on the final pl. not described by the vendor. The hand coloring is too
amateurish to be by Raymond Lister (1919-2001), an accomplished miniature painter and president of the Royal
Society of Miniature Painters from 1970 to 1980. The coloring may be based on a copy colored by Blake, but I
have not been able to identify any such.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Poems from William Blake’s Songs of Innocence</hi>, illus. Maurice Sendak, 1967.
Aleph-Bet Books, Dec. 2007 cat. 87, #504, presentation inscription from Sendak to the playwright William
Archibald, with a Sendak Christmas card sent to Archibald, original wrappers, slight wear to outer edge,
illus. color ($6500). Previously sold EB, Sept. 2000 ($5,151.51). A poor investment, yielding only 3.7% per
annum if sold at full price.</p>
            <p>Robert R. Wark, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illuminated Manuscript of Genesis</hi>, c. 1975(?).
Proofs of an essay by Wark, 14 pp., accompanied by a full-size color reproduction of the manuscript, loose in
a cloth portfolio, “William Blake / The Genesis / Manuscript” gilt-stamped on the front cover. Printed for
the American Blake Foundation as a vol. in its facsimile series, but never published. John Windle, Dec.
private offer, 1 of 2 known copies ($975, acquired by Victoria University Library, Toronto).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, Manchester Etching Workshop facsimile,
1983. Bonhams, Los Angeles and New York, 15 Oct., #1061, colored issue (no. 8 of 40) and uncolored issue (no.
8 of 35), 2 vols., publisher’s morocco (colored issue) and loose in paper mounts (uncolored issue),
clamshell boxes, illus. color ($2400).</p>
            <p>R. N. Essick, <hi rend="i">A Troubled Paradise</hi>, afterword by J. Windle, 1999.
Windle/Sotheran, June cat., #85, “de-luxe” issue with an original impression of Blake’s 6<hi
rend="s">th</hi> Virgil wood engraving (stormy night with tree and moon), not the “fifth” engraving as
noted in the cat., publisher’s wrappers and quarter-cloth box (£1800).</p>
            <p>Barry Moser (American artist, 1940-), wood-engraved portrait of Blake based on the life mask.
Image 13.3 × 8.3 cm. EB, March, 2000 printing of 70 impressions (according to the vendor), leaf 31.8 × 24.1
cm. ($105); April, apparently another impression (no bids on a required minimum bid of $105).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Blake’s Circle and Followers</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Works are listed under artists’ names in the following order: paintings and drawings sold in
groups, single paintings and drawings, letters and manuscripts, separate plates, books by (or with plates by
or after) the artist.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">BARRY, JAMES</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>“Venus Anadyomene,” mezzotint by Valentine Green. CSK, 12 March, #109, “good impression
with margins” (£1500; estimate £500-700).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">BASIRE, JAMES</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Archaeologia: or, Miscellaneous Tracts Relating to Antiquity</hi>, vol. 3, 1775
or 1776. Barnaby Rudge Bookseller, Dec. 2007 online cat., title p. misdated “MDCCLXXXVI,” modern cloth,
binding illus. color ($294). Includes 19 pls. signed by Basire as the engraver; the 8 unsigned pls. were
probably also executed in Basire’s shop. Blake may have participated in the production of some of these pls.
while an apprentice to Basire (see <hi rend="i">CB</hi> 116 and <hi rend="i">BBS</hi> 191).</p>
              <p>Bryant, <hi rend="i">New System . . . of Ancient Mythology</hi>, and Stuart and Revett, 
<hi rend="i">Antiquities of Athens.</hi> See under Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake,
above.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">BUTTS, THOMAS, Father and Son</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>“Man on a Drinking Horse,” etching, 1806. EB, Feb., sheet 11.4 × 15.2 cm., browned
($75). For illus. and information about this print, see Alexander S. Gourlay, “‘Man on a Drinking
Horse’: A Print by Thomas Butts, Jr.,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 37.1 (summer 2003): 35-36.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">CALVERT, EDWARD</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>“The Bride,” engraving. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, from the 
<hi rend="i">Memoir</hi> (price on request). BL, 23 Oct., #459, from the <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, some browning,
framed, illus. color (£1000; estimate £300-500).</p>
              <p>“The Cyder Feast,” wood engraving. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, from the 
<hi rend="i">Memoir</hi> (price on request).</p>
              <p>“The Flood,” lithograph. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, “lifetime proof”
(price on request).</p>
              <p>“The Lady with the Rooks,” wood engraving. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, from
the 1904 Carfax portfolio (price on request).</p>
              <p>“The Ploughman,” wood engraving. Larkhall Fine Art, April online cat., 1904 Carfax
printing on laid India, from the collection of Raymond Lister, illus. color (£2800); same impression, and
another from the <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, July-Sept. exhibit (prices on request).</p>
              <pb id="p42-133" n="133"/>
              <p>“The Return Home,” wood engraving. Larkhall Fine Art, April online cat., 1904 Carfax
printing on laid India, from the collection of Raymond Lister, illus. color (£1350); July-Sept. exhibit,
impression from the <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi> (price on request).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">CROMEK, ROBERT</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>“Important collection of papers relating to the engraver and literary entrepreneur Robert
Hartley Cromek and his son, the painter Thomas Hartley Cromek.” SL, 17 July, #9, illus. color (£20,000;
estimate £5000-7000). This archive, for many years in the possession of the Warrington family (descendants of
both Cromeks through the female line), includes a copy of R. Cromek’s long letter to Blake of May 1807
rejecting his design for the dedication to the queen in Cromek’s ed. of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 241-44); a copy of R. Cromek’s letter to Thomas Bewick of 13 Aug. 1808 mentioning
Cromek’s ed. of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 262); T. Cromek’s transcription of
Frederick Tatham’s letter of 1 April 1829 written on behalf of Blake’s widow Catherine 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 495-96); and (according to the auction cat.) “extracts from Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> with T. H.’s critical comments on ‘Many slanderous assertions’ (‘.
. . here again, assertions are not proofs . . .’, ‘. . . In defense of my father, I must, though
unwillingly, relate <hi rend="i">my</hi> anecdote . . .’, etc.).”</p>
              <p>R. H. Cromek, ed., <hi rend="i">Reliques of Robert Burns</hi>, 1808. EB, May, pp. 389-402
badly stained, contemporary half calf worn (no bids on a required minimum bid of $100); same copy, June-July
(no bids on a required minimum bid of $75). Includes an advertisement for Cromek’s 1808 ed. of Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrated by Blake.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">FLAXMAN, JOHN</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Thirty-seven pencil and gray ink drawings, possibly the preliminary drawings for the Hesiod
designs engraved by Blake and published in 1817, or possibly a set created by Flaxman independent of the
production of the engravings. 22.7 × 30.5 cm. and slightly smaller, 5 leaves with 1809 and 1815 watermarks,
bound in a 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco album. Maggs, June private offer, on consignment from the
estate of H. D. Lyon ($125,000). Previously offered CL, 7 June 2001, #78, illus. color (not sold; estimate
£80,000-120,000).</p>
              <p>Six pencil sketches, some for a pediment for Buckingham Palace, each approx. 12.5 × 17.5 cm.
BH, 11 March, #14, sketch of a standing woman illus. color (not sold; estimate £700-900).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Holy Family.</hi> Watercolor, 72.0 × 51.0 cm. BH, 11 March, #43, illus.
color (£960).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Misses Harrison, Sharpe and Rogers and Mrs. Sharpe at Samuel Rogers’s
Party, 1800.</hi> Pen and ink, 22.7 × 16.0 cm. W/S Fine Art, Nov. online cat., illus. color (not priced).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Scene from Medieval History.</hi> Pen and ink, gray wash, 47.0 × 62.0 cm. W. M.
Brady &amp; Co., New York, advertisement in <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 150 (Jan. 2008): [10],
illus. color (not priced). Similar in size and style to <hi rend="i">The Massacre of the Britons by
Hengist’s Party at Stonehenge</hi> and <hi rend="i">St. Ethelburga with Her Chaplain St. Paulinus of
Rochester Bringing Christianity to Northumbria</hi> (both Fitzwilliam Museum), and thus datable to c.
1783.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of a Seated Male.</hi> Pencil, 29.5 × 23.5 cm., signed and inscribed by
another hand, “I sat behind Flaxman at the R. A. and saw him draw this C.H.S.” BH, 11 March, #25, illus.
color (withdrawn for unstated reasons; estimate £1500-2000).</p>
              <p>A collection of letters by Thomas Hope to Flaxman, c. 1792-1808. BH, 26 Nov., #143, bound,
illus. color (£3360; estimate £800-1200).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Acts of Mercy</hi>, etchings with aquatint by Lewis, 1831. EB, Dec. 2007,
small-paper issue, most pls. foxed, contemporary quarter calf ($68); Feb., 8 pls. in 2 lots, lacking only the
engraved title p., oddly attributed to Sir Thomas Lawrence as the “designer” and Flaxman as the
“artist” (no bids on a required minimum bid of £15.99 for each lot).</p>
              <p>Aeschylus designs, 1795. Galerie Bassenge auction, Berlin, 11 April, #1189, some browning and
spotting, recent cloth (€130). EB, July-Aug., scattered foxing, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century half calf
worn ($276).</p>
              <p>Dante designs. EB, Jan., engraved by Piroli, Milan, 1823, probably a reprint of the 1822 ed.,
scattered foxing, contemporary calf (€156); May, 1867 ed. with revised sts. of Piroli’s 1807 pls.,
publisher’s cloth (offered at the “buy it now” price of $200); another copy of the 1867 ed., modern
cloth (offered at the “buy it now” price of £149.95 or “best offer”); 1802 ed., bound as extra-illus.
in a copy of Dante’s <hi rend="i">Divina Commedia</hi>, Rome, 1815, 3 vols., contemporary vellum worn
($796). Ken Spelman, Nov. cat. 65, #138, engraved by Piroli, Milan, 1823, minor foxing, original wrappers worn
(£280).</p>
              <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Anatomical Studies</hi>, 1833. EB, July, original boards stained,
“crudely” rebacked with cloth, leaves coming loose from spine (£23.03); Aug., modern cloth (£73.12).</p>
              <p>Hesiod designs, engraved by Réveil, Paris, 1844. EB, Aug., original wrappers worn (no bids
on a required minimum bid of $225); same copy, Sept., same result. See also the album of 37 Hesiod drawings,
above, and Flaxman, Hesiod designs, under Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
              <pb id="p42-134" n="134"/>
              <p><hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs. EB, Jan., 1793 ed., light water stains and foxing on a few
pls., original wrappers ($385.02); Feb., <hi rend="i">Iliade d’Homere gravée par Thomas Piroli d’apres
les desseins composés par Jean Flaxman</hi>, Rome, n.d. (c. 1818?), marginal losses on final pl.,
contemporary quarter vellum very worn ($142.50). BL, 17 July, #65, with the <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> and
Hesiod designs, eds. with inscriptions in French, n.d. (c. 1818?), foxed, marginal damage, 2 vols., half
morocco very worn (not sold; estimate £300-500). See also Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs, under
Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> designs. EB, Feb., <hi rend="i">Darstellungen aus Homers
Odyssee</hi>, engraved by Edouard Schuler, bound with the <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> designs engraved by Schuler
(lacking the title p.), both Karlsruhe, n.d., foxed, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century half calf ($91 Canadian).
Both Schuler series are dated to 1828 by Detlef W. Dörrbecker, “A Survey of Engravings after Flaxman’s
Outline Compositions 1793-1845,” <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>, ed. David Bindman (London: Thames and
Hudson, 1979) 185. EB, April-May, lithographs by Feillet and Laqueson, Paris, 1823, publisher’s wrappers
worn ($9.99).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Œuvres de John Flaxman sculpteur anglais . . . [with] Les tragédies de
Sophocle par Giacomelli</hi>, Paris: A. Morel et C<hi rend="s">ie</hi>, n.d. EB, April, dated to 1860 by the
vendor, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century quarter calf (no bids on a required minimum bid of €150).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">FUSELI, HENRY</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Joseph Interpreting the Dreams of Pharaoh’s Baker and Butler.</hi> Oil, 86.6
× 65.1 cm., datable to c. 1768. CL, 2 Dec., #28, possibly Fuseli’s 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> painting, illus.
color (not sold; estimate £120,000-180,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of John Henry Fuseli</hi> by George Henry Harlow. Oil on panel, 51.0 ×
39.5 cm., datable to 1818 on the basis of an inscription by Robert Balmanno on the back. SL, 30 Oct., #190,
illus. color (£3750). Previously sold SL, 23 April 1996, #235 (£6900); offered SL, 15 Dec. 2005, #68 (not
sold; estimate £6000-8000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Salome with the Head of John the Baptist</hi>, attributed to Fuseli. Wash
drawing on cream laid paper with a 1795 watermark, 31.1 × 21.8 cm. Skinner auction, Boston, 12 Sept., #405,
framed, illus. color online ($1007). Possibly a preliminary drawing by Thomas Holloway for his engraving of
the design, dated 1798 in the imprint and published in Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, vol.
2, or an early copy after the pl.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Vision of the Deluge.</hi> Oil, 254.0 × 210.0 cm., painted in the 1790s for
Fuseli’s Milton Gallery. CL, 9 June, #209, illus. color (£505,250; estimate £80,000-120,000).</p>
              <p>“The Death of Oedipus,” mezzotint by Ward. CSK, 18 March, #530, with 3 pls. after Fuseli
from Boydell, <hi rend="i">Collection of Prints . . . Illustrating . . . Shakspeare</hi>, 2 for <hi rend="i">A
Midsummer Night’s Dream</hi> and 1 for <hi rend="i">The Tempest</hi> (£875). Apparently rare; the only
impression I’ve ever seen on the market.</p>
              <p>Portrait of Fuseli, designed and engraved by J. H. Lips, 1779. EB, June (€18.03).</p>
              <p>“Queen Katherine’s Dream,” engraved by Bartolozzi. EB, April, marginal stains (no bids
on a required minimum bid of €55). An important print, published by Macklin in 1788 for his “British
Poets” series, that may have influenced Blake’s versions of the subject (Butlin #247, 547.3, 548-49).</p>
              <p>“The Witches” from <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>, engraved by Tomkins. EB, Jan., trimmed
close to the image with inscriptions (except for the signatures) trimmed off, minor foxing (£47.78).</p>
              <p>Bible, Macklin ed., 1800. Michael Sharpe, Dec. 2007 cat. 2, #14, 6 vols., Richard
Westmacott’s copy, contemporary morocco, illus. ($20,000). Swann, 7 April, #17, 6 vols., considerable damp
staining, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco very worn, some covers detached ($1500). EB, April, 6 vols.
in 7, contemporary calf, 3 vols. rebacked (no bids on a required minimum bid of $9999); same copy, May
($5001). Phillip Pirages, Nov. cat. 56, #478, 7 vols. (including vol. 7, <hi rend="i">The Apocrypha</hi>,
1816), pls. before letters, lacking 1 leaf of text in vol. 7, sumptuous contemporary morocco, binding illus.
color ($85,000—a record asking price, probably based on the binding). The single pl. after Fuseli is in vol.
6.</p>
              <p>[Boothby], <hi rend="i">Sorrows, Sacred to the Memory of Penelope</hi>, 1796. EB, May-June,
large-paper issue, frontispiece after Fuseli in the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st., uncut in original boards,
printed cover label, scattered foxing (no bids on a required minimum bid of £199); same copy, July, same
result.</p>
              <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">The American Edition of Boydell’s Illustrations of the Dramatic Works
of Shakspeare</hi>, 1852. EB, April, 2 vols., some damp staining in vol. 2, recent half morocco ($1425). The
pls. in this work are the original British pls., “restored.”</p>
              <p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Collection of Prints . . . Illustrating . . . Shakspeare</hi>, c. 1803.
SNY, 11 Dec. 2007, #108, 2 vols., 96 pls., lacking the portraits, some marginal stains and tears, 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century half morocco worn, illus. color ($5000). BL, 31 Jan., #169, “a few plates proofs
before letters,” light browning on some pls., contemporary morocco worn, illus. color (£2800); 21 Feb.,
#132, 1 pl. only, “King Lear,” engraved by Earlom, marginal stains, with 2 other pls. from Boydell’s
Shakespeare series, the Fuseli illus. color (£100); #135, 1 pl. only, “Hamlet,” engraved by Thew,
marginal stains, with a pl. for “Hamlet” by Legat after West, the Fuseli illus. color (£140). EB, May, 1
pl. only, “King Henry the Fourth,” engraved by Leney, lower margin stained, framed ($99.90). EB, Oct., 1
pl. only, “King Lear,” engraved by Earlom (offered at the “buy it now” price of $325); 1 pl. only,
<pb id="p42-135" n="135"/>
“King Henry the Fourth,” engraved by Leney (offered at the “buy it now” price of $225); Nov., 1 pl.
only, “King Henry the Fifth,” engraved by Thew (£23). Bauman Rare Books, Dec. online cat., 2 vols., 19<hi
rend="s">th</hi>-century half morocco rebacked and repaired ($28,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Boydell’s Graphic Illustrations of . . . Shakspeare</hi>, c. 1803. See under
Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
              <p>Cowper, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1806. Thornton’s Bookshop, June online cat., 2 vols.,
foxed, contemporary calf very worn, vol. 2 rebacked (£75).</p>
              <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi>, New York, 1807. EB, Feb., 2 vols. in 1, foxed,
contemporary calf worn (no bids on a required minimum bid of $199.95). Includes 3 pls. after Fuseli,
‘Nightmare,” “Flora Attired by the Elements,” and “Fertilization of Egypt.” See also Darwin under
Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
              <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Temple of Nature</hi>, 1803. Bauman Rare Books, June online cat.,
“period-style full . . . calf” ($2600).</p>
              <p>Gray, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, published by Du Roveray, 1800. Jeff Weber, June online cat.,
Edwards of Halifax calf binding and fore-edge painting, rebacked ($4000). Georges de Lucenay, June online
cat., full morocco (€750).</p>
              <p>Homer, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, published by Du Roveray,
1805-06. PBA, 26 June, #2127, 12 vols. in 6, occasional foxing, later 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century calf,
binding illus. color online ($550).</p>
              <p>Hume, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi>, [1852]. EB, Aug., Fuseli’s pl. only, “The
Death of Beaufort” engraved by Rogers, marginal browning (no bids on a required minimum bid of £1.50);
Aug.-Sept., another impression (no bids on a required minimum bid of £3.99).</p>
              <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man.</hi> See under Letterpress Books with Engravings by
and after Blake, above.</p>
              <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, 1789-98. EB, May, 1 pl. only, “S<hi
rend="s">t</hi>. John,” engraved by Holloway (€9.99); 1 pl. only, “Christ at the Sepulchre: A Scene from
Raphael,” engraved by Holloway (no bids on a required minimum bid of €9.99). For complete copies of the
book, see under Letterpress Books with Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, published by Suttaby, Evance, and Fox, 1821. James
Cummins, Dec. 2007 online cat., contemporary calf ($200). Includes 2 pls. after Fuseli, “The Birth of Sin”
(frontispiece) and “The Shepherd’s Dream” (vignette on the title p.).</p>
              <p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works.</hi> EB, Feb., published by Chidley, 1842, publisher’s
cloth (no bids on a required minimum bid of £10); May, 2 vols., published by Suttaby, 1808 (vol. 1), 1806
(vol. 2), pls. badly foxed, contemporary calf very worn, 1 cover detached (£12.50). Houle Rare Books, June
online cat., published by Churton, 1838, full morocco ($175). Rulon-Miller, June cat. 136, #896, published by
Chidley, 1844, contemporary morocco ($250). EB, Aug., published by Bohn, 1848, some stains, contemporary calf
very worn (no bids on a required minimum bid of $49.95). Vol. 1 of the Suttaby ed. includes a frontispiece
after Fuseli, “The Birth of Sin,” 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> published in the 1806 issue, and “The
Shepherd’s Dream” after Fuseli on the title p., both later used by Suttaby in the 1821 ed. of 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (see previous entry). The Churton, Chidley, and Bohn eds. include “Silence,”
engraved by Rogers.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Penny Magazine of the Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge</hi>,
vol. 1, issue of 14 July 1832. EB, Dec. 2007, disbound (£2.50). Includes John Jackson’s wood engraving of
“Lycidas” after Fuseli.</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi>, 1802. See under Letterpress Books with
Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, Basil, 1800. EB, Feb., 1 pl. only, “Prospero,
Miranda, Caliban and Ariel,” engraved by Wolf, marginal tears and soiling (no bids on a required minimum bid
of $9, but “the seller ended this listing early because the item” was “no longer available for
sale”).</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi>, London, 1811. See under Letterpress Books with
Engravings by and after Blake, above.</p>
              <p>Sotheby, <hi rend="i">Oberon</hi>, 1805. EB, Feb., 2 vols. in 1, contemporary calf worn
($173.50). Veatchs Arts of the Book, June online cat., 2 vols., contemporary calf ($280). Libreria Antiquaria
Gozzini, June online cat., 2 vols., calf worn (€220).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Tatler</hi>, published by Sharpe, 1803-04. EB, Jan.-Feb., vol. 3 (of 1804) only,
with “Tiresias Appearing to Odysseus in the Underworld,” engraved by Bromley after Fuseli, and 1 pl. by
Parker after Thomson, contemporary calf worn, part of spine missing ($34).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Works of the British Poets</hi>, ed. Park, 1805-11. Golden Books Group, Dec.
2007 online cat., 49 vols., full calf worn (£1450). Includes 2 pls. after Fuseli illustrating 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi></p>
              <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the . . . Collection . . . of . . . Angerstein</hi>, 1823.
EB, July, light marginal staining, fancy contemporary morocco ($310).</p>
              <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Pictures by British Artists, in the Possession of Sir John
Fleming Leicester</hi>, 1821. Quaritch, Nov. online cat., #12, uncut in contemporary half morocco worn
(£250).</p>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p42-136" n="136"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">LINNELL, JOHN</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Three drawings in a folio. See the 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> entry under Richmond, below.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">An Afternoon Fishing</hi>, attributed to Linnell. Oil, 25.5 × 30.0 cm. BH, 9
Sept., #284, illus. color (£3360). I suspect that this painting might be by William Linnell, John Linnell’s
son.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">An Area of Cleared Ground with a Mound of Earth at Bayswater.</hi> Watercolor,
10.0 × 13.5 cm., signed and dated “Bayswater 1812.” CSK, 11 Nov., #509, illus. color (£6250; estimate
£600-800).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Boar Hunt in Olden Times.</hi> Oil, 30.0 × 47.0 cm., signed. SL, 19 Nov.,
#51, illus. color (£3750).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Distant View of Lancing College.</hi> Watercolor, 22.8 × 40.6 cm. CSK, 12
March, #22, illus. color (not sold; estimate £3000-5000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Evening.</hi> Oil, 38.1 × 55.9 cm., signed and dated 1849. CNY, 8 April, #81,
illus. color ($11,250).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Evening, Storm Clearing Off.</hi> Oil, 39.0 × 58.4 cm., signed, datable to
1818-19. Fine Art Society and Lowell Libson, April cat., <hi rend="i">Power and Poetry: The Art of John
Linnell</hi>, #2, illus. color (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">An Extensive Landscape, Possibly the Weald of Kent.</hi> Pen and ink and
watercolor over pencil, 27.0 × 37.0 cm., datable to c. 1813-16. BH, 11 March, #31, illus. color (£50,400;
estimate £4000-6000). See illus. 7.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Farmer’s Boy.</hi> Oil, 61.0 × 44.0 cm., signed and dated 1830. Fine Art
Society and Lowell Libson, April cat., <hi rend="i">Power and Poetry: The Art of John Linnell</hi>, #4, illus.
color (price on request). For earlier sales and cat. listings, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.4 (spring 2007):
140. Possibly related in subject to Blake’s “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>; see
also <hi rend="i">Piping down the Valley Wild</hi>, below.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Harvest Field.</hi> Oil and watercolor, 22.0 × 30.0 cm., signed and dated
1851. SL, 19 Nov., #53, illus. color (£3750).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Harvest Time in Sussex.</hi> Oil, 63.2 × 101.6 cm., signed. SNY, 18 April,
#111, illus. color (not sold; estimate $60,000-80,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Hastings Beach</hi>, attributed to Linnell. Oil, 26.0 × 18.0 cm. EB, Oct.
(offered at the “buy it now” price of $2495 or “best offer”).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Haymakers.</hi> Oil, 30.5 × 48.0 cm. SL, 19 Nov., #52, illus. color
(£2500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Heathland.</hi> Oil, 22.9 × 30.5 cm., signed. GL, 23 Oct., #1138, illus. color
online (£950). Previously sold GL, 25 April 2007, #1256 (£1200). I am a little uneasy about the attribution
to Linnell.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Isle of Wight from Lymington Quay.</hi> Oil, 28.6 × 40.0 cm., signed and
dated 1825. Fine Art Society and Lowell Libson, April cat., <hi rend="i">Power and Poetry: The Art of John
Linnell</hi>, #3, illus. color (price on request). For earlier cat. listings, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 40.4
(spring 2007): 140.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Midday Rest.</hi> Oil, 71.0 × 92.0 cm., signed and dated 1852. BH, 29 Oct.,
#103, illus. color (£6600).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">An Old Mill near Redhill, Surrey</hi>, circle of John Linnell. Watercolor, 33.0
× 46.0 cm., signed. BH, 11 March, #29, illus. color (£1560). The printed cat. attributes this work to
Linnell, but this was amended at the beginning of the auction to “Circle of John Linnell.” This may be a
drawing by one of Linnell’s sons.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Piping down the Valley Wild.</hi> Oil, 56.0 × 68.7 cm., signed. CSK, 12 March,
#24, illus. color (£5250). The title, which may not be Linnell’s own, suggests a relationship with
Blake’s “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> See also <hi rend="i">The Farmer’s
Boy</hi>, above.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Mrs. Nasmyth.</hi> Pencil, colored chalks, and watercolor, 56.1 ×
40.5 cm., signed and dated 1836. W/S Fine Art, July cat., <hi rend="i">British Works on Paper</hi>, #38,
illus. color (£10,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Professor Mylne.</hi> Oil, 41.5 × 34.5 cm., signed. BH, 8 April,
#62, illus. color (£1680).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Road to the Village of Sudfield, Sussex.</hi> Oil, 50.8 × 81.3 cm., signed.
CSK, 12 March, #25, illus. color (£3500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">St. John the Baptist Preaching in the Wilderness.</hi> Oil, 98.0 × 136.0 cm.,
signed and dated 1828-33. BH, 29 Oct., #102, illus. color (not sold; estimate £6000-8000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Sky Study.</hi> Black and white chalk, 15.5 × 23.3 cm., signed. Guy Peppiatt
Fine Art, winter 2008-09 cat., #18, illus. color (£300).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Storm in Harvest Time.</hi> Oil, 45.7 × 61.0 cm., signed and dated 1856.
Fine Art Society and Lowell Libson, April cat., <hi rend="i">Power and Poetry: The Art of John Linnell</hi>,
#9, illus. color (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Studies of Children.</hi> Pencil and chalk on blue paper, 27.0 × 25.5 cm.,
signed and dated 1811. BL, 23 Oct., #153, illus. color (£220).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of Harvesters.</hi> Black and white chalk, 19.4 × 28.6 cm. Guy Peppiatt
Fine Art, Winter 2008-09 cat., #19, illus. color (£400).</p>
              <pb id="p42-137" n="137"/>
              <figure n="wealdkent.42.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="357">
                <head>7. John Linnell (or Samuel Palmer?)</head>
                <figDesc><hi rend="i">An Extensive Landscape, Possibly the Weald of Kent.</hi> Pen and ink and
watercolor over pencil, 27.0 × 37.0 cm., datable to c. 1813-16. Sold BH, 11 March, #31, firmly attributed to
“John Linnell,” for £50,400 on an estimate of only £4000-6000. John Windle tells me that the surprising
price resulted from speculations, on the part of several leading London dealers, that this drawing is by
Palmer. As the auction catalogue points out, this watercolor is stylistically similar to Linnell’s
landscapes <hi rend="i">North Wales, Dolbadern</hi>, and <hi rend="i">River Kennet, near Newbury</hi> (both
signed by Linnell); for illustrations, see <hi rend="i">John Linnell: A Centennial Exhibition</hi>, ed.
Katharine Crouan, Fitzwilliam Museum and Yale Center for British Art (1982-83), nos. 26, 35. These works,
however, lack the strong, sharp outlining of forms in pen and ink exemplified by the landscape reproduced
here. In this regard, <hi rend="i">An Extensive Landscape</hi> is closer to Palmer’s work of a later
date—see, for example, <hi rend="i">Study of a Garden at Tintern</hi> of 1835 (Raymond Lister, 
<hi rend="i">Catalogue Raisonné of the Works of Samuel Palmer</hi> [Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1988], no. 232).
Both artists drew landscapes of the Weald of Kent. I suspect that further evidence, such as provenance
records, will be needed before a definite attribution can be proposed. Photo courtesy of Bonhams.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <p><hi rend="i">Woodcutters and Shepherds.</hi> Oil, 71.1 × 91.4 cm., datable to the 1850s.
Bill Hood &amp; Sons auction, Delray Beach, Florida, 25 Nov., #202, illus. color online ($4400).</p>
              <p>Autograph letter signed to Richard E. Tagart, July 1846. EB, Oct., 2 pp. concerning
Linnell’s portrait of G. W. Wood (offered at the “buy it now” price of £150).</p>
              <p>“Sheep at Noon” or “Midday,” etching, 1818. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit
(price on request).</p>
              <p>Linnell, <hi rend="i">Michael Angelo’s Frescoes in the Sistine Chapel</hi>, 1834. J &amp; S
Wilbraham, Aug. online cat. 76, #146, pls. lightly water stained, contemporary half morocco (£750). Probably
the same copy offered by Wilbraham in Feb. 2006 for £1000.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">MORTIMER, JOHN HAMILTON</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Three Gentlemen in a Landscape.</hi> Oil, 75.0 × 63.0 cm., probably dating from
the mid-1760s. SL, 5 June, #49, illus. color (£34,850).</p>
              <p>“An Academy,” engraved by Ravenet, 1771. EB, Jan., stains in lower margin (offered at the
“buy it now” price of £90); same impression?, March (£37).</p>
              <pb id="p42-138" n="138"/>
              <p>“King John Delivering Magna Charta to the Barons,” engraved in stipple by Ryland, 1783.
St. Charles Gallery auction, New Orleans, 8 Dec. 2007, #261, color printed and with touches of hand coloring,
matted and framed close to the image, illus. color online ($125).</p>
              <p>“Nebuchadnezzar Recovering His Reason,” engraved by Blyth, 1781. BL, 17 July, #57,
printed in brown, framed, with 2 prints after Henry Bunbury (not sold; estimate £150-200).</p>
              <p>“Packhorse with Soldiers” (inscribed “To Colonel William Butler . . .”), etching by
Blyth, 1783. EB, Dec. 2007, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> st., marginal tears and stains ($40).</p>
              <p>“Shylock,” etching, 1776. EB, Sept., hand colored (no bids on a required minimum bid of
$50).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">PALMER, SAMUEL</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Beddgelert Bridge, North Wales.</hi> Watercolor, 25.0 × 36.0 cm., datable to
1837. SL, 4 Dec., #158, illus. color (£7500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Bright Cloud, Shepherd and Windmill.</hi> Brown wash, 8.5 × 11.0 cm., datable
to 1832-33. BH, 11 March, #28, illus. color (not sold; estimate £15,000-20,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Children Gleaning in a Cornfield.</hi> Watercolor, 18.7 × 40.0 cm., signed and
datable to 1846. CL, 4 June, #92, illus. color (not sold; estimate £15,000-20,000). Previously sold SL, 10
Nov. 1994, #181 (£9200).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The End of the Day: A Recollection of Italy.</hi> Watercolor, 14.3 × 21.0 cm.,
signed, datable to the early 1870s. W/S Fine Art, July cat., <hi rend="i">British Works on Paper</hi>, #43,
illus. color (£75,000). Previously offered by W/S Fine Art, June-July 2007 cat., #35, illus. (price on
application).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">An Extensive Landscape, Possibly the Weald of Kent.</hi> See under Linnell,
above, and illus. 7.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Landscape with a Glowing Cloud.</hi> Watercolor, 6.2 × 11.8 cm., possibly
dating from the early 1830s. W/S Fine Art, July cat., <hi rend="i">British Works on Paper</hi>, #42, illus.
color (“sold”). Previously offered by W/S Fine Art and Andrew Wyld, June 2005 cat., #50, illus.
(£8500).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Road past a Farm.</hi> Watercolor, 6.7 × 13.0 cm., possibly dating from the
early 1830s. W/S Fine Art, July cat., <hi rend="i">British Works on Paper</hi>, #41, illus. color (£8500);
SL, 4 Dec., #157, illus. color (not sold; estimate £4000-6000). Previously sold CL, 22 March 1966, #59, with
another watercolor by Palmer, illus. (to Anthony Reed Gallery, London, no price record), and CL, 19 Nov. 1985,
#207, both watercolors, illus. (£3240).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Vintage.</hi> Pencil and brown wash, 13.6 × 7.7 cm., an illus. to Dickens,
<hi rend="i">Pictures from Italy</hi>, 1846. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit (price on request).</p>
              <p>Edmund Spenser, <hi rend="i">The Workes</hi> (1679), and Abraham Cowley, <hi rend="i">The
Works</hi> (1688), both with a few annotations by Palmer. Quaritch, winter 2008-09 cat. 2008/20, #52, from the
collection of Raymond Lister, both vols. contemporary calf rebacked (£8500).</p>
              <p>“The Bellman,” etching. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, “proof in the published
state” (price on request). Hindman auction, Chicago, 7 Sept., #306, described as a “working proof” but
the illus. suggests 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st. (possibly with some hand touching), small repair in image, mat
burn, some discoloration and foxing, illus. color online ($11,000; estimate $3000-5000).</p>
              <p>“Christmas,” or “Folding the Last Sheep,” etching. Larkhall Fine Art, Dec. 2007
online cat., 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> st. from the <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, 1882, illus. color (£3250);
July-Sept. exhibit, “fine early proof” (price on request).</p>
              <p>“The Cypress Grove,” etching. EB, Sept.-Oct., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. (no bids on a
required minimum bid of $699.99).</p>
              <p>“The Early Ploughman,” etching. EB, March, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st. from Hamerton, 
<hi rend="i">Etching and Etchers</hi>, 1868, scattered foxing ($295); another impression, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi>
st. from Hamerton, 1868 (no bids on a required minimum bid of $699.99); April, another impression, probably
5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., pencil signature, framed ($698). Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, 4
impressions, “fine fourth state proof,” “fine sixth state proof,” “fine seventh state proof,” and
“final [9<hi rend="s">th</hi>] state printed by Griggs” (prices on request). EB, July, 5<hi
rend="s">th</hi> st. (no bids on a required minimum bid of $899.99); same impression, Oct. (offered at the
“buy it now” price of $999.99).</p>
              <p>“The Herdsman’s Cottage,” etching. EB, May, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. from Hamerton,
<hi rend="i">Etching and Etchers</hi>, 1880 ($430); June, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. (no bids on a required
minimum bid of £475). Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, “published [2<hi rend="s">nd</hi>] state”
(price on request). Hindman auction, Chicago, 11 Sept., #2407, 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st., paper browned
($100).</p>
              <p>“The Morning of Life,” etching. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, 3 impressions,
“touched trial proof,” “superb pattern proof in an unrecorded state,” and “published [7<hi
rend="s">th</hi>] state” (prices on request). EB, Sept., 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st. ($560). BL, 23 Oct.,
#476, 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., illus. color (£650). SL, 19 Nov., #20, 5<hi rend="s">th</hi> st., pencil
signature, illus. color (not sold; estimate £3000-4000).</p>
              <p>“Opening the Fold,” etching. EB, Oct., 8<hi rend="s">th</hi> st. (offered at the “buy
it now” price of $1599.99 or “best offer”).</p>
              <pb id="p42-139" n="139"/>
              <p>“The Rising Moon,” etching. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, “published [7<hi
rend="s">th</hi>] state” (price on request).</p>
              <p>“The Sepulchre,” etching. Abbott and Holder, May online cat. 388, #216, 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> st. (£395). EB, Sept.-Oct., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st. (offered at the “buy it now” price
of $699.99 or “best offer”).</p>
              <p>“The Skylark,” etching. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, “published [7<hi
rend="s">th</hi>?] state” (price on request).</p>
              <p>“The Weary Ploughman,” etching. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, “published [8<hi
rend="s">th</hi>?] state” (price on request). SL, 19 Nov., #21, st. not identified but probably 8<hi
rend="s">th</hi>, illus. color (£1125).</p>
              <p>“The Willow,” etching. Larkhall Fine Art, April online cat., 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.,
illus. color (£1650); July-Sept. exhibit, “early first state proof” and “final [3<hi rend="s">rd</hi>]
state printed by Griggs or Short” (prices on request).</p>
              <p>Dickens, <hi rend="i">Pictures from Italy</hi>, 1846. CNY, 2 April, #125, 1<hi
rend="s">st</hi> ed., publisher’s cloth, “unrecorded variant issue binding,” title p. illus. color
($438).</p>
              <p>Hamerton, <hi rend="i">Etching and Etchers</hi>, 1880. BL, 19 Dec. 2007, #87, foxed and
browned, original roan-backed cloth worn (£1300). Includes Palmer’s etching, “The Herdsman’s
Cottage,” 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.</p>
              <p>A. H. Palmer, <hi rend="i">Life and Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>, 1892. BL, 19 Dec. 2007,
#398, lightly foxed, later half morocco worn (£110); 29 Feb., #894, publisher’s cloth rebacked and worn,
with Dickens, <hi rend="i">Pictures from Italy</hi>, 1846, with an “amateur foreedge painting,” apparently
publisher’s cloth very worn (£160). EB, Aug., publisher’s cloth (offered at the “buy it now” price of
$425 or “best offer”). <hi rend="i">Life and Letters</hi> includes Palmer’s etching, “The Willow,”
2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> st.</p>
              <p>S. Palmer, <hi rend="i">English Version of the Eclogues of Virgil.</hi> EB, Sept., 2<hi
rend="s">nd</hi> ed., 1884, large-paper issue, publisher’s vellum, scattered light foxing (no bids on a
ridiculously high starting bid of $7999.99). BL, 30 Oct., #148, 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed., 1883, large-paper
issue, some marginal browning to the pls., publisher’s vellum worn, illus. color (£2200; estimate
£800-1200).</p>
              <p>S. Palmer, <hi rend="i">The Shorter Poems of John Milton</hi>, 1889. BL, 16 May, #9,
large-paper issue, publisher’s vellum (£160).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">PARKER, JAMES</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Akenside, <hi rend="i">Pleasures of the Imagination</hi>, 1795. J &amp; S Wilbraham, July
online cat. 75, #1, contemporary calf (£35). Includes 1 pl. by Parker after Stothard.</p>
              <p>Falconer, <hi rend="i">Shipwreck</hi>, 1806. EB, April, contemporary calf worn (no bids on a
required minimum bid of $99.99). Includes 3 pls. by Parker after Stothard dated 1795 in their imprints.</p>
              <p>Hume, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi>, 1793-1806. EB, May, 1 pl. only, “Charles II and
Sir William Temple,” Parker after Stothard (no bids on a required minimum bid of £3.99).</p>
              <p>Johnson, <hi rend="i">Rasselas</hi>, 1796. EB, Feb., contemporary calf (£19.87). Includes 4
pls. by Parker after Stothard.</p>
              <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">The Plays of William Shakspeare</hi>, ed. Manley Wood, 14 vols.,
London: George Kearsley, 1806. Vangsgaards Antikvariat, Dec. 2007 online cat., contemporary calf worn,
bindings illus. color ($2500). Includes 4 pls. by Parker, dated 1803 and 1804 in their imprints, 2 after
Stothard, 1 after Philip De Loutherbourg, and 1 after Edward Burney. Not recorded in G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
“The Journeyman and the Genius: James Parker and His Partner William Blake with a List of Parker’s
Engravings,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 49 (1996): 208-31.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Tatler</hi>, published by Sharpe, 1803-04. See under Fuseli, above.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">RICHMOND, GEORGE</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Three drawings by Richmond, and 3 by John Linnell, in a folio. Pencil, pen and ink, 32.7 ×
44.2 cm. and smaller. SL, 4 Dec., #121, including a self-portrait of Richmond dated 1871 and a drawing of the
New Road, Paddington, by Linnell dated 1811, the self-portrait illus. color (not sold; estimate £4000-6000).
The self-portrait previously sold SL, 27 Nov. 1975, #33 (£320).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Figure Weeping over a Grave.</hi> Pen and brown ink, brown wash, 8.0 × 12.7
cm., signed and dated Jan. 1827 on a sheet attached to the backboard. SL, 4 Dec., #124, illus. color
(£17,500; estimate £4000-6000). A record auction price for a drawing by Richmond. Previously sold SL, 16
March 1978, #55, illus. (£550 to Agnew’s).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Isaac Going Forth to Meditate.</hi> Oil, 51.0 × 30.5 cm. SL, 5 June, #88,
illus. color (not sold; estimate £20,000-30,000); 28 Oct., #148, illus. color (not sold; estimate
£3000-5000). Previously sold SL, 30 Jan. 1985, #94 (£1430 to Agnew’s acting for a private collector,
Philadelphia).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Portrait of Henry Walter.</hi> Pencil with touches of pen and brown ink, 22.0 ×
16.4 cm., initialed and dated 28 Dec. 1827. SL, 19 Nov., #22, illus. color (£6250). Henry Walter (1799-1849)
was among the circle of young artists who gathered around Blake in his final years.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">St. John at Patmos.</hi> Oil, 47.0 × 29.0 cm. SL, 5 June, #89, illus. color
(not sold; estimate £10,000-15,000); 28 Oct., #147,
<pb id="p42-140" n="140"/>
illus. color (not sold; estimate £3000-5000). Previously sold SL, 30 Jan. 1985, #95 (£1760 to Agnew’s
acting for a private collector, Philadelphia).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Samson Carrying the Gates of Gaza.</hi> Pen and brown ink, study of a standing
male nude on the verso, 16.5 × 12.2 cm., inscribed “jany 1827” on the recto. SL, 4 Dec., #123, illus.
color (£3750). Previously sold SL, 18 Nov. 1976, #181A, illus. (£150), and CL, 19 March 1985, #35, from the
collection of Donald Heald, illus. (£302).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Samson Slaying the Philistines with the Jawbone of an Ass.</hi> Pen and brown
ink, figure studies on the verso, 15.2 × 14.1 cm. SL, 4 Dec., #122, “recorded” as having been “made by
Richmond on 24<hi rend="s">th</hi> January 1827,” illus. color (£4375). Previously sold CL, 12 June 1973,
#172 (no price record).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study for “Comus—The Measure.”</hi> Pencil and black chalk, 24.6 × 29.2
cm., probably dating from the 1830s. W/S Fine Art, July cat., <hi rend="i">British Works on Paper</hi>, #39,
illus. color (£6000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">View across a Wooded Valley.</hi> Watercolor, 19.2 × 39.4 cm. W/S Fine Art,
Master Drawings exhibit at Dickinson, New York, 14-26 Jan., #20, illus. color online (price on request); July
cat., <hi rend="i">British Works on Paper</hi>, #40, illus. color (£7500).</p>
              <p>“The Fatal Bellman,” engraving. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit, “superb early
impression” (price on request).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">ROMNEY, GEORGE</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">Crouched and Huddled Figures.</hi> Pencil, 65.0 × 140.0 cm., datable to c.
1790. BL, 23 Oct., #80, illus. color (£360). Possibly a study for John Howard visiting a lazaretto.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Infant Shakespeare.</hi> Pen and ink, 11.0 × 18.7 cm. W/S Fine Art, Master
Drawings exhibit at Dickinson, New York, 14-26 Jan., #21, illus. color online (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">John Howard Visiting a Lazaretto.</hi> Pencil, 13.7 × 23.2 cm. W/S Fine Art,
July cat., <hi rend="i">British Works on Paper</hi>, #8, illus. color online (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Macbeth Discovering Banquo’s Ghost.</hi> Pen and gray ink, gray wash, 32.7 ×
49.2 cm. SL, 5 June, #159, illus. color (not sold; estimate £3000-4000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Standing Figure.</hi> Pen and brown ink, 18.1 × 7.4 cm. SL, 5 June, #160,
illus. color (£4000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study for the Head of a Sailor</hi> (<hi rend="i">Act 1 of Shakespeare’s</hi>
The Tempest). Oil, 44.0 × 35.0 cm., datable to c. 1787. SL, 5 June, #57, illus. color (£51,650).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Study of a Gentleman.</hi> Pencil and brown wash, 42.0 × 28.0 cm. W/S Fine Art,
Master Drawings exhibit at Dickinson, New York, 14-26 Jan., #22, illus. color online (price on request).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Study of Elizabeth Warren, Later Viscountess Bulkeley, as Hebe.</hi> Pen and
brown ink, brown wash, 16.9 × 9.1 cm. SL, 5 June, #161, illus. color (£10,000).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Thelassie, the French Dancer.</hi> Pen and sepia ink, 10.2 × 17.8 cm. Abbott
and Holder, March “Selected Six,” online cat. 387 (£1750). Previously offered Agnew’s, Feb. 1998 cat.,
#1, illus. color (£2750); previously sold under the title <hi rend="i">Studies of Thelassie, the French
Dancer, Reclining</hi>, CL, 21 Nov. 2007, #13, illus. (£875).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">RUNCIMAN, ALEXANDER</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>“Cormar Attacking the Spirit of the Waters,” etching. EB, Feb., incorrectly titled
“Perseus and Andromeda,” framed (no bids on a required minimum bid of $174.99).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">SHERMAN, WELBY</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>“The Shepherd,” engraving. Larkhall Fine Art, July-Sept. exhibit (price on request).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">STOTHARD, THOMAS</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Books with illustrations by Stothard are listed only for editions not recorded in the
standard reference works, A. C. Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London: Bullen, 1906), and
Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard: The Mechanisms of Art Patronage in England circa 1800</hi>
(Columbia: U of Missouri P, 1988).</p>
              <p>Fifteen pen and ink and wash drawings, dating from the late 1770s to the late 1820s, ranging
in size between 3.8 × 3.8 cm. and 22.9 × 17.8 cm. Abbott and Holder, June online cat., #1-15 of the
“Select Group,” sold individually, illus. color (£275-425 each).</p>
              <p>Five monochrome wash drawings datable to the early 1780s, each approx. 13.5 × 8.5 cm., 4 for
<hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi> (<hi rend="i">Tales of the Genii, Arabian Nights</hi> [2], and 
<hi rend="i">Chinese Tales</hi>) and 1 for Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Rasselas</hi> (“Achmet and Selima”) in 
<hi rend="i">Lady’s Magazine.</hi> EB, May-June, offered at “buy it now” prices of £150-190 each.</p>
              <p>Three monochrome wash drawings, each approx. 9.0 × 7.0 cm., for Mackenzie’s 
<hi rend="i">The Man of Feeling</hi>, 1800. GL, 12 June, #2313, framed, illus. color (£240).</p>
              <pb id="p42-141" n="141"/>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Dancers.</hi> Pencil, leaf 6.4 × 11.4 cm., probably executed in the 1780s.
EB, March-April (£21).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Measure for Measure</hi>, attributed to Stothard. Oil, 8.3 × 8.3 cm. CSK, 11
Nov., #534, illus. color (£138; estimate £300-500). Possibly by Stothard, but this might be a copy to size
of the engraving of the design by Charles Warren, published in <hi rend="i">The Plays of William
Shakspeare</hi>, ed. Manley Wood (London: G. Kearsley, 1806) 2: facing 293.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Sheet of Figural and Animal Studies</hi>, attributed to Stothard. Pencil, pen
and ink, 19.1 × 24.2 cm. CSK, 11 Nov., #562, illus. color (not sold; estimate £600-800). The attribution
seems solid to me.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Sylvia and the Outlaws: A Scene from Shakespeare’s “Two Gentlemen of
Verona.”</hi> Oil, 69.9 × 52.4 cm., indistinctly signed. CSK, 3 Sept., #183, illus. color (not sold;
estimate £8000-12,000). Very probably painted for Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, engraved by John Ogborne
and published in Boydell’s edition of the <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi> (1802) and 
<hi rend="i">Boydell’s Graphic Illustrations of . . . Shakspeare</hi> (c. 1803).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">The Tempest.</hi> Oil, 101.5 × 127.0 cm. SL, 30 Oct., #198, illus. color (not
sold; estimate £3000-5000). I am uneasy about the attribution to Stothard.</p>
              <p>“Charlotte’s Visit to the Vicar,” engraved by Ogborne, 1785. EB, April, foxed and
stained (£9.16). A separate pl. illustrating Goethe’s <hi rend="i">Sorrows of Young Werther.</hi> Not in
Coxhead or Bennett, but listed in <hi rend="i">Poetic Description of Choice and Valuable Prints, Published by
Mr. Macklin</hi> (1794) 64.</p>
              <p>“The Evening Prayer” and “The Morning Lesson,” a pair engraved by Nutter, 1792. EB,
April, slight foxing, framed (no bids on a required minimum bid of £99). Apparently separate pls., but
possibly removed from a book; not in Coxhead or Bennett.</p>
              <p>“Joseph Interpreting the Dream of Pharaoh’s Chief,” mezzotint by Young, 1798. EB,
April, laid paper, water stain on verso (£21).</p>
              <p>“Joseph’s Brethren Presenting His Bloody Coat to Jacob Their Father,” mezzotint by
Young, 1798. EB, May, laid paper (no bids on a required minimum bid of £12.99); same impression, Aug.
(£11.50).</p>
              <p>“Pilgrimage to Canterbury,” engraved by Schiavonetti and Heath, 1817. Cheffins auction,
Cambridge, 10 July, #297, framed, illus. color online (£150). EB, Sept., framed (no bids on an aggressive
minimum bid of $499.99); same impression, Sept.-Oct. (offered at the “buy it now” price of $595 or “best
offer”).</p>
              <p>“Sailors in Port,” engraved by Ward, 1798. EB, Jan., marginal stains and foxing
(€68).</p>
              <p>“Shakespeare’s Seven Ages of Man Illustrated,” engraved by Bromley. BNY, 5 April, #97,
a series of 7 color-printed and hand-colored prints, 20<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco, illus. color
($3000). EB, Sept., uncolored set, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century half calf very worn, front cover detached
($177.50).</p>
              <p>Bray, <hi rend="i">Life of Stothard</hi>, 1851, extra-illus. copies only. Donald Heald, Oct.
online cat., #6120, extended to 10 vols. quarto, 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century morocco by Riviere, binding
illus. color ($28,500). The copy that failed to sell at BNY, 24 Oct. 2007, #118 (estimate $20,000-30,000). For
details, including a list of the pls. engraved by Blake, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.4 (spring 2008): 162.
John Windle, Nov. private offer, extended to 10 vols. quarto, extra-illus. with 10 autograph manuscripts, 69
drawings, and 759 prints (including a proof of Blake’s engraving for Chaucer’s <hi rend="i">Poetical
Works</hi>, 1782—see appendix 1), 19<hi rend="s">th</hi>-century half morocco worn, some covers detached
(acquired by Victoria University Library, Toronto).</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Companion to the Altar, Shewing the Nature and Necessity of a Sacramental
Preparation</hi>, n.d. (c. 1794). EB, June, bound with <hi rend="i">A New Version of the Psalms of David</hi>,
1794, later quarter roan (no bids on a required minimum bid of £4.99). Includes 5 pls. after Stothard also
published in <hi rend="i">The Book of Common Prayer</hi>, London, 1794.</p>
              <p>Gray, <hi rend="i">Elegy Written in a Country Church-Yard</hi>, London: John Van Voorst,
1839. EB, Dec. 2007, contemporary calf ($65). Includes 1 wood engraving by Charles Gray after Stothard.</p>
              <p>Mary Holland, <hi rend="i">The Modern Family Receipt Book</hi>, London: Thomas Tegg, 1825.
EB, Sept., uncut in original printed boards worn ($175). Includes a frontispiece, divided into 3 vignettes,
based on Stothard’s designs. Listed in Coxhead 217-18 only as a “Cookery Book” without author or title;
see also Bennett 86. The book has very little to do with cooking but is concerned with a wide variety of
domestic tasks, including “Brewing,” “Bleaching,” “Perfumes and Cosmetics,” and “Destroying
Vermin.”</p>
              <p>Swift, <hi rend="i">Gulliver’s Travels</hi>, London: H. McLean, n.d. (pls. dated 1823). EB,
April, browning and staining, contemporary calf rebacked ($14.99). Includes re-engravings of 2 Stothard
designs 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> published in <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, 1782.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">VON HOLST, THEODOR</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">A Man with a Club.</hi> Pencil, 16.5 × 14.0 cm., signed and dated 1844. BH, 11
March, #24, illus. color (not sold; estimate £1500-2000).</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p42-142" n="142"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Appendix 1: New Information on Blake’s Engravings</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Listed below are substantive additions or corrections to Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate
Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (1983), and Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
Illustrations</hi> (1991). Abbreviations and citation styles follow the respective volumes. Newly discovered
impressions of previously recorded published states of Blake’s engravings are listed for only the rarer
separate plates.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>“Job,” pp. 17-20. A previously unrecorded impression on laid paper, 41.1 × 59.0 cm., was
on exhibit at Tate Britain, 3 Nov. 2007 through 22 June 2008, on loan from a private collection. It is
reported to be a proof before letters, or at least before the signature immediately below the design, but with
the image the same as in the first state. The only recorded impression of the first state is in the Keynes
Family Trust, on deposit at the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. I have not seen this newly discovered
impression; the information given here is based on Martin Butlin and Robin Hamlyn, “Tate Britain Reveals
Nine New Blakes and Thirteen New Lines of Verse,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 42.2 (fall 2008): 52-54, illus.
The print, framed, was “acquired by the present owner at a south London market” (52). See the important
Butlin and Hamlyn essay for further information.</p>
            <p>“Enoch,” p. 56. For the sale of impression 1D, see the prefatory essay and Separate Plates
and Plates in Series, above.</p>
            <p>“George Cumberland’s Card,” pp. 111-22. For a previously unrecorded impression printed in
brown, see under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, above.</p>
            <p>“The Fall of Rosamond,” pp. 134-38. For a previously unrecorded impression, see under
Separate Plates and Plates in Series, above.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Chaucer, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, 1782, pp. 29-30. A proof before all letters of
Blake’s single pl. is included in an extra-illus. copy of A. E. Bray, <hi rend="i">Life of Thomas
Stothard</hi> (1851), now in the Victoria University Library, Toronto.</p>
            <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of George Romney</hi>, 1809, pp. 94-95. Text leaves of large-paper
copies show an “1807” watermark. Small-paper copies are watermarked “Rye Mill / 1807.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Appendix 2: Ruskin on Blake</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>John Ruskin (1819-1900) made numerous references to Blake in his many books, essays, and
letters. Those written (but not necessarily published) before 1863 (i.e., before the publication of
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>) are listed in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1400, 2592-95. There are,
however, many other comments by Ruskin on Blake and his works, including quotations from or allusions to his
writings, outside the purview of <hi rend="i">BB</hi> because brief and post-1863. Given Ruskin’s prominence
as Britain’s most important art critic of the Victorian era, all these passages (both listed and not listed
in <hi rend="i">BB</hi>) are worthy of citation and brief quotation in the journal of record for Blake
studies. Most of the texts quoted below are printed (some for the first time) in <hi rend="i">The Works of
John Ruskin</hi>, ed. E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn, 39 vols. (London: G. Allen; New York: Longmans,
Green, and Co., 1903-12), cited hereafter as <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> Passages are arranged in chronological
order to show Ruskin’s changing attitudes toward Blake’s life and art. There may be other references to
Blake haunting Ruskin’s vast oeuvres, but these are all I have been able to find.</p>
            <p>Letter to George Richmond, dated in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 36: 32 to “[1843?].” First
printed in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 36: 32-33, from which the entire letter is quoted here. 
<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2593.</p>
			<q>
My Dear Richmond,—Since I last saw you I have been looking very carefully over the portfolio of Blake’s
drawings, and I have got nervous about showing them to my father when he comes home, in the mass. He has been
<hi rend="i">very</hi> good to me—lately—with respect to some efforts which I desired to make under the
idea that Turner would not long be able to work—and these efforts he has made under my frequent assurances
that I should never be so captivated by any other man. Now I am under great fear that when he hears of my
present purchase, it will make him lose confidence in me, and cause him discomfort which I wish I could avoid.
If, therefore, I could diminish the quantity, and retain a few only of the most characteristic, I should be
glad.<lb/>
Now I feel the ungraciousness of saying this to you, but yet the purchase was so thoroughly of my own seeking
and determination, in spite of all you could say, that I trust you will not see the smallest ground for
finding fault with any one but me. I thought also that I should have hurt your feelings, if I had treated
directly with Hogarth [the dealer Joseph Hogarth]—otherwise I would have wished not to trouble you on the
subject; but I find the nervousness increasing upon me—not that I think less of the drawings than I did, but
that several circumstances have since taken place, which you shall know of hereafter, which make me feel
unwilling to ask my father for this sum at present to be so spent. Now, if I <hi rend="i">may</hi> treat with
Hogarth, pray do not give one further thought to the affair—the purchase was entirely and 
<hi rend="i">is</hi> completely mine, and <hi rend="i">but for you</hi> I should probably have paid 150 [pounds?]
instead of 100; but if you would rather that I should not speak directly to Hogarth, I wish you would see for
me on what terms he would either receive back the portfolio, and also let me retain four of the Larger
Drawings,—the Horse, the owls, the Newton, and the Nebuchadnezzar—or five including the Satan and Eve, and
the Goblin Huntsman, and Search for the Body of Harold. Forgive me this. I do assure you I love the memory of
your friend, and I shall love <hi rend="i">these</hi> drawings and never part with them, but I am afraid of
giving pain to my Father. <hi rend="i">My hope</hi> is that you will <hi rend="i">leave it to</hi> ME to treat
<pb id="p42-143" n="143"/>
with Hogarth at once—but I thought you would have felt it unkind. I think it would have been wrong—taking
your feelings towards Blake into consideration—to have done so without telling you.—Remember me most
faithfully to Mrs. Richmond, and believe me, my dear Richmond, ever most affectionately yours, J. Ruskin.
</q>
            <p>The works Ruskin mentions are probably either <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (“the Horse,” Butlin #295, Metropolitan Museum of Art; 312, Yale Center for British
Art), <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</hi> (“the owls,” Butlin
#318, Huntington Library), <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (Butlin #307, Lutheran Church in America, on deposit at
the Philadelphia Museum of Art), <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (Butlin #304, untraced since 1887), 
<hi rend="i">Satan Exulting over Eve</hi> (Butlin #292, J. Paul Getty Museum), probably <hi rend="i">Nimrod or
“Let Loose the Dogs of War,” Possible Study for “Night Thoughts”</hi> (“the Goblin Huntsman,”
Butlin #331, Nelson Art Gallery, Atkins Museum of Fine Arts), and <hi rend="i">The Search for the Body of
Harold</hi> (Butlin #61, untraced since Ruskin’s letter).
<q>
The editors of <hi rend="i">Works</hi> add in a footnote (36: 33) the following “subsequent note” showing
“that the matter was arranged”:<lb/>
Dear Richmond,—Best thanks for your kind note. I have spoken to Hogarth, who says he will think over it, and
arrange it to my satisfaction. After I hear his proposals I will make mine. Remember me to Mrs. Richmond,
Mary, and Julia [two of Richmond’s daughters].—Ever most affectionately yours, J. Ruskin.
</q></p>
            <p>Among the works Ruskin names as those he wished to “retain,” only <hi rend="i">Nimrod</hi>
is recorded by Butlin as once in Ruskin’s collection. He may have acquired some of the others and kept them
for a few years, but there is no record of his ownership. <hi rend="i">Newton, Nebuchadnezzar</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Satan Exulting</hi> were sold at auction in 1854; <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>
were acquired by Arthur Burgess c. 1878-80; Mrs. Gilchrist owned <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> by 1863.
See the diary entry for 22 Feb. 1878, below, for another of Blake’s large color prints Ruskin apparently
owned at that time. Most of the first letter is reprinted in Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">George Richmond: A
Critical Biography</hi> (London: Robin Garton, 1981) 64; the Blake references are quoted in Butlin 1: 157. See
also <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> (1887), below, for another description of the same
episode.</p>
            <p>The manuscript of <hi rend="i">The Seven Lamps of Architecture</hi> (1<hi rend="s">st</hi> ed.,
1849), a passage first printed in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 8: 256, from which quoted here. <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
#2595.</p>
			<q>
We have had two [men of genius] in the present century, two magnificent and mighty—William Blake and J. M.
W. Turner. . . . two men who if they had been given to us in a time of law, and of recognized discipline, if
they had had either teaching in their youth, or reverence in their manhood, might have placed our age on a
level with the proudest periods of creative art. But what have they done for us? The influence of the one
[Blake] is felt as much as the weight of last winter’s snow: and that of the other [Turner] has been so
shortened by our dulness [sic], and distorted by our misapprehension, that it may be doubted whether it has
wrought among us more of good or of evil.
</q>
            <p>Letter to the artist Mrs. Hugh Blackburn (née Jemima Wedderburn) dated “27 May.” First
printed in Ellen C. Clayton, <hi rend="i">English Female Artists</hi>, 2 vols. (London: Tinsley Brothers,
1876) 2: 406, from which quoted here. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #1400, 2593. No year is given for the letter, but
the context of other letters and references in Clayton’s book suggests 1855. <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 36: 109
dates the letter “[1850].”</p>
			<q>
I think this love of horror generally, in us British people, rises out of distress of mind, mixed with (I pray
your pardon) some slight affectation, and love of surprising people. But it seems to be natural to you, and to
some of the Germans. You and [Gottfried Augustus] Bürger [German poet, 1748-94] would have trumped each
other’s best tricks to some purpose. We have had one grand man of the same school—William Blake—whose
“Book of Job” fail not to possess yourself of—if it comes in your way; but there is a deep morality in
his horror—as in Dante’s: in yours there is little but desperation.
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 36: 109-10 (with some differences in wording and
punctuation).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Modern Painters</hi>, vol. 3, part 4 (London: Smith, Elder, 1856) 103, 259n1. 
<hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2594A.</p>
			<q>
Blake, perfectly powerful in the etched grotesque of the book of Job, fails always more or less as soon as he
adds colour; not merely for want of power (his eye for colour being naturally good), but because his subjects
seem, in a sort, insusceptible of completion; .... (103)<lb/>
Blake was sincere, but full of wild creeds, and somewhat diseased in brain. (259n1)
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 5: 137-38, 323.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Elements of Drawing</hi> (London: Smith, Elder, 1857), “Appendix: Things to
Be Studied,” 342. <hi rend="i">BB</hi> #2592A.</p>
			<q>
6. Blake.<lb/>
The “Book of Job,” engraved by himself, is of the highest rank in certain characters of imagination and
expression; in the mode of obtaining certain effects of light it will also be a very useful example to you. In
expressing conditions of glaring and flickering light, Blake is greater than Rembrandt.
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 15: 223.</p>
            <p>“The Cestus of Aglaia: Prefatory,” <hi rend="i">Art-Journal</hi> ns 4 (1 Jan. 1865): 6.</p>
			<q>
. . . one who might have been among the best of them, the last we heard of, finding refuge for an entirely
honest heart from a world which declares honesty to be impossible, only in a madness nearly as sorrowful as
its own;—the religious madness which makes a beautiful soul ludicrous and ineffectual; and so passes away,
bequeathing for our inheritance from its true and strong life, a pretty song about a tiger, another about a
bird-cage, two or three golden couplets, which no one will ever take the trouble to understand,—the
spiritual portrait of the ghost of a flea,—and the critical opinion that “the unorganised blots of Rubens
and Titian are not Art.”
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 19: 56. Ruskin alludes to three identifiable texts by
Blake, “The Tyger” (E 24-25), “Auguries of Innocence”
<pb id="p42-144" n="144"/>
(E 490, “A Robin Red breast in a Cage / Puts all Heaven in a Rage”), and “A Public Address” (E 576,
“The unorganized Blots &amp; Blurs of Rubens &amp; Titian are not Art . . .”). The “two or three golden
couplets” may be other lines from “Auguries of Innocence,” such as those Ruskin quotes elsewhere in his
writings (see below). For another reference to Blake’s criticism of Titian, see the diary entries for 22
Feb. 1878, below. Ruskin probably learned of the engraving of Blake’s “Ghost of a Flea” in John
Varley’s <hi rend="i">Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi> (1828) from the description and reproduction in Alexander
Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1863) 1: 254-55. Gilchrist 2: 148 is
probably the source for Ruskin’s quotation from “A Public Address”; Gilchrist also prints “Auguries of
Innocence” (2: 94-97). The “editorship” of these selections from Blake’s writings was “performed by
Mr. Dante Gabriel Rossetti” (Anne Gilchrist’s preface, 1: v-vi).</p>
            <p>“The Cestus of Aglaia: Chapter V”, <hi rend="i">Art-Journal</hi> ns 4 (1 June 1865):
178.</p>
			<q>
Our imagination is slower and clumsier than the French—rarer also, by far, in the average English mind. The
only man of power equal to [Paul Gustave] Doré’s [French artist, 1832-83] whom we have had lately among us,
was William Blake, whose temper fortunately took another turn.
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 19: 117.</p>
            <p>“The Cestus of Aglaia: Chapter VI,” <hi rend="i">Art-Journal</hi> ns 4 (1 July 1865):
199.</p>
			<q>
These are the opposite effects of Law and of Liberty on men of the highest powers. In the case of inferiors
the contrast is still more fatal. . . . But the inferiors under a system of license for the most part perish
in miserable effort; a few struggle into pernicious eminence—harmful alike to themselves and to all who
admire them; many die of starvation; many insane, either in weakness of insolent egotism, like [Benjamin
Robert] Haydon [English artist, 1786-1846], or in a conscientious agony of ignorant purpose and warped power,
like Blake.
</q>
            <p>The passage is reprinted in Ruskin, <hi rend="i">The Queen of the Air</hi> (London: Smith,
Elder &amp; Co., 1869) 183-85, with “ignorant purpose” changed (apparently by Ruskin) to “beautiful
purpose” in the final sentence. The reprint in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 19: 132-33 follows the 1869 text.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Eagle’s Nest</hi> (Keston, Kent: Smith, Elder, 1872) 23-24 (Lecture 2, “Of
Wisdom and Folly in Science,” delivered at Oxford, 10 Feb. 1872).</p>
			<q>
You must have nearly all heard of, many must have seen, the singular paintings; some also may have read the
poems, of William Blake. The impression that his drawings once made is fast, and justly, fading away, though
they are not without noble merit. But his poems have much more than merit; they are written with absolute
sincerity, with infinite tenderness, and, though in the manner of them diseased and wild, are in verity the
words of a great and wise mind, disturbed, but not deceived, by its sickness; nay, partly exalted by it, and
sometimes giving forth in fiery aphorism some of the most precious words of existing literature. One of these
passages I will ask you to remember; it will often be serviceable to you—<lb/>
<lb/>
“Doth the Eagle know what is in the pit,<lb/>
Or wilt thou go ask the Mole?”<lb/>
<lb/>
It would be impossible to express to you in briefer terms the great truth that there is a different kind of
knowledge good for every different creature, and that the glory of the higher creatures is in ignorance of
what is known to the lower.
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 22: 138. The quotation is from <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel</hi> (E 3), with the first word changed from “Does.” See also the letter of c. 1877, below.</p>
            <p>Letter 27, dated 27 Jan. 1873, published in <hi rend="i">Fors Clavigera</hi>, vol. 3
(Sunnyside, Orpington, Kent: George Allen, 1873) 8.</p>
			<q>
I lost great part of my last hour for reading, yesterday evening, in keeping my kitten’s tail out of the
candles,—a useless beast, and still more useless tail—astonishing and inexplicable even to herself.
Inexplicable, to me, all of them—heads and tails alike. “Tiger—tiger—burning bright” [“The
Tyger,” E 24]—is this then all you were made for—this ribbed hearthrug, tawny and black?
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 27: 495, where letter 27 is dated March 1873 and the
concluding punctuation changed from a question mark to an exclamation mark. See also 
<hi rend="i">Proserpina</hi>, 1879, below.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Ariadne Florentina: Six Lectures on Wood and Metal Engraving, with Appendix</hi>
[part 7] (Sunnyside, Orpington, Kent: George Allen, 1876), appendix, article 1, “Notes on the Present State
of Engraving in England,” 239-40.</p>
			<q>
The few who have sense and strength to assert their own place and supremacy, are driven into discouraged
disease by their isolation, like Turner and Blake; the one abandoning the design of his “Liber Studiorum”
after imperfectly and sadly, against total public neglect, carrying it forward to what it is,—monumental,
nevertheless, in landscape engraving; the other producing, with one only majestic series of designs from the
book of Job, nothing for his life’s work but coarsely iridescent sketches of enigmatic dream.
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 22: 470.</p>
            <p>Letter of 8 May 1876 to Richard Herne Shepherd, first printed in Sotheby’s auction catalogue
of 21 May 1890, #98. Quoted here in full from <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 34: 521-22. According to the editors of
<hi rend="i">Works</hi>, the “little book” sent to Ruskin was Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
of Experience</hi>, ed. Shepherd (London: Pickering, 1868). Perhaps we can exclude the possibility that the
volume was <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi>, ed. Shepherd (London: Pickering, 1874), since that
work contains an “introduction” rather than the “preface” referred to by Ruskin.</p>
			<q>
My dear Sir,—Putting my books in order after a long interval, I find to-day your gift of Aug. 6th, 1874,
never before seen by me. It came when I was in Italy, and I have never got my books sifted since! I am very
sorry, for I would fain have
<pb id="p42-145" n="145"/>
thanked you at once for the precious little book, of which you must have thought me so careless. But, as I now
glance through it, I am a little pained by what, I suppose, is its truth of text, but is nevertheless not
satisfactory after Rossetti’s emendations. You do not, I think, make clear enough in your preface the
authority for your readings. In the tiger, for instance, Rossetti’s “What dread hand made thy dread
feet?” is far more striking (to me) than your “What dread hand and what,” etc., which is forced and
unintelligible.<lb/>
Will you kindly tell me more clearly the relations of your text to Rossetti’s in such particulars? and
believe me already, very faithfully yours,<lb/>
J. Ruskin.
</q>
            <p>Shepherd’s version of the line from “The Tyger” follows Blake’s relief-etched text,
except for the change of “&amp;” to “and” (E 24). Ruskin misquotes D. G. Rossetti’s version, which
reads “What dread hand formed thy dread feet?” (Gilchrist 2: 59). Rossetti’s reading accords with a pen
and ink emendation, probably written by Blake, in copy P of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> (“Formd thy”). Rossetti may have seen copy P or one of the two early facsimiles made from
it, although the provenances of these works offer no direct link to the Pre-Raphaelite or Gilchrist
circles.</p>
            <p>Letter dated 3 Sept. 1876, first published in an appendix to <hi rend="i">Fors Clavigera,
Works</hi> 29: 577.</p>
			<q>
Religion, without love of man, becomes madness; love of man, without tenderness to the lower creature, becomes
insolence; and as<lb/>
<lb/>
“The bat that flits at close of eve<lb/>
Has left the brain that won’t believe,”<lb/>
[“Auguries of Innocence,” E 490]<lb/>
<lb/>
so also Religion, without love of man,—is that possible?
</q>
            <p>Letter 74, dated to “Christmas Day, 1876,” published in <hi rend="i">Fors Clavigera</hi>,
vol. 7 (Sunnyside, Orpington, Kent: George Allen, 1877) 32-33.</p>
			<q>
Finally, here are four of the grandest lines of an English prophet, sincere as [Vittore] Carpaccio [Venetian
painter, c. 1460-1525], which you will please remember:<lb/>
<lb/>
“The bat that flits at close of eve,<lb/>
Hath left the brain that won’t believe.”<lb/>
<lb/>
“Hurt not the moth, nor butterfly,<lb/>
For the Last Judgment draweth nigh.”
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 29: 36. The couplets are quoted from “Auguries of
Innocence” (E 490-91). Blake wrote “Has” at the beginning of the second line in the first quotation and
“Kill” at the beginning of the first line in the second quotation. Neither variant appears in Gilchrist 2:
95 (see “Cestus,” 1 Jan. 1865, above) nor in the Pickering and Rossetti editions of 1874.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Bibliotheca Pastorum</hi>, ed. Ruskin, vol. 2, <hi rend="i">Rock Honeycomb. Broken
Pieces of Sir Philip Sidney’s Psalter. . . . With a Preface and Commentary by the Editor</hi> (London: Ellis
and White; Sunnyside, Orpington, Kent: George Allen, 1877).</p>
			<q>
Even his <hi rend="i">feet</hi> have reigned over the works of Thy <hi rend="i">hands.</hi> God makes the
worm, and moth, and the wild beast; and <hi rend="i">we</hi> tread on them, or subdue. Compare Blake, of the
tiger:—<lb/>
<lb/>
“And what shoulder, and what art,<lb/>
Could twist the sinews of thy heart.” [“The Tyger,” E 24]
</q>
            <p>Quoted from <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 31: 158.</p>
			<q>
Compare Blake, of “ill meaning sound [Sidney, psalm 17],”<lb/>
<lb/>
“A truth that’s told with bad intent<lb/>
Beats all the lies you can invent.”<lb/>
[“Auguries of Innocence,” E 494]
</q>
            <p>Quoted from <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 31: 187.</p>
            <p>Letter of c. 1877 to Susan Beever, first published in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 37: 224.</p>
			<q>
But you may tell her I should be very sorry if my eyes were <hi rend="i">no</hi> better than eagles’!
“Doth the eagle know what is in the pit?” <hi rend="i">I</hi> do.
</q>
            <p>The quotation is from <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> (E 3), with the first word changed
from “Does.” See also <hi rend="i">The Eagle’s Nest</hi>, 1872, above.</p>
            <p>Diary entries, 22 Feb. 1878, as printed in <hi rend="i">The Brantwood Diary of John
Ruskin</hi>, ed. Helen Gill Viljoen (New Haven: Yale UP, 1971) 100-01.</p>
			<q>
—And on my chimney piece, Turners Jerusalem—and Blake’s Ruth. Left there also ....<lb/>
<lb/>
I have not looked back, nor took my hand from the Jason plough.<lb/>
And when Gold and Gems adorn the plough!<lb/>
Oh—you dear Blake—and so mad too—<lb/>
Do you know what Titians good for <hi rend="i">now</hi> you stupid thing?
</q>
            <p>Ruskin owned Turner’s watercolor, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem—The Pool of Bethesda</hi>, at this
time; see <hi rend="i">Notes by Mr. Ruskin on His Collection of Drawings by the Late J. M. W. Turner, R A.
Exhibited at the Fine Art Society’s Galleries</hi> (London: Fine Art Society, 1878) 47, #51. He apparently
also owned “Blake’s Ruth”—possibly the large color print <hi rend="i">Naomi Entreating Ruth and Orpah
to Return to the Land of Moab</hi> (Butlin #300, Keynes Collection, Fitzwilliam Museum). Butlin gives no
provenance record for this work prior to 1901, when J. W. Pease bequeathed it to Miss S. H. Pease. J. W. Pease
did not acquire two of his other Blake color prints, <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> (or
<hi rend="i">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</hi>), until 1887 at the earliest (Butlin #312, 318). Both 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> were among the works by Blake Ruskin purchased, or at least
came close to purchasing, from the dealer Joseph Hogarth; see the letter to Richmond of c. 1843, above.
Perhaps <hi rend="i">Naomi Entreating Ruth</hi> came from the same source.</p>
            <p>In the second diary entry, Ruskin alludes to lines from Blake’s “Auguries of Innocence”:
“When Gold &amp; Gems adorn
<pb id="p42-146" n="146"/>
the Plow / To peaceful Arts shall Envy Bow” (E 495). The reference to Titian alludes to Blake’s criticism
of his art—see “The Cestus of Aglaia: Prefatory,” 1 Jan. 1865, above.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Proserpina: Studies of Wayside Flowers</hi>, vol. 1 (Sunnyside, Orpington, Kent:
George Allen, 1879), chapter 11, “Genealogy,” quoted here from <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 25: 361.</p>
			<q>
. . . still the fifth sweet leaf unfold for the Rose, and the sixth spring for the Lily; and yet the wolf rave
tameless round the folds of the pastoral mountains, and yet the tiger flame through the forests of the night!
</q>
            <p>“Wolf rave” and “round the folds” allude to Blake’s “Night”: “When wolves and
tygers howl for prey” and “. . . walking round the fold” (E 14). The allusion at the end of the sentence
is to the opening lines of Blake’s “The Tyger”: “Tyger Tyger, burning bright, / In the forests of the
night” (E 24). See also letter 27 of 1873 in <hi rend="i">Fors Clavigera</hi>, above.</p>
            <p>Letter of 27 March 1881 to Alexander Macdonald, as printed in Tim Hilton, <hi rend="i">John
Ruskin: The Later Years</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 2000) 425.</p>
			<q>
. . . the doctors know really nothing about the conditions of insanity which attack men like Blake or Turner
or me . . . The Doctors enrage me more and more the longer I live.
</q>
            <p>Letter of 20 May 1881 to George Richmond, first published in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 37:
361.</p>
			<q>
. . . a course of saintly studies for <hi rend="i">Amiens</hi>, which I fancy the Devil objected to;—but
I’m getting quietly into work again, for all that, and hope he’ll get the worst of it, at last—nor even
now has he done me much harm, in teaching me what kind of temper Blake worked in—and one or two more in old
days—leaving me, now, just as practical and rational a person as ever I was!
</q>
            <p>A lecture delivered at Oxford, 26 and 30 May 1883; first published as “Lecture IV, Fairy
Land,” in 1883. Quoted here from the first collected edition of the lecture series, <hi rend="i">The Art of
England: Lectures Given in Oxford</hi> (Sunnyside, Orpington, Kent: George Allen, 1884), Lecture IV, “Fairy
Land. Mrs. Allingham and Kate Greenaway,” 131.</p>
			<q>
You must, however, always carefully distinguish these states of gloomy fantasy, natural, though too often
fatal, to men of real imagination,—the spectra which appear, whether they desire it or not,—to men like
Orcagna [Florentine painter, 1308-68], Durer [Albrecht Dürer], Blake, and Alfred Rethel [German painter,
1816-59],—and dwelt upon by them, in the hope of producing some moral impression of salutary awe by their
record—as in Blake’s Book of Job, in Durer’s Apocalypse, in Rethel’s Death the Avenger and Death the
Friend, ....
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 33: 334-35.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Proserpina: Studies of Wayside Flowers</hi>, a passage first published in part 10
(1886), quoted here from <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 25: 514-15 (in the first collected edition of 
<hi rend="i">Proserpina</hi> vol. 2, this passage is placed in chapter 9, “Salvia Silvarum”).</p>
			<q>
The dark blossom . . . is an entirely innocent and pleasant flower, the white variety of it so full of honey,
that children, as well as bees, enjoy it: whence Proserpina’s name for it, “Melitta dulcissima”; called
“Archangel” in old English—by some corruption of Latin, I fancy, but my wisely fanciful botanical friend
writes: “The blossoms do seem to stand in solemn order like Blake’s angels in the Book of Job.”
</q>
            <p>Letter of 28 Aug. 1886 to Charles Eliot Norton, first printed in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 37:
569.</p>
			<q>
How many wiser folk than I go mad for good and all, or bad and all, like poor Turner at the last, Blake
always, [Walter] Scott in his pride, [Edward] Irving [preacher, 1792-1834] in his faith, and [Thomas] Carlyle,
because of the poultry next door.
</q>
            <p>The letter is also printed, with minor differences in punctuation, in <hi rend="i">The
Correspondence of John Ruskin and Charles Eliot Norton</hi>, ed. John Lewis Bradley and Ian Ousby (Cambridge:
Cambridge UP, 1987) 494.</p>
            <p>“Arthur Burgess,” <hi rend="i">Century Guild Hobby Horse</hi> no. 6 (April 1887):
51-52.</p>
			<q>
He [Burgess] was again in London . . . and possessed himself of some of Blake’s larger drawings—known to
me many and many a year before. George Richmond had shown them to me—with others—I suppose about
1840,—original studies for the illustrations to Young’s Night Thoughts—and some connected with the more
terrific subjects etched for the Book of Job. I bought the whole series of them at once;—carried it home
triumphantly—and made myself unhappy over it—and George Richmond again delivered me from thraldom of their
possession.<lb/>
They were the larger and more terrific of these which poor Arthur had now again fallen in with—especially
the Nebuchadnezzar [Butlin #304, untraced since 1887]—and a wonderful witch with attendant owls and grandly
hovering birds of night unknown to ornithology [<hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Night of
Enitharmon’s Joy</hi>, Butlin #318, Huntington Library].<lb/>
No one at the time was, so far as I know, aware of the symptoms of illness which had been haunting me for some
days before, and I only verify their dates by diary entries,—imaginative, then beyond my wont, and proving
that before the Blake drawings came, my thoughts were all wandering in their sorrowful direction,—with
mingled corruscations [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] of opposing fancy, too bright to last.
</q>
            <p>Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> 14: 354-55 and quoted in part in Butlin 1: 157. Burgess,
who died in 1887, was a wood engraver and friend of Ruskin’s. In addition to the two works by Blake to which
Ruskin refers, Burgess may have owned a third large color print, <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (Butlin #312, Yale
Center for British Art). Butlin dates Burgess’s acquisition of these works to c. 1878-80. See also the
letter of c. 1843, above, for more information on Ruskin’s attempted purchase of works by Blake.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
	  </div1>
	</body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
