<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.2.lincoln</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert Rix, William Blake and the Cultures of Radical Christianity</title>
		<author n="Lincoln">Andrew Lincoln</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2009</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <pb id="p43-69" n="69"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title type="main">Robert Rix.  <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Cultures of Radical
Christianity</hi>.  Aldershot: Ashgate, 2007. x + 182 pp. £55.00/$99.95, hardcover.</title>
            </head>
            <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Andrew <name>Lincoln</name></docAuthor></byline>
            <p>ANYONE who has tried to keep up with the developing field of Blake studies will find in this
book much that seems familiar. But Robert Rix surveys the field of Swedenborgianism and related movements with
a thoroughness that clarifies many issues. He demonstrates that in order to deal adequately with the question
of how Blake was influenced by Swedenborg and other religious writers, we must take into account “the
reading practices of late eighteenth-century interpretive communities” (1) and be alert to the intricate
relations and rivalries among them. The complexities are expertly unraveled and lucidly explained here, which
will make this book a helpful introduction for anyone new to the field and a useful point of reference for
seasoned scholars. At the same time, though, the study exposes the difficulty of evaluating the relevance of
historical “microcultures” to an understanding of Blake’s works.</p>
            <p>Rix has a deep and wide knowledge of the intriguing world of religious groups relatively little
known beyond the realm of Blake studies. This usually allows him to avoid settling too easily on an individual
strand or tendency as the key to Blake and to provide a gentle corrective for those who do. In the face of
previous attempts to compare or associate Blake’s ideas 
              <pb id="p43-70" n="70"/>
              with those found within specific “antinomian” groups, he points out that antinomianism
“was not a well-defined sectarian position, but a tendency that could be found with varying emphases across
the board of the religious spectrum” (19). Blake’s phrase “Everlasting Gospel” cannot be identified
with a single tradition or set of ideas, since it was applied “loosely” within a “number of traditions,
sermons and publications in England.” “It was favoured by radical seventeenth-century dissenters. It was
also habitually employed in Behmenist and other mystical circles” (16-17). Rix offers an alternative to the
“unbroken tradition” model of antinomian influence proposed by A. L. Morton: “that Blake radicalized
antinomian ideas inherited from Moravian or similar milieus” (28). In developing this view—which builds on
the discovery by Marsha Keith Schuchard and Keri Davies that Blake’s mother was a Moravian—Rix
characteristically emphasizes the plurality of influence, outlining the connections between Moravianism and
the traditions of continental mysticism and insisting that it makes little sense to identify Blake simply as a
Behmenist or a Swedenborgian, since “each of these traditions meant several and often contradictory things
at Blake’s time” (2). He also shows that hostility does not preclude affinity, and that those with
different aims can follow parallel routes. In his discussion of the “Visionary Marketplace,” which reviews
the commercial dimension of “vision and spirit communications” (135), he considers animal magnetism, a
treatment sought by affluent Londoners and a favored pursuit among Swedenborgians. As Rix notes, Blake was
critical of three contemporary magnetizers, but may nevertheless have been attracted to some aspects of the
rhetoric of magnetism—which provided a kind of analogy with his own work (conceived as “a sort of faith
healing” [139]).</p>
            <p>One of the strengths of this book is Rix’s willingness to concede that evidence of historical
connection is not necessarily evidence of influence. So, for example, his brief historical overview of the
Moravians carries the warning that there are no “definite signs of Moravian doctrine” (11) in Blake’s
writing. But this does not make the Moravian example irrelevant: the more progressive circles of Moravianism
had an interest in prophetic and visionary culture that predates the spate of prophetic publications which
appeared in the wake of the French revolution. And if there is no clinching evidence of specific Moravian
ideas, Rix finds elements “characteristic of a certain kind of dissent” (22) that is compatible with
Moravianism. In particular, he examines two relatively neglected works, “The Couch of Death” and
“Samson,” relating them to the doctrine of free grace, and comparing them with Charles Wesley’s “Where
Shall My Wond’ring Soul Begin?” (said to have been written on a night of “decisive religious experience
... among Moravians”) (22-24). The argument provides a good illustration of how a discussion of influence
can be illuminating while remaining tentative in its claims.</p>
            <p>Swedenborg emerges as the central focus in this study, a cultural presence that catalyzes
Blake’s thinking and an important interpretive context for individual works. Swedenborg is seen not simply
as a writer who can be accessed through his texts, but as a field upon which the opposing interests that
constitute Swedenborgianism contend. Rix reminds us of the extent of the contemporary fascination with the
Swedish writer, and of the hostile reactions his legacy provoked (often exaggerated and sensationalist). He
offers brief accounts of the Swedenborgian discussion group, the Theosophical Society (attended by Philip
James de Loutherbourg, Richard Cosway, John Flaxman, and William Sharp), and of the First General Conference
of the New Jerusalem Church (which Blake and his wife attended), and he carefully reviews the divisions within
the London Swedenborgians—on the one hand, the move towards ridding the New Jerusalem Church of its radical
associations (exemplified in, among other things, Robert Hindmarsh’s criticisms of Thomas Paine), and on the
other, the “widespread tendency among the London Swedenborgians to turn their prophet’s teaching into a
social gospel fitting a radical and anticlerical outlook” (74). Chapter 5 focuses on a group of radical
believers who were active in the New Jerusalem Church around the time that Blake attended its conference,
including Benedict Chastanier, Count Grabianka, “Count” Cagliostro, and the diplomat Carl Frederick
Nordenskjöld (the translator of Paine’s <hi rend="i">Rights of Man</hi> into Swedish).</p>
            <p>This kind of study certainly helps to create an appropriate intellectual milieu for Blake.
However, the relevance of the lovingly detailed exploration of microcultures to the interpretation of
Blake’s poems is sometimes, perhaps inevitably, unclear. The key issues of doctrine upon which
interpretation appears to depend may be contained in isolated phrases, removed from their immediate context in
Blake’s writing; the relevant “vocabulary” may be represented by a relatively small number of favored
symbols; the analogies with Blake may be fleeting. The historical context, on the other hand, can expand
almost indefinitely, unimpeded by the requirements of specific interpretation, once some kind of parallel has
been established with Blake’s own career or beliefs. At one point Rix acknowledges that “there are no
records of Blake using identifiable magnetic techniques ... when composing his poetry. But someone who did
make use of such techniques was the diplomat and writer George Baldwin” (145). The non sequitur opens the
door for a brief outline of Baldwin’s career. This outline is interesting in itself and potentially
illuminating (since Blake was certainly aware of Baldwin, and criticized him in a <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>
poem). But here, as the awkward handling suggests, the outline seems oddly inconsequential, as if Blake has
become a peg upon which to hang information.</p>
            <p>In terms of its interpretive value, the most secure part of this study is chapter 7, which
discusses <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> as a satire on Swedenborg. Rix claims with some
justice that “the extent to which he [Blake] subverts the theosophist’s conclusions through close parody
has not been fully realized” (121). He suggests that the work targets a particular kind of reader, one
familiar with Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">True Christian Religion</hi>, and that it satirizes those
Swedenborgians who regarded
              <pb id="p43-71" n="71"/>
            the theosophist’s writing as the word of God. He shows how Blake appropriates Swedenborg’s own
terms as weapons (for example, Swedenborg’s terms for false preachers: “religious” and “apes”), or
parodies specific episodes (Swedenborg’s imagined conversion of Luther from the doctrine of justification by
faith alone, or his description of a house in hell with many apartments). Rix is well aware that Blake’s
criticism in <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> is not limited to Swedenborg, but he shows convincingly how a
knowledge of Swedenborg’s texts, and of the assumptions of his followers, can help illuminate some of the
obscurities of Blake’s work.</p>
            <p>In other areas, the interpretive payoff is more questionable. Rix tends to discount the literal
in Blake in ways that recall Swedenborg’s separation of the natural and the spiritual. He claims, for
example, that the “theological vocabulary” of “The Little Black Boy” “points directly to
Swedenborg’s idea of God represented as a spiritual Sun,” a sun, according to Swedenborg, “distinct from
that of the Natural World” (114). One might with more justice see the poem as conspicuously refusing such a
distinction. Oothoon’s offer to catch girls for Theotormon in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi> is seen, Urizenically, as “not about satisfying carnal lust” but as a “sort of parable of a
spiritual principle: the utmost reach of unselfish love” (103). Rix argues that “when Blake wrote his late
epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, he did not, like [Richard] Brothers, imagine
            <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
            the Heavenly City to be built with bricks and mortar. It was the same London, but its inhabitants
would be reformed to become a community of true Christianity” (106). This is to separate the resurrected
community from its habitation, to ignore the importance Blake gives to poetic genius, to the arts and sciences
(including the art of architecture), and to forget that Blake’s figure for the eternal prophet, Los, is
often seen with a hammer in his hand. A true Christian community would surely strive to rebuild London brick
by brick. In such instances it seems (to this reader, at least) that the close encounter with Swedenborg has
tended to obstruct, rather than to clarify, Rix’s understanding of Blake’s quarrel with the
theosophist.</p>
            <p>I have two other minor criticisms of this study. One is that, in the absence of concrete
evidence, Rix allows reasonable inferences to harden into factual certainties, as when he assumes (as his
argument demands) Blake’s “extensive reading in the writings of contemporary radicals” (34), or asserts
that “Blake was most certainly familiar with” Volney’s <hi rend="i">Ruines</hi> (37) (I assume Blake did
read Volney—but there is no certainty about this). Rix argues plausibly that, in the wake of Burke’s
attack on Richard Price’s “enthusiasm,” Blake’s poem <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> may have
become “a casualty in the campaign for respectability of [the publisher] Johnson and his associates”
(151). This interesting suggestion quickly solidifies into a factual premise: “Johnson’s decision to
cancel the publication of Blake’s poem undoubtedly contributed to Blake’s decision to set up as an
independent bookseller of his own works” (153). This kind of unnecessary rhetorical coercion weakens, rather
than strengthens, the authority of the argument. As my own proofreading is poor, I hesitate to mention the
second criticism—but there are quite a few typographical errors here, some of which (random movements
between font sizes, obviously malformed words) can be laid at the door of Ashgate (did they provide a copy
editor?).</p>
            <p>In his conclusion Rix claims that the cultures of radical Christianity “have inhabited only
the fringes of scholarly interest,” and their absence has “shaped the distorted image of Blake as either
an isolated genius or as a poor madman” (155). But surely the efforts of several generations of scholars
have made this area a familiar part of the mainstream of Blake studies, and only those needing to justify
another contribution to this well-populated field have an interest in maintaining the idea of its marginality,
or n resurrecting the obsolete image of Blake. Rix’s own contribution can be justified on other
grounds—his book is lucid and readable, and in its exceptional grasp of the complex interrelations between
religious traditions and reading communities in Blake’s age it sets an example that exposes the limitations
of some earlier studies of influence, an example that others will be able to build on.</p>
          </div3>
          </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
