<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.2.miner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Possible Sketch of Blake’s Napoleon</title>
		<author n="Miner">Paul Miner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2009</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-2-0008">     
        <pb id="p43-76" n="76"/> 
        <div2>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title type="main">A Possible Sketch of Blake’s Napoleon</title>
            </head>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>PAUL <name>MINER</name></docAuthor></byline>
            <p><hi rend="i">THE Spiritual Form of Napoleon</hi>, an apotheosis in “fresco” by William
Blake, disappeared in the last quarter of the nineteenth century. Blake’s design of Napoleon was exhibited
in 1876 at the Burlington Fine Arts Club, and H. H. Statham briefly described it in <hi rend="i">Macmillan’s
Magazine</hi> (34 [1876]: 60-61). According to Statham, Napoleon was flanked by “less explicable” angels,
whereas the French emperor was portrayed as a “strong energetic figure grasping at the sun and moon with his
hands, yet chained to earth by one foot, and with a pavement of dead bodies before him in the foreground
....” Also on display at the Burlington Club was Blake’s “<hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of W. Pitt
guiding Behemoth</hi>,” a work depicting the English statesman, his head encompassed with an
“extraordinary ‘halo’ effect ....” Although Statham concluded that the picture of Napoleon was “the
most striking ... of the two” allegorical paintings, the “central figure” of Napoleon (who died in 1821)
was “not the finest in execution,” since the figure was “but loosely drawn.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">1</ref></p>
			<p>Though nothing has come to light on the lost picture of
			Napoleon, attention should be called to a faint and loosely
			drawn sketch by Blake in which a giant allegorical figure in
			the heavens is abutted by two winged angels (as in Statham’s
			description). One angel holds a key (to heaven?), while the
			other holds an open book (of judgment?). The sketch is reproduced
			in Martin Butlin’s <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of
			William Blake</hi>, where it is speculatively titled <hi rend="i">Satan between
			Two Angels (?)</hi>, c. 1815-20 (?) (#592, plate 828). Each hand of
			the colossus holds a globe, the sun and moon respectively,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">2</ref>
			and these cosmic spheres are shackled as a ball and chain to
			his wrists.</p>
			<note id="n56">1. In reference to Statham’s comments, see also Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and
the Imagination: A Study of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970) 182-83,
and note Bo Lindberg’s conjectural reconstruction of the Napoleon design, based upon Statham’s
description, in <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi> (Åbo: Åbo Akademi,
1973) 301-11, fig. 106.</note>
			<note id="n57">2. Compare <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night IX (117.6-9, E 386), where gigantic
			Los with “his right hand ... Siezd the Sun,” while “His left hand ...
			coverd the Moon,” for he “tore ... down” these turning spheres, “cracking
			the heavens across from immense to immense,” as “judgment” is at
			hand. Blake’s language is borrowed from Thomas Paine’s <hi rend="i">Age of Reason</hi>,
			where fierce Mohamet refuses to alter his divine actions, even “<hi rend="i">Wert thou
			... to come to me with the sun in thy right hand and the moon in thy left
			...</hi>” (Paine’s emphasis). See <hi rend="i">The Complete Writings of Thomas Paine</hi>, ed.
			Philip S. Foner, vol. 1 (New York: Citadel Press, 1945) 533. Note also <hi rend="i">Night
			Thoughts</hi> 236, where a nude male plunges precipitously through the heavens,
			holding a cosmic globe in each hand, a scene attended by flaming
			comets or meteors.</note>
			<p>One foot of Blake’s giant male (aspiring to heaven) is
			chained to earth, possibly connoting Napoleon’s imprisonment
			on Elba or St. Helena.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">3</ref> He is nude
(as in Blake’s apotheosis
			of Lord Nelson) and has a huge triple aureole about his
			head (iconography utilized by Blake in his apotheosis of Pitt).
			The beak of a huge carnivorous bird(?) menaces the vitals of
			the shackled colossus,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">4</ref> and to the
right and left, at the bottom
			foreground of the page, two smaller birds also threaten the
			giant. Pertinently, the verso of the sketch portrays the same
			scene in reverse, although the large bird on the recto is not
			present. When Butlin catalogued the recto, it had been untraced
			since 1949, and he was unaware of the verso at that
			time. It seems probable that Blake’s verso and recto sketches
			of “Satan” are preliminary designs for Blake’s apotheosis of
			Napoleon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">5</ref></p>
			<note id="n58">3. In a design probably intended for the Book of Enoch, a figure soars
			among the stars, though chained to earth (Butlin, <hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings</hi>,
			plate 1052).</note>
			<note id="n59">4. The giant bird may reflect (as well as revise) Revelation 19.17-18,
			where a giant “angel” appears, “standing in the sun,” and “cried [out] ... to
			all the [ravenous] fowls that fly in the midst of heaven, Come and gather
			yourselves together unto the supper of the great God,” where “ye may
			eat the flesh of kings, and the flesh of captains.” In <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night 
			VIIb (88[96].19-27, E 361) “naked” Los “reard his mighty stature” into
			the heavens—“on Earth stood his feet”—and the moon “circled” his “furious
			forehead,” while his “knees” were “Bathed in bloody clouds,” a scene
			where flesh-hungry “Eagles cry &amp; ... Vultures laugh,” for “Now comes the
			night of Carnage now the flesh of Kings &amp; Princes” serve as “our food,”
			while “the blood of Captains” will serve as “our drink.” Such language is
			reminiscent of chapter 19 of Revelation. The reader also should not miss
			Blake’s subtle allusion to book 1 of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (221-24), where Satan
			“rears” his “mighty Stature” off the burning “Pool,” phrasing that Blake in
			his <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> (see E 801) planned as a motto for the emblem of fire in <hi rend="i">The
			Gates of Paradise</hi>, though the motto was not used in either of the engraved
			versions of this work.</note>
			<note id="n60">5. Martin Butlin, in private correspondence, agrees with my suggestion
			that the recto/verso sketches are possibly preliminary designs related
			to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Napoleon</hi>.</note>
			<pb id="p43-77" n="77"/> 
			<figure n="BUT592-recto.043.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="281"/>
			<figure n="BUT592-verso.043.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="278">
				<head>Recto (above) and verso (below) of Blake’s sketch, reproduced by kind permission of Giuliano
Ceseri.</head>
				<figDesc>The recto is from Butlin, <hi rend="i">The
				Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1981), plate 828, and the
verso from Butlin, “Two Blakes
				Reappear and Make Three,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 18.2 (fall 1984): 119, by permission of the author.
The original is at the Georgia Museum of Art,
				which is currently closed for renovation and not accepting requests for photography.</figDesc>
			</figure>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
