<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.2.scott</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Blake (1757-1827): The Visionary Genius of British Romanticism, Petit
Palais, 2 April-28 June 2009</title>
		<author n="Scott">Grant F. Scott</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2009</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
      <pb id="p43-61" n="61"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-2-0007">
        <figure n="exhibit-1.043.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="488">
			<figTranscr>William Blake<lb/>
			Le Génie visionnaire du romantisme anglais</figTranscr>
			<figDesc>© [MAW]</figDesc>
		</figure>      
        <head>
            <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <div3>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake (1757-1827): The Visionary Genius of British Romanticism. Petit
Palais, Musée des Beaux-Arts de la Ville de Paris, 2 April-28 June 2009. Guest curated by Michael Phillips
with Daniel Marchesseau, Directeur du Musée de la Vie Romantique.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Exhibition reviewed by <docAuthor>Grant F. <name>Scott</name></docAuthor></byline>
              <p>THE FIRST to appear in France since 1947, this retrospective contains over 130 of Blake’s
works and, as the official web site states, “introduces William Blake as poet, painter and
artist-printmaker.” The exhibition spans Blake’s career, offering work from his apprenticeship to his
final engraved calling card for George Cumberland. A number of media are represented, from early pencil
sketches and stipple engravings to relief etchings, illuminated prints, large color-printed drawings, and
paintings. On display as well is the burnished copperplate for plate 11 of <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the
Book of Job</hi> (1825 [1826]) alongside the resulting printed page, a pairing that reveals the fine marriage
of metal and paper that is so difficult to visualize without the material fact of the plate itself. These two
items alone are worth the price of admission, though the rarely seen color print <hi rend="i">Newton</hi>
(1795) from the Philadelphia Museum of Art and the vividly colored second-state engraving of the 
<hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> (c. 1810-20) offer equal delights. The exhibit concludes with several
contemporary tributes to Blake, including a lithograph of Francis Bacon’s <hi rend="i">Study after the Life
Mask of William Blake</hi> (1955), Jean Cortot’s <hi rend="i">Hommage à William Blake</hi> (1985), and a
clip from Jim Jarmusch’s film <hi rend="i">Dead Man</hi> (1995). Many of the original works on display are
drawn from the collection of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, though a significant number are on loan from
the British Museum, the British Library, Glasgow University, Manchester Art Gallery, the Victoria University
Library (Toronto), the Louvre, and several private collectors.</p>
          <p>Anyone looking for a synopsis of the variety and breadth of Blake’s artwork would be hard
pressed to find a more splendid visual introduction than the one guest curator Michael Phillips has assembled
here. The great strength of this exhibit is that it succeeds admirably in making these works accessible to
native French and English speakers alike—no small feat given Blake’s visual-verbal designs and his often
diminutive
            <pb id="p43-62" n="62"/>
            <figure n="exhibit-2.043.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="340">
				<head><hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (Philadelphia Museum of Art) mounted next to its sketch (Fitzwilliam
Museum).</head>
				<figDesc>© [MAW]</figDesc>
			</figure>
          calligraphy. In its straightforward chronological organization, its clear presentation of a variety
of works, and its progressive movement through the stages of a revolutionary career, the exhibition offers a
magnificent introduction to Blake’s versatility and range, not to mention his evolution as an engraver and
thinker. Deliberately, I think, it represents only two complete sequences of plates from, appropriately, 
<hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi> (1794) and the Virgil woodcuts. The rest of the works are grouped according to
six periods of Blake’s life, outlined in the exhibition’s information sheet: “Blake’s
Apprenticeship,” “First Visions/First Poems,” “Blake as a Copy Engraver,” “Relief Etching and
Illuminated Books,” “The Large Colour Prints,” and “The Last Twenty Years.” Each section is
introduced by a helpful paragraph by the curators stenciled on the walls in French and English, and each is
accompanied by a famous quotation from Blake’s poetry: “How do you know but ev’ry Bird that cuts the
airy way, / Is an immense world of delight, clos’d by your senses five?” “To see a World in a Grain of
Sand / And a Heaven in a Wild Flower,” etc. This is a greatest-hits album which will not fail to please the
specialist as well—the sheer amplitude and quality of the work on display are staggering, and richly reward
close attention.</p>
            <p>On the morning I visited (26 May), gallery traffic was light, so I was able to linger in front
of the artworks and inspect details without the insistent pressure of fellow patrons to move me along. I
drifted backwards through the space several times, pausing to revisit favorites like plates 8 (naked Orc) and
12 (Orc aflame) from the Fitzwilliam’s <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi>, and loitering before the three
large sheets from <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> that were intelligently sheathed in vertical glass sections so as to
display both recto and verso. Spending time before works like these made me think about the online Blake
Archive, a miracle of technology which has now become essential for classroom and conference use, but still no
substitute for the original manuscripts and plates. While the screen may register an accurate palate of
colors, it necessarily flattens the composition and texture of the paper, smoothing the rough geography of the
page and bathing each work in a shimmering cyberglow. In the original plate 8, by contrast, I was able to spy
fine flecks of gold dusting the pictured leaves and foliage, gold not apparent in the online version. I could
also see more layers of applied watercolor and, lo and behold, even the wiry mesh of pubic hair sprouting
luxuriantly around Orc’s exposed groin (I had always thought Blake airbrushed his heroes’ genitals!).</p>
            <p>I had never seen the exhibited plate of “The Tyger,” an early color-printed copy which
belonged to the late Sir Geoffrey Keynes and is now in the Fitzwilliam Museum. The plate is not represented
among the eleven versions in the Blake Archive, and is significantly different from most copies, which
features a marked contrast between the light shadings of the tree and the more brightly colored tiger. In this
version the tiger is printed in the same mottled, earthy tones as the tree, its head splashed with what looks
like patches of brown enamel. There are swirls of muted blue highlighting the legs and gesturing at stripes on
the shoulders, but there are also hints of blue in several places on the tree, most noticeably on the branch
opposite the “grasp/clasp” rhyme. The tiger’s hindquarters look like they’re growing directly out of
the tree, or almost as if they have fused with it (the back right leg is nearly impossible to distinguish), a
decidedly organic effect that is echoed by the bending branches that separate the stanzas. So here tree and
tiger are one and the tiger is even more rooted and static than usual. While the lightly printed text reaches
for the stars, the image remains brown and heavy, earthbound. The terrifying textual beast prowls “the
forests of the night,” his visual counterpart fixed harmlessly below. Small discoveries
            <pb id="p43-63" n="63"/>
            like these make any visit to an exhibition of artworks or manuscripts worthwhile, especially to
those of us weaned on print and screen facsimiles. It’s refreshing to have the chinks of the cavern briefly
widened. And the great wonder of Blake is that he never stops compelling you to see, to see further,
finer.</p>
            <p>The exhibit also affords the opportunity to compare the pencil sketch of the frontispiece for
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, for example—and that not all are in the pristine state of
the <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> or <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea</hi> (1773). These blemishes serve to pull
the works out of the airless sanctity of the museum and trammel them with time. Some will disagree, but I
think it’s useful to find artworks humanized (and historicizes) in this way, brought closer to the temporal
experience of the viewer.</p>
            <p>Other highlights of the exhibition include the life mask by J. S. Deville and portraits by John
Linnell and Blake’s wife, Catherine; one of only two known intaglio prints of <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> (c.
1826-27); several drawings and engravings based on the Book of Job; a number of Blake’s watercolor
illustrations to the Bible; and selected plates from the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>. An edition of John Gabriel Stedman’s 
<hi rend="i">Narrative, of a Five Years’ Expedition, against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</hi> (1796), for
which Blake engraved the plates (here colored), is displayed open to several graphic scenes of punishment, and
thoughtfully paired with the frontispiece and title page from <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi>, which depict scenes of captivity and flight. Other sequences in the exhibition are more puzzling,
however. Midway through we encounter a wall that features, from left to right: “The Chimney Sweeper” from
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, “Holy Thursday,” from 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, “Nurses Song” from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, “Nurse’s Song” from 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, and finally “A Divine Image” from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>. The first pairing
allows us to compare the two versions and note Blake’s keen psychological awareness of point of view.
“Holy Thursday,” however, lacks its companion piece, and the two plates of “Nurse’s Song” are in the
wrong order. “A Divine Image” is a small but powerful statement
              <figure n="exhibit-3.043.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="537">
				<figDesc>© [MAW]</figDesc>
			  </figure>
              <pb id="p43-64" n="64"/>
              rooting man’s inhumanity in “the Human Form Divine” rather than an abstract God. But
lacking its counterpunch in “The Divine Image” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, the plate loses its
qualifying irony as well as additional layers of meaning. I wonder also about the decision to stack the plates
from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> one above the other in a double line, a configuration that disrupts the linear
sequence of the book. For those French visitors having trouble following the work because it is a difficult
narrative and written in English, this presentation will be confusing. Wouldn’t one want to adhere as
closely as possible to Blake’s intended visual order and thus mimic for the viewer the actual experience of
reading the book?</p>
            <p>Michael Phillips, who co-curated the major Blake exhibitions at Tate Britain and the
Metropolitan Museum in 2000-01, deserves a lot of credit not only for assembling such a stunning array of
artwork from so many different institutions and collections, but also for pulling it all together abroad. I
suspect the negotiations were laborious and time-consuming. Difficult too must have been the logistics of
organizing the details of the exhibition, from laying out the floor-plan to creating bilingual labels and
publicity material. My one regret is that more of this energy wasn’t expended on the installation and on
imagining the overall structure and design of the space, which is rather orthodox, moving us back and forth
through a series of rectangular blocks. As we enter the gallery, the initial “confrontation” consists of
three massive Stonehenge-like walls which magnify a portion of a watercolor and wash it in a pastel blue that
blurs the represented form of an angel. These walls serve to thwart our entrance rather than inviting us in,
and do not clearly enough direct our path. Located on the basement level of the museum, the entire space seems
to small and confining, as if Blake’s work is once again contained in its volumes rather than being
liberated from them. (I imagined figures like Orc and Urizen trying to jump off the walls.) Of course I
realize that the fragility of these works on paper, many in watercolor, limits a curator’s options, and that
they must be displayed under reduced lighting conditions. But one can’t help feeling the absence of an
opening or vista, a circular passageway up or out as in the watercolor from Blake’s Dante series exhibited
here, <hi rend="i">The Circle of the Lustful</hi> (1824-27), with its upswelling river of bodies. Blake
himself might have wished for a bit more irreverent pizzazz in the overall conception and design. Standard
labels and fonts—why not more variety and color? Blocked rectangles and lines—where are the circles and
vortexes, the irresistible sweep upwards? Bacon and Cortot at the end—why not Ginsberg, the Doors?</p>
            <p>In view of the quantity and quality of the works presented, however, these are small
complaints. This is an ambitious show of great scope and power, sure to mobilize an army of new Blake converts
on the continent. Even as I was leaving the exhibit something was already brewing. The gallery began to fill
with French visitors murmuring excitedly about the works. Unexpectedly, a single guard began shushing them. He
shushed three times, each more loudly, but to no avail. The murmurs grew to a buzz and then to a glorious
din.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
