<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.2.ripley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Printed References to and Known Prices of Blake’s Night Thoughts,
1796-1826</title>
		<author n="Ripley">Wayne C. Ripley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2009</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
      <pb id="p43-72" n="72"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-2-0008">     
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
            <head>
              <title type="main">Printed References to and Known Prices of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>, 1796-1826</title>
            </head>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>WAYNE C. <name>RIPLEY</name></docAuthor></byline>
			<div3>
            <p>THERE are precious few contemporary printed references to Blake’s illustrations and
engravings of Edward Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>. In November 1796 the <hi rend="i">Monthly
Magazine</hi> was the first to anticipate the publication of the volume; it listed the price of the entire
nine-night work at five guineas for subscribers and six for non-subscribers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n45">1. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale University
Press, 2004) [hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)] 74. The <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>
announcement was reprinted in the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Magazine</hi> (December 1796): 450.</note> That
December Blake’s publisher, Richard Edwards, released an advertisement without prices, and in January 1797
the <hi rend="i">Monthly Epitome and Catalogue of New Publications</hi> announced that the first part would be
published “in a few days” and repeated the price mentioned by the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 77). These “few days,” however, turned into months, and in the spring Edwards issued a
prospectus, which promised publication in June and claimed that the first volume would have forty “very
spirited engravings.” It repeated the price of five guineas to subscribers, but emphasized that “the price
will be considerably advanced to non-subscribers,” without giving a specific figure (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
78-79). In November 1797 the first and only volume was finally published, and that month William Roscoe paid
£1.1 for the first number and £1.1 as a down payment for the subscription (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
79).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n46">2. Whether this money was ever returned to him or any of the other subscribers when the
project failed is unknown.</note> Despite Edward’s threat to raise the price for non-subscribers, when the
<hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> announced the published volume in June 1798, the price for the general
public was the same as Roscoe had paid: “Young’s Night Thoughts, decorated with appropriate Designs, by
Mr. <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Part I. 1l.1s.” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 82).</p>
            <p>While Bentley notes that after the book was published “it was scarcely noticed” 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 76), I want to examine the known references in light of eleven recently discovered
notices, which are not recorded in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> and which were found using Google Books. I
have coordinated these discoveries with the known references in table 1; the first four, from 1798 to 1801,
are given below:</p>
            <p>1. White, John. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of Rare, Splendid, and Valuable Books, in Every Branch
of Polite Literature; Including the Entire Libraries of the Rev. Harvey Spragg ... also of the Rev. Henry
Putman ...: Comprehending a Large Assortment of Learned Theological Books. ... The Sale Will Begin on February
19, 1798</hi> .... London, 1798.
			<q>Young’s Night Thoughts, a magnificent edition, with <hi rend="i">Engravings</hi> from
Drawings by Blake, 5l 5s <hi rend="i">to subscribers, when completed, boards</hi> — — — 1797</q></p>
            <p>2. Schubart, Ludwig. <hi rend="i">Englische Blätter</hi>. Erlangen, 1798.
			<q>Young’s Night Thoughts, decorated with appropriate Designs, by Mr. Blake, Part. I.</q></p>
            <p>3. Payne, Thomas. <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Valuable Books, in Various Languages, and in Every
Class of Literature: Which Are to Be Sold, at the Prices Affixed to Each Article ....</hi> London, 1799.
			<q>Young’s Night Thoughts, <hi rend="i">with engravings round each page from the designs of
Blake</hi>, 2 numbers, <hi rend="i">boards</hi>, — 1797 &amp; 98</q></p>
            <p>4. White, John. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of Books, in Every Department of Literature, Now on
Sale ....</hi> London, March 1801.
			<q>Young’s Night Thoughts, a magnificent edition, with <hi rend="i">Engravings</hi> from
Drawings by Blake, <hi rend="i">boards</hi>, 5l 5s — 1797</q></p>
            <p>As brief as these descriptions are, they do raise some interesting points. White’s catalogue
entries borrow their description of the volume as a “magnificent edition” from the spring 1797 prospectus.
            This echo makes the second mention of Blake’s edition by the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>
more notable, since the latter steps away from the laudatory language of the prospectus for the more tempered
“appropriate.” 
            While Jon Mee has argued that Blake’s designs employed many images current in the radical
millenarian culture of the 1790s,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">3</ref>
            <note id="n47">3. “‘As portentous as the written wall’: Blake’s Illustrations to 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William Blake in Honor of John E.
Grant</hi>, ed. Alexander S. Gourlay (West Cornwall: Locust Hill Press, 2002) 171-203.</note> 
            the description of the designs as “appropriate” suggests that at least one early reader saw
them as entirely suitable to Young’s poem, a viewpoint that anticipated the opinion of readers in the
1820s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">4</ref>
            <note id="n48">4. In 1824 Thomas Frognall Dibdin, who obviously admired the sublimity of Young
over that of Blake, conceded, “At times, the pencil of the artist attains the sublimity of the poet ...”
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 398-99).</note> 
            The reprinting of the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> entry in Schubart signals, to my
knowledge, the first international reference to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, 
            and in Germany the description of the designs as “appropriate” to Young would have had special
resonance, given the popularity of Young and his impact on German romanticism.</p>
            <p>Both White and Payne were involved in other projects that Blake worked on. Blake either knew
the men or was familiar with them through his immediate circle. Both took subscriptions for <hi rend="i">The
Grave</hi>, and late in Blake’s life John Linnell bought
              <pb id="p43-73" n="73"/>              
            paper from White and used him to bind illustrations of the Book of Job (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
785).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n49">5. Linnell’s accounts refer only to “White,” but Bentley includes this man under John
White in his index.</note> There is no doubt that Blake knew Payne by 1804; on 23 October, Blake wrote to
William Hayley that he had given Payne the note Hayley had sent and had received cash from Payne.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n50">6. David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>,
newly rev. ed. (New York: Anchor-Random House, 1988) [hereafter cited as E] 756.</note> Through James Basire
or John Flaxman, Blake’s acquaintance with Payne may have come much earlier. Payne was one of the four
publishers of Jacob Bryant’s <hi rend="i">Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi> (1774-76), for which Blake
likely provided an engraving. In 1799 Blake engraved Flaxman’s designs for the <hi rend="i">Letter to the
Committee for Raising the Naval Pillar</hi>, which was printed for T. Cadell, W. Davies, R. H. Evans, and
Payne. In 1804, after Blake returned to London from Felpham, he engraved Flaxman’s frontispiece for
Hoare’s <hi rend="i">Academic Correspondence</hi>, for which Payne was also a publisher. If Blake was not
acquainted directly with Payne in the late 1790s, the latter did collaborate on several projects with James
Edwards, brother of Richard Edwards, and Payne, C. Dilly, and Richard Edwards were listed as the only London
sellers of Francis Wrangham’s <hi rend="i">The Restoration of the Jews</hi> (1795).</p>
            <p>Given Blake’s possible connections to White and Payne, the descriptions in their catalogues
of the book and its publication details are significant for what they say about the expected production
schedule. Even though the first and only <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> number was published in November
1797, White’s 1798 catalogue, which was likely printed in January or February, still references subscribers
and uses the phrase “when completed.” This phrase originates in neither the advertisement nor the
prospectus, and White’s description and price refer to the full four-volume set, which suggests that in
early 1798 further volumes were expected. Payne’s 1799 catalogue raises even larger issues, since it lists
“2 numbers” with the dates of “1797 &amp; 98.” We know that Blake began to work on an engraving for
Night the Fifth, which would have been included in a second volume.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n51" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n51">7. John Grant et al., eds., <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s</hi>
Night Thoughts<hi rend="i">: A Complete Edition</hi>, vol. 1 (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980) 7.</note> Was
Payne, and perhaps Blake himself, still expecting a second volume as late as 1799? Or were both catalogues
committing errors that resulted from the slow and uncertain production of the first volume and its aborted
sequels? Unfortunately, Payne’s catalogue makes no mention of a price for these two supposed volumes, even
though most of the other books in the catalogue are priced. At what point Edwards and Blake finally abandoned
the project is unclear, but because Payne’s only reference to it comes more than a year after the
publication of the volume, it is highly likely that the work may have been given up much later than we have
recognized. For his part, White must have been attuned to the production of the book, since he omits the
phrase “when completed” in his 1801 description.</p>
            <p>White’s 1801 price was either an oversight or an overestimation of the solitary volume’s
value, since in the English marketplace at least the book appears to have done little to help the fortunes of
any booksellers lucky or unlucky enough to have a copy. The next mention of the book occurred in Germany, when
Jean Paul Richter received a copy from Erbprinz Emil August von Gotha in November 1801 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 113). Schubart’s 1798 reference may explain how von Gotha came to know of the book’s
existence. Before giving it to Richter, he had it richly bound and included “a real gold 
[<hi rend="i">chain</hi>] ending with a huge pearl,” which Richter was inclined to give to his wife as a
necklace. Richter valued the book at fifteen guineas, declaring “Perhaps there is not a second 
[<hi rend="i">copy of the book</hi>] in Germany, [<hi rend="i">a fact</hi>] which may help me a good deal in
selling it” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 115, Bentley’s emendations). We do not know if Richter did sell the
volume, and if he did, whether he was able to obtain his price. He also recognized the beauty of Blake’s
designs, and in a book he published in 1804 described the figure peering over a bush in Night the First, p. 4,
in terms Blake would have appreciated: “its seeing becomes vision for me” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)
186-87). In any case, Richter’s estimation of both its visionary and market value far exceeded what anyone
in England was willing to concede for years to come.</p>
            <p>The next printed references to the book are found in three catalogues by William Gardiner; I
have included the catalogue number before each entry:</p>
            <p>5. <hi rend="i">A List of Books, for Sale at W. Gardiner’s, 48, Pall-Mall, at the Ready Money
Prices Affixed</hi>. London: J. Barker, 1808.
			<q>860  Young’s Night Thoughts, <hi rend="i">curious cuts</hi>, <hi rend="i">by Blake</hi>, 
<hi rend="i">boards</hi>, 1<hi rend="i">l</hi> 5<hi rend="i">s</hi> 1797</q></p>
            <p>6. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of Books ... for Sale at W. Gardiner’s, 48, Pall-Mall, at the
Ready Money Prices Affixed</hi>. London: J. Barker, 1809.
			<q>860  Young’s Night Thoughts, <hi rend="i">curious cuts</hi>, <hi rend="i">by Blake</hi>,
<hi rend="i">boards</hi>, 1<hi rend="i">l</hi> 5<hi rend="i">s</hi> 1797</q></p>
            <p>7. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of a Small Collection of Ancient and Modern Books ... for Sale at
W. Gardiner’s, 48, Pall-Mall, at the Ready Money Prices Affixed</hi>. London: J. Barker, 1810.
			<q>691  Young’s Night Thoughts, <hi rend="i">curious cuts</hi>, <hi rend="i">by Blake</hi>, 
<hi rend="i">boards</hi>, £1 5s — — 1796</q>
			<q>1213  Young’s Night Thoughts, with Engravings by Mr. Blake, fol. <hi rend="i">boards</hi>,
£1 5s — — 1797
			<q>This is one of the most singular and eccentric works that ever appeared.</q></q>
            Presumably, the 1796 date for item 691 in the 1810 catalogue is an error. If so, it may be safe to
assume that the four listings all refer to the same volume, which Gardiner classified in different ways. The
1808 and 1809 catalogues listed the book in the
              <pb id="p43-74" n="74"/>  
              category “Poetry, Plays, &amp;c.” By doing so, Gardiner chose not to list it with the other
“Books of Prints” he offered, a decision that privileged Young’s poetry over Blake’s designs. Failing
to attract a buyer that way, however, Gardiner may have been motivated to cross-list the book in 1810 in the
new category of “English Poetry and Miscellanies” and in “Books of Prints.”</p>
            <p>After Gardiner, James Lackington listed it in his <hi rend="i">General Catalogue</hi> (1811)
for £2.10 and <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Books</hi> (1815) for £2.2 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 600fn).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n52">Note that the price Bentley lists for the 1811 catalogue, £2.12, is an error. I have not been
able to check the 1815 catalogue.</note> The 1811 catalogue gives two separate copies of the book, which are
prefaced here with their lot number:
			<q>264  Young’s Night Thoughts, <hi rend="i">finely printed, with curious plates, designed and
etched by Blake</hi>, first 4 Books, <hi rend="i">bds.</hi> 21. 10s. 1797</q>
			<q>6569  Young’s Night Thoughts, (first four nights of) <hi rend="i">finely printed, with
marginal plates, from designs by Blake, bds.</hi> 2l. 10s.</q>
            Both repeat Gardiner’s description of the engraved plates as “curious,” and it is
interesting that Lackington describes the volume as “finely printed,” when, in fact, it was very sloppily
done. Perhaps this idea of the fine printing helped him raise the price more than a pound over Gardiner’s
copy, which itself was only four shillings more than the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> had announced for
the book on the open market in 1798. Strikingly, Gardiner’s catalogues appeared when Blake’s edition of
<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> was being published and when Blake was receiving the most positive attention he
would ever receive; this increased attention may have motivated Lackington to push up his prices in 1811.
Given that he again offered two copies of the work in 1815, it is highly probable that he failed to sell his
copies in 1811 and tried again at slightly lower prices. We do not know if they sold. In 1810, Henry Crabb
Robinson bought his copy for £1.11.5, which was between the prices offered by Gardiner and Lackington.
Despite the likelihood that Lackington failed to sell two copies in 1811, Robinson claimed in his German
article on Blake that the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> volume “is no longer to be bought, so excessively
rare has it become.” Either Robinson believed the book was rare, or he wanted, perhaps, like Richter, to
push up the value of his copy (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 771, 600).</p>
            <p>A bookseller with more direct connections to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> was William Ford of
Manchester, who, as announced in the 7 November 1807 advertisement in the <hi rend="i">Manchester
Gazette</hi>, had displayed Blake’s original drawings for the project and taken subscriptions 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 248). Like Lackington, Ford had two copies of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> for sale in
1811, which are found in both parts of a two-part catalogue:</p>
            <p>8. Ford, W[illiam]. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of a Curious and Valuable Collection of Books, in
Various Languages and Classes of Literature. ... Part the First for 1810</hi>. Manchester, 1811.
			<q>Night Thoughts on Life, Death, and Immortality, with the singular designs round the margins by
BLAKE, calf cleg. ib. ....<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n53">9. The first part of Ford’s catalogue is not available for full viewing on Google Books.
Both parts are held by Oxford, shelfmark 2593 e.51.</note></q></p>
            <p>9. Ford, W[illiam]. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue (Part the Second for 1810-11) of a Curious and
Valuable Collection of Books, in Various Languages and Classes of Literature</hi>. Manchester, 1811.
			<q>Young’s Complaint, and the Consolation; or Night thoughts with Blake’s singular designs
round the text. ib. 1797.—<hi rend="i">Blair’s</hi> Grave, with engravings from the designs of Blake.
LARGE PAPER. <hi rend="i">eleg. bd. in blue mor. &amp;c.</hi> 8<hi rend="i">l</hi>8<hi rend="i">s</hi>. ib.
1808</q></p>
            <p>It was perhaps sometime during the interest in Blake following <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> that
the British Museum obtained its copy (now in the British Library), which is listed in an 1819 catalogue:</p>
            <p>10. <hi rend="i">Librorum Impressorum, Qui in Museo Britannico Adservantur, Catalogus</hi>.
Vol. 7. London, 1819.
			<q>The Complaint and the Consolation or Night Thoughts, with marginal Designs by Mr. Blake. fol.
<hi rend="i">Lond.</hi> 1797.</q></p>
            <p>The following year, another catalogue listed two copies at prices in the same range as
Gardiner’s. They are given below, prefaced by their catalogue number:</p>
            <p>11. Evans, E. and A. <hi rend="i">Bookseller’s and Printseller’s Catalogue</hi>. London,
1820.
			<q>421  Blake (Wm.) Illustrations of Young’s Night Thoughts, 4to. <hi rend="i">bds</hi>. 30s.
— 1797</q>
			<q>566  Young’s Night Thoughts, with numerous fine plates by <hi rend="i">William Blake, fol.
Bds.</hi> 1<hi rend="i">l.</hi> 1<hi rend="i">s.</hi> — — 1797</q></p>
            <p>This Evans is likely Edward Evans (1789-1835), who on 19 April 1830 wrote to Linnell about
selling copies of <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 528). Their
association dates from at least 23 November 1826, when Linnell listed Evans in his account book 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 789). The relationship may have begun earlier, since in the catalogue entry for another
item by Blake, he is described as an “eminent genius.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n54" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n54">10. “422 — an additional plate to Young by this eminent genius, hitherto unpublished,
engraved by Perry, 4to. 1s”. Unfortunately, this is not the lost engraving for Night the Fifth first
described in the 1927 catalogue of Francis Edwards (Grant et al. l: 87n18), but Blake’s wild, full-page
engraving for Bürger’s <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi>, which had an excerpt from Young beneath it. It was
published in 1796, along with two other designs by Blake, all engraved by Perry. Item 423 is a copy of
Blake’s designs for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>.</note></p>
            <p>After the Evans’ catalogue, Thomas Edwards, the brother of the original <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> publisher Richard, attempted to sell the original watercolor designs in 1821. He also offered an
uncolored copy of the engraved edition, listed at £2.12.6.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n55" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n55">11. G. E. Bentley, Jr., “The 1821 Edwards Catalogue,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 17.4 (spring
1984): 154-56.</note> Edwards
              <pb id="p43-75" n="75"/> 
            was unsuccessful in selling the designs, and there is no indication if he disposed of the
uncolored copy. The price of the book is not recorded again until the collection of Rebekah Bliss was sold in
April 1826. She had both a colored and an uncolored copy, with the former selling for four guineas and the
later for £1.19 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 444). The price of this uncolored copy was only slightly higher than
Gardiner’s 1808-10 asking price of £1.5 and the Evans’ £1.10 in 1820, which suggests that there still
remained very little demand. Unless Lackington and Edwards successfully sold their copies, the obtainable
market price for an uncolored copy had not risen more than eighteen shillings between 1798 and 1826. In 1824,
Alexander Akehurst found it very easy to find a copy after reading a biography of Hayley that mentioned Blake.
He wrote to Philip Bliss, “I lately picked up a Copy of this Work, which is [<hi rend="i">word del</hi>]
[thought] to be now reposing in the warehouses of some of the London Booksellers, as it is believed to have
met with little encouragement” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 388, Bentley’s emendations). Akehurst’s opinion,
rather than Robinson’s, must remain the consensus on how readily available Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> was to the reading public. But we at least know now that a few more people noted its publication
and sale, even though these notices did nothing for Blake’s (or anyone else’s) fortune.</p>
			</div3>
			<div3>
			<head>
				<title>Table 1: Printed References to and Known Prices of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
(1797), 1796-1826 (newly discovered references are shaded)</title>
			</head>
			<table>
				<row>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Source</cell>
					<cell>Price</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>November 1796</cell>
					<cell><hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi></cell>
					<cell>£5.5 for subscribers/£6.6 for 
non-subscribers<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">*</ref></cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>December 1796</cell>
					<cell><hi rend="i">Edinburgh Magazine</hi></cell>
					<cell>£5.5 for subscribers/£6.6 for 
non-subscribers<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" n="b" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
					(reprint of <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> announcement)</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>22 December 1796</cell>
					<cell>Richard Edwards’s advertisement</cell>
					<cell>No price given</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>January 1797</cell>
					<cell><hi rend="i">Monthly Epitome</hi></cell>
					<cell>£5.5 for subscribers/£6.6 for 
non-subscribers<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" n="c" type="note">*</ref></cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>Spring 1797</cell>
					<cell>Richard Edwards’s prospectus</cell>
					<cell>£5.5 for subscribers/“considerably advanced” for 
non-subscribers<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" n="d" type="note">*</ref></cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>November 1797</cell>
					<cell>Likely publication</cell>
					<cell>William Roscoe billed £1.1 for first number and £1.1
					as down payment for subscription</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>January or February? 1798</cell>
					<cell>White’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>£5.5 for subscribers/no mention of non-subscriber 
price<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" n="e" type="note">*</ref></cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>June 1798</cell>
					<cell><hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi></cell>
					<cell>£1.1</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1798, after June</cell>
					<cell><hi rend="i">Englische Blätter</hi></cell>
					<cell>No price given</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1799</cell>
					<cell>Payne’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>Two numbers mentioned; no prices given</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>March 1801</cell>
					<cell>White’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>£5.5</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>November 1801</cell>
					<cell>Richter’s correspondence</cell>
					<cell>£15.15 (his estimate of value)</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1808</cell>
					<cell>Gardiner’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>£1.5</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1809</cell>
					<cell>Gardiner’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>£1.5</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1810</cell>
					<cell>Gardiner’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>£1.5</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>1810</cell>
					<cell>Henry Crabb Robinson</cell>
					<cell>Paid £1.11.6</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1811</cell>
					<cell>Ford’s catalogue (part 1)</cell>
					<cell>Not available</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1811</cell>
					<cell>Ford’s catalogue (part 2)</cell>
					<cell>£8.8 (with Blake’s edition of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>)</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>1811</cell>
					<cell>Lackington’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>Two volumes: £2.10 each</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>1815</cell>
					<cell>Lackington’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>£2.2 each (perhaps same two volumes from 1811)</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1819</cell>
					<cell>Catalogue of books in the British Museum</cell>
					<cell>Price paid not given</cell>
				</row>
				<row rend="shaded">
					<cell>1820</cell>
					<cell>E. and A. Evans’ catalogue</cell>
					<cell>Two volumes: 30s (£1.10) and £1.1</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>1821</cell>
					<cell>Thomas Edwards’s catalogue</cell>
					<cell>£2.12.6</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>1824</cell>
					<cell>Akehurst’s correspondence</cell>
					<cell>Price paid not given</cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>1826</cell>
					<cell>Collection of Rebekah Bliss</cell>
					<cell>£4.4 paid for a colored copy; £1.19 paid for an uncolored copy</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<note id="n56">* These prices refer to the never completed four-volume set.</note>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
