<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.3.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Waxed in Blake</title>
		<author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2009-10</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009-10</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009-10"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-3-0008">
        <pb id="p43-110" n="110"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Waxed in Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>BY <docAuthor>NELSON <name>HILTON</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <div3>
            <p>THOSE who write on Bob Dylan appear to take for granted the influence of Blake on his “Gates
of Eden” (in performance by 31 October 1964, then issued on <hi rend="i">Bringing It All Back Home</hi>,
March 1965, and as the flip side to the single version of “Like a Rolling Stone,” July 1965). Michael Gray
speaks for many, if at greater length, in stating that “the purposive force of what is palpably Blakeian
impinges in every verse. It is the major Dylan song prior to ‘Every Grain Of Sand’ that is most like
Blake, and like the most characteristic Blake at that.” Without giving specifics, Gray argues that “the
general themes of ‘Gates of Eden’ could not be more Blakeian and nor could their treatment. Dylan is
treating of balances of opposites—of material wealth and spiritual; of earthly reality and the imaginatively
real; of the body and soul; of false gods and true vision; of self-gratification and salvation; of mortal
ambitions and the celestial city; of sins and forgiveness; of evil and good.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105" type="note">1</ref> Lawrence Wilde suggests, more concretely but equally without
evidence, that “William Blake’s poem ‘Gates of Paradise’ may well have inspired Dylan’s
composition,” and Mike Marqusee finds “an apt reference to Blake” in the song’s seventh-stanza
reference to “kingdoms of Experience.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n106"
type="note">2</ref></p>
            <note id="n105">1. <hi rend="i">Song and Dance Man III: The Art of Bob Dylan</hi> (London:
Continuum, 2000) 61, 62. See also John Hinchey, <hi rend="i">Like a Complete Unknown: The Poetry of Bob
Dylan’s Songs, 1961-1969</hi> (Ann Arbor: Stealing Home Press, 2002) 88.</note>
            <note id="n106">2. Lawrence Wilde, “The Cry of Humanity: Dylan’s Expressionist Period,” 
<hi rend="i">The Political Art of Bob Dylan</hi>, ed. David Boucher and Gary Browning (Basingstoke: Palgrave
Macmillan, 2004) 92; Mike Marqusee, <hi rend="i">Chimes of Freedom: The Politics of Bob Dylan’s Art</hi>
(New York: New Press, 2003) 166.</note>
            <p>The recent publication in facsimile of a manuscript version of “Gates of Eden” enables
further speculation about Blake’s presence in the song’s first stanza, at least, and how it came to
pass.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107" type="note">3</ref> As published and recorded, the
first stanza reads:
			<q>Of war and peace the truth just twists<lb/>
            Its curfew gull just glides<lb/>
            Upon four-legged forest clouds<lb/>
            The cowboy angel rides<lb/>
            With his candle lit into the sun<lb/>
            Though its glow is waxed in black<lb/>
            All except when ’neath the trees of Eden.</q>
            The facsimile has in the third line not “four-legged” but “fungus forest cloud.” This,
together with the twisting of the truth, the black glow, and the setting “‘neath the trees,” seems
strongly to recall “A Memorable Fancy” in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, plates 17-18.
There the speaker, in the company of “An Angel,” finds himself “sitting in the twisted root of an oak.
he was suspended in a fungus” and beholding “the sun, black but shining” (E 41).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108" type="note">4</ref> In the facsimile the cowboy angel “lights his candle in
the sun” (itself replacing the original “his candle burns the day”), which flips us a few plates forward
in <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> to the argument that a “man of mechanical talents” producing volumes—or
vinyl recordings “waxed in black”—from the writings of inspired authors should “not say that he knows
better than his master, for he only holds a candle in sunshine” (pl. 22, E 43).</p>
            <note id="n107">3. Robert Santelli, <hi rend="i">The Bob Dylan Scrapbook, 1956-1966</hi> (New
York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 2005) 41 (insert).</note>
            <note id="n108">4. The power of this image is evident again several years later in John
Gardner’s <hi rend="i">Grendel</hi> (New York: Knopf, 1971), where the protagonist “recall[s] something. A
void boundless as a nether sky. I hang by the twisted roots of an oak, looking down into immensity. Vastly far
away I see the sun, black but shining...” (137).</note>
            <p>It seems likely that Dylan may have come upon or have been reminded of Blake’s work through a
rapidly developing friendship with Allen Ginsberg that began in early 1964.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n109" type="note">5</ref> Ginsberg’s long-standing and idiosyncratic, deep
involvement with Blake is well known, and he “had studied, in particular, the visionary masterpiece, 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n110"
type="note">6</ref> Dylan may have come to his title image not only through Blake’s <hi rend="i">Gates of
Paradise</hi>, but also through Ginsberg’s very early collection <hi rend="i">The Gates of Wrath</hi>.
Though not published until 1972, the unique manuscript of these “rhymed poems, 1948-1952,” was,
surprisingly, in Dylan’s possession.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n111"
type="note">7</ref> There, beginning his twenty-fourth year in May 1964, Dylan could have read “Ode: My 24th
Year” and its concluding line, “Here is no Eden: this
              <pb id="p43-111" n="111"/>
            is my store.” By the release of “Gates of Eden,” Dylan was close enough to Ginsberg that
they are depicted each wearing the same top hat in photographs on the back cover of <hi rend="i">Bringing It
All Back Home</hi> (pictures evidently taken early in 1964).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n112" type="note">8</ref> For his part, Ginsberg felt strongly enough about the song that in “Who Be
Kind To,” first read at the International Poetry Incarnation, 11 June 1965, Royal Albert Hall (shortly after
he accompanied Dylan’s UK concert tour recorded in <hi rend="i">Don’t Look Back</hi>), he celebrates the
raising up of “joyful voices and guitars / in electric Afric hurrah / for Jerusalem— / The saints come
marching in, Twist &amp; / Shout, and Gates of Eden are named / in Albion again.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113" type="note">9</ref></p>
            <note id="n109">5. Michael Schumacher, <hi rend="i">Dharma Lion: A Critical Biography of Allen
Ginsberg</hi> (New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1992) 405; Bill Morgan, <hi rend="i">I Celebrate Myself: The
Somewhat Private Life of Allen Ginsberg</hi> (New York: Viking, 2006) 383; Richard E. Hishmeh, “Marketing
Genius: The Friendship of Allen Ginsberg and Bob Dylan,” <hi rend="i">Journal of American Culture</hi> 29.4
(2006): 395-405.</note>
            <note id="n110">6. Paul Portugés, <hi rend="i">The Visionary Poetics of Allen Ginsberg</hi>
(Santa Barbara: Ross-Erikson, 1978) 101.</note>
            <note id="n111">7. Ginsberg relates in a “Hindsight” to the 1972 edition published by Grey Fox
Press (Bolinas) “<hi rend="i">Gates of Wrath</hi> ms. was carried to London by lady friend early fifties, it
disappeared, and I had no complete copy till 1968 when old typescript was returned thru poet Bob Dylan—it
passed into his hands years earlier.” The volume has Blake’s “Right thro’ the Gates of Wrath” as one
of its epigraphs and two directly Blake-inspired poems, “On Reading William Blake’s ‘The Sick Rose’”
and “The Eye Altering Alters All.”</note>
            <note id="n112">8. Barry Miles, <hi rend="i">Ginsberg: A Biography</hi>, rev. ed. (London: Virgin
Publishing, 2000) 330.</note>
            <note id="n113">9. Allen Ginsberg, <hi rend="i">Collected Poems: 1947-1997</hi> (New York:
Harper-Collins, 2006) 368 (text is dated 8 June 1965); see also Schumacher 447.</note>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
