<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.3.gourlay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Blake’s 1809 Exhibition, Tate Britain, 20 April-4 October 2009; Martin
Myrone, ed., Seen in My Visions: A Descriptive Catalogue of Pictures</title>
		<author n="Gourlay">Alexander Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2009-10</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009-10</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009-10"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
      <pb id="p43-96" n="96"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title type="main">William Blake’s 1809 Exhibition. Room 8, Tate Britain. 20 April-4 October
2009.</title>
			  <title type="main">Martin Myrone, ed. <hi rend="i">Seen in My Visions: A Descriptive Catalogue of
Pictures</hi>. London: Tate Publishing, 2009. 128 pp., illus. £12.99, hardcover.</title>
            </head>
            <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Alexander <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor></byline>
            <p>For the bicentennial of Blake’s utterly disastrous 1809 “Exhibition of Paintings in Fresco,
Poetical and Historical Inventions,” Tate Britain has recreated the show in its room 8, including ten of the
original sixteen pictures. Even though considerable energy and intelligence went into the exhibit and the
augmented edition of Blake’s original <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> published in conjunction with
it, the result is no more successful than the original seems to have been in communicating Blake’s ideas or
persuading an audience that he had discovered the lost secret of painting. Whereas Blake’s show took place
in mundane rooms above the haberdashery shop operated by his brother, the recreated exhibition has the benefit
of the exalted cultural domain of the Tate, and the curators may have hoped that this, together with Blake’s
greatly improved reputation, might be enough to save the show this time around. But in 1809 all Blake’s
pictures were present, including the gigantic painting on canvas of <hi rend="i">The Ancient Britons</hi> (the
square footage of which probably equaled the rest of the pictures combined), most of the pictures looked the
way Blake wanted them to look, and the relevant cultural and political contexts were at hand. The audience
decidedly didn’t get it then. Now we don’t have enough left to figure out what there once was to get.</p>
            <p>Only eleven of the original pictures survive. The show includes all ten that are still in
Britain, but some of those that are lost, such as <hi rend="i">The Ancient Britons</hi>, may have been
essential to understanding Blake’s purposes in mounting the exhibition in the first place. The watercolors
in the Tate show are fairly bright and most are bonny, but none of the surviving temperas is in good
shape—<hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of Nelson</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Spiritual</hi>
            <figure n="exhibition1.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="306">
			  <figTranscr>‘THE GRAND STYLE OF<lb/>
			  ART RESTORED’<lb/>
			  William Blake’s<lb/>
			  1809<lb/>
			  exhibition<lb/>
			  <lb/>
			  Blake’s exhibition</figTranscr>
              <figDesc><hi rend="i">Nelson</hi>, <hi rend="i">Pitt</hi>, <hi rend="i">Sir Jeffery Chaucer and
the Nine and Twenty Pilgrims</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Bard</hi>, a space for <hi rend="i">A Spirit Vaulting from
a Cloud</hi>, and <hi rend="i">As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds</hi>. In the foreground is a case
containing a copy of the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>.<lb/>
              Courtesy Sam Drake/Tate Photography.</figDesc>
            </figure>
              <pb id="p43-97" n="97"/>
              <figure n="exhibition2.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="303">
                <figDesc><hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions</hi> in the middle, with spaces to the left
for <hi rend="i">The Goats</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Preceptor</hi> and to the right for 
<hi rend="i">The Bramins</hi> and the watercolor <hi rend="i">Cain Fleeing</hi> (the tempera is above). The case
contains catalogues from other 1809 exhibitions.<lb/>
                Courtesy Sam Drake/Tate Photography.</figDesc>
              </figure>
            <hi rend="i">Form of Pitt</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Bard</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His
Legions</hi> are so browned and/or otherwise damaged that it is hard to see what is going on in them (though
in the case of <hi rend="i">Satan Calling</hi> and at least one lost picture the obscurity may have been a
deliberate effect). <hi rend="i">Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the Nine and Twenty Pilgrims on Their Journey to
Canterbury</hi> is the most presentable of the original temperas, though it too is in sadly deteriorated
condition, so Blake’s plan of demonstrating the superiority of the “Ancient Method of Fresco Painting
Restored” (E 529) with a group of exemplary and durable pictures is definitely not realized in room 8. The
curators have gestured toward the cultural context in 1809 by displaying some other 1809 catalogues and
dedicating one wall to a selection of exhibition pictures in oil and watercolor by other artists, but most of
them seem to have been chosen because they were available at the Tate, not because they are especially
relevant to Blake’s show. With the exception of Thomas Stothard’s Chaucer painting, the importance of
which is discussed below, the pictures that are provided for context merely indicate that Blake’s works were
far out of the mainstream without giving any clues to why they might have been that way, and the contemporary
exhibition catalogues displayed under glass do not reveal very much either.</p>
            <p>The surviving pictures from the 1809 exhibition are arrayed on the remaining three walls,
mostly following the order in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, which may have been the
sequence in which they were originally displayed. Blank spaces of appropriate dimensions represent lost or
absent works, and in some cases related pictures by Blake are nearby: for instance, the Tate’s
well-preserved tempera of <hi rend="i">The Body of Abel</hi> (c. 1826) stands in for the somewhat less
impressive watercolor of the subject that was actually in the 1809 show (and is now at the Fogg), and the
British Museum’s handsome watercolor called <hi rend="i">As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds</hi>
takes the place of the lost tempera of <hi rend="i">A Spirit Vaulting from a Cloud</hi>. In one case even the
original pictures stands in need of supplementation. The conditions for viewing the fragile and profoundly
obscure tempera <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions</hi> in room 8 are very good, and a great
improvement over those at its home in the Victoria and Albert (where as I recall one must view it flat, under
glass, directly beneath a skylight). But even in these circumstances little more than darkness is visible. It
might have been edifying if this “experiment Picture” had been accompanied by the “more perfect” (E
547) later version of the same subject at Petworth House, which even today is comparatively successful at
making the forms subtly apparent.</p>
            <p>One major issue in Blake’s original exhibition was the relationship between vision, light,
and darkness; these are of course central to Blake’s work in general, but many of the pictures
              <pb id="p43-98" n="98"/>
              <figure n="exhibition3.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="306">
                <figDesc>The space for <hi rend="i">The Ancient Britons</hi>. Courtesy Sam Drake/Tate
Photography.</figDesc>
              </figure>
            he exhibited in 1809 prominently thematize light or its absence, as well as explicitly contrasting
spiritual and natural vision (at that time a very sore point for Blake, lately stung by the reviews of his 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations). And though it probably was not quite so impossibly murky in Blake’s day,
<hi rend="i">Satan’s Calling</hi> was always expected to challenge the viewer to appreciate Blake’s
visions, even when severely deprived of Newtonian light. Darkness was also important in another “experiment
Picture” in the 1809 show, <hi rend="i">The Goats</hi>, now lost. Blake explained in his catalogue that it
was inspired by an episode in Wilson’s <hi rend="i">A Missionary Voyage to the Southern Pacific Ocean</hi>
(1799) in which native women dressed in leaves were stripped naked by hungry shipboard goats. The
representation “varied from the literal fact, for the sake of picturesque scenery,” Blake wrote, and
though it was “laboured to a superabundant blackness,” he called it to the special attention of the
“Artist and Connoisseur” (E 546). The Tate’s gallery label suggests that “Blake may have intended the
picture as a joke at the expense of the straight-laced [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] missionaries,” but while it
probably was a joke it probably wasn’t aimed at the missionaries, if only because Blake never mentioned them
or their laces.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">1</ref> My guess it that not
all the goats of the title are four legged, and that Blake mischievously imagined lecherous artists and
connoisseurs jostling each other to peer into the superabundant blackness to glimpse the naked dark-skinned
women.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">2</ref></p>
            <note id="n82">1. In a similar misconstruction, the gallery label for the lost picture 
<hi rend="i">The Bramins</hi> suggests that Blake’s acknowledgement that the “Costume is incorrect” (E 548)
refers to the clothing worn by Wilkins, the Englishman who consulted Brahmins in translating the 
<hi rend="i">Gita</hi>. It is much more likely that Blake erred in representing the garb of the Brahmins.</note>
            <note id="n83">2. For a discussion of a comparable racially charged work by Stothard, see
“‘Art Delivered’: Stothard’s <hi rend="i">The Sable Venus</hi> and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of
the Daughters of Albion</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 31.4 (2008): 529-50,
in which I suggest that <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> began as an outraged revisionary reconstruction of
Stothard’s picture and the poem it illustrates.</note>
            <p>But recognizing this gag, if that’s what it was, in the middle of the exhibition hardly helps
us to understand Blake’s purposes in general. Certainly <hi rend="i">The Ancient Britons</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Sir Jeffery Chaucer</hi> were not jokes, even if the latter had satiric dimensions, and neither were
<hi rend="i">Pitt</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi>, though they may have been deeply ironic as heroic
portraits. The curators (perhaps inadvertently) provide a potentially helpful clue to understanding Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Nelson</hi> (1807), in which the pillow behind the martyr’s head generates the impression of a
saintly—or Christ-like—aura. The painting itself is in the collection of the National Maritime
              <pb id="p43-99" n="99"/>
              Museum and not in the Tate show: it would have been good if it or another such image of Nelson
had been available to contextualize Blake’s apotheosis of the national hero, which borrows more from Hindu
than Christian art.</p>
            <p>Fortunately, Blake’s Chaucer picture is supplemented not only by the painting that Blake
treats in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> as its direct rival, Stothard’s 
<hi rend="i">Pilgrimage to Canterbury</hi>, but also the large-scale engraving Blake first published in 1810 as
well as the long-delayed engraving by Schiavonetti and Heath after Stothard. All three are clustered in one
corner of the context wall, a few steps from Blake’s tempera, and for me the close proximity of Blake’s
picture with these constitutes the most important element of the 2009 exhibition, in part because it suggests
a possible motivation for Blake’s whole show. I am still pretty much alone in believing that Blake’s
Chaucer tempera—which is usually thought to have preceded Stothard’s 1806-07 picture even though it is
dated 1808—was conceived from the start as a riposte to Stothard’s <hi rend="i">Pilgrimage</hi>,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">3</ref> but it may be less controversial to assert
that the primary impetus for the 1809 show was to showcase Blake’s “fresco” of the pilgrims as the
competitor to Stothard’s oil painting and also to promote Blake’s engraving (just as Cromek’s touring
exhibitions of Stothard’s picture were calculated to promote lucrative sales of the projected engraving
after it). Blake’s exhibition, an extraordinarily uncharacteristic foray into self-promotion, can be seen as
having an unsettled mixture of motivations, at once earnest—he really did want to sell more pictures and
engravings to the public at large—and a game, as Chaucer would say, an anxious parody of the sordid
promotional hoopla used by Cromek and others to drum up public interest. In order to respond to Cromek’s
provocations<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">4</ref> it was not enough for
Blake to paint and engrave a Chaucer picture of his own, in the same odd format as theirs (though proceeding
in the opposite direction)—he also had to mount his own promotional campaign. This scenario might suggest
why the promotion was ultimately so incoherent: it seems likely that Blake didn’t have his heart in
commercial puffery, and that in
              <figure n="exhibition4.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="307">
                <figDesc>The context paintings to the left, with the Chaucer engravings and Stothard’s 
<hi rend="i">Pilgrimage to Canterbury</hi> at the end of that wall. Courtesy Sam Drake/Tate Photography.</figDesc>
              </figure>              
              <pb id="p43-100" n="100"/>
            his marketing efforts he therefore adopted raillery, prophecy, and parody by turns as well.</p>
            <note id="n84">3. For some of my reasons see “‘Idolatry or Politics’: Blake’s Chaucer, the
Gods of Priam, and the Powers of 1809,” in my collection <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William
Blake in Honor of John E. Grant</hi> (West Cornwall, CT: Locust Hill Press, 2002) 100-03.</note>
            <note id="n85">4. In a letter (May 1807) Cromek asks Blake why he detests Stothard’s Chaucer
painting and invites him to produce “a better” if he doesn’t like it; see G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2004) 241-44.</note>
            <p>The rivalry between the Chaucer pictures may have spurred Blake’s exhibition, but rather than
presenting only one picture, carrying it from town to town with expensive ballyhoo as Cromek had done, Blake
instead brought together an assortment of sixteen works, many of them falling into subject categories popular
at the time but rare in Blake’s oeuvre. It’s hard to tell how many besides the Chaucer picture were really
for sale, since several had been borrowed from Thomas Butts, the “experiment Pictures” were probably not
saleable, and <hi rend="i">The Ancient Britons</hi> was commissioned by William Owen Pughe. Some might have
been throwaway parodies (especially <hi rend="i">The Goats</hi>), and others (<hi rend="i">Pitt</hi>, 
<hi rend="i">Nelson</hi>) may have been created for the occasion as Blake’s ironic alternatives to such
dead-celebrity art as Devis’s <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi> or West’s <hi rend="i">Death of Wolfe</hi>. 
<hi rend="i">The Bramins</hi> could have been a response to the popular genre depicting interactions between
Britons and colonial subjects.</p>
            <p>I am not sure that a fully coherent conception of the exhibition could have been communicated
in room 8 by lining up an ideally suggestive array of contextual works or expanding the wall labels to include
more of Blake’s descriptions, but the new edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> that
accompanies the show does not go as far as it might have to help us either. This handsome quasi-catalogue by
Martin Myrone, curator of the show, is for the most part intelligently executed but not very ambitious.
Although the introductory chapter efficiently and even-handedly summarizes scholarly opinion about the 1809
exhibition and much more clearly explains its contexts than the 2009 exhibit itself does, there is little
attempt to put it all together or go beyond what has been said about the pictures in Butlin’s 
<hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>. The presentation of the complete text of Blake’s
catalogue is perfunctory, with informative but uneven notes, and the biographical and glossarial “indexes”
at the back are mostly unhelpful and often mysterious. There are good images of the surviving pictures
(including the Fogg’s <hi rend="i">Cain Fleeing</hi>, which is not in the Tate show); several, especially
<hi rend="i">The Bard</hi> and <hi rend="i">Satan Calling</hi>, appear to have been enhanced so that they
reveal much more than can now be seen in the actual pictures.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
