<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.3.whitehead</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Mark and Eleanor Martin, the Blakes’ French Fellow Inhabitants at 17 South
Molton Street, 1805-21</title>
		<author n="Whitehead">Angus Whitehead</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2009-10</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009-10</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009-10"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
    <pb id="p43-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Mark and Eleanor Martin, the Blakes’ French Fellow Inhabitants at 17 South
Molton Street, 1805-21</title>
          </head>
          <byline>BY <docAuthor>ANGUS <name>WHITEHEAD</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref></byline>
          <p>As the first major Paris exhibition of the poet-artist’s works in over sixty years has recently
taken place,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> it seems fitting to
discuss William and Catherine Blake’s sixteen-year association with a Parisian: their landlord at 17 South
Molton Street, Mark Martin. In this paper, after a brief discussion of his predecessors, I present new
information concerning Martin, his wife, his nationality, and his trade. I also discuss the relationship
between the Martins and the Blakes and how the nature of that relationship throws light on the Blakes’
seventeen-year residence in South Molton Street (illus. 1-2), a period of Blake’s life of which we still
know very little.</p> 
          <note id="n0">* For advice and assistance during my research for and writing of this paper, I wish
to thank Robert Essick, Ian Chipperfield, Rory Lalwan, Michael Phillips, Mark Crosby, and especially
Anne-Laure Robert.</note>
          <note id="n1">1. William Blake, le génie visionnaire du romantisme anglais, Petit Palais, Musée
des Beaux-Arts de la Ville de Paris, Apr.-June 2009.</note>
          <p>Mark Martin is at least in name not unfamiliar to Blake scholarship. In April 1830, almost three
years after Blake’s death, John Linnell recalled: “When I first became acquainted with Mr. Blake he lived
in a first floor in South Molton Street and upon his Landlord leaving off business &amp; retiring to France,
he moved to Fountain Court Strand, where he died.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> In 1958 Paul Miner, on the basis of data from early nineteenth-century rate books for the
parish of St. George, Hanover Square, first identified “the rate-payer [at 17 South Molton Street] for the
period 1803-1821, presumably Blake’s landlord,” as Mark Martin.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Although most subsequent biographers have utilized Miner’s discovery, none
has expanded upon it. Martin has remained no more than a name, referred to as “Mark Martin,” “one Mark
Martin,” or “a certain Mark Martin.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> Commenting upon Linnell’s recollection, Miner observed that, although Martin appears to
have retired to France in 1821, “he seems to have retained ownership of the property; at any rate a ‘Mark
Martin’ continued to pay the rates as late as 1829.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref> No subsequent biographer has discussed Martin or identified the business he must have left
off in order to retire. Ruthven Todd observed that “it is not known whether the ground floor [of no. 17] was
then used commercially as it has been for at least a century.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">6</ref> However, Peter Ackroyd first suggested that the Blake’s two rooms would have
been situated “no doubt above some kind of commercial establishment.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> In this essay I demonstrate that both Miner and Ackroyd were
correct.</p>
          <note id="n2">2. Letter to Bernard Barton, quoted in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
[hereafter <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)] 526. Alexander Gilchrist states in his 1863 biography that the move to
Fountain Court occurred in 1821 (Gilchrist 282).</note>
          <note id="n3">3. Miner 544.</note>
          <note id="n4">4. See respectively Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 260fn, King 158, Ackroyd
249.</note>
          <note id="n5">5. Miner 544. He thanks “G. F. Osborn, Archivist, Westminster Public Libraries, for
this information” (549n32).</note>
          <note id="n6">6. Todd 63.</note>
          <note id="n7">7. Ackroyd 248-49.</note>
          <p><hi rend="b">The Blakes’ Previous Landlord(s?) at South Molton Street: John Lytrott</hi></p>
          <p>However, Miner is mistaken in some details. Martin was not ratepayer (and consequently not
landlord) at 17 South Molton Street between 1803 and 1804, when William and Catherine Blake first lodged
there; he was their second or perhaps third landlord at this residence. The ratepayer in March 1803 is
recorded as John Lytrott,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> and the
residential section of <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory</hi> lists a Captain John Lytrott.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> It is therefore possible that the Blakes
initially corresponded with, met, and even lodged briefly with Lytrott between his last appearance in the rate
book in March 1803 and his absence therein the following year. Since the Blakes moved in about October
1803,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Lytrott may have been their
landlord (if not necessarily their fellow inhabitant) for a period of up to five and a half months.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref></p>
          <note id="n8">8. St. George’s Parish, Hanover Square, Brook Street Ward, poor, watch, and paving
rates, 1803 (City of Westminster Archives Centre [hereafter COWAC] C596).</note>
          <note id="n9">9. <hi rend="i">Holden’s Triennial Directory</hi> 1802-03-04 (1802) n. pag.</note>
          <note id="n10">10. See Erdman [hereafter E] 737 (letter of 26 Oct. 1803). However, the South Molton
Street address on this letter is in fact an insertion by Gilchrist (see Gilchrist 170). A letter of 7 Oct.
1803 suggests that the Blakes had only recently arrived in London (E 736-37).</note>
          <note id="n11">11. Several facts concerning Lytrott’s life can be traced. He was baptized in 1763
at St. George’s Church, Hanover Square (<hi rend="i">International Genealogical Index</hi>
&lt;http://www.familysearch.org&gt;), so was almost certainly born and bred in Mayfair. However, his name and
choice of regiment suggest Scottish ancestry. On 19 Dec. 1777 he was commissioned as quartermaster for the
first battalion of Major-General John Mackenzie, Lord Macleod’s Highlanders, Seventy-Third Regiment, a
Scottish regiment raised in response to the outbreak of the American war (see <hi rend="i">A List of the
General and Field Officers, As They Rank in the Army</hi> [Dublin: Executors of David Hay, 1780] 148). The
Seventy-Third served in southern India and sustained heavy losses at Cuddalore on 13 June 1783. In 1784
Lytrott appears in the army lists as second lieutenant (a commission almost certainly purchased) in the Royal
North British Fusiliers, Twenty-First Foot. However, the entry indicates that he was collecting half pay,
which suggests that he had retired or was unfit for active service (<hi rend="i">A List of the Officers of the
Army... Complete to 1st June 1784</hi> [Dublin: Abraham Bradley King, 1784] 294). Lytrott’s listing in a new
regiment and on half pay shortly after the battle of Cuddalore, coupled with his later appointment as captain
of the Seventh Royal Veterans, a regiment for servicemen unfit for active duty (see below), implies that he
was wounded or incapacitated during his service in India.</note>
          <p>On 17 May 1788, after partially retiring from the army, Lytrott married Ann MacDonald at St.
George’s, Hanover
            <pb id="p43-85" n="85"/>
            <figure n="17smoulton-wc.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="259" height="400">
				<figTranscr>Fredk. Adcock<lb/>
				17 SOUTH MOULTON STREET</figTranscr>
			</figure>
            <figure n="17smoulton-photo.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="270" height="400">
				<figTranscr>CMC<lb/>
				CMC</figTranscr>
				<head>1-2. 17 South Molton Street</head>
				<figDesc>c. 1912 (watercolor by Frederick Adcock; City of Westminster Archives Centre, C138) and in August
2002
(photograph by Angus Whitehead).</figDesc>
			</figure>
            Square.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> A “Mrs
MacDonald” and a “Ms MacDonald,” probably Ann’s daughter (named Christian, a common Scottish female
forename in the period), had been ratepayers at 17 South Molton Street since 1786,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> the year in which Alexander MacDonald, Ann’s first husband
and the previous ratepayer, had died.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> In 1790 Lytrott replaced his wife and stepdaughter as ratepayer and, as we have seen,
continued until sometime between March 1803 and March 1804.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">15</ref> His ceasing to pay rates during this period is probably explained by the
fact that on 25 December 1802 he became a captain in the Seventh Royal Veteran Battalion, raised under
Major-General Thomas Murray and formed for those men discharged from cavalry and foot guards regiments as good
for garrison duties only. It is likely that between December 1802 and March 1804 Lytrott moved from South
Molton Street to the battalion’s quarters at Fulham garrison.</p>
          <note id="n12">12. St. George, Hanover Square, marriage register, vol. 254 (COWAC).</note>
          <note id="n13">13. In 1786 “Mrs MacDonald,” 1787-89 “Mrs, Ms MacDonald” (for 1788 and 1789
these entries have been subsequently scored through), 1790 “John Lytrott.” See St. George’s rates,
1786-90 (COWAC C382, 383, 384, 387, 583).</note>
          <note id="n14">14. “Will of Alexander MacDonald or McDonald, Gentleman of South Molton Street
Grosvenor Square, Middlesex,” proved 11 May 1786 (PRO PROB 11/1142, Prerogative Court of Canterbury Will
Registers, Norfolk Quire Numbers: 262-311). With Hugh Blair, Joseph Johnson, Anna Seward, Helen Maria
Williams, and Richard Cosway, he was a subscriber to fellow Scots Maria and Harriet Falconar’s 
<hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (see Falconar xxv), although the book was published after his death.</note>
          <note id="n15">15. In 1793 Lytrott’s regiment, the Twenty-First Foot, formed part of an expedition
to  the West Indies. However, his remaining on half pay suggests that he did not travel with it 
(<hi rend="i">A List of the Officers of the Army</hi> [Dublin: Printed by James King and A. Bradley King, 1795]
357). On 27 Aug. 1794 he was promoted to captain in the Twenty-First (<hi rend="i">The Monthly Army List ... 1
Jan. 1798-1 June 1809</hi> [London, 1798-1809] 483), and in 1795 he is recorded as captain on half pay in the
Late Loyal Sheffield Regiment of Foot.</note>
          <p>Whether Lytrott’s wealth derived from his wife or was his own, he appears to have been a man of
some means, leaving
            <pb id="p43-86" n="86"/>
          generous sums to servants on his death in 1809.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> This suggests that these servants had been employed for several years and had therefore
lived at South Molton Street five years earlier. Lytrott also bequeathed £100 to his stepdaughter, Mrs.
Christian Hargreaves, née MacDonald. His evident wealth indicates that no. 17 was the well-kept home of a man
of substance.</p>
          <note id="n16">16. He bequeathed Eleanor Ryan £500 and Thomas Branning “my servant and a private
soldier in the Seventh Royal Veteran Battalion fifty pounds together with all my shirts and wearing apparel
except my regimental cloak boots and accoutrements ... ” (will of John Lytrott of Hanover Square, Middlesex,
proved 17 July 1809 [PRO PROB 11/1501, Prerogative Court of Canterbury Will Registers, Loveday Quire Numbers:
560-617]). According to his will, Lytrott was living in Lower Swan Street, Chelsea, by 1809.</note>
          <p>MacDonald and Lytrott describe themselves in their wills as gentlemen and as resident or formerly
resident at South Molton Street. This may suggest that during the residence of both men, and probably since
its construction (c. 1755), no. 17 served the purpose for which it was built: to accommodate one household.
However, it is also possible that a shopkeeper or lodger may have rented a floor. Nevertheless, from the time
that the house was built until the Blakes’ arrival, persons of social rank paid the rates. From March 1804
until several decades after the Blakes left, the ratepayers were tradesmen, indicating a social shift in the
history of the house.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref></p>
          <note id="n17">17. In the 1861 census William Arnold, breeches maker, is listed as residing and
trading at no. 17 (PRO RG9/93/4-15); in 1868 a Mrs. Dodkin, private resident, is recorded as living there 
(<hi rend="i">Kelly’s London Directory</hi> 1868 [n. pag.]).</note>
          <p><hi rend="b">The Blakes’ Previous Landlord(s?) at South Molton Street: William Enoch</hi></p>
          <p>A ratepayer at no. 17 who we can be certain preceded Martin as the Blakes’ landlord and fellow
inhabitant is William Enoch, who ran a tailor’s shop from this address, presumably on the ground floor.
Rate-book entries indicate that he assumed the rates as Lytrott ceased paying and in all probability left the
premises, i.e. between March 1803 and March 1804. Enoch lived with his wife, Mary Naylor Enoch, and their
infant son, William, above the shop.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
In a letter of January 1804, written after his trial for sedition at Chichester, Blake informed William
Hayley, “my poor wife has been near the Gate of Death as was supposed by our kind &amp; attentive fellow
inhabitant. the young &amp; very amiable Mrs Enoch. who gave my wife all the attention that a daughter could
pay to a mother.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> This implies
extremely amiable relations between the Blakes and the Enochs, perhaps suggesting that they remained friends
after the family left no. 17.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
However, the business appears to have been experiencing difficulties by the closing months of 1804,
necessitating the Enochs’ departure from the shop and apartment, certainly by March 1805 and perhaps as
early as the autumn of 1804. As Mary Enoch had provided aid and solace to Catherine Blake in early 1804, the
Blakes may have tried to assist their co-inhabitants at the end of that year as the business went under.</p>
          <note id="n18">18. For further details, see Whitehead, “New Information.”</note>
          <note id="n19">19. E 740.</note>
          <note id="n20">20. This may strengthen Bentley’s suggestion that there is a connection between the
Enochs and Blake’s lithograph <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 750).</note>
          <p>Entries from the <hi rend="i">London Gazette</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jackson’s Oxford
Journal</hi> during the first half of 1805 explain the brief duration of the Enochs’ residence.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> The <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> for 22 January
1805 indicates that by this date Enoch had already ben declared bankrupt. The fact that he is referred to as
“late of 17 South Molton” suggests that the family had left by the end of 1804. However, no new address is
mentioned. The same article reveals that Enoch had been ordered to surrender himself to the commission at
Guildhall for examination on 5 and 9 February and 9 March to “make a full Discovery and Disclosure of his
Estate and Effects.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> On Saturday 2
February <hi rend="i">Jackson’s Oxford Journal</hi> included Enoch in a list of bankrupts: 
“<hi rend="i">William Enock</hi> ..., late of South Molton Street, Oxford Street, Middlesex, Tailor, February 5, 9,
March 9 at Guildhall.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> The
settling of Enoch’s affairs before the issuing of a certificate of bankruptcy must have taken longer than
anticipated, as proceedings were adjourned on 9 March 1805 and reconvened on the 23rd at a meeting in which
final creditors proved their debts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref>
On 14 May the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> reported:
		<q>Whereas the acting Commissioners in the Commission of Bankrupt awarded and issued forth against
William Enock, late of South-Molton-Street, Oxford-Street, in the County of Middlesex, Tailor, Dealer and
Chapman, have certified to the Right Honorable John Lord Eldon, Lord High Chancellor of Great Britain, that
the said William Enock hath in all Things conformed himself according to the Directions of the several Acts of
Parliament made concerning Bankrupts; This is to give Notice, that, by virtue of an Act passed in the Fifth
Year of His late Majesty’s Reign, his Certificate will be allowed and confirmed as the said Act directs,
unless Cause be shewn to the contrary on or before the 8th Day of June next.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref></q>
          </p>
          <note id="n21">21. References to Enoch’s bankruptcy in the press consistently use an alternative
spelling of his surname: Enock. In addition, his business is described as that of “Tailor, Dealer and
Chapman.”</note>
          <note id="n22">22. <hi rend="i">London Gazette</hi> 22 Jan. 1805: 118.</note>
          <note id="n23">23. My thanks to Keri Davies for bringing this reference to my attention.</note>
          <note id="n24">24. See <hi rend="i">London Gazette</hi> 9 Mar. 1805: 324.</note>
          <note id="n25">25. <hi rend="i">London Gazette</hi> 14 May 1805: 665.</note>
          <p><hi rend="b">Mark Martin</hi></p>
          <p>The rate-book entries for no. 17 reveal that Martin was first recorded as ratepayer in March
1805, approximately eighteen months after the Blakes moved into their lodgings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> However, it is possible that he had replaced the bankrupt
Enoch as landlord and ratepayer as early as the autumn of 1804. Miner’s statement that “a ‘Mark
Martin’ continued to pay the rates as
            <pb id="p43-87" n="87"/>
            <figure n="ratebook.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="511">
				<figTranscr>46)<lb/>
				                        Rents   Poor and Highways   Watch   Pav[ing] Cleans[ing] &amp; Lighting   Total<lb/>
				       Robt. Huttersly .   28   3._.8   _.7._   _.14._   4.1.8<lb/>
				IIII   Wm. Spicer . . . .  28   3._.8   _.7._   _.14._   4.1.8<lb/>
				IIII   Wm. Small . . . .   28   3._.8   _.7._   _.14._   4.1.8<lb/>
				IIII   W: A: Scripps . .   28   3._.8   _.7._   _.14._   4.1.8<lb/>
				IIII   Edwd. Parish . . .  28   3._.8   _.7._   _.14._   4.1.8<lb/>
				IIII   Maria Radcliffe .   28   3._.8   _.7._   _.14._   4.1.8<lb/>
				IIII   Richd. May . . . .  40   4.6.8   _.10._   1._._   5.16.8<lb/>
				IIII   Edmd. Treherne .    40   4.6.8   _.10._   1._._   5.16.8<lb/>
				       Wm. Rowe . . . . .  40   4.6.8   _.10._   1._._   5.16.8<lb/>
				IIII   Bynon Wilkinson     40   4.6.8   _.10._   1._._   5.16.8<lb/>
				IIII   John Wilson . . . . 40   4.6.8   _.10._   1._._   5.16.8<lb/>
				IIII   Robt. Morgan . .    40   4.6.8   _.10._   1._._   5.16.8<lb/>
				IIII   Archd. Newland .    40   4.6.8   _.10._   1._._   5.16.8<lb/>
				IIII   Martin &amp; Stockhurn   44   4.15.4   _.11._   1.2._   6.8.4<lb/>
				IIII   Fras. Tucker . . .  44   4.15.4   _.11._   1.2._   6.8.4<lb/>
				IIII   Jos: Ward . . . . . 44   4.15.4   _.11._   1.2._   6.8.4<lb/>
				IIII   Grace Weightman     40   4.6.8   _.10._   1._._   5.16.8<lb/>
				IIII   Eliz: Parvin . . . . 44   4.15.4   _.11._   1.2._   6.8.4<lb/>
				IIII   James Lay . . . .   44   4.15.4   _.11._   1.2._   6.8.4<lb/>
				IIII   Benj: Bayfield .    44   4.15.4   _.11._   1.2._   6.8.4<lb/>
				                                81.9.4   9.8._   18.16._  109.13.4</figTranscr>
				<head>3. Entry for “Martin and Stockhurn” (<hi rend="i">sic</hi>);</head>
				<figDesc>rate book for St. George’s, Hanover Square, Brook Street Ward, March 1821
(City of Westminster Archives Centre, C617, p. 46).</figDesc>
			</figure>
            <pb id="p43-81" n="81"/>
			  <figure n="haynes-hogarth-staymaker.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="482">
				<head>Cover: Detail of “The Stay-Maker,” Joseph Haynes after William Hogarth, 1782</head>
				<figDesc>(from Heath edition, 1822); image courtesy of Darvill’s Rare Prints,
Durango, CO.</figDesc>
			  </figure>
            <pb id="p43-88" n="88"/>
            late as 1829”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> is
problematic. Martin is indeed recorded as ratepayer for 1829;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">28</ref> however, in 1821, the year the Blakes are reported by Gilchrist to have
moved to Fountain Court, the entry reads Martin and Stockham (illus. 3).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref> The entry is actually “Martin and Stockhurn,” but from
directory evidence it is clear that the name of the business was Martin and Stockham. Martin and Stockham are
recorded as ratepayers for the property between 1821 and 1825.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n30">30</ref> In 1826 the name in the rate book reverts to Mark Martin and remains so until 1831, when
Martin is crossed out and replaced by Charlotte Lohay.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">31</ref> After having retired to Paris c. 1821-26, Martin appears to have returned to live and
work as a staymaker at no. 17 before March 1826. London commercial directories indicate that for the periods
1805-20/21 and 1826-30 “Mark Martin, Staymaker,” and for the period 1821-25 “Martin &amp; Stockham,
staymakers,” conducted business at no. 17.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">32</ref> This evidence confirms Ackroyd’s suggestion that the Blakes lived above a commercial
establishment, or at least lodged at a house that was also used as a commercial establishment: first Enoch’s
tailoring business, and then Martin’s staymaking shop.</p>
          <note id="n26">26. St. George’s rates, 1805 (COWAC C598).</note>
          <note id="n27">27. See also Lindsay 241n.</note>
          <note id="n28">28. St. George’s rates, 1829 (COWAC C626).</note>
          <note id="n29">29. The relevant rate book is dated Mar. 1821 (COWAC C617). As stated above, Linnell
suggests that the Blakes left South Molton Street on Martin’s retirement, therefore probably in or perhaps
sometime before Mar. 1821.</note>
          <note id="n30">30. St. George’s rates, 1825 (COWAC C622).</note>
          <note id="n31">31. St. George’s rates, 1831 (COWAC C629). Lohay was also a staymaker (see 
<hi rend="i">Robson’s Directory</hi> 1833 [n. pag.]). Her father, Ambroise Lohay, is recorded as previously
resident at no. 17 with Martin (<hi rend="i">Robson’s Directory</hi> 1828-29 (1828) n. pag.).</note>
          <note id="n32">32. See <hi rend="i">Robson’s Directory</hi> 1822 (209) and 1823 (n. pag.) and 
<hi rend="i">Pigot &amp; Co.’s Directory</hi> 1824 (153). In 1831, Charlotte Lohay’s staymaking business is
the sole trade recorded at no. 17.</note>
          <p>The change in ratepayer and business proprietor’s name from Martin to Martin and Stockham c.
1821 suggests that, as Linnell claimed, Martin retired to France. However, his retention in the new name of
the firm implies either that he remained a (silent?) partner of Stockham’s or that Stockham agreed to take
on his name.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> This information is
significant, as it appears to be the sole contemporary evidence to support Gilchrist’s undocumented claim,
followed by subsequent biographers, that the Blakes moved to Fountain Court, Strand, in 1821. However, Mark
Martin’s trade, rather than his lodgers, would have been his principal source of income;<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">34</ref> its significance should be explored.</p>
          <note id="n33">33. Alternatively, Martin may have employed a relative to co-run the business in his
absence.</note>
          <note id="n34">34. “A tradesman in London ... expects to maintain his family by his trade, and not
by his lodgers” (Adam Smith, quoted in Schwarz 325).</note>
          <p>A staymaker made, fitted, and sold stays, essentially a laced underbodice or corset stiffened by
the insertion of strips of whalebone (see cover illus.). R. Campbell, writing about
1747, observed that
		<q>The Stay-Maker ... ought to be a very polite Tradesman, as he approaches the Ladies so nearly;
and possessed of a tolerable Share of Assurance and Command of Temper to approach their delicate Persons in
fitting on their Stays, without being moved or put out of Countenance. He is obliged to inviolable Secrecy in
many Instances, where he is obliged by Art to mend a crooked Shape, to bolster up a fallen Hip, or distorted
Shoulder. ... After the Stays are stitched, and the Bone cut into thin Slices of equal Breadths and the proper
Lengths, it is thrust in between the Rows of Stitching: This requires a good deal of Strength, and is by much
the nicest Part of Stay Work; there is not above one Man in a Shop who can execute this Work, and he is either
Master or Foreman, and has the best Wages. When the Stays are boned, they are loosly [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]
sewed together, and carried Home to the Lady to be fitted ....</q>
			<q>This is a Species of the Taylor’s Business, and rather the most ingenious Art belonging to
the Mechanism of the Needle. The Masters have large Profits when they are paid ....<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref></q></p>
          <note id="n35">35. Campbell 224, 225-26. In 1737 Samuel Johnson had “take[n] humble lodgings with
a staymaker named Richard Norris just off the Strand” (see Rogers). Blake’s friend Tom Paine was a trained
staymaker (Keane 30). Joseph Taylor, father of Blake’s acquaintance Thomas Taylor the Platonist, was a
staymaker at Round Court, St. Martin’s-le-Grand (see Louth).</note>
          <p>Martin’s shop, like all London shops of the period, probably kept long hours, possibly from
7.00 in the morning until 10.30 in the evening.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">36</ref> However, such a trade as staymaking in Mayfair was dependent upon the fashion seasons and
seasonal work, with a discrepancy between a brisk time of full employment, pressure of too much work, and long
hours during the London season from late November to July, and a slack time with little or no work from the
end of the London season until late autumn.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">37</ref> Martin, like Blake, probably chose to trade in Mayfair for a reason, as explained by one
of Blake’s visitors at South Molton Street, Robert Southey.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n38" type="note">38</ref> About 1800 Southey wrote:
		<q>There is an imaginary line of demarcation which divides [Westminster and London] from each other.
A nobleman would not be found by any accident to live in that part which is properly called the City ...
whenever a person says that he lives at the West End of the Town, and consequently he is supposed to make my
coat in a better style of fashion: and this opinion is carried so far among the ladies, that if a cap was
known to have come from the City, it would be given to
            <pb id="p43-89" n="89"/>
            my lady’s woman, who would give it to the cook, and she perhaps would think it prudent not to
inquire into its pedigree.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref></q></p>
          <note id="n36">36. See George 206.</note>
          <note id="n37">37. George 209, 263. One might draw a parallel between Martin’s capricious schedule
of work (ebbing and flowing according to the London season) and Blake’s experiences as a commercial engraver
during a period (post 1804) in which he appears to have been neglected in favor of the “softer” style of
engravers such as Caroline Watson.</note>
          <note id="n38">38. See <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 310.</note>
          <note id="n39">39. Quoted in Porter 118.</note>
          <p>As most women wore stays or corsets of some form or another during this period, staymaking was a
well-established and popular trade. Martin’s business probably thrived particularly during the second half
of the Blakes’ residence at no. 17, as a change in fashion prompted a renewed demand for stays. In the 1790s
many liberals had expressed reservations about the fashion: Anna Laetitia Barbauld condemned stays in her
letter “Fashion, A Vision,” published in the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> in April 1797, describing
them as “the most common, and one of the worst instruments of torture, ... a small machine, armed with
fish-bone and ribs of steel, wide at top, but extremely small at bottom. ... this detestable
invention....”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">40</ref> Frances Burney,
visiting Paris in 1802, incredulously remarked “STAYS? every body has left off even corsets!”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref> Rousseau’s tomb featured “a number of
naked children burning women’s whalebone stays.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">42</ref> Valerie Steele has observed that “throughout its history, the corset was widely
perceived as an ‘instrument of torture’ and a major cause of ill health and even death. ... But the corset
also had many positive connotations—of social status, self-discipline, artistry, respectability, beauty,
youth, and erotic allure.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref> Steele
recounts the reemergence of stays as fashionable women’s undergarment during the first decade and a half of
the nineteenth century:
		<q>After a brief interregnum around 1800, the boned corset not only reappeared but spread throughout
society. We might have expected that having once loosened their stays, women would never again wear corsets.
Yet they did, in greater numbers than ever before. At the end of the Napoleonic Wars, in 1814 and 1815, the
fashion for high-waisted “empire” gowns was waning. As the waistline on fashionable dresses began to drop
to its normal position, skirts became fuller and boned corsets increasingly reappeared. Already by 1811, a
writer for <hi rend="i">The Mirror of the Graces</hi> was predicting a return to tight-lacing, “Deformity
once more drawing the steeled boddice [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] upon the bruised ribs.” The fashion for
neoclassical dress and no stays was regarded, in retrospect, as having been part and parcel of the disorder
and promiscuity of the Revolutionary era. For the next century, boned corsets were an essential component of
women’s fashion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">44</ref></q>
          Further evidence of the increasing popularity of stays is revealed by the fact that Martin appears
to have experienced competition from another staymaker’s shop in South Molton Street from c. 1816
onwards.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">45</ref></p>
          <note id="n40">40. McCarthy and Kraft 287.</note>
          <note id="n41">41. Quoted in Ribeiro 94.</note>
          <note id="n42">42. Ribeiro 4.</note>
          <note id="n43">43. Steele 1.</note>
          <note id="n44">44. Steele 33.</note>
          <note id="n45">45. Although he lodged in Charles Street, William Bridges (or Brydges) rented a
ground floor for his staymaking shop at “34 South Moulton Street” from Robert Gould. See 
<hi rend="i">Proceedings of the Old Bailey</hi>: trials of John Williams for “burglariously breaking and
entering the dwelling-house of William Brydges,” 3 Apr. 1816, ref. t18160403-9,
&lt;http://www.oldbaileyonline.org/browse.jsp?ref=t18160403-9&gt;. The address of his business is given in 
<hi rend="i">Pigot &amp; Co.’s Directory</hi> 1823-24 (1823) 593. Brydges’s shop, on the same side of the
street as Martin’s, would have been closer to the fashionable thoroughfare of Oxford Street at the heart of
“the greatest Emporium in the known world” (national census [1801], quoted in Porter 123).</note>
          <p>Some indication of the quality of Martin’s Mayfair customers survives in the form of a bill
(illus. 4) to the recently widowed Lady Augusta Leith, daughter of George, fifth earl of Granard, and widow of
the late Lieutenant-General Sir James Leith.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46">46</ref>
Martin’s bill suggests that he produced luxury corsets for the aristocracy and gentry. Numerous other
fashionable female and possibly male Westminster residents must also have called at his shop. The three
separate transactions may indicate that Lady Leith and her daughter were regular customers.</p>
          <note id="n46">46. See Townend 1488 and Chichester. Sir James Leith of Leith Hall, Aberdeenshire,
governor of Barbados and commander of the forces of the Windward and Leeward Islands, died of yellow fever in
Barbados on 16 Oct. 1816. His will, written on the day he died and proved 27 Mar. 1817, left all his
possessions to Lady Augusta and their children (PRO PROB 11/1590, Prerogative Court of Canterbury Will
Registers, Effingham Quire Numbers: 106-66). His remains were interred in Westminster Abbey in Mar.
1817.</note>
          <p>At the head of the bill is a copperplate intaglio engraving printed in black ink giving details
of Martin’s staymaking business.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">47</ref>
The design is not stylistically distinctive, and there is no evidence that Blake ever produced such engraved
tradesmen’s bills.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">48</ref> However, it is
also possible that Martin may have asked Blake to engrave and print this for him sometime before mid-February
1817. During this period the Blakes may have been glad of even such jobbing work. Details of Martin’s trade
and address are engraved in an egg- or oval-shaped border and surrounded by a simple brickwork design:
“Martin, / STAYMAKER, / (From Paris) / N<hi rend="s">o</hi>. 17 South Molton Street, / Oxford Street, /
LONDON. / Fait toutes Sortes de Corps et de Corsets a la Francoise.” (“makes all manner of French-style
stays [or bodices] and corsets”). Martin’s use of the word “corps,” which translates roughly as
“bodice” or “stays,” is of
            <pb id="p43-90" n="90"/>
            <figure n="staymakerbill.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="288">
				<figTranscr>Martin,<lb/>
				STAYMAKER<lb/>
				(From Paris)<lb/>
				N°. 17 South Molton Street,<lb/>
				Oxford Street,<lb/>
				LONDON.<lb/>
				Fait toutes Sortes de Corps et de Corsets a la Francoise.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				Lady Leith<lb/>
				Dr<lb/>
				1817<lb/>
				feby 17th for pair of blak and white Silk Corsets  —  —  £ 3.0 -<lb/>
				august 9 Miss Leith for pair of Long Dimity Corsets —  —  —  1.18 -<lb/>
				16 Lady Leith for pair of White Silk Corsets  —  —  3.0 -<lb/>
				£ 7.18.
				</figTranscr>
				<head>4. Bill from Martin, staymaker,</head>
				<figDesc>17 South Molton Street, to Lady Leith (City of Westminster Archives Centre, Tilbury Papers, entry
number Til/947).
				<q>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>Lady Leith</cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell>Dr [?]<lb/>
</cell>
							<cell></cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>1817</cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>feb<hi rend="s">y</hi></cell>
							<cell>17<hi rend="s">th</hi></cell>
							<cell>for pair of blak and white Silk Corsets</cell>
							<cell>  —  —  </cell>
							<cell>£ 3.0 -</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>august</cell>
							<cell>9</cell>
							<cell>Miss Leith for pair of Long Dimity Corsets</cell>
							<cell> —  —  —  </cell>
							<cell>1.18 -</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell>16</cell>
							<cell>Lady Leith for pair of White Silk Corsets</cell>
							<cell>  —  —  </cell>
							<cell>3.0 -</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell></cell>
							<cell>£ 7.18.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</q>
              I wish to thank Rory Lalwan for his assistance in tracing this document. It is clear from the
bill that Martin had originally made it out for the first two corsets and then erased the original total,
added the third purchase, and revised the total. On the verso “Lady Leith” is written in the same hand.
Dimity, of which Miss Leith’s pair of long corsets was made, is a cotton fabric woven with stripes or
checks. Ian Chipperfield, an authority on eighteenth- and nineteenth-century staymaking (see the 
<hi rend="i">Staymaker</hi> web site &lt;http://www.thestaymaker.co.uk&gt;), has not hitherto encountered
references to black corsets in this period. He observes that the color is impractical as the undergarment
would show through the outer garments (e-mail, 20 July 2005). However, the color may be connected with Lady
Leith’s mourning for her husband and the burial of his remains at Westminster Abbey, which took place a few
weeks after this purchase. A pair of corsets (as referred to in the bill) means in fact one corset, which was
manufactured in two parts, later worn laced together.</figDesc>
			</figure>
            <pb id="p43-91" n="91"/>
          interest. In her definitive history of the corset, Norah Waugh states that
		<q>at the beginning of the nineteenth century the Grecian figure—the natural figure (high rounded
breasts, long well-rounded limbs)—was the ideal every woman hoped to attain. Her soft, light muslin dress
clung to her body and showed every contour, so all superfluous undergarments which might spoil the silhouette
were discarded—among them the boned stay. In France, where the social order had been completely overturned,
with consequent loosening of morals and deportment, this fashion was more followed than in England. ... It is
significant that in France the old name <hi rend="i">corps</hi> had quite disappeared, and from now on any
tight-fitting body garment is known as a “corset”, a fashion that was copied in England though the old
form “stays” was also retained.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">49</ref></q>
          In April 1816 Ackermann’s <hi rend="i">Repository of Arts</hi> noted:
		<q>We have been favoured with the sight of a new stay, the “corset des Grâces”, which we
understand has received very distinguished patronage. This stay possesses the double advantage of improving
the shape, and conducing towards the preservation of the health; no compression, no pushing the form out of
its natural proportions; it allows the most perfect ease and freedom to every motion, while, at the same time,
it gives that support to the frame, which delicate women find absolutely necessary.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">50</ref></q>
          Such evidence suggests that, as the bottom had fallen out of the market for staymakers in the French
capital, Martin may have migrated to London, where stays remained fashionable. This may have occurred c. 1800
(perhaps between the Treaty of Amiens of 25 March 1802 and Britain’s declaration of war on 18 May 1803),
certainly by March 1805, the date of Martin’s first appearance in the rate books for no. 17.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">51</ref> In addition, the bill suggests that
Martin’s surname, and therefore the name of his business, was pronounced in the French rather than the
English manner.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">52</ref> Finally, the new
discovery helpfully supplements Linnell’s claim that the reason for the Blakes’ leaving South Molton
Street was “his Landlord leaving off business &amp; retiring to France.” It appears that by the spring of
1821 Martin was returning as well as retiring to France and very probably to Paris, his former residence, if
not the city of his birth. </p>
          <note id="n47">47. The rectangular platemark measures approximately 47 mm. x 65 mm.</note>
          <note id="n48">48. The nearest surviving equivalents are Blake’s engraving of an advertisement for
Moore &amp; Co. (1797) and the bookplate/calling card for George Cumberland (1827), far more ambitious
projects with scope for Blake to exercise his own ideas (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 819, 823). Therefore, it
is likely that the stamp was engraved and printed for Martin by a professional writing engraver, such as
William Staden Blake. However, the ink on the edge of the platemark on the top right and lower right corners
might suggest that this was not the work of a general plate printer. No watermark is visible.</note>
          <note id="n49">49. Waugh 75.</note>
          <note id="n50">50. Quoted in Waugh 100.</note>
          <note id="n51">51. According to Chipperfield, before the mid-1790s and after 1815 some London
staymakers claimed to be French to attract a high-quality clientele (e-mail, 13 July 2005). However, of the
numerous staymakers listed in London directories, few have French surnames. Two exceptions are Mes Dames
Harman, 350 Oxford Street, and H. De Cleve, 5 Holywell Street, Strand (<hi rend="i">Pigot &amp; Co.’s
Directory</hi> 1823-24 [1823] 222). I have found no evidence of another staymaker with a recognizably French
surname trading in Mayfair c. 1790-1830.</note>
          <note id="n52">52. However, evidence from Martin’s marriage record suggests that he anglicized his
name (see below). If this was the case, his surname may have been pronounced in the English manner.</note>
          <p>At his shop Martin probably employed several assistants to attend customers in the ground-floor
front room or to bone and sew stays and corsets in the back room. The basement may also have served as another
workshop as well as store-room. Martin may have spent some time away from no. 17, calling upon genteel
customers such as Lady Leith for a last fitting before their stays were finished at the shop. His business was
just one of the numerous “brilliant and fashionable” shops in South Molton Street and the surrounding
Mayfair streets selling luxury items.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">53</ref> These included John Bruckner, ladies’ shoemaker, at no. 52, Heron and Jones, tailors,
at no. 58, I. and J. Hunt, hatters, at no. 22, William Keith’s china and Staffordshire warehouse at no. 44,
James Lay, hatter, hosier, and glover, at no. 22, and Francis Perico, surgeon, apothecary, and midwife, at no.
29.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">54</ref> Such businesses substantiated
the contemporary claim that in London, “the first city of the world,” “shops are unrivalled for
splendour, as well as for their immense stocks of rich and elegant articles.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">55</ref></p>
          <note id="n53">53. See <hi rend="i">Pigot &amp; Co.’s Directory</hi> 1823-24 (1823) 15.</note>
          <note id="n54">54. See Whitehead, “New Discoveries” 2: 326-30.</note>
          <note id="n55">55. <hi rend="i">Pigot &amp; Co.’s Directory</hi> 1823-24 (1823) 15. In 1818 the
<hi rend="i">Ladies’ Monthly Museum</hi> featured two fashionable dresses, a ball dress and a walking dress,
designed by a Miss Macdonald of no. 50, which was opposite no. 17 (<hi rend="i">Ladies’ Monthly Museum</hi>
Mar. 1818: 169-70). Perhaps Miss Macdonald was a relative of Ann and Christian MacDonald, wife and
stepdaughter of John Lytrott.</note>
          <p>Martin’s conducting a staymaker’s business may also be pertinent in the light of two examples
of Blake’s minor verse from the period. Blake makes references to stays in annotations to his copy of volume
one of <hi rend="i">The Works of Sir Joshua Reynolds</hi> (1798). On pages xiv-xv of his introductory “Some
Account of the Life and Writings of Sir Joshua Reynolds,” Edmond Malone quotes Reynolds describing how, on a
visit to the Vatican, he was “disappointed and mortified at not finding [him]self enraptured with the works
of [Raphael] ....”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">56</ref> Blake responds:
		<q>I am happy I cannot say that Rafael Ever was from my Earliest Childhood hidden from Me. I saw
&amp; I Knew immediately the difference between Rafael &amp; Rubens<lb/>
          <lb/>
          Some look. to see the sweet Outlines<lb/>
          And beauteous Forms that Love does wear<lb/>
          Some look. to find out Patches. Paint.<lb/>
          Bracelets &amp; Stays &amp; Powderd Hair<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">57</ref></q>
          Here Blake appears to be criticizing Reynolds’s evident inability to distinguish between
Raphael’s and Rubens’s paintings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">58</ref> However, in the fourth discourse, Blake also refers to stays in an annotation signaling
approval of Reynolds’s criticism of the Venetian school—Titian, but more particularly Paolo
            <pb id="p43-92" n="92"/>
          Veronese and Tintoretto. On page 98 Reynolds states, “it appears, that the principal attention of
the Venetian painters, in the opinion of Michael Angelo, seemed to be engrossed by the study of colours, to
the neglect of the <hi rend="i">ideal beauty of form</hi> ...”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n59" type="note">59</ref> On the opposite page, Blake writes:
		<q>If the Venetians Outline was Right his Shadows would destroy it &amp; deform its appearance<lb/>
          <lb/>
          A Pair of Stays to mend the Shape<lb/>
          Of crooked Humpy Woman:<lb/>
          Put on O Venus! now thou art,<lb/>
          Quite a Venetian Roman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">60</ref></q></p>
          <note id="n56">56. Reynolds is alluding to Raphael’s frescoes in the Stanze, which he encountered
in 1750.</note>
          <note id="n57">57. E 637. For Blake’s unfavorable comparison of Rubens to Raphael, see E
513-14.</note>
          <note id="n58">58. Elsewhere Blake comments that Reynolds’s “Praise of Rafael is like the
Hysteric Smile of Revenge” (E 642).</note>
          <note id="n59">59. See Wark 66.</note>
          <note id="n60">60. E 651. This annotation appears to have been influenced by two earlier passages in
the fourth discourse. On page 90 Reynolds asserts that “Carlo Maratti [thought] that the disposition of
drapery was a more difficult art than even that of drawing the human figure ...,” to which Blake responds,
“I do not believe that Carlo Maratti thought so or that any body can think so. the Drapery is formed alone
by the Shape of the Naked [next word cut away in binding]” (E 650). On page 95 Reynolds writes, “Such as
suppose that the great style might happily be blended with the ornamental, that the simple, grave and
majestick dignity of Raffaelle could unite with the glow and bustle of a Paolo, or Tintoret, are totally
mistaken,” to which Blake responds, “What can be better Said. on this Subject? but Reynolds contradicts
what he says Continually He makes little Concessions, that he may take Great Advantages” (E 651).
          <p>Blake appears to agree with Reynolds’s view that trying to ally the Roman ideal form with the
Venetian school’s emphasis on costume is unsatisfactory. He plainly saw stays as an apposite image for the
manipulation of the outline of the human form. It seems clear that he dislikes both stays and Venetian art for
their immersion in and preoccupation with transient fashions rather than for any role they might have in
idealization of form. Blake’s verse satirizes what he considers the artificial, ephemeral, and therefore
inferior nature of Venetian painting, and the impossibility of uniting this style with the grand Roman
style.</p></note>
          <p>Blake’s annotations of Reynolds have been dated c. 1798-1809 by David Erdman.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">61</ref> This overlaps the period in which the Blakes
lived above Martin’s staymaker’s shop. However, there are problems with Erdman’s dating. According to
Bentley, “Blake’s annotations to Reynolds were probably written at two distinct periods, perhaps first
about 1801-2 and second in 1808-9.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">62</ref> The annotations referring to stays, written in ink at first glance, appear to date from
the second period.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">63</ref> However, those on
pages xiv and xv were first written in pencil and then overwritten in ink.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">64</ref> The underlying pencil may suggest that these annotations
were part of the first round that Bentley dates to 1801-02, several years before Blake met Martin in late
1804-early 1805. But the dating of Blake’s annotations to Reynolds remains imprecise and inconclusive. It is
therefore possibly that both references to stays date from 1805 on. Whether these references date from
Blake’s period of residence with Martin or not, the perpetual presence of stays, instruments which for Blake
hid and distorted the naked female form, may have served as a regular reminder of the “seducing qualities”
and “Vulgar Stupidity” of the Venetian school.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="65">65</ref></p>
          <note id="n61">61. See E 886.</note>
          <note id="n62">62. Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> [hereafter <hi rend="i">BB</hi>]
692.</note>
          <note id="n63">63. See <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 693.</note>
          <note id="n64">64. Bentley indicates that pencil is overwritten in ink on p. xv 
(<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 693), but Erdman claims that the ditty on that page is in ink only (E 637).</note>
          <note id="n65">65. Wark 67; E 651. Women in stays or corsets feature in Blake’s early engravings
of designs by Thomas Stothard and others in the 1780s and early 1790s (see Essick, pls. 30, 32-34, 38, 39, 41,
43, 45, 54, 56, 103). However, in Blake’s illuminated works, female figures appear naked (see 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> pl. 3), in transparent and form-revealing clothes 
(<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> pl. 2), or in fashionable free-flowing empire gowns 
(<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> pls. 2 and 4). As Blake wrote in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>, “The nakedness of woman is the work of God” (E 36).</note>
          <p><hi rend="b">“A Frenchwoman”</hi></p>
          <p>Writing in 1927 of the Blakes’ residence in South Molton Street, Margaret Irwin wondered,
“what did the landlady at Number 17 think of ‘them first floors’?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">66</ref> Commenting upon Linnell’s account of the “Landlord
leaving off business &amp; retiring to France,” Bentley observes that
		<q>it is tempting to speculate whether Martin retired to France because his wife was French, and, if
she was, whether Blake was referring to her when he said of his fresco of “The Last Judgment”: “I
spoiled that—made it darker; it was much finer, but a Frenchwoman here (a fellow lodger) didn’t like
it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">67</ref></q>
          Blake’s statement derives from Gilchrist, who commented, “ill-advised, indeed, to alter 
<hi rend="i">colour</hi> at a fellow lodger and Frenchwoman’s suggestion!”</p>
          <note id="n66">66. Irwin 15.</note>
          <note id="n67">67. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 750, quoting Gilchrist 350. In a footnote Bentley argues
that the Frenchwoman’s advice was given before Apr. 1815, when George Cumberland, Jr., described 
<hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi> as “nearly as black as your Hat.”</note>
          <p>The “Frenchwoman” may very well have been Martin’s wife. A Mark Anthony Martin, widower,
married Eleanor Larché, spinster, on Tuesday 20 May 1806 at St. Mary’s Church, St. Marylebone Road (illus.
5).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">68</ref> The church, just two blocks
north of Oxford Street, would have been, along with the parish church of St. George, Hanover Square, the
nearest place of worship in which the inhabitants of South Molton Street could marry. The name Mark Martin
appears rarely in contemporary directories or in the marriage registers of the two local churches. This point,
coupled with the fact that this Mark Martin married a woman with a French surname, suggests that he and the
Blakes’ landlord are one and the same.</p>
          <note id="n68">68. St. Mary’s Church, parish of St. Marylebone, marriage register, vol. 131 (City
of London, London Metropolitan Archives, and COWAC).</note>
          <p>Although Martin was an extremely common name in France during the late eighteenth and early
nineteenth centuries, Larché was not. The name appears in genealogical records almost exclusively in the
small town of Gignac, in the Hérault Valley in Languedoc. However, despite a search of the 
<hi rend="i">International Genealogical Index</hi> and church records held at the mairie in Gignac, the early life
and subsequent history of
            <pb id="p43-93" n="93"/>
          <figure n="marriage-martin-larche.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="194">
			<figTranscr>No. 31 } Mark Anthony Martin of this Parish<lb/>
			Widower and Eleanor Larchey, of the same Parish<lb/>
			Spinster were<lb/>
			Married in this Church by Banns<lb/>
			this Twentieth Day of May in the Year One Thousand Eight Hundred<lb/>
			and Six By me Benjn. Lawrence Curate<lb/>
			This Marriage was solemnized between Us {<lb/>
			Mark Anthny Martin<lb/>
			Eleanor Larche<lb/>
			In the Presence of {<lb/>
			Peter Larché<lb/>
			William Woodward</figTranscr>
            <head>5. Entry for the marriage of Mark Martin and Eleanor Larché,</head>
			<figDesc>St. Mary’s Church, parish of St. Marylebone, marriage register, vol. 131 (courtesy of the City
of London, London Metropolitan Archives, and the parish of St. Marylebone; image courtesy of the City of
Westminster Archives Centre).</figDesc>
          </figure>
            Eleanor Martin, née Larché, have yet to be recovered. William and Catherine Blake may have
attended the wedding of their landlord of over a year and participated in the celebrations. To have given her
opinion of <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi>, Eleanor Martin must have entered the Blakes’ front-room
studio, viewed the work, presumably on the wall opposite the fireplace and adjoining no. 16, the only wall
large enough to display it,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">69</ref> and
discussed it with her lodger. Eleanor’s visit and the fact that her comments prompted the revision of the
painting suggest a cordial relationship between the Blakes and the Martins as well as Blake’s apparent
respect for her opinions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">70</ref></p>
          <note id="n69">69. See Whitehead, “New Discoveries” 1: 54.</note>
          <note id="n70">70. Indeed, Eleanor may have had some artistic knowledge: it is likely that Peter
Larché, a witness at their wedding, was a nearby gilder at 22 Rathbone Place (see <hi rend="i">Holden’s
Triennial Directory</hi> 1799 [415]). Interestingly, a William Martin, historical painter, lived at no. 17 in
1831, during the last months of Mark Martin’s residence, or soon after his departure (see 
<hi rend="i">London Gazette</hi> 27 Dec. 1831: 2787, and 23 Aug. 1833: 1585); perhaps he was Martin’s son.
However, he may have been Norwich-born William Martin (1753-c. 1836), recorded as living in Marylebone in this
period (see Fiske).</note>
        <p>Although they were married according to the rites of the Church of England, still a statutory
requirement in 1806, Eleanor and her husband appear to have been born in France and may have been of Huguenot
descent. While the officiating curate, Benjamin Lawrence, anglicized her surname to Larchey on the marriage
certificate, Eleanor retained the French spelling, Larché. In contrast her husband, probably baptized Marc
Antoine Martin, seems to have anglicized his name. Among the Blakes’ neighbors there appear to have been a
number of other French people or individuals of French descent. These included Louis Claude Augarde, a
hairdresser and ratepayer at no. 3, E. Blondeel, embroiderer, at no. 52, James Mivart, haircutter and
perfumer, at no. 5, Claude Olivier, merchant, at no. 10, L. S. O. Petit, also at no. 10, who about July 1806
composed, published, and sold from his residence <hi rend="i">Observations sur les moyens de perfectionner la
tournure des jeunes demoiselles</hi> [<hi rend="i">Observations on the Means of Improving the Shape and
Carriage of Young Women</hi>],<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">71</ref>
George Parvin, coal merchant, at no. 21, Frederick Fladong, wine merchant, at no. 28, John Periot, gentleman
and hotelier, at no. 1, Robert Sabine, haircutter and perfumer, at no. 41, and George Saffery, music teacher,
at no. 63.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">72</ref> As noted above, some
years after the Blakes’ departure the staymaker Charlotte Lohay, daughter of the artisan painter Ambroise
Lohay, succeeded Martin as ratepayer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73"
type="note">73</ref></p>
          <note id="n71">71. The work was advertised in the <hi rend="i">Morning Chronicle</hi> of 2 July
1806. A copy survives in the British Library.</note>
          <note id="n72">72. See Whitehead, “New Discoveries” 2: 323-27.</note>
          <note id="n73">73. Catherine Blake, née Boucher, is likely to have been of French Huguenot descent
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 1-2), and Blake’s brother James had been apprenticed to a Huguenot weaver, Gideon
Boitoult (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 11-12). As early as 1780, Blake, along with two fellow artists, was arrested
as a suspected French spy near Chatham docks (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 58-60). Gilchrist wrote that
to Blake in the early 1790s, “the French Revolution was the herald of the millennium, of a new age of light
and reason. He courageously donned the famous symbol of liberty and equality—the <hi rend="i">bonnet
rouge</hi>—in open day, and philosophically walked the streets with the same on his head” (Gilchrist 81).
On 19 Oct. 1801, five months before the signing of the short-lived Peace of Amiens, and while residing in
Felpham, Blake had written to John Flaxman observing that Felpham was as near to Paris as to London, and
adding “I hope that France &amp; England will henceforth be as One Country and their Arts One ...” (E
718). In 1803-04, during his trial for sedition and as fears of French invasion were growing in England, Blake
and his wife were accused of voicing support for Napoleon. Private John Scofield claimed that Catherine said
“altho she was but a Woman she wo<hi rend="s">d</hi>. fight as long as she had a Drop of Blood in her—to
which the said Blake said, my Dear you wo<hi rend="s">d</hi>. not fight against France—she replied, no, I
wo<hi rend="s">d</hi>. fight for Buonaparte as long as I am able” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 160). Catherine
is also recorded as having expressed pro-French sentiments to George Cumberland, Jr., at South Molton Street:
in Apr. 1815, during the Hundred Days and six weeks before the battle of Waterloo, Catherine exclaimed, “if
this Country does go to War our K—g ought to loose his head” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 320). This remark
has been interpreted as indicative of either Catherine’s madness or of Blake’s influence over her. Perhaps
her impassioned utterance should be viewed in the context of the Blakes’ having lodged for the past decade
in the house of a couple of French descent in a neighborhood with a significance French presence. As such, her
remarks might be interpreted as a desire for peaceful coexistence between England and France. Blake advocates
peaceful coexistence with France in his annotations to Malone’s preface to Reynolds’s 
<hi rend="i">Works</hi> (E 641). A sympathetic reference to France can be found in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, a
work composed and created during Blake’s residence at no. 17 (see <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 66:15, E
218).</note>
          <pb id="p43-94" n="94"/>
          <p>Blake’s facility with languages was noted on more than one occasion. According to Gilchrist,
“Blake, who had a natural aptitude for acquiring knowledge, little cultivated in youth, was always willing
to apply himself to the vocabulary of a language, for the purpose of reading a great original author. He would
declare that he learnt French, sufficient to read it, in a few weeks.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">74</ref> Bentley observes that “we know nothing else of his French
except one use of it about 1808 in his Reynolds marginalia.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n75">75</ref> On the contents pages of Reynolds’s <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, Blake transcribes several
lines of Voltaire in French and comments upon them. The subject is Giovanni de Medici, Pope Leo X, the
principal patron of Raphael. Hitherto this unique instance of Blake’s written use of French has received
little attention.
		<q>The Foundation of Empire is Art &amp; Science  Remove them or Degrade them &amp; the Empire is No
More—Empire follows Art &amp; Not Vice Versa as Englishmen suppose<lb/>
          On peut dire que la<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">76</ref> Pape
Léon X<hi rend="s">me</hi> en encourageant les Seigneur Anglais qu’il avait vu une Lettre du Seigneur
Polus, ou de La Pole, depuis Cardinal, à ce Pape; dans laquelle, en le félicitant sur ce qu’il etendait le
progrès de Science en Europe, il l’avertissait <hi rend="i">qu’il était dangereux de rendre les hommes
trop Savans</hi>—<lb/>
          <hi rend="i">VOLTAIRE Moeurs de</hi>[<hi rend="i">s</hi>] <hi rend="i">Nation</hi>[<hi
rend="i">s</hi>], <hi rend="i">Tome</hi> 4<lb/>
          O Englishmen! why are you still of this foolish Cardinals opinion?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">77</ref></q>
          Blake is referring to <hi rend="i">Essay sur l’histoire générale, et sur les moeurs et
l’esprit des nations, depuis Charlemagne jusqu’à nos jours.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n78" type="note">78</ref> There is no evidence of Blake’s owning this work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">79</ref> Is it possible that he borrowed it from the library of his
Parisian landlord? <hi rend="i">Essay sur l’histoire générale</hi> is not written in the most
straightforward French. Blake therefore may have been grateful for the assistance of native French speakers,
as Mark and Eleanor Martin presumably were, in understanding this passage.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">80</ref> The Martins may have also assisted Blake’s “learn[ing]
French, sufficient to read it, in a few weeks.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81"
type="note">81</ref></p>
          <note id="n74">74. Gilchrist 151.</note>
          <note id="n75">75. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 400fn.</note>
          <note id="n76">76. The grammatically correct “le” is transcribed in Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> 2: 1451.</note>
          <note id="n77">77. E 636. The passage may be translated as:
		<q>You can say that Pope Leo X, by encouraging studying, gave weapons against himself. I have heard
an English gentleman say that he had seen a letter from Seigneur Polus, or Seigneur de La Pole [Reginald Pole
(1500-58), cardinal and archbishop of Canterbury], who has since been made a Cardinal, to that Pope; in which,
even as he congratulated him because he was extending the progress of science in Europe, he warned him that
<hi rend="i">it was dangerous to make men too knowledgeable</hi>.</q></note>
          <note id="n78">78. The work was translated as <hi rend="i">An Essay on Universal History, the
Manners, and Spirit of Nations, from the Reign of Charlemaign to the Age of Lewis XIV</hi> (London: J. Nourse,
1759).</note>
          <note id="n79">79. Bentley includes no reference to the work in <hi rend="i">BB</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>.</note>
          <note id="n80">80. There are parallels here with Blake’s apparent problems with Italian in
Alessandro Vellutello’s sixteenth-century edition of Dante during the creation of his illustrations to 
<hi rend="i">The Divine Comedy</hi>, as discussed in Paley 111-12.</note>
          <note id="n81">81. Living with two native speakers would certainly have facilitated his progress.
Blake’s knowledge of French may lie behind Henry Crabb Robinson’s conversation with him on 18 Feb. 1826
(approximately five years after he had parted company with the Martins) concerning his frequent “intercourse
with Voltaire”: “I asked in what langu<hi rend="s">e</hi>. Voltaire spoke[;] [Blake] gave an ingenious
answer—[“]To my Sensations it was English—It was like the touch of a musical key—He touched it
probably French, but to my ear it became English[”]<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> 
(<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 434). Blake may also have learned some French while a neighbor of Hayley’s at Felpham,
1800-03.</note>
          <p></p>
          <p>The findings discussed in this paper suggest a far more differentiated picture of life at South
Molton Street over the almost two decades of William and Catherine Blake’s residence than has been
previously realized. In earlier discussions of the inhabitants of South Molton Street, Mark Martin, “M<hi
rend="s">rs</hi> Enoch” and “a Frenchwoman,” though said to have been fellow lodgers of the Blakes, were
little more than unrelated names. We can now begin to identify these fellow inhabitants, their relationship to
one another, and the years they shared no. 17 with the Blakes. We can better imagine the relationships between
William and Catherine and a number of their neighbors and fellow inhabitants—those who peopled their
domestic universe. I hope that I have suggested how these discoveries enhance our knowledge of the Blakes
during the first two decades of the nineteenth century, a period for which records relating to them are
virtually nonexistent.</p>
          <pb id="p43-95" n="95"/>
          <p><hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi></p>
          <p></p>
          <p>Ackroyd, Peter. <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>. London: Sinclair-Stevenson, 1995.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1995.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>. 2nd ed. New Haven: Yale
University Press, 2004.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William
Blake</hi>. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2001.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">—,</corr> ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi>. 2 vols. Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1978.</p>
          <p>Campbell, R. <hi rend="i">The London Tradesman, Being a Compendious View of All the Trades,
Professions, Arts, Both Liberal and Mechanic, Now Practised in the Cities of London and Westminster</hi>.
London: T. Gardner, 1747.</p>
          <p>Chichester, H. M. “Leith, Sir James (1763-1816).” Rev. Roger T. Stearn. <hi rend="i">Oxford
Dictionary of National Biography</hi>. &lt;http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/16409&gt;.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., ed., with commentary by Harold Bloom. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and
Prose of William Blake</hi>. Newly rev. ed. New York: Anchor-Random House, 1988.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations: A Catalogue and
Study of the Plates Engraved by Blake after Designs by Other Artists</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991.</p>
          <p>Falconar, Maria, and Harriet Falconar. <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>. London: J. Johnson, 1788.</p>
          <p>Fiske, Tina. “Martin, William (b. 1753, d. in or after 1836).” <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary
of National Biography</hi>. &lt;http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/18217&gt;.</p>
          <p>George, M. Dorothy. <hi rend="i">London Life in the Eighteenth Century</hi>. Harmondsworth:
Penguin, 1966.</p>
          <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>. Ed. Ruthven Todd. Everyman’s
Library, no. 971. London: J. M. Dent &amp; Sons Ltd.; New York: E. P. Dutton &amp; Co. Inc., 1945.</p>
          <p>Irwin, Margaret. <hi rend="i">South Molton Street Then As Now, the Favoured Resort of Modish
Mayfair</hi>. London: G. A. Male &amp; Son, 1927.</p>
          <p>Keane, John. <hi rend="i">Tom Paine: A Political Life</hi>. London: Bloomsbury, 1995.</p>
          <p>King, James. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Life</hi>. London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson,
1991.</p>
          <p>Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Life and Work</hi>. London: Constable, 1978.</p>
          <p>Louth, Andrew. “Taylor, Thomas (1758-1835).” <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National
Biography</hi>. &lt;http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/27086&gt;.</p>
          <p>McCarthy, William, and Elizabeth Kraft, eds. <hi rend="i">Anna Laetitia Barbauld: Selected Poetry
and Prose</hi>. Ormskirk: Broadview Press, 2002.</p>
          <p>Miner, Paul. “William Blake’s London Residences.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York
Public Library</hi> 62.11 (Nov. 1958): 535-50.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Traveller in the Evening: The Last Works of William Blake</hi>.
Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2003.</p>
          <p>Porter, Roy. <hi rend="i">London: A Social History</hi>. London: Penguin, 2000.</p>
          <p>Ribeiro, Aileen. <hi rend="i">The Art of Dress: Fashion in England and France 1750 to 1820</hi>.
New Haven: Yale University Press, 1995.</p>
          <p>Rogers, Pat. “Johnson, Samuel (1709-1784).” <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National
Biography</hi>. &lt;http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/14918&gt;.</p>
          <p>Schwarz, L. D. “Social Class and Social Geography: The Middle Classes in London at the End of
the Eighteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth-Century Town: A Reader in English Urban History,
1688-1820</hi>. Ed. Peter Borsay. London: Longman, 1990. 315-37.</p>
          <p>Steele, Valerie. <hi rend="i">The Corset: A Cultural History</hi>. New Haven: Yale University
Press, 2001.</p>
          <p>Todd, Ruthven. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Artist.</hi> London: Studio Vista Ltd., 1971.</p>
          <p>Townend, Peter, ed. <hi rend="i">Burke’s Genealogical and Heraldic History of the Peerage,
Baronetage and Knightage</hi>. 104th ed. London: Burke’s Peerage, 1967.</p>
          <p>Wark, Robert R., ed. <hi rend="i">Sir Joshua Reynolds: Discourses on Art</hi>. New Haven: Yale
University Press, 1975.</p>
          <p>Waugh, Norah. <hi rend="i">Corsets and Crinolines</hi>. London: B. T. Batsford Ltd., 1954.</p>
          <p>Whitehead, Angus. “New Discoveries Concerning William and Catherine Blake in Nineteenth Century
London: Residences, Fellow Inhabitants, Neighbours, Friends and Milieux, 1803-1878.” PhD diss. 2 vols.
University of York, 2006.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">—.</corr> “New Information Concerning Mrs Enoch, William and Catherine
Blake’s “fellow inhabitant” at 17 South Molton Street.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> 250 (ns
52).4 (Dec. 2005): 460-63.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
