<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.3.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“And the sun dial by Blake” (Butlin #374A)</title>
		<author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2009-10</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2009-10</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2009-10"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
      <pb id="p43-105" n="105"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“And the sun dial by Blake” (Butlin #374A)</title>
          </head>
          <byline>BY <docAuthor>MORTON D. <name>PALEY</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <div3>
            <p>WILLIAM Hayley’s art collection was sold at Christie’s in a single day, 15 February
1821.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">1</ref> Hayley owned, as one would
expect, a number of drawings and sketches by his friends George Romney and John Flaxman, as well as paintings
attributed to, among others, Both, Breughel, and Quentin Matsys. Among the 140 numbered lots is one of
particular interest to readers of this journal:
			<q>Pamela ...... 106 A pastoral drawing in body colours: and the sun dial by Blake</q>
            The existence of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Sun Dial</hi> has been known since the publication of
Butlin’s great catalogue,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">2</ref> but the
identity of “Pamela” has not been established, nor the means by which Hayley acquired Pamela’s
“pastoral drawing.” These subjects can now be clarified, although Blake’s <hi rend="i">Sun Dial</hi>
remains untraced.</p>
            <p>Hayley first met Pamela, then aged fourteen, when visiting Paris with Romney (both sympathizers
with the young revolution) in 1790. There they were entertained by the celebrated writer on education, Madame
de Genlis, who was also governess and tutor to the children of the duc d’Orléans. It was given out that
Pamela, so called after Samuel Richardson’s heroine, had been born in Newfoundland, that her name had been
Nancy Sims, that she had been taken by her mother back to Hampshire after her father’s death, and then had
been brought to Paris by a British diplomat and introduced into the family of Louis-Philippe, where she was
brought up with his children under the governance of Mme. de Genlis. However, many believed that the girl, now
called Anne Caroline Stéphanie, was the daughter of Mme. de Genlis and the duke.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">3</ref> She was evidently a girl of beauty and charm, for Hayley
singled her out in the “impromptu” he wrote before he and Romney left Paris:
			<q><hi rend="i">TO MADAME DE GENLIS, AND HER COMPANIONS,</hi><lb/>
            SATURDAY, AUGUST 21, 1790.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="i">So great the favors shewn us here,<lb/>
            Which time can ne’er efface,<lb/>
            Our gratitude can scarce appear<lb/>
            Proportioned to their grace.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            In this distress sure aid I seek,<lb/>
            Dear Pamela, from you,<lb/>
            If those sweet lips will deign to speak<lb/>
            Our thanks, and our adieu!</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
type="note">4</ref></q></p>
            <p>In 1791-92 Pamela and her tutor were in England, and Romney accompanied them to the theater
many times. In January 1792 the artist began painting two portraits of Pamela. These were never finished, nor
was a portrait of Mme. de Genlis begun at the same time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91"
type="note">5</ref> Although it appears that Mme. de Genlis did not see Hayley during this visit, they were in
correspondence, and she sent him a copy of her <hi rend="i">Leçons d’une gouvernante à ses élèves, ou
Fragmens d’un journal, qui a été fait pour l’education des enfans de Monsieur d’Orléans</hi> (Paris,
1791), as Hayley tells his wife, Elizabeth, in a letter dates 19 October 1791.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92" type="note">6</ref> This book, Hayley says, “is a detail of all her minute
attention to the children,” and Pamela plays a role in it, as do the other Orléans children. “She,”
writes Hayley, “has just had the kindness to send me, with her new publication, a very pretty drawing from
the pencil of Pamela, the lovely girl whom she educates with her princely disciples.” Although we cannot be
sure that this was the “pastoral drawing,” it is Hayley’s only published mention of receiving a drawing
by Pamela, who would shortly have little time for pastoral scenes.</p>
            <note id="n87">1. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of an Interesting Assemblage of Pictures, Drawings,
Prints ... the Property of W. Hayley, Esq. Deceased ... (London, 1821). Lugt 9959. Photocopy (incomplete) in
the Frick Art Reference Library. I thank Ms. Erin Elzi, Reference Associate, for making this catalogue
available to me. Martin Butlin has kindly informed me that in the complete copy at Christie’s there is only
one other work by Blake: his engraving after Hogarth’s <hi rend="i">Beggar’s Opera</hi>, lot
46.</hi></note>
            <note id="n88">2. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New
Haven: Yale University Press, 1981) #374A, conjecturally dated 1800-03.</note>
            <note id="n89">3. This and other facts about Pamela not related to Hayley and his circle are
derived from Liam Chambers, “Fitzgerald, Pamela (1776?-1831),” <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National
Biography</hi>, Jan. 2008 &lt;http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/9580&gt;, accessed 4 May 2009. See also
Morchard Bishop, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Hayley: The Life, Works, and Friendships of William Hayley</hi>
(London: Gollancz, 1951) 138, 143, 199.</note>
            <note id="n90">4. William Hayley, <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney, Esq.</hi> (London: T.
Payne, 1809) 153.</note>
            <note id="n91">5. Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi> 169.</note>
            <note id="n92">6. <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend
and Biographer of Cowper ...</hi>, ed. John Johnson, 2 vols. (London: H. Colburn, 1823) 1: 419. 
<hi rend="i">Leçons</hi> was published in English as <hi rend="i">Lessons of a Governess to Her Pupils. Or,
Journal of the Method Adopted by Madame de Sillery-Brulart, (Formerly Countess de Genlis) in the Education of
the Children of M. d’Orleans .... Published by Herself. Translated from the French</hi>, 3 vols. (London: G.
G. J. and J. Robinson, 1792).</note>
            <p>After returning to Paris in 1792, Pamela attended a performance of Cherubini’s opera, 
<hi rend="i">Lodoïska</hi>, and was seen in a loge by Lord Edward Fitzgerald, who was struck by her beauty. The
resulting <hi rend="i">coup de foudre</hi> led to their marrying at Tournai on 27 December 1792, less than a
month later. Lady Fitzgerald then went to live with her husband in County Kildare, and became deeply involved
in his revolutionary activities. Just prior to the rising of the United Irishmen in 1798, Lord Edward, a
leader of the movement, was wounded in a gunfight with the
              <pb id="p43-106" n="106"/>
              authorities and was left to die in prison without medical attention. The crown seized the
Fitzgerald estates, and Pamela eventually returned to France, where she lived on a pension from the Orléans
family. It must have been a small one, for she died destitute in 1831.</p>
            <p>What the association between Pamela’s “pastoral drawing” and “the sun dial by Blake”
may be, or even whether there is one, is a matter for speculation. Auction catalogues are not models of
scholarship. Presumably there are two separate drawings here, arbitrarily lumped together, although it is
possible that Hayley thought that Pamela’s landscape needed a sun dial and had Blake draw one into it. The
wording of the entry for lot 106 is ambiguous at best. One additional fact is of interest, although for the
moment it will lead only to further questions. The Frick Collection library’s copy of this catalogue is
marked with buyers’ names and the prices paid. Lot 106 was bought for nine shillings by “Peacock.”
Peacock was the buyer of at least two other lots in this sale, numbers 110 and 116. Was he a dealer or a
collector? Further investigation may yet lead to the rediscovery of “the sun dial by Blake.”</p>
            <figure n="catalogue-1821.43.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="392">
              <figTranscr>( 12 )<lb/>
                Flaxman .... 100 Head of Minerva in chalk, from<lb/>
              the antique<lb/>
              ---------- 101 Three Chalk Drawings, from<lb/>
              antique Busts<lb/>
              ---------- 105 Head of Romney, 1798, <hi rend="i">sketch<lb/>
              in blake lead;</hi> and Romney Robinson,<lb/>
              the poet of 10 years; by Robinson<lb/>
              of Windermere, a pupil of<lb/>
              Romney, a high finished drawing<lb/>
              in Indian ink<lb/>
              Pamela ....... 106 A pastoral drawing in body colours:<lb/>
              and the sun dial by Blake<lb/>
              ---------- 107 Three plaster casts, one from Mr.<lb/>
              Hawkins’s famous Antique of<lb/>
              Paris and Helen: and infant Her-<lb/>
              cules and Venus<lb/>
              ---------- 108 A fruit piece, in cruels; the<lb/>
              young Samuel in oils after Sir<lb/>
              Joshua Reynolds; and smokers<lb/>
              after Heemskerk by Romney—<hi rend="i">the<lb/>
              first effort of this painter in oil<lb/>
              colours</hi><lb/>
              <lb/>
              PAINTINGS.<lb/>
              Romney...... 109 Portrait of an officer, oval; and<lb/>
              a small oval Study of a female with<lb/>
              a hat and feather by ditto<lb/>
			  <lb/>
			  211 4.6<lb/>
			  103 10.6 A. Godfrey.<lb/>
			  104 11 . do<lb/>
			  105 . 19 .<lb/>
			  106 . 9 . . Peacock.<lb/>
			  107 1 . 1 . Loddige;<lb/>
			  108 1 . .	Sewel;<lb/>
			  109 . 18 .<lb/>
			  216.13.</figTranscr>
              <head>From <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of an Interesting Assemblage of Pictures</hi> (1821);</head>
			  <figDesc>photocopy from the Frick Art Reference Library.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
