<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>43.4.conferences</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Upcoming Conferences</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2010</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2010</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">43.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2010"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_43">
    <body>
      <pb id="p43-151" n="151"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-43-4-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <div3>
            <p><hi rend="b">Conference in Oxford</hi></p>
            <p>Blake, Gender, and Sexuality in the Twenty-First Century, organized by Helen Bruder and
Tristanne Connolly, will take place 15-16 July 2010 at St. Aldate’s Church, Oxford.</p>
            <p>According to the organizers, over the many years since Irene Tayler’s classic “The Woman
Scaly” opened up feminist debate about Blake’s art, generations of critics have wrestled and struggled
with, delighted in and savored, Blake’s provocative and abundant sexual visions. Throughout the 70s, 80s,
90s, and 00s, trends, tastes, and judgments shifted and swirled, from angry critique and searching
psychoanalysis, through heavy theory and politicized interpretation, to wary appreciation and queer
celebration. Outside academia, too, Blake’s reputation as a prophet of free love and naked beauty remained a
nuanced yet perennial global presence. And yet, amazingly, there has to date never been a gathering of
critics, artists, writers, and fans solely devoted to appreciation of and keen debate about these significant
aspects of Blake’s work. Blake, Gender, and Sexuality in the Twenty-First Century aims to become that
gathering, to celebrate and build upon past knowledge as it reaches toward likely concerns of the future.</p>
            <p>For information and registration, please visit
&lt;http://www.arts.uwaterloo.ca/~tjconnol/sexy.blake&gt;.</p>
            <p><hi rend="b">... and in Toronto</hi></p>
            <p>Blake in Our Time will celebrate the future of Blake studies and the legacy of G. E. Bentley,
Jr., on 28 August 2010 at Victoria University in the University of Toronto.</p>
            <p>According to the organizers, the symposium will explore new directions and approaches to the
study of Blake using manuscript archives, online resources, forgeries and oddities, variations in Blake’s
illuminated books, and Blake’s commercial engravings, as well as studies of the major collections amassed by
private scholar-collectors. The day will feature a series of short illustrated papers and then illustrated
panel presentations in an open forum.</p>
            <p>Victoria University Library houses the Northrop Frye papers and the G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
collection of nearly 3000 works by and about Blake and his contemporaries.</p>
            <p>For information, or to make a proposal for the panel presentations (by 1 May), please contact
Karen Mulhallen (kmulhall@ryerson.ca or karenmulhallen@rogers.com).</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
