<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-44" status="new">
    <idno>44.2.whittaker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Nicholas M. Williams, ed., Palgrave Advances in William Blake Studies</title>
        <author n="Whittaker">Jason Whittaker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2010</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2010</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">44.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2010"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_44">
    <body>
      <pb id="p44-73" n="73"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEW</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Nicholas M. Williams, ed. <hi rend="i">Palgrave Advances in William Blake
Studies</hi>. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2006. xii + 283 pp. £65.00/$115.00, hardcover; £19.99/$42.00,
paperback.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Jason <name>Whittaker</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>THE Palgrave Advances series is intended to outline the boundaries of a discipline for students
and new scholars. <hi rend="i">Palgrave Advances in William Blake Studies</hi>, edited by Nicholas M. Williams
(author of the excellent <hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William Blake</hi>), offers a
fairly comprehensive view of critical approaches to Blake in the early twenty-first century. In contrast to
other introductory guides, such as the 2003 <hi rend="i">Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, this
collection of essays emphasizes metacritical approaches rather than introducing Blake’s life and work, and
is arranged into two main sections dealing with textual and cultural approaches.</p>          <p>Williams’s
introduction reviews the critical reception of Blake in the century following his death, noting how the
relative lack of contemporary attention contrasts remarkably with the widespread appreciation and enthusiasm
that flourished from the late nineteenth century onwards. The summary of nineteenth-century reception,
providing a generous critical appraisal of Gilchrist and Swinburne in particular, while noting the
significance of Yeats and Ellis in systematizing Blake (important for him to be taken “seriously” as a
thinker in the early twentieth century, for all that it distorted his views), covers familiar ground very
ably. With the exception of Colin Trodd’s forthcoming book on Blake and Victorian art (to be published in
2011 as <hi rend="i">Visions of Blake: William Blake in the Art World 1830-1930</hi>), the responses to Blake
in the Victorian literary sphere were largely mapped out by Deborah Dorfman’s <hi rend="i">Blake in the
Nineteenth Century</hi> (1969) and G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Critical
Heritage</hi> (1975). Yet it was during the twentieth century that the appreciation of Blake exploded, and
this is where Williams’s summary is less effective: to be fair, the limits of an introductory essay restrict
what he is able to write, and it is perfectly reasonable for him to concentrate on the period of 1900 to 1954
as that time when the foundations of subsequent Blake scholarship were laid. Although his contrast of Blakean
systematizers and historicists is perhaps a little too neat, there is some truth in this categorization.</p>
          <p>The first chapter of the section devoted to textual approaches, John H. Jones’s “Blake’s
Production Methods,” is one of the better introductions to this subject for the general reader that I have
encountered. Although it is not as expert as Joseph Viscomi’s account in the <hi rend="i">Cambridge
Companion</hi> in terms of describing how Blake worked to produce his copperplates, it does offer a succinct
account of reproduction innovations that were taking place during the late eighteenth century, such as
aquatint and mezzotint. Jones also provides a careful outline of some of the recent scholarly controversies
surrounding those production methods, particularly those between Phillips and Essick/Viscomi over whether
Blake used a one- or two-pull process; after considering the available evidence presented by these scholars,
as well as historical precedents, he settles in favor of Essick and Viscomi. One fault with the Palgrave
collection is that after this excellent chapter, the attention paid to the material culture of Blake’s work
is rather brief, although the following chapter by Peter Otto, “Blake’s Composite Art” (Hagstrum’s
notable phrase, popularized by Mitchell), goes some way to returning focus to that material culture which has
been so important in much recent scholarly work within Blake studies. The account of the debate among
Hagstrum, Mitchell, and De Luca is, again, useful and particularly interesting in terms of some of the
slightly more recent interventions (for example, Mitchell’s ideas around “chaosthetics”),<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">1</ref> although a degree of tension emerges when Otto
moves from this summary to his own reading of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion.</hi> By concentrating
on how this particular tract offers a critique of Newton’s and Locke’s empiricism, Otto provides a
sophisticated example of reading Blake’s work, and yet I found myself frustrated by this focus on Blake’s
early, experimental, and minor text. The vigor with which Otto turns to plate 62 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which depicts a giant head and feet framing a strangely corporeal slab of text, makes
me wish that he had chosen from Blake’s varied corpus of illuminated printing a few more vivid examples that
could more clearly demonstrate
            dramatic visionary forms as well as composite art.</p>
          <note id="n72">1. W J. T. Mitchell, “Chaosthetics: Blake’s Sense of Form,” 
<hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 58.3-4 (1995): 441-58.</note>
          <p>Textual approaches continue with Angela Esterhammer on “Blake and Language” and Nelson Hilton
on Blake’s textuality. Each is a masterly summary, with Esterhammer offering an account that provides
considerable insight into theoretical linguistic speculations that have been inspired by Blake’s poetry,
notably in the work of Essick and De Luca (who also features strongly in Hilton’s essay and has a not
inconsiderable role to play throughout the whole collection). Although their approaches and aims are
different, it is tempting to compare these two essays with Susan Wolfson’s on Blake’s poetic language and
form in the <hi rend="i">Cambridge Companion</hi>. Esterhammer concentrates in considerably more detail on
critical responses
            to Blake, while Hilton pays more attention to the texture of Blake’s words as the product of
illuminated printing, emphasizing that material condition of the words insofar as it can transform the
presentation and meaning of Blake’s books. However, while both essays, particularly when taken together, are
a much stronger approach to Blake’s language than that provided by Wolfson’s close readings, the inclusion
of both of
          <pb id="p44-74" n="74"/>
            them does point to probably the most serious flaw in <hi rend="i">William Blake Studies</hi> as a
whole: Blake the poet, the writer, and, to a lesser extent, the printmaker of illuminated books is much
stronger in the collection than Blake the artist, the painter, the engraver. At least one chapter dedicated to
Blake’s visual arts along the lines, for example, of Martin Myrone’s accessible and informative study of
Blake’s art, <hi rend="i">The Blake Book</hi> (2007), would have greatly improved the collection.</p>
          <p>By contrast, the second part of <hi rend="i">William Blake Studies</hi>, dealing with cultural
approaches, is comprehensive in its judicious selection of topics, with chapters by Helen Bruder, David
Punter, Saree Makdisi, and Mark Lussier on subjects ranging from Blake and gender studies to the appropriation
of Blake as a metaphor for contemporary scientific ideas. In some respects, the most important chapter is that
by Stephen Prickett and Christopher Strathman on “Blake and the Bible”—important because Blake’s
relationship to biblical motifs and religious ideas, so evident within his art and writing, is often neglected
by Blake critics. Prickett and Strathman obviously do not deal with the considerable amount of material that
has come to the fore very recently with regard to the possible relations of Blake with Moravian ideas.
Nonetheless, this chapter offers an extremely good starting point for considerations of some of Blake’s
readings of Milton, as well as the Deist controversy surrounding Paine’s publication of <hi rend="i">The Age
of Reason</hi> in the 1790s. The discussion of Blake’s rejection of both Paine’s Deism and Bishop
Watson’s naturalism in favor of the new biblical criticism that was beginning to emerge in Germany in
particular, and which may have been available to Blake via writers such as Alexander Geddes, is finely
nuanced.</p>
          <p>Although it does not follow “Blake and the Bible,” Andrew Lincoln’s chapter on “Blake and
the History of Radicalism” is in many respects a useful companion piece to the Prickett-Strathman essay. As
well as considering the appreciation of Blake’s radical politics by critics from Jacob Bronowski and Mark
Schorer to David Worrall, Jon Mee, and Makdisi via, of course, the magisterial work of David Erdman, Lincoln
pays considerable attention to the radical religious dissenting and antinomian traditions in which such
politics frequently operated 
            <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
            during the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. Lincoln’s chapter and that which
follows, Makdisi on “Blake and the Communist Tradition,” obviously strongly complement each other. As with
the essays by Hilton and Esterhammer, there is inevitably some overlap, although Makdisi concentrates on some
of the wider political contexts for Blake studies, notably Marxist and post-Marxist thinkers. Neither Lincoln
nor Makdisi considers alternative traditions of later communist thinking that, with their origins in Diggers
and Ranters and inspired by later revolutionaries such as Kropotkin, espoused a view of anti-authoritarian
communism that often appears closer to Blake than Marxism does. Indeed, many of those figures, such as William
Morris and Herbert Read, made explicit their appreciation of Blake in a way that simply does not apply to
Marx, for whom Blake would have surely appeared suspiciously idealistic.</p>
          <p>Of the remaining chapters, Bruder’s on “Blake and Gender Studies” and Punter’s on
“Blake and Psychology” follow on from each other, with Bruder’s being the much wider ranging and more
assured of the two. Part of this stems
            from the fact that Blake and gender has been a much more
            active topic since the late nineties than those psychological readings, particularly Jungian,
which informed a glut of texts from the sixties to the eighties. (Interestingly, R. D. Laing, one of the only
major thinkers to work in the psychiatric field who specifically refers to Blake, is omitted from Blake
studies almost certainly because of the many flaws of his anti-psychiatry, yet this is explicitly to neglect a
trend in twentieth-century psychology where Blake, for better or for worse, appears to have had a significant
influence.) Punter’s contribution, with the exception of some discussion of Ronald Britton, reads a little
like a historical dead end in terms of Blake studies, and if there is to be any future in this field it
probably lies with the schizoanalytic studies of Deleuze and Guattari. By contrast, it was only toward the end
of the twentieth century that gender studies, particularly when extended to encompass queer theory and studies
of masculinity, began to play a more pronounced role in the analysis of Blake, making Bruder’s chapter a
particularly vivid read.</p>
          <pb id="p44-75" n="75"/>
          <p>Two other contributions, Lussier on “Blake and Science Studies” and Edward Larrissy on
“Blake and Postmodernism,” share a few conceptual boundaries, particularly with regard to Lussier’s
discussion of Blake’s role within contemporary physics. Lussier’s carefully argued essay, which rightly
emphasizes the important contributions of Donald Ault, leads the reader through a sophisticated reading of
Blake’s critique of the mechanistic materialism of his day to the ways in which his visionary poetics,
particularly in “Auguries of Innocence,” is “capable of imaging for lay person and scientist alike the
quirkiness resident in relativity and quantum” (206-07). Larrissy’s chapter, which concludes the volume,
draws upon some of the material dealt with at much greater length in his <hi rend="i">Blake and Modern
Literature</hi> (2006). As such, in a necessarily brief form, it provides some insight into the next stage of
reception that is implied in Williams’s introduction to the collection, blurring the boundaries of responses
to Blake’s works to consider creative and artistic as well as critical and scholarly reactions. This final
chapter is considerably different from many that precede it in that significant activity in reception studies
of this kind has, with one or two exceptions such as work on Blake in the Victorian period, only really begun
in the past decade.</p>
          <p>This collection provides a fresh perspective by concentrating on the critical discourse that has
built up within Blake studies over the past four to five decades in particular. The primary aim of 
<hi rend="i">Palgrave Advances in William Blake Studies</hi> is, of course, to summarize and synthesize
contemporary scholarly work, but it does not refrain from making suggestions for further development, for
example a return to studying the relations between Blake and science, or further examination of posthumous
reception. Those new (or relatively new) to Blake studies will be provided with a good grounding in the
scholarly field. Inevitably, those with a stronger sense of that scholarship will find a number of criticisms
to make, of which two are in my opinion most important. The lesser is that perhaps a little more attention
could have been paid to the effect of not only Blake’s production techniques but also the impact of
subsequent reproductive technologies, notably the <hi rend="i">Blake Archive</hi>, on the reception and
understanding of what is a unique corpus of composite art. This leads to the second, much more substantial
criticism, which is that Blake the artist is almost entirely absent from this collection, <hi rend="i">William
Blake Studies</hi> being much more concerned with Blake the poet, writer, and printer of illuminated
texts.</p>
          </div2>
      </div1>
	  </body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>