<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-44" status="new">
    <idno>44.2.miner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Design of Nebuchadnezzar</title>
        <author n="Miner">Paul Miner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2010</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2010</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">44.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2010"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_44">
    <body>
	<pb id="p44-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-2-0008">
        <figure n="mhh.d.p24" id="mhh.d.illbk.24" work-copy="mhh.d" rend="db" width="688" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>24<lb/>
	-pulse. not from rules.<lb/>
	When he had so spoken: I beheld the Angel who<lb/>
	stretched out his arms embracing the flame of fire<lb/>
	&amp; he was consumed and arose as Elijah.<lb/>
	Note. This Angel, who is now become a Devil, is<lb/>
	my particular friend: we often read the Bible together<lb/>
	in its infernal or diabolical sense which<lb/>
	the world shall have if they behave well.<lb/>
	I have also; The Bible of Hell: which the world<lb/>
	shall have whether they will or no.<lb/>
	One Law for the Lion &amp; Ox is Oppression</figTranscr>
          <figDesc>1. Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, copy D (1795), pl. 24 (Library
of Congress). Image courtesy of the <hi rend="i">William Blake Archive</hi>.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Design of Nebuchadnezzar</title>
          </head>
          <byline>BY <docAuthor>PAUL <name>MINER</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>ONE of William Blake’s most enigmatic designs relates to his figure of Nebuchadnezzar in plate
24 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, c. 1790 (illus. 1). Although several
            graphic sources may have influenced Blake’s conception of Nebuchadnezzar,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">1</ref> a suggestion of more than 130 years ago,
          <pb id="p44-76" n="76"/>
            now tracked to its origins, crucially adds to such a corpus of speculation.</p>
          <note id="n73">1. Martin Butlin calls attention to Albrecht Dürer’s engraving of “The Penance
of St. John Chrysostomus” in <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New
Haven: Yale University Press, 1981) #301, pl. 393. Anthony Blunt in “Blake’s Pictorial Imagination,” 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</hi> 6 (1943): illus. 60b, points to a werewolf
woodcut by Lucas Cranach. Additionally, Kenneth Clark, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Rebellion: Romantic versus
Classic Art</hi> (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1973) 168, observes that “there can be no reasonable doubt
that it derives from a German engraving, probably a wood-cut illustration of a werewolf by Cranach, although
there is some evidence of an earlier prototype” (also quoted in Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
Viscomi, eds., <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Early Illuminated Books</hi> [London: Tate Gallery/Blake Trust,
1993] 139).</note>
          <p>Anthony Blunt in “Blake’s Pictorial Imagination,” assessing details of Blake’s graphic
derivations, makes reference to S. Foster Damon’s <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and
Symbols</hi>, in which Damon mentions Frederick York Powell’s comments in the <hi rend="i">Academy</hi> (16
January 1875).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">2</ref> Powell, a scholar at
Christ Church, Oxford,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">3</ref> categorically
asserts that the “figure of Nebuchadnezzar in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> is without
doubt derived from Plate 146 [i.e., 148, see note 10, below] of <hi rend="i">The Bible Commentary</hi>
(Richard Blome, 1703).”</p>
          <note id="n74">2. Blunt, “Blake’s Pictorial Imagination” 203n6; Damon, <hi rend="i">William
Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1924) 328; Powell, “Blake’s Etchings,”
<hi rend="i">Academy</hi> 7 (16 Jan. 1875): 66.</note>
          <note id="n75">3. Powell (1850-1904) became Regius Professor of Modern History in 1894. An
enthusiast of French poetry as well as a connoisseur of Japanese art, he was a stimulating teacher and
sufficiently prominent to be featured in a caricature that appeared in <hi rend="i">Vanity Fair</hi> for 21
Mar. 1895.</note>
          <p>Damon, however, adds that he was “unable to see this volume” and, curiously, almost two
decades later, Blunt was “unable to trace a copy.” The difficulty in locating the work was occasioned by
Powell’s casual bibliographical reference, for in point of fact he referred to the voluminously illustrated
English edition (9″ × 7¼″) of Nicolas Fontaine’s <hi rend="i">The History of the Old and New
Testament</hi> (1703), which was published by Blome, one of the most active publishers in post-Restoration
London. Powell, as Damon notes, further declares that the illustration of Nebuchadnezzar “was probably drawn
by G. Freeman and engraved by some Dutch or Flemish engraver, as is the case with most of the plates in the
same volume.” Blome’s 1703 edition of Fontaine includes engravings by Michael van de Gucht, Frederick
Hendrick van Hove, Johannes Kip, and Peter Paul Bouche.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">4</ref></p>
          <note id="n76">4. I am indebted to Eric White of Southern Methodist University’s Perkins School of
Theology, Special Collections Department (Bridwell Library), for his extensive assistance in supplying digital
photographs of the 1703 and 1705 editions of Fontaine (the library also possesses a copy of Blome’s 1691
edition) and for answering numerous inquiries concerning the volumes in question. I also wish to thank Mary
Nelson, library assistant for the Special Collections Department at Wichita State University, for her
assistance in providing information on the 1691 edition. I owe a further debt of gratitude to Debra Madera,
Special Collections reference assistant, Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, for clarifying many details
concerning the original French edition as well as the 1703 English edition.</note>
          <p>Significantly, the frontispiece of the 1703 edition in the collection of Pitts Theology Library,
Emory University, illustrates an allegorical vignette of events in the Bible by “G Freman,” engraved by
“J. Kip.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">5</ref> Johannes Kip
(1653-1722) was
            <figure n="FontaineHistoryOldNewTestament.44.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="658">
            <figDesc>2. [Nicolas Fontaine], <hi rend="i">The History of the Old and New Testament</hi> (1703),
pl. 148. 6 ⅞″ × 4 ⅛″. Reproduced by permission of Bridwell Library Special Collections, Perkins
School of Theology, Southern Methodist University.</figDesc>
          </figure>
            a Dutch engraver who lived in London. “G. Freman” (sometimes “Freeman”) was a recognized
artist of the period, and a “Mr. Freeman” is mentioned on the title page of Blome’s 1691
edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">6</ref> The title page of the 1691
edition records that the volume was “Translated from the works of ... le Sieur de Royaumont,” a pseudonym
of Nicolas Fontaine, a French scholar who composed his biblical commentary while he was confined in the
Bastille for unorthodox religious sympathies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79"
type="note">7</ref>
          <pb id="p44-77" n="77"/>
            Fontaine’s work became one of the important influences relative to the Protestant Reformation in
France.</p>
          <note id="n77">5. Freman’s vignette in the 1703 edition in Pitts Theology Library in part portrays
two horizontally positioned angels kissing among clouds in the mid-heavens, distantly reminiscent of Blake’s
nude kissing figures among clouds on the title page of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>.</note>
          <note id="n78">6. The English version of the New Testament appeared in 1688, followed by the Old
Testament in 1690. The combined English edition appeared in 1691.</note>
          <note id="n79">7. Fontaine’s volume, <hi rend="i">L’histoire du Vieux et du Nouveau
Testament</hi>, was first published in French in 1670, with hundreds of illustrations (prints slightly smaller
than the later English editions). The volume became popular throughout Europe.</note>
          <p>The rare 1691 volume, as preserved in the Special Collections Department of Wichita State
University, was published in “<hi rend="i">LONDON</hi>” and “Printed for and sold by 
<hi rend="i">Richard Blome</hi>” (emphasis per title page), and the contemporary binder’s spine title for this
volume was “Blame’s Hist. of the Bible” (cf. Powell’s reference to “<hi rend="i">The Bible
Commentary</hi>”). Blome was preeminently associated with the initial English translation of Fontaine’s
work, and he and his copublishers were instrumental in popularizing the translation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">8</ref> The 1691 English edition was copiously illustrated (424 pages
of text, with 236 “sculptures” [engravings] on 216 leaves), as were the 1703 and 1705 editions (though
with minor variations in the number of plates). Thus, Blake could have seen the figure of Nebuchadnezzar in
the 1691, 1703, or 1705 edition (as well as in other intervening—or later—editions).</p>
          <note id="n80">8. Blome early on became the signal publisher of Fontaine’s English editions. The
1703 volume is identified as the third edition, “Printed for S. and J. Sprint, C. Brome [R. Blome?], J
Nicholson, B. Tooke, T Leigh and D. Midwinter.” There are also other editions that record the same
publishing constellation. A photographic facsimile (which I have not seen) of the 1701 folio edition (16″ ×
11″), printed for Blome, Sprint, Nicolson, and Pero, has recently been published (2008). The 1701 edition is
described as a second edition, enlarged and corrected. Many editions, some abbreviated, by various publishers,
appeared in the decades that followed.</note>
          <p>King Nebuchadnezzar, his “mind hardened in pride” (Daniel 5.20), was forced into the
wilderness, where like “beasts of the field” he ate “grass as oxen” while his “hairs” were
transformed into “eagles’ <hi rend="i">feathers</hi>” and his “nails” formed into “birds’ 
<hi rend="i">claws</hi>” (Daniel 4.32-33).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81"
type="note">9</ref> Prideful Nebuchadnezzar’s sanity was restored after seven years, and he became a more
tractable ruler. In Blame’s 1703 edition, plate 148 (a number at the top of the plate—an integral part of
the engraving, as also in the 1691 edition)<ref target="n82">10</ref> illustrates an uncrowned,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">11</ref> long-bearded and nude (i.e., featherless)<ref
target="n84">12</ref> Nebuchadnezzar, crawling (left to right) in a vast wilderness, his face looking outward,
with crossed tree trunks in front of a mound in the immediate background (illus. 2; no artist’s or
engraver’s name appears on the 1703 plate, nor in fact in any of the editions under discussion).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">13</ref>
            <figure n="bb122.1.46.ms" rend="file" width="793" height="1000">
            <figDesc>3. Blake, Notebook p. 44. Sketch c. 3 ½″ × 3 ¼″. © British Library Board. Add. MS
49460.</figDesc>
          </figure>
            In Blake’s tightly focused original pencil sketch in his Notebook (p. 44), an agonized nude
Nebuchadnezzar with streaming mustache and long beard, his face directed to the viewer, crawls from left to
right, while pronounced crossed tree trunks are indicated in the immediate background (illus. 3).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">14</ref> Blake’s Nebuchadnezzar on plate 24 of 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, however,
          <pb id="p44-78" n="78"/>
            proceeds from right to left (perhaps because the Notebook sketch was reversed in the etching
process).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">15</ref></p>
          <note id="n81">9. Italics in the King James version signify editorial clarifications of meaning or
context.</note>
          <note id="n82">10. Powell, in his note in the <hi rend="i">Academy</hi>, erroneously identifies the
plate in the 1703 edition as “146,” due to faulty transcription, a bad memory, or an error in
printing.</note>
          <note id="n83">11. Blake added a crown to Nebuchadnezzar’s head in pl. 24 of <hi rend="i">The
Marriage</hi> as a form of emblematic identification, for no reference is made to this biblical ruler in 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>.</note>
          <note id="n84">12. The original French edition of 1670 portrays Nebuchadnezzar with body hair, but
no feathers per se. Although the image of Nebuchadnezzar in the wilderness in this French edition (with
crossed tree trunks) influenced the plate that appeared in the Blome publications, in the English editions
Nebuchadnezzar is given central prominence, while in the French volume he is consigned to the lower left
portion of the plate, face down, eating grass, proceeding from right to left.</note>
          <note id="n85">13. Though there is no specific mention of Nebuchadnezzar on pl. 148 of the 1703
edition, the heading on the preceding page declares: “<hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi> turned into a Beast.
I Nebuchadnezzar <hi rend="i">the</hi> King, <hi rend="i">by a just Punishment from GOD for his</hi> / Pride
<hi rend="i">and</hi> Arrogance, <hi rend="i">is changed into a</hi> Beast” (phrasing also used in the 1691
edition). The blank space at the bottom of the plate indicates that it was unsponsored (most of the plates in
the 1703 edition were dedicated by individuals, including several by Blome). Nebuchadnezzar was not a
particularly popular subject among painters and illustrators of the Bible.</note>
          <note id="n86">14. A smaller emblematic version of Nebuchadnezzar on p. 48 (2″ × 1¾″),
probably executed after the larger figure on p. 44, is “crowned with leaves” (see <hi rend="i">The
Notebook of William Blake: A Photographic and Typographic Facsimile</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman with the
assistance of Donald K. Moore, rev. ed. [(New York): Readex Books, 1977], illus. N48). In this smaller sketch
a nude Nebuchadnezzar, crawling left to right, appears with massive crossed tree trunks in the background. Two
copies of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> in the <hi rend="i">William Blake Archive</hi> clearly indicate
crossed tree trunks in Blake’s design of Nebuchadnezzar: copy C, 1790 (Morgan Library and Museum) and copy
G, 1818 (Houghton Library). Blake’s large version of Nebuchadnezzar as a separate color print also indicates
abstract crossed tree trunks in the background. Blake emphasized the bloody veins on Nebuchadnezzar’s nude
body in his color print, iconography supported by the fact that Daniel (3.13) speaks of King
Nebuchadnezzar’s incessant “rage and fury,” pertinent to Blake’s allegory wherein wrath generates
nervous tissue.</note>
          <note id="n87">15. In the 1705 folio edition of Fontaine (Bridwell Library, 18″ × 12″), the
plate of Nebuchadnezzar was reengraved, hence reversing the perspective of the 1703 print. The 1705 engraving
(13″ × 8″) is numbered “146,” though the number was added as a separate script in space provided at
the bottom of the plate, rather than at the top as in the 1703 edition. The 1705 folio engravings are larger
copies of the 1703 edition, all reengraved (some reversed, some not). The reengraved plates in the 1705
edition are slightly more sophisticated, presenting more drapery detail and the development of facial
characteristics.</note>
          <p>Considering artist-engraver Blake’s profound interest in the Bible and his predilection for
utilizing themes from other artists, Fontaine’s frequently published, profusely illustrated English editions
(as published by Blome) presumably would have been of some interest.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n88" type="note">16</ref> Thus, Frederick York Powell’s conjecture concerning Nebuchadnezzar
presents an early candidate for one of several sources that potentially influenced Blake’s pictorial
imagination.</p>
          <note id="n88">16. For a historical perspective on Nebuchadnezzar in relation to the English
political scene of the 1790s, see Miner, “Blake’s London: Times and Spaces,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 41 (summer 2002): 284-86.</note>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <figure type="ad"/>
	  </body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>