<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-44" status="new">
    <idno>44.2.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 2010</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2010</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">44.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2010"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_44">
    <front id="issue_02">
      <pb id="p44-49-50" n="49-50"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.044.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="344">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
          AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            A Rediscovered Letter from Blake to Hayley<lb/>
          VOLUME 44<lb/>
          NUMBER 2<lb/>
          FALL 2010</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-2-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="3" cols="6">
          <row>
          	<cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>CONTENTS</title>
        	  </head>
          	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="44.2.crosby">“the fiends of Commerce”: Blake’s Letter to
William Hayley, 7 August 1804</ref><lb/>
              <hi rend="i">By Mark Crosby and Robert N. Essick</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">52</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell>
          		<hi rend="b">Review</hi>
          	</cell>
          	<cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell><ref type="article" issue="44.2.whittaker">Nicholas M. Williams, ed., <hi rend="i">Palgrave
Advances in William Blake Studies</hi></ref><lb/>
          		<hi rend="i">Reviewed by Jason Whittaker</hi>
          		</cell>
          	<cell>
          		<hi rend="i">73</hi>
          	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell>
          		<hi rend="b">Minute Particular</hi>
          	</cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell>
          		<ref type="article" issue="44.2.miner">Blake’s Design of Nebuchadnezzar</ref><lb/>
          		<hi rend="i">By Paul Miner</hi>
          	</cell>
          	<cell>
          		<hi rend="i">75</hi>
          	</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Zürich</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p44-51" n="51"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>MARK CROSBY is the Leverhulme Early Career Fellow at Queen’s University, Belfast. He is currently
coediting, with Robert N. Essick, an edition of Blake’s Genesis manuscript to be published by the Huntington
Library Press in 2012.</p>
        <p>ROBERT N. ESSICK is Distinguished Professor Emeritus of English at the University of California,
Riverside. He is currently coediting, with Mark Crosby, an edition of Blake’s Genesis manuscript to be
published by the Huntington Library Press in 2012.</p>
        <p>JASON WHITTAKER is professor of English and Media Arts at University College Falmouth and the
author and coeditor of four books on Blake, including <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, <hi rend="i">Modernity and
Popular Culture</hi> (with Steve Clark, 2007) and <hi rend="i">Blake 2.0: William Blake and Twentieth-Century
Art, Music and Culture</hi> (with Steve Clark and Tristanne Connolly, forthcoming). He is also the editor of
the Blake 2.0 blog, <hi rend="i">Zoamorphosis.com</hi>.</p>
        <p>PAUL MINER has published 25 articles on William Blake and currently is working on a volume-length
study of the poet, <hi rend="i">The Bard’s Prophetic Song</hi>.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Alexander S. Gourlay</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sarah.jones@rochester.edu<lb/>
 TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Alexander S. Gourlay, Department of English, Rhode Island School of Design, 2 College Street,
Providence RI 02903-2717<lb/>
Email: agourlay@risd.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham
NG11 8NS UK<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
            <div1 id="BQ-44-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $66 for institutions, $33 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the US, Canada, and
Mexico require a $20 per volume postal surcharge for airmail delivery. Credit card payment is available. Make
checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and
related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of
Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for information on issues
and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and
documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to
either of the editors. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope.
For electronic submissions, you may send a disk, or send your article as an attachment to an email message;
please number the pages of electronic submissions.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x.<lb/>
        <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s
International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English
Language and Literature, Humanities International Complete, Arts and Humanities Citation Index, Current
Contents, Scopus, and the Bibliography of the History of Art.</p>
        <p>© 2010 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>Cover: Blake, autograph letter signed to William Hayley, 7 August 1804, page 1. Essick
collection.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
	</text>
</TEI.2>