<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-44" status="new">
    <idno>44.3.cardinale</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">A Newly Discovered Blake Book: William Blake’s Copy of Thomas Taylor’s The
Mystical Initiations; or, Hymns of Orpheus (1787)</title>
        <author n="Cardinale">Philip J. Cardinale</author>
        <author n="Cardinale">Joseph R. Cardinale</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2010-11</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2010-2011</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">44.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2010-2011"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_44">
	<body>
    <pb id="p44-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Newly Discovered Blake Book: William Blake’s Copy of Thomas Taylor’s 
<hi rend="i">The Mystical Initiations; or, Hymns of Orpheus</hi> (1787)</title>
          </head>
          <byline>BY <docAuthor>PHILIP J. <name>CARDINALE</name></docAuthor> AND <docAuthor>JOSEPH R.
<name>CARDINALE</name></docAuthor><gap type="emend"/> <ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref></byline>
          <note id="n0">The late Reginald Alton (1919-2003) gave insightful critique, enthusiasm, and
encouragement at the earliest stage of this discovery. The article is dedicated to his memory. G. E. Bentley,
Jr., Paul Betz, and Michael Phillips are also owed great thanks for their thoughtful comments, especially on
paleographic matters. Jon Mee and Steve Critchley also provided invaluable feedback in response to drafts of
this essay.</note>
          <p>THERE is a book in the collection of the Bodleian Library at Oxford University that appears to
contain marginalia written by the poet and painter William Blake. These marginalia were discovered several
years ago by one of the authors of this paper during graduate 
research.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> 
The book is a first edition, 1787 copy of Thomas Taylor’s
<hi rend="i">The Mystical Initiations; or, Hymns of Orpheus</hi> (Bodleian call number Arch. H e.181). Its
author, sometimes referred to as “Taylor the Platonist,” was the first to translate the complete works of
Plato and Aristotle into English and has long been considered a Blake associate.</p>
          <note id="n1">1. They were first noticed by Phil Cardinale in June 2001 during initial research for
an Oxford English literature dissertation on Virgil and the romantics. The project of identifying,
authenticating, and publishing the annotations was postponed until his academic studies were complete. His
brother, Joseph Cardinale, a visiting student at Oxford when the marginalia were discovered, assisted with
research and drafting, and later revived the project and helped bring it to fruition.</note>
          <p>Upon the discovery of the marginalia, their style and content prompted a comparison with a
facsimile of Blake’s prose manuscript <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> (c. 1784-85). The handwriting
is strikingly similar. The annotator of <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> left no autograph. The book
contains one long and two short handwritten comments, as well as numerous passages underscored by the same
pen. The comments and highlighted passages fit what is known of Blake’s intellectual interests
            during the period in which he composed <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (c.
1787-94). If this attribution is accepted, it will shed further light on the artist’s association with
Taylor and likely confirm a suspected source for Blake’s poem “Ah! Sun-Flower” (see transcript, pp.
75-76). An especially heavily marked page may also record Blake’s receptivity to Taylor’s assertion that
“in the universe, there is one harmony though composed from contraries” (transcript, p. 70).</p>
          <p>This article argues for attributing to Blake the marginalia in the Bodleian’s copy of 
<hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi>. Part I describes the book and accounts for its provenance. Part II
transcribes the marginalia. A third section delineates Blake’s relationship with Taylor. Part IV compares
the marginalia with specimens of Blake’s handwriting, and Part V offers initial ideas about how these
annotations might correlate with Blake’s known thought.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title><hi rend="b">I. Description and Provenance</hi></title>
            </head>
            <p>The Bodleian copy is an octavo-sized, 227-page book bound
              in brown calfskin. It is in good condition. Gilt letters on the spine read “HYMNS / OF /
ORPHEUS / TAYLOR / 1787”, and a book stamp inside the front cover marks its entrance into the Bodleian
collection on 29 September 1928. A librarian’s pencil-written note also inside the front cover records that
the book was “Bt. from Quaritch” (Bernard Quaritch, bookseller of London, est. 1847). The purchase is
traceable to the following listing in <hi rend="i">Bernard Quaritch’s Catalogue, Number 414</hi> (London,
February 1928):<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
			<q>ORPHEUS. The Mystical Initiations, or Hymns of Orpheus, translated from the original Greek:
With a preliminary Dissertation on the Life and Theology of Orpheus; by THOMAS TAYLOR. Post 8vo., 
<hi rend="i">newly bound in calf	 Printed for the author</hi>, 1787	 £2, 2s</q>
              The October 1927 issue of <hi rend="i">Quaritch’s Catalogue</hi> (number 410) advertises
several of Taylor’s books without including <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi>, hinting that the
bookseller may have acquired the book in the intervening months. The description “newly
bound in calf” implies that Quaritch rebound the volume. In
response to an inquiry, the bookseller searched its records to
attempt to trace the original supplier. It appears, however,
that the firm did not retain a bill of sale due to the relatively low selling price of the 
item.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref></p>
            <note id="n2">2. P. 23, item 221. The book is listed in the catalogue’s classics section, which
is described as “including a choice selection ... from the library of the late Lt. Col. Sir George
Holford” (18). However, this copy of <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> must have a different source, as
it is not listed in Sotheby’s 1927-28 Holford estate auction catalogues.</note>
            <note id="n3">3. The authors are grateful to Ted Hofmann, a director at Bernard Quaritch, who
searched the firm’s records shortly after the marginalia were discovered and concluded that a bill of sale
had not been retained.</note>
            <p>According to the August 1788 issue of the <hi rend="i">Monthly Review</hi>,
<hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> originally sold for five shillings, “sewed,” with its leaves
loosely stitched so that buyers could have their copies bound as individual taste and funding
allowed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4">4</ref> The
title page states that the volume was originally distributed by “T. Payne and Son, at the Mews-gate; L.
Davis, Holborn; B. White and Son, Fleet-street; and G. Nichol, Strand.” Since this was Taylor’s first
philosophical work it can be assumed that the print run was modest, almost certainly fewer than 1,000
<pb id="p44-85" n="85"/>
copies. In 1792 the book reached a second printing under the shortened title <hi rend="i">The Hymns of
Orpheus.</hi></p>
<note id="n4">4. <hi rend="i">Monthly Review</hi> 79 (Aug. 1788): 133.</note>
<p>If at some point the Bodleian copy belonged to Blake, it is unclear who, owned the book immediately prior
to its acquisition in 1918. The artist died in 1827, leaving his property to his wife, Catherine. On her death
four years later, Blake’s belongings fell into the possession of Frederick Tatham, who over the course of
more than thirty years sold off or disposed of the artist’s legacy piece by piece. In 1864 Tatham recalled
that Blake
<q>had a most consummate knowledge of all the great writers
in all languages. To prove that, I may say that I have possessed books well thumbed and dirtied by his graving
hands,
in Latin, Greek, Hebrew, French, and Italian, besides a large
collection of works of the mystical writers, Jacob Behmen, Swedenborg, and others. His knowledge was immense
....<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref></q>
During the years that he kept Blake’s possessions, Tatham
became an adherent of the Christian minister Edward Irving
and it has been said that, convinced by some of that sect that
Blake’s works were satanic, he destroyed many of the artist’s
original manuscripts, blocks, plates, and 
drawings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> 
Blake’s library presumably suffered similar cleansing, though many
of the books survived and have since come to light. Bentley’s
Blake Records Supplement lists fifty-one books known to have
been in the poet’s collection, of which twenty-one have been
traced.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7">7</ref> 
Among that number fifteen contain annotations,
which are reprinted in Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry and 
Prose</hi>.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8">8</ref> 
<hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> is not listed in <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi>,
but the critical work of George Mills Harper, Kathleen Raine,
and others has established a likelihood that the poet had access to this book in the late 1780s and early
1790s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9">9</ref></p>
<note id="n5">5. Letter to Francis Harvey (8 June 1864), quoted in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2004) [hereafter <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)]
57fn.</note>
<note id="n6">6. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William
Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2001) 446.</note>
<note id="n7">7. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1988) [hereafter <hi rend="i">BRS</hi>] 124-29. <hi rend="i">BRS</hi> rather than the more recent 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) is cited here because the latter does not contain an appendix on Blake’s library. 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995), in Part V: Books Owned by Blake, lists
three more titles, and reveals that another in <hi rend="i">BRS</hi> (Homer, #26) has been traced.</note>
<note id="n8">8. David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly
rev. ed. (New York: Anchor-Random House, 1988) [hereafter E] 583-670.</note>
<note id="n9">9. Harper, <hi rend="i">The Neoplatonism of William Blake</hi> (Chapel Hill: University of North
Carolina Press, 1961); Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, 2 vols. (Princeton: Princeton University
Press, 1968).</note>
<p>In 1998 a copy of Blake’s 1809 Chaucer prospectus was
found in the possession of the Bodleian Library, where it had lain unrecorded for 165 years.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10">10</ref> This discovery makes it plausible that another item
connected to Blake could have
remained undetected in the same library.</p>
<note id="n10">10. J. B. Mertz, “An Unrecorded Copy of Blake’s 1809 Chaucer Prospectus,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 32.3 (winter 1998-99): 73-74.</note>
          </div3>
          <div3>
          <head>
          <title><hi rend="b">II. Transcription of the Marginalia</hi></title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> is presented in three parts: a preface (iii- xii); “A
Dissertation on the Life and Theology of Orpheus” (1-106); and a translation from ancient Greek of the
Orphic hymns (107-227). The “Dissertation” is subdivided into three sections: an account of Orpheus’s
life (1-12), an interpretation of his theology (12-84), and an introduction to his hymns (85-106).</p>
          <p>The annotator of the Bodleian copy wrote marginalia on pages vii (see illus. 1 and 3), viii
(illus. 2), and 69, corrected printer’s errors on pages 89 and 225, and underscored numerous passages,
primarily in the first two sections of Taylor’s “Dissertation.” All the handwriting and most of the
underlining in the book appear in orange-brown ink; some underlining and markings are in a darker, brown-black
shade of ink. Pencil marks appear on pages 14, 30, 44, 68, 70, and 97.</p>
          <p>The transcription that follows generally gives text on the left side and explanatory details on
the right. For ease of reading, instances of the long “s” have been changed to the modern short “s.”
As much of Taylor’s context has been reproduced as space allows, but necessarily only annotated and
underlined sections are given. The full text of the 1787 edition may be consulted through 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century Collections Online</hi>
&lt;http://gdc.gale.com/products/eighteenth-century-collections-online&gt; (subscription required).
Alternatively, <hi rend="i">Thomas Taylor the Platonist: Selected Writings</hi>, ed. Kathleen Raine and George
Mills Harper (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1969), reproduces the 1792 reprint. Readers should note
that the text of <hi rend="i">The Mystical Hymns of Orpheus</hi> (1824, a second edition), reproduced in 
<hi rend="i">Hymns and Initiations</hi>, volume 5 of the Thomas Taylor Series (Frome: Prometheus Trust, 1994),
differs substantially from that of 1787 and 1792.</p>
		<q>( iii )<lb/>
<lb/>
          PREFACE.<lb/>
<lb/>
          THERE is doubtless a revolu<lb rend="-"/>tion 
          in the literary, correspond<lb rend="-"/>ent 
          to that of the natural world.<lb/>
          The face of things is continually<lb/>
          changing; and the perfect, and per<lb rend="-"/>petual 
          harmony of the universe, sub<lb rend="-"/>sists 
          by the mutability of its parts.<lb/>
          In consequence of this fluctuation,<lb/>
          different arts and sciences have flou<lb rend="-"/>rished 
          at different periods of the<lb/>
          world: but the complete circle of<lb/>
          human
		</q>
		<q>( iv )<lb/>
<lb/>
          human knowledge has I believe, never<lb/>
          subsisted at once, in any nation or age.<lb/>
          <pb id="p44-86" n="86"/>
            <figure n="marginalia-vii.44.3.bonus" rend="file" width="575" height="923">
              <figTranscr>There is no instance of a poet writing good Eng.<lb/>
				Blank verse who has not also written good<lb/>
				Rhyme: but many have written good rhyme<lb/>
				( vii )<lb/>
				who have shewn no capability of writing. good<lb/>
				Blank verse .<lb/>
				<lb/>
				rhyme, which is certainly when well<lb/>
				executed, far more difficult than blank<lb/>
				verse, as the following Hymns must<lb/>
				evince, in an eminent degree.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				And, here it is necessary to observe,<lb/>
				with respect to translation, that<lb/>
				nothing is more generally mistaken<lb/>
				in its nature; or more faulty in its<lb/>
				execution. The author of the Letters<lb/>
				on Mythology, gives it as his opinion,<lb/>
				that it is impossible to translate<lb/>
				an ancient author, so as to do justice<lb/>
				to his meaning. If he had confined<lb/>
				this sentiment, to the beauties of<lb/>
				the composition, it would doubtless<lb/>
				have been just; but to extend it,<lb/>
				to the meaning of an author, is to<lb/>
				make truth and opinion, partial and<lb/>
				incommunicable. Every person, indeed,</figTranscr>
              <figDesc>1-2. Thomas Taylor, <hi rend="i">The Mystical Initiations; or, Hymns of Orpheus</hi>
(London, 1787), pp. vii (this page) and viii (facing page). The Bodleian Libraries, University of Oxford
(Arch. H e.181). See illus. 3 for detail of the annotation on p. vii.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p44-87" n="87"/>
            <figure n="marginalia-viii.44.3.bonus" rend="file" width="580" height="956">
            	<figTranscr>( viii )<lb/>
            	<lb/>
				[in]deed, acquainted with the learned languages,<lb/>
				must be conscious how much<lb/>
				the beauty of an ancient author generally<lb/>
				suffers by translation, though<lb/>
				<lb/>
				because _<lb/>
				<lb/>
				undertaken by men, who have devoted<lb/>
				the greatest part of their lives to<lb/>
				the study of words alone. This failure,<lb/>
				which has more than any thing contributed<lb/>
				to bring the ancients into contempt<lb/>
				with the unlearned, can only<lb/>
				be ascribed to the want of genius in<lb/>
				the translators: for the sentiment of<lb/>
				Pythagoras is peculiarly applicable to<lb/>
				such as these; that many carry the<lb/>
				Thyrsis, but few are inspired with<lb/>
				the spirit of the God. But this observation<lb/>
				is remarkably verified, in<lb/>
				the translators of the ancient philosophy,<lb/>
				whose performances are for the<lb/>
				most part without animation; and consequently</figTranscr>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p44-88" n="88"/>
			<supplied type="emend" rend="plain">
				<figure n="marginalia-viiidetail.44.3.bonus" rend="file" width="671" height="110">
					<figTranscr>the beauty of an ancient author generally<lb/>
					suffers by translation, though<lb/>
					<lb/>
					because _<lb/>
					<lb/>
					undertaken by men, who have devot[ed]</figTranscr>
					<figDesc><supplied type="emend">2b. Thomas Taylor, <hi rend="i">The Mystical Initiations; or, Hymns of
Orpheus</hi> (London, 1787), detail of p. viii. The Bodleian Libraries, University of Oxford (Arch. H
e.181).</supplied></figDesc>
				</figure>
			</supplied>
            Where accurate and profound re<lb rend="-"/>searches, 
            into the principles of things<lb/>
            have advanced to perfection; there,<lb/>
            by a natural consequence, men have<lb/>
            neglected the disquisition of particu<lb rend="-"/>lars: 
            and where sensible particulars<lb/>
            have been the general object of pur<lb rend="-"/>suit, 
            the science of universals has<lb/>
            languished, or sunk into oblivion and<lb/>
            contempt.
		</q>
		<q>
            <p>Thus <hi rend="u">wisdom</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">*</ref> the object of all<lb/>
              true philosophy, <hi rend="u">considered as explor-<lb/>
              ing the causes and principles of things</hi>,<lb/>
              <hi rend="u">flourished in high perfection among<lb/>
                the Egyptians first, and afterwards<lb/>
                in Greece.</hi> <hi rend="u">Polite literature was the<lb/>
                pursuit of the Romans</hi>; a<hi rend="u">nd experi-<lb/>
                  mental enquiries increased without</hi><lb/>
            end,</p></q>
            <note id="n11">* The annotator’s ink is orange brown.</note>
			<q><hi rend="u">end, and accumulated without order,<lb/>
            are the employment of modern phi<lb rend="-"/>losophy</hi>. 
            Hence we may justly con<lb rend="-"/>clude, 
            that the age of true philosophy<lb/>
            is no more. In consequence of very<lb/>
            extended natural discoveries, trade<lb/>
            and commerce have increased; while<lb/>
            abstract investigations, have necessarily<lb/>
            declined: so that <hi rend="u">modern enquiries</hi>,<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">never rise above sense</hi>; <hi rend="u">and</hi> <hi rend="u">every</hi><lb/>
            <hi rend="u">thing is despised, which does not in<lb/>
            some respect or other, contribute to<lb/>
            the accumulation of wealth</hi>;<hi rend="u"> the gra<lb rend="-"/>tification 
            of childish admiration;</hi> <hi rend="u">or<lb/>
            the refinements of corporeal delig</hi>ht.<lb/>
            The author of the following transla<lb rend="-"/>tion, 
            therefore, cannot reasonably ex<lb rend="-"/>pect, 
            that his labours will meet with<lb/>
            the approbation of the many: since<lb/>
            these Hymns are too ancient, and<lb/>
            too</q>
			<q>( vi )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            too full of the Greek philosophy, to<lb/>
            please the ignorant, and the sordid.<lb/>
            However, he hopes they will be ac<lb rend="-"/>ceptable 
            to the few, who have drawn<lb/>
            wisdom from its source; and who<lb/>
            consider the science of universals, as<lb/>
            first in the nature of things, though<lb/>
            last in the progressions of human un<lb rend="-"/>derstanding.
            <p>The translator has adopted rhyme,<lb/>
            not because most agreeable to gene<lb rend="-"/>ral 
            taste, but because he believes it<lb/>
            necessary to the poetry of the English<lb/>
            language; which requires something<lb/>
            as a substitute, for the energetic ca<lb rend="-"/>dence, 
            of the Greek and Latin Hex<lb rend="-"/>ameters. 
            Could this be obtained by<lb/>
            any other means, he would imme<lb rend="-"/>diately 
            relinquish his partiality for<lb/>
            rhyme,</p></q>
			<q><hi rend="gray">There is no instance of a poet writing good 
			Eng.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            Blank verse who has not also written good<lb/>
            Rhyme: but many have written good rhyme<lb/>
</hi>
            ( vii )<lb/>
            <hi rend="gray">who have shewn no capability of writing. good<lb/>
            Blank verse .<lb/>
</hi>
            <hi rend="u">rhyme</hi>, which is certainly <hi rend="u">when well<lb/>
            executed, far more difficult than blank<lb/>
            verse</hi>, as the following Hymns must<lb/>
            evince, in an eminent degree.
            <p>And, here it is necessary to ob<lb rend="-"/>serve, 
            with respect to translation, that<lb/>
            nothing is more generally mistaken<lb/>
            in its nature; or more faulty in its<lb/>
            execution. The author of the Letters<lb/>
            on Mythology, gives it as his opi<lb rend="-"/>nion, 
            that it is impossible to translate<lb/>
            an ancient author, so as to do justice<lb/>
            to his meaning. If he had confined<lb/>
            this sentiment, to the beauties of<lb/>
            the composition, it would doubtless<lb/>
            have been just; but to extend it,<lb/>
            to the meaning of an author, is to<lb/>
            make truth and opinion, partial and<lb/>
            incommunicable. Every person, in<lb rend="-"/>deed,</p></q>
            <note id="n12">* See illus. 1 and 3.</note>
			<q>( viii )<lb/>
            deed, acquainted with the learned lan<lb rend="-"/>guages, 
            must be conscious <hi rend="u">how much<lb/>
            the beauty of an ancient author ge<lb rend="-"/>nerally 
            suffers by translation</hi>, <hi rend="uu">though</hi><ref target="n13">*</ref><lb/>
            <hi rend="u">undertaken by men</hi>, <hi rend="u">who have devot</hi><lb rend="-"/><hi rend="u">ed 
            the greatest part of their lives to<lb/>
            the study of </hi><hi rend="uu">words</hi><hi rend="u"> alone</hi>. This failure,<lb/>
            which has more than any thing con<lb rend="-"/>tributed 
            to bring the ancients into con<lb rend="-"/>tempt 
            with the unlearned, can only<lb/>
            be ascribed to the want of genius in<lb/>
            the translators: for the sentiment of<lb/>
            Pythagoras is peculiarly applicable to<lb/>
            such as these; that<hi rend="u"> many carry the</hi>
            <pb id="p44-89" n="89"/>
            <hi rend="u">Thyrsis</hi>, <hi rend="u">but few are inspired with<lb/>
            the spirit of the God.</hi> But this ob<lb rend="-"/>servation 
            is remarkably verified, in<lb/>
            the translators of the ancient philoso<lb rend="-"/>phy, 
            whose performances are for the<lb/>
            most part without animation; and con<lb rend="-"/>sequently ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <note id="n13">* See illus. 2. “though” is double underlined, and the annotator replaces it
with the word “because.” (quite faded) in the left margin. “words” is also underscored twice.</note>
            <p>[There are no further marked passages in the preface.]</p>
			<q>[1]<lb/>
            <lb/>
            A<lb/>
            DISSERTATION<lb/>
            ON THE<lb/>
            Life and Theology of ORPHEUS.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            SECT. I.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            THE great <hi rend="u">obscurity</hi> and uncertainty<lb/>
            in which the history of Orpheus is<lb/>
            involved, <hi rend="u">affords very little matter</hi> for<lb/>
            our information; and even renders that<lb/>
            little, inaccurate and precarious. Upon<lb/>
            surveying the annals of past ages, it<lb/>
            seems that the greatest <hi rend="u">geniuses</hi>, have<lb/>
            been <hi rend="u">subject to</hi> this <hi rend="u">historical darkness</hi>;<lb/>
            as is evident in those great lights of an<lb rend="-"/>tiquity, 
            Homer and Euclid, whose writ<lb rend="-"/>ings 
            indeed enrich mankind with per<lb rend="-"/>petual</q>
			<q>( 2 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            petual stores of knowledge and delight;<lb/>
            but whose lives are for the most part<lb/>
            concealed in impenetrable oblivion. But<lb/>
            this historical uncertainty, is no where so<lb/>
            apparent, as in the person of Orpheus;<lb/>
            whose name is indeed acknowledged and<lb/>
            celebrated by all antiquity (except per<lb rend="-"/>haps 
            Aristotle alone); while scarcely a<lb/>
            vestige of his life is to be found amongst<lb/>
            the immense ruins of time. For who has<lb/>
            ever been able to affirm any thing with<lb/>
            certainty, concerning his origin, his age,<lb/>
            his parents, his country, and condition?<lb/>
            This alone may be depended on, from ge<lb rend="-"/>neral 
            assent, that there formerly lived a per<lb rend="-"/>son 
            named<hi rend="u"> Orp</hi>heus, whose father was Œa<lb rend="-"/>grus, 
            who lived in Thrace, and who was the<lb/>
            son of a king, who was the founder of<lb/>
            theology, among the Greeks; the i<hi rend="u">nsti<lb rend="-"/>tutor</hi> 
            <hi rend="u">of</hi> their <hi rend="u">life</hi> and morals; the first of<lb/>
            prophets, and the prince of poets; <hi rend="u">himself<lb/>
            the offspring of a Mus</hi>e; who taught the<lb/>
            Greeks</q>
			<q>( 3 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            Greeks their sacred rites and mysteries, and<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">from whose wisdom, as from a perpetual<lb/>
            and abundant fountain, the divine </hi><hi rend="uu">muse</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            <hi rend="u">of Homer, and the philosophy of Pytha<lb rend="-"/>goras, 
            and Plato, </hi><hi rend="uu">flowed</hi>; <hi rend="u">and, lastly, who<lb/>
            by the melody of his lyre, drew rocks,<lb/>
            woods, and wild beasts, stopt rivers in<lb/>
            their course, and even moved the inexor<lb rend="-"/>able 
            king of hel</hi>l; <hi rend="u">as every page, and al</hi>l<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">the writings of antiquity sufficiently evince.</hi><lb/>
            Since thus much then may be collected<lb/>
            from universal testimony, let us pursue<lb/>
            the matter a little farther, by investigat<lb rend="-"/>ing 
            more accurately the history of the<lb/>
            original Orpheus; with that of the great<lb/>
            men who have, at different periods, flou<lb rend="-"/>rished 
            under this venerable name.<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <p>[The next few marked passages are in a brown-black ink; this may or may not be the same
annotator. The orange-brown ink returns at p. 69.]</p>
            <note id="n14">* “muse” and “flowed” are underlined twice.</note>
			<q>( 4 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            <p>Our poet, according to fabulous tradi<lb rend="-"/>tion, 
            was torn in pieces by Ciconian<lb/>
            women:</p></q>
			<q>( 5 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            women: on which account, Plutarch af<lb rend="-"/>firms 
            <hi rend="u">the Thracians were accustomed 
            to</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            <hi rend="u">beat their wives</hi>, <hi rend="u">that they might revenge<lb/>
            the death of Orpheus</hi>. Hence, in the vision<lb/>
            of Herus Pamphilius ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <note id="n15">* The annotator has made a long dark X in the margins.</note>
			<q>( 6 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            having recalled Eurydice to life, and not<lb/>
            being able to detain her, he destroyed<lb/>
            himself; <hi rend="u">nightingales building their 
            nests,</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            <hi rend="u">and bringing forth their young upon his<lb/>
            tomb</hi>; <hi rend="u">whose melody, according to re<lb rend="-"/>port</hi>,<hi rend="u"> 
            exceeded every other of this spe<lb rend="-"/>cies.</hi> 
            Others again ascribe his laceration,<lb/>
            to his having celebrated every divinity<lb/>
            except Bacchus ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <note id="n16">The annotator again has made a long X beside this passage.</note>
            <pb id="p44-90" n="90"/>
			<q>( 9 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            siderable space of time. Afterwards, when<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">Neanthus, the son of Pittacus the tyran</hi>t,<lb/>
            found that the lyre drew trees and wild<lb/>
            beasts with its harmony, he earnestly<lb/>
            desired its possession; and having cor<lb rend="-"/>rupted 
            the priest privately with money, he<lb/>
            t<hi rend="u">ook the Orphean lyr</hi>e, <hi rend="u">and fixed anothe</hi>r<lb/>
            s<hi rend="u">imilar to it, in the temp</hi>le. But <hi rend="u">Nean</hi><lb rend="-"/>thus 
            considering that he was not safe in<lb/>
            the city in the day time, <hi rend="u">departed</hi> from<lb/>
            it <hi rend="u">by nigh</hi>t;<hi rend="u"> having concealed the lyre in<lb/>
            his bosom, on which he began to play</hi>.<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">But as he was a rude and unlearned youth</hi>,<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">he confounded the chords</hi>; <hi rend="u">yet pleasing<lb/>
            himself with the sound,</hi> <hi rend="u">and fancying he<lb/>
            produced a divine harmo</hi>ny, <hi rend="u">he conside</hi>r<lb rend="-"/><hi rend="u">ed 
            himself as the blessed successor of Or</hi><lb rend="-"/>pheus.</q>
			<q>( 10 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="u">pheus</hi>. However, in the midst of his<lb/>
            transports, the neighbouring dogs, roused<lb/>
            by the sound, fell upon the unhappy harper<lb/>
            and tore him to pieces.<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <p>[On p. 12 “SECT. II” begins, moving the discourse from Orpheus’s life to his
theology.]</p>
			<q>( 14 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            The belief indeed of the man, who looks<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">no higher than sense,</hi> must be 
            necessarily<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            terminated by appearances. Such a one<lb/>
            introduces a dreadful chasm in the uni<lb rend="-"/>verse; 
            and <hi rend="u">diffuses the deity through 
            the</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            <hi rend="u">world like an extended substance</hi>; <hi rend="u">divid<lb rend="-"/>ed 
            with every particle of matt</hi>er, <hi rend="u">and<lb/>
            changed into the infinite varieties of sen<lb rend="-"/>sible 
            forms.</hi> But with the ancient philoso<lb rend="-"/>pher, 
            the <hi rend="u">deity is an immense and per<lb rend="-"/>petually 
            exuberant fountai</hi>n; <hi rend="u">whose stream</hi>s<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">originally filled the continually replenish</hi><lb/>
            the</q>
            <note id="n17">* This mark is in a lighter gray shade that may be pencil.</note>
            <note id="n18">* Brown-black ink here and below.</note>
			<q>( 15 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="u">the world with life</hi>. Hence the universe<lb/>
            contains in its ample bosom all general<lb/>
            natures; divinities visible and invisible ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
			<q>( 19 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            And hence we con<lb rend="-"/>clude 
            that there is another certain nature<lb/>
            exempt from the passivity and imperfection<lb/>
            of bodies, existing not only in the heavens,<lb/>
            but in the ever-changing elements, from<lb/>
            which the motion of bodies is prim<lb rend="-"/>rily 
            derived. And this nature is no<lb/>
            other than 
            <hi rend="uthick">soul</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">*</ref> 
            <hi rend="u">from which animals de<lb rend="-"/>rive 
            their life and motive power</hi>; and<lb/>
            which even affords an image of self-motion<lb/>
            to the unstable order of bodies.
            <p>If then the self-motive essence is more<lb/>
            ancient than that which is moved by an<lb rend="-"/>other, 
            but soul is primarily self-motive,<lb/>
            hence soul must be more ancient than<lb/>
            body; and all corporeal motion must be<lb/>
            the</p></q>
            <note id="n19">* “soul” is underlined boldly.</note>
			<q>( 20 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            the progeny of soul, and of her inherent<lb/>
            energy. <hi rend="u">It is necessary, therefore, that th</hi>e<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">heavens,</hi> <hi rend="u">with all their boundless content</hi>s,<lb/>
            and their various natural motions (for a<lb/>
            circular motion, is natural to such bodies),<lb/>
            sh<hi rend="u">ould be endued with governing souls</hi>,<lb/>
            essentially more ancient than their revolv<lb rend="-"/>ing 
            bodies. According to the Platonic philosophers ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
			<q>( 21 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            Because it is also<lb/>
            necessary that the soul, essentially rational,<lb/>
            should receive intellect by participation,<lb/>
            and that <hi rend="u">intellectual energy</hi> should be <hi rend="u">of<lb/>
            two</hi></q>
			<q>( 22 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="u">two kinds</hi>; <hi rend="u">one primarily subsisting in the<lb/>
            divine intellect</hi>; <hi rend="u">but the other subsisting<lb/>
            secondarily in its offspring soul</hi>. You<lb/>
            may add too, the presence of intellectual<lb/>
            illumination in body, which is received<lb/>
            in as great perfection as its unstable and<lb/>
            obscure nature will admit. For <hi rend="u">how is i</hi>t<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">possible that the celestial orbs should </hi>be<lb/>
            f<hi rend="u">or ever circularly moved in one definite<lb/>
            order</hi>, <hi rend="u">preserving the same form, and th</hi>e<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">same immutable power</hi>, <hi rend="u">unless they pa</hi>r-<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">ticipated of an intellectual </hi>nature. For<lb/>
            soul is indeed the constant supplier of mo-
            <pb id="p44-91" n="91"/>
            tion; but the cause of perpetual station,<lb/>
            of indentity and uniform life, reducing<lb/>
            unstable motion to a circular revolution,<lb/>
            and to a condition eternally the same,<lb/>
            must be more ancient than soul.<lb/>
            ...</q>
			<q>( 25 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            <p>In consequence of this reasoning, Or<lb rend="-"/>pheus 
            filled all things with Gods, subor<lb rend="-"/>dinate 
            to the demiurgus of the whole<lb/>
            Δημιουργῷ, every one of which performs the<lb/>
            office destined to his divinity, by his supe<lb rend="-"/>riour</p></q>
			<q>( 26 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            riour leader. Hence according to his<lb/>
            theology there are two worlds, the intel<lb rend="-"/>ligible 
            and the sensible. Hence too his<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">three demiurgic principles: Jovial</hi>, <hi rend="u">Dio<lb rend="-"/>nysiacal</hi>, 
            <hi rend="u">and Adonical,</hi> Δΐιος , Διονυσιακὴ,<lb/>
            Αδωναϊκὴ, <hi rend="u">from whence many orders and<lb/>
            differences of Gods proce</hi>ed, intelligi<lb rend="-"/>ble 
            ..., intellectual, super-mundane, mun<lb rend="-"/>dane, 
            celestial, authors of generation.<lb/>
            And among these some in the order of<lb/>
            guardian, demiurgic, elevating and com<lb rend="-"/>prehending 
            Gods; perfecters of works,<lb/>
            vivific, immutable, absolute, judicial,<lb/>
            purgative, &amp;c. and <hi rend="u">besides these to eac</hi>h<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">particular divin</hi>ity<hi rend="u">, he added a particular<lb/>
            multitude of ang</hi>els,<hi rend="u"> dæmons</hi>, <hi rend="u">and hero</hi>es;<lb/>
            for according to Proclus, relating the<lb/>
            opinion</q>
			<q>( 27 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            opinion of Orpheus, and the theologists:<lb/>
            ... “<hi rend="u">About every God there is a kindred<lb/>
            multitude of angel</hi>s, <hi rend="u">heroes</hi>, <hi rend="u">and dæmons</hi>.<lb/>
            For every God presides over the form of<lb/>
            that multitude which receives the divinity.”<lb/>
            He likewise considered <hi rend="u">a difference of sex<lb/>
            in these deities</hi>, calling some male, and<lb/>
            other female ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
			<q>( 28 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            For<lb/>
            that we may begin with the extremes, hea<lb rend="-"/>ven 
            corresponds with earth, in the order<lb/>
            and proportion of male to female. Since the<lb/>
            motion of the heavens imparts particular<lb/>
            properties and powers, to particular things.<lb/>
            But on the other hand <hi rend="u">earth receiving the<lb/>
            celestial defluxio</hi>ns, <hi rend="u">becomes pregnant</hi>,<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">and produces plants and animals of every<lb/>
            kind</hi>. And of the Gods existing in the<lb/>
            heavens, some are distinguished by the<lb/>
            male division, and others by the female ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
			<q>( 30 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
</q>
			<q>And in the same place, Proclus has pre<lb rend="-"/>served 
			to us another copy of Orphic<lb/>
            verses, which are also found in the writer<lb/>
            (de Mundo); previous to which he ob<lb rend="-"/>serves, 
            that the demiurgus, or artificer of<lb/>
            the world, b<hi rend="u">eing full of ideas, compre<lb rend="-"/>hended 
            by these all things within 
            himself,</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            as that theologer (Orpheus) declares.<lb/>
            With these verses we have connected others,<lb/>
            agreeable to the order of Stephens, Eschen<lb rend="-"/>bach, 
            and Gesner, as follows.<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <note id="n20">* This mark is in the lighter gray shade that is also on p. 14.</note>
			<q>( 43 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            For it is surely astonishing that the<lb/>
            soul should live immaterially, in material<lb/>
            concerns; and preserve itself uncontamin<lb rend="-"/>ated 
            amidst such base defilements; that it<lb/>
            should drink of the cup of oblivion, and<lb/>
            not be laid asleep by the intoxicating<lb/>
            draught; that it should elevate its eye<lb/>
            above</q>
			<q>( 44 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
</q>
			<q>above the sordid darkness with which it is<lb/>
            surrounded; and be able to open the gates<lb/>
            of truth, which, though contained in 
            its<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            essence, are guarded and shut by terrene<lb/>
            and material species. But that it is pos<lb rend="-"/>sible 
            to know more of such exalted natures<lb/>
            than is generally believed, by the assistance<lb/>
            of the ancient philosophy, accompanied<lb/>
            with a suitable life, is, I am persuaded, true;<lb/>
            and I would recommend the arduous and<lb/>
            glorious investigation to every liberal<lb/>
            mind.</q>
			<q><p>Let us now consider the nature of sacri<lb rend="-"/>fice 
			according to Orpheus and the Pla<lb rend="-"/>tonists; 
			previous to which, I must beg<lb/>
            leave to inform the reader, that <hi rend="u">the 
            Greek<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            theologists and philosophers were not</hi> (as<lb/>
            they are represented by modern writers on<lb/>
            mythology) <hi rend="u">so stupid as to worship the<lb/>
            creature instead of the Creator</hi>; <hi rend="u">and to neg</hi>-
            <pb id="p44-92" n="92"/>
            <hi rend="u">lect or confound that homage and ven</hi>e<lb rend="-"/>ration,</p></q>
            <note id="n21">* This and the next five lines are marked with a single vertical stroke, probably
pencil as on pp. 14 and 30.</note>
            <note id="n22">* The ink in this section is brownish black.</note>
			<q>( 45 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="u">ration</hi>, <hi rend="u">which is due to the first cause of all.</hi><lb/>
            On the contrary, <hi rend="u">they considered the su</hi><lb rend="-"/><hi rend="u">preme 
            Being as honoured by the reverence<lb/>
            paid to his most illustrious offspr</hi>ing; and<lb/>
            carefully distinguished between the worship<lb/>
            proper to the Deity, and to the subordinate<lb/>
            Gods ....<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            But<lb/>
            as I cannot give a better account of the<lb/>
            nature and antiquity of sacrifice than from<lb/>
            the writings of <hi rend="u">Porphyry</hi>, I shall present<lb/>
            the reader with the following paraphrase,<lb/>
            on</q>
			<q>( 46 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            on part of the second book of his excellent<lb/>
            work <hi rend="u">on abstinence</hi>.</q>
			<q><p>“The period of time appears to have<lb/>
            been immensely distant, from which, as<lb/>
            Theophrastus says, <hi rend="u">a nation the </hi><hi rend="uu">most</hi><hi rend="u"> learn<lb rend="-"/>ed 
			</hi><hi rend="uu">of</hi><hi rend="u"> all 
			</hi><hi rend="uu">others</hi><hi rend="u">,</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">*</ref>
			and inhabiting the sacred<lb/>
            region formed by the Nile, began first of<lb/>
            all, from the domestic fire, to sacrifice to<lb/>
            the celestial divinities ....<lb/>
            For at first<lb/>
            they performed sacrifices, not with aro<lb rend="-"/>matics,</p></q>
            <note id="n23">* “most”, “of”, and “others” are underlined twice.</note>
			<q>( 47 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            matics, but with the first fruits of the<lb/>
            green herb; plucking it with their hands,<lb/>
            as a certain soft down or moss of prolific<lb/>
            nature. <hi rend="u">Indeed the earth produced trees<lb/>
            before animals</hi>; <hi rend="u">but prior to trees</hi>, <hi rend="u">the an<lb rend="-"/>nually 
            rising gras</hi>s, t<hi rend="u">he leaves,</hi> <hi rend="u">and roots</hi>,<lb/>
            and entire produce of which having collect<lb rend="-"/>ed, 
            they sacrificed with fire ....<lb/>
            ...[”]</q>
			<q>( 67 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            Besides, since we are as child<lb rend="-"/>ren 
            torn from the bosom of our parent,<lb/>
            we</q>
			<q>( 68 )<lb/>
</q>
			<q>we ought on this account to request by<lb/>
            our prayers that we may return to 
            the<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            Gods our true intellectual parents. If this<lb/>
            is the case, do not they who deny that<lb/>
            prayers are to be offered to the Gods, and<lb/>
            who prevent their souls from being united<lb/>
            with the divinities, that is with beings<lb/>
            more excellent than themselves, appear<lb/>
            similar to those who are deprived of their<lb/>
            parents?<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <note id="n24">* The first four lines of p. 68 are marked by a single vertical stroke, probably
made with a pencil.</note>
			<q>( 69 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            <p>For a conversion to the universe pro<lb rend="-"/>cures 
            safety to every thing which it con<lb rend="-"/>tains. 
            If therefore you possess virtue, it is<lb/>
            requisite you should invoke that divinity<lb/>
            which previously comprehended in 
            <hi rend="strike">him</hi>self<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            every virtue: for universal good is the<lb/>
            cause of that good which belongs to you<lb/>
            by participation. And if you seek after<lb/>
            some corporeal good, the world is endued<lb/>
            with a power which contains universal<lb/>
            body. From hence therefore it is necessary<lb/>
            that perfection should also extend to the<lb/>
            parts. Thus far that most excellent philo<lb rend="-"/>sopher 
            Porphyry; in which quotation, as<lb/>
            well as the preceding, the reader must<lb/>
            doubtless confess, that Proclus did not<lb/>
            without reason admire him, for what he<lb/>
            calls his τὰ ιεροπρεπῆ νοήματα, or conceptions<lb/>
            adapted to holy concerns; for surely no<lb/>
            philo-</p></q>
            <note id="n25">* In orange-brown ink, the annotator has crossed out “him” and above written
“it”. This appears to be the same ink and hand as on p. vii.</note>
			<q>( 70 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            philosopher ever possessed them in a more<lb/>
            eminent degree.</q>
			<q><p><hi rend="u">If it should be asked, in what the 
			power<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            of prayer consists, according to these<lb/>
            philosophers? I answer, in a certain sym<lb rend="-"/>pathy 
            and similitude of natures to each<lb/>
            other</hi>: j<hi rend="u">ust as in an extended chord, where<lb/>
            when the lowest part is moved, the highest<lb/>
            presently after gives a responsive motio</hi>n.<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">Or as in the strings of a musical instrument,<lb/>
            attempered to the same harmony;</hi> <hi rend="u">one<lb/>
            chord trembling from the pulsation of<lb/>
            another, as if it were endued with sensa<lb rend="-"/>tion 
            from symphon</hi>y. S<hi rend="u">o in the universe,<lb/>
            there is one harmony though composed<lb/>
            from contraries;</hi> <hi rend="u">since they are at the<lb/>
            same time similar and allied to each othe</hi>r.<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">For from the soul of the world, like an<lb/>
            immortal self-motive lyre, life every wher</hi>e<lb/>
            <pb id="p44-93" n="93"/>
            <hi rend="u">resounds, but in some things more inferi</hi>or<lb/>
            and</p></q>
            <note id="n26">* This page is particularly heavily marked; in addition to underscores in
orange-brown ink, a single vertical line in what appears to be pencil runs down the margin.</note>
			<q>( 71 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="u">and remote from perfection than in others.</hi><lb/>
            And with respect to the super-mundane<lb/>
            Gods, sympathy and similitude subsists in<lb/>
            these as in their most perfect exemplars;<lb/>
            from whence they are participated by sen<lb rend="-"/>sible 
            natures, their obscure and imperfect<lb/>
            images. Hence (say they) we must not<lb/>
            conceive, that our prayers cause any ani<lb rend="-"/>madversion 
            in the Gods, or, properly speak<lb rend="-"/>ing, 
            draw down their beneficence; but that<lb/>
            they are rather the means of elevating the<lb/>
            soul to these divinities, and disposing it<lb/>
            for the reception of their supernal illumi<lb rend="-"/>nation. 
            F<hi rend="u">or the divine irradiation, which<lb/>
            takes place in prayer, shines and energizes<lb/>
            spontaneously, restoring unity to the soul,<lb/>
            and causing our energy to become one with<lb/>
            divine energy</hi>. For such, according to these<lb/>
            philosophers, is the efficacy of prayer,<lb/>
            that it unites all inferior with all superior<lb/>
            beings.</q>
			<q>( 72 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            beings. Since, as the great Theodorus<lb/>
            says, all things pray except the first.</q>
			<q><p><hi rend="u">Indeed so great is the power of simili<lb rend="-"/>tude, 
			that through its</hi> <hi rend="uthick">unifying</hi> <hi rend="u">nature 
			all</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            <hi rend="u">things coalesce, and impart their particular<lb/>
            properties to others</hi>. Whilst primary na<lb rend="-"/>tures 
            distribute their gifts to such as are<lb/>
            secondary, by an abundant illumination,<lb/>
            and effects are established in the causes from<lb/>
            which they proceed.<lb/>
            ...</p></q>
            <note id="n27">* “unifying” is very boldly underlined.</note>
			<q>( 75 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            For<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">how shall we account for those plants<lb/>
            called heliotrop</hi>es, <hi rend="u">that is attendants on<lb/>
            the sun</hi>, <hi rend="u">moving in correspondence with<lb/>
            the revolution of its or</hi>b;<hi rend="u"> but selenitropes,<lb/>
            or attendants on the moon, turning in<lb/>
            exact conformity with her motion</hi>? <hi rend="u">it is<lb/>
            because all things pray, and compose<lb/>
            hymns to the leaders of their respective or</hi><lb rend="-"/><hi rend="u">ders</hi>; 
            but some intellectually, and others<lb/>
            rationally;</q>
			<q>( 76 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            rationally; some in a natural, and others<lb/>
            after a sensible manner. <hi rend="u">Hence the sun<lb rend="-"/>flower, 
            as far as it is able, moves in a cir<lb rend="-"/>cular 
            dance towards the sun; so that if<lb/>
            any one could hear the pulsation made by<lb/>
            its circuit in the air, he would perceive<lb/>
            something composed by a sound of this<lb/>
            kind, in honours of its king, such as a<lb/>
            plant is capable of framing</hi>. Hence we<lb/>
            may behold the sun and moon in the earth,<lb/>
            but according to a terrene quality. But<lb/>
            in the celestial regions, all plants, and<lb/>
            stones, and animals, possessing an intellec<lb rend="-"/>tual 
            life according to a celestial nature.<lb/>
            Now the ancients having contemplated<lb/>
            this mutual sympathy of things, applied<lb/>
            for occult purposes both celestial and ter<lb rend="-"/>rene 
            natures, by means of which through<lb/>
            a certain similitude they deduced divine<lb/>
            virtues into this inferior abode. For in<lb rend="-"/>deed</q>
			<q>( 77 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            deed similitude itself is a sufficient cause<lb/>
            of binding things together in union and<lb/>
            consent. Thus if a piece of paper is<lb/>
            heated, and afterwards placed near a lamp,<lb/>
            though it does not touch the fire, the pa<lb rend="-"/>per 
            will be suddenly inflamed, and the<lb/>
            flame will descend from the superior to the<lb/>
            inferior parts. This heated paper we<lb/>
            may compare to a certain relation of in<lb rend="-"/>feriors 
            to superiors; and its approxi<lb rend="-"/>mation 
            to the lamp, to the opportune<lb/>
            use of things according to time, place,<lb/>
            and matter. But the procession of fire<lb/>
            in the paper aptly represents the presence<lb/>
            of divine light, to that nature which is<lb/>
            capable of its reception. Lastly, the in<lb rend="-"/>flammation 
            of the paper may be com<lb rend="-"/>pared 
            to the deification of mortals, and<lb/>
            to the illumination of material natures,<lb/>
            which are afterwards carried upwards like<lb/>
            the</q>
			<q>( 78 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            the fire of the paper, from a certain par<lb rend="-"/>ticipation 
            of divine seed. <hi rend="u">Again, the lo<lb rend="-"/>tus 
            before the rising of the sun, folds its<lb/>
            leaves into itself, but gradually expands<lb/>
            them on its rising</hi>: <hi rend="u">unfolding them in<lb/>
            <pb id="p44-94" n="94"/>
            proportion to the sun’s ascent to the<lb/>
            zenith</hi>; <hi rend="u">but as gradually contracting them<lb/>
            as that luminary descends to the west.<lb/>
            Hence this plant by the expansion an</hi>d<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">contraction of its leaves appears no less<lb/>
            to honour the sun than men by the<lb/>
            gesture of their eye-lids, and the motion<lb/>
            of their lips</hi>. But <hi rend="u">this imitation a</hi>nd cer<lb rend="-"/>tain 
            participation of supernal light is not<lb/>
            only visible in plants, which possess<lb/>
            but a vestige of life, but <hi rend="u">likewise in par</hi><lb rend="-"/><hi rend="u">ticular 
            stones.</hi> Thus the sun-stone, by<lb/>
            its golden rays, imitates those of the<lb/>
            sun; but the stone called the eye of<lb/>
            heaven, or of the sun, has a figure<lb/>
            similar</q>
			<q>( 79 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            similar to the pupil of an eye, and a ray<lb/>
            shines from the middle of the pupil.<lb/>
            Thus too <hi rend="u">the lunar stone, which has a<lb/>
            figure similar to the moon when horned,<lb/>
            by a certain change of itself, follows the<lb/>
            lunar motion</hi>. Lastly, the stone called<lb/>
            Helioselenus, i. e. of the sun and moon,<lb/>
            imitates after a manner the congress of<lb/>
            those luminaries, which it images by its<lb/>
            colour. So that all things are full of<lb/>
            divine natures ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
			<q>( 83 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            In consequence of a blind<lb/>
            and mistaken zeal it is common to ridicule<lb/>
            the opinions of the ancient philosophers,<lb/>
            in order to establish the certainty of the<lb/>
            Christian religion. But surely revelation<lb/>
            does not require so unwarrantable and<lb/>
            feeble a support, which in reality only be<lb rend="-"/>trays 
            the cause it endeavours to defend, by<lb/>
            giving infidels occasion to suspect, either<lb/>
            weakness</q>
			<q>( 84 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            weakness in its evidence, or obscurity in<lb/>
            its fundamental doctrines. Besides, the<lb/>
            generality of these uncandid opponents<lb/>
            know nothing of the Platonical writers,<lb/>
            from whom alone genuine information<lb/>
            can be derived on this sublime and intri<lb rend="-"/>cate 
            subject; and from whose works the<lb/>
            preceding Dissertation has been so abun<lb rend="-"/>dantly 
            enriched. Were these invaluable<lb/>
            books more generally known and under<lb rend="-"/>stood, 
            if they did not refine our taste, at<lb/>
            present so depraved, they would at least<lb/>
            teach us to admire the strength which hu<lb rend="-"/>man 
            reason is capable of exerting, and to<lb/>
            be more modest in our pretensions to wis<lb rend="-"/>dom; 
            they would silence ignorant de<lb rend="-"/>claimers, 
            and stop <hi rend="u">the immense increase o</hi>f<lb/>
            <hi rend="u">books on modern philosophy, which are<lb/>
            so rapidly hastening to the abyss of forget</hi><lb rend="-"/><hi rend="u">fulnes</hi>s, 
            <hi rend="u">like streams into the ocean from<lb/>
            which they originally flowed.</hi><lb/>
            SECT.<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <p>[The remainder of the tract, “SECT. III” (pp. 85-106), introduces the Orphic hymns. This
section features only a correction in brown-black ink on p. 89, and a light, vertical pencil mark on p.
97.]</p>
			<q>( 89 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
</q>
			<q>It is on this<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            account we have entitled them mystical<lb/>
            initiations, which is doubtless their pro<lb rend="-"/>per 
            appellation<hi rend="strike">s</hi>. The author too of the<lb/>
            Allegories in the Theogony of Hesiod ....<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <note id="n28">* In brown-black ink the annotator blots out the “s” in
“appellations”.</note>
			<q>( 97 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
</q>
			<q>Now Onomacritus 
			calls<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">*</ref><lb/>
            Hercules and Vulcan, Καρτεροχειρ, or strong-<lb/>handed; 
            and he celebrates Hercules and<lb/>
            Mercury as “having an almighty heart.”<lb/>
            ...</q>
            <note id="n29">* A light, vertical pencil mark runs alongside this sentence.</note>
            <p>[No marks appear in Taylor’s translation (pp. 107-227), except for a correction in
orange-brown ink at the lower-right corner of p. 225, within a footnote to “To Death.” The annotator adds
“cted” to a word that should say “contracted” but lacks those letters due to a printing error.]</p>
			<q>( 225 )<lb/>
            ...<lb/>
            You then, as the votaries of truth, will, I doubt not, unite with me in most earnest wishes, that
every valuable work on the Platonic philosophy was well translated into our native tongue; that we might no
longer be subject to the toil of learning the ancient languages. The mischief, indeed, resulting from the
study of words is almost too apparent to need any illustration: as the understanding is generally 
contra<hi rend="gray">cted,</hi></q>
			<q>( 226 )<lb/>
            <lb/>
            its vigour exhausted; and the genius fettered to verbal criticism, and grammatical trifles.</q>
            <pb id="p44-95" n="95"/>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title><hi rend="b">III. Blake and Taylor: An Overview</hi></title>
            </head>
            <p>Taylor (1758-1835) was a believer in ancient Greek theology who in the late 1780s began
publishing a rapid succession of works that denounced Enlightenment thought and promoted paganism. 
<hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> was the first of these works. Taylor ultimately published the first
complete translations in English of Plato (1804, partly revised from the work of Floyer Sydenham) and
Aristotle (1806-12), as well as translations of many of the Neoplatonists whose philosophy he preferred.
Called by contemporaries “Taylor the Platonist” and “Taylor the Pagan,” he was a mathematician and
metaphysician who taught himself Greek through Plato, and to whom university jobs were closed because of his
religious dissent. He was one of the great classicists of his time, who presented Greek thought (or distorted
it, some said) in a new and revolutionary light.</p>
            <p>Taylor and Blake were six months apart in age and began their literary careers in the same
intellectual circle. They may have met as early as 1783, probably through the sculptor John Flaxman. 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, Blake’s first work, was published that year in part through Flaxman’s
patronage, and in 1785 Taylor delivered a series of twelve lectures on Platonic philosophy at Flaxman’s
home. He also lectured in late 1784 at the Freemasons’ Tavern opposite the residence of James Basire, the
engraver to whom Blake had been apprenticed. It does not seem improbable that Blake attended some of these
lectures. Blake is thought to have caricatured Taylor in his fragmentary prose satire <hi rend="i">An Island
in the Moon</hi> (c. 1784-85), alongside representations of the Unitarian thinker Joseph Priestley, the
radical bookseller Joseph Johnson, and Blake’s younger brother Robert, among others. Taylor may have
inspired the character Obtuse Angle, who sings an early version of “Holy Thursday” (from 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>) and whose arrival, at the point where the manuscript tantalizingly ends, gladdens
Quid the Cynic (Blake’s pseudonym for himself).</p>
            <p>Through lecturing in 1784 Taylor met William Meredith, a businessman whose patronage allowed
him to quit his job as a banker’s clerk and write <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi>. The book received
its first notice in June 1787 and was followed within four months by Taylor’s “paraphrase translation”
of Plotinus’s <hi rend="i">Concerning the Beautiful</hi>.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n30" type="note">11</ref> In February 1787 Blake’s younger brother Robert had died of tuberculosis,
an event that would be pivotal in William’s career. According to Blake’s first biographer, Alexander
Gilchrist, Blake nursed his dying brother until, at the last, he said he witnessed the young man’s soul rise
through the ceiling “clapping its hands for joy.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">12</ref> Blake claimed that Robert’s spirit soon after appeared to him and taught him the
secrets of illuminated printing.</p>
            <note id="n30">11. <hi rend="i">Critical Review</hi> 63 (June 1787): 401-06 and 64 (Oct. 1787):
286-88.</note>
            <note id="n31">12. Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, “Pictor Ignotus,”</hi> 2
vols. (London: Macmillan, 1863) 1: 59.</note>
            <p>It is in the context of Robert’s recent death that we might imagine Blake’s reading 
<hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi>, which in large part passionately expounds Neoplatonic ideas of the soul.
There is reason to suppose that Taylor may have been the sort of person with whom Blake could have conversed
about the soul at that time. In addition to possibly having known Robert (alter egos of both men appear in 
<hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>), Taylor would likely not have dismissed Blake’s claim of seeing his
brother’s spirit. Though he does not affirm it in his public writing, in private marginalia Taylor refers to
his own mystical experience. He suggests that the soul, in such a state, “will spontaneously utter musical
sounds, as indications of the harmony 
within.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">13</ref></p>
            <note id="n32">13. Quoted in S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi>, rev. ed.
(Hanover: University Press of New England, 1988) 396. The quoted passage appears in Taylor’s 
<hi rend="i">The Philosophical and Mathematical Commentaries of Proclus</hi>, 2 vols. (London, 1788) 2: 277. In
Taylor’s own copy, his comment beside this passage states “I wrote this from my own experience at the
time. T. T.”</note>
            <p>S. Foster Damon first posited Blake’s connection with Taylor in 1924, four years before the
Bodleian bought its copy of Mystical Initiations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">14</ref> Harper thoroughly investigated that link in the 1950s. His <hi rend="i">The Neoplatonism
of William Blake</hi> devotes several pages to <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi>, asserting that
			<q>Blake may have found much that excited him, including a metaphysical discussion, based upon
the Theory of Forms and the Theory of Emanation, of the participation of all earthly things in the divine
order and an explanation of several Neoplatonic symbols. Chief among these was the sun .... The immediate
product most likely was Blake’s “Ah! Sunflower.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">15</ref></q></p>
            <note id="n33">14. See <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (Boston:
Houghton Mifflin, 1924) 32, where Damon states of Taylor: “Blake, we imagine, was alternately shocked and
delighted at this ‘philosophical polytheist’; but at first he could only laugh.”</note>
            <note id="n34">15. Harper 119 (discussion on 119-23).</note>
            <p>Bibliographic evidence confirming Blake and Taylor’s friendship did not come to light until
the early 1970s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">16</ref> It took the form of
two anecdotes, the first written between 1867 and 1869 in the <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi> of Taylor’s
longtime friend Alexander Dyce (1798-1869):
			<q>Taylor, so absurd himself in many aspects, was ready enough to laugh at the strange fancies
of others,—for instance, at those of that half-crazed man of real genius, Blake the artist. “Pray, Mr.
Taylor,” said Blake one day, “did you ever find yourself, as it were, standing close beside the vast and
luminous orb of the moon”?—[“]Not that I remember, Mr. Blake: did you ever?”—“Yes, frequently; and
I have felt an almost irresistible desire to throw myself into it headlong.”—“I think, Mr. Blake, you
had better not; for if you were to do so, you most probably would never come out of it 
again.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">17</ref></q>
              Dyce may have had in mind the passage in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
(1790) where the narrator throws himself
            <pb id="p44-96" n="96"/>
              <figure n="marginalia-viidetail.44.3.bonus" rend="file" width="667" height="199">
              	<figTranscr>There is no instance of a poet writing good Eng.<lb/>
				Blank verse who has not also written good<lb/>
				Rhyme: but many have written good rhyme<lb/>
				( vii )<lb/>
				who have shewn no capability of writing. good<lb/>
				Blank verse .<lb/>
				<lb/>
				rhyme, which is certainly when well</figTranscr>
                <figDesc>3. Thomas Taylor, <hi rend="i">The Mystical Initiations; or, Hymns of Orpheus</hi>
(London, 1787), detail of p. vii. The Bodleian Libraries, University of
                  Oxford (Arch. H e.181).</figDesc>
              </figure>
into the sun (pl. 19).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">18</ref> 
William Meredith (1804-31), the nephew of Taylor’s patron of the same name, recalled in
1829 another incident:
			<q>T. Taylor gave Blake, the artist, some lessons in mathematics &amp; got as far as the 
5<hi rend="s">th</hi>. proposit<hi rend="s">n</hi>. wch proves that any two angles at the base of an isoceles
triangle must be equal. Taylor was going thro the demonstration, but was interrupted by Blake, exclaiming,
“ah never mind that—what’s the use of going to prove it, why I see with my eyes that it is so, &amp; do
not require any proof to make it clearer.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38">19</ref></q>
              Both anecdotes are of undetermined chronology and may date as early as the 1780s, though a diary
entry by George Cumberland implies that Taylor and Blake were in contact late in life. Cumberland breakfasted
with Taylor on 15 October 1825 and spoke of old friends, after which he wrote in his diary “The Duke of
Sussex is also Taylor’s friend—memo to see Blake.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
type="note">20</ref></p>
            <note id="n35">16. James King, “The Meredith Family, Thomas Taylor, and William Blake,” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 11 (1972): 153-57, and Richard J. Schrader, ed., <hi rend="i">The
Reminiscences of Alexander Dyce</hi> ([Columbus]: Ohio State University Press, 1972) 134-35, established that
Blake and Taylor were acquainted.</note>
            <note id="n36">17. Quoted in Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 500.</note>
            <note id="n37">18. See Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 500fn.</note>
            <note id="n38">19. Quoted in Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 500.</note>
            <note id="n39">20. Quoted in Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 2nd ed. (Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1971) 247-48.</note>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title><hi rend="b">IV. Handwriting Authentication</hi></title>
            </head>
            <p>Only one annotation in <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> is longer than a
              word, but in certain ways it is a very desirable sample. Several words recur, displaying the
writer’s variations on particular letter pairings, and it is in a distinctive shade of ink. The annotation,
which appears above the text of page vii (see illus. 3), reads:
			<q>There is no instance of a poet writing good Eng.<lb/>
                Blank verse who has not also written good<lb/>
                Rhyme: but many have written good rhyme<lb/>
                who have shewn no capability of writing. good<lb/>
                Blank verse .</q>
                The best bases for comparative analysis with Blake’s handwriting, according to G. E.
Bentley, Jr., an authority on Blake’s handwriting who reviewed this article prior to publication, are
capital letters (“B,” “E,” “R,” and “T”) and letters that have ascenders and descenders (as in
“good,” “many,” “of,” “poet,” “who,” “writing,” and “capability”).</p>
            <p>If it is accepted as plausible that the marginalia date to around the same time as the
publication of <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi>, the best comparative source for Blake’s handwriting
is the manuscript of <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> (c. 1784-85). Its first page is reproduced here
as a sample for comparison (see illus. 4).</p>
            <p>The table on the following pages compares samples of the annotator’s handwriting in 
<hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> with corresponding instances from <hi rend="i">An Island in the
Moon</hi>.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">21</ref> The table includes
capital letters, letters with ascenders and descenders, and finally some additional words paralleled in the
<hi rend="i">Island</hi> manuscript. The samples have been enhanced in order to provide easier comparisons of
letter formation.</p>
            <note id="n40">21. The authors are indebted to G. E. Bentley, Jr., for recommending these specific
comparisons.</note>
            <p>Collectively these samples display a likeness between the annotator’s handwriting and
Blake’s, which supports an attribution of the marginalia to the artist. The shade of the orange-brown ink
may provide another argument for attribution. The ink is fairly bright and its shade is comparable to the
orange-brown text in some of Blake’s illuminated prints, although there are differences between writing ink
and printing ink.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">22</ref> In addition, the
somewhat peculiar shade of the ink offers the best evidence that the ink underliner was the author of the
marginalia. The other underlinings in the book are not as easy to associate with the same person and can only
be linked through the general consistency of the content underlined.</p>
            <note id="n41">21. The authors are indebted to G. E. Bentley, Jr., for recommending these specific
comparisons.</note>
            <pb id="p44-97" n="97"/>
            <figure n="bb74.1.1.ms" id="bb74.1.ms.01" work-copy="bb74.1" rend="db" width="605" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>FITZWILLIAM<lb/>
              MUSEUM<lb/>
              <lb/>
              In the Moon, is a certain Island near by a mighty continent, which small<lb/>
              island seems to have some affinity to England, &amp; what is more extraordinary the<lb/>
              people are so much alike &amp; their language so much the same that you would<lb/>
              think you was among your friends. in this Island dwells three Philosophers<lb/>
              Suction, the Epicurean, Quid the Cynic, &amp; Sipsop the Pythagorean. I call them<lb/>
              by the names of those sects tho’ the sects are not ever mentiond there as being<lb/>
              quite out of date however the things still remain, and the vanities are the<lb/>
              same. the three Philosophers sat together thinking of nothing. in comes -<lb/>
              Etruscan Column the Antiquarian &amp; after an abundance of Enquiries to<lb/>
              no purpose sat himself down &amp; described something that nobody listend to<lb/>
              so they were employd when Mrs Gimblet came in              the corners of her<lb/>
              mouth seemd I dont know how. but very odd as if she hoped you had not<lb/>
              an ill opinion of her. to be sure we are all poor creatures, well she seated<lb/>
              &amp; seemd to listen with great attention while the Antiquarian seemd<lb/>
              to be talking of virtuous cats. but it was not so. she was thinking of<lb/>
              the shape of her eyes &amp; mouth &amp; he was thinking. of his eternal fame<lb/>
              the three Philosophers at this time were each endeavouring to conceal<lb/>
              his laughter. (not at them but) at his own imagination, this was the situation<lb/>
              of this improving company. when in a great hurry, Inflammable Gass<lb/>
              the Wind finder. enterd. they seemd to rise &amp; salute each other<lb/>
              Etruscan Column &amp; Inflammable Gass. fixd their eyes on each other. their<lb/>
              tongues went in question &amp; answer, but their thoughts were otherwise employd<lb/>
              I dont like his eyes said Etruscan Column. he’s a foolish puppy said<lb/>
              Inflammable Gass, smiling on him. the 3 Philosophers        the Cynic<lb/>
              smiling the Epicurean seeming studying the flame of the candle &amp;<lb/>
              the Pythagorean playing with the cat. listend with open mouths to the<lb/>
              edifying discourses.<lb/>
              Sir said the Antiquarian I have seen these works &amp; I do affirm that they<lb/>
              are no such thing. they seem to me to be the most wretched paltry flimsy Stuff<lb/>
              that ever ___ What d’ye say What dye say said Inffammable Gass, why<lb/>
              why I wish I could see you write so. Sir said the Antiquarian. according<lb/>
              to my opinion. the author is an errant blockhead.__ Your reason Your reason<lb/>
              said Inflammable Gass_ why why I think it very abominable to call a man<lb/>
              a blockhead that you know nothing of._ . Reason Sir said the A[n]tiquarian<lb/>
              I’ll’ give you an example for your reason As I was walking        ng the<lb/>
                            vast<lb/>
              street I saw a ^ number of swallows on the rails of an<lb/>
              old Gothic square they seemd to be going on their passage, as Pliny says<lb/>
              as I was looking up. a little outré fellow pulling me by the sleeve cries<lb/>
              pray Sir who do all they belong to, I turnd myself about with great</figTranscr>
              <figDesc>4. Blake, <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, p. 1. © Fitzwilliam Museum,
Cambridge. Image courtesy of the <hi rend="i">William Blake Archive</hi>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p44-98" n="98"/>
            <table>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi></hi></cell>
                <cell><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi></hi></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Capital letters</cell>
                <cell>“B” in “Blank” (two instances)</cell>
                <cell>“Bible” (pp. 3, 4); “Before” (p. 7)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="Blank1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="308" height="100"><figTranscr>Blank</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="Blank2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="319" height="100"><figTranscr>Blank</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="Bible1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="117" height="60"><figTranscr>Bible</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="Bible2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="103" height="50"><figTranscr>Bible</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="Before.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="202" height="100"><figTranscr>Before</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“E” in “Eng.”</cell>
                <cell>“Epicurean,” “Etruscan,” “Enquiries”<lb/>
                (p. 1, first instances)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="Eng.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="129" height="150"><figTranscr>Eng.</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="Epicurean.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="145" height="60"><figTranscr>Epicurean</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="Etruscan.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="154" height="50"><figTranscr>Etruscan</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="Enquiries.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="135" height="50"><figTranscr>Enquiries</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“R” in “Rhyme”</cell>
                <cell>“Reason” (p. 1)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="Rhyme.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="317" height="125"><figTranscr>Rhyme</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="Reason.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="115" height="50"><figTranscr>Reason</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“T” in “There”</cell>
                <cell>“Tactics,” “Theology,” “Tilly”<lb/>
                (p. 3, first instances)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="There.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="186" height="100"><figTranscr>There</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="Tactics.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="124" height="50"><figTranscr>Tactics</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="Theology.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="143" height="70"><figTranscr>Theology</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="Tilly.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="83" height="50"><figTranscr>Tilly</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <p>Editor’s note: The words from <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> were scanned at 500%
from the Bodleian’s photograph of page vii, then enhanced with Adobe Photoshop to darken the handwriting and
lighten the background, and reduced to 350% of the original size. The samples from <hi rend="i">An Island in
the Moon</hi> were cropped from the <hi rend="i">William Blake Archive</hi>’s scans, then enlarged to 150%
of the original. The Bodleian Libraries, University of Oxford (Arch. H e.181), and © Fitzwilliam Museum,
Cambridge, respectively; <hi rend="i">Island</hi> images courtesy of the <hi rend="i">William Blake
Archive</hi>.</p>
            <pb id="p44-99" n="99"/>
            <table>
              <row>
                <cell>Ascenders and descenders</cell>
                <cell>“d” in “good” (four instances)</cell>
                <cell>“odd” (p. 1)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="good1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="153" height="100"><figTranscr>good</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="good2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="192" height="90"><figTranscr>good</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="good3.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="164" height="100"><figTranscr>good</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="good4.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="142" height="100"><figTranscr>good</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="odd.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="52" height="40"><figTranscr>odd</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“many”</cell>
                <cell>“many” (pp. 12, 13)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="many1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="256" height="90"><figTranscr>many</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="many2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="102" height="40"><figTranscr>many</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="many3.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="88" height="40"><figTranscr>many</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“of” (two instances)</cell>
                <cell>“of” (p. 1, first three instances)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="of1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="91" height="110"><figTranscr>of</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="of2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="90" height="100"><figTranscr>of</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="of3.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="53" height="55"><figTranscr>of</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="of4.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="58" height="60"><figTranscr>of</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="of5.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="55" height="55"><figTranscr>of</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“poet”</cell>
                <cell>“purpose” (for “p”, p. 1); “Poet” (p. 6)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="poet.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="185" height="100"><figTranscr>poet</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="purpose.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="132" height="50"><figTranscr>purpose</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="Poet2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="99" height="50"><figTranscr>Poet</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
            </table>
              <pb id="p44-100" n="100"/>
            <table>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“who” (two instances)</cell>
                <cell>“who” (p. 1)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="who1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="138" height="60"><figTranscr>who</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="who2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="164" height="70"><figTranscr>who</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="who3.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="76" height="50"><figTranscr>who</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“writing” (two instances)</cell>
                <cell>“writing” (p. 17)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="writing1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="230" height="120"><figTranscr>writing</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="writing2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="221" height="105"><figTranscr>writing</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="writing3.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="125" height="60"><figTranscr>writing</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Other words</cell>
                <cell>“a”</cell>
                <cell>“a” (p. 1, first three instances)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="a1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="42" height="30"><figTranscr>a</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="a2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="35" height="30"><figTranscr>a</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="a3.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="38" height="30"><figTranscr>a</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="a4.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="42" height="30"><figTranscr>a</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“verse” (two instances)</cell>
                <cell>“verses” (p. 9)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="verse1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="197" height="40"><figTranscr>verse</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="verse2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="177" height="45"><figTranscr>verse</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="verses.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="111" height="35"><figTranscr>verses</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>“capability”</cell>
                <cell>“abilities” (p. 17, three instances)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="capability.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="348" height="100"><figTranscr>ii<lb/> capability</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <figure n="abilities1.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="177" height="60"><figTranscr>abilities</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="abilities2.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="134" height="50"><figTranscr>abilities</figTranscr></figure><lb/>
                  <figure n="abilities3.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="152" height="50"><figTranscr>abilities</figTranscr></figure>
                </cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <pb id="p44-101" n="101"/>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title><hi rend="b">V. Content of the Annotations</hi></title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake is perhaps best known for marginalia that are fiery and indignant, such as the scornful
comments in the margins of his copy of Sir Joshua Reynolds’s <hi rend="i">Discourses</hi>. However, he
refers to another style of annotation in his copy of Lavater’s 1788 <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man:</hi>
			<q>I hope no one will call what I have written cavilling because he may think my remarks of
small consequence For I write from the warmth of my heart. &amp; cannot resist the impulse I feel to rectify
what I think false in a book I love so much. &amp; approve so generally<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">23</ref></q>
              The marginalia in the Bodleian copy of <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi> similarly convey a
tone of friendly correction and general as- sent. Another similarity lies in the long, rough Xs that appear in
the margins of pages 5 and 6, a feature known to have been used by Blake as his “mark of
uneasiness.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">24</ref> The annotator appears
to have worked attentively, frequently lifting the pen to underscore or double-underscore particular words and
clauses rather than quickly running the pen under whole lines at a time. The apparent purpose of the
underlining was to anthologize passages that aroused the annotator’s interest. There is no way of knowing
whether the marks in pen and pencil were made by the same person, but the material to which the annotator is
drawn seems consistent.</p>
            <note id="n42">23. E 600. See also H. J. Jackson, <hi rend="i">Marginalia: Readers Writing in
Books</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2001) 82.</note>
            <note id="n43">24. See E 583.</note>
            <p>This concluding section offers some ideas about how the marginalia in <hi rend="i">Mystical
Initiations</hi>, if accepted as authentic, correlate with Blake’s thought in the late 1780s. Discussion is
by page number of Taylor’s book, with handwritten annotations and some of the most interesting underlinings
examined first. Other comments follow in ascending page order.</p>
            <div4>
              <p>P. vii (see illus. 1, 3): This annotation has a lilt like Blake’s, and its substance
carries the conviction of someone who has written poetry.</p>
              <p>Like many writers of the romantic period, Blake considered blank verse superior to rhyme.
Geoffrey Hartman notes that Blake’s use of this meter in the <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> of 1783 is
				<q>unusual, not only for its personality (the free enjambments, the energetic beat) but also
for its very presence in short poems. Not until the 1790’s will Southey, Coleridge, and Wordsworth
experiment with <hi rend="i">lyrics</hi> in blank verse.	With certain important exceptions, unrhymed lyrics
before Blake were obvious imitations of the classics or paraphrases of the Psalms, so that Blake’s choice of
verse may signify an “ancient liberty recover’d” and evoke the prophetic portions of both
traditions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">25</ref></q></p>
              <note id="n44">25. <hi rend="i">Beyond Formalism: Literary Essays 1958-1970</hi> (New Haven:
Yale University Press, 1970) 194.</note>
              <p>Later, in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (1804-20), Blake would reject even blank verse as too
fettered. His introductory statement “To the Public” alludes to “English Blank Verse, derived from ...
Rhyming” (pl. 3, E 145), perhaps echoing the hierarchy of verse forms suggested in the annotation.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>P. viii (see illus. 2): The annotator attacks translators as pedants, altering Taylor’s
phrase to say that authors suffer by translation “because [it is] undertaken by men, who have devoted the
greatest part of their lives to the study of words alone.”</p>
              <p>Blake’s view of translation might be epitomized by biblical phrases that he imports into
the first plate of his 1825 <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, “The Letter Killeth I The
Spirit giveth Life” (2 Corinthians 3.6) and “It is Spiritually Discerned” (1 Corinthians 2.14). He
valued translations that conveyed the spiritual more than the literal qualities of their originals, as the
annotator seems to suggest here.</p>
              <p>Taylor likely would have sympathized. His translations are notoriously loose, and he argues
against the mischief of emphasizing words rather than ideas in both the preface to <hi rend="i">Mystical
Initiations</hi> and, at greater length, in his introduction to Plotinus’s <hi rend="i">Concerning the
Beautiful</hi>.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">26</ref> Taylor’s
diversions from literality provoked great criticism from the intellectuals of his time. However, as one of his
defenders, G. R. S. Mead, asserted in the late nineteenth century, “what was true of his critics then is
true of his critics today: though they may know more Greek, he knew more Plato.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">27</ref></p>
              <note id="n45">26. Taylor also directly references “mischief” on page 225 of 
<hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi>: “The mischief, indeed, resulting from the study of words is almost too
apparent to need any illustration.”</note>
              <note id="n46">27. Thomas Taylor, <hi rend="i">Select Works of Plotinus</hi>, ed. Mead (London:
George Bell &amp; Sons, 1895) ix, quoted in Kathleen Raine and George Mills Harper, eds., <hi rend="i">Thomas
Taylor the Platonist: Selected Writings</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1969) 22-23.</note>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>P. 69: A curious correction: the annotator changes the gender of the being that “previously
comprehended ... every virtue” from the “divinity ... himself” to the “divinity ... itself,”
apparently suggesting that androgyny is requisite to such a divinity. If Blake is the annotator, this perhaps
could be linked to the assertion on plate 11 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> that “All
deities reside in the human breast” (E 38). If the “divinity which previously comprehended ... every
virtue” resides within individuals, its sex cannot be restricted.</p>
            </div4>
            <p>Some of the most interesting underlinings are as follows:</p>
            <div4>
              <p>P. 1: The annotator has underlined the phrase “<hi rend="u">obscurity</hi> ... 
<hi rend="u">affords very little matter</hi>,” which is reminiscent of Blake’s annotation to Reynolds,
“Obscurity is Neither the Source of the Sublime nor of any Thing Else” (E 658).</p>
              <p>Blake asserts in his Reynolds marginalia that “when very Young” he had rejected Edmund
Burke’s <hi rend="i">Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful</hi>
(1757), which stresses the value of obscurity in art (E 660).</p></div4>
              <pb id="p44-102" n="102"/>
            <div4>
              <p>P. 70: Some of the most noticeable and continuous underlining in the book highlights
Taylor’s metaphor for the “power of prayer,” culminating with
			<q><hi rend="u">one<lb/>
              chord trembling from the pulsation of<lb/>
              another, as if it were endued with sensa-<lb/>
              tion from symphon</hi>y. S<hi rend="u">o in the universe,<lb/>
              there is one harmony though composed<lb/>
              from contraries</hi> ....</q>
                It almost seems redundant to recite Blake’s famous maxim from <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi>, “Without Contraries is no progression” (E 34). Blake describes contraries in
Jerusalem (pls. 10 and 17) as differences or oppositions that complement rather than negate, and in that sense
they agree with Taylor’s use of the term here. “Pulsation” is similarly evocative. When Blake describes
the “Moment” of artistic inspiration in Milton (pls. 28-29, E 126-27) he repeatedly equates it to a
“pulsation of the artery.”</p>
              <p>The content of this annotated passage calls to mind Coleridge’s 1795 poem, <hi rend="i">The
Eolian Harp</hi>. It also has an analogy in the aforementioned reference to Taylor’s mystical experience,
wherein, he indicates, his soul had “spontaneously utter[ed] musical sounds, as indications of the harmony
within.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">28</ref></p>
              <note id="n47">28. See note 13, above.</note>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>Pp. 75-76: Taylor’s discussion of heliotropes, or plants that turn toward the sun, is
largely translated from Proclus. Harper suggests this as the source of Blake’s “Ah! Sun-Flower” in a
1953 article later incorporated into <hi rend="i">The Neoplatonism of William Blake</hi>. Harper asserts that
in Taylor’s presentation of the Plotinian doctrine of emanation, “everything in the universe participates
in the first good—usually symbolized by the sun, the properties of which are everywhere apparent in the
phenomenal world.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">29</ref> This concept of
an “alliance between ‘natural things’ and occult power” is presented in Blake’s opening verse:
				<q>Ah Sun-flower! weary of time,<lb/>
                  Who countest the steps of the Sun:<lb/>
                  Seeking after that sweet golden clime<lb/>
                  Where the travellers journey is done.</q>
                The second stanza extends the concept to “man, who, after all, is separated from the flower
only in degree, not in kind”:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">30</ref>
				<q>Where the Youth pined away with desire,<lb/>
                  And the pale Virgin shrouded in snow:<lb/>
                  Arise from their graves and aspire,<lb/>
                  Where my Sun-flower wishes to go. (E 25)</q>
                The poem is a pure aspiration, consisting of two exhaled clauses rather than statements
employing verbs in the usual sense. In Harper’s interpretation the poem likens humanity to the sunflower,
anchored in the material world yet “aspir[ing] to the sun’s eternality.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">31</ref></p>
              <note id="n48">29. Harper 119.</note>
              <note id="n49">30. Harper 119, 120.</note>
              <note id="n50">31. Harper 120.</note>
              <p>There is no known manuscript of “Ah! Sun-Flower.” If Blake was the annotator, these
underlinings shed further light on the poem’s philosophical roots.</p>
            </div4>
            <p>Some other observations:</p>
            <div4>
              <p>P. v: These and other anti-materialistic statements marked in <hi rend="i">Mystical
Initiations</hi> might be related to Blake’s 1788 tracts <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> and
<hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>Pp. 2-3: This genealogy of theology is reminiscent of that expressed in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, pl. 11.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>Pp. 9-10: The story of a tyrant king’s son unable to control the lyre of Orpheus would have
had obvious attractions for Blake as a revolutionary poet.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>Pp. 14-15: A passage underlined in brown-black ink likens the deity to “an immense and
perpetually exuberant fountain; whose streams originally filled and continually replenish the world with
life.” Harper links this passage to Blake in <hi rend="i">The Neoplatonism of William Blake</hi>.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">32</ref> If the poet was the annotator, this
underlining lends support to the idea that the same person probably marked the book in brown-black and
orange-brown ink. (There is also the possibility that the ink is the same, but appears darker where the pen
was redipped.)</p>
              <note id="n51">32. Harper 123.</note>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>P. 19: “Soul,” here marked heavily, is underlined five times in this text. The annotator
seems attracted to passages about animating energies. Could this reflect Blake’s contemplation of
metempsychosis in the wake of his brother Robert’s death in 1787?</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>P. 26: That the annotator does not underline Greek text but marks its English translation is
consistent with the practice of Blake, who is thought not to have been proficient in Greek until 1803.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <p>P. 78: Blake uses the lotus as a symbol of evanescence in <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>
(1789).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">33</ref></p>
              <note id="n52">33. Harper 122.</note>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    </text>
      </TEI.2>