<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-44" status="new">
    <idno>44.3.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2010-11</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2010-2011</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">44.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2010-2011"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_44">
    <front id="issue_03">
      <pb id="p44-81-82" n="81-82"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.044.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="342">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
          AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            Found in the Bodleian:<lb/>
            Blake’s Copy of Thomas Taylor’s <hi rend="i">Mystical Initiations</hi>?<lb/>
          VOLUME 44<lb/>
          NUMBER 3<lb/>
          WINTER 2010-11</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-3-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="3" cols="5">
          <row>
          	<cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>CONTENTS</title>
        	  </head>
          	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="44.3.cardinale">A Newly Discovered Blake Book: William Blake’s
Copy of Thomas Taylor’s <hi rend="i">The Mystical Initiations; or, Hymns of Orpheus</hi> (1787)</ref><lb/>
              <hi rend="i">By Philip J. Cardinale and Joseph R. Cardinale</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">84</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell>
          		<hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
          	</cell>
          	<cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell><ref type="article" issue="44.3.essick">Martin Butlin, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Watercolour Inventions in Illustration of</hi> The Grave <hi rend="i">by Robert Blair</hi>; William Blake, 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, a Portfolio of Eighteen Facsimile Impressions (Flying
Horse Editions)</ref><lb/>
          	  <hi rend="i">Reviewed by Robert N. Essick</hi>
          	</cell>
          	<cell>
          		<hi rend="i">103</hi>
          	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell>
          		<ref type="article" issue="44.3.rovira">Michael Phillips and the Infernal Method of William Blake,
Cornell Fine Arts Museum, Rollins College, 12 September 2009-3 January 2010</ref><lb/>
          		<hi rend="i">Reviewed by James Rovira</hi>
          	</cell>
          	<cell>
          		<hi rend="i">110</hi>
          	</cell>
            </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Zürich</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p44-83" n="83"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>PHILIP CARDINALE (drpjcardinale@gmail.com) is an intellectual property law attorney specializing in
copyright law at Drinker Biddle &amp; Reath LLP in Washington, DC. He holds a doctorate in English literature
from Oxford University.</p>
        <p>JOSEPH CARDINALE (josephcardinale@hotmail.com) is a doctoral candidate in creative writing at the
University of Hawaii (Manoa) and holds an MFA from the University of Massachusetts (Amherst). His book of
creative fiction, <hi rend="i">The Size of the Universe</hi>, was published by FC2 in October 2010.</p>
        <p>ROBERT N. ESSICK has been collecting and writing about Blake for over forty years.</p>
        <p>JAMES ROVIRA (jamesrovira@gmail.com) is assistant professor of English and program chair of
Humanities at Tiffin University in Tiffin, Ohio. His monograph, <hi rend="i">Blake and Kierkegaard: Creation
and Anxiety</hi>, is now available from the Continuum International Publishing Group.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Alexander S. Gourlay</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY
14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sarah.jones@rochester.edu<lb/>
 TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Alexander S. Gourlay, Department of English, Rhode Island School of Design, 2 College Street,
Providence RI 02903-2717<lb/>
Email: agourlay@risd.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham
NG11 8NS UK<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
            <div1 id="BQ-44-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $66 for institutions, $33 for individuals.
All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments
received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the US, Canada, and
Mexico require a $20 per volume postal surcharge for airmail delivery. Credit card payment is available. Make
checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and
related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of
Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for information on issues
and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
              <p>Please send submissions in electronic form, documented according to the <hi rend="i">MLA
Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to either of the editors.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x.<lb/>
        <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s
International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English
Language and Literature, Humanities International Complete, Arts and Humanities Citation Index, Current
Contents, Scopus, and the Bibliography of the History of Art.</p>
        <p>© 2011 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
              <p>Cover: Thomas Taylor, <hi rend="i">The Mystical Initiations; or, Hymns of Orpheus</hi>
(London, 1787), detail of p. vii. The Bodleian Libraries, University of Oxford (Arch. H e.181).</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    </text>
      </TEI.2>