<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-44" status="new">
    <idno>44.3.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Martin Butlin, ed., William Blake’s Watercolour Inventions in Illustration of
The Grave by Robert Blair; William Blake, Songs of Innocence and of Experience, a Portfolio of Eighteen
Facsimile Impressions (Flying Horse Editions)</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2010-11</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2010-2011</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">44.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2010-2011"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_44">
    <body>
      <pb id="p44-103" n="103"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">William Blake’s Watercolour Inventions in Illustration of</hi>
The Grave <hi rend="i">by Robert Blair</hi>. Edited with Essays and Commentary by Martin Butlin and an Essay
on the Poem by Morton D. Paley. Lavenham, Suffolk: William Blake Trust, 2009. 186 copies printed for sale, of
which 36, numbered I-XXXVI, are quarter bound in calf to accompany a replica of the original portfolio
containing the 19 now-dispersed “Designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>” reproduced in facsimile
and mounted like the originals. Copies numbered 1-150 for sale without the replica portfolio. 95 pp., 62
illus. £2500 for the issue with the replica portfolio containing an additional suite of reproductions; £295
for the volume alone. Distributed worldwide by John Windle, Antiquarian Bookseller, San Francisco.</title>
            <title type="main">William	Blake.	<hi rend="i">Songs	of Innocence	and	of Experience</hi>. A
Portfolio of Eighteen Facsimile Impressions. Orlando: Flying Horse Editions, University of Central Florida,
2009. With “A Note on Production” by Michael Phillips. 33 copies printed, plus 3 printer’s proofs and 1
archive copy.	Accompanying paperback booklet 36 pp., 10 illus. $1950.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>THESE two publications appeared within days of each other in fall 2009. Although there are many
differences between them, both are elegant works, of interest to collectors of fine books as well as Blake
enthusiasts, and both are major contributions to the long and fascinating history of reproducing Blake’s
art. Although reviews generally focus on the verbal contents of books, while ignoring (or only mentioning in
passing) their physical containers, the visual impact and even tactile nature of these publications are part
of their significance.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">1</ref></p>
          <note id="n53">1. In the interest of full disclosure, let me point out that the Blake Trust sent me
a complimentary copy of the issue with portfolio, “O.o.s” (out of series).	Flying Horse Editions sold me
copy no. 1 at a reduced, pre-publication price. I had a minor role in assisting the Blake Trust acquire
digital files for its publication; I have had e-mail correspondence with Theo Lotz, director of Flying Horse
Editions, and Michael Phillips about their publication.</note>
          <p>The William Blake Trust has a distinguished record as the last century’s foremost publisher of
reproductions of Blake’s works. In association with the Trianon Press, the trust produced a series of color
facsimiles of the illuminated books, beginning with <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in 1951 and concluding with
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> in 1976. These limited editions, generally bound in quarter leather over
marbled boards, were produced through a combination of collotype and hand coloring through stencils. The trust
concluded its efforts using these processes in 1987 with the publication of Blake’s various illustrations of
the Book of Job. In the 1990s, the trust shifted its focus toward a more affordable series of six volumes
featuring more extensive scholarly apparatus and commercially produced, but high-quality, color reproductions.
The trust’s latest publication, reproducing Blake’s watercolor illustrations for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, combines the limited-edition features (and prices) of its first series with the
commercial reproductions of the second—but based on digital files rather than color transparencies.
Sophisticated ink-jet technology was employed in printing the illustrations.</p>
          <p>The edition of the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors with the additional suite of reproductions
is more sumptuous than even the Blake Trust/Trianon Press facsimiles. The volume is bound by the distinguished
firm of Smith Settle (Yeadon, West Yorkshire) in quarter maroon calf over boards covered in black moiré silk,
the spine lettered in gilt, the front cover bearing a maroon calf label also lettered in gilt.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">2</ref> The cover label is decorated with a skull and
crossbones device, repeated on the title page. This is appropriate for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, but also
brings to mind the Jolly Roger. I’m confident, however, that there is nothing piratical about the trust’s
publication. The top edges of the leaves, 37.2 × 27.0 cm., are gilt. The text and illustrations are
exceptionally well printed on 200-gram archival paper. The real treat is the accompanying portfolio, a
reproduction of the wallet-style portfolio in which nineteen of the watercolors were discovered in 2001 after
an absence of 165 years. The original was offered as the last lot in the auction of the watercolors at
Sotheby’s New York, 2 May 2006. It was knocked down to John Windle, the San Francisco book dealer who is
also the distributor of the Blake Trust <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, for $4,200 and is now in a California private
collection. The main differences between the original portfolio and the re-creation are
            the inclusion of an inner paper folder (complete with cover label) to enclose the mounted plates,
a pull ribbon, the use of calf rather than morocco, and the lack of wear on the new portfolio (I am tempted to
do a bit of antiquing). The volume and the portfolio are housed together in a black moiré silk slipcase.
Depending on one’s tastes, this is either an overly
          <pb id="p44-104" n="104"/>
            rich soufflé or the sort of splendid treatment Blake’s works deserve. I am of the latter
opinion, for the packaging does not overwhelm the contents.</p>
          <note id="n54">2. I have not seen the issue without the additional suite of illustrations in
portfolio, but the prospectus indicates that the volume is bound in silk without the quarter calf.</note>
          <p>As John Commander, executive director of the Blake Trust, explains in a brief foreword, the
raison d’être of the publication is the full-color reproduction of the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors,
now widely dispersed in private and institutional collections. To the group of nineteen recently rediscovered
drawings is added <hi rend="i">Prone on the Lowly Grave—She Drops</hi>, sometimes titled <hi rend="i">The
Widow Embracing Her Husband’s Grave</hi>. Now in the Yale Center for British Art, this watercolor is on the
same type of mount as the others and must have once been part of the set of “20” which Robert Hartley
Cromek, who commissioned Blake’s designs for an illustrated edition of Blair’s poem, “proposes [to] have
engraved.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">3</ref> This main sequence,
reproduced
            <figure n="BlakeGraveBook.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="198"/>
            in color “at approximately 98% of the originals’ size” (29), includes the framing lines on
nineteen of the mounts to which the watercolors are affixed and is supplemented by twenty-nine illustrations,
mostly in color, of related works. The volume also includes a reproduction on a reduced scale of the text of
Cromek’s 1808 edition of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, followed by almost full-size reproductions of
Blake’s twelve illustrations etched and engraved by Louis Schiavonetti, plus the frontispiece portrait of
Blake (Schiavonetti after Thomas Phillips). The plates are in the second published state appearing in the
quarto issue of the 1808 edition. The additional suite of reproductions appropriately includes only the
nineteen watercolors found in the original portfolio, each mounted like the originals on thick card. The
title-page design extends to the edges of its backing mat; the mounts for all the other designs are, like the
originals, inscribed with framing lines. When I first saw the newly discovered <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
watercolors in London in 2002, they were spread out on a large table. The Blake Trust portfolio permits repeat
performances of that amazing sight.</p>
          <note id="n55">3. John Flaxman’s letter to William Hayley of 18 Oct. 1805, quoted in G. E.
Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2004) [hereafter 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)] 207.</note>
          <p>The reproductions of the twenty <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors are excellent. Based on
high-resolution digital files, the illustrations lend an almost relief appearance to Blake’s fine pen and
ink outlining. I suspect, however, that the paper in the title-page design, <hi rend="i">Friendship</hi>, and
<hi rend="i">Prone on the Lowly Grave</hi> has shifted to a hue slightly browner than the originals. Capturing
paper tone is always very difficult; getting it right often results in misrepresenting some other colors. A
more significant problem in my copy is that three of the reproductions in the bound volume (but not in the
portfolio) have been trimmed along one or more of their margins. The toes on the right foot of the descending
trumpeter have been cut off at the top margin of the title page. In <hi rend="i">The Meeting of a Family in
Heaven</hi>, the foot of the hovering angel on the left, most of the left foot of the angel on the right, and
most of the right foot of the boy lower right have been amputated. The top of the head of the fleeing soul in
<hi rend="i">Death of the Strong Wicked Man</hi> has been lowered. As noted, the original title page is
mounted to the edge of its backing, but all the other reproductions in the volume include the ruled lines on
the backing mounts as part of a single image, and thus these trimmings of the watercolors within the ruled
lines are difficult to explain. Windle, the distributor of the work, has told me that these faults, having
been identified in a preliminary run of copies not for sale, were rectified and are not present in regularly
numbered copies. Other, less significant, differences between the reproductions in the bound volume and in the
portfolio, such as the darkness of the foxing evident in the originals, teach us once again that no two
reproductions of the same object are ever identical, even within the same publication.</p>
          <pb id="p44-105" n="105"/>
          <p>I have compared the images in the Blake Trust volume to two of the originals, <hi rend="i">The
Death of the Good Old Man</hi> and <hi rend="i">Heaven’s Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In</hi>, both in my
collection. It is very difficult to tell them apart. If I were truly conservation-minded I would take the
originals off the wall and replace them with the reproductions. Nobody would notice. I have also been able to
compare one of the supplementary illustrations, Blake’s white-line etching of “Deaths Door,” to the
unique impression of the original. The reproduction is a bit darker and obscures the rolled mat or bedding
within the tomb, but the velvety texture of its black ink makes it look like another—and
better?—impression from Blake’s copperplate on much the same paper as the original, time-darkened to a
light tan. Should you see a second “original” impression of “Deaths Door” on the market, be suspicious
that it is the Blake Trust reproduction cut out of the book.</p>
          <p>Blake scholars are now in the fortunate position of having three complete color reproductions of
the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors: Sotheby’s 2 May 2006 auction catalogue, the online 
<hi rend="i">William Blake Archive</hi> &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;, edited by Morris Eaves, Joseph
Viscomi, and this reviewer, and the Blake Trust publication. The last two add <hi rend="i">Prone on the Lowly
Grave</hi> to the nineteen offered by Sotheby’s; the archive illustrations do not include the framing lines
on the backing mats. The archive arranges the designs according to the sequence of the passages illustrated,
with those not based on any specific passage grouped at the end. The Blake Trust sequences the designs
published in 1808 according to their order in that work, followed by the unpublished designs. Sotheby’s
arranged its lots so that the most valuable objects would fall in the middle of the sale—apparently in a
failed attempt to maximize prices (the drawings with the highest estimates did not sell). The reproductions
are exceptionally good for an auction catalogue, but have the most color shifts. The archive images were made
from the same color transparencies used by the auction house, but corrected according to notes Joe Viscomi
made in his copy of the catalogue while comparing its reproductions to the originals. Because the archive
images are backlit on a monitor, the colors tend to be more saturated, and hence the paper and paler washes
lighter, than either the originals or the Blake Trust illustrations. This inevitable distortion highlights
certain very thin washes, such as the yellows and reds in <hi rend="i">The Reunion of the Soul and the
Body</hi>. The archive images also reveal a good deal more of the foxing and staining on the watercolors,
particularly on <hi rend="i">The Meeting of a Family in Heaven</hi>. I wonder if some of the Blake Trust
digital files were cleaned up a bit in Adobe Photoshop. The 300dpi enlargements available in the archive are
unsurpassed for the study of details, the closest approach to viewing the originals with a powerful magnifying
glass. The Blake Trust illustrations are not suitable for similar levels of magnification because they will
dissolve into a dot-matrix pattern, the paper-print equivalent of pixelation in a digital image. Each
reproductive technology has its own virtues and its own limitations.</p>
          <p>The dazzling pictorial contents of the volume should not be allowed to hinder attention to the
accompanying texts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">4</ref> Morton Paley’s
brief essay, “William Blake and Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>,” builds fruitfully on his
1982 coauthored book.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">5</ref> He offers some
new information about Philip Doddridge’s involvement in the composition and publication of Blair’s poem.
Paley also proposes that Blake “sympathized with the evangelicism of the poem” (10) and suggests that we
consider Blake’s responses to it within the context of his “conversionary experiences during the years
1801-03” (11) and the impact of those experiences on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>. The white-line etching of “Deaths Door” is singled out as expressing a sense of
“inner rebirth” and an “almost primitive sense of death and resurrection” (11), but what other designs
can be related to Blake’s religious beliefs? The essay ends abruptly, leaving me wanting more, much more,
about this fascinating thesis.</p>
          <note id="n56">4. A few typos crept into the text, including “reseaches” (for “researches”)
in the “Editor’s Acknowledgements” (7). Would it be mere pedantry for me to suggest that the second
“of” in the title <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> should not be omitted, as it is
on page 58?</note>
          <note id="n57">5. Essick and Paley, <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave 
<hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake: A Study with Facsimile</hi> (London: Scolar Press, 1982).</note>
          <p>Martin Butlin’s contributions, set forth with his usual clarity and precision, are divided into
three sections, “The History of Blake’s Illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>,” “The Newly
Discovered Watercolours,” and “The Watercolours: Catalogue and Commentary.” A good deal has been
written, both before and after the discoveries of 2001, about Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> project and
his relationship with Cromek; Butlin necessarily covers much of this material, particularly when factual in
nature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">6</ref> There is, however, some new
information and well-informed speculation, some of which might easily go unnoticed. For example, I believe
that this is the first recording of some of the watermarks: EDMEADS &amp; PINE in several of the watercolors,
JWHATMAN / 1800 on one mount, JWHATMAN without a date on two mounts, and JRUSE / 1800 on one mount (21). I was
also interested to learn that the “full-page design [for the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> title page] is mounted
on the same card as the rest of the newly discovered watercolours” (30).</p>
          <note id="n58">6. See particularly <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) and the Essick and Paley volume. Most of
the basic facts about the watercolors were previously published in Butlin, “New Risen from the Grave:
Nineteen Unknown Watercolors by William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 35.3 (winter 2001-02): 68-73, and in
the 2 May 2006 Sotheby’s auction catalogue.</note>
          <p>The watermarks and some of Butlin’s other perceptions about the backing mounts open up
interesting possibilities. He comments that “the fact that all of the watercolours are treated in the same
way suggests that this must have happened before Blake, or Cromek, knew that the number of engravings was
going to be cut down from the original twenty” (21). This is not necessarily the case. The suite of
watercolors, executed in fall 1805, may have been assembled and mounted in the next year as a unique
collection for sale independent of the 1808 book. The final break between illustrator and publisher did not
occur until May 1807, when Cromek refused Blake’s
          <pb id="p44-106" n="106"/>
            dedicatory design “To the Queen.” At least some involvement with the mounts on Blake’s part
is possible. <hi rend="i">Prone on the Lowly Grave</hi> is inscribed on the mount below the drawing “W.
Blake. del” and three lines are quoted from the poem. I believe that Butlin may be right when he states that
these inscriptions “would indeed appear to have been done by Blake himself” (68). Did Blake also produce
the mounts himself, including the framing lines in the so-called “French” style, possibly at Cromek’s
request? The watermarks, two of which include a date of 1800, show that the mounts were made with papers
familiar to Blake, for he used Whatman and Ruse &amp; Turners papers for many of his illuminated books and
drawings. By no later than 1821, Blake began to inscribe framing lines around the prints in some of his
illuminated books. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy V, available in the Blake
Archive, is a representative example.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">7</ref>
Blake has drawn, as with the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolor mounts, three framing lines (not counting an
outline contiguous with the edges of the image) on each page and added pale color washes between two of the
lines. Even if Blake did not personally mat and inscribe the frames for the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
watercolors, their treatment may have prompted his own later practices.</p>
          <note id="n59">7. Copy designations for the illuminated books follow G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977).</note>
          <p>Some of Butlin’s most interesting observations concern drawings related to Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> commission. <hi rend="i">A Destroying Deity</hi>, a watercolor in the Philadelphia Museum
of Art, can be associated in size and format with <hi rend="i">The Grave Personified</hi> as its “negative
counterpart” (54). This relationship continues the pairing of contrary companions found throughout Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs. As Butlin points out, the male figure in <hi rend="i">A Destroying Deity</hi>
may actually be a personification of Sin, as described on pages 26-27 of the 1808 <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>. He
does not take the final step of changing the title of this drawing to <hi rend="i">Sin Personified</hi>,
perhaps because Sin (as in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>) is “described as female” on page 27.</p>
          <p>Butlin tentatively proposes the deattribution of two drawings. He suspects that “the drawing
apparently from the Butts collection” of an ascending trumpeter (Yale Center for British Art), associated
with the descending angel in the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> title-page design, “is perhaps not by Blake”
(30), and that <hi rend="i">Death Pursuing the Soul through the Avenues of Life</hi> (Essick collection) “is
perhaps a pencil drawing gone over by someone else to make it more saleable in the later 19th century” (24).
Might the trumpeter be wholly or in part the work of Thomas Butts, father or son, when the latter was learning
etching from Blake, c. 1806-08? When sold at Sotheby’s, 22 March 1910, the drawing was grouped in lot 447
with “a number of engravings and drawings, by William Blake and some by T. Butts, his patron ....” I will
pursue the attribution of <hi rend="i">Death Pursuing</hi> in a separate essay; the Yale Center may have more
to say about its drawing.</p>
          <p>The title-page design also suffers a partial deattribution: “It is difficult to believe that
Blake himself could have written out the title [on the title-page watercolor] crediting the engravings to
Schiavonetti; one can only assume that the lettering was done either by Schiavonetti himself or by Cromek or
one of his assistants” (30). As Butlin points out, “Blake seems to have remained on relatively good terms
with Cromek well into 1807” (16), and thus well past the time when Blake must have known that he had been
replaced by Schiavonetti as the engraver.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">8</ref> The hand that inscribed the title page also inscribed the watercolor of an alternative
title page for “A Series of Designs: Illustrative of The Grave” (Huntington Library); both include an
“1806” date. The pen and ink used for the inscriptions appear to me to be the same used to outline many
motifs in the designs of both drawings; the lettering shows the same elegance as Blake’s so-called
“copperplate” hand in the <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> manuscript. The unusual formation of the lower-case
“g” with serif, particularly in the first line of the inscription on the Huntington drawing, and the
addition of a serif to the lowercase “s” in the same line, recall Blake’s calligraphy in the illuminated
books (for example, plate 3 in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>). Butlin may be right, but I
have only slight difficulty in believing that “Blake himself could have written out the title” in both
watercolors, even if reluctantly.</p>
          <note id="n60">8. The second prospectus names Schiavonetti as the engraver and is dated, like the
first, “Nov. 1805” (see Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 210-12, 214-15 for reproductions of both
prospectuses). Cromek must have delivered Blake’s watercolors to Schiavonetti by late 1805 or very early in
1806, for a proof of Schiavonetti’s “Death’s Door” plate, with the design completed, is dated
“Feb<hi rend="s">y</hi> 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> 1806” in the imprint.</note>
          <p>I have only one severe caveat about the Blake Trust’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>. The verso of its
title page includes the following in small type: “Design and production by John Commander.” I feel certain
that he was the guiding hand for the entire project. His bibliographic wit gave birth to the brilliant idea of
re-creating the original leather portfolio. Commander’s name should have been on the <hi rend="i">recto</hi>
of the title page.</p>
          <p></p>
          <p>The Flying Horse publication does not have the eye-catching richness of the 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> watercolors and their presentation by the Blake Trust, but it is certainly a handsome
object. The eighteen prints of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> are printed on the
rectos only of eighteen leaves, 19.5 × 14.l cm. These are fitted unbound into a re-creation of the buff paper
wrappers, with string stitched through three stabholes on the front cover only, into which Catherine Blake
bound some of her husband’s illuminated books—a nice touch roughly equivalent to the trust’s re-creation
of the leather portfolio. The prints and their wrapper are housed in a rectangular well that is sunk into the
right side of a triple-folding, four-section clamshell box, covered in finely woven dark-brown cloth, gilt
stamped on the back and with a beige cloth interior; the accompanying paperbound pamphlet, 19.4 × 13.9 cm.,
is fitted into a depression on the left side of the box. Some may find that the container, at 37.0 × 132.5
cm. when fully opened, is out of proportion to its contents. The raised panels holding the prints and booklet
measure a more modest 35.2 × 29.8 cm.</p>
          <pb id="p44-107" n="107"/>
          <figure n="FlyingHorsePortfolio.44.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="213"/>
          <p>As with the Blake Trust <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, the pictures are the main event in the Flying
Horse portfolio. These are the general title page from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
and, from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, the title page, “The Lamb,” “Holy Thursday,” “Nurse’s
Song,” “The Chimney Sweeper,” both plates of “A Cradle Song,” and “The Divine Image.” 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> contributed its title page, “The Tyger,” “Holy Thursday,” “Nurses Song,”
“The Chimney Sweeper,” “London,” “My Pretty Rose Tree” and its two companions on the same plate,
“The Human Abstract,” and “A Divine Image.” The last is printed in black, as is the only impression
definitely printed by Blake (<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy BB), all others in golden yellow ochre. As an
untitled, unsigned essay at the beginning of the accompanying booklet explains, the yellow ochre ink is based
on one that “Blake used in the first printing of the combined Songs” (7). The color accords with 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copies E and F (both probably printed 1789), and is a particularly close
match to the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> plates in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
copies B and D, printed in 1794 to join <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> plates printed earlier in raw
sienna.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">9</ref> Some of the 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> plates in copy E of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> are also from this first
printing in yellow ochre; the ochre ink in copy C is a bit darker. The graininess and subtle variations in
tone and texture of the Flying Horse prints replicate these characteristics in Blake’s own impressions.</p>
          <note id="n61">9. For ink colors and printing histories, see Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and
the Idea of the Book</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1993) 241-43, 267-75. Phillips dates the
printing of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy E to “about the same time” as “the combined 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in 1794” (25). Copies Band C of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> are available in
the <hi rend="i">Blake Archive</hi>.</note>
          <p>The contrast between the ivory paper and the yellow ochre ink is not strong. In his own early
copies of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Blake partly compensated for this by color printing and/or
hand coloring the designs. The monochrome prints in the Flying Horse edition do not have this advantage. I
wonder if the choice of ink color was the best. Blake also printed early impressions of 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> plates for copies of the combined Songs in green; that color would have made stronger
pictorial statements without violating historical considerations. Some prints made by Phillips in the early
1990s—I believe from copperplates the same as, or very similar to, those used by Flying Horse—in blue and
black inks have greater visual presence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">10</ref></p>
          <note id="n62">10. See the announcements for Phillips’s presentations to the Bibliographical
Society, 20 Nov. 1990 (<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> title page) and 17 Nov. 1992 (“Holy Thursday” from 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>). Both are on Whatman laid paper; my copy of the 1990 announcement has an “1801”
watermark. Phillips very kindly gave me impressions from his “London” copperplate in black ink, one on
laid paper and one on wove.</note>
          <p>The unsigned essay (5-8) and Phillips’s “Note on Production” (9-31) in the booklet provide
information about the Flying Horse impressions. They were “printed from relief etched copper plates made by
Michael Phillips ... using exact-size photo negatives of original monochrome impressions.” The “negatives
were modified to eliminate printing flaws in the original—such as poor inking, smudging and splattering—in
order to establish the clearest and most complete example.” “Further refinements” were made on the
copperplates “by scraping out unwanted details and adding missing ones” (5). “Each plate has been etched
in two stages” (6) to the “same shallow depths as the <hi rend="i">America</hi> fragment” (23)—that
is, the step-etched fragment of canceled plate a of <hi rend="i">America</hi> in the National Gallery of Art,
Washington, the only extant copperplate etched by Blake in relief. “The paper has been handmade to match the
color,
          <pb id="p44-108" n="108"/>
            texture, size and weight of the wove papers that Blake used for printing, the illuminated books.
The ink used to print this edition has been hand mixed for each plate from the same historic dry pigments that
we know Blake used—and approximates as closely as possible the colors and texture of many of the originals.
The facsimile relief etched plates have been inked using a leather-covered dauber, painstakingly building up
the ink in stages on the relief surfaces” (6). Three copies of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, B, C,
and D, were “used to guide the way in which each facsimile plate has been wiped and printed for this
edition” (6-7). “The inking of each plate with a leather dauber, and then wiping the plate ..., has
consistently taken more than 30 minutes, and considerably more with some plates, before an impression could be
taken” (23). The booklet includes four illustrations of the inking daubers, three in color.</p>
          <p>This wealth of information raises as many questions as it answers. Exactly which “original
monochrome impressions” were used as models? What is meant by “clearest and most complete example”?
Example of what? Why the fiddling with the negatives and the copperplates?</p>
          <p>To garner some answers, I e-mailed Phillips on 2 November 2009. His reply of the next day is both
generous and fascinating. The copperplates used by Flying Horse were selected from “over 30” produced by
Phillips in several stages over many years. Some of the plates began as photo-etchings based on the
electrotypes printed in Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 1863 and 1880. The
photographic negatives, and later the images etched in copper, were corrected on the basis of “more than one
impression of a plate ... until details that do not belong [in the copperplate image]—foul inking for
example—[are removed] and others that do and are not present—the tail of a letter or tiny element of a
design—are added in stop-out varnish by hand.” One such copperplate, the title page for 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, is reproduced in color in the booklet.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n63" type="note">11</ref> The sixteen Gilchrist prints could have supplied Phillips with models for
only nine or ten of his eighteen plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">12</ref> The other eight plates in the Flying Horse portfolio have their origin in, or at least
were corrected in response to, several copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> printed by Blake, including 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy U (Houghton Library) and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> copies O (Houghton Library) and BB (private collection). Phillips also consulted posthumous
copy a of the combined <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in the British Museum. His plate of “The Divine Image”
bears two letters from the platemaker’s mark in white line lower right, as in posthumous impressions. For
“A Divine Image,” he “used the [posthumous] impression in Geoffrey Keynes collection now in the
Fitzwilliam Museum and the impression present in copy BB.”</p>
          <note id="n63">11. This is probably the same copperplate exhibited by Phillips at Tate Britain, 9
Nov. 2000-11 Feb. 2001, and at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 27 Mar.-24 June 2001. The plate, and
several stages in its development, are illustrated in the catalogue; see Robin Hamlyn and Michael Phillips,
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: Tate Publishing, 2000) 105, 112.</note>
          <note id="n64">12. Gilchrist includes the title page for <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, but
that would seem to be a re-creation rather than an electrotype mold-made from Blake’s original copperplate.
If Phillips used this as the basis for his plate, it has been considerably modified in accord with Blake’s
impressions. The eight Phillips/Flying Horse plates not among the Gilchrist electrotypes are the general title
page, “Holy Thursday,” “The Chimney Sweeper,” and the second plate of “A Cradle Song” from 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, and “The Tyger,” “Nurses Song,” “The Chimney Sweeper,” and “A Divine
Image” from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>.</note>
          <p>I conclude from the booklet in the Flying Horse portfolio and Phillips’s e-mail that he has
tried to recover and re-create the images on Blake’s copperplates. Thus the “clearest and most complete
example” is a new copperplate that comes closest to Blake’s own. Surprisingly, this ambitious and worthy
goal is nowhere made explicit in the publication, even though it would seem to be one of the guiding
principles of the entire enterprise.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">13</ref>
Another goal, one that receives ample attention in the booklet, is the recovery and reenactment of Blake’s
inking and printing methods. When combined, these activities do not produce a “reproduction” or
“facsimile” as I wish to define them here. Phillips’s alterations in the negatives and copperplates mean
that no single impression by Blake (or by Frederick Tatham, the printer of posthumous impressions) is
reproduced. Nor are the relief plateaus and white-line incisions on Blake’s own (lost) copperplates
reproduced; rather, they are re-created. Impressions from those archaeological reconstructions are, in some
senses of the term, “original” prints. They are an attempt to come as close as possible to publishing a
new edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>.</p>
          <note id="n65">13. I would have printed “Blake’s Copperplates Re-created” as a sub-title in
the Flying Horse booklet. While experimenting with relief etching in the 1970s, I was tempted to undertake a
similar restoration, but took it no further than photo-etchings on zinc and copper without correcting these
plates against multiple original impressions to recover Blake’s copperplate images and texts. Impressions
from some of these plates, inked with a roller, were printed directly from the facsimile metal plates (not
reproduced photographically from impressions) in Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Relief Inventions</hi>
(Los Angeles: Press of the Pegacycle Lady, 1978).</note>
          <p>How can we evaluate the accuracy of Phillips’s reconstructions? Posthumous copies of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> offer some answers. They were printed rather flatly from the original copperplates and do
not contain the color printing, hand coloring, or special inking manipulations that grace Blake’s own
impressions but also diverge from the images etched in copper. Copy h, in my collection, contains fifty-seven
impressions of fifty-four plates, including “A Divine Image.” Many were poorly inked but printed with
considerable pressure; the resulting embossments create shallow molds of Blake’s copperplates as they
existed when Tatham was printing them c. 1832. These impressions provide a good benchmark by which to judge
the success of Phillips’s copperplates in re-creating the originals. Comparisons, with and without low-power
magnification, reveal only a few details that would appear to indicate differences between Phillips’s
copperplates and Blake’s:<lb/>
            “The Lamb.” The solid form on the ground lower right is differently shaped in the
original.<lb/>
            “Holy Thursday” (<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>). Horizontal white lines at the bottom are
differently configured.<lb/>
          <pb id="p44-109" n="109"/>
            “Nurse’s Song” (<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>). A bit of white-line work in the large leaf
above “rs” in the title may not be in the re-creation.<lb/>
            “The Divine Image.” Phillips’s plate may not have the same configuration of white lines in
the vine left of the final two stanzas.<lb/>
            “Holy Thursday” (<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>). The dot of the question mark at the end of
line 4 of the text is missing, as in the Gilchrist electrotype.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n66" type="note">14</ref> The outline between mountain and sky above and to the left of the standing
woman’s right hand is a single line in the original. This line is oddly fragmented, at least in the Flying
Horse impression from Phillips’s plate.<lb/>
            “London.” The hyphen is missing from “Chimney-sweepers” (line 9), as in the Gilchrist
electrotype.<lb/>
            Plate including “Ah! Sun-Flower.” The hyphen is missing from the title, as in the Gilchrist
electrotype.</p>
          <note id="n66">14. Differences between the electrotypes and Blake’s copperplates are listed in
Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1980) 95.</note>
          <p>All other differences, and perhaps even some of those listed above, can be accounted for by
variations in inking and the wiping of etching borders (following Blake’s own practice in the 1790s) in the
Flying Horse impressions. The “colophon” on a separate leaf in the Flying Horse publication states that
“the copper plates for this facsimile edition were made by Michael Phillips from original William Blake
impressions.” The repetition of characteristics indicative of the Gilchrist electrotypes and not Blake’s
own plates leads me to question this statement for three of the Phillips copperplates. These may have been
corrected in accord with “original William Blake impressions,” but the three details noted above
overlooked. The electrotype of “Holy Thursday” (<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>) is missing part of the
“n” in “rain” (line 14); the first plate of “A Cradle Song” lacks the first letter of “dreams”
(line 3). These elements are present in the Flying Horse impressions.</p>
          <p>Both the Flying Horse printer and Tatham, in his posthumous impressions, had difficulty capturing
Blake’s fine white- line work, as I was able to confirm by consulting reproductions of a few impressions by
Blake. Among the Flying Horse prints, this is a significant feature only in the second plate of “A Cradle
Song.” Several of the prints from Phillips’s copperplates would seem to reveal more of the original
copperplate image than Tatham’s prints, particularly in comparison to his miserably over-inked impression of
the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> title page in posthumous copy h. Similar inking and printing differences can
be found among Blake’s own impressions.</p>
          <p>Comparisons between the Flying Horse publication and the uncolored issue of the Manchester
Etching Workshop portfolio of 1983 are inevitable.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">15</ref> Phillips himself initiates such comparisons by noting, in the Flying Horse booklet, that
the Manchester copperplates were etched much more deeply than the <hi rend="i">America</hi> fragment and his
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> plates (33n2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">16</ref> Perhaps the similarity is accidental, but the Flying Horse folding box is covered in
brown cloth only slightly darker than the cloth covering the folding box housing the Manchester prints and
their accompanying paperbound booklet, <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated Prints</hi>, by
Joseph Viscomi. Both editions are printed on handmade paper produced specifically for their projects, the
Manchester leaves with a blind-embossed “Inv / WB” and some Flying Horse leaves showing a “WB”
watermark. Both sets were printed from photo-etched copperplates; sixteen of the Manchester plates, like some
of Phillips’s, used the Gilchrist electrotypes as prototypes, although in somewhat different ways.</p>
          <note id="n67">15. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
(Manchester: Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983). “Monochrome Edition” limited to thirty-five copies each
with nineteen plates, two hand colored, boxed loose in folders. See also Joseph Viscomi, “Recreating
Blake’s Illuminated Prints: The Facsimiles of the Manchester Etching Workshop,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
19.l (summer 1985): 4-23, and my review of both the colored and uncolored editions in the same issue,
39-51.</note>
          <note id="n68">16. Phillips cites Paul Ritchie of the Manchester Etching Workshop as the source for
information about depth of bite in its copperplates. In <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated
Prints</hi> included in the Manchester portfolio, Viscomi suggests that “the depth of plates executed before
1793 was probably greater than of those executed afterwards” (12).</note>
          <p>Detailed, letter by letter and motif by motif, comparisons between the Manchester and Flying
Horse impressions would be tedious and serve little purpose. Both are important publications, the products of
expertise and dedication; both attempt to recapture Blake’s original copperplate images. Both sets were
printed on softer paper than is typical of Blake’s impressions, thereby creating more prominent platemarks
and embossments of small relief elements, such as letters. The Manchester set restores to the impressions the
three textual details, noted above, missing from the Gilchrist electrotypes and the Flying Horse
plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">17</ref> Following combined 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy B as a precedent, the Manchester plates of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> were printed
in raw sienna, the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> plates in a yellow ochre a little darker than the yellow ochre
of the Flying Horse prints. The Manchester inks make a stronger visual impact. The plates were inked with a
roller, and thus have more evenly printed surfaces than the Flying Horse impressions, inked with
leather-covered daubers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">18</ref> Rollers had
not been invented until very late in Blake’s career; he probably inked his relief-etched plates with either
leather-covered or linen-covered inking balls. Thus, the inking of the Flying Horse
          <pb id="p44-110" n="110"/>
            plates comes closer to Blake’s own practices. This difference in inking methods between the
Manchester and Flying Horse impressions underscores the tension between an attempt to re-create aesthetically
pleasing prints with the visual qualities of Blake’s own and an attempt to reenact his processes. In my
review of the Manchester portfolio I complained (mildly) about the rough texture of the paper on which the
plates were printed. To my eyes, the texture and lighter color of the Flying Horse paper are a little closer
to Blake’s own. We should, however, be grateful for the instructive differences between the two
publications. Except for the minor problems noted here, I suspect that the Manchester and Flying Horse
editions of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> are as close as we are likely to come to new prints from
Blake’s own plates—short of a discovery even more breathtaking than the nineteen <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
watercolors.</p>
          <note id="n69">17. Viscomi, “Recreating Blake’s Illuminated Prints,” comments that “we
corrected the missing characters in a matching ink on the impressions themselves, rather than correct the
electrotypes” (6). The Manchester Etching Workshop had a set of electrotypes, mold-made from the Gilchrist
set, on loan from the Victoria and Albert Museum, but by “electrotypes” I take it that Viscomi means in
this statement the photo-etched copperplates based on impressions of the electrotypes, the production of which
is explained on page 5 of his essay.</note>
          <note id="n70">18. Viscomi states that Paul Ritchie of the Manchester Etching Workshop “applied
the ink ... with a roller, rather than a linen dabber, the tool Blake most likely used. We resorted to the
‘unBlakean’ tool ... because it produced more consistent results. With dampened paper, light printing
pressure, and stiff handmade intaglio ink, we succeeded in duplicating the surface texture, as well as the
colors of the originals” (“Recreating Blake’s Illuminated Prints” 7). For a detailed but rather
inconclusive discussion of Blake’s possible inking tool(s), see Essick, <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>
99-102.</note>
          <p>Much of Phillips’s essay in the Flying Horse portfolio deals with Blake’s own etching and
printing methods rather than with their reenactment. Many of his observations are controversial, including the
depth of bite in Blake’s early relief etchings and the type of inking instrument he used (see notes 16 and
18 here). Phillips relies heavily on the description of Blake’s methods in Jackson and Chatto, 
<hi rend="i">A Treatise on Wood Engraving</hi>, and particularly their comment that Blake “was accustomed to
wipe the ink out where it had touched in the hollows. As this occupied more time than the mere inking of the
plate, his progress in printing was necessarily slow.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">19</ref> Phillips believes that the Jackson and Chatto account has considerable authority because
it “suggests that they visited Blake in his studio at No. 3 Fountain Court, the Strand, some time between
Jackson’s arrival in London in 1824 and Blake’s death in August 1827” (11). These statements and
Phillips’s own experiences with relief printing lead him to conclude that Blake’s art of illuminated
printing required exacting craftsmanship and painstaking, time-consuming labor. For Phillips, “the
evidence” shows “that the processes of creation and reproduction were rarely accomplished simply or
easily” and that “Blake’s method of production was neither simple nor efficient ....”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">20</ref></p>
          <note id="n71">19. [John Jackson and William Andrew Chatto], <hi rend="i">A Treatise on Wood
Engraving, Historical and Practical</hi> (London: Charles Knight, 1839) 716- 17.</note>
          <note id="n72">20. Phillips, “The Printing of Blake’s <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi>,”
<hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi> 21.1 (2004): 20n5, 38.</note>
          <p>In the 453 double-column pages of <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>, Viscomi does
not cite the Jackson and Chatto description of Blake’s method and, in stark contrast to Phillips’s views,
claims that “inking small relief plates ... and printing them ... was relatively easy” and that,
“working alone with handmade ink and a linen dabber,” he “pulled thirty good impressions” from
“electrotypes” of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> title page and “The Lamb” in “less than
two hours.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">21</ref> My own study of
Blake’s prints etched in relief led me to conclude that, “in the majority of his relief etchings, Blake
did not have to wipe bitten surfaces in order to keep them clean enough to meet his own inking and printing
requirements.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">22</ref> I have consistently
emphasized the ways in which relief etching is a direct and autographic process joining invention and
execution, one that freed Blake from the trammels of his profession as an intaglio engraver of other
artists’ designs. These practical characteristics allowed Blake to claim that his process “combines the
Painter and the Poet” and “produces works at less than one fourth of the expense” of “Letter-press and
Engraving.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">23</ref> These differing views
are not merely trivial disputes over technical details, for they evince fundamentally different visions of
Blake. Perhaps Viscomi and I could be accused of succumbing to a now-discredited romantic ideology in which
“first thoughts are best in art, second thoughts in other matters.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">24</ref> Perhaps Phillips could be accused of assuming that original
composition and execution are as time-consuming as replication and succumbing to a modernist literary ideology
in which complexity is the hallmark of genius.</p>
          <note id="n73">21. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 118, 397n22. See also Viscomi,
“Illuminated Printing,” <hi rend="i">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves
(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003) 41: “Illuminated printing was not mysterious, complex, or
difficult.”</note>
          <note id="n74">22. Essick, <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi> 104.</note>
          <note id="n75">23. “To the Public,” <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (New York: Anchor-Random House, 1988) 692. I suspect that part of the savings
in “expense” can be accounted for by savings in labor.</note>
          <note id="n76">24. A remark attributed to Blake in Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William
Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (London: Macmillan, 1863) 1: 370.</note>
          <p>This is not the place to engage further in this long-running debate. Rather, it is the time to
welcome, indeed to celebrate, the two publications of scholarship and beauty which it has been my pleasure to
review in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    </text>
      </TEI.2>