<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-44" status="new">
    <idno>44.4.tambling</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Mind-Forg’d Manacles: William Blake and Slavery, Whitworth Art Gallery,
University of Manchester, 26 January-6 April 2008; Blake’s Shadow: William Blake and His Artistic Legacy,
Whitworth Gallery, 26 January-20 April 2008</title>
        <author n="Tambling">Jeremy Tambling</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 2011</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2011</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">44.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributor</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2011"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_44">
    <body>
	<pb id="p44-142" n="142"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-44-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEW</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Mind-Forg’d Manacles: William Blake and Slavery. Whitworth Art Gallery,
University of Manchester, 26 January-6 April 2008. Blake’s Shadow: William Blake and His Artistic Legacy.
Whitworth Gallery, 26 January-20 April 2008.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Jeremy <name>Tambling</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>TWO Blake exhibitions were to be seen at the same moment at Manchester’s Whitworth Gallery in
2008. The first, which was touring Britain, originated in 2007 as a dual anniversary: 250 years after
Blake’s birth, and the bicentenary of the abolition of the British transatlantic slave trade. Called
Mind-Forg’d Manacles: William Blake and Slavery, it was curated by David Bindman, who wrote one of the two
essays in the catalogue, published by the British Museum (the other essay is by Darryl Pinckney); the
catalogue claims that the British Museum has “the most complete representation of Blake’s work anywhere in
the world,” and everything in the exhibition came from there.</p>
          <p>I will discuss this after the other, which was curated by Colin Trodd (University of Manchester)
and Heather Birchall (Whitworth Gallery). While called Blake’s Shadow, the exhibition was not drawing
attention to the Spectre in Blake, but to the shadow Blake’s work has cast over three groups: his
contemporaries, and then the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. Virtually all the pictures and books on
display were to be found in the holdings of the Whitworth Gallery, with one or two from Manchester City
Galleries. While it was very pleasant to note how much material there is in the possession of the gallery that
could be brought in so easily, the limitation also made the exhibition, however carefully put together,
necessarily appear patchy, especially in contrast to Mind-Forg’d Manacles.</p>
          <pb id="p44-143" n="143"/>
          <p>Yet there was also much to admire in the concept of Blake’s Shadow. In the first group of works
were pictures by Calvert, Flaxman, Fuseli, Linnell, and Palmer, and five pen and ink and watercolor by
Stothard. Also, though Dickens’s artist George Cattermole (1800-68) was classed as a Victorian, it was good
to see his <hi rend="i">Unidentified Historical Scene</hi>, both Gothic and Scott-like, but also suggesting
some of the Blake of the Poetical Sketches, such as “King Edward the Third.” The second group comprised
work that comes after Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> (1863), Swinburne’s <hi rend="i">Critical
Essay</hi> (1868), and the Burlington Fine Arts Club exhibition of 1876. The first of these laid much emphasis
on Blake as a book illustrator, and therefore, in a pre-Morris way, as an artist integrating design with
craftwork and with the production of artifacts; the effects of this are seen in Walter Crane’s wallpaper
design, and in the work of all the artists here: William Linton, John Everett Millais, John Trivett
Nettleship, George Richmond, Charles Ricketts, D. G. Rossetti, Frederic Shields, Simeon Solomon, Henry Stock,
and G. F. Watts, whose huge <hi rend="i">Chaos</hi> (c. 1875) works on an entirely different scale—an
overstated one—from anything Blakean, or the woodcuts or book illustrations made by Blake and his
contemporaries. The Shields work included <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
          Work-Room and Death-Room</hi> (1882), showing Blake’s lodging in Fountain Court, looking over the
Thames, with angels dimly seen, hovering over the bed where Blake died; the D. G. Rossetti sonnet written for
Shields about the picture, “This is the place,” was also quoted in full. A certain quasi-Catholic
spirituality is evident in both the painting and the poem; Rossetti was outstanding for bringing together
Blake and Dante in his thinking, and the influence of his reading of Dante is apparent. Shields’s
contribution to the exhibition included another picture featuring London: <hi rend="i">The Plague of London:
Solomon Eagle Denouncing the Impenitent</hi> (1863). Solomon Eagle, a figure written about by Defoe, and also
depicted by Cruikshank, becomes a Blakean prophet (a radical Quaker, he denounced London’s sins during the
plague of 1665): this Nonconformist tradition suggests another Blake, more marginal, more mad, but as
interesting as the Dante Blake was so ambivalent about.</p>
          <p>The section devoted to “Modern and Contemporary Blake” included Austin Osman Spare, Paul
Nash, David Jones (another artist and poet), Ceri Richards, Cecil Collins, Leslie Hurry, John Craxton, Keith
Vaughan, Patrick Procktor, Anish Kapoor, and Christopher Bucklow. A final section, “Blake and Popular
Culture,” stressed the filmwork of Jim Jarmusch (<hi rend="i">Dead Man</hi>) and Gus Van Sant 
(<hi rend="i">Last Days</hi>). Here, the exhibition would have needed much more substantiation to have been
effective or less suspiciously cliché-like. While a few of the artworks from the twentieth century required a
certain special pleading, and assumed a dehistoricized Blake, the exhibition was beautiful in places, and
useful in showing how many Blakean shadows there are and how many have been the appropriations of his work:
that there is no single Blake is apparent from all the images that can claim to have drawn from his already
plural and composite art.</p>
          <p>Mind-Forg’d Manacles was full of essential material: for example, some of Blake’s sixteen
engravings for J. G. Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative, of a Five Years’ Expedition, against the Revolted
Negroes of Surinam</hi>, which appeared in 1796, some Gillray cartoons, and William Hackwood’s design for
the 1787 medallion inscribed with the words “Am I Not a Man and a Brother?” and used by Josiah Wedgwood.
The main part of the exhibition, however, was given over to plates from the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, notably
“The Little Black Boy,” and then to <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">The
First Book of Urizen</hi>, <hi rend="i">The House of Death</hi>, one of the twelve color prints, 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, <hi rend="i">Queen Katharine’s Dream</hi>, various designs for <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>.
Everything here was interesting, obviously, and well presented, but I couldn’t help wondering at the
certainty of some of Bindman’s interpretations, which consequently seemed oversimplifying, as with his
characterizations of Innocence as related to childhood, and, for “London,” that “the poem expresses the
idea in its reference to ‘mind-forg’d manacles’ that enslavement to false values and the materialism of
society can be self-inflicted.” Of course this is true, but there are three caveats: manacles do not
necessarily suggest slavery, and so the use of the trope of chains is a little imprecise for considering the
issue of the slave trade; the manacles are not, in the expression in “London,” necessarily self-inflicted,
and education and the church and state, to say nothing of the minds of
            others, do the work of inflicting effectively enough for Blake; and third, however much “mental
slavery,” one of Bindman’s headings, may mean, it is not the same as physical slavery, and runs the danger
of minimizing what slavery meant, and perhaps means: it makes slavery too metaphorical a concept.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    </text>
      </TEI.2>