<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>5.3.paley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Two Pictorial Sources for Jerusalem 25</title>
                <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
                <author n="Toomey">Deirdre Toomey</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter, 1971-72</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971-72</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/an illustrated quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">05.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Roberta Goetsch</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971-72"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_05">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-05-3-0003">
                <pb id="p05-185" n="185"/>
                <div2>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="i">MORTON D. </hi><name><hi
rend="i">PALEY</hi></name>:</docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, BERKELEY</hi> and 
<hi rend="i"><docAuthor>DEIRDRE <name>TOOMEY</name>:</docAuthor> UNIVERSITY COLLEGE, LONDON</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Two Pictorial Sources for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 25</title>
                    </head>
                    <figure n="jerusalem.e.p25" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.25" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="752" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>25<lb/>
	And there was heard a great lamenting in Beulah: all the Regions<lb/>
	Of Beulah were moved as the tender bowels are moved: &amp; they said:<lb/>
	Why did you take Vengeance O ye Sons of the mighty Albion?<lb/>
	Planting these Oaken Groves: Erecting these Dragon Temples<lb/>
	Injury the Lord heals but Vengeance cannot be healed:<lb/>
	As the Sons of Albion have done to Luvah: so they have in him<lb/>
	Done to the Divine Lord &amp; Saviour. who suffers with those that suffer;<lb/>
	For not one sparrow can suffer. &amp; the whole Universe not suffer also,<lb/>
	In all its Regions, &amp; its Father &amp; Saviour not pity and weep.<lb/>
	But Vengeance is the destroyer of Grace &amp; Repentance in the bosom<lb/>
	Of the Injurer; in which the Divine Lamb is cruelly slain;<lb/>
	Descend O Lamb of God &amp; take away the imputation of Sin<lb/>
	By the Creation of States &amp; the deliverance of Individuals Evermore Amen<lb/>
	Thus wept they in Beulah over the Four Regions of Albion<lb/>
	But many doubted &amp; despaird &amp; imputed Sin &amp; Righteousness<lb/>
	To Individuals &amp; not to States, and these Slept in Ulro.</figTranscr>
                        <head>1 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 25.</head>
                        <figDesc>From the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon. We are grateful to Mr. and
Mrs. Mellon for permission to reproduce these pictures and to Mr. Willis Van Devanter for his assistance in
obtaining them.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p05-186" n="186"/>
                    <figure n="jerusalem.e.p91" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.91" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="735" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>91<lb/>
	It is easier to forgive an Enemy than to forgive a Friend:<lb/>
	The man who permits you to injure him, deserves your vengeance:<lb/>
	He also will recieve it: go Spectre! obey my most secret desire!<lb/>
	Which thou knowest without my speaking: Go to these Fiends of Righteousness<lb/>
	Tell them to obey their Humanities, &amp; not pretend Holiness;<lb/>
	When they are murderers: as far as my Hammer &amp; Anvil permit<lb/>
	Go, tell them that the Worship of God, is honouring his gifts<lb/>
	In other men: &amp; loving the greatest men best. each according<lb/>
	To his Genius; which is the Holy Ghost in Man; there is no other<lb/>
	God, than that God who is the intellectual fountain of Humanity:<lb/>
	He who envies or calumniates: which is murder &amp; cruelty,<lb/>
	Murders the Holy-one! Go tell them this &amp; overthrow their cup,<lb/>
	Their bread, their altar-table, their incense &amp; their oath:<lb/>
	Their marriage &amp; their baptism, their burial &amp; consecration:<lb/>
	I have tried to make friends by corporeal gifts but have only<lb/>
	Made enemies: I never made friends but by spiritual gifts;<lb/>
	By severe contentions of friendship &amp; the burning fire of thought.<lb/>
	He who would see the Divinity must see him in his Children<lb/>
	One first, in friendship &amp; love; then a Divine Family, &amp; in the midst<lb/>
	Jesus will appear; so he who wishes to see a Vision; a perfect Whole<lb/>
	Must see it in its Minute Particulars; Organized &amp; not as thou<lb/>
	O Fiend of Righteousness pretendest; thine is a Disorganized<lb/>
	And snowy cloud; brooder of tempests &amp; destructive War<lb/>
	You smile with pomp &amp; rigor: you talk of benevolence &amp; virtue!<lb/>
	I act with benevolence &amp; virtue &amp; get murderd time after time:<lb/>
	You accumulate Particulars, &amp; murder by analyzing, that you<lb/>
	May take the aggregate; &amp; you call the aggregate Moral Law:<lb/>
	And you call that Swelld &amp; bloated Form; a Minute Particular,<lb/>
	But General Forms have their vitality in Particulars: &amp; every<lb/>
	Particular is a Man; a Divine Member of the Divine Jesus.<lb/>
	So Los cried at his Anvil in the horrible darkness weeping!<lb/>
	The Spectre builded stupendous Works, taking the Starry Heavens<lb/>
	Like to a curtain &amp; folding them according to his will<lb/>
	Repeating the Smaragdine Table of Hermes to draw Los down<lb/>
	Into the Indefinite, refusing to believe without demonstration<lb/>
	Los reads the Stars of Albion! the Spectre reads the Voids<lb/>
	Between the Stars; among the arches of Albions Tomb sublime<lb/>
	Rolling the Sea in rocky paths! forming Leviathan<lb/>
	And Behemoth; the War by Sea enormous &amp; the War<lb/>
	By Land astounding: erecting pillars in the deepest Hell.<lb/>
	To reach the heavenly arches; Los beheld undaunted furious<lb/>
	His heavd Hammer; he swung it round &amp; at one blow,<lb/>
	In unpitying ruin driving down the pyramids of pride<lb/>
	Smiting the Spectre on his Anvil &amp; the integuments of his Eye<lb/>
	And Ear unbinding in dire pain, with many blows,<lb/>
	Of strict severity self-subduing, &amp; with many tears labouring.<lb/>
	Then he sent forth the Spectre all his pyramids were grains<lb/>
	Of sand &amp; his pillars: dust on the flys wing: &amp; his starry<lb/>
	Heavens; a moth of gold &amp; silver mocking his anxious grasp<lb/>
	Thus Los alterd his Spectre &amp; every Ratio of his Reason<lb/>
	He alterd time after time, with dire pain &amp; many tears<lb/>
	Till he had completely divided him into a separate space.<lb/>
	Terrified Los sat to behold trembling &amp; weeping &amp; howling<lb/>
	I care not whether a Man is Good or Evil; all that I care<lb/>
	Is whether he is a Wise Man or a Fool, Go! put off Holiness<lb/>
	And put on Intellect: or my thundrous Hammer shall drive thee<lb/>
	To wrath which thou condemnest: till thou obey my voice<lb/>
	So Los terrified cries; trembling &amp; weeping &amp; howling! Beholding</figTranscr>
                        <head>2 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 91, bottom.</head>
                        <figDesc>From the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="i">I Morton Paley:</hi> The Martyrdom of St. Erasmus</title>
                        </head>
                        <p>“The difference between a bad Artist &amp; a Good One Is: the Bad Artist Seems to
Copy a Great deal The Good one Really Does Copy a Great deal.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n14" type="note">1</ref> As Sir Anthony Blunt has shown, Blake really did copy a great deal,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">2</ref> though when he borrowed for one of his own
works, the borrowing was seldom without some kind of transformation. Such is the case with the design on plate
25 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [fig. 1]. 
                            <note id="n14">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    1
                                </hi> Annotations to Reynold’s <hi rend="i">Discourses, The Complete
Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1966), pp. 455-56. (This
edition hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">K.</hi>)</note>
                            <note id="n15">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    2
                                </hi>
                                <hi rend="i"> The Art of William Blake</hi> (New York: Columbia Univ. Press,
1959).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The central figure in this picture is Albion, as we know from the presence of the
sun, moon, and stars in his limbs. (Two plates later we are told “ ‘But now the Starry Heavens are fled from
the mighty limbs of Albion.’ ”—<hi rend="i">K</hi> 649). He is bound in a position strongly reminiscent of
that of the central figure of <hi rend="i">The Blasphemer</hi>
                            <ref target="n16" type="note">3</ref> in the Tate Gallery, but here the figure at
the right is drawing something out of his body. This action has been variously interpreted as “winding a
‘clue’ of vegetation from his navel,” “drawing out the umbilical cord from his navel” and
“disembowelment.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">4</ref> Actually, it is all
three, for to Blake the bowels and the umbilical cord are equally manifestations of those fibres of vegetation
which play so large a thematic role in Blake’s later works. In this particular picture the same fibres that
the figure on the right winds out of Albion’s body and into a ball stream down the plate on either side from
the fingers of the central female figure. The identity of substance is more apparent in the Mellon copy than
in the black-and-white copies, for Blake uses the same russet coloration for fibres of vegetation throughout
(compare for example plate 57 [fig. 3], where the russet fibres stream from the fingers of the two female
figures above and seem to entrap the one below). This winding of Albion’s “bowels of compassion” (56:34)
into a ball is a demonic parody of the activity Blake urges on the reader in plate 77 [fig. 4] with its
accompanying picture. Winding and unwinding, weaving and unweaving are indeed among the central motifs of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [cf. fig. 5]. 
                            <note id="n16">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    3
                                </hi> Also known by the W. M. Rossetti title, <hi rend="i">The Stoning of
Achan</hi>, but see Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake / A Complete Catalogue of the Works in the Tate
Gallery</hi> (London, 1971), p. 45. A similar Michelangelesque posture may be seen in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 91
[fig. 2].</note>
                            <note id="n17">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    4
                                </hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and
Symbols</hi> (1924; rpt. Gloucester, Mass.: Peter Smith, 1958), p. 470; Joseph Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Jerusalem</hi> (New York: The Beechurst Press, 1955), p. 155; Butlin, p. 45.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The meaning, then, is thoroughly Blakean. But the depiction of a figure whose
bowels are being unwound is a rather unusual subject, and the existence of just such a figure in a painting by
an artist whom Blake admired suggests that Blake was following his own advice in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 25. The
painting is <hi rend="i">The Martyrdom of St. Erasmus</hi> by Nicolas Poussin. Blake praises Poussin several
times in the Annotations to Reynolds (<hi rend="i">K</hi> 469, 477), and according to Raymond Lister Blake
made a copy of Poussin’s <hi rend="i">The Giant Polypheme</hi> which was engraved by George Byfield c.
1820.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">5</ref> Saint Erasmus was martyred by
having his entrails drawn out and wound on a winch, and although Blake cannot have seen Poussin’s powerful
rendering of this scene in Rome—or in Paris, to which it was removed during the Napoleonic period<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">6</ref>—he could easily have been familiar with the
version by Joseph Marie Mitelli [fig. 6], an engraving listed as one of Mitelli’s “principal works” by
Michael Bryan in 1816 (<hi rend="i">A Biographical and Critical Dictionary of Painters and Engravers</hi>
[London], II, 76). Blake has of course shifted Poussin’s supine suffering figure to a more Michelangelesque
pose,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">7</ref> yet the drawing out and winding
of the entrails remain the central conception of both pictures.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">8</ref>
                            <note id="n18">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    5
                                </hi>
                                <hi rend="i"> William Blake: An Introduction to the Man and His Work</hi> (New
York: Ungar, 1970), p. 165.</note>
                            <note id="n19">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    6
                                </hi> See Anthony Blunt, <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Nicholas Poussin / A
Critical Catalogue</hi> (London, 1966), pp. 66-68.</note>
                            <note id="n20">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    7
                                </hi> C. H. Collins Baker suggests that the figure may derive from Flaxman;
see “The Sources of Blake’s Pictorial Expression,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>, 4
(1940-41), 365.</note>
                            <note id="n21">
                                    <hi rend="s">
                                        8
                                    </hi> Miss Deirdre Toomey points out that <hi rend="i">The Martyrdom of
St. Erasmus</hi> was seen and remarked on by Henry Fuseli when he visited the Louvre in 1802. John Knowles
summarizes Fuseli’s view of the painting as follows:
<q>
The actual martyrdom of St. Erasmus is one of those subjects which ought not to be told to the eye—because
it is equally loathsome and horrible; we can neither pity nor shudder; we are seized by qualms, and detest.
Poussin and Pietro Testa are here more or less objects of aversion, and in proportion to the greater or less
energy they exerted. This is the only picture of Poussin in which he has attempted to rival his Italian
competitors on a scale of equal magnitude in figures of the size of life; and here he was no longer in his
sphere; his drawing has no longer its usual precision of form, it is loose and Cortonesque; his colour on this
scale has neither the breadth of fresco, nor the glow, finish, or impasto of oil.<lb/>
                                        <lb/>
—<hi rend="i">The Life and Writings of Henry Fuseli</hi> (London, 1831), I, 270-71.
</q>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="p05-187" n="187"/>
                    <figure n="jerusalem.e.p57" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.57" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="732" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>57<lb/>
	London<lb/>
	York<lb/>
	And the voices of Bath &amp; Canterbury &amp; York &amp; Edinburgh. Cry<lb/>
	Over the Plow of Nations in the strong hand of Albion thundering along<lb/>
	Among the Fires of the Druid &amp; the deep black rethundering Waters<lb/>
	Of the Atlantic which poured in impetuous loud loud. louder &amp; louder<lb/>
	And the Great Voice of the Atlantic howled over the Druid Altars:<lb/>
	Weeping over his Children in Stone-henge in Malden &amp; Colchester.<lb/>
	Round the Rocky Peak of Derbyshire London Stone &amp; Rosamonds Bower<lb/>
	What is a Wife &amp; what is a Harlot? What is a Church? &amp; What<lb/>
	Is a Theatre? are they Two &amp; not One? can they Exist Separate?<lb/>
	Are not Religion &amp; Politics the Same Thing? Brotherhood is Religion<lb/>
	O Demonstrations of Reason Dividing Families in Cruelty &amp; Pride!<lb/>
	But Albion fled from the Divine Vision. with the Plow of Nations enflaming<lb/>
	The Living Creatures maddend and Albion fell into the Furrow, and<lb/>
	The Plow went over him &amp; the Living was Plowed in among the Dead<lb/>
	But his Spectre rose over the starry Plow. Albion fled beneath the Plow<lb/>
	Till he came to the Rock of Ages. &amp; he took his Seat upon the Rock.<lb/>
	Wonder siezd all in Eternity! to behold the Divine Vision. open<lb/>
	The Center into an Expanse, &amp; the Center rolled out into an Expanse<lb/>
	Jerusalem</figTranscr>
                        <head>3 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 57.</head>
                        <figDesc>From the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="jerusalem.e.p77" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.77" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="779" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>77<lb/>
	To the Christians.<lb/>
	Devils are<lb/>
	False Religions<lb/>
	“Saul Saul”<lb/>
	“Why persecutest thou me,<lb/>
	I give you the end of a golden string,<lb/>
	Only wind it into a ball:<lb/>
	It will lead you in at Heavens gate,<lb/>
	Built in Jerusalems wall.<lb/>
	We are told to abstain from fleshly desires that we may lose no time from the<lb/>
	Work of the Lord. Every moment lost, is a moment that cannot be redeemed<lb/>
	every pleasure that intermingles with the duty of our station is a folly unredeemable<lb/>
	&amp; is planted like the seed of a wild flower among our wheat. All<lb/>
	the tortures of repentance. are tortures of self-reproach on account of our leaving<lb/>
	the Divine Harvest to the Enemy, the struggles of intanglement with incoherent<lb/>
	roots. I know of no other Christianity and of no other Gospel than<lb/>
	the liberty both of body &amp; mind to exercise the Divine Arts of Imagination<lb/>
	Imagination the real &amp; eternal World of which this Vegetable Universe is<lb/>
	but a faint shadow &amp; in which we shall live in our Eternal or Imaginative<lb/>
	Bodies, when these Vegetable Mortal Bodies are no more. The Apostles knew<lb/>
	of no other Gospel. What were all their spiritual gifts? What is the Divine<lb/>
	Spirit? is the Holy Ghost any other than an Intellectual Fountain? What is<lb/>
	the Harvest of the Gospel &amp; its Labours? What is that Talent which it is a<lb/>
	curse to hide? What are the Treasures of Heaven which we are to lay up for<lb/>
	ourselves, are they any other than Mental Studies &amp; Performances? What<lb/>
	are all the Gifts of the Gospel. are they not all Mental Gifts? Is God a<lb/>
	Spirit who must be worshipped in Spirit &amp; in Truth and are not the Gifts<lb/>
	of the Spirit Every-thing to Man? O ye Religious discountenance every<lb/>
	one among you who shall pretend to despise Art &amp; Science! I call upon<lb/>
	you in the Name of Jesus! What is the Life of Man but Art &amp; Science?<lb/>
	is it Meat &amp; Drink? is not the Body more than Raiment? What is Mortality<lb/>
	but the things relating to the Body, which Dies? What is Immortality but the<lb/>
	things relating to the Spirit, which Lives Eternally! What is the Joy of Heaven<lb/>
	but Improvement in the things of the Spirit? What are the Pains of Hell<lb/>
	but Ignorance, Bodily Lust, Idleness &amp; devastation of the things of the Spirit<lb/>
	Answer this to yourselves, &amp; expel from among you those who pretend to despise<lb/>
	the labours of Art &amp; Science, which alone are the labours of the Gospel:<lb/>
	Is not this plain &amp; manifest to the thought? Can you think at all, &amp;<lb/>
	not pronounce heartily! That to Labour in Knowledge. is to Build up Jerusalem:<lb/>
	and to Despise Knowledge, is to Despise Jerusalem &amp; her Builders.<lb/>
	And remember: He who despises &amp; mocks a Mental Gift in another; calling<lb/>
	it pride &amp; selfishness &amp; sin; mocks Jesus the giver of every Mental Gift.<lb/>
	which always appear to the ignorance-loving Hypocrite, as Sins. but that<lb/>
	which is a Sin in the sight of cruel Man. is not so in the sight of our kind God.<lb/>
	Let every Christian as much as in him lies engage himself openly &amp; publicly<lb/>
	before all the World in some Mental pursuit for the Building up of Jerusalem<lb/>
	I stood among my valleys of the south<lb/>
	And saw a flame of fire, even as a Wheel<lb/>
	Of fire surrounding all the heavens: it went<lb/>
	From west to east against the current of<lb/>
	Creation, and devourd all things in its loud<lb/>
	Fury &amp; thundering course round heaven &amp; earth<lb/>
	By it the Sun was rolld into an orb:<lb/>
	By it the Moon faded into a globe.<lb/>
	Travelling thro the night: for from its dire<lb/>
	And restless fury, Man himself shrunk up<lb/>
	Into a little root a fathom long.<lb/>
	And I asked a Watcher &amp; a Holy-One<lb/>
	Its Name? he answerd. It is the Wheel of Religion<lb/>
	I wept &amp; said. Is this the law of Jesus<lb/>
	This terrible devouring sword turning every way<lb/>
	He answerd; Jesus died because he strove<lb/>
	Against the current of this Wheel: its Name<lb/>
	Is Caiaphas, the dark Preacher of Death<lb/>
	Of sin, of sorrow, &amp; of punishment;<lb/>
	Opposing Nature! It is Natural Religion<lb/>
	But Jesus is the bright Preacher of Life<lb/>
	Creating Nature from this fiery Law,<lb/>
	By self-denial &amp; forgiveness of Sin:<lb/>
	Go therefore, cast out devils in Christs name<lb/>
	Heal thou the sick of spiritual disease<lb/>
	Pity the evil. for thou art not sent<lb/>
	To smite with terror &amp; with punishments<lb/>
	Those that are sick. like to the Pharisees<lb/>
	Crucifying &amp; encompasing sea &amp; land<lb/>
	For proselytes to tyranny &amp; wrath.<lb/>
	But to the Publicans &amp; Harlots go!<lb/>
	Teach them True Happiness. but let no curse<lb/>
	Go forth out of thy mouth to blight their peace<lb/>
	For Hell is opend to Heaven; thine eyes beheld<lb/>
	The dungeons burst &amp; the Prisoners set free.<lb/>
	England! awake! awake! awake!<lb/>
	Jerusalem thy Sister calls!<lb/>
	Why wilt thou sleep the sleep of death?<lb/>
	And close her from thy ancient walls.<lb/>
	Thy hills &amp; valleys felt her feet.<lb/>
	Gently upon their bosoms move:<lb/>
	Thy gates beheld sweet Zions ways;<lb/>
	Then was a time of joy and love<lb/>
	And now the time returns again:<lb/>
	Our souls exult &amp; Londons towers<lb/>
	Recieve the Lamb of God to dwell<lb/>
	In Englands green &amp; pleasant bowers.</figTranscr>
                        <head>4 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 77, top.</head>
                        <figDesc>From the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="jerusalem.e.p59" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.59" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="679" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>59<lb/>
	And formed into Four precious stones. for enterance from Beulah<lb/>
	For the Veil of Vala which Albion cast into the Atlantic Deep<lb/>
	To catch the Souls of the Dead: began to Vegetate &amp; Petrify<lb/>
	Around the Earth of Albion. among the Roots of his Tree<lb/>
	This Los formed into the Gates &amp; mighty Wall, between the Oak<lb/>
	Of Weeping &amp; the Palm of Suffering beneath Albions Tomb.<lb/>
	Thus in process of time it became the beautiful Mundane Shell.<lb/>
	The Habitation of the Spectres of the Dead &amp; the Place<lb/>
	Of Redemption &amp; of awaking again into Eternity<lb/>
	For Four Universes round the Mundane Egg remain Chaotic<lb/>
	One to the North: Urthona: One to the South: Urizen;<lb/>
	One to the East: Luvah: One to the West, Tharmas;<lb/>
	They are the Four Zoas that stood around the Throne Divine<lb/>
	Verulam: London: York &amp; Edinburgh: their English names<lb/>
	But when Luvah assumed the World of Urizen Southward<lb/>
	And Albion was slain upon his Mountains &amp; in his Tent.<lb/>
	All fell towards the Center, sinking downwards in dire ruin<lb/>
	In the South remains a burning Fire: in the East. a Void<lb/>
	In the West, a World of raging Waters; in the North: solid Darkness<lb/>
	Unfathomable without end: but in the midst of these<lb/>
	Is Built eternally the sublime Universe of Los &amp; Enitharmon<lb/>
	And in the North Gate, in the West of the North. toward Beulah<lb/>
	Cathedrons Looms are builded. and Los’s Furnaces in the South<lb/>
	A wondrous golden Building immense with ornaments sublime<lb/>
	Is bright Cathedrons golden Hall, its Courts Towers &amp; Pinnacles<lb/>
	And one Daughter of Los sat at the fiery Reel &amp; another<lb/>
	Sat at the shining Loom with her Sisters attending round<lb/>
	Terrible their distress &amp; their sorrow cannot be utterd<lb/>
	And another Daughter of Los sat at the Spinning Wheel<lb/>
	Endless their labour, with bitter food. void of sleep.<lb/>
	Tho hungry they labour; they rouze themselves anxious<lb/>
	Hour after hour labouring at the whirling Wheel<lb/>
	Many Wheels &amp; as many lovely Daughters sit weeping<lb/>
	Yet the intoxicating delight that they take in their work<lb/>
	Obliterates every other evil; none pities their tears<lb/>
	Yet they regard not pity &amp; they expect no one to pity<lb/>
	For they labour for life &amp; love, regardless of any one<lb/>
	But the poor Spectres that they work for, always incessantly<lb/>
	They are mockd, by every one that passes by. they regard not<lb/>
	They labour; &amp; when their Wheels are broken by scorn &amp; malice<lb/>
	They mend them sorrowing with many tears &amp; afflictions,<lb/>
	Other Daughters Weave on the Cushion &amp; Pillow, Network fine<lb/>
	That Rahab &amp; Tirzah may exist &amp; live &amp; breathe &amp; love<lb/>
	Ah, that it could be as the Daughters of Beulah wish!<lb/>
	Other Daughters of Los, labouring at Looms less fine<lb/>
	Create the Silk-worm &amp; the Spider &amp; the Catterpiller<lb/>
	To assist in their most grievous work of pity &amp; compassion<lb/>
	And others Create the wooly Lamb &amp; the downy Fowl<lb/>
	To assist in the work: the Lamb bleats! the Sea-fowl cries<lb/>
	Men understand not the distress &amp; the labour &amp; sorrow<lb/>
	That in the Interior Worlds is carried on in fear &amp; trembling<lb/>
	Weaving the shuddring fears &amp; loves of Albions Families<lb/>
	Thunderous rage the Spindles of iron. &amp; the iron Distaff<lb/>
	Maddens in the fury of their hands, Weaving in bitter tears<lb/>
	The Veil of Goats-hair &amp; Purple &amp; Scarlet &amp; fine twined Linen</figTranscr>
                        <head>5 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 59, center.</head>
                        <figDesc>From the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p05-188" n="188"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="i">II Deirdre Toomey:</hi> Le Tre Parche</title>
                        </head>
                        <p>The anonymous engraving after Il Rosso Fiorentino<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">1</ref> known as <hi rend="i">Le Tre Parche</hi> [fig. 7] is usually
attributed to Rene Boyvin, a sixteenth century French engraver and designer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">2</ref> Boyvin was born in Angers in 1530, worked in Paris and died
in Rome in 1598. About 226 prints can be attributed to him, mainly engraved after Il Rosso and Primaticcio.
Boyvin engraved two versions of this subject; in the other, also after Il Rosso, the Fates are clothed.
According to Robert-Dumesnil a bad copy of the engraving exists with the following inscription in the margin:
“Dum terrae Iovis ante pedes fera pensa sorores devolvunt; cave ne tempus mane fluvat.” 
                            <note id="n22">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    1
                                </hi> The Rosso original is lost.</note>
                            <note id="n23">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    2
                                </hi> However Yves Metman argues that much of the work hitherto attributed to
Boyvin must be assigned to another Fontainbleu engraver, Pierre Millan: this version of the 
<hi rend="i">Parche</hi> is among those reattributed. See Metman, “Pierre Millan; un Graveur inconnu de l’École
de Fontainbleu”, <hi rend="i">Bibliothèque D’Humanisme et Renaissance</hi> (1941), pp. 202-21A [including a
supplement of documents].</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The resemblance between this Boyvin print and plate 25 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> [fig. 1] in general design and minute detail is striking enough to lead one to
conclude that Blake had seen and studied it. The engraving is, and presumably was, extremely rare, and I can
find no record of it in Cumberland’s Catalogue; it is possible that a copy was owned by Fuseli, who
possessed an interesting collection of Mannerist prints. Two copies of this rare print were acquired by the
British Museum in 1850 from the collection of a Mr. Bowerfield.</p>
                        <p>Blake’s debt to the Rosso design is immediately evident. It can be seen in his
use of the unusual pyramidical composition of three female nudes; in the torso and outstretched arms of the
central figure and the bundles of cord-like substance that she holds; in the relationship of her arms to the
heads of the other two figures; and in the head, features, tear-stained face and hunched pose of the
right-hand figure. Indeed the very theme of plate 25 can be seen to be derived from the 
<hi rend="i">Parche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Blake alters the proportion from rectangle to square to 
<corr type="emend">accommodate</corr> the extra figure. He discards the left-hand Fate for a more compositionally
symmetrical adaptation of Michaelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Night.</hi> The central Fate is considerably
foreshortened, her sprawling legs are removed and her arms are straightened.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">3</ref> The right-hand Fate suffers a slight rearrangement of her
legs and arms; her hunched pose remains remarkably unmodified. Blake enlarges the picture depth, at the same
time concentrating the movement within the design. In the Rosso there is a characteristic tendency towards
diffuseness; the strong triangle formed by the three bodies is broken by the outward thrust and gaze of all
the figures. Blake’s modifications all tend towards making the design more concentrated, dramatic and
energetic. The self-consciousness of the Fates disappears and their potential energy is harnessed by the
introduction of the fourth figure and hence an action. In typical Mannerist fashion the diagonals in the Rosso
bisect on the pudendum of the central Fate, which is thus the focal point of the design. In plate 25 this
central figure is foreshortened and the focal point becomes Albion’s agonized chest. Blake also ignores the
merely ornamental parts of the design; the “Testa Divina” head-dresses disappear and blocks of stone are
substituted for the draperies, pedestal and basket of flowers. 
                            <note id="n24">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    3
                                </hi> They come to resemble those of the floating female in the Victoria and
Albert <hi rend="i">Allegorical Design with a River God.</hi>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Blake takes the spinning motif of <hi rend="i">Le Tre Parche</hi> a stage further
both formally and iconographically. Instead of the symbolic thread, the females really wind “the thin-spun
life,” Albion’s “tender bowels.” This winding of entrails can be seen to be taken from Poussin’s 
<hi rend="i">St. Erasmus</hi> [fig. 6]: two sources are thus admirably conflated in plate 25. The bundles of flax
held by the central Fate also undergo a curious transformation, being enlarged into long willow-like roots. It
is important to note that, in taking over and elaborating the Rosso spinning motif, Blake disrupts the
process: in the former, the bundles of flax are being spun into thread, in the latter there is no visually
logical connection between the “roots” and the entrails.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">4</ref> Blake’s interest in spinning and weaving can be seen elsewhere in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, viz., plates 59 [fig. 5] and 91 [fig. 2]. The bands worn by two of the Fates and used
as distaff-holders are rather surprisingly ignored by Blake: similar bands are to be seen more than once on
Blake’s male figures, viz., <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> p. 60, and, more debatably, on female figures in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The most plausible of these is seen in plate 59, a spinning scene; the bands in
plates 5, 8 and 24 are nearer to harnesses of some sort. The female band was a classical device, often used in
the Renaissance and available to Blake in countless engravings. Blake’s source for the male band is probably
Fuseli. 
                            <note id="n25">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    4
                                </hi> However if we turn to the text connections can be made: the roots can be
seen as Vala’s veil being thrown over Albion’s “deep wound of sin” by the leaning central figure.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The sun, moon and stars seen on Albion’s body in this plate can be read as
symbolic references to his microcosmic nature:
<q>
You have a tradition that Man anciently contain’d in his mighty limbs all things in Heaven &amp; Earth: this
you received from the Druids.<lb/>
“But now the Starry Heavens are fled from the mighty limbs of Albion.” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 27)
</q>
They can also be read, more simply, as primitive decorations, very similar to those seen on the bodies of the
Ancient Britons in Speed’s <hi rend="i">Historie</hi> [fig. 8]. Here the ancient Britons are seen as “naked
Heroes,” dwelling in “naked simplicity,” though Speed’s Britons are not Blake’s original Britons,
“learned, studious, abstruse in thought and contemplation” but, as we see from the heads that they car
<pb id="p05-189" n="189"/>
                            <figure n="Mitelli.5.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="791">
                                <figTranscr>Nicholaus Pusin Pi.<lb/>
                                <lb/>
                                Arnold: Van Westerhout, formis Romæ<lb/>
                                <lb/>
                                Sc. Mitellus Del</figTranscr>
                                <head>6 Mitelli’s engraving of Poussin’s <hi rend="i">The Martyrdom of St.
Erasmus.</hi>
                                </head>
                                <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British
Museum.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
                            <figure n="Boyvin.5.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="720">
                                <head>7 Rene Boyvin’s [?] engraving of <hi rend="i">Le Tre Parche</hi>,
after Il Rosso Fiorentino.</head>
                                <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British
Museum.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
                            <pb id="p05-190" n="190"/>
ry and trample upon, belong rather to the corrupt age “which began to turn allegoric and mental signification
into corporeal command, whereby human sacrifice would have depopulated the earth.” Suns, moons and stars form
part of their body-decoration, as do birds and beasts: “ . . . Man contain’d in his Limbs all Animals . . . ” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 27).</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">Deirdre Toomey will discuss the two states of</hi> J <hi rend="i">25
in</hi> Blake Newsletter 21 <hi rend="i">(Summer 1972). (Eds.)</hi>
                        </p>
                        <figure n="Speed.5.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="353">
                            <head>8 “The Portraitures and paintings of the Ancient Britains,” from John
Speed’s <hi rend="i">Historie of Great Britaine . . . from JULIUS CAESAR, to . . . KING JAMES.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>“The Second Edition Revised, and enlarged with sundry descents of the
Saxons Kings, Their Marriages and Armes” (London, 1623), Book V, Chap. 6, p. 39.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>