<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>5.3.minnick</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">A New Rossetti Letter</title>
                <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter, 1971-72</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971-72</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/an illustrated quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">05.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Roberta Goetsch</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971-72"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_05">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-05-3-0003">
            	<pb id="p05-181" n="181"/>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">THOMAS L.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">MINNICK</hi>
                            </name>:</docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">THE OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">A New Rossetti Letter</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>I recently had the good fortune to buy an unpublished holograph letter by Dante Gabriel
Rossetti. As it concerns Blake and Mrs. Anne Gilchrist, it may be of interest to the readers of the 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter.</hi> On a folded sheet of mourning notepaper Rossetti wrote:
<q>
59 Lincoln’s Inn Fields<lb/>
Wednesday<lb/>
                            <lb/>
My dear W. Ireland<lb/>
                            <lb/>
I am very sorry I cannot manage to be with you so early as 7, either today or tomorrow, so must decline your
kind invitation to dinner, but shall be very glad to come a little later tomorrow evening, and will take the
liberty of bringing my brother if he can come—say at half past 8. He, as well as I, wrote the other day to
Mrs. Gilchrist, but the letters, being directed to Earl’s Colne, have not perhaps yet reached her. We shall
both be very glad to see her again &amp; go over Blake business by word of mouth. I am very sorry to have
delayed answering but was not sure till now which evening I could come. With kind remembrances to Mrs.
Gilchrist<lb/>
                            <lb/>
I am yours very truly<lb/>
                            <lb/>
D G Rossetti
</q>
The paper is watermarked “1860”; the envelope is lost.</p>
                    <p>Although the note is undated, the address implies that it was written between the end
of April, 1862, and 24 October of the same year, the only time when Rossetti lived at 59 Lincoln’s Inn
Fields.<hi rend="s">
                            <hi rend="i">1</hi>
                    </hi> He had moved there when, after Lizzie’s death in February, Chatham Place became
unbearable and when a few weeks<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">1</ref> stay
on Newman Street proved unsatisfactory. These several months in 1862 were filled with projects and excursions
which helped to distract Rossetti from his grief. The completion of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
of Blake</hi> (1863) was one such project and is certainly the “Blake business” to which the letter alludes. 
                        <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                1
                            </hi> So Oswald Doughty in <hi rend="i">A Victorian Romantic: Dante Gabriel
Rossetti</hi>, 2nd ed. (London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1960), pp. 307, 310. But Oswald Doughty and John Robert
Wahl, eds., give 22 October as the date Rossetti left; see <hi rend="i">Letters of Dante Gabriel Rossetti</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1965), II, 458.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>After Alexander’s death from scarlet fever, Mrs. Gilchrist moved her children to
Earl’s Colne, sometimes called “the garden of Essex,” her mother’s home, her own home for most of her
early and middle life, and the home of her ancestors since the Norman Conquest.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">2</ref> But like Rossetti the recent widow had her periods of
depression, and they also made her restless; in late August, for example, she wrote to her sister-in-law, 
“ . . . Colne is intolerably painful to me, and I quite pine to get back to my quiet cottage among the dear Surrey
hills . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">3</ref>
                        <note id="n8">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                2
                            </hi> Herbert Harlakenden Gilchrist, ed., <hi rend="i">Anne Gilchrist: Her Life
and Writings</hi>, 2nd ed. (London: T. Fisher Unwin, 1887), pp. 2-9.</note>
                        <note id="n9">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                3
                            </hi> The cottage was Brookbank, at Shottermill near Haslemere. This is the home
Anne Gilchrist let to George Henry Lewes and George Eliot in 1871 where they read her husband’s life of
Blake and where, in a study lined with Blake drawings and engravings, George Eliot wrote the second part of
<hi rend="i">Middlemarch.</hi> Gilchrist, pp. 155-56, 215-19.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Apparently Rossetti had written to Earl’s Colne, then learned, probably through a
dinner invitation from Mr. Ireland who lived in Chelsea, that Mrs. Gilchrist had moved for a while. I suspect
she was visiting the Irelands who had been her neighbors on Great Cheyne Row. (She and Alexander lived at no.
6; Thomas Carlyle and his wife lived at no. 5, next door; and later in 1862 Rossetti himself moved to nearby
16 Cheyne Walk.) Mrs. Isabella Ireland had offered help tending the children who were also sick with
“Scarlatina” when their father died.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">4</ref>
“Mr. Ireland” appears in several of Rossetti’s letters from this period, usually as a source of materials
for Rossetti’s projected memoir of Alexander Gilchrist.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">5</ref> But Rossetti names him “<hi rend="i">W.</hi> Ireland” while Herbert H. Gilchrist, writing
his mother’s memoir, calls him “Edwin.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">6</ref> Perhaps he had a familiar name (“Winny”?). Perhaps Rossetti’s pen or memory slipped. Or
perhaps Herbert Gilchrist, the only source for “Edwin,” misremembered: he was five years old and seriously ill
when his family left Chelsea. 
                        <note id="n10">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                4
                            </hi> Gilchrist, pp. 101, 107, 114.</note>
                        <note id="n11">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                5
                            </hi> Doughty and Wahl, II, 441, 452, 454, 455.</note>
                        <note id="n12">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                6
                            </hi> Gilchrist, p. 107.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>A final word. This note is one of several written to arrange a meeting between Anne
Gilchrist, Dante Rossetti and, occasionally, William Michael Rossetti. There are almost as many letters
postponing meetings or apologizing for missed ones. In fact, the direct evidence that the Rossettis saw much
of Mrs. Gilchrist in the process of bringing the <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> to publication is slight.
What William Rossetti wrote of Alexander Gilchrist characterizes the relationship, in 1862, between Dante and
Anne: “. . . I cannot remember that I saw him more than once or twice again. We were both busy men, and one
casualty or another kept us apart.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">7</ref>
                        <note id="n13">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                7
                            </hi> “Prefatory Notice” in Gilchrist, pp. ix-x. I wish to express my appreciation
to Mrs. Imogen Dennis, of Oxford, England, for her kind permission to publish this Rossetti letter.</note>
                    </p>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p05-182" n="182" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>