<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>5.3.tayler</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">The Source of Bring out number, weight &amp; measure in a year of
dearth</title>
                <author n="Tayler">Edward W. Tayler</author>
                <author n="Frost">Everett C. Frost</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter, 1971-72</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971-72</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/an illustrated quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">05.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Roberta Goetsch</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971-72"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_05">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-05-3-0005">
            	<pb id="p05-213" n="213"/>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">EDWARD W.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">TAYLER</hi>
                            </name>:</docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">EVERETT C.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">FROST</hi>
                            </name>:</docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">LOS ANGELES</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">The Source of “Bring out number, weight &amp; measure in a year of
dearth”</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Edward W. Tayler</hi> Louis Middleman asserts (<hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 4 [Spring 1971], 147) that Blake’s use of the Bible, though “copiously documented,”
includes an unnoticed allusion to <hi rend="i">mene, mene, tekel, upharsin.</hi> But the infernal Proverb in
question, “Bring out number, weight &amp; measure in a year of dearth,” unquestionably relies on the
apocryphal book of the Wisdom of Solomon 11.21: <hi rend="i">omnia in mensura et numero et pondere
disposuisti</hi> (“thou hast disposed all in measure and number and weight”). This verse is quoted, varied
from, and alluded to frequently in medieval and renaissance literature. Blake, doubtless, knew the original;
but he could also have encountered it in any number of neo-platonic treatises, not to mention John Donne and
Ben Jonson. In any case Blake would have had to go no farther than his edition of John Milton which would
include the commendatory lines of Andrew Marvell:
<q>
Thy verse created like thy <hi rend="i">Theme</hi> sublime,<lb/>
In Number, Weight, and Measure, needs not <hi rend="i">Rhime.</hi>
						</q>
There is no need, then, to confuse Blake’s Proverb with Daniel’s “numbered, numbered, weighed,
divided.”</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Everett C. Frost</hi> Louis Middleman argues that the fourteenth Proverb
of Hell (“Bring out number, weight &amp; measure in a year of dearth”) “is built on a close translation of the
Aramaic writing on the wall (Daniel 5.25-28), ‘mene, mene, tekel, upharsin,’ or ‘numbered, numbered,
weighed, divided.’ ”</p>
                    <p>But first, Middleman’s translation of this perplexing phrase is hardly “close”
(literal), though it is viable enough working <hi rend="i">backwards</hi> from a knowledge of Blake’s
Proverb; and, while the apocalyptic concerns of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> invite an astute reader to find
a <hi rend="i">parallel</hi> in the Daniel passage (and in many other Biblical passages as well), they do not,
of themselves, justify a derivation.</p>
                    <p>Second, a much less elliptical possibility lies closer to hand. Much more likely that
Blake’s Devil is having corrosive fun with one of Milton’s angelic interpreters, Andrew Marvell, whose
poem, “On Paradise Lost,” typically prefaces Milton’s poem and concludes with the lines:
<q>
Thy verse, created like thy Theme sublime,<lb/>
In Number, weight, and measure needs not rime.
</q>
Blake’s Devil may be thought of as mocking Marvell for being cowed by Milton’s resonances into accepting
Milton’s Deistical Trinity of Destiny, ratio of the five senses, and vacuum. He agrees with Marvell that
“number, weight, and measure” is a fit description of Milton’s poem—though not of the verse only.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>