<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>5.3.bindman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Ruthven Todd, William Blake the Artist</title>
                <author n="Bindman">David Bindman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter, 1971-72</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971-72</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/an illustrated quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">05.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Roberta Goetsch</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971-72"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_05">
        <body>
	<pb id="p05-210" n="210"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-05-3-0004">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Ruthven Todd. <hi rend="i">WILLIAM BLAKE THE ARTIST.</hi> Studio
Vista/Dutton Pictureback. London: Studio Vista; New York: Dutton, 1971. Pp. 160, illus. £1.80 hardbound, 80p
paper. $2.25 paper, U.S.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="i">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="i">David</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="i">Bindman</hi>
                            </name>,</docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">Lecturer in the History of Art, Westfield College, University of
London</hi>
                    </byline>
                    <p>Ruthven Todd has been something of a legend to students of Blake, and this book is his
most lengthy contribution to Blake studies for many years. Most people who have been lucky enough to get hold
of his long out-of-print <hi rend="i">Tracks in the Snow</hi> treasure it as one of the few classics on the
subject of English Romantic painting, particularly on the painters of the Sublime, of whose company Blake was
proud to regard himself a member.</p>
                    <p>The present book is an excellent if unconventional introduction to Blake, for it
concentrates not on the interpretation of the Prophetic Books, but on Blake as a craftsman working within the
limitations of his situation as a penurious engraver. The book follows the career of Blake year by year, and a
picture of the man emerges, not just as a visionary, but as a proud and even defiant craftsman, prepared to
take on any engraving work to give himself time to work on his visions. Even in his last illness nothing
persuaded him to put down the large folio in which he was making the
<pb id="p05-211" n="211"/>
Dante watercolors, and in certain years, in particular the year 1795, the amount of constructive and
experimental activity was breathtaking. The author is at pains to show what was actually involved in the 
<hi rend="i">making</hi> of Blake’s Prophetic Books and color prints, and he puts into perspective Blake’s
innovations in relief printing.</p>
                    <p>The most useful parts of the book for Blake scholars will be the regrettably brief
accounts of Blake’s stereotype and color-printing processes. Mr. Todd has carried out his own experiments,
and has provided a convincing account of Blake’s solution to one of the most obvious difficulties involved
in combining text and design on a copper plate: getting the lettering the right way round. What slightly
worries me is how Blake stopped the nitric acid, which must have covered the plate for some length of time,
from eating away <hi rend="i">under</hi> the lettering—or was some simple method known at this time of
preventing it? The problems of Blake’s color-printing processes are harder to fathom, and it is to be hoped
that Mr. Todd will devote a much lengthier work to the whole problem of Blake’s printing techniques in the
near future.</p>
                    <p>Some mention should also be made of the excellent choice of illustrations. They are
hardly ever the most obvious examples, and English readers can be particularly grateful that he has not
reproduced works from the Tate when less familiar ones will do. One is grateful, for example, for
reproductions of the Minneapolis <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi>, the Metropolitan Museum 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and the Edinburgh <hi rend="i">Hecate.</hi> With well over 100 illustrations the book seems
to me to be an excellent value, and its modest format makes a refreshing change from the bulkiness of many
recent books on Blake.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>