<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>5.3.checklist</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="checklist">A Checklist of Blake Scholarship, October 1970 - March 1972</title>
                <author n="Foreman">Foster Foreman</author>
                <author n="Grossman">Susan Grossman</author>
                <author n="Wyatt">David Wyatt</author>
                <author n="Goetsch">Roberta Goetsch</author>
                <author n="Nakamura">Kenji Nakamura</author>
                <author n="Le Vot">Andre Le Vot</author>
                <author n="Keller">Michael A. Keller</author>
                <author n="Connolly">Thomas Connolly</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter, 1971-72</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1971-72</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/an illustrated quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">05.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Donald D. Ault</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Roberta Goetsch</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1971-72"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_05">
        <body>
	<pb id="p05-214" n="214"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-05-3-0007">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">A CHECKLIST OF BLAKE SCHOLARSHIP<lb/>
						OCTOBER 1970—MARCH 1972</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <p>This is our fourth checklist. It was compiled principally by Foster Foreman, Susan
Grossman, and David Wyatt, all of the University of California, Berkeley and by Roberta Goetsch, of the
University of New Mexico. The Japanese items were kindly contributed by Kenji Nakamura, College of Education,
Tokyo University; the French items by Professor Andre Le Vot of the Sorbonne; and all the musical scores by
Michael A. Keller, Music Library, State University of New York at Buffalo. Our thanks to Professor Thomas
Connolly for his initiative in getting the list of musical scores compiled. To the best of our knowledge, the
scores have not been listed previously in any Blake bibliography or checklist.</p>
                <p>Again this year we have included entries for many items that are not scholarly, but that we
believe our readers will be interested in knowing about, such as films, videotapes, theatrical productions,
phonograph records, tapes, and musical scores And again, especially in the non-scholarly categories but also
in the scholarly ones, we have listed a number of items whose dates fall far outside our nominal 1970-71
boundaries. For the first time we have listed the contents of the <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> itself in the
Checklist. The contents of the present issue are not included.</p>
                <p>We would appreciate corrections and additions from our readers.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="i">The list is divided into these categories: Bibliography/Catalogues/New
and Revised Books/Reprinted Books/Articles and Sections of Books/Reviews/Films and Videotapes/Tapes and
Phonograph Records/Theater/Musical Scores.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb id="p05-215" n="215"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">BIBLIOGRAPHY</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Allentuck, Marcia. “Addendum to Bentley and Nurmi: Stillman on Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi>, 64 (4th quarter 1970), 463.</p>
                    <p>Erdman, David V. “Blake.” <hi rend="i">English Poetry: Select Bibliographical
Guides.</hi> Ed. A. E. Dyson. London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1971. Pp. 144-66.</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="i">et al.</hi> “The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical
Bibliography for 1970.” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes.</hi> 9 (Supplement) (Sept. 1971), 27-35.</p>
                    <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">A Finding List of Reproductions of Blake’s Art.</hi>
Published as the combined Summer-Fall 1971 issue of the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Gorham, L., <hi rend="i">et al.</hi> “A Checklist of Blake Scholarship / June
1969-September 1970.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Fall 1970), 51-59. <hi rend="i">See also</hi> 
“ ‘A Checklist of Blake Scholarship / June 1969-1970,’: Additions and Corrections.” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971), 73-74.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">CATALOGUES</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of Mrs. London K. Thorne.</hi>
New York: Pierpont Morgan Library, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the
Fitzwilliam Museum. Cambridge.</hi> Cambridge: Heffer, for the Syndics of Fitzwilliam Museum, 1970.</p>
                    <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Complete Catalogue of the Works in the
Tate Gallery.</hi> London: Tate Gallery, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Water-Colour Designs for the Poems of
Thomas Gray.</hi> Introduction and commentary by Geoffrey Keynes. Paris: Trianon Press for the William Blake
Trust, 1971. [“ . . . a Commemorative Catalogue to accompany the exhibition” of Blake’s designs at the Tate
Gallery, London, and the Paul Mellon Center for British Art and British Studies, Yale University, 1971-72]</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">NEW AND REVISED BOOKS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Alldritt, Keith. <hi rend="i">The Visual Imagination of D. H. Lawrence.</hi> London:
Edward Arnold, 1971. [Blake noted briefly but frequently.]</p>
                    <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">America: A Prophecy. Stony Brook ¾</hi> (1969), 1-16.
[monochromatic facsimile]</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Auguries of Innocence, by William Blake.</hi> Illustrated by Paul P.
Piech. 2 Willow Dene, Bushey Heath: Taurus Press, 1970.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake: Complete Writings.</hi> Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. Reprinted with
corrections. Oxford Standard Authors. London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1971.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Gray.</hi> Ed. Irene Tayler.
Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press; London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1971.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel: A Facsimile and a Critical Text.</hi> Ed. Nancy
Bogen. Providence, R. I.: Brown Univ. Press; New York: N. Y. Public Library, 1971.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Chimney Sweeper.</hi> Bushey Heath: Taurus Press, 1969.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">A Choice of Blake’s Verse.</hi> Ed. Kathleen Raine. London: Faber,
1970.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Divine Image, by William Blake.</hi> Illustrated by Paul P.
Piech. 2 Willow Dene, Bushey Heath: Taurus Press, 1970.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Drawings of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. New York: Dover
Publications; London: Constable, 1970.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Infant Sorrow, by William Blake.</hi> Illustrated by Duine Campbell.
Leicester: Black Knight Press, 1970.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Letters from William Blake to Thomas Butts, 1800-1803.</hi>
Facsimile. Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Press, 1969.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">London.</hi> Illustrated by Paul Piech. Bushey Heath: Taurus Press,
1969 (?).</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Poemas Profeticos y Prosas.</hi> Version y prologo de Christobal
Serra. Barcelona: Barral Editores, 1971.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Poemes.</hi> Trans. and pref. by M. L. Cazamian. (Bilingual
French-English ed.) <hi rend="i">Bilingue Aubier-Flammarin ll.</hi> Paris: Aubier-Flammarin, 1968.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake.</hi> Ed. W. H. Stevenson, text by David
V. Erdman. Longmans Annotated English Poets. London: Longmans, 1971. [distributed in U. S. by Norton]</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> [color facsimile]. New York: Dover, 1971.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience: Shewing the Contrary States of
the Human Soul</hi> [color facsimile]. Introduction and commentary by Sir Geoffrey Keynes. Oxford: Oxford
Univ. Press, 1970.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Then She Bore Pale Desire.</hi> Illustrated by Jeff Nuttall.
Brighton: Hand-printed by T. Kavanaugh, 1969.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Tyger, Tyger.</hi> Illustrated by Paul Piech. Bushey Heath: Taurus
Press, 1969.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Ed. with selections by John Adlard. London:
Studio Vista, 1970.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Water-Colour Designs for the Poems of Thomas
Gray.</hi> Introduction and commentary by Geoffrey Keynes. Paris: Trianon Press for the William Blake Trust,
1971. [“ . . . a Commemorative Catalogue to accompany the exhibition” of Blake’s designs at the Tate
Gallery, London, and the Paul Mellon Center for British Art and British Studies, Yale University, 1971-72]</p>
                    <p>Brunskill, Ann. <hi rend="i">Aphrodite: A Mythical Journey in Eight Episodes with
Etchings by Ann Brunskill.</hi> Accompanying Poems by William Blake (and others). London [?]: World’s End
Press, 1970.</p>
                    <p>Dorfman, Deborah. <hi rend="i">Blake in the Nineteenth Century: His Reputation as a
Poet from Gilchrist to Yeats.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 1969.</p>
                    <p>Dumbaugh, Winnifred. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Vision of America.</hi> Pacific
Grove, Calif.: Boxwood Press, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Erdman, David V. and John E. Grant, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic.</hi> Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press; London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1970. The contents of this volume
are as follows: Eben Bass, “<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience:</hi> The Thrust of Design”;
Irene H. Chayes, “The Presence of Cupid and Psyche”; David V. Erdman, “<hi rend="i">America:</hi> New
Expanses”; John E. Grant, “Envisioning the First <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>”; Jean H. Hagstrum, “Blake
and the Sister-Arts Tradition”; William F. Halloran, “The French Revolution: Revelation’s New Form”; Kenneth
R. Johnston, “Blake’s Cities: Romantic Forms of Urban Renewal”; Henry Lesnick, “Narrative Structure and the
Antithetical Vision of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”; Helen T. McNeil, “The Formal Art of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>”; W. J. T. Mitchell, “Blake’s Composite Art”; Ben F. Nelms, “Text and Design in 
<hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>”; George Quasha, “Orc as a Fiery Paradigm of Poetic Torsion”;
E. J. Rose, “ ‘Forms Eternal Exist Forever’: The Covenant of the Harvest in Blake’s Prophetic Poems”;
Robert E. Simmons, “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>: The Symmetry of Fear”; Irene Tayler, “Metamorphoses of a
Favorite Cat”; Michael J. Tolley, “<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>: ‘to those ychain’d in sleep’ ”; Janet A.
Warner, “Blake’s Use of Gesture”; Brian Wilkie, “Epic Irony in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>”.</p>
                    <p>Harris, Eugenie. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Blake.</hi> Monarch Notes. New
York: Monarch Press, 1965.</p>
                    <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">Blake Studies.</hi> 2nd ed. Clarendon
<pb id="p05-216" n="216"/>
Press: Oxford Univ. Press, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Okamoto, Kenjiro. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> “Masters of Art” Series 3. Tokyo:
Iwasaki Bijutsu-sha, 1970.</p>
                    <p>O’Neill, Judith, ed. <hi rend="i">Critics on Blake.</hi> Readings in Literary
Criticism, 7. London: George Allen and Unwin, 1970.</p>
                    <p>Pointon, Marcia R. <hi rend="i">Milton and English Art.</hi> Manchester: Manchester
Univ. Press, 1970.</p>
                    <p>Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, 1970; New
York: Praeger, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Rasmussen, Egil. <hi rend="i">William Blake: En psykologisk studie.</hi> Oslo: Dreyers
Forlag, B. A. Butenschøn A/S &amp; Co., 1969.</p>
                    <p>Reubart, A. <hi rend="i">et al.</hi>, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake through Student
Eyes.</hi> Oakland: Mills College, Roussel Sargent, 1971. [student papers and poems on Blake for courses
taught January 1970 and 1971]</p>
                    <p><corr type="emend">Revol, Enrique L.</corr> <hi rend="i">Caminos del Exceso: William Blake y el Marques de
Sade.</hi> Argentina: Universidad Nacional de Cordoba, 1964.</p>
                    <p>Rousselot, Jean. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Paris: Edition P. Seghers (Poetes
d’Aujourd’hui) 118, 1964.</p>
                    <p>Singer, June K. <hi rend="i">The Unholy Bible: A Psychological Interpretation of
William Blake.</hi> New York: Putnam, 1970.</p>
                    <p>Tayler, Irene. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Gray.</hi>
Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press; London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Todd, Ruthven. <hi rend="i">William Blake the Artist.</hi> Studio Vista/Dutton
Pictureback. London: Studio Vista; New York: Dutton, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Vogler, Thomas A. <hi rend="i">Preludes to Vision: The Epic Venture in Blake,
Wordsworth, Keats, and Hart Crane.</hi> Berkeley: Univ. of Calif. Press, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Wilson, Mona. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. 3rd ed.
London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Wittreich, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century Accounts of William Blake.</hi>
Gainesville, Fla.: Scholars Facsimiles, 1970.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">REPRINTED BOOKS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Note-Book of William Blake Called the Rossetti
Manuscript.</hi> Ed. Geoffrey Keynes, 1935; rpt. New York: Cooper Square, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Clutton-Brock, Alan Francis. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> 1933; rpt. Haskell House,
1970.</p>
                    <p>Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary.</hi> 1965; rpt. New York: E. P.
Dutton, 1971. [a reprint of the first Brown Univ. Press printing]</p>
                    <p>Gardner, Charles. <hi rend="i">William Blake, the Man.</hi> 1919; rpt. New York:
Haskell House, 1970.</p>
                    <p>James, Laura DeWitt. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Tree of Life.</hi> Berkeley and
London: Shambala Press, 1971. [reprint of <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Finger on the Furnace</hi> (New
York: Vantage Press, 1956) with new illustrations]</p>
                    <p>Jugaku, Bunsho. <hi rend="i">A Bibliographical Study of William Blake’s
Notebook.</hi> 1953; rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1971.</p>
                    <p>Lowery, Margaret Ruth. <hi rend="i">Windows of the Morning: A Critical Study of William
Blake’s “Poetical Sketches.”</hi> 1940; rpt. New York: Archon Books, 1970.</p>
                    <p>Rudd, Margaret. <hi rend="i">Divided Image: A Study of William Blake and W. B.
Yeats.</hi> 1953; rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1970.</p>
                    <p>Story, Alfred. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Life, Character, and Genius.</hi> 1893;
rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1970.</p>
                    <p>Swinburne, Algernon C. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> 1868; rpt. Lincoln, Neb.: Univ.
of Nebraska Press, 1970.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">ARTICLES AND SECTIONS OF BOOKS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Adlard, John. “The Garden of Love.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring
1971), 147-48.</p>
                    <p>Allentuck, Marcia. “Dorothy Richardson on William Blake and the Broadside: An
Unrecorded Appraisal.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Spring 1971), 195-96.</p>
                    <p>Anon. Notice of a Blake exhibition. <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> [of London], 21 Jan.
1971, 9d.</p>
                    <p>—. Notice of a Blake musical to be produced. <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> [of London],
11 July 1970, 14h.</p>
                    <p>Archibald, Douglas N. “Yeats’s Encounters: Observations on Literary Influence and
Literary History.” <hi rend="i">New Literary History</hi>, 1 (1970), 439-69.</p>
                    <p>Bacon, Mary E. “Blake’s Imitation of Pope: A Compliment To The Ladies and A Pretty
Epigram For The Entertainment of Those Who Paid Great Sums In The Venetian And Flemish Ooze.” <hi rend="i">The
Explicator</hi>, 9 (May 1970), item no. 79.</p>
                    <p>Beer, John. “Blake at the Fitzwilliam.” <hi rend="i">Cambridge Review</hi>, 29 Jan.
1971, pp. 110-13.</p>
                    <p>—. “A Reply to Irene Chayes.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring 1971),
144-47.</p>
                    <p>—. “A Reply to John Grant.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971),
103-06.</p>
                    <p>—. Reply to Richard Downing (“Blake and Augustine,” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 18 June
1970, p. 662). <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 2 July 1970, pp. 726-27.</p>
                    <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “An Apocryphal Blake Engraving: <hi rend="i">The Minor’s Pocket
Book</hi> (1814).” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971), 107-08.</p>
                    <p>—. “Blake Scholars and Critics: Commentators and Exhibitions.” 
<hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi>, 40 (Fall 1970), 86-101.</p>
                    <p>—. “Two Contemporary Facsimiles of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi>, 64 (4th quarter 1970)
450-63.</p>
                    <p>Bindman, David. [on the Blake sale at Christie’s, 15 June 1971]. 
<hi rend="i">Guardian Weekly</hi>, 5 June 1971, p. 22.</p>
                    <p>—. “An Unpublished Blake Pencil Drawing of the Lambeth Period,” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Fall 1970), 38-40.</p>
                    <p>—. “William Blake and the Victorians.” <hi rend="i">Cambridge Review</hi>, 29 Jan.
1971, pp. 113-15.</p>
                    <p>Blake, William. “A Vision of the Last Judgment. (From The Notebook).” 
<hi rend="i">Tree: 1</hi> (Winter 1970), 80-82.</p>
                    <p>Bloom, Harold. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: The Bard of Sensibility and the
Form of Prophecy.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1970), 6-20.</p>
                    <p>—. “First and Last Romantics.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 9 (Fall
1970), 225-32.</p>
                    <p>—. “To Reason with a Later Reason: Romanticism and the Rational.” 
<hi rend="i">Midway</hi> 11 (Summer 1970), 96-112.</p>
                    <p>Campbell, William Royce. “The Aesthetic Integrity of Blake’s ‘Island in the
Moon’,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Spring 1971), 137-47.</p>
                    <p>Connolly, Thomas E. “A Blakean Maze,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Fall 1970),
61-68. [on bibliographical description of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>]</p>
                    <p>Crook, J. Mordaunt. “A Neo-Classical Visionary: The Architecture of Thomas
Harrison—III.” <hi rend="i">Country Life</hi>, 6 May 1971, p. 1089.</p>
                    <p>Davie, Donald. “The Poetry of Samuel Menashe.” (Summer 1970), 107-15. [Menashe’s
poetry is compared to Blake’s]</p>
                    <p>deGroot, H. B. “R. H. Horne, Mary Howitt and a Mid-Victorian Version of ‘The Echoing
Green.’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971), 81-88.</p>
                    <p>Downing, Richard. “Blake and Augustine” (letter). <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 18 June 1970, p. 662. [<hi rend="i">see also</hi> Beer, John]</p>
                    <p>Easson, Roger R. “Blake and the Contemporary Art Market.” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring 1971), 137-39.</p>
                    <p>Eaves, Morris. “A List of the Entries in Damon’s <hi rend="i">Blake Dictionary.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Fall 1970), 69-85.</p>
                    <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake’s Newton.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Spring 1971),
149-62.</p>
                    <p>—. “The Blakes at UCLA.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971),
75-78.</p>
                    <p>—. “A Finding List of Reproductions of
<pb id="p05-217" n="217"/>
Blake’s Art.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 5 (Summer-Fall 1971), 1-160 [entire combined issue].</p>
                    <p>Fawcus, Arnold. “Early States of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> Series.” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring 1971), 150.</p>
                    <p>—. “William Blake’s Watercolour Desings Illustrating Gray’s Poems—and Mr. Paul
Mellon.” <hi rend="i">The Connoisseur</hi> 179 (Jan. 1972), 10-14.</p>
                    <p>Finch, G. J. “ ‘Never Pain to Tell Thy Love’—Blake’s Problem Poem.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971), 73-79.</p>
                    <p>Fussell, Paul, Jr. “Writing as Imitation: Observations on the Literary Process.” In A.
Cheuse and R. Koffler, eds., <hi rend="i">The Rarer Action: Essays in Honor of Francis Ferguson.</hi> New
Brunswick, N. J.: Rutgers Univ. Press, 1970. Pp. 218-39. [Blake is discussed pp, 230-32]</p>
                    <p>Ginsberg, Allen. “A Talk with Allen Ginsberg” [interviewed by Alison Colbert]. 
<hi rend="i">Partisan Review</hi>, 38 (no. 3, 1971), 289-309. [more about setting the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> to
music]</p>
                    <p>—. “To Young or Old Listeners: Setting Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> to Music,
and a Commentary on the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971), 98-103.
[reprinting of the liner notes to Ginsberg’s recording of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>; also reprinted in 
<hi rend="i">Caterpillar 14</hi> (January 1971)]</p>
                    <p>Grant, John E. “Addenda and Some Solutions to Tolley’s Blake Puzzles.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Spring 1971), 129-35.</p>
                    <p>—. “Blake’s Designs for <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il
Penseroso</hi>, Part I: A Survey of the Designs.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring 1971),
117-34.</p>
                    <p>—. “Redemptive Action in Blake’s ‘Arlington Court Picture’.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 10 (Winter 1971), 21-26.</p>
                    <p>Hall, Jean. “Blake’s Everlasting Gospel.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall
1971), 61-72.</p>
                    <p>Halloran, W. F. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>: Snakes, Curses, and a Blessing.”
<hi rend="i">South Atlantic Quarterly</hi>, 70 (Spring 1971), 161-79.</p>
                    <p>Harding, Eugene J. “Jacob Boehme and Blake’s ‘The Book of Urizen.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Unisa English Studies</hi>, 8 (June 1970), 3-11.</p>
                    <p>Hazen, James. “Blake’s Tyger and Milton’s Beasts,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>,
3 (Spring 1971), 163-70.</p>
                    <p>Helmstadter, Thomas H. “Blake and Religion: Iconographical Themes in the 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 10 (Spring-Summer 1971), 199-212.</p>
                    <p>Holloway, John. “Blake—The Lyric Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Unisa English Studies</hi>, 8
(March 1970), 33-41.</p>
                    <p>Honnighausen, L. “Aspekte des Blakeverständnisses in der Ästhetik des Neunzehnten
Jahrhunderts.” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Kunstgeschichte</hi>, 33 (1970), 41-53.</p>
                    <p>Howard, John. “An Audience for <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Fall 1970), 19-52.</p>
                    <p>Jackson, M. V. “Prolific and Devourer: From Nonmythic to Mythic Statement in 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and <hi rend="i">A Song of Liberty.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Journal
of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 70 (April 1971), 207-19.</p>
                    <p>Jakobson, Roman. “On the Verbal Art of William Blake and Other Poet-Painters. I. One of
the <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Linguistic Inquiry</hi>, 1 (January 1970), 3-23.</p>
                    <p>James, Laura DeWitt. “Sweet Science.” <hi rend="i">Tree: 1</hi> (Winter 1970), 83-95.
[reprinted from <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Tree of Life</hi>]</p>
                    <p>John, Brian. “William Blake’s ‘Hereford, Ancient Guardian of Wales.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971), 33-42.</p>
                    <p>Jones, M. “Blake’s ‘To Spring’: A Formative Source?” <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi>, n.s. 17 (August 1970), 313-14.</p>
                    <p>Kay, Wallace G. “Blake, Baudelaire, Beckett: The Romantics of Nihilism.” 
<hi rend="i">The Southern Quarterly</hi>, 9 (April 1970), 253-59.</p>
                    <p>Kmetz, Gail. “A Reading of Blake’s ‘The Gates of Paradise.’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, 3 (Spring 1971), 171-85.</p>
                    <p>Knights, L. C. “Early Blake.” <hi rend="i">The Sewanee Review</hi>, 79 (July-Sept.
1971), 377-407.</p>
                    <p>Kroeber, Karl. “Graphic-Poetic Structuring in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of
Urizen.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Fall 1970), 7-18.</p>
                    <p>—. “The Relevance and Irrelevance of Romanticism.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 9 (Fall 1970), 297-306.</p>
                    <p>Leyris, Pierre. “William Blake et Nous.” <hi rend="i">Le Monde</hi>, 8 Oct. 1971, pp.
20-21. [article accompanied by French translation of Blake poems]</p>
                    <p>McGann, Jerome. “Blake and a Tradition.” <hi rend="i">Poetry</hi>, 117 (Oct. 1970),
45-49.</p>
                    <p>Maxwell-Mahon, W. D. “The Prophetic Mind: An Aspect of the Poetry of Blake and Yeats.”
<hi rend="i">Unisa English Studies</hi>, 2 (March 1964), 11-16.</p>
                    <p>Mellor, Anne K. “Blake’s Designs for <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>: An
Affirmation of Innocence.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 50 (April 1971), 193-207.</p>
                    <p>—. “The Human Form Divine and the Structure of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi>, 11 (Autumn 1971), 595-620.</p>
                    <p>Middleman, Louis. “Bring out number, weight, &amp; measure in a year of dearth.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring 1971), 147.</p>
                    <p>Pache, Walter and Ursula Salacki. “Blake and Ovid.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4
(Fall 1971), 89-92.</p>
                    <p>Paley, Morton D. “Blakes at Buffalo.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter
1971), 81-86.</p>
                    <p>Parr, James. “Songs of Imprudence.” <hi rend="i">Humanities Association Bulletin</hi>,
17 (Autumn 1966). [graphic and literary parodies]</p>
                    <p>Peckham, Morse. “On Romanticism: Introduction.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 9 (Fall 1970), 217-24.</p>
                    <p>Pfefferkorn, Eli. “The Question of the Leviathan and the Tiger.” <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, 3 (Fall 1970), 53-60.</p>
                    <p>Phillips, Michael. “Blake’s Corrections in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Fall 1970), 40-47.</p>
                    <p>—. “ ‘Blake’s Corrections in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>’: A
Forthcoming Supplement and the Britwell Court Library Copy.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring
1971), 148-49.</p>
                    <p>Raine, Kathleen. “Blake’s Last Judgment.” <hi rend="i">The Ampleforth Journal</hi>,
76 (Summer 1971), 70-84.</p>
                    <p>Reid, Anthony. “Ralph Chubb, the Unknown; Part I: His Life, 1892-1960.” 
<hi rend="i">Private Library</hi>, 2nd series, 3 (Autumn 1970), 141-56. [parallels between the career and art of
Chubb and Blake]</p>
                    <p>Reisner, Mary E. “The Wages of Art: Blake and His Public.” <hi rend="i">Culture</hi>, 4
(Dec. 1970), 327-37.</p>
                    <p>Reisner, Thomas A. “Cain: Two Romantic Interpretations.” <hi rend="i">Culture</hi>, 2
(June 1970), 124-43.</p>
                    <p>Rhodes, Judith. “Blake’s Designs for <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>: Thematic Relationships in Diagram.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring
1971), 135-36.</p>
                    <p>Rice, Howard C., Jr. “Lesser Known Examples of Blake’s Engraving Skill.” 
<hi rend="i">University: A Princeton Quarterly</hi>, no. 46 (Fall 1970), 2, 26-32; also (with one less
illustration) in <hi rend="i">Princeton Alumni Weekly</hi>, 29 Sept. 1970, pp. 38-44.</p>
                    <p>Rose, Edward J. “Blake’s Fourfold Art.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 49
(July 1970), 400-23.</p>
                    <p>—. “Blake’s Metaphorical States.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971),
9-31.</p>
                    <p>—. “The 1839-Wilkinson Edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in Transcendental
America.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971), 79-81.</p>
                    <p>—. “The Spirit of the Bounding Line: Blake’s Los.” <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 8
(Winter 1971), 54-76.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg, Marc. “Style and Meaning in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Style</hi>, 4 (Fall 1970), 197-212.</p>
                    <p>Salacki, Ursula. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Pache, Walter.</p>
                    <p>Simmons, Robert and Janet Warner. “Blake’s ‘Arlington Court Picture’: The Moment
of Truth.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 10 (Winter 1971), 3-20.</p>
                    <p>Spicer, Harold. “Biblical Sources of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">America.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Ball State University Forum</hi>, 8 (Summer 1967), 23-39.</p>
                    <p>Stevenson, W. H. “Death’s Door.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>,
<pb id="p05-218" n="218"/>
4 (Fall 1970), 49.</p>
                    <p>Takemori, Osamu. “William Blake’s ‘To Tirzah’: An Interpretation.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi> (English Literary Society of Japan), 42 (March 1971), 179-98 [in
Japanese; synopsis in English, pp. 325-26].</p>
                    <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru. “A Study of Spectres in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Questions of Counterpart and Negation.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Reitaku University</hi>
[Reitaku University, Kashiwa], 12 (August 1971), 140-58 [in Japanese].</p>
                    <p>Tarr, Rodger L. “ ‘The Eagle’ versus ‘The Mole’: The Wisdom of Virginity in 
<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Spring 1971),
187-94.</p>
                    <p>Taylor, Peter Alan. “Providence and the Moment in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971), 43-60.</p>
                    <p>Todd, Ruthven. “Blake’s Copy of Dante.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Fall
1970), 49.</p>
                    <p>—. “The Bohn Catalogue and James Vine.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring
1971), 149.</p>
                    <p>Toki, Kohji. “Icons of Albion.” <hi rend="i">English Quarterly</hi> [Apollon-sha,
Kyoto], 8 (August 1971), 222-34 [in Japanese].</p>
                    <p>Tolley, Michael J. “Some Blake Puzzles—Old and New.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>,
3 (Spring 1971), 107-28.</p>
                    <p>Trawick, Leonard M. “The Present State of Blake Studies.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Burke
and His Time</hi>, 40 (Winter 1970-71), 1784-1803.</p>
                    <p>Tsuchiya, Shigeko. “Who is Milton-Blake?” <hi rend="i">English Quarterly</hi>
[Apollon-sha, Kyoto], 8 (March 1971), 144-57 [in Japanese].</p>
                    <p>Uphaus, Robert. “Thomas Traherne: Perception as Process.” <hi rend="i">University of
Windsor Review</hi>, 3 (Spring 1968), 19-27. [Traherne’s idea of perception compared and contrasted with
Blake’s]</p>
                    <p>Valdés, M. J. “Archetype and Recreation: A Comparative Study of William Blake and
Miguel de Unamuno.” <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi>, 40 (Fall 1970), 58-72.</p>
                    <p>Warner, Janet. “James Vine.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971),
106-07.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">See also</hi> Simmons, Robert.</p>
                    <p>Wimsatt, W. K. “Imitation as Freedom—1717-1798.” <hi rend="i">New Literary
History</hi>, 1 (Winter 1970), 215-36.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Beer, John. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Universe.</hi> Reviewed by Rodney M.
Baine, <hi rend="i">Georgia Review</hi>, 25 (Summer 1971), 238-41; Margaret Bottrall, <hi rend="i">Critical
Quarterly</hi>, 12 (Autumn 1970), 286; Irene H. Chayes, <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971),
87-90; Brian John, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971), 107-10; W. H. Stevenson, 
<hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 63 n.s. 32 (Dec. 1970), 74-75.</p>
                    <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> Reviewed by Rodney M. Baine, 
<hi rend="i">Georgia Review</hi>, 25 (Summer 1971), 238-41; F. W. Bateson, <hi rend="i">Review of English
Studies</hi>, 22 (May 1971), 221-22; David Bindman, “Blake through the Eyes of His Contemporaries,” 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 113 (April 1971), 218-19; Norman Brennan, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>,
4 (Fall 1971), 103-07; <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 7 (Nov. 1970), 1229; David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">English
Language Notes</hi>, 9:suppl. to no. 1 (Sept. 1971), 27; T. J. Galvin, <hi rend="i">Library Journal</hi>, 95
(April 1970), 1370; Max F. Schulz, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 4 (Summer 1970), 490-92.</p>
                    <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the
Fitzwilliam Museum. Cambridge.</hi> Reviewed by <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp.
1-3.</p>
                    <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">All Religions Are One</hi> (Blake Trust facsimile).
Described by Arnold Fawcus, <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Fall 1970), 33-34; reviewed by 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Blake-Varley Sketch-book of 1819.</hi> Ed. Martin Butlin.
Reviewed by T. Crombie, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 92 (Oct. 1970), 319.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Drawings of William Blake. 92 Pencil Studies.</hi> Selection,
introduction, and commentary by Geoffrey Keynes. Reviewed by Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971), 99-103; <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Europe, A Prophecy</hi> (Blake Trust facsimile). Reviewed by 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 22 Jan. 1970, p. 14.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Illustrations to the Divine Comedy of Dante.</hi> Reviewed by C.
Ryskamp, <hi rend="i">Master Drawing 8</hi> (Spring 1970), 56.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake Called the Rossetti Manuscript</hi>
(rpt. facsimile). Reviewed by Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring 1971),
142-44.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi> (Longman’s Annotated English
Poets). Ed. W. H. Stevenson, text by David V. Erdman. Reviewed by <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>,
10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake.</hi> Ed. W. B. Yeats (1905; rpt. Harvard
Univ. Press, 1969). Reviewed by <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 6 (Dec. 1969), 1390; Murray Patrick, 
<hi rend="i">Studies</hi> [Dublin], 59 (1970), 215-18; John Wren-Lewis, <hi rend="i">The New Statesman</hi>, 22
Aug. 1969, p. 249.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi> Reviewed by A. Weinberg,
<hi rend="i">Unisa English Studies</hi>, 8 (Nov. 1970), 34-36.</p>
                    <p>Bloom, Harold, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic Argument.</hi>
Reviewed by Rodney M. Baine, <hi rend="i">Georgia Review</hi>, 25 (Fall 1971), 380-81.</p>
                    <p>Boutang, Pierre. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Robert Louit, “Blake Le
Liberateur,” <hi rend="i">Magazine Litteraire</hi>, no. 48 (Jan. 1971), 38-39.</p>
                    <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Complete Catalogue of the Works in the
Tate Gallery.</hi> Reviewed by <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3.</p>
                    <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> (4th printing
with revisions). Reviewed by Rodney M. Baine, <hi rend="i">Georgia Review</hi>, 25 (Fall 1971), 380-81.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Prophet Against Empire</hi> (2nd ed.). Reviewed by Rodney M. Baine,
<hi rend="i">Georgia Review</hi>, 25 (Summer 1971), 238-41; Patrick J. Callahan, <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, 3 (Fall 1970), 87-89; E. J. Rose, <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Fall 1970), 48-49; 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3.</p>
                    <p>Erdman, David. V. and John E. Grant, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic.</hi> Reviewed by Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971), 93-99; 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3; <hi rend="i">Virginia Quarterly</hi>, 47
(Summer 1971), 110.</p>
                    <p>Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry.</hi> Reviewed by Alan Weinberg, 
<hi rend="i">Unisa English Studies</hi>, 8 (Nov. 1970), 34-36.</p>
                    <p>Gardner, Stanley. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Mary Lynn Johnson, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 1 (Fall 1970), 94-98.</p>
                    <p>Ginsberg, Allen. <hi rend="i">Allen Ginsberg/William Blake: “Songs of Innocence and
Experience” by William Blake, tuned by Allen Ginsberg</hi> [a recording]. Reviewed by Morris Eaves, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Winter 1971), 90-97.</p>
                    <p>Goff, Phyllis. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Catalogue of the Preston Blake Library.</hi>
Reviewed by Kenneth Garlick, <hi rend="i">Apollo 92</hi> (1970), 398.</p>
                    <p>Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">William Blake: An Introduction to the Man and to His
Work.</hi> Reviewed by T. E. Luddy, <hi rend="i">Library Journal</hi>, 95 (August 1970), 2682.</p>
                    <p>Mitchell, Adrian. <hi rend="i">Tyger</hi> [a musical]. Reviewed by Michael Billington,
<hi rend="i">The Times</hi>, 22 Jan. 1971, p. 13. [reprinted in this issue of the 
<hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi>]</p>
                    <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of
Blake’s Thought.</hi> Reviewed by Rodney M. Baine, <hi rend="i">Georgia Review</hi>, 25 (Summer 1971),
238-41; <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 7 (Oct. 1970), 1042; Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">Modern Language
Quarterly</hi>, 32 (Sept. 1971), 326-28; John Howard, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Spring 1971),
197-99;
<pb id="p05-219" n="219"/>
John D. Jump, <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi>, 13 (Spring 1971), 87-88; R. E. Luddy, <hi rend="i">Library
Journal</hi>, 95 (Aug. 1970), 2682; P. Malekin, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, n.s. 22 (Aug.
1971), 352-54; Robin Mayhead, <hi rend="i">English</hi>, 22 (Summer 1971), 59-62; <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3; <hi rend="i">Virginia Quarterly</hi>, 47 (Summer 1971), 110.</p>
                    <p>—, ed. <hi rend="i">Twentieth Century Interpretations of “Songs of Innocence and of
Experience”: A Collection of Critical Essays.</hi> Reviewed by Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, 3 (Fall 1970), 91-94; A. Weinberg, <hi rend="i">Unisa English Studies</hi>, 8 (Nov. 1970),
34-36.</p>
                    <p>Pointon, Marcia R. <hi rend="i">Milton and English Art.</hi> Reviewed by J. R. Harvey,
<hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 63 n.s. 32 (June 1971), 244-46.</p>
                    <p>Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition.</hi> Reviewed by P. Malekin, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, 22 (Feb. 1971), 93-95; E. J. Rose, <hi rend="i">Dalhousie
Review</hi>, 50 (Summer 1970), 269-71; Peter Russell, <hi rend="i">Southern Review</hi>, n.s. 7 (Oct. 1971),
1145-56.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Jean Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">Modern
Philology</hi>, 68 (Aug. 1970), 76-82; <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3; H.
R. Wackrill, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall 1971), 110-13.</p>
                    <p>Rosenfeld, Alvin H., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon.</hi>
Reviewed by Margaret Bottrall, <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi>, 12 (Autumn 1970), 286; P. Malekin, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, 22 (Feb. 1971), 93-95; Max F. Schulz, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi>, 4 (Winter 1970-71), 223-29.</p>
                    <p>Tayler, Irene. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Gray.</hi> Reviewed
by Thomas Helmstadter, <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (Spring 1971), 140-42; <hi rend="i">Times
Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3.</p>
                    <p>Todd, Ruthven. <hi rend="i">William Blake: the Artist.</hi> Reviewed by 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3.</p>
                    <p>Wells, William. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s “Heads of the Poets.”</hi> Reviewed by
Desirée Hirst, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (Fall 1970), 98-100.</p>
                    <p>Wilson, Mona. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. 3rd ed.
Reviewed by <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 Dec. 1971, pp. 1-3.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">FILMS AND VIDEOTAPES</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Blake’s “America.”</hi> Produced and directed by Janet Warner, John
Sutherland, and Robert Wallace. York University, 1970. [videotape]</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Blake’s “Visions of the Daughters of Albion.”</hi> Produced and
directed by Janet Warner, John Sutherland, and Robert Wallace. York University, 1971. [videotape]</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Holy Thursday.</hi> George F. Hood and Richard Blakeslee, 1969. 20
minutes. Sound, color, 16 mm. [“A visual poem . . . . to explore the meaning of William Blake’s Holy
Thursday section of his <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi>”]</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">William Blake: Innocence and Experience.</hi> Produced and directed for
ABC-TV’s <hi rend="i">Directions</hi> by Aram Boyajian. First telecast 16 Jan. 1972.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">William Blake: Prophet.</hi> Produced and directed for ABC-TV’s 
<hi rend="i">Directions</hi> by Aram Boyajian. First telecast 23 Jan. 1972.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">TAPES AND PHONOGRAPH RECORDS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Britten, Benjamin. <hi rend="i">Songs &amp; Proverbs of William Blake, Op. 74; The Holy
Sonnets of John Donne, Op. 35.</hi> Peter Pears, tenor, Dietrich FischerDieskau, baritone, and Benjamin
Britten, piano. London OS 26099. [a new recording]</p>
                    <p>DeMott, Benjamin. <hi rend="i">Blake and Manchild.</hi> Sound Seminars 75998. New York:
McGraw-Hill, n.d., [tape recording]</p>
                    <p>Parry, Hubert. “Jerusalem” [“And did those feet in ancient time”] in <hi rend="i">The
Last Night of the Proms.</hi> BBC Symphony conducted by Colin Davis. Philips 6502-001. [Edward Elgar’s
arrangement, with the Proms audience as chorus]</p>
                    <p>Vaughan Williams, Ralph. <hi rend="i">Job, A Masque for Dancing</hi> [1930]. London
Symphony Orchestra conducted by Sir Adrian Boult. Angel-EMI S-36773, [based on Blake’s Job illustrations; a
new recording; the old was conducted by Boult with the London Philharmonic, Everest 3019]</p>
                    <p>—. [A recording that includes V-W’s Blake songs, sung by Ian Partridge]. EMI
HQS-1236.</p>
                    <p>—. <hi rend="i">Three Song Cycles.</hi> Desto DC-6482. [includes V-W’s “Ten Blake
Songs” with Lois Winter, soprano, John Langstaff, baritone, and Ronald Roseman, oboe]</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">THEATER</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Fischetti, Michael, director. “Blake’s Songs of Innocence and Experience.” Part III
of <hi rend="i">Three Pieces in Multi Media.</hi> Performed in New York by the Dance and Drama Theatre of New
York City, January 1972.</p>
                    <p>McGann, Jerome <hi rend="i">et al. The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> Performed by
Cain’s Company at Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, Chicago, 8-12 May 1970.</p>
                    <p>Mitchell, Adrian. <hi rend="i">Tyger.</hi> Performed by the British National Theatre in
London, 1971. [musical comedy]</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">MUSICAL SCORES</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Anson, H. V. Three Blake Partsongs for female or boys’ voices. n.d.</p>
                    <p>Bantock, G. Three Blake Songs: 1. In a myrtle shade, 2. The wildflower’s song, 3.
Love’s secret. 1909.</p>
                    <p>Beeson, J. Three Songs: 1. I laid me down upon a bank, 2. Never seek to tell thy love,
3. I asked a thief. 1945.</p>
                    <p>Bezanson, P. T. Songs of Innocence. New York: American Composers Alliance, 1962.</p>
                    <p>Birch, R. F. Memory, come hither. (Op. 21, no. 1,) New York: Patelson, 1952.</p>
                    <p>Brian, H. Songs which include settings of Blake. Not published, no date.</p>
                    <p>Brook, H. “The Shepherd” in Kinley, E. A. <hi rend="i">A song book.</hi> Toronto:
Clarke, Irwin, 1940.</p>
                    <p>Busch, W. Four Songs: 1. Memory, come hither, 2. Laughing song, 3. The Echoing green,
4. The shepherd. 1943.</p>
                    <p>Davies, H. W. I love the jocund dance. (Op. 18, no. 4.) 1905.</p>
                    <p>Delaney, R. M. Night. Boston: E. Schirmer, 1934.</p>
                    <p>Duke, V. Four songs. New York: Broude, 1955.</p>
                    <p>Goosens, E. Two songs. 1922.</p>
                    <p>Hart, F. Seven songs. (Op. 25.) 1917.</p>
                    <p>Homer, S. The sick rose and Infant sorrow. (Op. 26.) New York: G. Schirmer, 1912.</p>
                    <p>Lloyd, C. H. To morning, for 8 part chorus. n.d.</p>
                    <p>Luening, O. Three songs for high voice and piano, no. 2 “Young love”, no. 3 “Auguries
of innocence.” New York: G. Schirmer, 1944.</p>
                    <p>McLain, M. S. To a child asleep. New York: Morris, c1946.</p>
                    <p>Moeran, E. J. The echoing green. 1933.</p>
                    <p>Poldowski, Lady D. P. Song. n.d.</p>
                    <p>Powell, L. To Spring. London: Williams, c1922.</p>
                    <p>—. To Summer. London: Williams, c1930.</p>
                    <p>Spelman, T. M. I love the jocund dance. New York: Galaxy, c1938.</p>
                    <p>Thomson, V. The sunflower. 1919.</p>
                    <p>Voynich, E. L. The golden net, a cantata. n.d.</p>
                    <p>Whiting, A. B. The golden cage. New York: G. Schirmer, c1926.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>