<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.antippas</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Thomas A. Vogler, Preludes to Vision</title>
                <author n="Antippas">Andy P. Antippas</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
	<pb id="p06-34" n="34"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0006">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Thomas A. Vogler. <hi rend="i">Preludes to Vision: The Epic Venture
in Blake, Wordworth, Keats, and Hart Crane.</hi> Berkeley: University of California Press, 1971. Pp. 222.
$7.50.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Andy P. <name>Antippas</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n70" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>Mr. Vogler’s study examines in detail Blake’s <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Wordsworth’s <hi rend="i">Prelude</hi>, Keats’ <hi rend="i">Fall of Hyperion</hi>,
and Crane’s <hi rend="i">Bridge.</hi> Crane is by no means a stranger to the “visionary company” (the phrase
is from Crane’s “The Broken Tower”); however, I would have also liked included a discussion of Tennyson or
Browning or Meredith to avoid reopening the abyss now sealed over by Bloom, Langbaum, Kermode, and Miller.
Vogler chooses his poems on the basis of a “set of intuitive criteria” (p. 12)—the same decision, he reminds
us, Aristotle made when he selected certain dramas to define tragedy. Vogler’s analogy is apt. Just as
Aristotle entered his subject with certain philosophic prepossessions and set forth a poetic that satisfies
one play, <hi rend="i">Oedipus Rex</hi>, so Vogler comes to Blake, Wordsworth, and Keats with certain critical
predispositions gathered over the years from his work on Crane’s <hi rend="i">Bridge.</hi> Whether these
criteria illuminate the <hi rend="i">Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and contribute something new to
our understanding of Blake is questionable.</p>
                    <p>The introductory section, “In Search of the Epic,” presents the less-than-novel view
that the epic genre died after Milton. More interestingly, Vogler observes that poets had “not given up the
[‘desire,’ (p. 2), or the] attempt to write epic poetry” (p. 4). His comments, however, concerning the
difficulty in writing an epic in the absence of a common ideology, and concerning the epic poet’s obligation
“to give to his race or age a completion and embodiment of the meaning of life that he finds in the accepted
but not necessarily conscious metaphysic of the time” (p. 8), go back at least as far as Arnold’s “Function
of Criticism,” A. C. Bradley’s “The Long Poem in Wordsworth’s Age,” and echo uncomfortably Lascelles
Abercrombie’s classic essays on the epic: “We see him [the epic poet] accepting, and with his genius
transfiguring, the general circumstances of his time; we see him symbolizing, in some appropriate form,
whatever sense of the significance of life he feels acting as the accepted unconscious metaphysic of his
age.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">1</ref>
                        <note id="n44">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> The Epic</hi> (London: Martin Secker, n.d.), p. 39.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Since Vogler has undertaken to discuss, in Wellek and Warren’s terms, the “inner
form” of the epic (“attitude, tone, purpose”), one might expect some difficulty in pinning down a working
definition or description of the material. We must be satisfied with: a long narrative poem whose subject
<note id="n70">
                            <hi rend="i">Andy P. Antippas, Assistant Professor of English at Tulane
University, has published articles on Romantic and Victorian poets. He is presently co-editing a volume of
essays on the Gothic novel.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-35" n="35"/>
is the poet’s heroic exploratory attempt “to find a personal visionary perspective” (p. 14) and records “the
poet in the process of ordering his experience of reality into the poetic fabric” (p. 11)—a definition, in
short, roughly similar to those of Elizabeth Sewell and Karl Kroeber.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">2</ref> Vogler, as Abercrombie and others do, enlarges the meaning of the internal
<hi rend="i">geste</hi> from the heuristic and potentially egoistic to the social level whereby the epic
awakens “man as well as the poet” (p. 13). <note id="n45">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                2
                            </hi> Sewell, <hi rend="i">The Orphic Voice</hi> (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press,
1960), pp. 302 f.; Kroeber, <hi rend="i">Romantic Narrative Art</hi> (Madison: Wisconsin Univ. Press, 1960),
pp. 84 f.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Each of the poems discussed, Vogler contends, is a “prelude to vision”; it records the
failed effort of the poet to achieve an ordered and adequate envisagement of the world from which still point
he could have then proceeded to give fuller scope to his creativity in a long, philosophical poem in the
manner outlined by Wordsworth. The critic should at least be wary of reading a body of poetry with an eye to
seeing one poem as an anticipation of, or a prelude to, the poem it precedes, especially when there are
problems of chronological sequence. This approach, at the outset, deprives a “prelude” poem of any aesthetic
unity, since it must await fulfillment elsewhere; when this approach is carried out too literally, it becomes
a taxonomical suggestion that the “prelude” poem is less significant than its successor. Further, (and this is
implied by Frye’s reluctance to consider one particular literary period as merely a precursor to another),
this approach commits us to imposing a “false teleology on everything we study”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">3</ref>—in Blake’s case, a “false eschatology” would be the
result. <note id="n46">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                3
                            </hi> “Towards Defining an Age of Sensibility,” in <hi rend="i">Fables of
Identity</hi> (New York: Harcourt, 1963), p. 130.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Peter F. Fisher was the first, I think, to use Blake’s own term “Preludium” to
explain the relationships between the <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, the
minor prophecies and the <hi rend="i">Zoas</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>; he is careful to suggest, however, that a
“Preludium” means “Correction, definition and presentation of subject-matter . . . the author ‘finding’
his theme, and <hi rend="i">at the same time, presenting it.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n47" type="note">4</ref> In other words, although one poem may well presage another, it has its own
purpose and its own end. In his second chapter, “The Holy Vessel,” Vogler argues that only the “elements of
the change [in Los] are present . . . in a way that gives us little more than the fact stated, as if in
anticipation of the central problem of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> The question we have been trying to answer
unsuccessfully from Night 7a will be answered in full in [<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>] . . . ” (p. 37). If one
looks for an answer in a poem that does not pose the question, one will certainly find the poem incomplete.
Vogler does further disservice to the <hi rend="i">Zoas</hi> by discounting the problems raised by 7b (which
Bloom calls a “rival” vision of 7a, not merely another version<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n48" type="note">5</ref>), and by omitting all consideration of Nights 8 and 9. Even accepting the
limitations imposed on the text, I cannot agree that 7a ends with a “shift in focus, barely discernible in the
confusion . . . ” (p. 32). Where formerly irresponsible chaos ruled, now Urthona’s Spectre and Los are fused
in artistic labor, raising the pillars and domes of Golgonooza; and when Enitharmon merges with Los, they
together illuminate the heavens with “immortal lines.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">6</ref> Where for six unholy Nights darkness and ignorance prevailed, Los’ fires now burn: “look
my fires enlume afresh . . . ” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 356). Because art and love permeate the cosmos, even Orc
and Tharms are comforted. Most importantly, redemption is both immanent and imminent: “but look! behold! take
comfort! / Turn inwardly thine Eyes &amp; there behold the Lamb of God / Clothed in Luvahs robes of blood
descending to redeem” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 355). None of this, I submit, is either “barely discernible” or
confused and should be seen as a hopeful and major turn of events—whether considered as a conclusion to the
<hi rend="i">Zoas</hi> or as a link to Night 8, wherein these new relationships immediately stir Albion from
his sleep of death. <note id="n47">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                4
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Valley of Vision</hi>, ed. N. Frye (Toronto: Univ. of Toronto Press,
1963), pp. 246-47; italics added.</note>
                        <note id="n48">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                5
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Blake’s Apocalypse</hi> (New York: Doubleday, 1963), p.
244.</note>
                        <note id="n49">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                6
                            </hi> Erdman’s edition, p. 356; hereafter <hi rend="i">E.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Chapter Three, “Blake: Mental Fight,” follows much too closely Bloom’s “Prelude to
Apocalypse: Milton.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">7</ref> There is nothing
to comment upon in Vogler’s summary of the narrative or his contention, already convincingly argued by
Bloom,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">8</ref> that “Although the poem is in
part a purification and recreation of the poet Milton, it is more basically an expression of the self-creation
of the poet, embodied in Blake . . . ” (p. 39). The instructive difference between Bloom’s and Vogler’s
treatments of the “prelude” theme in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> brings us back to the difficulties discussed
above in connection with the handling of the <hi rend="i">Zoas.</hi> Bloom concludes by celebrating the
achievement in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> for “the moving passion with which Blake believed in the truth of the
awakened imagination. . . . ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">9</ref> And
that, after all, is what the poem set out to do: awaken Milton-Blake’s imagination with the assistance of
Los and prepare the slumberous mass of Albion for Christ’s entry into his bosom. Because Vogler is intent on
reading <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as merely a presentiment of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, he can only observe
that the poem ends without the “vision of the apocalypse itself”; and, he continues, since 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, finally, does not fulfill the apocalypse prophesied at the end of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, the latter poem is consigned to “a somewhat strange position in the canon of Blake’s
writing” (pp. 58-59). <note id="n50">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                7
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Apocalypse</hi>, pp. 304-64.</note>
                        <note id="n51">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                8
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Apocalypse</hi>, p. 303.</note>
                        <note id="n52">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                9
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Apocalypse</hi>, p. 364.</note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p06-36" n="36"/>
                    <p>Vogler seems to have forgotten what Bloom clearly remembers, and what Frye cites at the
beginning and the end of his study<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">10</ref>—namely, Blake’s own injunction: “Every poem must necessarily be a perfect Unity. . .
. when a work has unity, it is as much in a part as in the whole . . . ” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 267). The
Prophetic Books certainly develop and expand into each other: Blake’s comment on 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, that it is a “more consolidated &amp; extended Work . . . ” (<hi rend="i">E</hi>
143), could be prefixed to each of the long poems in turn. They requite and reprise each other, and together
reach out toward a supreme fiction, in Erich Kahler’s phrase, for that “all embracement of
discontinuity”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">11</ref> which is the essence
of the modern long poem—Aiken’s <hi rend="i">Preludes</hi>, for example. Each of the Prophetic Books is in
itself a unified, concordant gesture against Error and an epic probe into Albion’s sleeping brain. That they
may be said to end <hi rend="i">in mediis rebus</hi>, inside history and before the Fullness of Time, is not
to deny them an authentic eschatology. Blake fills and ends his Prophetic Books with spiritual and mental
crises because he knew Albion and his creative reader both, striking down selfishness, ignorance, and apathy,
could at any moment awaken to glory. Blake would have agreed with <corr type="emend">Bultmann:</corr> “In
every moment slumbers the possibility of being the eschatological moment. You must awaken it.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">12</ref>
                        <note id="n53">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                10
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Fearful Symmetry</hi> (1947; rpt. Boston: Beacon Press, 1962), pp.
10, 426.</note>
                        <note id="n54">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                11
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> The Tower and the Abyss</hi> (New York: Viking, 1967), pp. 110,
132.</note>
                        <note id="n55">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                12
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> History and Eschatology</hi> (Edinburgh: Univ. Press, 1957), p.
155.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Because Blake would not approve the Newtonian subdivision here in isolating a few
chapters for review (“Sacrifice the Parts, What becomes of the Whole” [<hi rend="i">E</hi> 639]), I will say
simply that Vogler’s consideration of Wordsworth, Keats, and Crane is judicious and insightful.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>