<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.todd</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">A Recollection of George Richmond by His Grandson</title>
                <author n="Todd">Ruthven Todd</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0005">
            	<pb id="p06-24" n="24"/>
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Minute Particulars.</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">A RECOLLECTION OF GEORGE RICHMOND BY HIS GRANDSON</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Ruthven <name>Todd</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n64" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>At Christmas 1971, David Bindman sent me the most generous gift of a page, c. 1850,
from a sketchbook by George Richmond, of some semi-aquatic plants and a tiny woodland scene in the lower left
corner. This sent me hunting through some unsorted papers in search of a note which I remembered making,
although, as I had not then moved into the cottage which I now occupy, I feared that it might have been lost
with so many other unfiled items. However, I was fortunate and it turned up. This reads:
<q>
Sir Arthur Richmond told me that he remembered his grandfather, George, very clearly and that, toward the end
of his life, his memories of his early youth became particularly bright. It was a pity that Arthur was up here
for such a short time as I wanted to know so much. He suggested that probably these recollections of extreme
old age were more vivid than anything he had produced for Alexander Gilchrist in the 1850s. (I had introduced
the name of Gilchrist.) One thing he told me was that, when Blake died, George closed his eyes: “to keep the
vision in,” George explained. Galilea.
</q>
I had stupidly forgotten to date the note, but an application to John Yeoman, who with his wife had
accompanied Sir Arthur and his wife Greta on this and previous visits to Galilea, has supplied the information
that it was in June 1966. I met Sir Arthur again, for the last time, at lunch in the Chelsea Arts Club at the
end of August in 1967. George Richmond was born in 1809 and lived until 1896. Sir Arthur was born in 1879 and
died in November 1968, three months short of his 90th birthday. This was the only occasion of our meetings
upon which I remember having managed to bring up the subject of Blake. I think that, in explanation of his
saying that George’s memories of his youth were sharper as an old man than when trying to help Gilchrist,
Sir Arthur made the point that, in the 1850s, George was extremely busy making a living and so had more things
upon his mind. When Sir Arthur mentioned the detail of George Richmond’s having closed Blake’s eyes, I did
not at once remember having seen it mentioned before, but then recollected that it was mentioned by H. H.
Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Anne Gilchrist: Her Life and Writings</hi>, 1887, pp. 258-59, and quoted by Mona
Wilson in a note. The remark, “to keep the vision in,” however, has not been previously recorded. There is no
reason to doubt that it is a genuine recollection by a very old man trying to recapture the feelings of the
teen-ager who was present at the deathbed, and who wrote the heartfelt and agitated note to Samuel Palmer, for
his own young grandson. As such I feel that it deserves this explanation of how I came to be the recipient of
the added detail from the only person I have known, so far as I can recall, who was able to give me anything
new which he had actually received from the person who was present. The stretch from August 1827 to August
1967, 140 years, is long enough in all truth, but the fact that David Bindman’s present now hangs in a
cottage in the same village where I heard the remark helps strengthen the cord which pulls me back to examine
the nearly seventy years preceding the first of these dates. <note id="n64">
                            <hi rend="i">Ruthven Todd’s most recent published work on Blake is</hi>
William Blake, the Artist. <hi rend="i">He is an authority on Blake’s biography, among many other things. He
lives on Mallorca.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>