<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.grant</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">On Mary Ellen Reisner’s Locations of Copy U of Songs of Innocence
and Copy d of Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title>
                <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <pb id="p06-22" n="22"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0004">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Discussion.</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">ON MARY ELLEN REISNER’S “LOCATIONS OF COPY U OF 
<hi rend="i">SONGS OF INNOCENCE</hi> AND COPY d OF <hi rend="i">SONGS OF INNOCENCE AND OF EXPERIENCE</hi>” FROM
<hi rend="i">BLAKE NEWSLETTER 19</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>John E. <name>Grant</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n61" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>It seems odd that Mary Ellen Reisner should have had so much difficulty as she reported
in locating <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> Copy U or that she should have thought it
could be found at Harvard. As was reported in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 3 (15 December 1967), pp.
6-7, <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> Copy U was acquired by the Princeton University Library. Further particulars are
to be found in Charles Ryskamp, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Engraver: A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>,
(Princeton, 1969), p. 38, and there is also a reproduction of the remarkable general title page in this
volume. Reisner’s additional note that posthumous Copy d is not at Yale, as was reported in the 
<hi rend="i">Census</hi>, is of more interest.</p>
                    <p>Some further considerations: Reisner speaks of the “new <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>
by Bentley and Nurmi” as being helpful in finding the locations of illuminated books; but the 1964 
<hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> is not “new” and does not attempt to duplicate the work of the 
<hi rend="i">Census.</hi> One gathers, however, that the real “new” Bentley <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>, which
has been in the press for some time, will, when published, at last make up-to-date information as to locations
generally available. It is certainly unfortunate that when the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> was reissued no effort
was made to give current locations.</p>
                    <p>The problem of how information about locations should be used, however, is frequently
mentioned in private but ought also to be frankly considered at least in the semi-public columns of 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter.</hi> The question is, who wants to see a Blake work and why does he wish to do so?
At present accessibility varies greatly in the several major public and private collections. There seems to be
little relationship between the present condition of the works and their accessibility. Some copies of the
illuminated books that are in poor condition and in which the pages have not been properly mounted are
nevertheless quite easily available. In other cases one could argue that the security regulations are
unreasonably restrictive.</p>
                    <p>But everyone who gets an urge to see a Blake book ought to ask himself why he needs to
do it. Certainly no teacher should be party to the kind of make-work assignment that is too common of
requiring his class in Introduction to Graduate Study to go, one by one, to look at a genuine Blake book. A
Blake seminar is, of course, another matter. But even in this case one should expect that interested students
will first carefully study Blake Trust facsimiles (or better, get to know photographic reproductions, such as
will soon be available in the Erdman edited Doubleday edition) before seeking out the originals. It might seem
as though such a stricture is of the Urizenic sort designed to postpone the day when at least a few more of
the Lord’s people become prophets. But it is not so. Until one has trained his eye up to seeing a Blake
Trust facsimile he isn’t going to be able to get very much from an original. Indeed, as I have pointed out
elsewhere, he may never get as much from some putative “originals,” since by no means all of them are as good
works of art as the Blake Trust facsimiles. The great Princeton copy of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, of course, is
much finer than the Blake Trust facsimile of the beautiful <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> Copy Z. But it is to be
hoped that having Copy U now more clearly located will not much lengthen the lines at the Princeton Rare Book
Room. The best Blake works are worth waiting for. Meanwhile everyone should take advantage of the abundance of
materials that are generally available. <note id="n61">
                            <hi rend="i">John E. Grant (University of Iowa) co-edited</hi> Blake’s Visionary
Forms Dramatic. <hi rend="i">By means of a grant from the American Philosophical Society he was recently able
to visit the Princeton University Library and six other Eastern Blake collections in the spring of 1972.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>