<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.works</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Works in Progress</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0002">
            	<pb id="p06-5" n="5"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">WORKS IN PROGRESS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Mary V. Jackson (Assistant Professor, The City College of New York, CUNY): “I will
indicate how Blake created by experimental changes in the representation of character and, more especially, of
time and space, myth as a poetic device which gradually gave him another language through which he could
express as well as fully understand complex and interdependent psychic processes and historical phenomena for
which no adequate language existed.”</p>
                    <p>Mary V. Jackson and Elaine Mozer Kauvar (The City College of New York, CUNY): “Major
Trends in Blake Criticism from 1901 to 1971, A Bibliographical Essay.”</p>
                    <p>Carolyn Wilkinson: “You Are What You Behold: A Study of the Narrative Structure of
William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” a Ph. D. dissertation directed by Victor Paananen at Michigan
State University, concerning “the relation between the perceptions and actions of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s characters. It concludes with a study of the reader’s perceptions of the entire
action of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as conditioned by the structural techniques of the narrator.”</p>
                    <p>Joanne Witke: “The Empiricism of William Blake’s Metaphysics,” a Ph. D. dissertation
directed by Morton Paley at the University of California, Berkeley.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>