<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.watercolors</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">3 Blake Watercolors Now in Public Collections</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0002">
            	<pb id="p06-5" n="5"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">3 BLAKE WATERCOLORS NOW IN PUBLIC COLLECTIONS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>According to Martin Butlin of the Tate Gallery, three Blake watercolors from the Esmond
Morse collection have been given to British public collections by the Morse family. The Victoria and Albert
Museum has received “The Angels hovering over the body of Jesus in the Sepulchre” and “The Angel rolling the
stone from the Sepulchre,” two of the Biblical subjects painted for Thomas Butts circa 1800-1805. Butlin
remarks that “These are two of the best and most moving examples [of the Biblical subjects painted by Blake
for Butts], very sensitive in their quiet emotion and delicate symmetry, and seem to form a group within the
main group together with ‘The Resurrection’ in the Fogg Museum, ‘The Magdelene at the sepulchre’
belonging to the Mount Trust, and the two watercolors at the Tate Gallery, ‘The Crucifixion’ and ‘The
Entombment.’ It is perhaps a pity that the new gifts cannot be seen together with the works at the Tate
Gallery, but that is typical of the illogicalities of the London art scene!” The third gift, “And the Waters
prevailed upon the Earth an hundred and fifty days,” has gone to the Abbot Hall Art Gallery at Kendal in
Westmorland. On the back, according to Butlin, is “a drawing of a humanoid elephant dangling an infant on its
foot which has sometimes been seen as a caricature of John Varley.”</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>