<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.paley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Geoffrey Keynes, William Blake’s Water-Colour Designs for Gray’s Poems</title>
                <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
	<pb id="p06-33" n="33"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0006">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Water-Colour Designs for Gray’s Poems—A
Commemorative Catalogue.</hi> With an introduction and commentary by Geoffrey Keynes Kt. London: Trianon Press
for the William Blake Trust, 1971. Pp. xx + 72. Illustrated. $7.50 + $1 postage from the Yale University Art
Gallery, New Haven, Conn.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n69" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>1971-72 were vintage years for the study of Blake’s illustrations to the poems of
Gray. Previous to that, very little had been seen of this major series of designs and still less written about
them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">1</ref> In 1971, however, appeared
Irene Tayler’s fine study<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">2</ref>; the
illustrations themselves were published in a magnificent facsimile by the Trianon Press for the William Blake
Trust; and an exhibition of originals and facsimiles opened at the Tate Gallery. The following spring this
exhibition, for which the publication at hand is the catalogue, was mounted at the Yale University Art Gallery
in collaboration with the Paul Mellon Center for British Art and British Studies. Although modestly described
by its author as “an introductory handbook,” this catalogue is in itself a major contribution to the
interpretation of its subject. <note id="n42">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> For reproductions prior to 1971, see Robert Essick, 
<hi rend="i">A Finding List of Reproductions of Blake’s Art, Blake Newsletter</hi>, 5 (1971), 69-72. For a
detailed history of the illustrations and the literature about them, see Irene Tayler, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Illustrations to the Poems of Gray</hi>, pp. 3-25.</note>
                        <note id="n43">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Reviewed by Thomas H. Helmstadter, <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 4 (1971), 140-42; see also my review in <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 14 (1972), 93-96.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>What inevitably strikes one first is the wealth of illustrations in the catalogue.
Sixteen designs (eighteen, counting the front and back covers) are reproduced full-page in color and one in
monochrome, and at the back of the book all 116 are given, four to a page, in reduced monochrome. Also
reproduced full-page are Flaxman’s pencil drawing of Blake and the titlepage of the 1790 edition of Gray
which Blake used. There is a useful “Concordance of Blake’s handwritten titles” which correlates Blake’s
titles, the lines from Gray illustrated (as Blake transcribed them), Blake’s manuscript numbers, the page
numbers of the 1790 edition, and the design numbers. (As Blake numbered his designs for each poem as a
separate sequence, his manuscript numbers necessarily differ from the design numbers for the entire series.)
This is a very welcome tool for anyone who wishes to study the series at length. <note id="n69">
                            <hi rend="i">Morton D. Paley (University of California, Berkeley) is Executive
Editor of the</hi> Newsletter. <hi rend="i">He is the author of</hi> Energy and the Imagination: A Study of
the Development of Blake’s Thought. <hi rend="i">He is a Guggenheim Fellow for 1972-73, working on a book on
Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem.</note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p06-34" n="34"/>
                    <p>In addition to providing a succinct introduction, Sir Geoffrey Keynes has written a
commentary, some thirty pages in length, which is at the same time inobtrusive and rich with insight. When
viewed as a whole, the designs have one aspect which bulks surprisingly large: their social satire. One
expects to find this element in illustrations for “The Bard” and the “Elegy,” but it is interesting to find
it, for example, in “A Long Story.” The pictures that accompany this frothy poem end, as Sir Geoffrey points
out, “with a satirical picture of how polite society receives the serious artist” (p. 51); and the designs for
“The Progress of Poesy” undermine Gray’s celebration of the flight of the Muse to Albion’s shore in order,
as Keynes says, “to express Blake’s view of the effect of political tyranny on the state of poetry in
England” (p. 55). This dimension of social commentary may also be seen in Blake’s renditions of the “Ode on
a Distant Prospect of Eton College” and the “Ode for Music.” In some of these pictures Blake, who believed
that education, at least in its institutional sense, was “the great wrong,” seems to suggest that all is not
well at Eton and Cambridge. The public school boys engage in picayune activities that do everything but
prepare them for the rigors of Experience; even the poet-figure of “Ode for Music” (design 97) is shown
walking away from the Gothic spire and waning Beulah-moon of the background, to pass under the barren limbs of
two desolate trees, hardly the “brown o’er-arching groves” of Gray’s line.</p>
                    <p>The Keynes commentary is also valuable in making use of Gray’s own published notes to
the poems and in pointing out instances where Blake has changed Gray’s wording, used non-consecutive lines,
or even illustrated a sequence of pages different from that of Gray’s text. Also, some interesting remarks
are made about parallels between the figures in these designs and in some of Blake’s other works, as, for
example, in the commentary on design 77 (<hi rend="i">The Serpent who girds the Earth</hi>). This catalogue,
rich in both word and image, deserves a place in the library of every student of Blake.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>