<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.gibson</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">William Blake and Henry Emlyn’s Proposition for a New Order in
Architecture: A New Plate</title>
                <author n="Gibson">William A. Gibson</author>
                <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0003">
                    <pb id="p06-12" n="12"/>
                    <figure n="EmlynProposition.6.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="512">
                        <head>1 Henry Emlyn, <hi rend="i">A Proposition for a New Order in Architecture</hi>
(1781), plate II.</head>
                        <figDesc>Courtesy of Mr. Lessing J. Rosenwald.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p06-13" n="13"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">WILLIAM BLAKE AND HENRY EMLYN’S <hi rend="i">PROPOSITION FOR A
NEW ORDER IN ARCHITECTURE:</hi> A NEW PLATE</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>William A. <name>Gibson</name>
                        </docAuthor> and <docAuthor>Thomas L. <name>Minnick</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n56" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>Very early in his professional life as an articled engraver, William Blake made one
sally into the business of reproducing architectural designs in a publishable form. He engraved at least one
of the designs which accompanied Henry Emlyn’s <hi rend="i">A Proposition for a New Order in Architecture</hi> 
(London, for J. Dixwell, 1781).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">1</ref> 
Plate II [fig. 1] in both the first and second (1784) editions of Emlyn’s treatise is
clearly signed “Blake sculp.” This plate is of interest for several reasons. It is among Blake’s earliest
commercial jobs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">2</ref> It is his only known
work in engraving plans or directions for architects, although, of course, he showed an interest in
architecture in much of his art.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">3</ref> And
the plate is among Blake’s largest engravings. It measures 537 mm. high in the platemark, and about 370 mm.
wide. We give the measurement of width as approximate because most copies have been cropped, and measurement
of this dimension is uncertain, sometimes impossible. The platemarks are light, and the width suffered most in
binding. 
						<note id="n16">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                1
                            </hi> This plate was first noticed by William A. Gibson in the British Museum in
1966, while doing work supported, in part, by the Ohio State University Development Fund through its Faculty
Summer Fellowship program, and by a grant from the Penrose Fund of the American Philosophical Society.</note>
                        <note id="n17">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                2
                            </hi> It is certainly among the first five or six pieces which he did on his own
after leaving Basire. Indeed, since it was not uncommon for the engravings which would accompany a book to be
completed long before publication of a volume, the Emlyn plate may antedate all the rest of Blake’s early
commercial work except perhaps his single plate for J. Oliver’s <hi rend="i">Fencing Familiarized</hi>
(1780). For a list of Blake’s earliest work, see Gerald E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
(Oxford: The Clarendon Press, 1969), p. 609.</note>
                        <note id="n18">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                3
                            </hi> Expressions of Blake’s interest in architecture range from the homely
sketch of his Felpham cottage in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, plate 36, to his engravings for Stuart and
Revett’s <hi rend="i">Antiquities of Athens.</hi> But the engraving he did for Emlyn’s treatise is unique
of its kind in the body of Blake’s work.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Emlyn’s treatise is now very rare. Of the first edition we have traced three copies
in England; one is in Sir John Soane’s Museum, another is in the private library of Mr. John Harris, Curator
of the Drawings Collection of the Royal Institute of British Architects, and recently a third copy was offered
for sale by Mr. Paul Breman of London.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">4</ref> In the United States the only known copy is in the collection of Mr. Lessing J. Rosenwald.
Of the second edition we have located two copies, one in the British Museum, shelfmark 1733.d.25, and another
in Cambridge University Library, bought from King’s College Library in 1923. The third edition of 1797 is
the commonest; there are copies in the British Museum, the library of the Royal Institute of British
Architects, the Avery Library of Columbia University, the Print Room of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and
elsewhere. But for this edition the plates were reduced to a platemark of 445 mm. by 282 mm. <note id="n19">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                4
                            </hi> The treatise was offered for sale by Mr. Paul Breman of Paul Breman Ltd., 7
Wedderburn Road, London NW3. The Emlyn volume is item 12 in his catalogue 14, “English Architecture
1598-1838,” priced at £345.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Henry Emlyn (c. 1729-1815) was an obscure Windsor carpenter.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">5</ref> He tried in his treatise to establish a native English order
in architecture to rival the orders of classical origin, basing his plans for the column on an analogy with
the oak that flourishes in Windsor Forest. To support the column, Emlyn proposed a formal pedestal at the
center of whose die stone is an heraldic trophy. This pedestal is the subject of Plate II of the first
edition, the plate which bears Blake’s signature. Such trophies were common devices. Similar ones (but none
close enough to be considered Blake’s or Emlyn’s model) appear in Piranesi, and visitors to London today
can see others atop the gateposts of the Royal Chelsea Hospital (see fig. 2, a sketch of a trophy provided by
Mr. Peter Spurrier of the Chelsea Arts Club). <note id="n20">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                5
                            </hi> See H. M. Colvin, <hi rend="i">Biographical Dictionary of English Architects
1660-1840</hi> (London: John Murray, 1954), p. 195.</note>
                    </p>
                    <figure n="Gatepost.6.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="200" height="321">
                        <head>2 A Gatepost of the Royal Chelsea Hospital, surmounted by a trophy.</head>
                        <figDesc>Courtesy of Mr. Peter Spurrier.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In Emlyn’s order a single elliptical shaft rises to a fifth of the total height, then
divides into two thin circular shafts; at the fork of the column Emlyn placed the Shield of the Order of Saint
George. This shield is the focus of Plate V [fig. 3], which Emlyn describes as follows: “The Knights Shield
and Armour, with the Skin of a Wolf, hanging down on each Side, and bending down the twigs of the tree; all
which together Cap the Center 
						<note id="n56">
                            <hi rend="i">William A. Gibson, Chairman of the Department of English at Idaho
State University, is head of the English section of the</hi> MLA Bibliography <hi rend="i">and interested in
the relationship of literature to architecture. Thomas L. Minnick is finishing his doctoral thesis, “On Blake
and Milton: An Essay in Literary Relationship,” at Ohio State University.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-14" n="14"/>
                        <figure n="PropositionV.6.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="533">
                            <head>3 Henry Emlyn, <hi rend="i">A Proposition for a New Order in
Architecture</hi> (1781), plate V.</head>
                            <figDesc>Courtesy of Sir John Summerson, Director, Sir John Soane’s
Museum.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
of the trunk on both Sides.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">6</ref> Plate V
is not signed, but since it bears some striking similarities to the engraving signed by Blake we believe that
Mr. Breman is correct in attributing this plate also to him. The similarities are not merely stylistic, for
these could admittedly reflect Emlyn’s original designs as much as Blake’s practice as an engraver. We can
enumerate here only a few correspondences between the two plates. First, the fine dimension lines running from
the figures in both plates to the scales at the left are executed in the same manner—very closely spaced
dots made by minute pricks of an engraving tool. Second, the scales themselves are alike in the spacing and
relative heaviness of the vertical lines, and in the length of the short arrows and the shape of their heads.
Third, the numerals on the scales appear to be the work of the same hand. This is especially noticeable in the
<hi rend="i">2</hi>’s, <hi rend="i">3</hi>’s, and <hi rend="i">5</hi>’s; all of these numerals have
unusually large loops and therefore a proportional scaling down of their horizontal and vertical lines. In the
<hi rend="i">3</hi>’s the loop thins very discernibly across the bottom of the numerals. The short vertical
lines of the <hi rend="i">5</hi>’s tilt to the right about 15°, necessitating a considerable shortening of
the top horizontal, and making the numerals appear to roll to the right. <note id="n21">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                6
                            </hi> Henry Emlyn, <hi rend="i">A Proposition for a New Order in Architecture</hi>
(London, 1781), p. 3.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The architectural elements and their ornaments do not provide such precise points of
comparison as the numerals and dimension lines, for the trophy on the signed plate [fig. 1] is less intricate
in its detail and more sharply outlined than the coat of arms on the unsigned one [fig. 3]. Yet even here a
close examination reveals some similarities in line and execution. The modelling of the breast of the armored
trophy is created by the same curved lines as those that compose the lion’s facial features in the coat of
arms. The volute at the lower right-hand corner of the oval shield in the coat of arms has the same
configuration as the volutes on the hilts of the two swords in the trophy; and it is also the same as the
volute that adorns the forehead line of the helmet seen in profile at the hips of the trophy’s torso. While
it must be admitted that the eyes of the volute at the ends of the bow in figure 1 are tighter than those on
the bow in figure 3, the curves of both bows have similar sweeping rhythms. The open-eyed volutes of figure 3
do repeat those of the ornaments to the bottom shield in figure 1; they also resemble the volutes with which
Blake has adorned the “B” of his own name. And again, the pointed fletching of the arrows in the sheath of
figure 1 is outlined and textured by the same short, wedge-shaped lines as those that form the fletching in
the fluting of figure 3. A close examination of such features as the plumes, leaves, acorns, fleurs-de-lis,
and animal motifs would be instructive but appropriate only in a fuller study of Blake and Emlyn. We might
note, however, that Plates I, III, VI to X, and XVIII are also unsigned and could be by Blake. Several plates
(XI to XVII and XIX to XXI) are signed “Sparrow sculp.”; Plate IX of the unsigned plates resembles Sparrow’s
work.</p>
                    <p>The plate originally signed by Blake (Plate II, 1781—fig. 1) has almost certainly
been reworked, rather than re-engraved entirely, for the scaled-down version in the third edition (Plate IV,
1797—fig. 4). The numerals along the left vertical scale appear to be identical in both versions, as well as
the horizontal dimension lines and the heavy and light lines of the vertical scale itself. A few vertical
dimension lines have been eliminated from the left side of the plate, but new scales and dimension lines have
been added to the right side to replace them. The fleur-de-lis and leaf designs on the cyma reversa and cyma
recta mouldings respectively remain intact. The trophy itself appears to be most extensively altered, but the
changes are in fact nothing but additions carefully fitted into the open spaces within the oval framing line.
The points of the newly added anchor, for example, just touch the edges of the original upper shields and
swords. The new anchor cable runs through open spaces between the original emblems,
<pb id="p06-15" n="15"/>
with its free end apparently hidden somewhere behind the lower helmet or its plume (the cable happily tightens
the composition of the entire trophy, for it helps to link the spears and upper helmet to the torso). The
compass and chain are similarly integrated with the original emblems so as to change virtually none of their
outlines. Cropping the plate to the new dimensions provided no special problems for the engraver. To shorten
the plate the dimension lines at the top have been eliminated, the top plinth thinned slightly, and the tall
bottom plinth reduced to a sliver. To narrow the plate the margins have simply been cropped, necessitating
only the elimination of a semi-circular dimension line at the left. If our argument is correct, this plate in
the third edition remains largely Blake’s work.</p>
                    <p>Since Plate V could not be so easily cropped, it was entirely re-engraved, with some
loss of the original grace, for the third edition (Plate V, 1797—fig. 5). The scale—now on the right side
of the plate—is more difficult to interpret than the original one, and the numerals far more conventional in
their configurations. The individual oak leaves in the border framing the shield have lost their original
undulating curves; the paws hanging below are now thick-ankled and club-like. The lines intended to model the
lion’s face only make the lion appear old, tired and wrinkled. We can only speculate whether the same
engraver is responsible for both this plate and the alterations of Blake’s plate. The most obvious
similarities between the new plate and the alterations are the reliance upon short, light dashes for dimension
lines and the hard outlining of such emblems as weapons, animal motifs, chain, cable, and anchor.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Breman’s remark about the “obvious parallel between Emlyn’s work and that of
the French architect Ribart Chamoust, whose ‘L’ordre francois trouvé dans la nature’ appeared two years
later,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">7</ref> fails to suggest the
significance of either work. Both represent the rather desperate attempts of late eighteenth-century
architectural theorists to establish new aesthetic premises on which to base architectural criticism and
design. As Rudolf Wittkower has demonstrated, the theological-philosophical bases of Renaissance architectural
theory were being undermined by the development of new habits of thinking.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">8</ref> By the middle of the eighteenth century, the old systems of
mathematical and harmonic proportion were increasingly being ignored, misunderstood, or half-consciously
avoided. <note id="n22">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                7
                            </hi> Breman, item 12.</note>
                        <note id="n23">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                8
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Architectural Principles in the Age of Humanism</hi>, 3rd ed.
(London: Alec Tiranti, 1962), pp. 142-54.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Emlyn’s attempt is not, however, an entirely new departure. Vitruvius traces the
evolution of the orders from primitive man’s looking to trees as his first models for supporting columns in
building (<hi rend="i">De Architectura</hi>, II.i.4). Even Isaac Ware, whose encyclopedic 
<hi rend="i">Complete Body of Architecture</hi> (1756) ignores entirely the theological-philosophical bases of
Renaissance theory, begins his affirmation of
<figure n="PropositionIVandV.6.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="316" height="1000">
                            <head>4 &amp; 5 Henry Emlyn, <hi rend="i">A Proposition for a New Order in
Architecture</hi>, 3rd ed.</head>
                            <figDesc>(1797), plates IV and V. Courtesy of the Avery Memorial Library of
Columbia University.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p06-16" n="16"/>
Palladian principles and proportions with the seemingly irrefutable proposition that columns imitate tree
trunks.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">9</ref> Second, the assumption that
an order has an emblematic significance, which determines the uses to which that order may be put, is entirely
consistent with Vitruvius’s rule of <hi rend="i">decor</hi>, as Emlyn himself was well aware.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">10</ref> Third, even Emlyn’s rather arbitrary
proportions are not so radically different from those of the classical orders as they may first appear. Emlyn
explains, “The whole Height is twenty-five Diameters, which happens to be the Number of the Knights Companions
of the Noble Order of the Garter.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">11</ref>
The shafts are not so slender as this may seem to imply, for Emlyn takes his module not from the elliptical
base, but rather from the diameter of the circular shafts. Thus, since there are two of these shafts, the
design yields an overall proportion of 12.5:1 rather than 25:1. This is reasonably close to the proportions of
the Corinthian order which in practice vary from about 9:1 to 11:1. <note id="n24">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                9
                            </hi> Ware, new ed. (1768), pp. 135-37.</note>
                        <note id="n25">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                10
                            </hi> Emlyn, pp. 2-3; for a fuller discussion of <hi rend="i">decor</hi>, see
William A. Gibson, “Three Principles of Renaissance Architectural Theory in Pope’s <hi rend="i">Epistle to
Burlington</hi>,” <hi rend="i">SEL</hi>, 11 (1971), 491-93.</note>
                        <note id="n26">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                11
                            </hi> Emlyn, p. 17.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>One might profitably speculate about the extent to which Blake appreciated the
emblematic significance of the details he engraved for Emlyn’s treatise. Although Emlyn himself generally
stresses the political and moral rather than the religious meanings of his motifs, many of the same motifs
occur in the eighteenth-century treatises that attempt to establish Great Britain as an early haven for the
undefiled religion of the Old Testament patriarchs, and to establish the Druids as the priests of Abraham’s
faith. For example, William Stukeley summarizes the new legend thus in his treatise on Stonehenge:
<q>
                            <hi rend="i">The patriarchal history, particularly of</hi> Abraham, 
<hi rend="i">is largely pursu’d; and the deduction of the</hi> Phoenician <hi rend="i">colony into the Island
of</hi> Britain, <hi rend="i">about or soon after his time; whence the origins of the</hi> Druids, 
<hi rend="i">of their Religion and writing; they brought the patriarchal Religion along with them, and some
knowledge of symbols or hieroglyphics, like those of the ancient</hi> Egyptians; <hi rend="i">they had the
notion and expectation of the Messiah, and of the time of year when he was to be born, of his office and
death.</hi>
                            <ref target="n27" type="note">12</ref>
                            <note id="n27">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    12
                                </hi>
                                <hi rend="i"> Stonehenge, A Temple Restor’d to the British Druids</hi>
(London, 1740), Preface, n. p.</note>
						</q>
The major link between Stukeley and Emlyn is the oak tree of Windsor Forest, the primary model for Emlyn’s
order (following the example of Callimachus’s design for the Corinthian order).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">13</ref> According to Stukeley’s account, Abraham, whom he seems to
identify as the first Druid, planted an oak grove in which the Deity lived. Besides endowing the oak with
unique sanctity, this act also gives architecture a special place among the arts: “From these groves arose the
first ideas of architecture. first [sic] was it employ’d for sacred purposes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">14</ref> Another motif that arouses some curiosity is what appears to
be a ram’s horn on the helmet crowning the trophy (fig. 1). Stukeley associates the ram’s horn with
Jupiter Ammon, and thence back to a religious and political ritual of the ancient Israelites.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">15</ref>
                        <note id="n28">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                13
                            </hi> Vitruvius, IV.i.10-11.</note>
                        <note id="n29">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                14
                            </hi> William Stukeley, <hi rend="i">Palaeographica Sacra</hi> (London, 1763), pp.
8, 17.</note>
                        <note id="n30">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                15
                            </hi> Stukeley, <hi rend="i">Palaeographica Sacra</hi>, pp. 59-60.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>This preoccupation with religious emblems, with the early history of an uncorrupted
faith, with Druid lore, and with the establishment of religion and learning in prehistoric Britain is one that
Blake shared with such men as John Toland, William Stukeley, John Wood of Bath, and Henry Emlyn. Blake surely
knew Stukeley’s companion volume to <hi rend="i">Stonehenge, Abury</hi>, and he knew it perhaps as early as
1773 when Basire copied part of one of the plates from <hi rend="i">Abury</hi> for an illustration to Jacob
Bryant’s <hi rend="i">A New System, or an Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi> (3 vols., 1774-76) for which
Blake engraved at least one plate. John Beer has recently suggested that Blake’s early engraving after
Michelangelo, later titled “JOSEPH of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion,” resembles an engraving in
Sammes’s <hi rend="i">Britannia Antiqua Illustrata</hi> and another in Stukeley’s 
<hi rend="i">Stonehenge.</hi>
                        <ref target="n31" type="note">16</ref> But of course Blake was also familiar with
other studies of Druid lore, widely popular in the antiquarian researches of the 1770’s and 1780’s. To
this varied body of works Emlyn added a treatise which might well have been congenial to Blake as encouraging
the kind of native “republican art” Blake envisioned would reinvigorate his England. <note id="n31">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                16
                            </hi> John Beer, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Universe</hi> (Manchester:
Manchester Univ. Press, 1969), pp. 15-19. See also Peter F. Fisher, “Blake and the Druids,” 
<hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 58 (1959), 589-612, and especially Ruthven Todd, <hi rend="i">Tracks in the Snow</hi>
(London: The Grey Walls Press, 1946), pp. 29-60.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>As far as is known, Emlyn’s designs were attempted in stone only once, at Beaumont
Lodge in Berkshire. A house had stood at Berkshire since at least the seventeenth century, but Henry
Griffiths, who purchased the estate in 1789, had it embellished with the British Order. Work was completed
about 1790.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">17</ref> Perhaps unfortunately,
in this only
<pb id="p06-17" n="17"/>
instance, the trophy which Blake engraved was not used, and Griffiths chose the seal of the Order of the
Garter instead of the Shield of the Order of St. George to mark the column’s fork. As Miss Sandra Blutman
writes, “Poor Emlyn’s order was doomed to failure. It was never copied or adapted to modern requirements and
Beaumont Lodge, an otherwise rather ordinary Georgian house, stands empty today—the only surviving example
of this curious idea.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">18</ref>
                        <note id="n32">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                17
                            </hi> Sandra Blutman, “Beaumont Lodge and the British Order” in H. M. Colvin and
John Harris, eds., <hi rend="i">The Country Seat: Studies in the History of the British Country House
Presented to Sir John Summerson</hi> (London: Allen Lane, 1970), p. 181.</note>
                        <note id="n33">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                18
                            </hi> Blutman, p. 184.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Beaumont Lodge was, interestingly enough, beside the home of Blake’s friend of later
years, George Cumberland, who bought his estate in Windsor Great Park in 1792.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">19</ref> Did Blake ever see the British Order executed in stone?
Perhaps, for he might have visited Cumberland at Bishopsgate, as Cumberland visited Lambeth. Cumberland, at
least, probably did know Beaumont Lodge, for he had a dispute with Griffiths about a destitute family which
had squatted, with Cumberland’s permission, on some waste land between the two houses.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">20</ref> The altercation found its way into print in
Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">A Letter to Henry Griffiths, esq., of Beaumont Lodge</hi> (1797), to which came
the due response, <hi rend="i">Mr. Griffiths’ Remarks, upon the Letter Signed George Cumberland</hi> (1797).
<note id="n34">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                19
                            </hi> Geoffrey Keynes, “Some Uncollected Authors XLIV: George Cumberland
1754-1848,” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 19 (1970), 38.</note>
                        <note id="n35">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                20
                            </hi> Keynes, p. 60.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>As a final note we might remark that the third edition of Emlyn’s treatise (1797) was
printed by one “J. Smeeton, St. Martin’s Lane, Charing Cross.” This is the same house, reestablished after a
fire, as “G. Smeeton, Printer, 17, St. Martin’s Lane, London,” that set the second prospectus of Blake’s
“Canterbury Pilgrims.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">21</ref> This
connection provides, however, no reason to suppose that Blake was involved in the re-engraving for the third
edition. He was by then engaged with other work.
                    </p>
                            <note id="n36">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    21
                                </hi> See David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi>, 4th printing, rev. (Garden City: Doubleday, 1970), p. 559.</note>
<note type="unreferenced">In preparing this announcement the authors have benefited from the generous
help of several individuals and institutions. We are grateful to Professor G. E. Bentley, Jr., Mr. Paul
Breman, Mr. James Carter, Mr. Paul Grinke, Mr. John Harris, Sir Geoffrey Keynes, Miss Michèle Roberts, Mr.
Lessing J. Rosenwald, Mr. Peter Spurrier, and Sir John Summerson; and to the Avery Memorial Library of
Columbia University, the British Museum, the Print Room of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and Sir John
Soane’s Museum. Our special thanks go to Mr. Ruthven Todd who throughout this project has given of his time
and wide knowledge of Blake, and who has willingly opened for us doors of whose existence we were too often
ignorant.</note>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>