<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.metcalf</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Reason and Urizen: The Pronunciation of Blakean Names</title>
                <author n="Metcalf">Francis Wood Metcalf</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
	<pb id="p06-17" n="17"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0003">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">REASON AND “URIZEN”: THE PRONUNCIATION OF BLAKEAN NAMES</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Francis Wood <name>Metcalf</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n58" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>The suggestions put forward by Kerrison Preston concerning the pronunciation of
Blake’s invented names (<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 3 [May 1970], 106) are useful for spurring
discussion of this vexing subject, but are in some cases difficult to assess. There probably is no way to 
<hi rend="i">test</hi> the pronunciation of “Los,” “Luvah,” and “Vala,” and a number of other names, because the
question is one of vowel-quality, not placement of accent. Where stressing is the issue, as in “Urizen” and
“Ololon,” the name can be checked against the metrical contexts in which it occurs (see below). But since no
such technique exists for testing vowels, we may eternally muddle along with hunches based on word-echoes,
philosophical associations, and phonological probability. There surely is substance for debate on these
grounds, but nothing like the hard evidence provided by metrics in the matter of accent.</p>
                    <p>The great bone of accentual contention, more often stubbornly mouthed at both ends than
fought for with intellectual spears, is the name “Urizen.” At either end are <hi rend="i">YUR</hi> / I / ZEN
and YU / <hi rend="i">REE</hi> / ZEN (or, alternatively, UR / <hi rend="i">AYE</hi> / ZEN). Doubtless there
are other variants, but these seem to be the main ones. The question may be put: is “Urizen” correctly
pronounced with the primary stress on the first or the second syllable? The aim of the following is to settle
this question by means of a method which will, I hope, also be helpful with regard to other names. The
conclusion—that Blake pronounced “Urizen” with a primary stress on the first syllable—is not intended to
inflict One Law, but only to demonstrate Blake’s practice.</p>
                    <p>Fortunately for our purpose, Blake adhered to a rather strict iambic heptameter scheme
in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion, America</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> These poems
not only provide a common, and firm, metrical context (as <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> does not) they
also contain the first ten appearances of “Urizen,” fresh as it were from Blake’s forehead:</p>
<p>
<q>
<corr type="emend">
1. O<metSym value="-"/> U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n! Cr<metSym
value="-"/>ea<metSym value="+"/>to<metSym value="-"/>r o<metSym value="-"/>f me<metSym value="+"/>n! mi<metSym
value="-"/>st<metSym value="+"/>ake<metSym value="-"/>n D<metSym value="+"/>emo<metSym value="-"/>n o<metSym
value="-"/>f he<metSym value="+"/>ave<metSym value="-"/>n (<hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 5:3)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
2. Th<metSym value="-"/>e f<metSym value="+"/>ie<metSym value="-"/>ry<metSym value="-"/> 
<corr type="emend" rend="plain">jo<metSym value="+"/>y, tha<metSym value="-"/>t</corr> U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym
value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n pe<metSym value="-"/>rve<metSym value="+"/>rte<metSym value="-"/>d 
<corr type="emend" rend="plain">to<metSym value="-"/></corr> te<metSym value="+"/>n co<metSym value="-"/>mma<metSym
value="+"/>nds (<hi rend="i">A</hi> 8:3) <note id="n58">
                                <hi rend="i">Francis Wood Metcalf is writing a Ph.D. dissertation at New York
University on rhetoric and style in the Prophetic Books and has contributed previously to the</hi>
Newsletter.</note>
                            <pb id="p06-18" n="18"/>
3. Th<metSym value="-"/>e He<metSym value="+"/>ave<metSym value="-"/>ns me<metSym value="+"/>lte<metSym
value="-"/>d <corr type="emend" rend="plain">fro<metSym value="-"/>m</corr> nor<metSym value="+"/>th t<metSym
value="-"/>o sou<metSym value="+"/>th; an<metSym value="-"/>d U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym
value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n wh<metSym value="-"/>o sa<metSym value="+"/>t (<hi rend="i">A</hi>
16:2)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
4. I<metSym value="-"/>n th<metSym value="+"/>at dre<metSym value="+"/>ad nig<metSym value="+"/>ht wh<metSym
value="-"/>en U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n ca<metSym value="+"/>ll’d
th<metSym value="-"/>e sta<metSym value="+"/>rs rou<metSym value="+"/>nd hi<metSym value="-"/>s fe<metSym
value="+"/>et (<hi rend="i">A</hi> canc. b:5)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
5. A<metSym value="-"/>nd U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n u<metSym
value="-"/>nlo<metSym value="+"/>os’d <corr type="emend" rend="plain">fro<metSym value="-"/>m</corr>
cha<metSym value="+"/>ins (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 3:11)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
6. Ti<metSym value="-"/>ll al<metSym value="+"/>l th<metSym value="-"/>e so<metSym value="+"/>ns o<metSym
value="-"/>f U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n lo<metSym value="-"/>ok ou<metSym
value="+"/>t an<metSym value="-"/>d e<metSym value="+"/>nv<metSym value="-"/>y Lo<metSym value="+"/>s 
(<hi rend="i">E</hi> 4:2)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
7. H<metSym value="-"/>e sa<metSym value="+"/>w U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym value="-"/>ze<metSym
value="+"/>n o<metSym value="+"/>n th<metSym value="-"/>e A<metSym value="-"/>tla<metSym value="+"/>nti<metSym
value="-"/>c (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 11:2)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
8. Fo<metSym value="-"/>r U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n u<metSym
value="-"/>ncla<metSym value="+"/>spd hi<metSym value="-"/>s Bo<metSym value="+"/>ok; fe<metSym
value="+"/>edin<metSym value="-"/>g hi<metSym value="-"/>s so<metSym value="+"/>ul wi<metSym value="-"/>th
p<metSym value="+"/>ity<metSym value="-"/> (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 12:4)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
9. B<metSym value="-"/>etwe<metSym value="+"/>en th<metSym value="-"/>e clo<metSym value="+"/>uds o<metSym
value="-"/>f U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n th<metSym value="-"/>e fla<metSym
value="+"/>mes o<metSym value="-"/>f Or<metSym value="+"/>c ro<metSym value="-"/>ll he<metSym
value="+"/>avy<metSym value="-"/> (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 12:32)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
10. Wa<metSym value="+"/>kin<metSym value="-"/>g th<metSym value="-"/>e sta<metSym value="+"/>rs o<metSym
value="-"/>f U<metSym value="+"/>ri<metSym value="-"/>ze<metSym value="+"/>n wi<metSym value="-"/>th
the<metSym value="+"/>ir im<metSym value="-"/>mo<metSym value="+"/>rta<metSym value="-"/>l son<metSym
value="+"/>gs (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 14:33)
</corr>
</q>
</p>
                    <p>Notice that in every context except the seventh, “Urizen” begins on an even-numbered,
stressed syllable unless preceded by an anapest (as in two an three), in which case the syllable is stressed
and odd-numbered. The apparent exception of context seven is equivocal since it occurs in a group of short and
metrically irregular lines. Context five is also short, but sturdily iambic. To remove the primary stress from
the first syllable of “Urizen” and the secondary stress from the last, and to accent arbitrarily the name’s
middle syllable, would be to commit unjustifiable violence on each line. We then would have an unbroken series
of pyrrhic feet followed by medial inversions, or else no heptameters at all. Later on in Blake’s poetry,
when the metrical scheme is less clearly defined, the mid-stress could in isolated cases perhaps be reasonably
suggested; but these very rhythmic lines allow no alternative to a front-stressed “Urizen.”</p>
                    <p>A contrast with “Urthona” is instructive. In each of its first ten occurrences,
“Urthona”—to the contrary of “Urizen”—begins on an <hi rend="i">odd</hi>-numbered, 
<hi rend="i">un</hi>stressed syllable unless preceded by an anapest. This positioning would prevail in the case of
“Urizen” were it mid-stressed like “Urthona,” but since it is not, it begins on the contrary syllable.</p>
                    <p>Further evidence for a front-stressed “Urizen” may also be seen in contrast to an
“Urthona” paradigm. In its ninety-four occurrences in Blake’s poetry (counting possessives), “Urthona”
begins nine times in a line’s first syllable but only once in its second: “Of Urthona. Los embracd” 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> VII: 85:29). Blake deliberately avoided the latter placement because it gives the effect of
anacrusis—an extra unstressed syllable before the proper beginning of an iambic line. But “Urizen” begins in
a line’s second syllable about sixty times—almost characteristically. The initial syllable is usually a
conjunction—cf. “And . . . ” and “For Urizen,” above—which forms, with front-stressed “Urizen,” a normal
iambic opening. That “Urizen” should also by itself begin many lines is not surprising in view of the Miltonic
and even Augustan precedents for initial inversion. In such cases, the name’s third syllable becomes the
unstressed first half of the succeeding iamb: “Urizen knew them not” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> VI:67:7).</p>
                    <p>Whether Blake usually spoke “Urizen” as a pure dactyl or with a secondary final
stress—as “Benjamin” or as “Benjamite”—is not finally deducible from the metrics, and raises the
forbidding problem of vowel-quality. On this subject our only assurance is that the middle vowel is neither EE
or AYE, but a swallowed short “i” or a schwa.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">1</ref> One is tempted to speculate that the doubly-emphasized “-zen!”-“men!” pairing of the first
appearance of “Urizen,” quoted above, is an internal rhyme designed to aid pronunciation, and that the
attachment of an off-glided “y” to the first vowel is probable since it eliminates hiatus, but Blake’s
practice remains obscure—excepting, of course, the initial stress. In this connection, it would seem that
despite Mr. Preston’s suggestion that “Ololon” be accented on the second syllable, Blake stressed it on the
first. It begins in a line’s second syllable proportionately even more often than “Urizen” does. All
students of Blake will be pleased to know, however, that on the basis of the method outlined above, “Bromion”
and “Enion” have been pronounced by them correctly all along. 
                        <note id="n37">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                1
                            </hi> Mona Wilson, in Keynes’s new edition of <hi rend="i">The Life of William
Blake</hi> (Oxford, 1971), p. 106, states in a footnote about “Urizen” that “ . . . the i scans short.” Her
judgment agrees with mine, but its bearing upon the stressing of the whole name is not entirely clear. Does
she advocate <hi rend="i">YUR</hi> / I / ZEN or YU / <hi rend="i">RIZZ</hi> / EN?</note>
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>