<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.exhibition</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Blake on Exhibition in London</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
	<pb id="p06-4" n="4"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0002">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">BLAKE ON EXHIBITION</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">The Age of Neo-Classicism</hi>, the fourteenth Exhibition of the Council
of Europe that was held in London from 9 September to 19 November 1972, included eight pictures by Blake, as
compared to twenty-two items by Flaxman besides sculpture, thirteen by Fuseli, and ten by Romney. Here was an
opportunity to show some seldom-seen Blakes, such as the Arlington Court picture, but the organizers of this
part of the Exhibition seem to have had trouble getting out of London. Seven of the Blakes were loaned by the
British Museum, one by the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. And one of the eight, “Letho Similis,” is almost
certainly not by Blake. The catalogue notes that the authorship “has been disputed” but “was accepted as
Blake’s work by Binyon.” It would be interesting to know whether any reputable scholar would agree today,
and even more interesting to learn why this undistinguished drawing of disputed origin was selected at all.
The catalogue entries, numbers 506-513 (pp. 310-14), add nothing to the existing literature on these pictures.
“Male Nude” and “The Judgment of Paris” are reproduced as plates 91 and 92. It is a pity that in an exhibition
of
<pb id="p06-5" n="5"/>
such great scope and magnitude Blake could not have been represented more intelligently. Paradoxically,
visitors to the British Council exhibition in Paris (see <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 19, p. 163) saw a
far more interesting selection of Blake pictures. Though there were only twelve, they were chosen from nine
different collections and represented a much more characteristic range of Blake’s art.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Original Printmaking in Britain, 1600-1900</hi> was held 2 November-1
December 1972 at P. and D. Colnaghi and Co. The Blakes, with their prices, were
<table rows="4" cols="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>No. 108</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, pl. ix (3rd state of 3, Binyon 114), £240</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>No. 111</cell>
                                <cell>“The Fly” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (Binyon 219),
£1,200</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>No. 112</cell>
                                <cell>“Enoch” lithograph (Keynes 14), £5,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>No. 127</cell>
                                <cell>“The Canterbury Pilgrims” (posthumous impression, 4th state of 5, Keynes
17), £120</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
This superb exhibition and fine catalogue included, with minor exceptions, only prints designed and executed
by the same artist. The prices of numbers 111 and 112 are not typographical errors!—and all had been sold by
the third day of the exhibition. “The Fly” is reproduced as plate xxv, “Enoch” as plate xxvii.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">The Art of Drawing</hi> is the title of this winter’s exhibition in the
splendid new gallery of the British Museum’s Department of Prints and Drawings. The show is magnificent,
featuring both Oriental and Western material—an enormous Raphael cartoon and sketches by Leonardo among
other things. There are two Blakes, “Jacob’s Ladder” and a Dante illustration.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>