<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.hoover</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Pictures at the Exhibitions</title>
                <author n="Hoover">Suzanne R. Hoover</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <pb id="p06-6" n="6"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0003">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Notes.</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">PICTURES AT THE EXHIBITIONS</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Suzanne R. <name>Hoover</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>“At the Manchester Art-Treasures Exhibition of 1857, among the select thousand
water-colour drawings, hung two modestly tinted designs by Blake, of few inches in size . . . Both are
remarkable displays of imaginative power, and finished examples in the artist’s peculiar manner. Both were
unnoticed in the crowd, attracting few gazers, few admirers.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Thus Gilchrist, near the beginning of his biography, described the
insensitivity of the Victorians to the genius of Blake. Gilchrist was right, of course; but, as always in the
history of Blake’s reputation, there was more to the story. 
                        <note id="n1">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                1
                            </hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi> (London,
1863), I, 3.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Probably the two largest exhibitions of fine art in nineteenth-century England were the
Manchester Art Treasures Exhibition of 1857 and that of the Fine Art Department of the International
Exhibition of 1862 at London. Both of these great aggregations included works by Blake—a fact which has been
noted only by “Gilchrist,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> and which
bears retelling: for, taken together, the seven works by Blake that were displayed (two at Manchester, five at
London) might have been seen by some three million people in all—a mass audience, even by today’s
standards.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> A figure such as that,
while conjectural, should surely raise questions about the usual assumption that the Blake Revival, begun by
Gilchrist, “introduced Blake to a mass audience for the very first time, both as an artist and as a
poet.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Not only was Blake’s work
presented at the exhibitions, but also, in some of the literature associated with them it was mentioned, even
discussed. Owing to the exhibitions, then, we may now add seven new items to the scant number of references to
Blake between the time of his death and the publication of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life.</hi> (See the
Appendix below.) These are: references to Blake in the Official Catalogue of each exhibition; in a Handbook to
each exhibition; and in two periodical notices of the International Exhibition. Their value is not simply in
their rarity, of course, but in the glimpse they give us of the critical response, or lack of it, to some
examples of Blake’s art—at the only public showings of his painting between 1812 and 1876. 
                        <note id="n2">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                2
                            </hi> Gilchrist died in 1861, before completing his manuscript of the 
<hi rend="i">Life</hi>, and, presumably, before he knew about the Blakes at the International Exhibition.
Therefore, he himself wrote only about the Blakes at Manchester, in the passage already quoted. But in William
Michael Rossetti’s <hi rend="i">Annotated Catalogue</hi> (which, with Dante Gabriel Rossetti’s 
<hi rend="i">Selections</hi> from Blake’s poems, comprised the second volume of the <hi rend="i">Life</hi>) all
seven of the works that were exhibited bear notes to that effect. When the <hi rend="i">Life</hi> was revised
for a second edition in 1880, brief sentences were added, where appropriate, to the biography proper, to
indicate that the pictures discussed had been sent to the International Exhibition (<hi rend="i">Life</hi> I,
57, 274). Blake’s participation in the exhibitions has been noted, elsewhere, only in catalogues, in notes
to specific pictures, as part of their history. See, for example, <hi rend="i">The Tempera Paintings of
William Blake</hi> (London: Arts Council of Great Britain, 1951), pp. 15, 26. Nothing about Blake’s part in
the exhibitions is included in either of the two full-scale Blake bibliographies.</note>
                        <note id="n3">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                3
                            </hi> One million fifty-five thousand people attended the Exhibition at
Manchester. I have no attendance figure for the International Exhibition, but I think it fair to assume that
it would have been at least double that for Manchester, considering the difference in location, the broader
nature of the London exhibition, and the fact that it lasted two weeks longer than that at Manchester.</note>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                4
                            </hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr. and Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake
Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: Univ. of Minnesota Press, 1964), p. 15.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The common ancestor of both the 1857 and 1862 exhibitions was the Great Exhibition of
1851, conceived in England and dedicated to the promotion of industry and the improvement of design in
manufactures. As Prince Albert had been the guiding spirit behind that first and most successful of
international exhibitions his judgment was naturally sought by the Manchester Committee, whom he influenced in
favor of a national, rather than international, exhibit, one whose sole purpose would be to educate the public
taste in art, thereby to create a demand for better design in manufactures. It was to be a gathering of the
finest works held by private collectors in England. The Queen and Prince Consort led the way with generous
loans from their own collections; soon, the Committee received twice as many offerings as they were able to
use. Prince Albert opened the Exhibition on May 5th in the Blakean faith that “art is the purest expression of
the state of mental and religious culture, and of general civilization of any age or people.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> For the next five and a half months the two
“modestly tinted” Blake paintings gazed at visitors from the walls of Manchester’s Old Trafford. 
<note id="n5">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                5
                            </hi> “The Exhibition of Art Treasures at Manchester,” <hi rend="i">Art
Journal</hi> (June, 1857), p. 187.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Blake’s works as listed in the Official Catalogue were: “130. Oberon and Titania on a
Lily, lent by Wm. Russell, Esq.; 130a. Vision of Queen Catherine, lent by C. W. Dilke, Esq.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> [figs. 1 and <note id="n0">
                            <hi rend="i">Suzanne R. Hoover has taught at the City College of New York and at
Wellesley College. She has contributed previously to the</hi> Newsletter. <hi rend="i">She is presently in
London studying English Romantic art on a fellowship from the National Endowment for the Humanities.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-7" n="7"/>
                        <figure n="OberonAndTitania.6.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="624">
                            <head>1 “Oberon and Titania.”</head>
                            <figDesc>Private Collection.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
2]. Both paintings are included in W. M. Rossetti’s <hi rend="i">Annotated Catalogue</hi> in the second
volume of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life.</hi> William Russell’s collection is briefly and uninformatively
described by Dr. Waagen in <hi rend="i">Galleries and Cabinets of Art in Great Britain.</hi>
                        <ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Dilke is, of course, Keats’s friend, an early
collector of Blake’s work. <note id="n6">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                6
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Catalogue of the Art Treasures of the United Kingdom. Collected at
Manchester in 1857.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">7</hi> Dr. [Gustav Friedrich] Waagen, <hi rend="i">Galleries and
Cabinets of Art in Great Britain</hi> (London, 1857), a supplement to <hi rend="i">Treasures of Art in Great
Britain</hi>, 3 vols. (London, 1854).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In all the prose expended on the Manchester Exhibition, which is to say a very great
deal, there is, to my knowledge, only one notice of Blake—in the <hi rend="i">Handbook to the Water Colours,
Drawings, and Engravings in the Art Treasures Exhibition</hi>, a reprint of critical notices originally
published in the <hi rend="i">Manchester Guardian.</hi> Blake is compared in this passage to Richard Dadd, a
(then living) painter born in 1817, who travelled in Asia Minor and Egypt, where he had a mental breakdown;
and who then returned home, murdered his father in 1843, and was imprisoned for life in Bethlehem Hospital,
where he continued to produce some remarkable works of art. Blake and Dadd, says the author, “may be classed
together as examples of painters in whom a disordered
						<figure n="BUT548.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="500" height="639">
                            <head>2 “Vision of Queen Catherine” (“Queen Katherine’s Dream”).</head>
                            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
brain rather aided than impeded the workings of fancy.”
<q>
Do not be deterred by the strangeness of Blake’s work, or the sadness of Dadd’s, from looking closely into
both. Both were mad, but the insanity of Blake was of the kind separated by a thin partition from great wit.
It was rather from preponderance of the imaginative faculty that he must be classed among lunatics, than from
any ruin of mind such as hurried poor Dadd into parricide. Blake’s fancies were lovely rather than terrible.
He was poet and musician as well as painter. If his music was like his verse, it must have been among the
sweetest ever written.
</q>
The author quotes “To the Muses” in full, with great admiration, and then offers some biographical details,
including the usual account, from Cunningham, of Blake’s serene and pious death. He continues, in some
confusion:
<q>
The great dead came to him . . . All his works were records of these visions; whether they be the pictures and
songs of innocence and experience, the illustrations of Job, or of the grave and Dante, his twelve inventions
of man and death, his wild allegories of Urizen, and
<pb id="p06-8" n="8"/>
his prophecies of England and America. His death . . . is one of the loveliest upon record. . . . One is
almost tempted to envy such unreason, which seems to make a man unfit for earth only by lifting him nearer
heaven.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
                            <note id="n8">
                                <hi rend="s">8</hi>
                                <hi rend="i"> A Handbook to the Water Colours, Drawings, and Engravings, in
the Manchester Art Treasures Exhibition</hi> (London, 1857), pp. 12-13. I have not been able to check the 
<hi rend="i">Manchester Guardian</hi> for the original article in which, presumably, Blake was mentioned.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Exhibition of 1862 grew out of those of 1851 and 1857. It was really two
exhibitions in one: an international showing of industrial arts and design on the tenth anniversary of the
Great Exhibition (postponed a year because of the death in 1861 of the Prince Consort); and an art exhibition
designed to surpass its predecessor at Manchester. The exhibits of manufactures were not as striking as those
ten years before—with some exceptions, notably Japan’s display, the first in the West, which had a most
profound effect on English taste within the next few years. On the other hand, the fine art exhibit was
wholeheartedly approved by everyone who saw it. It was one of the most popular parts of the exhibition.
Smaller than Manchester—for example, six hundred and twenty-four watercolors compared to Manchester’s
thousand—it nevertheless was a finer collection, better displayed. On this occasion Blake was represented by
five pictures, four among
						<figure n="BUT471.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="862" height="1000">
                            <head>3 “Christ in the Lap of Truth” (“The Holy Family”), watercolor
drawing.</head>
                            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Cleveland Museum of Art, John L.
Severance Fund.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
the watercolors and one among the oil paintings. The listings in the Official Catalogue were: “221. Christ in
the Lap of Truth, and Between his Earthly Parents [fig. 3] . . . R. M. Milnes, Esq.; 965. Joseph Ordering
Simeon to be bound [fig. 4] . . . J. D. Coleridge, Esq.; 966. Joseph Making himself Known to his brethren
[fig. 5] . . . J. D. Coleridge, Esq.; 967. Joseph’s Brethren Bowing Before Him [fig. 6] . . . J. D.
Coleridge, Esq.; 968. Canterbury Pilgrimage . . . W. Stirling, Esq.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">9</ref> The
<pb id="p06-9" n="9"/>
                        <figure n="BUT156.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="700" height="509">
                            <head>4 “Joseph ordering Simeon to be bound.”</head>
                            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
first of these was listed as an oil painting, the next three were watercolors, the last a tempera listed with
the watercolors. All of these paintings were entered by Rossetti in the <hi rend="i">Annotated Catalogue</hi>;
all but one were discussed in the biography by Gilchrist. <hi rend="i">Christ in the Lap of Truth</hi>, wrote
Rossetti, is “the interesting and characteristic, though not salient, picture which was rather concealed than
displayed at the International Exhibition.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> There is no mention of it in the biography. <note id="n9">
                            <hi rend="s">9</hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> International Exhibition of 1862. Official Catalogue of the Fine Art
Department</hi> [corrected, 1862]. Milnes and Stirling are well known as early Blake collectors. “J. D.
Coleridge” refers to Sir John Duke Coleridge (1820-1894), first Baron Coleridge, who became Lord Chief Justice
of England in 1880.</note>
                        <note id="n10">
                            <hi rend="s">10</hi> Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life</hi> (1863), II, 211. Sir
Geoffrey Keynes, in <hi rend="i">The Tempera Paintings of William Blake</hi>, states that <hi rend="i">Christ
in the Lap of Truth</hi> is a tempera, “erroneously described as an ‘oil picture’ by Rossetti”; however,
the true identity of the painting of that title exhibited in 1862 remains uncertain. A watercolor with the
title “Christ in the Lap of Truth” is reproduced in <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the
Bible</hi> (Trianon Press, 1957) as #104. The same picture, entitled “The Holy Family: or Christ in the Lap of
Truth,” is described in <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of W. Graham Robertson</hi>, ed. Kerrison Preston
(London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1952), pp. 144-45. Robertson writes, “A larger version of this design was in oil .
. . and in the possession of Lord Crewe.” Mr. Martin Butlin, Keeper of the British Collection at the Tate
Gallery, has been kind enough to offer the following remarks about <hi rend="i">Christ in the Lap of
Truth</hi>: “I have always suspected that the version of Blake’s ‘Christ in the Lap of Truth’ exhibited
at the International Exhibition in London in 1862 . . . was the oil painting that was lent from the Crewe
Collection to the Arts Council ‘Blake Temperas’ Exhibition in 1951, but withdrawn as probably not an
original. Alternatively, the untraced picture, probably a tempera, ‘The Holy Family,’ described by
Rossetti (1862, p. 230, no. 182) may have perished in Captain Butts’s sister’s attic. The water-colour
version of this composition is now in the Cleveland Museum of Art.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Perhaps because more of his art was shown, more was written about Blake in 1862 than in
1857. In addition to the Catalogue listings there were four notices this time—few enough! and one of these
was utterly inconsequential; but the consequential ones had at least got out of the Cunningham-anecdote rut
that so much commentary on Blake had already fallen into, and was to continue in for many years to come. The
two signed items are both by F. T. Palgrave, art critic, future anthologist and professor of poetry at
Oxford—known to students of Blake’s reputation as one of the early admirers and collectors of Blake’s
work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
                        <note id="n11">
                            <hi rend="s">11</hi> For Palgrave’s early interest in Blake, see Gwenllian F.
Palgrave, <hi rend="i">Francis Turner Palgrave: His Journals and Memories of His Life</hi> (London, 1899), pp.
26-27.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Palgrave wrote the essay on “The British School of Water Colour Painting” for that
section of the Official Catalogue. It is only three pages long, and yet nearly one page of it is given to a
comparison between Blake and Stothard,
<q>
two men singularly contrasted in their life and in their genius, gifted respectively with exquisite fancy and
intense imagination, and to whom England is indebted for a long series of
<pb id="p06-10" n="10"/>
                            <figure n="BUT157.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="700" height="508">
                                <head>5 “Joseph making himself known to his brethren.”</head>
                                <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Fitzwilliam Museum,
Cambridge.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
works, which, take them all in all, no other water-colourists in this style have equalled. But it is hardly as
art that the strange creations of the visionary Blake appeal to us; the drawing and execution are rarely
successful; it is in the force of the penetrative imagination that their value lies,—in their almost painful
intensity,—in their sublime suggestions of some earlier world of patriarchal days, or the mysteries of
spiritual and ecstatic existence.
</q>
Palgrave describes “the gentle-hearted Stothard,” the charm and delicacy and grace of his art. Then, with a
hard-heartedness that sets him apart from his contemporaries, Palgrave repudiates “Stothard’s world” as
lacking the “depth and impressiveness” of real existence. And he finds Blake’s world to be distorted in an
opposite way: he “saw all things through a morbid imagination.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">12</ref> (Had Palgrave not seen the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>?) 
<note id="n12">
                            <hi rend="s">12</hi> F.[rancis] T.[urner] P.[algrave], “The British School of
Water Colour Painting,” <hi rend="i">International Exhibition . . . Catalogue</hi>, p. 46.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Such criticism, while it misapprehends Blake, neither condescends to him, nor dismisses
him as a madman, nor elevates him to sainthood: all of which makes it rather refreshing. Palgrave discussed
Blake again in his <hi rend="i">Handbook</hi> to the Exhibition. The theme is the same as that in the
Catalogue—it is even expressed in some of the same words; but in addition, he mentions here the other Blake
paintings at the Exhibition. Again, he compares Blake with Stothard,
<q>
within certain limits, two of the most inventive and original designers in English art. Neither is here
represented fully, but they may be compared in their rival illustrations of the <hi rend="i">Pilgrimage to
Canterbury</hi> from the Prologue to Chaucer’s Tales. Blake’s work has more poetic
penetration,—Stothard’s more poetical grace; he reaches greater completeness and balance in the whole,
Blake goes to the heart of the matter where he succeeds (the Host, the Prioress), but misses much entirely.
The contrast indicated runs through their whole life and genius; Stothard the man of boundless and practised
fancy, Blake of restricted and intense imagination.
</q>
There follows a passage about Blake that repeats, virtually word-for-word, the one in the Catalogue, already
quoted. Blake’s imaginative qualities, says Palgrave, “are seen more in his strange oil-picture, 
<hi rend="i">Christ on the Lap of the Church</hi> [fig. 3],—Blake’s conception of the favorite design of early
art,—than in the little-characteristic scenes from Genesis [i. e., the <hi rend="i">Joseph</hi>
paintings].”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> By analyzing and
re-naming the “strange” picture owned by his friend Milnes, Palgrave intended to show that Blake, however
original in his invention, was inspired by traditional Christian art. Prior to Yeats, any insight into
Blake’s relation to a tradition was a critical rarity. Palgrave’s
<pb id="p06-11" n="11"/>
                        <figure n="BUT155.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="700" height="505">
                            <head>6 “Joseph’s brethren bowing before him.”</head>
                            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
remark about the <hi rend="i">Joseph</hi> paintings suggests that he was unfamiliar with Blake’s early work.
(These were the first, or among the first, of Blake’s paintings on Biblical subjects.) <note id="n13">
                            <hi rend="s">13</hi> Francis Turner Palgrave, <hi rend="i">Handbook to the Fine
Art Collections in the International Exhibition of 1862</hi> (London, 1862), pp. 65-66. In Gwenllian F.
Palgrave, p. 72, there is only a hint of the hubbub caused by the <hi rend="i">Handbook</hi>’s forthright
opinions of some contemporary artists. Widely read at that time, the <hi rend="i">Handbook</hi> has never
before, to my knowledge, been discussed in connection with Blake.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The only one of the two periodical notices of Blake’s pictures that has any substance
is a short passage that damns Blake to praise Stothard. Unfortunately, this judgment appeared in a periodical
that might have been expected to produce something more than perfunctory or conventional criticism of an
“unknown” painter, the influential <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi>, the most important Victorian periodical in
the field of the visual arts. The passage concludes:
<q>
Neither artist took firm hold on the actual, yet, of the two, Blake shows himself the more shadowy and
visionary. The painter, indeed, who maintained spiritual converse with the Virgin Mary, was scarcely likely to
do justice to the ‘Wife of Bath.’<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref>
                            <note id="n14">
                                <hi rend="s">
                                    14
                                </hi> “International Exhibition, 1862: Pictures of the British School,” 
<hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi> (July, 1862), p. 151.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Last, and least, of the exhibition notices is one incomprehensible sentence in an 
<hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> article on the English watercolors. The sentence preceding it, about Dadd, is given
here for whatever light it may shed on the meaning of the sentence about Blake: “Some works of exceptional
interest will be found under the names [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] of Dadd,—<hi rend="i">Moonlight in the
Desert</hi> and <hi rend="i">A Rocky Valley.</hi> Blake’s transcendental fancies are freely seen.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Freely seen? <note id="n15">
                            <hi rend="s">
                                15
                            </hi> “International Exhibition. The English Watercolour Pictures,” 
<hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi>, 17 May 1862, p. 663. This passage was reprinted, <hi rend="i">verbatim</hi>, in the
popular compendium (“Uniform with the official catalogues”) entitled, <hi rend="i">What Do You Think of the
Exhibition? A Collection of the Best Descriptions and Criticisms from the Leading Journals Concerning the
International Exhibition</hi> (London, 1862), pp. 179-81. The compendium was edited by Robert Kempt.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>On that baffling note our glimpse of Blake’s pictures at the exhibitions may be,
appropriately, concluded. An ideal art-lover who had seen the pictures and read the commentaries, while he
might have been intrigued by the first, was then surely befuddled by contradiction between critics about first
principles, such as whether Blake’s imagination was “lovely” (Manchester <hi rend="i">Handbook</hi>) or
“morbid” (Palgrave). Nevertheless, something must have been gained from the little of Blake’s work that was
seen, and the little that was written about that little. For present-day students of Blake, some questions
persist: in neither exhibition did Blake appear among the engravers, although he had been known primarily as
an engraver during his lifetime, and the collections of engravings were supposedly exhaustive (especially at
Manchester). Those pictures that were hung did not show Blake at the height of his powers—another curious
circumstance, when we consider that some excellent Blakes had already been “collected” and that there were
persons with influence in the “art world” who knew perfectly well what Blake could do. In sum, we discover
here, as at other times throughout the nineteenth century, a highly mysterious compound: first, we find a
surprising general neglect of Blake, and then, considering that neglect, we meet with some equally surprising
specific attentions.</p>
                    <pb id="p06-12" n="12"/>
                    <div3>
                    <head>
                    	<title><hi rend="i">APPENDIX: NEW REFERENCES TO BLAKE</hi></title>
                    </head>
                    <p>New references to Blake in connection with 
the Manchester Art Treasures Exhibition of 1857 
and the International Exhibition of 1862. The arrangement 
is chronological. Palgrave’s article 
(No. 4) is entered separately from the Catalogue 
itself (No. 3) in order to distinguish it from the 
list of Blake paintings contained in the Catalogue.</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Art Treasures of the United 
Kingdom. Collected at Manchester in 1857.</hi>
Nos. 130 and 130a. </p>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="i">A Handbook to the Water Colours, Drawings, 
and Engravings, in the Manchester Art Treasures Exhibition</hi>
(London, 1857), pp. 12-13.</p>
                    <p>3. <hi rend="i">International Exhibition of 1862. Official 
Catalogue of the Fine Art Department</hi> [corrected, 
1862]. Nos. 221, 965-68.</p>
                    <p>4. P.[algrave], F.[rancis] T.[urner], “The 
British School of Water Colour Painting,” <hi rend="i">International 
Exhibition of 1862. Official Catalogue of 
the Fine Art Department</hi> [corrected, 1862], pp. 46-47.</p>
                    <p>5. Palgrave, Francis Turner. <hi rend="i">Handbook to the 
Fine Arts Collections in the International Exhibition 
of 1862</hi> (London, 1862), pp. 65-66.</p>
                    <p>6. Anon. “International Exhibition. The 
English Water-colour Pictures,” <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi>, 17 May 
1862, p. 663.</p>
                    <p>7. Anon. “International Exhibition, 1862: 
Pictures of the British School,” <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi>, I 
(July, 1862), 151.</p>
					</div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>