<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.mellor</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">W. H. Stevenson, ed., The Poems of William Blake</title>
                <author n="Mellor">Anne Kostelanetz Mellor</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0006">
                <pb id="p06-32" n="32"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake.</hi> Edited by W. H. Stevenson, text by
David Erdman. Annotated English Poets. London: Longman, 1971. Pp. xxiv + 877. £4.25. New York: W. W.
Norton.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Anne Kostelanetz <name>Mellor</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n68" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>W. H. Stevenson’s annotated edition of David Erdman’s text of Blake’s poems has
much to commend it, particularly to students reading Blake for the first time. For the general reader, it
combines what are perhaps the most satisfying features of both the Keynes (Oxford Standard Authors) text and
the Erdman (Doubleday) text. Stevenson follows Keynes in placing Blake’s poems in chronological order,
following (with only one exception) the most recently accepted datings of the poems. The exception is 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, which Stevenson (following G. E. Bentley, Jr.) dates 1789 and places before 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, despite the persuasive stylistic, substantive, and bibliographical evidence
offered by Erdman for dating <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> 1790, midway between <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, plates 1-5
(1789) and <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, 6 and Motto (1791 on). Stevenson helpfully inserts “To Tirzah” (c. 1804-5
or after 1809) after the “Pickering Manuscript,” and offers convincing historical and bibliographical
considerations for dating the “Pickering Manuscript” itself c. 1805, rather than 1803.</p>
                    <p>Stevenson also follows Keynes in modernizing Blake’s spelling and punctuation.
Scholars may here prefer to consult Erdman’s own text which preserves Blake’s eccentric spelling and
punctuation, but the average reader will be helped by Stevenson’s judicious punctuation, especially in such
poems as “The Everlasting Gospel” where different voices speak. In choosing the Erdman text over the Keynes
text, Stevenson has correctly selected the most authoritative text we have. Unfortunately for the scholar,
however, Stevenson’s edition is limited solely to Blake’s poetry, thus omitting the prose and letters upon
which most of us depend for teaching and research purposes. Even more annoying is the omission of the 
<hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi> emblems, especially since Stevenson provides such insightful comments on the
emblems, captions and the relationship of the 1793 and 1818 versions.</p>
                    <p>In arranging Erdman’s text, Stevenson makes three important editorial decisions, all
of which he convincingly justifies. He accepts W. F. Halloran’s reordering of lines 1-121 of 
<hi rend="i">The French Revolution.</hi> Secondly, he reorders Nights VIIa and VIIb of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,
printing Night VIIa before VIIb and arguing that Night VIIb was intended to follow directly upon VIIa. Readers
of the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> (1[March 1968], 6-8) will already be familiar with Stevenson’s
persuasive arguments based on internal as well as bibliographical evidence for this ordering. Finally,
Stevenson relegates plates 3, 4, 5, 10, 18 and 32 of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (which appear only in the later
copies C and D) to the end of the poem as an Appendix. He argues plausibly that these plates are “largely
digressive” and added for the purpose of increasing the total number of plates in the poem to 50 (p. 484).</p>
                    <p>The great achievement of this volume lies in its annotations, and here we must be
extremely grateful to Stevenson for providing us with such detailed, extensive and insightful notes. I found
particularly useful his commentaries on the polypus, the Druids, the Holy Thursday services at St. Paul’s,
the Ovidian echoes in “Ah! Sunflower,” and the numerous Biblical allusions (supplied in great part, we are
told, by Michael Tolley). Stevenson also provides brief descriptions of the designs for the illuminated poems
(although he unaccountably omits the design for the titlepage of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> [p. 209]) and occasionally gives a reference to a reproduction. In future editions, he will be
able to bring such references up to date by including the numerous reproductions listed in Robert Essick’s
<hi rend="i">Finding List</hi> published in the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 5 (Summer-Fall 1971).</p>
                    <p>I have only one large quarrel and a few small bones to pick with this annotated
edition. In his Preface, Stevenson writes, “I have tried in this edition not to interpret or expound any
‘system’ in [Blake’s] works, but to give whatever information is necessary for the exposition of each
poem or passage . . . ” (p. xi). Stevenson’s intention is laudable, but again and again we find him offering
interpretations as though they were facts, without acknowledging that some critics disagree with him. For
example, it is surely an interpretation—and to my mind a dubious one—to identify the “Holy Word” in the
“Introduction” of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> as the production of “Blake’s oppressive
tyrant-father-god,” a production designed “to bully mankind” (p. 209). Many readers may question Stevenson’s
assertions that we should not “doubt the sincerity of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>” (p. 53); that
the questions of the Voice of Sorrow on Plate 6 of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> are merely “rhetorical” (p. 100);
and that the angel in “I heard an angel singing” from the Notebook “is one of the deluded creatures referred
to in <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>” (p. 147). And why is this angel “deluded” while the “Good” referred to in
the unused Motto for <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> is definitively called “a term of
approval—not the satiric ‘good’ of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>” (p. 166)? Moreover, Stevenson’s
apparent assumption that Blake was a Platonist (see pp. 106, 112, 861) comes perilously close to expounding a
“system” in Blake’s works. I am not arguing, of course, that Stevenson should not put forth interpretations,
or even that his interpretations are necessarily in error, but only that he should not have presented them as
wholly objective “information.”</p>
                    <p>In several cases I take issue with Stevenson’s descriptions of the designs. Too often
his descriptions seem inaccurate, inadequate or overly subjective. Since Blake’s illuminated designs vary
significantly from copy to copy, Stevenson may simply have described copies other than the Trianon 
<note id="n68">
                            <hi rend="i">Anne K. Mellor is Assistant Professor of English at Stanford
University. Her study of the development of form in Blake’s art and poetry</hi>, Blake’s Human Form
Divine, <hi rend="i">will be published by the University of California Press this spring. She currently holds
a Guggenheim Fellowship and is working on a book on English Romantic irony.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-33" n="33"/>
Press facsimiles and Micro Methods microfilms I have checked; but he has not identified the copies he used
and, in any case, one could argue that he should have used these more generally available copies. In copies D
and I of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, plate 11 depicts both a personified sun with flaming hair and a
crowned figure within a wave, tree or plant, as opposed to the single “tritonlike male figure” (p. 111)
Stevenson records. Again, the design for “The Argument” in both these copies probably depicts a woman in the
tree rather than the “gowned youth” Stevenson sees there (p. 103). Stevenson’s description of Oothoon and
Bromion, “bound and shackled back to back,” in the tailpiece (or frontispiece) of <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi> omits mention of a very important detail, that Oothoon is not visibly chained (p.
186). Stevenson also ignores the large bird in the upper left corner of the design for “The Shepherd”—a bird
which might possibly be the Holy Dove and therefore potentially significant enough to deserve mention (p. 55).
Nor is it a “fact” that the “shepherd” (Piper?) in the frontispiece for <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
is “holding the child’s arms so that he cannot fly away” (p. 209)—he might be simply balancing the child
so that he doesn’t fall off.</p>
                    <p>A few annotations are disappointing: Tharmas, in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, seems
more complex a figure than Stevenson’s identification of him as “Compassion” (p. 288) suggests; his
discussion of “Havilah” solely in terms of its Biblical usage (p. 665) ignores Blake’s own associations with
it in his letter to Hayley, 12 March 1804; and his de-emphasis of the word “system” in “I must create a
system” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 10:20, p. 644) underestimates the importance of an organized system to Blake’s
late art and poetry. I would also argue against Stevenson’s annotation of “dominion of Edom” in 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, plate 3, as “dominion <hi rend="i">over</hi> Edom” (p. 105). It seems at least
possible that Blake was following Biblical usage here: dominion <hi rend="i">of</hi> in the sense of dominion
<hi rend="i">by.</hi> Compare II Chronicles 21:8: “In his [Jehoram’s] days the Edomites revolted from under
the dominion of Judah, and made themselves a King.”</p>
                    <p>These are niggling details, however, and Stevenson more than compensates for such minor
flaws by giving us so much useful material. In addition to the excellent annotations already mentioned,
Stevenson provides illuminating comparisons with the early drafts of “Infant Sorrow” and “The Tyger” and with
Isaac Watts’ “Cradle Hymn”; helpful maps of Biblical Palestine, of the environs of London mentioned in
Blake’s poems, and of the city of London in c. 1810; and interesting bibliographical notes telling which
poems were paired in seven of the eight earliest copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> All of
Blake’s readers will want to have ready access to the wealth of background and bibliographical information
gathered together in this book. Stevenson’s volume is the second step toward the ideal edition of Blake: his
complete poems, letters and prose writings edited by David Erdman, together with colored photographic
reproductions of his illuminated pages, and annotations by W. H. Stevenson.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>