<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.eaves</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Benjamin DeMott, Blake and Manchild</title>
                <author n="Eaves">Morris Eaves</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <pb id="p06-25" n="25"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0006">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Reviews.</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Benjamin DeMott. <hi rend="i">Blake and Manchild</hi>, a tape
recording. Sound Seminars. New York: McGraw-Hill, recorded 1968. 36 minutes. Reel-to-reel (75998-7) or
cassette (81580-1) format. $11.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Morris <name>Eaves</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n65" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Blake and Manchild</hi> is thirty-six minutes of meandering, and the
meandering begins with a title that has nothing to do with the matter recorded on the tape. After an apology
to the audience for his cold, and a related anecdote about his visit to the office of President Johnson, where
DeMott’s cultivated sensibility was thrown off balance by the old warrior’s secret tic, a ferocious snort
before speaking, DeMott announces the ostensible subject of his talk: “the Higher Innocence,” which he
promises to get to by a road through “The Lamb” and “The Chimney Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>But to recall the terrain before setting out, we listen to pleasant recitations of the
poems. Then, not “The Lamb” and “The Chimney Sweeper” as expected, but a fifteen-minute detour through the
eighteenth century, looking for its “characteristic gesture,” which when we find it turns out to be
“comprehension” and “mastery at a remove.” In the poetry of the century, we “hear” this “gesture” in the voice
of the “preceptor”—the voice that says such things as “Whatever IS, is RIGHT” and “Let Observation, with
extensive view, / Survey mankind, from China to Peru.” Side 1 of the tape is over.</p>
                    <p>Side 2 sets out in search of the characteristic gesture of “The Lamb,” which we learn
is “cuddling”—taking life to oneself, as the child takes the lamb into his arms, and acting tenderly towards
it, even if still a little bit preceptorially. It is not clear whether DeMott means that the narrator actually
takes the lamb into his arms or not. Nothing in the words of the poem tells him that, and the lower part of
the plate shows the child standing at arm’s length from the lamb, which is about the closest DeMott can
afford to get to “The Lamb” and still find his “characteristic gesture.”</p>
                    <p>He then brings in “The Tyger” in order to conclude that Romantic man’s characteristic
gesture is a motion back and forth between the pole of the “act” of “The Lamb”—cuddling—to the pole of
“The Tyger”—cosmic “nagging.” Thus Blake represents those Romantics who want “Innocence beyond Innocence,”
as “The Lamb” and “The Tyger” combine into a “vision of the Higher Innocence,” the chief pleasure of which
is—<hi rend="i">memory</hi>! And the tape runs past its last electromagnetic squiggles to tell us that “the
great pleasure, the first Romantic pleasure, is, then—in Blake, in my imagination of him—is the pleasure
of memory.”</p>
                    <p>On the one hand DeMott knows enough about Blake’s critics to have picked up a thesis
about Higher Innocence, while on the other he knows too little about Blake or his critics to know that, if
other Romantic poets were gesturing Memory, Blake was standing in the window of Higher Innocence gesturing
Imagination back at them. Even when stopped up with a cold, DeMott is as pleasant to listen to as most
lecturers, and his words on the “preceptorial gesture” of the eighteenth century are probably worth the time
it takes to hear them, but on Blake he’d have done better to leave off at a summary of other people’s
opinions.</p>
                    <p>The lecture never gets to “The Chimney Sweeper” as promised. DeMott may have quit, the
tape recorder may have broken, or McGraw-Hill may have economized. No one will care which, because one more
meander would have added only another layer of diffuseness to this uninstructive thirty-six minute gyp.</p>
                    <p>But DeMott is not the only culprit in this media game, and questions about his
understanding of Blake are not the only questions his lecture raises. McGraw-Hill has shown little good sense
and less good will in publishing its Sound Seminars. The prices are outrageously high and the pricing policy
is irrational. Tapes that run fifteen minutes and those that run seventy minutes are all $11 apiece. No matter
how short the tape, $11. No matter how long? Well, no: the price jumps to $12.50 for tapes over about 70
minutes.</p>
                    <p>If $11 for DeMott’s thirty-six-minute tape is in line with the prices on
McGraw-Hill’s books—that is, if the retailer’s profit is about 40%—then tapes are simply too expensive
to produce for the mass market. But why the recording companies can produce tapes of, say, forty-five minutes
of <hi rend="i">music</hi> for less than $6, and yet McGraw-Hill cannot seem to produce fifteen minutes of 
<hi rend="i">voice</hi> for less than $11 is beyond me. Musical recording requires enormous expenditures on
studios, musicians, composers, and technical assistance. The kind of recordings McGraw-Hill is producing could
be done at home by anyone with semi-professional equipment.</p>
                    <p>I would estimate that a transcription of DeMott’s recording would take up fewer than
ten pages of type. The question, then, is what special use justifies the publication of <hi rend="i">Blake and
Manchild</hi> as an extraordinarily expensive tape recording rather than as an essay in one of DeMott’s
books? First, DeMott probably wouldn’t want the matter recorded on the tape to appear in the slightly
classier company of his essays. Second, I frankly can’t imagine any special use that the tape allows.
Teaching? Who would spend the better part of an hour having students listen to something that could be
summarized without loss in five minutes? Students themselves would not stand for the tape unless they 
<note id="n65">
                            <hi rend="i">Morris Eaves (University of New Mexico) is Managing Editor of
the</hi> Newsletter. <hi rend="i">He has published essays recently on Blake, Shakespeare, and James Merrill.
He is completing a comprehensive index of Damon’s</hi> Blake Dictionary <hi rend="i">and a book on Blake and
art history.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-26" n="26"/>
were being relieved of something alive and worse. Home? I would have DeMott to dinner, but only to write a
review would I trap myself in a room with his taped voice.</p>
                    <p>In short, what could be deadlier than a taped lecture, except a required live one? What
is designed to bring more certain calamity to the classroom and the home? Only reviewers, teachers without
consciences, and practical jokers would mess with this stuff. Readings by poets with stirring voices at
reasonable prices, yes. The hypnotic spells of jumbo-mumbling lecturers spun on reels of brown tape,
nevermore.</p>
                    <p>Available in the same series with <hi rend="i">Blake and Manchild</hi>: Benjamin
DeMott, <hi rend="i">Hardy and Manchild</hi>, fifty minutes, $11. Could that be a better buy?</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>