<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.beer</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Brief Ripostes</title>
                <author n="Beer">John Beer</author>
                <author n="Chayes">Irene Chayes</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
	<pb id="p06-22" n="22"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0004">
            	<div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">BRIEF RIPOSTES</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>John <name>Beer</name>
                        </docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">*</ref>
and <docAuthor>Irene <name>Chayes</name>
                        </docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">*</ref>
                    </byline>
                    <p>Mrs. Chayes and I have now each had a chance to defend our respective views of
Blake’s art, and Mrs. Chayes in fact states the difference between us with some precision when she declares
roundly that while a work of art may be created through memory and imagination acting upon each other with
equal force, an imagination which was <hi rend="i">interpreting</hi> the images presented to it “could not
have created a single drawing, painting or etched design.” What is for me the essence of “prophetic” art, as
practiced by Blake, is for her a simple impossibility, and perhaps we ought to leave it at that.</p>
                    <p>While it might be tedious and repetitious to go over the same ground again, however, I
should like to discuss briefly one or two of the new points that she makes. She is kind enough to regret 
<note id="n62">
                            <hi rend="i">John Beer, who lectures at Cambridge, is the author of</hi> Coleridge
the Visionary, The Achievement of E. M. Forster, Blake’s Humanism, <hi rend="i">and</hi> Blake’s Visionary
Universe. <hi rend="i">He has also produced an edition of Coleridge’s</hi> Poems <hi rend="i">and is
currently doing further work on Wordsworth and Coleridge.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <note id="n63">
                            <hi rend="i">Irene H. Chayes has taught at the University of Maryland, SUNY
Binghamton, and elsewhere. She has published many critical essays, most of them on Blake and the Romantics.
Her most recent publication is “Blake and the Seasons of the Poet,” which appeared in</hi> Studies in
Romanticism, <hi rend="i">Summer, 1972. She is writing a book on the interrelations of Blake’s art and his
poetry.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-23" n="23"/>
that I did not defend the organization of my illustrations and special commentary as a private miniature
prophetic book of my own; but she does not explain why she thinks I should want to defend a conception which
is entirely of her own devising. And she still shows little sign of recognizing that my main discussions of
particular designs are usually <hi rend="i">in the text of the book itself</hi> and not in the more
summarizing and thematic commentary. Thus, in discussing <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 75, she states that the
entwining creatures are “less serpents proper than the ‘dragon forms’ referred to in [Blake’s]
text”—as if I had been maintaining that they were serpents. I can only refer her despairingly to page 192 of
my book, and to the statement, “Benevolent dragons of energy are depicted . . . .”</p>
                    <p>It is worth continuing the discussion of this plate for the sake of the light that may
be thrown on a very crucial question—that of the relationship between text and illustration in Blake’s
prophetic books. This question, which is topical in view of the welcome news of David Erdman’s forthcoming
Doubleday edition, would seem to lie near the center of the controversy. If one could take it for granted that
Blake is always concerned to illustrate, directly and in detail, a line or more of the text on his plate,
there would be a firm basis for interpretation. But although it is a good point of scholarly discipline to
look hard for such possibilities, the search often breaks down. Sometimes, for example, the relationship is
better described as one of counterpoint, as in <hi rend="i">America</hi> 7, where the peaceful pastoral images
can hardly be making anything but a satirical comment on the speech of Albion’s Angel. And this
diversification of practice is not surprising when we recall that Blake called his designs not “illustrations”
but “illuminations.”</p>
                    <p>So with <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 75. Certainly, the vegetative eye sees a possible
connection between the women and dragons of the design and those in the lines above, ending
<q>
Thus Rahab is revealed—<lb/>
Mystery, Babylon the Great, the Abomination of Desolation,<lb/>
Religion hid in war, a dragon red &amp; hidden harlot . . .
</q>
The eye of direct emotional response, on the other hand, if it is anything like mine, sees an immediacy of
beauty in the design which is distinctly at variance with the sinister tone of the lines about Rahab and the
Churches. When the connections made by the vegetative eye and the response of the human being behind that eye
conflict so sharply it seems natural to call on the eye of interpreting imagination and to try to resolve the
difficulty by arguing that Blake is here not illustrating but illuminating—penetrating further into the
conflict described on the plate to suggest a state in which what is, in the text, a destructive interaction
between fallen vision and tyrannical energy might yet become a productive alliance between vision and energy,
once restored to their proper functions. If so, this is another of Blake’s counterpointing designs. While
the early part of the text continues the conflicts recorded in the poem, the illumination, catching a moment
of reconciliation—though still a reconciliation held in tension—looks forward to the restored alliance of
vision and energy that will be more firmly prophesied in the last chapter of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
While the motifs are taken from the harlot and dragon forms, in other words, the interpretation is dominated
(or the illumination illuminated) by the next lines of the plate:
<q>
But Jesus, breaking through the central zones of death &amp; hell<lb/>
Opens Eternity in time &amp; space, triumphant in mercy.
</q>
(These points may be found, amplified, on pages 190-91 of my book.)</p>
                    <p>It may be that modes of interpretation such as this offend the “public critic,” but the
public critic will always have some difficulty in dealing with writers who, like Blake, regard the public
language of their time (whether in art or poetry) as inadequate to express the vision by which they are
possessed. In such circumstances it seems more profitable to look for the modes of interpretation which make
the best total sense of what is there on the plates (both individually and as a sequence) and then leave
theoretical criticism to account for any successes which are achieved. In Blake’s case (to put it another
way) the purposes of scholarship would seem to be best served by the commentators who are willing to go along
with him and look “through” as well as “with” the vegetable eye. It might be easier to apply more traditional
methods if the two modes of seeing could be separated, but in many instances, I would maintain, such a
separation makes nonsense of what he is attempting. So we return to the basic disagreement which I mentioned
at the beginning. I believe that the imagination of an artist like Blake is capable of working towards the
expression of new significances as well as of new forms, whereas Mrs. Chayes does not. No doubt the issue will
continue to divide Blake scholars.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>MRS. CHAYES WRITES:</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>I am sorry that by misrepresenting my position Mr. Beer makes it necessary for me to
reply again, I hope for the last time.</p>
                    <p>“Impossible” was neither my word nor my meaning for the suggestion—with which I
generally agree, as I pointed out—that Blake was likely to interpret in his own way the art themes and
motifs he borrowed. What I did mean and believed I was saying clearly enough was that the allegorizing
represented by Mr. Beer’s captions and descriptions would be <hi rend="i">inadequate</hi> to account for the
complexity of the designs in question and <hi rend="i">inappropriate</hi> to a non-verbal art medium. I do not
separate “significances” new or old from “forms” (again, we are talking about pictures), and I would not
exempt Blake’s own intentions and predispositions from the process of mutual modification out of which, as I
see it, the new significances stressed by Mr. Beer
<pb id="p06-24" n="24"/>
(but not necessarily those found by Mr. Beer) would have arisen.</p>
                    <p>To me, the design on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 75 is the product of such a process,
involving the Laocoön motifs and resulting in a new significance which is bound up with the revelation of
Rahab, the dragon-harlot. There is a great deal more that could be said about this plate, both text and
design, and about Mr. Beer’s new comments, in which he will not allow Rahab to be both sinister and
beautiful or error to wear an appearance of reconciliation. Much could be said, too, about Mr. Beer’s theory
of “visionary” criticism, which disappointingly turns out to be affective criticism, long familiar. In the
hope of putting an end to this debate, which actually began between Mr. Beer and John Grant, I will say only
that it has been a reminder that by no means do Blakeists nearly always agree with each other, or differ only
on matters that can be resolved in dialogue. A consideration of critical methodology as such has been too long
neglected in Blake studies; perhaps space can be found in the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> someday for
an exploratory discussion.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>