<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.1.essick</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">G. E. Bentley, Jr., The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne</title>
                <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter. An Illustrated Quarterly.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Jo Ann Kottke</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
	<pb id="p06-26" n="26"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-1-0006">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne.</hi> Catalogue by G.
E. Bentley, Jr. Introduction by Charles Ryskamp. New York: Pierpont Morgan Library, 1971. Pp. 65 + 30 plates.
$10 paperback.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n66" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>Although <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne</hi> was issued in
conjunction with the exhibition of Mrs. Thorne’s collection held at the Pierpont Morgan Library from 19
November 1971 to 22 January 1972, it is not an exhibition catalogue. Rather, Bentley’s work is the
definitive catalogue of one of the last three great Blake collections in private hands. As such, this
handsomely produced volume goes far beyond the commemorative function of the usual exhibition handbook both in
the amount of detailed information it provides and in its lasting importance to Blake scholarship.</p>
                    <p>Bentley’s description of Mrs. Thorne’s ten illuminated books, five of which are
color printed, and her copy of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> form the heart of the
catalogue. The format is more convenient than that used in the Keynes and Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi>
because the information is arranged under marginal headings (“Paper Sizes,” “Numbering,” “Binding,” etc.)
rather than lumped together in paragraph-length notes. The bibliographic details provided for each book
frequently add to the information in the <hi rend="i">Census.</hi> For example, Keynes and Wolf state only the
number of pages with a watermark, whereas Bentley lists each page where it occurs. Further, Bentley has paid
more attention to offsetting, stab holes, and other keys to binding history. This may appear to some as only
so much useless trivia, but it can be crucially important to someone investigating the original sequence of
plates and whether or not the present arrangement corresponds to Blake’s intended ordering of his work. I
have not been able to check Bentley’s entries against Mrs. Thorne’s copies themselves, but I suspect that
the enrichment of details has brought with it an increase in accuracy. Only the following comments seem called
for.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 19 There Is No Natural Religion</hi>, title-page. Bentley’s
statement that “in no copy is the author, printer, place, or date supplied” is potentially misleading. This is
true of the title-page, under which heading this sentence appears, but it is of course not true of the whole
book. As the first reproduction in the catalogue reveals, Blake inscribed in reverse “The Author &amp; Printer
W Blake” on the frontispiece to the first series of <hi rend="i">There Is No Natural Religion.</hi> Bentley
considers the reverse lettering an error, stating that Blake “forgot to etch it reversed to make it print
straight” (p. 20) while experimenting with his new technique of relief etching. It seems unlikely that Blake
would have made this kind of mistake. Although his new mode of printing no doubt offered some unique
difficulties, Blake had been long familiar with intaglio etching and engraving where writing in reverse on the
plate, or employing some process for transferring writing from paper to plate in a way that reverses its
direction, is no less necessary than in relief work. One should at least consider the possibility that Blake
had a purpose for reverse lettering on his first frontispiece, just as he did years later in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> However, the fact that the inscription is very faintly printed, and in some copies
partly colored over, suggests that Bentley may be right, and further that Blake tried to minimize the
consequences of his error.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 21</hi> watermark. Bentley states that “no copy of 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> is watermarked,” but the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> records three different watermarks in the
Morgan proofs (copy a), in copy F, and in copies N and O. In her facsimile edition of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>,
Nancy Bogen confirms the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> readings.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 21</hi> variants. “In pl. 3, the men at the right . . . ” should
read “In pl. 3, the men at the left . . . .”</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 22 The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, title-page. In his
transcriptions of titles, Bentley consistently makes no distinction between vertical and slanted letters,
except in this case, where the decorative letters of “<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>,” are transcribed as italics.
It is practically impossible to represent accurately an etched title with type, but it seems possible to
indicate slanted letters in Blake’s titles without getting into too many difficulties. For example, THE |
<hi rend="i">BOOK</hi> | <hi rend="i">of</hi> | THEL is a little closer to the original than Bentley’s THE |
BOOK | of | THEL. “<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>” presents special problems, and only a reproduction can give a
sense of the original. <note id="n66">
                            <hi rend="i">Robert N. Essick, Assistant Professor of English at California State
University, Northridge, is Review Editor for</hi> Blake Studies. <hi rend="i">He is the author of</hi> A
Finding List of Reproductions of Blake’s Art, <hi rend="i">which appeared as</hi> Blake Newsletter 17-18;
<hi rend="i">co-author of</hi> William Blake: Book Illustrator; <hi rend="i">and editor of a forthcoming
volume of reprinted articles on Blake’s art.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p06-27" n="27"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 24</hi> variants. Bentley writes that “ordinarily” the top of the
frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> is “open sky” and not “colored like the
mouth of a cave” as it is in the Thorne copy. In all copies I have examined (A, C, E, G, L, P—6 of the 16
recorded in the <hi rend="i">Census</hi>) the top of the cave, and the vegetation hanging from it, appear to
have been printed from the copper-plate itself. Although in some cases the top of the cave is not emphasized
with strong coloring, in no copy examined is it painted over to indicate sky.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 28 Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, title-page. Bentley
records a period after the “W” of “W Blake” on the title-pages to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and to 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> in the Thorne copy. These periods are not found in any of the eight copies of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence &amp; Experience</hi> I have examined (three originals, the rest through reproductions). It
seems unlikely that these periods ever appeared on the copper-plate, but Bentley does not record them as a
variant unique to the Thorne copy. Like Blake’s etched letters, his punctuation in the illuminated books
presents special problems for the descriptive bibliographer since it is often difficult to tell the difference
between a punctuation mark and an element of the coloring or design. I suspect that any attempt to weed out
all the commas from the vegetation and record every variant splash of color that might be punctuation would be
a frightfully complicated task, and the sheer number and rendomness of variants discovered would militate
against their significance. These are good reasons for not recording punctuation variants, but if they are
part of the rationale for Bentley’s bibliographic procedures they should be pointed out as such. Otherwise,
users of the work might waste time fussing over matters with which the catalogue is not concerned.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 35 For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, title-page.
Bentley’s statement that “no copy gives author, printer, publisher, place, or date” may mislead some
readers. As with the similar statement about <hi rend="i">No Natural Religion</hi> (noted above), this is true
of the title-page only, for in <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> at least some of this information
appears on sixteen other plates in the book.</p>
                    <p>The remainder of the catalogue is devoted to descriptions of manuscript materials
(including the “Pickering Manuscript,” the only long fair copy of Blake’s poems extant), Mrs. Thorne’s
three Blake watercolors, and fourteen printed or engraved works ranging from <hi rend="i">A Descriptive
Catalogue</hi> of 1809 to an impression of “The Man Sweeping the Interpreter’s Parlor.” I have not been able
to check Bentley’s transcriptions of printed title-pages against Mrs. Thorne’s own copies, but a
comparison with other copies has turned up a number of discrepancies. These may indicate that Mrs. Thorne owns
an astonishing number of variant issues, but none of her copies are indicated as such in the catalogue. Many
of these possible errors listed below are of course the most minute of particulars, but Bentley’s catalogue
commands the kind of authority to make their recording here worthwhile.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 37 A Descriptive Catalogue.</hi> There is a comma after “Soho” in
the Huntington Library copy and in the reproduction of the title-page in Keynes’ 
<hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> (1921), verso of p. 85.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 41 Tragedies of Aeschylus.</hi> There is a period after “TRANSLATED”
in the Huntington copy.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 56</hi> Gay’s <hi rend="i">Fables.</hi> In four copies examined,
the “F” of “FABLES,” the “<hi rend="i">J</hi>” of “<hi rend="i">John</hi>,” and the “<hi rend="i">G</hi>” of
“<hi rend="i">GAY</hi>” are a few millimeters larger than the other letters in these words. The “ol” of “Vol.”
is in small capitals. There is no period after “1793” in either volume and none after “Piccadilly” in the
second volume. There is a period after “Blake Mr” in the subscription list.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 57</hi> Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> In nineteen
copies examined, the Latin inscription is printed in italics.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 58</hi> Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). In ten copies
examined, the “E” of “Esq.” is an italic capital and the “sq” is in small italic capitals. I was not able to
check the transcription of Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Letter . . . for Raising the Naval Pillar</hi> also on
this page of the catalogue.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 60</hi> Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> In five copies examined,
“William Blake” is in italics (capitalization as recorded by Bentley).</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 61</hi> Chaucer’s <hi rend="i">Prologue.</hi> In the three copies
examined and in the reproduction in Keynes’ <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> (1921), p. 210, all but the “C”
of “Colnaghi’s” is in small capitals. A period appears after the “M” in the date rather than after the
“D.”</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Page 62</hi> Dante illustrations. In the Huntington copy and the
reproduction in Keynes’ <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> (1921), p. 182, there is no period after “2.” There
is a period after the Roman numeral in “Canto xxii. line 70,” not a comma as Bentley records for the Thorne
copy.</p>
                    <p>Other sections of the volume contain Mr. Ryskamp’s introduction, a brief essay on
“The Great Collections of Blake’s Books” followed by a list of important collectors past and present, and a
concluding selection from Blake’s writings. This last part is clearly directed at the general reader, but
even the informed Blakean should find much to value in the list of collectors where Bentley records the copies
of the illuminated books, with their <hi rend="i">Census</hi> designations, owned by the collectors. Many of
the copies now owned by Mr. Paul Mellon were acquired after the publication of the <hi rend="i">Census</hi>,
and thus their recording here can help in updating the work of Keynes and Wolf. The thirty high-quality
monochrome plates were chosen with care in order to illustrate aspects of Blake’s art unique to the Thorne
collection and some of the variants listed in the catalogue. After seeing the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings
reproduced over and over again, one is pleased to come upon plates which open up some new vistas. Of
particular interest are the two sets of the same page from different copies of an illuminated book,
<pb id="p06-28" n="28"/>
one color printed and the other water colored. Some of the differences between the two coloring methods are
revealed by these comparisons, although monochrome reproductions, and even most color reproductions, never do
justice to the richness of color printing. Unfortunately, these important illustrations were published too
late to be included in my <hi rend="i">Finding List</hi> of Blake reproductions, <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 5 (Summer and Fall, 1971).</p>
                    <p>Bentley has written an excellent catalogue, setting a high standard for future
bibliographies of important collections. This book is a paper-back, but the value of its contents and the
quality of the sewn binding, paper, and illustrations justify the price. A good deal of space in this review
has been devoted to pointing out probable errors, but to my mind these do not seriously hamper the great
usefulness of Bentley’s work. It has already become an essential part of any Blake library.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>