<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.2.lister</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Two Blake Drawings and a Letter from Samuel Palmer</title>
                <author n="Lister">Raymond Lister</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Marta Field</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-2-0003">
                <pb id="p06-53" n="53"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">TWO BLAKE DRAWINGS AND A LETTER FROM SAMUEL PALMER</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Raymond <name>Lister</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n41" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>In the Department of Prints and Drawings at the British Museum are two sketches by
Blake, one on either side of the same piece of paper, of “Isaiah foretelling the Crucifixion” [illus. 1 and
2]. They are thought to have been made about 1821, measure 4 3/4 by 3 inches, and came from the collection of
Samuel Palmer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">1</ref> The two sketches are
two stages in the development of the composition, the second, more detailed sketch being inscribed in
Palmer’s hand: “The ‘First Lines’, on the preservation of which Mr Blake used so often to insist, are on
the other side.” 
                        <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Pencil
Drawings</hi>, 2nd series, (London: Nonesuch Press, 1956), pl. 39.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The prophet is shown seated, with his left hand on an open scroll, and his right hand
raised above his head. The background details of the second sketch show, from left to right, the Crucifixion,
the Holy Ghost as a dove, and the Ascension. The sketches were obviously preliminary studies for a third,
almost identical, drawing on a wood block, also in the British Museum, which depicts “Isaiah foretelling the
destruction of Jerusalem.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">2</ref>
                        <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Drawings of William Blake 92 Pencil
Studies</hi> (New York: Dover Publications, 1970), pl. 83.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Accompanying the sketches is a fragment of a letter from Samuel Palmer to an unknown
addressee. It is undated, but from the handwriting and signature, <note id="n41">
                            <hi rend="i">Raymond Lister is President of the Royal Society of Miniature
Painters, Sculptors and Cravers, President of the Private Libraries Association, and Honorary Senior Member of
Wolfson College, Cambridge. He is the author of</hi> Edward Calvert <hi rend="i">(1962)</hi>, William Blake,
An Introduction <hi rend="i">(1968)</hi>, Samuel Palmer and His Etchings <hi rend="i">(1969)</hi>, British
Romantic Art <hi rend="i">(1973), and many other books. He is currently editing Samuel Palmer’s letters for
Clarendon Press, Oxford, and writing Palmer’s biography for Faber and Faber.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-54" n="54"/>
I would roughly assign it to about 1849; and from the allusion to the spring in the last paragraph, it would
appear to have been written during the autumn, or perhaps during the winter.</p>
					<q>
Allow me to contribute to your Album 2 small and faint—but undoubtedly genuine Blakes.<lb/>
By attaching a thin piece of paper at one side, they can both be visible on turning over—The fainter is a
design perhaps from the Pilgrim’s Progress<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">3</ref>—the first inventive lines—from which he was always most careful not to depart. But
finding that it was the <hi rend="i">right</hi> hand which ought to have been elevated he has traced the lines
through at the window and gone on a little, intending then to transfer the second to another paper for
completion which he probably did. The state in which Blakes drawings and those of other inventors are most
interesting to myself are either the finished state or that in which the first thought is just breathed upon
the paper—of the latter—the faint side of the enclosed is a fair specimen. Would that I had one, only one
specimen of his finished work—but I cannot send you such, as I never possessed 
it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">4</ref>
                        <lb/>
How long it is since we have met! You must take Time by the forelock if we live till the spring, and come and
see what care has been taken of those excellently contrived anti-dust-hangings which you made for my
study shelves. They remind daily of your kindness.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
Yrs ever truly<lb/>
                        <lb/>
S. Palmer— 
                        <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Palmer is wrong here. Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> designs were made about 1824. There were twenty-nine of them and they are
reproduced in color in <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, introduction by Geoffrey Keynes (New York:
Spiral Press, 1941).</note>
                        <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Palmer did, in fact, own Blake’s tempera picture,
“The spiritual form of Pitt, guiding Behemoth,” now in the Tate Gallery, London. Palmer refers to this in a
letter to George Gurney, written in October 1880 (Victoria and Albert Museum, London). It is, of course,
possible that the tempera did not come into Palmer’s possession until after the letter in the British Museum
was written. Cf. Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Complete Catalogue of the Works in the Tate
Gallery</hi> (London: Tate Gallery, 1971), pp. 56-57.</note>
					</q>
                    <p>One of the most interesting aspects of the letter is the light it throws on Blake’s
method of work—his inability or unwillingness to depart from “the first inventive lines.” This no doubt
explains much of the vitality and immediacy of his work. In the work of many painters, the difference between
the original conception and the finished composition is vast. That is why, for example, Constable’s sketches
and drawings are so often more moving than his canvases. And it is one reason why Blake is as powerful in his
finished works as in his initial inspirations.</p>
					<figure n="BUT772.1.1v.PD" rend="file" width="683" height="1000">
						<figTranscr/>
					</figure>
                    <figure n="BUT772.1.1r.PD" rend="file" width="717" height="1000">
						<figTranscr>The “First Lines” on the preservation of which Mr. Blake used 
so often to insist are on the other side.</figTranscr>
						<head>1 &amp; 2 Two sketches, recto and verso, of “Isaiah foretelling the
Crucifixion,” by Blake, c. 1821.</head>
						<figDesc>4 ¾ × 3 inches. Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British
Museum.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>