<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.2.bentley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">A New Blake Engraving in Lavater’s Physiognomy</title>
                <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Marta Field</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-2-0003">
                <pb id="p06-48" n="48"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">A “NEW” BLAKE ENGRAVING IN LAVATER’S 
<hi rend="i">PHYSIOGNOMY</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n38" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>Increasing interest in William Blake has been accompanied by, perhaps has caused, the
discovery of a number of previously unknown engravings signed “Blake”. Six were found in <hi rend="i">The
Seaman’s Recorder</hi> (1824-27),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">1</ref>
two more in James Earle’s <hi rend="i">Practical Observations on the Operation for the Stone</hi> (1793,
1796, 1803),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">2</ref> and yet another is in
Henry Emlyn’s <hi rend="i">Proposition for a New Order in Architecture</hi> (1781, 1784).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">3</ref> All these are in recently noticed and obscure
books. Doubtless more such backwater-books will be found with plates by the poet in them. 
                        <note id="n14">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> “Byron, Shelley, Wordsworth, Blake, and <hi rend="i">The
Seaman’s Recorder</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 9 (1970), 21-36. Sir Geoffrey Keynes
“defend[s] his [Blake’s] reputation against . . . [this] mistaken attribution” in “Blake’s Engravings for
Gay’s <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 21 (1972), 60. I agree that the “Blake”
whose name appears on the <hi rend="i">Seaman’s Recorder</hi> plates often exhibited lamentable
craftsmanship there. The crux of the matter appears to me to be that the poet William Blake is the only
engraver known to have been signing “Blake” to plates at this time—the writing-engraver William Staden Blake
(fl. 1770-1817) is not known to have worked so late (see “A Collection of Prosaic William Blakes,” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n. s. 12 [1965], 172-78).</note>
                        <note id="n15">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Leslie F. Chard, “Two ‘New’ Blake Engravings,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> (1973). This and the next essay were generously shown me by their authors in
draft.</note>
                        <note id="n16">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> William A. Gibson and Thomas L. Minnick, “William Blake and
Henry Emlyn’s <hi rend="i">Proposition for a New Order in Architecture</hi>: A New Plate,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 21 (Summer 1972), 13-17.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Blake made engravings for some seventy-seven books, and all except those named above
are well known and have repeatedly been pored over by scholars for their Blake significance. However, in one
of them, John Caspar Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, there has lurked, undetected, a
plate not only perfectly characteristic of Blake in form but signed, minutely but legibly, “<hi rend="i">Blake
Sc</hi>” [illus. 1]. The reason why the design has been so long overlooked is quite simple: the signature is
not in the normal place, below the design, but is in a gap in the foliage near the foot of the right-hand old
man, and it is so small (c. 0.4 × 0.05 cm.) that it is very difficult to find and almost impossible 
<note id="n38">
                            <hi rend="i">G. E. Bentley, Jr., recently edited and annotated</hi> A Handlist of
Works by William Blake in the Department of Prints &amp; Drawings of the British Museum <hi rend="i">for
the</hi> Newsletter. <hi rend="i">He is the editor of Blake’s</hi> Vala or The Four Zoas <hi rend="i">(1963)
and of Blake’s</hi> Tiriel <hi rend="i">(1967); compiler of</hi> The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K.
Thorne <hi rend="i">(1971) and, with Martin K. Nurmi, of</hi> A Blake Bibliography <hi rend="i">(1964); author
of</hi> The Early Engravings of Flaxman’s Classical Designs <hi rend="i">(1964) and of</hi> Blake Records
<hi rend="i">(1969).</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-49" n="49"/>
to read confidently without a magnifying glass. Once it has been located,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">4</ref> however, its presence, details, and significance are
unmistakable. 
                        <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">4</hi> It was in a list of the Blake holdings of the Osler
Library, McGill University, generously sent to me by Miss Ellen B. Wells, Acting Osler Librarian.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>There can, I think, be no doubt that this “<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>” plate was engraved
by the poet, for not only did he sign other plates in the same volume (Vol. I, pp. 159, 206, 225) which have
never been challenged, but the design itself seems to me to be characteristically Blakean. It is a small
tail-piece (platemark: 8.5 × 6.1 cm.) of a decorative rather than a demonstrative nature, representing two
old men with flowing white beards and long gowns apparently planting a grove of some fourteen young trees; the
man on the left seems to be putting a tree in the ground, the man on the right, who is bald, is watering
another tree with a large watering can, and in the foreground are a rake and a shovel on the ground. Behind
the little grove of trees is an open space which may be water, and in the distance among low hills and trees
are buildings, one of which may have a crenellated tower.</p>
                    <p>In Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> there are two kinds of plates, generally,
one exemplifying Lavater’s principles of physiognomy, often copied from famous painters such as Rubens and
Raphael, and the other not directly related to the text, ordinarily anonymous as to designer, and decorative.
Blake’s plate is in the second category,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">5</ref> and I think it may have been designed as well as engraved by him. The patriarchal old men
are perfectly familiar from other Blake designs such as those for <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>
titlepage (?1788), <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (?1789), “The Voice of the Ancient Bard” from <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence</hi>
                        <figure n="BB481.1.1.COM" rend="file" width="800" height="579">
                            <head>1 The “new” Blake engraving from Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi>,
signed, near the right-hand man’s foot, “<hi rend="i">Blake Sc</hi>”.</head>
                            <figDesc>This is an enlarged reproduction; the true dimensions are 8.5 × 6.1 cm.
Reproduced by the permission of the University of California, Berkeley.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
(1789), <hi rend="i">For Children</hi> (1793) pl. “11,” “13,” “15,” “The Little Vagabond,” “London,” and “To
Tirzah” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (1794), and “Joseph of Arimathea Preaching” (1794). Even
the young trees are not unlike those in the background of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> designs and
elsewhere. If the form is not all Blake’s, he may yet have adapted a design by another artist into one
virtually his own, as Sir Geoffrey Keynes has shown us<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">6</ref> he did with that for “The Shepherd and the Philosopher” in Gay’s 
<hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793). 
                        <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">5</hi> It may be related somehow to the text on the same
page, in which Lavater says his Work “contains not a complete Treatise, but merely Fragments of Physiognomy,”
which perhaps need to be watered and nurtured.</note>
                        <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">6</hi> “Blake’s Engravings for Gay’s Fables.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> was originally issued in forty-one folio
parts at irregular intervals. The “new” plate appeared in Part V, issued in July 1788, and was described on
its cover as “Aged Figures, Gardening”. The whole work was issued in three-volumes-bound-in-five, and the
“new” Blake plate is in Volume I (1789), page 127. The three-volumes-in-five were published again in 1810.</p>
                    <p>Whether or not the plate was designed by Blake, it is one of the earliest examples
known of the patriarchal figure who presides over his work. The design is either one of the first examples of,
or a stimulus for, what seems now a characteristically Blakean type.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>