<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.2.antippas</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., ed., The Romantics on Milton</title>
                <author n="Antippas">Andy P. Antippas</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Marta Field</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <pb id="p06-55" n="55"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-2-0004">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. <hi rend="i">The Romantics on Milton:
Formal Essays and Critical Asides</hi> [Blake, Wordsworth, Coleridge, Lamb, Landor, Hazlitt, Hunt, DeQuincey,
Byron, Shelley, and Keats]. Cleveland: The Press of Case Western Reserve University, 1970. Pp. 594.
$15.00</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Andy P. <name>Antippas</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n42" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>Miltonists, Romanticists, and historians of criticism must be grateful for the material
plentifully garnered by Mr. Wittreich. He has harvested the references and allusions to Milton from the
essays, journals, diaries, notebooks, marginalia, letters, reported conversations, and poems of the major
writers of the Romantic period, and he has thus provided us with a <hi rend="i">vade mecum</hi> into the
hearts and minds of those most perspicacious readers, and, not surprisingly, with a considerable amount of
excellent reading.</p>
                    <p>Wittreich does not pretend to offer complete bibliographical apparatus, but,
nonetheless, the cross-referenced notes at the end of every chapter contain everything of importance
concerning the influence of Milton on the Romantics. The slighter remarks of Lamb, Landor, Hazlitt, Hunt, and
DeQuincey and a brief description of Coleridge’s lectures are listed in two appendices. The Coleridge
section will no doubt be expanded when a new edition of this volume is called for and new material is made
generally available. An additional appendix will serve to list any oversights such as the Milton references in
<hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of William Wordsworth</hi>, ed. de Selincourt, I, 35; De-Quincey, 
<hi rend="i">Collected Writings</hi>, ed. Masson, V, 211; and <hi rend="i">The Letters of John Keats</hi>, ed.
Rollins, I, 397.</p>
                    <p>Wittreich intelligently surmounts the dangers of Bartlettizing and avoids the atomism
and gnomic isolation of remarks by constantly quoting a sufficient amount of material to preserve the
coherence and the context of each observation. This generous sampling itself assists in making the case
Wittreich presents in his valuable introductory essay: namely, that the Romantics “are the unacknowledged
architects of Milton criticism as we know it today” (p. ix), and that somehow, the pro-Miltonists and con were
a party to either ignoring the issues raised by the Romantic critics or imperfectly labeling Romantic
commentary as too narrowly concerned with verse techniques or too radically Satanizing.</p>
                    <p>Additionally, the collection makes it clearer that Milton, more than Shakespeare, was
the fulcrum and the omphalos of the critical theorizing of the period and especially of resolving the problem
of the role and function of the poet. The Romantics decidedly exercised Wellek’s “perspectivism” which
“tries to see the object from all possible sides and is convinced that there <hi rend="i">is</hi> an object.”
As if in rejoinder to Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, the Romantics numbered the streaks on the tulip and
considered Milton as polemicist, Puritan, prophet, mythopoeicist, and poet; always before them, however, was
the object of their deliberations, Milton the Man. It is more than chronologically appropriate, therefore,
that the Blake selections begin the anthology.</p>
                    <p>In his literal-imaginativist way, Blake does apotheosize Milton the Man, and it is a
testimony to the strength of character of Case Western Reserve Press that they printed the whole of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> from the Keynes edition. In its new setting, jostled by similar if more
parochially-formed expressions, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> gains new significance and becomes at once more
singular yet more conventional. Blake’s other mode of criticism, his ninety-odd illustrations of Milton’s
poems, is an acknowledged omission (note 72, p. 21; note 22, p. 101). The cost would no doubt have been
prohibitive and we can get by, at least for the time being, with Marcia R. Pointon’s numerous reproductions
and interesting commentary in <hi rend="i">Milton and English Art.</hi> All in all, Wittreich has demonstrated
that the Romantics were Milton’s fittest audience and that Blake was front row center. <note id="n42">
                            <hi rend="i">Andy P. Antippas, Assistant Professor of English at Tulane
University, has published articles on Romantic and Victorian poets. He is presently co-editing a volume of
essays on the Gothic novel.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>