<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.2.butlin</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">A Minute Particular Particularized: Blake’s Second Set of Illustrations
to Paradise Lost</title>
                <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Marta Field</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <pb id="p06-44" n="44"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-2-0003">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Notes</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">A “MINUTE PARTICULAR” PARTICULARIZED: BLAKE’S SECOND SET OF
ILLUSTRATIONS TO <hi rend="i">PARADISE LOST</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>In his otherwise admirable article on Blake’s illustrations to Milton, published in
the collection of essays on <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> and <hi rend="i">Samson Agonistes</hi> in
honor of John S. Diekhoff,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Joseph
Anthony Wittreich challenges my statement in an earlier issue of the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> that
the second set of illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, painted for Thomas Butts in 1808,
originally consisted of twelve watercolors, thus following the earlier, smaller series done in 1807 for the
Rev. Joseph Thomas and now in the Huntington Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> Although he now accepts that “The Judgment of Adam and Eve” in the Houghton Library can be
added to the nine designs in the Boston Museum, I should perhaps spell out the main arguments for also
including “Satan arousing the Rebel Angels” in the Victoria and Albert Museum and the larger version of
“Satan, Sin and Death” in the Huntington Library, though most of these arguments can in fact be deduced from
the available printed sources. 
                        <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., “William Blake:
Illustrator-Interpreter of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>” in <hi rend="i">Calm of Mind: Tercentenary
essays on</hi> Paradise Regained <hi rend="i">and</hi> Samson Agonistes <hi rend="i">in Honor of John S.
Diekhoff</hi>, ed. Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. (Cleveland and London: Press of Case Western Reserve Univ.,
1971), pp. 93-132.</note>
                        <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Newsletter</hi>, 3 (1969), 57.
For Thomas’ ownership of the 1807 series see Leslie Parris, “William Blake’s Mr. Thomas” in 
<hi rend="i">The Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 5 December 1968, p. 1390.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Wittreich’s first objection is that the two last-named designs are larger than the
Boston watercolors. I have examined and measured all the watercolors (that in the Houghton Library
unfortunately only in its mount) and the dimensions are as follows (inches first, followed by centimeters in
parentheses):
<table rows="12" cols="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>i</cell>
                                <cell>“Satan arousing the Rebel Angels” 20 3/8 × 15 1/2 (51.8 × 39.3)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>ii</cell>
                                <cell>“Satan, Sin and Death” 19 1/2 × 15 7/8 (49.5 × 40.3)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>iii</cell>
                                <cell>“Christ offers to redeem Man” 19 1/2 × 15 1/2 (49.6 × 39.3)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>iv</cell>
                                <cell>“Satan watching the Endearments of Adam and Eve” 20 × 15 1/16 (50.7 ×
38.2)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>v</cell>
                                <cell>“Adam and Eve asleep” 19 3/8 × 15 5/16 (49.2 × 38.8)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>vi</cell>
                                <cell>“Raphael warns Adam and Eve” 19 9/16 × 15 5/8 (49.7 × 39.7)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>vii</cell>
                                <cell>“The Rout of the Rebel Angels” 19 5/16 × 15 1/16 (49.1 × 38.2)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>viii</cell>
                                <cell>“The Creation of Eve” 19 11/16 × 15 3/4 (49.9 × 40)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>ix</cell>
                                <cell>“The Temptation and Fall of Eve” 19 5/8 × 15 1/4 (49.7 × 38.7)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>x</cell>
                                <cell>“The Judgment of Adam and Eve” 19 9/16 × 15 3/8 (49.6 × 39) (sight
measurements only; possibly larger)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>xi</cell>
                                <cell>“Michael foretelling the Crucifixion” 19 3/4 × 15 (50.1 × 38.1)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>xii</cell>
                                <cell>“The Expulsion of Adam and Eve” 19 11/16 × 15 1/4 (50 × 38.8)</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
From this it will be seen that “Satan, Sin and Death” is in no way exceptional in size, while the extra height
of “Satan arousing the Rebel Angels” represents no greater variation than that between other works in the
series.</p>
                    <p>Wittreich’s second argument is that the two designs excluded by him are conventional
in subject matter. Both Blake and Thomas Butts might well have contradicted this expression of personal
opinion. In fact the latter might well have been annoyed had Blake omitted two of the subjects that one might
most reasonably expect to find included in a series of illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (he
already had a color print of another famous scene from the poem, “The House of Death” now in the Tate
Gallery). The long tradition of eighteenth-century representations of “Satan, Sin and Death,” to say nothing
of Burke’s use of this subject as the ideal exemplar of the Sublime, is also an argument in favor of its
inclusion in any series. Conventional though they may be, Blake did duplicate these subjects for some reason
or other: the completion of Butts’ set seems the most obvious.</p>
                    <p>Thirdly, Wittreich argues from the premise that “ ‘Satan calling [up] his Legions’
was, in Blake’s words, ‘painted at intervals’ as an experiment Picture.’ ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> This quotation from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi> refers however to the last of the tempera paintings included in his exhibition of 1809, not to
one of the watercolors, each of which was qualified as “A Drawing.” The tempera, which belonged to Samuel
Palmer, is now, like the watercolor, in the Victoria and Albert Museum, while the “more perfect Picture,
afterward executed for a Lady of high rank,” who was in fact Lady Egremont, is still at Petworth. 
                        <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Wittreich, p. 100. See Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> 1809, p. 54 no. ix, reprinted in Keynes, <hi rend="i">Complete Writings of
William Blake</hi>, 1957 and subsequent editions, p. 582.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>All twelve of the larger watercolors came from the Butts collection, though the nine at
Boston left that collection at a different time from the other three, being sold by Thomas Butts, Jr., at
Foster’s on 29 June 1853, lot 139, when they were bought by J. C. Strange; like other works from Strange’s
collection they were with Quaritch’s in the 1880’s, figuring in catalogues in 1883 and 1887, and they were
sold by Quaritch’s to the Boston Museum in 1890. The other three watercolors were all included in List 3
(“Works of Unascertained Method”) of the catalogue of Blake’s works by William Rossetti included in the
second volume of the first, 1863 edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> All three
were <note id="n0">
                            <hi rend="i">Martin Butlin is Keeper of the British Collection at the Tate
Gallery, London, and a specialist on the work of Blake and J. M. W. Turner. He is the author of</hi> William
Blake: A Complete Catalogue of the Works in the Tate Gallery, <hi rend="i">and he is compiling a complete
catalogue of Blake’s paintings, watercolors, and drawings.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-45" n="45"/>
starred as “more probably coloured” and described as being in the collection of “Mr. Fuller, from Mr.
Butts.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> A number of Apocalyptic
subjects from the series of illustrations to the Bible painted in watercolor for Thomas Butts between 1800 and
1805, similarly described as belonging to “Mr. Fuller, from Mr. Butts,” are listed by Rossetti<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> with quotations from an unspecified
“Sale-catalogue” which unfortunately cannot be traced, and all, together with the three <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi> watercolors, passed to H. A. J. Munro and were sold from his collection at Christie’s on 24 April
1868. The full details for the three <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs are as follows:
<table rows="4" cols="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>i</cell>
                                <cell>“Satan arousing the Rebel Angels.” Listed by Rossetti, no. 17, as 
“ ‘Awake, arise, or be for ever fallen.’ ” Munro sale 1868, lot 501, under the same title, bought by
Colnaghi, sold 1869 to the Victoria and Albert Museum.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>ii</cell>
                                <cell>“Satan, Sin and Death.” Listed by Rossetti, no. 18, as “ ‘O Father,
what extends thy hand, she cried, Against thy only son?’ (Satan, Sin, and Death, from ‘Paradise
Lost’).”</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Munro sale 1868, lot 500, as “ ‘O Father! what intends thy hand,’ ”
etc., bought by “Cuff”; lent to the Burlington Fine Arts Club Blake exhibition of 1876 by R. P. Cuffe; sold
anonymously by “Chas. De C. Cuff” (see annotated catalogue at Christie’s) at Christie’s on 19 July 1907,
lot 46, bought by F. T. Sabin; it was with Rosenbach’s by 1911, and was sold in 1916 to Henry E. Huntington.
An inscription on the back confirms that this was “drawn for Mr. Butts from whom it passed to Mr.
Fuller.”</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>x</cell>
                                <cell>“The Judgment of Adam and Eve.” Listed by Rossetti, no. 16, as “ ‘So
judged He man.’ - (Paradise Lost).” Munro sale 1868, lot 502, as “ ‘So judged he man, both judge and
Saviour sent,’ ” bought by Kibble; passed, with other Blakes from Kibble, to Marsden J. Perry; sold 1908 to
Walter A. White; presented 1966 by John H. White and Harold T. White to the Houghton Library.</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Gilchrist (1863), II, 255, nos. 16, 17 and 18. In
Rossetti’s own notes to his lists, now in the Houghton Library (see <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 2
[1968], 39-40, and 3 [1969], 48-51), he mistakenly associates “The Judgment of Adam and Eve” with the earlier
version of the subject in the 1807 set, then in the possession of Alfred Aspland, which he had not included in
his 1863 lists. In the revised lists printed in the 1880 edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi>,
which included the Aspland set, Rossetti omitted all three <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> watercolors from
his List 3, inserting “Satan at the Gate of Hell, guarded by Sin and Death” into his main List 1 (of “Works in
Colour”) as no. 234 with the note: “May presumably have belonged at first to the set of Nine Designs from
‘Paradise Lost’, No. 90 [the Butts-Boston set].” He also inserted as no. 233 a “Satan calling up his
Legions.” This he described as a tempera, different in composition from his no. 51 (the Palmer-V. &amp; A.
version), but as he also lists the Petworth tempera as no. 52, his no. 233 was in fact probably the V. &amp;
A. watercolor; in many ways his 1880 lists, though fuller, are more confused than those of 1863.</note>
                        <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Gilchrist (1863), II, 255, nos. 174-77.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>While Butts’ other sets of illustrations to Milton have remained intact, it is not
impossible that his son, in his dispersal of the collection, should have broken up the <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi> illustrations into two groups, selling the majority in 1853 and the other three at the other,
untraced sale at which they were bought by Fuller. The admittedly much larger group of illustrations to the
Bible was sold off at a number of different times.</p>
                    <p>A further, though contradictory, line of inquiry is provided by the form in which the
watercolors are signed and dated. All of those at Boston with the exception of no. xi, “Michael fore-telling
the Crucifixion,” which is unsigned, are inscribed “WBlake 1808.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Nos. i, “Satan arousing the Rebel Angels,” and x, “The Judgment of Adam and
Eve,” are inscribed in precisely the same way. The exception is no. ii, “Satan, Sin and Death,” which bears
Blake’s standard “WB inv” monogram and no date. It is tempting, but probably unreliable, to use the form of
Blake’s signature as an argument for dating his works. For instance, one set of the large color prints of
1795 was inscribed with the “WB inv” monogram, though perhaps not until they were sold to Butts in 1805. Those
of the Biblical temperas and watercolors that were signed and dated between 1799 and 1805 were similarly
inscribed, as was the first, Rev. Joseph Thomas’ set of illustrations to <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> of c. 1801,
now in the Huntington Library. Four isolated Biblical watercolors of 1806 and 1809 are, on the other hand,
signed more fully.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> The first set of
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs also represent a transition, some being signed “WB,” without “inv,”
others “WBlake,” in either case with or without the date “1807.” Later works, such as the Rev. Joseph
Thomas’ set of illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity</hi> of 1809
(Whitworth Institute, Manchester), those to <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>
(Pierpont Morgan Library, New York) and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> (Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge),
both of which are watermarked “M &amp; J LAY 1816” (evidence for their date omitted by Wittreich in his
essay<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>), and the late temperas at the
Tate Gallery of “The Ghost of a Flea,”
<pb id="p06-46" n="46"/>
<corr type="emend">c. 1819,</corr> and “The Body of Abel found by Adam and Eve” and “Satan
smiting Job with Sore Boils” of c. 1826, are all signed “WBlake” in full. The Dante illustrations of 1824-27,
when signed, bear a simple “WB” without “inv.” The great exception to this rule is the first, Butts set of
illustrations to the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi> in the Morgan Library, three of which are signed “WB inv”
in Blake’s standard monogram (but perhaps, as I suspect for stylistic reasons, these date from much earlier
than is usually thought, though 1805-06 is even earlier than I would otherwise have placed them). 
                        <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> No. iv, “Satan watching the Endearments of Adam and
Eve,” is in fact so inscribed twice in the lower right-hand corner; presumably Blake’s original mount
obscured the lower inscription so he repeated it immediately above. The inscription can be clearly seen in the
reproduction in Helen D. Willard, <hi rend="i">William Blake water-color drawings</hi> (Boston: Museum of Fine
Arts, 1957), which includes plates of all nine Boston designs for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> “The Assumption of the Virgin” in the Royal
Collection, Windsor Castle, is inscribed “WB. inv. [<hi rend="i">not</hi> in monogram] 1806” (repr. Geoffrey
Keynes, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Bible</hi>, 1957, p. 51, no. 174); “The Repose of
the Holy Family in Egypt” in the Metropolitan Museum, New York, and “By the Waters of Babylon” in the Fogg Art
Museum are inscribed “1806 WB inv,” again not in monogram (repr. Keynes, <hi rend="i">Illustrations</hi>, p.
31, no. 96b); and “The Whore of Babylon” in the British Museum is inscribed “WBlake inv &amp; del 1809” (repr.
Keynes, <hi rend="i">Illustrations</hi>, p. 51, no. 168).</note>
                        <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Wittreich, pp. 96-97, 125 no. 15.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Absolute consistency cannot, however, always be hoped for and, even if only two of the
three candidates match those at Boston in the form of their signatures, all three match them in style. As
compared with the earlier series the figures in the Boston watercolors are marked by a much greater degree of
finish and monumentality: their heads are larger in scale, their bodies less elongated and more firmly
modeled. Exactly the same development is found between the three other large designs and their prototypes in
the 1807 set. In particular, it is impossible, looking at the two watercolors of “Satan, Sin and Death” side
by side in the Huntington Library,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> to
imagine Blake painting the larger one before that from the 1807 set; in every way it is an improvement, in the
opposition of the two main protagonists, in the weight of the figures, and in the compactness and power of the
design as a whole. On the other hand it certainly cannot date from as late as the three illustrations to 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> done in 1822 for John Linnell, perhaps as the beginning of a complete
set.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> These are typical of Blake’s
late style in their soft modeling and subtle, broken coloring, having a grace and sensuous quality completely
different from Blake’s works in the first decade of the century, whereas “Satan, Sin and Death” is typical
of the firm modeling, restricted coloring, and wirey outlines of the middle of that decade. 
                        <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Or conveniently juxtaposed in C. H. Collins Baker
and Robert R. Wark, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of William Blake’s Drawings and Paintings in the Huntington
Library</hi> (1963), pls. 2 and 3; the rest of the 1807 set is repr. pls. 1 and 4-13.</note>
                        <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> “Satan watching the Endearments of Adam and Eve”
and “The Creation of Eve” are in the National Gallery of Victoria, Melbourne; “Michael foretelling the
Crucifixion” in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. See David Bindman, <hi rend="i">William Blake, Catalogue of
the Collection in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge</hi> (1970), pp. 44-45, the last-named repr. pl.
36.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The common-sense solution, even in the case of Blake, is sometimes the best. In 1807
Blake did twelve illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> for the Rev. Joseph Thomas. The next year he
repeated the set (with one change, replacing “Satan spying on Adam and Raphael’s Descent into Paradise” by
“Adam and Eve Sleeping”) for his most important patron Thomas Butts, as he was also to do in the case of his
illustrations to <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity.</hi>
                        <ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Of twelve designs similar in style and
dimensions, all but two dated 1808, and all traceable to the Butts collection, three have by chance become
separated from the other nine, but to disprove the obvious it needs more than an <hi rend="i">a priori</hi>
theory about Blake dropping his illustrations to the first two books of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> in
order to begin his series “with the Son’s offering of himself as Redeemer,” thus reflecting the way that he
“casts off his early Satanism as he apprehends the Christocentric character of Milton’s diffuse
epic.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
                        <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See Parris, my n. 2 above.</note>
                        <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., “A Note on Blake
and Fuseli” in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 2 (1969), 4, no. 2, and Wittreich in <hi rend="i">Calm of
Mind</hi>, p. 101.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>