<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.2.butlinnews</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Another Blake Watercolor Cleaned at Tate Gallery</title>
                <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1972</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Marta Field</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1972"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-2-0002">
            	<pb id="p06-43" n="43"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">ANOTHER BLAKE WATERCOLOR CLEANED AT THE TATE GALLERY</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <byline><hi rend="i">Report by <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name>,</docAuthor> 
Keeper of the British Collection, The Tate Gallery, London.</hi></byline>
The Tate Gallery, continuing its policy of cleaning and, where necessary, remounting and
re-framing its Blakes, has just treated the large early watercolor of “Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies
Dancing,” c. 1785-90. As can be seen from the reproduction in the second, 1971, edition of the Tate Gallery
Blake catalogue, it was badly discolored with, in addition, several localized stains. The main discoloration
was in the paper itself and this has been successfully bleached out and practically all of the stains removed,
revealing the original delicacy and translucency of Blake’s watercolor washes. In particular, the reds are
now much cooler and accord better with the exceptionally delicate blue of Titania’s dress; Oberon’s robe
is now white. Also more evident is the pentimento by which Blake changed the position of Titania’s head;
this was originally higher on the paper, making her tower over her consort. The first pair of eyes drawn by
Blake can now be seen in the middle of her forehead and the original chaplet round her hair retains its blue
coloring, whereas that in the revised position was left uncolored.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>