<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>6.3.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Martin Butlin, The Blake Collection of Mrs. William T.
Tonner; The Pickering Manuscript, facsimile published by the Morgan Library</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1972-73</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1972-73</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">06.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
              <name>Michael Davies</name>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Foster Foreman</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1972-73"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_06">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-06-3-0005">
        <pb id="p06-78" n="78"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Bulletin</hi> / Philadelphia Museum of Art. Vol. 67, no. 307
(July-September 1972). Pp. 34. $1; <hi rend="i">The Pickering Manuscript / William Blake.</hi> Introduction by
Charles Ryskamp. New York: Pierpont Morgan Library, 1972. Pp. 6 + 22. $3</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The entire July-September issue of the Philadelphia Museum’s <hi rend="i">Bulletin</hi> for
1972 is devoted to an illustrated essay by Martin Butlin: <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of Mrs. William T.
Tonner.</hi> This publication marks an event of the first importance to those interested in Blake, the gift of
eleven works from Mrs. Tonner’s estate, which as Mr. Butlin says “promotes the Museum at one bound into the
ranks of leading American Blake collections.” All the pictures are reproduced—one (the beautiful 
<hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> painted for Butts) in color, the rest in halftone along with six other pictures and one
inscription. Mr. Butlin’s commentary is both cogent and informative, so that it is not so much necessary to
review this publication as to call attention to its contents.</p>
          <p>Four other Butts pictures are included in the Tonner gift: <hi rend="i">Christ Baptizing, Mary
Magdalene Washing Christ’s Feet, Samson Subdued</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jephthah Met by his Daughter</hi>,
all watercolors. The <hi rend="i">Samson</hi> is informatively reproduced with its companion picture, 
<hi rend="i">Samson Breaking his Bonds</hi> from the collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne. There is also the
watercolor <hi rend="i">Malevolence</hi>, which gave rise to Blake’s imbroglio with Dr. Trusler and hence to
one of Blake’s most spirited defenses of his art. Perhaps the most important single picture in the
collection is the color print <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>, which Butlin considers “the most dramatic
copy” of the three known examples.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">1</ref>
The four remaining designs are the sketch for <hi rend="i">The Sacrifice of Isaac</hi>, the Flaxmanesque 
<hi rend="i">Warring Angels</hi>, the drawing of <hi rend="i">The Death of Ezekiel’s Wife</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">A Destroying Deity.</hi> The last named is perhaps the most interesting of
<pb id="p06-79" n="79"/>
the four. Butlin dates it very late (c. 1825-26), comparing the figure’s webbed wings with those in the
tempera <hi rend="i">Satan Smiting Job with Sore Boils.</hi> There is also something in the sculpture-like
massiveness of the figure which recalls some of the illustrations to the <hi rend="i">Inferno.</hi>
	<note id="n48">1 Butlin points out that for the Tate copy of this work Blake received one guinea from Thomas
Butts, giving the U. S. equivalent as about $2.50. It is only fair to Butts, however, to remember that both
the guinea and the dollar are not, alas, what they once were. In 1793, for example, Blake advertised 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> at 10<hi rend="i">s</hi> 6<hi rend="i">d</hi>; and in 1806, the year of the receipt for
<hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>, Blake sold John Flaxman a “singularly grand drawing of the Last Judgment”
for one guinea (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 575).</note></p>
          <p>Butlin’s valuable pamphlet is a kind of <hi rend="i">hors d’oeuvre</hi> which makes us all
the more anticipate the feast of his forthcoming complete catalogue of Blake’s paintings, watercolors, and
drawings. Conversely, <hi rend="i">The Pickering Manuscript</hi> is a welcome dessert, following what the 
<hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi>’s reviewer called “the definitive catalogue of one of the last three great Blake
collections in private hands”: <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne</hi> by G. E.
Bentley, Jr.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">2</ref> That catalogue was
published by the Morgan Library in conjunction with its exhibition of the Thorne collection; now we are
informed in Charles Ryskamp’s brief Introduction to <hi rend="i">The Pickering Manuscript</hi>, that Mrs.
Thorne gave the Manuscript itself to the Morgan Library at the end of 1971, thus adding even further to the
Library’s magnificent Blake collection. The fact that the entire Manuscript is here reproduced in facsimile
for the first time speaks for itself. We might, however, reiterate a point made by John E. Grant in 
<hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> 21: with the ever-growing interest in Blake, facsimiles now perform two
functions—they make material widely available, and they also reduce unnecessary wear on the originals. 
<hi rend="i">The Pickering Manuscript</hi> should serve both purposes admirably. <note id="n49">2 Robert Essick,
<hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> 21, p. 26.</note>
	<note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">Morton D. Paley is Executive Editor of the</hi>
Newsletter.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
