<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>6.3.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Inscription on Evening Amusement</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1972-73</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1972-73</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">06.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
              <name>Michael Davies</name>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Foster Foreman</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1972-73"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_06">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-06-3-0004">
        <pb id="p06-74" n="74"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">THE INSCRIPTION ON <hi rend="i">EVENING AMUSEMENT</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Geoffrey Keynes, in his book on <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The Separate
Plates</hi> (Dublin, 1956), (p. 64), reconstructs the last line on Blake’s engraving after Watteau’s 
<hi rend="i">Evening Amusement</hi> on the basis of that on the companion print of <hi rend="i">Morning
Amusement.</hi> However, the discovery of a third, untrimmed impression in red shows that in fact the wording
is slightly different. As Keynes’ transcription is not entirely accurate even in the first line, I give the
full inscription:</p>
          <p>Watteau pinx<hi rend="s">t</hi>. W. . Blake fecit / EVENING AMUSEMENT / From an Original Picture
in the Collection of M.<hi rend="s">r</hi>. A. . Maskin. / Pub.<hi rend="s">d</hi>. as the Act directs August
21. . 1782 by T. . Macklin. N.<hi rend="s">o</hi>. 39 Fleet Street.</p>
          <p>The punctuation after certain initials and in abbreviations such as “M.<hi rend="s">r</hi>.”,
which is represented here by two full-stops, is in fact more in the form of two little dashes. It is also
found in the inscription under <hi rend="i">Morning Amusement</hi> as can be seen from Keynes’ reproduction
though not from his transcription (<hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi>, p. 63). In this connection it should be
pointed out that the “s” of “sculp<hi rend="s">t</hi>” is lower case, not a capital. In addition, at least on
the copy of the print belonging to me, there is no full-stop at the end of the last line but there are two
little dashes
                        above the stop following “Tho” suggesting a slightly fuller form of the abbreviation
for Thomas, though they do not appear to take the form of an “s”: “Tho<hi rend="s">.</hi>.<hi
rend="s">.</hi>”</p>
          <p>It should be noted that the inscription on <hi rend="i">Evening Amusement</hi> gives the name of
the owner of the original painting as “Maskin” without a concluding “s”. This is in fact correct. However,
even allowing for the fact that the oval format of the engravings does not necessarily represent the shape of
the original paintings, it appears that Maskin’s paintings are not those now in the Wallace Collection. The
provenances of <hi rend="i">Les Champs Elysees</hi> and <hi rend="i">Le <corr type="emend">Rendez-vous</corr> de Chasse</hi> (as the
paintings related to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Evening Amusement</hi> and <hi rend="i">Morning Amusement</hi> are
now known) seem to exclude Maskin’s ownership, neither having left France till 1787 at the earliest (see 
<hi rend="i">Wallace Collection Catalogues: Pictures and Drawings</hi>, 1968 edition, pp. 360, 364-65). 
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">Martin Butlin is Keeper of the British Collection at the Tate
Gallery, London, and a specialist on the work of Blake and J. M. W. Turner. He is the author of</hi> William
Blake: A Complete Catalogue of the Works in the Tate Gallery, <hi rend="i">and he is compiling a complete
catalogue of Blake’s paintings, watercolors, and drawings.</hi></note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
