<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>6.3.wills</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="note">An Additional Drawing for Blake’s Bunyan Series</title>
        <author n="Wills">James T. Wills</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1972-73</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1972-73</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">06.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
              <name>Michael Davies</name>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Foster Foreman</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1972-73"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_06">
    <body>
      <pb id="p06-62" n="62"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-06-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">Notes</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <figure n="ChristianGoesForth.6.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="362">
          <head>1 “Christian Goes Forth Armed,” from Blake’s Bunyan series.</head>
          <figDesc>Copyright the Frick Collection, New York. Reproduced by permission.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p06-63" n="63"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">AN ADDITIONAL DRAWING FOR BLAKE’S BUNYAN SERIES</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>James T. <name>Wills</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>On 29 April 1862 Sotheby’s offered for sale “a series of 28 designs [by William Blake] for the
<hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, nineteen of them highly finished in colours.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> W. M. Rossetti described these twenty-eight drawings in the
list of Blake’s works he prepared for Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> in 1863. When Geoffrey
Keynes discussed the illustrations in his 1941 introduction to the Spiral Press edition of 
<hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> and later in his <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> (1949, 2nd ed. 1971), he
observed that Rossetti “omitted to mention No. XVII, ‘Christian in the Arbour’ 
. . . . ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> 
Sir Geoffrey’s new total of twenty-nine
included, as Rossetti’s had done earlier, the troublesome No. XXII, but Sir Geoffrey remarked that this
drawing had probably been misplaced from the <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> 
series.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> 
If No. XXII is not, in fact, one of the
original Bunyan drawings, then the number of actual illustrations should stand at twenty-eight as it did in
the 1862 sale. I propose, however, that there are at least twenty-nine genuine designs in the series. This
total may be achieved by the inclusion of an additional drawing not previously mentioned by Rossetti or
Keynes. The following investigation will attempt to show that this additional drawing is a legitimate Bunyan
design and at the same time try to settle some problems of sequence within the series. 
	<note id="n1">1 Sotheby &amp; Co., Sale Catalogue of Drawings and Paintings, Lot 187, 29 April 1862.</note>
	<note id="n2">2 Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> (London: Rupert Hart-Davis, 1949), p.
174.</note>
	<note id="n3">3 Keynes, p. 184.</note></p>
          <p>The existence of an additional drawing was first brought to light in Martin Butlin’s “An Extra
Illustration to <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter 19</hi> (Winter
1971-72), 213-14. At the time Mr. Butlin’s note first appeared, my study of this drawing was already
completed and ready for submission. The design in question [illus. 2] is currently housed in the Alverthorpe
Gallery of the Rosenwald Collection and it is titled, with apparently no real authority, “A Warrior Attended
by Angels.” Further explorations into the physical appearance and subject of this pencil and watercolor
drawing leave little doubt that “A Warrior Attended by Angels” is indeed one of Blake’s original 
<hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> designs.</p>
          <p>The physical appearance of the Rosenwald drawing is remarkably similar to that of the
twenty-eight Bunyan drawings which are now in the Frick Collection. The design size of “A Warrior” measures
180 by 122 mm., while the sheet on which it is executed measures 244 by 189 mm. Although the sizes of the
Frick drawings vary slightly, they are substantially the same as those of “A Warrior.” The watermark of “A
Warrior” runs off the page from the center of the upper half of the sheet to the left; it reads J WHAT / 182.
Exactly the same watermark appears on number six and twenty-eight of the Frick series,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> and the entire watermark of J WHATMAN / 1824 may be
constructed through evidence shown on the other drawings of the series. <note id="n4">4 The numbers used here
are those which appear in pencil on the drawings of the Frick series.</note></p>
          <p>The recto of the Rosenwald design [illus. 2] has no descriptive or explanatory inscriptions, and
the verso is blank. The number 20 appears just above the border of the design in the right-hand corner, and at
the base of the drawing, just below the border on the right-hand side, is what appears to be Blake’s
signature. One minor difficulty stems from the possibility that the zero of the number twenty was at first a
one and was later rubbed out and altered to its present state.</p>
          <p>The technique employed in the Frick Collection series is basically pencil sketching colored over
with various water-color washes. In the same way, “A Warrior Attended by Angels” is a pencil sketch colored
over with gray wash and heightened with other washes of blue, yellow, green and pink. Similarities of
technique would in themselves be of comparatively little value in proving that the Rosenwald design belongs
with the Frick series. Yet when details of technique and physical appearance are combined with the evidence
provided by the subject matter of “A Warrior,” inclusion in the original genuine series becomes clearly
unavoidable.</p>
          <p>As the title suggests, the Rosenwald drawing presents an armed figure surrounded by four others
who seem to be ministering to him. The most significant 
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">James T. Wills is writing a Ph.D. dissertation on Blake’s designs for</hi> Pilgrim’s Progress 
<hi rend="i">under the direction of G. E. Bentley, Jr., at the University of Toronto.</hi></note>
	<pb id="p06-64" n="64"/>
aspect of the drawing, for present purposes at least, centers in the warrior’s armament. The illustration
clearly shows a shield buckled to his left arm and a broad sword hanging at his left side. He also appears to
be wearing a helmet of some sort and possibly a type of armor on his lower legs. It is difficult to determine
whether he wears any body armor, such as a breast plate, since he is partially covered by a flowing coat.</p>
          <p>This warrior is Christian, the pilgrim of Bunyan’s narrative. Such a statement is readily
defensible by comparing him with the figure presented in two drawings from the Frick series, while the scene
represented is readily identifiable as an illustration to <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> Indeed, “A
Warrior Attended by Angels” should be placed between the Frick design called “Christian Goes
<figure n="ChristianTakesLeave.6.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="490">
	<head>2 “Christian Takes Leave of His Companions” (“A Warrior Attended by Angels”), from Blake’s Bunyan
series.</head>
	<figDesc>National Gallery of Art, Rosenwald Collection. Reproduced by permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
Forth Armed” [illus. 1] and the one entitled “Apollyon and Christian” [illus. 3]. 
The pencil numbers which appear on the Frick drawings are at best of questionable value, 
but it may be worth noting that “Apollyon and Christian,” like “A Warrior,” 
shows the number 20.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5">5 The numbering has been dealt with more completely by G. E. Bentley, Jr., in his article, “The
Inscriptions on Blake’s Designs to <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi>”</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s “Christian Goes Forth Armed” illustrates a very specific scene in Bunyan’s work.
According to Bunyan, once Christian has been armed by the four maidens who inhabit the Lord of the Hill’s
house, Discretion, Piety, Prudence and Charity, he walks from the gate of the house accompanied
<pb id="p06-65" n="65"/>
by the porter. As they proceed, Christian questions his guide about pilgrims who may have preceded him, and
the porter replies that one named Faithful has gone before but, “he is got by this time at least below the
Hill.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n6">6 John Bunyan, <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress From This World to That Which is to
Come</hi>, ed. James Blanton Wharey, 2nd ed. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1960), p. 55.</note></p>
          <p>In “Christian Goes Forth Armed,” Blake depicts Christian and the porter at the moment they leave
the gate and move towards the steep descent of the Hill of Difficulty [see illus. 1]. The drawing is sketchy
in part, but the figure of Christian definitely includes a shield buckled to his left arm, what appears to be
a sword hilt in his left hand, and what probably represents a type of armor on his right leg. There may be a
slight suggestion of a helmet, but this detail is not nearly so clear as the others noted. As in the Rosenwald
design, Christian is shown wearing a flowing coat; this is
<figure n="ApollyonAndChristian.6.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="502">
	<head>3 “Apollyon and Christian,” from Blake’s Bunyan series.</head>
	<figDesc>Copyright the Frick Collection, New York. Reproduced by permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
probably the “Broidred Coat” he says was given him by the three shining ones.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n7">7 Bunyan, p. 49.</note></p>
          <p>Christian takes leave of the porter in Bunyan’s narrative, and
<q>
he began to go forward; but ‘Discretion’, ‘Piety’, ‘Charity’, and ‘Prudence’ would accompany
him down to the foot of the Hill. So they went on together, reiterating their former discourses, till they
came to go down
<pb id="p06-66" n="66"/>
the Hill. Then said ‘Christian’, As it was ‘difficult’ coming up, so (so far as I can see) it is
‘dangerous’ going down. . . . therefore, said they, are we come out to accompany thee down the Hill.<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
Then I saw in my dream that these good companions, when ‘Christian’ was gone down to the bottom of the
Hill, gave him a loaf of Bread, a bottle of Wine, and a cluster of Raisins; and then he went on his
way.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8">8 Bunyan, pp. 55-56.</note></q>
The drawing in the Rosenwald Collection [illus. 2] undoubtedly shows Christian at the bottom of the Hill
surrounded by his four “good companions.” Behind and above them the house of the Lord of the Hill is sketchily
outlined. Although the presents mentioned by Bunyan are not obviously identifiable, the maiden to
Christian’s immediate right may be holding a bottle in her left hand. The design portrays Christian at the
moment he departs from his four friends and enters the Valley of Humiliation; a more appropriate title might
therefore be “Christian Takes Leave of His Companions.”</p>
          <p>The ultimate purpose of Christian’s armament becomes apparent in the next sequence of events in
<hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, and Blake’s illustration for it provides yet more evidence for
including “Christian Takes Leave of His Companions” in the series. As soon as he enters the Valley of
Humiliation, Christian is confronted by the horrible Apollyon:
<q>
Now the Monster was hidious to behold: he was cloathed with scales like a Fish (and they are his pride); he
had Wings like a Dragon, feet like a Bear, and out of his belly came Fire and Smoak; and his mouth was the
mouth of a Lion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n9">9 Bunyan, p. 56.</note></q>
The battle which ensues at first goes badly for Christian:
<q>
Then ‘Apollyon’ espying his opportunity began to gather up close to ‘Christian’ and, wrestling with
him, gave him a dreadful fall; and with that ‘Christian’s’ sword flew out of his hand. . . . But as God
would have it, while ‘Apollyon’ was fetching of his last bow, . . . ‘Christian’ nimbly reached out his
hand for his sword and caught it, saying, ‘Rejoyce not against me, O mine Enemy! When I fall I shall
arise’. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n10">10 Bunyan, pp. 59-60.</note></q></p>
          <p>“Apollyon and Christian” [illus. 3] illustrates the moment just before Christian regains his
sword and vanquishes the monster. Blake pictures Apollyon with great attention to detail, while at the same
time spending a large amount of time on the figure of Christian. The design is in a more finished state than
either of the two drawings just discussed, and it shows much more clearly that Christian is indeed wearing
armor on his legs and body. Most important for present purposes, however, the drawing also shows exactly the
same sword, shield and helmet seen in the Rosenwald design. These facts, as well as the striking facial
resemblance between the two detailed representation of Christian, complete the overwhelming pictorial
evidence for including “Christian Takes Leave of His Companions” in the original Bunyan series. In addition,
the sections of <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> quoted establish a firm textual basis for accepting the
design and for placing it between the two Frick drawings.</p>
          <p>The question of how the Rosenwald drawing became separated from the other twenty-eight designs
remains to be solved, but after the initial separation the subsequent history of “Christian Takes Leave of His
Companions” may be easily traced. The Alverthorpe Gallery accession records
<pb id="p06-67" n="67"/>
<figure n="AngelsSinging.6.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="204">
	<head>4 K. Schutz, undated pencil drawing of three angels singing, Number 17 in the Aders album.</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of the Harvard College Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
reveal that Mr. Rosenwald acquired the drawing from Sotheby’s on 10 December 1958, and according to the
auction catalogue it was “formerly contained in an album of letters from Blake, Coleridge and Lamb formed by
Mrs. Charles Aders. . . . ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> The
remainder of the album was eventually sold by Sotheby’s on 15 December of the same year and is now in the
Houghton Library, Harvard University. The exact original position of the Blake drawing within the album cannot
now be easily ascertained, especially since nearly fifty leaves have been cut out. Still, there is a strong
possibility that the design originally appeared between entry Nos. 17 and 26.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n11">11 Sotheby &amp; Co., Sale Catalogue of Drawings and Paintings, Lot 72, 10 December
1958.</note>
	<note id="n12">12 I am using here the notation of the Houghton Library. The discussion of the album which
follows is taken in part from a description provided by Mr. Rodney G. Dennis, Curator of Manuscripts at the
Houghton Library.</note></p>
          <p>Containing materials which range in date from 1811 to 1874, the Aders album is arranged in a
roughly chronological manner. The ten entries in question are significantly grouped, at least so far as their
dates can be ascertained, around 1827, the year of Blake’s death. Support for placing the Rosenwald design
between Nos. 17 and 26 arises primarily from the angel motif of a large proportion of these entries. Number 17
is an undated pencil drawing, heightened with white and gold, of three angels singing, by K. Schutz [illus.
4]; number 20 is a manuscript of Charles Lamb’s “Angel Help,” dated 1827; and number 21 is an undated pen
drawing, heightened with gold, of angels assisting a poor family, by Jacob Götzenberger [illus. 5].
Götzenberger may be remembered as the German artist who commented favorably on Blake’s Dante
designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Entries 22 and 23 deal with
“Angel Help”; the former is an 1827 version of the poem by Mary Lamb, the latter an 1827 letter from Charles
Lamb concerning the same poem. Between Nos. 17 and 26 there are eight leaves cut from the album and one blank
leaf, No. 25, from which something has been removed. <note id="n13">13 Henry Crabb Robinson, 
<hi rend="i">Diary Reminiscences and Correspondence</hi>, ed. Thomas Sadler (Boston: James R. Osgood and Co.,
1871), II, 74.</note></p>
          <p>It may well be that in 1827 Mrs. Blake, knowing that the Bunyan series had twenty-nine drawings,
sold that number to Tatham, simply confusing the <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> design with “Christian
Takes Leave.” Consequently, Mrs. Aders could have acquired
<figure n="AngelsAssisting.6.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="249">
	<head>5 Jacob Götzenberger, undated pen drawing of angels assisting a poor family, Number 21 in the Aders
album.</head>
	<figDesc>By permission of the Harvard College Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
the latter drawing, placed it in her album in one of the spaces mentioned above, and given it what she
considered an appropriate title.</p>
          <p>Regardless of whether these conjectures about placement in the album and separation from the
series prove correct, there is no doubt that “Christian Takes Leaves of His Companions” is a Bunyan design.
Taken together, the three drawings discussed are a fine example of Blake’s method of illustrating 
<hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>; and barring any further additions to the new total of genuine
designs—there is a possibility that there may be several more<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n14" type="note">14</ref>—the way now seems open for the completion of a full scale study of
Blake’s designs for Bunyan.</p>
<note id="n14">14 There are two Blake drawings in the British Museum each of
which represents a figure seated before a burning city. According to a description I received from Miss Dinah
Mitchell of the Department of Prints and Drawings, the designs are accompanied by a note by Samuel Palmer. The
note says, in part, that they are two states of “a design perhaps from the <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s
Progress.</hi>” There seems to be no substantial evidence at this time to support Palmer’s conjecture. For
further information on these drawings, see Raymond Lister, “Two Blake Drawings and a Letter by Samuel Palmer,”
in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 23, forthcoming.
	<p>There are also three designs, formerly in the possession of W. G. Robertson but now untraced, which are
related to the Bunyan series. <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of W. Graham Robertson</hi>, ed. Kerrison
Preston in 1952 for the Blake Trust, lists these three designs as Nos. 104, 105, and 106. The respective
titles are “Christian and Worldly Wiseman,” “The Interpreter’s House,” and “Vanity Fair.” Frederick Tatham
vouched for all three as genuine Blakes, but he was firmly convinced only that No. 106 was definitely a Bunyan
design.</p></note>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
