<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>6.3.king</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A New Piece of Tayloriana</title>
        <author n="King">James King</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1972-73</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1972-73</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">06.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
              <name>Michael Davies</name>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Foster Foreman</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1972-73"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_06">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-06-3-0004">
        <pb id="p06-72" n="72"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A NEW PIECE OF TAYLORIANA</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>James <name>King</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>A manuscript notebook closely related to Thomas Taylor has been acquired by the Division of
Archives and Special Collections, Mills Memorial Library, McMaster University. The notebook, “The only
fragments which remain of the Writings of the Philosopher Celsus,” seems to be the working notes for the
Celsus portion of Taylor’s 1830 <hi rend="i">Arguments of Celsus, Porphyry, and the Emperor Julian, Against
the Christians</hi> . . . (the cover title reads <hi rend="i">Fragments of Porphyry, Julian, &amp;c. against
the Christians</hi>). The notebook (3 3/4 × 5 3/4 inches, 104 pages, undated with no watermarks) contains a
translation of all of Celsus’s anti-Christian writings, as preserved by Origen; the Celsus section of
Taylor’s book contains only a portion of Celsus’s attack against Christianity, frequently interrupted by
Taylor’s commentary.</p>
          <p>Although the notebook is not in Taylor’s hand, it might well be a translation prepared on his
behalf or Taylor’s working notes as transcribed by an amanuensis. Two circumstances make the latter case the
more likely. First, aside from Taylor, there is no significant interest in Celsus’s religious writings in
the 1820’s and 30’s. Second, the manuscript was found in the stockroom of the late Donald Berry of Eltham.
In the same location was recently discovered the 1929-30 commonplace book of W. G. Meredith (1804-31), which
contains the first positive evidence that Blake knew Taylor (see my “The Meredith Family, Thomas Taylor, and
William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 11 [1972], 153-57). Although one must exercise
caution in determining the extent of the dependency of <hi rend="i">Arguments of Celsus</hi> on “The only
fragments . . . ,” the notebook is a piece of evidence of real interest to students of Taylor. 
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">James King, Assistant Professor of English at McMaster
University, is the co-editor of the forthcoming edition of Cowper’s correspondence to be published by the
Clarendon Press, Oxford.</hi></note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
