<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>6.3.duerksen</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Crucial Line in Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title>
        <author n="Duerksen">Roland A. Duerksen</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1972-73</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1972-73</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">06.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
              <name>Michael Davies</name>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Foster Foreman</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1972-73"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_06">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-06-3-0004">
      	<pb id="p06-72" n="72"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A CRUCIAL LINE IN <hi rend="i">VISIONS OF THE DAUGHTERS OF ALBION</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Roland A. <name>Duerksen</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Perhaps the most elusive while also the most significant line in <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi> is plate 2, line 5: “Bound back to back in Bromion’s caves, terror and meekness
dwell.” Blake’s full-plate illustration for this and the succeeding two lines depicts two human figures
chained back to back in a cave. They are a rugged male with fear-distorted face and an utterly dejected
female. Nearby, at the cave’s entrance, another male figure (clearly identified in the text as Theotormon)
abjectly sits, hiding his face in his folded arms. The generally-accepted interpretation is that the bound
figures are Bromion and Oothoon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">1</ref>
Neither the characterizations of these two nor the narrative progression of the poem, however, seems to
support this reading. <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Mark Schorer, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
Politics of Vision</hi> (New York: Henry Holt, 1946), p. 249; Stanley Gardner, <hi rend="i">Infinity on the
Anvil: A Critical Study of Blake’s Poetry</hi> (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1954), p. 51; Harold Bloom, 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic Argument</hi> (Garden City: Doubleday, 1963), p. 112; Foster
Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi> (Providence, R. I.: Brown
Univ. Press, 1965), pp. 308, 437; and David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, rev.
ed. (Garden City: Doubleday, 1969), p. 236.</note></p>
          <p>An alternate and, in my opinion, more plausible interpretation is that the two bound figures are,
indeed, terror and meekness. Thus juxtaposed, masculinity terrified and femininity meekly submissive
constitute the very principle upon which Bromion maintains his position as slave-holder. Throughout the poem
Bromion is tyrannical and blatantly assertive. Quite the contrary of a prisoner subdued and shackled in his
own habitat, he has exercised his power to bind terror and meekness together, thus subjecting them totally to
his will and purposes.</p>
          <p>As indicated by plate 2, line 22, and the illuminated portion of plate 4 (where the chain about
her ankle appears loosened), Oothoon is free to hover about the hopeless, weeping, deafened Theotormon at the
entrance to the cave, presenting the case for liberation as persuasively as she can. In the light of this
liberated activity on her part, the explanation that Oothoon is bound meekly back to back with Bromion appears
incongruous with regard to both characterization and narrative continuity. The binding of terror and meekness
in Bromion’s caves becomes, then, symbolically the oppression of mind and spirit from which Oothoon seeks to
liberate the enslaved daughters of Albion—and from which Blake seeks to liberate us. 
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">Roland A. Duerksen, Professor of English at Miami University
(Oxford, Ohio), has published articles on British and American Romantic writers—including several on Blake.
His books include</hi> Shelleyan Ideas in Victorian Literature <hi rend="i">(Mouton, 1966) and editions of
various works by Shelley.</hi></note></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
