<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>6.3.todd</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Rev. Dr. John Trusler</title>
        <author n="Todd">Ruthven Todd</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1972-73</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1972-73</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">06.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
              <name>Michael Davies</name>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Foster Foreman</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1972-73"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_06">
    <body>
      <pb id="p06-71" n="71"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-06-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">Minute Particulars</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">THE REV. DR. JOHN TRUSLER (1735-1820)</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Ruthven <name>Todd</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In his Preface to <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake</hi>, 2nd ed., 1968, p. 16, Sir
Geoffrey Keynes mentions that Trusler “established a business as a bookseller with the object of abolishing
publishers.” A printer friend, Bernard Roberts, has recently sent me a booklet which he wrote and printed, 
<hi rend="i">Writers and Printers in Clerkenwell</hi>, Printed for their friends by The John Roberts Press 14
Clerkenwell Green London E.C. 1 [n.d.]. This contains further information about Trusler, “a clergyman turned
printer and publisher, [who] was in a fair way of business in Red Lion Street during the 1780’s, being also
the author of <hi rend="i">The Honours of the Table</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Principles of Politeness.</hi> .
. . Dr. Trusler also wrote, printed and published collections of sermons. He had the curious idea of printing
these in a script type, so that a preacher would sound (so Trusler imagined) as though he was reading from his
own manuscript rather than from a printed book.” Sir Geoffrey says that his “mind was wholly antipathetic to
Blake’s, and they could never have come to terms.” It does strike me, however, that, if the business about
the drawing “Malevolence” had not interfered, Blake and the Rev. Dr. might have spent a pleasant hour or two
discussing the abolition of publishers, and also the unsuspected advantages of script as a type from which to
read. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">Ruthven Todd of Mallorca is well known as the
editor of the Everyman</hi> Life of Blake <hi rend="i">by Gilchrist, and as the author of numerous books and
articles on Blake and related subjects. The most recent is</hi> Blake the Artist <hi rend="i">(Studio Vista,
1971).</hi></note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
