<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>6.3.kupersmith</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">S. Foster Damon Collection at Brown University</title>
        <author n="Kupersmith">John Kupersmith</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1972-73</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1972-73</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">06.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
              <name>Michael Davies</name>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Foster Foreman</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1972-73"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_06">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-06-3-0002">
      	<pb id="p06-60" n="60"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Damon Collection</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Foster Damon had a fine Blake collection of some 300 items (not including manuscripts). Besides
copies of most secondary works on Blake, standard and non-standard editions, and Trianon, Dent, Muir, and
other facsimiles, the collection contains original editions of some of Blake’s source materials and of his
own works, including several early editions of Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, Hayley’s 
<hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, and works by Flaxman and Cumberland on which Blake collaborated. There are also such
items as an excellent collection of sheet music for Blake’s poems, a wide variety of prints, a Blake Bible,
and so forth.</p>
          <p>The collection also has value as “Damoniana,” including as it does many books bearing Damon’s
marginalia, his notebooks, a good deal of correspondence, and some unpublished manuscripts.</p>
          <p>Damon was associated with the John Hay Library at Brown University for some years, and at his
death in 1971 the collection (in its entirety, as far as I have been able to determine) passed to the library,
where it presently awaits cataloguing. The library intends to keep the collection together (a very reassuring
decision), and is building it up through such acquisitions as the Trianon facsimile of the Gray illustrations.
<hi rend="i">(Our thanks to John Kupersmith for this item. He is now preparing for the</hi> Newsletter 
<hi rend="i">an account of the history and principal contents of the Damon collection. Eds.)</hi></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
