<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>6.3.adlard</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Age and Virginity of Lyca</title>
        <author n="Adlard">John Adlard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1972-73</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1972-73</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">06.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
              <name>Michael Davies</name>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Foster Foreman</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1972-73"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_06">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-06-3-0004">
        <pb id="p06-73" n="73"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">THE AGE AND VIRGINITY OF LYCA</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>John <name>Adlard</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In Blake’s “The Little Girl Lost” Lyca is a virgin seven years old and Kathleen Raine finds the
choice of age “inexplicable” (<hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, I, 145). But the Commentary of Hierocles
on the Golden Verses of Pythagoras tells us that the number seven itself is a virgin, a surprising statement
explained in a single sentence from a translation Blake could well have read:
<q>
Now, the powers and properties of the unit, and of the septenary, are very great and excellent: for the unit,
as the principle of all the numbers, contains in itself the powers of them all; and the seven being a virgin,
and without any mother [Lyca had lost both father and mother], holds, in the second place, the virtue and the
perfection of the unit, because it is not ingendered by any number within the interval of ten, as four is
produced by twice two, six by twice three, and eight by twice four, nine by three times three and ten by twice
five: neither does it produce any number within that interval, as the number two produces four, the
<figure n="vda.j.p1" id="vda.j.illbk.01" work-copy="vda.j" rend="db" width="712" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>Left <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, frontispiece.</head>
	<figDesc>Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. Reproduced by permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
three nine, and the five ten.<lb/>
<hi rend="i">The Commentary of Hierocles upon the Golden Verses of Pythagoras, translated from the Greek. The
Second Edition, Corrected and Improved</hi> (Glasgow, 1756), p. 154. (The following page has a passage on the
“quaternion,” which “contains and binds together all beings whatsoever, the elements, numbers, seasons, ages,
societies, or communities,” of great relevance to Blake’s concept of the Four Zoas.)
</q>
It may be significant that a cloud tells another virgin, Thel, that he passes away “to tenfold life, to love,
to peace and raptures holy” (<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> 3:11), since virginity in Hierocles is
represented by an inability to “produce any number within that interval.” 
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">John Adlard edited the</hi> Blake <hi rend="i">volume in the Studio Vista Pocket
Poets series (1970), and he authored a biography of Yeats’ early friend Count Eric Stenbock (1970), as well
as</hi> The Sports of Cruelty <hi rend="i">(1972), a book mainly about Blake and folklore.</hi></note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
