<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.4.curtis</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">The Geddes Bible and the Tent of the Eternals in the Book of Urizen</title>
                <author n="Curtis">F. B. Curtis</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
	<pb id="p06-93" n="93"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-4-0002">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">THE GEDDES BIBLE AND THE TENT OF THE ETERNALS IN <hi rend="i">THE
BOOK OF URIZEN</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">F. B.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Curtis</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n26" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>The reaction of the Eternals to the creation of the “first female form now separate”
(<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, pl. 18), is to close off the fallen Los and Enitharmon in a tent:
<q>
“Spread a Tent, with strong curtains around them<lb/>
“Let cords &amp; stakes bind in the Void<lb/>
That Eternals may no more behold them”<lb/>
                            <lb/>
They began to weave curtains of darkness<lb/>
They erected large pillars round the Void<lb/>
With golden hooks fasten’d in the pillars<lb/>
With infinite labour the Eternals<lb/>
A woof wove, and called it Science<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, pl. 19, 11.2-9)
</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although Blake was possibly thinking here of a traditional Biblical image—the tents
of the wandering Jews—it is perhaps more than a coincidence that we find the following description of a tent
and darkness in A. Geddes’ <hi rend="i">The Holy Bible</hi> (Vol. 1, 20 June 1792), published two years
before the printing of Blake’s poem: 
                        <note id="n26">
                            <hi rend="i">Francis B. Curtis is a Lecturer in English at the University of
Cologne. He has published an article in</hi> Philological Quarterly <hi rend="i">on Blake’s interest in
mathematics, and he is currently working on a study of Blake’s medical and scientific knowledge.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-94" n="94"/>
						<q>
And St Basil ascribes the darkness that covered the earth, before the appearance of light, to the
interposition of an opaque body between it and heavens. This he illustrates by an example that excludes all
ambiguity. “Place around you”, says he, “at high mid-day, a tent, composed of dense and opaque materials: the
temporary darkness which, by shutting yourself up in it, you will procure, may give you an idea of that
darkness, which covered the deep, and which did not antecedently subsist, but was the consequence of other
things.”<lb/>
(Preface, p. V)
</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The closeness in imagery is striking: Blake’s “strong curtains” and “curtains of
darkness” remind us of the “dense and opaque materials” in Geddes; both tents are interposed between the
fallen earth and the heavens. Finally, the Geddes description states that the darkness “was the consequence of
other things,” which readily invokes the reason for the Eternals’ action:
<q>
Wonder, awe, fear, astonishment,<lb/>
Petrify the eternal myriads;<lb/>
At the first female form now separate<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, pl. 18, 11. 13-15)
</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Of course, Blake’s fiery imagination has transmuted and refined this source. The
labor of the Eternals is “infinite,” the adjective “golden” in “golden hooks” promises brightness and light to
come, and the word “woof” will become an integral image in Blake’s developing mythology.</p>
                    <p>However, it is not unlikely that Blake had read this description in the Geddes Bible,
sold as it was by the bookseller with whom Blake had the closest contact in this period, Joseph
Johnson.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">1</ref> Blake had engraved plates
for Johnson as early as 1780, visited his shop frequently and would hardly have failed to notice an important
new edition of his beloved Bible among the immense volume of scriptural criticism, writings on prophecy, and
sermons that stocked Johnson’s premises in St. Paul’s Churchyard.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">2</ref>
                        <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">1</hi> An article on Blake’s relationship to the London
booksellers, “Blake and the Booksellers,” has been accepted for a forthcoming issue of <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, and contains detailed remarks on the Blake-Johnson relationship.</note>
                        <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">2</hi> There were over eighty works on Prophecy and
Revelation alone (excluding sermons and editions of the Bible) published in the period 1792-1818, and Joseph
Johnson published nearly half—thirty-nine—of them. See article in note 1, above.</note>
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>