<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.4.morkan</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake’s Ancient Forests of Europe</title>
                <author n="Morkan">Joel Morkan</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-4-0002">
                <pb id="p06-93" n="93"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">BLAKE’S “ANCIENT FORESTS OF EUROPE”</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Joel <name>Morkan</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n25" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>In <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>, Blake’s Moloch, the Duke of Burgundy,
exhorts the king “To rouze up the ancient forests of Europe, with clarions of cloud breathing war” (1.
101).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">1</ref> Burgundy warns that if this is
not done the nobles will see “the ancient forests of chivalry hewn, and the joys of combat burnt for fuel” (1.
93). 
                        <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake: Complete
Writings</hi> (Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press, 1971), p. 138.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>David Erdman has commented on the power of Blake’s epithet for the feudal
aristocracy, but he has not chosen to explicate it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">2</ref> The epithet, however, is another instance of Blake’s careful fusion of history and myth
in the poem, and it repays examination. On the mythic level the old nobility is Druidic, representing the
primeval forest and the domination of the natural over the human. The historical reference, in turn,
reinforces and intensifies the mythic dimension. 
                        <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">2</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet
Against Empire</hi> (Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1969), p. 167.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In 1669 Colbert promulgated an ordinance that closed the forests to the
peasants.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">3</ref> They were banned from
hunting in the forests or from gathering fuel wood. In the years just prior to the outbreak of the Revolution,
the burden of this edict became more onerous. Agents of the nobility exercised “planting rights” by growing
trees on the road-side property of peasants, and further enforced the laws prohibiting them from the
forests.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">4</ref>
                        <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Georges Lefebvre, <hi rend="i">The Coming of the
French Revolution, 1789</hi>, trans. Robert R. Palmer (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton Univ. Press, 1947), p.
122.</note>
                        <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Lefebvre, p. 14.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>During the weeks and days of turmoil immediately before the Revolution the agrarian
lower classes vented their rage at these laws and moved to have “the ancient forests hewn, and the joys of
combat burnt for fuel.” When the Revolution was victorious, in fact, one of the first things the peasants did
was to invade the forests and lay claim to them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">5</ref> Furthermore, “forest rights” continued to be a serious political issue well into the
nineteenth century. As Stendhal shows in Chapter XXIII, “Le Clergé, Les Bois, La Liberté,” of 
<hi rend="i">Le Rouge et Le Noir</hi>, both the upper clergy and nobility intrigued to repossess <hi rend="i">les
forets domaniales</hi> after the Restoration. 
                        <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Lefebvre, p. 129.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>This historical data establishes the precision of Blake’s epithet for the nobility.
They represent the old world of privilege and dominance that maintains the world of Nature over the human
world. The revolutionary forces, on the other hand, represent the human urge to liberate mankind from the
domination of Nature and to subordinate natural forces to human needs. Through this compact and appropriate
epithet for the aristocracy Blake conflated his mythic and historical intentions into a dense and dramatically
functional metaphor. <note id="n25">
                            <hi rend="i">Joel Morkan is an Associate Professor of English at Florida State
University. He has published essays on Milton and the Romantics.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>