<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.4.warner</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake and English Printed Textiles</title>
                <author n="Warner">Janet Warner</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <pb id="p06-84" n="84"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-4-0002">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">
                            <hi rend="i">Notes</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <figure n="but335.1.9.wc" id="but335.1.wc.09" work-copy="but335.1" rend="db" width="781" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>3</figTranscr>
                    <head>1 <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Water-Colour Designs for the Poems of Thomas
Gray</hi>, design no. 3 for “Ode on the Death of a Favourite Cat Drowned in a Tub of Gold Fishes.”</head>
                    <figDesc>From the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <pb id="p06-85" n="85"/>
                <figure n="CottonPrint.6.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="379">
                    <head>2 Cotton, plate-printed in blue, ca. 1775.</head>
                    <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">BLAKE AND ENGLISH PRINTED TEXTILES</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Janet <name>Warner</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>One of the most charming elements of Blake’s designs are his flower forms,
particularly those in the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and Experience, The Book of Thel</hi>, and the 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> series. Blake was no careful observer of Nature, preferring to humanize the
material world through imagination, so these flower forms are not exactly “natural.” To modern eyes, they
appear abstract and very contemporary in their dream-like suggestiveness. Yet it seems possible that Blake’s
inspiration for his floral designs was found in eighteenth century embroidery patterns and textile
designs.</p>
                    <p>It is known that Mrs. Thomas Butts, wife of Blake’s patron and friend, was expert at
needlework, and that Blake probably designed for her a needlework panel called <hi rend="i">Two Hares in Long
Grass.</hi>
                        <ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> And it is possible that most women of Blake’s
acquaintance, including his wife, engaged in needlework as a pastime. But as a printer, Blake would be also
familiar with textile designs through <note id="n0">
                            <hi rend="i">Janet Warner is an Associate Professor of English at Glendon College,
York University (Toronto). She is presently spending a sabbatical leave in Cambridge, England.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb id="p06-86" n="86"/>
the growing English textile-printing industry which—in the mid-eighteenth century—was just beginning to be
transformed by the use of engraved copper plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> Thus during Blake’s apprenticeship as an engraver in the 1770s, the districts around
London were a center for copper-plate textile printing, a position they were to lose by 1800, by which time
Lancashire firms had forced most of the London printers out of business. Pattern books which came to light as
recently as 1955 reveal that a particular group of designs using large flowers and birds was
characteristically English.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Popular
designs were also “Chinoiseries” based on the published patterns of Jean Pillement (1760).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Blake must have known of these designs, and
some of them seem to have been adapted by him. For instance, his design in 1797 for plate 3 of Gray’s 
<hi rend="i">Ode on the Death of a Favourite Cat</hi> is reminiscent of a plate-printed
<figure n="songsie.y.p38" id="songsie.y.illbk.38" work-copy="songsie.y" rend="db" width="713" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>38<lb/>
	NURSES Song<lb/>
	When the voices of children. are heard on the green<lb/>
	And whisprings are in the dale:<lb/>
	The days of my youth rise fresh in my mind,<lb/>
	My face turns green and pale.<lb/>
	Then come home my children. the sun is gone down<lb/>
	And the dews of night arise<lb/>
	Your spring &amp; your day. are wasted in play<lb/>
	And your winter and night in disguise.</figTranscr>
                            <head>3 “Nurses Song,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Rogers Fund, 1917.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
cotton dated about 1775 (illus. 1 and 2). This type of floral design was also typical of one of the biggest
London printers, Thomas Nash of Morris’ Causeway, Lambeth, who worked from 1767 to 1782. The oriental
feeling of Blake’s floral spray is beautifully apt, for the poem begins:
<q>
‘Twas on a lofty vase’s side,<lb/>
Where China’s gayest art had dy’d<lb/>
The azure flowers that blow. . . .
</q>
                        <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Now in the collection of Sir Geoffrey Keynes. See
David Binaman, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the Fitzwilliam Museum</hi>
(Cambridge: W. Heffer and Sons, 1970), pp. 68-69.</note>
                        <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See <hi rend="i">English Printed Textiles</hi>
(London: Victoria and Albert Museum, 1960), p. 2.</note>
                        <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> English Printed Textiles</hi>, p.
3.</note>
                        <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> English Printed Textiles</hi>, p.
3.</note>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p06-87" n="87"/>
                    <figure n="GrapeVine.6.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="600">
                        <figTranscr>214.—VINE.<lb/>
                        VITIS VINIFERA. G. 725.1.</figTranscr>
                        <head>4 Grape vine from John Gerarde’s <hi rend="i">The Herball or General Historie
of Plants</hi>, reproduced from Richard G. Hatton, <hi rend="i">Handbook of Plant and Floral Ornament.</hi>
                        </head>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p06-88" n="88"/>
                    <figure n="Roses.6.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="356">
                        <figTranscr>28.—HUNDRED-LEAFED ROSE.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        VARIOUSLY-COLOURED ROSE. C. v. d. P.<lb/>
                        (Rosaceæ.)</figTranscr>
                        <head>5 Roses from Crispian van de Passe, <hi rend="i">Hortus Floridus</hi>,
reproduced from Richard G. Hatton, <hi rend="i">Handbook of Plant and Floral Ornament.</hi>
                        </head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="songsie.y.p39" id="songsie.y.illbk.39" work-copy="songsie.y" rend="db" width="656" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>39<lb/>
	The SICK ROSE<lb/>
	O Rose thou art sick.<lb/>
	The invisible worm.<lb/>
	That flies in the night<lb/>
	In the howling storm:<lb/>
	Has found out thy bed<lb/>
	Of crimson joy:<lb/>
	And his dark secret love<lb/>
	Does thy life destroy.</figTranscr>
                        <head>6 “The Sick Rose,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Rogers Fund, 1917.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p06-89" n="89"/>
                    <p>Of course another possible source for Blake and probably the textile designers as well
would have been the Herbals of the sixteenth century, books of wood-cuts or engraved drawings of plants which
would have been known to anyone engaged in the printer’s craft.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Similarities between Blake’s floral patterns and the Herbals can be seen
here in illustrations 3 and 4, 5 and 6. A mid-seventeenth century needlework tulip is also illustrated which
bears a striking resemblance to the flower in Blake’s title page to <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>
(illus. 7 and 8). Blake’s tulip and leaf designs on <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>’s title page bear even closer
resemblances to forms in eighteenth-century Indian chintz (illus. 9). Another needlework tulip recalls
Blake’s design for “Infant Joy” (illus. 10 and 11), and anyone who has seen an oak leaf in crewel work will
be reminded of Blake’s oak-leaf designs. Many English textile designs were based on designs of Indian
chintz, which was so popular in England in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries that the wool industry
legislated against its import. The oriental flavor of the animals and botanical forms of some of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs may owe
<figure n="thel.d.p2" id="thel.d.illbk.02" work-copy="thel.d" rend="db" width="704" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>THE<lb/>
	BOOK<lb/>
	of<lb/>
	THEL<lb/>
	The Author &amp; Printer Willm. Blake. 1789</figTranscr>
                            <head>7 Title page, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="BedCurtain.6.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="332">
                            <head>8 English bed curtain, mid-17th century (detail).</head>
                            <figDesc>Wool on cotton and linen, twill weave. The Victoria and Albert
Museum.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="Quilt.6.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="540">
                            <head>9 Quilt from India, Coromandel Coast (northern region), first half of the
18th century.</head>
                            <figDesc>Painted and dyed cotton. Note especially the tulip on the left, midway up
the tree. Royal Ontario Museum, Toronto.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p06-90" n="90"/>
                        <figure n="songsie.y.p25" id="songsie.y.illbk.25" work-copy="songsie.y" rend="db" width="678" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>25<lb/>
	Infant Joy<lb/>
	I have no name<lb/>
	I am but two days old.__<lb/>
	What shall I call thee?<lb/>
	I happy am<lb/>
	Joy is my name,__<lb/>
	Sweet joy befall thee!<lb/>
	Pretty joy!<lb/>
	Sweet joy but two days old,<lb/>
	Sweet joy I call thee;<lb/>
	Thou dost smile.<lb/>
	I sing the while<lb/>
	Sweet joy befall thee.</figTranscr>
                            <head>10 “Infant Joy,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Rogers Fund, 1917.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="CrewelWork.6.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="467">
                            <head>11 Crewel-work curtain, detail.</head>
                            <figDesc>English, 18th century. Royal Ontario Museum, Toronto.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="BUT675.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="786">
                            <figTranscr>ΠΑΡΙς<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            inv<lb/>
                            WB 1811</figTranscr>
                            <head>12 Blake, <hi rend="i">The Judgment of Paris.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p06-91" n="91"/>
                        <figure n="CottonParis.6.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="647">
                            <head>13 Plate-printed cotton design of the Judgment of Paris and the game of
blindman’s buff.</head>
                            <figDesc>English, ca. 1795. Blue on white cotton. The Metropolitan Museum of
Art.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p06-92" n="92"/>
something to Blake’s familiarity with such textiles.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
                        <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See for example Richard G. Hatton, 
<hi rend="i">Handbook of Plant and Floral Ornament</hi> (1909 [as <hi rend="i">The Craftsman’s Plant Book</hi>];
rpt. New York: Dover, 1960).</note>
                        <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For many examples see John Irwin and Katharine B.
Brett, <hi rend="i">Origins of Chintz</hi> (London, 1970). I am most grateful to Mrs. Brett of the Royal
Ontario Museum Textile Department for her help in preparing this essay.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Mythological scenes were also utilized by the English designers of plate-printed
cottons, and one of these scenes from a design dated about 1795 bears interesting resemblance to Blake’s own
design, <hi rend="i">The Judgment of Paris</hi>, executed in 1817<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n7" type="note">7</ref> (see illus. 12 and 13). Barbara J. Morris, who wrote extensively about the
English textile designs when they were first discovered, could not find a source for this design but thought
it reminiscent of Stothard.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
                        <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The most obvious similarities lie in the general
arrangement of the characters, and the stance of the woman at extreme right. Blake specialists will find the
differences as significant as the similarities.</note>
                        <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Barbara J. Morris, “English Printed Textiles, V.
Sports and Pastimes,” <hi rend="i">Antiquee</hi>, 62 (Sept. 1957), 253. This is one of nine articles on
English eighteenth-century copper-plate textiles and early nineteenth-century roller prints by Peter Floud and
Barbara Morris, printed March 1957 to April 1958 in <hi rend="i">Antiques.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>There is no known record of Blake’s involvement in commercial textile design, though
there is one existing example of an engraved trade card which he designed for Moore and Co., a firm which
manufactured carpets and hosiery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
Since Blake’s brother James was a hosier, and his father had been one, it is not surprising to see that
Blake’s design shows a real familiarity with the machinery involved. It seems possible that he would have
been familiar with more commercial ventures of this nature than is usually supposed. In the Metropolitan
Museum’s collection of tradesmen’s cards is an eighteenth-century printer’s card whose emblem of an
eagle closely resembles Blake’s eagle in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, plate 38 (illus. 14 and 15). 
<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Reproduced in Ruthven Todd, <hi rend="i">William Blake the Artist</hi> (London:
Studio Vista, 1971), p. 26.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Since Blake wrote a good deal about his own capacities for drawing and the quality of
his “execution,” and since we also know he could draw in any way he chose—realistically or
symbolically—his choice of floral motifs and the sources he chose to emulate are of some importance to an
understanding of his purpose. It is possible that he chose the iconographically familiar forms of popular
textile designs because in this way he reaffirms a language of Art which he firmly believed was available to
everyone (“ . . . no one can ever Design till he has learned the Language of Art by making many Finished
Copies both of Nature and Art and of what ever comes in his way from Earliest Childhood” [<hi rend="i">Annot.
to Reynolds</hi>]). The universality of such forms, which transcend linguistic differences, implies a unity in
the human imagination which makes all art and all religions one. The full significance of Blake’s visual
symbols continues to be explored by Blake scholars; I have here called attention to a more mundane aspect of
Blake’s technique as a designer, yet it may indicate the attention and importance attached to “Minute
Particulars” as the foundation of divine Vision. As Blake wrote in the <hi rend="i">Annotations to
Reynolds</hi>, “Minute Discrimination Is Not Accidental All sublimity is founded on Minute
Discrimination.”</p>
                    <figure n="TradeCard.6.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="251">
                        <head>14 Trade card, S. Burton Stationer.</head>
                        <figDesc>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Bella C. Landauer Collection, 1921.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="milton.a.p38" id="milton.a.illbk.38" work-copy="milton.a" rend="db" width="776" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>38</figTranscr>
                        <head>15 Plate 38 of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>