<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.4.reiman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">A Significant Early Review of Blake</title>
                <author n="Reiman">Donald H. Reiman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-4-0002">
            	<pb id="p06-94" n="94"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">A SIGNIFICANT EARLY REVIEW OF BLAKE</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Donald H.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Reiman</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n27" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>In <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi> by G. E. Bentley, Jr., and Martin K. Nurmi,
there are recorded only 102 type-printed references to William Blake or his works through 1827, the year of
his death.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">1</ref> Suzanne R. Hoover has
added one allusion (for 1796) in her “Fifty Additions to Blake Bibliography.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">2</ref> Of these items, only a handful comment substantively on
Blake’s poetry or his designs, fewer name him, and even fewer comment favorably. 
                    </p>
                        <note id="n27">
                            <hi rend="i">Donald H. Reiman of The Carl H. Pforzheimer Library, New York, is
editor of Volumes V and VI of</hi> Shelley and His Circle <hi rend="i">(Harvard, 1973), as well as the nine
volumes of</hi> The Romantics Reviewed <hi rend="i">(1972). He has previously published books on Shelley and
articles on subjects ranging from</hi> Beowulf, <hi rend="i">Chaucer, and Shakespeare, to Hopkins, James, and
Salinger.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">1</hi> This figure, derived from the “Table of
Type-Printed References to Blake before 1863” (p. xvii), may be slightly askew; that list’s entry for the
year 1789 is, for instance, a mistake.</note>
                        <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Newsletter</hi> 19, 5 (Winter,
1971-72), 167-72.</note>
                    <p>The addition of even a brief notice favorable to Blake as an artist is, therefore, of
some value. The following short notice of one of Blake’s least significant publications is the second
earliest published notice, I believe, to comment favorably on Blake’s art<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">3</ref> and is certainly the first to name him in doing so. It
appeared in the <hi rend="i">European Magazine and London Review</hi> for August 1802 (42: 125-26). 
                        <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The single earlier favorable mention listed by
Bentley and Nurmi occurred in passing in the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi>’s notice of Mary
Wollstonecraft’s translation of C. G. Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality, for the Use of
Children</hi> (1791). But the question of Blake’s participation in that work is still open. See Bentley and
Nurmi, item 402A (pp. 149-50).</note>
                    </p>
					<q>
                        <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads written by William Hayley, Esq. and
founded on Anecdotes relating to Animals, drawn, engraved, and published, by William Blake. With the 
<pb id="p06-95" n="95"/>
Ballads
annexed by the Author’s Permission. Two Numbers.</hi> 4to. Printed at Chichester.
</q>
                    <p>It appears by the Preface to this work, that Mr. Hayley is now busily employed in
rendering an affectionate tribute of justice to the memory of Cowper the Poet, and that Mr. Blake has devoted
himself with indefatigable spirit to engrave the plates intended to decorate the work. To amuse the artist in
his patient labour, and to furnish his fancy with a few slight subjects for an inventive pencil that might
afford some variety to his incessant application, without too far interrupting his most serious business, Mr.
Hayley proposed to furnish him with a series of ballads for a few vacant moments’ employment, to be
published periodically, and to be completed in fifteen numbers. Two of these are now before us. The subjects,
the gratitude of an elephant, and the heroism of a mother in rescuing her child from the fangs of an eagle.
The artist has executed his share of the undertaking much to his credit; and from Mr. Hayley’s pen, though
carelessly employed, the Public will not be disappointed in their expectation of elegant, chaste, and pathetic
compositions. To the inhabitants of Chichester, where it is printed, this work is inscribed.</p>
                    <p>I came across this notice while preparing my nine-volume edition of facsimile reprints
of reviews of the Romantic poets and their circles, <hi rend="i">The Romantics Reviewed</hi> (New York:
Garland Publishing, Inc., 1972). Though tempted to include it, together with the few other substantive early
comments on Blake, I concluded that the notices of Blake did not belong with those of Wordsworth, Coleridge,
Byron, Shelley, and Keats both because the reviews of Blake deal primarily with his work as an artist and
because—had I followed uniform criteria for inclusion—most of the critical comments on Blake would have
been excluded as passing references in reviews of books by others. Moreover, inasmuch as I came across the 
<hi rend="i">European Magazine</hi> notice while looking for something else, I concluded that a systematic search
of periodicals might turn up a few more items to add to the items reprinted by G. E. Bentley, Jr., in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford, 1969). Blake’s name does appear, for example, in the lists of painters
and engravers in Leigh Hunt’s <hi rend="i">Literary Pocket Book</hi> for some though not all of the annual
issues of that pocket diary. 
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>