<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>6.4.connolly</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Songs of Innocence Copy U</title>
                <author n="Connolly">Thomas E. Connolly</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">06.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_06">
        <body>
        	<pb id="p06-96" n="96"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-06-4-0003">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">
                                <hi rend="i">SONGS OF INNOCENCE</hi> COPY U</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Thomas E.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Connolly</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n30">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>On p. 214 of <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 19, Mary Ellen Reisner states that
Keynes-Wolf copy U of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> is not at the Houghton Library of Harvard
University but is owned by Mrs. Harold White. Unfortunately, Mrs. Reisner was given the same misinformation
that I was recently given when I wrote to the Houghton Library to purchase a set of 2″ × 2″ Kodachrome
slides of this copy.</p>
                    <p>Let me try to unscramble this bit of confusion. When Mrs. Reisner and I wrote to
Harvard, an unfortunate mixup occurred between K-W copy U of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (described
on p. 18 of <hi rend="i">Census</hi>) and K-W copy U of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
(described on p. 63 of the <hi rend="i">Census</hi>). Copy U of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> is
actually at Harvard in the Houghton Library. I quote from a letter dated 27 November 1972, from Miss Eleanor
M. Garvey of the Houghton Library: “We do have the Keynes-Wolf copy: U, not fully catalogued but finally
located.”</p>
                    <p>Keynes-Wolf copy U of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> did once
belong to the White family. It was recently donated by Miss Caroline Newton, of Berwyn, Pennsylvania, to
Princeton University where it now rests. For an account of this gift see Charles Ryskamp, “Library Notes: 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> and Miss Caroline Newton’s Blake Collection,” 
<hi rend="i">The Princeton University Library Chronicle</hi>, 29 (Winter 1968). <note id="n30">
                            <hi rend="i">Thomas E. Connolly is Professor of English at the State University of
New York at Buffalo. He is the author or editor of books on Joyce, Swinburne, and Hawthorne, and is currently
writing a book on Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</note>
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>