<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.1.toomey</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, William Blake: Book Illustrator,
Volume I</title>
                <author n="Toomey">Deirdre Toomey</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-1-0003">
                <pb id="p07-19" n="19"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">William Blake:
Book Illustrator: A Bibliography and Catalogue of the Commercial Engravings.</hi> Normal, Illinois: The
American Blake Foundation, 1972. Volume I: Plates Designed and Engraved by Blake. Pp. xvi + 58 + 82 pls.
$8</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Deirdre <name>Toomey</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n7" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi>, Volume I, is the first in a series
of three publications which will reproduce and catalogue all of Blake’s commercial engravings. The first
volume deals with designs invented and engraved by Blake, the second will deal with designs invented but not
engraved by Blake and the third with engravings by Blake after other artists. The editors, Roger R. Easson and
Robert N. Essick, have been cautious in their acceptance of attributions: thus doubtful works such as the
engravings in Bryant’s <hi rend="i">Mythology</hi>, Gough’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments, Vetusta
Monumenta</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi> have not been included in the first volume. They
have also been cautious in their classifications: “Laocoon,” the Wedgewood engravings and the non-pastoral
engravings in Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi> have all been excluded from the first volume on the
grounds—perhaps debatable in the case of the “Laocoon”—that they are not “original,” being “essentially
copies of another artist’s work.” These have been relegated to the third volume.</p>
                    <p>Clearly <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi> in its final form will be a
very useful work of reference for Blake scholars. The unusually large amount of bibliographical data is
helpful and this blending of “The descriptive bibliography and the print catalogue” is quite successful,
although the seven pages of bibliographical description which accompany the one plate of Herries’ 
<hi rend="i">Bible</hi> are, at first sight, somewhat daunting. It is enlightening to see the commercial
engravings, not just as isolated prints, but in the context of the books for which they were executed.</p>
                    <p>The editors main purpose is, however, as they have said, “the complete reproduction of
Blake’s commercial book illustrations” and their “prime concern is to assist the student of Blake’s art.”
Sadly the reproductions themselves are, for the most part, of rather low quality, and this may tend to modify
the usefulness of <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi> as a work of reference. Some of the
reproductions are highly inaccurate: those of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> engravings are particularly
bad. Here the values are distorted to such an extent that some pages, in particular 33, 35 and 72, look as if
they have been re-engraved by John Jackson. The thick black shadows that appear everywhere in the 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> reproductions are most unpleasing. This tendency towards excessive blackness is
also apparent in Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi> and in the Cowper plate, in both cases obscuring areas
of fine detail. The other reproductions are less positively bad, tending to omit detail rather than distort
values. Thus in “The Hiding of Moses” whole areas of detail are missing from the left-hand side of the design.
The same is true, to a lesser extent, of the fine detail in the Wollstonecraft illustrations. It is indeed
most unfortunate that so useful a work should be marred by technical defects, and that such scrupulous and
thorough editors as Roger Easson and Robert Essick should be so badly served by their reproductions. Yet, even
with these defects <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi> remains a valuable work of reference and
I look forward to seeing the next two volumes. <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="i">Deirdre Toomey is writing her doctoral thesis at the University of
London. Her most recent contribution to the</hi> Newsletter <hi rend="i">was</hi> “<hi rend="i">The States of
Plate 25 of</hi> Jerusalem” <hi rend="i">in #22.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>