<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.1.checklist</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="checklist">A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship, August 1972-September
1973</title>
                <author n="Candela">Gregory Candela</author>
                <author n="Field">Marta Field</author>
                <author n="Foreman">Foster Foreman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Executive Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants for Production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant for Subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-1-0002">
                <pb id="p07-11" n="11"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">A CHECKLIST OF RECENT BLAKE SCHOLARSHIP</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">Compiled by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Gregory</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Candela</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>, <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Marta</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Field</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>, <hi rend="b">and</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Foster</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Foreman</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n4" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>This is our fifth checklist, and the aim and format are basically the same as for the
checklists of the past two years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">*</ref>
Again this year we have included entries for items that are not scholarly, and again we have listed items
whose dates fall far outside our nominal August 1972-September 1973 boundaries.</p>
                    <p>As always, we would appreciate corrections and additions from our readers. But we would
especially like to appeal for help in compiling the checklist for next year. We do our best to cover all
journals and other periodicals, but our comprehensiveness depends to a much greater extent on our readers than
most of them realize, especially for out-of-the-way material. We want to list everything of interest,
including newspaper articles, filmstrips, videotapes, and ephemera. We are particularly grateful to authors
who send offprints for the checklist, because recent copies of journals can take a long time to reach the
shelves of the library. Past experience shows that the categories we are most likely to miss are book reviews,
sections of books whose titles do not mention Blake, and material in foreign languages. Please keep us in mind
when you run across items that should be in the checklist. <note id="n3">
                            <hi rend="i">The list is divided into these categories: New and Revised
Books/Reprinted Books/Articles and Sections of Books/Reviews/Films/Phonograph Records.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="i">Gregory Candela and Marta Field are graduate students at the
University of New Mexico and editorial assistants for the</hi> Newsletter. <hi rend="i">Foster Foreman is the
bibliographer for the</hi> Newsletter <hi rend="i">at Berkeley.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">New and Revised Books</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Blake, William. Songs of Innocence and of Experience. “Facsimile of sixteen
original plates etched by William Blake.” London: Academy Editions, 1971.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. William Blake’s Water-Colours: Illustrating the Poems of Thomas
Gray. Intro. and commen. by Sir Geoffrey Keynes. Chicago: J. Philip O’Hara, Inc., 1972. $25.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. See also Bloom, Bredvold, Feldman.</p>
                        <p>Bloom, Harold and Lionel Trilling, eds. The Oxford Anthology of English Literature
(General eds., Frank Kermode and John Hollander). 2 vols. cloth and pa.; 6 vols. pa. only. N.Y.: Oxford Univ.
Press, 1973. 2 vol. ed., cloth $9.95 each, paper $7.95 each; 6 vol. ed., $3.95 each. [175 illus.; Blake is in
Vol. 2, 10-124, 2 vol. ed.; Vol. 4, 6 vol. ed.]</p>
                        <p>Bredvold, Louis, et. al. Eighteenth Century Poetry and Prose. 3rd ed. N.Y.: Ronald
Press, 1973. $11.50. [Includes Blake]</p>
                        <p>Curran, Stuart and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., eds. Blake’s Sublime Allegory:
Essays on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Madison: Univ. of
Wisconsin Press, 1973. $17.50. [38 illus.] The contents are as follows: Jerome J. McGann, “The Aim of
Blake’s Prophecies and the Uses of Blake Criticism”; Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., “Opening the Seals:
Blake’s Epics and the Milton Tradition”; Ronald L. Grimes, “Time and Space in Blake’s Major Prophecies”;
Edward J. Rose, “Los, Pilgrim of Eternity”; Jean H. Hagstrum, “Babylon Revisited, or the Story of Luvah and
Vala”; Morton D. Paley, “The Figure of the Garment in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”; John E. Grant, “Visions in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>: A Consideration of Some Pictures
in the Manuscript”; Mary Lynn Johnson and Brian Wilkie, “On Reading <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Inscape
and Analogy”; Irene Tayler, “Say First! What Mov’d Blake? Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs and 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>”; James Rieger, “ ‘The Hem of Their Garments’: The Bard’s Song in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>”; W. J. T. Mitchell, “Blake’s Radical Comedy: Dramatic Structure as Meaning in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>”; Roger R. Easson, “William Blake and His Reader in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”; Stuart
Curran, “The Structures of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”; Karl Kroeber, “Delivering 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”</p>
                        <p>Duncan, Robert. The Truth and Life of Myth: An Essay in Essential Autobiography.
Fremont, Mich.: Sumac Press, 1968. [Blake is discussed; Blake’s “Ezekiel’s Vision” on cover]</p>
                        <pb id="p07-12" n="12"/>
                        <p>Essick, Robert N., ed. The Visionary Hand. Los Angeles: Hennessey and Ingalls,
1973. $7.95 paper. [A collection of essays on Blake’s art; contents not available for listing at
press-time]</p>
                        <p>Feldman, Burton and Robert D. Richardson. The Rise of Modern Mythology, 1680-1860.
Bloomington: Indiana Univ. Press, 1972. [Anthology and critical history that includes Blake]</p>
                        <p>Fletcher, Angus John Stewart. The Transcendental Masque: An Essay on Milton’s 
<hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell Univ. Press, 1972. [Blake’s illus. to <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> in
eight scenes inserted between pp. 256-57]</p>
                        <p>Gaunt, William. The Restless Century: Painting in Britain, 1800-1900. New York:
Praeger-Phaidon, 1972. $25; £6.5. [171 pictures]</p>
                        <p>Gillam, David George. William Blake. British Authors: Introductory Critical Series.
London: Cambridge Univ. Press, 1973. £3.70, $12.95; pa. £1.30, $4.95.</p>
                        <p>Grimes, Ronald L. The Divine Imagination: William Blake’s Major Prophetic
Visions. ATLA Monograph Series, No. 1. Metuchen, N.J.: Scarecrow Press, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Keynes, Sir Geoffrey. See Blake.</p>
                        <p>Kremen, Kathryn R. The Imagination of the Resurrection: The Poetic Continuity of a
Religious Motif in Donne, Blake, and Yeats. Lewisburg, Penn.: Bucknell Univ. Press, 1972. $15.
[Illustrated]</p>
                        <p>Nelson, Cary. The Incarnate Word: Literature as Verbal Space. Urbana: Univ. of
Illinois Press, 1973. $10.00. [Includes Blake]</p>
                        <p>Paley, Morton D. and Michael Phillips, eds. William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir
Geoffrey Keynes. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973. £10.50. [83 illus.] The contents of this volume are as
follows: Michael Phillips, “Blake’s Early Poetry”; David Bindman, “Blake’s ‘Gothicised Imagination’
and the History of England”; Robert N. Essick, “The Altering Eye: Blake’s Vision in the 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> Designs”; F. R. Leavis, “Justifying One’s Valuation of Blake”; Josephine Miles,
“Blake’s Frame of Language”; Michael J. Tolley, “Blake’s Songs of Spring”; Jean H. Hagstrum, “Christ’s
Body”: G. Wilson Knight, “The Chapel of Gold”; David V. Erdman with Tom Dargan and Marlene Deverell-Van Meter,
“Reading the Illuminations of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>”; Janet Warner,
“Blake’s Figures of Despair: Man in his Spectre’s Power”; Morris Eaves, “The Title-page of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>”; John Beer, “Blake, Coleridge, and Wordsworth: Some Cross-currents and
Parallels, 1789-1805”; Morton D. Paley, “William Blake, The Prince of the Hebrews, and The Woman Clothed with
the Sun”; Martin Butlin, “Blake, the Varleys, and the Graphic Telescope”; Raymond Lister, “References to Blake
in Samuel Palmer’s Letters”; Suzanne R. Hoover, “William Blake in the Wilderness: A Closer Look at his
Reputation, 1827-1863”; G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Geoffrey Keynes’s Work on Blake: <hi rend="i">Fons et
Origo</hi>, and a Checklist of Writings on Blake by Geoffrey Keynes, 1910-1972.”</p>
                        <p>Sachs, Arieh, ed. The English Grotesque: An Anthology from Langland to Joyce.
Jerusalem: Israel Universities Press, 1969. [Pp. 155-61: Memorable Fancies from <hi rend="i">MHH</hi>; “I Saw
a Chapel All of Gold”; <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon.</hi> Pls. 15 and 42: “Ghost of a Flea” and
“Nebuchadnezzar.” Blake also in Introduction]</p>
                        <p>Tomory, Peter. <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of Henry Fuseli.</hi> N.Y.: Praeger,
1972. $25. [Illustrated]</p>
                        <p>Wagenknecht, David. Blake’s Night: William Blake and the Idea of Pastoral.
Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard Univ. Press; Belknap Press, 1973. $12.</p>
                        <p>Wright, Andrew. Blake’s Job: A Commentary. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1972. $9. [23
illustrations]</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Reprinted Books</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Berger, P. William Blake: Poet and Mystic, Studies in Blake Series, No. 3. 1914;
rpt. N.Y.: Haskell House, 1969.</p>
                        <p>Berger, Pierre. William Blake: Poet and Mystic, trans. D. H. Connor. 1914; rpt.
Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft, 1973.</p>
                        <p>Binyon, Laurence. Followers of William Blake. 1925; rpt. N.Y.: Benjamin Blom,
1972.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. Blake’s Poetical Works. Ed. John Sampson. 1905; rpt.
Kennebunkpart, Me.: Milford House, 1971.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. See also Campbell, Clarke, Keynes.</p>
                        <p>Bronowski, J. William Blake: A Man without a Mask. 1947(?); rpt. N.Y.: Haskell
House, 1969.</p>
                        <p>Campbell, Kathleen W., ed. An Anthology of English Poetry: Dryden to Blake. 1930;
rpt. Freeport, N.Y.: Books for Libraries, 1971.</p>
                        <p>Clarke, John H. William Blake on the Lord’s Prayer: 1757-1827, Studies in Blake
Series, No. 5. 1927; rpt. N.Y.: Haskell House, 1971.</p>
                        <p>De Selincourt, Basil. William Blake. 1909; rpt. N.Y.: Cooper Square, 1972.</p>
                        <p>De Selincourt, Basil. William Blake. 1909; rpt. Port Washington, N.Y.: Kennikat,
1971.</p>
                        <p>Dutt, Sukumar. The Supernatural in English Romantic Poetry, 1780-1830. 1938; rpt.
Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Ellis, Edwin J. The Real Blake. 1906; rpt. N.Y.: Haskell House, 1970.</p>
                        <p>Garnett, Richard. William Blake: Painter and Poet, Studies in Blake Series, No. 3.
1895; rpt. N.Y.: Haskell House, 1970.</p>
                        <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. The Life of William Blake. Ed. W. Graham Robertson. 1907;
rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. The Life of William Blake. 2 vols. 1880; rpt. N.Y.: Phaeton,
1969.</p>
                        <p>Keynes, Sir Geoffrey. Blake Studies: Notes on His Life and Works in Seventeen
Chapters. 1949; rpt. N.Y.: Haskell House, 1971.</p>
                        <p>Keynes, Sir Geoffrey. William Blake’s Engravings. 1950; rpt. N.Y.: Cooper Square,
1972.</p>
                        <p>Kortelling, Jacoming. Mysticism in Blake and Wordsworth, Studies in Poetry Series,
No. 38. 1928; rpt. N.Y.: Haskell House, 1969.</p>
                        <p>Lindsay, Jack. William Blake: Creative Will and the Poetic Imagination. 1929; rpt.
N.Y.: Haskell House, 1970.</p>
                        <p>Norman, Hubert J. Cowper and Blake. 1913; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library
Editions, 1972.</p>
                        <pb id="p07-13" n="13"/>
                        <p>Rossetti, William Michael. Lives of Famous Poets. 1878; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.:
Folcroft Library Editions, 1971.</p>
                        <p>Rudd, Margaret. Organized Innocence: The Story of Blake’s Prophetic Books. 1956;
rpt. Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1973.</p>
                        <p>Singer, June K. The Unholy Bible. 1970; rpt. N.Y.: Harper, 1973. $2.95. [Paperback
rpt.]</p>
                        <p>Symons, Arthur. William Blake. 1907; rpt. N.Y.: Cooper Square, 1970.</p>
                        <p>Wicksteed, Joseph H. Blake’s Vision of the Book of Job, Studies in Blake Series,
No. 3. 1924; rpt. N.Y.: Haskell House, 1970.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Articles</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>SEE ALSO THE COLLECTIONS OF ESSAYS LISTED ABOVE UNDER CURRAN, ESSICK, AND
PALEY.</p>
                        <p>Anon. “The Tate Gallery, London, Exhibit.” Art and Artists, 6 (Jan. 1972), 46-47,
49. (Designs to Gray’s poems]</p>
                        <p>Anon. “Two Shows at Yale.” Art Journal, 31 (Spring 1973), 303. [Designs to Gray’s
poems]</p>
                        <p>Anon. “William Blake’s Watercolour Designs Illustrating Gray’s Poems—and Mr.
Paul Mellon.” Connoisseur, 179 (Jan. 1972), 10-14.</p>
                        <p>Baine, Rodney. “Blake and Defoe.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Fall 1972), 51-53.</p>
                        <p>Baine, Rodney. “Thel’s Northern Gate.” Philological Quarterly, 51 (Oct. 1972),
957-61.</p>
                        <p>Baird, Julian. “Swinburne, Sade, and Blake: The Pleasure-Pain Paradox.” Victorian
Poetry, 9 (Spring-Summer 1971), 49-75.</p>
                        <p>Beer, John B. “Blake, Mr. Tolley and the Scholarly Imagination.” Southern Review:
An Australian Journal of Literary Studies, 4 (1971), 247-55.</p>
                        <p>Beer, John. “Brief Riposte.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 19-23.</p>
                        <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> Copperplates.” Library, 26
(Sept. 1971), 234-41.</p>
                        <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “A Handlist of Works by William Blake in the Department of
Prints and Drawings of the British Museums.” With supplementary notes. Blake Newsletter, 5 (Spring 1972),
223-58.</p>
                        <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “A ‘New’ Blake Engraving in Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Physiognomy.</hi>” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Fall 1972), 48-49.</p>
                        <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Thorne Blake Collection at the Pierpont Morgan Library,
New York.” Apollo, NS 94 (Nov. 1971), 416.</p>
                        <p>Bishop, Morchard. “The Poet and the Attorney: The Story of a Legacy.” The Book
Collector, 21 (Summer 1972), 245-54. [A discussion of a painting by Romney whose subjects are Flaxman, Hayley,
and Hayley’s son; the article mentions Blake, who was working for Hayley while Hayley was arguing with the
attorney Thomas Greene for possession of the painting]</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. “From the Note-Book” [pp. 68, 68-69, 69-70, 82-87]. Tree: 1, Winter
1970. [Christopher Books, 1819 Sycamore, Canyon Rd., Santa Barbara, Ca.]</p>
                        <p>Bloom, Harold. Yeats. N.Y.: Oxford Univ. Press, 1970. [Chapter 5, “Blake and
Yeats”; Blake mentioned throughout]</p>
                        <p>Bly, Robert. “Looking for Dragon Smoke.” The Seventies, No. 1 (Spring 1972),
3-8.</p>
                        <p>Brogan, Howard O. “Relevance in Literary Study.” CEA Critic, 33 (May 1971),
23-24.</p>
                        <p>Butlin, Martin. “A ‘Minute Particular’ Particularized: Blake’s Second Set of
Illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi>” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Fall 1972), 44-46.</p>
                        <p>Butlin, Martin. “William Blake in the Hubert P. Horne Collection.” Blake
Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 19-21.</p>
                        <p>Chaffee, Alan J. “The Rendezvous of Mind.” Wordsworth Circle, 3 (Autumn 1972),
196-203.</p>
                        <p>Chayes, Irene. “Brief Riposte.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 23-24.</p>
                        <p>Curran, Stuart. “Blake and the Gnostic Hyle: A Double Negative.” Blake Studies, 4
(Spring 1972), 117-33.</p>
                        <p>DiSalvo, Jackie. “William Blake on the Unholy Alliance: Satanic Freedom and Godly
Repression in Liberal Society.” Wordsworth Circle, 3 (Autumn 1972), 212-22.</p>
                        <p>Doherty, F. M. J. “Blake’s ‘The Tyger’ and Henry Needler.” Philological
Quarterly, 46 (Oct. 1967), 566-67.</p>
                        <p>Eaves, Morris. “A Reading of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>, plates 17-20: On and Under the Estate of the West.” Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 81-116.</p>
                        <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake and the Tradition of Reproductive Engraving.” Blake
Studies, 5 (Fall 1972), 59-103.</p>
                        <p>Essick, Robert N. “A Preliminary Design for Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi>”
Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 9-13.</p>
                        <p>Firestone, Evan R. “John Linnell and the Picture Merchants.” The Connoisseur, 182
(Feb. 1973), 124-34.</p>
                        <p>Fletcher, Ian. “The Ellis-Yeats-Blake Manuscript Cluster.” The Book Collector, 21
(Spring 1972), 72-94. [4 plates]</p>
                        <p>Freiberg, S. K. “The Fleece-Lined Clock: Time, Space, and the Artistic Experience
in William Blake.” Dalhousie Review, 49 (Autumn 1969), 404-15.</p>
                        <p>Gage, S. “Blake’s Newton.” Journal of Warburg and Courtauld Institute, 34 (1971),
372-77.</p>
                        <p>Garnett, David. “The Appendix.” The Book Collector, 21 (Spring 1972), 54-58. [On
Sir Geoffrey Keynes]</p>
                        <p>Gibson, William A. and Thomas L. Minnick. “William Blake and Henry Emlyn’s 
<hi rend="i">Proposition for a New Order in Architecture</hi>: A New Plate.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972),
13-17.</p>
                        <p>Grant, John E. “On Mary Ellen Reisner’s Locations of Copy U of <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence</hi> and Copy D of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> from <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>
19.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 22.</p>
                        <p>Grant, John E. “The Visionary Perspective of Ezekiel.” Blake Studies, 4 (Spring
1972), 153-57.</p>
                        <p>Harper, George M. (Florida State). “The Odyssey of the Soul in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” [A paper read at the 1971 South Atlantic Modern Language Association convention and
reported in PMLA, Sept. 1972, p. 642]</p>
                        <p>Hart-Davis, Rupert. “A Little Injudicious Levity.” The Book Collector, 21 (Spring
1972), 51-53. [On Sir Geoffrey Keynes]</p>
                        <pb id="p07-14" n="14"/>
                        <p>Helmstadter, Thomas H. “Blake and the Age of Reason: Spectres in the 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” Blake Studies, 5 (Fall 1972), 105-39.</p>
                        <p>Hoover, Suzanne R. “Pictures at the Exhibitions.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer
1972), 6-12.</p>
                        <p>Horovitz, Michael. “Blake and the Voice of the Bard in Our Time.” Books, 10 (Winter
1972), n.p.</p>
                        <p>Horovitz, Michael. “The Need for the Non-Literary.” Times Literary Supplement, 29
Dec. 1972, pp. 1582-83.</p>
                        <p>James, G. Ingli. “Blake’s Woodcuts, Plain and Coloured.” Times Literary
Supplement, 18 May 1973, p. 564.</p>
                        <p><corr type="emend">Ketterer, David.</corr> “New Worlds for Old: The Apocalyptic Imagination, Science, Fiction,
and American Literature.” Mosaic, 5 (Fall 1971), 37-57.</p>
                        <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. “Blake’s Engravings for Gay’s Fables.” The Book Collector, 21
(Spring 1972), 59-64. [12 plates included]</p>
                        <p>King, James. “The Meredith Family, Thomas Taylor, and William Blake.” Studies in
Romanticism, 11 (Spring 1972), 153-57.</p>
                        <p>Kjellberg, P. “Le primier coup d’audace des peintres anglais.” Connaissance Arts,
240 (Feb. 1972), 87.</p>
                        <p>Leary, D. J. “Shaw’s Blakean Vision: A Dialectical Approach to 
<hi rend="i">Heartbreak House.</hi>” Modern Drama, 15 (May 1972), 89-103.</p>
                        <p>Lister, Raymond. “A Fragmentary Copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</hi>” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 19.</p>
                        <p>Lister, Raymond. “Two Blake Drawings and a Letter from Samuel Palmer.” Blake
Newsletter, 6 (Fall 1972), 53-54.</p>
                        <p>Lister, Raymond. “The Writings of Samuel Palmer.” Gazette des Beaux-Arts, 81 (April
1973), 253-56.</p>
                        <p>Lodge, David. “ ‘Crow’ and the Cartoons.” Critical Quarterly, 13 (Spring 1971),
37-42, 68.</p>
                        <p>Merewether, Mary A. “<hi rend="i">The Burden of Tyre</hi> and Brennen’s 
<hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (1913).” Southerly, 30 (1970), 267-84. [A poem cycle showing influence of Blake]</p>
                        <p>Metcalf, Francis Wood. “Reason and ‘Urizen’: The Pronunciation of Blakean
Names.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 17-18.</p>
                        <p>Meynell, Francis. “A Reminiscence.” The Book Collector, 21 (Spring 1972), 50. [On
Sir Geoffrey Keynes]</p>
                        <p>Minnick, Thomas L. See Gibson.</p>
                        <p>Moss, John G. “Structural Form in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
of Albion.</hi>” Humanities Association Bulletin, 22 (Spring 1971), 9-18.</p>
                        <p>Ower, John. “The Epic Mythologies of Shelley and Keats.” Wascana Review, 4 (1969),
61-72.</p>
                        <p>Raine, Kathleen. “Blake and the Education of Childhood.” The Southern Review, 8
(Spring 1972), 253-72.</p>
                        <p>Raine, Kathleen. “Blake: Maker of Myths.” In Man, Myth and Magic: An Illustrated
Encyclopedia of the Supernatural. Ed. Richard Cavendish. N.Y.: Marshall Cavendish Corp., 1970. II, 278-85
[Color illus. included; see also I, 3]</p>
                        <p>Rose, Edward J. “Goodbye to Orc and All That.” Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972),
135-51.</p>
                        <p>Rose, Edward J. “Wheels within Wheels in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”
Studies in Romanticism, 11 (Winter 1972), 36-47.</p>
                        <p>Rosenblum, Robert. “German Romantic Painting in International Perspective.” Yale
University Art Gallery Bulletin, 33 (Oct. 1972), 23-36.</p>
                        <p>Sandler, Florence. “The Iconoclastic Enterprise: Blake’s Critique of
‘Milton’s Religion.’ ” Blake Studies, 5 (Fall 1972), 13-57.</p>
                        <p>Sharp, Dennis. “Blake Into Print.” The Royal Institute of British Architects
Journal, 80 (Feb. 1972), 80. [Designs for Gray’s poems: Tate Gallery exhibit]</p>
                        <p>Siemens, Reynold. “Boarders in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Little Girl
Lost-Found.</hi>” Humanities Association Bulletin, 22 (Spring 1971), 35-43.</p>
                        <p>Sutherland, John. “Blake: A Crisis of Love and Jealousy.” PMLA, 87 (May 1972),
424-31.</p>
                        <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie. “Blake’s Art of Crypsis: <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>
and Genesis.” Blake Studies, 5 (Fall 1972), 141-64.</p>
                        <p>Tayler, Irene. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs.” Blake Studies, 4
(Spring 1972), 45-80.</p>
                        <p>Todd, Ruthven. “<hi rend="i">The Battle of Ai.</hi>” Paul Grinke (London) Catalogue
Five, 1972, pp. 17-19. [Illus.]</p>
                        <p>Todd, Ruthven. “A Recollection of George Richmond by His Grandson.” Blake
Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 24.</p>
                        <p>Toomey, Deirdre. “The States of Plate 25 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Blake
Newsletter, 6 (Fall 1972), 46-48.</p>
                        <p>Walling, William. “The Death of God: William Blake’s Version.” Dalhousie Review,
48 (Summer 1968), 237-50.</p>
                        <p>Welch, Dennis G. “<hi rend="i">America</hi> and Atlantis: Blake’s Ambivalent
Millenialism.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Fall 1972), 50.</p>
                        <p>Whittaker, Edward Keith. “Sorrow and the Flea.” Tri-Quarterly, 19 (Autumn 1970),
35-55. [Dahlberg compared to Blake]</p>
                        <p>Wilton, Andrew. “Blake and the Antique.” [A lecture given at the Victoria and
Albert Lecture Theatre, 16 Nov. 1972]</p>
                        <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. “Blake and Tradition: A Prefatory Note.” Blake
Studies, 5 (Fall 1972), 7-11.</p>
                        <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. “ ‘Sublime Allegory’: Blake’s Epic Manifesto
and the Milton Tradition.” Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 15-44.</p>
                        <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. “William Blake: Illustrator-Interpreter of 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Regained.</hi>” In Calm of Mind: Tercentenery Essays on Paradise Regained and Samson
Agonistis. Cleveland: Case Western Reserve Univ. Press, 1971. Pp. 93-132. [Also Appendix A, “Illustrators of
<hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> and their Subjects: 1713-1816,” pp. 309-29; Appendix B, “A Catalogue of
Blake’s Illustrations to Milton,” pp. 331-42]</p>
                        <p>Won, Ko. “The Symbolists’ Influence on Japanese Poetry.” Comparative Literature
Studies, 8 (Sept. 1971), 254-65.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Adams, Hazard. William Blake: A Reading of the Shorter Poems. Reviewed by Henri
Lemaitre, “A propos de William Blake,” Etudes Anglaise, 20 (July-Sept. 1967), 289-96.</p>
                        <p>Adams, Hazard, ed. William Blake: Jerusalem, Selected Poems and Prose. Reviewed by
Thomas H. Helmstadter, Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 163-66.</p>
                        <pb id="p07-15" n="15"/>
                        <p>Beer, John B. Blake’s Visionary Universe. Reviewed by Michael J. Tolley, “A
Superficial Vision,” Southern Review: An Australian Journal of Literary Studies, 4 (1971), 242-46.</p>
                        <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne. Reviewed by
Robert Essick, Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 26-28.</p>
                        <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. Vala or The Four Zoas. Reviewed by Henri Lemaitre, “A propos de
William Blake,” Etudes Anglaise, 20 (July-Sept. 1967), 289-96.</p>
                        <p>Bindman, David. William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the Fitzwilliam
Museum. Reviewed by Morchard Bishop, The Book Collector, 21 (Spring 1972), 133-34; Robert R. Wark, Blake
Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 160-62.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. See Adams, Bentley, Bindman, Bogan Butlin, Keynes, Stevenson,
Wittreich.</p>
                        <p>Bogan, Nancy, ed. The Book of Thel: A Facsimile and Critical Text. Reviewed by
Andrew Wright, Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 162-63.</p>
                        <p>Boutang, Pierre. William Blake. Reviewed by Simone Pignard, Blake Newsletter, 6
(Fall 1972), 55-56.</p>
                        <p>Butlin, Martin, ed. Blake-Varley Sketchbook of 1818. Reviewed by D. Irwin,
Burlington Magazine, 113 (June 1971), 341-42.</p>
                        <p>Butlin, Martin. William Blake: A Complete Catalogue of Works in the Tate Gallery,
2nd ed. Reviewed by Michael J. Tolley, Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 28-31; Robert R. Wark, Blake
Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 160-62.</p>
                        <p>DeMott, Benjamin. Blake and Manchild [tape recording]. Reviewed by Morris Eaves,
Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 25-26.</p>
                        <p>Denvir, B. “Sensibility and Cybernetics: Some Recent Books about Art.” Art
International, 16 (Feb. 1972), 64-66. [Some recent studies on Blake noted]</p>
                        <p>Erdman, David V. and John E. Grant, eds. Visionary Forms Dramatic. Reviewed by
Daniel Hughes, “The Luck of William Blake,” Massachusetts Review, 13 (Autumn 1972), 707-25.</p>
                        <p>Gillham, D. G. William Blake. Reviewed in Times Literary Supplement, 18 May 1973,
p. 564.</p>
                        <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. William Blake, Poet and Painter: An Introduction to the
Illuminated Verse. Reviewed by Henri Lemaitre, “A propos de William Blake,” Etudes Anglaise, 20 (July-Sept.
1967), 289-96.</p>
                        <p>Hirsch, E. D. Innocence and Experience: An Introduction to Blake. Reviewed by Henri
Lemaitre, “A propos de William Blake,” Etudes Anglaise, 20 (July-Sept. 1967), 289-96.</p>
                        <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. All Religions Are One; There Is No Natural Religion (Trianon
Press for the William Blake Trust). Reviewed by Kay Parkhurst Easson, Blake Studies, 5 (Fall 1972),
168-75.</p>
                        <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. Blake Studies: Essays on His Life and Work, 2nd ed. Reviewed by
Robert F. Gleckner, Blake Studies, 5 (Fall 1972), 165-68.</p>
                        <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. Songs of Innocence and of Experience: Shewing the Two
Contrary States of the Human Soul. Reviewed by John E. Grant, Philological Quarterly, 47 (Oct. 1968),
571-80.</p>
                        <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. William Blake’s Water-Colour Designs for Gray’s Poems—A
Commemorative Catalogue. Reviewed by Morton D. Paley, Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 33-34.</p>
                        <p>Lister, Raymond. British Romantic Art. Reviewed in Times Literary Supplement, 4 May
1973, pp. 499-500.</p>
                        <p>Paley, Morton D. Energy and Imagination. Reviewed by John E. Grant, English
Language Notes, 9 (Mar. 1972), 210-16; Daniel Hughes, “The Luck of William Blake,” Massachusetts Review, 13
(Autumn 1972), 717-25; J. Janssens, Dutch University Review (1972-73), 103.</p>
                        <p>Raine, Kathleen. Blake and Tradition. Reviewed by C. Gellhar, Pantheon, 30 (July
1972), n.p.; Ants Oras, “Kathleen Raine, The Ancient Springs, and Blake,” Saturday Review, 80 (Winter 1972),
200-11; D. Weeks, Journal of Aesthetics, 29 (Spring 1971), 424-25.</p>
                        <p>Raine, Kathleen. William Blake. Reviewed by J. C. Battye, Art and Artists, 6 (July
1971), 68; Michael Tolley, Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 28-31.</p>
                        <p>Singer, June K. The Unholy Bible: A Psychological Interpretation of William Blake.
Reviewed by Robert L. Corey. Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 167-68.</p>
                        <p>Stevenson, W. H., ed. The Poems of William Blake. Reviewed by Anne Kostelanetz
Mellor, Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 32-33.</p>
                        <p>Tayler, Irene. Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Gray. Reviewed by Hugh
Honour, New York Review of Books, 25 Jan. 1973, pp. 34-35; Daniel Hughes, “The Luck of William Blake,”
Massachusetts Review, 13 (Autumn 1972), 717-25; W. J. T. Mitchell, Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 159-60;
Morton D. Paley, Criticism, 14 (Winter 1972), 93-96.</p>
                        <p>Todd, Ruthven. William Blake The Artist. Reviewed by K. Bazarov, Art &amp; Artists,
7 (May 1972), 56-57; H. R. Wackrill, Blake Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 168-69.</p>
                        <p>Tomory, Peter. The Life and Art of Henry Fuseli. Reviewed by Hugh Honour, New York
Review of Books, 25 Jan. 1973, pp. 34-35; Times Literary Supplement, 4 May 1973, pp. 499-500.</p>
                        <p>Vogler, Thomas A. Preludes to Vision: The Epic Venture in Blake, Wordsworth, Keats,
and Hart Crane. Reviewed by Andy P. Antippas, Blake Newsletter, 6 (Summer 1972), 34-36; Jenijoy LaBelle, Blake
Studies, 4 (Spring 1972), 163-64.</p>
                        <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. The Romantics on Milton: Formal Essays and Critical
Asides. Reviewed by Andy P. Antippas, Blake Newsletter, 6 (Fall 1972), 55.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Films</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Tyger, Tyger. BBC-TV, London, 1969. 30 minutes, 16 mm. Released in the U.S. by
Time-Life Films.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">Records</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Vaughan Williams, Ralph. Ten Blake Songs. England: Argo ZR6 732. [Robert Tea,
tenor, Philip Ledger, piano, and Neil Black, oboe]</p>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>