<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.2.grant</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Illuminated Books in the Cincinnati Art Museum</title>
                <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
                <author n="Johnson">Mary Lynn Johnson</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-2-0003">
                <pb id="p07-40" n="40"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">Illuminated Books in the Cincinnati Art Museum</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>JOHN E. <name>GRANT</name>
                        </docAuthor> &amp; <docAuthor>MARY LYNN <name>JOHNSON</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n5" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <figure n="thel.n.p1-2" id="thel.n.illbk.01" work-copy="thel.n" rend="db" width="725" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>THE<lb/>
	BOOK<lb/>
	of<lb/>
	THEL<lb/>
	The Author &amp; Printer Will m Blake. 1789.</figTranscr>
</figure>
                    <pb id="p07-41" n="41"/>
                    <p>Until the forthcoming Bentley <hi rend="i">Census</hi> appears, it is helpful to get
information about the present location of illuminated books listed as untraced or as privately owned in the
Keynes-Wolf <hi rend="i">Census.</hi> Whether any particular location is desirable could be debated. If the
most important consideration were accessibility of at least one Blake original to the largest number of people
in the widest possible area, all should rejoice to hear that an illuminated book has found a home outside one
of the well-known Blake repositories. But given the practical necessity of arranging to study several works
during a single research trip, as well as the importance of comparing more than one copy of the same work, the
scholar may find himself hoping that a sale or a bequest will send a book to one of the great public
collections where Blake’s works are already concentrated. Happily, democratic and scholarly interests are
not always at odds: an account of the holdings of the Cincinnati Art Museum contains good news for everyone.
Somewhat remote from other Blake collections but worth an excursion from anywhere, Cincinnati has an exquisite
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, a long-untraced <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, and a closely contemporary 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Nancy Bogen, ed., William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel: A Facsimile and a
Critical Text</hi> (Providence and New York, 1971), notes that <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> copy N is now in the
Cincinnati collection (accession number 1969.510—as the gift of John J. Emery). Since Bogen’s color
descriptions are sometimes unreliable, one should consult the Keynes-Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi> for an idea
of the brilliance of this copy. Only the Rosenwald copy O, on which the Blake Trust Facsimile is based, is a
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> of comparable magnificence, though in quieter and calmer tones. If a facsimile of copy
N were made by the Trianon Press—or even if it were as well reproduced as the Dent volumes—we would have a
clearer idea of the power and range of Blake’s coloring. These intimately related copies differ strikingly:
both sumptuously painted in Blake’s later style, both done on Ruse &amp; Turners paper watermarked 1815,
copy N is impressive for its splendor, copy O for its refinement. Added details also vary: copy N has more
birds, water, and peculiar cloud effects; copy O more trees and roots [see illus.].</p>
                    <p>But on-the-spot comparison of originals is obviously a far better method of study than
comparison of notes and facsimiles, and the Cincinnati Art Museum also affords an opportunity for this kind of
work. Its <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and the Innocence section of its <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi> are both on paper watermarked J WHATMAN/1808, both arranged in the same
order, both decorated with gold. The <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> may be identified as copy S of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, formerly in the George C. Smith, Jr. collection, but listed as untraced in
the <hi rend="i">Census.</hi> The following addenda and corrections to the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> account
may be presented:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
						<q>
S 28 plates on 28 leaves. Watermark J WHATMAN/1808 *on verso of pl. 25, “Infant Joy,” and fragmentary
watermarks on 3 other pages. Printed in shades of brown, gray, and black, with some greenish-black.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><hi rend="s">G-J</hi> [Called simply “gray” in the <hi rend="i">Census</hi>, “gray,
greenish-brown, and brown” in the Smith sale catalogue.] *A few letters strengthened by hand. Considerable
foxing. Carefully painted in water colors and gold, with gold usually applied to titles.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><hi rend="s">G-J</hi> [The <hi rend="i">Census</hi> term “subdued” understates the
actual effect of the coloring.] Foliated by Blake 2-28. Arrangement: 1-3, 15, 10-11, 8, 29-30, 9, 13, 20, 21,
28, 18-19, 12, 23, 16-17, 27, 25-26, 22, 14, 31, 4, 24. Lacks 5-7. [Because the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> uses
a different standard of pagination for <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> from that of <hi rend="i">Innocence and
Experience</hi>, it is not evident that this order exactly corresponds to that in <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi>, copy S, also Cincinnati, as described below.] Blake’s foliation shows that
a frontispiece, which has recently been supplied from another source, was originally included; *the present
frontispiece, badly foxed, measures 18.8 × <note id="n5">
                                <hi rend="i">The writings of John E. Grant (University of Iowa) on Blake have
been widely published. He is now collaborating with E. J. Rose, M. J. Tolley, and D. V. Erdman on the
Clarendon Press edition of</hi> Blake’s Designs for Young’s Night Thoughts. <hi rend="i">Mary Lynn Johnson
(Georgia State University) has published on Wordsworth in</hi> SiR, <hi rend="i">Blake in</hi> JEGP. 
<hi rend="i">Her essay on Blake and emblem literature recently appeared in</hi> Huntington Library Quarterly, 
<hi rend="i">her note on</hi> Milton <hi rend="i">in</hi> Blake Studies. <hi rend="i">Johnson and Grant are
working on a comprehensive study of the copies of</hi> The Book of Thel.</note>
                            <pb id="p07-42" n="42"/>
                            <figure n="thel.n.p2-3" id="thel.n.illbk.02" work-copy="thel.n" rend="db" width="741" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>2<lb/>
	THEL<lb/>
	I<lb/>
	The daughters of Mne Seraphim led round their sunny flocks,<lb/>
	All but the youngest, she in paleness sought the secret air.<lb/>
	To fade away like morning beauty from her mortal day:<lb/>
	Down by the river of Adona her soft voice is heard:<lb/>
	And thus her gentle lamentation falls like morning dew.<lb/>
	O life of this our spring! why fades the lotus of the water?<lb/>
	Why fade these children of the spring? born but to smile &amp; fall.<lb/>
	Ah! Thel is like a watry bow, and like a parting cloud.<lb/>
	Like a reflection in a glass, like shadows in the water.<lb/>
	Like dreams of infants, like a smile upon an infants face,<lb/>
	Like the doves voice, like transient day. like music in the air:<lb/>
	Ah! gentle may I lay me down, and gentle rest my head,<lb/>
	And gentle sleep the sleep of death, and gentle hear the voice<lb/>
	Of him that walketh in the garden in the evening time.<lb/>
	The Lilly of the valley breathing in the humble grass<lb/>
	Answerd the lovely maid and said: I am a watry weed,<lb/>
	And I am very small, and love to dwell in lowly vales:<lb/>
	So weak, the gilded butterfly scarce perches on my head<lb/>
	Yet I am visited from heaven, and he that smiles on all.<lb/>
	Walks in the valley, and each morn over me spreads his hand<lb/>
	Saying, rejoice thou humble grass. thou new born lilly flower,<lb/>
	Thou gentle maid of silent valleys. and of modest brooks:<lb/>
	For thou shalt be clothed in light, and fed with morning manna;<lb/>
	Till summers heat melts thee beside the fountains and the springs<lb/>
	To flourish in eternal vales: then why should Thel complain,<lb/>
	Why</figTranscr>
</figure>
                            <figure n="thel.n.p3-4" id="thel.n.illbk.03" work-copy="thel.n" rend="db" width="747" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>2<lb/>
	Why should the mistress of the vales of Har, utter a sigh.<lb/>
	She ceasd &amp; smild in tears, then sat down in her silver shrine.<lb/>
	Thel answerd, O thou little virgin of the peaceful valley.<lb/>
	Giving to those that cannot crave, the voiceless, the o’erfired.<lb/>
	Thy breath doth nourish the innocent lamb. he smells thy milky garments,<lb/>
	He crops thy flowers. while thou sittest smiling in his face,<lb/>
	Wiping his mild and meekin mouth from all contagious taints.<lb/>
	Thy wine doth purify the golden honey, thy perfume,<lb/>
	Which thou dost scatter on every little blade of grass that springs,<lb/>
	Revives the milked cow, &amp; tames the fire-breathing steed.<lb/>
	But Thel is like a faint cloud kindled at the rising sun;<lb/>
	I vanish from my pearly throne, and who shall find my place<lb/>
	Queen of the vales the Lilly answerd, ask the tender cloud,<lb/>
	And it shall tell thee why it glitters in the morning sky.<lb/>
	And why it scatters its bright beauty thro’ the humid air.<lb/>
	Descend O little cloud &amp; hover before the eyes of Thel,<lb/>
	The Cloud descended. and the Lilly bowd her modest head:<lb/>
	And went to mind her numerous charge among the verdant grass.</figTranscr>
                                <head>The pictures: Reproduced with the article are plates ii (the
title-page), 1, and 2 of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> copy N, Cincinnati Art Museum, gift of John J.
Emery.</head>
                                <figDesc>By permission.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
                            <pb id="p07-43" n="43"/>
13.5 cm. and is printed in green. Size: varies from 19.5 × 14.5 cm. to 20.1 × 15.0 cm.,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><hi rend="s">G-J</hi> untrimmed. The leaves, whch show the original stitch-holes,
*were formerly mounted on sunk mats and bound in full brown crushed levant morocco, gilt, by Riviere &amp;
Son. Now the pages are mounted on large mats 48.5 × 34.5 cm. and are kept in two boxes.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><hi rend="s">G-J</hi> [The earlier provenance, so far as it is known, is given in
the <hi rend="i">Census.</hi>] After it was sold to Gannon for $2300 as lot 16 in the George C. Smith sale of
1938, *it was acquired by Rouillier and resold in 1941 to Herbert Greer French, who bequeathed it to the
Cincinnati Art Museum, where the accession number is 1943.559.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><hi
rend="s">G-J</hi>
						</q>
                        <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Extensive corrections or additions to the 
<hi rend="i">Census</hi> are marked with an asterisk at the beginning and a G-J at the end; information in the 
<hi rend="i">Census</hi> that we assume to be correct but cannot independently verify is marked with an asterisk
followed by a <hi rend="i">C.</hi> We have not attempted to bring our style and spelling into absolute
conformity with the <hi rend="i">Census.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>As in other copies, some of the variants in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy S seem
significant, others rather whimsical. Two vines are redrawn to reverse the direction of the spiral: the one on
the title page is made to go counter-clockwise and the one on the tree overshadowing the Little Black Boy and
his mother becomes clockwise. On the next plate the Black Boy is smoky gray, in contrast to the white boy, and
the Good Shepherd has a distinct smile. Four of the boys in the main design under the title of “The Ecchoing
Green” wear white tops and light yellow breeches, and the two boys below, beside the text, wear pale cream
knickers; the effect is of a group in a team uniform. The figures in “Holy Thursday” are all retouched in
painstaking detail, so that some of the children look at the reader, some at the person behind, some have
their arms linked, and the girls’ beadle appears to be a female wearing a white bonnet. Throughout the
volume almost all the titles and many of the smaller figures have been gilded with a metallic pigment which is
somewhat duller than the heavy gold used, for instance, in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy E; a thinner
solution of this gilding is sometimes used on larger areas such as the clouds and the sheep in “The
Shepherd.”</p>
                    <p>The Cincinnati copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, which
also happens in the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> to be designated copy S of the combined anthology, is obviously a
composite copy: <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> is printed in gray, and <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> is printed in
dark brown. The fact that <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> is bound after <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> in an old
binding may also reflect its having been made up of two separate printings. The following addenda and
corrections to the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> account may be presented:
<q>
S 54 plates on 54 leaves. Watermark [J W]HATMAN/[J] 1808 *on the recto of pl. 27 (page 28), “On Another’s
Sorrow,” and fragments on 3 other plates (8, 21, 26) of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, which is printed
in gray predominantly, with letters unstrengthened. Some foxing, occasionally heavy. Painted in quiet varied
watercolors, more effectively in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, with some gold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><hi rend="s">G-J</hi> [The <hi rend="i">Census</hi> description “very lightly tinted” implies paler
and thinner washes. The gold is a dull gilding like that in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy S.] The general
title-page unnumbered, the other pages foliated by Blake in two series, 1-25 and 1-28, with <hi rend="i">Songs
of Experience</hi> misbound after pl. 1 before <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> Arrangement: 1, 28-32,
38, 42, 37, 49, 45, 33, 43, 47, 50, 41, 48, 34-36, 46, 44, 39, 40, 51, 52; 2-21, 53, 22-25, 54, 26, 27.
[Exactly, as noted above, the same arrangement as in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy S.] Size: 19 × 12.5 cm.
Bound in old calf, *<hi rend="i">ca.</hi> 1830,<hi rend="s">
                                <hi rend="i">C</hi>
                            </hi> a sheet of brown paper, *possibly part of the original wrappers,<hi
rend="s">
                                <hi rend="i">C</hi>
                            </hi> inserted between the two series. *Watermark on the verso of the first
flyleaf: 1/1822.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><hi rend="s">G-J</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <lb/>
*Probably the copy sold at Sotheby’s, 7 August 1890 (lot 2171, Maggs, £48). In 1905 in the possession of
Mrs. John R. Wade, of New York.<hi rend="s">
                                <hi rend="i">C</hi>
                            </hi> Later in the collection of Beverly Chew, *who added his bookplate,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><hi rend="s">G-J</hi> and sold with his books, Anderson’s, 8 December 1924 (lot
29, Rosenbach, $5500). Later in the collection of John J. Emery, *whose name is inscribed in pencil. Gift of
John J. Emery to the Cincinnati Art Museum, accession number 1969.509.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><hi
rend="s">G-J</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="i">Exhib</hi>: Philadelphia, 1939, no. 42.
</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Among the noteworthy features of this copy is the fact that water has been indicated at
the bottom of “The Lamb” and in the bottom foreground only (not the sides) of “Spring,” pl. 2, as well as on
“The Little Black Boy,” pl. 2, where it always occurs because it was actually cut on the plate. But no water
has been added to “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, “The Ecchoing Green,” pl. 2, “The Chimney
Sweeper,” or “Night,” pls. 1 and 2, pages where it often occurs in later copies. The Little Black Boy is made
darker than the white boy, and the Good Shepherd smiles at the white boy. There is a small gray stump with a
broken branch at the left beside the water on this second plate of “The Little Black Boy,” in an area Blake
frequently varied either by depicting assorted vegetation or by eliminating it entirely.</p>
                    <p>The statement in the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> that no authentic separate copy of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> is known to exist has sometimes been taken as proof that Blake never issued
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> separately. This assumption has been used as the basis for theories concerning
Blake’s over-all meaning. Yet the evidence of copy S, as well as of F, O, Q, and R—some of which have
differences in paper and pagination as well as in printing between <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>—suggests that these composite copies may not originally have been issued as whole
copies by Blake. Perhaps the fact that <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> was bound after 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> in the Cincinnati copy indicates an owner’s effort to put together what Blake had
issued separately. It is true, however, that despite the differences in <hi rend="i">printing</hi> of the two
cycles of poems in copy S, there is a considerable similarity in the general quality of the painting
throughout, although to less attractive effect in <hi rend="i">Experience.</hi> On the other hand, the
character of the coloring in the Innocence section of this copy is almost as close to that in the separate 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy S as it is to that in its own companion Experience section. Perhaps in
that happy far-off day when filmstrips of all the illuminated books will become available we shall be better
able to explain the affinities and variations among copies.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>