<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.2.berkeley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Berkeley Blake Weekend</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
	<pb id="p07-28" n="28"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-2-0002">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">BERKELEY BLAKE WEEKEND</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>“William Blake: A Celebration” was the theme of a weekend conference held 1-2 March
1974 at the Berkeley campus of the University of California under the auspices of the University of California
Extension. Morton Paley, program coordinator, introduced the program, which included slides, films, and a
series of lectures.</p>
                    <p>David Erdman, State University of New York at Stony Brook, presented the first lecture
of the series, “The Burden of the Present,” examining some of the contemporary political events that
influenced Blake and other Romantic poets. He supplemented his lecture with a number of slides and offered an
interpretation of some of the designs in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> His lecture was followed by the
presentation of three films, <hi rend="i">The Vision of William Blake, Tyger, Tyger</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Holy Thursday</hi>, which concluded the first day of the Celebration.</p>
                    <p>The Saturday morning session included lectures by Hazard Adams, University of
California, Irvine, Robert Essick, California State University at Northridge, and Morris Eaves, University of
New Mexico. With particular attention to a passage from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, Hazard Adams examined some
of the influences on “Blake’s Symbolism.” Blake as etcher and engraver was the subject of lectures by Robert
Essick and Morris Eaves. In “William Blake, Book Illustrator,” Essick used slides to survey the development of
Blake’s commercial engraving style and to explore some of the relationships between Blake’s work as a
commercial engraver and as poet-painter. In a complementary lecture, “Blake versus the Printing Press,” Eaves
used microphotographs of engravings to explain Blake’s rejection of ordinary means of printing and
publishing in favor of “illuminated printing.”</p>
                    <p>Anne K. Mellor, Stanford University, opened the Saturday afternoon session of the
series with her lecture “The Major Paintings,” using slides to show the iconography of Blake’s paintings.
Taking a cue from the phrase, “I was only making a fool of you” (<hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi>), Robert
Gleckner, University of California, Riverside, speculated that there may be a good deal more humor in
Blake’s works than his readers are usually inclined to recognize. In “The Shorter Poems,” Gleckner pointed
to passages in the lyrics where Blake may be using “non-sense” on his readers. In the concluding lecture, “The
Longer Poems,” Morton D. Paley, University of California, Berkeley, showed slides of some of the plates of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to illustrate his interpretation of the major designs in
both poems.</p>
                    <p>In addition to the slides and films supplementing the lectures, there were a number of
Blake’s prints on display at two exhibitions on the Berkeley campus. Among forty Blake prints shown at the
University Art Museum from 13 February through 17 March were some of the illustrations to the Book of Job, to
Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, and Young’s
<pb id="p07-29" n="29"/>
                        <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> This exhibition was organized by Museum Registrar
Joy Feinberg and Morton Paley. The prints displayed were from the University Art Museum and other Bay Area
collections, including the collection of Robert Essick. Materials for an exhibition of Blake books presented
in the Main Library at Berkeley, 23 February-31 March, were from the Bancroft Library, Biology Library, the
collection of Mrs. Charles C. Cushing, and the University Art Museum. Leslie Clark, Rare Books Librarian at
the Bancroft Library, assisted Morton Paley with the arrangement of and commentary for this exhibition. 
<hi rend="i">(Our thanks to Donna Rix of the University of New Mexico for this item. Eds.)</hi>
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>