<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.2.bibliography</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="checklist">A Bibliography of Blake Scholarship in the United Kingdom,
1972-73</title>
                <author n="Ferguson">James B. Ferguson</author>
                <author n="Parisi">Frank M. Parisi</author>
                <author n="Phillips">Michael Phillips</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Fall 1973</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Michael Davies</name>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1973"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-2-0003">
                <pb id="p07-44" n="44"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">
                                <hi rend="i">1972-73: A Bibliography of Blake Scholarship in the United
Kingdom</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="b">JAMES B.</hi> <name><hi rend="b">FERGUSON</hi></name></docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">&amp;</hi>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="b">FRANK M.</hi> <name><hi rend="b">PARISI</hi></name></docAuthor><lb/>
                        <hi rend="b">ASSISTED BY</hi>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="b">MICHAEL</hi> <name><hi rend="b">PHILLIPS</hi></name></docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n6" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>The editors have attempted, as far as possible, a comprehensive bibliography of all
books, sections of books, learned articles, reviews, and reproductions of Blake’s art published in the
United Kingdom during the period 1 January 1972 to 1 January 1974. Additional descriptive information,
supplied by the editors, is given in square brackets thus: [ ].</p>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">NEW &amp; REPRINTED BOOKS</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Adlard, John. The Sports of Cruelty: Fairies, Folk-songs, Charms and Other Country
Matters in the Work of William Blake. London: Cecil and Amelia Woolf, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. Songs of Innocence and of Experience. Facsimile of sixteen original
plates. London: Academy Editions, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. There is No Natural Religion. Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. Facsimile, 2
vols. Clairvaux, Jura, France: Trianon Press, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. William Blake’s Watercolour Designs for the Poems of Thomas Gray.
Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. Clairvaux, Jura, France: Trianon Press, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Blake, William. William Blake’s Watercolour Designs for the Poems of Thomas Gray.
Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. London: Eyre Methuen, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Bronowski, Jacob. William Blake and the Age of Revolution [First pub. William
Blake, 1757-1827, 1943]. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Campbell, Duina. Proverbs of Hell by William Blake; Illustrations. Leicester: Black
Knight Press, 1972. [Limited edition—100].</p>
                        <p>Carr, J. L., ed. William Blake, Twelve Poems. London: Florin Poets Series,
1972.</p>
                        <p>Clark, Kenneth. Blake and Visionary Art. Glasgow: University of Glasgow Press, 1973
[W. A. Cargill Memorial Lectures in Fine Art: 2].</p>
                        <p>Damon, S. F. A Blake Dictionary—The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake [First
pub. 1965]. London: Thames and Hudson, 1973.</p>
                        <p>Erdman, D. V., ed., with the assistance of Donald K. Moore. The Notebook of William
Blake: a photographic and typographic facsimile. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973.</p>
                        <p>Gilchrist, A. Life of William Blake [Photo rpt. 1880]. Introduction by W. A. G.
Doyle-Davidson [pp. v-xiii]. Wakefield, Yorks.: E. P. Publications Ltd., 1973.</p>
                        <p>Gillham, D. G. William Blake. London: Cambridge University Press, 1973 [British
Authors, Introductory Critical Series].</p>
                        <p>Kettle, Arnold. William Blake (1757-1827). Bletchley, Bucks.: Open University
Press, 1973 [For the “Age of Revolution” Course Team].</p>
                        <p>Lord, John. William Blake—Private Painter. Melton Mowbray, Leics.: Brewhouse
Press, 1972 [Broadsheet No. 10].</p>
                        <p>Moore, Donald K., ed. See Erdman, D. V.</p>
                        <p>Paley, M. D. and Michael Phillips, eds. William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir
Geoffrey Keynes. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973. For contents, see this item in the Checklist of Recent Blake
Scholarship, Newsletter 25. 
                        	<note id="n6"><hi rend="i">James B. Ferguson and Frank M. Parisi are Ph.D. candidates
at the University of Edinburgh. Ferguson is writing a thesis on “Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem <hi rend="i">with
special reference to the Book of Ezekiel and the English epic tradition,” Parisi on “‘The Gates of
Paradise’ and the Emblem Tradition.” Michael Phillips is Associate Editor of the</hi> Newsletter.</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb id="p07-45" n="45"/>
                        <p>Phillips, Michael, ed. See Paley, M. D. Sabri-Tabrizi, G. R. The “Heaven” and
“Hell” of William Blake. London: Lawrence and Wishart, 1973.</p>
                        <p>Wright, Andrew. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>: A Commentary. Oxford: Clarendon
Press, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Wright, Thomas. The Life of William Blake [Photo rpt. 1929]. Chicheley, Bucks.: P.
P. B. Minet, 1972.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">SECTIONS OF BOOKS</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Bloom, Harold. The Anxiety of Influence: A Theory of Poetry. London: Oxford
University Press, 1973.</p>
                        <p>Budgen, Frank. James Joyce and the Making of <hi rend="i">Ulysses</hi> and other
writings. London: Oxford University Press, 1972. [Esp. pp. 318-320].</p>
                        <p>Clark, Kenneth. The Romantic Rebellion: Romantic versus Classic Art. London: John
Murray, 1973 [In association with Sotheby Parke Bernet].</p>
                        <p>Leavis, F. R. Nor Shall My Sword: Discourses on Pluralism, Compassion and Social
Hope. London: Chatto and Windus, 1972.</p>
                        <p>Lister, Raymond. British Romantic Art. London: Bell, 1973.</p>
                        <p>Powell, Nicholas. Fuseli: the Nightmare. London: Allen Lane, The Penguin Press,
1972 [Art in Context Series].</p>
                        <p>Roberts, Mark. The Tradition of Romantic Morality. London: MacMillan Press, 1973
[Ch. 3, “Blake and the Damnation of Reason: <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell; Annotations on
Watson</hi>”].</p>
                        <p>Tomoroy, P. The Life and Art of Henry Fuseli. London: Thames and Hudson, 1972.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">ARTICLES</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Bateson, F. W. Editorial comment on V. Doyno’s “Blake’s Revision of
‘London’.” Essays in Criticism, 22 (Jan. 1972), 61-62.</p>
                        <p>Bishop, Morchard. “The Poet and the Attorney: The Story of a Legacy.” Book
Collector, 21:2 (Summer 1972), 245-54.</p>
                        <p>Cohen, Sandy. “Is William Blake’s Concept of Marriage Kabbalistic?” Notes and
Queries, N. S. 20:3 (March 1973), 100-01.</p>
                        <p>Denvir, B. “Sensibility and Cybernetics; some recent books about art.” Art
International, 16 (Feb. 1972), 64-66.</p>
                        <p>Doyno, V. “Blake’s Revision of ‘London’.” Essays in Criticism, 22 (Jan.
1972), 58-63.</p>
                        <p>Fawcus, Arnold. “William Blake’s Watercolour Designs illustrating Gray’s
Poems—and Mr. Paul Mellon.” Connoisseur, 179 (Jan. 1972), 10-14.</p>
                        <p>Fletcher, Ian. “The Ellis-Yeats-Blake Manuscript Cluster.” Book Collector, 21:1
(Spring 1972), 72-94.</p>
                        <p>Grant, John. “Blake’s Illustrations of the Book of Job.” Times Literary
Supplement, 30 Nov. 1973, p. 1484.</p>
                        <p>Horovitz, Michael. “Blake and the Voice of the Bard in our time.” Books, 10 (Winter
1972), 18-24.</p>
                        <p>James, G. Ingli. “Blake’s Woodcuts, Plain and Coloured.” Times Literary
Supplement, 18 May 1973, p. 564.</p>
                        <pb id="p07-46" n="46"/>
                        <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. “Blake’s Engravings for Gay’s Fables.” Book Collector, 21:1
(Spring 1972), 59-64.</p>
                        <p>Kjellberg, P. “Le premier coup d’audace des peintres anglais: leurs aquarelles.”
Connaissance Arts, 240 (Feb. 1972), 87.</p>
                        <p>Packer, William and G. S. Whittet. “London” [Tate Gallery, London; Exhibit of
Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Thomas Gray]. Art and Artists, 6 (Jan. 1972), 46-47, 49.</p>
                        <p>Paulson, Ronald. “The Spectres of Blake and Rowlandson.” The Listener, 90 (2 Aug.
1973), 140-42.</p>
                        <p>Roberts, Neil. “The Spirit of Crow.” Delta, 50 (Spring 1972), 3-15.</p>
                        <p>Sharp, Dennis. “On show: exhibitions reviewed: Blake into Print.” [Tate Gallery,
London: Exhibit of Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Thomas Gray]. Journal of the Royal Institute of
British Architects, 80:2 (Feb. 1972), 80.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Anon. G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed., The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne. Times
Literary Supplement, 28 April 1972, p. 470.</p>
                        <p>Anon. The Book of Thel, ed. Nancy Bogan. Times Literary Supplement, 29 Sept. 1972,
p. 1145.</p>
                        <p>Anon. There is No Natural Religion [Trianon Press facsimile]. Times Literary
Supplement, 28 April 1972, p. 470.</p>
                        <p>Anon. Jacob Bronowski, William Blake and the Age of Revolution. Times Literary
Supplement, 28 April 1972, p. 470.</p>
                        <p>Anon. Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips, eds., William Blake: Essays in honour
of Sir Geoffrey Keynes. British Book News, Nov. 1973.</p>
                        <p>Anon. Andrew Wright, Blake’s “Job”: A Commentary. Times Literary Supplement, 29
Sept. 1972, p. 1145.</p>
                        <p>Bazarov, K. Ruthven Todd, William Blake the Artist. Arts and Artists, 7 (May 1972),
56.</p>
                        <p>Beer, John. Geoffrey Keynes, Blake Studies: Essays on his Life and Work. Notes and
Queries, N. S. 20:8 (Aug. 1973), 305-07.</p>
                        <p>Beer, John. Morton D. Paley, Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development
of Blake’s Thought. Notes and Queries, N. S. 20:2 (Feb. 1973), 75-76.</p>
                        <p>Beer, John. W. H. Stevenson, ed., The Poems of William Blake. Notes and Queries, N.
S. 20:8 (Aug. 1973), 305-07.</p>
                        <p>Beer, John. Mona Wilson, The Life of William Blake, ed. Geoffrey Keynes. Notes and
Queries, N. S. 20:8 (Aug. 1973), 305-07.</p>
                        <p>Edwards, R. Raymond Lister, British Romantic Art. Apollo, N. S. 98 (July 1973),
65-66.</p>
                        <p>Edwards, R. Nicholas Powell, Fuseli: the Nightmare. Apollo, N. S. 97 (June 1973),
619-21.</p>
                        <p>Edwards, R. P. Tomoroy, The Life and Art of Henry Fuseli. Apollo, N. S. 97 (June
1973), 619-21.</p>
                        <p>Garlick, K. William Blake’s Watercolour Designs for the Poems of Thomas Gray, ed.
Geoffrey Keynes. Apollo, N. S. 98 (July 1973), 71.</p>
                        <p>Henn, T. R. Geoffrey Keynes, Blake Studies: Essays on his Life and Work. The
Yearbook of English Studies, 3 (1973), 302-04.</p>
                        <p>Hirst, Desiree. John Beer, Blake’s Visionary Universe. The Yearbook of English
Studies, 2 (1972), 294-95.</p>
                        <p>Hirst, Desiree. D. V. Erdman and J. E. Grant, eds., Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic. The Review of English Studies, 24:93 (Feb. 1973), 95-99.</p>
                        <p>Hirst, Desiree. Geoffrey Keynes, Blake Studies: Essays on his Life and Work. The
Review of English Studies, 24:93 (Feb. 1973), 95-99.</p>
                        <p>Hirst, Desiree. Irene Taylor, Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Gray. The
Review of English Studies, 24:93 (Feb. 1973), 95-99.</p>
                        <p>Hopkins, Kenneth. Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips, eds., William Blake: Essays
in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes. Eastern Daily Press, 7 Sept. 1973.</p>
                        <p>Laws, Frederick. S. F. Damon, A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William
Blake. The Daily Telegraph, 13 Sept. 1973, p. 8.</p>
                        <p>Laws, Frederick. Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips, eds., William Blake: Essays
in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes. The Daily Telegraph, 13 Sept. 1973, p. 8.</p>
                        <p>Muir, Kenneth. J. A. Wittreich, Jr., ed., The Romantics on Milton. Notes and
Queries, N. S. 20:2 (Feb. 1973), 77-78.</p>
                        <p>Rosenthal, M. Raymond Lister, British Romantic Art. Connoisseur, 183 (July 1973),
228.</p>
                        <p>Williams, Raymond. D. V. Erdman and D. K. Moore, eds., The Notebook of William
Blake. The Guardian, 29 Nov. 1973, p. 15.</p>
                        <p>Williams, Raymond. G. R. Sabri-Tabrizi, The “Heaven” and “Hell” of William Blake.
The Guardian, 29 Nov. 1973, p. 15.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="b">REPRODUCTIONS</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>“Angel Rolling away the Stone” (1808). Burlington Magazine, 114 (Sept. 1972),
652.</p>
                        <p>“Le Christ au Tombeau.” Gazzette Beaux Arts, Series 6, 81, supp. 206 (Feb.
1973).</p>
                        <p>“Dessin pour un poeme de Mr. Gray, a long story.” Gazzette Beaux Arts, series 6,
81, supp. 32 (Jan. 1973).</p>
                        <p>“L’Eternel.” La Revue du Louvre, 22:1 (1972), 52.</p>
                        <p>“Fall of the Rebel angels.” Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes, 34
(1971), pl. 71.</p>
                        <p>“Le Pitie” (1795). Connoisseur, 179 (Feb. 1972), 144.</p>
                        <p>“Pity.” The Times, 28 Jan. 1972, p. 12.</p>
                        <p>“Mary Magdalene at the Sepulchre: she turned herself back and saw Jesus standing.”
Apollo, 97 (May 1973), 24.</p>
                        <p>“St. Matthew and the Angel.” Connoisseur, 179 (Feb. 1972), 144.</p>
                        <p>“Tiriel supporting the swooning Myratana and addressing his sons.” Apollo, 95 (Feb.
1972), 154.</p>
                        <p>“Wise and Foolish Virgins.” Burlington Magazine, 155 (Feb. 1973), 138.</p>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>