<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.3.essick</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Jerusalem 25: Some Thoughts on Technique</title>
                <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1973-1974</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1974"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
	<pb id="p07-64" n="64"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-3-0004">
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">
                                <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> 25: Some Thoughts on Technique</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>ROBERT N. <name>ESSICK</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n23" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <p>In the Fall 1972 issue of the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> Deirdre Toomey
presented her interesting discovery of three states of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 25. As a
bibliographic description of a page from five copies of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> her article is
perspicacious and thorough, but as a chalcographic description of a copper-plate it seems to me that it leaves
several important questions unattended.</p>
	<note id="n23">
                        <hi rend="i">Robert N. Essick (California State University, Northridge) has recently
co-authored a commentary on the</hi> Night Thoughts <hi rend="i">engravings (forthcoming, Dover) and edited a
collection of reprinted articles on Blake’s art</hi>, The Visionary Hand <hi rend="i">(Hennessey &amp;
Ingalls).</hi>
                    </note>
                    <p>The additional lines pointed out by Toomey to distinguish between the three states are
of two different types. The white lines in the hair of the central and right females in the third state were
very likely added to the plate by removing some of the copper with an engraving tool, as Toomey states. An
alternate method for making white lines is “Woodcut on Copper,” as Blake called it (Keynes, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Writings</hi>, p. 440), but this would require covering the entire plate with an etching
ground—certainly more work than necessary for the limited area reworked. All the other added lines described
by Toomey, such as the body contours on the right female in the second state, are far more puzzling. They
print black, and thus must be in relief. How were these lines produced? No matter which etching or engraving
process is used, copper can only be subtracted from a plate, and thus it has always been my assumption that
adding relief lines to the parts of a plate already bitten in by acid or graver is very difficult, if not
impossible. The only way that comes to my mind for adding relief lines is to work the plate up from the back
and then engrave away the whites, leaving in relief only those areas to be printed. But the new lines on the
second state of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 25 have a delicacy and a spontaneity suggesting etching
rather than engraving. If etched, they could have been formed on the worked-up areas by applying a
stopping-out material with a small brush or pen, covering all other 
                        <pb id="p07-65" n="65"/>
relief lines with the stopping-out substance, and then immersing the plate in an acid bath to eat away the
exposed areas adjacent to the new lines. This is the only way I can account for the addition of the lines to
the copper-plate described by Toomey, but the process is clumsy, inefficient, and very time-consuming. It is
difficult to believe that Blake would go through such involved procedures just to add a few lines of contour
and shading. I would be happy to hear from anyone who knows an easier way for adding new relief lines to an
etching.</p>
                    <p>One simple way out of these technical difficulties remains. Toomey writes that the
considerable differences between the Pierpont Morgan copy (<hi rend="i">Census</hi> copy F) and the
Fitzwilliam copy (H) can be accounted for by differences in printing. It is certainly possible, as well as
convenient, to consider all the black line changes in the five impressions reproduced with Toomey’s article
as the result of inking and printing differences, either accidental or intentional. In the British Museum copy
(copy A, first state) the faint and poorly inked outline of some of the contours on the right female can be
seen, even though these lines were, according to Toomey, added in the second state. The gray wash shading in
copy A which Toomey points to as an indication of reworking to be done for the second state may actually be
Blake’s attempt to improve on poor printing. The Rosenwald copy of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (copy E) shows
a good deal of added wash for just this purpose. Printing a copper-plate, either relief or intaglio, is a
tricky business, and great differences in impressions can be caused by the way in which the plate is inked,
wiped, and imposed on the paper. Even the texture and moisture content of the paper can make significant
differences. Copy C of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (not discussed by Toomey) offers ample testimony to
Blake’s problems with, or cavalier attitude towards, clean printing. Many plates in this copy (almost all of
which are in Chapter 2, later rearranged and reprinted) have smudges in the white areas that result from
sloppy or too heavy inking—or a failure to clean out the hollows properly before imposition. On the other
hand, excessive or careless wiping can eliminate fine lines surrounded by relatively large white areas (i.e.,
just the sort of lines missing from plate 25 in Toomey’s first state). In copy C, the text area and major
lines on plate 25 indicate that it was very lightly inked, and thus it should be no surprise that this
impression shows (at least in the Blake Trust facsimile) even less evidence of the fine contour lines than
copy A. The method of inking can also affect impressions in a way that seems like a change in the copper
itself. Inking with a dabber or soft roller will cover all raised surfaces, but also get ink into the hollows;
inking with a very hard roller or from an unengraved plate (as Ruthven Todd did during his experiments with
relief etching in 1948) can miss fine lines slightly below the level of the major relief areas. One or more of
these variables can account for the differences in black lines described by Toomey.</p>
                    <p>My point here is not to dispute the particulars of Toomey’s article, but rather to
suggest the need to consider the technical potentials and limitations of Blake’s processes before making too
many assumptions about changes on a copper-plate. Armed with a heady combination of patience, twelve-power
magnifying glasses, and a tendency to promote all differences in impressions to the rank of different states,
we can end up with a bibliographer’s (or botanist’s) night-mare—that is, as many species as there are
individuals. In “The Suppressed and Altered Passages in Blake’s
<pb id="p07-66" n="66"/>
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” in <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, 17 (1964),
1-54, David Erdman points out that it is “almost impossible” to add new words in black line to a relief
etching. His statement serves as an ample warning to those eager to find textual <hi rend="i">additions</hi>
(as distinct from easily made deletions) on Blake’s copper-plates. The same warning must be extended to
include <hi rend="i">any</hi> additions of black lines to a relief plate. When confronted with a black line
addition in a print made from a relief etching, three possible explanations should be considered in an
ascending order of technical difficulty, as listed below.</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="i">1.</hi>
                                </label>
                                <hi rend="i">The additional lines were added in wash or pen and ink. No change
in the copper-plate.</hi> Wash or pen and ink work can usually be discovered through close scrutiny 
<hi rend="i">of the original print.</hi> For example, in the article cited above Erdman writes that the additional
lines covering deleted text on plate 3 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in copy D were drawn on the print, even
though the Pearson facsimile of this copy reproduced these lines in such a way that they look identical to the
lines printed from the plate. If however the additional lines are unquestionably printed, as I assume Toomey
found the additional lines on plate 25 to be, then the second alternative explanation requires
consideration.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="i">2.</hi>
                                </label>
                                <hi rend="i">Differences in inking and/or printing caused the differences in
the impressions. No change in the copper-plate.</hi> Almost every impression from one of Blake’s relief
etchings shows some variance from all other impressions due to these variables. The changes in the size and
darkness of the patch of ink on Albion’s right knee on plate 25 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the five
copies reproduced with Toomey’s article are a good case in point. A listing of all such variations in the
illuminated books would serve no purpose that I can foresee. Certainly the vast majority of these differences
are not intentional. Even an apparently significant addition to major lines, such as the definition of the
central female’s pudendum in copy D of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 25, is probably an accident of
inking (assuming it was not added with pen and ink to a single print), particularly when the addition vanishes
from later copies.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="i">3.</hi>
                                </label>
                                <hi rend="i">The additional lines result from a change in the copper-plate
itself.</hi> Until some expert in such matters comes forth with a satisfactory method of adding black lines to
relief plates, this must be the last and least attractive alternative. And even if Blake could make additions,
surely he did so only for some important aesthetic or iconographic purpose. Those who wish to argue for
additions to a relief plate should be asked to give good reasons for such changes. There are good reasons for
Blake to have filled in the rather messy and visually awkward areas of deleted text on 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 3, but he did so only with pen and ink in copy D, and made no additions in most
copies. If Blake could add to the copper-plate the small and in most cases unimportant lines that appear in
Toomey’s second state of plate 25, why didn’t he do something about plate 3? Until new evidence is
produced, I can only assume that Blake had no simple method for adding black lines to either plate.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>I hope that these questions and suggestions will seem not to be argumentative trivia of
the sort that stifles research, but rather necessary warnings and guidelines helpful to others interested in
Blake’s etchings.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>