<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.3.trawick</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Nature and Art in Milton: Afterthoughts on the 1973 MLA
Seminar</title>
                <author n="Trawick">Leonard Trawick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1973-1974</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1974"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-3-0004">
                <pb id="p07-67" n="67"/>
                <div2>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>LEONARD <name>TRAWICK</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n24" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">Nature and Art in <hi rend="u">Milton:</hi> Afterthoughts on the 1973
MLA Seminar</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>The 1973 MLA seminar “Perspectives on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>” (based on
five papers published in advance in <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 6 [Fall 1973]) produced some stimulating
discussion, but like most such sessions it opened up more avenues for thought than it fully explored. In the
following comments I seek the rare gratification of saying at leisure some things that I lacked the wit or
opportunity to say during the seminar.</p>
	<note id="n24">
                        <hi rend="i">Leonard M. Trawick is Professor of English at The Cleveland State
University. He is editor of</hi> Backgrounds of Romanticism <hi rend="i">(Indiana University Press, 1967) and
has written on Blake for</hi> Studies in Burke and His Time.</note>
                    <p>In his opening remarks Karl Kroeber, the discussion leader, challenged the group to
consider, among other problems, the ways in which <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is an expression of Blake’s
critical or aesthetic ideas. Though none of the five papers deals with this question directly, it seems to me
probably the most important one to ask about this particular poem. <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> has often been
compared with <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>, and for good reason. Here Blake not only comes to grips with his
personal role as poet-prophet, but, like Wordsworth in his autobiographical poem, he explores the nature of
imagination in general, and in particular the relation of the poet’s mind to nature. Only the first two of
the five papers touch on this topic at all, and neither deals with it in a satisfying way. Mary Lynn
Johnson’s quite penetrating essay emphasizes the importance of the Christology that underlies 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, but does not go on to relate this valuable idea to the poem’s central theme, the
relation of the artist to salvation. Thomas W. Herzing cogently analyzes “Natures cruel holiness” as it is
portrayed in Book I, but by failing to point out the equally true contrary of sensuous Nature’s necessary
place in Los’s task of regeneration, leaves a misleading impression about the direction of the poem as a
whole.</p>
                    <p>The discussion of the papers was similarly more tantalizing than satisfying. Alicia
Ostriker asked Mary Lynn Johnson about the other eternals who were not, like Milton, moved by the Bard’s
song—does this imply that only the artist can respond properly to visionary inspiration? Johnson replied
first by citing Blake’s wish that all the Lord’s people were prophets, ’and then went on to say that
Milton’s response is not to write a poem but to begin to act in a way that leads to self-annihilation.
Stuart Curran also asked Johnson a pertinent question about the relation of theology to art. But these lines
of discussion were cut off before they were much developed.</p>
                    <p>What needed to be said at the seminar was, first, that Milton’s descent, union with
Ololon, and triumph over his selfhood are events simultaneously theological and aesthetic in their
implications—indeed, the two are hardly separable in Blake; and, second, that the great problem that is
solved in the poem is precisely the paradox that physical Nature, while a delusion of fallen humanity and the
source of man’s continuing error, is nevertheless the only means by which the poet-prophet, or the divine
humanity in every man, is able to regain Eternity.</p>
                    <p>Herzing is misleading when he says in his essay that “All of being . . . possesses two
forms: the external form is perceived by the easily enticed and easily deluded sensate eye; poetic vision
perceives the inward form, the infinite and eternal character” (p. 30). But Blake is a monist; for him the
very existence of those external forms is only an illusion we fall into when our mental powers become dormant,
and we allow our selfhood to impose its limitations on our perception of the infinite. Our souls return to
wholeness, to renewed participation in Eternity, by casting away the limiting selfhood (i.e., by
self-annihilation) and sharing more fully in true reality through imaginative activity. The external forms are
not cruel and delusive <hi rend="i">per se</hi>, but only when we see them as detached from Eternity, from the
infinite within, as Natural Religion does. The energies of Eternity seem terrible when reversed in “the
Printing-Press of Los,” but that is because we are viewing them with dulled and fragmented vision. In 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Blake believes as he did in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, that “Body
is a portion of Soul discerned by the five Senses, the chief inlets of Soul in this age” (Plate 4, E 34). When
we see “the Constellations in the deep &amp; wondrous Night . . . the gorgeous clothed Flies . . . the Trees
on mountains,” we are seeing true “Visions of Eternity” (Plates 25-26, E 121-22), visions which are valid to
the extent that our limited minds can handle them. We see only “the hem of their garments”: the phrase implies
limitation but not derogation. As participants in the MLA seminar pointed out, the phrase alludes both to the
angels’ limited view of God in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (III, 380) and to the curative powers of
Jesus’ hem (cf. Matthew 9:20-21). Hence it is through <hi rend="i">acceptance</hi> and assimilation of the
sense world rather than rejection of it that man—and preeminently the prophetic artist—returns to
Eternity. That is what Los is doing when he builds Golgonooza, and 
                        <pb id="p07-68" n="68"/>
what Blake is doing when “All this Vegetable World appeared on my left Foot,” and he binds it on as a bright
sandal “to walk forward thro’ Eternity” (Plate 21, E 114). We must remember that Beulah—where, to put it
crudely, Eternal forms take on garments of limiting materiality—is not only the exit leading to Ulro, but
also the entranceway back to Eternity, via “holy Generation [<hi rend="i">Image</hi>] of regeneration” 
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> I, 7; E 149). So in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Enitharmon, the selfish gates of
her heart permanently broken, works toward salvation by weaving “Bodies of Vegetation” for the poor wandering
spectres (Night VIII, p. 100, E 358). Very similar versions of this paradox of using the senses as a
stairsteps to transcend the sense world are prominent in Coleridge, Wordsworth, Shelley, and Keats; it is in
fact a form of the familiar Platonic ladder of love.</p>
                    <p>None of these Romantic poets, including Blake, draws a line between poetic and
religious inspiration. Coleridge’s phrase in “Dejection: an Ode” for the happy consequence of his “shaping
spirit of imagination” operating with the intense energy of Joy is the apocalyptic “New Heaven and a New
Earth” (Revelation 21:1) also echoed in the millenial promise that follows Christ’s decision to descend to
man in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> III (line 335). Both religious and aesthetic vision involve the ability
to see the Divine—the One Mind—that is always immanent in experience for those who can see through the
corporeal eye and not with it. Coleridge’s famous definition of the primary imagination as “the living Power
and prime Agent of all human Perception, and as a representation in the finite mind of the eternal act of
creation in the infinite I AM” is a good gloss for Blake’s four levels of vision: the greater the intensity
at which the imagination operates in all perception, the more fully we share in the infinite creativity of the
Divine mind, and approach fourfold vision. The fool sees not the same tree that the wise man sees, because the
wise man perceives with a well developed primary imagination, whereas the fool, victim of his selfhood, cuts
himself off from divine vision by depending on what Coleridge would call the fixities and definites of
understanding and memory.</p>
                    <p>Blake consistently identifies Christ as the imagination in every man (e.g., in the 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> inscriptions, transcribed E 271). A Blakean Christology must therefore in some sense be
an “Imaginationology.” Milton, one of the supreme embodiments of imagination, in Blake’s poem closely
parallels Christ’s career: his incarnation—that is, his decision to go to Eternal Death—resembles
Christ’s decision as described in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> III; Milton has a temptation in the
wilderness, well described by Thomas Herzing’s article; his crucifixion and atonement is his choice of
self-annihilation rather than opposition to Satan, his spectre—a parallel to Jesus’ self-sacrifice in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, 96, and, incidentally, to the refusal by Shelley’s Prometheus to curse Jupiter; his
resurrection is, as Mary Lynn Johnson says, “the emergence of the Real Human from the dead selfhood”; and his
ascension is his final merging with Jesus in Plate 42.</p>
                    <p>All of these events have significance in terms of Blake’s aesthetics, i.e., of his
beliefs about imagination. When he decides to descend to Eternal Death, Milton takes off the “robe of the
promise”—that is to say, he rejects a legalistic Puritan theology for one of Christlike self-annihilation;
the aesthetic equivalent is rejection of a rational, Lockean use of the senses and the daughters of memory, in
favor of living imagination and the daughters of inspiration. Christ’s incarnation is the necessary clothing
of the Word in a form assimilable by fallen humanity: “God becomes as we are, that we may be as he is.” Even
the Eternals converse in “Visionary Forms Dramatic,” and “Man cannot unite with Man but by their Emanations”
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 88, E 244). Milton must be perfected through a fuller and more imaginative acceptance of
the natural world, of the body and the senses, than his poetry originally achieved; it culminates in his
proper union with his purified emanation Ololon. In Blake’s plot, Milton’s temptation and agon are the
sorting out of the right and wrong uses of sensation. When Milton’s shadow, or spectre, finally separates
from him, and he refuses to fight it, this is itself victory over selfhood and the Not Human: it is inevitably
followed by—in fact, it constitutes—an apocalypse for Milton (though not quite yet for Blake and the rest
of the world) and by his union with the similarly purified Ololon in Jesus, the Divine Humanity. The
Revelation to Milton of a new Heaven and Earth includes an explicitly literary aspect: he is able “To cast off
the rotten rags of Memory by Inspiration” and to reject “the tame high finisher of paltry blots,” and those
“Who pretend to Poetry that they may destroy Imagination; / By imitation of Natures Images drawn from
Remembrance” (Plate 41, E 141). In other words, sensation is wrongly used whenever it ceases to be a living
part of the Divine mind shared in the act of Imagination, and the error is worst when embodied in Poetry,
which ought to be the highest expression of Vision. Such abstraction in Poetry is spiritual death
corresponding to Mystery in religion. The Bard’s song in the first third of the poem, it should be noted, is
a kind of Preludium presenting, in different terms, a misuse of imaginative powers similar to that which
Milton eventually overcomes.</p>
                    <p>Thus in his poem Blake winnows out the eternal, Reprobate Milton from his Elect portion
in a literary as well as a theological sense. As a personal document <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> records the
impact on Blake of his predecessor. We recall that the Bard in Book I says he is himself inspired by the
Divine Humanity; the Bard enters Milton’s bosom, Milton enters Blake’s heel, and Blake simultaneously
merges with Los. In other words Milton’s writings—in spite of some reservations Blake has about
them—allow Blake to participate more fully in Eternal reality, and to contribute to Jerusalem’s return to
England’s green and pleasant land. Significantly, Milton and Los appear to Blake as he is binding on the
material world as a sandal in which to walk through Eternity. From the placement of this circumstance at such
a climactic moment in Book I, it would seem that one of the things Blake learned from Milton was the proper
use of the sense world.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>