<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.3.wilton</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">A Fan Design by Blake</title>
                <author n="Wilton">Andrew Wilton</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1973-1974</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Foster Foreman</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1974"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-3-0003">
                <pb id="p07-61" n="61"/>
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">A Fan Design by Blake</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>ANDREW <name>WILTON</name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>The issue of the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> for spring 1972, listing Blake’s
works in the British Museum Print Room, refers on p. 226 to the verso of Binyon 
32<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> 
as: “Design for a fan (probably not by Blake).” This entry
seems to have been derived from Binyon’s own description which reads: “Design for a fan. An oval with Cupid
and Psyche. Not by Blake.” In spite of this categorical rejection, the <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> checklist,
with its “probably,” reflects a doubt not unnaturally engendered by the fact that the fan design is on the
same sheet as a characteristic pencil study of Blake’s maturity, sketching an idea for a
title-page;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> no one has ever disputed
the authenticity of this. 
                    <note id="n21">The pictures on pp. 60-63 are reproduced by permission of the Trustees of
the British Museum.</note>
                    <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Lawrence Binyon, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Drawings by
British Artiste . . . in the British Museum</hi>, I (1898), 127. The sheet was presented to the Museum in 1874
by John Deffett Francis, register no. 1874. 12. 12. 147.</note>
                    <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> (Spring 1972),
repro.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The contrast between the loose, rapid pencil drawing of the title-page study and the neat,
brightly colored decoration on the reverse is sufficiently great to have prompted the reaction that, when he
made the rough sketch, Blake must have used a scrap of paper from some other artist’s portfolio. The lower
half of this reverse side of the sheet<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
is empty; in the center, near the top, is an oval vignette measuring 7.9 × 12.4 cm. [illus. 1 &amp; 2]. The
subject is drawn in pencil, colored with bright pink, mauve and green watercolor, and strengthened with some
outlines in pen and black ink. Above it a few curling sprays of foliage, with pink buds, soften the hard oval.
To the left, a little below the central horizontal axis of the oval, is a putto with a loop of blue drapery,
carrying a torch; to the right, opposite him, a fairy with small wings, curling yellow and pink drapery, and a
garland. A sinuous tendril of scant-leaved ivy describes an arc over all three groups suggesting, as Binyon
saw, that the drawing was conceived as a decoration for a fan. This is borne out by the typically fan-like
placing of the central vignette, a common feature on fans of the late eighteenth century, often contained in
just such an oval and frequently flanked, like this one, with supporting figures or ornaments. Binyon was
wrong, however, in identifying the subject as Cupid and Psyche, since the girl holds a pen or stylus and not a
lamp: it shows the incident of the “Corinthian Maid” or the daughter of Dibutades the potter, who, as Fuseli
put it, “traced the shade of her departing lover by the secret lamp”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n4" type="note">4</ref> the incident, in fact, known as “the Origin of Painting,” used by Joseph
Wright of Derby and many other Neo-classicists, and actually engraved, in one version, for use on fan-leaves.
<ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
                    <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Overall measurements 26.3 × 38.2 cm.</note>
                    <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> John Knowles, <hi rend="i">Life and Writings of Henry
Fuseli</hi> (1831), II, 25 (Lecture on Ancient Art).</note>
                    <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The designer is not known. See Lionel Cust, 
<hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Collection of Fans and Fan-leaves presented to the <corr type="emend">Trustee</corr> of the British Museum by
the Lady Charlotte Schreiber</hi> (1893), p. 76, no. 61. Wright’s painting is now in the collection of Mr.
and Mrs. Paul Mellon.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The choice of subject is not typical of Blake, who rarely used Classical sources,
preferring (when he was not concerned with his own private myths) to illustrate English history or literature:
his <hi rend="i">Edward and Elenor</hi>
                    <ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> and <hi rend="i">The Penance of Jane</hi>
                <pb id="p07-60" n="60"/>
                <figure n="BUT223A.1.1v.WC" rend="file" width="800" height="544">
                    <head>1 Blake’s design for a 
                    fan.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">*</ref></head>
                </figure>
                <figure n="BUT223A.1.1v.WC.detail" rend="file" width="800" height="504">
                    <head>2 The central oval for the fan design, slightly enlarged.</head>
                </figure>
                    <pb id="p07-62" n="62"/>
                    <figure n="Cherub.7.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="336">
                        <head>3 “Morning Twilight,” from the Abbe Montfaucon’s <hi rend="i">Antiquity
Explained.</hi>
                        </head>
                    </figure>
                    <hi rend="i">Shore</hi>
                    <ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> are early examples. The theme, and the simple, stark
design, have something in common with the Classical fantasies of Romney; but the drawing of the pen outlines,
and the color, are very much Blake’s. At first sight it is precisely in its color that the work seems
farthest removed from Blake; but there are close parallels in the coloring of some of the designs which he was
producing in the early 1780s. The small sketch of the composition of the <hi rend="i">Death of Earl
Godwin</hi>, of about 1780,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> for
instance, makes use of similar yellows and of the characteristic lavender-mauve; and, on a larger scale but
with something of the same concentration, so does the dramatic design of <hi rend="i">Saul and the Witch of
Endor</hi>, dated 1782.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> It is to some
date such as this that the drawing under consideration should be assigned; Blake was at that time about
twenty-five years old. If the colors, intensified and concentrated as they are here in a decorative context,
recall the sweet, sugar-icing palette of Adam’s decorators—Angelica Kauffmann and Biago Rebecca, for
example—we should not be surprised: it was the kind of influence which any young artist of the period would
have absorbed, and one particularly well suited to the ornamental purpose of the fan. 
                    <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Blake’s engraving after his own painting (now lost) is
catalogued in Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi> (1956), no. VI, pl.
11. It is dated 1793 but was perhaps executed considerably earlier.</note>
                    <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Produced about 1778. Now in the Tate Gallery.</note>
                    <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> British Museum, register no. 1964. 12. 12. 13. The
finished drawing was exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1780 (no. 315).</note>
                    <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> In the New York Public Library, Department of
Prints.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The composition itself, on the other hand, anticipates the mature Blake and furnishes the
most striking evidence of his authorship. The upright figure beside a body stretched horizontally on a bed
recurs, with increased austerity and grandeur, as the titlepage of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> in
1794 (an early specimen of several comparable death-scenes by Blake). Here the recumbent figures are starkly
supine, the arms rigid and not relaxed as in the fan vignette; but the stooping posture of the mourners is
close to that of the Corinthian Maid, whose bent left leg is also echoed by the foremost of them.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Even the figure of Cupid, flying in
diagonally at the left of the vignette, is remembered in the 1794 plate, though transmuted into a robed spirit
floating above the principal scene, to the left of the title lettering. This type of fairy, in a long curling
gown, is characteristic of Blake’s decorations and is closely prefigured in the right-hand “supporter” of
the fan design. Unlike the Cupid, which has conventional angel or bird’s wings, this figure is equipped with
the small butterfly wings which are occasionally to be found in Blake’s evocations of fairyland.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> The device is unusual at this date, although
it was sometimes used by Neo-classical artists;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">12</ref> it looks forward to Victorian painters of Faerie such as Doyle and Noel Paton. 
                    <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Compare also the pose of such figures as that on the
right of <hi rend="i">Ruth and Naomi</hi> in the Victoria and Albert Museum.</note>
                    <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> For example, on p. 1 (pl. 3) of <hi rend="i">The Book
of Thel</hi>; and, larger, in the “Sunshine Holiday” illustration to Milton’s <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>
in the Pierpont Morgan Library.</note>
                    <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Such as Richard Westall and Henry Howard. Butterfly
wings were also used by Baroque artists, especially the French. They seem to derive from those in the Raphael
School <hi rend="i">Marriage of Cupid and Psyche</hi> in the Villa Farnesina, known through the engraving of
Nicolas Dorigny in <hi rend="i">Psyches et Amoris Nuptiae ac Fabula</hi> (Rome, 1693), and consciously
imitated by James Barry in his composition of <hi rend="i">Pandora</hi> (a drawing now known only from an
engraving by Louis Schiavonetti).</note>
                </p>
                <p>By contrast, the left-hand supporter is taken directly from the Classical antique. Its loop
of drapery recalls those of Poussin’s nymphs, and of their Roman originals, especially those found in
Pompeian wall-paintings. The putto may be assumed to represent Cupid again: the torch is as much an attribute
of the god as the bow which Blake shows him holding in the principal scene; but, just as the fairy has no
obvious symbolic function, this figure too may be simply a decorative motif. It does, however, allude
unmistakably to the Roman figure of a boy holding a torch and a veil which is reproduced in the Abbé
Montfaucon’s <hi rend="i">Antiquity Explained</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> and stated there to represent “Morning Twilight” [illus. 3]. The position of the arm
holding the torch differs slightly from Blake’s design, but we should not expect Blake to copy any image
precisely. In fact, the arm and torch of his putto can be exactly paralleled in a very similar figure in
Pietro Testa’s etching of the <hi rend="i">Season of Spring</hi>, a print well known to eighteenth-century
collectors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
                    <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Bernard de Montfaucon, <hi rend="i">L’Antiquité
Expliquée et representée en figures</hi>, 5 vols. with 5 supplementary vols. (1719); translated into English
by D. Humphreys as <hi rend="i">Antiquity Explained and represented in Sculptures</hi> (1721-25). See the
Supplement, Vol. I, pl. 4 and facing page.</note>
                    <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Bartsch XX, 36.</note>
                </p>
                <p>A more immediate instance of the putto-and-torch motif is to be found in one of the
vignettes which Blake himself engraved after designs by Thomas
<pb id="p07-63" n="63"/>
Stothard for Joseph Ritson’s <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi>, published in
1783<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> [illus. 4] It shows a
Magdalen-like figure leaning mournfully against a rock while two cupids fly away from her. One carries a
flaming torch, the other a bow and quiver; this second also has a loop of drapery fluttering in an arc. Both
the putti of Blake’s fan design are thus to be found together in this vignette. Another illustration to the
same book<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> shows Cupid standing with
a lamp behind a lady who is penning a love-letter by moonlight; here, beyond the incidental appearance of
Cupid, there is no direct connection with the fan design, but it is worthy of note that the whole scene, with
figures confined to the extreme left and the background a plain wall broken only by the vertical of the
door-post and the moon beyond, is of an austerity unusual in Stothard and altogether closer in spirit to
Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> The compact rectangular
format of these vignettes is not far removed from the oval of Blake’s fan, and it seems at least possible
that the latter was executed while Blake was at work on the engravings. It is certainly reasonable to point to
Stothard as a link between the youthful Blake and the earlier generation of Neo-classical decorators. 
                    <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> In 3 vols., I, 170. See A. G. B. Russell, 
<hi rend="i">The Engravings of William Blake</hi> (1912), p. 145, no. 55 (vii).</note>
                    <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> I, 157. Russell, no. 55 (vi). Reproduced in Raymond
Lister, <hi rend="i">William Blake, an Introduction to the Man and to his Work</hi> (1968), pl. 2.</note>
                    <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The Blakean character of the illustrations for Ritson
was noticed by Gilchrist in his <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 2nd ed. (1880), I, 51; quoted by
Russell, no. 55.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Although Blake turned his hand to conventional book-illustration like Stothard’s, and
occasionally produced designs to order for commercial and other 
purposes,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> there are few instances of his work as
a decorative artist in so overtly frivolous a vein as this fan-leaf. It is impossible to say precisely why it
was drawn, or why it was never cut out and used, but its probable date of around 1782 prompts the sentimental
conjecture that it was intended for Blake’s new bride, Catherine, whom he married in August of that
year.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> At about the same time he was
introduced by Flaxman to the circle of Mrs. Mathew,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref> and the drawing might have been a response to the more elegant social milieu which Blake
encountered there. These however are suggestions without circumstantial support, and they must therefore
remain speculative and largely fanciful. 
                    <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Such as his advertisement for Moore’s Carpet and
Hosiery Manufactory; see Keynes, <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi>, no. V, pl. 10.</note>
                    <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Gilchrist, I, 41.</note>
                    <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Gilchrist, I, 43.</note>
                </p>
                    <figure n="BB491.1.7.COM" rend="file" width="958" height="719">
                        <head>4 A vignette engraved by Blake after Stothard for Ritson’s <hi rend="i">Select
Collection of English Songs.</hi>
                        </head>
                    </figure>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>