<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.4.ryan</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">Poisonous Blue</title>
                <author n="Ryan">Robert M. Ryan</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1974</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1974</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1974"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <pb id="p07-87" n="87"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-4-0003">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Robert M. <name>Ryan</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n27" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">
                                <hi rend="i">“Poisonous Blue”</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>I would like to suggest an interpretation of a curious phrase which appears on Plate 65
of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
	<note id="n27">
                        <hi rend="i">Robert M. Ryan teaches Romantic literature at Rutgers University in
Camden.</hi>
                    </note>
						<q>
They vote the death of Luvah &amp; they nail’d him to Albion’s Tree in Bath,<lb/>
They stain’d him with poisonous blue, they inwove him in cruel roots<lb/>
To die a death of Six thousand years bound round with vegetation. (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 65:8-10, K 699)
</q>
Damon identifies “poisonous blue” as woad.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">1</ref> And given the general context, a Druid sacrificial rite, it does seem likely that Blake
was thinking of the dye with which ancient Britons colored their skin. Yet there is nothing particularly
poisonous in the chemical makeup of woad. Therefore I suspect that Blake may also have had in mind another
coloring substance—the pigment known as Prussian blue. 
                        <note id="n16">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy
and Symbols</hi> (1924; rpt. New York: Peter Smith, 1947), p. 459.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Prussian blue was first produced in Berlin in 1704 and by the end of the century had
come into wide use among artists—Blake included.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">2</ref> In 1782, the new pigment aroused the curiosity of the Swedish<gap type="emend"/>
<pb id="p07-89" n="89"/>
<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/>
chemist, Karl Wilhelm
Scheele, and he performed a series of experiments attempting to analyze the “coloring principle” in Prussian
blue.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">3</ref> Scheele was successful in
isolating the chemical, and four years later the French <hi rend="i">Encyclopédie</hi> gave it the name 
“<hi rend="i">l’acide prussique.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">4</ref>
Prussic acid is today more generally known as hydrocyanic acid or hydrogen cyanide, and it is recognized as
one of the most poisonous substances in existence. Scheele himself was apparently not aware of the dangerous
qualities of the acid he had discovered: it was not until 1803 that its highly poisonous character was fully
understood.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">5</ref> Since then the chemical
has had an inglorious history: the Zyklon-B used at Auschwitz and the gas released in execution chambers in
this country were both forms of hydrocyanic acid. 
                        <note id="n17">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Edwin Wolf 2nd, <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Illuminated Books: A Census</hi> (New York: Grolier Club, 1953), pp. 44. One instance of Blake’s
use of the color is mentioned.</note>
                        <note id="n18">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> His account of the experiments is included in <hi rend="i">The
Chemical Essays of Charles-William Scheele</hi>, trans. Thomas Beddoes (London: John Murray, 1786).</note>
                        <note id="n19">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> J. R. Partington, <hi rend="i">A History of Chemistry</hi>,
III (London: Macmillan, 1962), 527.</note>
                        <note id="n20">
                            <hi rend="s">5</hi> Partington, III, 234. In 1803, the poison derived from laurel
leaves was identified as prussic acid. Was it coincidental that in this year (probably) Blake wrote: “The
Strongest Poison ever known / Came from Caesar’s Laurel Crown”? (K 433) Or had he read somewhere an account
of the discovery?</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>What was Blake’s point in alluding to Prussian blue in this passage? David Erdman
suggests that Plate 65 was revised at about the time of Napoleon’s Hundred Days.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">6</ref> In the Belgian campaign—that final assault by the sons of
Albion against Luvah—England’s chief ally was Prussia. It was the arrival of Prussian troops under
Blücher that determined the outcome of the battle at Waterloo. In describing the sacrificial death of Luvah,
Blake saw the appropriateness of identifying the blue dye of the Druids with the poison-based color named for
Prussia. 
                        <note id="n21">
                            <hi rend="s">6</hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Blake, Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 2nd ed., rev. (Princeton:
Princeton Univ. Press, 1969), p. 466n.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>