<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.4.connolly</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">Songs of Innocence, Keynes 1921 Copy U, Keynes-Wolf 1953 Copy U</title>
                <author n="Connolly">Thomas E. Connolly</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1974</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1974</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1974"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-4-0003">
                <pb id="p07-88" n="88"/>
                <div2>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Thomas E. <name>Connolly</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n29" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">Songs of Innocence, <hi rend="i">Keynes (1921) Copy U, Keynes-Wolf
(1953) Copy U</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>This copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, in the Houghton Library, Harvard
University (see <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> 19, p. 214, and <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> 24, p. 96) requires,
perhaps, just one more note to present it properly to contemporary students of Blake. Physical examination of
the volume as it now exists reveals the following details to be added to the standard bibliographical
descriptions cited above:
	<note id="n29">
                        <hi rend="i">Thomas E. Connolly is Professor of English at the State University of New
York at Buffalo. He is currently at work on a book on Blake’s</hi> Songs.</note>
<list type="ordered">
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(1)</label> pl. 29, the first of two plates of “The Little Black
Boy.” For this copy two pulls were made from this plate. Consequently two leaves for pl. 29 appear in this
copy. The leaves were not numbered by Blake, but numbers in pencil have been added in the upper right-hand
corners of the leaves. Because of the extra print of or pull from pl. 29, these numbers run from 1-32, not
from 1-31 as the bibliographies cited above declare.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(2)</label> Included in this copy, but unnoticed in either of the
bibliographies cited in my title are three leaves from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> numbered in
pencil in the upper right-hand corners 1a, 2a, 3a. These are:</p>
                                <list type="ordered">
                                    <item>
                                        <p>
                                            <label>(a)</label>
                                            <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> pl. 29,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">1</ref> Title page to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> on which is
written in pencil: “Taken in 1838: From the original plates in possession of Mr. Tatham.” 
                                            <note id="n23">
                                                <hi rend="s">1</hi> The Keynes-Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi>
uses one set of plate numbers for extant copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (p. 9) and another set
of plate numbers for extant copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (p. 50). A
certain amount of confusion will always arise in referring to the plates of individual poems in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> One must be careful always to indicate whether one is citing the plate
number for a poem of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> as it appears in the single anthology 
(<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> only) or in the double anthology (<hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience</hi>): For
example, Keynes-Wolf number the plate for “A Dream” 4 in the former and 26 in the latter; they number the two
plates for “The Little Black Boy” 29 and 30 in the former and 9 and 10 in the latter.</note>
                                        </p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>
                                            <label>(b)</label>
                                            <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> pl. 30, “Introduction” to 
<hi rend="i">Experience.</hi>
                                        </p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>
                                            <label>(c)</label>
                                            <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> pl. 37, “The Chimney Sweeper” of 
<hi rend="i">Experience.</hi>
                                        </p>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(3)</label> Also originally bound into this copy are many leaves
containing excerpts from the “Prologue” to <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Tales</hi> with modernized versions on
facing leaves.</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>A corrected description of this copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> reads as
follows:
<q>
U 31 plates on [32]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">2</ref> leaves. Watermark
WHATMAN, on one leaf. Printed in black. Uncoloured. Formerly arranged: 2, 1, 3, 10-11, 29-30, 9, 22, 28, 13,
14, 8, 20, 21, 16-17, 27, 24, 18-19, 12, 23, 25-26, 31, 4, 15, 5-7. Size: 19 × 11.7 cm. Now loose in binding
together with the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, 1809, and the <hi rend="i">Canterbury
Pilgrims</hi>, 1812; fly-leaf with watermark dated 1818. [Uncoloured prints of pls. 29, 30, 37 of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> bound in after <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> The following notation
in pencil appears on pl. 29 (<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>), Title page to <hi rend="i">Experience:</hi> “Taken
in 1838: From the original plates in possession of Mr. Tatham.” Excerpts from Chaucer’s “Prologue” with
modernized texts facing the originals have also been bound into this copy.] 
    <note id="n24">
                                <hi rend="s">2</hi> Material in square brackets is either a correction of or
an addition to the bibliographic description in the Keynes-Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi> (pp. 17-18).</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Formerly in the possession of Robert Balmanno, an English journalist, who emigrated to
New York. He had been friendly with Stothard and Fuseli and other artists who knew Blake, and may have had the
books direct from him. Afterwards in the collection of E.W. Hooper, of Boston. Reproduced in 1883 by Little,
Brown, and Co. For many years in 
                        <pb id="p07-89" n="89"/>
the possession of Hooper’s daughter, Mrs. Greely S. Curtis, Jr., of Boston, and given by her sister, Mrs.
Ward Thoron to the Houghton Library, Harvard University, in 1951 in memory of her father.</p>
                    <p>Further pencil notations, that are not necessarily essential to the physical
description of Copy U, appear as follows:
<list type="ordered">
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(1)</label> On the verso of pl. 3 “Introduction” to 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> appears the following notation: “Typ 6500 (50-208-210)”.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(2)</label> Inside the front cover is a history of the ownership of
this copy.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(3)</label> On the verso of pl. 21 (“The Little Boy found”) appears
the notation: “H.D. Chapin 60 Beacon St. Boston High 3-4 40 inches - 11246”.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(4)</label> On p. 30 of the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>
in the margin opposite “H—says” in the text appears the name, “Hoppner”.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(5)</label> On p. 32 of the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>
in the margin opposite “Mr. S—” appears the name, “Stothard”.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <label>(6)</label> On the end paper appears the note: “A copy of the/<hi
rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809/Sold in the Beckford Libr<hi rend="s">y</hi>/Hamilton Palace Sale
for £9/E.W.H.”</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>One does not know when the pages of this copy became loose. They may have been loosened
sometime between 1921 and 1953. The extra leaf for “The Little Black Boy” may have been inserted after Keynes
originally described this copy, but it is unlikely. Similarly, the three leaves from 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> may have been added subsequent to 1921, again unlikely. If the three leaves from 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> were actually added to this copy in 1838 or shortly thereafter, as the pencil note
indicates, the pages of this copy may have been loosened before Keynes originally described it in 1921.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>