<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.4.pearcy</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake’s Tyger &amp; Richard Crashaw’s Paraphrase of Thomas of
Celano’s Dies Irae</title>
                <author n="Pearcy">Roy J. Pearcy</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1974</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1974</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1974"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-4-0002">
                <pb id="p07-80" n="80"/>
                <div2>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Roy J. <name>Pearcy</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n25" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">
                                <hi rend="i">Blake’s Tyger &amp; Richard Crashaw’s Paraphrase of Thomas of
Celano’s</hi> Dies Irae</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Within the past several years, critics have become increasingly aware that Blake may
have known and been influenced by the poetry of Crashaw, <ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> whose works,
available in partial anthologies published in 1648, 1652, and 1670,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref> attracted a growing interest during the eighteenth century, and received
frequent and favorable commentary.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> One
particular poem often singled out for praise was his “Hymn of the Church in Meditation of the Day of
Judgment,” a paraphrase of Thomas of Celano’s <hi rend="i">Dies Iras</hi>, originally composed in the
thirteenth century as a <hi rend="i">pia meditatio</hi>, but popularized through its incorporation into the
burial service of the Roman Church as a sequence in the requiem mass, and through its eventual adoption as an
advent hymn by the Protestant churches. By Blake’s time the Latin poem had achieved fame as a
nondenominational masterpiece, lauded by Anglicans and Catholics alike for the sublimity of its theme and the
splendid “hammer strokes” of its triple rhymes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> Crashaw’s translation of 1646, the second in English,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> takes great liberties with the Latin text,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> changing the form and paraphrasing the sense to
achieve a distinctive sublimity of expression that reappears in Blake’s “The Tyger,” a poem generally
supposed to be concerned with the same themes of divine wrath and the punishment of sins.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
                        <note id="n25">
                            <hi rend="i">Roy J. Pearcy, an Associate Professor of English at the University of
Oklahoma, has taught at UCLA and the University of Kent in Canterbury. He teaches Chaucer, Chaucer’s
contemporaries, and History of the English Language, and does research on Chaucer, Old French fabliaux, and
medieval popula narrative. Articles on these topics have appeared in each journals on these topics have
appeared in such journals as</hi> The Chaucer Review, Revue belge de philologie et d’histoire, Fabula,
Romance Notes, <hi rend="i">and</hi> Notes &amp; Queries.</note>
                        <note id="n1">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> For example, Josephine Miles, <hi rend="i">Eras and Modes in
English Poetry</hi> (Berkeley: Univ. of California Press, 1957), pp. 48-49; and Morton d. Paley, 
<hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon,
1970), p. 104.</note>
                        <note id="n2">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Bibliographical details in <hi rend="i">The Poems of Richard
Crashaw</hi>, ed. L.C. Martin (Oxford: Clarendon, 1957), pp. xliii-1xxxvi. Quotations of Crashaw’s poem are
from this edition, pp. 298-301. The first allegedly complete edition of Crashaw, Robert Anderson’s 
<hi rend="i">A Complete Edition of the Poets of Creat Britain</hi> (1793), IV, 707-54, appeared a year after “The
Tyger” had essentially achieved its finished form.</note>
                        <note id="n3">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> See Austin Warren, “The Reputation of Crashaw in the
Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries,” <hi rend="i">SP</hi>, 31 (1934), 385-407.</note>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> Text of the poem and a commentary on it are given by F. J. E.
Raby, <hi rend="i">A History of Christian-Latin Poetry</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1927), pp. 443-52. A writer in
the <hi rend="i">Christan Magazine</hi> of 1760 made the claim that the <hi rend="i">Diee Irae</hi> “savoureth
more of Protestantism than of Popery.”</note>
                        <note id="n5">
                            <hi rend="s">5</hi> The first was made by Joshua Sylvester in 1621.</note>
                        <note id="n6">
                            <hi rend="s">6</hi> A stanza by stanza comparison with the Latin original is given
by Sister Margaret Claydon, <hi rend="i">Richard Crashaw’s Paraphrases of the Vexilla Regis . . . Dies Iras,
O Gloriosa Domina</hi> (Washington: Catholic Univ. of America Press, 1960), pp. 78-99.</note>
                        <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">7</hi> As, for example, in Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the
Imagination</hi>; S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (Boston:
Houghton Mifflin, 1924); Jesse Bier, “A Study of Blake’s ‘The Tyger,’ ” <hi rend="i">Bucknell Univ.
Studies</hi>, 1 (1949), 35-46; and Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Reading of the Shorter
Poems</hi> (Seattle: Univ. of Washington Press, 1963).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Crashaw’s treatment of eschatological wrath is not only in verse, but in the same
quatrains (rhymed <hi rend="i">aabb</hi>) as “The Tyger,” and close scrutiny reveals a still more detailed
metrical correspondence between the two poems. Both alternate catalectic trochaic tetrameters with iambic
tetrameters, although there is an 18:6 preponderance of the former in Blake’s poem, a 16:8 preponderance of
the latter in the first six stanzas of Crashaw’s seventeen-stanza poem. In stanzas 1 and 5 of the “Hymn,”
which most closely resemble Blake, are found exactly the same patterns of iambic and trochaic lines as in
stanzas 1, 5, and 6 of “The Tyger”:
<q>
II<lb/>
                            <lb/>
O that fire! before whose face<lb/>
Heaun &amp; earth shall find no place.<lb/>
O those eyes! whose angry light<lb/>
Must be the day of that dread Night.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
V<lb/>
                            <lb/>
O that Book! whose leaues so bright<lb/>
Will sett the world in seuere light.<lb/>
O that Iudge! whose hand, whose eye<lb/>
None can indure; yet none can fly. 
						</q>
                        <pb id="p07-81" n="81"/>
Both poets have strong caesural pauses in catalectic lines, although the caesura follows the fourth syllable
in Blake, the third in Crashaw. Substituting “What the . . . ?” phrases from Blake for “O that . . . !”
phrases in Crashaw conveniently illuminates the resemblances, and while final meaning is certainly affected by
one poet’s preference for rhetorical questions over the other’s exclamations, the poems are nevertheless
alike in their incantatory repetition of the respective figures chosen, and both employ the same cadences to
evoke a similar sense of religious awe.</p>
                    <p>This sense is intensified by both poets’ use of similar diction. The word 
<hi rend="i">dread</hi> occurs three times in each poem, “dread hand,” “dread feet,” and “dread grasp” in Blake,
“dread Night,” “dread Lord,” and “dread <hi rend="i">Ite</hi>” in Crashaw. Blake’s “deadly terrors” is
matched by Crashaw’s “Horror of . . . Death,” and the word <hi rend="i">horrid</hi> itself appears as
“horrid ribs” in an earlier draft of “The Tyger.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref>
                        <note id="n8">
                            <hi rend="s">8</hi> Texts of the various drafts and a detailed discussion of their
significance for an understanding of the evolution of the poem may be found in Martin K. Nurmi, “Blake’s
revisions of <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi>,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 71 (1956), 669-85.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Josephine Miles has discussed Blake’s use of the imagery of cosmic passion and sense
impression, designed to evoke a sense of the sublime of terror, and Morton Paley has applied her observations
specifically to “The Tyger.” Blake’s practice in this regard could be modelled on Crashaw’s in the “Hymn.”
Blake’s cosmos of “Distant deeps or skies” and star-filled heaven is matched by the “Heaun &amp; earth,” the
“round [of] the circling sun,” and the “hell . . . beneath” of Crashaw. As Blake’s cosmos is penetrated by
an immortal hand or eye, and traversed on aspiring wing, so Crashaw’s world on the Day of Judgment, alerted
by the trump of doom, responds with a universal groan before the inescapable hand and eye of its Judge.
Crashaw’s depiction of divine wrath, while not achieving anything approaching Blake’s concreteness,
confronts us with a figure of fire possessed of a “face” and eyes which burn with an “angry light,” closer to
Blake’s tiger than other manifestations of divine wrath cited to explain this image.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> In Blake the tiger stalks the “forests of the night,” and the
image of the forest sometimes appears in the Bible in conjunction with visions of divine retribution. In the
<hi rend="i">Dies Irae</hi> the trump of doom resounds through the <hi rend="i">sepulchra regionem</hi>, which
Crashaw renders as “the caues of night,” literally the graves of the dead, but perhaps like Blake’s image
signifying more generally the fallen world. Finally, the most intriguing coincidence of images may be that
between the reference in the “Hymn” to the moment “When starres themselues shall stagger,” and the reference
in “The Tyger” to the moment “When the stars threw down their spears.” There is no source in Thomas of Celano
for Crashaw’s image, an indication that Crashaw’s version is the most promising place to look for any
possible influence of the <hi rend="i">Dies Irae</hi> on Blake, and if the influence is genuine it suggests
that the image in Blake may be more conventionally apocalyptic than has generally been supposed. 
                        <note id="n9">
                            <hi rend="s">9</hi> Paley, pp. 41-42, cites Biblical examples of divine wrath
conceived “in images of fire and beasts of prey.” In most instances, however (Mal. 3:2 and Amos 5:6 are
exceptions), God is not identified with fire but uses it as His means to destroy the world. In Zephaniah
1:14-18, the source of the opening stanzas of the <hi rend="i">Dies Irae</hi>, there is reference to the
Lord’s wrath and “the fire of his jealousy.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>By the late 1700s the <hi rend="i">Dies Irae</hi> was established as the most famous
short treatment of the subject matter of doomsday, and Crashaw’s English version of the Latin hymn was also
well-known and much admired. It is therefore quite likely that the “Hymn” would have come to mind when Blake
was composing “The Tyger,” and since, through its poetic rhythms, diction, and imagery much of the distinctive
flavor of the “Hymn” is recaptured in “The Tyger,” Crashaw’s poem may indeed have been quite fresh in
Blake’s memory.</p>
                    <p>Whatever his literary indebtedness, Blake certainly wrote poetry of a kind to elude
definitive explication by comparison with other poets’ similar treatments of similar themes. But for the
purpose of understanding the material transubstantiated in the crucible of his imagination, some note of the
inferences to be drawn from a recognition of the possible influence of Crashaw’s “Hymn” on “The Tyger” may
legitimately be offered in conclusion. That Blake subscribed to Jakob Boehme’s doctrine of contraries is
well known, and often cited to explain certain aspects of the tyger, in whose fearful symmetry are reconciled
beauty and ferocity, Christ and Yahweh, divine mercy and divine justice. The most significant effect of seeing
in “The Tyger” reminiscences of the “Hymn” is to focus attention on Blake’s poem as an apocalypse, to fasten
certain of its activities in time, and to make it a manifestation of divine wrath <hi rend="i">in actu</hi>
rather than <hi rend="i">in posse.</hi> By combining apocalyptic images with the act of creation conceived as
the forging of the tiger, Blake has added to the sense of fearful symmetry a sense of fearful simultaneity. In
God’s (or the visionary poet’s) eternal present, a world created to be destroyed is a world at once
created <hi rend="i">and</hi> destroyed, the two activities blurring and fusin in the finely appropriate image
of the smith at his forge. Blake’s poem suggests such a perspective by seeming to speculate on the future
possibility of creation/destruction (what hand <hi rend="i">could</hi> frame, what hand <hi rend="i">dare</hi>
seize, what art <hi rend="i">could</hi> twist),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> when the stars have already capitulated to chaos and destruction of the not-yet-created
is complete. This view of time accords with what is elsewhere known of Blake’s imagination. In 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> he says: “I see the Past, Present &amp; Future existing all at once Before me.”
Crashaw’s “Hymn” helps us, I think, to recognize that imaginative power to fuse time functioning in “The
Tyger.” 
                        <note id="n10">
                            <hi rend="s">10</hi> The tense and mood of <hi rend="i">dare</hi> is already a
vexed question. See Fred C. Robinson, “Verb Tense in Blake’s ‘The Tyger,’ ” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 79
(1964), 666-69; and John E. Grant and Fred C. Robinson, “Tense and the Sense of Blake’s ‘The Tyger,’ ”
<hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 81 (1966), 596-603.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>