<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.4.essick</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake, Linnell, &amp; James Upton: An Engraving Brought to Light</title>
                <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1974</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1974</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1974"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
        <pb id="p07-78" n="78"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-4-0002">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">NOTES</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">
                                <hi rend="i">Blake, Linnell, &amp; James Upton: An Engraving Brought to
Light</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Shortly after their first meeting, John Linnell hired Blake to lay in an engraving
after the younger artist’s oil portrait of the Baptist preacher James Upton (1760-1834). Linnell’s
journal, account book, manuscript autobiography, and the miscellaneous Blake-Linnell accounts now at Yale and
in Sir Geoffrey Keynes’ collection document this commission as thoroughly as any of Blake’s separate
plates. We know when, for whom, and at what fee the work was done, but from 1912 until the present no one has
actually seen the engraving and recognized it as in part Blake’s work. By a stroke of good fortune I was
able to acquire two impressions of this plate—as far as I can determine, the only ones extant—in London
during the summer of 1973. While it hardly embodies the energetic imagination found in Blake’s most admired
engravings, it is a fine piece of craftsmanship with historical importance as the first product of Blake’s
relationship with Linnell and as a strong influence on Blake’s later engraving style.</p>
	<note id="n0">
                        <hi rend="i">Robert N. Essick is an Associate Professor of English at California State
University, Northridge. He has recently co-authored a commentary on the</hi> Night Thoughts 
<hi rend="i">engravings (forthcoming from Dover) and edited a collection of reprinted articles on Blake’s
art</hi>, The Visionary Hand <hi rend="i">(Hennessey &amp; Ingalls).</hi>
                    </note>
                    <p>On 24 June 1818, Linnell wrote in his journal that he had gone “To Mr. Blake evening.
Delivered to Mr Blake the picture of Mr Upton &amp; the Copperplate to begin the engraving” (Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 256). Years later, Linnell wrote about this same first employment of Blake in
his manuscript “Autobiography”:
<q>
At Rathbone place 1818 my first Child Hannah was born Sep. 8, and here I first became acquainted with William
Blake to whom I paid a visit in company with the younger Mr Cumberland. Blake lived then in South Molton St.
Oxford St second floor. We soon became intimate &amp; I employed him to help me with an engraving of my
portrait of Mr Upton a Baptist preacher which he was glad to do having scarcely enough employment to live by
at the prices he could obtain[;] everything in Art was at a low ebb then. (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
257)
</q>
With this modest endeavor Linnell began a friendship which was to sustain Blake throughout the last nine years
of his life.</p>
                    <p>The sequence of payments for Blake’s work on the Upton plate is fully recorded in
receipts made by both men. On 12 August 1818, Linnell paid Blake £2, and again on 11 September paid Blake
another £5. The second payment is specifically entered for the “Plate of Mr Upton” in Linnell’s general
account book (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 584). Both payments are confirmed by Blake’s receipts, the
second reading “Recievd 11 Septembr 1818 of Mr Linnell the Sum of Five pounds on account of Mr Uptons Plate”
(<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 580). In his journal for 12 September, Linnell wrote that “Mr Blake
brought a proof of Mr Uptons plate[,] left the plate &amp; named £15 as the price of what was already done by
him” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 258). Blake’s note of 19 September gives the full amount to be
paid “For Laying in the Engraving of Mr Uptons portrait” as £15.15s., of which £7 had already been paid (on
12 August and 11 September). The outstanding £8.15s. was paid in two installments, £5 on 9 November and
£3.15s. on 31 December (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 581). Thus Blake worked on the plate from 24 June
to 12 September 1818, and payment for his labors was completed on the last day of that year.</p>
                    <p>The earlier of the two impressions reproduced here [illus. 1] is a proof on India
paper, laid on a sheet of unwatermarked white wove paper, lacking all letters except for “James Upton” very
lightly scratched into the plate 1.8 cm. below the design. Most of the lines appear to have been engraved,
although a few lines on the right margin have the blunt ends typical of etching. There was probably some
initial etching of basic outlines, but this work has been covered by subsequent engraving. A. T. Story in 
<hi rend="i">The Life of John Linnell</hi> (London, 1892) notes that the plate was executed in part in dry point
(II, 242), and this may well have been the method used to produce the fine lines in the face.</p>
                    <p>Just above the lower plate-mark is the date <hi rend="i">March. 1819</hi>— written in
pencil, and to the right also in pencil is <hi rend="i">Unfinished Proof. must be returned to Mr. J.
Linnell.</hi> This writing is very similar to the pencil notes on Fuseli’s drawings of Michelangelo and the
frontispiece to Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> once in Linnell’s collection which Ruthven Todd
believes were “undoubtedly made by members of the Linnell family” (<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter 19</hi>
[Winter 1971-72], p. 176). It seems likely therefore that the note on the Upton proof was 
     					   <pb id="p07-76" n="76"/>
						<figure n="UptonEngraving.7.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="778">
							<head>1 Portrait of James Upton, engraved by Blake and Linnell after Linnell’s painting.</head>
							<figDesc><corr type="emend">Proof before letters. Author’s collection.</corr></figDesc>
						</figure>
				        <pb id="p07-77" n="77"/>
						<figure n="ESXL.1.2B.SP" rend="file" width="600" height="955">
							<head>2 Portrait of James Upton, open letter proof.</head>
							<figDesc>Author’s collection.</figDesc>
						</figure>
                        <pb id="p07-79" n="79"/>
made by Linnell. The recipient of this loan is unknown, although perhaps it was the writing engraver to whom
the copperplate was also sent to engrave the inscriptions found on the second state of the plate reproduced
here [illus. 2]: PAINTED AND ENGRAVED BY J<hi rend="s">NO</hi>. LINNELL. | JAMES UPTON | <hi rend="i">Pastor
of the Baptist Church Meeting in Church Street Blackfriars Road</hi> | <hi rend="i">London Published June 
1<hi rend="s">st</hi> 1819 by.</hi> In this state a stick pin now adorns Upton’s shirt just below the collar, the
mole on his right cheek and a few lines on the collar beneath his chin have been removed, and the shading in
the background has been deepened slightly. This is the same state of the print, and very likely the same
impression on white laid paper without a watermark, as the one recorded by Archibald G. B. Russell in 1912,
“an open-letter proof in the Linnell collection” (<hi rend="i">The Engravings of William Blake</hi>, p. 136).
In his catalogue of <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi> (Dublin, 1956), p. 83,
Geoffrey Keynes simply repeats the information given by Russell; apparently Keynes had never seen the print
himself. The lack of a publisher’s name in the imprint, together with the rarity of the print, suggests that
it was never actually published. Story writes that “the price paid to Linnell for this engraving was 50
guineas” (<hi rend="i">Life of Linnell</hi>, I, 159), but this was probably received from whoever commissioned
the original portrait—perhaps Upton’s family or congregation. In both impressions the design size is 26 ×
19.3 cm. and the plate-mark measures 35.2 × 27.2 cm.</p>
                    <p>It is very difficult to determine the extent of Blake’s work on the plate. “Laying
in” an engraving could mean anything from etching the bare outline to doing all but the finish work on the
central figure. The amount which Blake requested for his work suggests that he did more than just outline
etching. If indeed Blake’s financial situation was as tenuous as Linnell indicates in his “Autobiography,”
then it would seem likely that Blake must have done considerable work on the copperplate to charge a new
friend and potential patron £15.15s. The Hesiod illustrations executed in stippled lines after Flaxman’s
designs brought Blake only £5.5s. for each plate in 1816. In 1824 and 1825 Linnell paid Blake £20 for his
work on the portrait engraving of Wilson Lowery, and Blake’s contribution was in this case extensive enough
for him to receive second billing on the plate (<hi rend="i">Drawn from Life by J. Linnell, &amp; Engraved by
J. Linnell &amp; W. Blake</hi>). But it is unlikely that the first state reproduced here is the proof which
Blake brought to Linnell on 12 September 1818. The six months between the delivery of the copperplate to
Linnell and the pencil inscription on the India paper proof would have allowed Linnell to do a good deal of
work on the plate. Further, had Blake almost finished the engraving himself, Linnell would surely have given
him some recognition on the plate—or we would have a record of Blake’s reaction to such double-dealing and
the entire Blake-Linnell relationship would not have been as fruitful as we know it to have been.</p>
                    <p>The Upton portrait marks an important watershed in Blake’s career as an engraver.
Only the presentation of wood grain in the table seems characteristic of Blake’s earlier style, as in the
“Beggar’s Opera” plate of 1788-90, the sixth illustration to Mary Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original
Stories</hi> (1791), and “Our End is come” (1793). Blake’s engraved portraits prior to and immediately
following his contacts with Linnell demonstrate the influence that the Upton plate, and perhaps other
engravings by Linnell, had on his craft. The profile of Lavater (1800) is a remarkably fine example of dot and
lozenge engraving, but bears no resemblance to the Upton plate. In the portrait of Earl Spencer (1811), Blake
returned to the techniques he learned in his youth from Basire. The engraving is burdened with a heavy net of
lines unresponsive to differing textures, and although it does have a certain blunt power the total effect is
unfortunate. In contrast, the Upton portrait is a first-class piece of work, with great subtlety in the
handling of flesh tones and patterns of light and dark.</p>
                    <p>While nothing in Blake’s earlier work prepares us for the high-finish techniques of
the Upton plate, Linnell’s own engraved portrait of Rev. John Martin, dated 1813 in the imprint, shows the
same characteristics of modulated but basically dark ruled background, heavy cross-hatching on the clothing,
and fine lines with dot and flick work on the hands and face. The same techniques appear again in Blake’s
next engraving after the Upton plate, a portrait of Reverend Robert Hawker published by A. A. Paris in 1820.
Although this plate reproduces a painting by Ponsford, not Linnell, the almost identical building up of the
lines produces the same textures of cloth and skin, and even the same background shading, found in the Upton
engraving. Clearly, Linnell’s techniques as an engraver embodied in the Upton plate, and perhaps in other
examples seen by Blake, had a profound effect of Blake’s own methods. Even the Job illustrations show this
influence, particularly in the use of swelling lines to delineate rounded forms, such as arms and legs, and in
the dramatic use of light and shadow effects. The fine lines and dot and flick work used so effectively for
the faces in the Job plates also owe a good deal to Linnell’s practice.</p>
                    <p>The sudden flowering of Blake’s late engraving style in the Job illustrations has
never been explained. The Upton plate, regardless of the extent to which the work is by Blake or by Linnell,
now makes the transition from the techniques of the 1790s to the Job less of a mystery. I would suggest that
Blake’s reworking of “Joseph of Arimathea” and “Mirth” was also stimulated by his contacts with Linnell,
although this theory would require dating the final state of the “Joseph” somewhat later than Keynes gives in
his <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi> catalogue. The Job series—surely Blake’s masterpiece as an intaglio
engraver—could not have been possible without Linnell’s financial assistance. With the rediscovery of the
Upton plate it becomes clear that Linnell’s artistic influence was also crucial.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>