<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>7.4.morkan</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">Milton’s Eikonoklastes &amp; Blake’s Mythic Geography: A
Parallel</title>
                <author n="Morkan">Joel Morkan</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1974</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1974</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">07.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
                            <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
                            <name>Graham Conley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1974"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_07">
        <body>
            <pb id="p07-87" n="87"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-07-4-0003">
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Joel <name>Morkan</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    <ref target="n28" type="note">*</ref></byline>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">
                                <hi rend="i">Milton’s</hi> Eikonoklastes <hi rend="i">&amp; Blake’s Mythic
Geography: A Parallel</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>There is an interesting parallel between a passage in Milton’s 
<hi rend="i">Eikonoklastes</hi> and the way Blake conflates Biblical and English geography for mythic purposes in
<hi rend="i">Milton, The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
                        <note id="n28">
                        <hi rend="i">Joel Morkan is an Associate Professor of English at Florida State
University. He has published essays on Milton and the Romantics. He is particularly interested in the
relationship between Milton and Blake.</hi>
                    </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In his attack on Charles I as a Urizenic tyrant, Milton wrote:
<q>
                            <hi rend="i">Ireland</hi> was as <hi rend="i">Ephraim</hi>, the strength of his
head, <hi rend="i">Scotland</hi>, as <hi rend="i">Judah</hi>, was his Law-giver; but over 
<hi rend="i">England</hi> as over <hi rend="i">Edom</hi> he meant to cast his Shoo; and yet so many sober
Englishmen not sufficiently awake to consider this, like men inchanted with the Circaean cup of servitude,
will not be held back from running thir own heads into the Yoke of Bondage.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">1</ref>
                            <note id="n22">
                                <hi rend="s">1</hi> Merritt Y. Hughes, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Prose
Works of John Milton</hi> (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1962), II, 488.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The fusion of English and Biblical geography, the mythic humanization of the nation,
and the figure of the whole people as a sleeping or enchanted giant under the foot of a brutal tyrant are all
elements familiar from Blake’s poetry. Some of this is attributable to the imaginative compatibility of the
two writers, and also, no doubt, to their common grounding in such scriptural passages as Psalm 60:7-8:
“Ephraim also is the strength of mine head, Judah is my lawgiver. / Over Edom will I cast out my shoe.”</p>
                    <p>There are, however, more specific connections between Blake’s use of allegorical
geography and this passage from Milton. In <hi rend="i">Eikonoklastes</hi>, Ireland is Ephraim, and in
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (72:23) the seven counties of Connaught are assigned to Ephraim. In
Milton’s passage Scotland is Judah, whereas in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (16:54) one of Judah’s
functions is to<gap type="emend"/>
<pb id="p07-89" n="89"/>
<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/>
guard Aberdeen, Berwick, and Dumfries. Finally, in Blake, Edom is a fallen land 
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 17:20; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 49:43; 92:23; 96:9), but is also both the giant who
must recover his lost inheritance and the land that must be transformed before the apocalypse 
(<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 2:14-20, 3:5-6).</p>
                    <p>One hesitates to put more weight on these parallels than they will bear; however, they
do point in a direction that could be fruitful in further explorations of both Blakes’s mythic geography and
history in the prophetic Books, that is Milton’s historical and polemical prose and his native antecedents
in the use of allegorical geography: Spenser, Drayton, <corr type="emend">Phineas Fletcher,</corr> and William Browne of Tavistock. 
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>