<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
	<idno>8.1-2.tolley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">John Todhunter: A Forgotten Debt to Blake</title>
        <author n="Tolley">Michael J. Tolley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer-Fall 1974</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1974</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.1-2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1974"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <pb id="p08-15" n="15"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-1_2-0003">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">John Todhunter: A Forgotten Debt to Blake</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="b">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">MICHAEL J.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">TOLLEY</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <ref target="n58" type="note">*</ref>
        </byline>
        <p>John Todhunter, the Anglo-Irish poet (1839-1916) is known to Yeats scholars, being mentioned
several times in <hi rend="i">Autobiographies</hi> and associated with Yeats in several dramatic and literary
ventures. He is remembered chiefly for some of his later work and for his interest in Shelley. His early debt
to Blake, perceived in the nineteenth century, is now forgotten.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">1</ref> Perhaps this debt is less pervasive in the later work (which I do not know),
if Yeats’ interesting assessment is accurate: “If he had liked anything strongly he might have been a famous
man . . . but with him every book was a new planting, and not a new bud on an old bough” 
(<hi rend="i">Autobiographies</hi> [London, 1955], p. 117). Certainly in the early poetry (which is sometimes
impressive), he ranges widely in style and subject. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See, however, Ian
Fletcher’s recent article in <hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi>, 21 (Spring 1972), pp. 72-94, “The
Ellis-Blake-Yeats Manuscript Cluster,” which has a short section on Todhunter and Blake.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="i">Michael J. Tolley is Senior Lecturer in English at the University of Adelaide. He
recently completed his thesis for London University on Blake’s use of the Bible, part of which will be
published, with additions, in the</hi> Newsletter.</note></p>
        <p>Todhunter figures in Evelyn Noble Armitage’s <hi rend="i">The Quaker Poets of Great Britain and
Ireland</hi> (London, 1896), though by that time he was, we are told, no longer in membership of the Society
of Friends. Introducing the short selection of Todhunter’s poems, Armitage writes that “He is a strong poet;
full of vigour and imagination, and yet with a delicate beauty of workmanship and touch, which render his
poems delightful to read and remember, apart from their essential truth of thought and imagery.” She goes on
to note that “In the two poems ‘Lost’ and ‘Found,’ he has caught the very spirit of Blake, and the
strange mystical charms of that singer of dreams and visions” (pp. 266-67). The poems in question are
reprinted from Todhunter’s first book, <hi rend="i">Laurella and Other Poems</hi> (London, 1876), pp.
274-75. They are a kind of pastiche of Blake’s loose octosyllabic quatrains, borrowing rhythm, diction and
imagery from (at least, I think) “A Dream,” “William Bond,” “The Crystal Cabinet,” “Mary,” “The Mental
Traveller,” “A Little Boy Lost” and other “lost” and “found” poems, as well as (I suspect) the poem “To My
Dear Friend, M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Anna Flaxman” in Mrs. Blake’s letter of 14 September 1800 and also the
letter of Blake’s to Flaxman of 21 September 1800.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Lost</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
		<q>
I WANDERED from my mother’s side<lb/>
In the fragrant paths of morn;<lb/>
Naked, weary, and forlorn,<lb/>
I fainted in the hot noon-tide.<lb/>
<lb/>
For I had met a maiden wild,<lb/>
Singing of love and love’s delight;<lb/>
And with her song she me beguiled,<lb/>
And her soft arms and bosom white.<lb/>
<lb/>
I followed fast, I followed far,<lb/>
And ever her song flowed blithe and free;<lb/>
‘Where Love’s own flowery meadows are,<lb/>
There shall our golden dwelling be!’<lb/>
<lb/>
I followed far, I followed fast,<lb/>
And oft she paused, and cried, ‘O here!’<lb/>
But where I came no flower would last,<lb/>
And Joy lay cold upon his bier.<lb/>
<lb/>
I wandered on, I wandered wide,<lb/>
Alas! she fleeted with the morn;<lb/>
Weary, weeping, and forlorn,<lb/>
She left me in the fierce noontide.
</q>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Found</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
		<q>
NAKED, bleeding, and forlorn,<lb/>
I wandered on the mountain<lb/>
To hide my wounds from shame and scorn,<lb/>
I made a garment of my pride.<lb/>
<lb/>
Till there came a tyrant grey,<lb/>
He stript and chained me with disgrace,<lb/>
He led me by the public way,<lb/>
And sold me in the market-place.<lb/>
<lb/>
To many masters was I bound,<lb/>
And many a grievous load I bore;<lb/>
But in the toil my flesh grew sound,<lb/>
And from my limbs the chains I tore. 
                        <pb id="p08-16" n="16"/>
I ran to seek my mother’s cot,<lb/>
And I found Love singing there,<lb/>
And round it many a pleasant plot,<lb/>
And shadowy streams and gardens fair.<lb/>
<lb/>
Like virgin gold the thatch I see,<lb/>
Like virgin gold the doorway sweet;<lb/>
And in the blissful noon each tree<lb/>
A ladder for the angel’s feet.
</q>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Laurella</hi> itself, “Lost” and “Found” are but two of several lyrics in the
Blakean manner: indeed, two similar poems, “Paradise Lost” and “Paradise Found,” are stated in a fictional
preface to be the work of Blake himself! These and other Blakean poems are in a section of 
<hi rend="i">Laurella</hi> entitled “The Mystic,” the fictional author of the section, who is “a crazy Atheist”
named “M—.” The lengthy preface to the section records the Mystic’s opinions and character in a manner
heavily reminiscent of passages in Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> where, as it were, the enthusiasm of a
Samuel Palmer is combined with Crabb Robinson’s memory for dialogue. While there are other influences on
poems in “The Mystic,” for instance Goethe and Shelley, the section suggests strongly that it is the response
of an enthusiastic convert to Blake, presumably after a perusal of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi>
(1863).</p>
          <p>It is possible that these Blakean poems were written a long time before the publication of 
<hi rend="i">Laurella</hi> in 1876. Evelyn Armitage, who may have known the author, states that most of the pieces
in <hi rend="i">Laurella</hi> “had been written many years before.” Todhunter himself, in his general preface
to <hi rend="i">Laurella</hi>, writes: “Most of the poems in this volume were written many years ago, and
several have already appeared in Magazines and in <hi rend="i">Kottabos</hi>—a periodical published each
term in connection with Dublin University.” Todhunter was a graduate of Trinity College, Dublin (B.A. 1865,
M.B. and M.Ch. 1866), but, according to Armitage, he then left Dublin to walk “the hospitals of Vienna and
Paris,” before returning to Dublin to be Professor of English Literature at Alexandra College (1870-74) and
also Assistant Physician to Cork St. Fever Hospital. He received his M.D. in 1871. These dates, then, suggest
the periods within which a search may be made of the University magazines for an earlier publication of the
Blake poems in <hi rend="i">Laurella.</hi> The Preface to “The Mystic” smacks strongly of undergraduate
hoaxing and 1865 is thus a likely date. Unfortunately, I have been unable to pursue a search for the poems at
this stage, owing to the limited library resources here.</p>
          <p>This interesting post-Romantic poet would well repay further study, and I would be interested to
hear if any one is, in fact, working on Todhunter.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Preface to “The Mystic” [Excerpt]</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>It is now many years since I first met the strange person who was the Author of the following
Poems. I made his acquaintance at a soiree at the house of the late Dr. A. B—, whose passion for collecting
‘<hi rend="i">characters</hi>’ rivalled in intensity the china-mania of the present day. He was not the
lion of the evening, having been collected some time previously; but I at once felt that he was no ordinary
<hi rend="i">eccentric.</hi> His dress was shabby, and, without being sordid, had a pleasant student-like
slovenliness about it, like the well-worn binding of some precious old volume; to which his sensitive face,
with its delicate curves of suffering and wrinkles of thought, formed a fitting title-page. The whole man had,
indeed, a Faust-like look of antiquity—an aging older than his years, which had grizzled his hair and beard
somewhat before their time; and, as he stood a little apart, sometimes turning over the pages of a book,
sometimes letting his dreamy grey eyes wander absently around the room, I gazed at him with a strange
fascination,—
<q>
‘Like some watcher of the skies<lb/>
When a new planet swims into his ken.’
</q>
I felt that I was in the presence of what Goethe would have called a ‘<hi rend="i">Nature.</hi>’</p>
          <p>His views about the Bible were peculiar and paradoxical. ‘To fools only is it an ordinary book.
It is more even than the literature of an inspired nation. It contains a real revelation as no other book
does.’ Yet he was no Bibliolater, and gave full play to his critical faculties in his reading of it. ‘It
is not a perfect mirror reflecting the face of God. It is full of flaws; but the best we have as yet. As a
final authority the Bible abrogates itself. It is not that light of which it bears witness—the Logos
indwelling in our hearts. A church built upon its infallibility is a house built on the sand; an ark ready to
go to pieces when the wind of change blows roughly. Then the passengers must make shift to escape, ‘some on
boards and some on broken pieces of the ship’—as the Protestants are doing now. But it is the breath of
God that raises the storm. Does not the wind of a new Pentecost begin to blow over this world that faints for
a new revelation?’</p>
          <p>He frequently expressed himself in rather Antinomian language: ‘What is this nonsense about the
Moral Law? God is not a moral being at all. The universe exists for beauty, not for good and evil.’ Yet,
like most theoretic Antinomians, he acknowledged the practical necessity of morality in the finite world; and
his life was, so far as my observation reaches, singularly pure.</p>
          <p>For Blake, as some of his poems prove, he had a profound admiration. ‘ “Paradise Lost” and
“Paradise Found” are his, not mine,’ he declared. ‘He sang them to me one night. I wrote them down on the
spot.’ ‘As a painter Blake would have been much greater, if Raffaelle had not clung round him like a
serpent, breathing academic poison. What had he to do with Raffaelle? When his drawing is wrong, it is wrong
from academic vanity and bad taste rather than ignorance and weakness. In his instinctive impulses he is
greater than Michael Angelo—much greater than every one else.’</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>