<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
	<idno>8.1-2.carey</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">James Smetham (1821-1889) and Gilchrist’s Life of Blake</title>
        <author n="Carey">Frances Carey</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer-Fall 1974</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1974</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.1-2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1974"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <pb id="p08-17" n="17"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-1_2-0004">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">James Smetham (1821-1889) and Gilchrist’s <hi rend="u">Life of Blake</hi></hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>BY <docAuthor>FRANCES A. <name>CAREY</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">*</ref></byline>
        <corr type="emend" rend="plain">
        	<figure n="StruggleAndSorrow.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="726">
        		<figTranscr>ÆT[ATIS] 26.]<lb/>
        		STRUGGLE AND SORROW.<lb/>
        		55<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		of the same suggestive theme, is Let loose the Dogs of War—a<lb/>
        		Demon cheering on blood-hounds who seize a man by the throat;<lb/>
        		of which Mr. Ruskin possesses the original pencil sketch, Mr. Linnell<lb/>
        		the water-colour drawing.<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		1784<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		S[u]nd[a]y July .4. Ja[me]s B[lake]<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		During the summer of 1784, died Blake’s father, an honest<lb/>
        		shopkeeper of the old school, and a devout man—a dissenter. He<lb/>
        		was buried in Bunhill Fields, on the fourth of July (a Sunday) says<lb/>
        		the Register. The eldest son, James,—a year and a half William’s<lb/>
        		senior,—continued to live with the widow Catherine, and succeeded<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		Catherine<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		W[illiam] B[lake]<lb/>
        		Rob[er]t<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		to the hosier’s business in Broad Street, still a highly respectable<lb/>
        		street, and a good one for trade, as it and the whole neighbourhood<lb/>
        		continued until the era of Nash and the ‘first gentleman in<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		Nash.<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		Europe.’ Golden Square was still the ‘town residence’ of some<lb/>
        		half-dozen M.P.’s—for county or rotten borough; Poland Street and<lb/>
        		Great Marlborough Street of others. Between this brother and the<lb/>
        		artist no strong sympathy existed, little community of sentiment<lb/>
        		or common ground (mentally) of any kind; although indeed, James<lb/>
        		— for the most part an humble matter-of-fact man—had his spiritual<lb/>
        		and visionary side too; would at times talk Swedenborg, talk of<lb/>
        		seeing Abraham and Moses, and to outsiders seem like his gifted<lb/>
        		brother ‘a bit mad’—a mild madman instead of a wild and stormy.<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		Ja[me]s B[lake]<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		On his father’s death, Blake, who found Design yield no income,<lb/>
        		Engraving but a scanty one, returned from Green Street, Leicester<lb/>
        		Fields, to familiar Broad Street. At No. 27, next door to his brother’s,<lb/>
        		he set up shop as printseller and engraver, in partnership with a<lb/>
        		former fellow-apprentice at Basire’s: James Parker, a man some six<lb/>
        		or seven years his senior. An engraving by Blake after Stothard,<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		27. Ja[me]s Parker. 34<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		W[illiam] B[lake]<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		Zephyrus and Flora (a long oval), was published by the firm ‘Parker<lb/>
        		and Blake’ this same year (1784). Mrs. Mathew, still friendly and<lb/>
        		patronizing, though one day to be less eager for the poet’s services<lb/>
        		as Lion in Rathbone Place, countenanced, nay perhaps first set the<lb/>
        		scheme going—in an ill-advised philanthropic hour; favouring it,<lb/>
        		<lb/>
        		Zeph[yru]s &amp; Flora.</figTranscr>
        		<figDesc><corr type="emend"/></figDesc>
        	</figure>
        </corr>
        <pb id="p08-18" n="18"/>
        <p>James Smetham’s claim on posterity has largely rested upon his 1869 review of Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> which was incorporated in the second edition at Rossetti’s instigation. This
sympathetic but conventional mid-Victorian interpretation of Blake only represents a minor aspect of
Smetham’s career; his letters and paintings do far greater justice to the complexity of a man, whom Geoffrey
Grigson has described as “an imaginative artist who surpasses almost all his time in England.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">1</ref> This article will concentrate upon Smetham’s
visual imagination seen in the light of the marginal illustrations with which he annotated his own copy of the
Gilchrist <hi rend="i">Life.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. Grigson, <hi rend="i">The Harp of Aeolus</hi> (London, 1948), pp.
96-97.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Collection of Dr. Gerald Bindman.</note></p>
        <p>An almost overwhelming degree of spirituality pervades Smetham’s small scale biblical and
landscape compositions, which prompted Rossetti to invoke parallels with the work of Blake and Palmer: “In all
these he partakes greatly of Blake’s immediate spirit, being also often allied by landscape intensity to
Samuel Palmer.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">3</ref> The emotional energy
required to achieve such an effect, did, however, contain the seeds of self-destruction as
<figure n="ValeDarkens.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="194">
	<head>p. 39: “away I go, / And the vale darkens at my pensive woe.”</head>
</figure>
Ruskin prophesied in 1854,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">4</ref> and
Smetham was eventually to subside into an endogenous depressive illness from 1878 until his death of 1889. The
Smetham correspondence exhibits some of the same 
                    <pb id="p08-19" n="19"/>
intimate, revelatory quality as the Haydon diaries,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">5</ref> unfolding a personality which partook of “Blake’s immediate spirit” transmuted by a
powerful strain of Methodist piety; this bifurcal influence clearly emerges in the unifying theme of the
letters, Smetham’s concept of destiny in terms of a <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> which, in visual
form, was poignantly summarized by one of his last paintings, <hi rend="i">Going Home</hi>, depicting an old
man on the road to death.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">6</ref> Smetham’s
endeavor to develop a fully integrated imagination combining “art, literature and the religious life all in
one,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">7</ref> was reflected in a self-imposed
regime of intense, disciplined study, the results of which were enshrined in a system of 
<hi rend="i">monumentalism</hi>; the grandiose designation of <hi rend="i">monument</hi> was in fact applied to a
tiny, squared pen drawing, encapsulating in the margin Smetham’s thoughts on the text in question.
Shakespeare, the Bible, Tennyson and Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> were all subjected to this
approach, which was initiated by the artist at eleven o’clock on the evening of 18 February 1848. The
creative fervor and elevation of purpose infusing the thumbnail sketches, is eloquently expressed by
Smetham’s account of how, in later years, he would revisit his <hi rend="i">monuments</hi>, “pouring the oil
of joy on the shapeless stone in which I saw my thought as Michael Angelo in his marble saw hidden the
gigantic shapes of Night and Day.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">3</hi> A. Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 2nd ed. (London,
1880), p. 429.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">4</hi> J. Ruskin, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, ed. E. T. Cook and Alexander
Wedderburn (London, 1903-12), XIV, 461.</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">5</hi> J. Smetham, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, eds. W. Davies and Sarah Smetham
(London, 1891).</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Walker Art Gallery, Liverpool.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Smetham, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, p. 13.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Smetham, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, p. 92.</note></p>
        <p>Smetham’s copy of <hi rend="i">Gilchrist</hi> is a peculiarly apt example of 
<hi rend="i">monumentalism</hi> since he had been recommended by Rossetti in 1861 as a suitable draughtsman for
the line drawings in the text. In the event Smetham was deprived of the commission but in July 1867 supplied
his own miniature cycle of the life of Blake, which paid a self-conscious
<figure n="Robert.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="412">
	<figTranscr>and<lb/>
	[cheris]hed<lb/>
	[blen]ded<lb/>
	[be]fore<lb/>
	[techn]ical<lb/>
	[desi]gn.<lb/>
	[half-a-cro]wn,<lb/>
	[1]0d.<lb/>
	[n]ew</figTranscr>
	<head>p. 69: “In a vision of the night, the form of Robert stood before him, and revealed the wished-for
secret, directing him to the technical mode by which could be produced a fac-simile of song and
design.”</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p08-20" n="20"/>
homage to the marginal illustrations of medieval manuscripts. For Smetham an illuminated book was “a mystery,
like the Microcosm” into whose borders were wrought “the whole life and soul and history of the men who did
them; but thinly veiled.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">9</ref> The 
<hi rend="i">Gilchrist</hi> marginal designs provide just such a documentation of the artist’s inner life
concealed beneath the commentary on Blake’s spiritual history; author portraits of Smetham himself
periodically intrude upon the Blakean cycle, again reminiscent of the practice of medieval scribes and
illuminators. The main pictorial narrative includes not only episodes and personalities from Blake’s
material existence but also those from his visionary world; “majestic shadows, grey but luminous and superior
to the common height of men” encountered on the Felpham shore (p. 159), have as much substance as Mrs.
Mathew’s bluestockings (p. 45) or the Godwin circle of radicals (p. 92); a corporeal Robert Blake plays
leap-frog with J. T. Smith on one page (p. 57), then later appears in spiritual form to reveal to his elder
brother the secret of stereotype printing (p. 69), while funeral processions, whether they be for fairies (p.
159) or Sir Joshua Reynolds
<figure n="IsaiahAndEzekiel.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="259">
	<figTranscr>Is[aiah]<lb/>
	Ezek[iel]<lb/>
	<lb/>
	[H]ELL.   83</figTranscr>
	<head>p. 83: Blake’s vision of Isaiah and Ezekiel in “A Memorable Fancy,” <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell.</hi></head>
</figure>
                    (p. 96), are all treated to the same loving delineation. In the second volume the 
<hi rend="i">monuments</hi> are almost exclusively confined to William Michael Rossetti’s annotated catalogue,
where Smetham used the descriptions attached to each item as a basis for illustration; his own knowledge of
Blake’s visual art was probably limited to the reproductions in <hi rend="i">Gilchrist.</hi> Smetham’s
naive, literal renderings of poetic images constitute a further category of <hi rend="i">monument</hi>;
punctuating the line from the <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, “And the vale darkens at my pensive woe,” a
lonely figure is represented wandering amidst gloomy obscurity (p. 39). These evocative visual annotations
serve to underline the unifying links between the “whole life and soul and history” of Smetham and his
subject, which are perhaps epitomized by his impression of Blake’s soul finding “refuge amid the slights of
the outward vulgar throng” in the invisible world (p. 245). <note id="n32">9 Smetham, 
<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, p. 93.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="i">Frances Carey has undertaken postgraduate study at Harvard and the Institute of
Fine Arts, New York. She is currently writing her doctoral thesis on “English Religious Painting 1770-1830”
for the Courtauld Institute, London University. She is the</hi> Newsletter<hi rend="i">’s new Associate
Editor for the United Kingdom.</hi></note></p>
        <pb id="p08-21" n="21"/>
        <figure n="Saturn.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="407">
          <figTranscr>[Ang]el;<lb/>
          [weste]rly<lb/>
          [Th]en<lb/>
          I<lb/>
          [volum]es,<lb/>
          [ca]me<lb/>
          [betw]een</figTranscr>
          <head>p. 85: “A Memorable Fancy”—“Here I stayed to rest, and then leaped into the void between
Saturn and the fixed stars.”</head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p08-22" n="22"/>
        <figure n="Johnson.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="260">
          <figTranscr>Godwin.   Fuseli<lb/>
          H[olcroft]<lb/>
          Price   Priestley   Blake</figTranscr>
          <head>p. 92: The radicals in Johnson’s house.</head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p08-23" n="23"/>
        <figure n="Felpham.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="300">
          <head>p. 157: Blake at Felpham.</head>
          <figDesc>“Often, in after years, Blake would speak with enthusiasm of the shifting lights on the sea
he had watched from those windows.”</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="MajesticShadows.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="316">
          <head>p. 159: “majestic shadows, grey but luminous, and superior to the common height of
men.”</head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p08-24" n="24"/>
        <figure n="FairyFuneral.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="242">
          <head>p. 159: A fairy funeral.</head>
        </figure>
        <figure n="FindingRefuge.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="252">
          <head>p. 245: Blake’s soul finding refuge in the invisible world amid the slights of the outward
vulgar throng.</head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p08-25" n="25"/>
        <figure n="RoyalAcademy.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="307">
          <head>p. 248: Blake drawing the Laocoon in the Royal Academy.</head>
        </figure>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>