<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
	<idno>8.1-2.macmillan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Dialogue Between Blake and Wordsworth</title>
        <author n="Macmillan">Malcolm Kingsley Macmillan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer-Fall 1974</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1974</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.1-2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1974"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <pb id="p08-38" n="38"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-1_2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main"><hi rend="b">Dialogue between Blake and Wordsworth</hi>: WRITTEN IN ROME BEFORE
17 APRIL 1889 AND LEFT UNFINISHED</title>
        </head>
        <byline>BY <docAuthor>MALCOLM KINGSLEY <name>MACMILLAN</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">*</ref></byline>
        <figure n="Radicals.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="263">
          <figTranscr>Godwin.   Fuseli<lb/>
          <lb/>
          Price   Priestley   Blake</figTranscr>
        </figure>
        <p>
          <hi rend="i">Notes on Blake and Wordsworth Dialogue</hi>
        </p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Nature.</hi> Taedium Elysii: Blake and Wordsworth.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Scene.</hi> A broad plain covered with high spreading plants, flowering into small
blossoms of a dull rose colour. A slow black river seems to gird it round. From a sky, like the roof of a
cavern, a skirt of water is pouring down.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">William Wordsworth</hi>, in a white smock and gray hat, is seated a few yards from the
river.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">William Wordsworth</hi> (murmuring)—
<q>
“Apart from happy ghosts, that gather flowers<lb/>
Of blissful quiet ’mid unfading bowers.”
</q></p>
        <p>Such was the doom to which the gods, Protesilaus, and I condemned the hapless Laodamia. But here am
I in the very high tide of Elysium, the equable and utter quietude, the unfading Asphodels, and yet I am the
only ghost who seems at all happy in it. A chorus of heroes and heroines performs daily at noon, and there is
much rhythmical and regulated reunion. But no one seems to appreciate the bliss except myself. A number of
indignant shades cross my path; but they shout for ichor and blood and all kinds of unseemly revivifications.
Who can that be, walking impatiently on, and regarding a large-leaved waterplant which he holds in his hand? I
protest it is no other than William Blake, the mad painter and songwriter. Most excellent shade, I prithee
pause a moment!</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Not an instant. This devilish dulness is bad enough without the
conversation of the worst of all devils, a dull rascal.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> Rascal!</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> A renegade, a presumer, a blasphemer.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> I was always true to my principles. I sought something which I could
not find realised in the sanguinary orgies of the Revolution.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> You sought death; you sought the glorification of your dead self. The
Revolution was a manuscript which God wrote in an ink too red for your liking. God heard the wail of the
children, the fettering of the captives, the champings of cruel giants; and He bade Freedom unloosen with
flame and steel. You fled to Nature, the ancient enemy of God and man, and bade her quench and blunt the
flashing edges. By the side of the blotching devil Rubens and the blearing devil Titian I can now see the
bleating devil, Wordsworth.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth</hi> (smiling). Strong language, Mr. Blake.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Coin of God’s realm, Mr. Deputy-Stamp-Collector. 
                </p>
        <pb id="p08-39" n="39"/>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> Yet I have ever considered that your own early lyrics were
anticipations of my own humble and proud efforts to emancipate English verse from the fetters of a “poetic
diction.”</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Ah, hm! “Humble and proud” is pretty well. You had considerable talents,
Mr. Wordsworth.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> How am I to understand you, Mr. Blake?</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> As you please, sir. For my own part I can see more clearly than I could
formerly. Under the guise of a liberator you bound the human spirit to the tethering-post of blockheadism. But
neither a tethering-post “under Government” nor a bribed and brief posterity can put the stamp of immortality
on atheistic balderdash.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> The gods are good to us here. That old vagary of yours, to accuse me
of atheism, is singularly out of keeping with this—
<q>
“Elysian beauty, melancholy grace.”
</q></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Pah! The simper of one of Worlett’s engravings! I tell you we are mere
apprentices here. We are put in these lifeless fields among these watery shadows and broken colours, that we
may find out afresh the divine art of living in truth and pity and justice.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> Excellent maxims. But surely the first step is gained here by the
subduing of passion and the preparation of the heart for wisdom?</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> God only is wise, and before Him alone is it any merit to subdue our
passion. Our passion comes from Him. He is a consuming fire.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> And whence comes our endurance?</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> From our cowardice, and very often from the devil himself, who is the most
enduring of creatures, as long as the Divine Order seems able to endure him. As for you, sir, you look at a
large stone, or at a sheep couched on the grass, and you say, “How enduring! how permanent! how patient!” And
I tell you the very stone would smite you, if it could, and the sheep would tumble you over. I have seen and
drawn sheep with their necks bowed. But it is under the mighty hand of God. And He spreads His hands over them
in tenderness, and joy springs in their hearts and love. They will see their lambs skipping with the angels.
But you sing of their aches and ills, and how they weigh on the earth, and soon the earth will weigh on them.
Weight and weight! Blind effort and hopeless suffering! The meekness of an idiot and the self-worship of a
duck-pond!</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> I cannot help thinking, Mr. Blake, that your impatience deprives you
of many sources of pure and refined pleasure.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> There can be no pleasure without passion. A straw tickling one’s nose
may be amusing, but pleasantness comes only with dreams and desires.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> I choke my resentment, Mr. Blake. I have great hope we may ultimately
agree. Let me ask you, as a slight diversion, what you now think of that very clever young lord, who used to
speak of my humble productions much as you do. He wrote verses himself, I believe.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Lord Byron was half one of the original giants of Albion! He climbed out
of this elemental Greek hell and had one foot on the Greek Parnassus. He caught the splendour of Jehovah’s
face, and was in the train of Satan when he asked leave to tempt Job. He worked too much in mezzo-tint, and
could not draw the pure and firm lines of Dante and
<pb id="p08-40" n="40"/>
Chaucer. He was troubled too much with the shadows of good and evil. Nevertheless he had the love of freedom
and of the “high passions” that dwell in the reasonable soul.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi>
		<q>
“Wisdom and spirit of the universe,<lb/>
Thou soul which art the eternity of thought.”
</q>
        </p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Doubtless, Mr. Wordsworth, you could write noble lines. Ah! 
<hi rend="i">si sic omnia!</hi> But you were a Pagan, a worshipper of stocks and stones, of natural life and
growth, with no intuition of Jehovah and Jesus, the creative Mind and the redeeming Activity.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> I felt those august Presences diffused and interfused through all
things.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Yes, and lost in the “Elements of this world,” which the apostle tells us
are not “according to Christ.”</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> And Lord Byron, doubtless, was a more orthodox preacher of apostolic
truth.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> He never at any rate bowed before natural force, or confused it with God.
His Prisoner of Chillon is surrounded with as much harsh material as one of your own gaping peasants; but he
preserves his manhood and the dignity of his sufferings.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> I trust that his lordship’s own sufferings are borne with dignity.
I hear that he is at present yoked with Sisyphus, and rolling uphill that rock of offence, his very singular
biography.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> O Pharisee! O interminable Scribe! when will you learn that it is not by
passions resisted that men inherit a glory, but by good done?</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> I thought, Mr. Blake, that you attributed just now to the “noble
poet” too much preoccupation with the “shadows of good and evil.”</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> I did, sir. That was his error. But he recognised at the same time that
the material universe is nothing—
<q>
“The mind which is immortal makes itself<lb/>
Requital of its good and evil deeds,<lb/>
Is its own origin of ill and end,<lb/>
And its own place and time.”
</q>
That is Manichean, if you will. But it is not atheistic. For it declares the mind, which is of God, to be
alive and active for the punishment of its failures and the joy of its triumphs. Lord Byron’s “sense of sin”
was excessive and paralysing. But it at any rate showed that his mind and reasonable faculties were awake.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> But have not I too said of the winds and waves that they “in
themselves” are nothing?</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Yes; but you keep that “in themselves” to ride off on when the winds and
waves frighten you very much. How can a wave “roll Deity”? You make the Eternal a sport of chance.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> Of law rather—
<q>
“One control<lb/>
Gave laws to them, and said that by the <hi rend="i">soul</hi><lb/>
Only the nations should be great and free.”
</q></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Nations are great by their thoughts, and their enterprises, and their
visions. Those are the expression of their soul. But your whole work ties them to the earth and the soil. You
think of them as growing, and then as buried—
<q>
“Rolled round in earth’s diurnal course<lb/>
With rocks and stones and trees.”
</q></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> Those lines are doubtless a stumbling-block. But taken in connection
with the whole chain of my thought, they sin neither against Christianity nor imagination. Humility is the
first of religious virtues, and nothing encourages it so much as remembering that on one side we are dust.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> To the imaginative artist the most literal fact may be spiritual; but it
must be used symbolically. Our five senses give the limit to the energy and fire of soul, making some
embodiment seem <hi rend="i">there</hi>, and outside of us, and dead. That is the dust; but out of the dust we
most behold the glory. Otherwise where is the contrast which art and truth demand? The prophet Ezekiel lay in
the dung that he might have a vision of Jehovah, the God made human. But you lie in the dust out of a
dastardly love for humility and quietness.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> But Lord Byron surely, infected doubtless by the prevailing poetic
inspiration of his time, my own, filled his verses with mountains and seas and clouds as much as I did.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Yes, but with this difference, that he scales the Summits and rides on the
waves,— he is for ever aspiring towards something. You, sir, with an original capacity for imaginative
expression infinitely greater than his, succumbed to the delusion and lie of Nature, asserting mendaciously
that she
<q>
“Never did betray<lb/>
The heart that loved her,”
</q>
and have done your best to leave the human spirit in the art-destroying and blind limbo of the Greek and Roman
sophists.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi><q>
“The Sacred laws<lb/>
Framed in the schools, where wisdom dwelt retired,<lb/>
Intent to trace the ideal path of right.”
</q>
Are those the lines you are thinking of?</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Partly; but still more of your pervading Greek spirit, servile to the two
most
<pb id="p08-41" n="41"/>
damnable forms of death, nature and temperance. All truly great artists see and create better when they are
drunk.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">1</hi> v. “Marriage of Heaven and Hell,” reprinted in the 
<hi rend="i">Hobby-Horse</hi> for October 1887.</note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="i">According to Ian Fletcher, Malcolm Kingsley Macmillan belonged to the publishing
family but published little himself, though he had a remarkable range of knowledge of literature and art. The
privately printed edition of his</hi> Selected Letters <hi rend="i">appeared in 1893. In an appendix it
contains miscellaneous literary remains. Kingsley published anonymously a novel entitled</hi> Dagonet the
Jester <hi rend="i">in 1886. He disappeared 11 July 1889 while climbing Mount Olympus—a mystery which has
never been resolved.</hi></note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> I am no advocate for excluding any simple pleasure, any touching
weakness from the domain of poetic sympathy.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> You can concede a great deal, doubtless; but it is all in the way of
balance and moderation. The wine-cup, the strong and fiery juices are not conceded by our enemy, Nature; they
are wrenched from her.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> Turbulence and revolt and distraction—the storm-clouds of the
wine-cup—are these to be eternal? [Blake makes the gesture of drinking.] You are satiated with bliss, I see,
and long for battle. Hence your assault on me. But there is one knotty point which I should like to propose to
you, Mr. Blake. You speak perpetually of Nature as accursed, the enemy of God and of art, and yet advocate
those forms of licence which are generally defended on the plea that they are natural.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> And on that plea wrongly defended, whatever they may be. But explain
yourself further.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Wordsworth.</hi> It is not generally known that I have myself had conceptions and
hauntings of erotic imagery and orgiastic poesy which would have been among the most tremendous feats of that
kind which the literature of the world can show. So strong was the impulse towards this vein of composition,
that, short of yielding to it, my only alternative was rigidly to exclude the voice of amatory passion from
the almost perfect diapason of my poetical production. You, on the other hand, have given free expression to
this side of life, not only in your lyrics, but, as I understand, still more in your “designs” and
“inventions.” You must justify to yourself, as best you can, this laying anew on the human race “the weight of
chance desires.” But my puzzle meanwhile, without the solution of which I cannot so well defend myself against
charges which I can only imperfectly understand, is this: Do not these desires and impulses belong to nature?
Is it not the function of imagination and religion to control them?</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Sir, I am a painter and draughtsman as well as a poet. I can best explain
myself by lines and images.</p>
      </div1>
      <figure n="RadicalsNegative.8.1-2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="298">
          <figTranscr>Godwin.   Fuseli<lb/>
          <lb/>
          Price   Priestley   Blake</figTranscr>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>