<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.3.jackson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Additional Lines in Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title>
        <author n="Jackson">Mary V. Jackson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1974-75</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1974-75</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
			<biblScope unit="volIss">08.3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix (in charge)</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
	<pb id="p08-91" n="91"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-3-0005">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">VDA:</hi> The Frontispiece and a Crucial Line</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <figure n="vda.j.p1" id="vda.j.illbk.01" work-copy="vda.j" rend="db" width="712" height="1000">
            	<figTranscr/>
            </figure>
            <head>
              <title type="main">Additional Lines in <hi rend="i">VDA</hi></title>
            </head>
            <byline>by <docAuthor>Mary V. <name>Jackson</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">*</ref></byline>
            <p>In “A Crucial Line in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi> 23 (Winter 1973), pp. pp. 72-73, Roland A. Duerksen suggests that, contrary to the generally
accepted view, the bound figures in the frontispiece are not Oothoon and Bromion but rather are
representations of the states of terror and meekness bound by a Bromion who is not pictured in the plate. In
support of his view Mr. Duerksen points to Bromion’s assertiveness, his boast of owning slaves and his
tyrannical disposition. While it is true that these qualities and acts are Bromion’s, they do not
automatically preclude the depiction of Bromion as a manacled, fear-ridden figure, though they do indeed raise
a crucial question about the force that binds him.
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="i">Mary V. Jackson (City College of New York) has published on Blake in</hi> JEGP
<hi rend="i">and is writing a book on Blake.</hi></note></p>
            <pb id="p08-92" n="92"/>
            <p>In order to accept this interpretation of the frontispiece, we must accept several questionable
assumptions: First, because Bromion is a tyrant, slave-holder and, one should add, rapist, he cannot also be
horrified at his own acts, perhaps even at himself. In other words, his face cannot be “fear-distorted.”
Second, because Theotormon despairs and seems abject, he cannot also be capable of rage, jealousy and the will
to bind and thus punish “the adulterate pair.” Finally, because Oothoon is freer in plate 4, she cannot be
bound in the frontispiece.</p>
            <p>The problem with this logic is that it imposes too static an interpretation on the
illuminations. It does not allow for either the “narrative progression” or the evolving vision clearly
conveyed in the words and successive designs of the poem. One might as plausibly argue that Oothoon cannot
appear in a cloud above Albion’s daughters in plates 7 and 8 because there is a chain on her ankle in plate
4.<hi rend="s"><hi rend="i">2</hi></hi> And yet she does. (I do not agree with the assertion that the chain
around Oothoon’s leg “appears loosened” in the detail of plate 4, for it seems securely fitted to her
distinctly tapered ankle.)</p>
            <figure n="vda.j.p2" id="vda.j.illbk.02" work-copy="vda.j" rend="db" width="798" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>VISIONS<lb/>
	of<lb/>
	the Daughters of<lb/>
	Albion<lb/>
	The Eye sees more than the Heart knows.<lb/>
	Printed by Will:m Blake : 1793.</figTranscr>
              <head><hi rend="i">p. 91 Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (copy J), frontispiece 
<hi rend="i">p. 92</hi> title page <hi rend="i">p. 93, col. 1, top</hi> pl. 4, detail <hi rend="i">p. 93,
bottom</hi> pl. 8, detail Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection</head>
            </figure>
            <p>I think Bromion is indeed pictured in the frontispiece, just as it is he who appears, bearded,
with arms folded in a curiously passive gesture, bearing down upon Oothoon in a thunder-cloud on the
title-page; that Oothoon, so daunted initially by her ordeal (Bromion’s and Theotormon’s cruelties) that
she cannot speak or even weep, is the meek, bound female figure in the plate. If so, who does have the will
and the power to bind them? The answer is suggested, in my opinion, in two additional lines of plate 2:
<q>
Then storms rent Theotormon’s limbs: he roll’d his waves around / And folded his black jealous waters
round the adulterate pair. (2:3-4)
</q>
It is easy to be deflected by Bromion’s tauntings and Theotormon’s representation of himself as a pathetic
victim from realizing that he is also a furious, vindictive lover. His rage is clearly indicated in the lines
quoted above, and his sadistic pleasure at Oothoon’s physical suffering and at her brief acceptance of 
<hi rend="i">his</hi> judgment of her is apparent: He “severely smiles” as the eagles rend her (2:18).</p>
            <p>There seems to me no convincing reason to assume that Theotormon’s enfolding of the
“adulterate pair” and the binding of terror and meekness are not the same act. Because Theotormon seems
passive in the frontispiece, we need not assume that he is powerless. It is reasonable to assume that the
illumination depicts the moments after the “folding” or binding and that the apparently passive Theotormon is
not so much a helpless onlooker as a brooding, self-pitying participant. If so, then the freedom or
enslavement of the three main characters depends upon Theotormon’s will to accept or resist perversely the
wholeness and love Oothoon embodies. In the light of this interpretation, it is right that Bromion should be
given no further attention by Blake in the illuminations after the frontispiece or by Oothoon (after 3:1),
whose instincts correctly tell her to address Theotormon and Urizen.</p>
            <p>It is significant that Theotormon’s feelings toward Oothoon are more consistently punitive
and rejecting than are his feelings toward Bromion. There is a curious affinity between aggrieved lover and
rapist: Theotormon thinks Oothoon a harlot no less than Bromion. Both are puritanical, and in their view,
Oothoon’s move toward imaginative and sexual freedom (the plucking of the flower) makes her deserve to be
raped and then requires that she be punished for her impurity. Theotormon’s ambiguity toward Bromion stems
in part from the fact that he both approves and disapproves of the rape. He is indeed a “sick man’s dream,”
a type of spiritually poisoned humanity which must defile in order to be able to reject the innocent, lovely
gratification Oothoon offers. Theotormon and Bromion can accept only two categories of existence, good or
evil. The freedom of imagination that transcends these categories is worse than either, because dangerous
<pb id="p08-93" n="93"/>
<figure n="vda.j.p7.detail" id="vda.j.illbk.07" work-copy="vda.j" rend="file" width="958" height="606">
	<figTranscr/>
</figure>
to a narrow vision, and must be annihilated. In a sense, Bromion embodies the spectrous, life-denying impulse
within Theotormon, and it may be that he is sent or willed by Theotormon to defile and thereby arrest
Oothoon’s move toward liberty. At the very least, Theotormon endorses Bromion’s judgment of Oothoon, as
his own treatment of her indicates. The relationship between these three characters anticipates Blake’s
concepts of emanation and spectre.</p>
            <p>This interpretation of Theotormon’s controlling role in Oothoon’s ordeal is supported, I
think, by two elements in the poem and qualified by a third.
<figure n="vda.j.p11.detail" id="vda.j.illbk.11" work-copy="vda.j" rend="file" width="958" height="914">
	<figTranscr>The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho back her sighs.<lb/>
	The End</figTranscr>
</figure>
The detail of plate 6 shows a female and male figure; the latter holds a scourge as if to strike the
distraught female whose hands cover her face. Oothoon’s words on this plate clearly express her growing
awareness, a flowering of the imagination that might deliver her from the death-like single vision of
Theotormon and Urizen. But the illumination represents another aspect of the unfolding vision, for Oothoon is
still vulnerable to her lover’s judgment, shamed by his belief that she is a whore. Although she is pictured
as physically unshackled and her words show her to be intellectually freer than at any earlier point in the
poem, she is not entirely free from Theotormon. Indeed, the final lines of the poem suggest that she cannot be
free, that she is doomed—“Thus every morning wail<hi rend="i">s</hi> Oothoon” (8:11, italics mine)—because
Theotormon will not hear. As with a man and his emanation, their destinies seem inextricably intertwined. The
passion and beauty of Oothoon’s triumphant final speech would be tragic, chillingly hopeless were it not for
the mitigating effect of the design of plate 8. Oothoon appears, David Erdman suggests, in a thundercloud
portending storm and change. Also, the clouds to the lower left are funnel shaped, like a tornado. Oothoon
flies toward Albion’s daughters, one might note, from the left or West. She is still the “soft soul of
America,” though now a stronger impulse toward freedom; she has weathered the deadly storm unleashed upon her
precisely because she moved to take her bliss. With the detail of the final plate, the horror of Oothoon’s
relationship to Theotormon is lessened and the work has come full circle: Oothoon has progressed from one
pursued by a flame-wrapped terror in a cloud (title page) to the embodiment, mantled in flame, of liberating
vision riding apocalyptic clouds.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
