<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.3.subscriptions</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Our New Subscription System</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1974-75</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1974-75</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix (in charge)</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <pb id="p08-48" n="48"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">News</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Our New Subscription System</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Some subscribers have had good reason to wonder why The <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> can’t
handle its affairs with the business like efficiency of <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> and <hi rend="i">Playboy.</hi>
The main reason is a chronic shortage of money and clerical help. Another reason is a primitive addressing and
mailing operation in the University of New Mexico post office. We have tried for years to keep our dealings
with individuals, libraries, and subscription agencies clean and efficient, and our occasional failures have
made us more and more unhappy with things as they are.</p>
          <p>So we have decided to get rid of at least one large trouble spot, our revolving subscription
system. We publish four issues a year, and you have been able to begin subscribing with any one of the four
issues. That is, your subscription may expire with the summer issue, while someone else’s may expire with
spring, winter, or fall. This system is easy for a computer to handle, and convenient for subscribers, and
thus it is the standard system for commerical magazines.</p>
          <p>But the system is very difficult to manage efficiently with limited money and clerical help, and
a system that might ideally be convenient to the subscriber becomes inconvenient. Everyone knows that there is
no better analogy to the Gordian knot than a fouled-up magazine subscription, and we have decided to go with
Alexander the Great.</p>
          <p>Our new system of handling subscriptions will be the one used by <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> and some
other large scholarly journals—subscription <hi rend="i">by the volume.</hi> Every subscription will begin
with the summer issue (the issue with which <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> volumes begin) and end with spring.
All renewal notices will be sent out at the same time every year. New subscribers will be sent the current
issue, plus all the previous issues in the current volume.</p>
          <p>The new system is much simpler than the old for us, and we are certain it will mean fewer
problems for you. But shifting from the old system to the new will be a lot of trouble for all of us, and we
are asking you in advance to help us—mainly to bear with us—when the change-over begins this spring.</p>
          <p>The procedure will not be complicated. The aim is to move each subscription from its present
expiration date to expire with the spring issue. Every subscription will then begin with the summer issue. Of
course, subscriptions that now expire with the spring issue will not be changed. All others will be. You will
receive a bill for an amount large enough to bring your subscriptions into the new subscription cycle. You
will not be paying extra money, of course—just paying on a slightly different schedule.</p>
          <p>The procedure and the reasons for it will be explained again when you receive your bill.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
