<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.3.duerksen</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Bromion’s Usurped Power—Its Source, Essence, and Effect: A
Replication</title>
        <author n="Duerksen">Roland A. Duerksen</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1974-75</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1974-75</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix (in charge)</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-3-0005">
          <pb id="p08-95" n="95"/>
          <div2>
            <head>
              <title type="main">
                <hi rend="b">Bromion’s Usurped Power—Its Source, Essence, and Effect: A Replication</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <byline>by <docAuthor>Roland A. <name>Duerksen</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">*</ref></byline>
            <p>In their respective responses to my note, both Professor Jackson and Professor Murray present
some good insights that are conducive to a better understanding of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi> as a whole. Yet, with reference particularly to the one line in question, I find fewer
difficulties when I continue to read it as my note suggests. Let me first point out what I consider the
strengths of the two responses.</p>
            <note id="n13"><hi rend="i">Roland A. Duerksen (Miami University, Oxford, Ohio) has published
articles on British and American Romantic writers, including several on Blake. His books include</hi>
Shelleyan Ideas in Victorian Literature <hi rend="i">(1966) and editions of various works by
Shelley.</hi></note>
            <p>The relating of Oothoon, Theotormon, and Bromion to Blake’s emanation-and-spectre concept
strikes me as the most solid aspect of Jackson’s commentary. That Theotormon is essentially aligned with
Bromion is also an important insight. And corollary to it is the assertion that the destinies of Oothoon and
Theotormon are inextricably inter-twined. Murray’s best argument, it seems to me, comes in his final
paragraph. If Bromion does indeed see in the offing the success of Oothoon’s address to Theotormon, he has
cause (from his limited, ego-oriented perspective) to be terrified because of the coming end of his
dominion.</p>
            <p>But strong though these points are, they do not solve the problem I find in the conventional
reading of the crucial line. I am not at all convinced that Theotormon has any strength of his own in the
emanation-spectre entity. Separated as he is from his emanation (Oothoon), he has fallen prey to his spectre
(Bromion) who has usurped his realm. That is why Bromion rapes with impunity in “Theotormon’s reign.”
Bromion is the power ethic that is commissioned from the lofty heaven of reason by Urizen himself. But
Theotormon should not be dominated by this power ethic; he should receive his primary direction from Oothoon,
the imaginative impulse, and should make a venture parallel to her plucking of the marigold. Bromion would
then necessarily find his rightful subservient place as keeper of the outer bound of reason around their life
of joyous energy. The question, then, is not about Theotormon’s power; in himself he has none. Nor does
Oothoon stand a chance, by herself, to overpower Bromion. If, however, she could break through to Theotormon,
the two together <hi rend="i">could</hi> simply do all that Bromion forbids.</p>
            <p>And it is this possibility that Murray finds as the terrifying element for Bromion. Yet I find
no indication in the poem that Bromion senses any need to fear. His questions (4:13-24) are all of the
“Don’t you know that?” variety—clearly indicating that he does not doubt the reason-oriented basis of his
power system. Nor does it seem that the horror at his own acts (Jackson’s suggestion) would be adequate for
the drastic depiction of terror—such horror not being indicated in the text. And since I find no indication
in the poem of his losing control over Theotormon, whose hearing shows no signs of being restored, I fail to
see coherence in any characterization of Bromion himself as terror bound to meekness.</p>
            <p>The poem would appear to be considerably weakened by the interpretation that Oothoon’s spirit
is in any sense subdued after once she has plucked the marigold. By that act, symbolically, she has achieved
what Herbert Marcuse calls “the end of utopia”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">1</ref>; that is, she has broken through to the new state of being in which what is generally
called utopian (unattainable) is actually achieved. The rape does not defile her or make her feel guilty. She
purposefully, “with holy voice,” calls the eagles to rend her breast—to demonstrate to Theotormon her
absolute invulnerability to the restrictive codes that torment him. Her lamentations are not meek, subdued
supplications but, rather, emphatic and desperate argumentations. Granted, there appears to be a certain
degree of irony or ambiguity in her situation of being in a new state of freedom and yet wailing and lamenting
over Theotormon’s unresponsiveness. Again Marcuse’s theory may serve to elucidate:
<q>
All the material and intellectual forces which could be put to work for the realization of a free society are
at hand. That they are not used for that purpose is to be attributed to the total mobilization of existing
society against its own potential for liberation. But this situation in no way makes the idea of radical
transformation itself a utopia.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">2</ref></q>
Throughout the poem, after her experience of “radical transformation,” Oothoon never once appears to doubt the
validity and power of that experience. That Theotormon is totally mobilized against this potential for
liberation does not obliterate the knowledge that she has gained from her own experience—though it does
frustrate her efforts. 
                            <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">1</hi> “The End of Utopia,” in <hi rend="i">Five
Lectures: Psychoanalysis, Politics, and Utopia</hi> (Boston: Beacon Press, 1970), pp. 62-69.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “The End of Utopia,” p. 64.</note></p>
            <p>A number of particular points raised by the two respondents deserve individual attention, and I
shall now add my commentary on these. 
                        </p>
            <pb id="p08-96" n="96"/>
            <p>I do not agree with Murray that the graphic art needs to have the narrative consistency or
coherence that we rightfully expect of the literary art. Since the engraving in question is a full-page
representation apparently meant to serve as frontispiece, since the women depicted in the various plates are
not individually identifiable by specific traits or features, and since Blake frequently presents the female
figures in a similar way (and without more particular identification) throughout his engravings, it does not
seem necessary to conclude that he intends the female figure in each of the plates for <hi rend="i">VDA</hi>
consistently to represent Oothoon.</p>
            <p>Unlike Murray, I see on the title page, not an Oothoon fleeing in terror, but a joyous Oothoon,
leaping and running in her enjoyment of new-found freedom while a disgruntled Urizen stalks after her.</p>
            <p>I agree with Murray that the rock and cloud imagery has reference to Bromion. But since the
entirety of the poem after the plucking of the marigold (as I see it) takes place in a realm usurped from
Theotormon by Bromion, this background symbolism is only a matter of consistency.</p>
            <p>Both Jackson and Murray deal with the question of the chain depicted in plate 4. In my note I
should have referred to the chain not as loosened, but as broken from its mooring or as apparently attached to
nothing more solid than the dark wave in which Oothoon appears. My view is that Blake wished, in this
particular plate, to symbolize Oothoon’s former imprisonment—prior to the plucking of the marigold—and
that the broken chain achieves this symbolism.</p>
            <p>Jackson’s assertion that Oothoon is not entirely free from Theotormon is true enough, but
only in the sense of her love for him, not in the sense of her enslavement to him. I do not see any indication
that Oothoon accepts Theotormon’s judgment of her. She knows that the eagles will rend away the appearance
of defilement and reveal her “pure transparent breast.” When this occurs, Theotormon “severely smiles,”
indicating not his dominance over her, but a dull, stupified wonder that indicates his lack of both
comprehension and identification.</p>
            <p>In regard to plate 6, I agree with Murray’s view that Theotormon is depicted in the act of
self-flagellation, and it appears that Oothoon is reacting in agonized, pitying love. Consequently, I must
disagree with Jackson’s assertion that this plate has to do with Oothoon’s being shamed by Theotormon’s
judgment of her.</p>
            <p>That Oothoon addresses Urizen instead of Bromion in the later portion of the poem would appear
to be evidence of her recognition of the source of Bromion’s power, not evidence (as suggested by Jackson)
that Theotormon’s power is greater than Bromion’s.</p>
            <p>Because I think it a critical aspect, I have left until the end my response to Jackson’s
reading of lines 3 and 4 of plate 2. I see the folding of the “adulterate pair” in Theotormon’s “jealous
waters” not as his act of angry assertion, but as his means of avoiding both thought and action. By accepting
as substantial the laws of Urizen (whom Oothoon later refers to as “Father of Jealousy”), Theotormon can fold
this event from his sight—can in essence wash his hands of the affair. In his jealousy, he does precisely
the opposite of what Oothoon (7:28) declares that she would do: “Oothoon shall view his dear delight, nor
e’er with jealous cloud come in the heaven of generous love.” Since Theotormon wraps in the dark waters what
could be his and Oothoon’s “heaven of generous love,” the realm remains under the usurped control of
Bromion, and Theotormon remains at the threshold of the cave in which Bromion’s control is symbolized by the
enslaved juxtaposition of terror and meekness.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
