<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.3.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="correction">Corrections of the BMPR Handlist</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1974-75</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1974-75</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for production</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix (in charge)</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants: for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Graham Conley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-3-0005">
        <pb id="p08-90" n="90"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Corrections of the BMPR Handlist</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Robert N.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Essick</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
            <ref target="n10" type="note">*</ref>
          </byline>
          <p>The following are a few additions and corrections to “A Handlist of Works by William Blake in the
Department of Prints &amp; Drawings of the British Museum,” appearing as the Spring 1972 issue of the 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, vol. 5, no. 4, whole number 20.</p>
          <note id="n10">
            <hi rend="i">Bob Essick lives in Pasadena, California, and is not to be confused with Easson of
Illinois, Eaves of New Mexico, or Erdman of New York.</hi>
          </note>
          <p>P. 226 of the Handlist. Drawings Royal Size Vol. 11.</p>
          <p>LB3, “The resurrection of the dead” (1806) has been transferred to Drawings Imperial Size, vol.
1A.</p>
          <p>P. 226. Drawings Royal Size Vol. 12A.</p>
          <p>LB35, “The Ancient of Days,” watercolor, is very probably a copy by someone other than Blake.</p>
          <p>P. 236. Engravings by Blake: Royal Size Mounted (c2*) vol. I.</p>
          <p>R30xxvi and R30xxvii, “Caius Julius Caesar” and “Epicurus,” are <hi rend="i">not</hi> proofs.</p>
          <p>The inventory numbers of the four Virgil engravings have been transposed in the Handlist. The
proper numbers are as follows: R30xxiii, “Publius Virgilius Maro” (1867. 10. 12. 225); R30xxv, Group of five
medallions (1867. 10. 12. 224); R30xxvi, “Caius Julius Caesar” (1874. 12. 12. 381); R30xxvii, “Epicurus”
(1874. 12. 12. 382).</p>
          <p>R32, “The Finding of Moses,” is a proof, after the plate was cut down for publication, but before
all letters.</p>
          <p>P. 236. Engravings by Blake: Royal Size Mounted (c2*) vol. III.</p>
          <p>R34iii and R34iv, two of “five Dante trial proofs,” are <hi rend="i">not</hi> proofs, but are in
the same state as published impressions.</p>
          <p>P. 237. Engravings by Blake: Unmounted (c14*) After <hi rend="i">Stothard</hi></p>
          <p>R48iv, <hi rend="i">John Scott</hi>, tailpiece, is <hi rend="i">not</hi> a proof in the sense
that the copperplate is in the same state as published impressions. This impression, however, is printed on a
card rather than the paper used in the book.</p>
          <p>After <hi rend="i">Fuseli</hi></p>
          <p>R79, “Tornado,” is a proof lacking the finish work in the design.</p>
          <p>Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793)</p>
          <p>R80ii, “Fable VI,” (1894. 6. 12. 31) is a proof before signature and lacking some finish work in
the design.</p>
          <p>P. 239. Prints after Fuseli (c21*)</p>
          <p>Add: “Tornado” for Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> (1795), a proof lacking finish work
in the design. 1863. 5. 9. 19.</p>
          <p>P. 241. Engravings after Stothard vol. I (c20) R45, Enfield, <hi rend="i">The Speaker</hi>, is a
proof, lacking all letters, with the profile of the angel visible rather than covered by his hair.</p>
          <p>P. 242. Engravings after Stothard vol. I (c20) R49Ai, <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>,
vol. VIII, <hi rend="i">Don Quixote</hi> (Mambrino’s helmet), is a proof before all letters.</p>
          <p>R49Aii, <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, vol. VIII, <hi rend="i">Don Quixote</hi> (Death
of Quixote), is a proof before all letters.</p>
          <p>Add: R49B, <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, vol. IX, <hi rend="i">Sentimental
Journey</hi> (Dance of the Peasants), a proof before all letters. 49. 7. 21. 256.</p>
          <p>R49Di should be R49C.</p>
          <p>R49D (not R49Dii), <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, vol. IX, <hi rend="i">Launcelot
Greaves</hi> (the hustings), is a proof before all letters.</p>
          <p>R49Ei, <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, vol. X, <hi rend="i">Sir Charles Grandison</hi>
(Miss Byron visiting Miss Irvoise), is a proof before all letters.</p>
          <p>R49Eii, <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, vol. X, <hi rend="i">Sir Charles Grandison</hi>
(duel of Sir Charles, O’Hare, and Salmonet), is a proof before all letters.</p>
          <p>R55iii and R55iv, engravings for Ritson, <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi>,
pp. 86 and 108, are proofs with the signatures of Stothard and Blake not appearing in the published state.
These signatures are not handwritten but are in the plate. 
                    </p>
          <pb id="p08-91" n="91"/>
          <p>Add: R58i, <hi rend="i">The Wit’s Magazine</hi>, January issue, proof before letters of one of
two alternate plates engraved by Blake for this issue. Names of Stothard and Blake added in pencil. 49. 7. 21.
502.</p>
          <p>R63ii, “The Battle of Ain,” is a cropped impression, with remants of the border. There is nothing
to indicate that it is a proof as the Handlist states.</p>
          <p>P. 242. Engravings after Stothard Vol. II (c20) R47, Bonnycastle, <hi rend="i">Introduction to
Mensuration</hi>, title-page vignette, is a proof on India paper with a double line border not appearing in
the published state, and with signatures of Stothard and Blake not in the published state.</p>
          <p>Add: John Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, plates as follows:</p>
          <p>R48i, pl. 1 (proof before all letters). 49. 7. 21. 925.</p>
          <p>R48ii, pl. 2 (proof before all letters). 49. 7. 21. 923.</p>
          <p>R48ii, pl. 2 (published state). 49. 7. 21. 920.</p>
          <p>R48iii, pl. 3 (proof before all letters). 49. 7. 21. 924.</p>
          <p>R48iv, pl. 4 (published state). 49. 7. 21. 926.</p>
          <p>Addition: Besides the proof before all letters of “The Right Honourable Earl Spencer” engraved by
Blake after Phillips listed in the Handlist (p. 239, R104, 1873. 5. 10. 2651), there is another impression of
this plate, Portraits Class II, Period 4, inventory number 1863. 8. 8. 73. This impression is signed in the
plate <hi rend="i">T. Phillips R.A. pinx</hi> (lower left), <hi rend="i">W. Blake Sculp</hi> (lower right),
and <hi rend="i">The Right Honourable Earl Spencer.</hi> This impression is particularly important since its
inscriptions are the basis for attributing the plate to Blake.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
