<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.4.ostriker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">D. G. Gillham, William Blake</title>
        <author n="Ostriker">Alicia Ostriker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial assistant for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Deborah Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
	<pb id="p08-136" n="136"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-4-0003">
          <head>
            <title type="main">D. G. Gillham. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> British Authors: Introductory
Critical Series. General Ed., Robin Mayhead. Cambridge: Cambridge Univ. Press, 1973. Pp. 216. Cloth, $12.95;
paper, $4.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Alicia <name>Ostriker</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">*</ref></byline>
          <p>D. G. Gillham is a horse of instruction.
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="i">Alicia Ostriker, Rutgers University, is author of</hi> Vision and Verse in
William Blake <hi rend="i">and editor of the forthcoming Penguin edition of Blake’s poetry.</hi></note> He
is quite a good horse. He approaches Blake cautiously, sensibly, step by step, appearing to take nothing for
granted. Ruminant, judicial, he works his way through the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>, concentrating on the ethical implications of each Song, and of the two sets together. His
stated assumptions, that the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> form “an artistic whole,” that their speakers
“demonstrate a range of human potentialities,” and that one can read them without reference to “background,”
or Blake’s other works, or the biography and personality of the poet, run from the obvious to the
acceptable. Gillham’s readings are essentially those of his earlier work, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Contrary
States</hi> (Cambridge 1966), with most of the critical infighting omitted. A tone of sweet reasonableness
prevails, and the method does elicit valuable insights about the characters of Blake’s speakers, as well as
some good generalizations about the Contraries—for example, a fine appreciation of the erotic elements in
Innocence. But what of Gillham’s nervousness about the social implications of Experience? What can one make,
for example, of a reading of “The Voice of the Ancient Bard” which transforms William Blake into Edmund Burke,
asserting that the poem shows us the folly of revolutionaries and the necessity of building on foundations of
past tradition? What of a reading of “A Little Girl Lost” which explains Ona and her father excellently, but
insists that the “future age” will be no better off than this one, and that Blake was certainly not advocating
free love for persons caught in the state of Experience?</p>
          <p>By the time Gillham comes to the conclusion that Innocence is a “touchstone” and “ideal measure”
but that “most of us spend the greater part of our lives meeting our obligations in the deliberate and
laboured ways of Experience, performing duties and following programmes that purposely exclude the possibility
of much spontaneous goodness or imaginative wisdom,” he is about three-fourths through the book. A bit later,
he adds that the glad grace of innocent virtue is “the sort of thing we can aim at in our more deliberate
programmes of conduct.” Flashes of it may come as a compensation, or reward, for
                        <pb id="p08-137" n="137"/>
good responsible behavior in this world. Perhaps this sounds more like William Wordsworth than William
Blake?</p>
          <p>None of Blake’s later lyric work, from “Auguries of Innocence” to “And did those feet,” from
“Mock on, mock on” to “The Everlasting Gospel,” receives mention in this volume. Chapter Seven, entitled
“Blake’s Longer Works,” tells us not to worry about the poet’s sources, then turns to the “unusual,”
“decidedly strange” and “eccentric” matters of the <hi rend="i">Natural Religion</hi> series, 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (“unsatisfactory”), a backflash at <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (“some of the
shorter pieces are beautiful and some show originality”), <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> (“Moving . .
. though written in a heightened, apocalyptic manner”), <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
(“abstract” and “mysterious”). As for <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen, The Book of Los, The Book of Ahania,
Vala, Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, these are lumped together as “the more abstruse prophetic
books,” and they all “fail” because Blake stopped grounding his vision “on the real circumstances of life.”
These real circumstances, he explains, are the ones Wordsworth had the good poetic sense to stick close to,
while other Romantic poets took laboured flight into realms of unreality.</p>
          <p>Gillham’s resumé of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, at the end of this
chapter, deals adequately and seriously with the moral contraries, though one would never guess, from the
sobriety of his exposition, that the work (here called a “poem”) is funny, or that its beautiful exuberance
was, and is, an incitement to mental revolution, the artist’s cry “Du müss dein leben ändern.” He does not
mention anything so gross as the idea of practical politics in the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (e.g. “The Song
of Liberty”), or so outré as the idea of cleansing the doors of perception in order to see the infinite.
Having quoted Frye on the risen body with the mystified shrug of a commonsense person, he reassures us that
the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> does not involve “escape into a realm beyond the normal.”</p>
          <p>The final two chapters, on <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi>, are full and fine, and Gillham’s interpretation of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> as an amusing
allegory on the follies of amateur metaphysics, should provoke controversy. Whether or not the author expects
those who have required his candle-in-sunshine readings of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> to follow
him here, I cannot say.</p>
          <p>The experienced Blake scholar will not need to be told that Blake’s poetry differs throughout,
in some breathtaking ways, from most of what we read; and he will know how to stitch Gillham’s little patch
of analysis into the total fabric of his understanding. However, this book is not aimed at Blake scholars. It
is (see Mayhead’s “General Preface” to the series) for the general reader and the student, throughout
Britain, the Commonwealth, the English-speaking world, and even the non-English speaking world. In brief, as
the Preface hints, it is for people who want to pass Examinations. One does not assume that these people adore
literature, or recognize their friends. It seems to me interesting that a man who, by his own admission, does
not understand most of the major works of a
<figure n="Onlookers.8.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="200" height="554"/>
major English poet, should undertake to write a Critical Introduction to that poet. I am also interested by
the book jacket’s promise that Gillham “enables” the reader “at last to come to grips with the Prophecies.”
Perhaps it is a good thing that Blake’s poetry emerges from this volume, after the patient attention
recommended by its author, looking boring and pious—or else too inaccessible to be worth one’s attention.
For how would the future obedient civil servant of Uganda or New Delhi—or Birmingham—cope with a Blake who
was passionate, prophetic, apocalyptic, Jacobin, visionary, deeply Christian, wildly comic, bitterly satiric,
and thrilling to read? Of course, no literary scholar goes about with malice aforethought dampening the
fairest joys of literature for the express purpose of maintaining an established civil and emotional order
among his readers. But if the poet himself were to examine this study, carefully considering its pedagogical
methods and the tenor of its understanding, he might conclude in the words of his esteemed predecessor that
the hungry sheep look up and are not fed.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
