<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.4.conference</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Santa Barbara Conference</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial assistant for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Deborah Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-4-0002">
      	<pb id="p08-107" n="107"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Santa Barbara Conference</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The Art History Department and the Department of English at University of California, Santa
Barbara, will co-sponsor an interdisciplinary conference 2-5 March 1976 on the theme of “Blake in the Art of
His Time.” The idea of the conference is to bring together (Blake himself being the precedent) literary
students and art historians of Blake’s work and period, with the intention of viewing his complex
achievement in a wide perspective. Emphasis will be on Blake’s work as painter-poet-engraver-illustrator
seen alongside the work of several eminent contemporaries (such as Flaxman, Fuseli, Linnell, Barry) to reveal
more clearly what in Blake “belonged to his age” and what was Blake’s own and Blake’s only.</p>
          <p>There will be morning and afternoon scholarly sessions, each featuring three or four twenty to
thirty minute papers, on aspects of the general theme of Blake in the Art of his Time, by established scholars
from both disciplines; but also a sprinkling of papers by newcomers in both fields who have fresh things to
say about Blake. There will be considerable use made of color slides as well as other visual aids.
Concurrently with the conference dates, there will be an exhibition of about 100 original items, by Blake and
other artists (named above), on loan to us from various national collections, in the U.C.S.B. art gallery. The
Huntington Library and Art Gallery are planning to mount special exhibitions of Blake and Blake-related
materials during the period of the conference at their nearby Pasadena galleries.</p>
          <p>There will also be evening events of a less academic character—e.g., musical performances of
certain of Blake’s songs and other texts, in both new and traditional settings, examples of the music of
Blake’s time, theatrical treatments of some of his work (perhaps <hi rend="i">An Island in the
Moon</hi>).</p>
          <p>The editorial committee for the conference invites interested scholars to submit papers for
possible presentation at one of the conference sessions. Papers should be kept to about twenty minutes total
delivery time and should be keyed to the theme of the conference (e.g., literary and artistic sources of
Blake’s work; the relation of his work to the pictorial arts and art theories of his time; the relation of
text and design on Blake’s pages viewed in some kind of art-historial perspective, etc.).</p>
          <p>Mail to:<lb/>
Blake Conference<lb/>
Prof. Donald Pearce, Department of English<lb/>
<hi rend="i">or</hi> Corlette Walker, Dept. of Art<lb/>
University of California<lb/>
Santa Barbara, CA. 93106</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
