<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.4.eaves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">On Reflection: Adrian Mitchell on William Blake, 
        a film produced by London Weekend Television; Catharine Hughes, ed., 
        The Clouded Hills: Selections from William Blake</title>
        <author n="Eaves">Morris Eaves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial assistant for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Deborah Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-4-0003">
        <pb id="p08-139" n="139"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">On Reflection: Adrian Mitchell on William Blake.</hi> A film
produced by London Weekend Television. Directed by John Reardon, graphics by John Tribe. U.S. rental agent:
Richard Price Television Associates Ltd., 145 W. 58 St., New York, N.Y. 10019. Date of first showing: not
known. Price of rental: not known.; Catharine Hughes, editor. <hi rend="i">The Clouded Hills: Selections from
William Blake.</hi> Mysticism and Modern Man Series. New York: Sheed &amp; Ward, 1973. $2.95 (paper).</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Morris <name>Eaves</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">*</ref></byline>
          <p>If I could choose one Blake film to show to a class, this would be it.
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="i">Morris Eaves, University of New Mexico, coedits the</hi> Newsletter 
<hi rend="i">with Morton Paley. On an NEH summer fellowship he is finishing a book on Blake’s artistic
principles in relation to the technology of printing and printmaking.</hi></note> In no way does it approach
the best that could be done, but in comparison to the other things that have been done, <hi rend="i">Adrian
Mitchell on William Blake</hi> is the best of the lot.</p>
          <p>The film was made a few years ago for <hi rend="i">On Reflection</hi>, a London Weekend
Television series of personal television “essays” by reflectors of various names and kinds. Adrian Mitchell is
a poet with a fairly standard but still lively view of Blake as a gadfly who liked to say disturbing things
about art, sex, and the state of the culture that are as pertinent now as in 1800.</p>
          <p>As a format Mitchell chose to blend elements of a happening (as we used to say in 1963) in the
style of <hi rend="i">Long Days Night</hi>, with narration, a series of Blake pictures, and readings of poems
and prose to shots of modern London. The assembly has the weight and coherence of a typical highbrow one-man
TV show, which is to say, pretty light and pretty baggy. But compared to the inert, heavy, and dull
sado-masochistic coagulations that have flowed down to etherize us in our seats, <hi rend="i">Mitchell on
Blake</hi> is electrical magic.</p>
          <p>The film opens in the Tate Gallery, moves to Mitchell on camera first emphasizing Blake’s
modernness, then reading <hi rend="i">London</hi> to shots of the modern city and the print itself, and ending
with a little moral lesson based on William Blake House, flats for old people, on the site of one of Blake’s
residences.</p>
          <p>Then we move to the workshop of artist and craftsman Ken Sprague, which becomes the base for the
rest of the program. Here Mitchell misses the chance to build a parallel between Sprague’s workshop and
Blake’s, and thus the chance to show how Blake did what he did as watercolorist and printmaker. Television
is the perfect medium for a good close look at printmaking, not to <corr type="emend">demonstrate</corr> the
technology for itself, but to build a strong image of Blake as a craftsman. But Mitchell’s idea of the
artist—including himself as poet and graffitist and Sprague as graphic artist—seems to be mainly
sociological, which is interesting enough but not complete enough or big enough, and consequently the rest of
the film is thinner than it had to be.</p>
          <p>After a narrative sketch of Blake’s radicalism in religion, politics, and sex, followed by a
reading of <hi rend="i">The Garden of Love</hi> with modern photographic images of chapel, graveyard, and
boy—which sounds more embarrassing than it turns out to be—the film reaches its high point in a hilarious
supermarket scene. Mitchell reads from the Preface to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Public
Address</hi> over the public-address system of the supermarket, with “Rouze up O Young Men of the New Age! set
your foreheads against the ignorant Hirelings!” replacing Musak and “William Bell to cash register number 4,
please” for five minutes with the total result of two half-second surprised looks signaled by two raised
heads, and two dozen dumb expressions fixed firmly on the canned peas—“Suffer not the fashionable Fools to
depress your powers by the prices they pretend to give for contemptible works or the expensive advertizing
boasts that they make of such works.” It was a tuned-out crowd that day down at the supermarket, with other
prices and expensive advertizing boasts to worry about and no time to spare for freaked-out dead artists being
resurrected over the PA system. But it was a marvelous scene.</p>
          <p>The rest is anti-climax, really. Standing by Blake’s life mask, Mitchell tacks on to his
supermarket scene a few of Blake’s epigrams and jingles on Reynolds, Hayley, and Fuseli, with the intention,
I suppose, of reinforcing the impression of Blake as forceful, righteous personality. Then we pick up the next
theme with a series of Blake prints emphasizing sensuality and sexual love, but soon we move to what I’m
sure Mitchell thought was to be the climax of his “reflection,” and the big Happening of the piece, when he
carries paintcans and paintbrushes to the wall of a London building and makes it into a work of 
<corr type="emend">street art</corr> by filling it up with slogans from the Proverbs of Hell, capped by his 
own invention—“Blake Lives!”—over the door. The level of interest in the film drops to a low point here. 
Housepainting is a slower and duller business than Mitchell probably figured it would be. The supermarket 
scene was fun because there were people in the supermarket to react to the PA system, and nonreactions were 
even funnier. But here it’s just Mitchell and his brush and the wall, and the only dynamism in the episode 
comes from our sense of what might happen if there <hi rend="i">were</hi> some spectators. This source of 
interest is tapped at the end of the episode, with the predictable appearance of a couple of bobbies who 
don’t take much more interest in a fouled wall than the shoppers did in the loss of their shopping music. 
The point is made, all right, but for the second time; and if it had to be made twice, the order of the 
two happenings should have been reversed.</p>
          <pb id="p08-140" n="140"/>
          <p>The last theme is poverty, developed with prints from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> alternated with
photographs of starving children, accompanied by a reading of the “It is an easy thing to speak of patience to
the afflicted” speech from <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
          <p>The final section of the film is the most useful in the classroom. In good color and detail,
there is an ample selection from all of Blake’s original graphic work except the paintings: drawings and
prints from the Job and Dante series, and prints from the <hi rend="i">Songs, The Marriage, Europe, America,
Visions of the Daughters of Albion, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, mostly to inoffensive music,
but with a little reading of passages from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Altogether, in selection, arrangement,
and quality of reproduction, this is the best showing of Blake’s work on any film, and it makes a fine
introduction to Blake’s books in illuminated printing for students who have seen only black and white (or
no) reproductions.</p>
          <p>Information for would-be consumers: the print of the film that RPTV sent for viewing was a good
one: intensity and hue were accurate, the print was relatively free of scratches and splices, and sound was
clear with ample volume. Mailing from RPTV was on time, but the company has not answered my inquiries about
the year of the film’s first appearance on London Weekend Television or the price of rental.</p>
          <p>This is another production by the folks who bring us <hi rend="i">Dreams and Regrets: Selections
from the Russian Mystics, Leaves in the Dust: Selections from the Jewish Mystics</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The
Weeping Sky: Selections from American Indian Mysticism</hi> (Indian translation of Psalm 23: “The Great Father
above a Shepherd Chief is, I am His and with Him I want not. . . . and afterward I will go to live in the
‘Big Teepee’ and sit down with the Shepherd Chief forever”—indeed, the very same Shepherd Chief who
spends most of his time in Blake tromping the shit out of us, but all’s fair in love, war, and mysticism),
<hi rend="i">Darkness and Light: Selections from St. John of the Cross</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Prison of
Love: Selections from St. Teresa of Avila.</hi></p>
          <p>The eye and head of Catharine Hughes spend most of their time lost back in the late 50’s when
there was <hi rend="i">The Family of Man, Motive</hi> magazine, Tillich, and lingering interests in Christian
theology, the small church-related liberal arts college, and the arts as manifestations of Christian Witness.
The rest of their time she spends figuring out how to get all that brotherhood, universalism, and concern
together with the masscult mysticism of the 60’s. The Lord bless her soul, Ms. Hughes may have harvested
every good intention planted by every brotherly-love poem and picture of the last two decades, but she is
still deaf and blind. I will forgive her what I don’t approve—which is all of this stuff—but I’ll have
to beg her to get on with the exertion of her talents in some other area. If Jeffrey and his 
<hi rend="i">Edinburgh Review</hi> were still around, the old acid-throated buzzard could spit some of his
Wordsworth juice this way with a lot more justice. “This,” he could say again with the stiff-spined moral
force I wish I had a little of, “will never do.”</p>
          <p>The religious columnists in hometown weeklies have more talent for Catharine Hughes’ sort of
thing than she does, and they produce as much light, or as little, if not as much sweetness. Hughes has
cultivated her skills and tastes in the direction of the facile juxtaposition (“Beautifully produced . . .
juxtaposing modern photographs with brief selections from the words of the saint,” says 
<hi rend="i">Publishers Weekly;</hi> “One medium complements and illuminates the other,” says Msgr. John S.
Kennedy in <hi rend="i">Our Sunday Visitor</hi>) and the obscure juxtaposition (“powerful, provided that one
does not just flip through them. One should pause over each combination, allowing words and pictures to
interact and do their work of inspiration,” Msgr. Kennedy), with some help from the Big Point and the Bitter
Truth, all offered with the feeling for significance displayed by the American poetesses in 
<hi rend="i">Martin Chuzzlewit.</hi> The Hughes wit is chuzzled in the style and on the scale of Eeyore.</p>
          <p>Some pithy instances:</p>
          <p>“All that can happen to Man in his pilgrimage of seventy years,” she selects to bear the Meaning
of a photo of a man walking across a concrete mall in the middle of the day.</p>
          <p>“If you have form’d a Circle to go into, Go Into It yourself &amp; see how you would do,” she
chooses to extract the deepest significance from the photo of a hemp rope wound in a spiral.</p>
          <p>“To see a World in a Grain of Sand etc.” is her choice for a picture of sand with the shadow of a
cross on it.</p>
          <p>“Think not thou canst sigh a sigh And thy maker is not by” is the companion to a closeup of a
crucifix seen from below, with Christ’s toes hanging over the foreground, his groin unfocused above.</p>
          <p>“For man has closed himself up, till he sees all things thro’ narrow chinks of his cavern”—a
closed door and a railway-station tunnel.</p>
          <p>“And was Jerusalem builded here”—Manhattan.</p>
          <p>“Enough! or Too much”—Catharine Hughes hawking copies of <hi rend="i">The Clouded Hills</hi>
and <hi rend="i">The Weeping Sky</hi> at special discount price of $2.50 at Seattle World’s Fair William
Blake and American Indian Pavilion, with Blake life mask in door of teepee, Jewish and Russian mystics
chanting around campfire, and in awesome background, the Church of the Whited Sepulchre, the Mormon
Tabernacle, the Vatican, the Space Needle, Mt. Ranier, the Angel Moroni, and rainclouds.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
