<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.4.jannoud</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Pierre Leyris, trans., Volume I of William Blake, Works</title>
        <author n="Jannoud">Claude Jannoud</author>
        <author n="Gabriella">Katharyn R. Gabriella</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial assistant for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Deborah Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-4-0003">
        <pb id="p08-121" n="121"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Pierre Leyris. Volume I of <hi rend="i">William Blake, Works.</hi> Paris:
Auber-Flammarion, 1974. 40F.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Claude <name>Jannoud</name>.</docAuthor> Translated by
<docAuthor>Katharyn R. <name>Gabriella</name></docAuthor> from <hi rend="i">Le Figaro</hi>, 29 June 1974, p.
8, and reprinted by permission.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">*</ref></byline>
          <figure n="Clocktower.8.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="521"/>
          <p>This bi-lingual edition of the principal works of William Blake one has awaited for a long time.
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="i">Katharyn Gabriella, the translator, is author of</hi> The Imagination of the
Resurrection: The Poetic Continuity of a Religious Motif in Donne, Blake, and Yeats 
<hi rend="i">(1972).</hi></note> Certainly, Andre Gide, who discovered Blake, or believed he did, at the beginning
of the century, launched a permanent interest for us in this great English visionary. But the attended
supervision, in the circumstances of publication, did not follow. Also, Blake belonged to this unfortunate
category of authors about whom one speaks and whom one reads little.</p>
          <p>The masterpiece of this first volume is <hi rend="i">The Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>, the first of which were written in 1789, the second, five years later, but the poet decided
to join them in a single collection. In the intervening time, Blake published <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi> and his poem <hi rend="i">The French Revolution.</hi> In his presentation Pierre Leyris,
to whom one owes the translation of the works in this first volume, emphasizes that if <hi rend="i">The Songs
of Innocence</hi> express the “pure and virginal apprehensions” of young childhood, they do not render an
account of any lost paradise. The chimney-sweepers of 8 years or less, sold by their fathers to an employer
and sleeping in ashes, waiting to contract cancer of the scrotum, or an illness of the lungs or of the eyes,
bear witness that innocence does not exclude the experience of suffering. It concerns a state of perception.
In the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> written five years later, Blake sets up an indictment. To be is to be
restricted, walled in by egotism, the prey of evil, suppressed by the forbidden things which one orders on
oneself.</p>
          <p>The questions of the fall of man and of the mystery of evil are posed. Developing his discoveries
of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, influenced by his reading of Jacob Boehme, Blake does
not assign to evil only a negative and scandalous role. The French revolution, which he admires, confirms his
intuition about the ambiguity of violence. The condition of all progress, of existence even, is the struggle
between contraries, the confrontation between good and evil.</p>
          <p>That [dialectic] does not naturally signify that the poet of the <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> is a precursor of Hegel and of <corr type="emend">Nietzsche,</corr> as certain people lightly claim. Blake is not a
western philosopher. He is a mystic who, as a child, contemplating the reapers, behind them, saw an angel. He
conversed every day with the spirit of his younger brother, who died in 1787. He writes under the dictation of
those dead whom he cherished. All his life, Blake will be in a familiar relation with the supernatural. His
cosmology and his cosmogony are determined by this interior experience. If upon close consideration he appears
as a prophet, his vision of history is antipodal to that of the rationalists. As much by the nature of the
questions as by the answers he brings to them, he is extraordinary.</p>
          <p>Neither philosophies nor theologies can annex this prodigious William Blake, inspired engraver,
painter, water-colorist, solitary thinker, and one of the greatest English poets. In this respect also, he
does not resemble anyone, not even those who influence him, Shakespeare and Milton; at the same time he is
easily manageable and extraordinarily complex.</p>
          <p>For Blake, art is not an end in itself, a worldly ambition, but a necessity, an inflexible part
of the mystery, as are good and evil. 
                    </p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
