<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.4.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert N. Essick, ed., The Visionary Hand: Essays for the Study 
of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial assistant for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Deborah Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
	<pb id="p08-130" n="130"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-4-0003">
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert N. Essick, ed. <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand: Essays for the Study of
William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics.</hi> Los Angeles: Hennessey &amp; Ingalls, Inc., 1973. 558 pp., 165
illus. $7.95, paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Thomas L. <name>Minnick</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">*</ref></byline>
          <p>The formal notice of Blake’s art has undergone a slow resurrection, though the subject has not
yet come fully into health.
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="i">Thomas L. Minnick, the Coordinator for Honors at University College of Ohio State
University, is author of several notes and articles on Blake. Most recently, he edited</hi> Christopher Smart:
Hymns for the Amusement of Children (1772) <hi rend="i">for the Scolar Press, London.</hi></note> For a long
while the patient was simply dead. Thanks to successive injections like the publication of Gilchrist’s life
of this <hi rend="i">pictor ignotus</hi> and the Burlington exhibit of 1876, interest turned at least
moribund. And slowly but steadily, as the frequency of major exhibitions increased and the number of permanent
gallery homes for Blake’s art grew, and as the price of Blake works rose to the record paid last summer for
<hi rend="i">Mary Magdalen at the Sepulchre</hi>—well, if the patient isn’t yet entirely healthy, at least
he can afford the best doctors. One positive recent sign is Robert Essick’s new collection, <hi rend="i">The
Visionary Hand: Essays for the Study of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics.</hi></p>
          <p>Until genius and inspiration work the final miracle, information and reflective understanding are
the best treatments, and both of these are in abundance in the fine selection of essays which Essick has now
made generally available in his useful book. This is the first anthology of work by various hands on Blake’s
art, and although the critical notice of this aspect of Blake’s work has grown so rapidly that several
excellent studies were published even while <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi> was in press, in many cases
readers will find here the most recent statements about many of Blake’s pictures and illuminated books.
Essick’s frequent additions to the original notes are helpful where information has come forward since the
first appearance of an essay, and in several instances the authors themselves have reworked and updated their
contributions. The variety of subjects and approaches is surprising: virtually every kind of Blake’s work is
extensively represented, and gaps generally indicate something about the state of scholarship rather than the
editor’s selectivity. There are twenty-two essays plus six bits reprinted from contemporary sources clearly
relevant to Blake—Cumberland on etching on copper, for example, and a cut from the Rees 
<hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> article on “Etching.”</p>
          <p>In general the format is satisfactory. There are 165 illustrations, Blake a-plenty, but 
                        <pb id="p08-131" n="131"/>
unfortunately none is in color, as the price to printer and reader would doubtless have been prohibitive. The
type is readable and well chosen, except for the first section of passages from Blake’s contemporaries where
a smaller type could have been used for the editorial introductions, to distinguish them visually from the
selections themselves.</p>
          <p>Ruthven Todd’s still unique study of “The Techniques of Blake’s Illuminated Printing” is here
(and hard to locate elsewhere), combining the insights of the practicing artist (Todd himself, and his
co-workers Miró, Tanguy and Hayter from Atelier 17) and the scholar-collector (Todd again, and his late
friend Graham Robertson). And Essick has happily included his own study of Blake and the conventions of
reproductive engraving in the late eighteenth century, though occasionally he sees nets where I see minute
particulars that Blake held to in defiance of the popular fuzziness of Bartolozzi and his admirers. What can
be said of both Todd’s and Essick’s contributions applies more widely to much of the volume: there remains
much to be done—and done, one hopes, by the scholars represented here—but the first difficult questions
have been asked and some directions toward answers discovered. Essick incorporates this aspect of the present
state of criticism by including two multi-author dialogues (on the illustrations to 
<hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> and the Arlington Court Picture), neither of
which has reached a satisfactory conclusion.</p>
          <p>Here are several standard pieces—Binyon on Blake’s engravings, Frye on poetry and design in
the illuminated books, Collins Baker on Blake’s pictorial sources. But here is also a considerable selection
of the best recent work. I found most valuable those essays which were best informed on Blake’s writing and
which highlighted the interaction of Blake’s two great talents—Mitchell on “Poetic and Pictorial
Imagination in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>,” Rose on Blake <hi rend="i">contra</hi> Rubens, and
Burke’s suggestive study, “The Eidetic and Borrowed Image: An Interpretation of Blake’s Theory and
Practice of Art.” Also included are studies of works that are seldom seen or mentioned—Brown on the 
<hi rend="i">Book of Enoch</hi>, Nanavutty on the Huntington <hi rend="i">Genesis</hi>, and Merchant on the
illustrations to Shakespeare, for example. For these essays especially, the illustrations in this volume are
helpful.</p>
          <p>Only Jenijoy LaBelle’s “Words Graven with an Iron Pen: The Marginal Texts in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi>” appears here for the first time. Her essay will be useful to the student looking at the 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> series without a Bible concordance handy. Ms. LaBelle remarks accurately that “the marginal
inscriptions on Blake’s plates serve the same function as the marginal notes in [many seventeenth- and
eighteenth-century] Bibles: both refer the reader to similar events or images to establish new perspectives
from which one can view the biblical text—or in Blake’s case, the central design” (pp. 539-40). But she
dedicates more space to hunting sources than to revealing significances. I would have found her work more
instructive had she woven the minute particulars of Blake’s biblical
<figure n="AngelNarrow.8.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="567"/>
inscriptions into a more developed explanation of his typology at work in the series. Also, this reviewer at
least would have been more comfortable had she quoted Blake, as did most other recent essayists, from David
Erdman’s text.</p>
          <p>Essick is responsible for easing the reader’s way by providing for all quotations from Blake
the appropriate page references to both the Keynes and Erdman editions. Also, after citations to those
pictures by Blake which are reproduced in the volume, Essick has added the illustration number, even sometimes
when the illustration was not included with the original publication of the essay. But the editor is also
responsible for a number of errors—some merely distracting, others more troublesome. For example, one of the
illustrations is taken from a wrong photograph, as Professor Essick confirmed in correspondence: Illustration
4, captioned as a “fragment of <hi rend="i">America</hi> copper-plate.
<pb id="p08-132" n="132"/>
Printed by method described in the text,” is actually, like Illustration 8, inked for intaglio with the
surfaces wiped.</p>
          <p>Of the numerous errors in the text, some are easy to interpret: “insistance” (p. 13), “platten”
(p. 40), “resistent” (p. 43), “artifical” (p. 180), “philosopy” (p. 148), “sysmbolism” (p. 210) and many
others. More serious are errors in direct quotations from Blake, as “Gallary” (p. 192: see E 568); in titles,
as “<hi rend="i">Euorpe</hi>” (p. 152), “<hi rend="i">Satan exculting over Eve</hi>” (p. 304), and 
“<hi rend="i">Titania and Puck</hi> with <hi rend="i">Fairies Dancing</hi>” (pp. 241-42) where if “with” were
properly italicized, one would not look for two separate works; in proper names, as “grant” (p. 482) for [John
E.] Grant, “Tanguay” (p. 40) for Yves Tanguy, “Malfy” (p. 136) for Malfi, “Emergy Walker” (p. 225) for Emery
Walker, the publisher of Keynes’s catalogue of the separate plates, and “Haley” (p. 331) for, I suppose,
Hayley, among other errors; and in dates and other numbers, as “pp. 47-47” (p. 225) and “1840-1500” (p. 94).
The technical terms used of printing methods may be unfamiliar to some (I would have liked a glossary for
“blankets,” “bougies” and “stopping out”), and the reader who doesn’t recognize “gouche” (p. 40) as
“gouache” will be confused. Additionally, Essick has twice substituted “Illustration” for “Plate” in Frye’s
contribution (p. 156) with resultant awkwardness. The sentence in question should read: “At the bottom of
Plate 8 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is a female figure harnessed to the moon: the symbol is not mentioned
in the text until Plate 63.”</p>
          <p>In spite of these faults, which make the book a bad example to the graduate and advanced
undergraduate students who will otherwise benefit from it most, Essick has provided a useful service to
Blakeans by making easily available many essays important for their quality and for the attempt implicit in
each to redress the long dearth of attention to Blake’s visual art. I would have liked some other things
included. Selections from the catalogues to important exhibits—Burlington (1876), Carfax (1906) and
Philadelphia (1939), for example—might have plotted the rise of favor toward Blake and suggested something
about the development of a taste for his pictorial imagination. And rather than duplicate some illustrations,
perhaps works mentioned but not reproduced could have been included—in John Grant’s words, “the very great
but little known picture of ‘The Fall of Man’ ” (p. 436), for example. I was startled to find virtually no
mention of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, although it has been treated several times at length in the
available literature. But here is abundance nonetheless, and I hope this book will enjoy a wide working
audience.</p>
          <p>At $7.95 for an unsewn paperback, the book may seem no bargain, although to xerox even just the
best essays would run higher, and the photographs would reproduce less well. Libraries at least should be
encouraged to get the book, in multiple copies if heavy use is likely. If all students of Blake knew these
essays and a half-dozen other works on Blake’s art, understanding of this aspect of his genius would
increase—perhaps flourish.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
