<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.4.kroeber</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Wagenknecht, Blake’s Night</title>
        <author n="Kroeber">Karl Kroeber</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial assistant for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Deborah Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-4-0003">
        <pb id="p08-116" n="116"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Wagenknecht. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night: William Blake and the Idea of
Pastoral.</hi> Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1973. Pp. xi + 320. $12.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Karl <name>Kroeber</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">*</ref></byline>
          <p>No brief review can do justice to Professor Wagenknecht’s minutely particularized
interpretations.
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="i">Karl Kroeber, Chairman of the Department of English and Comparative Literature,
Columbia University, is author of numerous studies of Romantic literature.</hi></note> It is difficult even to
place his readings in any main line of recent Blakean criticism, for his effort to depict Blake as a
“pastoral” poet depends almost entirely on a study of Renaissance pastoral, <hi rend="i">The Landscape of the
Mind.</hi> There the pastoral poet is defined as one who presents “a fiction imitating an ideal difficult to
credit in terms of the imagery which supports the fiction,” and the idea of pastoral as that “this-worldliness
and otherworldliness can be reconciled, and that a truly cultivated man, whatever his intimations of divinity,
may find a natural human voice.” Despite the somewhat unpromising nature of these quotations, Wagenknecht
makes but a single reference to Empson and does not use his ideas, and completely ignores John Holloway’s
discussion of the psychologizing of pastoral in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, an unfortunate omission.
Wagenknecht’s commitment is to abstract critical constructs. In <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night</hi> literary
history is at best discontinuous: “even in minute particulars there is nothing fanciful in the comparison
between Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Shepheardes Calendar.</hi>” Nothing fanciful,
to be sure, but ignoring the two hundred years which separate them may not be the most adroit fashion for
developing the significance of such a comparison.</p>
          <p>Pivotal for Wagenknecht is his interpretation of “Night,” proving, he believes, “that the themes
appropriate to [Blake’s] pastorals are central to his imaginative and intellectual concerns . . . we may
expect to find an important pastoral element in his mature work. This is in fact so much the case that we can
read right through Blake’s career regarding him distinctly as pastoral or as epic poet.” Blake, in other
words, is to be understood as following the celebrated Renaissance/Virgilian pattern of poetic development
from pastoral to epic. <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> is interpreted to elucidate this pattern, yielding the insight
that “we cannot <hi rend="i">conceive</hi> of avoiding Experience without falling into it; therefore the
language by means of which we conceive Innocence is dependent upon Experience and tends to reinforce it. This
means that whatever else the picture of Thel’s world is like, it is not unreal.” This is one of the more
interesting suggestions in the book, and from it flows Wagenknecht’s final statement of the link between
Blake’s early and late work, or, rather, their essential identity: “the interposition of the Covering
Cherub, of the darkness of Generation, between Albion and Jesus—and more particularly the joyous acceptance
of this sacrifice by the Divine Imagination in Los—is Blake’s final version
<figure n="SoulsAscending.8.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="521"/>
of the idea of pastoral. The complexity of that idea—whereby the human imagination must simultaneously
apprehend reality as fallen and as capable of transcendence—is very great in the last pages of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, but there is no difference in kind from the many analogous realizations of the idea
in pages of Blake which we have already seen.”</p>
          <p>I should think few readers would want to quarrel with Wagenknecht’s fundamental idea, but some
may feel discomfort at his mode of presentation. Unity can be perceived and demonstrated in Blake’s poetry
without confining it within the limits of a rigid, statically conceived pattern of Renaissance art. Closer
attention to the processes by which traditions, genres, and modes of literary sensibility changed between the
later sixteenth and the later eighteenth centuries would have enriched and strengthened the power of
Wagenknecht’s criticism. The hermetic spirit of <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night</hi> makes it seem more like a
work of ten or fifteen years ago than a contemporary piece of Blake criticism, but, by the same token, the
dated quality of the book indicates its freedom from the pernicious fads of 1970s Blake scholarship. 
                    </p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
