<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.4.taylor</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship</title>
        <author n="Taylor">Ron Taylor</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial assistant for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Deborah Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
      <pb id="p08-146" n="146"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-4-0004">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="b">Compiled by</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">Ron</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">Taylor</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <ref target="n28" type="note">*</ref>
        </byline>
        <note id="n28"><hi rend="i">Ron Taylor, an advanced graduate student in English at Berkeley, is the
Bibliographer for the</hi> News letter.</note>
        <div2>
          <figure n="Reclining.8.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="219"/>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Bibliography</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Anon. “Bibliography: the Eighteenth Century.” Philological Quarterly, Fall 1974 number.</p>
          <p>Candela, Gregory, Marta Field, and Foster Foreman. “A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship.”
Blake Newsletter, 7 (Summer 1973), 11-15.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., et al. “Bibliography of Romanticism, 1972.” English Language Notes, 12 (Sept.
1974), supplement to no. 1. (See Blake section.)</p>
          <p>Ferguson, James B., and Frank M. Parisi, comps., assisted by Michael Phillips. “1972-73: A
Bibliography of Blake Scholarship in the United Kingdom.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Fall 1973), 44-46.</p>
          <p>Hoover, Suzanne R. “Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi>: A List of Reviews and Articles.” Blake
Newsletter, 8 (Summer-Fall 1974), 31.</p>
          <p>Roberts, Peter. “On Tame High Finishers of Paltry Harmonies: A Blake Music Review &amp;
Checklist.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Spring 1974), 90-99. (4 illus. from 1972 production of <hi rend="i">Job—a
Masque for Dancing.</hi>)</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">New &amp; Revised Books</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Abrams, M. H. et. al., eds. The Norton Anthology of English Literature, Major Authors Edition.
Third Edition. New York: Norton, 1975. $12.95 cloth; $10.95 paper. (New inclusions by Blake are “The Mental
Traveller” and parts of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Adlard, John. The Sports of Cruelty: Fairies, Folksongs, Charms and Other Country Matters in the
Work of William Blake. London: Cecil &amp; Amelia Woolf, 1972.</p>
          <p>Ault, Donald D. Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton. Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press,
1974. $12.50.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. William Blake: Catalog of the Collection of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge,
West Orange, N. J.: Albert Saifer, 1973. $10.00. Amer. ed.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. America. Bushey Heath, Hertshire: Taurus Press of Willow Dene, 1976.
(Forthcoming)</p>
          <p>Blake, William. America: A Prophecy (facsimile). See Easson.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Book of Ahania (facsimile). Paris: Trianon Press, 1974. £85./£32. (Distr.
by Bernard Quaritch.)</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Clouded Hills: Selections from William Blake. (Mysticism and Modern Man.)
Catharine R. Hughes, ed. New York: Sheed &amp; Ward, 1973. £1.75; $2.95, paper.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Die Illuminationen zu den <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>:
Lieder der Unschuld und der Erfahrung. Wiesbaden: Limes-Verlag, 1972.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Grave: A Poem. Illustrated by Twelve Etchings executed by Louis Schiavonetti,
from the Original Inventions of William Blake, 1808 (facsimile). Wildwood 
                        <pb id="p08-147" n="147"/>
House, 1974. £2.50.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Holy Thursday, from the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> Illustrated by Paul
Peter Piech. Bushey Heath: Taurus Press of Willow Dene, 1971.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Illuminated Blake. David V. Erdman, ed. Garden City, N. Y.: Anchor-Doubleday,
1974. $7.95, paper.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Marriage of Heaven and Hell. East Ardsley, Yorkshire: Micromethods, 1969.
Microfilm positive, 1 reel, 35 mm. No. 534. (Reprod. from Fitzwilliam Museum copy.)</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Materials for the Study of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">America: A
Prophecy.</hi> Roger R. Easson and Kay Parkhurst Easson, eds.; Robert N. Essick, assoc. ed. Bibliographical
Intro. by Gerald E. Bentley, Jr. Normal: The American Blake Foundation, 1975. (Reproduces Copy E, Rosenwald
Collection.)</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Mental Traveller. Drawings by Emil Antonucci. New York: Journeymen Press,
1970.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Mental Traveller. Iowa City: Washington Press, 1967.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Notebook of William Blake: A Photographic &amp; Typographic Facsimile. David
V. Erdman, ed., assisted by Donald K. Moore. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973. $45.00.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Pickering Manuscript. Intro. by Charles Ryskamp. New York: Pierpont Morgan
Library, 1972. $3.00, paper.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Poems of William Blake. Selected, edited &amp; introduced by Aileen Ward,
with illus. from Blake’s Illuminated Books. Cambridge, England: Printed for the members of the Limited
Editions Club (New York) at the University Printing House, 1973. (12 color pls.)</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Proverbs of Hell. Illus. by Duine Campbell. Intro. by Jack Schofield. Leicester:
Black Knight Press, 1972. £2.50. (Limited edition—100; 8 illus.)</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Selected Poems. Ruthven Todd, ed. New York: Dell Publishing Co., 1973. $.40,
paper.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Songs of Innocence and of Experience. East Ardsley, Yorkshire: Micromethods Ltd.,
1971. Microfilm, 1 reel, color, 54 pls. Nos. 529-31. (Reprod. from the Fitzwilliam Museum copy.)</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Songs of Innocence and of Experience (facsimile). Norwood, PA.: Norwood Editions,
1973.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. There is No Natural Religion. Geoffrey Keynes, ed. Clairvaux, Jura, France:
Trianon Press, 1972. (2 vols., facsimile for The Blake Trust.)</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Twelve Poems. J. L. Carr, ed. London: Florin Poets Series, 1972. £0.10.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. William Blake’s Illustrations for John Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regain’d.</hi> With an intro. by Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. Cleveland: Press of the Case Western Reserve
University, 1971.</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. The Visionary Company: A Reading of English Romantic Poetry. Revised and Enlarged
Edition. Ithaca: Cornell Univ. Press, 1971. Paper, $3.95. (pp. 7-123 on Blake.)</p>
          <p>Brisman, Leslie. Milton’s Poetry of Choice and Its Romantic Heirs. Ithaca: Cornell Univ. Press,
1973. (See esp. Chapter 4 for Blake.)</p>
          <p>Bronowski, Jacob. The Ascent of Man. Boston: Little, Brown and Co., 1973. $15.00. (Blake
mentioned in passing; 2 Blake illus.)</p>
          <p>Budgen, Frank. James Joyce and the Making of <hi rend="i">Ulysses</hi> and other writings.
London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1972. (See esp. pp. 318-20.)</p>
          <pb id="p08-148" n="148"/>
          <p>Clark, Kenneth. Blake and Visionary Art. Glasgow: Univ. of Glasgow Press, 1973. (W. A. Cargill
Memorial Lectures in Fine Art, No. 2)</p>
          <p>Clark, Kenneth. The Romantic Rebellion: Romantic Versus Classic Art. London: John Murray (Sotheby
Parke Bernet), 1974. £4.75. (pp. 147-74 on Blake; 308 illus., 24 in color; see also television series.)</p>
          <p>Colnaghi &amp; Co. A Loan Exhibition of Drawings, Watercolours, and Paintings by <corr type="emend">John Linnell</corr> and
his Circle. London: Colnaghi &amp; Co., 1973. (pp. xii+62; 56 pls.; paper) (Exhibition Jan. 10, 1973, to Feb.
2, 1973.)</p>
          <p>Donoghue, Denis. Thieves of Fire. Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press, 1974. $6.95. (On the works of
Milton, Blake, Melville, and D. H. Lawrence.)</p>
          <p>Easson, Roger R., and Kay Parkhurst Easson, eds., and Robert N. Essick, assoc. ed.
Bibliographical Intro. by Gerald E. Bentley, Jr. Materials For the Study of William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America: A Prophecy.</hi> (Materials for the Study of William Blake: A Facsimile Series for the
General Reader, Vol. I.) Illinois State Univ., Normal: The American Blake Foundation, 1975.</p>
          <p>Easson, Roger R., and Robert N. Essick. William Blake: Book Illustrator. Vol. I. Tulsa: Joseph
Nichols, Publisher, 1973. $5.00, paper.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. The Illuminated Blake. Garden City, N. Y.: Anchor-Doubleday, 1974. $7.95,
paper.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., ed., assisted by Donald K. Moore. The Notebook of William Blake: A Photographic
and Typographic Facsimile. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973. £16.00; $45.00.</p>
          <p>Frosch, Thomas R. The Awakening of Albion: The Renovation of the Body in the Poetry of William
Blake. Ithaca: Cornell Univ. Press, 1974. $10.00.</p>
          <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. The Life of William Blake. Intro. by W. A. G. Doyle-Davidson. East Ardsley,
Wakefield, England: E. P. Publishing Ltd., 1973. Vol. I. £5.00. (Facsimile reprint of 1880 edition.)</p>
          <p>Guilhamet, Leon. The Sincere Ideal: Studies on Sincerity in Eighteenth-Century English
Literature. Montreal: McGill-Queens Univ. Press, 1974. (On Blake, pp. 259-68.)</p>
          <p>Hickman, Trevor, Don Humberston, Bob Simpson, and Caspar Standing. William Blake—Private
Printer. The Orchard, Wymondham, Leicestershire: Brewhouse Private Press, 1972. (Broadsheet with inserts; 12
Blake illus.)</p>
          <p>John, Brian. Supreme Fictions: Studies in the Work of William Blake, Thomas Carlyle, W. B. Yeats,
and D. H. Lawrence. Montreal: McGill-Queens Univ. Press, 1974. $13.50.</p>
          <p>Ketterer, David. New Worlds for Old: the Apocalyptic Tradition, Science Fiction, and American
Literature. Bloomington, Ind.: Indiana Univ. Press, 1974. (A chapter on Blake.)</p>
          <p>Kettle, Arnold. William Blake (1757-1827). Walton Hall, Bletchley, Bucks: The Open Univ. Press,
1972. (Textbook module for Units 21-22 in “The Age of Revolutions,” a course in The Open University Dept. of
Harper &amp; Row Publishers: 56 pp., 13 illus.)</p>
          <p>Kumashiro, Soho. Blake wo tadashiku yomu. Tokyo: Hokuseido.</p>
          <p>Leavis, F. R. Nor Shall My Sword: Discourses on Pluralism, Compassion and Social Hope. London:
Chatto &amp; Windus, 1972.</p>
          <p>Lindberg, Bo. William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of Job. Acta Academiae Aboensis, Ser.
A: Humaniora, Vol. 46. Abo: Abo Akademi, 1973.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. British Romantic Art. London: Bell, 1973.</p>
          <p>Mayoux, Jean-Jacques. La Peinture Anglaise de Hogarth aux Preraphaelites. (Peinture, Couleur,
Histoire, No. 18.) Geneva: Skira, 1972. Fr. 230.00. (128 pls.)</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne Kostelanetz. Blake’s Human Form Divine. Berkeley: Univ. of California Press, 1974.
$15.00.</p>
          <p>Morris, David B. The Religious Sublime: Christian Poetry and Critical Tradition in
Eighteenth-Century England. Lexington: Univ. Press of Kentucky, 1972. (Discusses Blake in passing.)</p>
          <p>Nemerov, Howard. Reflexions on Poetry and Poetics. New Brunswick: Rutgers Univ. Press, 1972.
(“Poetry, Prophecy, Prediction,” pp. 103-23; “Two Ways of the Imagination: Blake and Wordsworth,” pp.
208-21.)</p>
          <p>Nurmi, Martin K. William Blake. London: Hutchinson Univ. Library, 1975. £1.95, paper. (4
pls.)</p>
          <p>Palmer, Samuel. The Letters. Raymond Lister, ed. 2 Vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1974.
£28.00.</p>
          <p>Powell, Nicolas. Fuseli: The Nightmare. London: Allen Lane, The Penguin Press, 1973. (Art in
Context Series.) $1.95. (57 illus.)</p>
          <p>Preston, Kerrison, ed. Notes for a Catalogue of the Blake Library at the Georgian House,
Merstham. West Orange, N. J.: Albert Saifer, 1973. $6.00.</p>
          <p>Purce, Jill. The Mystic Spiral: Journey of the Soul. New York: Avon Books, 1974. $4.95, paper.
(References to and reproductions of Blake.)</p>
          <p>Quennell, Peter. A History of English Literature. London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, 1974. (pp.
243-48 on Blake; 5 illus.)</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen. Blake and Antiquity. Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press (Bollingen Series), 1974.
$3.95. (A paper edition of <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Roberts, Mark. The Tradition of Romantic Morality. London: MacMillan Press, 1973. (Chapter 3,
“Blake and the Damnation of Reason.”)</p>
          <p>Ryskamp, Charles, ed. The Pickering Manuscript (facsimile). New York: Pierpont Morgan Library,
1972. $3.00.</p>
          <p>Sabri-Tabrizi, G. R. The “Heaven” and “Hell” of William Blake. London: Lawrence and Wishart,
1973. £4.75; $13.50. (Illus.)</p>
          <p>Sharpless, F. Parvin. The Myth of the Fall: Literature of Innocence and Experience. (Hayden
Humanities Series.) Rochelle Park, N. J.: Hayden Book Co., 1974. $3.68. (Textbook; treats Augustine, Milton,
Blake, and others.)</p>
          <p>Stevenson, Warren H. Divine Analogy: A Study of the Creation Motif in Blake and Coleridge.
(Romantic Reassessment Series.) Salzburg: Dr. James Hogg, Institute fur Englische Sprache und Literatur, Univ.
of Salzburg A-5020, 197?.</p>
          <p>Thorburn, David, and Geoffrey Hartman, eds. Romanticism: Vistas, Instances, Continuities. Ithaca:
Cornell Univ. Press, 1974. (Blake
<pb id="p08-149" n="149"/>
mentioned in passing.)</p>
          <p>Thorpe, Peter. Eighteenth Century English Poetry. Chicago: Nelson-Hall Co., 1975. $8.95. (Blake
mentioned in regard to Augustan verse forms.)</p>
          <p>Tomory, Peter. The Life and Art of Henry Fuseli. London: Thames and Hudson, 1972. Brit. ed.</p>
          <p>Warren, Barbara. The Feminine Image in Literature. (Hayden Humanities Series.) Rochelle Park, N.
J.: Hayden Book Co., 1974. $3.68. (Textbook; Blake mentioned among many.)</p>
          <p>Whitworth Art Gallery. British Watercolours from the John Edward Taylor Collection in the
Whitworth Art Gallery. Foreword by C. R. Dodwell. Intro. by Francis W. Hawcroft. Manchester: Whitworth Art
Gallery, 1973. £0.50; paper. (Exhibition <corr type="emend">17 May 1973–28 July 1973.</corr>)</p>
          <p>Williams, Raymond. The Country and the City. Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press, 1973. $9.75. (Blake
mentioned in passing.)</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of Milton. Madison: Univ. of
Wisconsin Press, (May 1975, forthcoming). Price not set.</p>
          <p>Zigrosser, Carl. Prints and Their Creators: A World History. New York: Crown Pubs., Inc., 1974.
(6 black and white illus.)</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Reprinted Books</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Blake, William. See Milton.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Drawings of William Blake: Ninety-Two Pencil Studies. Geoffrey Keynes, ed. 1970;
rpt. Santa Fe: William Gannon, 1973. $5.75.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Drawings of William Blake: Ninety-Two Pencil Studies. Geoffrey Keynes, ed. 1970;
rpt. New York: Peter Smith, 1973. $6.00.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Mary Wollstonecraft’s Original Stories. 1907; rpt. Folcroft PA: Folcroft
Library Eds., 1973. $10.00.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Milton. A. Russell &amp; E. Maclagan, eds. 1907; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft
Library Eds., 1973. $6.50.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Poems &amp; Prose. Jacob Bronowski, ed. Rpt. New York: Penguin, 1973. Paper,
$1.25.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Poetical Works of William Blake. William Michael Rossetti, ed. 1914; rpt. New
York: AMS Press, 1972. $15.00.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Selected Poems. 1947; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973. $10.00.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. Songs of Innocence &amp; of Experience. Ruthven Todd, ed. 1794; rpt. Folcroft,
PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973. $5.00.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Works of William Blake; Poetic, Symbolic, &amp; Critical . . . Edwin John
Ellis and William Butler Yeats, eds. 1893; rpt. New York: AMS Press, 1973. 3 Vols., $100.00; $35.00 each.
(Illus.)</p>
          <p>Blake, William, and John Donne. Complete Poetry. (Modern Library Giants.) 1941; rpt. New York:
Modern Library, 1973. $4.95.</p>
          <p>Blois, R. E. The American Reputation &amp; Influence of William Blake. 1941; rpt. New York:
Gordon Press, 1973. $11.25.</p>
          <p>Bronowski, Jacob. William Blake and the Age of Revolution. 1944, 1965; rpt. London: Routledge and
Kegan Paul, 1972. £2.25; £0.90, paper.</p>
          <p>Bruce, Harold. William Blake in This World. 1925; rpt. Books for Libraries (Select Bibliographies
Reprint Series), 1972. $13.50.</p>
          <p>Bruce, Harold. William Blake in This World. 1925; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973.
$25.00.</p>
          <p>Burdett, Osbert. William Blake. 1926; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973. $15.00.</p>
          <p>Butterworth, Adeline M. William Blake: Mystic. 1911; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds.,
1973. $12.50.</p>
          <p>Clarke, John H. The God of Shelley and Blake. 1930; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds.,
1973. $4.50.</p>
          <p>Clarke, John H. William Blake on the Lord’s Prayer. 1927; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library
Eds., 1973. $5.00.</p>
          <p>Clarke, John H. William Blake on the Lord’s Prayer. 1927; rpt. Havertown, PA: Richard West,
1973. $9.75.</p>
          <p>Clutton-Brock, Alan. Blake. 1933; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973. $8.75.</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster. A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake. 1965; rpt. Boston:
Brown Univ. Press, 1973. $20.00.</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster. A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake. 1965; rpt. London:
Thames &amp; Hudson, 1973. £1.95, paper.</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster. William Blake: His Philosophy &amp; Symbols. 1924; rpt. Magnolia, Mass.: Smith
Smith, 1973. $12.50.</p>
          <p>Dickinson, Tate L. William Blake’s Anticipation of the Individualistic Revolution. 1915; rpt.
Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973. $5.00.</p>
          <p>Gardner, Charles. Vision &amp; Vesture. 1916; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973.
$7.45.</p>
          <p>Gardner, Charles. William Blake: The Man. 1919; rpt. New York: AMS Press, 1973. $9.00.</p>
          <p>Garnett, Richard. William Blake: Painter &amp; Poet. 1895; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library
Eds., 1971. $8.50.</p>
          <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. The Life of William Blake. 1880; rpt. Totowa, N. J.: Rowman and
Littlefield, 1973. $16.50. (Illus.)</p>
          <p>Hamblen, Emily S. On the Minor Prophecies of William Blake. 1930; rpt. Havertown, PA: Richard
West, 1973. $14.75.</p>
          <p>Harris, Eugenie. Monarch Literature Notes on the Poetry of Blake. 1965; rpt. New York: Monarch
Press, 1973. $1.00.</p>
          <p>Levis, H. C. A Bibliography of the Art and History of Engraving. 1912-13; rpt. London:
Dawson’s, 1974. £35.00.</p>
          <p>MacDonald, Greville. The Sanity of William Blake. (Studies in Blake Series, No. 3.) 1908; rpt.
New York: Haskell House, 1970. $3.95.</p>
          <p>MacDonald, Greville. The Sanity of William Blake. 1908; rpt. Havertown, PA: Richard West, 1973.
$3.75.</p>
          <p>Milton, John. Poems in English, with Illus. by William Blake. London: Nonesuch Press, 1926;
<pb id="p08-150" n="150"/>
rpt. St. Clair Shores, Mich.: Scholarly Press, 1970.</p>
          <p>Murry, John M. William Blake. 1933; rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1971. $14.95.</p>
          <p>Murry, John M. William Blake. 1933; rpt. Havertown PA: Richard West, 1973. $13.75.</p>
          <p>Nicoll, Allardyce. William Blake &amp; His Poetry. 1922; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library
Eds., 1973. $7.50.</p>
          <p>Nicoll, Allardyce. William Blake &amp; His Poetry. 1922; rpt. New York: AMS Press, Inc., 1973.
$7.25.</p>
          <p>Nurmi, Martin. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> 1957; rpt. New York:
Haskell House, 1972. $7.95.</p>
          <p>Pinto, Vivian de Sola, ed. The Divine Vision. 1957; rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1973.
$10.95.</p>
          <p>Pointon, Marcia R. Milton and English Art: A Study in the Pictorial Artist’s Use of a Literary
Source. 1970; rpt. Manchester: Manchester Univ. Press, 1974. £1.20, paper.</p>
          <p>Preston, Kerrison. Blake &amp; Rossetti. 1944; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973.
$16.75.</p>
          <p>Preston, Kerrison. Blake &amp; Rossetti. (Studies in Comparative Literature, No. 35.) 1944; rpt.
New York: Haskell House, 1970. $16.95.</p>
          <p>Robinson, Henry Crabb. Blake, Coleridge, Wordsworth, Lamb, Etc., Being Selections from the
Remains of Henry Crabb Robinson. Edith J. Morley, ed. 1922; rpt. New York: AMS Press, 1973. $10.00.</p>
          <p>Rossetti, William Michael. Letters of William Michael Rossetti. Clarence Gohdes and Paull F.
Baum, eds. 1934;rpt. New York: AMS Press, 1973. $10.00.</p>
          <p>Russell, Archibald G. The Engravings of William Blake. 1912; rpt. New York: Benjamin Blom, 1973.
$12.50.</p>
          <p>Short, Ernest H. Blake. 1926; rpt. Havertown, PA: Richard West, 1973. $8.75.</p>
          <p>Story, Alfred T. William Blake: His Life, Character &amp; Genius. 1893; rpt. Folcroft, PA:
Folcroft Library Eds., 1973. $8.75.</p>
          <p>Swinburne, Algernon C. William Blake: A Critical Essay. 1868; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library
Eds., 1973. $12.00.</p>
          <p>Swinburne, Algernon C. William Blake: A Critical Essay. 1868; rpt. Havertown, PA: Richard West,
1973. $12.45.</p>
          <p>Swinburne, Algernon C. William Blake: A Critical Essay. 1868; rpt. New York: Benjamin Blom, 1973.
$12.50. (Illus.)</p>
          <p>Symons, Arthur. William Blake. 1907; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973. $12.00.</p>
          <p>Symons, Arthur. William Blake. 1907; rpt. Havertown, PA: Richard West, 1973. $12.45.</p>
          <p>Wicksteed, Joseph H. Blake’s Innocence &amp; Experience: A Study of the Songs and Manuscripts.
1928; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds., 1973. $35.00.</p>
          <p>Wicksteed, Joseph H. Blake’s Innocence &amp; Experience: A Study of the Songs and Manuscripts.
1928; rpt. St. Clair Shores, Mich.: The Scholarly Press, 1973. $14.50.</p>
          <p>Wicksteed, Joseph H. Blake’s Vision of the Book of Job. 1924; rpt. Havertown, PA: Richard West,
1973. $11.75.</p>
          <p>Witcutt, W. P. Blake: A Psychological Study. 1941; rpt. Folcroft, PA: Folcroft Library Eds.,
1973. $5.00.</p>
          <p>Witcutt, W. P. Blake: A Psychological Study. 1946;rpt. New York: Gordon Press, 1973. $13.50.</p>
          <p>Wolf-Gumpold, Kaethe. William Blake: Painter, Poet, Visionary—An Attempt at an Introduction to
his Life and Work. 1969; rpt. Spring Valley, N. Y.: Anthroposophic Press, Inc., 1973. $4.95.</p>
          <p>Wright, Thomas. The Life of William Blake. 1929; rpt. New York: Abner Schram, 1972. $22.50.
(Illus.)</p>
          <p>Wright, Thomas. The Life of William Blake. (2 vols. in 1.) 1929;rpt. Chickeley, England: Paul P.
B. Minet, 1972. $22.50.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Parts of Books</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Beaty, F. L. “The New Moralists.” In Light From Heaven. DeKalb: Northern Illinois Univ. Press,
1971. pp. 109-31.</p>
          <p>Butter, P. H. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of Urizen</hi> and Boehme’s <hi rend="i">Mysterium
Magnum.</hi>” In Le Romantisme Anglo-Americain: Melanges Offerts a Louis Bonnerot (Etudes Anglaises). Ed.
Roger Asselineau, et. al. Paris: Didier, 1971. pp. 35-44.</p>
          <p>Curran, Stuart. “The Mental Pinnacle: <hi rend="i">Paradise Regain’d</hi> and the Romantic
Four-Book Epic.” In Calm of Mind: Tercentenary Essays on <hi rend="i">Paradise Regain’d</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Samson Agonistes.</hi> Cleveland: Case Western Reserve Univ. Press, 1971. pp. 133-62.</p>
          <p>Epstein, E. L. “Blake’s ‘Infant Sorrow’: An Essay in Discourse Analysis.” In Current Trends
in Stylistics. (Papers in Linguistics Monograph Series 2.) Eds. Braj B. Kachru and Herbert F. W. Stahlke.
Edmonton, Alberta/Champaign, Ill.: Linguistic Research, Inc. pp. 231-41.</p>
          <p>Frye, Northrop. “Blake’s Case Against Locke.” In English Literature and British Philosophy: a
Collection of Essays. Ed. S. P. Rosenbaum. Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press, 1971. pp. 119-35. (Reprint of 1947
essay, Chapter 1 of <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. “ ‘Such, Such Were the Joys’ : The Boyhood of the Man of Feeling.” In
Changing Taste in Eighteenth-Century Art and Literature: Papers Read at a Clark Library Seminar, April 17,
1971. Eds. Robert E. Moore and Jean H. Hagstrum. Intro. by Earl Miner. Los Angeles: William Andrews Clark
Memorial Library (UCLA), 1972. pp. 43-61.</p>
          <p>Hartman, Geoffrey H. “Blake and the Progress of Poesy.” In Beyond Formalism. New Haven: Yale
Univ. Press, 1970. pp. 193-205.</p>
          <p>Hartman, Geoffrey H. “Reflections on the Evening Star: Akenside to Coleridge.” In New
Perspectives on Coleridge and Wordsworth (Selected Papers from the English Institute). Ed. Geoffrey H.
Hartman. New York: Columbia Univ. Press, 1972. pp. 85-132. (Discusses Blake’s star symbolism.)</p>
          <p>Hilles, Frederick W. “Reynolds Among the Romantics.” In Literary Theory and Structure: Essays in
Honor of William K. Wimsatt. Eds. Frank Brady,
<pb id="p08-151" n="151"/>
John Palmer, and Martin Price. New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1973. pp. 267-82. (Treats Blake’s, Haydon’s,
and Hazlitt’s marginalia on the <hi rend="i">Discourses.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Kaplan, Fred. “Blake’s Artist.” In Miracles of Rare Device: The Poet’s Sense of Self in
Nineteenth-Century Poetry. Detroit: Wayne State Univ. Press, 1972. pp. 17-28.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Lemaître, Henri.</corr> “William Blake, Vision et Poesie.” In Le Romantisme Anglo-Americain: Melanges
Offerts a Louis Bonnerot (Etudes Anglaises). Ed. Roger Asselineau et. al. Paris: Didier, 1971. pp. 45-54.</p>
          <p>Leavis, F. R. “Introductory: ‘Life’ is a Necessary Word.” In Nor Shall My Sword. London:
Chatto &amp; Windus, 1972. pp. 11-37. (Discusses Blake among others.)</p>
          <p>Lovell, Ernest J., Jr. “The Heretic in the Sacred Wood.” In Romantic and Victorian: Studies in
Memory of William H. Marshall. Paul W. Elledge and Richard L. Hoffman, eds. Rutherford, N. J.: Fairleigh
Dickinson Univ. Press, 1971.</p>
          <p>Manning, Sylvia. “William Blake.” In Images of the City: London in Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-
Century Literature. New York: Harper &amp; Row (Harper Studies in Language and Literature), 1974. pp.
10-11.</p>
          <p>Neubauer, John. “The Sick Rose as an Aesthetic Idea: Kant, Blake, and the Symbol in Literature.”
In Irrationalism in Eighteenth-Century Culture (Vol. 2, Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture). Cleveland: The
Press of the Case Western Reserve Univ., 1972. pp. 167-79.</p>
          <p>Nichols, Maryann. “An Epochal Palimpsest.” In The Celtic Bull: Essays on James Joyce’s 
<hi rend="i">Ulysses.</hi> (Tulsa Monograph Series, No. 1.) Tulsa: Univ. of Tulsa Dept. of English, 1961. pp.
1-23. (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as one among several analogs for <hi rend="i">Ulysses.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Rexroth, Kenneth. “William Blake.” In The Elastic Retort. New York: <corr type="emend">Seabury</corr> Press, 1973. pp.
77-80.</p>
          <p>Roberts, Mark. “Blake and the Damnation of Reason.” In The Tradition of Romantic Morality. New
York: Barnes &amp; Noble Books, 1973. pp. 82-122.</p>
          <p>Spinks, C. William. “Blake’s Spectre.” In Studies in Relevance: Romantic and Victorian Writers
in 1972. (Salzburg Studies in English Literature, Romantic Reassessment, 32) Ed. Thomas Meade Harwell.
Salzburg: Univ. of Salzburg, 1973. pp. 24-35.</p>
          <p>Thorslev, Peter L., Jr. “Some Dangers of Didactic Thinking, with Illustrations from Blake and His
Critics.” In Romantic and Victorian: Studies in Memory of William H. Marshall. Paul W. Elledge and Richard L.
Hoffman, eds. Rutherford, N. J.: Fairleigh Dickinson Univ. Press, 1971. pp. 43-74.</p>
          <p>Ward, Aileen. “The Forging of Orc: Blake and the Idea of Revolution.” In Literature in
Revolution. (A Triquarterly Book.) George A. White and Charles Newman, eds. New York: Holt, Rinehart and
Winston, 1972. pp. 204-27.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Articles</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Adams, Hazard. “Blake and the Philosophy of Literary Symbolism.” New Literary History, 5 (1973),
135-46.</p>
          <p>Adamson, Arthur. “Structure and Meaning in Blake’s ‘The Mental Traveller,’ ” Mosaic, 7
(Summer 1974), 41-58.</p>
          <p>Adlard, John. “Blake’s ‘The Little Girl Lost and Found.’ ” Archiv, 210 (Dec. 1973),
330-34.</p>
          <p>Adlard, John. “Los Enters London.” English Studies, 54 (June 1973), 227-30.</p>
          <p>Allentuck, Marcia. “Blake, Flaxman, and Thomas: A New Document.” Harvard Library Bulletin, 20
(July 1972), 318-19.</p>
          <p>Avni, Abraham. “Blake’s ‘Tiriel’—The Meaning of ‘Ijim’.” Notes &amp; Queries, 21
(Feb. 1974), 60-61.</p>
          <p>Bateson, F. W. Editorial comment on Doyno, “Blake’s Revision of ‘London.’ ” Essays in
Criticism, 22 (Jan. 1972), 61-62.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. “Blake and Cromek: The Wheat and the Tares.” Modern Philology, 71 (May
1974), 366-79.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. “A Unique Prospectus for Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> Designs.” The
Princeton University Library Chronicle, 35 (Spring 1974), 321-25.</p>
          <p>Bishop, Morchard. “The Poet and the Attorney: The Story of a Legacy.” Book Collector, 21 (Summer
1972), 245-54.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. (Various poems and excerpts translated into Danish by Gunnar Harding and
Percival). Horisont, 20 (1973), 12-13, 27, 29-33.</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. “<hi rend="i">Clinamen</hi> or Poetic Misprision.” New Literary History, 3 (1972),
373-91. (Milton’s influence on the Romantics, esp. Blake.)</p>
          <p>Borck, Jim S. “Blake’s ‘The Lamb’: The Punctuation of Innocence.” Tennessee Studies in
Literature, 19 (1974), 163-75.</p>
          <p>Brantlinger, Patrick M. “Classic and Romantic: An Augury of Innocence.” College English, 33
(March 1972), 702-11.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. “The Blake Collection of Mrs. William T. Tonner.” Bulletin of the Philadelphia
Museum of Art, 67 (July-Sept. 1972): No. 307. (pp. 34, 18 illus.) $1.00.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. “Five Blakes from a Nineteenth-Century Scottish Collection.” Blake Newsletter, 7
(Summer 1973), 4-8. (6 illus.)</p>
          <p>Carey, Frances A. “James Smetham (1821-1889) and Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake.</hi>”
Blake Newsletter, 8 (Summer-Fall 1974), 17-25. (11 illus.)</p>
          <p>Charmet, Raymond. “Le Courant Fantastique Souterrain <corr type="emend">XVIe–XIXe</corr> Siecles.” 
Jardin des Arts, 204 (Nov. 1971), 34-41. (Discusses Callor, Arcimboldo, Desideriro, Fuseli, and Blake.)</p>
          <p>Chayes, Irene H. “Blake and the Seasons of the Poet.” Studies in Romanticism, 11 (Summer 1972),
225-40.</p>
          <p>Chayes, Irene H. “The Marginal Design on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 12.” Blake Studies, 7
(1974), 51-76.</p>
          <p>Cohen, Sandy. “Is William Blake’s Concept of
<pb id="p08-152" n="152"/>
Marriage Kabbalistic?” Notes &amp; Queries, 20 (March 1973), 100-01.</p>
          <p>Colbert, Alison. “A Talk with Allen Ginsberg.” Partisan Review, 38 (Fall 1971), 289-309. (On
Ginsberg’s musical settings of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Connolly, Thomas E. “<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Keynes (1921) Copy U, Keynes-Wolf
(1953) Copy U.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Spring 1974), 88-89.</p>
          <p>Cook, Albert. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” Costerus, 6 (1972), 27-33.</p>
          <p>Curtis, F. B. “Blake and the ‘Moment of Time’: An Eighteenth-Century Controversy in
Mathematics.” Philological Quarterly, 51 (1972), 460-70.</p>
          <p>Denvir, B. “Sensibility and Cybernetics; some recent books about art.” Art International, 16
(Feb. 1972), 64-66.</p>
          <p>Doxey, William S. “William Blake and the Lunar Society.” Notes &amp; Queries, 18 (Sept. 1971),
343.</p>
          <p>Doyno, V. “Blake’s Revision of ‘London’.” Essays in Criticism, 22 (Jan. 1972), 58-63.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. “The Steps (of Dance and Stone) that Order Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>”
Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 73-87.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1972-73.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Winter 1973-1974),
52-59. (1 illus.)</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake, Linnell, &amp; James Upton: An Engraving Brought to Light.” Blake
Newsletter, 7 (Spring 1974), 76-79. (2 illus.)</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 25: Some Thoughts on Technique.” Blake Newsletter,
7 (Winter 1973-1974), 64-66.</p>
          <p>Evanoff, Alexander. “The Visions of William Blake.” Antigonish Review, 2 (Sept. 1971), 11-18.</p>
          <p>Fawcus, Arnold. “Blake’s Illustrations for the Book of Job.” Times Literary Supplement, 15
March 1974, pp. 271-72. (6 illus.)</p>
          <p>Fawcus, Arnold. “Illustrations de William Blake Pour Les Poems de Thomas Gray.” Jardin des Arts,
205 (Dec. 1971), 2.</p>
          <p>Fawcus, Arnold. “William Blake’s Watercolour Designs Illustrating Gray’s Poems—and Mr. Paul
Mellon.” Connoisseur, 179 (Jan. 1972), 10-14.</p>
          <p>Fletcher, Ian. “Edwin Ellis’s Letter to Fairfax Murray, 31 Jan. 1892.” Book Collector, 21
(Autumn 1972), 414. (corrections to letter printed in Book Collector, 21 (Spring 1972); Ellis’s letter
mentions a Blake MS.)</p>
          <p>Fletcher, Ian, ed. “John Todhunter’s Lectures on Blake, 1872-1874.” Blake Newsletter, 8
(Summer-Fall 1974), 4-14.</p>
          <p>Goslee, Nancy M. “ ‘In England’s green &amp; pleasant Land’: The Building of Vision in
Blake’s Stanzas from <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 105-25.</p>
          <p>Grant, John E. “Blake’s ‘Illustrations of the Book of Job.’ ” Times Literary Supplement, 30
Nov. 1973, p. 1484.</p>
          <p>Grant, John E., and Mary Lynn Johnson. “Illuminated Books in the Cincinnati Art Museum.” Blake
Newsletter, 7 (Fall 1973), 40-43. (3 illus.)</p>
          <p>Helms, Randel. “Blake at Felpham: A Study in the Psychology of Vision.” Literature and
Psychology, 22 (1972), 57-66.</p>
          <p>Helms, Randel. “Ezekiel and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Studies in Romanticism, 13
(Spring 1974), 127-40.</p>
          <p>Helms, Randel. “Proverbs of Heaven and Proverbs of Hell.” Punch, 38 (March 1974), 51-58.</p>
          <p>Herzing, Thomas W. “Book I of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Natural Religion as an Optical
Fallacy.” Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 19-34.</p>
          <p>Hoover, Suzanne R. “The Public Reception of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake.</hi>” Blake
Newsletter, 8 (Summer-Fall 1974), 26-30.</p>
          <p>Hutchison, Alexander N. “Blake’s Illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">On the Morning of
Christ’s Nativity.</hi>” British Columbia Library Quarterly, 36 (Oct. 1972-Jan. 1973), 9-20.</p>
          <p>Jackson, Wallace. “William Blake in 1789: Unorganized <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi>” Modern
Language Quarterly, 33 (Dec. 1972), 396-404.</p>
          <p>Jakubec, Doris. “ ‘La Rose Malade’ de William Blake.” Etudes de Lettres, 5 (April-Sept.
1972), 51-59.</p>
          <p>James, G. Ingli. “Blake’s Woodcuts Illuminated.” Apollo, 99 (March 1974), 194-95. (illus.)</p>
          <p>James, G. Ingli. “Blake’s Woodcuts.” Times Literary Supplement, 8 June 1973, p. 645. (Answer to
a query from Reynolds Stone in Times Literary Supplement, 1 June 1973, p. 617.)</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. “Blake.” Times Literary Supplement, 5 May 1972, p. 521. (Reply to Pierre Leyris
on emending <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. “The Blake Trust Gray Catalogue and the Blake Trust Facsimiles.” Blake
Newsletter, 7 (Winter 1973-1974), 64-66.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. “William Blake &amp; Bart’s.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Summer 1973), 9-10. (1
illus.)</p>
          <p>Kroeber, Karl. “Perspectives on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: A Prefatory Note.” Blake
Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 7-9. (Preface to the 1973 MLA Seminar papers. See Johnson, Herzing, Jeffrey Mitchell,
W. J. T. Mitchell, and Erdman.)</p>
          <p>La Belle, Jenijoy. “Theodore Roethke and Tradition: ‘The Pure Serene of Memory in One Man.’ ”
Northwest Review, 11 (Summer 1971), 1-18. (Blake mentioned as an influence on later Roethke.)</p>
          <p>Lefcowitz, Barbara F. “Omnipotence of Thought and the Poetic Imagination: Blake, Coleridge, and
Rilke.” Psychoanalytic Review, 59 (Fall 1972), 417-32. (Discusses “A Poison Tree,” pp. 418-21.)</p>
          <p>Leyris, Pierre. “Blake.” Times Literary Supplement, 28 April 1972, p. 496. (On emending 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>—see Keynes’ reply.)</p>
          <p>McConnell, Frank D. “Romanticism, Language, Waste: A Reflection on Poetics and Disaster.”
Bucknell Review, 20 (Winter 1972), 121-40. (pp. 135-39 discusses “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> and other Blake.)</p>
          <p>Mackerness, E. D. “Blake and the Malkins.” Durham University Journal, 66 (March 1974),
179-84.</p>
          <p>MacMillan, Malcolm Kingsley. “Dialogue Between Blake and Wordsworth: written in Rome before 17
April 1889 and left unfinished.” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Summer-Fall 1974), 38-41.</p>
          <p>Marks, Mollyanne. “Self-Sacrifice: Theme and Image in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Blake
Studies, 7 (1974), 27-50.</p>
          <p>Mitchell, Jeffrey. “Progression from the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> into the Bard’s Song of 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 35-45.</p>
          <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. “Style and Iconography in the Illustrations of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” Blake
<pb id="p08-153" n="153"/>
Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 47-71.</p>
          <p>Moore, Donald K. “Blake’s Notebook Versions of <hi rend="i">Infant Sorrow.</hi>” Bulletin of
the New York Public Library, 76 (1972), 209-19. (3 illus.)</p>
          <p>Morkan, Joel. “Milton’s <hi rend="i">Eikonoklastes</hi> &amp; Blake’s Mythic Geography: A
Parallel.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Spring 1974), 87, 89.</p>
          <p>Muir, Kenneth. “William Blake and the Eighteenth-Century.” Literary Half-Yearly, 12 (1971),
87-97.</p>
          <p>Murray, E. B. “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Reversed.” Blake Studies, 7 (1974), 11-25.</p>
          <p>Murray, Roger. “Blake and the Ideal of Simplicity.” Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974),
89-104.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. “The Critical Reception of <hi rend="i">A Critical Essay.</hi>” Newsletter, 8
(Summer-Fall 1974), 32-37. (4 illus.)</p>
          <p>Parker, Patricia. “The Progress of Phaedria’s Bower: Spenser to Coleridge.” English Literary
History, 40 (1973), 372-97. (Traces bower motifs in Spenser, Milton, Thomson, Blake and Keats.)</p>
          <p>Packer, William, and G. S. Whittet. “London.” Art and Artists, 6 (Jan. 1972), 46-47, 49. (About
the Tate Gallery Exhibit of Blake’s Illustrations to Gray.)</p>
          <p>Paulson, Ronald. “The Spectres of Blake and Rowlandson.” Listener, 90 (2 Aug. 1973), 140-42.
(illus.)</p>
          <p>Pearcy, Roy J. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tyger</hi> &amp; Richard Crashaw’s Paraphrase of Thomas
of Celano’s <hi rend="i">Dies Irae.</hi>” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Spring 1974), 80-81.</p>
          <p>Percival (Milton 0.?) “Fem ut drag ur boken Jerusalem.” Horisont, 20 (1973), 27-28.</p>
          <p>Percival, (Milton 0.?) “Visionaren William Blake—den skapande fantasins profet.” Horisont 20
(1973), 14-26. (7 illus.; includes several of the lyrics translated into Swedish.)</p>
          <p>Peschel, Enid Rhodes. “Violence and Vision: A Study of William Blake and Arthur Rimbaud.” Revue
de Litterature Comparee, 46 (July-Sept. 1972), 376-95.</p>
          <p>Peterson, Jane E. “The <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>: A Problem in
Perception.” Philological Quarterly, 52 (April 1973), 252-64.</p>
          <p>Pittman, Philip McM. “Blake, Rossetti, and Reynolds: a Detail.” Notes &amp; Queries, 21 (June
1974), 215-16.</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen. “Hopkins, Nature and Human Nature.” Sewanee Review, 81 (Spring 1973), 201-24.
(Blake mentioned in comparison.)</p>
          <p>Reich, M. “Imagination of Elihu Vedder—As Revealed In His Book Illustrations.” American Art
Journal, 6 (May 1974), 48-50. (1 Blake illus.)</p>
          <p>Reisner, Mary Ellen. <corr type="emend">“The</corr> Rainbow in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>” Notes &amp; Queries, 18 (Sept. 1971), 341-43.</p>
          <p>Rizzardi, Alfredo. “Ungaretti e le visioni di Blake.” L’Approdo Letterario, 18 (March 1972),
114-19.</p>
          <p>Roberts, Neil. “The Spirit of Crow.” Delta, 50 (Spring 1972), 3-15.</p>
          <p>Rose, Edward J. “Preface—Perspectives on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Blake Studies, 7 (1974),
7-9. (Preface to the 1974 MLA Seminar papers. See Irene H. Chayes, Mollyanne Marks, and E. B. Murray.)</p>
          <p>Ryan, Robert M. “Poisonous Blue.’ ” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Spring 1974), 87, 89.</p>
          <p>Sanzo, Eileen. “William Blake and the Technological Age.” Thought, 46 (Winter 1971), 577-91.</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn. “ ‘Separating What Has Been Mixed’: A Suggestion for A Perspective on 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 11-17.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Serrano Poncela, Segundo.</corr> “Blake Sin Profecia.” Asomante, 23 (July-Sept. 1967), 7-24.</p>
          <p>Stevens, L. Robert. “The Exorcism of England’s Gothic Demon.” Midwest Quarterly, 14 (Winter
1973), 151-64.</p>
          <p>Stevenson, W. H. “On the Nature of Blake’s Symbolism.” Texas Studies in Literature and
Language, 15 (1973), 445-60.</p>
          <p>Tayler, Irene. “The Woman Scaly.” BMWMLA 6 (1973), 74-87.</p>
          <p>Taylor, Gary J. “The Structure of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>: A Revolutionary Primer.”
Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 141-45.</p>
          <p>Taylor, Peter Alan. “Blake’s Text for the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> Drawings.” Blake Newsletter,
7 (Spring 1974), 82-86. (6 illus.)</p>
          <p>Todhunter, John. See Fletcher.</p>
          <p>Tolley, Michael J. “John Todhunter: A Forgotten Debt to Blake.” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Summer-Fall
1974), 15-16.</p>
          <p>Trawick, Leonard. “Nature and Art in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Afterthoughts on the 1973 MLA
Seminar.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Winter 1973-1974), 67-68.</p>
          <p>Wardle, Judith. “Satan, not Having the Science of Wrath, but only of Pity.” Studies in
Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 147-54.</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet. “Blake and English Printed Textiles.” Blake Newsletter 6 (Winter 1973), 84-92. (15
illus.)</p>
          <p>Welch, Dennis M. “Blake, Nehemiah and Religious Renewal.” Christian Scholar’s Review, 2 (1973),
308-10.</p>
          <p>Williams, Harry. “Dylan Thomas’ Poetry of Redemption: Its Blakean Beginnings.” Bucknell Review,
20 (Winter 1972), 107-20.</p>
          <p>Williams, Harry. “The Tyger and the Lamb.” Concerning Poetry, 5:1, 49-56.</p>
          <p>Williams, Porter, Jr. “ ‘Duty’ in Blake’s ‘The Chimney Sweeper’ of <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence.</hi>” English Language Notes, 12 (Dec. 1974), 92-96.</p>
          <p>Wills, James T. “An Additional Drawing for Blake’s Bunyan Series.” Blake Newsletter, 6 (Winter
1973), 63-67. (1 illus.)</p>
          <p>Wilton, Andrew. “A Fan Design by Blake.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Winter 1973-1974), 60-63. (4
illus.)</p>
          <p>Witke, Joanne. “Blake’s Tree of Knowledge Grows Out of the Enlightenment.” Enlightenment
Essays, 3 (Summer 1972), 71-84.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. “ ‘Divine Countenance’: Blake’s Portrait and Portrayals of
Milton.” Huntington Library Quarterly, 38 (Feb. 1975), 125-60. (14 illus.)</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. “Domes of Mental Pleasure: Blake’s Epics and Hayley’s Epic Theory.”
Studies in Philology, 69 (Jan. 1972), 101-29.</p>
          <p>Wright, John. “Towards Recovering Blake’s Relief-Etching Process.” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Fall
1973), 32-39. (12 illus.)</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p08-154" n="154"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Adlard, John. The Sports of Cruelty: Fairies, Folksongs, Charms and Other Country Matters in the
Work of William Blake. Reviewed by Katharine M. Briggs, Blake Newsletter, 7 (Summer 1973), 22-23; Irene H.
Chayes, Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 155-64; T. R. Henn, Modern Language Review, 69 (April 1974),
379-80.</p>
          <p>Ault, Donald D. Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton. Reviewed by Stuart Curran,
Studies in English Literature 1500-1900, 14 (Autumn 1974), 639-40; Dewey R. Faulkner, “Starry Wheels and
Living Forms,” Yale Review, 64 (Winter 1975), 271-74; Dennis R. Dean, Library Journal, 99 (April 15, 1974),
1133.</p>
          <p>Beer, John. Blake’s Visionary Universe. Reviewed by Desiree Hirst, The Yearbook of English
Studies, 2 (1972), 294-95.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr., comp. The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne. Reviewed by John E.
Grant, Philological Quarterly, 51 (1972), 642-43; “Is there a natural Blake?” Times Literary Supplement, 28
April 1972, p. 470.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. Blake Records. Reviewed by Jerome J. McGann, Modern Philology 69 (Feb.
1972), 261-66.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr., ed. Tiriel. Reviewed by Manfred Putz, Anglia, 89:2, 265.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, comp. William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the Fitzwilliam Museum.
Reviewed by John E. Grant, Philological Quarterly, 51 (1972), 643.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Book of Ahania. (Trianon Press, facsimile.) Reviewed in “The Processes of
William Blake,” Times Literary Supplement, 15 (Feb. 1974), pp. 145-47.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Grave: A Poem. Illustrated by Twelve Etchings executed by Louis Schiavonetti,
from the Original Inventions of William Blake 1808. (Wildwood House, facsimile.) Reviewed in “The Processes of
William Blake,” Times Literary Supplement, 15 Feb. 1974, pp. 145-47.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. There is no Natural Religion. (Trianon Press, facsimile.) Reviewed in “Is there a
natural Blake?” Times Literary Supplement, 28 April 1972, p. 470.</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. The Anxiety of Influence. Reviewed in America, 128 (14 April 1973), 341;
Commonweal, 99 (2 Nov. 1973), 112; Economist, 248 (7 July 1973), 108-09; New Leader, 56 (30 April 1973), 16;
New York Times Book Review, 4 March 1973, p. 27; New Republic, 168 (10 Feb. 1973), 36; John Hollander, Poetry,
122 (Aug. 1973), 298-303; Times Literary Supplement, 26 Oct. 1973, p. 1308; Virginia Quarterly Review, 49
(Summer 1973), cxv; David Gordon, Yale Review, 62 (Summer 1973), 588-91; New York Times Book Review, 2 Dec.
1973, p. 2; Partisan Review, 40 (Fall 1973), 494; The Nation, 218 (20 April 1974), 498; Daniel Hoffman,
“Misinterpretations,” American Scholar, 43 (Autumn 1974), 658-71; Comparative Literature, 26 (Summer 1974),
269; Journal of English and Germanic Philology, 73 (March 1974), 266; Choice, 10 (Sept. 1973), 965-66; Kirkus
Reviews, 40 (1 Dec. 1972), 1383; Alison Heinemann, Library Journal, 98 (15 May 1973), 1583.</p>
          <p>Bogen, Nancy, ed. The Book of Thel: A Facsimile and a Critical Text. Reviewed by John E. Grant,
Philological Quarterly, 51 (1972), 643-44; <corr type="emend">Kerry McSweeney,</corr> Queen’s Quarterly, 79 (1972), 236-37; W. H.
Stevenson, Studies in Romanticism, 11 (1972), 71-72; “Disorientations,” Times Literary Supplement, 29 Sept.
1972, p. 1145; Francis Wood Metcalf, Blake Newsletter, 7 (Summer 1973), 17-19; Donald D. Ault, Modern
Philology, 71 (Nov. 1973), 218-21; Max F. Schultz, Eighteenth-Century Studies, 7 (Fall 1973), 120-23.</p>
          <p>Brisman, Leslie. Milton’s Poetry of Choice and Its Romantic Heirs. Reviewed by Leslie
Tannenbaum, Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 84-85; David V. Erdman, English Language Notes, 12 (Sept. 1974,
Supplement No. 1), 23; Herbert E. Shapiro, Library Journal, 98 (15 Feb. 1973), 546; Choice, 10 (Oct. 1973),
1188.</p>
          <p>Bronowski, Jacob. William Blake and the Age of Revolution. Reviewed in The Times, 23 March 1972,
p. 10; “Is there a natural Blake?” Times Literary Supplement, 28 April 1972, p. 470.</p>
          <p>Bronowski, Jacob, narrator. William Blake (BBC). Reviewed by Morton D. Paley, “BBC Blake,” Blake
Newsletter, 7 (Summer 1973), 16.</p>
          <p>Burstall, Christopher, director. <hi rend="i">Tyger, Tyger</hi> (BBC-TV, London, 1969.) Reviewed
by Morton D. Paley, “BBC Blake,” Blake Newsletter, 7 (Summer 1973), 16.</p>
          <p>Clark, Kenneth, et. al., compositors. “Romantic Painting in Britain from Gainsborough to the
Pre-Raphaelites.” An Exhibition at the Petit Palais, Paris, <corr type="emend">Jan.–Feb. 1972.</corr> 
Reviewed by Guy Brett, “Romanticism Seen as the English Grand Style,” The Times, 28 Jan. 1972, p. 12 
(Illus.: Blake’s “Pity”).</p>
          <p>Colnaghi &amp; Co., A Loan Exhibition of Drawings, Watercolours, and Paintings by John Linnell
and his Circle. Reviewed by Robert N. Essick, Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 107-08.</p>
          <p>Curran, Stuart, and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., eds. Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Reviewed by Hazard Adams, Blake
Newsletter, 7 (Winter 1973-1974), 69-72; “The Processes of William Blake,” Times Literary Supplement, 15 Feb.
1974, pp. 145-47; Irene H. Chayes, Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 155-64; Florence Sandler, Western
Humanities Review, 28 (Autumn 1974), 389-91; David V. Erdman, English Language Notes, 12 (Sept. 1974,
Supplement No. 1), 29-30; “The Processes of William Blake,” Times Literary Supplement, 15 (Feb. 1974), pp.
145-47; Mary R. Baine, Georgia Review, 28 (Spring 1974), 146-47; Dewey R. Faulkner, “Secrets of Dark
Contemplation,” Yale Review, 63 (Summer 1974), 590-99; Frank P. Riga, Library Journal, 98 (Aug. 1973), 2296;
Choice, 10 (Jan. 1974), 1715.</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster. A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake. Reviewed by Bill
Platypus, Spectator, 231 (14 July 1973), 52; Times Literary Supplement, 20 July 1973, p. 828; Marie Peel,
“Symbolism in Blake,”
<pb id="p08-155" n="155"/>
Books &amp; Bookmen, 18 (Sept. 1973), 58-59; Frederick Laws, The Daily Telegraph, 13 Sept. 1973, p. 8.</p>
          <p>Donoghue, Denis. Thieves of Fire. Reviewed by David Ellis, “Head for Heights,” New Statesman, 87
(8 March 1974), 332-33; “Promythology,” Times Literary Supplement, 1 March 1974, p. 206; Book World
(Washington Post), 23 June 1974, p. 4; The Observer, 31 March 1974, p. 39; Andrew von Hendy, America, 131 (10
Aug. 1974), 60; Milton Quarterly, 8 (Oct. 1974), 91-92; Keith Cushman, Library Journal, 99 (Aug. 1974),
1952-53; Choice, 11 (Nov. 1974), 1306.</p>
          <p>Dumbaugh, Winnifred. William Blake’s Vision of America. Reviewed by Max F. Schulz,
Eighteenth-Century Studies 7 (Fall 1973), 120-23.</p>
          <p>Easson, Roger R., and Robert N. Essick. William Blake: Book Illustrator—A Bibliography and
Catalogue of the Commercial Engravings. Reviewed in Times Literary Supplement, 16 Feb. 1973, p. 189; Doublas
Cooper, Books &amp; Bookmen, 18 (Aug. 1973), 40-42; Deidre Toomey, Blake Newsletter, 7 (Summer 1973), 19;
Irene H. Chayes, Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 155-64.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., ed. The Illuminated Blake. Reviewed by Lincoln Kirstein, The Nation, 219 (16
Nov. 1974), 503-04; Dewey R. Faulkner, “Starry Wheels and Living Forms,” Yale Review, 64 (Winter 1975),
271-74.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., and John E. Grant, eds. Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic. Reviewed by William
Vaughan, “The Third Blake,” Studio International, 182 (Nov. 1971), 210-12; Anthony Blunt, “Blakomania,” Yale
Review, 61 (Winter 1972), 301-06; Desiree Hirst, Review of English Studies, 24 (Feb. 1973), 95-99; Mario Praz,
English Studies, 54 (1973), 516-18; Max F. Schulz, Eighteenth-Century Studies, 7 (Fall 1973), 120-23;
Burlington Magazine, 116 (Aug. 1974), 482.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., ed. Donald K. Moore, asst. The Notebook of William Blake: A Photographic and
Typographic Facsimile. Reviewed by Raymond Williams, “Radical Blake,” Guardian, 29 (Nov. 1973); Dewey R.
Faulkner, “Secrets of Dark Contemplation,” Yale Review, 63 (Summer 1974), 590-99; G. Ingli James, Apollo, 99
(Nov. 1974), 428; “The Processes of William Blake,” Times Literary Supplement, 15 Feb. 1974, pp. 145-47; The
Listener, 91 (10 Jan. 1974), 54; The Economist, 250 (26 Jan. 1974), 105; Frank P. Riga, Library Journal, 99
(11 March 1974), 657; Choice, 11 (April 1974), 256.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. Blake: Prophet Against Empire. Reviewed by Jerome J. McGann, Modern Philology,
69 (Feb. 1972), 261-66.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N., ed. The Visionary Hand. Reviewed by Stuart Curran, Studies in English
Literature 1500-1900, 14 (Autumn 1974), 642-43; Choice, 11 (July/Aug. 1974), 746.</p>
          <p>Feldman, Burton, and Robert D. Richardson. The Rise of Modern Mythology, 1680-1860. Reviewed by
Robert Ackerman, “Writing about Writing about Myth,” Journal of the History of Ideas, 34 (Jan.-March 1973),
147-55; American Anthropologist, 75 (Dec. 1973), 1888; Journal of American Folklore, 86 (Oct. 1973), 407.</p>
          <p>Frosch, Thomas R. The Awakening of Albion: The Renovation of the Body in the Poetry of William
Blake. Reviewed by Pam Bromberg, Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 169-71; “Cleansing the Organs of
Perception,” Times Literary Supplement, 5 July 1974, p. 704; David V. Erdman, English Language Notes, 12
(Sept. 1974, Supplement No. 1), 33; Stuart Curran, Studies in English Literature 1500-1900, 14 (Autumn 1974),
640-41; Hazard Adams, English Language Notes, 12 (Dec. 1974), 152-53; Dewey R. Faulkner, “Secrets of Dark
Contemplation,” Yale Review, 63 (Summer 1974), 590-99; Virginia Quarterly Review, 50 (Summer 1974), lxxvi;
Donald Gilzing, Library Journal, 99 (1 Jan. 1974), 57; Choice, 11 (April 1974), 258.</p>
          <p>Gaunt, William. The Restless Century: Painting in Britain, 1800-1900. Reviewed by Robert
Melville, “Token Selection,” New Statesman, 84 (29 Dec. 1972), 988; American Artist, 37 (June 1973), 62;
Graham Reynolds, “The Victorian Heritage,” Apollo, 97 (Feb. 1973), 196-97; Books &amp; Bookmen, 18 (March
1973), 24; Contemporary Review, 221 (Dec. 1972), 335; David Coombs, Connoisseur, 182 (Feb. 1973), 138; Denys
Sutton, “On the Scrutiny of Labels: Nineteenth-Century Art Revalued,” Encounter, 40 (Feb. 1973), 63-67; New
York Times Book Review, 3 Dec. 1972, p. 90; “Victorian Masters,” Times Literary Supplement, 22 Dec. 1972, p.
1550; Library Journal, 98 (15 Jan. 1973), 154-56; Choice, 10 (June 1973), 608.</p>
          <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. The Life of William Blake. Intro. by W. A. G. Doyle-Davidson. Reviewed by
Robert N. Essick, Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 108; Books &amp; Bookmen, 18 (Sept. 1973), 95.</p>
          <p>Gillham, D. G. William Blake. Reviewed by Luther S. Luedtke, Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973),
98-103; David V. Erdman, English Language Notes, 12 (Sept. 1974, Supplement No. 1), 33; David Kwinn, Library
Journal, 98 (1 June 1973), 1820; Choice, 10 (Dec. 1973), 1549.</p>
          <p>Grimes, Ronald L. The Divine Imagination. Reviewed by David Kwinn, Library Journal, 98 (1 April
1973), 1167.</p>
          <p>Harbison, John, conductor. Five Songs of Experience. Reviewed by Richard Dyer, The Nation, 218
(13 April 1974), 477.</p>
          <p>Hartman, Geoffrey H., ed. New Perspectives on Coleridge and Wordsworth. Reviewed by Hugh Luke,
“Critics and Romantics,” Prairie Schooner, 46 (Winter 1972-73), 368-69; Choice, 9 (Feb. 1973), 1590.</p>
          <p>Hughes, Catharine, ed. The Clouded Hills: Selections from William Blake. Reviewed in Book World
(Washington Post), 7 (12 Aug. 1973), 13; Books &amp; Bookmen, 19 (Dec. 1973), 110.</p>
          <p>Kaplan, Fred. Miracles of Rare Device. Reviewed in Modern Language Review, 68 (Oct. 1973), 895;
Choice, 10 (June 1973), 619-20.</p>
          <p>Ketterer, David. New Worlds for Old. Reviewed by Mark Rose, Yale Review, 64 (Autumn 1974),
122-28; New York Book Review, 14 April 1974, p. 22; Dorothy Sternlicht, Library Journal, 98 (15 Dec. 1973),
3637; American Libraries, 5 (Jan. 1974), 29-30; Publishers’ Weekly, 204 (5 Nov. 1973), 58; Choice, 11
(July/Aug. 1974), 760.</p>
          <pb id="p08-156" n="156"/>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. Blake Studies, 2nd Ed. Reviewed by Morton D. Paley, Studies in Burke and His
Time, 15 (1973), 100-04; Desiree Hirst, Review of English Studies, 24 (Feb. 1973), 95-99; John B. Beer, Notes
&amp; Queries, 20 (1973), 305-07; Max F. Schulz, Eighteenth-Century Studies, 7 (Fall 1973), 120-23; T. R.
Henn, The Yearbook of English Studies, 3 (1973), 302-04.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. The Complete Writings of William Blake, with Variant Readings. Reviewed by
Robert N. Essick, Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 103-06. (Includes a collation of the Huntington Library
Thornton Marginalia with the Keynes and Erdman texts.)</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. William Blake’s Engravings. Reviewed in Choice, 10 (Nov. 1973), 1368;
Robert N. Essick, Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 109.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. William Blake’s Water-colours: Illustrating the Poems of Thomas Gray.
Reviewed by J. Canaday, New York Times Book Review, 3 (Dec. 1972), p. 90; Books &amp; Bookmen, 18 (March
1973), 96; Apollo, 98 (July 1973), 71; Irene H. Chayes, Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 155-64.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. The Life of William Blake, by Mona Wilson. Reviewed by Max F. Schulz,
Eighteenth-Century Studies, 7 (Fall 1973), 120-23; John B. Beer, Notes &amp; Queries, 20 (1973), 305-07.</p>
          <p>Kremen, Kathryn R. The Imagination of the Resurrection: The Poetic Continuity of a Religious
Motif in Donne, Blake, and Yeats. Reviewed by Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., Blake Newsletter, 6 (1973),
97-99; Florence Sandler, Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 96-98; Choice, 10 (May 1973), 440.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. British Romantic Art. Reviewed by Raymond Mortimer, The Sunday Times, 18 March
1973, p. 31; Timothy Bainbridge, “Romantic Artists,” Spectator, 230 (24 March 1973), 367; Apollo, 98 (July
1973), 65; Books &amp; Bookmen 18 (July 1973), 120; Connoisseur, 183 (July 1973), 228; Robert N. Essick, Blake
Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 108.</p>
          <p>Mayoux, Jean-Jacques. La Peinture Anglaise de Hogarth aux Preraphaelites. Reviewed by Robert N.
Essick, Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 107.</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne Kostelanetz. Blake’s Human Form Divine. Reviewed by Dewey R. Faulkner, “Secrets of
Dark Contemplation.” Yale Review, 63 (Summer 1974), 590-99; Stuart Curran, Studies in English Literature
1500-1900, 14 (Autumn 1974), 641-42; David Kwinn, Library Journal, 98 (1 Dec. 1973), 3562; Choice, 11
(July/Aug. 1974), 762.</p>
          <p>Morris, David B. The Religious Sublime: Christian Poetry and Critical Tradition in
Eighteenth-Century England. Reviewed by Martin Price, Modern Language Quarterly, 35 (March 1974), 85-87; Roger
Lonsdale, Review of English Studies, 25 (Feb. 1974), 94-95; South Atlantic Quarterly, 72 (Fall 1973), 616;
Philological Quarterly, 52 (July 1973), 444; Booklist, 69 (1 Jan. 1973), 423-24; Choice, 10 (May 1973),
459.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D., and Michael Phillips, eds. William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey
Keynes. Reviewed in British Book News, (Nov. 1973), p. 763; “The Processes of William Blake,” Times Literary
Supplement, 15 Feb. 1974, pp. 145-47; David Wagenknecht, Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 164-69;
Richard Harter Fogle, “Romanticism Reconsidered,” Sewanee Review, 82 (April-June 1974), 383-92; Dewey R.
Faulkner, “Secrets of Dark Contemplation,” Yale Review, 63 (Summer 1974), 590; Virginia Quarterly Review, 50
(Summer 1974), lxxiv-lxxvi; Stuart Curran, Studies in English Literature 1500-1900, 14 (Autumn 1974), 642;
John E. Grant, Blake Studies, 7 (Fall 1974), 85-96; Kenneth Hopkins, Eastern Daily Press, 7 (Sept. 1973);
Frederick Laws, The Daily Telegraph, 13 (Sept. 1973), p. 8; Choice, 10 (Feb. 1974), 1871; Library Journal, 98
(15 Dec. 1973), 3638.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of Blake’s Thought.
Reviewed by Jerome J. McGann, Modern Philology, 69 (Feb. 1972), 261-66; John Adlard, English Studies, 54
(1973), 74-75; John B. Beer, Notes &amp; Queries, 20 (1973), 75-76; Max F. Schulz, Eighteenth-Century Studies,
7 (Fall 1973), 120-23; G. S. Rousseau, Archiv, 210 (Dec. 1973), 407-09.</p>
          <p>Pointon, Marcia R. Milton and English Art. Reviewed by G. Bullough. English, (Autumn 1970), p.
101; A. Rudrum, West Coast Review, (June 1971), p. 56; J. Blondel, Etudes Anglaises, (Oct.-Dec. 1971), p. 530;
Gerald E. Bentley, Jr., The Library, (Dec. 1971), p. 356; Roland Mushat Frye, English Language Notes, 9 (March
1972), 205-06.</p>
          <p>Powell, Nicolas. Fuseli: The Nightmare. Reviewed in Apollo, 97 (June 1973), 619; Rackstraw
Downes, New York Times Book Review, 2 Dec. 1973, p. 93; The Nation, 217 (24 Dec. 1973), 696; Booklist, 69 (15
June 1973), 974.</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen. William Blake. Reviewed by John E. Grant, Philological Quarterly, 50 (July
1971), 409; American Artist, 35 Dec. 1971, 68; Times Literary Supplement, 10 Dec. 1971, p. 1537; Books &amp;
Bookmen, 16 (Fall 1971), 32; Library Journal, 96 (1 April 1971), 1270; Choice, 8 (Nov. 1971), 1166.</p>
          <p>Roberts, Mark. The Tradition of Romantic Morality. Reviewed in The Economist, 246 (3 March 1973),
92-93; Martin Green, “Working at Morality,” Guardian Weekly, 108 (31 March, 1973), 20; Library Journal, 98 (1
June 1973), 1821; Encounter, 41 (July 1973), 61; Choice, 10 (Sept. 1973), 968.</p>
          <p>Sabri-Tabrizi, G. R. The ‘Heaven’ and ‘Hell’ of William Blake. Reviewed by Raymond
Williams, “Radical Blake,” Guardian, 29 (Nov. 1973); Book Newsletter, 9 (Oct.-Dec. 1973), n.p.; Library
Journal, 99 (1 Feb. 1974), 364; “The Processes of William Blake,” Times Literary Supplement, 15 Feb. 1974, p.
145-47; David V. Erdman, English Language Notes, 12 (Sept. 1974, Supplement No. 1), 36-37.</p>
          <p>Singer, June D. The Unholy Bible. Reviewed by Margaret Shaefer, Blake Newsletter 6 (1973),
100-04.</p>
          <p>Smith, Eric. Some Versions of the Fall. Reviewed by Charles E. Lloyd, “The Myth of the Fall,”
Sewanee Review, 83 (Winter 1975), xxii-xxiv.</p>
          <p>Stevenson, W. H., ed. The Poems of William Blake. Reviewed by John B. Beer, Notes &amp; Queries,
20 (1973), 305-07.</p>
          <pb id="p08-157" n="157"/>
          <p>Tayler, Irene. Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Gray. Reviewed by Anthony Blunt,
“Blakomania,” Yale Review, 61 (Winter 1972), 301-06; Wallace Jackson, South Atlantic Quarterly, 71 (Winter
1972), 131-32; James Rieger, Philological Quarterly, 51 (1972), 646-47; Gilbert Thomas, English, 21 (1972),
114; Brian Wilkie, Journal of English and Germanic Philology, 71 (Jan. 1972), 142-46; Desiree Hirst, Review of
English Studies, 24 (Feb. 1973), 95-99; Luther S. Luedtke, Eighteenth-Century Studies, 6 (Spring 1973),
389-94; Alan Watson, Art Bulletin, 55 (1973), 465-66; William Vaughan, “The Third Blake,” Studio
International, 182 (Nov. 1971), 210-12; Irene H. Chayes, Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 155-64;
Gerald E. Bentley, Jr., Apollo, 99 (June 1974), 481-82.</p>
          <p>Thorburn, David, and Geoffrey Hartman, eds. Romanticism: Vistas, Instances, Continuities.
Reviewed by Jonathan Culler, “Text, Theme, and Theory,” Yale Review, 63 (Spring 1974), 439-47; Richard Harter
Fogle, “Romanticism Reconsidered,” Sewanee Review, 82 (April-June 1974), 383-92; Library Journal, 98 (15 Oct.
1973), 3004; Choice, 11 (April 1974), 253.</p>
          <p>Todd, Ruthven. William Blake the Artist. Reviewed by William Vaughan, “The Third Blake,” Studio
International, 182 (Nov. 1971), 210-12; Burlington Magazine, 116 (April 1974), 233; Gerald E. Bentley, Jr.,
Apollo, 99 (June 1974), 481-82; K. Bazarov, Arts and Artists, 7 (May 1972), 56.</p>
          <p>Tomory, Peter. The Life and Art of Henry Fuseli. Reviewed in American Artist, 37 (July 1973), 15;
Apollo, 97 (June 1973), 619; Books &amp; Bookmen, 18 (March 1973), 24; New York Times Book Review, 3 Dec.
1972, p. 90; Laurence Alloway, Nation, 215 (11 Dec. 1972), 599; Burlington Magazine, 116 (June 1974), 335;
Robert S. Fraser, Library Journal 98 (1 March 1973), 730; Choice, 10 (July-Aug. 1973), 762.</p>
          <p>Vogler, Thomas A. Preludes to Vision: The Epic Venture in Blake, Wordsworth, Keats, and Hart
Crane. Reviewed by Brian Wilkie, Journal of English and Germanic Philology, 71 (April 1972), 255-60.</p>
          <p>Wagenknecht, David. Blake’s Night: William Blake and the Idea of Pastoral. Reviewed in “The
Processes of William Blake,” Times Literary Supplement, 15 Feb. 1974, pp. 145-47; Thomas Wieskel, Studies in
Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 172-77; Virginia Quarterly Review, 50 (Summer 1974), lxxvi; Dewey R. Faulkner,
“Secrets of Dark Contemplation,” Yale Review, 63 (Summer 1974), 590-99; Irene H. Chayes, English Language
Notes, 12 (Sept. 1974, Supplement No. 1), 37-38; Library Journal, 98 (15 Oct. 1973), 3005; Choice, 10 (Jan.
1974), 1723.</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet, John Sutherland, and Robert Wallace, producers and directors. Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America.</hi> (York Univ. 1970 Videotape.) Reviewed by Morris Eaves, Blake Newsletter, 7 (Summer
1973), 20-23.</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet, John Sutherland, and Robert Wallace, producers and directors. Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> (York Univ. 1971 Videotape.) Reviewed by Morris Eaves, Blake
Newsletter, 7 (Summer 1973), 20-23.</p>
          <p>White, G. A., and C. Newman, eds. Literature in Revolution. Reviewed by David V. Erdman, English
Language Notes, 12 (Sept. 1974, Supplement No. 1), 38.</p>
          <p>Whitworth Art Gallery. British Watercolours from the John Edward Taylor Collection in the
Whitworth Art Gallery. Foreword by C. R. Dodwell. Intro. by Francis W. Hawcroft, Reviewed by Robert N. Essick,
Blake Studies, 6 (Fall 1973), 108-09.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr., ed. Calm of Mind: Tercentenary Essays on <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regain’d</hi> and <hi rend="i">Samson Agonistes.</hi> Reviewed by D. T. Mace, Review of English Studies, 24
(May 1973), 210-13.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr., ed. The Romantics on Milton. Reviewed by Kenneth Muir, Notes
&amp; Queries, 20 (Feb. 1973), 77-78.</p>
          <p>Wright, Andrew. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>: A Commentary. Reviewed in “Disorientations,”
Times Literary Supplement, 29 Sept. 1972, p. 1145; Suzanne R. Hoover, Blake Newsletter, 6 (1973), 75-79;
Morris Eaves, Eighteenth-Century Studies, 7 (1973), 226-33; Brian Wilkie, Journal of English and Germanic
Philology, 72 (July 1973), 452-54; Philological Quarterly, 52 (July 1973), 467; Stuart Curran, Modern
Philology, 71 (May 1974), 450-52; Irene H. Chayes, Studies in Romanticism, 13 (Spring 1974), 155-64; David V.
Erdman, English Language Notes, 12 (Sept. 1974, Supplement No. 1), 38-39; Choice, 10 (March 1973), 77.</p>
          <p>Wright, Thomas. The Life of William Blake. Reviewed by Lawrence S. Thompson, “Wright’s Blake,”
American Book Collector 23 (May-June 1973), 11-12; Max F. Schulz, Eighteenth-Century Studies, 7 (Fall 1973),
120-23; Bibliographic Society of America—Papers, 67 (July 1973), 368; Choice, 10 (June 1973), 626.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Films, Videotapes, Etc.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Clark, Kenneth. “William Blake.” Romantic Rebellion (TV series). 45 mins.</p>
          <p>The English School of Painting. Prod. by Educational Productions, East Ardley, Wakefield,
Yorkshire. Distr. by Prothmann Associates, Inc., Baldwin, N. Y. 1966. Filmstrip, b&amp;w, 30 frames. LC No.
76-734235.</p>
          <p>English Water Colors. Prod. and Distr. by Herbert E. Budek, Santa Barbara, Calif. Filmstrip,
color, 18 frames. n.d.</p>
          <p>An Essay on William Blake. Narrated by Jacob Bronowski. Produced by National Educational
Television and the British Broadcasting Corp. Distr. by Indiana Univ., Audio-Visual Center. 1970. Film, color,
52 mins. $550.00 Order No. KSC-357. (Note: same as <hi rend="i">As a Man Is—So He Sees.</hi>)</p>
          <p>The History of Western Art. No. 12: French Revolution to 1900. London: Visual Publications.
Released in the U. S. by Prothmann Associates, Baldwin, Long Island, N. Y., 1963.</p>
          <p>Images of Man, by Robert Starer. New York: CBS, Dec. 1974. (Symphony based on lines from 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>; videotape of Washington, D. C., performance available to educ. institutions
<pb id="p08-158" n="158"/>
through Religious Dept., CBS News, 524 West 57th St., New York, N. Y. 10019.)</p>
          <p>On Reflection: Adrian Mitchell on William Blake. British <corr type="emend">Broadcasting</corr>
Corp., London Weekend. Available in U. S. through Mrs. Robin Breed, Richard Price TV Associates, New York;
rental $50. Film, color, 27 mins.</p>
          <p>Painting in Georgian England. National Gallery of Art. Illus. from the Paul Mellon Collection. 60
slides and phonodisc, 50 mins. Write: National Gallery of Art, Extension Service, Washington, D. C.</p>
          <p>Poetry and Pictures. Part No. 2: “William Blake.” Bayside, N. Y.: AIDS: Audio-visual
Instructional Devices, 1971. Filmstrip, with phonodisc or phonotape in cassette, 42 mins.; color.</p>
          <p>William Blake. London: Visual Publications, 1964. Released in the U. S. by McIntyre Visual
Publications, Champlain, N. Y., 1970. Filmstrip.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Music, Records, Tapes</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Avshalomov, Jacob. Proverbs of Hell, for men’s chorus, a cappella. New York: Duchess Music
Corp., 1970. MCA Music, distr.</p>
          <p>Blake. Read by Alan Bates and others. Argo RG428, 1964. Phonodisc.</p>
          <p>Five Songs of Experience. John Harbison, conductor. The Cantata Singers and Ensemble. CRI SD313.
$5.98. (1974?)</p>
          <p>The Marriage of Heaven and Hell. Los Angeles/San Francisco: KPFK/KPFA, 1974.</p>
          <p>The Poems of William Blake. New Rochelle, N. Y.: Spoken Arts, 1961. Phonodisc.</p>
          <p>The Poetry of Blake. Caedmon TC 1101, 1958. Phonodisc.</p>
          <p>The Poetry of William Blake. Read by Wendy Hiller, Peter Jeffrey, David King, and Peter Orr. New
Rochelle, N. Y.: Spoken Arts, 1971. Phonodisc, 43 mins., with jacket notes. $6.50. Order No. 1061.</p>
          <p>Starer, Robert. Images of Man. New York: MCA Music, 1975. (Symphonic score based on lines from
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Starer, Robert. Never Seek to Tell thy Love, for male chorus, a cappella. 1958. On deposit
Library of Congress, 1970.</p>
          <p>William Blake. (Portraits for Today, Series II.) Bloomington, Ind.: Indiana Univ., Audio-Visual
Center, 1961. Audio-tape, 15 mins.</p>
          <figure n="Horse.8.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="200" height="273">
	<figTranscr/>
</figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
