<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>8.4.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Bo Lindberg, William Blake’s Illustrations of the Book of Job</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">08.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Ron Taylor</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Judith Wallick Page</name>
              <name>Donna Rix</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Sharon Stell</name>
              <resp>Editorial assistant for subscriptions</resp>
              <name>Deborah Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_08">
    <body>
	<pb id="p08-125" n="125"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-08-4-0003">
          <head>
            <title type="main">Bo Lindberg. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of
Job.</hi> Ph.D. thesis, published in 1973 in the <hi rend="i">Acta Academiae Aboensis.</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor><ref
target="n18">*</ref></byline>
          <p>Blake’s engraved illustrations to Job (1826) are probably his best known series of designs, and
there have been many books dealing wholly or significantly with Job, notably by Norton (1875), Binyon (1905),
Wickstead (1910, 1924), Russell (1912), Damon (1924, 1966), Binyon &amp; Keynes (1935), Hofer (1937), Hamblen
(?1939), Patchen (1947), Lande (1948), and Wright (1972).
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="i">G.E. Bentley, Jr. (University of Toronto) is editor of</hi> Vala 
<hi rend="i">(1963)</hi>, Tiriel <hi rend="i">(1967), and</hi> The Writings of William Blake <hi rend="i">(in the
press); and author of</hi> Blake Records <hi rend="i">(1969)</hi>, The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K.
Thorne <hi rend="i">(1971), and, with M.K. Nurmi, of</hi> A Blake Bibliography <hi rend="i">(1964) (a revised
edition by GEB is in the Clarendon Press).</hi></note> The subject, therefore, is not novel, and to undertake
a doctoral study of it at this date is an act of formidable temerity, an act which Mr. Lindberg has
triumphantly justified.</p>
          <p>The most important part of the dissertation is the catalogue (pp. 183-352), which includes not
only the conventional descriptions, provenances, size, collection, etc., but also elaborate and extremely
persuasive studies of the sources and meaning of each drawing or print. This catalogue raisonné of Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> designs will for very long remain the standard work on the subject.</p>
          <p>Chapter I, on the chronology of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> designs, is useful but somewhat
abstract and tabular in form, with summaries of relevant documents. I think it might most usefully appear as
an appendix.</p>
          <p>Chapter II, with the Introduction and Synopsis of Job, serves its purpose very well, but I think
it should be the first chapter.</p>
          <p>Chapter III, about Blake’s drawing, painting, and engraving techniques, and his use of 
<hi rend="i">The Testament of Job</hi>, is novel and extremely useful. In particular, the account of Blake’s use
of the visual tradition of Job illustration is highly original, persuasive, and important.</p>
          <p>Chapter IV, “Blake’s Visions and the <hi rend="i">Job</hi>,” is very brief (pp. 151-66) and,
dealing as it does with Blake as a mystic, is interesting and plausible but not, I think, especially relevant
to this work. Perhaps it belongs in an appendix.</p>
          <p>Chapter V, on technique again, is original and penetrating, but the matter seems to overlap with
that in Chapter III and might well have been included there. 
                    </p>
          <pb id="p08-126" n="126"/>
          <p>In terms of originality, the book is important primarily in six ways: (1) Mr. Lindberg looks at
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> with the eyes of an artist and an art historian, not as a literary critic (the
mode adopted by almost all his predecessors)—I believe it may be said that Mr. Lindberg is the first to see
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> truly and see it whole; (2) The treatment is very systematic, and, with such a
very large bulk of material, and an artist as unconventional and irregular as Blake, this is of the first
importance, though Mr. Lindberg’s predecessors have rarely been able to see, or cope with, its importance;
(3) The dating of the Butts watercolors in 1810 and the well-founded dismissal of the New Zealand set from the
Blake canon are original and important; (4) The dating of the first separate Job sketches and engravings in
1793 is very welcome; (5) The elaborate study of sources, and the conclusion that Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> is entirely traditional, are important and reliable; and (6) The analysis of Blake’s
designs of “The Spiritual Form of Pitt,” of “Nelson,” and of “Napoleon” (with a visual recreation of the last,
lost, drawing), which contradicts, I believe, every previous discussion of these works, seems persuasive to
me, and will prove the nucleus for future discussions of these important Blake works. The book is thus much
more than a study of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> series of engravings of 1825; it is a systematic analysis of
allusions to the Biblical Job in all Blake’s writings and drawings. In future, scholars concerned with any
aspect of Blake’s treatment of Job, indeed scholars dealing with iconography of Job after 1700, should
consult, understand, depend upon, and be grateful to, <corr type="emend">Mr. Lindberg’s</corr> study of <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Illustrations to the Book of Job.</hi></p>
          <p>The book would have been significantly improved by the addition of a few small details. It needs
a Table of Abbreviations, for a number of the abbreviations are distinctly unfamiliar to literary scholars.
The sources of the photographs should be given, and the locations of the originals reproduced (e.g., 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>) should regularly be identified. The captions to the illustrations should have
cross-references to the text. It would be useful to have, in one place, a survey of Blake scholarship
concerning <hi rend="i">Job.</hi></p>
          <p>The difficulties of printing a book with a printer whose language is not that of the text are
notorious, and in general Mr. Lindberg has overcome them heroically. It yet needed to be proofread thoroughly
and effectively once more. For a book of the distinction of this one, there are considerably too many defects
of a mechanical kind, particularly of spelling, punctuation and diction, but also of capitalization, and
agreement of subject and verb. (Per contra, I should remark that the English is often remarkably eloquent and
effective, not mere run-of-the-mill scholarly writing.) The bibliography (pp. 353-62) and the bibliographical
details elsewhere are often surprisingly irregular. There is no such book as “Keynes, <hi rend="i">George
Cumberland</hi>, 1970” (pp. 44, 357), for example, and John Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Lectures</hi> were not
published in “1792” (pp. 290, 311). There are as well a few minor omissions, such as Robert Essick’s Finding
List of Blake’s designs in the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, Janet Warner’s essays on Blake’s
pathos-formulae published recently, and the 1971 edition of Keynes’s <hi rend="i">Blake Studies.</hi> The
facts given are on the whole remarkably reliable, but a few are suspect, for example, that Westall “knew Blake
personally” (p. 327) or that proofs of Job are in the “National Gallery of Art, Washington” (p. 30)—they are
in the National Gallery, but the location is Jenkintown, Pennsylvania. Often it is not easy to ascertain with
confidence whether Mr. Lindberg has seen the original of the design he is describing or only a photograph, and
occasionally he confidently describes what can only be an inference—for example that a bag in a girl’s
hand contains jewels (p. 334); this last is the kind of fault for which Mr. Lindberg justly and acerbically
criticizes his predecessors and which is very rare here.</p>
          <p>Beside these petty faults, the merits of the book are major and extensive. It is methodical and
comprehensive, meticulously accurate, and consistently persuasive. Mr. Lindberg describes the 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> with the eyes of an artist and of an art historian, in sharp and vital contrast to most of
his predecessors. The study of the sources of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, particularly of 
<hi rend="i">The Testament of Job</hi>, is excellent and of very great importance; indeed, I think it is safe to
say that most of these sources have not been related to Blake’s work before and that it is impossible to
understand Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> adequately without them. The interpretation of each design is
elaborate and in almost every case convincing; the dating of a number of the earlier drawings is new and
well-argued; and the analyses of “Pitt” and “Nelson” are both highly original and highly commonsensical.</p>
          <p>In summary, I conclude that Mr. Bo Lindberg’s dissertation on <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi> is the best dissertation I have ever examined, one of the two or three
best I have ever read, and one of the half dozen most important books on Blake’s art. Every responsible
Blake scholar must read it. It is a work of the highest distinction. We are all indebted to Mr. Bo
Lindberg.</p>
          <figure n="Pouring.8.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="192"/>
       </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
