<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.evans</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake, Locke, and the Concept of “Generation”</title>
        <author n="Evans">James C. Evans</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0004">
      	<pb id="p09-47" n="47"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake, Locke, &amp; The Concept of “Generation”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>James C. <name>Evans</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The concept of “generation” as a level of existence in Blake’s poetry has been related to its
use both in the Neoplatonists and in Swedenborg. In both instances, the term generally implies a world of
generative being in a material sphere as opposed to a world of continuous being in a spiritual one.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">1</ref> There is, however, another possible source as
undeniably central in Blake’s reactions to his philosophical milieu as any, John Locke’s 
<hi rend="i">Essay on Human Understanding</hi>, and about which Blake stated he felt “the same Contempt and
Abhorrence” from first reading it “when very Young” onwards.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See, for example, George Mills Harper, <hi rend="i">The Neoplatonism of
William Blake</hi> (Chapel Hill: Univ. of North Carolina Press, 1961), p. 154; Kathleen Raine, 
<hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, (London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1968), I, 100-05.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">2</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes
(London: Oxford University Press, 1966), pp. 476-77.</note></p>
          <p>The particularly relevant passage in the <hi rend="i">Essay</hi> occurs amidst Locke’s
speculations about the perception of cause-effect relationships. Having defined a cause as that which operates
to produce an idea or collection of ideas, he proceeds to divide effects into two categories. The first is
“creation,” an effect “wholly made new, so that no part thereof did ever exist before.” The second category,
however, is extremely interesting in the light it throws on Blake’s choice of terms for a world barely
human.</p>
		<q>
When a thing is made up of particles which did all of them before exist, but that very thing, so constituted
of pre-existing particles which, considered all together, make up such a collection of simple ideas, had not
any existence before as this man, this egg, rose, or cherry, etc. And this, when referred to a substance
produced in the ordinary course of nature by an internal
<pb id="p09-48" n="48"/>
principle, but set on work by and received from some external agent or cause, and working by insensible ways
which we perceive not, we call “generation”. . . . Thus, a man is generated. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">3</hi> John Locke, <hi rend="i">An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi>,
14th ed., (London: S. Birt et al., 1753), I, 27.</note></q>
          <p>Both the language and the concepts in this passage would indeed have been totally abhorrent to
Blake, for Locke presents the generative principle in man as consisting of an “agent” working “insensibly” and
uncomprehendingly on another “internal principle” and resulting in a unique configuration of “pre-existing
particles.” There is no better description of the Blakean state of generation than this sterile meeting of two
forces seemingly without communication, without emotion and even without a conscious purpose, but merely
following the “ordinary course of nature.” It is, in fact, man’s existence reduced to its absolute natural
limits in which he is seen as a combination of “simple ideas,” to use a Lockean term. Now, we know that Locke
intended the passage as a neutral, objective description of simple cause and effect: sexual desire results in
coitus which produces a human being made up of the atoms of the mother and father. But when Blake read it, it
surely seemed to him to epitomize everything that is the exact opposite of man’s unified Edenic existence in
pure imaginative perception. He found a ready-made image with a ready-made title to describe “the Barren waste
of Locke and Newton,” the “philosophy of five senses” into which the eighteenth century was securely “Locked”
(Blake himself makes this pun in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>). So, the two words, Locke and
generation, become closely associated in Blake’s poetry, and both appear in conjunction with the image of
looms, a mechanical form of creation which produces the veil of nature that must be rent at the apocalyptic
moment. Locke, whose way of perceiving the world continually creates and sustains such generation, becomes
synonymous with that state. In using the term generation, Blake gathers up the Lockean methodology in its own
epitome, imbues it with his own symbolic meaning and turns it with the deftness of irony against its own
source.</p>
          <p>Nor is this the only instance of Blake ironically borrowing from Locke to illustrate the primary
Lockean error. Quite obviously, the lines from “Auguries of Innocence,” “We are led to Believe a Lie / When we
see not Thro’ the Eye,” are at the heart of Blake’s rebellion against the whole physical basis of
eighteenth century science and philosophy. But a point generally missed is that Blake is ironically countering
Locke’s statement of faith in reason by quoting a phrase from that statement. Toward the end of his 
<hi rend="i">Essay</hi>, Locke enumerates various kinds of errors that have crept into philosophy and rounds the
discussion off by prescribing the only guard against such error.
<q>
Light, true light in the mind, is or can be nothing else but the evidence of the truth of any proposition; and
if it be not a self-evident proposition, all the light it has, or can have, is from the clearness and validity
of those proofs upon which it is received. To talk of any other light in the understanding, is to put
ourselves in the dark, or in the power of the prince of darkness, and, by our own consent, to give ourselves
up to delusion, to believe a lie.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Locke, <hi rend="i">Essay</hi>, II, 323. In this passage, Locke goes on to
remark of divine revelation, “When he [God] illuminates the Mind with supernatural Light, he does not
extinguish that which is natural. . . . Reason must be our last Judge and Guide in every Thing. . . . Consult
it we must and by it examine whether it be a Revelation from God or no . . . ” (pp. 323-24). Surely Blake
would have thought this the most pernicious of all lies.</note></q>
Not only does Blake use the phrase “to believe a lie” in correcting Locke’s premise that all we really know
is sense data, but he follows this with Locke’s own dark-light imagery: “God appears &amp; God is Light / To
Those poor Souls who dwell in Night, / But does a Human Form Display / To those who dwell in Realms of day”
(11. 129-32). As with “generation,” the trouble lies in Locke’s perspective. In saying that we must use
reason to determine “whether [a revelation] be from God or no,” Locke is placing a non-existent barrier
between human and divine and binding himself to a severely limited view of the world. He fails to realize that
“God is man &amp; exists in us &amp; we in Him.” Again, Locke’s definition of generation both epitomizes
such a narrow, physical, totally rational concept of man and perfectly describes the mental state of those who
dwell in so circumscribed a world. This is the dual role which made Locke’s work so inviting a quarry from
which Blake could build his image of the fallen world.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
