<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.reiman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="poem">A Significant New Blakean Fragment</title>
        <author n="Reiman">Donald H. Reiman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0004">
      <pb id="p09-44" n="44"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Significant New Blakean Fragment</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Donald H. <name>Reiman</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Though Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
are familiar to all students above the age at which they first visit the zoo, his fragmentary 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Education</hi>—not yet found in the collected editions of Blake’s works—are less well
known. I have known respected Blake scholars, in fact, who were appallingly ignorant of this seminal work.</p>
          <p>Originally intended for a volume in William and Mary Jane Godwin’s Juvenile Library, 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Education</hi> was left unfinished when Blake became afflicted by extreme gastric
indigestion while reading at the British Museum. His only comment on the work occurs in Barron Field’s
report of the conversation between Blake and Leigh Hunt at Horsemonger Lane Gaol. When asked by either Hunt or
Thomas Massa Alsager (Field is uncertain which) what place <hi rend="i">Songs of Education</hi> would have
occupied in his <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi>, Blake replied: “I cannot tell how the whole might have developed;
certain I am, however, that Education, while not consonant with Experience, destroys Innocence.”</p>
          <p>Heretofore scholars have been handicapped by having available only brief, disconnected fragments
of <hi rend="i">Songs of Education</hi>—couplets and quatrains that Blake composed on the letter-covers of
Godwin’s appeals for money. Recently, however, there has come into my possession an extended passage from
the work that incorporates some of the earlier fragments and suggests the tone and purpose, if not the full
scope and shape, of the projected volume. While browsing in a bookshop near Exit 10 of the New York State
Thruway, I was fortunate enough to discover (and purchase for thirty-five cents) a copy of Swedenborg’s 
<hi rend="i">Proverbs of Pisgah</hi>, the excessively rare London edition of 1801 printed by W. E. Inkell for the
New Church. Imagine my joy when I discovered that its title page bore the inscription, in a clearly
identifiable hand, “W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Blake/ Poet and Painter/ 1807” and that between the
otherwise-unrecorded half-title and the title page was a leaf—artistically sewn in with pastel
thread—containing the following lines from Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Education:</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">1</ref>
</p>
<q>
Then woke the spirit of bald William Blake—<lb/>
Word-lover, foe of orthodoxies’ kind;<lb/>
He swept across two school-infested lands<lb/>
To chastise all self-satisfied of mind.<lb/>
<lb/>
Not one to FOSTER DAMONs for a fee,<lb/>
With rusty KROE BER thumping their stout KEYNES<lb/>
He drove them to the SHOR; ERe they could flee,<lb/>
A voice boomed out, inflicting deeper pains:<lb/>
</q>
<pb id="p09-45" n="45"/>
<q>
“I GRANT that publishers who mind the PURSE<lb/>
SEE VALue<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p45u1" type="note">*</ref> in the books these scholars write.<lb/>
<hi rend="i">I’d</hi> rather hear a HAG STRUM on a HARP<lb/>
ER watch RAINE beating down yon blasted BLOOM<lb/>
Than, with back BENT, LEYn reading through the night,<lb/>
Conning their jargon by the PALEY light.<lb/>
<lb/>
“ADAM’S a GARDNER who has lost his place<lb/>
Through sad neGLECK, NER do I find it odd<lb/>
That when aN URMI of the pedants’ race<lb/>
ROSE up, our father left that sacred sod.<lb/>
<lb/>
“He could not TAYLER to their sketches Gray<lb/>
Eden’s bright scenes, and so he fled away.<lb/>
From that day on, the CUR RAN wild, small FRYE<lb/>
Anatomized each WITT REICH merrily.”<lb/>
<lb/>
The prophetic thunder ceased. Another spoke:<lb/>
“I tells yer, gov’ner, this, an’ no mistake—<lb/>
That last loud chap ain’t none of Billy Blake.<lb/>
‘Aven’t yer ‘ERD, MAN? ‘e’s a Cockney bloke.’”
</q>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I have edited the fragment heuristically according to the following
principles: (1) all substantive features of the text have been transcribed literally; (2) all accidental
features have been emended to conform to my notion of what constitutes communicative English.</note>
	<note id="p45u1">* Another MS reads “PERCIVALue”</note>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
