<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.wagenknecht</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Brian John, Supreme Fictions</title>
        <author n="Wagenknecht">David Wagenknecht</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0005">
      <pb id="p09-55" n="55"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Brian John. <hi rend="i">Supreme Fictions: Studies in the Work of William
Blake, Thomas Carlyle, W. B. Yeats, and D. H. Lawrence.</hi> Montreal &amp; London: McGill-Queen’s
University Press, 1974. Pp. 318. $13.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>David <name>Wagenknecht</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Taken one observation at a time, Brian John’s <hi rend="i">Supreme Fictions</hi> is intelligent
and right-minded, but it is one of those studies of which the modesty and sanity are undone by scope. Such a
range demands that one simultaneously manage general perspective as well as interpretive detail; this book,
decent as it is, seemed to me neither out far nor in deep. The intention, for one thing, is rather uneasily
divided between historical and critical implication: the reader must suspend himself between (on the one hand)
landscapes of likemindedness so misty and general that the only distinct observations can be exceptions, and
(on the other) specific interpretive patches which illustrate the author’s admiration for his subjects more
than these subjects’ relationship to the larger view. Given the quality of the author’s intelligence and
the genuineness of his affections, this is a pity.</p>
          <p>On the one hand John wants to argue for a Romantic “vitalist” tradition (stressing characteristic
imagery more than his subjects’ rhetorical relationship to historically conditioned audiences), but he is
not very curious about Romanticism as an historical phenomenon, and neither the provenance nor the
transference of the ideas and imagery he is concerned with interests him. Consequently the reader feels
himself to be dealing less with a tradition than with four quite distinct expositions of similar ideas, and
his first impression that the argument will have vast scope is replaced by a feeling of arbitrariness. Not
only are we not told sufficiently why author X belongs (in the tradition designated), why not author Y: we are
left finally with no very developed sense of the ways in which John’s chosen (and unruly) four might be
related—they simply often sound alike, which is not enough point to unify the discussion. Indeed, the idea
of tradition is most active in the study by negative implication, for John is often anxious because ideas
which are “good” in one context (usually Blake, but often Lawrence as well) are undesirable in another
(Carlyle, sometimes Yeats). The word “fascist” recurs often enough to make one uncomfortable, but it is
exactly the book’s undeveloped sense of history which makes the anxiety unresolvable.</p>
          <p>The book’s potential for an interpretive dimension is reflected in the title, determined by an
interest in Romantic projection, but this too is swallowed up by mere expostion of ideas. There is no shortage
of specific commentary in the book, but the relentlessly expository method stands far enough outside the texts
that no sense of the competition between imagination and reality convincing enough to support the title
emerges. The Carlyle chapter is probably the least convincing in this regard—the concluding third of it
rather desperately announces a critical dimension, arguing that the sage was a literary fictionist as much as
prophetic factualist (the demonstration bogs down in impressionistic appreciations of style)—but the Blake
chapter may be taken as more characteristic. As a whole the chapter is a worthy general introduction to
Blake’s poetry (though very thin on the epics), but John decides to concentrate on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
for reasons which have little to do with his general argument (it is the “shortest” as well as the “most
‘finished’” epic, we are told), and the commentary manages to avoid nearly all the troubling minute
particulars of the poem. Even on the level of general commentary it tells us nothing new. There is an
attractive enthusiasm to the discussion, but—like the book as a whole—it implicitly begs more questions
than it explicitly answers.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
