<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.ober</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Poor Robin” and Blake’s “The Blossom”</title>
        <author n="Ober">Warren U. Ober</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0004">
      <pb id="p09-42" n="42"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Poor Robin” &amp; Blake’s “The Blossom”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Warren U. <name>Ober</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In one of his notes on “The Cool World of Samuel Taylor Coleridge” (<hi rend="i">The Wordsworth
Circle</hi>, 5 [Winter 1974], 61) P. M. Zall quotes part of a bawdy ballad recollected by Francis Place, “the
radical tailor of Charing Cross”:
<q>
One night as I came from the play<lb/>
I met a fair maid by the way<lb/>
She had rosy cheeks and a dimpled chin<lb/>
And a hole to put poor Robin in.<lb/>
<lb/>
A bed and blanket have I got [“I have got” in Zall’s source]<lb/>
A dish a Kettle and a pot<lb/>
Besides a charming pretty thing<lb/>
A hole to put poor Robin in.
</q></p>
          <p>Though the context in which the ballad is quoted in part in Professor Zall’s source (Place, 
<hi rend="i">Autobiography</hi>, ed. Mary Thale [Cambridge: Univ. Press, 1972], p. 58n.) does not make clear the
precise date of the ballad, the evidence provided by the editor tends to confirm Zall’s suggestion: “about
1780.” Place, who was born in 1771, is quoted as saying that he listened to such songs at a social gathering
“when a boy of 10 years of age.” Certainly it is clear that the song was very popular, since Place says of it
and others (p. 58n.), “There is not one of them that I have not myself heard sung in the streets.”</p>
          <p>This popular song of the London streets is of especial interest in that it may shed some light on
a long-standing problem of interpretation involving Blake’s “The Blossom,” one of his <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi> (1789):
<q>
Merry Merry Sparrow<lb/>
Under leaves so green<lb/>
A happy Blossom<lb/>
Sees you swift as arrow<lb/>
Seek your cradle narrow<lb/>
Near my Bosom.<lb/>
<lb/>
Pretty Pretty Robin<lb/>
Under leaves so green<lb/>
A happy Blossom<lb/>
Hears you sobbing sobbing<lb/>
Pretty Pretty Robin<lb/>
Near my Bosom.
</q></p>
          <p>A popular reading of the poem is that of Joseph H. Wicksteed (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Innocence
and Experience</hi> [London: Dent, 1928], p. 126): “The birds are the male element as seen by the maiden. They
represent the whole range of the lover’s love, from the winged thought to the accomplished act.” Geoffrey
Keynes (<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [London: Hart-Davis, 1967], pl. 11 commentary)
supports Wicksteed’s interpretation: “The sparrow ‘swift as arrow’ is a phallic symbol seeking
satisfaction in the blossom of the maiden’s bosom. The robin sobs perhaps with the happiness of experience.”
Similarly, D. G. Gillham (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Contrary States</hi> [Cambridge: Univ. Press, 1966], pp.
164-65) sees the subject of the poem as being sexual intercourse. “The blossom, herself, despite her
tenderness,” Gillham says, “is rather disengaged, and tends to be aware of the male sexual organ almost as a
sort of pet.” E. D. Hirsch, Jr., however, comments on “The Blossom” (<hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience: An
Introduction to Blake</hi> [New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1964], p. 181) as follows: “This is the most
difficult poem in the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> The only full-dress explication I know of is by
Wicksteed, whose theory that the poem symbolizes love and sexual intercourse I cannot accept.” And W. H.
Stevenson rather stiffly says (<hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi>, ed. Stevenson [London: Longman,
1971], p. 64): “The extreme simplicity of this poem has puzzled interpreters, who have had to delve deep for
its symbolism. It is more than doubtful that B. would embody such symbolism so deeply in a book planned for
children. . . .”</p>
          <p>The suggestion that the ballad recalled by Francis Place is a part of the context within which
“The Blossom” was created, if not an actual source for it, should shock no one familiar with the scatology and
robust satire of <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, in the manuscript of which appear the “Nurse’s
Song,” “The Little Boy Lost,” and “Holy Thursday” of the later <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> The facts
that in the London street song recollected by Place the penis is called Robin and that Blake could reasonably
have been expected to know the song and
<pb id="p09-43" n="43"/>
to have assumed that his audience was aware of it are, I believe, evidence in support of Wicksteed’s reading
of “The Blossom.” Other less significant supporting details are the repetition of the word “pretty,” the
substitution of “blossom” for “rosy cheeks and dimpled chin,” and the fact that “poor” Robin becomes the
“sobbing” Robin of Blake’s poem. Finally, the OED records a use of the phrase “merry-bout” in the 
<hi rend="i">Newgate Calendar</hi> of 1780 as slang for “an act of sexual intercourse.” Hence the appropriateness
of Blake’s “merry, merry sparrow.”</p>
          <p>If this widely known street song was in fact in Blake’s mind when he composed “The Blossom” and
in the minds of Blake’s readers as well, perhaps the poem is more complex and ironic than Stevenson is
prepared to admit, even if it was destined to appear “in a book planned for children.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
