<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.zall</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Martin K. Nurmi, William Blake</title>
        <author n="Zall">Paul M. Zall</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0005">
      <pb id="p09-54" n="54"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Martin K. Nurmi. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> London: Hutchinson University
Library, 1975. Pp. 175, 8 illus. $1.95, paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Paul M. <name>Zall</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Those who have long since despaired of keeping a body count in Blake studies will be cheered by
the appearance of a Blake volume in Hutchinson’s series for students and general readers. The focal point is
Blake’s poetry, however, abstracted from his art (“it has not been possible to give much attention to his
art”), and for that reason alone will probably cause consternation among Blake camps of whatever critical
persuasion. But this is a book for beginners, and should be greeted accordingly, with all due allowance for
puns (“a Woman of Experience”) and topicality (“Blake was not a male chauvinist”).</p>
          <p>The overview in this respect is very good, with an introductory chapter enticing beginners with
visions of good things to come (“as we shall see later”) and a biographical summary that gives much Blake in
brief compass. Successive chapters then lead through the early verse—stressing the metrics in 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, then the philosophical countersystem in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
and Hell</hi>—gradually snaking through Blake’s more complicated mythic structures. While the seasoned
Blakean may scoff from the trenches at the redundancy inherent in this method, it seems to fit the needs of
new recruits.</p>
          <p>Of course the method risks the oversimplification of <hi rend="i">Cliff’s Notes</hi>, but there
is little of that here, except in a statement about <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> being “one of the very
greatest works of literature” (p. 26)—alas not demonstrated in the introductory chapter in which it appears
nor in the ultimate chapter where the poem is discussed in detail and the aid of both Erdman and Frye is
invoked. Or in the discussion of “The Tyger,” plateless, where after four pages of possibilities we are given
a series of questions asserted to be logically unanswerable—with no suggestion that logic is not the only
way to answer them. Or in the discussion of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, where the student and
<pb id="p09-55" n="55"/>
general reader meet Blakean irony without being sure about the difference between the satire of “Island in the
Moon” and the irony here or later—the name seems the same, but sometimes refers to techniques like parody,
now to theme, later to mode of perception, a multisensory device where the plate shows one thing and the poem
another, and finally to “mythic irony” (p. 100). But this is to quibble.</p>
          <p>Given the restrictions under which the labor was performed, its real strength appears in the
masterful explanation of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, where the action is made to appear truly dramatic and the
subject made clearly the mind of Man. Sometimes the explanation of other plots comes cluttered with roll calls
of commentators which seem superfluous since their names appear in the notes anyway. The real weakness,
however, is the lack of a clear-cut conclusion to match the introductory chapters. The student and general
reader are taken to Jerusalem and left suspended there—hanging by the thumbs as it were. Having been led
from <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> to this loftiest of heights, it would be nice to look back at the
trackless wastes behind us and ahead. The “Suggestions for Further Reading” seem sparse enough, the
“Criticism” list very heavy on collections of essays at the expense of individual studies. And the index tells
us something about the current state of Blake studies when it lists Franklin P. Adams (FPA) but not Hazard
S.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
