<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.metcalf</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Tiriel: Two Corrected First Readings</title>
        <author n="Metcalf">Francis Wood Metcalf</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0004">
      <pb id="p09-40" n="40"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Tiriel:</hi> Two Corrected First Readings</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Francis Wood <name>Metcalf</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The following corrections of the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> transcript will be incorporated in the
next revised printing of David Erdman’s Doubleday text.</p>
          <p>1. “To raise his dark &amp; burning visage thro the cleaving [world <hi rend="i">del</hi>]
ground.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s facsimile edition of <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>
(Oxford, 1967), line 247. All line references are to this edition.</note></p>
          <p>The deleted word is <hi rend="i">not</hi> “world,” but “earth.” The cause for the unanimous
misreading by editors is probably the <hi rend="i">d</hi>-like form of the last of the deleting loops.
However, this loop cannot be a <hi rend="i">d</hi> because it is preceded by two vertical strokes where 
<hi rend="i">rl</hi> would be in “world.” Nor can these strokes be considered <hi rend="i">ld</hi> in “world”:
ninety-two percent (336 of 363) of the serifs of word-ending <hi rend="i">d</hi> curve leftward in the poem as
a whole; all of them (34) do so in this section. Either there is a very rare occurrence here of a straight 
<hi rend="i">d</hi> serif, or the deleted word is not “world.”</p>
          <p>On the positive side, and bearing in mind the narrow range of synonyms for “ground,” the deleted
word looks more like “earth” than “world” under the deleting loops. Michael Tolley, who very generously agreed
to examine the manuscript in the British Museum, reports that the original’s initial letter looks like 
<hi rend="i">e</hi> but not <hi rend="i">w.</hi> In addition, the vertical strokes are similar to those of the 
<hi rend="i">th</hi> in “Earth” of the preceding line (246), and to those of the many other 
<hi rend="i">th</hi>’s in the surrounding text. Only the right-most portion of the crossing stroke of 
<hi rend="i">t</hi>, crossing <hi rend="i">h</hi> as well, is clear of the loops, and it is quite faint. But many
similar strokes are equally faint, and two nearby <hi rend="i">th</hi>’s have no crossing strokes at all:
“the” in 243 and “doth” in 244.</p>
          <p>The terminal hump of <hi rend="i">h</hi> is not visible, but if it were as short and flat as the
one in “earth” of 258, it would be obscured by the last deleting loop. Finally, from a semantic stand-point
the deleted word must be “earth.” “Earth” and “ground,” the replacement, are natural synonyms; “world” and
“ground” are not.</p>
          <p>2. The sequence of vicissitudes in 385-86 is recorded erroneously in Damon’s 
<hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>: “Such was Tiriel, [hypocrisy, the idiot’s wisdom &amp; the wise man’s folly, 
<hi rend="i">del</hi>] compell’d . . . ” (p. 406). Alone among editors, Bentley notes that “is” in 385 was
changed to “was,” but gives no evidence of understanding the full sequence of revision in these lines: that
when “is” became “was,” “Tiriel” was affixed to the line-end, and the next line was cancelled.</p>
          <p>Originally, 385 ended with “Such is,” the sense continuing in the next line: “Such is / Hypocrisy
the idiots wisdom &amp; the wise mans folly.” Since 386 ends the page we can speculate that the sense ran on
to perhaps an entirely different conclusion on a now-lost recto. But at some point Blake decided against an
abstract sermon on hypocrisy
<pb id="p09-41" n="41"/>
and in favor of the case of the particular hypocrite<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref>; at which time he saw that he could maintain continuity and therefore save the verso by
revising 385, deleting 386, and continuing on the present recto. Thus “Such is / Hypocrisy . . . ” became
“Such was Tiriel / Compelld. . . .” <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> A similar strategy lay behind the
wholesale cancellation of 364-74, which marks a shift from a panoramic to a developmental treatment of
Urizenic depravity. Observe in 364-69 the fourfold analysis of man in reptile form: dragon, viper, plague
serpent, and python. The python of 369 seems to represent the class of Kings and Judges.</note></p>
          <p>It might be objected that “Tiriel” need not have been added to 385 when 386 was cancelled; in
other words, that “Hypocrisy” could be taken as an appositive to “Tiriel,” as Damon takes it. But Damon’s
construction contains a double appositive, which besides sounding tortured and inept, does not sound like
Blake, who was sparing of appositives. The correction offered above mollifies this stylistic Medusa, accounts
for the changing of “is” to “was,” and explains the bad grammar of “Such was Tiriel Compelld” by supposing an
originally correct “Such is Hypocrisy.”</p>
          <figure n="Tiriel.9.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="322">
          	<figTranscr>Earth thus I stamp thy bosom rouse the earthquake from his den<lb/>
			To raise his dark &amp; burning visage thro the cleaving &lt;earth&gt; ground<lb/>
			To thrust these towers with his shoulders. let his fiery dogs<lb/>
			Rise from the center belching flames &amp; roarings. dark smoke<lb/>
			<lb/>
			<lb/>
			footsteps<lb/>
			Upon the sand. &amp;c<lb/>
			<lb/>
			And when the &lt;foolish crawling&gt; drone has reachd his crawling length<lb/>
			Black berries appear that poison all around him. Such &lt;is&gt; was Tiriel<lb/>
			&lt;Hypocrisy the idiots wisdom &amp; the wise mans folly&gt;<lb/>
			<lb/>
			<lb/>
			Compelld to pray repugnant &amp; to humble the immortal spirit<lb/>
			Till I am subtil as a serpent in a paradise<lb/>
			<lb/>
			9</figTranscr>
            <head>Lines from the manuscript of <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi></head>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
