<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.folsom</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Nobodaddy: Through the Bottomless Pit, Darkly</title>
        <author n="Folsom">L. Edwin Folsom</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0004">
      <pb id="p09-45" n="45"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Nobodaddy: Through the Bottomless Pit, Darkly</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>L. Edwin <name>Folsom</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The names of Blake’s poetic characters are, of course, vast in their associations, often
incorporating puns, conflations and anagrams based upon key words or Biblical, classical, and historical
characters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">1</ref> Nobodaddy, the farting,
belching “Father of Jealousy” (E 462) who hides himself in clouds and loves “hanging &amp; drawing &amp;
quartering / Every bit as well as war &amp; slaughtering,” (E 490) has received general critical agreement as
to the significance of his name. “Old daddy Nobody” and “Nobody’s daddy”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">2</ref> seem logical expansions of the compact name of this
destructive divinity who appears in several of the Notebook poems and who manifests himself elsewhere as
Urizen, Winter, the Will, and the Old Testament God.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">3</ref> But “Nobodaddy,” it should be noted, is also a close anagram of the name of a character
who appears in two of Blake’s favorite Biblical books, Job and Revelation: Abaddon (Hebrew for
“destruction”). Anagrammatized, “Abaddon” becomes “Nobadad.” He is “the angel of the bottomless pit” who
appears in Revelation 9:11 and is mentioned in Job 26:6.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See the informative footnotes explaining the origins of many of the names
in David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, rev. ed. (Garden City: Doubleday &amp;
Company, 1969), especially the notes on pp. 25, 253.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See Erdman, <hi rend="i">Prophet</hi>, p. 179.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See Harold Bloom, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell
Univ. Press, 1963), p. 106, and Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ.
Press, 1947), pp. 62-63.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Abaddon also appears as a place of destruction in Psalms 88:11 and in
Proverbs 15:11. In the King James Version, Abaddon is translated into “destruction” in the passages in Job,
Psalms, and Proverbs, but remains in the Herbrew form “Abaddon” in Revelation. Revelation 9:11 tells us that
the “name in the Hebrew tongue is Abaddon, but in the Greek tongue hath his name Appollyon.” Blake, of course,
chooses to work with the Hebrew name.</note></p>
          <p>Like Blake’s Nobodaddy, who hides himself in clouds and thrives in “darkness &amp; obscurity,”
(E 462) Abaddon exists, too, in an obscure beclouded place; when an angel of the apocalypse opens the shaft of
Abaddon’s realm, there “arose a smoke out of the pit, as the smoke of a great furnace; and the sun and the
air were darkened by reason of the smoke of the pit” (Rev. 9:2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">5</ref> Abaddon is the king of the locusts that are released during the apocalypse in
order to torture but not to kill “those men which have not the seal of God in their foreheads” (Rev. 9:4). Old
Nobodaddy, who is (with his love of “hanging &amp; drawing &amp; quartering . . . war &amp; slaughtering”),
like Abaddon, the personification of destruction, reflects nonetheless Abaddon’s less than humane decision
to torture but not to kill: “To kill the people I am loth,” (E 490) swears Nobodaddy solemnly and
hypocritically. And in his satiric verse, “When Klopstock England Defied” (E 491), Blake portrays Nobodaddy
ordering a miniature apocalypse, with Blake himself commanded by Nobodaddy to inflict torture but not death on
the infidel Klopstock. As the smoke rising from Abaddon’s bottomless pit accompanies the release of the
locusts, Nobodaddy’s “Fart[ing] &amp; Belch[ing] &amp; cough[ing]” (1. 4) bring on “a ninefold yell” from
“all the devils that were in hell” (11. 13-14), and the moon “blush[es] scarlet red” (1. 11) in a parody of
“the moon [becoming] as blood” (Rev. 6:12) when the sixth seal is opened. No seal is opened in Blake’s poem,
however; rather, Klopstock’s bowels are sealed shut as Blake obeys Nobodaddy and inflicts “nine fold pain”
(1. 28) on the hapless German poet who “defied” England by attempting to carry on Milton’s legacy in German,
reason enough to be fit, like those in Revelation, for torture. Klopstock’s plight—not to be relieved
until “to the last trumpet it was farted” (1. 20)—can be likened to that of the men tortured by the locusts,
who, in their pain, “shall . . . seek death, and shall not find it . . . ” (Rev. 9:6). Nobodaddy, however,
ultimately withdraws his sadistic, destructive orders and by the end of the poem Blake characteristically
begins to pity Klopstock: “From pity then he redend round / And the Spell removed unwound” (11. 29-30). 
<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">5</hi> This description of the smoke-filled abyss also parallels several scenes
elsewhere in Blake’s works; see, for example, “A Memorable Fancy” in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> where “we beheld the infinite Abyss, fiery as the smoke of a burning city” (E 40); 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> where the Sons of Albion divide and “Arise as the smoke of the furnace” from “a
hideous orifice” (E 222); and in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Third, where Urizen’s fall takes
place amidst “thunders &amp; thick clouds” and moves into the “smoke” of “The nether Abyss” (E
322-23).</note></p>
          <p>Abaddon, then, the embodiment of destruction, sadistic torturer of any man who failed to gain
God’s favor, cloud-obscured and smoke-hidden angel of the bottomless pit, is an ideal Biblical model for
Blake’s Nobodaddy, whose name reflects Abaddon’s in a scrambled, “dark and obscure” way.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p09-46" n="46" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
