<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <front>
      <pb id="p09-33-34" n="33-34"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.009.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="329">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            NEWS-<lb/>
            LETTER<lb/>
            34<lb/>
            Volume 9<lb/>
          Number 2<lb/>
          Fall 1975</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="20" cols="2">
          <row>
          	<cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>
            	  <hi rend="b">Contents</hi>
          		</title>
        	  </head>
          	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>News</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
            	<supplied type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="9.2.interlandi">Editorial Cartoon</ref>,</supplied> 
            	<ref type="article" issue="9.2.mla">MLA Blake and Moderns Seminar</ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="9.2.america">New Reproduction of <hi rend="i">America</hi></ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="9.2.allentuck">Allentuck Lectures on Fuseli</ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="9.2.journal">New Journal</ref><supplied type="emend">,
            	<ref type="article" issue="9.2.eldridge">AEthel-Gram</ref></supplied>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Minute Particulars</cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>David V. Erdman, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.erdman">Errors in the 1973 Edition of 
<hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi> and in the First Printing of <hi rend="i">The Illuminated
Blake</hi></ref></cell>
            <cell>39</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Francis Wood Metcalf, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.metcalf"><hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>: Two
Corrected First Readings</ref></cell>
            <cell>40</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Geoffrey Keynes, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.keynes">Blake in the Provinces</ref></cell>
            <cell>41</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Warren U. Ober, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.ober">“Poor Robin” and Blake’s “The
Blossom”</ref></cell>
            <cell>42</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>G. P. Tyson, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.tyson">An Early Allusion to Blake</ref></cell>
            <cell>43</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Michael Ferber, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.ferber">A Possible Source for “Thel’s
Motto”</ref></cell>
            <cell>43</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Donald H. Reiman, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.reiman">A Significant New Blakean
Fragment</ref></cell>
            <cell>44</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>L. Edwin Folsom, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.folsom">Nobodaddy: Through the Bottomless
Pit, Darkly</ref></cell>
            <cell>45</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Eileen Sanzo, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.sanzo">Blake’s Beulah and Beulah Hill,
Surrey</ref></cell>
            <cell>46</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Judith Wardle, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.wardle">The Influence of Wynne’s 
<hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> on Blake</ref></cell>
            <cell>46</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>James C. Evans, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.evans">Blake, Locke, and the Concept of
“Generation”</ref></cell>
            <cell>47</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Martin Butlin, <ref type="article" issue="9.2.butlin">The Catalogue of Blake’s Designs
Completed, and a Last-Minute Inclusion</ref></cell>
            <cell>48</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Reviews</cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Edward J. Rose, on <ref type="article" issue="9.2.rose"><hi rend="i">The Illuminated
Blake</hi> by David V. Erdman</ref></cell>
            <cell>50</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Paul Zall, on <ref type="article" issue="9.2.zall"><hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> by Martin
K. Nurmi</ref></cell>
            <cell>54</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>David Wagenknecht, on <ref type="article" issue="9.2.wagenknecht"><hi rend="i">Supreme
Fictions</hi> by Brian John</ref></cell>
            <cell>55</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>Photo credits. Cover: detail from picture reproduced on p. 49, below. Page 36: editorial cartoon by
Frank Interlandi, copyright Los Angeles <hi rend="i">Times</hi>, 1 Oct. 1974, reprinted by permission (our
thanks to Robert F. Gleckner for calling the cartoon to our attention). Page 37: Athel-Gram reproduced by
permission of Aethelred Eldridge. Page 38: detail from picture reproduced on p. 49, below. Page 41: lines from
the manuscript of <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, reproduced by permission of the British Library Board. Page 49: “A
Medieval Battle Scene” by Blake, reproduced by permission of Thomas Agnew and Sons, Ltd.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">Contributors</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p>Martin Butlin is Keeper of the British Collection at the Tate Gallery, London. He writes frequently
for the <hi rend="i">Newsletter.</hi></p>
        <p>David V. Erdman is Professor of English at the State University of New York, Stony Brook, and
Director of Publications for the New York Public Library. He has finished editing the volumes of Coleridge’s
journalism in the Bollingen series, and is busy preparing a new edition of <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against
Empire.</hi></p>
        <p>James C. Evans is Assistant Professor of English at the University of Texas at Austin. He has
contributed articles on Blake and Shelley to other journals and recently completed his Ph.D. dissertation on
Blake.</p>
        <p>Michael Ferber is a graduate student in his final year at Harvard. He is writing a thesis on
Blake’s political and social ideas.</p>
        <p>L. Edwin Folsom is an Instructor of English at the University of Rochester. He is investigating the
metaphorical meaning of America in twentieth-century poetry.</p>
        <p>Sir Geoffrey Keynes, M.D., F.R.C.S., Consulting Surgeon (retired), is known by his years of work in
textual criticism and bibliography to all students of Blake.</p>
        <p>Francis Wood Metcalf is writing a doctoral dissertation at New York University on Blake’s poetic
technique. He has contributed several articles and a review to the <hi rend="i">Newsletter.</hi></p>
        <p>Warren U. Ober is Chairman of the Department of English at the University of Waterloo, Waterloo,
Ontario, Canada. He has coedited several textbooks and published articles on Coleridge, Wordsworth, and
Southey. He is on the board of editorial advisors for <hi rend="i">Germano-Slavica.</hi></p>
        <p>Donald H. Reiman usually performs as a harmless drudge in the Shelley Factory at the Carl H.
Pforzheimer Library. His previous publications range, however, from a review of the <hi rend="i">Creation</hi>
to an analysis of the <hi rend="i">Apocalypse</hi>, and in an earlier incarnation he was best known for
parodies that appeared in his college newspaper.</p>
        <p>Edward J. Rose, Professor of English, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada, is one of the
editors of the forthcoming edition of Blake’s designs for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> He has
written a book on Henry George, and his publications on Blake, Melville, Emerson, Thoreau, Shelley, and others
have appeared in numerous journals.</p>
        <p>Eileen Sanzo, Albertus Magnus College, New Haven, Conn., has written a doctoral dissertation on
“William Blake: Poet of the City in the Industrial Age,” published on Blake in <hi rend="i">Thought</hi>, and
published poetry and reviews on other subjects.</p>
        <p>G. P. Tyson, in the Department of English at the University of Maryland, is presently preparing a
book-length study of Joseph Johnson and his circle.</p>
        <p>David Wagenknecht, Department of English, Boston University, is author of <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Night: William Blake and the Idea of Pastoral</hi>, published by Harvard in 1973. 
                </p>
        <pb id="p09-35" n="35"/>
        <p>Judith Wardle is a Lecturer in the Department of English, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria,
Australia.</p>
        <p>Paul M. Zall, Professor of English at California State University, Los Angeles, edited
Wordsworth’s critical essays in the Regents Critics series, and contributes “The Cool World of Samuel Taylor
Coleridge” column to <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle.</hi> He is now editing Benjamin Franklin’s 
<hi rend="i">Autobiography</hi> from the unique manuscript at the Huntington Library.</p>
        <p>The <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, is published four times a year
under the sponsorship of the Department of English of the University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Editors: Morris Eaves, University of New Mexico, and Morton D. Paley, Boston University.</p>
        <p>Associate Editor for Great Britain: Frances A. Carey, Assistant Curator, Department of Prints &amp;
Drawings, British Museum.</p>
        <p>Editorial Assistants: Corinne M. Henning, UCLA, and Virginia Masi, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Circulation Manager: Debra Sackett, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Manuscripts are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to the forms suggested in
the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Sheet</hi>, to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, Univ. of New
Mexico, Albuquerque, N.M. 87131; Morton Paley, Dept. of English, Boston University, Boston, Mass. 02215.</p>
        <p>Subscriptions are $5 for one year, one volume, four issues. Special rate for individuals, $4 for
one year, surface mail. For subscribers overseas who want to receive their issues by air mail, $8, U.S.
currency or international money order if possible. Make checks payable to the <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to Debra Sackett, Dept. of
English, Univ. of New Mexico, Albuquerque, N.M. 87131.</p>
        <p>Some back issues are available. Address Debra Sackett. Prices: whole numbers 1-8, bound together,
$5 (special rate for individuals, $4). Whole numbers 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 32, 33, 34, $2 each. Whole
number 20 (<hi rend="i">A Handlist of Works by William Blake in the Department of Prints &amp; Drawings of the
British Museum</hi>, edited by G. E. Bentley, (Jr.), $3. Whole numbers 14-19 are out of print.</p>
        <p>The International Standard Serial Number of the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> is
0006-453X.</p>
        <p>Design and layout for this issue: Corinne M. Henning and Virginia Masi.
	<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">Copyright © 1975 by Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
