<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2.america</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">New Reproduction of America</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-2-0003">
        <pb id="p09-37" n="37"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">New Reproduction of <hi rend="i">America</hi></title>
          </head>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> has just finished printing a new reproduction of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">America, a Prophecy.</hi> We designed it chiefly for classroom use, as its features show. It is
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p><label>1.</label><hi rend="i">America</hi> copy E, except for 2 plates from copy a* (proofs), plus
the 4 cancelled plates, all from the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection of the Library of Congress;</p></item>
	<item><p><label>2.</label> black and white, reproduced with good halftone screens, 150 lines to the inch, on
9″ × 12″ text paper;</p></item>
	<item><p><label>3.</label> approximately the size of the original;</p></item>
	<item><p><label>4.</label> printed <hi rend="i">one plate per page.</hi> There are 2 reproductions of 
<hi rend="i">each plate</hi>, one on one side of the page, one on the other. One reproduction is a “dropout”
halftone made from a high-contrast photograph, the other is a standard halftone made from a medium-contrast
photograph. Each kind of reproduction has its particular virtues, and we are experimenting to find out which
is more satisfactory;</p></item>
	<item><p><label>5.</label> unbound, loose sheets in an envelope, so that students can study sequences of
plates without turning pages back and forth;</p></item>
	<item><p><label>6.</label> very inexpensive, $2.50 per copy, so that, for example, you can supplement the
Blake section of an anthology of Romantic poetry—or even the Blake section of a broader anthology in a
survey course—with one of Blake’s works in illuminated printing, without having students spend too much
money on books for the course.</p></item>
</list>
If you would like to order <hi rend="i">America</hi> for your classes, please give your school bookstore our
address (below). They will want to know that our discount is 20%, standard for most textbooks, and that our
return policy is to refund money on all copies returned in good condition within a year.</p>
          <p>Please understand that we are publishing the reproduction of <hi rend="i">America</hi> strictly
as a service to teachers of Blake, with no intention of making a profit. We hope we can give you a good, cheap
reproduction of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, good service, and personal attention to make up for the resources
in personnel, money, and experience that commercial publishers have. We promise to do our best, but we hope
you won’t expect more than we can deliver.</p>
          <p>Send all orders to:<lb/>
Morris Eaves, Editor<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi><lb/>
Department of English<lb/>
University of New Mexico<lb/>
Albuquerque NM 87131</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
