<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.2b.mitchell</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Visions of the Last Judgment: Some Problems in Interpretation</title>
		<author n="Mitchell">W. J. T. Mitchell</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>December 28, 1975</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1975</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.2b</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2b</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <name>David Schnur</name>
              <name>Jean Stalker</name>
              <name>Donald Weeke</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
              <resp>Design and layout for this booklet</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1975"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
	<pb id="p09-2b-7" n="7"/>
    <div1 id="BQ-09-2b-0005">
			<head>
				<title type="main">Blake’s Visions of the Last Judgment: Some Problems in Interpretation</title>
			</head>
			<byline>By <docAuthor>W. J. T. <name>Mitchell</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="p7u1" type="note">*</ref></byline>
			<note id="p7u1">* <hi rend="i">W. J. T. Mitchell, Associate Professor of English at Ohio State University,
is the author of</hi> Blake’s Composite Art, <hi rend="i">forthcoming from Princeton University
Press</hi>.</note>
			<p>Unaccustomed as I am to presiding over Last Judgments, I have no intention of playing the Messiah at
this one. The following are some questions, problems, and a few hypotheses which I hope will stimulate
discussion of Blake’s pictures of the Last Judgment, and indicate directions for further investigation.</p>
			<div2>
				<head>
					<title>I. What did Blake mean by “A Vision of the Last Judgment”?</title>
				</head>
				<p>Perhaps we should begin by asking what he meant by a Vision, distinguishing it from such things as
hallucination, vivid visual memory, or Platonic “form.” What is the ontological status of a Vision? How can
Blake claim that it reveals “Permanent Realities” (E545) at the same time he admits that “to different People
it appears differently” (E544)? Can we arrive at a psychological definition that will correspond with
Blake’s literary definition (“The Last Judgment is not Fable or Allegory but Vision . . . Allegory &amp;
Vision ought to be known as Two Distinct Things” E544)? Is it sufficient to explain this distinction by
referring it to the distinction between imagination and memory? (“Fable or Allegory is Formd by the daughters
of Memory. Imagination is Surrounded by the daughters of Inspiration.”) Are memory, allegory, and fable simple
antitheses of inspiration, vision, and imagination, or are they constituents of these “higher” mental and
literary processes?</p>
				<p>What is the temporal significance of the word “Last”? Does it mean “last in time,” the final event of
history? Or does it mean something like “utmost” or “ultimate,” denoting an event of peak intensity and
significance (like the epiphanic “Moments” described in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>), rather than temporal
finality? What happens <hi rend="i">after</hi> a (or the) Last Judgment? Is it a collective or individual
experience, or both? Is Blake’s notion of the Last Judgment completely or only partially a-historical?</p>
				<p>What is the significance of the word “Judgment”? In particular, what are the implicit norms, values, or
moral standards behind Blake’s vision of Judgment? How can we reconcile his division of mankind into Just
and Wicked, Sheep and Goats in both his verbal and pictorial treatments of the Last Judgment with his satires
on categories of good and evil in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, and his notion of the
apocalypse as Universal Forgiveness in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>? Is Blake being blithely inconsistent or
consciously ironic and paradoxical when he provides the following definition of a Last Judgment: “The Last
Judgment when all those are Cast away who trouble Religion with Questions concerning Good &amp; Evil” (E544)?
Doesn’t Blake simply re-introduce new categories of good and evil (the good are those who don’t raise
questions concerning good and evil; the evil are the “troublesome questioners”)? Who or what is “cast away” in
a Last Judgment? Psychological “States” or “Individuals”? Who or what is “saved”? What does it mean to be
saved in Blake’s Last Judgment?</p>
			</div2>
			<div2>
				<head>
					<title>II. How are Blake’s ideas about the Last Judgment expressed pictorially?</title>
				</head>
				<p>We can wrangle over the preceding questions by referring to Blake’s writings, but the really
interesting problem, in my view, is to encounter his pictures of the Last Judgment on their own terms. If we
did not know these pictures had been created by William Blake, the radical, unorthodox visionary, would we be
so likely to suspect that they depart from Christian doctrine, or express unorthodox notions of the Last
Judgment? Suppose an orthodox Christian were to look at these pictures and tell us, “I don’t care what you
say Blake <hi rend="i">intended</hi> in these designs; what he accomplished was a very traditional image of
the Last Judgment as I understand it. The Messiah is in heaven, surrounded by his elders, apostles, and
angels; the saved are ascending to heaven on his right hand, the damned are falling into hell on his left. You
may claim that they are ‘States’ (whatever that is) but Blake drew them as human forms. If Blake was
trying to subvert my orthodox picture of the Last Judgment as the time when the Lord separates good people
from bad, he certainly failed to do so; in fact, he just confirms it!” (My apologies to orthodox Christians
for this caricature.)</p>
				<p>Albert S. Roe, in his ground-breaking study of Blake’s Last Judgment pictures, argues that “it is
important to remember that Blake had no belief in any eternal damnation of the individual,” and that it is
only the casting out of mental “error” that he represented in his Last Judgment drawings. (Roe’s essay first
appeared in <hi rend="i">HLQ</hi> in 1957; it is reprinted in <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi>, ed. Robert
Essick, Los Angeles, 1973, pp. 201-32.) I want to agree with this statement (although I suspect that Blake
means something different by “eternal” from what Roe means here); the problem is, do the pictures make this
statement in pictorial terms? Are there any pictorial clues to tell us that the human figures are not “really”
human beings, but representations of mental states? And what about the larger question of the relation of
Blake’s pictures to tradition? The symmetrical structure of saved and damned has been part of Last Judgment
iconography since the earliest days of Christian art; André Grabar (<hi rend="i">Christian Iconography</hi>,
Princeton, 1968) traces the theme ultimately to images of Manichean propaganda circulated around 
				<pb id="p09-2b-8" n="8"/>
				240 to 270 A.D. It is hardly surprising that an implacable moral dualism pervades the tradition. The
question is, did Blake simply accept and imitate this dualism (hence, the conventional symmetry of his
designs) or did he find some way of modifying and transforming it in his pictures of the Last Judgment? To
answer this question we need to investigate, not just Blake’s intentions, but the pictorial tradition within
which he was working.</p>
			</div2>
			<div2>
				<head>
					<title>III. How do Blake’s treatments of the Last Judgment adopt, modify, or transform the pictorial
conventions associated with this theme?</title>
				</head>
				<p>A. S. Roe argues that “traditional literary and artistic sources” do not have much bearing on Blake’s
treatment of the Last Judgment: “With another artist, this might very well constitute the major interest of
such a study as this, but with Blake, even when treating a theme involving so many traditional connotations as
the Last Judgment, his approach to it is essentially personal” (205). And yet, when Roe sets about defining
the “personal” quality of Blake’s compositions, he appeals to a modification of the tradition, suggesting
that the position of Christ’s hands in Blake’s drawings (resting on the book in the Pollok House version,
on the scroll in the Petworth copy, outstretched in the Rosenwald drawing) departs from “medieval tradition,
where He either holds His hands down by His sides with palms outward to display His wounds, or else holds His
right hand raised in blessing while His left is lowered in a gesture of judgment on the damned” (208). Roe’s
interpretive tactics seem to me superior to his overall strategy of minimizing tradition; in fact it is only
the knowledge of tradition that allows us to gauge the personal modifications Blake introduced. The question
is, what other aspects of Blake’s treatment of the Last Judgment disclose departures from pictorial
traditions? This is obviously a larger topic than we can handle in a few hours, but it might be helpful to
sketch out some possible lines of investigation.</p>
				<p>The first problem is to determine what pictorial renditions of the Last Judgment Blake might have
known, either first hand or through engravings. Aside from the certainty that he knew Michelangelo’s Sistine
Chapel fresco through engravings, and the high probability that he knew Dürer’s series of Apocalypse
engravings, it is surprising how little is known about this matter. Did the keen interest in the Italian
primitives among late eighteenth century connoisseurs (documented by Rosenblum and Irwin) extend to their
frescos of the Last Judgment? Could Blake have seen engravings after Last Judgments by Giotto or Fra Angelico?
Or, for that matter, could he have seen some indigenous English treatments of the theme depicted, as Samuel
Chew tells us (<hi rend="i">The Pilgrimage of Life</hi>, Yale, 1962, 257-58) “on the west wall of many church
naves”? Could Blake have seen the de Quincey Apocalypse in Lambeth Palace? What other treatments of the theme
in illuminated manuscripts, stained glass, or sculpture would have been available to him?</p>
				<p>Until we have answered these sorts of questions it will be very difficult to substantiate any claims
about transformations that Blake might have been making, and our sense of what is “personal” in his pictorial
treatment of the Last Judgment will be largely hypothetical. In the hope of stimulating refutation or
confirmation, however, let me advance the following sub-questions and hypotheses:</p>
				<p>1. Whatever medieval treatments of the Last Judgment Blake knew, they would probably conform to the
general style found in Anglo-Norman manuscripts, which divides the composition into compartments separated by
linear boundaries. A common device was to divide the picture into three levels (the Messiah with angels, the
saints, and mankind) separated by two horizontal lines. (This principle of separation, but not the groupings,
persists in Michelangelo’s fresco—note the two bands of empty space which traverse his Last Judgment.) How
does Blake respond to this highly structured treatment of the theme? What structural principles inform his
compositions?</p>
				<p>2. Emile Male suggests that the medieval artist understood the apocalypse as “a drama in five acts,”
including preliminary signs, Christ’s appearance, the Resurrection of the Dead, the Judgment, and the
Separation of the Sheep and the Goats. Treatments of the theme tended to focus on one of these acts, or
perhaps to combine the last two. Doesn’t it seem that Blake is trying to pack all five acts into one image?
The Last Judgment tends to attract an encyclopedic, comprehensive treatment, but Blake’s is by far the most
encyclopedic I have seen (the angels with trumpets in the center are the “preliminary signs,” the Messiah is
appearing in the clouds, the dead emerge from the ground at the bottom of the design, etc. The presence of the
Whore of Babylon and the Seven-Headed Beast also suggest the inclusion of an even earlier phase in the
apocalyptic drama, the so-called “Trial of Sin.”)</p>
				<p>3. Is the absence of the Archangel Michael (often depicted just below the throne of Christ) a
significant omission?</p>
				<p>We also should try to gauge Blake’s response to his primary challenge, the Sistine Chapel fresco by
Michelangelo. Although he could have known this design through at least ten different engravings, he was
probably best acquainted with the version by Bonasone which was in the collection of George Cumberland.
Blake’s chief debt to Michelangelo would seem to be the (no longer revolutionary) practice of filling his
Last Judgment with nudes, and the general tendency of Late Renaissance masters (including the hated Rubens) to
stress the dynamic, explosive possibilities of the theme, rather than (as in the Middle Ages) its
distributive, judicial character. And yet A. S. Roe’s intuition that Blake’s treatment is medieval “in
spirit and even in detail” (207) still seems compelling. Why? Does it have something to do with relative
flatness and non-illusionistic quality of Blake’s design, coupled with the sense of presiding symmetry and
controlled structure? Again, what is that structure?</p>
				<pb id="p09-2b-9" n="9"/>
				<p>As a footnote to our discussion of Michelangelo’s influence on Blake I offer the following. In 1806,
the year Blake composed his first known Last Judgment drawing (the Pollok House version), the first English
life of Michelangelo was published, a life which was to dominate English understanding of Michelangelo for the
next fifty years. This book includes a fold-out engraving by William Ottley of the Sistine Chapel fresco, and
a commentary on the painting by the author, Richard Duppa, which is less than reverential towards the Divine
Michelangelo. Duppa complains of his Last Judgment that “the indiscriminate application of one character of
muscular form and proportion makes the whole rather an assemblage of academic figures, than a serious,
well-studied, historical composition . . . . The mind is divided and distracted by the want of a great
concentrating principle of effect” (<hi rend="i">The Life of Michel Angelo 
<corr type="emend">Buonarroti,</corr></hi> 2nd ed., London, 1807, 204-05). I have my doubts that Blake would have
agreed with Duppa’s criticism. But it is interesting that his own Last Judgment pictures have precisely what
Duppa says is missing in Michelangelo, a “great concentrating principle of effect.” At some point we should
discuss what this principle is, but for now we can surely agree that there is some kind of structure or
gestalt in Blake’s Last Judgments which makes the multitude of figures seem like parts of a larger pattern
rather than an “assemblage.” Could not this sense of structural unity have been the thing that prompted Ozias
Humphreys to praise the Petworth version for “grandeur of conception . . . and the sublimely multitudinous
masses &amp; groups which it exhibits,” and to rate Blake’s composition as “in many respects superior to the
Last Judgment of Michael Angelo . . . . ”(see <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr., Oxford,
1969, 188-89)? Certainly it would be the overall structure and conception, not the individual figures, that
would be noticed by a man on the verge of blindness, as Humphreys was when he wrote the above remarks. (One
could argue, of course, that Humphreys’ blindness made him a very bad judge of <hi rend="i">anything</hi>
concerning these pictures.)</p>
				<p>Whatever new information we gather about Blake’s use of tradition, his response to the challenge of
Michelangelo, his tranformations of medieval <corr type="emend">iconography</corr> or structure, we will find,
I suspect, that his Last Judgments are a creative synthesis of Renaissance and medieval elements. A more
precise grasp of this synthesis will allow us to see more exactly the Vision of the Last Judgment that he
managed to articulate in pictorial terms. In the meantime, it might be interesting for us to meditate on that
“concentrating principle” of structure which keeps coming up as we try to analyze the effect of Blake’s Last
Judgment pictures.</p>
			</div2>
			<div2>
				<head>
					<title>IV. What is the structural pattern or “concentrating principle of effect” in Blake’s Last
Judgment pictures? How does it evolve in the various versions?</title>
				</head>
				<p>I offer below three schematic diagrams to clarify the structural skeletons of the Pollok House,
Petworth House, and Rosenwald drawings. I do not believe, however, that geometric forms are intrinsic bearers
of meaning in Blake’s art; on the contrary, it seems to me essential that these forms remain ambiguous. The
question here is, what <hi rend="i">range</hi> of ambiguity is suggested by these forms? What is Blake trying
to evoke? A concrete object or objects? A pattern of forces? An organ or organism? How does this structural
pattern develop? Is there evidence of a direction, a teleology—or must we settle for the answer that Blake
just wanted to try different ways of organizing it for no particular reason?</p>
				<p>While we are on the question of formal development, we might consider another major question, the
iconographic variations among the versions of the Last Judgment. What figures appear in every version? Which
ones do not? What is the effect or significance of changes in position, perspective? David Erdman detects an
increase in the number of human forms, a decrease in non-human forms in the sequence of drawings. In other
ways (position of trumpeting angels, perspective around Christ) the latest version seems to return to the
earliest. Can we guess what the lost tempera version (the climactic picture, presumably) looked like? What
things described in the notebook draft of <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> do not appear in the
Rosenwald drawing?</p>
				<p>If all these unanswered questions do not prove sufficiently irritating, perhaps the following summary
hypothesis will stir debate. The key to Blake’s structural conception of the Last Judgment is his remark on
the organization of the groups in the lost tempera: “when distant they appear as One Man but as you approach
they appear Multitudes of Nations” (E546). The early versions of the Last Judgment are organized around a
portion or organ of the human form—probably the skull—and the cyclic movement of the figures within that
form represents the cycle of consciousness casting off error and embracing truth. The figures are, as Blake
claimed, not “Persons” but mental “States” which exist inside persons. As Blake developed his notion of the
“Human Form Divine” and the myth of a Universal Man (Albion) in his prophetic books, so also his concept of
the Last Judgment as an event in the consciousness of this Universal Man began to develop, an event which can
be seen at the individual, microcosmic level as “a” Last Judgment or epiphany, at the collective, macrocosmic
level as “the” Last Judgment. The cyclical quality of his compositions, their mirror-like symmetry, the
even-handed posture of the Messiah, the absence of the warrior angel Michael, all these features are Blake’s
way of saying that the divisive, judgmental aspects of the Last Judgment have been subordinated to a Vision of
the Last Judgment as a continuing process, a recurrent event in the life of consciousness, a moment of
welcoming and awakening into the total life of the imagination.</p>
				<p>I am not sure that this will convince the hypothetical “orthodox Christian” I invented earlier, but
perhaps it will incite some Mental Warfare among us infidels.</p>
			</div2>
			<pb id="p09-2b-10" n="10"/>
			<figure n="judgment-schematic.009.02b.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="586">
				<figTranscr>A. Pollok House <lb/>
					B. Petworth House <lb/>
					C. Rosenwald Collection</figTranscr>
				<head>Schematic Diagrams of Blake’s Pictures of the Last Judgment</head>
			</figure>
    </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
