<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.4.baine</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="note">Blake’s Sketch for Hamlet</title>
        <author n="Baine">Rodney M. Baine</author>
        <author n="Baine">Mary R. Baine</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <name>Jean Stalker</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-4-0003">
        <pb id="p09-117" n="117"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="BoydellHamlet.9.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="368">
            <head>1 Illustration to <hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi>: Marcellus, Horatio, and Hamlet with the
Ghost.</head>
            <figDesc>Designed by Fuseli, engraved in 1796 for the 1803 Boydell 
<hi rend="i">Shakespeare.</hi></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Blake’s Sketch for</hi> Hamlet</title>
          </head>
          <byline>BY <docAuthor>RODNEY <name>M.</name></docAuthor> AND <docAuthor>MARY R.
<name>BAINE</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Before the middle of the eighteenth century the Ghost scene in <hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi> which
attracted artists and engravers was that of the apparition in the Queen’s “closet” (III. iv).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n18">Rodney and Mary Baine are in the English Department at the University of Georgia. They have
published a number of articles on Blake and are at work on a book-length study of his animal symbolism.</note>
In the latter half of the century, however, artists shifted their attention from this scene to that of the
Ghost’s earlier appearance on the battlements and, sometimes, below (I. iv, v). One of the first such
depictions was “Garrick as Hamlet,” by Benjamin Wilson, with the mezzotint by McArdell; here Hamlet, alone in
the picture, seems with slightly raised hands to listen almost incredulously to the unseen Ghost.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> The Ghost appears with Hamlet in John Hamilton
Mortimer’s version, engraved in 1782 by Walker; here the two figures are isolated, as they are in the scene
(I.v) which Blake later favored. Of course Mortimer, like his successors, represented the Ghost as the text
prescribes, clad in armor from head to foot, with beaver up, and with a “sable silvered” beard. Doubtless
Blake, who admired Mortimer’s work, knew at least the engraving; but Mortimer’s Hamlet, though with drawn
sword, seems little perturbed and is weakly represented.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> W. Moelwyn Merchant, <hi rend="i">Shakespeare and the Artist</hi> (London:
Oxford University Press, 1959), pp. 53, 58; plate 12 (a). We are indebted to Mr. William Gaither (research
assistant at the University of Georgia) and to Mr. Robert N. Essick for numerous suggestions. For permission
to reproduce the Blake sketch, we are indebted to the Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery; for the watercolor,
to the Trustees of the British Museum.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> William Ackerman Buell, <hi rend="i">The Hamlets of the Theatre</hi> (New
York: Astor-Honor, Inc., 1968), p. 32.</note></p>
          <p>Far more influential upon Blake’s <hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi> scenes was Henry Fuseli. In addition
to an inept pen sketch done in his teens,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> Fuseli thrice did the scene on the battlements (I. iv), each time with Marcellus, Horatio,
and Hamlet balanced against the Ghost. Weakest artistically of the three is the last, engraved in 1804 by
Joseph Smith for the Chalmers <hi rend="i">Shakespeare</hi>, for here the very corporeal Ghost, centrally
placed in a vertical design, faces away from us; and Hamlet, made less important by the dominance of the
Ghost, seems rather surprised than agonized.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> Far stronger is a pencil sketch, which Blake, however, may not have seen; it incorporates
some of the main features of terror and sublimity infused into the scene by Fuseli.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Strongest of all is the version Blake almost certainly knew,
that engraved in 1796 by Robert Thew for the 1803 Boydell 
                        <pb id="p09-118" n="118"/>
	<hi rend="i">Shakespeare</hi> (see illustration).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> In this version, as in the sketch, the violence is heightened by the tension of the
struggling group, as Horatio attempts to restrain the outrageous Hamlet, who is determined to make a Ghost of
whoever “lets” him. Here, as in the other versions, the Ghost points toward a rendezvous, and the sulfurous
moon behind the ghostly head and the turbulent sea in the background (tied to the Ghost by his trailing cape)
give a sense of unreality and violence to the scene. The staring eyes of the Ghost, moreover, suggest a goblin
damned. This scene deservedly attained with artists a success second only to that of Fuseli’s
“Nightmare.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Gert Schiff, <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli</hi> (Zurich:
Schweizerisches Institut für Kunstwissenschaft, 1973), II, 28; plate 201.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Schiff II, 409; plate 1296.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Schiff II, 216; plate 818.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Schiff II, 179; plates 731, 732.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Schiff I, 145-46.</note></p>
          <p>Perhaps because he despaired of excelling Fuseli in this scene, Blake selected for his
representations the subsequent scene (I.v) instead. Although it does not lend itself to as much movement, it
provides even more concentration of figures and allows as much terror.</p>
          <p>Blake’s sketch of the Ghost’s appearance to Hamlet, here evidently first reproduced (see
illustration 2), has been generally overlooked by Blake
<figure n="HamletSketch.9.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="366">
	<head>2 Blake’s sketch of the Ghost’s appearance to Hamlet (unfinished), 31 × 43 cm.</head>
</figure>
bibliographers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> An unfinished pen and
ink dilute India wash over pencil, it measures approximately 31 × 43 cm., on laid, undated Whatman paper. The
verso of a scene from <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe</hi>, it has been in the collections of Admiral Popham and
Samuel Timmins; it is now in the Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery. The sketch differs markedly from the
finished 1806 watercolor (an extra-illustration for a copy of the Shakespeare second folio) in the British
Museum (see illustration 3). It does so particularly in shape, background, the appearance of the figures, and
their relationship. Since the finished watercolor is vertical in design, the two figures are naturally closer
together than in the horizontal sketch; there they are separated by a massive pillar. In the watercolor the
mysterious moonlit background is made effective by a less localized foreground. The two figures seem to be
placed on the shore of Fuseli’s vexed sea. In the sketch the heavy pillars suggest a stronghold beyond which
we see only a slightly sketched, generalized background devoid of mystery. Though the watercolor seems
superior to the sketch in these regards, the sketch seems at least equal to the watercolor
<pb id="p09-119" n="119"/>
in its presentation of the two figures. In the sketch the Ghost is given the traditional luxuriant beard
balanced below by thick calves and thighs; the watercolor replaces this corporeal figure with a comparatively
wraithlike one. In both versions, however, the massive armor of Fuseli is replaced by armor which fits tightly
and suggests, following Shakespeare’s lines (I.v. 11-20), far more of the Ghost’s corporeality. More
important, the Ghost in the sketch appears much more sorrowful, more pitiably tormented than does the
watercolor Ghost, who, like Fuseli’s, appears threatening, even accusatory, with piercing eyes and rather
stiff body. The Hamlet of the sketch is almost featureless; but his wildly violent gesture toward the Ghost
suggests an even more violent emotion than Blake first intended: originally, perhaps following Fuseli, Blake
had Hamlet stretch his right hand just above the center of his body. In the watercolor Hamlet’s slightly
raised hands follow the pattern set by Benjamin Wilson. Fear of the frightful apparition has set Hamlet’s
hair on end (Cf. I.v. 18-20), yet one misses the unrestrained emotional abandon which characterizes the
sketch. Here, even more than in the watercolor, Blake equalled the intensity of Fuseli. 
<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Nor is it mentioned by W. Moelwyn Merchant in his informative “Blake’s Shakespeare,” in 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 79 (April, 1964), 318-24; reprinted in <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi>, ed. Robert
N. Essick (Los Angeles: Hennessey and Ingalls, 1973), pp. 233-52.</note></p>
          <figure n="BUT547.1.5.WC" rend="file" width="725" height="1000">
            <head>3 Blake’s 1806 watercolor of the Ghost’s appearance to Hamlet.</head>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
