<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.4.eaves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Postscript: Blake’s Abnormal Psychology</title>
        <author n="Eaves">Morris Eaves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <name>Jean Stalker</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
	<pb id="p09-121" n="121"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-4-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Postscript: Blake’s Abnormal Psychology</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Morris <name>Eaves</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Lest we drop off to sleep and dream that a few decades ago the subject of Blake’s lunacy passed
quietly into the innocent and nostalgic half-light of primitive psychology, it might not be a bad idea to add
a short postscript to Raymond Lister’s note. <hi rend="i">Abnormal Psychology: Current Perspectives</hi> is
a hefty and up-to-date textbook widely used, for instance, in upper-level undergraduate courses, the early
years of medical school, and the like. It was edited by a board of “contributing consultants” so long and so
pee-aitch-deed and em-deed that it would put the editorial pages of some scholarly journals to shame. It
professes the radical tolerance for mental differences of Laing and like-minded thinkers: “To see the manifest
problems and illnesses of our society is to question the concept of the ‘well-adjusted person.’ To know
the effect on language, literature, and art of the work of ‘mentally disturbed’ individuals is to be
hesitant in pressing the claims of the homogenous ‘normal’ society as the greatest good.” “Acceptance
means understanding.” “Establishing standard norms of acceptable behavior and labeling so-called inappropriate
acts ‘abnormal’ has important consequences in terms of sanctioning a form of social control. Only by
recognizing the importance of diversity and change does a society foster individual freedom and growth.”</p>
          <pb id="p09-122" n="122"/>
          <p>Then, in the section on “Psychoses,” a couple of pages after three of Van Gogh’s paintings are
reproduced with a caption remarking how his paintings “are a powerful representation of the blending of
psychotic chaos and artistic genius,” we come across a reproduction of Sin, Death, and Satan at the Gates of
Hell, from Blake’s illustrations of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, accompanying a caption that I suppose
the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> picture is intended to document.
<q>
An early-nineteenth-century writer referred to William Blake as “an unfortunate lunatic whose personal
inoffensiveness secures him from confinement.” A retrospective diagnosis of Blake would probably label him a
paranoid schizophrenic, for he made no secret of the fact that he was “ . . . under the direction of
Messengers from Heaven, Daily and Nightly.” Blake’s first hallucination involving divine personages occurred
at the age of four, and succeeding “visions” probably provided much of the material for his illustrations of
works such as Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, which includes <hi rend="i">Satan Comes to the Gates
of Hell</hi>, shown above. This watercolor illustration depicts Satan advancing from the left, preparing to
confront Death, right. In the center, thrusting them apart, is Sin. Flames writhe in the background, and to
the right is Hell’s latticed gate.<lb/>
<lb/>
Curtis L. Barrett et al., contributing consultants, <hi rend="i">Abnormal Psychology: Current
Perspectives</hi> (Del Mar, Calif.: CRM Books, 1972), p. 249, fig. 12.2.<lb/>
<lb/>
University of New Mexico
</q></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
