<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.4.warner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Contemporary Reference to Blake</title>
        <author n="Warner">Janet Warner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <name>Jean Stalker</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-4-0006">
		<pb id="p09-122" n="122"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Contemporary Reference to Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Janet <name>Warner</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>A reference to Blake which does not seem to have been previously noticed by scholars can be found
in Ackermann’s <hi rend="i">Repository</hi> for June 1810, in an article entitled “On Splendour of Colours
&amp;C” by Juninus, pp. 408-09. It reads as follows:
<q>
Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of Homer, Aeschylus and Dante</hi> engraved by Piroli, of Rome, and
Blake’s plates from Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, lately engraved, are excellent studies for a young
artist. Blake has lately received much deserved commendation from Fuseli. Perhaps this engraver has more
genius than any one in his profession in this country. If he would study the ornamental requisites more, he
would probably attain much higher celebrity than he has already acquired.
</q></p>
          <p>Isn’t it odd that this mentions Flaxman’s engraver, Piroli, but not Schiavonetti, who
engraved Blake’s designs and who died 7 June 1810? It also mentions Blake as an engraver rather than an
artist. Would 1808, when the Blair engravings were printed, be “lately engraved” in 1810? Interestingly
enough, we know that Blake’s own exhibition had opened in May 1810 and the “much deserved commendation from
Fuseli” may refer to that, but it is odd that the exhibition is not mentioned if Juninus knew about it. We
know that Crabb Robinson had seen the exhibition in April 1810 and that he took Charles and Mary Lamb to see
it on 11 June (G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 226).</p>
          <p>In September, 1810, in the same continuing article, Junius again refers to Blake. Two women are
speaking of prints, and after a description of <hi rend="i">The Fall of Rosamond</hi>, one says:</p>
		<q>
This artist seems to have relinquished engraving and to have cultivated the higher departments of designing
and painting with great success. His works show that he must have studied the antique with considerable
attention.
</q>
          <p>The other replies:
<q>
If those ingenious men, the engravers, were to ask the man of genius why he abandoned his profession, he might
with truth answer to most of those by whom it is followed, in the words of the poet:<lb/>
“I hear a voice you cannot hear<lb/>
That says I must not stay:<lb/>
I see a hand you cannot see<lb/>
That beckons me away.”
</q></p>
          <p>This is interesting since we know very little of Blake’s actions in the years 1810 to 1814.
This suggests he gave up engraving for a while, and indeed he exhibited three paintings at the exhibition of
the Water Colour Society in 1812, (The Canterbury Pilgrims, The Spiritual Forms of Pitt and Nelson) and
“Detached Specimens of an original illuminated Poem, entitled Jerusalem the Emanation of the Giant
Albion.”</p>
          <p>Who was Juninus? I would appreciate hearing from anyone who has ideas on his identity. Morton
Paley has found in his researches on Ackermann that even <hi rend="i">he</hi> did not know the identity at
first of this anonymous contributor, and when he did learn and sent him a gift of money, Juninus’
contributions ceased. Whoever he was, it is significant that he retained a high opinion of Blake’s work at a
time following Hunt’s attack in the <hi rend="i">Examiner</hi>, September 1809, when Blake’s fortunes, as
far as we can tell, were beginning to decline.</p>
          <p>Glendon College,</p>
          <p>York University</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
