<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.4.lister</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Appearance in a Textbook on Insanity</title>
        <author n="Lister">Raymond Lister</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <name>Jean Stalker</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
	<pb id="p09-120" n="120"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-4-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Appearance in a Textbook on Insanity</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Raymond <name>Lister</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>From the viewpoint of the unprofessional reader, one of the most fascinating books on insanity is
<hi rend="i">Mad Humanity its Forms Apparent and Obscure</hi> by L. Forbes Winslow, which was published in
London by C. A. Pearson Ltd. in 1898.</p>
          <pb id="p09-121" n="121"/>
          <p>Winslow, who was born in 1844 and died in 1913, was well qualified with degrees at both Oxford
and Cambridge. He had also been lecturer in insanity at Charing Cross Hospital, London, Vice-President of the
Medico-Legal Congress, New York, and Chairman of the Psychological Department, and he was founder of the
British Hospital for Mental Disorders. In addition to the foregoing book he wrote several others, including
<hi rend="i">Handbook for Attendants of the Insane</hi> and <hi rend="i">Lunacy Law in England. Mad
Humanity</hi>, which is 451 pages long, is full of details of the medical and legal aspects of insanity,
although many of the author’s opinions and conclusions would doubtless carry little authority in the medical
climate of our own times. There are also many intriguing anecdotes of madness, and, most arresting of all, a
series of photographs illustrating various aspects of insanity, such as “Delusions of Persecution in
Monomania”, “Hallucinations of Seeing and Hearing” and “Suicidal Dementia.” These photographs vary from the
pitiful to the horrific, with, among the physiognomies shown, expressions of terror, cunning, bewilderment,
mistrust, and even a species of sardonic humour.</p>
          <p>The whole of Chapter XII—a long one—is devoted to what Winslow describes as “Madness of
Genius.” For the author believed that genius was so abnormal as to be a species of neurosis. “Genius,” he
wrote, “like every other disposition of the intellectual dynamism, has necessarily its material substratum.
This substratum is a semi-morbid state of the brain, a true nervous erethism . . . ” (p. 337).</p>
          <p>The main part of the chapter consists of a series of studies of varying length of the alleged
madness of certain men of genius, and a very strange collection they make, ranging from such undoubted
examples of madness as William Cowper, John Clare and Christopher Smart, through such borderline cases as
Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Robert Southey and Percy Bysshe Shelley, to intellectual giants like Shakespeare and
Samuel Johnson. In this somewhat motley assortment, William Blake makes an appearance, but when the author’s
account of him is read, one’s confidence begins to abate, for surely, even when Blake’s reputation was at
its lowest ebb, there can have been no more muddled account of his visionary experiences. Indeed, one is left
with the impression that if this is how the author remembered a reading of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of
Blake</hi> (from which most of the details presumably originated) he would have been a candidate for inclusion
in his own book. But it is probably no more than an example of shoddy scholarship, repetition, perhaps, of
loose chatter. Nevertheless, the passage was printed in a scholarly book and it probably did Blake’s
reputation a certain amount of harm at a time when it was beginning to emerge from the shadows. Here it is, in
full:
<q><hi rend="i">Hallucinations of Demonomania and Strength</hi></q></p>
          <p>(William Blake, 1757-1827).—An artist of considerable fame, he was also a poet, and his
compositions were innumerable, leaving behind him one hundred MSS. for publication. He was regarded by his
many admirers as the equal of Shelley or Byron. He suffered from hallucinations, and being invited to Brighton
to illustrate his edition of Cowper, he was met on the Downs, in his own imagination, by the spirits of Dante,
Virgil, and Homer, whom he describes as coloured shadows and with whom he held high converse, watching the
fairies and their funerals, and all the milder and gentler forms of demonolatry. For some years he had sighed
for an interview with Satan, whom he had considered to be a grand and splendid spiritual existence, and whom
he ultimately alleges he saw as he was going up the stairs of his house, in his mind’s eye, the fiend
glaring upon him through the grating of a window, when his wife, conceiving that he was suffering from one of
his poetical hallucinations, induced him to execute a portrait of his infernal visitant, and in consequence of
this vision he conceived the idea that he had abnormal strength, and, whilst suffering from this delusion, he
attacked a soldier, and was tried for high treason. Many of the critics of the time described him as
eccentric, another as visionary, a third as an enthusiast, a fourth as a superstitious ghostseer; but that he
was mad they had not the slightest doubt. (pp. 371-72)</p>
          <p>Wolfson College,<lb/>
Cambridge</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
