<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.4.tannenbaum</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Mark Roberts, The Tradition of Romantic Morality</title>
        <author n="Tannenbaum">Leslie Tannenbaum</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <name>Jean Stalker</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
	<pb id="p09-126" n="126"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-4-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Mark Roberts. <hi rend="b">The Tradition of Romantic Morality.</hi> London:
Macmillan; New York: Harper and Row, Barnes and Noble Import Division, 1973. 398 pp. $15.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Leslie <name>Tannenbaum</name></docAuthor><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">*</ref></byline>
          <note id="n20">Leslie Tannenbaum, Assistant Professor of English at Wright State University, is
author of articles on Blake, Byron and Mary Shelley.</note>
          <p>As the title of the book indicates, and as Mark Roberts states in his first chapter, 
<hi rend="i">The Tradition of Romantic Morality</hi> deals with Romanticism as a moral phenomenon rather than as a
literary or artistic one. Roberts’ thesis is that there is at the center of Romanticism a moral position
that he calls “energy of the soul,” the establishment of energy as the exclusive source of values and as the
sole guide to human conduct. Furthermore, Roberts asserts, while Romanticism as a literary impulse has
exhausted itself, this Romantic morality survives and exerts an insidious influence—insidious because
unrecognized—that has revealed itself most blatantly in the ideas, attitudes and actions of dissidents
during the last decade.</p>
          <p>Robert’s purpose, then, is to establish the presence of this moral tradition, examine some of
the forms it takes and evaluate it. He begins with a discussion of John Osborne’s <hi rend="i">Look Back in
Anger</hi> to define the problem he is confronting and to postulate his answer to it. Disturbed at Osborne’s
sympathetic portrayal of Jimmy Porter, whose antisocial and frequently cruel behavior ordinarily would not
warrant our sympathy, Roberts sees this “failure of moral perspective” on Osborne’s part as a serious
aesthetic flaw in the play. The popularity of the play in spite of this flaw can be explained by the presence
of a moral tradition that permits the audience to identify with Osborne’s “over-simplifying emphasis upon
‘energy of the 
                        <pb id="p09-127" n="127"/>
soul.’” A modern audience will tolerate Jimmy’s excesses and will sympathize with him because he displays
a capacity for strong feeling and because he proclaims the value of openly immersing oneself in life, of
experiencing whatever pain, dirt or humiliation is necessary to maintain one’s sense of livingness.</p>
          <p>Osborne’s play exploits a moral position that has emerged since the late eighteenth century as
a reaction to neo-Stoicism, which Roberts, in his second chapter, sees as the orthodoxy of that period.
Discussing Johnson’s <hi rend="i">The Vanity of Human Wishes</hi> as a representative statement of the
prevailing moral beliefs of its time, Roberts maintains that Johnson and his contemporaries—however critical
they were of Stoicism—adhered to the essentially Stoic position of mistrusting the passions and seeking to
avoid the perturbations of mind that they cause. The familiar concepts of duty, the sufficiency of virtue, the
rule of Right Reason (which is synonymous with living in accord with the laws of Nature) Roberts identifies as
a part of the eighteenth century’s adaptation of Stoicism.</p>
          <p>The Romantic reaction to this moral position is described in a series of chapters that follow the
same method as the first two: each is devoted to a single author, focusing on one or more works by that
writer. Appropriately, the chapter on the established orthodoxy is followed by one on Blake, whom Roberts
finds to be the major spokesman of Romantic thought. The fourth chapter offers an almost Blakean reading of
Wordsworth, in which Roberts maintains that Wordsworth, despite his technical innovations, was essentially
orthodox in his thinking. Emily Bronte, in <hi rend="i">Wuthering Heights</hi>, is caught between the claims
of that orthodoxy and the newly emerging Romantic morality, while Carlyle’s thinking carries a less dramatic
but equally significant mixture of the old moral order and the new. Conrad’s <hi rend="i">Victory</hi>,
according to Roberts, is a critical analysis of Romantic morality, whereas Browning, Nietzsche, Ibsen and D.
H. Lawrence endorse that morality in varying degrees. The concluding chapter analyzes an anthology of dissent
called <hi rend="i">BAMN: Outlaw Manifestos and Ephemera 1965-70</hi>, whose glorification of energy and
mistrust of order and determinacy are cited as evidence of the continuing and pervasive influence of the
Romantic moral tradition. Here Roberts most explicitly condemns the Romantic morality he has been tracing. He
states that while the proponents of neo-Stoicism erred in separating Reason from the passions—siding with
the claims of Reason—the Romantics did not heal this break by swinging to the opposite pole. Ultimately,
says Roberts, the Romantic morality is an escape from the complexities of moral problems, a regression to a
childlike state.</p>
          <p>Although the discussion of Blake is crucial to his provocative thesis, it is an essentially
orthodox reading of Blake—orthodox in that it does not offer any new critical interpretation of Blake’s
works or ideas. More concerned with the historical ramifications of those ideas, most of Roberts’ discussion
relies upon ground that has been broken by previous scholars and critics. He is sensitive to the limitations
of the approach he is using and renders an accurate and tactful exposition of the moral ideas contained in
Blake’s writings. The discussion relies heavily upon <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,
identifying Blake—as one would expect—with the energetic proponents of the Devil’s party; but Roberts
also cites Blake’s later works to note that the poet’s emphasis upon energy shifts to an emphasis upon the
imagination as a source of values. However, Roberts insists upon the centrality of energy in Blake’s
thought, maintaining that Blake’s concern with the imagination is really a concern with the proper outlets
for energy.</p>
          <p>The chapter’s main virtue is the clarity with which Roberts deals with the complexities of
Blake’s thought. Perhaps the best part is the discussion of Blake’s annotations to Watson’s 
<hi rend="i">An Apology for the Bible</hi>, where Roberts delineates the precise grounds upon which Blake parts
company with both Paine and Watson. Equally helpful is Roberts’ careful consideration of the ways in which
Blake’s morality would work in practice. Only once does Roberts depart from this standard: when he asserts
that Blake’s radical conception of the Fall included the idea that “the corruption of nature had gone so far
that one could not find beauty in it”—an oversimplification that is the result of ignoring Blake’s
mythopoetics.</p>
          <p>It is this dealing with Blake as a polemicist that makes the chapter on Blake the least
interesting one in the book. The chapters on Bronte, Browning, Ibsen and Conrad show a greater sensitivity to
the ways that ideas operate in the context of a work of literature. The book’s delineation of the historical
significance of Blake’s ideas, which Roberts claims to be his contribution to current discussion of Blake,
offers very little on that subject. While it is pleasant to hear another voice affirming that Blake is at the
center—perhaps even at the head—of the Romantic movement, the net result of this assertion is to make
Blake the fountainhead of the “permissive morality” that has become a favorite target in the political
rhetoric of the past decade. Despite Roberts’ obvious intelligence and his constant effort to avoid facile
judgments, his book contains the oversimplifications of a finger-pointing moralist who is attempting to lay
present moral ills at the doorstep of the Romantics. His method necessarily begs the question when he selects
particular authors and works, at the expense of others, to support his thesis. An obvious omission is Shelley,
whose “Speculations on Morals,” <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi> and <hi rend="i">A Defense of Poetry</hi>
are central documents of the morality of the Romantics. Roberts briefly notes that Shelley was concerned with
moral questions, but dismisses him on the grounds that “his moral influence is comparatively restricted”—a
peculiar statement in light of Blake’s comparative obscurity and Shelley’s wider exposure during the
nineteenth century. Similarly, Byron is quickly dismissed as not being “a major moralist or a major moral
influence” because to English readers he represented “something far more complex and more equivocal” than the
figure he cut in the eyes of other Europeans.</p>
          <pb id="p09-128" n="128"/>
          <p>These and other exclusions make Blake not simply the major Romantic writer to assert the Romantic
morality that Roberts describes, but the only writer in the nineteenth century to do so—as all the other
literary figures discussed in the book, with the exception of Lawrence, see that morality as problematical.
Therefore, one doubts the viability of the term “Romantic morality” and Roberts’ belief that the morality he
is describing is essentially literary in its origin and influence. Clearly there are forces other than
literary ones that need to be accounted for. The book’s chapter on Nietzsche is a step in that direction,
but Roberts’ need to justify the inclusion of the philosopher in a literary study points to the book’s
main problem: it attempts to walk a tightrope between literary history and the history of ideas, failing at
the former because it often ignores important works and contexts, and failing at the latter because it is too
narrow in its selection of evidence.</p>
          <p>Because of these failures, <hi rend="i">The Tradition of Romantic Morality</hi> can be most
accurately described as a series of individual essays—some of which offer significant insights—which
Roberts attempts to unify with an untenable thesis. The readings of <hi rend="i">Wuthering Heights</hi>,
“Bishop Blougram’s Apology,” <hi rend="i">The Master Builder</hi> and <hi rend="i">Victory</hi> have a value
that is independent of the flaws in the book’s main argument. However, the author’s obvious lack of
sympathy for his subject gives the entire book a particularly cranky quality, and in its attack on the now
dated ephemera of the sixties, Roberts’ argument becomes what it beholds.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
