<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>9.4.murray</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">1974 Blake Seminar</title>
        <author n="Murray">E. B. Murray</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">09.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <name>Jean Stalker</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_09">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-09-4-0005">
      	<pb id="p09-120" n="120"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">DISCUSSION</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">1974 Blake Seminar</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>E.B. <name>Murray</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>I am pleased the December 1974 MLA Blake Seminar (“Perspectives on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”)
approved of the general tendency of my “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Reversed” paper (see 
<hi rend="i">Newsletter 32</hi>, Spring 1975, p. 105), though I’d suspect it took a smug dealer in
unconscionable paradox to confuse my Vala-Vahlu, Luvah-Lava syllabic reversals and consequent correspondences
with the wholesale importing of extraneous readings into Blake’s text that I was (gently) questioning.
Another case of the saw posing as a razor’s edge to hack up minute particulars—in lieu of an armed vision
to see through them. The reversals are closer to their nominal sources in the text than much Blakean word-play
of these and other days (e.g., earth-owner, horizon, lethe—and “lover” [come back to me?]), perhaps even as
close as that famous back-formation, Enitharmon. When this generation’s Blakean establishment has been laid
to waste, they’ll come glimmering through as well as these. (I shall not promise so much for “nada-nada” as
Udan Adan without evidence that a bit of simple Spanish had some currency to Blake.)</p>
          <p>It was too bad I could not be at the meeting. I accept the wrist-slapping of its reporter with
understanding. But sometimes things close in. Someone should suggest to those running Blake meetings in the
future that they really should give an appropriate by-line to the people actually contributing papers. While
my reasons for not showing were more substantial than this, I couldn’t tell from any listing in the MLA
program that I was really aboard—and so it came to pass. Also—the general carping tone of reported
commentary, though in keeping with the spectral self-righteousness of Blakean commentary everywhere evident
these days (perhaps contagious—<hi rend="i">ecce signum</hi>), suggests that, with only two of the
paper-contributors in absentia, the group had one too many warm bodies to pick at.</p>
          <p>University of Missouri,<lb/>
St. Louis</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
